<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天火明命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari (one of the gods in Japanese mythology)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Hoakari (one of the gods in Japanese mythology)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari (one of the gods in Japanese mythology)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天火明命（アメノホアカリ）は、日本神話に登場する神 (神道)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari is a (Shinto) god that appears in Japanese mythologies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Hoakari is a Shinto god that appears in Japanese mythologies.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari is a Shinto god that appears in Japanese mythologies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『古事記』に天火明命、『日本書紀』に火明命、天照国照彦火明命、また『先代旧事本紀』には天照国照彦天火明櫛玉饒速日尊（あまてるくにてるひこあめのほあかりくしたまにぎはやのみこと）と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described as Ame no Hoakari in &quot;Kojiki (The Records of Ancient Matters),&quot; Hoakari or Amateru Kuniteruhiko Hoakari no Mikoto in &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan),&quot; and Amaterukuniteruhiko Amenohoakari Kushitama Nigihaya no Mikoto in &quot;Sendai Kujihongi (Ancient Japanese History).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is described as Ame no Hoakari in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Hoakari or Amateru Kuniteruhiko Hoakari no Mikoto in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Amaterukuniteruhiko Amenohoakari Kushitama Nigihaya no Mikoto in &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; (Ancient Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The God is called Ame no Hoakari in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters), Hoakari or Amateru Kuniteruhiko Hoakari no Mikoto in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), and Amaterukuniteruhiko Amenohoakari Kushitama Nigihaya no Mikoto in &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; (Ancient Japanese History).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>他に膽杵磯丹杵穂命、『神社志料』では天照御魂神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Ikishinikiho no Mikoto, and furthermore, it was called Amaterasu Mitama no Kami in &quot;Jinja Shiryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Ikishinikiho no Mikoto, and furthermore, it was called Amaterasu Mitama no Kami in &quot;Jinja Shiryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Ikishinikiho no Mikoto, and Amaterasu Mitama no Kami in &quot;Jinja Shiryo&quot; (an history of shrines).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一般的には火明命と呼ばれることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is most commonly called Hoakari no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is most commonly called Hoakari no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The god is usually called Hoakari no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>尾張氏(尾張連)、海部氏など多くの氏族の祖神。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a soshin (ancestor honored as god) for many clans such as the Owari clan (Owari Muraji group) and the Kaifu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a soshin (ancestor honored as god) for many clans such as the Owari clan (Owari Muraji group) and the Kaifu clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoakari no Mikoto is an ancestor honored as a god for many clans such as the Owari clan (Owari Muraji group) and the Kaifu clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>アメノオシホミミとタカミムスビの娘栲幡千千姫命との間に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari was born between Amenooshihomimi and Takuhatachijihime no Mikoto, a daughter of Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Hoakari was born between Amenooshihomimi and Takuhatachijihime no Mikoto, a daughter of Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari was born to the deities Amenooshihomimi and Takuhatachijihime no Mikoto, a daughter of Takamimusubi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ニニギは弟だが、『日本書紀』の一書では子としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninigi was Ame no Hoakari&apos;s younger brother but was described as a son of Ame no Hoakari in one of the editions of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninigi was Ame no Hoakari&apos;s younger brother, but was described as a son of Ame no Hoakari in one of the editions of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninigi was Ame no Hoakari&apos;s younger brother, but was described as a son of Ame no Hoakari in one of the editions of &quot;Nihonshoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『先代旧事本紀』では物部氏の祖である饒速日命（ニギハヤヒノミコト）と同一神としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sendai Kujihongi,&quot; Ame no Hoakari was identified as Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who was the ancestor of the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sendai Kujihongi,&quot; Ame no Hoakari was identified as Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who was the ancestor of the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sendai Kujihongi,&quot; Ame no Hoakari was identified as Nigihayahi no Mikoto, who was the ancestor of the Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『播磨国風土記』では大国主の子とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Harimanokuni-fudoki,&quot; Ameno Hoakari was described as a child of Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo of the southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Harimanokuni-fudoki,&quot; Ameno Hoakari was described as a child of Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo of the southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Harimanokuni-fudoki&quot; (topography of Harima Province), Ameno Hoakari was described as a child of Okuninushi (chief god of Izumo of the southern Honshu Island, Japan, and the central character in the important cycle of myths set in that region).</e>
<cmt>(topography of Harima Province)補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>名前の「天照国照」「火明」からわかるように太陽の光や熱を神格化した神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the names Amateru Kuniteruhiko and Hoakari suggest, Ame no Hoakari is deification of sunlight or heat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the names Amateru Kuniteruhiko and Hoakari suggest, Ame no Hoakari is deification of sunlight or heat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the names Amateru Kuniteruhiko and Hoakari suggest, Ame no Hoakari is deification of sunlight or heat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、『古事記伝』では「ホアカリ」は「穂赤熟」で、稲穂が熟して赤らむ意味としており、天皇に繋る他の神と同様、稲に関係のある名前でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in &quot;Kojikiden (Commentaries on the Kojiki),&quot; &apos;Hoakari&apos; is written in a set of characters that expresses ripened and redden ears of rice; therefore, just like other gods that are linked to the Emperor, its name also is related to rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in &quot;Kojikiden&quot; (Commentaries on the Kojiki), &apos;Hoakari&apos; is written in a set of characters that expresses ripened and redden ears of rice; therefore, just like other gods that are linked to the Emperor, its name also is related to rice.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in &quot;Kojikiden&quot; (Commentaries on the Kojiki), &apos;Hoakari&apos; is written in a set of characters that expresses ripened and redden ears of rice; therefore, just like other gods that are linked to the Emperor, its name also is related to rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>太陽神、農業神として信仰されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari is worshipped as a god of the sun as well as agriculture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame no Hoakari is worshipped as a god of the sun as well as agriculture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame no Hoakari is worshipped as a god of the sun as well as agriculture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このようなことから天穂日命の系譜、つまり天津神系の出雲神を源流としていることが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the roots of Ame no Hoakari is believed to be in the lineage of Ameno Hohino Mikoto, which is an Izumogami of the Amatsu kami (god of heaven) group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the roots of Ame no Hoakari is believed to be in the lineage of Ameno Hohino Mikoto, which is an Izumogami of the Amatsu kami (god of heaven) group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the roots of Ame no Hoakari is believed to be in the lineage of Ameno Hohino Mikoto, which is an Izumogami of the Amatsu kami (god of heaven) group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>『新撰姓氏録』では、天火明命の子孫を「天孫族」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility),&quot; descendents of Ame no Hoakari are called the &apos;Tenson (grandsons of the sun goddess (clan).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), descendents of Ame no Hoakari are called the &apos;Tenson&apos; (grandsons of the sun goddess (clan).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility), descendents of Ame no Hoakari are called the &apos;Tenson&apos; (grandsons of the sun goddess (clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天孫族は大和国葛城の高尾張から尾張国に移り、子の天香山命（あめのかぐやまのみこと）の時に定住し、真清田神社（愛知県一宮市）に天火明命を祀ったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan relocated itself from Takaowari of Katsuragi in Yamato Province to Owari Province, settled down during the generation of Ame no Hoakari&apos;s child, Amenokaguyama no Mikoto, and enshrined Ame no Hoakari at the Mamisuda-jinja Shrine (Ichinomiya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan relocated itself from Takaowari of Katsuragi in Yamato Province to Owari Province, settled down during the generation of Ame no Hoakari&apos;s child, Amenokaguyama no Mikoto, and enshrined Ame no Hoakari at the Mamisuda-jinja Shrine (Ichinomiya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan relocated itself from Takaowari of Katsuragi in Yamato Province to Owari Province, settled down during the generation of Ame no Hoakari&apos;s child Amenokaguyama no Mikoto, and enshrined Ame no Hoakari at the Mamisuda-jinja Shrine (Ichinomiya City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>尾張氏は中部地方に勢力を持っていた氏族であり、物部氏と深い関係を持っていたことから、尾張氏が祀る天火明命が天照大神（伊勢神宮）の子とされたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Owari clan had power over the Chubu region and had a strong relationship with the Mononobe clan, therefore, Ame no Hoakari enshrined by the Owari clan was considered to be a child of Amaterasu Omikami (Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Owari clan had power over the Chubu region and had a strong relationship with the Mononobe clan, therefore, Ame no Hoakari enshrined by the Owari clan was considered to be a child of Amaterasu Omikami (Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Owari clan had power over the Chubu region and had a strong relationship with the Mononobe clan, therefore, Ame no Hoakari enshrined by the Owari clan was considered to be a child of Amaterasu Omikami (Ise-jingu Shrine).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また住吉三神を祀り住吉大社（大阪市住吉区）を創建した田蓑宿禰は尾張氏の一族であり、その子孫が住吉大社の歴代宮司家としての津守氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Sukune TAMINO who enshrined Sumiyoshi Sanjin and built the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City) was one of the Owari clan, and his descendents are the Tsumori clan that has been the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine gunji (chief priest) family for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Sukune TAMINO who enshrined Sumiyoshi Sanjin and built the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City) was one of the Owari clan, and his descendents are the Tsumori clan that has been the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine gunji (chief priest) family for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Sukune TAMINO who enshrined Sumiyoshi Sanjin and built the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City) was one of the Owari clan, and his descendents are the Tsumori clan that has held the position of chief priest of the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine for generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>また全国の天照御魂神社は天火明命を祀るところが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note also that Ame no Hoakari has been enshrined at many of the Amaterumitama-jinja Shrines nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note also that Ame no Hoakari has been enshrined at many of the Amaterumitama-jinja Shrines nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note also that Ame no Hoakari has been enshrined at many of the Amaterumitama-jinja Shrines nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Nnh(id:474), Junger(id:10282), KASAGI(id:24405), Watyo(id:160812), NPD(id:58640), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>