<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>天津麻羅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amatsumara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amatsumara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatsumara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天津麻羅（あまつまら）は、日本神話に登場する鍛冶の神 である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amatsumara is a deity of ironworking that appears in the Japanese Mythology.</e>
<cmt>原文の「(神道)」は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amatsumara is a deity of ironworking that appears in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>Article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatsumara is a deity of ironworking that appears in Japanese mythology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古事記にのみ登場し、日本書紀には登場しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears only in &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) but not in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He appears in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) but not in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;only&quot;Articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He appears in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) but not in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「神」「命」などの神号はつけられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No title of god such as &quot;kami&quot; or &quot;mikoto&quot; is given to Amatsumara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He has none of the titles, such as &quot;kami&quot; or &quot;mikoto,&quot; that are usually given to Shinto deities.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He has none of the titles, such as &quot;kami&quot; or &quot;mikoto,&quot; that are usually given to Shinto deities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>古事記では岩戸隠れの段に登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amatsumara is described in the section of Iwadokakure in &quot;Kojiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amatsumara appears in the Iwadokakure section of the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; which relates how the sun goddess, Amaterasu, hid in a cave and was lured out uing a mirror and the dancing of Amenouzume, the goddess of merriment.</e>
<cmt>*Added explanation of Iwadokakure (which I think is usually &apos;Iwatokakure&apos;)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amatsumara appears in the Iwatogakure section of the &quot;Kojiki,&quot; which relates how the sun goddess, Amaterasu, hid in a cave and was lured out uing a mirror and the dancing of Amenouzume, the goddess of merriment.</e>
<cmt>NCのご指摘で調べたところ、広辞苑他で Iwatogakure となっていたので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「鍛人（かぬち）天津麻羅を求（ま）きて」とあるだけで、何をしたのかは書かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kojiki only states that as the blacksmith, Amatsumara was called upon and there is no description about what he did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Kojiki&quot; states that the &quot;blacksmith, Amatsumara was called upon&quot; but there is no description of what he did.</e>
<cmt>PrepositionsPunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Kojiki&quot; states that the &apos;blacksmith, Amatsumara was called upon&apos; but there is no description of what he did.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その前に「天の金山の鉄（はがね）を取りて」とあることから、伊斯許理度売命（いしこりどめ）が鏡を作るための製鉄を行ったとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the prior text, Amatsumara was using the &quot;hard rocks of heaven&quot; and the &quot;metal mountain of heaven,&quot; so he is believed to refine the iron used by Ishikoridome for making mirrors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sentence before that states that Amatsumara was using &quot;steel from the metal mountain of heaven,&quot; so he is believed to have been refining the iron used by Ishikoridome to make the mirror.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - I&apos;m not sure if &quot;金山&quot; shouldn&apos;t just be &apos;mine&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sentence before that states that Amatsumara was &apos;using steel from the metal mountain of heaven,&apos; so he is believed to have been refining the iron used by Ishikoridome to make the mirror.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos; （using　から付けました。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、日本書紀の本文には、天鈿女命（あめのうずめ）が茅纏の矛を手にしたという記述があり、それを作った者の記述がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main text of Nihonshoki described that Amenouzume took Chimaki no Hoko but there is no description of the maker of the sword.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main text of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; says that Amenouzume was holding an enchanted spear, Chimaki no Hoko, but there is no description of its maker.</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity - &quot;矛&quot; is a kind of spear, not a sword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main text of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; says that Amenouzume was holding an enchanted spear, Chimaki no Hoko, but there is no description of its maker.</e>
<cmt>「茅纏」を調べましたが、enchanted なのか確認できませんでした。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このことから、天津麻羅は矛を作ったとも考えられる（第一の一書では石凝姥命（いしこりどめ）が日矛を作ったとある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be interpreted that Amatsumara made this sword (The first alternate writing indicates that Ishikoridome made the hihoko (spear)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be interpreted to mean that Amatsumara made the spear (The first addendum indicates that Ishikoridome made the hihoko [spear]).</e>
<cmt>*Revised for clarity &quot;alternate writing&quot;→&quot;addendum&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be interpreted to mean that Amatsumara made the spear (The first addendum indicates that Ishikoridome made the hiboko (spear)).</e>
<cmt>hihoko→hiboko() を [ ] にNC が訂正しています。[ ]は訳文であまり見ないので()にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>先代旧事本紀の天孫降臨の段では、「倭（やまと）の鍛師（かなち）等の祖、天津真浦（あまつまうら）」「物部造等の祖、天津麻良（あまつまら）、阿刀造等の祖、天麻良（あめのまら）」とあり、これらは天津麻羅と同神と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section of tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) in &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot;(Ancient Japanese History) reads &quot;the ancestor of Yamato no Kanachira called Amatsumaura&quot; and &quot;the ancestor of Monobeno miyatsutachi called Amatsumara and the ancestor of Atonomiyatsukora called Amenomara,&quot; these are considered as the same deity as Amatsumara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section on tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) in &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot;(Ancient Japanese History) reads &quot;the ancestor of Yamato no Kanachira called Amatsumaura&quot; and &quot;the ancestor of Monobeno miyatsutachi called Amatsumara and the ancestor of Atonomiyatsukora called Amenomara,&quot; all of which are considered to be the same deity as Amatsumara.</e>
<cmt>PunctuationRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section on tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess) in &quot;Sendai Kujihongi&quot; (Ancient Japanese History) reads &apos;the ancestor of Yamato no Kanachi and others called Amatsumaura&apos; and &apos;the ancestor of Mononobe no Miyatsuko and others called Amatsumara and the ancestor of Ato no Miyatsuko and others called Amenomara,&apos; all of which are considered to be the same deity as Amatsumara.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、神号がついていないことなどから、天津麻羅は一神の名ではなく鍛冶集団（またはその祖神）の総称ではないかとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory states that Amatsumara has no title of god so that it is not the name of a god but the common name (or soshin (ancestor honored as god)) of the blacksmith occupational groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory states that since there is no divine title, Amatsumara is not the name of a god but a general term for blacksmiths (or their deified ancestor).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory states that since there is no divine title, Amatsumara is not the name of a god but a general term for blacksmiths (or their deified ancestor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>アマツマラという神名のうち、アマツは天津神を示すものであるが、「マラ」については下記のように諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Amatsu&quot; in the name &quot;Amatsumara&quot; refers to Amatsukami (god of heaven), but there are several theories of the meaning of &quot;mara&quot; as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Amatsu&quot; in the name &quot;Amatsumara&quot; refers to the Amatsukami (gods of heaven), but there are several theories as to the meaning of &quot;mara.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ArticleRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Amatsu&quot; in the name &quot;Amatsumara&quot; refers to the Amatsukami (gods of heaven), but there are several theories as to the meaning of &apos;mara.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;mara&quot;→&apos;mara&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>「マラ」は「目占（めうら）」すなわち片目の意で、鍛冶が鉄の色でその温度をみるのに片目をつぶっていたことから（または鍛冶の職業病である）とする説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory states that &quot;mara&quot; comes from &quot;me-ura&quot; meaning &quot;one-eyed,&quot; a reference to a habit of blacksmiths closing one eye to see the color of iron to tell the temperature (or an occupational hazard of blacksmiths).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory states that &quot;mara&quot; comes from &quot;me-ura&quot; meaning &quot;one-eyed,&quot; a reference to the practice of blacksmiths closing one eye in order to check the iron&apos;s temperature from its color (or to an occupational hazard of blacksmiths).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory states that &apos;mara&apos; comes from &apos;me-ura&apos; meaning &apos;one-eyed,&apos; a reference to the practice of blacksmiths closing one eye in order to check the iron&apos;s temperature from its color (or to an occupational hazard of blacksmiths).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>「マラ」は蒙古語の鉄の意であるとする説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory states that &quot;mara&quot; is a Mongolian word that means iron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory states that &quot;mara&quot; is a Mongolian word that means iron.</e>
<cmt>&quot;A&quot;→&quot;Another&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory states that &apos;mara&apos; is a Mongolian word that means iron.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>鍛冶に必要な槌を男根にみたて、男根の別称「マラ」を神名としたとする説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A theory states that a hammer required for blacksmiths is compared to a penis and takes another name of penis, &quot;mara&quot; in the name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that blacksmith&apos;s hammers were compared to a penis and so &quot;mara,&quot; a slang word for penis, became part of the name.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory that blacksmith&apos;s hammers were compared to a penis and so &apos;mara,&apos; a slang word for penis, became part of the name.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（ただし、摩羅（まら）という言葉は仏教と共に日本に入ってきたものであり、男根の別称とされたのはさらに時代が下るものであるので、この説は後世の附会である）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It should be noted, however, that the word &quot;mara&quot; was introduced to Japan together with Buddhism and it was more recent times when the word come to be used as an alias of penis; therefore, this theory is a distortion of the meaning by more recent generations.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It should be noted, however, that since the word &quot;mara,&quot; which means &apos;obstacles to practicing buddhism,&apos; was introduced to Japan together with Buddhism and only later came to be used as another word for penis, this theory is an invention by more recent generations.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity - added definition of &quot;mara&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It should be noted, however, that since the word &quot;mara,&quot; which means &apos;obstacles to practicing buddhism,&apos; was introduced to Japan together with Buddhism and only later came to be used as another word for penis, this theory is an invention by more recent generations.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>一番目の説を採った場合、日本書紀や古語拾遺に登場する天目一箇神（あめのまひとつ）と同一神であるとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the first theory is accepted, Amatsumara can be the same deity as Amenomahitotsu no kami (the one-eyed kami of heaven) that appears in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (History of the Inbe clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the first theory is accepted, Amatsumara can be held to be the same deity as Amenomahitotsu no kami (the one-eyed kami of heaven), who appears in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (History of the Inbe clan).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the first theory is accepted, Amatsumara can be held to be the same deity as Amenomahitotsu no kami (the one-eyed kami of heaven), who appears in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Kogo-shui&quot; (History of the Inbe clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>天目一箇神も鍛冶の神であり、古語拾遺では岩戸隠れの際に金属製の武具を製作している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amenomahitotsu no kami was also a deity of ironworking, and in &quot;Kogo-shui,&quot; it made metal weapons at the time of Amaterasu&apos;s hiding away in the rock cave of heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amenomahitotsu no kami was also a deity of ironworking, and in &quot;Kogo-shui,&quot; he made metal weapons at the time of Amaterasu&apos;s hiding away in the cave.</e>
<cmt>PronounRevised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amenomahitotsu no kami was also a deity of ironworking, and in &quot;Kogo-shui,&quot; he made metal weapons at the time of Amaterasu&apos;s hiding away in the cave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>