<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>俊士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>俊士(しゅんし)とは、平安時代以降、文章生に与えられた称号。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunshi is the title given to monjosho (student of literary studies in the Imperial universities.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Heian Period, Shunshi was the title given to monjosho (students of literary studies in the Imperial University).</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense; added &quot;Heian Period&quot; details corresponding to the Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Heian Period, &quot;Shunshi&quot; was the title given to monjosho (students of literary studies at Imperial universities).</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他 2009/6/29）の指示により、Shunshi にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。用語集の表記に従い、at Imperial universities を in the Imperial University に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>俊士とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is shunshi?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;What is shunshi?&quot; does not sound like it belongs in an article like this</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>俊士は大学寮の学生たる文章生に与えられた称号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunshi is the title given to monjosho who were the students of Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the Ritsuryo system.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunshi was the title given to monjosho who were students at Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense; fixed grammar and period after parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunshi was the title given to monjosho who were students at Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大学平安時代初期、文章生が良家の子弟に限られた際に、成績優秀なる文章生5名に与えられた称号として定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunshi was set as a title given to the five students who made the most excellent achievement during the early Heian Period when monjosho was limited to children from good families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early Heian Period when monjosho was limited to children from privileged families, Shunshi was established as a title given to the five monjosho students with the highest scholastic standing.</e>
<cmt>good families→privileged families</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early Heian Period when monjosho was limited to children from privileged families, Shunshi was established as a title given to the five monjosho students with the highest scholastic standing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その後、良家以外の者についても俊士に補せられるようになったが、後に再び良家以外の者も文章生となる機会が拡がるにつれ、俊士の称号も廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later shunshi came to be also selected from students other than ones from good families, and after that with the increasing chances of students from other than good families being able to be a monjosho, the title of shunshi was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunshi later began to be made up of students other than those from privileged families, and as chances to become monjosho were extended to students who were not from privileged families, the title of shunshi fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunshi later began to be made up of students other than those from privileged families, and as chances to become monjosho were extended to students who were not from privileged families, the title of shunshi fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代末期に至り、明経問者生を俊士と呼んだ例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of Heian Period, there were some cases of calling myogyo-kanja-sho (a student who is a master of myokyo, Chinese classics of Confucianism) as shunshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Near the end of the Heian Period, there were a number of cases where shunshi were called myogyo-kanja-sho (a student who is a master of myokyo - Chinese classics of Confucianism).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Near the end of the Heian Period, there were a number of cases where shunshi were called Myogyomonjasho (a student who is a master of myogyo - Chinese classics of Confucianism).</e>
<cmt>原文「明経間者生」を「明経問者生」に修正しました。myogyo-kanja-sho を Myogyomonjasho に修正しました（※）。myokyo を myogyo に修正しました。※全体の読み方は不明ですが、以下のリンクを参考にしました。１．明経生（よみ）「みょうぎょうのしょう」http://kotobank.jp/word/%E6%98%8E%E7%B5%8C%E7%94%9F２．問者（よみ）「もんじゃ」http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%95%8F%E8%80%85</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>