<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>男爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baron</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>男爵（だんしゃく）とは爵位の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baron (called danshaku in Japanese) is a title of nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baron (called danshaku in Japanese) is a title of nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baron (called danshaku in Japanese) is a title of nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古代中国、近代日本、イギリスなどでは五等爵の第5位にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its rank is located around the fifth from the top (Gotoshaku) in ancient China, modern Japan, and England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the fifth highest rank of peerage (Gotoshaku) in ancient China, modern Japan, and England.</e>
<cmt>後列でスコットランドに触れている為、原文のイギリスはイングランドと表記するのが望ましいです。　Its rank is located around the fifth from the top (Gotoshaku) を It is the fifth highest rank of peerage (Gotoshaku) に書換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the fifth highest rank of peerage (Gotoshaku) in ancient China, modern Japan, and England.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>子爵の下位に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ranked below Viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is ranked below Viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is ranked below Viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>フランス、ドイツ、ロシアなど各国の爵位制度でも該当する爵位が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a title that corresponds to baron in the peerage systems of France, Germany, and Russia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a title that corresponds to baron in the peerage systems of France, Germany, and Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a title that corresponds to baron in the peerage systems of France, Germany, and Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>ヨーロッパの男爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">European baron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Barons in Europe</e>
<cmt>European baron を Barons in Europe に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Barons in Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本語の男爵に相当する爵位を英語ではバロン (称号)（Baron）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danshaku in Japanese corresponds to barron in English.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danshaku in Japanese corresponds to Baron in English.</e>
<cmt>表現の変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danshaku in Japanese corresponds to Baron in English.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>バロンの女性形はバロネス（Baroness）で、イギリスの制度では男爵の妻（男爵夫人）や男爵の爵位をもつ女性（女男爵）に用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The feminine equivalent of baron is baroness, and is used for the wife of a baron or a woman having the title of baron (female baron).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The feminine equivalent of Baron is Baroness, and is used for the wife of a Baron or a woman having the title of Baron (female Baron).</e>
<cmt>後列でスコットランドに触れている為、原文のイギリスはイングランドと表記するのが望ましいです。　Baron, Baroness の頭文字は大文字としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The feminine equivalent of Baron is Baroness, and is used for the wife of a Baron or a woman having the title of Baron (female Baron).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>イギリスでは男爵は上院議員になることができる貴族の最下位の称号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In England, baron is the title of the lowest rank that is eligible to become a peer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In England, a Baron is the lowest-ranked title that is eligible for a peerage.</e>
<cmt>baron を a Baron、the title of the lower rank を lowest-ranked title、peer を peerage に変更しました。　後列でスコットランドに触れている為、原文のイギリスはイングランドと表記するのが望ましいです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In England, a Baron is the lowest-ranked title that is eligible for a peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>英国ではこの爵位をもつ男性をBaron何々と呼ぶことはめったになく、貴族への一般的敬称であるLordを用いてLord Smithなどと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In England, it is rare to call a man of this peerage Baron; rather, they use the general title Lord, such as &apos;Lord Smith.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In England, it is rare to call a man of this peerage Baron; rather, they use the general title Lord, such as &apos;Lord Smith.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In England, it is rare to call a man of this peerage Baron; rather, they use the general title Lord, such as &apos;Lord Smith.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>スコットランドではバロンは爵位の称号ではなく、イングランドの男爵に相当する爵位はロード・オブ・パーラメントという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Scotland, Baron is not a title of peerage, and the corresponding peerage is called Lord of Parliament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Scotland, a Baron is not a title of peerage, and the corresponding peerage is called &apos;Lord of Parliament.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Baron を a Baron とし、 Lord of Parliament に引用符を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Scotland, a Baron is not a title of peerage, and the corresponding peerage is called &apos;Lord of Parliament.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>ヨーロッパのその他の国はロシアを含めてほとんどがバロン系統の称号を男爵の爵位に用いているが、ドイツのみ男爵に相当する爵位はフライヘル（Freiherr）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other European countries including Russia use the title of a lineage for baron, however, it is called Freiherr only in Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although almost all other European countries including Russia use the title Baron, Germany uses Freiherr instead.</e>
<cmt>訳文を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although almost all other European countries including Russia use the title Baron, Germany uses Freiherr instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本の男爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese baron</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese Barons</e>
<cmt>baron を Barons としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese Barons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>明治以降の華族制度において創設され、最下位の爵位とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established after the Meiji period, and it was determined as the peerage of the lowest rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established after the Meiji period, and it was determined as the peerage of the lowest rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established after the Meiji period, and it was determined as the peerage of the lowest rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以下のような人々が男爵位を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following people received the title of baron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following people received the title of Baron.</e>
<cmt>baron を Baron としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following people received the title of Baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>公家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuge (court of noble)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuge (court nobles)</e>
<cmt>nobles としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuge (court nobles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>維新後華族に列せられたる者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who were raised to the peerage after the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who were raised to the peerage after the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who were raised to the peerage after the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>すなわち明治以降に分家した家（26家）と、廃仏毀釈の風潮のなかで還俗した公家出身の興福寺の僧侶（いわゆる奈良華族。27家）がこれにあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families separated from their head families (26 families) and among Buddhist monks (those who were orignally court nobles of the Kofuku-ji Temple) who returned to secular life during the time when anti-Buddhist movement was getting stronger (called the Nara peerage,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families separated from their head families (26 families) and a number of Buddhist monks (those who were originally court nobles of the Kofuku-ji Temple) who returned to secular life during the time when anti-Buddhist movement was getting stronger (called the Nara peerage, 27 families).</e>
<cmt>among を a number of に置換え、「 27家）がこれにあたる。」を結合させ、訳文もここにに収めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families separated from their head families (26 families) and a number of Buddhist monks (those who were originally court nobles of the Kofuku-ji Temple) who returned to secular life during the time when anti-Buddhist movement was getting stronger (called the Nara peerage, 27 families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>さらにいわゆる地下家の中でも殊に家格が高かった押小路家、壬生家の2家、及び公家出身で明治維新に功績のあった玉松操の子孫である玉松家（閑院流出身）、太宰府天満宮宮司で高辻家傍流とされる西高辻家にも特に男爵が与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the following families received the title of baron: the Oshikoji family and the Mibu family, whose social standings were particularly high among the Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace), the Tamamasu family (Kanin-ryu, one of the Fijiwara clique), the descendants of Misao TAMAMATSU, who was from court noble and made a great contribution to the Meiji Restoration, and the Nishitakatuji family, who served as Guji (chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs) of Dazaifu Tenman-gu Shrine and who was a branch family of the Takatuji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the following families received the title of Baron: the Oshikoji family and the Mibu family, whose social standings were particularly high among the Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace); the Tamamasu family (Kanin-ryu, one of the Fujiwara faction); the descendants of Misao TAMAMATSU, who was from court nobility and made a great contribution to the Meiji Restoration; and the Nishitakatsuji family, who served as Guji (chief of those who serve shrines, control festivals and general affairs) of Dazaifu Tenman-gu Shrine and who were a branch family of the Takatsuji family.</e>
<cmt>baron を Baron に変更しました　各家の説明をコンマでなくセミコロンで区切りました　court noble は court nobility としました　those who 以下の動詞を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the following families received the title of Baron: the Oshikoji family and the Mibu family, whose social standings were particularly high among the Jige-ke (family status of non-noble retainers who are not allowed into the Emperor&apos;s living quarters in the imperial palace); the Tamamasu family (Kanin-ryu, one of the Fujiwara faction); the descendants of Misao TAMAMATSU, who was from court nobility and made a great contribution to the Meiji Restoration; and the Nishitakatsuji family, who served as Guji (chief of those who serve shrines, control festivals and general affairs) of Dazaifu Tenman-gu Shrine and who were a branch family of the Takatsuji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>武家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai family (buke)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai family (buke)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai family (buke)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>維新後華族に列せられたる者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who were raised to the peerage after the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who were raised to the peerage after the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who were raised to the peerage after the Meiji Restoration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>すなわち明治以降に大名家から分家した家（35家）がこれにあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are the people of the families who were separated from Daimyo family after the Meiji peroid (35 families).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are the people of the families who were separated from the Daimyo (Feudal Lord)&apos;s family after the Meiji period (35 families).</e>
<cmt>Daimyo に補足を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are the people of the families who were separated from the Daimyo (Feudal Lord)&apos;s family after the Meiji period (35 families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その他、御三家付家老として1万石以上を領していた紀伊田辺藩安藤家、美濃今尾藩竹腰家、常陸松岡藩中山家、尾張犬山藩成瀬家、紀伊新宮藩水野家の5家、交代寄合のうち維新時に現米1万石以上であった播磨福本池田家、出羽矢島生駒家、大和田原本平野家、常陸志筑本堂家、備中成羽山崎家、但馬村岡山名家の6家、長州藩の支藩とされてきた周防岩国藩吉川氏の計11家も、「江戸時代以前は藩とは見なされなかったが明治以後に華族になった」と見なして男爵を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following 11 families and the Yoshikawa clan of Suo Iwakuni Domain, who had been raised to the peerage since the Meiji era, received the title of Baron: 5 families who owned more than 10,000 koku of crop yields as the attendant chief retainer of three privileged branches - the Ando family of the Kii Tanabe Domain, the Takenokoshi family of the Mino Imao Domain, the Nakayama family of the Hitachi Matsuoka Domain, the Naruse family of the Owari Inuyama Domain and the Mizuno family of the Kii Shingu Domain, and 6 families of kotaiyoriai, a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period, who owned more than 10,000 koku of rice during the Meiji Restoration - the Ikeda family of the Harima Fukumoto Domain, the Ikoma family of the Dewa Yashima Domain, the Hirano family of the Yamato Tawaramoto Domain, the Hondo family of the Hitachi Shizuku Domain, the Yamazaki family of the Bitchu Nariwa Domain and the Yamana family of the Tajima Muraoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ　全文訳漏れのため、訳出を行いました。「江戸時代以前は藩とは見なされなかったが」部分は意味を成さない（江戸時代以前に藩は存在しなかった）ため訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following 11 families and the Yoshikawa clan of Suo Iwakuni Domain, who had been raised to the peerage since the Meiji era, received the title of Baron: 5 families who owned more than 10,000 koku of crop yields as the attendant chief retainer of three privileged branches - the Ando family of the Kii Tanabe Domain, the Takenokoshi family of the Mino Imao Domain, the Nakayama family of the Hitachi Matsuoka Domain, the Naruse family of the Owari Inuyama Domain and the Mizuno family of the Kii Shingu Domain, and 6 families of kotaiyoriai, a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period, who owned more than 10,000 koku of rice during the Meiji Restoration - the Ikeda family of the Harima Fukumoto Domain, the Ikoma family of the Dewa Yashima Domain, the Hirano family of the Yamato Tawaramoto Domain, the Hondo family of the Hitachi Shizuku Domain, the Yamazaki family of the Bitchu Nariwa Domain and the Yamana family of the Tajima Muraoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また戊辰戦争で改易された上総請西藩林家は士族から再度華族に列せられたという扱いで男爵を授爵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hayashi family, who were deprived of their samurai status during the Boshin War, received the title of Baron, having been raised to the peerage from the warrior class.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ　全文訳漏れのため、訳出を行いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hayashi family, who were deprived of their samurai status during the Boshin War, received the title of Baron, having been raised to the peerage from the warrior class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>徳島藩筆頭家老稲田家は戊辰戦争、北海道開拓に功績があったとして男爵を与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Inada family, Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) of the Tokushima Domain, was bestowed the title of baron as an award for their great achievement for the development of Hikkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Inada family, Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) of the Tokushima Domain, were bestowed the title of Baron as an award for their great achievement in the development of Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>achievement for を achievement in に、Hikkaido を Hokkaido に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Inada family, Hitto karo (the head of chief retainers) of the Tokushima Domain, were bestowed the title of Baron as an award for their great achievement in the development of Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>越前福井藩松平家の家老であった本多家（二万石）は、陪臣であると解釈されて一旦士族とされたが、旧家臣・領民らによる陳情・騒動（武生騒動）の結果、男爵となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Honda family, who was the chief retainer of the Matsudaira family of the Fukui domain, was first judged as baishin (indirect vassal) and was given the class of warriors, however, they were finally given the title of baron after the petition and riots (called Takefu incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honda family, who were the chief retainers of the Matsudaira family of the Fukui domain, were first judged as baishin (indirect vassal) and were given the class of warriors, however, they were finally given the title of Baron after the petition and riots known as the Takefu incident.</e>
<cmt>文頭の the を The に訂正、 the Honda family が主語の本文では動詞を複数扱いで表記し直しました。　小文字でなく大文字で Baron と表記しました。　Takefu incident は riots called でなく riots known に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honda family, who were the chief retainers of the Matsudaira family of the Fukui domain, were first judged as baishin (indirect vassal) and were given the class of warriors, however, they were finally given the title of Baron after the petition and riots known as the Takefu incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>僧職・神職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">priesthood and Shinto priesthood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist priesthood and Shinto priesthood</e>
<cmt>僧職のpriesthood はBuddhist priesthood としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist priesthood and Shinto priesthood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>特に内規としてあてはまるものはなかったが、各地の神職のうち特に古い家柄のもの（伊勢神宮荒木田家・河辺家、伊勢神宮松木家、阿蘇神社阿蘇家、宇佐神宮到津家・宮成家、日御碕神社小野家、物部神社 (大田市)金子家、日前神宮・國懸神宮紀家、出雲大社北島家・千家家、熱田神宮千秋家、住吉大社津守家、英彦山天台修験座主高千穂家。太字は国造家）、及び僧職のうち血縁によって職を世襲している家（浄土真宗木辺派管長木辺家、同渋谷派管長渋谷家、同高田派管長常盤井家、同興正寺派管長華園家）は華族に列せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">None of them was particularly applicable as baron in the bylaw, however, the following was raised to the peerage: Shinto priests of local areas, especially from the old families (the Arakita family of Ise Jingu Shrine, Kawabe family, Matsumoto family of ise Jingu Shrine, Aso family of Aso-jinja Shrine, Itozu family and Miyanari family of Usa-jingu Shrine, Ono family of Hinomisaki-jinja Shrine, Kaneko family of Mononobe-jinja Shrine (in Ota city), the Ki family of Hinokuma-jingu Shrine and Kunikakasu-jingu Shrine, Kitajima family and Sen family of Izumo-taisha Shrine, Senshu family of Atsuta-jingu Shrine, the Tsumori family of Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine, Takachjho family of Shugen zasu (temple&apos;s head priest) of HikosanTendai sec.</e>
<cmt>宮成家 miyanari</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">None of these were particularly suitable as a Baron under the bylaw, however, the following were raised to the peerage: Shinto priests of local areas, especially from the old families (the Arakita family of Ise Jingu Shrine, Kawabe family, Matsumoto family of Ise Jingu Shrine, Aso family of Aso-jinja Shrine, Itouzu family and Miyanari family of Usa-jingu Shrine, Ono family of Hinomisaki-jinja Shrine, Kaneko family of Mononobe-jinja Shrine (in Ota city), the Ki family of Hinokuma-jingu Shrine and Kunikakasu-jingu Shrine, Kitajima family and Sen family of Izumo-taisha Shrine, Senshu family of Atsuta-jingu Shrine, the Tsumori family of Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine, Takachiho family of Tendai Shugen zasu (head priest of the temple) of Hikosan; Family names in bold letters indicate that they were kuninomiyatsuko (the heads of local governments), and Buddhist priests&apos; families which inherited positions (the Kibe family, the chief abbot of the Kibe school of Jodo Shinshu - the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism, the Shibuya family, the chief abbot of the Shibuya school of Jodo Shinshu, and the Hanazono family, the chief abbot of the Kosho-ji Temple of Jodo Shinshu).</e>
<cmt>後列と一文であった為、結合させました。　applicable を suitable に変更しました。　baron を a Baron に変更しました。　the following に続く動詞は複数扱いに訂正しました　Itozu を Itouzu に訂正しました。　宮成家は Miyanari family で正しいです。　Takachjho を Takachiho に訂正しました。Shugen zasu （temple&apos;s head priest) of Hikosan Tendai sec を Tendai Shugen zasu （head priest of the temple) of Hikosan に変更しました。　国造家の訳文を訂正しました。　浄土真宗の説明文を読みやすさを考えて、コンマでなくハイフンで結びました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">None of these were particularly suitable as a Baron under the bylaw, however, the following were raised to the peerage: Shinto priests of local areas, especially from the old families (the Arakita family of Ise Jingu Shrine, Kawabe family, Matsumoto family of Ise Jingu Shrine, Aso family of Aso-jinja Shrine, Itouzu family and Miyanari family of Usa-jingu Shrine, Ono family of Hinomisaki-jinja Shrine, Kaneko family of Mononobe-jinja Shrine (in Ota city), the Ki family of Hinokuma-jingu Shrine and Kunikakasu-jingu Shrine, Kitajima family and Sen family of Izumo-taisha Shrine, Senshu family of Atsuta-jingu Shrine, the Tsumori family of Sumiyoshitaisha Shrine, Takachiho family of Tendai Shugen zasu (head priest of the temple) of Hikosan; Family names in bold letters indicate that they were kuninomiyatsuko (the heads of local governments), and Buddhist priests&apos; families which inherited positions (the Kibe family, the chief abbot of the Kibe school of Jodo Shinshu - the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism, the Shibuya family, the chief abbot of the Shibuya school of Jodo Shinshu, and the Hanazono family, the chief abbot of the Kosho-ji Temple of Jodo Shinshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>このうち東西本願寺の大谷家を除く18家は男爵とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, 18 families, except Otani family of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, were given the title of baron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, 18 families, except the Otani family of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, were given the title of Baron.</e>
<cmt>baron を Baron としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, 18 families, except the Otani family of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, were given the title of Baron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>新華族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New nobility</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New nobility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New nobility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>国家に勲功ある者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who have made outstanding contribution to the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who have made outstanding contributions to the country.</e>
<cmt>contribution を contributions にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who have made outstanding contributions to the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>政治家・官僚・軍人以外に、三井家、住友家、鴻池家、岩崎家のような実業家にも男爵が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except politicians, bureaucrats, and members of the armed forces, the title of baron was also given to businesspeople such as the Mitsui family, Sumitomo family, Konoike family, and Iwasaki family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except politicians, bureaucrats, and members of the armed forces, the title of Baron was also given to businesspeople such as the Mitsui family, Sumitomo family, Konoike family, and Iwasaki family.</e>
<cmt>baron を Baron としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except politicians, bureaucrats, and members of the armed forces, the title of Baron was also given to businesspeople such as the Mitsui family, Sumitomo family, Konoike family, and Iwasaki family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また維新時の功績などといった名目により、大藩の家老家のうちかなりの数が「国家に勲功ある者」として男爵を授けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, many families of karo (chief retainer of daimyo, Japanese territorial lord) of taihan (large scale domains) received the title of baron as the award for their outstanding contribution to the country during the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, many families of karo (chief retainer of daimyo, Japanese territorial lord) of taihan (large scale domains) received the title of Baron as a reward for their outstanding contribution to the country during the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>baron を Baron に、the award を a reward にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, many families of karo (chief retainer of daimyo, Japanese territorial lord) of taihan (large scale domains) received the title of Baron as a reward for their outstanding contribution to the country during the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>菊池武臣、五条頼定、名和長恭、南部行義、新田俊純などが南朝_(日本)の功臣の子孫であることを理由に新たに華族に列せられ、男爵を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeomi KIKUCHI, Yorisada GOJO, Nagayasu NAWA, Yukiyoshi NANBU, Toshizumi NITTA were also raised to the peerage and given the title of baron as the descendants of meritorious retainers of the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>菊池武臣 五条頼定 南部行義 新田俊純</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeomi KIKUCHI, Yorisada GOJO, Nagayasu NAWA, Yukiyoshi NANBU, Toshizumi NITTA were also raised to the peerage and given the title of Baron as the descendants of meritorious retainers of the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>baron を Baron としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeomi KIKUCHI, Yorisada GOJO, Nagayasu NAWA, Yukiyoshi NANBU, Toshizumi NITTA were also raised to the peerage and given the title of Baron as the descendants of meritorious retainers of the Southern Court (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>貴族院 (日本)へは男爵中で互選した者が議員となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The councilors of the House of Peers (Japan) were chosen from barons by mutual vote among themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The councilors of the Japanese House of Peers were chosen from barons by a mutual vote among themselves.</e>
<cmt>the House of Peers (Japan) を the Japanese House of Peers に変更、mutual vote を a mutual vote にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The councilors of the Japanese House of Peers were chosen from barons by a mutual vote among themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="33">
<j>日本においては公爵、伯爵と並んで知名度の高い爵位であり、文学作品、漫画作品などにも多くの男爵が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, baron is the most well known title as well as duke and hakushaku (count, earl in England); barons often appear in Japanese literary works and comic books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Baron is the most well known title as well as Duke and Hakushaku (Count, Earl in England); Barons often appear in Japanese literary works and comic books.</e>
<cmt>baron、 duke、 hakushaku、 count、 earl は全て大文字で始まるよう変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Baron is the most well known title as well as Duke and Hakushaku (Count, Earl in England); Barons often appear in Japanese literary works and comic books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その多くは大礼服よりも伝統的なスーツや乗馬服をまとった紳士風の人物として描かれており、貴族と言うよりは上位の紳士の称号として認識されている感が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many cases, they are discribed as gentlemen type of people wearing traditonal suits or riding suits; baron is recognized more as the title for gentlemen rather than for aristocrats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, they are described as gentleman types wearing traditional suits or riding suits; Baron is recognized more as the title for a gentleman rather than for aristocrats.</e>
<cmt>type を types に、baron をBaron に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, they are described as gentleman types wearing traditional suits or riding suits; Baron is recognized more as the title for a gentleman rather than for aristocrats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>男爵にちなんだ命名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words named after danishaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words named after Danshaku</e>
<cmt>danishaku を Danshaku に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words named after Danshaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>男爵いも</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danshaku imo (Baron potato)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danshaku imo (Baron potato)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Danshaku imo (Baron potato)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>ジャガイモの品種の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A breed of potato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A breed of potato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A breed of potato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>男爵いもは高知県出身の男爵・川田龍吉が北海道上磯町（現・北斗市）でアイリッシュ・コブラーという品種の芋を試験栽培し、普及させたことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name Danshaku imo comes from the fact that the Baron Ryukichi KAWATA cultivated and a breed of potato called Irish Cobbler in Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>Ryuikichi Kawata http://ocw.hokudai.ac.jp/Course/Faculty/Agriculture/AgricultureInHokkaido/2009/page/materials/AgricultureInHokkaido-2009-Text-02.pdf, Irish cobbler http://www.geocities.jp/a5ama/dansya.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name Danshaku imo comes from the fact that the Baron Ryukichi KAWATA cultivated a breed of potato called Irish Cobbler at Kamiiso town (present day: Hokuto city) in Hokkaido and popularized the potato.</e>
<cmt>cultivated and の and は削除しました。　訳漏れ　上磯町（現・北斗市）の英語表記を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name Danshaku imo comes from the fact that the Baron Ryukichi KAWATA cultivated a breed of potato called Irish Cobbler at Kamiiso town (present day: Hokuto city) in Hokkaido and popularized the potato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>空気男爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuki danshaku (Air baron)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuki danshaku (Air baron)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuki danshaku (Air baron)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>漫画家さいとうたかおのデビュー作。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuki danshaku is the debut volume of the cartoonist Takao SATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuki danshaku is the debut volume of the cartoonist Takao SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuki danshaku is the debut volume of the cartoonist Takao SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>髭男爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hige danshaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hige danshaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hige danshaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="41">
<j>サンミュージック所属の漫才コンビ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">a Japanese comic duo of Sun music group (entertainment agency)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">a Japanese comic duo of Sun music group (entertainment agency)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">a Japanese comic duo of Sun music group (entertainment agency)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>主な日本の男爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Japanese barons</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Japanese barons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Japanese barons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>青山胤通 東京帝国大医科大学校長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanemichi AOYAMA, pricipal of 東京帝国大医科大学</e>
<cmt>東京帝国大医科大学の英語名が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanemichi AOYAMA, principal of Tokyo Imperial Medical University</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ　東京帝国大医科大学を英語表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanemichi AOYAMA, principal of Tokyo Imperial Medical University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>伊丹重賢　錦鶏間祗候・勲一等瑞宝章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigekata ITAMI, recipient of Kinkei no mashiko and Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigekata ITAMI, recipient of Kinkei no mashiko and Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigekata ITAMI, recipient of Kinkei no mashiko and Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>渡辺清　錦鶏間祗候・勲一等瑞宝章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoshi WATANABE, recipient of Kinkei no mashiko and Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoshi WATANABE, recipient of Kinkei no mashiko and Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoshi WATANABE, recipient of Kinkei no mashiko and Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>幣原喜重郎　第44代内閣総理大臣、第40代衆議院議長、従一位勲一等旭日桐花大綬章</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kijuro SHIDEHARA, the 44th prime minister, the 40th chairman of House of Representatives, recipient of Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower of the Junior First Rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kijuro SHIDEHARA, the 44th prime minister, the 40th chairman of the House of Representatives, recipient of Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower of the Junior First Rank</e>
<cmt>House of Representatives の頭に the を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kijuro SHIDEHARA, the 44th prime minister, the 40th chairman of the House of Representatives, recipient of Grand Cordon of the Order of the Rising Sun with Paulownia Flower of the Junior First Rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>川崎正蔵　神戸川崎財閥創立者、貴族院議員</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozo KAWASAKI, the founder of Kobe Kawasaki Zaibatsu and a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozo KAWASAKI, the founder of Kobe Kawasaki Zaibatsu and a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozo KAWASAKI, the founder of Kobe Kawasaki Zaibatsu and a member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>橋本綱常　大日本帝国陸軍軍医総監、陸軍省医務局長、東京大学教授。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunatsune HASHIMOTO, general office director of Imperial Japanese Army (IJA), leader of Ministry of Army, professor at the University of Tokyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunatsune HASHIMOTO, general office director of Imperial Japanese Army (IJA), leader of the Ministry of Defense, professor at the University of Tokyo</e>
<cmt>Ministry of Army を the Ministry of Defence に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunatsune HASHIMOTO, general office director of Imperial Japanese Army (IJA), leader of the Ministry of Defense, professor at the University of Tokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>博士 (医学)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doctor of Medicine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doctor of Medicine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doctor of Medicine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="49">
<j>小池正直　陸軍軍医総監、貴族院議員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanao KOIKE, army surgeon general and member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanao KOIKE, army surgeon general and member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanao KOIKE, army surgeon general and member of Kizokuin (the House of Peers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="50">
<j>高木兼寛　海軍医務局長・海軍軍医総監。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanehiro TAKAGI, head of the Medical Bureau of the Navy and the general office director of the a Navy Medical Service</e>
<cmt>head of the Medical Bureau of the Navy http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=oK-7LOlWNpEC&amp;pg=PA69&amp;lpg=PA69&amp;dq=Kanehiro+TAKAGI%E3%80%80navy&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=HMgapIn-KO&amp;sig=dPnDt2PdLJkqSUbpJncPvcSaskQ&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=eAZCTKrrJsOC8gaIw-jqBQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CBgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Kanehiro%20TAKAGI%E3%80%80navy&amp;f=false</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehiro TAKAGI, head of the Medical Bureau of the Navy and the general office director of the a Navy Medical Service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehiro TAKAGI, head of the Medical Bureau of the Navy and the general office director of the a Navy Medical Service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>東京慈恵会医科大学の創設者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder of the Jikei University School of Medicine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder of the Jikei University School of Medicine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder of the Jikei University School of Medicine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>脚気の撲滅に尽力し、「麦飯男爵」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanehiro dedicated to the eradication of beriberi and was called &apos;barley rice baron.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehiro was dedicated to the eradication of beriberi and was called the &apos;barley rice baron.&apos;</e>
<cmt>dedicated を was dedicated に訂正、 &apos;barley rice baron.&apos; は the &apos;barley rice baron.&apos; としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehiro was dedicated to the eradication of beriberi and was called the &apos;barley rice baron.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="53">
<j>福原実　陸軍少将勲一等瑞宝章・錦鶏間祗候</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minoru FUKUHARA, Army Major General who was awarded with Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure and Kinkei no mashiko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minoru FUKUHARA, Army Major General who was awarded with Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure and Kinkei no mashiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minoru FUKUHARA, Army Major General who was awarded with Grand Cordon of the Order of the Sacred Treasure and Kinkei no mashiko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="54">
<j>西竹一　陸軍大佐、戦車二十一連隊長、ロサンゼルスオリンピック (1932年)馬術障害飛越競技金メダリスト。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeichi NISHI, Colonel of the Army, Colonel of the 21st tank regiment and gold medal winner of Equestrianism in the 1984 Summer Olympics (the Games of the XXIII Olympiad)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeichi NISHI, Colonel of the Army, Colonel of the 21st tank regiment and gold medal winner in Equestrianism in the 1932 Los Angeles Olympic Games.</e>
<cmt>the 1984 Summer Olympics (the Games of the XXIII Olympiad) を the 1932 Los Angeles Olympic Games に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeichi NISHI, Colonel of the Army, Colonel of the 21st tank regiment and gold medal winner in Equestrianism in the 1932 Los Angeles Olympic Games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="55">
<j>村田経芳 薩摩藩士、陸軍少将、日本陸軍の最初の国産小銃「村田銃」発明者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuneyoshi MURATA, feudal retainer of Satsuma, Army Major General, inventor of the first domestic rifle of the Japanese army, Murataju (Murata rifle)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuneyoshi MURATA, feudal retainer of Satsuma, Army Major General, inventor of the first domestic rifle of the Japanese army, Murataju (Murata rifle)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuneyoshi MURATA, feudal retainer of Satsuma, Army Major General, inventor of the first domestic rifle of the Japanese army, Murataju (Murata rifle)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="56">
<j>本庄繁　陸軍大将、侍従武官長、満洲事変当時の関東軍司令官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeru HONJO, Army General, military attache to the palace, Kwantung Army (Japanese armed forces in Manchukuo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeru HONJO, Army General, military attache to the palace, Kwantung Army (Japanese armed forces in Manchuria)</e>
<cmt>Mancukuo を Manchuria に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeru HONJO, Army General, military attache to the palace, Kwantung Army (Japanese armed forces in Manchuria)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="57">
<j>大角岑生　海軍大将、五・一五事件、二・二六事件当時の海軍大臣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mineo OSUMI, full admiral, Minister of the Navy at the time of May 15th Incident and February 26th Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mineo OSUMI, full admiral, Minister of the Navy at the time of May 15th Incident and February 26th Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mineo OSUMI, full admiral, Minister of the Navy at the time of May 15th Incident and February 26th Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="58">
<j>北里柴三郎　医学者の一覧・細菌学。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibasaburo KITASATO, medical scholar and bacteriologist</e>
<cmt>「の一覧」の部分は意味をなさない上、サイト内にはなかったので、省きました。また、「細菌学」だけでは意味をなさないため、サイト内の「細菌学者」を訳に採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibasaburo KITASATO, medical scholar and bacteriologist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibasaburo KITASATO, medical scholar and bacteriologist</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>北里大学の創設者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Founder of Kitasato University</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Founder of Kitasato University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Founder of Kitasato University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>医療行政や衛生行政の面でも大きな業績を残す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibasaburo made remarable achievements in the health services and public health administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibasaburo made remarable achievements in the health services and public health administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibasaburo made remarable achievements in the health services and public health administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="61">
<j>鈴木貫太郎　第42代内閣総理大臣、枢密院議長、侍従長、海軍軍令部長、連合艦隊司令長官、海軍大将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kantaro SUZUKI, the 42nd prime minister, Chairman of the Privy Council, Grand Chamberlain, department director of the Navy Department, navarch of combined fleet, and full admiral</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kantaro SUZUKI, the 42nd prime minister, Chairman of the Privy Council, Grand Chamberlain, department director of the Navy Department, navarch of the combined fleet, and full admiral</e>
<cmt>combined fleet を the combined fleet としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kantaro SUZUKI, the 42nd prime minister, Chairman of the Privy Council, Grand Chamberlain, department director of the Navy Department, navarch of the combined fleet, and full admiral</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="62">
<j>鮫島具重　海軍中将、戦艦長門 (戦艦)艦長。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomoshige SAMEJIMA, vice admiral, captain of the battleship Nagato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomoshige SAMEJIMA, vice admiral, captain of the battleship Nagato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomoshige SAMEJIMA, vice admiral, captain of the battleship Nagato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="63">
<j>大倉喜七郎　ホテルオークラ創業者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishichiro OKURA, the founder of Hotel Okura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishichiro OKURA, the founder of Hotel Okura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishichiro OKURA, the founder of Hotel Okura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), JYOQ2(id:7240), Wiki0825(id:34646), DragonBot(id:161936), Eskimbot(id:29676), MelancholieBot(id:31942), Tokyo Watcher(id:95142), Zorac(id:28001), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Aibot(id:104981), Snap55(id:89773), OKBot(id:143139), Iderukuti(id:19367), DaBot(id:128812), るがこむ(id:181), ＩＤＳ(id:49634), Myopia(id:9335), 寒(id:53831), Rei-bot(id:94097), 怪蘇(id:45514), Chobot(id:20846), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), BotMultichill(id:132395), Point136(id:211299), コバルトブルーとターコイズブルー(id:290948), FlaBot(id:30804), Emi1971(id:536), Super peace(id:25380), U3002(id:66126), 水野白楓(id:22811), MIO(id:31681), Yanahan(id:2437), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Zwobot(id:23873), Ef3(id:84901), Rusk(id:9895), Xqbot(id:273540), VolkovBot(id:105371), Amler(id:101250), YurikBot(id:18605), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 海衛士(id:19229), 663highland(id:18755), Chiether(id:77421), Ponsaku(id:31417), 伏儀(id:142093), Safkan(id:423), Akimoto(id:6951), Louperibot(id:128971), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>