<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>郡代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gundai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gundai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gundai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>郡代（ぐんだい）とは室町時代から江戸時代にかけての幕府・諸藩に置かれた職名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gundai (郡代: a magistrate of a region or an administrator of a town) is a name of post set in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as well as in Domains of the clans from the Muromachi Period to the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>郡代→a magistrate of a region or an administrator of a town　と説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gundai （郡代 a magistrate of a region or an administrator of a town) is the name of a post set in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and in clan domains from the Muromachi Period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gundai （a magistrate of a region or an administrator of a town) is the name of a post set in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and in clan domains from the Muromachi period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>郡代 削除用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>郡奉行（こおりぶぎょう）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Koribugyo (郡奉行: a magistrate of a country).</e>
<cmt>郡奉行→Koribugyo (郡奉行: a magistrate of a country)としました。.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post was also referred to as Koribugyo (magistrate of a country).</e>
<cmt>It→The post; took out kanji</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post was also referred to as Koribugyo (magistrate of a country).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代、郡を単位として軍事・警察権を行使していた守護代（守護の代官）が室町時代に入り、租税関係（年貢の徴収）も行うようになったことに始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The post was created when Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) (acting Shugo), who was exercising the military and police powers during the Kamakura Period, started to take charge of the affaires related to taxation (customs collection) as well, in the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post of Gundai was created when a Shugodai (deputy of Shugo; provincial constable) who had been exercising military and police powers during the Kamakura Period began taking charge of affairs related to taxation (tax collection) as well at the start of the Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>fixed sentence to read more smoothly; customs collection→tax collection</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post of Gundai was created when a Shugodai (deputy of Shugo; provincial constable) who had been exercising military and police powers during the Kamakura period began taking charge of affairs related to taxation (tax collection) as well at the start of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一般的には守護代の支配を受けて郡単位で支配した代官を郡代・郡奉行と呼んでいたが、守護代そのものを郡代・郡奉行と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gundai or Koribugyo was generally used to refer to Daikan (local governor), who controlled the unit of Gun (country) under the direction of Shugodai, but Shugodai itself was sometimes called Gundai or Koribugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gundai or Koribugyo was generally used to refer to a Daikan (local governor) who controlled a unit of Gun (country) under the direction of a Shugodai, but there were also times when these terms were also used to refer to a Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gundai or Koribugyo was generally used to refer to a Daikan (local governor) who controlled a unit of Gun (country) under the direction of a Shugodai, but there were also times when these terms were also used to refer to a Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>支配地域は1～2郡であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It controlled one or two countries under its jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person with this position had one or two countries under their jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt>It→a person with this position; its→their</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person with this position had one or two countries under their jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代には、幕府および諸藩に置かれた役職である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, it referred to the post set in the bakufu as well as in each Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Period, Gundai was a post set within the bakufu as well as in each domain.</e>
<cmt>it→Gundai; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Gundai was a post set within the bakufu as well as in each domain.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府では、比較的広域の幕府領を支配する代官のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the bakufu, it referred to local governor (Daikan) who controlled a relatively wide extension of bakufu&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the bakufu, the post referred to a local governer (Daikan) who controlled a relatively wide extension of government territory.</e>
<cmt>it→the post; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the bakufu, the post referred to a local governor (Daikan) who controlled a relatively wide extension of government territory.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸時代初期には関東郡代のほかに上方、尼崎、三河国、丹波国、河内国などほぼ1国単位に郡代が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the early period of Edo, besides Kanto gundai (a magistrate of Kanto region), in almost all the provinces, including Kamigata, Amagasaki, Mikawa Province, Tanba Province, and Kawachi Province, the post of Gundai was set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early on during the Edo period, aside from the Kanto region, a Gundai post was set in almost all of the provinces, including Kamigata, Amagasaki, Mikawa, Tanba and Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>took out &quot;province&quot; after Mikawa, Tanba and Kawachi; changed sentence structure to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early on during the Edo period, aside from the Kanto region, a Gundai post was set in almost all of the provinces, including Kamigata, Amagasaki, Mikawa, Tanba and Kawachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1642年（寛永19年）勘定頭制の施行に伴い、郡代・代官はその管轄下に置かれたが、その後関東郡代は老中支配となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1642, with the establishment of the Kanjogashira sei (a system controlled by a chief of financial officer), Gundai and Daikan were put under its jurisdiction, but afterwards, Kanto gundai was brought under the control of Roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders).</e>
<cmt>勘定頭制→定訳不明：Kanjogashira sei (a system controlled by a chief of financial officer)としました。 老中→定訳不明：Roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1642, the Kanjogashira sei (a system controlled by a chief financial officer) was established, which put Gundai and Daikan under its jurisdiction, but Kanto Gundai was brought under the control of the Roju (members of the Shogun&apos;s council of elders) later on.</e>
<cmt>changed sentence structure to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1642, the Kanjogashira sei (a system controlled by a chief financial officer) was established, which put Gundai and Daikan under its jurisdiction, but Kanto Gundai was brought under the control of the Roju (members of the Shogun&apos;s council of elders) later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>江戸時代中期以降は、関東郡代・美濃郡代・西国筋郡代・飛騨郡代の4郡代となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the middle Edo Period, their number was reduced to four; Kanto gundai, Mino gundai (a magistrate in Mino region), Saigokusuji gundai (a magistrate in Kyushu region), and Hida gundai (a magistrate in Hida region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the middle Edo Period, the number of Gundai was reduced to four: Kanto Gundai, Mino Gundai, Saigokusuji Gundai (Kyushu region) and Hida Gundai.</e>
<cmt>their number→the number of Gundai; eliminated content in parenthesis as it seemed unecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the middle Edo period, the number of Gundai was reduced to four: Kanto Gundai, Mino Gundai, Saigokusuji Gundai (Kyushu region) and Hida Gundai.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>郡代の身分・格式は、代官よりも上であるが、職務内容については代官とほぼ同じであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status and rank of Gundai was higher than Daikan, but the scope of the work was almost the same as that of Daikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status and rank of a Gundai was higher than that of a Daikan, but the scope of the work between the two was nearly the same.</e>
<cmt>fixed sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status and rank of a Gundai was higher than that of a Daikan, but the scope of the work between the two was nearly the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、江戸幕府初期には老中支配の郡代官が設置されて郡代とほぼ同様の職掌を扱ったが、寛文8年（1668年）に廃止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo Period, Koridaikan （local governer of a country (gun)), was set up under the control of Roju, and it took charge nearly the same dueties, but this post was abolished in 1668.</e>
<cmt>郡代官→定訳、読み不明：Koridaikan（local governer of a country (gun))としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo Period, the post called Koridaikan (local governor of a country) was set up under control of the Roju and had nearly all the same duties, but was abolished in 1668.</e>
<cmt>fixed sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the post called Koridaikan (local governor of a country) was set up under control of the Roju and had nearly all the same duties, but was abolished in 1668.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>諸藩でも直轄地支配を行うため郡代あるいは郡奉行を置いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In each Domain, Gundai or Koribugyo was set in order to control the directly controlled territory by the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Gundai or Koribugyo was set up in each domain in order to administer government in directly controlled clan territories.</e>
<cmt>fixed sentence to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Gundai or Koribugyo was set up in each domain in order to administer government in directly controlled clan territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 FOZ(id:44646), 茫々(id:66385), NPD(id:58640), Nerimaman(id:61206), Yanahan(id:2437), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), NDR(id:5500), Junger(id:10282), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>