<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勾当内侍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotononaishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotononaishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koto no naishi</e>
<cmt>定訳どおりに訂正</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>勾当内侍（こうとうのないし）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の公家の女性である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotononaishi was an female of a court noble in the northern dynasty and southern dynasty era (in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotononaishi was a female court noble during the northern dynasty and southern dynasty era (in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koto no naishi was a female court noble during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一条経尹、あるいは一条伊尹の娘、一条行房の娘、妹とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was said a daughter of Tsunetada ICHIJO or Koremasa/Koretada ICHIJO, or a daughter or younger sister of Yukifusa ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was said to be the daughter of Tsunetada ICHIJO or Koremasa/Koretada ICHIJO, or the daughter or younger sister of Yukifusa ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was said to be the daughter of Tsunetada ICHIJO or Koremasa/Koretada ICHIJO, or the daughter or younger sister of Yukifusa ICHIJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本名は不詳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her real name was not known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her real name was not known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her real name is not known.</e>
<cmt>was→is</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>新田義貞の妻（正妻は安東氏の娘）とされるが、新田義貞との関係が記されているのは『太平記』においてのみであり、年代的な推定などから創作である可能性が非常に高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is said that she was a wife of Yoshisada NITTA (his legally wedded wifwe was a daughter of the Ando clan), descriptions of her relationships with Yoshisada NITTA are included only in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; and it is highly likely that they were imagenary, considering chronological estimates and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is said that she was the wife of Yoshisada NITTA (his legally wedded wife was a daughter of the Ando clan), descriptions of her relationships with Yoshisada NITTA are included only in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; and it is highly likely that they were imagenary, considering chronological estimates and others.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is said that she was the wife of Yoshisada NITTA (his legally wedded wife was a daughter of the Ando clan), descriptions of her relationships with Yoshisada NITTA are included only in &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) and it is highly likely that they were imagenary, considering chronological estimates and others.</e>
<cmt>太平記の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、「勾当内侍」の実在すら疑わしいと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the existence of &quot;Kotononaishi&quot; herself is dubious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the existence of &quot;Kotononaishi&quot; herself is dubious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the existence of &apos;Koto no naishi&apos; herself is dubious.</e>
<cmt>Kotononaishi→Koto no naishi 以下この表記に訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personalities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personalities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personalities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>鎌倉時代後期に後醍醐天皇の討幕運動に加わり、鎌倉陥落に功績のあった上野国の新田義貞の妻になったいわれ、建武の新政を開始した後醍醐天皇が新田義貞への恩賞として与えたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why she became a wife of Yoshisada NITTA in the Kozuke province, who participated in Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s activities for defeating the bakufu and contributed to getting control of Kamakura, is said to be as follows: Emperor Go-Daigo who started the new government in the Kenmu era gave her to Yoshisada NITTA as a prize for his contribution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why she became a wife of Yoshisada NITTA in Kozuke province, who participated in Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s activities for defeating the bakufu and contributed to getting control of Kamakura, is said to be as follows: Emperor Go-Daigo who started the new government in the Kenmu era gave her to Yoshisada NITTA as a prize for his contribution.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why she became a wife of Yoshisada NITTA in Kozuke Province, who participated in Emperor Godaigo&apos;s activities for defeating the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and contributed to getting control of Kamakura, is said to be as follows: Emperor Godaigo who started the new government in the Kenmu era gave her to Yoshisada NITTA as a prize for his contribution.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigo幕府の説明補足&quot;province&quot; -&gt; &quot;Province&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>建武 (日本)3年（1336年）新田義貞は新政から離反した足利尊氏を楠木正成や北畠顕家らとともに京都で破り、足利尊氏らは九州へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, Yoshisada NITTA defeated Takauji ASHIKAGA, who alienated from the new government, in Kyoto together with Masashige KUSUNOKI and Akiie KITABATAKE, and Takauji ASHIKAGA and his followers fled to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, Yoshisada NITTA defeated Takauji ASHIKAGA, who was alienated from the new government, in Kyoto together with Masashige KUSUNOKI and Akiie KITABATAKE, and Takauji ASHIKAGA and his followers fled to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, Yoshisada NITTA defeated Takauji ASHIKAGA, who was alienated from the new government, in Kyoto together with Masashige KUSUNOKI and Akiie KITABATAKE, and Takauji ASHIKAGA and his followers fled to Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>建武政権が足利尊氏追撃を行わなかった理由は幾つか考えられているが、『太平記』では新田義貞は京都において勾当内侍との別れを惜しみ、出兵する時期を逃したとし、勾当内侍が結果的に義貞の滅亡の遠因を作った女性であるとする描き方がされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although several reasons were considered for why Yoshisada NITTA did not chase Takauji ASHIKAGA, &quot;Taiheiki&quot; described a reason as follows: He was reluctant to leave Kotononaishi in Kyoto, losing the timing to dispatch troops, and therefore, she was the woman who generated a remote cause of Yoshisada&apos;s fall resultantly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although several reasons were considered for why Yoshisada NITTA did not chase Takauji ASHIKAGA, &quot;Taiheiki&quot; described the reason as follows: He was reluctant to leave Kotononaishi in Kyoto, losing the timing to dispatch troops, and therefore, she was the woman who generated the cause of Yoshisada&apos;s fall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although several reasons were considered for why Yoshisada NITTA did not chase Takauji ASHIKAGA, &quot;Taiheiki&quot; described the reason as follows: He was reluctant to leave Koto no naishi in Kyoto, losing the timing to dispatch troops, and therefore, she was the woman who generated the cause of Yoshisada&apos;s fall.</e>
<cmt>Kotononaishi→Koto no naishi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>尊氏が上京して後醍醐天皇を追い、新田義貞は恒良親王らを奉じて北陸地方へ逃れ、足利軍の攻勢により1338年に越前国藤島で戦死するが、『太平記』においては、琵琶湖畔の今堅田において別れ、京にて悲しみの日々を送っていた勾当内侍は新田義貞に招かれ北陸へ向かうが、杣山（福井県南条町）において新田義貞の戦死を知り、獄門にかけられた新田義貞の首級を目にして落飾して比丘尼になったと描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji entered Kyoto and chased Emperor Go-Daigo, Yoshisada NITTA fled to the Hokuriku region with Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi placed as Emperor and died in a battle at Fujishima of the Echizen province attacked by ASIKAGA troops, and &quot;Taiheiki&quot; makes a description of Kotononaishi at around that time as in the following: Kotononaishi, who parted from Yoshisada NITTA at Imakatata beside Lake Biwa and spent days sadly in Kyoto, was invited by Yoshisada NITTA and started for Hokuriku, but at Somayama (present Najo Town, Fukui Prefecture), she knew that he died in a battle and became a (female) priest seeing his head hung on a prison gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji entered Kyoto and chased Emperor Go-Daigo, Yoshisada NITTA fled to the Hokuriku region with Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi placed as Emperor and died in a battle at Fujishima of the Echizen province attacked by ASIKAGA troops, and &quot;Taiheiki&quot; makes a description of Kotononaishi at around that time as in the following: Kotononaishi, who parted from Yoshisada NITTA at Imakatata beside Lake Biwa and spent days sadly in Kyoto, was invited by Yoshisada NITTA and started for Hokuriku, but at Somayama (present Najo Town, Fukui Prefecture), she knew that he died in a battle and became a (female) priest seeing his head hung on a prison gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji entered Kyoto and chased Emperor Godaigo, Yoshisada NITTA fled to the Hokuriku region with Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi placed as Emperor and died in battle at Fujishima of the Echizen Province attacked by ASHIKAGA troops in 1338, and &quot;Taiheiki&quot; makes a description of Koto no naishi at around that time as in the following: Koto no naishi, who parted from Yoshisada NITTA at Imakatata beside Lake Biwa and spent days sadly in Kyoto, was invited by Yoshisada NITTA and started for Hokuriku, but at Somayama (present Najo Town, Fukui Prefecture), she knew that he had died in a battle and became a (female) priest seeing his head hung on a prison gate.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→GodaigoASIKAGA→ASHIKAGA「1338年」訳抜け、追記しましたdied in a battle→died in battle下から二行目のhe died は　he had died だと思います。&quot;province&quot; -&gt; &quot;Province&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、勾当内侍の父とされる行房も新田義貞に従い、北陸で戦死していると記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also described that his father, Yoshifusa, followed Yoshisada NITTA and also died in a battle in Hokuriku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also described that his father, Yoshifusa, followed Yoshisada NITTA and also died in battle in Hokuriku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also described that her father, Yoshifusa, followed Yoshisada NITTA and also died in battle in Hokuriku.</e>
<cmt>his→her</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>あるいは勾当内侍は琴が浜で入水したという伝説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A legend also describes that Kotononaishi entered the sea at the Kotogahama beach and died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A legend also describes that Kotononaishi entered the sea at the Kotogahama beach and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A legend also describes that Koto no naishi entered the sea at the Kotogahama beach and died.</e>
<cmt>Koto no naishi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>今堅田には、勾当内侍を祭神とする野上神社や菩提寺の泉福寺などがあり、慰霊のための野上祭も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Imakatata, there exists Nogami-jinja Shrine whose god is Kotononaishi and a temple for her, Senpuku-ji Temple, and the Nogami festival was also held for consoling her spirit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Imakatata, there exists Nogami-jinja Shrine whose god is Kotononaishi and there is a temple for her, Senpuku-ji Temple, and the Nogami festival was also held for consoling her spirit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Imakatata, there exists Nogami-jinja Shrine whose god is Koto no naishi and there is a temple for her, Senpuku-ji Temple, and the Nogami festival was also held for consoling her spirit.</e>
<cmt>Koto no naishi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、江戸時代に講釈として『太平記』が流布すると、各地に勾当内侍の墓所が作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, after contents of &quot;Taiheiki&quot; became well-known through performances of storytellers in the Edo period, graves of Kotononaishi were built in various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, after contents of &quot;Taiheiki&quot; became well-known through performances of storytellers in the Edo period, graves of Kotononaishi were built in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, after contents of &quot;Taiheiki&quot; became well-known through performances of storytellers in the Edo period, graves of Koto no naishi were built in various places.</e>
<cmt>Koto no naishi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、新田義貞が戦死した藤島近くの三国湊は、勾当内侍局の収入源の1つであった事も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also pointed out that some of Kotononaishi-tsubone&quot;s (-tubone: a honorary suffix attachde to the name of a high-ranked female in the court) income came from Mikuniminato near to Fujishima where Yoshisada NITTA died in a battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also pointed out that some of Kotononaishi-tsubone&quot;s (-tubone: a honorary suffix attachde to the name of a high-ranked female in the court) income came from Mikuniminato near to Fujishima where Yoshisada NITTA died in a battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also pointed out that some of Koto no naishi-tsubone&quot;s (-tubone: a honorary suffix attachde to the name of a high-ranked female in the court) income came from Mikuniminato near to Fujishima where Yoshisada NITTA died in a battle.</e>
<cmt>Koto no nashi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、墓は群馬県太田市尾島町（旧新田郡尾島町）にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her grave is placed inOjimamachi, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture (former Ojimama Town, Nitta County)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her grave is located in Ojimamachi, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture (former Ojimama Town, Nitta County)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her grave is located in Ojima-machi, Ota City, Gunma Prefecture (former Ojima Town, Nitta County)</e>
<cmt>Ojimamachi→Ojima-machiOjimama→Ojima</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), でここ(id:9565), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Hannah(id:15935), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>