<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal Lord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal Lords</e>
<cmt>複数に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal Lords</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>領主（りょうしゅ）とは、一定の土地と其処に生活する人々（領地）の封建的な支配権を有する者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lords refer to the people who hold feudal dominion over a certain land and its residents (territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;feudal lord&quot; is used to refer to a person who holds feudal dominion over a certain area of land and its residents (territory).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;feudal lord&quot; is used to refer to a person who holds feudal dominion over a certain area of land and its residents (territory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>領主は、封建制の時代における政治ないし地方自治の形態で、その多くは世襲制による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lord is a form of government or local autonomy in the feudalism period, and many of them are hereditary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudalism was the form of government or local autonomy that was employed in feudal times, and the position of feudal lord was often hereditary.</e>
<cmt>A lord cannot be a system of government. I have had to 意訳 this a bit to get it to make some sense in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudalism was the form of government or local autonomy that was employed in feudal times, and the position of feudal lord was often hereditary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ヨーロッパ地域では近世から中世にかけ国家という単位が発生する過渡期的に多くの領主が貴族という形で国家に編入されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Europe as states were emerging as a unit from the medieval period to the early-modern times, many feudal lords were incorporated into the states as nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Europe, as states were emerging as single entities during the transition from the medieval period to early modern times, many feudal lords were given positions as nobles in the state&apos;s political structure.</e>
<cmt>&quot;lords were incorporated into the states as nobles&quot; doesn&apos;t really make much sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Europe, as states were emerging as single entities during the transition from the medieval period to early modern times, many feudal lords were given positions as nobles in the state&apos;s political structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>元々は開墾などの形で土地を自然のままの単なる荒地や原野から食料などの生産（農業）に即した状態（→穀倉地帯・治水）に整備するのは、個人や小集団の手には余る仕事であったし、まして近隣地域からの侵略から守ることは、民兵を組織化するにしても困難が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It exceeded the power of an individual or small group to cultivate the wilds or wasteland to change it into the state fitted to produce food (agriculture) (=&gt; breadbasket, flood control), and it was still more difficult to defend themselves from invasion of neighboring spots, even if they organized the militia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultivating the wilderness or wastelands and converting them into the appropriate condition for food production (agriculture) (=&gt; breadbasket and flood control) exceeded abilities of individuals or small groups, and it was, by and large, still difficult to defend themselves from invasion by neighboring territories, even if they organized a militia.</e>
<cmt>意味が不明瞭だったので、前後を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultivating the wilderness or wastelands and converting them into the appropriate condition for food production (agriculture) (breadbasket and flood control) exceeded abilities of individuals or small groups, and it was, by and large, still difficult to defend themselves from invasion by neighboring territories, even if they organized a militia.</e>
<cmt>→削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>こういった事業を手掛けていったのが、領主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lords undertook these projects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal lords undertook these projects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal lords undertook these projects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>領主は領地を得て、其処からの産品で財を成したが、この中には交易の整備や外交、また領内の住民（領民）に対する生活保護に絡んだ様々な問題解決が仕事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lords acquired the territory, and made their fortune selling products yielded there, and this involved improving trade circumstances, diplomacy, and a variety of problem-solving related to public assistance for residents in the territory (people of the domain).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal lords acquired territory and made their fortune from products on their properties, because of this, trade circumstances, diplomacy, and a variety of problems related to public assistance for residents in the territory (people of the domain) were improved.</e>
<cmt>語彙</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal lords acquired territory and made their fortune from products on their properties, because of this, trade circumstances, diplomacy, and a variety of problems related to public assistance for residents in the territory (people of the domain) were improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>ただ多くの伝承が伝えるように、こういった領主が増長して領民を苦しめたり、或いは周辺地域を侵略したりといった時代もあり、戦国時代 (日本)のような形態の時代には戦争に明け暮れ、その負担は領民を苦しめることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to many traditions, these feudal lords grew so arrogant as to torment the people of the domain or invaded a surrounding area in some times, and during the Sengoku period (the Age of Civil Wars in Japan) feudal lords devoted all their time to fighting, imposing a heavy load on people of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to many stories, these feudal lords grew so arrogant and tormented the people of the territory or invaded surrounding areas occasionally; during the Sengoku period (the Age of Civil Wars in Japan), feudal lords devoted all of their time to fighting, imposing a heavy toll on the people of the territory.</e>
<cmt>domainよりもterritoryの方が良いかもしれません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to many stories, these feudal lords grew so arrogant and tormented the people of the territory or invaded surrounding areas occasionally; during the Sengoku period (the Age of Civil Wars in Japan), feudal lords devoted all of their time to fighting, imposing a heavy toll on the people of the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらの領主はやがて大衆から遊離し、その権力を絶対のものとして代々受け継いでいったが、その中にはいわゆる名君と謳われ伝承に残るような善良ないし優秀な者たちもいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the course of time feudal lords became more and more detached from the people and handed down their authority as absolute power successively; however, some lords were good or excellent enough to have the reputation of wise ruler and be passed down to posterity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the course of time feudal lords were gradually detached from the people and handed down their dominance as the absolute authority; however, some lords were better or so excellent that they were admired as wise rulers and became legends.</e>
<cmt>ニュアンス</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the course of time feudal lords were gradually detached from the people and handed down their dominance as the absolute authority; however, some lords were better or so excellent that they were admired as wise rulers and became legends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>後に領主は国という形態が自己組織化の圧力もあって、次第に極大で各々の民衆の想像を絶するほどの政治的システムに変化する過程で取り込まれていったが、その多くは幾らかの自治権を保持し続け、地域の様々な産業に関与、地域の繁栄も困窮も領主の腹一つで決まる部分も根強く残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on as states gradually changed into the big political system beyond all imagination of each people, partly under pressure to systematize themselves, feudal lords were absorbed; however, many lords preserved part of their autonomy, and engaged in various industries in their region, so that there was a deep-seated aspect that prosperity or poverty in a region depended on a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As states gradually changed into bigger political systems beyond the average person&apos;s understanding, feudalism was disolved by the pressure to organize; however, many lords partially preserved their autonomies and engaged in various industries in their regions, so there was a deep-seated aspect that prosperity or poverty in a region depended upon a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>文章構成：直訳にしすぎているので、意味が伝わりにくい。語彙。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As states gradually changed into bigger political systems beyond the average person&apos;s understanding, feudalism was disolved by the pressure to organize; however, many lords partially preserved their autonomies and engaged in various industries in their regions, so there was a deep-seated aspect that prosperity or poverty in a region depended upon a feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>今日、様々な地域に残る市や県などの土地の区分けは、そういった領地の支配範囲の名残であることも多く、封建制から他の政治システムに移行した後でも、各々の政治システムの地域的な区分けに利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today divisions of land such as city and prefecture preserved in many regions are in many cases vestiges of control range of such territories, and even after feudalism was shifted to other political system, these are used for regional division in each political system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many cases, divisions of land such as cities and prefectures that remain in various regions today, are the vestiges of feudal territories in such areas, and even after feudalism shifted to other political systems, these were still used for regional division in each successive political system.</e>
<cmt>ニュアンス</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many cases, divisions of land such as cities and prefectures that remain in various regions today, are the vestiges of feudal territories in such areas, and even after feudalism shifted to other political systems, these were still used for regional division in each successive political system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>ヨーロッパにおける領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal Lord in Europe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal Lords in Europe</e>
<cmt>一人ではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal Lords in Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本における領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal Lord in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal Lords in Japan</e>
<cmt>一人ではないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal Lords in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>本家、領家、開発領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Head Family, Ryoke and Kaihatsu-ryoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Head Family, Ryoke, and Kaihatsu-ryoshu</e>
<cmt>Ryokeのあとのカンマ。あってもなくてもどちらでも良いようですが、カンマありで統一しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Head Family, Ryoke, and Kaihatsu-ryoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>開発領主（かいほつりょうしゅ）とは、平安時代中期以降、墾田開発をさかんにおこなって領地を確保した者の総称であり、元来は有力農民（田堵）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) is a generic name for those who secured a territory by extensive reclaimed land development after mid Heian period, and they were originally influential peasants (Tato).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-ryoshu (local nobles who actually developed the land) is a generic name for those who secured a territory by extensive reclaimed land development after the mid Heian period, and who were originally influential peasants (Tato).</e>
<cmt>冠詞忘れ。スペルミス。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu (local nobles who actually developed the land) is a generic name for those who secured a territory by extensive reclaimed land development after the mid Heian period, and who were originally influential peasants (Tato).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>彼らは国衙から田地の私有が認められたものの、その権利は危ういものであったため、開発した土地を荘園として受領層に寄進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although privatization of rice field was approved by kokuga (provincial government office compounds), their rights were very uncertain, so kaihatsu-ryoshu devoted their reclaimed land to Juryoso (career provincial official class) as shoen(manor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although privatization of rice fields was approved by kokuga (provincial government office compounds), the definition of rights was unclear; therefore, kaihatsu-ryoshu donated their reclaimed lands as shoen (private estates) to Juryoso (career provincial official class) as shoen (manors).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。語彙選択。口語的</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although privatization of rice fields was approved by kokuga (provincial government office compounds), the definition of rights was unclear; therefore, kaihatsu-ryoshu donated their reclaimed lands as shoen (private estates) to Juryoso (career provincial official class) as shoen (manors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>受領層は彼らを下司や公文などの荘官に任命し、その土地の実効支配を認める代わりに、一定の税収を受け取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juryoso appointed kaihatsu-ryoshu as shokan (lower ranked officer), and received regular tax yields in exchange for giving them effective control over the land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juryoso appointed kaihatsu-ryoshu as shokan (an officer governing a shoen (manor)) such as Geshi (lower ranked officer) and kumon (a local shoen official below the geshi in rank), and received regular tax yields in exchange for giving them effective control over the land.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juryoso appointed kaihatsu-ryoshu as shokan (an officer governing a shoen (manor)) such as Geshi (lower ranked officer) and kumon (a local shoen official below the geshi in rank), and received regular tax yields in exchange for giving them effective control over the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>こうして荘園を持つようになった受領層を領家と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus Juryoso who owned shoen is called ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juryoso who managed to own a shoen in such a manner is called ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor).</e>
<cmt>訳相違。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Juryoso who managed to own a shoen in such a manner is called ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>領家は次第に、国衙領を私領化するようになった国司と対立するようになり、自らの荘園をさらに権門勢家や大寺院に寄進し、保護を求める代わりに一定の税収を納めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoke became increasingly more opposed to kokushi (provincial governor) who privatized Kokugaryo, and donated their manors to the great and powerful or great temples to seek protection while paying regular tax yields in return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoke became increasingly more opposed to kokushi (provincial governors) who privatized Kokugaryo, and donated their manors to kenmon seika (powerful houses and influential families) or large temples to seek protection while paying regular tax yields in return.</e>
<cmt>語彙</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoke became increasingly more opposed to kokushi (provincial governors) who privatized Kokugaryo, and donated their manors to kenmon seika (powerful houses and influential families) or large temples to seek protection while paying regular tax yields in return.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>こうして荘園を集積した権門層や寺社を本家と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus influential families or temples and shrines who accumulated manors are called Honke (head family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influential families or temples and shrines who accumulated manors in such a manner are called Honke (head family).</e>
<cmt>意味相違：「こうして」は、副詞としてではなく、荘園へかかっている「このようにして」という解釈だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influential families or temples and shrines who accumulated manors in such a manner are called Honke (head family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このようにして、平安後期には本家、領家、開発領主の各層から成る領主層が形成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly in late Heian period feudal lords were composed of Honke, ryoke and Kaihatsu-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian period feudalism consisted of Honke, Ryoke, and Kaihatsu-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭。Accordinglyに繋がる文がありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Heian period feudalism consisted of Honke, Ryoke, and Kaihatsu-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、開発領主は、一方では在庁官人でもあり、国衙と結びつくことが有利な場合はそのまま国衙領にとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kaihatsu-ryoshu was also Zaichokanjin (provincial government officer), and they stayed in Kokugaryo when relation with kokuga was more profitable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaihatsu-ryoshu also concurrently performed as Zaichokanjin (provincial government officers) and they remained in the Kokugaryo position when the relation with kokuga was more profitable.</e>
<cmt>語彙選択：on the other handに追随する文章がないため、ここで使用することは不自然だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaihatsu-ryoshu also concurrently performed as Zaichokanjin (provincial government officers) and they remained in the Kokugaryo position when the relation with kokuga was more profitable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>武家政権のなかの領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal Lord in Military Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal Lords in the Military Government</e>
<cmt>冠詞、複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal Lords in the Military Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>地頭の領主化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jito to Become a Feudal Lord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jito as Feudal Lord</e>
<cmt>表現の変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usurping of the Power of the Feudal Lords by the Jito</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>平安中期以降、摂関政治にみられる藤原北家の官位独占などにより、中央政界からあぶれた下級貴族の多くが、地方へ下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After mid Heian period, because the Northern House of Fujiwara clan monopolized official rank by rule by regents and Imperial advisers, many lower-ranking nobles failed to get a job in national political arena, and went to the provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the mid Heian period, due to the monopoly of official ranks by Fujiwara-Hokke&apos;s (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan) regents, many lower-ranking nobles fell out of work in the national political arena and went to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>冠詞忘れ、意味不明瞭</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the mid Heian period, due to the monopoly of official ranks by Fujiwara-Hokke&apos;s (the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan) regents, many lower-ranking nobles fell out of work in the national political arena and went to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>開発領主はこれらの貴族と主従関係を結ぶことにより、荘園をめぐる紛争解決に役立てようとすることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Kaihastu-ryoshu established the relationship between lord and vassal with these nobles to facilitate a dispute resolution over manor, and armed themselves to become a samurai (warrior), while many lower-ranking nobles organized these warriors into armed groups and they were called Toryo (leader) of the groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many cases in which Kaihatsu-ryoshu established a master-servant relationship with these nobles to resolve disputes over manors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many cases in which Kaihatsu-ryoshu established a master-servant relationship with these nobles to resolve disputes over manors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>自らは武装して武士となり、また下級貴族のなかには、これらを武士団として組織して、その棟梁と呼ばれることも少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They sometimes armed themselves as samurai (warrior) while some lower-ranking nobles organized these warriors into armed groups; they were often called Toryo (leader) of the groups.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They sometimes armed themselves as samurai (warrior) while some lower-ranking nobles organized these warriors into armed groups; they were often called Toryo (leader) of the groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これら武家の棟梁のなかから、やがて奥州藤原氏、平氏政権が生まれ、12世紀末葉には鎌倉幕府の成立をみた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the course of time Oshu Fujiwara clan, Taira clan government appeared from these leaders of samurai family, and toward the end of the 12th century Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the course of time the Oshu Fujiwara clan and the Taira clan regime appeared from the leaders of samurai families, eventually forming the Kamakura bakufu (also known as Shogunate, a Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) at the end of the 12th century.</e>
<cmt>文章区切り</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the course of time the Oshu Fujiwara clan and the Taira clan regime appeared from the leaders of samurai families, eventually forming the Kamakura bakufu (also known as Shogunate, a Japanese feudal government headed by a Shogun) at the end of the 12th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>鎌倉時代では地頭の存在が知られるが、本来は地頭とは荘官の名称のひとつであり、文治の勅許の際にも、源行家・源義経追討を名目として荘園・公領から兵糧米を徴収する権限が与えられたにすぎず、土地の支配権を得たわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the Kamakura period jito (manager and lord of manor) is well-known, but it was originally one of the names of shokan, and at the Bunji imperial sanction jito was given only the power to collect provisions of rice for the army from manor and public land on the pretext of hunting down and killing MINAMOTO no Yukiie, Yoshitsune, and not the right to control land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existance of jito (manager and lord of manor) is well-known from the Kamakura period; however, jito was originally one of the names of shokan and was only given the authority to collect rice provisions for the army from manors and public lands under the pretext of hunting down and killing MINAMOTO no Yukiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune during the Bunji imperial sanction, not the authority to control lands.</e>
<cmt>As forが繋がらないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existance of jito (manager and lord of manor) is well-known from the Kamakura period; however, jito was originally one of the names of shokan and was only given the authority to collect rice provisions for the army from manors and public lands under the pretext of hunting down and killing MINAMOTO no Yukiie and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune during the Bunji imperial sanction, not the authority to control lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、その設置も当初は平氏没官領に限られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first disposing jito was limited to the public land that was originally private estates of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, installation of the jito position was limited to Heishi Mokkanryo (Land rights confiscated by Kamakura bakufu from the Taira family).</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペース。説明不明瞭。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, installation of the jito position was limited to Heishi Mokkanryo (Land rights confiscated by Kamakura bakufu from the Taira family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>しかしながら、幕府に忠誠を誓った武士すなわち御家人は、この地頭職の補任ないし安堵というかたちで論功行賞その他がおこなわれ、荘園・公領における年貢の徴収や土地の管理、治安の維持にあたって現地支配の実権をにぎった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Gokenin, warriors who pledged allegiance to bakufu, were granted honors in the form of appointment as Jitoshiki (manager and lord of manor), or guarantee by the shogunate of ownership of the inherited estate of samurai, and they held real power over local control taking charge of collecting nengu (land tax) from manor and public land, land management and maintaining public order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, warriors also known as gokenin, who pledged their allegiance to the bakufu, were granted with the honor of appointment or recognition as Jitoshiki (manager and lord of a manor) and took local control of the collection of nengu (annual tribute) from manors and public lands, property management, and maintaining public order.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。意味不明瞭。文章構成。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, warriors also known as gokenin, who pledged their allegiance to the bakufu, were granted with the honor of appointment or recognition as Jitoshiki (manager and lord of a manor) and took local control of the collection of nengu (annual tribute) from manors and public lands, property management, and maintaining public order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>鎌倉時代を通じて地頭による荘園侵略がさかんにおこなわれ、荘園領主との間に土地に関する紛争が激化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Throughout the Kamakura period, jito&apos;s invasion to manor occurred frequently, and a dispute over land with a lord of the manor intensified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Throughout the Kamakura period, jito&apos;s invasion to manors occurred frequently and disputes over land with manor lords intensified.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Throughout the Kamakura period, jito&apos;s invasion to manors occurred frequently and disputes over land with manor lords intensified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そこで荘園領主は、地頭請の契約を結んで、荘園管理の一切を地頭にまかせるかわりに年貢の納入を約束させたり、下地中分のとりきめをおこなって、荘園の土地そのものを領主と地頭で折半したりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore a lord of the manor made a contract of Jitouke to ensure receiving nengu payment in return for leaving the entire manor management to jito, while making an agreement of Shitaji chubun (physical division of land) to halve the land between feudal lords and jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lord of a manor then made a contract of Jitouke to ensure delivery of their nengu payment in return for leaving the entire manor management to jito, while making an agreement of Shitaji chubun (physical division of land) to halve the land between the feudal lords and the jito.</e>
<cmt>ダブルスペース。ニュアンス。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lord of a manor then made a contract of Jitouke to ensure delivery of their nengu payment in return for leaving the entire manor management to jito, while making an agreement of Shitaji chubun (physical division of land) to halve the land between the feudal lords and the jito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、この結果、荘園領主のねらいとはうらはらに、地頭の荘園支配はいっそう進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this accelerated jito&apos;s control over manor contrary to the aims of lord of the manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as a result, this accelerated jito&apos;s control over manors, which was contrary to the aim of the manor lords.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as a result, this accelerated jito&apos;s control over manors, which was contrary to the aim of the manor lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>守護の領主化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo to Become a Feudal Lord</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo as Feudal Lord</e>
<cmt>NC</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usurping of the Power of the Feudal Lords by the Shugo</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>守護は、地頭と同時期（1185年）に設置されたが、その性格はまったく異なっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo (provincial constable), disposed at the same time of jito (1185), held a totally different character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo (provincial constables) were installed at the same time as jito (1185), but they had a totally different role.</e>
<cmt>表現の変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo (provincial constables) were installed at the same time as jito (1185), but they had a totally different role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>地頭が徴税人として荘園ごとに置かれたのに対し、守護は幕府の地方官として令制国ごとに置かれ、国内の治安維持と大番役を柱とする大犯三箇条がその任務であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo was disposed in each province as the local official of the shogunate, and its duty involved Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping) mainly composed of maintenance of domestic security and Obanyaku (job to guard Kyoto), while jito was placed in each manor as tax collection officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo were placed in each province as the local official of the bakufu and their duties involved Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping), which was mainly composed of maintaining domestic security and Obanyaku (job to guard Kyoto), while jito were placed in each manor as tax collection officers.</e>
<cmt>disposeは少し不自然なため変更。複数形。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo were placed in each province as the local official of the bakufu and their duties involved Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping), which was mainly composed of maintaining domestic security and Obanyaku (job to guard Kyoto), while jito were placed in each manor as tax collection officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>14世紀前半に京都に室町幕府を建てた足利尊氏は、南北朝時代 (日本)の争乱を有利に進めるために従来の守護よりも強い権限を守護に与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA, who established the Muromachi bakufu in Kyoto in the first half of 14th century, gave stronger authority to shugo so that the conflict during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) was put forward to his advantage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA, who established the Muromachi bakufu in Kyoto in the first half of the 14th century, gave shugo a stronger authority to benefit himself from conflicts in the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) period.</e>
<cmt>表現の変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA, who established the Muromachi bakufu in Kyoto in the first half of the 14th century, gave shugo a stronger authority to benefit himself from conflicts in the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>鎌倉時代の大犯三箇条に加え、刈田狼藉を認め、また使節遵行権を守護に与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji gave shugo approval for Karita-rozeki (to reap rice illegally), and the right to pass a delegate the word, besides Taibon Sankajo in the kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji gave shugo approval for Karita-rozeki (to reap rice illegally) and the right to delegate judical authority to others besides Taibon Sankajo in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>使節遵行権：定訳のままだと文章がおかしいので、簡素化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji gave shugo approval for Karita-rozeki (to reap rice illegally) and the right to delegate judical authority to others besides Taibon Sankajo in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>さらに、半済や分国内の荘園管理を守護に任せる守護請などがおこなわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, other policies included hanzei: of nengu in manor that should be paid to feudal lords or nengu in Kokugaryo that should be paid to provincial governor, half of it might be given to local warriors as provisions of rice for the army while another half was given to feudal lords; and leaving manor management in provinces under control in shugo&apos;s hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, other policies were conducted, including hanzei and manor management in provinces, which shugo had control over.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, other policies were conducted, including hanzei and manor management in provinces, which shugo had control over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>半済とは、本来領主に納入すべき荘園の年貢や知行国主に納めるべき国衙領の年貢のうち、半分は領主に届けるものの、残り半分は兵糧米として現地の武士に与えてよいとするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The policy, hanzei, allowed ryoshu to split nengu in half, out of all nengu that was supposed to be given to feudal lords as manor nengu and to a provincial governor as Kokugaryo nengu, to deliver to both feudal lords as nengu and the local warriors as rice provisions when needed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The policy, hanzei, allowed ryoshu to split nengu in half, out of all nengu that was supposed to be given to feudal lords as manor nengu and to a provincial governor as Kokugaryo nengu, to deliver to both feudal lords as nengu and the local warriors as rice provisions when needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このような権限の強化を背景に、守護による地頭の被官化がさらに進行し、守護大名として軍事・警察権能だけでなく、経済的権能をも獲得して、分国内での領域的な支配を強化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supported by stronger authority, shugo encouraged increasing numbers of jito to become a vassal of a samurai family, and obtaining economic as well as military and police power as shugo daimyo (shugo that became daimyo), shugo strengthened territorial control over provinces under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supported by stronger authority, shugo encouraged increasing numbers of jito to become vassals of samurai families, and obtaining economic as well as military and police power as shugo daimyo (shugo that became daimyo), shugo strengthened territorial control over provinces under their control.</e>
<cmt>表現の変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supported by stronger authority, shugo encouraged increasing numbers of jito to become vassals of samurai families, and obtaining economic as well as military and police power as shugo daimyo (shugo that became daimyo), shugo strengthened territorial control over provinces under their control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>これを守護領国制と呼び、複数の国の守護に任じられて大勢力となる例もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called Shugo-ryogoku system, and some shugo daimyo exercised a lot of power by taking charge of shugo in more than one province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called the Shugo-ryogoku system, and some shugo daimyo exercised a lot of power by taking charge of shugo in more than one province.</e>
<cmt>意味相違</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called the Shugo-ryogoku system, and some shugo daimyo exercised a lot of power by taking charge of shugo in more than one province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、守護はもともと幕府権力を背景にして成長したものであり、もしも、この背景が何らかの理由で崩れる怖れのあるときは、守護自体の存立が危うくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, shugo originally grew up with the background of shogunate authority, and if this background might collapse for some reasons, the existence of shugo would be threatened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the shugo position originally grew out of the bakufu&apos;s authority and the existence of shugo could have been threatened if this background collapsed for some reason.</e>
<cmt>ニュアンス。grew up withはここではおかしいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shugo position originally grew out of the bakufu&apos;s authority and the existence of shugo could have been threatened if this background collapsed for some reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>守護が多くの場合邸宅を京内に構え、任地には守護代を派遣したのもそのためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was why many shugo took up residence in Kyoto, sending a deputy military governor to their post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was why many shugo owned their residences in Kyoto and sent Shugodai (deputy military governor) to their posts.</e>
<cmt>ニュアンス</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was why many shugo owned their residences in Kyoto and sent Shugodai (deputy military governor) to their posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、守護大名は、荘園内のさまざまな権利に基礎をおいており、荘園体制がくずれることは自らの経済基盤を失うことでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since shugo daimyo was founded on various rights within a manor, collapse of manor system meant loss of their economic base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the shugo daimyo position was founded on various rights in manors, collapse of the manor system meant the loss of their economic base.</e>
<cmt>表現の変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the shugo daimyo position was founded on various rights in manors, collapse of the manor system meant the loss of their economic base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>さらに、分国内の武士との主従関係も、所領そのものの授受ではなく軍事・警察における指揮権を通じての関係から始まったものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, relationship between lord and vassal with warriors within provinces under control arose from relationship through right of command in the military and police, not through the transfer of territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the master-servant relationship with warriors in the provinces did not grow out of territorial tranfers but of relations with commanding authorities in the military and the police.</e>
<cmt>表現の変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the master-servant relationship with warriors in the provinces did not grow out of territorial tranfers but of relations with commanding authorities in the military and the police.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>「守護の領主化」といってもそこには限界があり、室町時代が、南北朝の争乱後も常に中央、地方問わず波乱含みで政治的に不安定だった理由ともなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a limitation to shugo that became a feudal lord, and this was why in the Muromachi period political unrest continued with full of trouble both nationally and regionally after a disturbance of Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the limitations that did not allow shugo to become feudal lords was the disturbance of the Northern and Southern courts in the Muromachi period that led to the political instability and complications.</e>
<cmt>カッコ忘れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the limitations that did not allow shugo to become feudal lords was the disturbance of the Northern and Southern courts in the Muromachi period that led to the political instability and complications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>戦国時代以降の領主層</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal Lords after the Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal Lord Class after the Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal Lord Class after the Sengoku Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>荘園制がくずれ、地方の政治に一定の責任をもつという意味での領主層の誕生は戦国時代 (日本)にはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The appearance of feudal lords who bore responsibility for local politics after the collapse of manorialism started from the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appearance of the feudal lord class which bore responsibility for local politics after the collapse of manorialism started in the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>語彙</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appearance of the feudal lord class which bore responsibility for local politics after the collapse of manorialism started in the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>それは、守護大名とは異なり戦国大名が基本的には現地に居住したこと、また、それぞれ分国法と呼ばれる法令を公布し、通用させたこと、さらに、それぞれの大名が鉱山開発や農業用水の整備など殖産興業と富国強兵を目指したことに端的にあらわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is plainly shown in facts that unlike shugo daimyo, Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) basically lived locally, and individual lord enforced law in their own domain, spreading it, and that they aimed encouragement of new industry such as mine development and maintenance of agricultural water, and the policy of fortifying the country, strengthening the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This plainly shows the fact that unlike shugo daimyo, sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) basically lived locally, enforced the law bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain), and promoted new industry and fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military) including mine development as well as the maintenance of agricultural water.</e>
<cmt>語彙選択、直訳過ぎ、文章構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This plainly shows the fact that unlike shugo daimyo, sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) basically lived locally, enforced the law bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain), and promoted new industry and fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military) including mine development as well as the maintenance of agricultural water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>戦国時代には、大名を君主として土地そのものを媒介とする主従関係が発達し、これが江戸時代の地方知行制のもととなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, the relation between lord and vassal formed through land with daimyo as monarch developed, leading to Jigatachigyo system in Edo period (provision of lands from a feudal government to retainers as salary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sengoku period, the master-servant relationship, in which the daimyo ruled as monarch, was developed with land as its base; leading to the Jigatachigyo system in the Edo period (provision of lands from a feudal government to retainers as salary).</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭、冠詞わすれ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, the master-servant relationship, in which the daimyo ruled as monarch, was developed with land as its base; leading to the Jigatachigyo system in the Edo period (provision of lands from a feudal government to retainers as salary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>戦国時代を終息させた農民出身の豊臣秀吉は、1582年（天正10年）に太閤検地を開始し、1つの土地に数人のもの者が権利をもつ、複雑な土地所有関係を整理し、土地制度を一新させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI coming from peasants, who ended the Sengoku period, started Taiko-kenchi (nationwide land survey) in 1582, and improved complicated landholding relationship such as several persons holding a right to the same land, resulting in renewed land system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was a peasant, ended the Sengoku period and launched the Taiko-kenchi (nationwide land survey) in 1582 and improved upon complicated landholding relationships such as when several persons held rights to the same land, resulting in a renewed property system.</e>
<cmt>不自然、文章構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was a peasant, ended the Sengoku period and launched the Taiko-kenchi (nationwide land survey) in 1582 and improved upon complicated landholding relationships such as when several persons held rights to the same land, resulting in a renewed property system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ここに荘園制度を完全に崩壊し、石高制による近世的土地所有を実現し、農民には耕作権を認めるとともに年貢を納める義務を負わせるとともに、大名には所領をあてがうとともに、改易や国替を可能とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly the complete collapse of manorial system was followed by early-modern land holding based on Kokudaka system, and peasants assumed an obligation to pay nengu in return for the right to cultivate, while daimyo obtained territory in exchange for Kaieki (to forfeit rank of samurai and properties) and Kunigae (to transfer a daimyo from one fief to another).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the complete collapse of the manorial system, early-modern land holding based on the Kokudaka system was granted, and peasants assumed obligations to pay nengu in return for the right to cultivate, while the daimyo obtained territories in exchange for Kaieki (to forfeit rank of samurai and properties) and Kunigae (to transfer a daimyo from one fief to another).</e>
<cmt>原文意味不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the complete collapse of the manorial system, early-modern land holding based on the Kokudaka system was granted, and peasants assumed obligations to pay nengu in return for the right to cultivate, while the daimyo obtained territories in exchange for Kaieki (to forfeit rank of samurai and properties) and Kunigae (to transfer a daimyo from one fief to another).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="47">
<j>秀吉はまた、1588年に刀狩を実施して、百姓身分から帯刀権を奪い、武器使用を規制して兵農分離を完成させたいっぽうで、近世的な武士身分を創出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi conducted the disarmament of farmers in 1588, to deprive farming rank of the right to belt on a sword, and to impose control on weapons use, achieving heinobunri (separation of the warrior class from the soil) while creating early-modern samurai rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi also conducted the Sword Hunt in 1588 to deprive the farming rank the right to wear a sword and to restrict the use of weapons which completed the heinobunri (separation of the warrior class from the soil) while creating the early-modern samurai rank.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。不自然。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi also conducted the Sword Hunt in 1588 to deprive the farming rank the right to wear a sword and to restrict the use of weapons which completed the heinobunri (separation of the warrior class from the soil) while creating the early-modern samurai rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>武士は、苗字帯刀を許され、城下町に住まわせることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warriors were permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords, and was decided to live in a castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai were permitted to adopt a surname and to wear a pair of swords, and was requiered to live in a castle town.</e>
<cmt>よく知られている用語なので、Samuraiの方がいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai were permitted to adopt a surname and to wear a pair of swords, and was requiered to live in a castle town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これに前後して武士の間では家紋の研究が流行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About that time study on family crest became popular among warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, the study of family crests became popular among warriors.</e>
<cmt>語彙選択</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, the study of family crests became popular among warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>江戸時代の封建領主としては、江戸幕府の徳川将軍家をはじめとして、藩を単位とする1万石以上の大名、1万石未満だが御目見の特権を有する旗本、御目見の特権のない御家人江戸時代の御家人、また石高の高い大名の上級家臣があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal lords during the Edo period included the Tokugawa Shogunate Family in the Edo bakufu, daimyo with 10,000 koku crop yields and over with domain as a unit, hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu) who had less than 10,000 koku crop yields but enjoyed omemie privilege (audience with their lord), gokenin without omemie privilege and high-ranked vassal of daimyo with higher crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal ranks during the Edo period included the following: the Tokugawa Family in the Edo bakufu, daimyo with over 10,000 Goku crop yields (one domain per unit), hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu) who had less than 10,000 Goku crop yields but obtained the omemie privilege (privilege to have an audience with their lord), gokenin without the omemie privilege, and high-ranked vassal of daimyo with higher crop yields.</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal ranks during the Edo period included the following: the Tokugawa Family in the Edo bakufu, daimyo with over 10,000 Goku crop yields (one domain per unit), hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu) who had less than 10,000 Goku crop yields but obtained the omemie privilege (privilege to have an audience with their lord), gokenin without the omemie privilege, and high-ranked vassal of daimyo with higher crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>江戸初期には、大名は一定の土地を有力武士（給人）にあたえる地方知行制がとられていたが、給人が勝手に年貢を徴収することもあったため、大名は自ら治める支配領域を拡大し、1690年頃には俸禄制度が一般的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early Edo period, daimyo introduced Jigatachigyo system in which a certain land was granted to dominant Samurai (kyunin: upper class retainers); however, kyunin sometimes freely collected nengu, so that daimyo expanded the territory under their control, and about 1690 horoku system (salary) became common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, daimyo introduced the Jigatachigyo system in which property was granted to dominant Samurai (kyunin: upper class retainers); however, because kyunin sometimes freely collected nengu, daimyo expanded the territory under their control and the horoku system (salary) became a common system in around the 1690&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, daimyo introduced the Jigatachigyo system in which property was granted to dominant Samurai (kyunin: upper class retainers); however, because kyunin sometimes freely collected nengu, daimyo expanded the territory under their control and the horoku system (salary) became a common system in around the 1690&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>これ以後、知行制度をのこす藩の数は全体の17％となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, the number of domain adopting chigyo system (enfeoffment system) accounted for 17% of all domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, the numbers of domains who retained the chigyo system (enfeoffment system), accounted for 17% of all domains.</e>
<cmt>A lord cannot be a system of government. I have had to 意訳 this a bit to get it to make some sense in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, the numbers of domains who retained the chigyo system (enfeoffment system), accounted for 17% of all domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>その知行制度も、明治維新後の廃藩置県によって中央政府が任命した府知事・県令の派遣によって終わり、武士の特権も廃刀令と秩禄処分によって完全に廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, the central government abolished domains and appointed and sent prefectural governors, ending chigyo system, and privileges of warriors were fully abolished by the degree banning the wearing of swords and measures adopted by the government to abolish the hereditary stipends (chitsuroku) granted to nobility and samurai class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the abolition of domains and the employment of prefectural governance after the Meiji Restoration, the central government terminated the chigyo system, and Samurai privileges were fully abolished by Haitorei (the decree banning the wearing of swords) and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend).</e>
<cmt>&quot;lords were incorporated into the states as nobles&quot; doesn&apos;t really make much sense.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the abolition of domains and the employment of prefectural governance after the Meiji Restoration, the central government terminated the chigyo system, and Samurai privileges were fully abolished by Haitorei (the decree banning the wearing of swords) and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>インド・東南アジアにおける領主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal Lord in India and Southeast Asia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal Lords in India and Southeast Asia</e>
<cmt>複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal Lords in India and Southeast Asia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SnowBot(id:206320), Poohpooh817(id:157250), 水野白楓(id:22811), Wakkubox(id:30396), くっちゃめ(id:86793), Yanahan(id:2437), Mishika(id:276), Greenland4(id:114494), Wrightbus(id:13796), Yatobi(id:9686), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>