<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>造寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zojishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zojishi (Officials in Charge of Building Temples)</e>
<cmt>(Officials in Charge of Building Temples) を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zojishi (Officials in Charge of Building Temples)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>造寺司（ぞうじし）とは、奈良時代に官寺あるいはこれに准じた寺院を造営するために設置された令外官のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zojishi was an extra statutory office established in the Nara period for building a national temple or a temple corresponding to a national temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zojishi was an extra statutory office established in the Nara period for building national temples or those corresponding to national temples.</e>
<cmt>a national temple or a temple corresponding to a national temple をnational temples or those corresponding to national temples に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zojishi was an extra statutory office established in the Nara period for building national temples or those corresponding to national temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>寺院単位で設置され、施設の建築やそこで使われる用具の製造（経典の写経も含む）にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zojishi was established for each temple for building facilities and making Buddhist ceremony utensils used in the temple, including copying a sutra.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zojishi was established for each temple for building facilities and making Buddhist ceremony utensils used in the temple, including copying a sutra.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zojishi was established for each temple for building facilities and making Buddhist ceremony utensils used in the temple, including copying a sutra.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>最古の例は法興寺創建時において蘇我善徳（蘇我馬子の子）が任じられたとされ、飛鳥寺創建の際にも設置されていた（その施設内から大量の富本銭が発掘されている）が、本格的な設置は律令制導入以後とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zojishi was formally established after the ritsuryo system was installed, although--as the oldest example of Zojishi, SOGA no Zentoko, a son of SOGA no Umako, was appointed the official of Zojishi at the foundation of Hokoji temple, and Zojishi was also established at the foundation of Asukadera temple (a great number of ancient &apos;fuhonsen&apos; coins were found from the facilities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest example of Zojishi was SOGA no Zentoko (son of SOGA no Umako) appointed at the construction of Hoko-ji Temple, and Zojishi was also established at the construction of Asuka-dera Temple (a great number of Fuhonsen coins were found from the facilities); however, Zojishi was formally established after the introduction of the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest example of Zojishi was SOGA no Zentoko (son of SOGA no Umako) appointed at the construction of Hoko-ji Temple, and Zojishi was also established at the construction of Asuka-dera Temple (a great number of Fuhonsen coins were found from the facilities); however, Zojishi was formally established after the introduction of the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>本来こうした造営は木工寮などが担当することとなっていたが、鎮護国家の高まりによって造寺が盛んになり、更に遷都なども重なって木工寮への業務の集中を避けると同時に、権力や利権の集中を防ぐことも目的であったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction of temples was originally undertaken by the Carpentry Bureau and the like; however, as a lot of temple construction projects were planned to the accompaniment of development of the ideology of the protection of the state, and there was a capital removal project, Zojishi was established in order not only to prevent the Carpentry Bureau from overloaded but also to prevent authority and concessions from converging into the Carpentry Bureau.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction of temples was originally undertaken by the Bureau of Carpentry and so on; however, temple construction was flourished due to the growing of the nation protection thought, and furthermore, there was the transfer of the capital: Zojishi was established in order to prevent the Bureau of Carpentry from not only being overloaded but also concentration of the power, interests and rights.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was mainly the Bureau of Carpentry that was in charge of the construction of temples; however, in light of the temple construction boom that arose out a growing awareness of national protection and the transfer of the capital, the position of Zojishi was established in order to avoid such work being conducted exclusively by the Bureau of Carpentry, as well as to prevent the power and interests being concentrated in their hands.</e>
<cmt>全体的に書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>大規模な寺院造営を行う造寺司では四等官（長官・次官・判官・主典）が導入されて人員や官位相当は八省に准じる場合もあった他、下部の官司として「所」が設置されることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zojishi which undertook a large-scale construction installed the four-tiered hierarchy (kami, suke, jo, sakan) and followed the number of employees and &apos;government post&apos;-&apos;official rank&apos; equivalence system of the central government in some cases; besides, sometimes further installed a subordinate office &apos;Sho&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zojishi which undertook a large-scale construction installed the four-tiered hierarchy (kami, suke, jo, sakan) and followed the number of employees and official court rank equivalence system of the central government in some cases; besides, sometimes further installed a subordinate office &apos;Sho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>government post&apos;-&apos;official rank&apos; を official court rank に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zojishi which undertook a large-scale construction installed the four-tiered hierarchy (kami, suke, jo, sakan) and followed the number of employees and official court rank equivalence system of the central government in some cases; besides, sometimes further installed a subordinate office &apos;Sho&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>四等官の下には官人雑任・舎人、更には技術や熟練度によって位置づけられた大工・少工・長上・番上以下多数の工匠を抱えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the four-tiered hierarchy, Zojishi had kanjin-zonin, toneri, and further, a great number of kosho which were ranked according to their skills and mastery from top to downward, ookitakumi, sukunatakumi, chojoko, banjoko, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the four-tiered hierarchy, Zojishi had Kanjin Zonin (lower-ranking government official), toneri (servant) and further, a great number of artisan which were ranked according to their skills and mastery from top to downward, ookitakumi, sukunatakumi, chojoko, banjoko, and others.</e>
<cmt>kanjin-zonin, toneri をKanjin Zonin (lower-ranking government official) and toneri (servant) に修正しました。kosho を artisan に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the four-tiered hierarchy, Zojishi had Kanjin Zonin (lower-ranking government official), toneri (servant) and further, a great number of artisan which were ranked according to their skills and mastery from top to downward, ookitakumi, sukunatakumi, chojoko, banjoko, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>財源は封戸が主であったが、墾田永年私財法施行以後は初期荘園なども加えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A major revenue source for Zojishi was originally an ancient stipend system; after the Konden Einen Shizai Law was enacted, early manor and the like was added to the source.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A major revenue source for Zojishi was originally fuko (salary); however, after the Law Permitting Permanent Ownership of Newly Cultivated Land was enacted, early manor and the like was added to the source.</e>
<cmt>an ancient stipend system; after the Konden Einen Shizai Law をfuko (salary); however, after the Law Permitting Permanent Ownership of Newly Cultivated Land に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A major revenue source for Zojishi was originally fuko (salary); however, after the Law Permitting Permanent Ownership of Newly Cultivated Land was enacted, early manor and the like was added to the source.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>こうした財源は造寺司を経由して寺院の財源となるために、一面においては僧尼令や僧綱とは別の意味で寺院や三綱以下の僧侶を監督・統制する手段ともなり得たのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These revenue sources were, accordingly, for the temple through Zojishi; therefore, the sources could be used as a way of supervising and controlling monks at the positions with management roles and lower called &apos;sango&apos; as well as the temple in a sense, other than the regulations and the central monastic office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These revenue sources were, accordingly, for the temple through Zojishi; therefore, the sources could be used as a way of supervising and controlling priests at the positions with management roles and lower called &apos;sango&apos; as well as the temple in a sense, other than the regulations and the central monastic office.</e>
<cmt>monks を priests に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These revenue sources were, accordingly, for the temple through Zojishi; therefore, the sources could be used as a way of supervising and controlling priests at the positions with management roles and lower called &apos;sango&apos; as well as the temple in a sense, other than the regulations and the central monastic office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>だが、奈良時代末期の道鏡事件をきっかけとした仏教に対する規制強化や朝廷の財政難などによって造寺事業は縮小され、遅くても平安時代初期には殆どの造寺司は廃止され、財源や寺院の監督は別当や三綱に移ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hachiman Cult and the Dokyo incident occurred at the end of Nara period, Buddhism were regulated more tightly, on the other hand, the Imperial Court had financial pressure--Under that circumstances, temple construction had slowed down and most of Zojishi were abolished by the early Heian period; since then, temples and their revenue resources were supervised by betto and sango.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the tightening of regulations on Buddhism after the Dokyo Incident occurred at the end of the Nara period and the financial trouble of the Imperial Court, temple construction had slowed down and most of Zojishi were abolished by the early Heian period; since then, temples and their revenue resources were supervised by betto (head priest) and sango.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the tightening of regulations on Buddhism after the Dokyo Incident occurred at the end of the Nara period and the financial trouble of the Imperial Court, temple construction had slowed down and most of Zojishi were abolished by the early Heian period; since then, temples and their revenue resources were supervised by betto (head priest) and sango.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>主な造寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Zojishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Zojishi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Zojishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>奈良薬師寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Yakushiji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Yakushiji を Yakushi-ji に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>－造薬師寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoYakushjishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Nara Yakushi-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Nara Yakushi-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大安寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daianji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daian-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Daianji を Daian-ji に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daian-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>－造大安寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoDaianjishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Daian-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Daian-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東大寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Todaiji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Todaiji を Todai-ji に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>－造東大寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoTodaijishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Todai-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Todai-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>石山寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishiyamadera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishiyama-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>Ishiyamadera を Ishiyama-dera に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishiyama-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>－造石山寺所（造東大寺司の下部官司）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoIshiyamaderasho (subordinate office under ZoTodaijishi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* ZoIshiyamaderasho (subordinate office under Office of Todai-ji Temple Construction)</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* ZoIshiyamaderasho (subordinate office under Office of Todai-ji Temple Construction)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>下野薬師寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotsuke Yakushiji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotsuke Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Yakushiji を Yakushi-ji に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotsuke Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>－造下野薬師寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoShimotsukeYakushijishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Shimotsuke Yakushi-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Shimotsuke Yakushi-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>法華寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokkeji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokke-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Hokkeji を Hokke-ji Temple に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokke-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>－造法華寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoHokkejishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Hokke-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Hokke-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>西大寺 (奈良市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saidaiji (Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City)</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>－造西大寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoSaidaijishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Saidai-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Saidai-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>興福寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofukuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Kofukuji を Kofuku-ji Temple に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>造興福寺仏殿司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoKofukujibutsudenshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Constructing a Buddha Hall in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Constructing a Buddha Hall in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>西隆寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sairyuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sairyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Sairyuji を Sairyu-ji Temple に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sairyu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>－造西隆寺司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">* ZoSairyujishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">* Office of Sairyu-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">* Office of Sairyu-ji Temple Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Blue-comet(id:192801), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>