<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元勲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genkun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genkun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genkun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元勲（げんくん）は、倒幕・明治維新に絶大な功があり、明治の政治に重きを為した勤皇志士出身の政治家たちの一群のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genkun (the statesmen who contributed in Meiji Restoration) refer to the politicians who made considerable achievements in the overthrow of the Shogunate and the Meiji Restoration, who played an important roll in the Meiji Government, and who were from Kinno-no-Shishi (a royalist).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genkun (the statesmen who contributed to Meiji Restoration) refer to the politicians who made considerable achievements in the overthrow of the Shogunate and the Meiji Restoration, played an important role in the Meiji Government, and were from Kinno-no-Shishi (a royalist).</e>
<cmt>contributed in をcontributed toに変更、 roll をroleに変更、その他表現の見直ししました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genkun (the statesmen who contributed to Meiji Restoration) refer to the politicians who made considerable achievements in the overthrow of the Shogunate and the Meiji Restoration, played an important role in the Meiji Government, and were from Kinno-no-Shishi (a royalist).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>狭義では三条実美、岩倉具視、木戸孝允、西郷隆盛、大久保利通、伊藤博文、井上馨、山縣有朋、西園寺公望の九名を指している（ただし、下野期間が長く、西南戦争を引き起こした西郷隆盛に関しては、疑問符が付くかもしれない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In more narrow sense, it refers to 9 people: Sanetomi SANJO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO, Takamori SAIGO, Toshimichi OKUBO, Hirobumi ITO, Kaoru INOUE, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kinmochi SAIONJI (however, Takamori SAIGO who remained in retirement for long time and initiated Seinan War might come into question).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a narrow sense, it refers to 9 people: Sanetomi SANJO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO, Takamori SAIGO, Toshimichi OKUBO, Hirobumi ITO, Kaoru INOUE, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kinmochi SAIONJI (however, Takamori SAIGO, who retired from public life for a long time and initiated Seinan War, might come into question).</e>
<cmt>In more narrow senseを In a narrow senseに変更、remained in retirement for long timeをretired from public life for a long timeに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a narrow sense, it refers to 9 people: Sanetomi SANJO, Tomomi IWAKURA, Takayoshi KIDO, Takamori SAIGO, Toshimichi OKUBO, Hirobumi ITO, Kaoru INOUE, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kinmochi SAIONJI (however, Takamori SAIGO, who retired from public life for a long time and initiated Seinan War, might come into question).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>維新後を生き延びた薩長土肥出身者の場合、明治政府の共和制的な参議内閣制が確立された1871年（明治4年）6月25日以降、実質上の最高職である参議に採用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the republican-style Councillor-Cabinet System of the Meiji Government was established on June 25, 1871, Genkun who survived after the Restoration and who were from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa or Hizen, were assigned to be Sangi (a councillor) which was practically the highest position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the republican-style Councillor-Cabinet System of the Meiji Government was established on June 25, 1871, Genkun who survived the Restoration and were from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa or Hizen, were assigned to be Sangi (a councillor) which was practically the highest position.</e>
<cmt>who survived after the Restoration and who were from --&gt; who survived the Restoration and were from</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the republican-style Councillor-Cabinet System of the Meiji Government was established on June 25, 1871, Genkun who survived the Restoration and were from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa or Hizen, were assigned to be Sangi (a councillor) which was practically the highest position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>九名のうち、明治憲法下の世まで長生きしたのは後半の四名、伊藤博文、井上馨、山縣有朋、西園寺公望。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among 9 people, the latter four people lived long until the period under the Meiji Constitution: Hirobumi ITO, Kaoru INOUE, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the 9 people, the latter four people lived long until the period under the Meiji Constitution: Hirobumi ITO, Kaoru INOUE, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>Among 9 people --&gt; Among the 9 people</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the 9 people, the latter four people lived long until the period under the Meiji Constitution: Hirobumi ITO, Kaoru INOUE, Aritomo YAMAGATA and Kinmochi SAIONJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>既に維新の方向で社会が大きく変化していたため、元勲であること自体が希少価値と共に燻銀（いぶしぎん）的価値を持つこととなり、元勲という言葉が彼らの神がかり的な歴史と社会的重要性を示す言葉として新聞・書籍などで有名になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the society was already changed drastically toward the Restoration around that time, being Genkun became really rare and valuable, and thus the word Genkun became famous in the newspapers and books as a word indicating that they were historically and socially important like god.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「燻銀（いぶしぎん）的価値」はうまく表現できないので、「really valuable」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the society had already changed drastically toward the Restoration at that time, being Genkun became really rare and valuable, and thus the word Genkun became popular in the newspapers and books as a word indicating that they were historically and socially important like God.</e>
<cmt>表現の見直しをしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the society had already changed drastically toward the Restoration at that time, being Genkun became really rare and valuable, and thus the word Genkun became popular in the newspapers and books as a word indicating that they were historically and socially important like God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SeraphGood(id:144616), 木戸信長(id:23914), 代言人(id:33675), Skink(id:11281), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), Ikedat76(id:34218), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>