<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>准摂政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jun-Sessho (associate regent)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jun-Sessho (associate regent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jun-Sessho (associate regent)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>准摂政（じゅんせっしょう）は日本の律令制下において、関白または大臣が摂政に準じて国政を統べることを天皇から許されること、またはその権限を与えられた者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jun-Sessho indicates that Kanpaku (the top adviser to Emperor) or a minister is permitted, in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), by Emperor to govern the national politics like Sessho (a regent), or indicates the person who was given the right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jun-Sessho indicates that Kanpaku (the top adviser to Emperor) or a minister is permitted, in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), by the Emperor to govern the national politics like Sessho (a regent), or indicates the person who was given such a right.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jun-Sessho refers to the permission given by the Emperor to a Kanpaku (Chief Advisor to the Emperor) or minister to govern affairs of state as a Sesshu (regent) under the Ritsuryo system, and it also refers to the person who received this permission.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>令外官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中期から江戸時代後期まで全部で14例ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were 14 such examples between the middle of the Heian period and the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were 14 such examples between the middle of the Heian period and the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were 14 such examples between the middle of the Heian period and the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>准摂政が置かれる場合として、2つの型がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two types of timings when Jun-Sessho was placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two types of timings when Jun-Sessho was placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two ways that a Jun-Sessho could be appointed.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>第1の型は、幼少時に即位した天皇が元服するときである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first type of the timings was when an emperor who ascended the throne in his early years celebrated his coming of age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first type was when an emperor who ascended the throne in his early years celebrated his coming of age.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first type was when an emperor who ascended the throne in his early years celebrated his coming of age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>天皇が幼少であれば摂政が置かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When an emperor was young, a Sessho was placed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When an emperor was young, a Sessho was placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When an emperor was young, a Sessho was placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、天皇が元服すると摂政は政事を天皇に帰する復辟の上表を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the emperor celebrated his coming of age, the Sessho submitted a letter for returning the right of handling political affairs to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the emperor celebrated his coming of age, the Sessho submitted a letter for returning the right of handling political affairs to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the emperor celebrated his coming of age, the Sessho submitted a letter for returning the right of handling political affairs to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに対して天皇は摂政を解任して関白を補任し、同時に准摂政の宣旨を下して摂政と同じ権限を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the emperor dismissed the Sessho and appointed him to Kanpaku, and at the same time, proclaimed that he should become Jun-Sessho, giving him the same right as that of Sessho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the emperor dismissed the Sessho and appointed him to Kanpaku, and at the same time, proclaimed that he should become Jun-Sessho, giving him the same right as that of Sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the emperor dismissed the Sessho and appointed him to Kanpaku, and at the same time, proclaimed that he should become Jun-Sessho, giving him the same right as that of Sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平安時代後期、後一条天皇の元服後に摂政藤原頼通が摂政を辞任して関白に補任され、同時に准摂政の宣旨を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the Heian period, when Emperor Goichijo celebrated his coming of age, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi was dismissed his Sessho post and was appointed to Kanpaku, and it was proclaimed that he should become Jun-Sessho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the Heian period, when Emperor Goichijo celebrated his coming of age, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi was dismissed his Sessho post and was appointed to Kanpaku, and it was proclaimed that he should become Jun-Sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the Heian period, when Emperor Goichijo celebrated his coming of age, FUJIWARA no Yorimichi was dismissed his Sessho post and was appointed to Kanpaku, and it was proclaimed that he should become Jun-Sessho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>それが初例。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the first of such cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first of such cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first of such cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後、藤原師実（堀河天皇）・藤原忠通（崇徳天皇・近衛天皇）・藤原基房（高倉天皇）が関白に任ぜられたときに准摂政の宣旨を受けた（忠通は2度准摂政になっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, when FUJIWARA no Morozane (in relation to Emperor Horikawa), FUJIWARA no Tadamichi (in relation to Emperor Sutoku and to Emperor Konoe) and FUJIWARA no Motofusa (in relation to Emperor Takakura) were appointed to Kanpaku, it was proclaimed that they should become Jun-Sessho (Tadamichi became Jun-Sessho twice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, when FUJIWARA no Morozane (in relation to Emperor Horikawa), FUJIWARA no Tadamichi (in relation to Emperor Sutoku and to Emperor Konoe) and FUJIWARA no Motofusa (in relation to Emperor Takakura) were appointed to Kanpaku, it was proclaimed that they should become Jun-Sessho (Tadamichi became Jun-Sessho twice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, when FUJIWARA no Morozane (in relation to Emperor Horikawa), FUJIWARA no Tadamichi (in relation to Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Konoe) and FUJIWARA no Motofusa (in relation to Emperor) were appointed to Kanpaku, they were also proclaimed Jun-Sessho (Tadamichi became Jun-Sessho twice).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この場合における准摂政の任期は明確な規定はないものの天皇が15歳になる頃までとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the term of Jun-Sessho was not specified clearly but actually was by around the time when the emperor became 15 years old</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the term of Jun-Sessho was not specified clearly but actually was by around the time when the emperor became 15 years old</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though not clearly stipulated, in these cases the Jun-Sessho&apos;s term lasted until when the Emperor became around 15 years old.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>第2の型は、天皇が病気になったときである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second type of the timings was when an emperror became ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second type was when an emperror became ill.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second type was when an emperor became ill.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>天皇の不予（病気）の間、大臣または関白が摂政に準じて政務を見たものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this type, a minister or Kanpaku handled political affairs like Sessho, while an emperor was ill.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this type, a minister or Kanpaku handled political affairs like Sessho, while an emperor was ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these cases, the Kanpaku or the minister handled affairs of state like a Sessho while the emperor was ill.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>平安時代中期に冷泉天皇の不予の間、左大臣藤原実頼が准摂政となったのが初例。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the first of such cases that FUJIWARA no Saneyori, misnister of the left, became Jun-Sessho while Emperor Reizei was ill in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first of such cases that FUJIWARA no Saneyori, minister of the left, became Jun-Sessho while Emperor Reizei was ill during the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first example of such a case was when Minister of the Left FUJIWARA no Saneyori became Jun-Sessho while Emperor Reizei was ill during the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>次いで三条天皇の眼疾により左大臣藤原道長が准摂政になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then FUJIWARA no Michinaga, minister of the left, became Jun-Sessho while Emperor Sanjo suffered from eye illness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then FUJIWARA no Michinaga, minister of the left, became Jun-Sessho while Emperor Sanjo suffered from an illness of the eyes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then FUJIWARA no Michinaga, minister of the left, became Jun-Sessho while Emperor Sanjo suffered from an illness of the eyes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>特殊な例としては江戸時代の仁孝天皇が崩御した際、喪を秘して不予と称し、関白鷹司政通が道長の例に倣って准摂政となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There also was a special case described in the following: When Emperor Ninko died, Masamichi TAKATSUKASA, Kanpaku at that time, became Jun-Sessho following the example of Michinaga, saying that the emperor was ill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There also was a special case described in the following: When Emperor Ninko died, Masamichi TAKATSUKASA, Kanpaku at that time, became Jun-Sessho following the example of Michinaga, saying that the emperor was ill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also a special examples, such as when during the Edo period Emperor Ninko died and the kanpaku Masamichi TAKATSUKASA became Jun-Sessho, following Michinaga&apos;s example.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この場合における准摂政の任期は特に規定はなく、准摂政を置く理由の解除されるまでとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the term of Jun-Sessho was not set specifically but was terminated when the reason why Jun-Sessho had to be placed was removed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the term of Jun-Sessho was not set specifically but was terminated when the reason allowing the person in question to take up the position of Jun-Sessho no longer existed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these cases, the Jun-Sessho&apos;s term was not specifically stipulated, but came to end when the original reason for the appointment no longer applied.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>准摂政を任命するにあたっては、外記方と官（太政官）方から各1通ずつ宣旨が作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Jun-Sessho was to be appointed, an imperial decree was generated by each of Gekikata (the post for generating sentences to be presented to the emperor) and Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Jun-Sessho was to be appointed, an imperial decree was created by each of Gekikata (the post for generating sentences to be presented to the emperor) and Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a Jun-Sessho was to be appointed, an imperial decree was prepared by both the Gekikata (officials from the Secretaries&apos;s Office) and the Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>