<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>恩賞方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onshogata (office for the desk works of reward grants)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onshogata (office for administering reward grants)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onshogata (office for administering reward grants)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>恩賞方（おんしょうがた）とは、建武政府及び室町幕府に設置された恩賞業務を取り扱った部局。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onshogata was a department set up in the Kenmu Government and the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which took charge of desk works relating to the Onsho award (reward grants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onshogata was a department set up in the Kenmu Government and the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which took charge of desk work relating to administering Onsho award (reward grants).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onshogata was a department set up in the Kenmu Government and the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which took charge of desk work relating to administering Onsho award (reward grants).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>建武政府の恩賞方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onshogata in Kenmu Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onshogata in Kenmu Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onshogata in Kenmu Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>元弘3年（1333年）に鎌倉幕府を滅ぼした後醍醐天皇が、洞院実世・万里小路藤房・九条光経の3名を上卿として恩賞業務の審議・調査のために設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo, who had overthrown the Kamakura bakufu in 1333, set up the Onshogata for having the works of Onsho award deliberated and investigated, appointing three people, Saneyo TOIN, Fujifusa MADENOKO JI and Mitsutsune KUJO, as the Shokei (a high rank portfolio).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Daigo overthrew the Kamakura bakufu in 1333 and set up the Onshogata to deliberate, investigate, and administer Onsho awards, appointing three people, Saneyo TOIN, Fujifusa MADENOKO JI and Mitsutsune KUJO, as the Shokei (a high rank portfolio).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo overthrew the Kamakura bakufu in 1333 and set up the Onshogata to deliberate, investigate, and administer Onsho awards, appointing three people, Saneyo TOIN, Fujifusa MADENOKOJI and Mitsutsune KUJO, as the Shokei (a high rank portfolio).</e>
<cmt>人名の表記を修正スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>倒幕を実現させたと言えども、実際には直属の軍隊を持たない新政権にとって倒幕に参画した武士に恩賞を与えることは彼らの離反を防ぐ意味でも重要であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the new administration had overthrown the Kamakura bakufu, it was essential for the administration without its own military force to reward warriors, who participated in the coup to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu, so as to prevent them from plotting a breakaway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the new administration had overthrown the Kamakura bakufu, it was essential for the administration without its own military force, to reward warriors, who participated in the coup to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu, so as to prevent them from plotting a breakaway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the new administration had overthrown the Kamakura bakufu, it was essential for the administration without its own military force, to reward warriors, who participated in the coup to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu, so as to prevent them from plotting a breakaway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、恩賞方は審議機関でしかなく最終決定権を後醍醐天皇の親裁としたこと、天皇が恩賞問題の処理を恩賞方に一元化せずに（主に側近の要望を受けて）恩賞方の意見と違った綸旨を下したこと、そのために訴訟も頻発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, regarding the Onshogata as a mere deliberative organ, the ultimate decision-making authority was delegated to Emperor Go-Daigo, and granting the requests from his aides, the emperor did not leave the management of Onsho award to the Onshogata alone and gave orders differed from the Onshogata, with the result that lawsuits were frequently raised.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, regarding the Onshogata as a mere deliberative organ, the ultimate decision-making authority was delegated to Emperor Go-Daigo, and granting the requests from his aides, the emperor did not leave the management of Onsho awards to the Onshogata alone, but gave orders differing from the Onshogata, with the result that lawsuits were frequently raised.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, regarding the Onshogata as a mere deliberative organ, the ultimate decision-making authority was delegated to Emperor Godaigo, and granting the requests from his aides, the emperor did not leave the management of Onsho awards to the Onshogata alone, but gave orders differing from the Onshogata, with the result that lawsuits were frequently raised.</e>
<cmt>人名の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>更に訴訟機関が整備されていなかったために恩賞方に訴訟事務が殺到したことによって恩賞業務は混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With no organs to deal with the lawsuits, the Onshogata was inundated with works related to the lawsuits, and in turn, the works of Onsho award were confused.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With no organs to deal with the lawsuits, the Onshogata was inundated with work related to the lawsuits, and in turn, the work of awarding Onsho became confusing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With no organs to deal with the lawsuits, the Onshogata was inundated with work related to the lawsuits, and in turn, the work of awarding Onsho became confusing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため、翌建武_(日本)元年（1334年）に入ると、全国を4地域に分けてそれぞれに頭人を任命する四番制を導入。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1334, the administration introduced a system called Yon-ban-sei, under which the whole country was grouped into four regions and a tonin (the director) was appointed for each.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1334, the administration introduced a system called Yon-ban-sei, under which the whole country was grouped into four regions and a tonin (the director) was appointed for each.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1334, the administration introduced a system called Yon-ban-sei, under which the whole country was grouped into four regions and a tonin (the director) was appointed for each.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>吉田定房（東海道・東山道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadafusa YOSHIDA (tonin for the Tokaido and Tosando regions)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadafusa YOSHIDA (tonin for the Tokaido and Tosando regions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadafusa YOSHIDA (tonin for the Tokaido and Tosando regions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>九条光経（北陸道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsutsune KUJO (tonin for the Hokurikudo region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsutsune KUJO (tonin for the Hokurikudo region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsutsune KUJO (tonin for the Hokurikudo region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>万里小路藤房（畿内・山陽道・山陰道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI (tonin for the Kinai, Sanyodo and Sanindo regions)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI (tonin for the Kinai, Sanyodo and Sanindo regions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujifusa MADENOKOJI (tonin for the Kinai, Sanyodo and Sanindo regions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>四条隆資（南海道・西海道）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO (tonin for the Nankaido and Saikaido regions)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasuke SHIJO (tonin for the Nankaido and Saikaido regions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO (tonin for the Nankaido and Saikaido regions)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>を頭人に任命、楠木正成や名和長年を寄人に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">were appointed to the tonin, and Masashige KUSUNOKI and Nagatoshi NAWA were appointed to the Yoryudo (officer of the government).</e>
<cmt>寄人の読みですが辞書では「よりゅうど」となっていたため、これを用いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">were appointed to the tonin, and Masashige KUSUNOKI and Nagatoshi NAWA were appointed to the Yoryudo (officer of the government).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">were appointed to the tonin, and Masashige KUSUNOKI and Nagatoshi NAWA were appointed to the Yoryudo (officer of the government).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>彼らは雑訴決断所の頭人や寄人を兼務していたため、両者の連携が期待された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concurrently holding the posts of tonin and Yoryudo of Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government to file lawsuits), they were expected to cooperate with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrently holding the posts of tonin and Yoryudo of Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government to file lawsuits), they were expected to cooperate with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concurrently holding the posts of tonin and Yoryudo of Zasso-Ketsudansho (agency of Kenmu government to file lawsuits), they were expected to cooperate with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、足利尊氏とその周辺は恩賞方入りを辞退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA and his fellows, however, declined appointments to the posts in the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA and his fellows, however, declined appointments to the posts in the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA and his fellows, however, declined appointments to the posts in the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一方雑訴決断所の寄人になっていた旧幕府の法曹官僚も恩賞方からは排除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, a judicial bureaucrat from the overthrown bakufu, a Yoryudo of Zasso-Ketsudansho, was excluded from the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, a judicial bureaucrat from the overthrown bakufu, a Yoryudo of Zasso-Ketsudansho, was excluded from the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, a judicial bureaucrat from the overthrown bakufu, a Yoryudo of Zasso-Ketsudansho, was excluded from the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>更に後醍醐天皇による親裁に対して苦言を申し入れた万里小路藤房の要請を天皇が拒絶すると、藤房は出奔して政府から去ってしまったために恩賞方は機能停止に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Go-Daigo refused Fujifusa MADENOKOJI, who gave a candid advice to the emperor about his ultimate decision, Fujifusa absconded and quitted the government, and as a result the Onshogata stopped function.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Go-Daigo refused Fujifusa MADENOKOJI, who gave candid advice to the emperor about his ultimate decision, Fujifusa absconded and quit the government, and as a result the Onshogata stopped functing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo refused Fujifusa MADENOKOJI, who gave candid advice to the emperor about his ultimate decision, Fujifusa absconded and quit the government, and as a result the Onshogata stopped functioning.</e>
<cmt>人名の表記を修正スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>やがて伝奏の合議体である伝奏衆が恩賞業務を行うようになったが、間もなく建武政府は崩壊を迎えることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the denso-shu (a consultation form of denso (job to relay messages of court&apos;s people to Emperor) took charge of the works of Onsho award shortly, it was no longer before the Kenmu Government collapsed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the denso-shu (a consultation form of denso - the job to relay messages of court&apos;s people to the Emperor) took charge of the work of awarding Onsho shortly, it was not long before the Kenmu Government collapsed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the denso-shu (a consultation form of denso - the job to relay messages of court&apos;s people to the Emperor) took charge of the work of awarding Onsho shortly, it was not long before the Kenmu Government collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>室町幕府の恩賞方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Onshogata in the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Onshogata in the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Onshogata in the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>建武3年（延元元年/1336年）、建武政府を倒した足利尊氏は直ちに後の室町幕府となる新政府の樹立を図り、足利将軍家の家宰である執事高師直を頭人とする恩賞方（恩沢方（おんたくがた）とも）を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had overthrown the Kenmu government, aiming to establish a new government, which later became the Muromachi bakufu, set up the Onshogata (also called Ontakugata) by appointing KO no Moronao as the tonin, who was a high minister of the Ashikaga shogun family and Takauji&apos;s steward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had overthrown the Kenmu government, aiming to establish a new government, which later became the Muromachi bakufu, set up the Onshogata (also called Ontakugata) by appointing KO no Moronao as the tonin, who was a high minister of the Ashikaga shogun family and Takauji&apos;s steward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1336, Takauji ASHIKAGA, who had overthrown the Kenmu government, aiming to establish a new government, which later became the Muromachi bakufu, set up the Onshogata (also called Ontakugata) by appointing KO no Moronao as the tonin, who was a high minister of the Ashikaga shogun family and Takauji&apos;s steward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>尊氏は建武政府の恩賞方の失敗に学んで引き続き最終決定権は尊氏の親裁としたものの、恩賞方は恩賞の申請受理・恩賞地の選定・恩賞替地の沙汰（恩賞地が他者の所領であった場合の新旧領主間の裁判）・恩賞下文の紛失安堵などの広範な業務を任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thinking back on the failure of the Kenmu government, Takauji trusted the Onshogata a wide spectrum of works including acceptance of an application for the Onsho award, selection of a land given as a reward, instructions on a land change (in the trial held between new and old loads, if the land in question belonged to the old load) and Funshitsu Ando (work of providing authorization for a substitute document on the Onsho award), while he left the ultimate decision-making authority to himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thinking back on the failure of the Kenmu government, Takauji entrusted to the Onshogata a wide spectrum of work including acceptance of applications for the Onsho award, selection of land given as a reward, instructions on a land change (in the trial held between new and old lords, if the land in question belonged to the old lord) and Funshitsu Ando (providing authorization for a substitute document concerning the awarded Onsho), while he left the ultimate decision-making authority to himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thinking back on the failure of the Kenmu government, Takauji entrusted to the Onshogata a wide spectrum of work including acceptance of applications for the Onsho award, selection of land given as a reward, instructions on a land change (in the trial held between new and old lords, if the land in question belonged to the old lord) and Funshitsu Ando (providing authorization for a substitute document concerning the awarded Onsho), while he left the ultimate decision-making authority to himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>尊氏は幕府成立後は民政のみならず軍権の一部まで弟の足利直義に譲って、半ば象徴的存在にもなっていたが、恩賞方の業務のみは自らが把握して親裁を行い、必要があれば審議にも参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the establishment of bakufu, Takauji transferred not only civil administration but also a part of authority as a commander to his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA to be a symbolic person, however, concerning the Onshogata, Takauji made an ultimate decision by understanding the works and participated in discussions when necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the establishment of the bakufu, Takauji transferred not only the civil administration, but also partial authority as a commander to his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA for him to be a symbolic person, however, concerning the Onshogata, Takauji made the ultimate decision by understanding the work and participated in discussions when necessary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the establishment of the bakufu, Takauji transferred not only the civil administration, but also partial authority as a commander to his younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA for him to be a symbolic person, however, concerning the Onshogata, Takauji made the ultimate decision by understanding the work and participated in discussions when necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これを「御恩沙汰（ごおんさた）」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ultimate decision made by Takauji was called &quot;Goonsata&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「これを」が何を指すのかわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ultimate decision made by Takauji was called &quot;Goonsata&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ultimate decision made by Takauji was called &apos;Goonsata.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>皮肉にも観応の擾乱によって尊氏と直義が対立して直義とこれを支持する幕府官僚の多くが離反した時、室町幕府の機構の多くが機能停止に陥ったが、恩賞方のみは尊氏派の官僚がそのまま残留したためにこれを免れたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a confrontation between Takauji and Tadayoshi in the Kanno Disturbance forced Tadayoshi and many bureaucrats supporting Tadayoshi to break away, many organizations in the Muromachi bakufu stopped function, but ironically, only the Onshogata could maintain its function because bureaucrats supporting Takauji had occupied the posts in the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a confrontation between Takauji and Tadayoshi in the Kanno Disturbance forced Tadayoshi and many bureaucrats supporting Tadayoshi to break away, many organizations in the Muromachi bakufu stopped functioning, but ironically, only the Onshogata was able to maintain its function because bureaucrats supporting Takauji had occupied the posts in the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a confrontation between Takauji and Tadayoshi in the Kanno Disturbance forced Tadayoshi and many bureaucrats supporting Tadayoshi to break away, many organizations in the Muromachi bakufu stopped functioning, but ironically, only the Onshogata was able to maintain its function because bureaucrats supporting Takauji had occupied the posts in the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>幕府組織の再建を主導した後の2代征夷大将軍足利義詮は恩賞方を拠点として再建を図り、後にここで御前沙汰と呼ばれる会議を主宰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, who took the initiative in reconstructing the bakufu and later became the second Seii taishogun, designed the reconstruction work with setting a strategic base in the Onshogata, and later presided over a council called Gozensata at the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, who took the initiative in reconstructing the bakufu and later became the second Seii taishogun, designed the reconstruction work with setting a strategic base in the Onshogata, and later presided over a council called Gozensata at the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, who took the initiative in reconstructing the bakufu and later became the second Seii taishogun, designed the reconstruction work with setting a strategic base in the Onshogata, and later presided over a council called Gozensata at the Onshogata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>後に御前沙汰は義詮の後継者である足利義満によって恩賞以外の重要事項も審議するとともに、将軍の個人的な人選によって選ばれた重臣・側近による事実上の最高諮問機関へと変化していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, Gozensata was changed by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the successor of Yoshiakira, into the virtual highest advisory panel controlled by the chief vassals and close advisers chosen by the shogun personally, which discussed important matters besides works of Onsho award.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, Gozensata was changed by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the successor of Yoshiakira, into the virtual highest advisory panel controlled by the chief vassals and close advisers personally chosen by the shogun, which discussed important matters besides administering Onsho awards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, Gozensata was changed by Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the successor of Yoshiakira, into the virtual highest advisory panel controlled by the chief vassals and close advisers personally chosen by the shogun, which discussed important matters besides administering Onsho awards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>特に恩賞方などで事務を担当していた法曹官僚である奉行人が次第に奉行衆（右筆方）として幕政に深く関わってくると、本来恩賞方の下級官僚でしかない彼らが将軍の意向で御前沙汰の一員に加えられて恩賞方衆と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the bugyonin (magistrate, originally took charge in office works in the Onshogata) gradually took part in the administration as the bugyoshu (group of magistrate, also called yuhitsukata), despite their low ranks in the Onshogata, they were included among the members of Gozensata in accordance with the shogun&apos;s instruction and called Onshogatashu (members of the Onshogata).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the bugyonin (magistrate, who originally took charge of the office work in the Onshogata) gradually took part in administration as the bugyoshu (group of magistrate, also called yuhitsukata), despite their low ranking in the Onshogata, they were included among the members of Gozensata in accordance with the shogun&apos;s instruction and called Onshogatashu (members of the Onshogata).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the bugyonin (magistrate, who originally took charge of the office work in the Onshogata) gradually took part in administration as the bugyoshu (group of magistrate, also called yuhitsukata), despite their low ranking in the Onshogata, they were included among the members of Gozensata in accordance with the shogun&apos;s instruction and called Onshogatashu (members of the Onshogata).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに足利義教になると、御前沙汰そのものが恩賞方から離れて幕府中枢に置かれるようになり、恩賞方衆も「御前沙汰衆・御前奉行人」などと呼ばれるのが一般的となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the rule of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, separated from the Onshogata, the Gozensata was incorporated in the center of the bakufu, and the Onshogatashu was generally called &quot;Gozensatashu&quot; or &quot;Gozenbugyonin&quot; (bugyonin with qualification for attending the Gozensata).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the rule of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, separated from the Onshogata, the Gozensata was incorporated in the center of the bakufu, and the Onshogatashu was generally called &quot;Gozensatashu&quot; or &quot;Gozenbugyonin&quot; (bugyonin with qualifications for attending the Gozensata).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the rule of Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, separated from the Onshogata, the Gozensata was incorporated in the center of the bakufu, and the Onshogatashu was generally called &apos;Gozensatashu&apos; or &apos;Gozenbugyonin&apos; (bugyonin with qualifications for attending the Gozensata).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、恩賞方も実際には御前沙汰のための事務機関となり、御前沙汰衆の予備軍とも言える奉行人達が詰める様になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Onshogata was also changed into an office for the Gozensata in reality and occupied by the bugyonin, the reserve members of Gozensatashu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Onshogata was also changed into an office for the Gozensata in reality and occupied by the bugyonin, the reserve members of Gozensatashu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Onshogata was also changed into an office for the Gozensata in reality and occupied by the bugyonin, the reserve members of Gozensatashu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>このため、別個に奉行衆の中から「別奉行」として恩賞奉行あるいは御恩奉行などが任命されて恩賞業務を置いたと推定されているが、詳細は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that Onshobugyo or Goonbugyo (bugyonin who distributes the rewards) was separately appointed as the &quot;Betsubugyo (bugyo with special missions)&quot; from among the members of bugyoshu to engage in the works of Onsho award, however, details are uncertain.</e>
<cmt>「恩賞業務を置く」という表現は不明でしたので、「恩賞業務を行う」と判断しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was presumed that Onshobugyo or Goonbugyo (bugyonin who distributes the rewards), was separately appointed as the &quot;Betsubugyo (bugyo with a special mission)&quot; from among the members of bugyoshu to engage in the work of awarding Onsho, however, the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was presumed that Onshobugyo or Goonbugyo (bugyonin who distributes the rewards), was separately appointed as the &apos;Betsubugyo&apos; (bugyo with a special mission) from among the members of bugyoshu to engage in the work of awarding Onsho, however, the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&apos; の位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Wushi(id:107127), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>