<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>兵衛府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyoefu&quot; (the Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyoefu&quot; (the Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyoefu (the Middle Palace Guards)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>兵衛府（ひょうえふ）とは、律令制における官司。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Middle Palace Guards was an administrative office in the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Middle Palace Guard was an administrative office in the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Middle Palace Guard was an administrative office in the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>左兵衛府と右兵衛府の二つが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Middle Palace Guards consisted of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Middle Palace Guard consisted of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Middle Palace Guard consisted of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>長は兵衛督 （左兵衛督・右兵衛督）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyoe no kami&quot; (Captain) headed the Left and the Right Divisions of Middle Palace Guards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyoe no kami&quot; (Captain) headed the Left and the Right Divisions of Middle Palace Guard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyoe no kami (Captain) headed the Left and the Right Divisions of Middle Palace Guard.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>(左右)近衛府、(左右)衛門府とあわせて「六衛府」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called &quot;Rokuefu&quot; (the Six Palace Guards) along with the Left and the Right Divisions of Inner Palace Guards and the Left and the Right Divisions of Outer Palace Guards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called &quot;Rokuefu&quot; (the Six Palace Guards) along with the Left and the Right Divisions of Inner Palace Guard and the Left and the Right Divisions of Outer Palace Guard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called &quot;Rokuefu&quot; (the Six Palace Guards) along with the Left and the Right Divisions of Inner Palace Guard and the Left and the Right Divisions of Outer Palace Guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>和訓にて「つはもののとねりのつかさ」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Japanese name was &quot;Tsuwamono no toneri no tsukasa.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Japanese name was &quot;Tsuwamono no toneri no tsukasa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Japanese name was &apos;Tsuwamono no toneri no tsukasa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>唐名は武衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Chinese name was &quot;Buei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Chinese name was &quot;Buei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Chinese name was Buei.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>兵衛とは、天皇やその家族にの近侍・護衛のために国造の子弟から選抜された舎人の機能を強化・拡充する形で天武天皇時代に成立したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Middle Palace Guards was created during the time of Emperor Tenmu to attend or guard the Emperor and his family by enhancing and expanding a function of valets chosen from children of the regional administrators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Middle Palace Guard was created during the reign of Emperor Tenmu to attend to or guard the Emperor and his family by enhancing and expanding the function of valets chosen from children of the regional administrators.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Middle Palace Guard was created during the reign of Emperor Tenmu to attend to or guard the Emperor and his family by enhancing and expanding the function of valets chosen from children of the regional administrators.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大宝律令成立後に左右に分立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Taiho Code was established, it split into the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Taiho Code was established, it split into Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Taiho Code was established, it split into Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>養老律令において内部官職名の変更が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yoro Code, the names of the internal posts were changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yoro Code, the names of the internal posts were changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yoro Code, the names of the internal posts were changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>藤原仲麻呂政権下の天平宝字2年（758年）に虎賁衛（こほんえい）と改称したが、6年後の仲麻呂の没落とともに旧に復された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the rule of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, it was renamed &quot;Kohonei&quot; in 758, but six years later, the former name was restored with the fall of Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the rule of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, it was renamed &quot;Kohonei&quot; in 758, but six years later, the former name was restored with the fall of Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the rule of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, it was renamed &quot;Kohonei&quot; in 758, but six years later, the former name was restored with the fall of Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に地方において国造・郡司層が没落すると、新設の近衛府に主力の座を奪われて規模も縮小されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the decline of the regional administrators and locally appointed officials in provinces, the Middle Palace Guards gave the reins of power to the newly established Inner Palace Guards, and subsequently became downsized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the decline of the regional administrators and locally appointed officials in the provinces, the Middle Palace Guard gave the reins of power to the newly established Inner Palace Guard, and subsequently became downsized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the decline of the regional administrators and locally appointed officials in the provinces, the Middle Palace Guard gave the reins of power to the newly established Inner Palace Guard, and subsequently became downsized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内部官職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Internal posts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Internal posts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Internal posts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>兵衛督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyoe no kami&quot; (Captain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyoe no kami&quot; (Captain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyoe no kami (Captain)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>左右に各1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>四等官のうちの長官「カミ」に相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain corresponded to &quot;Kami&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan&quot; (administrative officials divided into four ranks: Kami, Suke, Jo, and Sakan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain corresponded to &quot;Kami&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan&quot; (administrative officials divided into four ranks: Kami, Suke, Jo, and Sakan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain corresponded to &apos;Kami&apos; out of the Shitokan (administrative officials divided into four ranks: Kami, Suke, Jo, and Sakan)</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>権官はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no substitute post for Captain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no substitute post for Captain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no substitute post for Captain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>令制では従五位上相当の官職であったが、延暦18年（799年）4月27日に従四位下相当に改訂された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system, it was a position corresponding to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, but was upgraded to Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade on 27 April 799.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo system, it was a position corresponding to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade, but was upgraded to Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade on 27 April 799.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system, it was a position corresponding to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade), but was upgraded to Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) on June 9, 799.</e>
<cmt>Jugoinojo, Jushiinoge補足グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>大宝律令においては「率」（読み方は同じ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A written form was &quot;率&quot; in the Taiho Code (the reading was the same).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A written form was &quot;率&quot; in the Taiho Code (the reading was the same).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A written form was &apos;率&apos; in the Taiho Code (the reading was the same).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>中納言・参議（位階）としては二位・三位）との兼官が多く、また左右衛門督を加えた計4名のうちの1人が検非違使別当を兼ねるのが慣例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain often served concurrently as Middle Counselor or Royal Advisor (Second Rank or Third Rank of the court rank), and traditionally, one out of four Captains, including Captains of the Left and the Right Divisions of Outer Palace Guards, served as the head of the Office of Police and Judicial Chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Captain often served concurrently as Middle Counselor or Royal Advisor (Second Rank or Third Court Rank), and traditionally, one out of four Captains, including Captains of the Left and the Right Divisions of the Outer Palace Guard, served as the head of the Police and Judicial Chief offices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Captain often served concurrently as Middle Counselor or Royal Advisor (Second Rank or Third Court Rank), and traditionally, one out of four Captains, including Captains of the Left and the Right Divisions of the Outer Palace Guard, served as the head of the Police and Judicial Chief offices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>とは言え、実態としてはかなり広範な任用例が見られ、兼官としては大弁や中弁、あるいは近衛府との兼務例が見られる他、五位からの抜擢の例もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were extensive cases of appointment; Captain also held the post of Major Controller, or Middle Controller, and served concurrently at the Inner Palace Guards; Captain was sometimes chosen out of those who were of Fifth Rank.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were extensive appointments; the Captain also held the post of Major Controller, or Middle Controller, and served concurrently in the Inner Palace Guard; a Captain was sometimes chosen amongst those who were of Fifth Rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were extensive appointments; the Captain also held the post of Major Controller, or Middle Controller, and served concurrently in the Inner Palace Guard; a Captain was sometimes chosen amongst those who were of Fifth Rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>非参議や散位である二・三位クラスの公卿に職を宛がうための官職でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Captain was such a post that was provided for court nobles of Second or Third Rank including non-Royal Advisor or &quot;Sani&quot; (a person who had the court rank but no official post).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Captain was such a post that was provided for court nobles of Second or Third Rank including non-Royal Advisor or &quot;Sani&quot; (a person who had the court rank but no official post).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Captain was such a post that was provided for court nobles of Second or Third Rank including non-Royal Advisor or Sani (a person who had the court rank but no official post).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>佐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Suke&quot; (Assistant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Suke&quot; (Assistant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suke (Assistant)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>左右に各1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>四等官のうちの次官「スケ」に相当するが、権官あり（権佐）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponded to &quot;Suke&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan,&quot; and there was a substitute post for Assistant (Gon no suke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It corresponded to &quot;Suke&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan,&quot; and there was a substitute post for Assistant (Gon no suke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It corresponded to &apos;Suke&apos; out of the Shitokan, and there was a substitute post for Assistant (Gon no suke).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>令制では正六位下相当の官職であったが、延暦18年4月27日に従五位上相当に改訂された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system, it was a post corresponding to Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade, but was upgraded to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade on 27 April 799.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo system, it was a post corresponding to Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade, but was upgraded to Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade on 27 April 799.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system, it was a post corresponding to Shorokuinoge (Senior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade), but was upgraded to Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade) on June 9, 799.</e>
<cmt>Shorokuinoge Jugoinojo補足グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>大宝律令においては「翼」（読み方は同じ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A written form was &quot;翼&quot; in the Taiho Code (the reading was the same).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A written form was &quot;翼&quot; in the Taiho Code (the reading was the same).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A written form was &apos;翼&apos; in the Taiho Code (the reading was the same).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>少納言との兼務が多い他、馬頭から近衛府に転じる際に空席がない場合において、暫くの間この職を拝命して中将の空席を待つ事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assistant often served concurrently as Lesser Counselor, and when there was no vacant post for a person who was transferred from the Bureau of Horses to the Inner Palace Guards, he was temporarily appointed Assistant to wait for the post of Middle Captain being available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An assistant often served concurrently as Lesser Counselor, and when there was no vacant post for a person who was transferred from the Bureau of Horses to the Inner Palace Guard, he was temporarily appointed assistant to wait the availability of the post of Middle Captain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An assistant often served concurrently as Lesser Counselor, and when there was no vacant post for a person who was transferred from the Bureau of Horses to the Inner Palace Guard, he was temporarily appointed assistant to wait the availability of the post of Middle Captain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>もっとも著名なのは右兵衛権佐に任じられた源頼朝である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most prominent figure that was appointed &quot;Uhyoe gon no suke&quot; (a substitute post for Assistant in the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) was MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most prominent figure that was appointed &quot;Uhyoe gon no suke&quot; (a substitute post for an assistant in the Right Division of Middle Palace Guard) was MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most prominent figure that was appointed Uhyoe gon no suke (a substitute post for an assistant in the Right Division of Middle Palace Guard) was MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>平治の乱の際にこの職に任じられた頼朝は20年に及ぶ流人生活（厳密にはこの期間は官職を剥奪されているが）を経て平家を倒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoritomo was appointed to this post at the Heiji Disturbance, he spent his life as an exile for as long as twenty years. (He was, to be precise, deprived of his official post during that time.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoritomo was appointed to this post at the Heiji Disturbance, he spent his life as an exile for as long as twenty years. (He was deprived of his official post during that time.)</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoritomo was appointed to this post at the Heiji Disturbance, he spent his life as an exile for as long as twenty years (he was deprived of his official post during that time) and defeated the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>原文修正and defeaded the Taira family補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>文治5年（1189年）に権大納言に任じられるまでの30年間（公式には計10年）この官にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retained this post for three decades (officially ten years in total) till he was appointed &quot;Gon Dainagon&quot; (Subustitute Major Councelor) in 1189.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retained this post for three decades (officially ten years in total) till he was appointed &quot;Gon Dainagon&quot; (Subustitute Major Councelor) in 1189.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retained this post for three decades (officially ten years in total) till he was appointed Gon Dainagon (Substitute Major Councilor) in 1189.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>このため、頼朝に仕えた御家人達は頼朝に敬意を払って「佐殿（すけどの）」と呼んだのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, Yoritomo&apos;s vassals respectfully called him &quot;Suke dono.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, Yoritomo&apos;s vassals respectfully called him &quot;Suke dono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, Yoritomo&apos;s vassals respectfully called him &apos;Suke dono.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>尉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jo&quot; (Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jo&quot; (Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jo (Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="32">
<j>正七位上相当の「大尉」と従七位上相当の「少尉」があり、四等官のうちの判官「ジョウ」に相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two posts: &quot;Senior Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Senior Seventh Rank, Upper Grade and &quot;Junior Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Junior Seventh Rank, Upper Grade; and they were equivalent to &quot;Jo&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two posts: &quot;Senior Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Senior Seventh Rank, Upper Grade and &quot;Junior Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Junior Seventh Rank, Upper Grade; and they were equivalent to &quot;Jo&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two posts: &apos;Senior Lieutenant&apos; corresponding to Shoshichiinojo (Senior Seventh Rank, Upper Grade) and &apos;Junior Lieutenant&apos; corresponding to Jushichiinojo (Junior Seventh Rank, Upper Grade); and they were equivalent to &apos;Jo&apos; out of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;Shoshichiinojo Jushichiinojo補足&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>当初はともに左右各1名であったが延暦18年4月27日に少尉が左右各2名制となり、久安4年（1148年）には大尉・少尉ともに一気に左右各20名に増加された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, one person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions, but two persons were assigned to Junior Lieutenant of the Left and the Right Divisions on 27 April 799, and then in 1148, the number of Senior and Junior Lieutenants dramatically increased to twenty in each Division.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, one person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions, but two persons were assigned to Junior Lieutenant of the Left and the Right Divisions on 27 April 799, and then in 1148, the number of Senior and Junior Lieutenants dramatically increased to twenty in each Division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, one person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions, but two persons were assigned to Junior Lieutenant of the Left and the Right Divisions on June 9, 799, and then in 1148, the number of Senior and Junior Lieutenants dramatically increased to twenty in each Division.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>更に保元3年（1158年）には更に25名に増員されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1158, the number of them further increased to twenty five.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1158, the number further increased to twenty five.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1158, the number further increased to twenty five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>志</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sakan&quot; (Assistant Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sakan&quot; (Assistant Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakan (Assistant Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>従八位上相当の「大志」と従八位下相当の「少志」があり、四等官のうちの主典「サカン」に相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two posts: &quot;Senior Assistant Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade and &quot;Junior Assistant Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Junior Eighth Rank, Lower Grade; they were equivalent to &quot;Sakan&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two posts: &quot;Senior Assistant Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade and &quot;Junior Assistant Lieutenant&quot; corresponding to Junior Eighth Rank, Lower Grade; they were equivalent to &quot;Sakan&quot; out of &quot;the Shitokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two posts: &apos;Senior Assistant Lieutenant&apos; corresponding to Juhachiinojo (Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade) and &apos;Junior Assistant Lieutenant&apos; corresponding to Juhachiinoge (Junior Eighth Rank, Lower Grade); they were equivalent to &apos;Sakan&apos; out of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;Juhachiinojo Juhachiinoge補足&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>左右ともされぞれ各1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>延暦18年4月27日に少志が左右各2名制となり、更に大志は正八位上相当、少志は従八位上相当に改められたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 27 April 799, two persons were assigned to Junior Assistnat Lieutenant of the Left and the Right Divisions, and the rank of Senior Assistant Lieutenant was upgraded to Senior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade; the rank of Junior Assistant Lieutenant was also upgraded to Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 27 April 799, two persons were assigned to Junior Assistnat Lieutenant of the Left and the Right Divisions, and the rank of Senior Assistant Lieutenant was upgraded to Senior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade; the rank of Junior Assistant Lieutenant was also upgraded to Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 9, 799, two persons were assigned to Junior Assistant Lieutenant of the Left and the Right Divisions, and the rank of Senior Assistant Lieutenant was upgraded to Shohachiinojo (Senior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade); the rank of Junior Assistant Lieutenant was also upgraded to Juhachiinojo (Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦Shohachiinojo Juhachiinojo補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="39">
<j>医師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ishi 医師&quot; (Physician)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ishi 医師&quot; (Physician)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishi (Physician)</e>
<cmt>医師削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>左右各1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>従八位上相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It corresponded to Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They corresponded to Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They corresponded to Juhachiinojo (Junior Eighth Rank, Upper Grade).</e>
<cmt>Juhachiinojo補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>養老5年（721年）設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was created in 721.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was created in 721.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was created in 721.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="43">
<j>番長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bancho 番長&quot; (low-level executive official)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bancho 番長&quot; (low-level executive official)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bancho (low-level executive official)</e>
<cmt>番長削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>左右各4名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four persons were assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four persons each were assigned to the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>the削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>兵衛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hyoe 兵衛&quot; (palace guards)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hyoe 兵衛&quot; (palace guards)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyoe (palace guards)</e>
<cmt>兵衛削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="46">
<j>左右各400名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">400 people were assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">400 people each were assigned to the Left and the Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">400 people each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.</e>
<cmt>他セルに合わせthe削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>六位以下八位以上の嫡子で21歳以上の者及び令制国の郡司の子弟で弓馬に巧みな者を国司が推薦して選抜した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provincial governors recommended and selected &quot;Hyoe 兵衛&quot; from the following: children of those who were of Eighth Rank upwards to Sixth Rank downwards at the age of twenty-one and above; and children of locally appointed officials under the Ritsuryo system who were good at archery and horseback riding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provincial governors recommended and selected &quot;Hyoe 兵衛&quot; from the following: children of those who were of Eighth Rank upwards to Sixth Rank downwards at the age of twenty-one and above; and children of locally appointed officials under the Ritsuryo system who were good at archery and horseback riding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provincial governors recommended and selected Hyoe from the following: children of those who were of Eighth Rank upwards to Sixth Rank downwards at the age of twenty-one and above; and children of locally appointed officials under the Ritsuryo system who were good at archery and horseback riding.</e>
<cmt>兵衛削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>大同_(日本)3年（808年）には左右各300名に、更に寛平3年（891年）に左右各200名に削減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 808, the number of &quot;Hyoe&quot; was reduced to 300 in the Left and the Right Division, and then to 200 in 891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 808, the number of &quot;Hyoe&quot; was reduced to 300 in the Left and Right Divisions, and then to 200 in 891.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 808, the number of Hyoe was reduced to 300 in the Left and Right Divisions, and then to 200 in 891.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="49">
<j>その他にも次の役職があったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were other posts as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were other posts as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were other posts as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>直丁（左右各2名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jikicho 直丁&quot; (Two persons were assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jikicho 直丁&quot; (Two persons each were assigned to the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jikicho (Two persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>直丁削除→定訳不明&quot;削除the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>廝庁（左右各4名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shicho 厮庁&quot; (Four persons were assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shicho 厮庁&quot; (Four persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shicho (Four persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>厮庁削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>府生（兵部省からの出向、人数等不詳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fusho 府生&quot; (low-level official) (temporarily assigned from the Ministry of Military; the number of the personnel was unknown)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fusho 府生&quot; (low-level official) (temporarily assigned from the Ministry of the Military; the number of personnel was unknown)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusho (low-level official) (temporarily assigned from the Ministry of the Military; the number of personnel was unknown)</e>
<cmt>府生削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>案主（左右各1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Anju 案主&quot; (secretary) (One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Anju 案主&quot; (secretary) (One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anju (secretary) (One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>案主削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>府掌（左右各1名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Fusho 府掌&quot; (One person was assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Fusho 府掌&quot; (One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusho (One person each was assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>府掌削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>吉上（人数等不詳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kichijo 吉上&quot; (subordinate official) (The number of personnel was unknown.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kichijo 吉上&quot; (subordinate official) (The number of personnel was unknown.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kichijo (subordinate official) (The number of personnel was unknown.)</e>
<cmt>吉上削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>使部（左右各30名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tsukaibe 使部&quot; (handyman) (Thirty persons were assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tsukaibe 使部&quot; (handyman) (Thirty persons each were assigned to the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukaibe (handyman) (Thirty persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>使部削除→定訳不明&quot;削除the削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>駕輿丁（左右各50名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kayocho 駕輿丁&quot; (palanquin bearer) (Fifty persons were assigned to each of the Left and the Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kayocho 駕輿丁&quot; (palanquin bearer) (Fifty persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayocho (palanquin bearer) (Fifty persons each were assigned to the Left and Right Divisions.)</e>
<cmt>駕輿丁削除→定訳不明&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>所管範囲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The extent of its purview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The extent of its purview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The extent of its purview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>大内裏のうち、宣陽門・承明門・陰明門・玄輝門より外側で建春門・建礼門・宜秋門・朔平門の内側を担当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Outer Palace Precincts, the assigned areas included the following: the outside of the Senyo, the Jomei, the Inmei, and the Genki Gates; and the inside of the Kenshun, the Kenrei, the Gishu, and the Sakuhei Gates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Outer Palace Precincts, the assigned areas included the following: the outside of the Senyo, the Jomei, the Inmei, and the Genki Gates; and the inside of the Kenshun, the Kenrei, the Gishu, and the Sakuhei Gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Outer Palace Precincts, the assigned areas included the following: the outside of the Senyo, the Jomei, the Inmei, and the Genki Gates; and the inside of the Kenshun, the Kenrei, the Gishu, and the Sakuhei Gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>天皇の護衛や内裏内における夜間の宿直も担当するなど六衛府の中でも最も宮廷の中枢部を担当した言わば「親衛隊」的な役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with other Six Palace Guards, the Middle Palace Guards was especially assigned to the important tasks, such as escorting the Emperor or keeping night watch in the Imperial Palace; thus, it virtually functined as &quot;bodyguards.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with the other Six Palace Guards, the Middle Palace Guard was assigned especially to important tasks, such as escorting the Emperor or keeping a night watch in the Imperial Palace so, it functioned virtually as a &quot;bodyguard.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with the other Six Palace Guards, the Middle Palace Guard was assigned especially to important tasks, such as escorting the Emperor or keeping a night watch in the Imperial Palace so, it functioned virtually as a &apos;bodyguard.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、民衆から選ばれた衛士が反抗して天皇及び内裏を攻撃しないように監視する役目も担っていたともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also monitored the guardsmen selected from the common people so that they could not rebel against the Emperor or attack on the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also monitored guardsmen selected from the common people so that they could not rebel against the Emperor or attack the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also monitored guardsmen selected from the common people so that they could not rebel against the Emperor or attack the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>行幸などの際には行幸の行列。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It protected the Emperor&apos;s procession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It protected the Emperor&apos;s procession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It protected the Emperor&apos;s procession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、夜間の京内の巡検も担当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also made a night patrol over the city of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also made night patrols around the city of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also made night patrols around the city of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kawai(id:5634), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>