<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大政所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omandokoro (大政所)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omandokoro (大政所)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omandokoro</e>
<cmt>(大政所)削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大政所（おおまんどころ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omandokoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omandokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omandokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の貴族社会において、摂政・関白の母親に対して、天皇の宣旨によって贈られた呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese aristocracy society, omandokoro is a title given to a mother based on an emperor&apos;s direction when her child was serving as the Sessho (a title of regent given to one who is named to assist an emperor when the emperor is still a child, or before the coming of age or female) or the Kanmpaku (a title of regent who assists an adult emperor.)</e>
<cmt>http://www.japan-101.com/history/sessho_and_kampaku.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Japanese aristocracy society, omandokoro is a title given to a mother based on an emperor&apos;s direction when her child was serving as the Sessho (the title of a regent given to who is named to assist an emperor when the emperor is still a child, or before coming of age, or when a female, or the Kanmpaku - the title of a regent who assists an adult emperor.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Japanese aristocracy society, omandokoro is a title given to a mother based on an emperor&apos;s direction when her child was serving as the Sessho (the title of a regent given to who is named to assist an emperor when the emperor is still a child, or before coming of age, or when a female), or the Kanpaku - the title of a regent who assists an adult emperor.</e>
<cmt>)補足スペース削除スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「大北政所」の略称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an abbreviation of okitanomandokoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an abbreviation of okitanomandokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an abbreviation of okitanomandokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>一般的には、豊臣秀吉の母、仲（なか）を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, omandokoro refers to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s mother, Naka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually, omandokoro refers to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s mother, Naka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually, omandokoro refers to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s mother, Naka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>本項で詳述。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More detailed information will be provided in this section.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More detailed information will be provided in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More detailed information will be provided in this section.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>仲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>大政所（おおまんどころ、永正10年（1513年） - 天正20年7月22日 (旧暦)（1592年8月29日））は、戦国時代 (日本)・安土桃山時代の女性。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omandokoro was a woman who lived from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan) through the Azuchi-Momoyama Period (1513 - August 29, 1592.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omandokoro was a woman who lived from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States - Japan) through the Azuchi-Momoyama Period (1513 - August 29, 1592.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omandokoro was a woman who lived from the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States - Japan) through the Azuchi-Momoyama Period (1513 - August 29, 1592).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>本名を仲（なか）といい、豊臣秀吉・豊臣秀長・日秀・朝日姫の生母である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her formal name was Naka, and she gave birth to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Nisshu and Asahihime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her formal name was Naka, and she gave birth to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Nisshu and Asahihime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her formal name was Naka, and she gave birth to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Nisshu and Asahihime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大政所というのは本来「大北政所」の略で、摂政・関白職にある者の母親への尊称であるが、現代では彼女一人を特定して指すことが主である（従一位）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omandokoro is an abbreviation of an original term &apos;okitamandokoro&apos;, and a honorific title given to a mother with a child serving as the sessho or kampaku, and in a modern era, it is common to refer to a particular woman (Juichii (Junior First Rank.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omandokoro is the abbreviation of the original term &apos;okitamandokoro,&apos; and a honorific title given to a mother with a child serving as the sessho or kampaku, and in a modern era, it is common to refer to a particular woman (Juichii - Junior First Rank.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omandokoro is the abbreviation of the original term &apos;okitamandokoro,&apos; and a honorific title given to a mother with a child serving as the sessho or kanpaku, and in a modern era, it is common to refer her (Juichii - Junior First Rank).</e>
<cmt>to a particular woman→her</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>永正10年（1513年）、尾張国愛知郡 (愛知県)御器所村に鍛冶屋を営み、武家でもあった関兼員の娘として生まれたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1513, she was born as a daughter of Kanesada SEKI (関兼員) who was running a forge shop and also in samurai class in Gokiso-mura, Aichi-gun, Owari Province (Aichi Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1513, she was born as the daughter of Kanesada SEKI (関兼員) who was running a forging shop and also in the samurai class in Gokiso-mura, Aichi-gun, Owari Province (Aichi Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1513, she was born as the daughter of Kanesada SEKI who was running a forging shop and also in the samurai class in Gokiso-mura, Aichi-gun, Owari Province (Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>(関兼員) 削除→読み方不明ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>関氏は刀鍛冶を業とする一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seki clan was a family who was engaged in the business of forging swards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seki clan was a family who was engaged in the business of forging swords.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seki clan was a family who was engaged in the business of forging swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>実際の生年は永正13年（1516年）とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also thought she was born 1516.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also thought she was born 1516.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also thought she was born 1516.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>織田信秀の足軽大将を勤めた木下弥右衛門（木下昌吉・中村弥助）のもとに嫁ぎ、日秀院と秀吉を生む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She got married with Yaemon KINOSHITA (Shokichi KINOSHITA and Yasuke NAKAMURA) who was serving as the head of conscripted foot-soldiers for Nobuhide ODA and gave birth to Nisshu-in and Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She got married with Yaemon KINOSHITA (Shokichi KINOSHITA and Yasuke NAKAMURA) who was serving as the head of conscripted foot-soldiers for Nobuhide ODA and she gave birth to Nisshu-in and Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She got married with Yaemon KINOSHITA (Shokichi KINOSHITA and Yasuke NAKAMURA) who was serving as the head of conscripted foot-soldiers for Nobuhide ODA and she gave birth to Nisshu-in and Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、夫がある戦で戦死すると（実際は病没）、信秀の同朋衆・水野昌盛（竹阿弥）と再婚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, after her husband died in the war (actually, died of a disease), she got married with Masamori MIZUNO (Chikuami) who was serving as doboshu (government post) for Hidenobu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, after her husband died in the war (actually, died of a disease), she got married with Masamori MIZUNO (Chikuami) who was serving as doboshu (government post) for Hidenobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, after her husband died in the war (actually, died of a disease), she got married with Masamori MIZUNO (Chikuami) who was serving as doboshu (government post) for Hidenobu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その間に、秀長と朝日姫を儲けた（秀長と朝日姫の父については弥右衛門説と竹阿弥説の両方がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She gave birth to Hidenaga and Asahihime during that period of time (Father of Hidenaga and Asahihime is believed to be Yaemon or Chikuami.)</e>
<cmt>「その間に」がどの期間を指しているのか定かでありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She gave birth to Hidenaga and Asahihime during that period of time (Father of Hidenaga and Asahihime is believed to be Yaemon or Chikuami.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She gave birth to Hidenaga and Asahihime during that period of time (Father of Hidenaga and Asahihime is believed to be Yaemon or Chikuami.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>晩年の大政所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later years of Omandokoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later years of Omandokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later years of Omandokoro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天正13年（1585年）、秀吉が関白になったのに際し大政所と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the promotion of Hideyoshi to the Kampaku in 1585, she began to be called Omandokoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the promotion of Hideyoshi to the Kampaku in 1585, she was called Omandokoro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the promotion of Hideyoshi to the Kanpaku in 1585, she was called Omandokoro.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>翌天正14年（1586年）、秀吉が徳川家康に上洛を勧めるがうまくいかなかったため、朝日姫を正室として、大政所を人質として三河国岡崎に送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, Hideyoshi advised Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to carry out the joraku (going to Kyoto to seize power), but it was unsuccessful, and he sent Asahihime for his legal wife and Omandokoro as a hostage to Okazaki, Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1586, Hideyoshi advised Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to carry out the joraku (going to Kyoto to seize power), but it was unsuccessful, and he sent Asahihime for his legal wife and Omandokoro as a hostage to Okazaki, Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, Hideyoshi advised Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to carry out the joraku (going to Kyoto to seize power), but it was unsuccessful, and he sent Asahihime for his legal wife and Omandokoro as a hostage to Okazaki, Mikawa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その結果、家康は上洛に応じたため、大政所は約1ヶ月で大阪に戻ることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Ieyasu agreed to the joraku, and Omandokoro could return to Osaka in a month or so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Ieyasu agreed to the joraku, and Omandokoro was able to return to Osaka in a month or so.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Ieyasu agreed to the joraku, and Omandokoro was able to return to Osaka in a month or so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>秀吉は長浜城主となった時に母を城に迎えているが、終生母を大事にしたことは有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi called his mother to live and stay in the castle when he became the owner of Nagahama Castle, and it is well known that he always cared about his mother for the rest of her life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi called for his mother to live and stay in the castle when he became the owner of Nagahama Castle, and it is well known that he always cared about his mother throughout the rest of her life.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi called for his mother to live and stay in the castle when he became the owner of Nagahama-jo Castle, and it is well known that he always cared about his mother throughout the rest of her life.</e>
<cmt>-jo補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、嫁である高台院との仲も非常に良かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omandokoro got along with Kodai-in very much, Hideyoshi&apos;s bride.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omandokoro got along with Kodai-in very well, who was Hideyoshi&apos;s bride.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omandokoro got along with Kodai-in very well, who was Hideyoshi&apos;s bride.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さまざまな逸話から、彼女が賢明な女性であったことが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to various tales, she was a wise and smart woman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to various tales, she was a wise and smart woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to various tales, she was a wise and smart woman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>子の朝日姫・秀長に先立たれた後、天正20年（1592年）に聚楽第で没した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After she sent off the preceding death of her children, Asahihime and Hidenaga, she died in 1592 at Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence in Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After she the preceding death of her children, Asahihime and Hidenaga, she died in 1592 at Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence in Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the preceding death of her children, Asahihime and Hidenaga, she died in 1592 at Jurakudai (Hideyoshi&apos;s residence in Kyoto.)</e>
<cmt>she 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>齢80（もしくは77）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She was eighty (or, seventy seven) year old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She was eighty (or, seventy seven) year old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She was eighty (or, seventy seven) year old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 M-sho-gun(id:88956), Ghchgch(id:189500), たね(id:10372), Cprobot(id:97843), Charenji(id:7908), 行動で挽回するしかない(id:31799), Hatsune(id:26654), A6M4(id:14155), YurikBot(id:18605), 海衛士(id:19229), Kanjy(id:36859), Knua(id:66861), ユッケ(id:53351), 越中掾(id:149423), 歴史研究家(id:108842), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>