<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御供衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御供衆（おともしゅう）とは、足利尊氏の挙兵にお供をして鎌倉から上洛した武将たちのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomoshu is an attendant group of busho (military commanders) who raised their army and attended the Shogun Takauji ASHIKAGA to go up to the ancient capital Kyoto when the shogun raised his army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomoshu were a group of busho (military commander) attendants who proceeded to the ancient capital of Kyoto from Kamakura and devoted themselves to raising Shogun Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Kamakura&quot; information to coincide with the Japanese; fixed grammar to not sound redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Otomoshu&quot; were a group of busho (military commander) attendants who proceeded to the ancient capital of Kyoto from Kamakura and devoted themselves to raising Shogun Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他 2009/6/29）の指示により、Otomoshu にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>お供をした武将の子孫はこの称号を世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of the group succeeded the title Otomoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Descendants of the busho who served as attendants in this group succeeded the title of Otomoshu.</e>
<cmt>added clarification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Descendants of the busho who served as attendants in this group succeeded the title of Otomoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>室町幕府での御供衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomoshu in Muromachi Shogunate (Japanese feudal government headed by Shogun)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomoshu within the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government head by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;shogunate&quot; to &quot;bakufu&quot; to be consistent with the word list</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomoshu within the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government head by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室町幕府の役職ではなく席次を示していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi Shogunate the title Otomoshu did not indicate the position but the order of precedence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather than being an official post in the Muromachi bakufu, the term was used to indicate class standing.</e>
<cmt>&quot;order of precendence&quot; seems too ambiguous to me, so I changed it to &quot;class standing&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather than being an official post in the Muromachi bakufu, the term was used to indicate class standing.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>さらに、大名（守護）の家格を区別していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it also differentiated the family status of Daimyo or Shugo (feudal Japanese territorial lord.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthmore, Otomoshu also differentiated from the family status of Daimyo or Shugo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt>differentiated→differentiated from; it→Otomoshu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Otomoshu also differentiated from the family status of Daimyo or Shugo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt>Furthmore を Furthermore に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>御供衆のほかにも、御相伴衆、国持衆、外様衆などがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Otomoshu there were several titles such as Oshobanshu (officials who accompanied Shogun), Kunimochishu (one of honorary terms for local governors who were in hereditary vassalage to the Shogun) and Tozamashu (military clans who were not a member the Shogun&apos;s family or did not originally support the Shogun.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Otomoshu, there were several titles such as Oshobanshu (officials who accompanied the Shogun), Kunimochishu (one of many honorary terms used for locals governors who were heredity vassals of the Shogun) and Tozamashu (military clans who were not related to the Shogun&apos;s family or did not originally support the Shogun).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Otomoshu, there were several titles such as Oshobanshu (officials who accompanied the shogun), Kunimochishu (one of many honorary terms used for local governors who were heredity vassals of the shogun) and Tozamashu (military clans who were not related to the shogun&apos;s family or did not originally support the shogun).</e>
<cmt>locals governors を local governors に修正しました。Shogun を shogun に修正しました（※）。※ここでは特定の将軍のタイトルとしてではなく、普通名詞的に使用されているものと思われます。よって、統一リスト（「用語統一」2009/06/29「将軍」）の指示により、文頭を小文字に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>主な御供衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the main Otomoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A few of the main Otomoshu</e>
<cmt>Some→A few</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A few of the main Otomoshu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>三好義興</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshioki MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshioki MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshioki MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>三好長慶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayoshi MIYOSHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>朝倉孝景 (10代当主)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA (the 10th lord)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA (the 10th lord)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA (the tenth head of the family)</e>
<cmt>(10th lord) を (the tenth head of the family) に修正しました。※1　統一リストでは序数が全て英単語で記載されていたため。※2　用語集では「当主」を&quot;family head&quot;と訳されていますが、米国版および英国版のYahooで検索をかけてもこの表記はほとんど全く出てきません。同様の表現で頻出する&quot;the head of the family&quot; の方が容認度が高いものと判断して修正しましたが、この表現における序数のつけ方が不明のため、ご確認願えれば幸いです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一色持信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mochinobu ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mochinobu ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mochinobu ISSHIKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>山名豊之</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyoyuki YAMANA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyoyuki YAMANA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyoyuki YAMANA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>源姓上野氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">UENO clan originally came from MINAMOTO clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The UENO clan originally came from the MINAMOTO clan</e>
<cmt>fixed to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The UENO clan originally came from the MINAMOTO clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">etc.</e>
<cmt>etc. sounds more natural in an article like this</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 伏儀(id:142093), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>