<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>郷士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshi (country samurai)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshi (country samurai)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshi (country samurai)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>郷士（ごうし）とは、江戸時代にあった武士身分の階級の一つをさす歴史学用語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshi is a terminology of history referring to samurai hierarchy which existed in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshi is historical terminology referring to samurai hierarchy that existed during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshi is historical terminology referring to samurai hierarchy that existed during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>幕府・各藩により身分や支配の実態が異なる為、共通する定義を打ち立てるのは難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is difficult to establish a common definition because the realities of a rank or how to control are different depending on bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and each domain, generally it refers to a lower-ranking samurai who lives in agricultural areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is difficult to establish a common definition because the realities of rank or how to control are different depending upon the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and each domain, generally it refers to lower-ranking samurai who lived in agricultural areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is difficult to establish a common definition because actual rank and method of rule differed depending between the bakufu (shogunate) and each clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般的に農村に居住する下級武士の者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a general sense, the term `goshi` came to refers to lower-ranking samurai residing in rural villages.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>苗字帯刀を許されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords, many of them have a clear place of origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being permitted to adopt a surname and to wear a pair of swords, many of them have a clear place of origin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gosho (rural samurai) were permitted to adopt a surname and to wear a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>出自がはっきりしている者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origins (birthplace etc) of many Gosho (rural samurai) was well known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語を他の記事に合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>通常、江戸時代における武士は原則的に城下町に集住する（こちらを城下士あるいは藩士という）のに対し、村（在、または在郷）に住む武士を呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually samurai warrior during the Edo period essentially live together in a castle town, while Goshi refers to a samurai warrior who lives in a village (Zai or Zaigo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usually samurai warriors during the Edo period essentially lived together in a castle town, while Goshi refers to a samurai warrior who lived in a village (Zai or Zaigo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typically during the Edo period samurai warriors tended to live gather together in castle towns (` jokashi` (castle town men) or hanshi (feudal retainer of a domain)), whereas, the goshi (rural samurai) generally indicated a lower level samurai warrior residing in a village or hamlet.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>身分は概ね城下に住む武士（藩士）より下、百姓より上という身分的中間層である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their status level is generally in the middle class which is lower than samurai (hanshi [feudal retainer of domain]) who lives in a castle town and upper than a peasant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their status was generally middle class which is lower than samurai (hanshi or feudal retainer of a domain) who lived in a castle town and higher than a peasant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of Goshi (rural samurai) was generally middle class: somewhat lower than samurai (hanshi) residing in castle towns but, higher than peasants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>郷士を大きく分類すると次のようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshi are mainly divided into the following.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshi are mainly divided into the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshi are mainly divided into the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>兵農分離以前に武士身分であった者が武士身分を維持しながら農村に居住し続けたケース。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the case that a goshi who had rank of samurai before heinobunri (a separation of the warrior class in this domain from the soil), kept living in an agricultural area while having rank of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were examples of goshi who held the rank of samurai before heinobunri (separation of the warrior class in this domain from the soil), kept living in an agricultural area while maintaining the rank of samurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were examples of goshi who held the rank of samurai prior to the `heinobunri` system (separation of samurai from farmer roles) coming into effect, but continued to reside in rural areas while maintaining the rank of samurai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>主家が改易または転封になったものの、在地を離れず、新たな領主から郷士と認められた者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although their master&apos;s house became Kaieki (forfeit rank of Samurai and properties) or their territory was changed, they did not leave their local and were recognized Goshi by a new feudal lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although their master&apos;s house became Kaieki (forfeited rank of Samurai and properties) or their territory was changed, they did not leave their local and were recognized Goshi by the new feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The goshi (rural samurai) experienced a change in status of their main residences, were forced to relocate or were not permitted to leave their local area and were given permission by the feudal lord to be goshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>改易された戦国大名の一族や重臣が仕官せず土着・帰農した者も散見されるが、多くはそれらの庶家や地侍クラスである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some family of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period who was forced to become Kaieki or senior vassals who settled and took up farming again, but most of them belong to the rank of their branch family or jizamurai (local samurai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some families of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku Period forced to become Kaieki or senior vassals who settled and took up farming again, but most of them belonged to the rank of their branch family or jizamurai (local samurai).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some families of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) forced to become Kaieki or senior vassals who settled and took up farming again, but most of them belonged to the rank of their branch family or jizamurai (local samurai).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>こうした者は在地における実力者であり、新たな領主がその懐柔策として百姓身分ではなく、士分としての郷士に取り立てたことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These people are influential leaders in local, and there are many cases that a new feudal lord made such people Goshi as samurai class instead of farming rank as an appeasement policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These people were influential local leaders, and there were many examples where a new feudal lord made such people Goshi in the samurai class, as an appeasement policy, instead of giving them a farming rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These people were influential local leaders, and there were many examples where a new feudal lord made such people goshi in the samurai class, as an appeasement policy, instead of giving them a farming rank.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>中世以来、大名家の転封が無かったため、家臣団の兵農分離が不十分で、地侍の地方知行が存続し、農村に居住し続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Middle Ages, because there were no changing the territory of Daimyo family (feudal lord family), heinobunri (a separation of the warrior class in this domain from the soil) of vassals was not enough, the institution of enfeoffment in local region of jizamurai kept existing, and jizamurai kept living in an agricultural area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Middle Ages, because there were no changes in the territory of Daimyo families (feudal lord family), heinobunri (separation of the warrior class in this domain from the soil) of vassals was not enough, the institution of enfeoffment in local regions of jizamurai continued and jizamurai continued living in agricultural areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there were no forced relocations of daimyo families from the middle ages onwards, there was insufficient separation of samurai and farmers amongst the ranks of vassals and as such, the fiefs of provincial samurai perpetuated and the goshi continued to live in rural villages..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>百姓、町人身分であった者が武士身分へ取りたてられたケース。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some cases that those who were peasants and townspeople were promoted to samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some examples of peasants and townspeople who were promoted to samurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some examples of peasants and townspeople who were promoted to samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>富商、豪農など百姓・町人身分であった者が、大名家に対しての献金や新田開発の褒美として士分としての郷士に取り立てられた者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were in the rank of peasnts and townspeople such as a rich merchant in Sakai or wealthy farmer became Goshi as samurai class as a reward of donations to Daimyo family (feudal lord family) or development of new field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who were peasnts and townspeople, such as a rich merchant in Sakai or wealthy farmer, became Goshi as samurai class as a reward for their donations to the Daimyo family (feudal lord family) or the development of a new field.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Individuals who were peasants and townspeople (eg. prosperous merchants or wealthy farmers) were awarded samurai status (by becoming goshi) as a reward for monetary tributes paid to the daimyo or in recognition of developments in new pursuits.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これら富商、豪農も出自は地侍、改易された戦国大名の一族や家臣である事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of these rich merchants in Sakai or wealthy farmers is often a family or vassal of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period who was punished by being deprived of one&apos;s fief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of such rich merchants in Sakai or wealthy farmers was often a family or vassal of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) during the Sengoku Period who was punished by being deprived of one&apos;s fief.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those prosperous merchants or wealthy farmers were often decedents of provincial samurai or family/vassals of daimyo who was punished during the Sengoku (Warring States) period by being dispossessed of their lands.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>下級武士がその低い身分故に城下で家禄のみによって生計を維持できず、城下郊外又は農村で農業を営むことを許されたケース。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some cases that lower-ranking samurai could not keep up their lives depending only on their Karoku (hereditary stipend) in a castle town, because of their low status, and these were allowed to do farming in agricultural village in the outskirts of the castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some examples of lower-ranking samurai who could not maintain their livelihood depending only on their Karoku (hereditary stipend) in a castle town, because of their low status, and they were allowed to farm in agricultural villages on the outskirts of the castle town.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some examples of lower-ranking samurai who could not survive just living on their Karoku (hereditary stipend) in a castle town because of their low status and because they were not allowed to farm in agricultural villages or the outskirts of the castle town.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>特別の所以があるもの（十津川郷士など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai, who had a special reason (for example, samurai from Totsugawa area in Nara, and so forth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai, who had a special reason (for example, samurai from the Totsugawa area in Nara, etc.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specially exempted samurai (eg. Goshi hailing from the Totsugawa area in Nara and others).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>以上は郷士となった経緯によって分類したものだが、これらに共通する本質的な性質は以下のように整理できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above has tried to categorize according to the process samurai became Goshi, but the essential nature these have in common is categorized as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above is an attempt to categorize samurai according to the process of becaming Goshi, but the essential nature they have in common is categorized as follows:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above goshi were categorized depending on the process by which they became goshi, however the essential elements they had in common were categorized as follows:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>郷士研究の第一人者である木村礎は、郷士とは以下の4点を併せ持つ者としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leading scholar of Goshi studies, Motoi KIMURA defines that Goshi is the one who has the following 4 characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leading scholar of Goshi studies, Motoi KIMURA defines Goshi as having the following 4 characteristics:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leading researcher of the goshi, Motoi KIMURA defines goshi as having the following 4 characteristics:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="22">
<j>城下士とは明確に区別され、在郷していること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are clearly distinguished from Jokashi (castle town men) and zaigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are clearly distinguished from Jokashi (castle town men) and zaigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshi were clearly differentiated depending on whether they resided in a castle town or in a rural village</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>所持地の全部、または一部を「知行」として与えられ、生活の基礎をそれに置くこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are given all or a part of the land as &quot;Chigyo (enfeoffment)&quot;, and place their basic life on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are given all or a part of the land as &quot;Chigyo (enfeoffment),&quot; and base their lives on this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All or a part of a goshi`s land forming their fief was given to them and was the basis of their livelihood.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>家臣団の身分階層性のなかに「郷士」（名称は各様）として正式に位置付けられていること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are positioned officially as &quot;Goshi&quot; (the name is different respectively) among the status hierarchy among vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are positioned officially as &quot;Goshi&quot; (the name is different respectively) among the status hierarchy among vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within a the hierarchy of a grouping of vassals, an individual was given a formal ranking of `goshi`.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>軍役を負担すること（但し、負担しない場合もあり）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They have to bear the burden of military service (however, in some cases they do not).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They have to bear the burden of military service (however, in some cases they do not).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The goshi had to bear the burden of military service but, there were cases where this did not occur.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="26">
<j>また、木村は郷士と混同されやすく、しかも郷士とは言い難いものとして以下の者を挙げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Kimura points out that there are those easy to be mixed up with Goshi, and those who are difficult to be considered Goshi follow below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Kimura points out that there are those who are easily mixed up with Goshi, and those who are difficult to be considered Goshi as described below:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, KIMURA (the academic mentioned above) points out that there are individuals who are easily mistaken for goshi, however, those individuals who are difficult to be considered as goshi as mentioned as follows:</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="27">
<j>これらは郷士という存在を考える際に別物として除外する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There the necessity to exclude these as a different category when considering the existence of Goshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is necessary to exclude these as being in a different category when considering Goshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is necessary to exclude these individuals by virtue they are in a different category to goshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="28">
<j>城下士でありながら、なんらかの事情により在郷している者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are Jokashi, but live local for some reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are Jokashi, but live locally for some reason.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castle town based samurai who for some reason or other lived in rural hamlets.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>陪臣にして在郷している者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who are zaigo as vavasor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who are zaigo as vavasor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vassals of a daimyo (commander) but residing in a rural hamlet.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>大庄屋など上層農民で苗字帯刀御免など武士並の格式を許可された者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those, who are upper-class peasants, such as a big village headman, but have been permitted the same suit-and-tie as Bushi, such as those who are permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those, who are upper-class peasants, such as a big village headman, but have been permitted the same dress as Bushi, such as those who are permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Individuals from the upper rungs of peasants and village headman permitted to dress as samurai, use a surname and wear a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="31">
<j>特に混同しがちなのは3点目の上層農民や豪商などで苗字帯刀御免など武士並の格式をもつ者であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially easy to mix up are those of the third category who are upper-class peasants and wealthy merchants, but have the same suit-and-tie as Bushi, such as those who are permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially easy to mix up are those of the third category who are upper-class peasants and wealthy merchants, but who dress the same as Bushi, such as those who are permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is particularly easy to confuse goshi with individuals in this third category: upper-rung peasants and wealthy merchants, dressed the same as samurai, permitted to adopt a surname and wore a pair of swords.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この場合、生活の基礎はあくまでも農民的土地所有や商業にあり、また家臣団には入っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the foundation of livelihood is the possession of agricultural land or a trade, and they do not belong to the vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the foundation of their livelihood is the possession of agricultural land or a trade, and they do not belong to the vassal category.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the foundation of this 3rd group&apos;s livelihood was the possession of agricultural land or a commerce, and they did not belong to the ranks of vassals.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="33">
<j>このような郷士身分ではないものの苗字帯刀を許された特権的な百姓・町人は全国的に存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peasants and city dwellers with special rights like these, who had been permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords, although they were not of Goshi status, existed throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peasants and city dwellers with special rights like these, who had been permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords, although they were not Goshi status, existed throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they were not of goshi status, peasants and city dwellers with special rights allowing them to use a surname and wear swords existed in every province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="34">
<j>百姓身分ではあるが、彼らは地域の有力者として支配の末端に位置する庄屋などの村役人に任ぜられたり、あるいはその子弟が足軽（薩摩藩）として用いられたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although their status was the one of a peasant as regional holders of power they were appointed as village officials such as Shoya that were positioned at the lowest end of the ruling structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although their status was one of a peasant as regional holders of power they were appointed as village officials such as Shoya that were positioned at the lowest end of the ruling structure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although of peasant status, such individuals held regional power, were appointed as village officials (eg. headman) at the lowest end of the ruling structure, or their children were used as common foot soldier by the Satsuma clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="35">
<j>支配の末端に連なるその役儀や藩財政への貢献ゆえ、特権として苗字帯刀を許されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of their contribution to Yakugi and financial policy of the province as being the lowest end of the ruling structure, they were permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords as a special right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of their contribution to Yakugi and financial policy of the province as being at the lowest end of the ruling structure, they were permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords as a special right.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such individuals received special dispensation to use a surname and wear swords by virtue of their responsibilities and contribution to the fringes of the fief&apos;s finances and control.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="36">
<j>彼らの中には、非公認の自称や私称として「郷士」を名乗る者も存在したが、制度ではなく私称であるので、学術的に郷士を考える際に混同すべきではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There existed those among them who called themselves &quot;Goshi&quot; as an unofficial self-given title and private title, but this was not a system, but a private title, and therefore they are easy to mix up when considering the Goshi academically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There existed those among them who called themselves &quot;Goshi&quot; as an unofficial self-given title and private title, but this was not a system, but a private title, and therefore they are easily mixed up when considering Goshi from and academic standpoint.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst such individuals there were people who gave themselves the (unofficial) private title of `Goshi` however this was not formal arrangement, but instead, a private title, and therefore such individuals can be easily confused with `true` goshi when considering goshi from an academic standpoint.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、郷士内においても、細分化された階層に分かれている場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there are cases where there were divisions into more classes within the Goshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there are examples where there were divisions into more classes within the Goshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there are examples where within goshi classes there was further sub-division.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>例としては、旧族郷士と取立郷士の別や給田・知行高、村役の有無などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, there are the difference between Kyuzokugoshi and Toritategoshi (appointed goshi) or with or without Kyuden (provided rice field), Chigyo daka (a stipend in terms of rice production of the fief) and Soneki (work service), and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, there are differences between Kyuzokugoshi and Toritategoshi (appointed goshi) or with or without Kyuden (provided rice field), Chigyo daka (a stipend in terms of rice production of the fief) and Soneki (work service), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, there are differentiations made based on whether a goshi was a Kyuzoku goshi (of ancient pedigree) and Toritate goshi (appointed goshi) owner of land or landless, receipt of a stipend (in the form of rice) from the fief), and whether or not they held a village role etc.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="39">
<j>なお、他の各時代・国において正規の武士、騎士より下位の軍事的特権階級を郷士と表記することがある（イギリスのEsquire、スペインのhidalgo等）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in some cases, in other time periods or countries, a class with special military rights that is lower in rank than regular Bushi or knights has been termed Goshi (e.g. The English Esquire or the Spanish Hidalgo, etc.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in some cases, in other time periods or countries, a class with special military rights that is lower in rank than regular Bushi or knight has been termed Goshi (e.g. The English Esquire or the Spanish Hidalgo, etc.)</e>
<cmt>word spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in various periods/provinces, legitimate samurai below the rank of Kishi (mounted samurai) that held special military rights were referred to as `goshi` (like titles given to an English Esquire or a Spanish Hidalgo, etc.).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>郷士の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples for Goshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of Goshi</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of Goshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>十津川郷士、八王子千人同心はそれぞれの項目参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For samurai from Totsugawa area in Nara and Hachioji Sennin Doshin, please refer to the respective paragraphs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For samurai from Totsugawa area in Nara and Hachioji Sennin Doshin, please refer to the respective paragraphs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please also refer to the respective paragraphs relating to samurai from the Totsugawa area in Nara and junior officials in Hachioji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>原方衆（米沢藩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harakatashu (the Yonezawa clan)</e>
<cmt>訳文がなかったので、補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>米沢藩上杉氏は豊臣政権下120万石の大大名家であったが、関ヶ原の戦いで30万石に減封された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uesugi Clan of the Yonezawa Domain was the family of Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) with 1.2 million goku under the Toyotomi government, but after the Battle of Sekigahara this was reduced to 300,000 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uesugi Clan of the Yonezawa Domain was the family of Daidaimyo (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) with 1.2 million goku under the Toyotomi government, but after the Battle of Sekigahara this was reduced to 300,000 goku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uesugi clan in the Yonezawa domain was a Dai-daimyo (a grand feudal lord) family of a 1.2 million koku income subordinate to the Toyotomi government, however, after the Battle of Sekigahara, their wealth was reduced to 300,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>しかし、家臣の召し放ちを行わなかったことから財政が逼迫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the Uesugi clan did not meshihanachi (confiscation) any of their vassals, the financial situation became were grim.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the Uesugi clan did not meshihanachi (confiscate) any of their vassals, their financial situation became grim.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Uesugi clan struggled financially because the clan did not press any vassals into service.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>さらに、1664年（寛文4年）に3代藩主上杉綱勝が嫡子がないまま急死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1664 the third lord of the domain, Tsunekatsu UESUGI died without a successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1664 the third lord of the domain, Tsunekatsu UESUGI died without a successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On top of this, in 1664 the third lord of the clan (Tsunakatsu UESUGI) died suddenly leaving no successor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>本来なら改易になるところを、石高を半分の15万石として吉良義央の子上杉綱憲を末期養子に迎えることが特別に許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Normally, he was supposed to be punished by being deprived of his fief, but he was permitted to have Tsunanori UESUGI, a son of Yoshinaka KIRA as matsugo yoshi (adopted as a son on one&apos;s deathbed), but his crop yield was reduced in half to 150 000 goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Normally, he was supposed to be punished by being deprived of his fief, but he was permitted to have Tsunanori UESUGI, the son of Yoshinaka KIRA as matsugo yoshi (adopted as a son on one&apos;s deathbed), but his crop yield was reduced in half to 150 000 goku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Normally, a change in the rankings would result in grain tributes being reduced by half to 150,000 koku but, special permission was given to Tsunanori UESUGI (son of Yoshinaka KIRA) to become an adopted son.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>石高が半減したのに家臣の召し放ちを行わなかったため、没収された福島城に詰めていた下級藩士は、米沢城城下の郊外に屋敷の他に農地が当てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As no vassals had been meshihanachi (confiscation), but the crop yield had been reduced in half, the lower-class samurai of the domain who had been living in the confiscated Fukushima Castle were given homes in the outskirts of the castle town below Yonezawa Castle, as well as farmland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No vassals had been meshihanachi (confiscated), but the crop yield had been reduced in half, the lower-class samurai of the domain who had been living in the confiscated Fukushima Castle were given homes on the outskirts of the castle town below Yonezawa Castle, as well as some farmland.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to rice stipend being reduced in half and no vassals pressed into service, the lower ranked samurai clansmen (who had been living in the confiscated Fukushima-jo Castle) were allocated homes and farmland on the outskirts of the castle town below Yonezawa-jo Castle,.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>彼らには知行が全くまたは家計を維持できない程度しか与えられない代わり、普段は農地の経営に専念でき、臨時の軍役にのみ従事すればよいとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As they had not been given a &quot;Chigyo&quot;, or only an amount that was not enough to keep up their household, they were told instead to concentrate on the running of their farmlands in normal times, and were only required to take up military duties during exceptional times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As they had not been given a &quot;Chigyo,&quot; or had been givine only an amount that was not enough to keep up their household, they were told instead to concentrate on the operation of their farmlands in normal times, and were only required to take up military duties during exceptional times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clansmen were not allocated a domain as such, nor given an amount sufficient for the upkeep up their household, but were told instead to concentrate on working their farmlands in normal times, and were only required to perform military duties on an ad hoc basis.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>このような下級武士を原方衆と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These lower-class Bushi were called harakatashu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These lower-class Bushi were called harakatashu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These lower-class samurai were called harakatashu.</e>
<cmt>用語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>なお、幕府に提出する城絵図には原方衆が居住する地域も武家地と明記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">in the pictorial map of the castle that was handed over to the Shogunate, the districts where the harakatashu were living had also been marked as residential areas of Bushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">in the pictorial map of the castle that was handed over to the Shogunate, the districts where the harakatashu were living had also been marked as residential areas of Bushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the pictorial map of the castle provided to the shogunate, the districts where people lived on the plains were marked as residential areas of samurai.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>土佐郷士（土佐藩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosa Gohi (Tosa Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosa Gohi (Tosa Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosa Goshi (the Tosa clan)</e>
<cmt>用語修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="49">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い以前に四国を支配していた長宗我部氏の旧臣一領具足層を懐柔するため郷士に取り立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were made Goshi in order to accommodate the ichiryo gusoku (allowing cultivators to arm themselves, later how local samurai-cultivators referred to themselves), the older vassals of the Chosokabe clan, which had controlled the Shikoku region before the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were made Goshi in order to accommodate the ichiryo gusoku (allowing cultivators to arm themselves, and later how local samurai-cultivators referred to themselves), the older vassals of the Chosokabe clan, which had controlled the Shikoku region before the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to the Battle of Sekigahara, as a conciliatory gesture, older vassals of the Chosokabe clan (that controlled the Shikoku region and who had been farmer-warriors) were made goshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一方、掛川衆や山内侍と呼ばれる上士は、山内一豊が掛川城主だった時からの家臣や土佐入封前に大坂牢人を取り立てたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Joshi (superior warrior), who were called kakegawashu and yamauchizamurai, are those where Osaka ronin were made</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Joshi (superior warrior), who were called kakegawashu and yamauchizamurai, were those who became Osaka ronin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, goshi were created from high ranking eminent samurai (also called `kakegawashu` and `yamauchi` (monk) samurai, had been vassals since the time when Kazutoyo YAMAUCHI was the lord of Kakegawa-jo Castle, or master-less `ronin` samurai taken from Osaka jail prior to entering Tosa ranks.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>土佐藩における郷士は武士とはいえ、他藩に比べると徹底した差別下にあったため土佐藩上士とは同じ藩士とはいえ潜在的には対立、敵対関係にあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Goshi of the Tosa Domain were samurai, but compared to the other Domains, they were subject to complete discrimination, and although they were the same feudal retainers as the Tosa Joshi, potentially they were in conflict and hostile towards each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Goshi of the Tosa Domain were samurai, but compared to other Domains, they were subject to discrimination, and although they were the same feudal retainers as the Tosa Joshi, potentially they were in conflict and hostile towards each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whilst it can be said the goshi from Tosa domain were samurai, they suffered from systematic discrimination compared to other domains resulting in a situation where although the upper samurai ranks of Tosa were domain samurai all the same, there was latent confrontation and antagonism.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>幕府や藩の権威が衰えた幕末には土佐郷士達の多くが尊皇攘夷運動に身を投じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, when the authority of the Bakufku and the domains had diminished, many of the Tosa Goshi committed themselves to the &quot;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&quot; movement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, when the authority of the Bakufku and the domains had diminished, many of the Tosa Goshi committed themselves to the &quot;Revere the Emperor and expel the barbarians&quot; movement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, when the authority of the bakufu and the clans had diminished, many of the Tosa goshi committed themselves to a movement whose rallying cry was &apos; Revere the emperor and expel the barbarians`.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>著名な人物には土佐郷士をまとめ土佐勤王党を結成した武市半平太や、海援隊 (浪士結社)の結成や薩長連合の斡旋、大政奉還の成立に尽力した坂本龍馬、初代衆議院議長の中島信行がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous persons were Hanbeta TAKECHI, who gathered the Tosa Goshi, and formed the Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa), and Ryoma SAKAMOTO, who formed Kaientai (an association of roshi), mediated the union of Satsuma Domain and Choshu Domain and made great efforts towards the realization of the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor), as well as Nobuyuki NAKAJIMA, who was the first chairman of House of Representatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous were Hanbeta TAKECHI, who gathered the Tosa Goshi, and formed the Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa), and Ryoma SAKAMOTO, who formed Kaientai (an association of roshi), mediated the union of Satsuma Domain and Choshu Domain and made great efforts towards the realization of the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor), as well as Nobuyuki NAKAJIMA, who was the first chairman of House of Representatives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous personalities included: Hanbeta TAKECHI, who organized the Tosa goshi, and formed the Tosa kinnoto (loyalist clique of Tosa), and Ryoma SAKAMOTO, who formed Kaientai association, mediated the union of the Satsuma clan and the Choshu clan and made great efforts towards the realization of transfer of power back to the Emperor, as well as Nobuyuki NAKAJIMA, who was the first Speaker of Japan&apos;s House of Representatives.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>また藩には土佐郷士の懐柔政策の一つとして、特別な家系や功績によっては上士扱いの白札とする制度があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there was a system in the Domain, meant as a policy to appease the Tosa Goshi, that made them Shirofuda which received the same treatment as Joshi, depending on a special family line or merit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there was a system in the Domain, meant as a policy to appease the Tosa Goshi, that made them Shirofuda who received the same treatment as Joshi, depending on their special family line or merit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in the domain there was a policy of conciliation whereby the Tosa goshi were honored with the special title of `Shirofuda` (based on family line or merit) so they would receive the same treatment as upper ranking samurai..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>武市半平太は白札であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanbeta TAKECHI was Shirofuda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanbeta TAKECHI was Shirofuda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanbeta TAKECHI was awarded the `Shirofuda` rank.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>肥後郷士（熊本藩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Echigo Goshi (Kumamoto Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Echigo Goshi (Kumamoto Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higo Goshi (the Kumamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>higoとし、the Kumamoto clanとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>実際の名称は郷士とは言わず在中御家人と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their actual title was not Goshi, but they were called Zaichu Gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their actual title was not Goshi, but they were called Zaichu Gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such cases, their actual title was not `goshi`, but Zaichu Gokenin (literally meaning lower ranked vassal).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>はじめは農村行政等の必要性から前領主、小西・加藤氏の帰農遺臣や土豪に士格を追認したのは他藩と同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar to other domains, at first a samurai title was confirmed for former local lords, Kino ishin of the Konishi and Kato clans and local clans, out of the need for agricultural administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar to other domains, at first a samurai title was confirmed for former local lords, Kino ishin of the Konishi and Kato clans and local clans, out of the need for agricultural administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially because of a need for administration of rural areas etc, samurai status was conferred upon surviving retainers of the previous domain rulers (Konishi and Kato clans) who had returned to farming as well as local clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>また、足軽を帰農させ軽格の「郷士」として苗字帯刀を許し、国境・辺境警備に当たらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furhtermore, ashigaru were returned to farming, but permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords as &quot;Goshi&quot; of low rank, and they were ordered to guard the national and other borders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furhtermore, ashigaru were returned to farming, but permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords as &quot;Goshi&quot; of low rank, and they were ordered to guard the national and other borders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, foot soldiers who returned to faming were given goshi` (rural samurai) status and as such were permitted use a surname and wear swords as well as guard province borders and to patrol frontier areas..</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>こうした例に「地筒・郡筒（じづつ・こうりづつ）」の鉄砲隊があり、これは無給に等しい「名誉職」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example there was a gun regiment called &quot;Jizutsu and Korizutsu&quot;, but this was a &quot;honorary position&quot; with almost no income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example there was a gun regiment called &quot;Jizutsu and Korizutsu,&quot; but this was an &quot;honorary position&quot; with almost no income.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of this include a regional regiment of unpaid/honorary fusiliers called &apos;Jizutsu and Korizutsu&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>実際、鉄砲隊とは名ばかりで、地役人や臨時の江戸詰め藩卒として動員されたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, it was a gun regiment only by name, and its members were recruited as local officials and Hansotsu working in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, it was a gun regiment only by name, and its members were recruited as local officials and Hansotsu working in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, it was a fusilier regiment in name alone and its members were mobilized to serve as local officials lower ranking samurai to work on an ad-hoc basis in Edo (now modern day Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>逆に、好奇心旺盛な郷士の子弟は、それらの制度を利用して、見聞を広めるために江戸詰め足軽に志願することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, curious sons of Goshi used these systems to apply for ashigaru working in Edo in order to broaden their horizons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, curious sons of Goshi used these systems to apply for ashigaru working in Edo in order to broaden their horizons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a strange twist, inquisitive sons of goshi (rural samurai) made use of these arrangements to volunteer as foot soldiers to serve in Edo as a means to broaden their horizons.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また江戸時代中期以降、藩は献金に応じ郷士格を乱発する傾向となり、昇格する格式によって金額まで定められ藩の収入の一部ともなり「寸志御家人」として制度化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also since the mid-Edo period, the domain developed the tendency to issue the title of Goshi in large numbers in exchange for donations, and this became part of the revenues of the domain as system where the amount of money which had to be paid to be promoted to a certain title, as a system which was called &quot;Sunshi Gokenin&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, since the mid-Edo period, the domain developed the tendency to issue the title Goshi in large numbers in exchange for donations, and this became part of the revenues of the domain in a system where a certain amount of money had to be paid to be promoted to a certain title, and this was called &quot;Sunshi Gokenin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, from the middle of the Edo period onwards, clans tended to confer goshi` (rural samurai) status in large numbers in return for a monetary contribution which came to form part of the clan&apos;s revenue; this practice of certain amounts of money changing hands to obtain particular titles became institutionalized and the practice was known as &apos;Sunshi Gokenin&apos; (literally meaning `gifted low ranked vassal`).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>それによって与えられる身分は、「一領一匹」と「地士」以外は概ね「足軽格」程度であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status one was given through this system was merely that of a &quot;Ashigaru&quot;, apart from the &quot;Ichiryo-ippiki&quot; and the Jizamurai (upper-rank in rural community), it was gossipped that those who had become Goshi by giving money were &quot;samurai risen through money&quot;, and since the Meiji period their descendants who had become shizoku were called &quot;shizoku risen through money&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status one was given through this system was merely that of &quot;Ashigaru,&quot; apart from the &quot;Ichiryo-ippiki&quot; and the Jizamurai (upper-rank in rural community), it was said that those who had become Goshi by giving money were &quot;samurai risen through money,&quot; and since the Meiji period their descendants who had become shizoku were called &quot;shizoku risen through money.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, the status conferred this way almost identical with that of the foot soldiers (with the exception of &apos;Ichiryo-ippiki&apos; (goshi senior Hosokawa clansmen) and upper-rank rural based samurai).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>献金郷士は「カネ上げ侍」と陰口された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice of `buying` goshi status also gave rise to gossip: recipient were called &apos;Kaneage zamurai&apos; (literally meaning `give you money samurai`).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>明治以降もそれらの子孫で士族となった者は「カネ上げ士族」といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Meiji period onwards, their descendants who in turn had inherited warrior class status were sniped at as &apos;Kaneage shizoku&apos; (literally meaning `give you money samurai descendants`).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>薩摩郷士（薩摩藩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satsuma Goshi (Satsuma Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satsuma Goshi (Satsuma Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satsuma Goshi (the Satsuma clan)</e>
<cmt>the Satsuma clanとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>旧族居付大名であるため、外城制の存在などに見られるように中世的であり、城下集住・俸禄制をとる大多数の藩とは異なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Satsuma was a Kyu Zokkyo Fudaimyo, as one see in the existence of the Tojosei, it was medieval, and different from most of the domains which took system of living grouped below the castle and receiving horoku (salary), because the kokujin (local samurai) of the Sengoku period (period of warring states), the Zaichi Bushi and the samurai who had joined the domain during the Shimazu clan&apos;s war for the unification of Satsuma, were all made vassals receving the title of Goshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Satsuma was a Kyu Zokkyo Fudaimyo, as seen in the existence of the Tojosei, it was medieval, and different from most of the domains which had a system of living grouped below the castle and receiving horoku (salary), because the kokujin (local samurai) of the Sengoku period (period of warring states), the Zaichi Bushi and the samurai who had joined the domain during the Shimazu clan&apos;s war for the unification of Satsuma, were all made vassals receving the title of Goshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshi (rural samurai) were considered part of the ranks of vassals because the daimyo of ancient clans believed that the goshi samurai had lived outside the castle grounds since mediaeval times and, resided in castle support towns (on a stipend) which was different to arrangements in a large number of other clans.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>戦国時代における国人、在地武士、そして島津氏の九州統一戦で傘下に入った武士等が郷士として家臣団に組み込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, samurai such as those who were minor provincial lords at the time of the Sengoku (Warring States) period, regional samurai, and those in the unified Shimazu clan army in Kyushu were included in the ranks of vassals as goshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>そのため、外城士とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore they are also called Tojoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore they are also called Tojoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the above reasons such goshi samurai were also called `Tojoshi` (literally meaning `samurai outside a castle`).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>参勤交代、軍役等、果たす役目は、一般の藩士と同じである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their duties, such as Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and military service were the same as those of ordinary feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their duties, such as Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and military service were the same as those of ordinary feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duties of the `Tojoshi` were identical with those of clan affiliated samurai and included roles such as: participating in the Sankinkotai detail (where feudal lords were required to spend alternate years residing in Edo) and, military service.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>江戸時代初期は、鹿児島城下に住む武士は「鹿児島衆中」と呼ばれ、外城士は所属する郷によって「出水衆中」、「国分衆中」と呼ばれ、大した区別はされていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of the Edo period, the samurai living below Kagoshima Castle were called &quot;Kagoshima shuchu&quot; and the Tojishi were called &quot;Izumi shuchu&quot; or &quot;Kokubu shuchu&quot;, depending on the Go (local district) they belonged to, and there did not exit much of a categorization as it happened often that Goshi were appointed to posts such as Amami-oshima Daikan fuyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the Edo period, samurai living below Kagoshima Castle were called &quot;Kagoshima shuchu&quot; and the Tojishi were called &quot;Izumi shuchu&quot; or &quot;Kokubu shuchu,&quot; depending on the Go (local district) they belonged to, and there wasn&apos;t much categorization as it happened often that Goshi were appointed to posts such as Amami-oshima Daikan fuyaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the Edo period, there was negligible difference between samurai calling themselves &apos;Kagoshima shuchu&apos; (living near Kagoshima-jo Castle) and Tojoshi (samurai living outside a castle) going by other local/hamlet demarking titles (&apos;Izumi shuchu&apos; or &apos;Kokubu shuchu&apos;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>奄美大島代官附役などに郷士が任命されることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also common for goshi to be appointed to posts such as Oshima Daikan Tsukiyaku (a post under the local governor in Amami-Oshima island).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>しかし、中期以降（特に島津重豪の藩政改革以降）、「鹿児島衆中」は「城下士」と呼ばれるようになり、「城下士」と「郷士」の間には厳格な身分差意識が誕生したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the middle Edo period (especially after the reformation of domain duties of Shigehide SHIMAZU, the &quot;Kagoshima shuchu&quot; were called &quot;Jokashi (castle town men)&quot; and consiciousness of strict status distinction between &quot;Jokashi&quot; and &quot;Goshi&quot; developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since middle Edo period (especially after the reformation of domain duties of Shigehide SHIMAZU), the &quot;Kagoshima shuchu&quot; were called &quot;Jokashi (castle town men)&quot; and consiciousness of strict status distinction between &quot;Jokashi&quot; and &quot;Goshi&quot; developed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the middle of the Edo period onwards (especially after Shigehide SHIMAZU instituted reformation of domain responsibilities), the &apos;Kagoshima shuchu&apos; (literally meaning samurai resident in the Kagoshima area) were given the title &apos;jokashi&apos; (literally meaning samurai outside the castle) which brought about an awareness of rigid status distinctions between &apos;Jokashi&apos; and &apos;Goshi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>但し、その後も城下士との間に養子縁組による身分の移動や通婚関係はあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even after that there were still changes in status by adoptions between Goshi and Jokashi and commuting relationships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even after that there were still changes in status because of adoptions between Goshi and Jokashi and commuting relationships.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even after that, there were still changes in status because of adoptions between goshi and jokashi and commuting relationships.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また、城下士が家制度家の設立、消滅後に「鹿児島」から他郷へ移住し、郷士となる例も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there were many examples that Jokashi migrated to other areas from &quot;Kagoshima&quot; and became Goshi after Jokashi established a family system and the system ceased to exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there were many examples that Jokashi who migrated to other areas from &quot;Kagoshima&quot; and became Goshi after Jokashi established a family system and the system then ceased to exist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there were many examples of individuals becoming `goshi` (regional samurai) after migrating from the Kagoshima region to other areas following the setting up of formalized `jokashi` (literally meaning samurai outside a castle) structured family systems.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>更に、郷士内部でも身分の上下があり、上中級郷士は麓と呼ばれる武家屋敷街に住み、事実上地方行政を取り仕切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, middle and upper class Goshi were living in samurai residence district called fumoto and virtually managed local administration because there was a hierarchical relation among Goshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, middle and upper class Goshi were living in samurai residential districts called fumoto and virtually managed local administration because there was a hierarchical relation among Goshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there was a hierarchical difference amongst goshi: middle and upper ranks resided in samurai residential districts called `fumoto` and in effect ran the local government administration.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>また、上級郷士ともなると多くの農地山林を抱え、さらに薩摩藩では武士同士の石高の売買が出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the upper-rank Goshi had vast farming lands, forests and mountains, and as it was possible to trade the crop yield among samurai in Satsuma Domain, there many Goshi who were richer than Jokashi although their status was lower, as they had bought crop yields up to the limit of the crop yields they were allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the upper-ranking Goshi had vast farming lands, forests and mountains, and as it was possible to trade the crop yield among samurai in the Satsuma Domain, there many Goshi who were richer than Jokashi although their status was lower, as they had bought crop yields up to their allocated limit of the crop yields.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, when a samurai became a senior ranking goshi they controlled vast farming lands, forests and mountains, and moreover, it was possible for them to trade produce among samurai in the Satsuma clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>そのため、持高制限一杯まで石高を買い集めるなどして、身分は低くとも城下士以上に豊かな者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to many goshi (rural samurai) using their trading right to the limits allowed and, although of lower status, many goshi lived more prosperous lives than their higher-ranked jokashi (samurai outside castles) counterparts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>だが、大半の郷士は無高の者が多かった（無高郷士）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, most of the Goshi were Mutaka (no crop yields) (Mutaka Goshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of the Goshi were Mutaka (no crop yields) (Mutaka Goshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the majority of goshi were considered `Mudaka` (receiving no stipend in the form of a share of crop yields).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>これらの郷士は、藩に許可されていた大工や内職で生計を立て、中には武士身分のままで上級郷士の小作人になる者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These Goshi made a living by becoming a carpenter or working at home, professions that had been allowed by the domain, and among them there were those who became kosakunin (tenant farmer), although they were upper-rank Goshi and retained their samurai status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Goshi made a living by becoming carpenters or working at home, professions that had been allowed by the domain, and among them were those who became kosakunin (a tenant farmer), although they were upper-rank Goshi and retained their samurai status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These unsubsidized `Mudaka` goshi made their livings by pursuing those professions permitted by the clan (carpentry, cottage industries) and, amongst the goshi there were individuals who maintained their senior goshi status whilst working as tenant farmers.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="80">
<j>明治維新後は俸禄を失い没落した城下士（藩士）に対し、郷士は農地を買い集め地主として成功した者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration there were many goshi, who were successful as land owners who had bought farmlands, in contrast to the Jokashi (feudal retainers) who had lost their horoku and become destitute, and there were many Goshi who took a cool attitude towards the Seinan War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration there were many goshi, who were successful as land owners who had bought farmlands, in contrast to the Jokashi (feudal retainers) who had lost their horoku and become destitute, and there were many Goshi who took a cool attitude towards the Seinan War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the Meiji Restoration, there were many goshi who successfully purchased and accumulated land holdings in contrast to jokashi/clan samurai who lost their stipends and were ruined.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>西南戦争に対しても冷ややかな態度をとる郷士が多かったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many goshi also maintained a frigid attitude in relation to the Satsuma Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>その後、城下士出身者の多くは郷里・鹿児島を離れ、藩閥の力で中央官吏や軍人として立身を目指し、一方の郷士出身者は警察で派閥を形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, many of those who were of Jokashi origin left their homeland of Kagoshima and pursued a career as central bureaucrats and soldiers with the power of their domain clique, while those of Goshi origin formed a clique within the police.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, many of those who were of Jokashi origin left their homeland of Kagoshima and pursued a career as central bureaucrats and samurai with the power of their domain clique, while those of Goshi origin formed a clique within the police.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, many jokashi (outside castle samurai) departed Kagoshima/home towns and leveraged clan links in pursuit of careers as central-government bureaucrats or in the military whereas those of goshi origin formed cliques within the police.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また、中央に出られない者は地元で公務員、教師、警察官や消防吏員の道に進むものが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also many of those who did not join the central government became public servants, teachers, police officers or firefighters locally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also many of those who did not join the central government became public servants, teachers, police officers, or local firefighters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many goshi who did not relocate to urban centers often pursued careers in local areas as: public servants, teachers, police officers, or firefighters.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>戦前の鹿児島県においては新政下で「平民」に置かれた者がこれらの公職に就くことは至難の道であったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in pre-war Kagoshima prefecture, for those who were placed as &quot;Heimin (commoner)&quot; under the new government it was extremely difficult to enter public service mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in pre-war Kagoshima prefecture, for those who were placed as &quot;Heimin (commoner)&quot; under the new government it was extremely difficult to enter the public service mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in pre-war Kagoshima Prefecture, it was extremely difficult for &apos;Heimin&apos; (commoners) to secure public service roles in a new government.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>昭和20年の敗戦により連合国軍最高司令官総司令部のてこ入れがあるまで、鹿児島県政のこの政治構造は変わらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the commitment of the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) after losing the war in 1945, this political structure of prefectural politics in Kagoshima did not change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the commitment of the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) after losing the war in 1945, this political structure of prefectural politics in Kagoshima did not change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">in 1945 after the war ended and until the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) took control, this political structure remained unchanged in Kagoshima political structures.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 生涯一薩摩人(id:75048), Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Afarus(id:146955), 松茸(id:27535), Zorac(id:28001), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 沢田(id:40580), Yudofu(id:81031), Parachutes(id:139813), Amler(id:101250), An-chan(id:14590), 海衛士(id:19229), Matangohouse(id:312713), 怪蘇(id:45514), 盛風力(id:54988), Loveless(id:129239), Tentou(id:195158), Point136(id:211299), こぶまき(id:38278), Junger(id:10282), Toho(id:62082), Bankokuya(id:91191), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>