<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>町代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machidai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machidai</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machidai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>町代（まちだい）とは、江戸時代の京都における町役人のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machidai was a town official in Kyoto in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Machidai&quot; was a town official in Kyoto in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Machidai にダブルコーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Machidai&quot; was a town official in Kyoto in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元は町役人の元締役として京都市民の代表的な地位にある存在であったが、後に京都町奉行の事務業務の代行を委任される事が多くなり、町奉行の下部組織として認識されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machidai originally represented Kyoto citizens as a manager of town officials; Later, it became authorized to act as a proxy in execution of secretarial works of the Kyoto city commissioner, gradually recognized as a subordinate organization of the city commissioner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machidai originally represented Kyoto citizens as a manager of town officials; Later, it became authorized to act as a proxy in execution of secretarial works of the Kyoto city magistrates, gradually recognized as a subordinate organization of the city magistrates.</e>
<cmt>commissioner を magistrates に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machidai originally represented Kyoto citizens as a manager of town officials; Later, it became authorized to act as a proxy in execution of secretarial works of the Kyoto city magistrates, gradually recognized as a subordinate organization of the city magistrates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>町代を「ちょうだい」と読ませた町役人は江戸・大坂にも存在したが、町年寄や町名主を補佐する事を職掌とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some town officials in Edo and Osaka adopted another way of pronunciation &apos;Chodai&apos; for &apos;Machidai&apos; and assisted town councilors and town chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some town officials in Edo and Osaka adopted another way of pronunciation &apos;Chodai&apos; for &apos;Machidai&apos; and assisted town councilors and town chief.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some town officials in Edo and Osaka adopted another way of pronunciation &apos;Chodai&apos; for &apos;Machidai&apos; and assisted town councilors and town chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>これに対して京都の町代は京都のうち上京に12、下京に8あった「町組」と称される組（地域）単位に1名、その下に１ないし2名の下町代が付属され、組内にある各町の町名主以下の町役人を統率した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, Machidai in Kyoto headed town officials including the town chiefs: There was one Machidai for each group of towns (i.e., each district) with one or two subordinate Machidai below, for heading town officials including town chief in each town of the group (Kamigyo area had 12 groups of towns and Shimogyo area had 8 groups of towns).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Machidai in Kyoto headed town officials including the town chiefs: There was one Machidai for each group of towns (i.e., each district) with one or two subordinate Machidai below, for heading town officials including town chief in each town of the group (Kamigyo area had 12 groups of towns and Shimogyo area had 8 groups of towns).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Machidai in Kyoto headed town officials including the town chiefs: There was one Machidai for each group of towns (i.e., each district) with one or two subordinate Machidai below, for heading town officials including town chief in each town of the group (Kamigyo area had 12 groups of towns and Shimogyo area had 8 groups of towns).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>京都町奉行の成立に先立つ寛文8年12月5日 (旧暦)に作成された「町代役之覚」という17ヶ条の町代と町奉行間で交わされた文書によると、町奉行から出された法令・触書の伝達、町から出された様々な請願・届出の提出、京都市民を代表して江戸城の征夷大将軍への年頭拝礼、町人役（町々への賦課）の徴収、火災・闕所・見廻などの出役などがあり、訴訟事務などのために公事・訴訟が行われる日には交替で1名が奉行所内の町代部屋に出仕して事務処理の補佐を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was documents exchanged between Machidai and the Kyoto city commissioner called &apos;Machidaiyaku no Oboe&apos; consisting of 17 Articles compiled on January 7, 1669 (prior to the establishment of the Kyoto city commissioner), which states duties of Machidai as follows: Outside works of transmission of ordinance and notification issued by the city commissioner, submission of various applications and written reports entrusted by the town, New Year visit to the shogun in Edo Castle as a representative of Kyoto citizens, collection of levy from towns, examination of the scene of a fire and a confiscated estate, and patrol; and Machidai alternately does desk works in Machidai room of the Kyoto city commissioner&apos;s office to assist court clerical on the day when a court is held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was documents exchanged between Machidai and the Kyoto city magistrates called &apos;Machidaiyaku no Oboe&apos; consisting of 17 Articles compiled on January 7, 1669 (prior to the establishment of the Kyoto city magistrates), which states duties of Machidai as follows: Outside works of transmission of ordinance and notification issued by the city magistrates, submission of various applications and written reports entrusted by the town, New Year visit to the shogun in Edo-jo Castle as a representative of Kyoto citizens, collection of levy from towns, examination of the scene of a fire and a confiscated estate, and patrol; and Machidai alternately does desk works in Machidai room of the Kyoto city magistrates&apos; office to assist court clerical on the day when a court is held.</e>
<cmt>commissioner を magistrates に修正しました。Edo Castle を Edo-jo Castle に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was documents exchanged between Machidai and the Kyoto city magistrates called &apos;Machidaiyaku no Oboe&apos; consisting of 17 Articles compiled on January 7, 1669 (prior to the establishment of the Kyoto city magistrates), which states duties of Machidai as follows: Outside works of transmission of ordinance and notification issued by the city magistrates, submission of various applications and written reports entrusted by the town, New Year visit to the shogun in Edo-jo Castle as a representative of Kyoto citizens, collection of levy from towns, examination of the scene of a fire and a confiscated estate, and patrol; and Machidai alternately does desk works in Machidai room of the Kyoto city magistrates&apos; office to assist court clerical on the day when a court is held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>町代部屋には雑用・筆者のために数名の小番（定員6名）と筆耕が配属された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several clerks (up to six) and a copyist were assigned to the Machidai room for miscellaneous duties and note taking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several clerks (up to six) and a copyist were assigned to the Machidai room for miscellaneous duties and note taking.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several clerks (up to six) and a copyist were assigned to the Machidai room for miscellaneous duties and note taking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これらの役職は有力な町名主から選ばれて代々世襲されるのが原則であり、町代の給料にあたる役銀及び町代部屋の維持費用は町々の負担とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, these roles were inherited by the selected influential town chiefs, and their salaries called &apos;Yakugin&apos; and the maintenance costs of the Machidai room were charged to the towns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, these roles were inherited by the selected influential town chiefs, and their salaries called &apos;Yakugin&apos; and the maintenance costs of the Machidai room were charged to the towns.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, these roles were inherited by the selected influential town chiefs, and their salaries called &apos;Yakugin&apos; and the maintenance costs of the Machidai room were charged to the towns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>享保年間には更に職務が拡大され、寺社の管理や町役人の交替及び家屋敷の売買に関する吟味、祭事の際の警備、罪人の捕縛・吟味への参加なども担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kyoho era (1716-1735), the duties of Machidai were expanded to cover supervising temples and shrines, examination of replacement of the town officials and purchase and sale of an estate, guard at festivals and events, arrest of a criminal, participation in city commissioner&apos;s examination, and the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kyoho era (1716-1735), the duties of Machidai were expanded to cover supervising temples and shrines, examination of replacement of the town officials and purchase and sale of an estate, guard at festivals and events, arrest of a criminal, participation in city magistrates&apos; examination, and so on.</e>
<cmt>and the like を and so on に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kyoho era (1716-1735), the duties of Machidai were expanded to cover supervising temples and shrines, examination of replacement of the town officials and purchase and sale of an estate, guard at festivals and events, arrest of a criminal, participation in city magistrates&apos; examination, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>更に京都の町は江戸幕府以前からの様々な法令・慣習などが定められており、奉行所の与力・同心がこれらを把握する事が困難となっていたために、彼らからの諮問を受けた町代が先例などに基づいて回答を行う事も町代の重要な職務となるなど、奉行所の職務・運営を円滑化に必要な事務業務の代行が町代に委任されるようになって、町奉行の組織維持のための一端を担うようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As ordinance and convention had been established in the towns in Kyoto before the Edo period, which ranged too wide for police sergeants and constables to comprehend, it became also an important duty for Machidai to answer the questions from the police sergeants and constables based on the precedents--As such, Machidai became authorized to act as a proxy in execution of secretarial works necessary for facilitating the duties and operations of the Koyto city commissioner&apos;s office, thereby contributed to keep organization of the city commissioner&apos;s office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As ordinance and convention had been established in the towns in Kyoto before the Edo period, which ranged too wide for police sergeants and constables to comprehend, it became also an important duty for Machidai to answer the questions from the police sergeants and constables based on the precedents--As such, Machidai became authorized to act as a proxy in execution of secretarial works necessary for facilitating the duties and operations of the Kyoto city magistrates&apos; office, thereby contributed to keep organization of the city magistrates&apos; office.</e>
<cmt>Koyto を Kyoto に修正しました。commissioner を magistrates に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As ordinance and convention had been established in the towns in Kyoto before the Edo period, which ranged too wide for police sergeants and constables to comprehend, it became also an important duty for Machidai to answer the questions from the police sergeants and constables based on the precedents--As such, Machidai became authorized to act as a proxy in execution of secretarial works necessary for facilitating the duties and operations of the Kyoto city magistrates&apos; office, thereby contributed to keep organization of the city magistrates&apos; office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、本来は京都市民の代表であった町人身分の町代が次第に町奉行所において地位を固めるようになると、京都の司法・行政に大きな影響力を与えた公家や寺社などとも関係を結んでいくようになってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machidai, a townsman who originally represented the Kyoto citizens, gradually built up a position in the Kyoto city commissioner&apos;s office, and also formed relationship with the court nobles, temples, and shrines, which were quite influential in legislature and administration of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machidai, a townsman who originally represented the Kyoto citizens, gradually built up a position in the Kyoto city magistrates&apos; office, and also formed relationship with the court nobles, temples, and shrines, which were quite influential in legislature and administration of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>commissioner を magistrates に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machidai, a townsman who originally represented the Kyoto citizens, gradually built up a position in the Kyoto city magistrates&apos; office, and also formed relationship with the court nobles, temples, and shrines, which were quite influential in legislature and administration of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうした風潮に対して身分制度を維持しようとする町奉行側、支配側の代理人と化した町代への反感と嫉妬を抱く市民側の双方から、町代が圧迫を受けるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To counter the trend, the Kyoto city commissioner managed to keep the class system and the Kyoto citizens had antipathy toward Machidai, who had become the ruler&apos;s proxy--Machidai caught between these two sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To counter the trend, the Kyoto city magistrates managed to keep the class system and the Kyoto citizens had antipathy toward Machidai, who had become the ruler&apos;s proxy--Machidai caught between these two sides.</e>
<cmt>commissioner を magistrates に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To counter the trend, the Kyoto city magistrates managed to keep the class system and the Kyoto citizens had antipathy toward Machidai, who had become the ruler&apos;s proxy--Machidai caught between these two sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、世襲によって町代としての能力の無い人物が町代になる例も発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make matters worse, as the position of Machidai was hereditary, some incompetent Machidai emerged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make matters worse, as the position of Machidai was hereditary, some incompetent Machidai emerged.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To make matters worse, as the position of Machidai was hereditary, some incompetent Machidai emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>文化 (日本)14年（1817年）から翌年にかけて町組による町代改義と呼ばれる訴訟が起こされて町奉行側が町組側を支持したことにより、町代は大きな打撃を受けることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1871 to 1872, the groups of towns filed a suit against Machidai (&apos;Machidai kaigi&apos; suit) and the city commissioner supported the groups side, which made a great impact on Machidai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1871 to 1872, the groups of towns filed a suit against Machidai (&apos;Machidai kaigi&apos; suit) and the city magistrates supported the groups side, which made a great impact on Machidai.</e>
<cmt>commissioner を magistrates に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1871 to 1872, the groups of towns filed a suit against Machidai (&apos;Machidai kaigi&apos; suit) and the city magistrates supported the groups side, which made a great impact on Machidai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>