<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>検非違使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi (police and judicial chief)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi (police and judicial chief)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi (police and judicial chief)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>検非違使（けびいし、けんびいし）は日本の律令制下の令外官の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi is one of the Ryoge no kans (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi was a Ryoge no kan post (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>fixed tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi was a Ryoge no kan post (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo Code).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「非違を検察する」の意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means &apos;doing justice.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of the post was to &quot;do justice.&quot;</e>
<cmt>first translation was too short of a sentence so I lengthened it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of the post was to &apos;do justice.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>検非違使庁の官人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi is a government official of Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi was a government official within the Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi was a government official within the Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>佐と尉の唐名は廷尉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tang name of suke (assistant) and jyo (military officer) are Eni (fourth rank of the Kyukei (nine government posts of Han dynasty)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tang name for the Suke (assistant) and Jyo (military officer) was Eni (Fourth Rank of the Kyukei [Nine government posts of the Han Dynasty]).</e>
<cmt>used brackets instead of double parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tang name for the Suke (assistant) and Jo (military officer) was Eni (Fourth Rank of the Kyukei (Nine government posts of the Han Dynasty)).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>京都の治安維持と民政を所管した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi took charge of maintaining security and handling civil affairs in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi were in charge of maintaining security and handling civil affairs in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi were in charge of maintaining security and handling civil affairs in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、平安時代後期には令制国にも置かれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To maintain security, it was also placed in ryoseikoku (province) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For security purposes, the post was also placed in Ryoseikoku (provinces) in the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>capitalized Ryoseikoku and Period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For security purposes, the post was also placed in Ryoseikoku (provinces) in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="7">
<j>平安時代の弘仁7年（816年）が初見で、その頃に設置されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first appearance of Kebiishi was in 816, the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the post of Kebiishi was created during the Heian Period in 816 as this was the first time it appeared.</e>
<cmt>combined the following sentence with this one for better flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the post of Kebiishi was created during the Heian period in 816 as this was the first time it appeared.</e>
<cmt>原文を1文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当初は衛門府の役人が宣旨によって兼務していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, government official of Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) combined with Kebiishi based on senji (imperial decree).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, government officials of Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) combined with Kebiishi based on Senji (Imperial Decree).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar; capitalized &quot;Imperial Decree&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, government officials of Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards) combined with Kebiishi based on Senji (Imperial Decree).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>官位相当は無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no Kebiishi equivalent to official court rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi did not have an official court rank.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi did not have an official court rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>五位から昇殿が許され殿上人となるため、武士の出世の目安となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because a Kebiishi could become a tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) who was allowed into access to the imperial palace when he or she was placed in goi (Fifth Rank), Kebiishi became a measure of success for Samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a Kebiishi could become a Tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) the post became a measure of success for a Samurai when they were placed in goi (Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>The content in the parenthesis and the content in the sentence say the same thing, so I eliminated one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a Kebiishi could become a Tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) the post became a measure of success for a samurai when they were placed in goi (Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>司法を担当していた刑部省、警察・監察を担当していた弾正台、都に関わる行政・治安・司法を統括していた京職等の他の官庁の職掌を段々と奪うようになり、検非違使は大きな権力を振るうようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi took more and more official duties out of other authorities such as Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice) responsible for judiciary branch, danjodai (Board of Censors) responsible for police and inspection, Kyoshiki（Capital Bureau）controlling administrative, security, and judiciary branches related to capital, and then exercised enormous power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi took more and more official duties from other authorities such as Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice) who was responsible for the judiciary branch, Danjodai (Board of Censors) who was responsible for police and inspections, Kyoshiki (Capital Bureau) who controlled administrative security and other judiciary branches related to the capital, and exercised enormous power.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar and made sure all job titles were capitalized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi took more and more official duties from other authorities such as Gyobusho (Ministry of Justice) who was responsible for the judiciary branch, Danjodai (Board of Censors) who was responsible for police and inspections, Kyoshiki (Capital Bureau) who controlled administrative security and other judiciary branches related to the capital, and exercised enormous power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>平安時代後期には刑事事件に関する職権行使のために律令とはちがった性質の「庁例」（使庁の流例ともいわれた慣習法）を適用するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period, Cho-Rei (the law enacted by the &quot;Kebiishi&quot;) (common law called historical custom of Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief)) different from the Ritsuryo codes was applied in order to exercise its authority on criminal cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian Period, Cho-Rei (the law enacted by the Kebiishi) (a common law called a historical custom of the Kebiishicho), different from the Ritsuryo Code, was applied in order to exercise the authority of the Kebiishi in criminal cases.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Period&quot; and &quot;Code&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Heian period, &apos;Cho-Rei&apos; (a common law called a historical custom of the Kebiishicho), different from the Ritsuryo Code, was applied in order to exercise the authority of the Kebiishi in criminal cases.</e>
<cmt>用語補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、この頃から検非違使庁における事務は別当の自宅で行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, clerical works for Kebiishicho was done at Betto&apos;s place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, clerical work for the Kebiishicho were taken care of at the Betto&apos;s home.</e>
<cmt>自宅 place→home; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, clerical work for the Kebiishicho were taken care of at the residence of Betto (Superintendent).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>平安時代末期になると院政の軍事組織である北面武士に取って代わられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of Heian period, Kebiishis were replaced with Imperial Palace Guards for the north side which were militant organization of Insei (rule by the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Heian Period, Kebiishi were replaced by Imperial Palace Guards for the North Side, who were a militant organization of Insei (ruled by the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Heian period, Kebiishi were replaced by Imperial Palace Guards for the North Side, who were a militant organization of Insei (ruled by the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>更に鎌倉幕府が六波羅探題を設置すると次第に弱体化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, when the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese federal government headed by shogun) established the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), Kebiishi was gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, when the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) established the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), Kebiishi were gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>fixed content in parenthesis pertaining to the Kamakura bakufu since it contained a spelling error and did nto match the word list; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, when the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) established the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto), Kebiishi were gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>そして、室町時代には幕府が京都に置かれ、侍所に権限を掌握されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, the bakufu was placed in Kyoto, and the power was held by Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi Period, the bakufu was placed in Kyoto and authority became held by the Samuraidokoro (Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the bakufu was placed in Kyoto and authority became held by the Samuraidokoro (Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内部官職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Government inner service</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Government Inner Service</e>
<cmt>capitalized since this is the title of a section</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Government Inner Service</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>別当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Betto (the superintendent)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Betto (Superintendent)</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;the&quot; and capitalized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Betto</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>四等官の長官（カミ）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to Kami (director) of Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Betto was equivalent to the Kami (director) of the Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Betto was equivalent to the Kami (director) of the Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>定員は1名で、左右衛門督と左右兵衛督のいずれかを兼ねる中納言・権中納言または参議が務めるのが慣例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Bettos was limited to one, and Chunagon (middle counsellor) or Sangi (councillor) who combined either Saemon no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Uemon no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) or Sahyoe no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) and Uhyoe no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards) used to serve as a Betto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was only one Betto post and was held by the Chunagon (middle counselor) or the Sangi (counselor) who also held the posts of either Saemon no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) or Sahyoe no Kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) or Uhyoe no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>fixed spelling errors; made sure all job titles were capitalized;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was only one Betto post and was held by the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), Gon Chunagon (a provisional vice-councilor of state) or the Sangi (counselor) who also held the posts of either Saemon no kami (Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Uemon no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) or Sahyoe no Kami (Captain of the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) or Uhyoe no Kami (Captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>一部補足し、用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、検非違使別当は検非違使を統轄する最高責任者ではあるが、自身は検非違使ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) was the highest responsible person of Kebiishi but not Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) held the highest authority of the Kebiishi but was not personally a Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi no Betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) held the highest authority of the Kebiishi but was not personally a Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>佐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suke (assistant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suke (assistant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suke</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>四等官の次官（スケ）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to Suke (assistant director) of Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Suke of the Government Inner Service was a post equivalent to the assistant director (also called Suke) of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>added details for clarification; fixed grammar; eliminated content in parenthesis pertaining to the Shitokan since it is already described above</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Suke of the Government Inner Service was a post equivalent to the assistant director (also called Suke) of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>定員は2名で、左右衛門権佐が兼務していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Sukes was limited to two, and Uemon Gon no suke (provisional assistant captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Saemon no gon no suke (provisional assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) served as a Suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were only two posts of Suke which were served by the Uemon Gon no Suke (provisional assistant captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Saemon no Gon no Suke (provisional assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were only two posts of Suke which were served by the Uemon Gon no Suke (provisional assistant captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Saemon no Gon no Suke (provisional assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>なお、原則として検非違使を務めるのは権官である左右衛門権佐であり、正官である左右衛門佐が検非違使を務めることはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a general rule, Uemon Gon no suke and Saemon no gon no suke who were kenkans (powerful post, official) served as a Kebiishi but Saemon no suke (assistant captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Uemon no suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) who were seikans (regular post, official) had never served as a Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a general rule, Uemon Gon no Suke and Saemon no Gon no Suke were Kenkan (a powerful offical post) and served as Kebiishi, but the Saemon no Suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Uemon no Suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) were Seikan (a regular official post) and never served as Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>made sure all job titles were capitalized; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a general rule, Uemon Gon no Suke and Saemon no Gon no Suke were Gonkan (a powerful official post) and served as Kebiishi, but the Saemon no Suke (Assistant Captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Uemon no Suke (Assistant Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) were Seikan (a regular official post) and never served as Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>「権官」は律令制では「ごんかん」と読むため修正しました。スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>別当は兼務が多かったので実質的に検非違使庁の責任者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Betto was often combined with other government post, virtually Suke was the responsible person of Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suke were essentially the person in charge at a Kebishiicho since Betto were often combined with other governments posts.</e>
<cmt>Changed sentence order and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suke were essentially the person in charge at a Kebiishicho since Betto were often combined with other governments posts.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>蔵人で検非違使佐を兼ねる蔵人佐や、蔵人・弁官・検非違使佐を兼ねる三事兼帯もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were also a kurodonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) who combined a Kurodo (Chamberlain) with a Kebiishi no suke (assistant official of the Police and Judicial Chief), and a sanji kentai (filling three positions) who combined a Kurodo with a benkan (officials of the dajokan) and a Kebiishi no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also a post of Kurodonosuke (assistant official of the Kurodo) who double posted as a Kurodo (Chamberlain) and a Kebiishi no Suke (assistant official of the Police and Judicial Chief), as well as a Sanji Kentai (a post that filled three positions) that held the post of Kurodo, Benkan (official of the Daijokan) and a Kebiishi no suke.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar, capitalization of titles, typos, and grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also a post of Kurodonosuke (assistant official of the Kurodo) who double posted as a Kurodo (Chamberlain) and a Kebiishi no Suke (assistant official of the Police and Judicial Chief), as well as a Sanji Kentai (a post that filled three positions) that held the post of Kurodo, Benkan (official of the Daijokan) and a Kebiishi no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>大尉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijo (Senior Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijo (Senior Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijo (Senior Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>四等官の判官（ジョウ）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to Hangan (inspector (third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period) of Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Daijo was equivalent to a Hangan (Inspector; third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period) of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>eliminated double parenthesis with a semi-colon; eliminated content in parenthesis pertaining to the Shitokan since has already been explained</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Daijo was equivalent to a Jo (Inspector; third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period; also known as Hogan) of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>「判官」は律令制では「じょう」とされるため修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>定員は4名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Daijos was limited to four.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Daijo posts was limited to four.</e>
<cmt>fixed pluralization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Daijo posts was limited to four.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そして、衛門大尉が兼務していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uemon no Taijo (Senior Lieutenant of Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Saemon no daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) combined with Daijo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uemon no Daijo (Senior Lieutenant of Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Saemon no Daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) held the position of Daijo as a second post.</e>
<cmt>兼務→holding two posts concurrently &lt;http://www.csse.monash.edu.au/~jwb/cgi-bin/wwwjdic.cgi?1F&gt;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uemon no Daijo (Senior Lieutenant of Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) and Saemon no Daijo (Senior Lieutenant at the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) held the position of Daijo as a second post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>明法家である坂上氏及び中原氏が世襲するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sakanoue clan and the Nakahara clan who were lawyers held this post by succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of Daijo became a hereditary post for the Sakanoue and Nakahara clans as they practiced law.</e>
<cmt>世襲→hereditary; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of Daijo became a hereditary post for the Sakanoue and Nakahara clans as Myohoka (teacher of law).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>少尉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shojo (junior lieutenant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shojo (Junior Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>capitalized job title in parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shojo (Junior Lieutenant)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>四等官の判官（ジョウ）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to Hangan (inspector (third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period) of Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Shojo was equivalent to a Hangan of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>eliminated all content in parenthesis since it is written directly above</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Shojo was equivalent to a Jo of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>定員は不定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Shojos was not limited.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no limit to the number of Shojo posts.</e>
<cmt>fixed pluralization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no limit to the number of Shojo posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>そして、衛門尉が兼務していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emon no jo (third-ranked officer of Outer Palace Guards) combined with Shojo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emon no Jo (Third Ranked Officers of Outer Palace Guards) were double posted as Shojo.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar and changed &quot;comination&quot; to &quot;double post&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emon no Jo (Third Ranked Officers of Outer Palace Guards) were double posted as Shojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>10世紀後半頃から源氏や平氏などの武士がなることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late 10th century, the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan often had this responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late 10th century, the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan often held this post.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late 10th century, the Minamoto clan and the Taira clan often held this post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>源義経を九郎判官と呼ぶのもこの官職に就いていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune was called Kuro-hangan because he had this responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune was called Kuro-hangan because he had this responsibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune was called Kuro-hogan because he had this responsibility.</e>
<cmt>読みを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="38">
<j>大志、少志</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daishi(senior assistant lieutenant), shoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daishi and Shoshi (Senior Assistant Lieutenants)</e>
<cmt>fixed capitalization and spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daishi and Shoshi (Senior Assistant Lieutenants)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>四等官の主典（サカン）に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to Sakan (secretary) of Shitokan (four classifications of bureaucrats&apos; ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This post was equivalent to the Sakan (secretary) of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>eliminated content in parenthesis pertaining to the Shitokan because it is already written above</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This post was equivalent to the Sakan (secretary) of the Shitokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>定員は不定で、若年の明法家がなることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Shojos was not limited, and young layers often had this responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no limit to the number officers who could old this post.</e>
<cmt>Is &quot;Shojos&quot; an error here? Shouldn&apos;t it be &quot;Daishi&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no limit to the number officers who could old this post and many young Myohoka assumed the post.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="41">
<j>看督長（かどのおさ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kadonoosa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadonoosa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadonoosa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>罪人を収監する監獄を管理する役であったが、後に罪人を捕縛する役になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kadonoosa was responsible for controlling the prison to lock up criminals, and later responsible for capturing criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadonoosa was responsible for controlling the prison, locking up criminals, and later responsible for capturing criminals.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadonoosa was responsible for controlling the prison, locking up criminals, and later responsible for capturing criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>赤狩衣、白衣、布袴に白杖を持つ異形のいでたちで職務に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kadonoosa performed a duty in his strange outfits, a red Kariginu (robe), a white frock, and hogo (hoko) with a while walking stick in his hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadonoosa performed their duty in an atypical outfit consisting of a red Kariginu (robe), a white frock, and held a white walking stick.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadonoosa performed their duty in an atypical outfit consisting of a red Kariginu (robe), a white frock, and held a white walking stick.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="44">
<j>案主（あんじゅ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anju (officer who recorded and stored documents at Shoens, authorities)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anju (officer who recorded and stored documents at a Shoen; manor)</e>
<cmt>Shoen→manor(?)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anju (officer who recorded and stored documents at a Shoen; manor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>検非違使庁の事務役人で、当初1名だったが後に人数が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anju is a clerical officer of Kebiishicho, and at the beginning, the number of Anjus was limited to one but later increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anju was a clerical officer of the Kebiishicho which was initially limited to one post but was later increased.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anju was a clerical officer of the Kebiishicho which was initially limited to one post but was later increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>火長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kacho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kacho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kacho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>衛門府の衛士から選抜された者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kacho was those who were selected from among Eshis (guards) of Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kacho were selected from the Eshi (guards) of Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kacho were selected from the Eshi (guards) of Emonfu (Headquarters of the Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そして、ここから看督長や案主が選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Kadonoosa and Anju were selected from among Kachos.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadonoosa and Anju were then selected among the Kacho.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadonoosa and Anju were then selected among the Kacho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="49">
<j>放免</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>元罪人で、下部とも呼び、罪を許され検非違使庁で働くものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homen was a former criminal and also called a Shimobe whose sin was forgiven and worked for Kebiishicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen was a former criminal, also referred to as a Shimobe, whose sins had been forgiven and worked for the Kebiishicho.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen was a former criminal, also referred to as a Shimobe, whose sins had been forgiven and worked for the Kebiishicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>実際に犯罪者を探索し、捕縛や拷問を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Homen searched for criminals and was responsible for capture and torture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen were in fact put in charge of searching for criminals and responsible for their capture and torture.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen were in fact put in charge of searching for criminals and responsible for their capture and torture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>初期のコンピュータゲーム『平安京エイリアン』のプレイヤーズ・キャラクターは検非違使という設定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Player&apos;s character of early computer game &quot;Heiankyo Alien&quot; was modeled on Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a player character from an early computer game called &quot;Heiankyo&quot; that was modeled after Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a player character from an early computer game called &quot;Heiankyo&quot; that was modeled after Kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Poe(id:16973), Enables(id:87497), Izayohi(id:13095), Blue-comet(id:192801), Nnh(id:474), 経済準学士(id:22656), 俊(id:14924), 海衛士(id:19229), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), Shimoxx(id:9332), 李(id:10582), 羊鶴(id:7557), Martin(id:6394), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>