<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>按察使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azechi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azechi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azechi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>按察使（あぜち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azechi (Inspector of the provincial government)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azechi (Inspector of the provincial government)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azechi (Inspector of the provincial government)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>奈良時代に設置された、地方行政を監督する令外官の官職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A government post of Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) which was established in the Nara period to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A government post of Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) which was established in the Nara period to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A government post of Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) which was established in the Nara period to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>詳細は按察使 (律令制)を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Azechi (in the Ritsuryo system) for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Azechi (in the Ritsuryo system) for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Azechi (in the Ritsuryo system) for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>明治維新後、明治政府によっておかれた地方政治を監督する官名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an official name of a government office which was set up by the Meiji Government after the Maiji Restoration to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a title of government officials who supervise local government, which was set up by the Meiji Government after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>表現変更Maiji → Meiji</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a title of government officials who supervise local government, which was set up by the Meiji Government after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>詳細は按察使 (明治政府)を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See Azechi (in the Meiji Government) for details.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See Azechi (in the Meiji Government) for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See Azechi (in the Meiji Government) for details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>按察使 (律令制)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azechi (in the Ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azechi (in the Ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azechi (in the Ritsuryo system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>按察使（あぜち）は、地方行政を監督する令外官の官職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azechi was a government post of Ryoge no kan to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azechi was a government post of Ryoge no kan to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azechi was a government post of Ryoge no kan to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>数カ国の国守の内から1人を選任し、その管内における国司の行政の監察を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among kokushu (head of provincial governors) from several provinces a person was elected to supervise the administration by kokushi (provincial governors) within its jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From kokushu (head of provincial governors) of several provinces, one person was selected to supervise the administration of kokushi (provincial governors) within its jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt>表現変更by　→ of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From kokushu (head of provincial governors) of several provinces, one person was selected to supervise the administration of kokushi (provincial governors) within its jurisdiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>奈良時代の719年（養老3年）に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established in 719 of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established in 719 of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established in 719 of the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>平安時代以降は陸奥国・出羽国の按察使だけを残し、納言（大納言・中納言・少納言）・参議などとの兼任となり実体がなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Heian period, except for the Azechi in Mutsu Province and Dewa Province, the post was held concurrently with Nagon (Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Chunagon (middle counsellor), Shonagon (lesser councilor of state), Sangi (councillor) and so on, making the post unsubstantial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Heian period, except for the Azechi in Mutsu Province and Dewa Province, the post was held concurrently with Nagon (Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Chunagon (middle counsellor), Shonagon (lesser councilor of state)), Sangi (councillor) and so on, making the post unsubstantial.</e>
<cmt>)の追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Heian period, except for the Azechi in Mutsu Province and Dewa Province, the post was held concurrently with Nagon (Dainagon [chief councilor of state], Chunagon [vice-councilor of state], Shonagon [lesser councilor of state]), Sangi (councillor) and so on, making the post unsubstantial.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。 (Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Chunagon (middle counsellor), Shonagon (lesser councilor of state))→（Dainagon [chief councilor of state], Chunagon [vice-councilor of state], Shonagon [lesser councilor of state])</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>初めて任命された按察使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Persons who were first appointed as Azechi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Persons who were first appointed as Azechi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Persons who were first appointed as Azechi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>『続日本紀』によると、奈良時代初頭の719年（養老3年）7月13日に以下の11名の国司が初めて按察使に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), the following eleven person in the position of kokushi (provincial governors) were appointed as Azechi for the first time on July 13, 719, of the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), the following eleven persons in the position of kokushi (provincial governors) were appointed as Azechi for the first time on July 13, 719, of the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt>person → persons</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), the following eleven persons in the position of kokushi were appointed as Azechi for the first time on July 13, 719, of the early Nara period.</e>
<cmt>(provincial governors) 前出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>門部王（伊勢国守、従五位上）は伊賀国、志摩国の2国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kadobe no Okimi (director of Ise Province and Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered two provinces, namely Iga Provinc and Shima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kadobe no Okimi (director of Ise Province and Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered two provinces, namely Iga Provinc and Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kadobe no Okimi (Ise no kuni no kami [Governor of Ise Province], Jugoinojo [Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade]) administered two provinces, namely Iga Provinc and Shima Province.</e>
<cmt>後列の表現に合わせました。(Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)→[Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>大伴山守（遠江国守、正五位上）は駿河国、伊豆国、甲斐国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomo no Yamamori (Totomi no kuni no kami (Governor of Totomi Province), Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Suruga Province, Izu Province, and Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomo no Yamamori (Totomi no kuni no kami (Governor of Totomi Province), Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Suruga Province, Izu Province, and Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomo no Yamamori (Totomi no kuni no kami [Governor of Totomi Province], Shogoinojo [Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade]) administered three provinces, namely Suruga Province, Izu Province, and Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>藤原宇合（常陸国守、正五位上）は安房国、上総国、下総国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Umakai (Hitachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Hitachi Province), Shogoinojo) administered three provinces, namely Awa Province, Kazusa Province, and Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Umakai (Hitachi no kuni no kami (Governor of Hitachi Province), Shogoinojo (Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Awa Province, Kazusa Province, and Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>(Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Umakai (Hitachi no kuni no kami [Governor of Hitachi Province], Shogoinojo) administered three provinces, namely Awa Province, Kazusa Province, and Shimosa Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ][Senior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade]既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>笠麻呂（美濃国守、従四位上）は尾張国、三河国、信濃国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasamaro (Mino no kuni no kami (the governor of Mino Province), Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Owari Province, Mikawa Province, and Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasamaro (Mino no kuni no kami (the governor of Mino Province), Jushiijo (Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Owari Province, Mikawa Province, and Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasamaro (Mino no kuni no kami [Governor of Mino Province], Jushiinojo [Junior Fourth Rank, Upper Grade]) administered three provinces, namely Owari Province, Mikawa Province, and Shinano Province.</e>
<cmt>the governor→Governor(他の列に合わせました）()→[ ]Jushiijo→Jushiinojo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>多治比縣守（武蔵国守、正四位下）は相模国、上野国、下野国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tajihi agatamori (Musashi no kuni no kami (governor of Musashi Province), Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Sagami Province, Kozuke Province, and Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tajihi agatamori (Musashi no kuni no kami (governor of Musashi Province), Shoshiinoge (Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Sagami Province, Kozuke Province, and Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tajihi agatamori (Musashi no kuni no kami [Governor of Musashi Province], Shoshiinoge [Senior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade]) administered three provinces, namely Sagami Province, Kozuke Province, and Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>多治比廣成（越前国守、正五位下）は能登国、越中国、越後国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAJIHI no Hironari (Echizen no kuni no kami (Governor of Echizen Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Noto Province, Ecchu Province, and Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAJIHI no Hironari (Echizen no kuni no kami (Governor of Echizen Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Noto Province, Ecchu Province, and Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAJIHI no Hironari (Echizen no kuni no kami [Governor of Echizen Province], Shogoinoge [Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade]) administered three provinces, namely Noto Province, Ecchu Province, and Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>小野馬養（丹波国守、正五位下）は丹後国、但馬国、因幡国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ONO no Umakai (Tanba no kuni no kami (governor of Tanba Province), Shogoinoge) administered three provinces, namely Tango Province, Tajima Province, and Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ONO no Umakai (Tanba no kuni no kami (governor of Tanba Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Tango Province, Tajima Province, and Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>(Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ONO no Umakai (Tanba no kuni no kami [governor of Tanba Province], Shogoinoge) administered three provinces, namely Tango Province, Tajima Province, and Inaba Province.</e>
<cmt>governor→Governor(他の列に合わせました）()→[ ] [Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade]既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>息長臣足（出雲国守、従五位下）は伯耆国、石見国の2国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKINAGA no Omitari (Izumo no kuni no kami (Governor of Izumo Province), Jugoinoge) administered two provinces, namely Hoki Province, and Iwami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OKINAGA no Omitari (Izumo no kuni no kami (Governor of Izumo Province), Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered two provinces, namely Hoki Province, and Iwami Province.</e>
<cmt>(Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OKINAGA no Omitari (Izumo no kuni no kami [Governor of Izumo Province], Jugoinoge [Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade]) administered two provinces, namely Hoki Province, and Iwami Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ]</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="20">
<j>鴨吉備麻呂（播磨国守、従四位下）は備前国、美作国、備中国、淡路国の4国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KAMO no Kibimaro (Harima no kuni no kami (the governor of Harima Province), Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered four provinces, namely Bizen Province, Mimasaka Province, Bicchu Province, and Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KAMO no Kibimaro (Harima no kuni no kami (the governor of Harima Province), Jushiinoge (Junior Forth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered four provinces, namely Bizen Province, Mimasaka Province, Bicchu Province, and Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KAMO no Kibimaro (Harima no kuni no kami [Governor of Harima Province], Jushiinoge [Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade]) administered four provinces, namely Bizen Province, Mimasaka Province, Bicchu Province, and Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>the governor→Governor(他の列に合わせました）()→[ ]Forth→Fourth</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="21">
<j>高安王（伊予国守、従五位上）は阿波国、讃岐国、土佐国の3国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKAYASU no Okimi (Iyo no kuni no kami (Governor of Iyo Province), Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Awa Province, Sanuki Province, and Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKAYASU no Okimi (Iyo no kuni no kami (Governor of Iyo Province), Jugoinojo (Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade)) administered three provinces, namely Awa Province, Sanuki Province, and Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAKAYASU no Okimi (Iyo no kuni no kami [Governor of Iyo Province], Jugoinojo) administered three provinces, namely Awa Province, Sanuki Province, and Tosa Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ] [Junior Fifth Rank, Upper Grade]既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="22">
<j>大伴宿奈麻呂（備後国守、正五位下）は安芸国、周防国の2国を管する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OTOMO no Sukunamaro (Bingo no kuni no kami (Governor of Bingo Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered two provinces, namely Aki Province, and Suo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OTOMO no Sukunamaro (Bingo no kuni no kami (Governor of Bingo Province), Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) administered two provinces, namely Aki Province, and Suo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OTOMO no Sukunamaro (Bingo no kuni no kami [Governor of Bingo Province], Shogoinoge) administered two provinces, namely Aki Province, and Suo Province.</e>
<cmt>()→[ ] [Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade]既出のため削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="23">
<j>管轄地域を巡回し治安維持することが按察使の主務であったため賊等の矛先が向けられることもあり、720年（養老4年）夏には陸奥国按察使の上毛野廣人が殺害される事件が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since patrolling and maintaining the public order of the jurisdiction area were the main function of the Azechi, he sometimes received rebels&apos; attack, developing an incident that KAMITSUKENO Hiroto, the Azechi of Mutsu Province, was murdered in the summer of 720.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since patrolling and maintaining the public order of the jurisdiction area were the main function of the Azechi, he sometimes received rebels&apos; attack, developing an incident that KAMITSUKENO Hiroto, the Azechi of Mutsu Province, was murdered in the summer of 720.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since patrolling and maintaining the public order of the jurisdiction area were the main function of the Azechi, he sometimes received rebels&apos; attack, developing an incident that KAMITSUKENO Hiroto, the Azechi of Mutsu Province, was murdered in the summer of 720.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>朝廷はただちに武蔵国按察使の多治比縣守を持節征夷将軍に任じて下毛野石代を副将軍に、また阿倍駿河を持節鎭狄将軍に据えてこれを鎮圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial court immediately appointed Tajihi agatamori, the Azechi of Musashi Province, as Jisetsu Sei Shogun (the general of conquering east-barbarians), SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro as vice-shogun, and ABE no Suruga as Jisetsu Chinteki Shogun (the general of pacifying north barbarians) to suppress this incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial court immediately appointed Tajihi agatamori, the Azechi of Musashi Province, as Jisetsu Sei Shogun (the general of conquering east-barbarians), SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro as vice-shogun, and ABE no Suruga as Jisetsu Chinteki Shogun (the general of pacifying north barbarians) to suppress this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial court immediately appointed Tajihi agatamori, the Azechi of Musashi Province, as Jisetsu Sei Shogun (the general of conquering east-barbarians), SHIMOTSUKENU no Iwashiro as vice-shogun, and ABE no Suruga as Jisetsu Chinteki Shogun (the general of pacifying north barbarians) to suppress this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="25">
<j>按察使 (明治時代)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azechi (in the Meiji Period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azechi (in the Meiji Period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azechi (in the Meiji Period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>明治政府における按察使（あぜち）は、地方政治を監督する官である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azechi under the Meiji Government was a government officer to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azechi under the Meiji Government was a government officer to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azechi under the Meiji Government was a government officer to supervise local government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="27">
<j>1869年（明治2年）政府の官制を律令制にならって改定した際に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was established in 1869 when the governmental regulations were revised after the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was established in 1869 when the governmental regulations were revised after the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was established in 1869 when the governmental regulations were revised after the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>官職には長官・次官・正判官・権判官を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a government post, a director, undersecretary, sei-hangan (inspector), and associate judge were set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a government post, a director, undersecretary, sei-hangan (inspector), and associate judge were set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a government post, a director, undersecretary, sei-hangan (inspector), and associate judge were set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>三陸（陸前国・陸中国・陸奥国）、両羽（羽前国・羽後国）、磐城国按察使府、越後按察使府が置かれただけで実際に活動することはなく、翌1870年（明治3年）10月に廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Sanriku (i.e. Rikuzen Province, Rikuchu Province, Mutsu Province), Ryouu (i.e. Uzen Province, Ugo Province),Iwaki Province Azechi Office, and Echigo Azechi Office were established but not actually worked and in October 1870, the next year, they were abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Sanriku (i.e. Rikuzen Province, Rikuchu Province, Mutsu Province), Ryouu (i.e. Uzen Province, Ugo Province), Iwaki Province Azechi Office, and Echigo Azechi Office were established but did not actually worked and in October 1870, the next year, they were abolished.</e>
<cmt>和句読点　、　→英文句読点　, didを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Sanriku (i.e. Rikuzen Province, Rikuchu Province, Mutsu Province), Ryouu (i.e. Uzen Province, Ugo Province), Iwaki Province Azechi Office, and Echigo Azechi Office were established but did not in fact worked and in October 1870, the next year, they were abolished.</e>
<cmt>actually→in fact</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Izayohi(id:13095), FCTR2(id:213046), 新アルパカ(id:65850), 海衛士(id:19229), Cprobot(id:97843), Dokutou(id:14850), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Yanahan(id:2437), NDR(id:5500), Lucas0123(id:130266), Ws227(id:208643), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>