<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>院司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshi/In no tsukasa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshi/In no tsukasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshi/In no tsukasa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>院司（いんし、いんのつかさ）は、日本の中世・古代において、太上天皇や女院の直属機関として設置された院庁の職員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshi (or In no tsukasa) is an agency official of the imperial agency which was set up directly under the retired emperors and nyoin (empress, empress dowager or grand empress dowager) in the ancient period to the middle ages in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshi (or In no tsukasa) is an agency official of the imperial agency set up directly under the retired emperors and nyoin (empress, empress dowager or grand empress dowager) during the ancient period to the middle ages in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshi (or In no tsukasa) is an official of In no cho (Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) set up directly under the retired emperors and nyoin (empress, empress dowager or grand empress dowager) during the ancient period to the middle ages in Japan.</e>
<cmt>agency official→official院庁の訳変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中流貴族が任命されることが多く、他の日本の官制と兼任する兼官だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally mid-ranking aristocrats were appointed to Inshi concurrently with other Japanese officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally mid-ranking aristocrats were appointed to Inshi concurrently with other Japanese officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally mid-ranking aristocrats were appointed to Inshi concurrently with other Japanese official posts.</e>
<cmt>officials→official posts</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代後期に院政が開始すると、上皇の政務機関である院庁の院司は、政治の枢要を担う重要職とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As cloistered rule started in the late Heian era, the post of Inshi in the imperial agency which was cloistered political organ became important post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As cloistered rule started in the late Heian era, the post of Inshi in the imperial agency, a cloistered political organ, became an important post.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the cloister government started in the late Heian period, the post of Inshi in In no cho, a retired emperor&apos;s political organ, became an important post.</e>
<cmt>era→periodcloistered→retired emperor&apos;s院司、院政の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>本項では、院政の院司について詳述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article details about the Inshi of cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article details the Inshi of cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section describes the details of the Inshi of the cloister government.</e>
<cmt>院政の表記変更&quot;This article details the Inshi of the cloister government.&quot; -&gt; &quot;This section describes the details of the Inshi of the cloister government.&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>院政の院司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshi in cloistered rule</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshi in cloistered rule</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshi in the cloister government</e>
<cmt>院政の表記変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>院司は、嵯峨天皇の835年（承和 (日本)2年）、院別当安倍安仁とあるのが初見である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first case of Inshi was confirmed as In-no betto (cloistered chief officer) ABE no Yasuhito in 835, in the reign of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first case of Inshi was confirmed as In-no betto (cloistered chief officer) ABE no Yasuhito in 835, during the reign of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first case of Inshi was confirmed as In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) ABE no Yasuhito in 835, during the reign of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>院別当の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当初、院庁は上皇の家政機関として設置され、所務沙汰・雑務沙汰が主要な用務であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, imperial agency was established as a household agency for retired emperors and its main works were trial dealing with land-related issues and with civil affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the imperial agency was established as a household agency for retired emperors and its main work consisted of trials dealing with land-related issues and with civil affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, In no cho was established as a household agency for retired emperors and its main work consisted of trials dealing with land-related issues and with civil affairs.</e>
<cmt>院庁の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長官は別当（べっとう）、次官を判官代（ほうがんだい）、主典を主典代（さかんだい）といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ranks of Inshi were Betto (chief officer), Hogandai (deputy chief officer) and Sakandai (the third rank officer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ranks of Inshi were Betto (chief officer), Hogandai (deputy chief officer) and Sakandai (the third rank officer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ranks of Inshi were Betto (chief officer), Hogandai (deputy chief officer) and Sakandai (secretary).</e>
<cmt>「主典代」は読み方どおりとし、括弧内もsecretaryのみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1086年（応徳3年）前後に白河天皇が院政を開始すると、院庁を構成する院司の役割は非常に重要なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Shirakawa started the cloistered rule around 1086, the role of inshi which made up the imperial agency became very important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Shirakawa started the cloistered rule around 1086, the role of inshi, which made up the imperial agency, became very important.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Shirakawa started the cloister government around 1086, the role of inshi, which made up In no cho, became very important.</e>
<cmt>院政、院庁の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>院司は、治天の君（皇室の家長）の命を受け、院庁下文・院庁牒・院宣を発給し、治天の政治意思を具現化するため、実務を遂行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshi issued letters and orders such as &quot;innocho kudashibumi&quot; (a letter issued by innocho, the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office), &quot;innochocho&quot; (orders issued by innocho) and &quot;inzen&quot; (a decree from the retired Emperor) under the &quot;Chiten no kimi&quot; (the retired emperor in power) in order to carry out the cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshi issued letters and orders such as &quot;innocho kudashibumi&quot; (a letter issued by innocho, the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office), &quot;innochocho&quot; (orders issued by innocho) and &quot;inzen&quot; (a decree from the retired Emperor) under the &quot;Chiten no kimi&quot; (the retired emperor in power) in order to carry out the cloistered rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshi issued letters and orders such as &quot;in no cho kudashibumi&quot; (a letter issued by in no cho), &quot;in no cho cho&quot; (orders issued by in no cho) and &quot;inzen&quot; (a decree from the retired Emperor) under the &quot;Chiten no kimi&quot; (the retired emperor in power) in order to carry out the cloister government.</e>
<cmt>院庁の表記変更the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office　既出のため削除cloistered rule→cloister government</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため、院司には、蔵人所・弁官・受領などを歴任した実務官僚が充てられることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, practical government officials such as kurodo (Emperor&apos;s secretary), benkan (central administrative controller) and zuryo (local governor) often became inshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, practical government officials such as kurodo (Emperor&apos;s secretary), benkan (central administrative controller) and zuryo (local governor) often became inshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, practical government officials who held successively the position of Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office), benkan (officials of the dajokan) and Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) often became inshi.</e>
<cmt>蔵人所、弁官、受領を定訳に修正「歴任した」を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>彼らは、摂関家のような上級貴族ではなかったが、実務能力をもって登用され、政治に大きな影響を及ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they were not high-ranking aristocrats like the sekkan family, they had political influence because of their business ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they were not high-ranking aristocrats like the sekkan family, they had political influence because of their business ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they were not high-ranking aristocrats like Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) people, they had political influence because of their business ability.</e>
<cmt>摂関家を定訳に修正like Sekkan-ke people としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>院司や他の中流貴族の中には、治天の側近となり、権勢をふるう者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some inshi and other mid-ranking aristocrats became close advisors of the emperor and cloistered emperor with real power and wielded influence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some inshi and other mid-ranking aristocrats became close advisors of the emperor and cloistered emperor with real power and wielded influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some inshi and other mid-ranking aristocrats became close advisors of the emperor and cloistered emperor with real power and wielded influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これを院の近臣という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were called In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were called In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were called In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>院司や院の近臣は、治天の権力を背景として、様々な利益を得ていたが、例えば知行国が給与されることもしばしば見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshi and In no kinshin made various profits behind imperial power and they often received chigyokoku (provincial fiefdom).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshi and In no kinshin made various profits behind imperial power and they often received chigyokoku (provincial fiefdom).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshi and In no kinshin made various profits behind imperial power and they often received chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom).</e>
<cmt>知行国を定訳に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>保元の乱以降の平清盛の急速な台頭も、後白河天皇の院司だったことが、主な理由の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the main reasons that TAIRA no Kiyomori gained power quickly after the Hogen Disturbance, was that he was an Inshi of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the main reasons that TAIRA no Kiyomori gained power quickly after the Hogen Disturbance, was that he was an Inshi of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the main reasons that TAIRA no Kiyomori gained power quickly after the Hogen War, was that he was an Inshi of Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Disturbance→War</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>白河～後鳥羽までの院政最盛期が経過した後も、実質的に院政が消滅する室町時代前期まで（一部の期間を除いて）、院司は政治の枢要を担う重要な役割を果たしていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshi had taken major roles in politics not only during the heights of cloistered rule between Emperor Shirakawa and Emperor Gotoba, also till the beginning of Muromachi era when the cloistered rule extinguished (except certain period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshi had taken major roles in politics not only during the heights of cloistered rule between Emperor Shirakawa and Emperor Gotoba, but also until the beginning of the Muromachi era when the cloistered rule was extinguished (except certain period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshi had taken major roles in politics not only during the heights of the cloister government between Emperor Shirakawa and Emperor Gotoba, but also until the beginning of the Muromachi period when the cloister government was extinguished (except certain period).</e>
<cmt>院政の表記変更era→period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>主な役職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main posts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main posts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main posts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>院別当…院司の最高責任者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office): the highest officer in inshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In no betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office): the highest officer in inshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In no betto: the highest officer of inshi</e>
<cmt>院別当既出のため括弧書き削除in→of（inshi は場所ではなく人）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>嵯峨上皇の譲位とともに南淵永河が任命されたのが最初。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first In no betto was MINAMIBUCHI no Nagakawa, who was appointed as the In no betto at the same time as the retired Emperor Saga abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first In no betto was MINAMIBUCHI no Nagakawa, who was appointed as the In no betto at the same time retired Emperor Saga abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first In no betto was MINAMIBUCHI no Nagakawa, who was appointed as the In no betto at the same time the Retired Emperor Saga abdicated the throne.</e>
<cmt>retired→Retired「the retired Emperor」の「the」を戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>複数名が任命されるのが通例で、公卿もしくは上皇の天皇在位中の蔵人頭が任命されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, several persons were appointed as In no betto, and mostly Kugyo (top court officials) or Kurodo no to (chief of the palace officer) who served for the retired emperor during the reign as the emperor were appointed as In no betto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, several persons were appointed as In no betto, and mostly Kugyo (top court officials) or Kurodo no to (chief of the palace officer) who served the retired emperor during the reign as the emperor were appointed as In no betto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, several persons were appointed as In no betto, and mostly Kugyo (the top court officials) or Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) who served the retired emperor during the reign as the emperor were appointed as In no betto.</e>
<cmt>公卿、蔵人頭を定訳に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>公卿が任命された場合には「公卿別当」、四位が任命された場合には「四位別当」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kugyo was appointed as betto, it was called &quot;Kugyo betto&quot;, and when Shii (Fourth Rank) was appointed, it was called &quot;Shii betto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kugyo was appointed as betto, it was called &quot;Kugyo betto&quot;, and when Shii (Fourth Rank) was appointed, it was called &quot;Shii betto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kugyo was appointed as betto, it was called &quot;Kugyo betto&quot;, and when Shii (Fourth Rank) was appointed, it was called &quot;Shii betto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>白河上皇の頃に公卿別当から院執事（いんのしつし・執事別当）、四位別当から院年預（いんのねんよ・年預別当）が1名ずつ任命されて院庁を統括した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of the retired Emperor Shirakawa, one In no shitsushi (steward of cloistered role) was selected from Kugyo bettos and one In no nenyo (administrative and clerical chief) was selected from Shii bettos to rule the imperial agency.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of the retired Emperor Shirakawa, one In no shitsushi (steward of cloistered role) was selected from Kugyo bettos and one In no nenyo (administrative and clerical chief) was selected from Shii bettos to rule the imperial agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of the retired Emperor Shirakawa, one In no shitsushi (chief officer) was selected from Kugyo bettos and one In no nenyo (one of the positions in In&apos;s office) was selected from Shii bettos to rule In no cho.</e>
<cmt>執事別当、年預別当を定訳に修正院庁の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>更に鎌倉時代にはその上に院執権（いんのしっけん）1名が置かれて公卿別当の中から選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in Kamakura era, the post of In no shikken was added above In no shitsushi and In no nenyo and selected from Kugyo bettos.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in the Kamakura era, the post of In no shikken was added above In no shitsushi and In no nenyo and selected from Kugyo bettos.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the Kamakura period, the post of In no shikken was added above In no shitsushi and In no nenyo and selected from Kugyo bettos.</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>院判官代…別当を補佐して庶務を処理し、院庁が発給した公文に署判する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">inhogandai (office work position) : the second highest officer in inshi and assisted betto, conducted general affairs and signed official letters issued by imperial agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">inhogandai (office work position): the second highest officer in inshi and assisted betto, conducted general affairs and signed official letters issued by imperial agency.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In hogandai : the second highest officer in inshi and assisted betto, conducted general affairs and signed official letters issued by In no cho.</e>
<cmt>inhogandai→In hogandai(office work position)→次が説明なので削除しました。院庁の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>宇多天皇の時代に設置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This position was set in the reign of Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This position was set during the reign of Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This position was set during the reign of Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>白河上皇の時には四位の判官代も存在したが、五位（1･2名）または六位（4･5名）から選出されるのが通例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of the retired emperor Shirakawa, there were hogandai with Shii (fourth rank), however, usually one or two hogandai were selected from Goi (fifth rank) and four or five hogandai were selected from Rokui (sixth rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of retired emperor Shirakawa, there were hogandai with Shii (fourth rank), however, usually one or two hogandai were selected from Goi (fifth rank) and four or five hogandai were selected from Rokui (sixth rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of the Retired Emperor Shirakawa, there were hogandai with Shii (fourth rank), however, usually one or two hogandai were selected from Goi (fifth rank) and four or five hogandai were selected from Rokui (sixth rank).</e>
<cmt>retired emperor→Retired Emperor「the retired Emperor」の「the」を戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>院主典代…別当・判官代の下にあって院の文書・記録作成や考勘、雑務に従事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inshutendai (secretary of the In no tsukasa, the third rank officer) : their main works were such as document and record creation and management in the imperial agency and civil affairs under the betto and the hogandai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inshutendai (secretary of the In no tsukasa, the third rank officer): their main works were such as document and record creation and management in the imperial agency and civil affairs under the betto and the hogandai.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inshutendai (secretary of the In no tsukasa, the third rank officer): their main works were such as document and record creation and management in In no cho and civil affairs under the betto and the hogandai.</e>
<cmt>the imperial agency→In no cho</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>朱雀天皇の時代に設置される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This position was set in the reign of Emperor Suzaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This position was set during the reign of Emperor Suzaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This position was set during the reign of Emperor Suzaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>六位の中から2・3名が任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two or three shutendai were selected from Rokui (sixth rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two or three shutendai were selected from Rokui (sixth rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two or three shutendai were selected from Rokui (sixth rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>後白河天皇の時代に院庁職員の責任者である庁年預（ちょうのねんよ、院年預とは別の役職）が1名選出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Goshirakawa, one &quot;Cho no nenyo&quot; which was the highest officer in the imperial agency (different post from In no nenyo) was selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the reign of Emperor Goshirakawa, one &quot;Cho no nenyo&quot; which was the highest officer in the imperial agency (different post from In no nenyo) was selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the reign of Emperor Goshirakawa, one &quot;Cho no nenyo&quot; which was the highest officer in In no cho (different post from In no nenyo) was selected.</e>
<cmt>院庁の表記変更先の記述で「長官は別当」となっているので、庁年預が「highest officer」なのか疑問です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>院蔵人…上皇の天皇在位中の六位蔵人のうち、院主典代の定員外となった者を特に待遇した役職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inkurodo (palace officer) : this post was for the Kurodo with the sixth rank who could not get the post of Inshutendai even though they had served for the retired emperor since his reign as the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inkurodo (palace officer): this post was for the Kurodo with the sixth rank who could not reach the post of Inshutendai even though they had served the retired emperor since his reign as emperor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inkurodo (palace officer): this post was for the Kurodo with the sixth rank who could not reach the post of Inshutendai even though they had served the retired emperor since his reign as emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>『拾芥抄』では定員4とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shugaisho (encyclopedia in the middle ages)&quot;, the fixed number of places was four.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shugaisho (encyclopedia in the middle ages),&quot; the fixed number of places was four.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia in 14c) the fixed number of places was four.</e>
<cmt>拾芥抄を定訳に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、女院である上西門院の院蔵人に左兵衛尉源頼朝が任命されたことが『山槐記』平治元年2月19日 (旧暦)条に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Sankaiki (diary of FUJIWARA no Tadachika)&quot;, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who was Lieutenant of the Left Division of Palace Guards (左兵衛尉) was appointed as Inkurodo of Josaimon-in (nyoin) on February 19, 1159 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>左兵衛尉→Lieutenant of the Left Division of Palace Guards[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Sankaiki (diary of FUJIWARA no Tadachika),&quot; MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who was Lieutenant of the Left Division of Palace Guards (左兵衛尉) was appointed as Inkurodo of Josaimon-in (nyoin) on February 19, 1159 (lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Sankaiki&quot; (Tadachika NAKAYAMA&apos;s diary) MINAMOTO no Yoritomo who was Sahyoe no jo (third-ranked officer of Sahyoe-fu, the Left Division of Middle Palace Guards) was appointed as Inkurodo of Josaimonin (nyoin (a close female relative of the Emperor or a womwan of comparable standing)) on February 19, 1159 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>山槐記、女院を定訳に修正左兵衛尉を定訳に変更し、文中の漢字削除Josaimon-in→Josaimoninlunar→old</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>院伝奏…上皇に各方面からの奏請を取次ぐ役。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indenso (introducing officer) : they were in charge of relaying various messages to the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indenso (introducing officer): they were in charge of relaying various messages to the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indenso (introducing officer): they were in charge of relaying various messages to the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>後白河上皇時代の吉田経房・高階泰経を初見とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the first Indenso, Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and TAKASHINA no Yasutsune in the reign of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa were confirmed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the first Indenso, Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and TAKASHINA no Yasutsune during the reign of retired Emperor Goshirakawa were confirmed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the first Indenso, Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and TAKASHINA no Yasutsune during the reign of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa were confirmed.</e>
<cmt>「the retired Emperor」の「the」を戻しました。retired→Retired</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>実際に機能したのは後嵯峨天皇の時代の宝治元年（1246年）に吉田為経・葉室定嗣を任命して関東申次が担当する事項以外の一切の取次を任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This post functioned in reality after Emperor Gosaga appointed Tametsune YOSHIDA and Sadatsugu HAMURO in 1246 and they were in charge of all messages except Kanto moshitsugi (introducing officer between the retired emperor and Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This post functioned in reality after Emperor Gosaga appointed Tametsune YOSHIDA and Sadatsugu HAMURO in 1246 and they were in charge of all messages except Kanto moshitsugi (introducing officer between the retired emperor and Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This post functioned in reality after Emperor Gosaga appointed Tametsune YOSHIDA and Sadatsugu HAMURO in 1246 and they were in charge of all messages except Kanto moshitsugi (adjusting works between the retired emperor and Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>introducing officer→adjusting works</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>亀山天皇の時代の弘安2年（1279年）には定員6名を3組に分け、交代で取次を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Kameyama, in 1279, six members of Indenso were divided in three pairs and each pair worked in rotation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Emperor Kameyama, in 1279, six members of Indenso were divided into three pairs and each pair worked in rotation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Kameyama, in 1279, six members of Indenso were divided into three pairs and each pair worked in rotation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>後に武家伝奏などへと派生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government) was derived from Indenso.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government) was derived from Indenso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buke tenso (liaison officers between the imperial court and the military government) was derived from Indenso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>江戸時代には現任あるいは前任の大納言・中納言が院伝奏を兼ねて大事にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo era, predecessor dainagon (Major Councilor) and predecessor chunagon (Middle Councilor) were appointed as Indenso and Buke tenso concurrently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo era, predecessor dainagon (Major Councilor) and predecessor chunagon (Middle Councilor) were appointed as Indenso and Buke tenso concurrently.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, incumbent or predecessor dainagon (chief councilor of state) and chunagon (vice-councilor of state) were appointed as Indenso and Buke tenso concurrently.</e>
<cmt>大納言、中納言を定訳に修正era→period「現任あるいは」→incumbentを追記し、中納言の前のpredecessorを削除しました。訳者は大納言・中納言が院伝奏と武家伝奏を兼ねた理解して訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>院御随身…上皇やその御所などを護衛する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inmizuijin (palace guard) : they worked as guard for the retired emperor and his palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inmizuijin (palace guard): they worked as guard for the retired emperor and his palace.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inmizuijin (palace guard): they worked as guard for the retired emperor and his palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>主として近衛府などから選ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly, they were selected from Konoefu (division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mostly, they were selected from Konoefu (division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mostly, they were selected from Konoefu (division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>退位した上皇に対して新しい天皇より尊号が授与されるとともに封戸・随身が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new emperor gave fuko (land) and zuijin (guard) to the retired emperor as well as a title of respect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new emperor gave fuko (land) and zuijin (guard) to the retired emperor as well as a title of respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new emperor gave fuko (Residential units (ko) assigned as prebends (fu) to support top-ranking officials, temples, shrines, and royal households such as those of the queen-consort and crown prince) and zuijin (guard) to the retired emperor as well as a title of respect.</e>
<cmt>封戸を定訳に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>左右近衛府からそれぞれ5名ずつ（後に6名ずつ）を定員とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fixed number of places was five each (later six each) from Left and Right divisions of palace guards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fixed number of places was five each (later six each) from Left and Right divisions of palace guards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fixed number of places was five each (later six each) from Sayu Konoefu (the left and right divisions of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>左右近衛府の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>上皇が出家して法皇となると、世俗から離れることを名目に随身は返上された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the retired emperor entered the priesthood and became cloistered emperor, he returned zuijins as a sign of renouncing the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the retired emperor entered the priesthood and became a cloistered emperor, he returned zuijins as a sign of renouncing the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the retired emperor entered the priesthood and became a cloistered emperor, he returned zuijins as a sign of renouncing the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>近衛将曹級の左右各1名ずつはそのまま法皇院司の職員として留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, each zuijin with the rank of Konoe shoso (fourth rank officer in palace guard division) from the Left and Right divisions of palace guards stayed in the cloistered imperial agency as officials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, each zuijin with the rank of Konoe shoso (fourth rank officer in palace guard division) from the Left and Right divisions of palace guards stayed in the cloistered imperial agency as officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, each zuijin with the rank of Konoe shoso (fourth rank officer in palace guard division) from the Left and Right divisions of palace guards stayed in the cloistered imperial agency as officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), Shimoxx(id:9332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>