<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>遠国奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ongoku Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ongoku Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ongoku Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>遠国奉行（おんごくぶぎょう）は、江戸以外の幕府直轄領(天領)内の重要な場所に置かれ、その土地の政務をとりあつかった奉行、役方に分類される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ongoku Bugyo were placed in important places withing Shogunate-owned land (tenryo) outside of Edo, and were divided into bugyo and yakugata who handled the governance of that land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ongoku Bugyo were placed in important places within Shogunate-owned land (tenryo) outside of Edo, and were divided into bugyo and yakugata who handled the governance of that land.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ongoku Bugyo were placed in important places within Shogunate-owned land (tenryo) outside of Edo, and were divided into bugyo (magistrate)and yakugata who handled the governance of that land.</e>
<cmt>奉行の説明補足yakugata は不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大坂・京都・駿府の町奉行のほか、長崎奉行などが置かれ、その職には主に幕府旗本が任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the machi-bugyo of Osaka, Kyoto and Sunpu, bugyo were placed in Nagasaki and elsewhere; and it was mainly the Shogun&apos;s retainers who were appointed to that post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the machi-bugyo of Osaka, Kyoto and Sunpu, bugyo were placed in Nagasaki and elsewhere; and it was mainly the Shogun&apos;s retainers who were appointed to that post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the machi-bugyo (town magistrate) appointed for Osaka, Kyoto and Sunpu, bugyo were also appointed for other places such as Nagasaki; these positions were mainly held by bakufu hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which is a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not sure if a bakufu hatamoto is exactly the same as a regular hatamoto but I have assumed that the former is a direct retainer of the bakufu as a whole, while the latter is a direct retainer of the shogun himself. Anyway, &quot;hatamoto (direct vassals of the shogun) of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)&quot; sounds a bit odd to me as it is effectively saying that a hatamoto is a direct vassal of the shogun of a type of Japanese government that is headed by a shogun...</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>老中の支配下で伺候席律令制役で、足高制は1000石から2000石と任地により異なり役料が支給されることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an office of the Ritsuryo system under control of the roju, the tashidaka system varied from 1000 to 2000 koku, depending on the location, and a salary was sometimes provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">伺候席(しこうせき)とは,江戸城に登城した大名,旗本が将軍に拝謁する順番を待っていた控席のこと</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an office of the Shikoseki (waiting place for their turns in which Daimyo or Hatamoto who attended to the Edo Castle to have an audience with a Shogun) -Ritsuryo system under control of the roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), the tashidaka system (a wage system established by Edo bakufu) varied from 1000 to 2000 koku, depending on the location, and a salary was sometimes provided.</e>
<cmt>「老中」、「伺候席律令制役」、「足高制」の説明を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>管轄地を奉行知行所と呼び、1868年江戸幕府が倒れると、明治政府によって江戸を含む主な9つの場所には明治初期の府の設置と変遷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of jurisdiction was called bugyo chigyosho, and when the Edo Shogunate fell in 1868, the Meiji government installed and transitioned the early Meiji fu in 9 places, including Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of jurisdiction was called bugyo chigyosho, and when the Edo Shogunate fell in 1868, the Meiji government installed and transitioned the early Meiji fu in 9 places, including Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of jurisdiction was called bugyo chigyosho, and when the Edo bakufu fell in 1868, the Meiji government installed and transitioned the early Meiji fu in 9 main places, including Edo.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu「主な」を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このうち江戸府は後東京府に名前を変えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these, the name of Edo-fu was later changed to Tokyo-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these, the name of Edo-fu was later changed to Tokyo-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these, the name of Edo-fu was later changed to Tokyo-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1871年の廃藩置県までの間に、東京府・大阪府・京都府をのぞく箱館府・神奈川府・越後府・新潟府・甲斐府・度会府・奈良府・長崎府の各府は明治初期の府の設置と変遷。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the abolition of domains and establishment of prefectures in 1871, the early Meiji fu of Hakodate-fu, Kanagawa-fu, Echigo-fu, Niigata-fu, Kai-fu, Watarai-fu, Nara-fu and Nagasaki-fu, and not Tokyo-fu, Osaka-fu or Kyoto-fu, were each established and transitioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the abolition of domains and establishment of prefectures in 1871, the early Meiji fu of Hakodate-fu, Kanagawa-fu, Echigo-fu, Niigata-fu, Kai-fu, Watarai-fu, Nara-fu and Nagasaki-fu, and not Tokyo-fu, Osaka-fu or Kyoto-fu, were each established and transitioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the abolition of domains and establishment of prefectures in 1871, the early Meiji fu of Hakodate-fu, Kanagawa-fu, Echigo-fu, Niigata-fu, Kai-fu, Watarai-fu, Nara-fu and Nagasaki-fu, excluding Tokyo-fu, Osaka-fu and Kyoto-fu, were each established and transitioned.</e>
<cmt>and not→excluding</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>京都町奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>詳細は京都町奉行参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details refer to Kyoto Machi-Bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details refer to Kyoto Machi-Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details refer to Kyoto Machi-Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>老中支配であるが、任地の関係で京都所司代の指揮下で職務を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roju ruled, but because of the location, he conducted business at the command of the Kyoto Shoshidai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roju ruled, but because of the location, he conducted business at the command of the Kyoto Shoshidai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roju ruled, but because of the location, he conducted business at the command of the Kyoto Shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy).</e>
<cmt>京都所司代の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>京都町政の他畿内天領および寺社領の支配も行うため、寺社奉行勘定奉行町奉行の三奉行を兼ねたような職務であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Kyoto&apos;s city governance, in order to exercise rule over Shogun-owned land in the Kinai area and shrine and temple lands, the post involved serving concurrently as 3 kinds of bugyo: jisha bugyo, kanjo bugyo and machi bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Kyoto&apos;s city governance, in order to exercise rule over Shogun-owned land in the Kinai area and shrine and temple lands, the post involved serving concurrently as 3 kinds of bugyo: jisha bugyo, kanjo bugyo, and machi bugyo.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Kyoto&apos;s city governance, in order to exercise rule over tenryo (bakufu-owned land) in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) and shrine and temple lands, the post involved serving concurrently as three kinds of bugyo: jisha-bugyo (magistrate of temples and shrines), kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), and machi bugyo.</e>
<cmt>天領の訳畿内、寺社奉行、勘定奉行の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>定員は2名で、東西2つの奉行所が設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were 2 positions, with 2 bugyo offices located in the east and west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were 2 positions, with 2 bugyo offices located in the east and west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were 2 positions, with 2 bugyo offices located in the east and west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>役高は1500石で、役料として現米600石が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The allotment was 1500 koku, and 600 koku of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allotment was 1500 koku, and 600 koku of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The allotment was 1500 koku, and 600 koku of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>配下には与力20騎と同心50人が付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As subordinates there were 20 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As subordinates there were 20 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As subordinates there were 20 yoriki (a police sergeant) and 50 doshin doshin (a police constable).</e>
<cmt>与力、同心の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>伏見奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>伏見城廃城後に城代に代わって置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Put in place of the jodai after Fushimi Castle was razed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Put in place of the jodai after Fushimi Castle was razed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Put in place of the Jodai (the keeper of castle) after Fushimi-jo Castle was razed.</e>
<cmt>城代の説明補足伏見城の訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>定員は1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>京都への入口である伏見宿及び淀川河岸を監督（大名が参勤交代の途中で勝手に入京して朝廷と接触しないように）するため、遠国奉行の中では唯一大名が就任することがあった役職である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to control (so that daimyo in the middle of their alternate attendance could not enter Kyoto without permission and contact the imperial court) Fushimi-juku and the banks of the Yodo River, which are the entrance to Kyoto, this was the only post among the Ongoku Bugyo that was filled by a daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to control (so that daimyo in the middle of their alternate attendance could not enter Kyoto without permission and contact the imperial court) Fushimi-juku and the banks of the Yodo River, which are the entrance to Kyoto, this was the only post among the Ongoku Bugyo that was filled by a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to control (so that daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the middle of their Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) could not enter Kyoto without permission and contact the imperial court) Fushimi-juku and the banks of the Yodo-gawa River, which are the entrance to Kyoto, this was the only post among the Ongoku Bugyo that was filled by a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>大名、参勤交代の説明補足&quot;Yodo River&quot;→&quot;Yodo-gawa River&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そのため足高制の対象になっていないが、役料として3000俵が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason the tashidaka system was not applicable, but a stipend of 3000 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason the tashidaka system was not applicable, but a stipend of 3000 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason the tashidaka system was not applicable, but a stipend of 3000 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>配下は与力10騎同心50人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、京都所司代や京都町奉行とのつながりが強く、京都での大事の際には支援に駆けつける事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, ties to the Kyoto Shoshidai and the Kyoto Machi-bugyo were strong, and sometimes he would run to assist them when there were major events in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, ties to the Kyoto Shoshidai and the Kyoto Machi-bugyo were strong, and sometimes he would run to assist them when there were major events in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, ties to the Kyoto Shoshidai and the Kyoto Machi-bugyo were strong, and sometimes he would run to assist them when there were major events in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、寛文年間には京都町奉行が形式上伏見奉行の員外で扱われていたり、逆に元禄・文化 (日本)年間には伏見奉行が京都町奉行に統合されることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Kanbun years, the Kyoto Machi-bugyo was treated as a non-member of the Fushimi Bugyo, although in the Genroku and Bunka years it was integrated with the Kyoto Machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kanbun years, the Kyoto Machi-bugyo was treated as a non-member of the Fushimi Bugyo, although in the Genroku and Bunka years it was integrated with the Kyoto Machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kanbun years, the Kyoto Machi-bugyo was formally treated as a non-member of the Fushimi Bugyo, although in the Genroku and Bunka years the Fushimi Bugyo was integrated with the Kyoto Machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>形式上→formally 追記it→Fushimi Bugyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、小堀政方が伏見奉行の時に伏見騒動と呼ばれる事件が発生し、政方の近江小室藩が改易される事態となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, when Masamichi KOBORI was Fushimi Bugyo, an incident called the Fushimi Riot occurred, Masamichi&apos;s Omi Komuro Domain came under feud suppression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, when Masamichi KOBORI was Fushimi Bugyo, an incident called the Fushimi Riot occurred, Masamichi&apos;s Omi Komuro Domain came under feud suppression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, when Masamichi KOBORI was Fushimi Bugyo, an incident called the Fushimi Riot occurred, and Masamichi&apos;s Omi Komuro Domain came under feud suppression.</e>
<cmt>and 追加&quot;Actually&quot;→&quot;In fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大坂町奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osaka Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osaka Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osaka Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>詳細は大坂町奉行参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details refer to Osaka Machi-Bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details refer to Osaka Machi-Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details refer to Osaka Machi-Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>定員2名で東西2つの奉行所が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were 2 positions, with 2 bugyo offices located in the east and west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were 2 positions, with 2 bugyo offices located in the east and west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were 2 positions, with 2 bugyo offices located in the east and west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>役高は1500石で、役料として現米600石が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The allotment was 1500 koku, and 600 koku of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allotment was 1500 koku, and 600 koku of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The allotment was 1500 koku, and 600 koku of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>配下は与力30騎同心50人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As subordinates there were 30 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As subordinates there were 30 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As subordinates there were 30 yoriki and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>駿府町奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sunpu Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sunpu Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sunpu Machi-Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>駿府城下の町政の他、東海道の江尻・丸子両宿および清水港を管轄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to governance of the town below Sunpu Castle, he controlled Ejiri and Maruko inns on the Tokaido road, and Shimiu Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to governance of the town below Sunpu Castle, he controlled Ejiri and Maruko inns on the Tokaido road, and Shimiu Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to governance of the town below Sunpu-jo Castle, he controlled Ejiri and Maruko inn towns on the Tokaido road, and Shimizu Port.</e>
<cmt>Sunpu→Sunpu-joinns→inn townsShimiu→Shimizu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>定員1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>役高は1000石で、役料として500俵が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 500 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 500 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 500 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>配下は与力8騎同心60人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As subordinates there were 8 yoriki horsemen and 60 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As subordinates there were 8 yoriki horsemen and 60 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As subordinates there were 8 yoriki and 60 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>長崎奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagasaki Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagasaki Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagasaki Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>詳細は長崎奉行参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details refer to Nagasaki Bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details refer to Nagasaki Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details refer to Nagasaki Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>長崎町政の他、オランダとの貿易も担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Nagasaki city governance, duties included trade with Holland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Nagasaki city governance, duties included trade with Holland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Nagasaki town governance, duties included trade with Holland.</e>
<cmt>city→town</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>定員は変動が多く、最初1名で、寛永10年（1633年）より2名、貞享3年（1686年）より3名、元禄13年（1700年）より4名と増員されたが、宝永以降は2名で固定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many changes in the number of positions, starting at 1, then increased to 2 from 1633, 3 from 1686, and 4 from 1700, but it was set at 2 from Kanei on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many changes in the number of positions, starting at 1, then increased to 2 from 1633, 3 from 1686, and 4 from 1700, but it was set at 2 from Kanei on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many changes in the number of positions, starting at one, then increased to two from 1633, three from 1686, and four from 1700, but it was set at two from the Hoei era on.</e>
<cmt>Kanei→the Hoei era</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>役高は1000石で、役料として440俵が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 440 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 440 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 440 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>配下は与力10騎同心15人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki horsemen and 15 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki horsemen and 15 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki and 15 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>下田奉行・浦賀奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimoda Bugyo / Uraga Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimoda Bugyo / Uraga Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimoda Bugyo/Uraga Bugyo</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>江戸湾に入る船舶の監視を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In charge of supervision of ships entering Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In charge of supervision of ships entering Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In charge of supervision of ships entering Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt>Edo Bay のスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>当初元和 (日本)2年(1616年)に伊豆国下田市に置かれていたが、享保5年(1720年)には江戸湾内の経済活動の活発化に伴って相模国浦賀に移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, in 1616, was stationed in Shimoda City in Izu Province, but in 1720, in keeping with the increased economic activity in Edo Bay, it was moved to Uraga in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, in 1616, was stationed in Shimoda City in Izu Province, but in 1720, in keeping with the increased economic activity in Edo Bay, it was moved to Uraga in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, in 1616, was stationed in Shimoda City in Izu Province, but in 1720, in keeping with the increased economic activity in Edo Bay, it was moved to Uraga in Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>定員1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>役高は1000石で、役料500俵を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 500 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 500 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The allotment was 1000 koku, and 500 bales of rice were provided as a stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>配下は与力10騎同心50人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As subordinates there were 10 yoriki and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>幕末期には外国との交渉の窓口となったため、増員が行われ、また天保13年(1842年)-天保15年(1844年)及び嘉永7年(1854年)-万延元年(1860年)にかけては外国船の来航に備えて下田奉行も再置され、この期間には浦賀・下田の両奉行所が並存していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it became a window of negotiations with foreign countries toward the end of the Shogunate, the number of positions was increased, and in 1842-1844 and 1854-1860 a Shimoda Bugyo was installed to provide for the arrival of foreign ships, during which time the Bugyo offices in Uraga and Shimoda existed concurrently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it became a window of negotiations with foreign countries toward the end of the Shogunate, the number of positions was increased, and in 1842-1844 and 1854-1860 a Shimoda Bugyo was installed to provide for the arrival of foreign ships, during which time the Bugyo offices in Uraga and Shimoda existed concurrently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it became a window of negotiations with foreign countries toward the end of the Shogunate, the number of positions was increased, and in 1842-1844 and 1854-1860 Shimoda Bugyo was installed again to provide for the arrival of foreign ships, during which time the Bugyo offices in Uraga and Shimoda existed concurrently.</e>
<cmt>「再置」とあるので again 追記Shinoda Bugyo の前の a を削除しましたがご確認ください</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>主として会津藩士が赴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Members of the Aizu Domain mainly filled the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members of the Aizu Domain mainly filled the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members of the Aizu clan mainly filled the post.</e>
<cmt>Domain → clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>山田奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamada Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamada Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamada Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>伊勢奉行とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called Ise Bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called Ise Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called Ise Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>当初、奉行所は伊勢国山田（現在の三重県伊勢市）に置かれ、のち伊勢国度会郡小林（現・伊勢市御薗村小林）に移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the Bugyo office was located at Yamada in Ise Province (present-day Ise City, Mie Prefecture), and was later moved to Kobayashi, Watarai District, Ise Province (present-day Kobayashi, Misono Village, Ise City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, the Bugyo office was located at Yamada in Ise Province (present-day Ise City, Mie Prefecture), and was later moved to Kobayashi, Watarai District, Ise Province (present-day Kobayashi, Misono Village, Ise City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, the Bugyo office was located at Yamada in Ise Province (present-day Ise City, Mie Prefecture), and was later moved to Kobayashi, Watarai District, Ise Province (present-day Kobayashi, Misono Village, Ise City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>伊勢神宮の守護と門前町の支配、伊勢、志摩における訴訟、鳥羽港の警備などを担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was in charge of guarding Ise Jingu Shrine and ruling the temple town, litigation in Ise and Shima, and security in Toba Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was in charge of guarding Ise Jingu Shrine and ruling the temple town, litigation in Ise and Shima, and security in Toba Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Was in charge of guarding Ise-jingu Shrine and ruling the temple town, litigation in Ise and Shima, and security in Toba Port.</e>
<cmt>Ise Jingu→Ise-jingu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>定員は1名、元禄9年（1696年）には2名となり、江戸と現地で交代勤務となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was one position, then became two in 1696, with stations alternating between the field and Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was one position, then became two in 1696, with stations alternating between the field and Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was one position, then became two in 1696, with stations alternating between the field and Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>役高は1000石で、役料1500俵を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 1500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 1500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 1500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>配下は与力6騎同心70人水主40人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subordinates were 6 yoriki horsemen, 70 doshin and 40 suishu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subordinates were 6 yoriki horsemen, 70 doshin and 40 suishu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subordinates were 6 yoriki, 70 doshin and 40 suishu (sailor).</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除suishu→sailor ご確認願います</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>御三家のひとつ紀州徳川家領と接していることからしばしば係争が発生し、将軍吉宗時代に江戸町奉行として活躍する大岡忠相が務めたこともあり、奉行時代の忠相の働きに感心した紀州藩主時代の徳川吉宗が、のちに抜擢したという伝説があることでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it had contact with the fief of the Kishu Tokugawa family, one of the 3 Tokugawa households, disputes occurred periodically; Tadasuke OOKA, who was active as the Edo Machibugyo at the time of Shogun Yoshimune, served at the post for a time; and there is known to be a legend that Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, who was impressed by Tadasuke&apos;s work as Bugyo when he was chief of the Hanshu Domain, later chose him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it had contact with the fief of the Kishu Tokugawa family, one of the 3 Tokugawa households, disputes occurred periodically; Tadasuke OOKA, who was active as the Edo Machibugyo at the time of Shogun Yoshimune, served at the post for a time; and there is known to be a legend that Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, who was impressed by Tadasuke&apos;s work as Bugyo when he was chief of the Hanshu Domain, later chose him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it had contact with the fief of the Kishu Tokugawa family, one of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family), disputes occurred periodically; Tadasuke OOKA, who was active as the Edo Machibugyo at the time of Shogun Yoshimune, served at the post for a time; and there is known to be a legend that Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, who was impressed by Tadasuke&apos;s work as Bugyo when he was chief of the Kishu clan, later chose him.</e>
<cmt>御三家の定訳Hanshu Domain→Kishu clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="48">
<j>慶長八年江戸幕府は伊勢大神宮神領地に「山田奉行所」を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1603 the Edo Shogunate placed the Yamada Bugyo Office on the shrine lands of Ise Daijingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1603 the Edo Shogunate placed the Yamada Bugyo Office on the shrine lands of Ise Daijingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1603 the Edo bakufu placed the Yamada Bugyo Office on the shrine lands of Ise-daijingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufuIse Daijingu→Ise-daijingu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>外宮・内宮両大神宮の警固は勿論の事、伊勢湾・南海での異国不審船の取締りや伊勢志摩神領以外も支配したが、「日光御奉行」と同等同格の「山田御奉行」の最重要任務は「二十一年目御遷宮奉行」を取り仕切る任務であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to security of the two grand shrines Geku and Naiku, he also controlled the supervision of suspicious foreign ships in Ise Bay and the southern sea, even outside of Ise-Shima Jinryo, but the most important duty of the Yamada Bugyo, who was equal in standing to the Nikko Bugyo, was to carry out the 21st year rebuilding of Ise Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to security of the two grand shrines Geku and Naiku, he also controlled the supervision of suspicious foreign ships in Ise Bay and the southern sea, even outside of Ise-Shima Jinryo, but the most important duty of the Yamada Bugyo, who was equal in standing to the Nikko Bugyo, was to carry out the 21st year rebuilding of Ise Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to security of the two grand shrines Geku (outer shrine) and Naiku (inner shrine), he also controlled the supervision of suspicious foreign ships in Ise Bay and the southern sea, even outside of Ise-Shima shrine territory, but the most important duty of the Yamada Bugyo, who was equal in standing to the Nikko Bugyo, was to carry out the &apos;21st year rebuilding of Ise Shrine.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Jinryo→shrine territory外宮、内宮の説明補足「」のところに&quot;&quot;を付けました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そもそも「御遷宮奉行」は伊勢大神宮の祭主が兼任して居ったが、「影流始祖愛洲久忠」の父であろう「愛洲伊予守忠行」が武家として初めて大神宮神領奉行職に文明年間任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To begin with, the head priest of Ise Shrine was also in charge of rebuilding the shrine, but AISU Iyomori Tadayuki, who might have been the father of Kageryu founder Hisatada AISU, was the first samurai to serve as bugyo over the Shrine lands during the Bunmei years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To begin with, the head priest of Ise Shrine was also in charge of rebuilding the shrine, but AISU Iyomori Tadayuki, who might have been the father of Kageryu founder Hisatada AISU, was the first samurai to serve as bugyo over the Shrine lands during the Bunmei years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To begin with, the head priest of Ise Shrine was also in charge of rebuilding the shrine, but Tadayuki AISU, the Governor of Iyo Province, who might have been the father of Kage-ryu school founder Hisatada AISU, was the first samurai to serve as bugyo over the Shrine lands during the Bunmei years.</e>
<cmt>影流→Kage-ryu schoolAISU Iyomori Tadayuki→Tadayuki AISU, the Governor of Iyo Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>［神領奉行所は岩出祭主館跡と思われる］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Shogunate, which thought the jinryo bugyo was the ruins of the chief priest of Iwade, continued the precedent set by AISU Iyomori Tadayuki and without missing a single time up until the Meiji Restoration, rebuilt the shrine, demonstrating worship of gods and ancestors even greater than that of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Shogunate, which thought the jinryo bugyo was the ruins of the chief priest of Iwade, continued the precedent set by AISU Iyomori Tadayuki and without missing a single time up until the Meiji Restoration, rebuilt the shrine, demonstrating worship of gods and ancestors even greater than that of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[The jinryo bugyo office was built where the Jingu saishu (head priest of the Ise Shrine) had once resided.]</e>
<cmt>岩出祭主館跡→岩出にあった祭主館の跡地の意味です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>江戸幕府は「愛洲伊予守忠行」の先蹤を引継ぎ、以来明治御維新迄只の一度も途切れず、源頼朝以上の「敬神敬祖」の範を示し御遷宮を行ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Bakufu continued the work begun by Tadayuki AISU, the Governor of Iyo Province, by rebuilding of the shrine without interruption until the Meiji Restoration, demonstrating a reverence of the gods and ancestors that was even greater than that of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>幕府→bakufu愛洲伊予守忠行を&quot;Tadayuki AISU, the Governor of Iyo Province&quot;に変えました。even greater 以下、源頼朝がやった以上にという意味と解釈し書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>御遷宮に掛かる費用は平成十五年第六十一回式年遷宮で約三百二七億円と云われており、如何に歴代山田奉行が伊勢大神宮に御奉仕したかが解る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cost of rebuilding the shrine was said to be about 32.7 billion yen in 2005 at the 61st rebuilding, which shows just how much the Yamada Bugyos did for Ise Jingu Shrine over the years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cost of rebuilding the shrine was said to be about 32.7 billion yen in 2005 at the 61st rebuilding, which shows just how much the Yamada Bugyos did for Ise Jingu Shrine over the years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cost of rebuilding the shrine is said to have been about 32.7 billion yen in 2005 at the 61st rebuilding, which shows just how much the Yamada Bugyos did for Ise-jingu Shrine over the years.</e>
<cmt>was said to be→is said to have beenIse Jingu→Ise-jingu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>「寛永十八年御奉行小林村に御居住したまへる以前より、孔雀丸・虎丸と謂う御船あり、享保十三年戊申五月はじめ御奉行保科淡路君如何なる故にや、虎丸の御船を大湊の沖に泛かしめ給ふ。尤も近来稀なることなり。孔雀丸は汚損せしと云へり、今御船の御公用なければ其の水主同心七十五人は常に御役所付の諸役を勤む。」と御普請役御組頭橋本市郎左衛門重永の［享保庚戌備忘録］に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Since before the Bugyo came to live in Kobayashi Village in 1641, there were ships called Kujaku-maru and Tora-maru, in May of 1728 for some reason Obugyo Hoshina Awaji no kimi sank the ship Tora-maru in the waters of Ominato. This is the most rare of recent events. If the Kujaku-maru is stained and there is no ship available for use, those 75 suishu/doshin will work regularly at their office duties.&quot; This is recorded in Gofushin-yaku Onkumigashira HASHIMOTO Ichirozaemon Shigenaga&apos;s Kyoho Kojutsu Biboroku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Since before the Bugyo came to live in Kobayashi Village in 1641, there were ships called Kujaku-maru and Tora-maru, in May of 1728 for some reason Obugyo Hoshina Awaji no kimi sank the ship Tora-maru in the waters of Ominato. This is the most rare of recent events. If the Kujaku-maru is stained and there is no ship available for use, those 75 suishu/doshin will work regularly at their office duties.&quot; This is recorded in Gofushin-yaku Onkumigashira HASHIMOTO Ichirozaemon Shigenaga&apos;s Kyoho Kojutsu Biboroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even before the Bugyo came to live in Kobayashi Village in 1641, there were ships called Kujaku-maru and Tora-maru, in May of 1728 for some reason the Bugyo, Hoshina of the Awaji Governor sank the ship Tora-maru in the waters of Ominato. This is the most rare of recent events. If the Kujaku-maru is stained and there is no ship available for use, those 75 suishu/doshin will work regularly at their office duties&apos; is written in Gofushin-yaku Onkumigashira HASHIMOTO Ichirozaemon Shigenaga&apos;s &quot;Kyoho Kojitsu Biboroku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Since→EvenObugyo Hoshina Awaji no kimi→the Bugyo, Hoshina of the Awaji Governor, 一文に書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>（御普請役御組頭子孫 橋本石洲著 『伊勢山田奉行沿革史』に依る）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(from Ise Yamada Bugyo Chronology, by Sekishu HASHIMOTO, descendant of Gofushin-yaku Onkumigashira)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(from Ise Yamada Bugyo Chronology, by Sekishu HASHIMOTO, descendant of Gofushin-yaku Onkumigashira)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Ise Yamada Bugyo Chronology&quot; by Sekishu HASHIMOTO, descendant of Gofushin-yaku Onkumigashira)</e>
<cmt>アンダーラインを&quot;&quot;に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>日光奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>日光東照宮守護を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In charge of Nikko Toshogu Shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In charge of Nikko Toshogu Shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In charge of Nikko Tosho-gu Shrine Shugo (provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>守護の説明補足東照宮を定訳に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>定員2名で、内1名は江戸詰となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 positions, 1 of which was stationed in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2 positions, 1 of which was stationed in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2 positions, 1 of which was stationed in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>役高は2000石で、役料500俵を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allotment was 2000 koku, and a stipend of 500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allotment was 2000 koku, and a stipend of 500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allotment was 2000 koku, and a stipend of 500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>配下は同心36人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subordinates were 36 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subordinates were 36 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subordinates were 36 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>奈良奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>興福寺・東大寺など奈良の大寺院の監視とその門前町（ならまち・奈良きたまち）の支配のため設置。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established for supervision of Kofuku-ji, Todai-ji and other large temples in Nara, and rule over their Temple Cities (Naramachi/Nara Kitamachi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established for supervision of Kofuku-ji, Todai-ji and other large temples in Nara, and rule over their Temple Cities (Naramachi/Nara Kitamachi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established for supervision of Kofuku-ji Temple, Todai-ji Temple and other large temples in Nara, and rule over their temple towns (Nara-machi/Nara Kita-machi).</e>
<cmt>Temple Cities→temple towns寺院名の表現変更machi の前にハイフンを入れました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>定員1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>役高1000石で、役料700俵を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 700 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 700 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 700 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>配下は与力7騎同心30人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subordinates were 7 yoriki horsemen and 30 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subordinates were 7 yoriki horsemen and 30 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subordinates were 7 yoriki and 30 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>奉行所は現・奈良女子大学の敷地内に置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bugyo office was located on the grounds of what is now Nara Women&apos;s University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bugyo office was located on the grounds of what is now Nara Women&apos;s University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bugyo office was located on the grounds of what is now Nara Women&apos;s University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>堺奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>詳細は堺奉行参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, refer to Sakai Bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, refer to Sakai Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, refer to Sakai Bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>定員1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>役高1000石で、役料現米600石を支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 600 koku in rice was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 600 koku in rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allotment was 1000 koku, and a stipend of 600 koku in rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>配下は与力10騎同心50人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subordinates were 10 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subordinates were 10 yoriki horsemen and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subordinates were 10 yoriki and 50 doshin.</e>
<cmt>horsemen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>佐渡奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sada Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sada Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sado Bugyo</e>
<cmt>Sada→Sado</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="69">
<j>佐渡金山の支配を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was responsible for rule of the Sado Gold Mine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was responsible for rule of the Sado Gold Mine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Was responsible for rule of the Sado Gold Mine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>箱館奉行（松前奉行）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakodate Bugyo (Matsumae Bugyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakodate Bugyo (Matsumae Bugyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakodate Bugyo (Matsumae Bugyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>北辺警護のため松前藩の領地であった蝦夷地を上知した享和2年（1802年）に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established for policing the northern frontier in 1802, when the Ezo lands that were part of the Matsumae Domain were made permanent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established for policing the northern frontier in 1802, when the Ezo lands that were part of the Matsumae Domain were made permanent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established for policing the northern frontier in 1802, when the bakufu confiscated the Ezo lands that had been part of the Matsumae Domain.</e>
<cmt>上知する→所領を没収すると理解し修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>幕末には開港地箱館における外国人の応対も担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also responsible for dealing with foreigners in the open port of Hakodate at the end of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also responsible for dealing with foreigners in the open port of Hakodate at the end of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also responsible for dealing with foreigners in the open port of Hakodate at the end of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>定員は2名で、内1名は江戸詰となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 positions, one of which was stationed in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2 positions, one of which was stationed in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2 positions, one of which was stationed in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>役高は2000石で、役料1500俵が支給された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Allotment was 2000 koku, and a stipend of 1500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Allotment was 2000 koku, and a stipend of 1500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Allotment was 2000 koku, and a stipend of 1500 bales of rice was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>奉行所は、最初は現在の元町公園（函館市元町）に置かれたが、五稜郭築城後にそちらへ移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bugyo office was originally located in present-day Motomachi Park (Motomachi, Hakodate City), but was moved to Goryokaku after it was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bugyo office was originally located in present-day Motomachi Park (Motomachi, Hakodate City), but was moved to Goryokaku after it was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bugyo office was originally located in present-day Motomachi Park (Motomachi, Hakodate City), but was moved to Goryokaku Castle after it was built.</e>
<cmt>五稜郭も城の一種と考え castle を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>新潟奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Niigata Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Niigata Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Niigata Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="75">
<j>天保14年に天領となった新潟市周辺の地域を支配するため新設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Established to rule the area around Niigata City that became Shogunate-controlled lands in 1843.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Established to rule the area around Niigata City that became Shogunate-controlled lands in 1843.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established to rule the area around Niigata City that became tenryo (bakufu-owned land) in 1843.</e>
<cmt>天領の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>設置の理由は日本海交通の要衝である新潟港の管理であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for establishment was management of Niigata Port, which was a key point for traffic on the Sea of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for the establishment was management of Niigata Port, which was a key point for traffic on the Sea of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for the establishment was management of Niigata Port, which was a key point for traffic on the Sea of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後、開国に当たり新潟が開港地となったため、その重要性が増した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when the country was opened, Niigata became an open port, so its importance increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, when the country was opened, Niigata became an open port, so its importance increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, when the country was opened, Niigata became an open port, so its importance increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>羽田奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haneda Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haneda Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haneda Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>天保13年（1842年）に、外国船の来航に備え江戸湾の防御を固めるための政策の一環として羽田 (大田区)に新設されたが、2年後に廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Was established in 1842 in Haneda (Ota Ward), as part of a policy to strengthen defenses of Edo Bay against the arrival of foreign ships, but was abolished 2 years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Was established in 1842 in Haneda (Ota Ward), as part of a policy to strengthen defenses of Edo Bay against the arrival of foreign ships, but was abolished 2 years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Was established in 1842 in Haneda (Ota Ward), as part of a policy to strengthen defenses of Edo Bay against the arrival of foreign ships, but was abolished 2 years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>羽田奉行就任者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Persons Serving as Haneda Bugyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Persons Serving as Haneda Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Persons Serving as Haneda Bugyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="80">
<j>田中勝行　天保13年(1842)12月24日-天保15年(1844)5月24日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuyuki TANAKA – December 24, 1842 to May 24, 1844</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuyuki TANAKA – December 24, 1842 to May 24, 1844</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuyuki TANAKA – December 24, 1842 to May 24, 1844</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>明治初期の府の設置と変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Institution and Transition in the Early Meiji Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Institution and Transition in the Early Meiji Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Institution and Transition in the Early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>Government→Period</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="81">
<j>日付は旧暦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dates are in the old calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dates are in the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dates are in the old calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 もね～るmoner(id:28477), こまくさ(id:42220), Hyuuga(id:14767), Auf(id:633), 水野白楓(id:22811), 花いちもんめ(id:39081), Yanahan(id:2437), Aphaia(id:3132), Roga246(id:53246), Sgi1962(id:80778), BAKU(id:55205), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), でここ(id:9565), Yonoemon(id:55450), Penpen(id:18815), 墓石と鉄塔(id:18104), 地図帳(id:122587), MizunoH(id:112470), Paotch(id:3039), Aisukageryuu(id:196205), Komura Jutaro(id:35057), けんち(id:5147), 史跡めぐり(id:95651), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>