<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>勘解由使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagetushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagetushi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageyushi</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>勘解由使（かげゆし）は、日本の律令制下の令外官の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kageyushi was one of ryoge no kan (official posts outside of the Ritsuryo code) under the Japanese Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kageyushi was a ryoge no kan (official posts outside of the Ritsuryo code) under the Japanese Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageyushi was a Ryoge no kan (official posts outside of the Ritsuryo code) under the Japanese Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代初期、地方行政を監査するために設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was created in the early Heian period for the purpose of inspecting local administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was created during the early Heian period for the purpose of inspecting local administration.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was created during the early Heian period for the purpose of inspecting local administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後、監査の対象は内官（京都の各官職）へと拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the target of its inspection extended to the naikan (offices locate in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the inspections extended to include the naikan (offices locate in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the inspections extended to include the naikan (offices locate in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>勘解由使の官庁である勘解由使庁は、太政官の北西、中務省の南に位置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kageyushicho, the office of Kageyushi, was located on the north-west of Daijokan (Council of State) and the south of Chumusho (Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kageyushicho, the office of Kageyushi, was located on the north-west side of Daijokan (Council of State) and to the south of Chumusho (Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageyushicho, the office of Kageyushi, was located on the north-west side of Daijokan (Council of State) and to the south of Chumusho (Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>和名は「とくるよしかんがふるのつかさ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Japanese name was &quot;Tokuruyoshikangafuruno tsukasa&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Japanese name was &quot;Tokuruyoshikangafuruno tsukasa&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Japanese name was &apos;Tokuruyoshikangafuruno tsukasa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>律令制の下では、国司の任期が満了したとき、事務引継ぎが問題なく行われた証として、後任国司から前任国司へ解由状（げゆじょう）という文書が交付されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system, when the term of kokushi (provincial governor) expired, a document called Geyujo (discharge certificate) was delivered from a predecessor to a successor as the evidence to prove that the handing over of job was carried out without any problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Ritsuryo system, when the term of kokushi (provincial governor) expired, a document called Geyujo (discharge certificate) was delivered from a predecessor to a successor as evidence to prove that the handing over of a job was carried out without any problems.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system, when the term of kokushi (provincial governor) expired, a document called Geyujo (discharge certificate) was delivered from a predecessor to a successor as evidence to prove that the handing over of a job was carried out without any problems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>奈良時代（8世紀後期）ごろになると、国司行政に公廨稲収入などの利得権が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Nara period (late 8th century), the post of kokushi became the source of additional gains, such as kugaito (local source of revenue).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Nara period (late 8th century), the post of kokushi became a source for additional gains, such as kugaito (local source of revenue).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Nara period (late eighth century), the post of kokushi became a source for additional gains, such as kugaito (local source of revenue).</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このため、前任・後任間で利得をめぐる紛争が発生するようになり、交替時の事務引継ぎが不調となるケースも出てきていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such situation, there were cases where disputes concerning such additional profits occurred between a predecessor and a successor and the handing over of job was not smoothly carried out.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under this situation, there were cases where disputes concerning additional profits would occur between a predecessor and a successor and the handing over of a job was not carried out smoothly.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under this situation, there were cases where disputes concerning additional profits would occur between a predecessor and a successor and the handing over of a job was not carried out smoothly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>8世紀末期に登場した桓武天皇は、王威を国内にあまねく拡げるために、弛緩しつつあった地方行政の再構築に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Kanmu, who ascended the throne in the end of 8th century, started to reconstruct slackened local administration in order to extend the Imperial power throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Kanmu, who ascended the throne during the end of the 8th century, started to reconstruct slackened local administration in order to extend the Imperial power throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;slackened local administration&quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Kanmu, who ascended the throne during the end of the eighth century, started to reconstruct slackened local administration in order to extend the Imperial power throughout the nation.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その結果、地方行政を監査・監督する勘解由使の職が新設されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Kageyushi was created as the post which was in charge of the inspection/supervision of local administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Kageyushi was created as a post to take charge of the inspection/supervision of local administration.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Kageyushi was created as a post to take charge of the inspection and supervision of local administration.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>勘解由使の職務は、前任国司が持ち帰った解由状の監査であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kageyushi&apos;s duty was to inspect Geyujo which was brought back by a predecessor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kageyushi&apos;s duty was to inspect Geyujo which was brought back by a predecessor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageyushi&apos;s duty was to inspect Geyujo which was brought back by a predecessor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これにより、国司交替時の紛争を抑制し、国司行政の品質改善を図ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By doing so, the government intended to reduce disputes associated with the change of kokushi and improve the quality of kokushi&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By doing so, the government intended to reduce disputes associated with the change of kokushi and improve the quality of kokushi&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By doing so, the government intended to reduce disputes associated with the change of kokushi and improve the quality of kokushi&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>勘解由使が設置されたのは、797年（延暦16年）ころとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Kageyushi was created in 797.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Kageyushi was created in 797.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Kageyushi was created in 797.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>806年（大同 (日本)元年）、勘解由使は一旦廃止され、代わりに五畿七道単位で地方行政を監察する観察使が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kageyushi was once abolished in 806, and instead Kansatsushi, whose duty was to inspect local administration on gokishichido (five provinces and seven circuits) basis, was created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kageyushi was once abolished in 806, and instead Kansatsushi, whose duty was to inspect local administration on gokishichido (five provinces and seven circuits) basis, was created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageyushi was once abolished in 806, and instead Kansatsushi, whose duty was to inspect local administration on gokishichido (five provinces and seven circuits) basis, was created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただ、解由状の審査実務は、左右弁官局が継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, inspection job of Geyujo was succeeded by the Left and Right Benkankyoku (Controllers&apos; Office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the inspection job of Geyujo was succeeded by the Left and Right Benkankyoku (Controllers&apos; Office).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the inspection job of Geyujo was succeeded by the Left and Right Benkankyoku (Controllers&apos; Office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>その後ほどなくして、国司の交替時における紛争が増加傾向となったため、824年（天長元年）、勘解由使が再置されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long, however, Kageyushi was recreated in 824 because the number of disputes associated with the change of kokushi was on the increase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long, however, Kageyushi was recreated in 824 because the number of disputes associated with the change of kokushi was on the increase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long, however, Kageyushi was recreated in 824 because the number of disputes associated with the change of kokushi was on the increase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この後、国司のみならず内官（京都の各官職）の交替時にも解由状を作成することとされ、勘解由使の監査対象に加えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, officials of naikan (offices locate in Kyoto) were also obliged to prepare Geyujo when they changed, and such Geyujo was added to the target of Kageyushi&apos;s inspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, officials of naikan (offices locate in Kyoto) were also obliged to prepare Geyujo when they changed, and such Geyujo was added to the target of Kageyushi&apos;s inspection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, officials of naikan were also obliged to prepare Geyujo when they changed, and such Geyujo was added to the target of Kageyushi&apos;s inspection.</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、事務引継ぎが不調に終わった場合、その理由と前任・後任両者の主張を併記した不与解由状（ふよげゆじょう）を作成することも新たに定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, when the handing over of job was not carried out successfully, a predecessor and a successor were obliged to prepare Fuyo-geyujo in which the reason thereof and the arguments of both parties were described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, when the handing over of a job was not carried out successfully, a predecessor and a successor were obliged to prepare Fuyo-geyujo in which the reason thereof and the arguments of both parties were described.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, when the handing over of a job was not carried out successfully, a predecessor and a successor were obliged to prepare Fuyo-geyujo in which the reason thereof and the arguments of both parties were described.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>こうして勘解由使は、中央行政と地方行政を監査・監督する重要な職となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Kageyushi became the important post which was in charge of the inspection/supervision of both central and local administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Kageyushi became an important post which was in charge of the inspection/supervision of both central and local administration.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Kageyushi became an important post which was in charge of the inspection and supervision of both central and local administration.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>職務には、不与解由状が発行されたときの紛争処理、官吏の交替に関する法規集である交替式（こうたいしき）の編纂などがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its duty included dispute settlement when Fuyu-geyujo was submitted as well as the compilation of Kotaishiki, a code concerning the change of officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its duty included dispute settlement when Fuyu-geyujo was submitted as well as comiling Kotaishiki, a code concerning the change of officials.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its duty included dispute settlement when Fuyo-geyujo was submitted as well as compiling Kotaishiki, a code concerning the change of officials.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>当時、勘解由使による監査を勘判と呼んでおり、政務の参考書籍として編まれた『政事要略』に勘判の記録（勘解由使勘判抄）が所載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kageyushi&apos;s inspection was called Kanpan at the time, and its record (Kageyushi-kanpanjo) was compiled in &quot;Seiji yoryaku&quot;, a reference book for politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kageyushi&apos;s inspection was called Kanpan at the time, and its record (Kageyushi-kanpanjo) was compiled in &quot;Seiji yoryaku&quot;, a reference book for politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kageyushi&apos;s inspection was called Kanpan at the time, and its record (Kageyushi-kanpanjo) was compiled in &quot;Seiji yoryaku&quot; (examples of the politics in the Heian period), a reference book for politics.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>平安中期～後期頃から、ある官職を特定の家系が相伝する「官司の家職化」が進行していき、勘解由使の存在意義は次第に薄れていったとする見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory asserts that the significance of Kageyushi gradually waned in the middle to the late of Heian period because official posts increasingly became &quot;family business&quot;, in other words, a certain post was exclusively inherited by a member of specific family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory asserts that the significance of Kageyushi gradually waned in the middle to late Heian period because official posts increasingly became &quot;family business&quot;, in other words, a certain post was exclusively inherited by a member of specific family.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory asserts that the significance of Kageyushi gradually waned in the middle to late Heian period because official posts increasingly became &apos;family business,&apos; in other words, a certain post was exclusively inherited by a member of specific family.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>一方で、同時期には受領が事実上の地方官として積極的な収奪活動を展開しており、そうした受領を監督することが勘解由使の主要な役割となっていったとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, another theory asserts that as zuryo (the head of provincial governors) was actively appropriating public properties at that time, Kageyushi&apos;s principal role shifted to the supervision of zuryo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, another theory asserts that as zuryo (the head of provincial governors) was actively appropriating public properties at that time, Kageyushi&apos;s principal role shifted to the supervision of zuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, another theory asserts that as Zuryo (the head of provincial governors) was actively appropriating public properties at that time, Kageyushi&apos;s principal role shifted to the supervision of Zuryo.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>勘解由使は、受領の活躍が見られた平安末期ごろまで、監査機関としての機能を担い続けたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Kageyushi continued to play a role of inspection until the end of Heian period when zuryo was active.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Kageyushi continued to play a role in inspection until the end of the Heian period when zuryo was active.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Kageyushi continued to play a role in inspection until the end of the Heian period when Zuryo was active.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>内部官職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Official posts at Kageyushicho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official posts at Kageyushicho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official posts</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>長官（正五位下相当）…1名　参議、弁官といった高官が充てられることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kami (Minister) (corresponded to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) - one person, high-ranking officials, such as Sangi (councillor) or Benkan (controllor), were often appointed to this post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kami (Minister) (corresponded to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)) - one person, high-ranking officials, such as Sangi (councillor) or Benkan (controllor), were often appointed to this post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami (Minister) (corresponded to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade)): One person, high-ranking officials, such as Sangi (councillor) or Benkan (controller), were often appointed to this post.</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>次官（従五位下相当）…2名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suke (vice-minister) (corresponded to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank. Lower Grade) - two persons</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suke (vice-minister) (corresponded to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank. Lower Grade) - two persons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suke (vice-minister) (corresponded to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade): Two persons</e>
<cmt>コロンを使用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>判官（従六位下相当）…3名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jo (secretary) (corresponded to Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank)) - three persons</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jo (secretary) (corresponded to Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank)) - three persons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jo (secretary) (corresponded to Jurokuinoge (Junior Sixth Rank, Lower Grade)): Three persons</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせ、原文・訳文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>主典（従七位下相当）…3名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakan (secretary) (corresponded to Jurokui or Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank)) - three persons</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakan (secretary) (corresponded to Jurokui or Jushichii (Junior Seventh Rank)) - three persons</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakan (secretary) (corresponded to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade)): Three persons</e>
<cmt>ウェブに合わせ、原文・訳文修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>史生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shisho (officer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shisho (officer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shisho (officer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>書生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosei</e>
<cmt>書生→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosei (a post managing paper works)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>使掌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shisho</e>
<cmt>使掌→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shisho (使掌, a post doing clerical works)</e>
<cmt>読みが確認できなかった漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>使部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibu</e>
<cmt>使部→定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibu (low rank bureaucrats)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Shimoxx(id:9332), アルパカ(id:49539), Blue-comet(id:192801), Alexbot(id:157199), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>