<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>臨時雑役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinjizoyaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinjizoyaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinjizoyaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>臨時雑役（りんじぞうやく）とは平安時代中期に国衙から農民に身役・交易などの名目で賦課された雑役の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinjizoyaku (臨時雑役) is a collective term for the odd-job tasks that kokuga (provincial government office) obliged the local farmers as a kind of tax imposition in the name of physical work or kyoyaku (trading).</e>
<cmt>臨時雑役→Rinjizoyaku 統一用語リストには、Rinji zoyaku (general term for odd-job tasks), (temporary odd-job tasks)などがありましたが、Rinjizoyakuとし、カッコ内は省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinjizoyaku is a collective term for the odd-job tasks that kokuga (provincial government office) obliged local farmers to perform as a kind of tax payable in labor or in kind.</e>
<cmt>revised to improve clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Rinjizoyaku&quot; is a collective term for the odd-job tasks that kokuga (provincial government office) obliged local farmers to perform as a kind of tax payable in labor or in kind.</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他 2009/6/29）の指示により、Rinjizoyaku にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「臨時雑役」という名称の租税が存在したわけではなく、「内裏雑事」「調沽買絹」などの名目で課された個々の賦課を一括する際に用いられた語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no taxation called &apos;Rinjizoyaku&apos; but the word was used to refer collectively to the types of taxation in a form of forced labor imposed to the people in the name of &apos;dairizatsuji&apos; (miscellaneous chores in the palace), &apos;chokonobai no kinu&apos; (調沽買絹) (acquisition and purchase of silk), etc.</e>
<cmt>「内裏雑事」→定訳不明：&apos;dairizatsuji&apos; (miscellaneous chores in the palace)としました。　「調沽買絹」→定訳不明：&apos;chokonobai no kinu&apos; (調沽買絹) [正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no tax called &apos;Rinjizoyaku&apos;, but the word was used to refer collectively to taxation in the form of forced labor imposed on the people in the name of &apos;dairizatsuji&apos; (miscellaneous chores in the palace), &apos;chokonobai no kinu&apos; (acquisition and purchase of silk), etc.</e>
<cmt>shortened and edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no tax called &apos;Rinjizoyaku,&apos; but the word was used to refer collectively to taxation in the form of forced labor imposed on the people in the name of &apos;dairizatsuji&apos; (miscellaneous chores in the palace), &apos;cho no kobai kinu&apos; (acquisition and purchase of silk), etc.</e>
<cmt>called &apos;Rinjizoyaku&apos;, のカンマをクォーテーション内に移動しました。&apos;&apos;chokonobai no kinu&apos; を &apos;cho no kobai kinu&apos; に修正しました。出典　http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%87%A8%E6%99%82%E9%9B%91%E5%BD%B9</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>9世紀末頃より、租庸調・雑徭・正税などといった律令制に基づく税体系が解体され始め、まず地方（国衙）レベルの徴収において官物と臨時雑役に分けた賦課・徴収が行われるようになり、次第に中央（朝廷）レベルでも同様の徴収が行われるようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the end of the 9th century, the tax system had been established base on the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code), such as Soyocho (the tax system composed of three elements of taxes: rice; labor or alternative goods; textile goods or alternative money), Zoyo (irregular corvee), and Shozei (the rice tax stored in provincial offices&apos; warehouse), however, this system was gradually dismantled, and in the local (kokuga) level, a dual taxation consisted of Kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and Rinjizoyaku, began to be imposed and collected, and gradually this way of taxation was extending to the central (Imperial Court) level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the end of the 9th century, the tax system had been based on the Ritsuryo system, with Soyocho (taxes on rice, labor or alternative goods, and textile goods or alternative money), Zoyo (irregular corvee), and Shozei (the rice tax stored in provincial offices&apos; warehouses), however, this system was gradually dismantled, and at the local (kokuga) level, dual taxation consisted of Kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and Rinjizoyaku began to be imposed and collected, and gradually this way of taxation extended to the central (Imperial Court) level.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit, corrected prepositions and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the end of the 9th century, the tax system had been based on the Ritsuryo system, with Soyocho (taxes on rice, labor or alternative goods, and textile goods or alternative money), Zoyo (irregular corvee), and Shozei (the rice tax stored in provincial offices&apos; warehouses), however, this system was gradually dismantled, and at the local (kokuga) level, dual taxation consisted of Kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and Rinjizoyaku began to be imposed and collected, and gradually this way of taxation extended to the central (Imperial Court) level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>臨時雑役は主に雑徭にあたる賦課が変質したものでそこに交易（租庸調などで徴収された米を元手に国家・国衙に必要な物資を調達すること）などの要素が加えられたものであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Rinjizoeki is a modified form of the corvee imposing the forced labor, but later other elements such as Kyoyaku (a task to acquire the necessary materials for the State and kokuga, using the rice collected through the Soyocho and other tax levying system) were added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinjizoeki is considered to be a modified form of the corvee imposing forced labor, but later other elements, such as Kyoyaku (a task to acquire the necessary materials for the State and kokuga, using the rice collected through the Soyocho and other tax levying system) were added.</e>
<cmt>rephrased the first bit to improve flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinjizoeki is considered to be a modified form of the corvee imposing forced labor, but later other elements, such as Kyoyaku (a task to acquire the necessary materials for the State and kokuga, using the rice collected through the Soyocho and other tax levying system) were added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>臨時雑役は荘園・公領を問わずに賦課されたが、荘園領主が国衙に対して臨時雑役免除を求める動きもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinjizoyaku was imposed to the manors (shoen) as well as to the public lands, and sometimes the lord of manor asked the kokuga for the exemption of Rinjizoyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinjizoyaku was imposed on the manors (shoen) as well as public lands, and sometimes the lord of manor asked the kokuga for exemption from Rinjizoyaku.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinjizoyaku was imposed on the manors (shoen) as well as public lands, and sometimes the lord of manor asked the kokuga for exemption from Rinjizoyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>