<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>将軍後見職</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun-kokenshoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun-kokenshoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun-kokenshoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>将軍後見職（しょうぐんこうけんしょく）は、江戸時代後期、幕末に新設された政事総裁職、京都守護職と並ぶ江戸幕府三要職の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun-kokenshoku is one of the three key posts in Edo shogunate created in the final years of the Edo period, along with Seiji-soukaishoku (president of political affairs) and Kyoto shugoshoku (military governor of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun-kokenshoku is one of the three key posts in Edo shogunate created in the final years of the Edo period, along with Seiji sosaishoku (president of political affairs) and Kyoto shugoshoku (military governor of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>Seiji-soukaishoku→誤訳のためSeiji sosaishokuに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun-kokenshoku is one of the three key posts in Edo shogunate created in the final years of the Edo period, along with Seiji sosaishoku (president of political affairs) and Kyoto shugoshoku (military governor of Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>安政6年（1858年）、幼少の徳川家茂が14代征夷大将軍に就任したために、同年8月前将軍徳川家定の遺命と、同じく幼少で将軍に付いた4代将軍徳川家綱時の保科正之・11代将軍徳川家斉における松平定信時の先例を名目に御三卿の田安慶頼が任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the 14th Seiitaishogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA assumed office in 1858 still in his youth, Yoshiyori TAYASU from gosankyo (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) was chosen to take this role in August of the same year, on the nominal claim that this was the will of former Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA and based on the precedent of Masayuki HOSHINA filling this role for the 4th Shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA and Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA for the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the 14th Seiitaishogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA assumed office in 1858 still in his youth, Yoshiyori TAYASU from gosankyo (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) was chosen to take this role in August of the same year, in the name of the will of former Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA and the precedent of Masayuki HOSHINA filling this role for the 4th Shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA and Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA for the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA (both shogun were assumed office in youth).</e>
<cmt>on the nominal claim that this was the will of former Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA and based on→in the name of the will of former Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA andに訂正しました。（文法上）「同じく幼少で将軍に付いた」の訳漏れを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the 14th Seiitaishogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA assumed office in 1858 still in his youth, Yoshiyori TAYASU from gosankyo (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) was chosen to take this role in August of the same year, in the name of the will of former Shogun Iesada TOKUGAWA and the precedent of Masayuki HOSHINA filling this role for the 4th Shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA and Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA for the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA (both shogun were assumed office in youth).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、実際には大老井伊直弼が形式的に擁立したもので正式な役職でもなく、実権も有しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was a ceremonial post created by the Tairo (chief minister) Naosuke II, without any real power and without official recognition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was a formal post created by the Tairo (chief minister) Naosuke II, without any real power or official recognition.</e>
<cmt>ceremonial→原文の意味に近いformalに訂正しました。and without→orに訂正しました。（文法上）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was a formal post created by the Tairo (chief minister) Naosuke II, without any real power or official recognition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ところが、文久2年（1862年）5月、朝廷内部に幕府内の親井伊派の処分を要求する動きがあり、その対応の一環として「家茂の成人」を理由に井伊に擁立された田安慶頼が後見職から退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, demand from the Imperial Court to take punitive action against the followers of Ii led to the resignation of Yoshiyori TAYASU appointed to the post by Ii, on grounds that the Shogun has reached adulthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in May 1862, demand from the Imperial Court to take punitive action against the followers of Ii inside the Edo shogunate led to the resignation of Yoshiyori TAYASU appointed to the post by Ii, on grounds that Iemochi had reached adulthood.</e>
<cmt>年月の訳漏れ、「幕府内の」の訳漏れを訂正しました。「家茂」を原文通りに名前での訳に訂正しました。has reached adulthood→had reached adulthoodに時制を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in May 1862, demand from the Imperial Court to take punitive action against the followers of Ii inside the Edo shogunate led to the resignation of Yoshiyori TAYASU appointed to the post by Ii, on grounds that Iemochi had reached adulthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>続いて朝廷より、一橋慶喜を幕府の正式な役職としての将軍後見職に任じるように勅諚が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was followed by an Imperial decree ordering Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI be appointed Shogun-kokenshoku, as an official position in the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was followed by an Imperial decree ordering Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI be appointed Shogun-kokenshoku, as an official position in the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was followed by an Imperial decree ordering Yoshinobu HITOTSUBASHI be appointed Shogun-kokenshoku, as an official position in the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これを受けて同年7月に慶喜が幕府の正式な役職として新設された将軍後見職に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, Yoshinobu was appointed to the post, now newly made official, in July of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, Yoshinobu was appointed to the post, now newly made official, in July of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Yoshinobu was appointed to the post, now newly made official, in July of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元治元年（1864年）3月、慶喜が禁裏守衛総督に転じたために廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The post was abolished in March 1864 when Yoshinobu was moved to the post of Kinri Goshuei Sotoku (post to guard Kinri Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post was abolished in March 1864 when Yoshinobu was moved to the post of Kinri Goshuei Sotoku (post to guard Kinri Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post was abolished in March 1864 when Yoshinobu was moved to the post of Kinri Goshuei Sotoku (post to guard Kinri Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rikuzen gun(id:107698), SK(id:64397), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>