<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三木一草</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboku-Isso</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboku-Isso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanboku-Isso</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三木一草（さんぼくいっそう）は後醍醐天皇の建武の新政下で寵遇を受けた4人の寵臣の呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboku-Isso is the four meritorious retainers who helped Emperor Godaigo and received the emperor&apos;s favor in Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboku-Isso was the name given to the four meritorious retainers who received the Emperor&apos;s favor by helping Emperor Go-Daigo with the Kemmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot; was the name given to the four meritorious retainers who received the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s favor under the Kemmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他 2009/6/29）の指示により、Sanboku-Isso にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。&quot;who received the Emperor&apos;s favor by helping Emperor Go-Daigo&quot;1. Go-daigo を Godaigo に修正しました。2. by helping とはどこにも記載がありませんので、削除の上語順を入れ替えwho received the Emperor Godaigo&apos;s favor under the Kemmu Restoration としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>楠木正成、結城親光、名和長年、千種忠顕をあわせて呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It came to be named after Masashige KUSUNOKI, Chikamitsu YUKI, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaki CHIGUSA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their names were Masashige KUSUNOKI, Chikamitsu YUKI, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaki CHIGUSA, and the title of Sanboku-Isso came from all of their names collectively.</e>
<cmt>made sentence more descriptive to prepare the reader for following explanation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their names were Masashige KUSUNOKI, Chikamitsu YUKI, Nagatoshi NAWA and Tadaaki CHIKUSA, and the title of Sanboku-Isso came from all of their names collectively.</e>
<cmt>用語集の表記に従い、Tadaki CHIGUSA を Tadaaki CHIKUSA に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>楠木は「クスノキ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;楠木&quot; is read as kusuno-ki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characters used for Masashige&apos;s family name were&quot;楠木&quot;which are read as &quot;kusuno-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>tried to make this easy to understand for an English reader</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characters used for Masashige&apos;s family name were&quot;楠木&quot;(camphor tree) which are read as &quot;kusuno-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>楠木の意味 (camphor tree) を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>結城は「ユウキ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;結城&quot;read as yu-ki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characters for Chikamitsu&apos;s family name were&quot;結城&quot; and are read as &quot;yu-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>tried to make this easy to understand for an English reader</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characters for Chikamitsu&apos;s family name were&quot;結城&quot; and are read as &quot;yu-ki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>名和長年は伯耆国であったことから「ホウキ」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;名和長年&quot;is called ho-ki because he was from Hoki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagatoshi was nicknamed &quot;ho-ki&quot; being that he was from Hoki Province.</e>
<cmt>tried to make this easy to understand for an English reader</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagatoshi was nicknamed &quot;ho-ki&quot; being that he was from Hoki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>千種は「チグサ」と4人の姓、あるいは呼び名からとられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;千種&quot;is read as Chi-gusa (the same pronunciation of &quot;kusa&quot; or grass in Japanese.) So the word Sanboku-Isso was coined after their name or nickname because &quot;木 (boku)&quot; is also read as &quot;ki (tree).&quot; Sanboku-Isso literally means &quot;three trees and one grass.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characters for Tadaki&apos;s family name were &quot;千種&quot; and are read as &quot;chi-gusa&quot; (&quot;gusa&quot; having the same pronunciation as &quot;kusa&quot; which means &quot;grass&quot; in Japanese). The title was coined after their names as the character &quot;木” (boku) is also read as &quot;ki&quot; which means &quot;tree,&quot; leading to &quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot; which literally means &quot;three trees and one grass.&quot;</e>
<cmt>I did what I could to make this easy to understand…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characters for Tadaaki&apos;s family name were &quot;千種&quot; and are read as &quot;chi-gusa&quot; (&quot;gusa&quot; having the same pronunciation as &quot;kusa&quot; which means &quot;grass&quot; in Japanese); their title &quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot; was coined after their names as the character &quot;木&quot; (boku) is also read as &quot;ki&quot; which means &quot;tree,&quot; leading to &quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot; which literally means &quot;three trees and one grass.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Tadaki&apos;s family name を Tadaaki&apos;s family name に修正しました。 &quot;chi-gusa&quot; (&quot;gusa&quot; having the same pronunciation as &quot;kusa&quot; which means &quot;grass&quot; in Japanese). The title was coined after their names as the character &quot;木” (boku) を &quot;chi-gusa&quot; (&quot;gusa&quot; having the same pronunciation as &quot;kusa&quot; which means &quot;grass&quot; in Japanese); the title &quot;Sanboku-Isso&quot;was coined after their names as the character &quot;木&quot; (boku) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>三木一草の4人に共通する点は下記のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What they have in common are the points that</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common points of the four Sanboku-Isso:</e>
<cmt>fixed to read like a bullet point</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common points of the four Sanboku-Isso:</e>
<cmt>原文に「下記のとおりである」を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鎌倉幕府体制の下であれば、日の当たる場所に出ることのなかった出自であること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">they would not have succeeded if they had been in their origin under Kamakura bakufu system,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They would not have succeeded if they had stayed in their original posts under the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) system.</e>
<cmt>fixed to read like a bullet point; added Kamakura bakufu to be consistent with the word list;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) system, they would not have succeeded due to their origins.</e>
<cmt>They would not have succeeded if they had stayed in their original posts under the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) system をUnder the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) system, they would not have succeeded due to their origins.に修正しました（※）。※本来は「鎌倉幕府体制の下では出世できなかった家柄」という意味であって、trans2 の表現は「鎌倉幕府体制下で以前の地位に留まっていたら」という誤訳になるかと思われます。参考：出自 http://tangorin.com/words/出自1. birthplace2. descent; blood-lines; origins3. one&apos;s outward self</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>「寵恩に誇っ」て高位に昇ったこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">all of them rose to high ranks by winning &quot;the Emperor&apos;s favor&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All four rose to high ranks by winning the &quot;Emperor&apos;s favor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed grammar slightly and fixed to read like a bullet point</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All four rose to high ranks by winning the &quot;Emperor&apos;s favor.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>その栄耀栄華の期間が、極めて短かったこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and that their period of prosperity was extremely short</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their periods of prosperity were extremely short.</e>
<cmt>Revised for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their periods of prosperity were extremely short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（4人ともに建武 (日本)3年（1336年）の足利氏との戦いで命を落としている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(all of them lost their lives in the battle with Ashikaga army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(All four lost their lives during the Kenmu Era in the battle with the Ashikaga army in 1336).</e>
<cmt>added year, &quot;Kenmu Era,&quot; and fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(All four lost their lives during the Kenmu Era in the battle with Ashikaga clan in 1336).</e>
<cmt>足利氏との戦いthe battle with the Ashikaga army を the battle with Ashikaga clan に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>南北朝騒乱の初期の段階で4人の軍事指揮官を失ったことで、南朝 (日本)は軍事的にかなりの劣勢に立たされることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that the lives of the four military commanders were lost at the early stage of the battle between South and North Dynasties led to extreme military disadvantage on the side of Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Losing the lives of the four Sanboku-Isse military commanders at an early stage in the battle between the Southern and Northern Dynasties led to an extreme military disadvantage for the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;Sanboku Isse&quot; to clarify that these four individuals are the &quot;military commanders&quot; being referred to; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Losing the lives of the four Sanboku-Isso military commanders at an early stage in the battle between the Southern and Northern Dynasties led to an extreme military disadvantage for the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Sanboku-Isse を Sanboku-Isso に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), Seibuabina(id:37532), Bayan(id:84446), Nobsan(id:129592), 水野白楓(id:22811), Bue(id:237847), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>