<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大宰権帥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dazai Gonnosochi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dazai Gonnosochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dazai Gonnosochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大宰権帥（だざいごんのそち）は大宰府の副司令官のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dazai Gonnosochi was the Provisional Governor General of Daziafu in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dazai Gonnosochi was the Provisional Governor General of Daziafu in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dazai Gonnosochi was the Provisional Governor General of Daziafu in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>初代は弘仁元年（810年）の阿保親王、2代目は承和 (日本)4年（837年）の藤原常嗣であるが、前者は薬子の変による連座、後者は遣唐大使としての功労による特殊事情による任命であるため、貞観_(日本)15年（873年）に任じられた3代目の在原行平（阿保親王の子）が事実上の初代とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Dazai Gonnosochi was the Imperial Prince Abo shinno who was demoted to the position in 810 for his implication in the Kusuko Incident, the second Dazai Gonnosochi was FUJIWARA no Tsunetsugu who was appointed in 837 in recognition of his services as an ambassador to the Tang Dynasty, and the third Dazai Gonnosochi was a son of the Imperial Prince Abo shinno, ARIWARA no Yukihira who was appointed in 873; therefore, ARIWARA no Yukihira is considered virtually the first Dazai Gonnosochi because he was appointed the position for no special reason as his predecessors were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Dazai Gonnosochi was the Imperial Prince Abo shinno who was demoted to the position in 810 for his implication in the Kusuko Incident, the second Dazai Gonnosochi was FUJIWARA no Tsunetsugu who was appointed in 837 in recognition of his services as an ambassador to the Tang Dynasty, and the third Dazai Gonnosochi was a son of the Imperial Prince Abo shinno, ARIWARA no Yukihira who was appointed in 873; therefore, ARIWARA no Yukihira is considered virtually the first Dazai Gonnosochi because he was appointed the position for no special reason unlike his predecessors.</e>
<cmt>as his predecessors were. --&gt; unlike his predecessors.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Dazai Gonnosochi was the Imperial Prince Abo shinno who was demoted to the position in 810 for his implication in the Kusuko Incident, the second Dazai Gonnosochi was FUJIWARA no Tsunetsugu who was appointed in 837 in recognition of his services as an ambassador to the Tang Dynasty, and the third Dazai Gonnosochi was a son of the Imperial Prince Abo shinno, ARIWARA no Yukihira who was appointed in 873; therefore, ARIWARA no Yukihira is considered virtually the first Dazai Gonnosochi because he was appointed the position for no special reason unlike his predecessors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>大宰府は大宰帥を長官とし、権帥を長官代理とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dazaifu was headed by the Governor General, Dazai no sochi, and the Provisional Governor General, Dazai Gonnosochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dazaifu was headed by the Governor General, Dazai no sochi, and the Provisional Governor General, Dazai Gonnosochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dazaifu was headed by the Governor General, Dazai no sochi, and the Provisional Governor General, Dazai Gonnosochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>朝廷の鎮西総司令部であり、九州地域の兵権を掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dazaifu was the general headquarters of the Imperial Western Defense army and controlled over the military power in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dazaifu was the general headquarters of the Imperial Western Defense army and controlled over the military power in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dazaifu was the general headquarters of the Imperial Western Defense army and controlled over the military power in the Kyushu area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この大宰府の長官として帥は位置づけられるが、弘仁年間以後には皇族が列せられる慣例があることから、実質的な支配権は権帥が握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dazai no sochi was regarded as the head of Dazaifu, but as there was a convention to appoint the Imperial family members to the position after the Konin era, the virtual control was held by Dazai Gonnosochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dazai no sochi was regarded as the head of Dazaifu, but as there was a convention to appoint the Imperial family members to the position after the Konin era, the virtual control was held by Dazai Gonnosochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dazai no sochi was regarded as the head of Dazaifu, but as there was a convention to appoint the Imperial family members to the position after the Konin era, the virtual control was held by Dazai Gonnosochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>従って、大宰権帥は実質的な大宰府の長官である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Dazai Gonnosochi was the virtual head of Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Dazai Gonnosochi was the virtual head of Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Dazai Gonnosochi was the virtual head of Dazaifu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、これ以降、大宰権帥と大宰府の次官大宰大弐を同時には任命できない慣習が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this period, it became a practice that Dazai Gonnosochi and Dazai Daini, an undersecretary to Dazai no sochi, were not served at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this period, it became a practice that Dazai Gonnosochi and Dazai Daini, an undersecretary to Dazai no sochi, were not appointed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>were not served --&gt; were not appointed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this period, it became a practice that Dazai Gonnosochi and Dazai Daini, an undersecretary to Dazai no sochi, were not appointed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>更に、中国（宋 (王朝)）との交易の利権も大宰府に集中したことからその利権を目当てに大宰権帥には中納言・大納言経験者がなることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As all the interests of trade with the Song dynasty of China were held by Dazaifu, the former Middle Councilors and Great Councilors frequently became Dazai Gonnosochi for the interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As all the interests of trade with the Song dynasty of China were held by Dazaifu, the former Middle Councilors and Great Councilors frequently became Dazai Gonnosochi for the interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As all the interests of trade with the Song dynasty of China were held by Dazaifu, the former Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) and Dainagon (chief councilor of state) frequently became Dazai Gonnosochi for the interests.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それらの例として自らが陣頭指揮を執って刀伊の入寇を撃退した藤原隆家や、大宰府を制圧した藤原純友に対抗した橘公頼、白河法皇の院政時代に活躍した大江匡房等が挙げられよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of that kind of Dazai Gonnosochi included FUJIWARA no Takaie who successfully commanded the army to repulse the pirates that tried to invade the northern Kyushu, TACHIBANA no Kimiyori who fought against FUJIWARA no Sumitomo when Sumitomo conquered Dazaifu, and OE no Masafusa who was active during the reign of the cloistered Emperor Shirakawa Hoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of that kind of Dazai Gonnosochi includes FUJIWARA no Takaie who successfully commanded the army to repulse the pirates that tried to invade the northern Kyushu, TACHIBANA no Kimiyori who fought against FUJIWARA no Sumitomo when Sumitomo conquered Dazaifu, and OE no Masafusa who was active during the reign of the cloistered Emperor Shirakawa Hoo.</e>
<cmt>included --&gt; includes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of that kind of Dazai Gonnosochi includes FUJIWARA no Takaie who successfully commanded the army to repulse the pirates that tried to invade the northern Kyushu, TACHIBANA no Kimiyori who fought against FUJIWARA no Sumitomo when Sumitomo conquered Dazaifu, and OE no Masafusa who was active during the reign of the cloistered Emperor Shirakawa Hoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、他方で大宰権帥は中央で失脚した大臣経験者の左遷ポストとなることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, Dazai Gonnosochi was sometimes the position to which the former Ministers who fell in the central government were demoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Dazai Gonnosochi was sometimes the position to which the former Ministers who had fallen in the central government were demoted.</e>
<cmt>fell --&gt; had fallen</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Dazai Gonnosochi was sometimes the position to which the former Ministers who had fallen in the central government were demoted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>例としては阿保親王・菅原道真・源高明・藤原伊周・藤原基房などが挙げられる｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of that kind of Dazai Gonnosochi included the Imperial Prince Abo shinno, SUGAWARA no Michizane, MINAMOTO no Takaakira, FUJIWARA no Korechika, and FUJIWARA no Motofusa.</e>
<cmt>独立した文章が最初から２つ入っておりましたので、セルを分けました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of that kind of Dazai Gonnosochi includes the Imperial Prince Abo shinno, SUGAWARA no Michizane, MINAMOTO no Takaakira, FUJIWARA no Korechika, and FUJIWARA no Motofusa.</e>
<cmt>included --&gt; includes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of that kind of Dazai Gonnosochi includes the Imperial Prince Abo shinno, SUGAWARA no Michizane, MINAMOTO no Takaakira, FUJIWARA no Korechika, and FUJIWARA no Motofusa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>本来こうした貴族は大宰員外帥と呼ばれ、正規の帥・権帥とは区別されていた（大宰員外帥に任じられた例としては藤原豊成・藤原浜成・藤原吉野など）が、前述の阿保親王左遷の際に本人に直接関わりない事件である事と太上天皇の皇子である事への配慮から特に「権帥」の称号を与えて従来の員外帥とは区別した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although those demoted nobles were titled Dazai Ingainosochi to be distinguished from the regular Dazai no sochi and Dazai Gonnosochi (e.g., FUJIWARA no Toyonari, FUJIWARA no Hamanari, and FUJIWARA no Yoshino were appointed Dazai Ingainosochi), the above-mentioned Imperial Prince Abo was especially titled &apos;Dazai Gonnosochi&apos; to be distinguished from the traditional Dazai Ingainosochi by taking account of the fact that he was punished for the Incident which had nothing to do with him in fact and that he was a son of the cloistered emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although those demoted nobles were titled Dazai Ingainosochi to be distinguished from the regular Dazai no sochi and Dazai Gonnosochi (e.g., FUJIWARA no Toyonari, FUJIWARA no Hamanari, and FUJIWARA no Yoshino were appointed Dazai Ingainosochi), the above-mentioned Imperial Prince Abo was especially titled &apos;Dazai Gonnosochi&apos; to be distinguished from the traditional Dazai Ingainosochi by taking account of the fact that he was punished for the Incident which had nothing to do with him in fact and that he was a son of the cloistered emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although those demoted nobles were titled Dazai Ingainosochi to be distinguished from the regular Dazai no sochi and Dazai Gonnosochi (e.g., FUJIWARA no Toyonari, FUJIWARA no Hamanari, and FUJIWARA no Yoshino were appointed Dazai Ingainosochi), the above-mentioned Imperial Prince Abo was especially titled &apos;Dazai Gonnosochi&apos; to be distinguished from the traditional Dazai Ingainosochi by taking account of the fact that he was punished for the Incident which had nothing to do with him in fact and that he was a son of the cloistered emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>やがて、平安時代中期になると員外帥と権帥の区別は失われて、ともに「権帥」と称される事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the middle of the Heian period, Ingainosochi became not to be differentiated from Gonnosochi so that both of them were titled &apos;Gonnosochi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the middle of the Heian period, Ingainosochi became not to be differentiated from Gonnosochi so that both of them were titled &apos;Gonnosochi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>During the middle of --&gt; In the middle of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the middle of the Heian period, Ingainosochi became not to be differentiated from Gonnosochi so that both of them were titled &apos;Gonnosochi&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため、正規の権帥の中には外聞を気にするものもおり、平惟仲のように懇願して大宰帥として任命されるものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, some of those who were appointed the regular Dazai Gonnosochi worried about their reputation such that TAIRA no Korenaka appealed to the government to appoint him Dazai no sochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, some of those who were appointed the regular Dazai Gonnosochi worried about their reputation such that TAIRA no Korenaka appealed to the government to appoint him Dazai no sochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, some of those who were appointed the regular Dazai Gonnosochi worried about their reputation such that TAIRA no Korenaka appealed to the government to appoint him Dazai no sochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>その後、在庁官人に権力が移り、保安 (元号)年間の源重賢を最後に権帥も遙任化していった（治承年間に藤原基房が左遷によって大宰権帥となりその監視の為に藤原隆季が大宰帥に任じられた例があるが、基房が途中の備前国で出家して同地に留まる事を許されたために派遣が中止されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the authority of Dazai Gonnosochi was absorbed into the local resident officials who assisted Dazai Gonnosochi; MINAMOTO no Shigetaka during the Hoan era was the last Dazai Gonnosochi who served in the office at Dazaifu, and thereafter, Dazai Gonnosochi became held by absentee officials (During the Jisho era, FUJIWARA no Motofusa was demoted to Dazai Gonnosochi and FUJIWARA no Takasue was appointed Dazai no sochi to keep an eye on Motofusa, but as Motofusa took the tonsure in Bizen Province on the way to Dazaifu and permitted to stay there, the dispatch of the two officials was canceled.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the authority of Dazai Gonnosochi was absorbed into the local resident officials who assisted Dazai Gonnosochi; MINAMOTO no Shigetaka during the Hoan era was the last Dazai Gonnosochi who served in the office at Dazaifu, and thereafter, Dazai Gonnosochi became held by absentee officials (During the Jisho era, FUJIWARA no Motofusa was demoted to Dazai Gonnosochi and FUJIWARA no Takasue was appointed Dazai no sochi to keep an eye on Motofusa, but as Motofusa entered into priesthood in Bizen Province on the way to Dazaifu and permitted to stay there, the dispatch of the two officials was canceled.)</e>
<cmt>「出家する」の訳をプロジェクトの用語集にある&quot;to enter into priesthood&quot;に変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the authority of Dazai Gonnosochi was absorbed into the local resident officials who assisted Dazai Gonnosochi; MINAMOTO no Shigetaka during the Hoan era was the last Dazai Gonnosochi who served in the office at Dazaifu, and thereafter, Dazai Gonnosochi became held by absentee officials (During the Jisho era, FUJIWARA no Motofusa was demoted to Dazai Gonnosochi and FUJIWARA no Takasue was appointed Dazai no sochi to keep an eye on Motofusa, but as Motofusa entered into priesthood in Bizen Province on the way to Dazaifu and permitted to stay there, the dispatch of the two officials was canceled.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), Carkuni(id:79281), 味っ子(id:17086), Junger(id:10282), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>