<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>侍大将</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai daisho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai daisho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>侍大将（さむらいだいしょう）とは、主に大将軍の下で一軍を指揮する者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai daisho is a man who commands an army under Dai Shogun (the great general).</e>
<cmt>「侍大将」はSamurai Daisho、「大将軍」はDai Shogunとすべて大文字になっていますが、ここではsamurai daishoは普通名詞として小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai daisho is a man who commands an army under Dai Shogun (the great general).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai daisho is a man who commands an army under Dai Shogun (the great general).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>または侍大将軍（さむらいたいしょうぐん）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or samurai taishogun.</e>
<cmt>ここも小文字に換えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or samurai taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or samurai taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>侍大将という役割は平安時代、源平合戦の頃より見られ、平家軍の伊藤五なる侍大将がいたことなどが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The role of the samurai daisho was recognized since the Genpei War in the Heian period, and it is known that there was a samurai daisho called Go ITO(伊藤五)in the Teira&apos;s army, and so on.</e>
<cmt>伊藤五(読み方不明）は平家の武将藤原忠清：http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%97%A4%E5%8E%9F%E5%BF%A0%E6%B8%85</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The role of the samurai daisho was recognized since the Genpei War in the Heian period, and it is known that there was a samurai daisho called Go ITO(伊藤五)in the Taira&apos;s army, and so on.</e>
<cmt>Teira&apos;s army →Taira&apos;s army</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The role of the samurai daisho was recognized since the Genpei War in the Heian period, and it is known that there was a samurai daisho called Go ITO(伊藤五)in the Taira&apos;s army, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>室町時代末期から、侍を預かり備・騎馬隊を指揮する性格を有するようになり、戦国時代_(日本)には総大将の次席、足軽大将の上席にあって、戦国大名の軍制において主要な役割を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the late Muromachi period, it came to take on the character to supervise samurai and command sonae (a troop) and cavalry, and in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) it played a leading role in the military system of sengoku daimyo, taking its position between one followed by the sodaisho (commander in chief) and precedence over samurai in command of infantry.</e>
<cmt>「足軽大将」は&apos;samurai in command of a troop of foot soldiers&apos;となっていますが、samurai in comandの後が長いので、infantry（歩兵）に変えました。ここでは「騎馬隊」としてcavalryを使っていますので、対になっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the late Muromachi period, it came to take on the character to supervise samurai and command sonae (a troop) and cavalry, and in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) it played a leading role in the military system of sengoku daimyo, taking its position between a rank next to sodaisho (commander in chief) and a rank over ashigaru taisho (samurai in command of infantry).</e>
<cmt>表現シンプル化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the late Muromachi period, it came to take on the character to supervise samurai and command sonae (a troop) and cavalry, and in the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan) it played a leading role in the military system of sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period), taking its position between a rank next to sodaisho (commander in chief) and a rank over ashigaru taisho (samurai in command of infantry).</e>
<cmt>(Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>著名な侍大将に西国の戦国大名　大内義隆の家臣で周防国守護代　陶晴賢がおり、西国無双の侍大将と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a famous samurai daisho, there llived Harutaka SUE, Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of the Suo Province and a vassal of Yoshitaka Ouchi, sengoku daimyo of Saigoku (Western part of Japan), where SUE was refered to as the Samurai Daisho Unrivaled in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt>「守護代」につきましては用語統一リスト（2010/2/19-1）の76欄にありましたので、大文字のまま使いますが、「戦国大名」はsengoku daimyoです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a famous samurai daisho, there lived Harutaka SUE, who was Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of the Suo Province and a vassal of sengoku daimyo of Saigoku (Western part of Japan) Yoshitaka Ouchi; SUE was refered to as the Samurai Daisho Unrivaled in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt>llived　→lived節の構造を修正。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a famous samurai daisho, there lived Harutaka SUE, who was Shugodai (the acting Military Governor) of the Suo Province and a vassal of sengoku daimyo of Saigoku (Western part of Japan) Yoshitaka Ouchi; SUE was refered to as the Samurai Daisho Unrivaled in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Okt(id:18107), じょ(id:21165), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), HI(id:72996), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>