<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>町奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machi-bugyo (a governmental post in the Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machi-bugyo (town magistrate)</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machi-bugyo (town magistrate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>町奉行（まちぶぎょう）とは江戸時代の職名で、領内の都市部（町方）の行政・司法を担当する役職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machi-bugyo is the name of the governmental post in the Edo period that was in charge of the administration and judicature in the urban area (called machi-kata) in a territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Machi-bugyo was a name of a governmental post in the Edo period that was in charge of administration and judicature in an urban area (called machi-kata) in a territory.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Machi-bugyo was a name of a governmental post in the Edo period that was in charge of administration and judicature in an urban area (called machi-kata) in a territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸幕府だけでなく諸藩もこの役職を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This post was also set up not only in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) but in domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This post was also set up not only in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) but in domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This post was also set up not only in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) but in domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかしながら、一般に町奉行とのみ呼ぶ場合は幕府の役職である江戸町奉行のみを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the only term of mach-bugyo was used, it generally indicated the Edo machi-bugyo that was a governmental post in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when just mach-bugyo was used, it generally indicated the Edo machi-bugyo that was the governmental post in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>文の簡略化、冠詞変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when just mach-bugyo was used, it generally indicated the Edo machi-bugyo that was the governmental post in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、江戸以外の天領都市の幕府町奉行は大坂町奉行など地名を冠しており、遠国奉行と総称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu machi-bugyo in the Tenryo cities (the cities directly controlled by the bakufu) other than Edo was called with the city name added to its head, for example, Osaka machi-bugyo, and was totally called ongoku-bugyo (literally, bugyo in remote provinces).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu machi-bugyo in the Tenryo cities (the cities directly controlled by the bakufu) other than Edo were called with the city name added to their heads, for example, Osaka machi-bugyo, and was generically called ongoku-bugyo (literally, bugyo in remote provinces).</e>
<cmt>複数化、totallyを変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu machi-bugyo in the Tenryo cities (the cities directly controlled by the bakufu) other than Edo were called with the city name added to their heads, for example, Osaka machi-bugyo, and was generically called ongoku-bugyo (literally, bugyo in remote provinces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>このページでは江戸町奉行および江戸町奉行所について記述する（以後、特別断りが無い場合、奉行とは町奉行、奉行所とは町奉行所を指す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this page, descriptions are made about the Edo machi-bugyo and the Edo machi-bugyo-sho office (the office for machi-bugyo)) (hereafter, bugyo and bugyo-sho office indicates machi-bugyo and machi-bugyo-sho office, respectively, if not specifically mentioned).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this page, descriptions are made about the Edo machi-bugyo and the Edo machi-bugyo-sho office (the office for machi-bugyo) (hereafter, bugyo and bugyo-sho office indicates machi-bugyo and machi-bugyo-sho office, respectively, if not specifically mentioned).</e>
<cmt>二重括弧削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this page, descriptions are made about the Edo machi-bugyo and the Edo machi-bugyo-sho office (the office for machi-bugyo) (hereafter, bugyo and bugyo-sho office indicates machi-bugyo and machi-bugyo-sho office, respectively, if not specifically mentioned).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸町奉行は寺社奉行・勘定奉行とあわせて三奉行と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo machi-bugyo, jisha-bugyo (in charge of temples and shrines), and kanjo bugyo (in charge of finance) were totally called san (three) bugyo posts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo machi-bugyo, jisha-bugyo (in charge of temples and shrines), and kanjo bugyo (in charge of finance) were generically called san (three) bugyo.</e>
<cmt>「posts)」削除、totally変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo machi-bugyo, jisha-bugyo (in charge of temples and shrines), and kanjo bugyo (in charge of finance) were generically called san (three) bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>他の二奉行と同様評定所の構成メンバーであり、幕政にも参与する立場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members in this post, together with those in the other two bugyo posts were also members of Hyojosho (the conference chamber), and were also concerned with affairs in the bakufu governments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members in this post, together with those in the other two bugyo posts were also members of Hyojosho (the conference chamber), and were also concerned with affairs in the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>単数化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members in this post, together with those in the other two bugyo posts were also members of Hyojosho (the conference chamber), and were also concerned with affairs in the bakufu government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>基本的に定員は2人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of officers in this post was basically two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of officers in this post was basically two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of officers in this post was basically two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>初期は大名が任命され、以後は旗本が任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, daimyo were appointed to this post, and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu) later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, daimyo were appointed this post, and later hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>to削除、語順変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, daimyo were appointed this post, and later hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>旗本が任命されるようになってから以降の町奉行の石高は3000石程度であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era when hatamoto became to be appointed to this post, the amount of rice crop earned by a member of this post was around 3000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era when hatamoto became to be appointed this post, the amount of rice yields for this post was around 3000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku)</e>
<cmt>文の簡略化、石高の表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era when hatamoto became to be appointed this post, the amount of rice yields for this post was around 3000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>その職務は午前中は江戸城に登城して老中などへの報告や打ち合わせを行い、午後は奉行所で決裁や裁判を行なうというもので、夜遅くまで執務していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A machi-bugyo officer entered the Edo castle in the morning, reporting to Roju members or holding meetings, and in the afternoon, made decisions and held trials, working until late at night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A machi-bugyo officer went to the Edo castle in the morning, reporting to Roju members or holding meetings, and in the afternoon, made decisions and held trials, working until late night.</e>
<cmt>登城を変更、at削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A machi-bugyo officer went to the Edo castle in the morning, reporting to Roju members or holding meetings, and in the afternoon, made decisions and held trials, working until late night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>激務で知られており在任中のまま死亡する率は有数であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The work in the post was known to be hard, and the rate of death while assuming the post was conspicuous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The work in the post was known to be hard, and the rate of death while in office was conspicuous.</e>
<cmt>文の簡略化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The work in the post was known to be hard, and the rate of death while in office was conspicuous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>役職上与力や同心は部下にあたるが、これらはあくまで将軍家の家臣であり、世襲制で奉行所に勤めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriki (police sergeants) and doshin (police constables) were subordinates of a bugyo officer, but were retainers of the shogun family and worked at a bugyo-sho office hereditarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriki (police sergeants) and doshin (police constables) were subordinates of the bugyo officer, but were retainers of the shogun family and worked at a bugyo-sho office hereditarily.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriki (police sergeants) and doshin (police constables) were subordinates of the bugyo officer, but were retainers of the shogun family and worked at a bugyo-sho office hereditarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>奉行はあくまで老中所轄の旗本に過ぎず、そのため、与力や同心たちとは直接の主従関係は無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, a bugyo officer was a hatamoto controlled by Roju, and therefore there were no direct master-servant relationship between the officer and yoriki/doshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bugyo officer was merely a hatamoto controlled by Roju, therefore there were no direct master-servant relationship between the officer and yoriki and doshin.</e>
<cmt>副詞変更、and削除＆挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bugyo officer was merely a hatamoto controlled by Roju, therefore there were no direct master-servant relationship between the officer and yoriki and doshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>逆に奉行と主従関係にあった与力を内与力と呼び、通常の与力とは区別された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a bugyo officer and a yoriki member were in a master-servant relationship, the yoriki was called uchi-yoriki to differentiate the yoriki member from other ordinary yoriki members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a bugyo officer and a yoriki member were in a master-servant relationship, the yoriki was called uchi-yoriki to differentiate from other ordinary yoriki members.</e>
<cmt>一部省略</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a bugyo officer and a yoriki member were in a master-servant relationship, the yoriki was called uchi-yoriki to differentiate from other ordinary yoriki members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一般に講談などでは南北奉行所は互いにライバル関係にあり仲が悪かったかのように描写される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally depicted, for example, in kodan storytelling, that the kita (north) bugyo-sho office and the minami (south) bugyo-sho office were in a rival relationship, not being intimate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally depicted, for example, in storytelling, that the kita (north) bugyo-sho office and the minami (south) bugyo-sho office were in a rival relationship and didn&apos;t get along with each other.</e>
<cmt>kodan削除、intimateを変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally depicted, for example, in storytelling, that the kita (north) bugyo-sho office and the minami (south) bugyo-sho office were in a rival relationship and didn&apos;t get along with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしながら、後述する南北奉行所の関係からもわかるように、むしろ、奉行の方が余所者であって信頼関係が薄かったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as shown in the later-described relationships between the two bugyo-sho offices, it is said that bugyo officers were outsiders in the area and their relationship of mutual trust was not firm.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as shown in the later-described relationships between the two bugyo-sho offices, it is said that bugyo officers were outsiders in the area and their relationship of mutual trust was not firm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as shown in the later-described relationships between the two bugyo-sho offices, it is said that bugyo officers were outsiders in the area and their relationship of mutual trust was not firm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>町奉行所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Machi-bugyo-sho offices</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">a Machi-bugyo-sho office</e>
<cmt>単数化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">a Machi-bugyo-sho office</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>1631年に幕府が町奉行所を建てるまで、町奉行所は、町奉行に任ぜられた者がその邸宅にお白洲を作ってその職務を執り行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until 1631when the bakufu built machi-bugyo-sho offices, the person appointed to a machi-bugyo officer used his residence as the office, executing his job by providing a court (called shirasu: literally, a white sand area) in the premises.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until 1631when the bakufu built machi-bugyo-sho offices, the person appointed a machi-bugyo officer used his residence as the office, executing his job by providing a court (called shirasu: literally, a white sand area) in the premise.</e>
<cmt>単数化、to削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until 1631when the bakufu built machi-bugyo-sho offices, the person appointed a machi-bugyo officer used his residence as the office, executing his job by providing a court (called shirasu: literally, a white sand area) in the premise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>管轄区域は江戸の町方のみで、面積の半分以上を占める武家地・寺社地には権限が及ばなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its territory of control was limited to machikata (the town area) of Edo, and its authority did not cover the samurai residences, shrines and temples that occupied an area more than a half of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its territory of control was limited to machikata (the town area) of Edo, and its authority did not cover samurai residences, shrines and temples that occupied more than a half of Edo.</e>
<cmt>an area削除、冠詞削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its territory of control was limited to machikata (the town area) of Edo, and its authority did not cover samurai residences, shrines and temples that occupied more than a half of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ただ寺社の門前町についてはのちに町奉行管轄に移管された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the control of the town areas in front of shrines or of temples was transferred to the machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the control of the town areas in front of the shrines and the temples was transferred to the machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更、orをandに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the control of the town areas in front of the shrines and the temples was transferred to the machi-bugyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>1818年には江戸の範囲が地図上に赤い線（朱引）で正式に定められたが、同時に町奉行の管轄する範囲も黒い線（墨引）で示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1818, the Edo area was officially specified on a map with a red line (called shu-biki), and at the same time, the area to be controlled by the machi-bugyo with a black line (called sumi-biki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1818, the Edo area was officially specified on a map with a red line (called shu-biki), and at the same time, the area to be controlled by the machi-bugyo was shown with a black line (called sumi-biki).</e>
<cmt>動詞挿入、ピリオド追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1818, the Edo area was officially specified on a map with a red line (called shu-biki), and at the same time, the area to be controlled by the machi-bugyo was shown with a black line (called sumi-biki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これは後の東京15区、即ち市制施行時の東京市の範囲とほぼ一致する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area roughly corresponds to that of 15 wards of Tokyo, or the area of Tokyo City when the city system started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area roughly corresponds to that of 15 wards of Tokyo, or the area of Tokyo City when the city system started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area roughly corresponds to that of 15 wards of Tokyo, or the area of Tokyo City when the city system started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>町奉行所と言う名称は、その役職から来た名であるため、町人たちからは御番所や御役所と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of machi-bugyo-sho came from the title of the governmental post, and therefore, the place was actually called go-bansho (a police station) or o-yakusho (a government office) by townspeople.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term of machi-bugyo-sho came from the name of the governmental post, therefore, the office was actually called go-bansho (a police station) or o-yakusho (a government office) by townspeople.</e>
<cmt>titleをnameに変更、and削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term of machi-bugyo-sho came from the name of the governmental post, therefore, the office was actually called go-bansho (a police station) or o-yakusho (a government office) by townspeople.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>月番制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monthly rotation system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monthly rotation system</e>
<cmt>冠詞挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monthly rotation system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>よく北町奉行（所）・南町奉行（所）と言われるように、（一部の時期を除き）江戸町奉行所は2ヶ所あった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the term of kita-machi-bugyo (-sho) and that of minami-machi-bugyo (-sho) were often used, two Edo-machi-bugyo-sho offices were placed (except for a certain period of time).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the term of kita-machi-bugyo (-sho) and minami-machi-bugyo (-sho) were often used, two Edo-machi-bugyo-sho offices were placed (except for a certain period).</e>
<cmt>that ofとof time削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the term of kita-machi-bugyo (-sho) and minami-machi-bugyo (-sho) were often used, two Edo-machi-bugyo-sho offices were placed (except for a certain period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかしながら、これは管轄区域を二分していた訳ではなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this did not mean that the control territory was divided between the two offices.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this did not mean that the control territory was divided between the two offices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this did not mean that the control territory was divided between the two offices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>月番制によって交互に業務を行っていたという制度であった（ただし、市中を巡回する廻り方同心は巡回すべき自身番を指定されておりそういった意味での管轄は存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The job was actually conducted in a monthly rotation system (however, for each of the doshin officers who walked around watching town situations, the jishinban (the town-watching places operated by townspeople themselves) to visit were specified, and in that sense, a control territory existed naturally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The job was actually conducted in a monthly rotation system (however, for each of the doshin officers who walked around watching town situations, jishinban [the town-watching places operated by townspeople themselves] to patrol were specified, and in that sense, a control territory existed naturally.</e>
<cmt>動詞変更、括弧の種類変更、冠詞削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The job was actually conducted in a monthly rotation system (however, for each of the doshin officers who walked around watching town situations, jishinban [the town-watching places operated by townspeople themselves] to patrol were specified, and in that sense, a control territory existed naturally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかし、この各同心が担当する自身番も、江戸市中に散在する形で割り当てられており、現今の警察の○○方面というような地域的にまとまったものではなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the jishinban places allotted to a doshin officer were scattered all over the Edo city area, and was not concentrated in an area, like the XX direction in the police today).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the jishinban places allotted to a doshin officer were scattered all over the Edo city area, and were not concentrated in an area, like the XX direction in the present police).</e>
<cmt>動詞の複数化、todayをpresentに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the jishinban places allotted to a doshin officer were scattered all over the Edo city area, and were not concentrated in an area, like the XX direction in the present police).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この月番制は、民事訴訟の受付を北と南で交替で受理していたことを指すものであり、民事訴訟の受理以外の通常業務（職権開始の刑事訴訟を含む）は当然行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This monthly rotation indicated that civil suits were accepted by the kita (north) office or by the minami (south) office for a month alternatively, and ordinary jobs of the office excepting the acceptance of civil suits (and including criminal suits whose examinations were underway) were conducted naturally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This monthly rotation system indicated that civil suits were accepted by the kita (north) office or by the minami (south) office alternatively, and ordinary jobs of the office except for the acceptance of civil suits (including criminal suits whose examinations were underway) were conducted naturally.</e>
<cmt>systemを追加、一部削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This monthly rotation system indicated that civil suits were accepted by the kita (north) office or by the minami (south) office alternatively, and ordinary jobs of the office except for the acceptance of civil suits (including criminal suits whose examinations were underway) were conducted naturally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また月番でない奉行所は、月番で受理し、未処理となっている訴訟の処理等も行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the bugyo-sho office being off duty for the month in the rotation system handled the law suits that were accepted by the office in the months when it was on duty in the system but had not been settled yet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the bugyo-sho office being its off duty turn handled unfinished law suits that were accepted by the office in its on duty turn.</e>
<cmt>文の簡略化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the bugyo-sho office being its off duty turn handled unfinished law suits that were accepted by the office in its on duty turn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>その南北と言う名称にしても、奉行所所在地の位置関係によりそう呼ばれていたということであり、南北は正式な呼称ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of kita and that of minami were used for identifying the location where a bugyo-sho office was placed, and were not used officially</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term of kita and minami were used for identifying a location where the bugyo-sho office was placed, and were not used officially</e>
<cmt>冠詞の変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term of kita and minami were used for identifying a location where the bugyo-sho office was placed, and were not used officially</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>公式には一律で町奉行とのみ呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officially, each of them was called a machi-bugyo-sho office uniformly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officially, each of them was called &quot;machi-bugyo-sho office&quot; uniformly.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、クォーテーションマーク追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officially, each of them was called &quot;machi-bugyo-sho office&quot; uniformly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>従って1つの奉行所が移転されたことによって、各奉行所間の位置関係が変更されると、移転されなかった奉行所の呼称も変更されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when a bugyo-sho office moved and the relationships among the bugyo-sho office locations changed consequently, the names of the bugyo-sho office that had not moved were also changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when a bugyo-sho office moved and the relationship between the bugyo-sho office locations changed consequently, the name of the bugyo-sho office that had not moved was also changed.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、単数化、amongをbetweenに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when a bugyo-sho office moved and the relationship between the bugyo-sho office locations changed consequently, the name of the bugyo-sho office that had not moved was also changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>宝永4年（1707年）に本来北町奉行所であった常盤橋門内の役宅が一番南側の数寄屋橋門内に移転した際には、その場所ゆえに南町奉行所と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1707 when the residence of a bugyo officer moved to the area within the gate of Sukiya-bashi Bridge, on the southernmost side, from the area within the gate of Tokiwa-bashi Bridge, the new residence became to be called the minami-bugyo-sho office due to its location.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1707 when a residence of a bugyo officer moved to an area within the gate of Sukiya-bashi Bridge on the southernmost side from an area within the gate of Tokiwa-bashi Bridge, the new residence became to be called the minami-bugyo-sho office due to its location.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更、コンマ削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1707 when a residence of a bugyo officer moved to an area within the gate of Sukiya-bashi Bridge on the southernmost side from an area within the gate of Tokiwa-bashi Bridge, the new residence became to be called the minami-bugyo-sho office due to its location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>従来鍛冶橋内にあった南町奉行所が中町奉行所に、同じく呉服橋門内にあった中町奉行所が北町奉行所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the minami-bugyo-sho office located in the area inside Kajiya-bashi Bridge became to be called the naka (middle)-bugyo-sho office, and the naka-bugyo-sho office located in the area inside Gofuku-bashi Bridge the kita-bugyo-sho office.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the former minami-bugyo-sho office located in an area inside Kajiya-bashi Bridge became to be called the naka (middle)-bugyo-sho office, and the former naka-bugyo-sho office located in an area inside Gofuku-bashi Bridge became to be called the kita-bugyo-sho office.</e>
<cmt>former追加、冠詞変更、動詞挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the former minami-bugyo-sho office located in an area inside Kajiya-bashi Bridge became to be called the naka (middle)-bugyo-sho office, and the former naka-bugyo-sho office located in an area inside Gofuku-bashi Bridge became to be called the kita-bugyo-sho office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>1702年（元禄15年）閏8月 - 1719年（享保4年）1月という短い間ではあるが中町奉行所というものも設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a short period of time between uruu August (the second August in the old calendar) of 1702 and January of 1719 (in the old calendar), the naka-machi-bugyo-sho office was introduced as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a short period between August of 1702 and January of 1719, the naka-machi-bugyo-sho office was introduced as well.</e>
<cmt>旧暦の説明を省略、althoughを変更、of time削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a short period between August of 1702 and January of 1719, the naka-machi-bugyo-sho office was introduced as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>設置された理由や職務内容はあまり定かではないが、南北町奉行所の補助役として設置されたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clear why the office was introduced and what it job was, but it is said that the office was established to support the jobs of the kita- and minami-machi-bugyo-sho offices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear why the office was introduced and what its job was, but it is said that the office was established to support the kita- and minami-machi-bugyo-sho offices.</e>
<cmt>一部省略、itをitsに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear why the office was introduced and what its job was, but it is said that the office was established to support the kita- and minami-machi-bugyo-sho offices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>明治以降、奉行所は取り壊されてしまったが、北町（東京駅八重洲口北側付近）・南町（有楽町マリオン付近）の両奉行所が存在していたとされる場所には、今でも石碑が建っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, the bugyo-sho offices were destroyed, but a stone monument has been built in the site where the kita-machi-bugyo-sho office is said to have been located (around on the north side of Yaesu-guchi Exit, Tokyo Station), and another one in the site where the minami-machi-bugyo-sho office is said to have been located (around Marion in Yurakucho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the Meiji period, the bugyo-sho offices were destroyed, but stone monuments have been built in the site where the kita-machi-bugyo-sho office is said to have been located (around on the north side of Yaesu-guchi Exit, Tokyo Station) and where the minami-machi-bugyo-sho office is said to have been located (around Marion in Yurakucho).</e>
<cmt>一部省略</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the Meiji period, the bugyo-sho offices were destroyed, but stone monuments have been built in the site where the kita-machi-bugyo-sho office is said to have been located (around on the north side of Yaesu-guchi Exit, Tokyo Station) and where the minami-machi-bugyo-sho office is said to have been located (around Marion in Yurakucho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ただし、いずれも幕末期における奉行所の位置を指すものであり、文化_(日本)2年（1812年）以後に固定化された場所に相応している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, either of them is the site where it existed towards the end of the Edo period, or in 1812 and later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, either of them is the site where it existed towards the end of the Edo period, or in 1812 and later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, either of them is the site where it existed towards the end of the Edo period, or in 1812 and later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>江戸町奉行の一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A list of Edo machi-bugyo officers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A list of Edo machi-bugyo officers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A list of Edo machi-bugyo officers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>初期は、北町・南町両奉行が置かれておらず、一つの奉行で成り立っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, neither the kita-machi-bugyo post nor the minami-machi-bugyo posts were introduced yet, with only a bugyo post existing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, neither the kita-machi-bugyo post nor the minami-machi-bugyo posts were introduced yet, with only a bugyo post existing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, neither the kita-machi-bugyo post nor the minami-machi-bugyo posts were introduced yet, with only a bugyo post existing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>正式な町奉行という役職ではなかったが事実上同じ働きを持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was not an official machi-bugyo post, their functions were essentially the same.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was not an official machi-bugyo post, its function was essentially the same.</e>
<cmt>単数化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was not an official machi-bugyo post, its function was essentially the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>正式に町奉行という官職ができたのは、北南町奉行が設置されてからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The post of machi-bugyo was introduced when the kita-machi-bugyo post and the minami-machi-bugyo post were established..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post of machi-bugyo was officially introduced when the kita-machi-bugyo post and the minami-machi-bugyo post were established..</e>
<cmt>officially挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post of machi-bugyo was officially introduced when the kita-machi-bugyo post and the minami-machi-bugyo post were established..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、途中中町奉行というものが設置されたが、わずか5代で廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naka-machi-bugyo post was introduced in an intermediate period, but the post was abolished only after the post was assumed by five persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The naka-machi-bugyo post was introduced in an intermediate period, but was abolished only after assumed by five persons.</e>
<cmt>繰り返しの削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naka-machi-bugyo post was introduced in an intermediate period, but was abolished only after assumed by five persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hyuuga(id:14767), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), ちんぐゎらっ(id:2733), Auf(id:633), 水野白楓(id:22811), Rikumio(id:99645), Krp(id:15909), Tokyosampo00(id:140349), Rai koku(id:1661), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Hatsune(id:26654), EULE(id:74209), 住めら尊(id:173954), アンダーソン(id:45729), VolkovBot(id:105371), Michey.M(id:906), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), ふんにゃらにゃ(id:27740), トホホ川(id:50502), Alexbot(id:157199), Chickchick(id:253292), Hermes(id:21387), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Jmho(id:10472), Newt(id:218172), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>