<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>荘官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>荘官（しょうかん）は、日本の荘園において、荘園領主（本所）から現地管理を委ねられた者の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokan is a general name of an officer governing Japanese shoen (manor) entrusted by lord of the manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokan was the general name of an officer governing Japanese shoen (manor) entrusted by the lord of the manor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokan was the general name of an officer governing Japanese shoen (manor) entrusted by the lord of the manor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>荘園を開発した開発領主（かいほつりょうしゅ）が寄進先の荘園領主から荘官として荘園管理者の地位を保全されることもあれば、寄進を受けた荘園領主が自らの荘園支配を強めるために家臣を荘官に任命して現地へ派遣することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Kaihotsu ryoshu (reclaimers) donated manors and the lords of the manor kept them as shokan to manage manors, also the lords of the manor sent their retainers to the local manors to reinforce their influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Kaihatsu ryoshu (reclaimers) donated manors and the lords of the manor kept them on as shokan to manage the manor, also the lords of the manor sent their retainers to the local manors to reinforce their influence.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Kaihatsu ryoshu (reclaimers) donated manors and the lords of the manor kept them on as shokan to manage the manor, also the lords of the manor sent their retainers to the local manors to reinforce their influence.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中期の10世紀後半から11世紀にかけて、田堵（たと、有力農民層のこと）が国司に認められた免田（租税免除された田地）を中心に田地の開発を進め、私有地化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Between the late tenth century and the eleventh century in the mid Heian era, Tato (powerful peasants) cultivated menden (reclaimed land exempt from charges) which was admitted by Kokushi (provincial governor) and privatized it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between the late tenth century and the eleventh century in the mid Heian era, Tato (powerful peasants) cultivated menden (reclaimed land exempt from charges) which was allowed by Kokushi (provincial governor), and privatized it.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between the late tenth century and the eleventh century in the mid Heian Period, Tato (powerful peasants) cultivated menden (reclaimed land exempt from charges) which was allowed by Kokushi (provincial governor), and privatized it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>（このような田堵を開発領主という）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[These tatos are called &quot;Kaihotsu ryoshu&quot; (reclaimers).]</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[These Tatos were called &quot;Kaihotsu ryoshu&quot; (reclaimers).]</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(These farmers were called &apos;Kaihotsu ryoshu&apos; [reclaimers]).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、そうした土地の所有権に係る法的根拠は極めて薄弱であり、国衙によって収公されるおそれが強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the legal basis of their property right was fragile and it was possible that kokuga (provincial government offices) dispossessed the properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the legal basis of their property rights was fragile and it was possible for kokuga (provincial government offices) to seize the properties.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the legal basis of their property rights was fragile and it was possible for kokuga (provincial government offices) to seize the properties.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため田堵は所有地を中央の有力貴族や有力寺社へ寄進することで、租税免除と土地支配権の確保を図っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, tatos donated their lands to the powerful nobles or powerful temples in the central government in order to be exempt from charges and to keep the power of their land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, tatos donated their land to the powerful nobles or powerful temples in the central government in order to be exempt from charges and to keep the power of their land.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, tatos donated their land to the powerful nobles or powerful temples in the central government in order to be exempt from charges and to keep the power of their land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>寄進を受けた荘園領主を領家（りょうけ）というが、寄進の際、開発領主は領家から下司（げし/げす）や公文（くもん）、出納 (荘園)（すいとう）などに任命されることにより、現地管理者としての地位を保全された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lord of manor who received a donated manor was called Ryoke, and as Ryoke appointed Kaihatsu ryoshu as Geshi/Gesu (lower ranked officer), Kumon (a local shoen official below the gesu in rank) or Suito (local shoen official below the gesu and kumon in rank), Kaihatsu ryoshu could keep their positions as manager of manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lord of the manor who received a donated manor was called Ryoke, and as Ryoke appointed Kaihatsu ryoshu as Geshi/Gesu (lower ranked officer), Kumon (a local shoen official below the gesu in rank) or Suito (local shoen official below the gesu and kumon in rank), Kaihatsu ryoshu could keep their positions as manager of the manor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lord of the manor who received a donated manor was called Ryoke, and as Ryoke appointed Kaihatsu ryoshu as Geshi/Gesu (lower ranked officer), Kumon (a local shoen official below the gesu in rank) or Suito (local shoen official below the gesu and kumon in rank), Kaihatsu ryoshu could keep their positions as manager of the manor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらの下司や公文などを総称して荘官という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokan is a general name including Gesu and Kumon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokan is a general name including Gesu and Kumon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokan is a general name including Gesu and Kumon.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>一般的に荘官には、荘園の一部から給田（きゅうでん）が与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, shokan received a land from a part of the manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally, shokan received land from a part of the manor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally, shokan received land from a part of the manor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>給田は免田とされ、収穫は全て荘官の得分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land shokan received was exempt from charges and shokan could get all harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land that shokan received was exempt from charges and shokan could keep all of the harvest.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land that shokan received was exempt from charges and shokan could keep all of the harvest.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、下司とは、上位の荘園領主を上司と見たときの対比から生まれた呼称であり、また公文は、荘園管理のための帳簿や文書を扱うことから来た呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geshi/Gesu (lower ranked officer) was named in contradistinction to the lord of the manor as Joshi (Geshi&apos;s superior), and the name of Kumon was derived from their role which was management of books and records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geshi/Gesu (lower ranked officer) were named, distinct from the lord of the manor, as Joshi (Geshi&apos;s superior), and the name of Kumon was derived from their role, which was management of books and records.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geshi/Gesu (lower ranked officer) were named, distinct from the lord of the manor, as Joshi (Geshi&apos;s superior), and the name of Kumon was derived from their role, which was management of books and records.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>領家からさらに皇族や摂関家へ荘園寄進されることもあり、この最上位の荘園領主を本家（ほんけ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoke often donated their manors to the imperial or sekkan families and the lord of manors at the top of relationship was called Honke (head family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoke often donated their manors to the imperial or sekkan families and the lord of the manor at the top of the relationship was called Honke (head family).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoke often donated their manors to the imperial or sekkan families and the lord of the manor at the top of the relationship was called Honke (head family).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>本家・領家のうち、荘園の実効支配権を持つ者は本所といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who controlled the manor among Honke and Ryoke was Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who controlled the manor among the Honke and Ryoke was Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person who controlled the manor among the Honke and Ryoke was Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>本所が自らの荘園支配を強化するために、家臣を現地へ派遣し、下司や公文などを指揮監督することがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To take greater control of manors, Honjo often sent down their retainers to supervise Gesu and Kumon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To take greater control of manors, Honjo often sent down their retainers to supervise Gesu and Kumon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To take greater control of manors, Honjo often sent down their retainers to supervise Gesu and Kumon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この現地へ派遣された者を預所（あずかりどころ/あずかっそ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainers who sent down to local manors was called Azukaridokoro/Azukasso (a deputy of &quot;Shoen&quot; manor lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainers who were sent down to local manors were called Azukaridokoro/Azukasso (deputy of the &quot;Shoen&quot; manor lord).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainers who were sent down to local manors were called Azukaridokoro/Azukasso (deputy of the &apos;Shoen&apos; manor lord).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>預所も荘官の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azukaridokoro was one of shokans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azukaridokoro was one of the shokan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azukaridokoro was also one of the shokan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのうち、開発領主（下司や公文に任命された者を含む）の中から預所に任じられる者も出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, some Kaihotsu ryoshu (including Gesu and Kumon) were appointed as Azukaridokoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, some Kaihatsu ryoshu (including Gesu and Kumon) were appointed as Azukaridokoro.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, some Kaihatsu ryoshu (including Gesu and Kumon) were appointed as Azukaridokoro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>武士化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Becoming Samurai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Becoming Samurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Becoming Samurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>荘園の支配・管理は、現代のように明確な法規定があった訳ではなく、荘園領主の権威に依存する不安定なものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As there was no clear legal rule, control and management of manors were not stable and depended on the authority of the lord of manors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As there was no clear legal rule, control and management of manors were not stable and depended on the authority of the lord of the manor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As there was no clear legal rule, control and management of manors were not stable and depended on the authority of the lord of the manor.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そのため、他の荘園の荘官や国衙との間に、荘園の支配・管理権や境界をめぐる紛争が発生することも多く、荘官がその対処に当たっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, conflicts over the control, management and boundary of the manors often occurred between other shokans and kokuga (provincial government offices), and the shokans handled these problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, conflicts over the control, management and boundaries of the manors often occurred between other shokans and kokuga (provincial government offices), and the shokans handled these problems.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, conflicts over the control, management and boundaries of the manors often occurred between other shokans and kokuga (provincial government offices), and the shokans handled these problems.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>当時、中央の官職にあぶれた武士身分の下級貴族が多数、地方へ下向してきており、荘官たちは荘園を巡る紛争解決のために、それらの武士貴族と主従関係を築いていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, as many lower ranking aristocrats with samurai rank who could not get the posts in the central government went down to the provinces, shokan established subordinate-superior relationship with them for solving conflicts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, many lower ranking aristocrats with samurai rank who could not get posts in the central government went down to the provinces, and shokan established subordinate-superior relationships with them in order to solve conflicts.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, many lower ranking aristocrats with samurai rank who could not get posts in the central government went down to the provinces, and shokan established heirachichal relationships with them in order to solve conflicts over the manors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>中には武士となる荘官も現れた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some shokans became samurai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some shokans became samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shokans became samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>（全ての荘官が武士化した訳ではないことに注意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Not all shokan became samurai.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Not all shokan became samurai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Not all shokan became samurai.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>鎌倉時代になると、鎌倉幕府によって御家人や地頭として認められる荘官も出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kamakura era, some shokans were admitted as Gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura era） or Jito (manager and lord of manor) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura era, some shokans were admitted as Gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura era） or Jito (manager and lord of the manor) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura era, some shokan were admitted as Gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura era） or Jito (manager and lord of the manor) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>このことは、荘園領主による地位保全では十分とは言えなくなり、新たな権威として台頭した幕府を頼り始めたことを意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This meant that the protection by the lord of manor was not enough and shokan began to rely on the Kamakura bakufu which rose as a new authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This meant that the protection by the lord of the manor was not enough and shokan began to rely on the Kamakura bakufu which rose as a new authority.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This meant that the protection by the lord of the manor was not enough and shokan began to rely on the Kamakura bakufu which rose as a new authority.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>荘官は次第に荘園領主（本所）を軽視していき、本所の権益を奪うようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shokan began to disrespect the lord of manor (Honjo) and deprive Honjo of their interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shokan began to disrespect the lord of the manor (Honjo) and deprive Honjo of their interests.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shokan began to disrespect the lord of the manor (Honjo) and rob Honjo of their interests.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>室町時代に入った頃から、荘官は在地領主としての国人へ変質した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the beginning of the Muromachi era, shokan transformed into kokujin (local samurai) as local lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning of the Muromachi era, shokan transformed into kokujin (local samurai) as local lords.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning of the Muromachi era, shokan transformed into kokujin (local samurai) as local lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>それでも荘官は荘園制とともに戦国時代 (日本)まで存続したが、荘園が解体した太閤検地により荘官も消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even so, shokan had existed with manorial system till the Sengoku period, however, it disappeared because manors were demised by Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even so, shokan had existed with the manorial system until the Sengoku period, however, they disappeared because manors were dissolved by Taiko-kenchi (the land survey of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even so, shokan had existed with the manorial system until the Sengoku period, however, they disappeared because manors were dissolved by Taiko-kenchi (the land survey of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ただし、江戸時代も荘官の名残として「庄屋」や「名主」などの呼称は残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some words such as &quot;Shoya&quot; (village headman) and &quot;Myoshu/Nanusi&quot; (village headman) were left in Edo era as the remnant of shokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But some words such as &quot;Shoya&quot; (village headman) and &quot;Myoshu/Nanusi&quot; (village headman) remained in the Edo era as the remnants of shokan.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But some words such as &quot;Shoya&quot; (village headman) and &quot;Myoshu/Nanusi&quot; (village headman) remained in the Edo era as the remnants of shokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Amler(id:101250), Malistan(id:121806), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>