<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>預 (官職)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azukari (official post)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azukari (official post)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azukari (official post)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>預（あずかり）とは、平安時代の官司・寺社・荘園などに置かれた職名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azukari was a post which was set up at government offices, temples/shrines and shoen (manor) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azukari was a post which was set up at government offices, temples/shrines and shoen (manor) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azukari was a post which was set up at government offices, temples or shrines and shoen (manor) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>『延喜式』には太政官厨家及び太政官文殿に設置されたことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Engishi&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), Azukari was set up at Daijokan chuke (kitchen of the Great Council of State) and Daijokan fumidono (repository of documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Engishi&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), Azukari was set up at Daijokan chuke (kitchen of the Great Council of State) and Daijokan fumidono (repository of documents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers), Azukari was set up at Daijokan chuke (kitchen of the Great Council of State) and Daijokan fumidono (repository of documents).</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>10世紀に入ると、後院や院庁、御厨子所、進物所、穀倉院をはじめ、国衙や郡衙などを含めて様々な官司において預が設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 10th century, Azukari was set up at various government offices including, without limitation, Goin (retired emperor&apos;s palace), In no cho (retired emperor&apos;s office), Shinmotsudokoro (serving office), Kokusoin (office of storehouses), Kokuga (provincial government office) and Gunga (country government office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 10th century, Azukari was set up at various government offices including, without limitation, Goin (retired emperor&apos;s palace), In no cho (retired emperor&apos;s office), Shinmotsudokoro (serving office), Kokusoin (office of storehouses), Kokuga (provincial government office) and Gunga (country government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 10th century, Azukari was set up at various government offices including, without limitation, Goin (retired emperor&apos;s palace), In no cho (retired emperor&apos;s office), Shinmotsudokoro (serving office), Kokusoin (office of storehouses), Kokuga (provincial government office) and Gunga (country government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>預が設置された中央の官司においては、通常は別当の下に置かれて公卿である別当に代わって実務を統括する立場に立つことが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of central government offices, Azukari was normally placed under Betto (head of office) and supervised practical jobs instead of Betto who was kugyo (top court noble).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of central government offices, Azukari was normally placed under Betto (head of office) and supervised practical jobs instead of Betto who was kugyo (top court noble).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of central government offices, Azukari was normally placed under Betto (head of office) and supervised practical jobs instead of Betto who was kugyo (top court noble).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>院庁などでは執事が設置されると、別当・執事の次に置かれる例があったが、執事と預の関係は官司によって異なっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azukari was sometimes placed next to Betto and Shitsuji (steward) at In no cho, but the ranking of Shitsuji and Betto was different depending on government offices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azukari was sometimes placed next to Betto and Shitsuji (steward) at In no cho, but the ranking of Shitsuji and Betto was different depending on government offices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azukari was sometimes placed next to Betto and Shitsuji (steward) at In no cho, but the ranking of Shitsuji and Betto was different depending on government offices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、1年交代で補任された年預という職は元は預から派生したとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the post of Nenyo (subordinate of Shitsuji), whose term was one year, derived from Azukari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the post of Nenyo (subordinate of Shitsuji), whose term was one year, derived from Azukari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the post of Nenyo (subordinate of Shitsuji), whose term was one year, derived from Azukari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>その他に荘園では在地において荘務を掌る職として預が置かれたり、神社の社務や寺院の寺務を掌る者として置かれた例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azukari was set up at shoen as the post which was responsible for the on-site management of shoen and in the case of temples/shrines, Azukari was set up as the post which was responsible for the management of temples/shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azukari was set up at shoen as a post which was responsible for the on-site management of shoen and in the case of temples/shrines, Azukari was set up as the post which was responsible for the management of temples/shrines.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azukari was set up at shoen as a post which was responsible for the on-site management of shoen and in the case of temples or shrines, Azukari was set up as the post which was responsible for the management of temples or shrines.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>春日大社や石清水八幡宮では上位の神官として正預・権預が任じられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Kasuga Taisha Shrine and Iwashimizu Hachimangu, Sho no Azukari (head custodian) and Gon no Azukari (assistant custodian) were set up as senior post of Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Kasuga Taisha Shrine and Iwashimizu Hachimangu, Sho no Azukari (head custodian) and Gon no Azukari (assistant custodian) were set up as senior posts for Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Kasuga Taisha Shrine and Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine, Sho no Azukari (head custodian) and Gon no Azukari (assistant custodian) were set up as senior posts for Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>