<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyaku (public duties)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyaku (public duties)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyaku (Public duties)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国役（こくやく/くにやく）とは、平安時代から南北朝時代 (日本)にかけて朝廷及び国衙が諸国に課した雑役・一国平均役などの課役のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyaku is labor duties, such as zatsueki (odd-job tasks) and Ikkoku heikinyaku (taxes and labor uniformly imposed on shoen (manor) and kokugaryou (provincial land) in a province), imposed by the Imperial Court and kokuga (provincial government offices) from the Heian period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyaku were labor duties, such as zatsueki (odd-job tasks) and Ikkoku heikinyaku (taxes and labor uniformly imposed on shoen (manor) and kokugaryou (provincial land) in a province), imposed by the Imperial Court and kokuga (provincial government offices) from the Heian period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyaku were duties imposed by the Imperial Court and kokuga (provincial government offices) from the Heian period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>転じて室町幕府が守護大名及び諸国に課した段銭などの課役、及び守護大名が独自に領国に対して賦課した課役のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By extension, it refers to labor duties, such as tansen (a kind of provisional tax in medieval Japan), imposed on Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and each province by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and labor duties imposed by the Shugo daimyo on their own territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By extension, it refers to labor duties, such as tansen (a kind of provisional tax in medieval Japan), imposed on Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and each province by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and labor duties imposed by the Shugo daimyo on their own territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By extension, it refers to duties, such as tansen (a kind of provisional tax in medieval Japan), imposed on Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and each province by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and duties imposed by the Shugo daimyo on their own territories.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>律令制の崩壊後、朝廷は造内裏役や役夫工米などを名目に国衙を通じて雑役（臨時雑役・雑公事）や一国平均役などを国衙領や荘園などに課していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a breakdown of the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the Imperial Court imposed zatsueki (temporary labor work and zoukuji (other labor work)) and Ikkoku heikinyaku on Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) and shoen (manor in medieval Japan) through kokuga in the name of zodairi-yaku (a public duty) or yakubukumai (a special kind of taxation on rice levied by the grand shrines).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After breakdown of the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the Imperial Court imposed zatsueki (temporary labor work and zoukuji (other labor work)) and Ikkoku heikinyaku on Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) and shoen (manor in medieval Japan) through kokuga in the name of zodairi-yaku (a public duty) or yakubukumai (a special kind of taxation on rice levied by the grand shrines).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After breakdown of the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the Imperial Court imposed duties including labor on territories governed by provincial government officrs and manors through provinical government officers in the name of public duty or yakubukumai (a special kind of taxation on rice levied by the grand shrines).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、国衙も同様の名目で自ら賦課・徴収を行うようになっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the kokuga themselves also imposed duties and collected taxes under the similar pretext.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the kokuga themselves also imposed duties and collected taxes under a similar pretext.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the provincial government officers themselves also imposed duties and collected taxes under a similar pretext.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>こうした国衙から当該令制国への賦課を11世紀中頃から「国役」と称するようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such imposition of duties by the kokuga on ryoseikoku (province) came to be called the &quot;kuniyaku&quot; after the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such imposition of duties by the kokuga on ryoseikoku (province) came to be called the &quot;kuniyaku&quot; after the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such imposition of duties by the provincial government officers came to be called the &apos;kuniyaku&apos; after the middle of the eleventh century.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>12世紀に入ると、在庁官人などが国役の一環として在家役を課して公領把握に努めるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 12th century, Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) imposed Zaikeyaku (taxation on residents) as one of the kuniyaku and strived to grasp Koryo (an Imperial demesne).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 12th century, Zaichokanjin (the local officials in the Heian and Kamakura periods) imposed Zaikeyaku (taxation on residents) as one of the kuniyaku and strived to grasp Koryo (an Imperial demesne).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the twelfth century, the local officials in the Heian and Kamakura periods imposed taxes on residents as one of the kuniyaku (public duties) and strived to gain control over the domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ると、朝廷による一国平均役が鎌倉幕府や守護の関与を得ながらも国役として展開される事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the Imperial Court began to develop the Ikkoku heikinyaku as kuniyaku with involvement by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and Shugo (provincial constable).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, the Imperial Court began to develop the Ikkoku heikinyaku as kuniyaku with involvement by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and Shugo (provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the Imperial Court began to develop the public duties with involvement by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and Shugo (provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>南北朝の戦乱の中で守護領国制が形成されていく中で室町幕府及び在地を支配する守護大名が朝廷・国衙に代わって国役の賦課・免除の権限を掌握するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a Shugo dominates a manor) was formed during wars between the Northern and Southern Courts, the Muromachi bakufu and Shugo daimyo which controlled lands secured the authority to impose or exempt kuniyaku on behalf of the Imperial Court and kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Shugo-ryogoku system (system were a Shugo dominated a manor) was formed during wars between the Northern and Southern Courts, the Muromachi bakufu and Shugo daimyo, which controlled lands, secured the authority to impose or exempt kuniyaku on behalf of the Imperial Court and kokuga.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the formation of the Shugo-ryogoku system at the time of the wars between the Northern and Southern Courts, the Muromachi bakufu and Shugo daimyo, who controlled lands, took over the authority to impose or exempt public duties or taxes from the Imperial Court and provincial officials.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>室町幕府は守護大名及び彼らを通じて諸国に対して段銭及び地頭御家人役などの形で課す事で財政収入を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu gained financial revenues by imposing taxes in the form of tansen and jito gokenin yaku (taxation on manager and lord of manor and vassal) on Shugo daimyo and each province via Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi bakufu gained financial revenues by imposing taxes in the form of tansen and jito gokenin yaku (taxation on manager and lord of the manor and vassal) on Shugo daimyo and each province via Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu gained financial revenues by imposing taxes on Shugo daimyo and each province under the Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、守護大名自らも国内に対して守護役として夫役・雑物・段銭などを課していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo daimyo themselves also imposed Buyaku (labor service), zomotsu (a kind of tax), and tansen as shugoyaku (taxation on shugo) in the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo daimyo themselves also imposed Buyaku (labor service), zomotsu (a kind of tax), and tansen as shugoyaku (taxation on shugo) in the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo daimyo themselves also imposed Buyaku (labor service), zomotsu (a kind of tax), and tansen as shugoyaku (taxation on shugo) in the province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>こうした賦課をまとめて国役と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These impositions were collectively called the kuniyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These impositions were collectively called the kuniyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These impositions were collectively called the kuniyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>こうした国役は室町幕府・守護大名の没落で消滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kuniyaku disappeared with the fall of the Muromachi bakufu and Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kuniyaku disappeared with the fall of the Muromachi bakufu and Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kuniyaku disappeared with the fall of the Muromachi bakufu and Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸幕府による諸藩や旗本、農民への国役普請はその復活と見ることも出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) imposed kuniyaku fushin (engineering work) on each domain, hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun), and peasants, which can be regarded as the restoration of kuniyaku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) imposed kuniyaku fushin (engineering work) on each domain, hatamoto (a direct vassal of the shogun), and peasants, which can be regarded as the restoration of kuniyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu forced the various clans, vassals and peasants to perform engineering work (kuniyaku fushin) and this can be regarded as the restoration of the system of public duties (kuniyaku).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>