<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五大老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotairo (five administrators in Toyotomi regime)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotairo (five administrators in Toyotomi regime)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotairo (five administrators in Toyotomi regime)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五大老（ごたいろう）とは、豊臣政権末期（文禄年間）に豊臣家の家老（大老）として政務にあたった有力五大名を指した言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotairo indicates the powerful five administrators who acted as executive organs in the government as Karo (or Tairo) of Toyotomi family at the last days of the Toyotomi Administration during the Bunroku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotairo indicates the five most powerful daimyo clans, appointed as Karo (or Tairo) of the Toyotomi family, and acted as executive organs of the Toyotomi Administration at the last days of the administration, during the Bunroku era (1593-1598).</e>
<cmt>五大老は五大名であることが抜けているので最初のadministrator→daimyo clansに変更。文禄年間に1593-1598を付記。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotairo indicates the five most powerful daimyo clans, appointed as Karo (or Tairo) of the Toyotomi family, and acted as executive organs of the Toyotomi Administration at the last days of the administration, during the Bunroku era (1593-1598).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、当時は「五大老」の呼び名は無く、「五人御奉行」などと呼ばれていたが、江戸時代にいわゆる五奉行（こちらは主に「五人御年寄」などと呼ばれていた）と混乱し、後に「五大老」と呼ばれるようになったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, they were called &apos;Gonin bugyo&apos;, which was quite confusing with &apos;Gonin gobugyo&apos; during the Edo period, who were mainly called &apos;Gonin otoshiyori&apos; in those days; therefore, the term &apos;Gotairo&apos; was coined later to indicate the former to distinguish between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, they were called &apos;Gonin bugyo&apos;, but it became quite confusing with &apos;Gonin gobugyo&apos; during the Edo period (though they were mainly called &apos;Gonin otoshiyori&apos; at the time); as a result, the term &apos;Gotairo&apos; was coined later to indicate the former to distinguish between them.</e>
<cmt>江戸時代になって混乱した、の意味が曖昧なので、which was quite confusing with…→it bacame quite confusing with Gonin gobugyo…</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, they were called &apos;Gonin bugyo,&apos; but it became quite confusing with &apos;Gonin gobugyo&apos; during the Edo period (though they were mainly called &apos;Gonin otoshiyori&apos; at the time); as a result, the term &apos;Gotairo&apos; was coined later to indicate the former to distinguish between them.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>豊臣秀吉は己の死後、その息子・豊臣秀頼を五大老が補佐し、合議制をとることにより徳川家康の台頭を防ごうと考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI intended to prepare a council system of Gotairo for supporting his son Hideyori in case of his death to prevent Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from gaining and expanding power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI established a council system of Gotairo to support his son Hideyori in case of his death, expecting the five members to balance each other to prevent the possible emergence of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>秀吉は五大老を設置したので、TOYOTOMI intended to prepare --&gt;&gt;&gt; TOYOTOMI established a council system of Gotairo 。　家康の台頭を防ごうと　prevent Ieyasu from gaining and expanding powre ----&gt;&gt; prevent the possible emergence of Ieyasu.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI established a council system of Gotairo to support his son Hideyori in case of his death, expecting the five members to balance each other to prevent the possible emergence of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、家康の度重なる盟約違反により有名無実化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through Ieyasu&apos;s frequent violations of alliance, the council system became a mere nominal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the council system became merely nominal through Ieyasu&apos;s frequent covenant violations.</e>
<cmt>盟約違反　&quot;violations of alliance ---&gt;&gt; covenant violations　五大老は同盟していたわけではないので。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the council system became merely nominal through Ieyasu&apos;s frequent covenant violations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、前田利家の存命だった慶長4年（1599年）までは、家康の専横までは防げなかったものの、家康が豊臣家より上回る権威を持つことを防ぐことはできた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the death of Toshiie MAEDA in 1599, Gotairo prevented Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from gaining power more than that of the Toyotomi family, although they could not prevent Ieyasu from domineering over them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotairo prevented Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from surpassing the Toyotomi family until the death of Toshiie MAEDA in 1599, though they could not stop Ieyasu to be dominating.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotairo prevented Ieyasu TOKUGAWA from surpassing the Toyotomi family until the death of Toshiie MAEDA in 1599, though they could not stop Ieyasu to be dominating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>大老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tairo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tairo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tairo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>徳川家康（関東に256万石）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (possessed lands worth 2,560,000 koku of rice in Kanto)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (possessed lands worth 2,560,000 koku of rice in Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (possessed lands worth 2,560,000 koku of rice in Kanto)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>前田利家（北陸地方・加賀など83万石）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiie MAEDA (possessed lands worth 830,000 koku of rice in the Hokuriku region, the Kaga Province and the like)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiie MAEDA (possessed lands worth 830,000 koku of rice in the Hokuriku region and in other areas including Kaga Province)</e>
<cmt>the Kaga Province and the like)---&gt;&gt; and in other areas including Kaga Province. and the likeは同類物を列記するような場合に使用されるのでいささか違うと見えたため。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiie MAEDA (possessed lands worth 830,000 koku of rice in the Hokuriku region and in other areas including Kaga Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>毛利輝元（中国地方・吉備西半・安芸など120万石）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Terumoto MORI (possessed lands worth 1,200,000 koku of rice in the Chugoku region, the western half of the Kibi Province, Aki Province, and the like)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Terumoto MORI (possessed lands worth 1,200,000 koku of rice in the Chugoku region, and in other areas including the western half of Kibi Province and Aki Province)</e>
<cmt>and the likeは同類物を列記するような場合に使用されるのでいささか違うと見えたため。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Terumoto MORI (possessed lands worth 1,200,000 koku of rice in the Chugoku region, and in other areas including the western half of Kibi Province and Aki Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>宇喜多秀家（中国地方・吉備東半57万石）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideie UKIATA (possessed lands worth 570,000 koku of rice in the Chugoku region and the eastern half of the Kibi Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideie UKIATA (possessed lands worth 570,000 koku of rice in the Chugoku region and the eastern half of Kibi Province)</e>
<cmt>the eastern half of the Kibi Province --&gt;&gt; the eastern half of Kibi Province</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideie UKIATA (possessed lands worth 570,000 koku of rice in the Chugoku region and the eastern half of Kibi Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>小早川隆景（北九州・筑前33万石）※文禄年間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (possessed lands worth 330,000 koku of rice in the Northern Kyushu, and Bizen Province) - during the Bunroku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (possessed lands worth 330,000 koku of rice in the northern Kyushu area and Bizen Province) - during the Bunroku era.</e>
<cmt>北九州は北部九州と理解して、in the Northern Kyushu -&gt;&gt; in the norther Kyushu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (possessed lands worth 330,000 koku of rice in the northern Kyushu area and Bizen Province) - during the Bunroku era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>上杉景勝（会津120万石）※1597年の隆景死後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI (possessed lands worth 1,200,000 koku of rice in the Aizu Province) - after the death of Takakage in 1597</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagekatsu UESUGI (possessed lands worth 1,200,000 koku of rice in Aizu Province) - after the death of Takakage in 1597</e>
<cmt>in the Aizu Province --&gt; in Aizu Province</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagekatsu UESUGI (possessed lands worth 1,200,000 koku of rice in Aizu Province) - after the death of Takakage in 1597</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>前田利家の死後は嫡子の前田利長がその地位を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Toshiie MAEDA, his heir Toshinaga inherited the post in Gotairo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Toshiie MAEDA, his heir Toshinaga inherited the post in the council of Gotairo.</e>
<cmt>the post in Gotairo.--&gt; the post in the council of Gotairo.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Toshiie MAEDA, his heir Toshinaga inherited the post in the council of Gotairo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Noir(id:45654), 幕僚(id:77716), Shizhao(id:1325), 出羽卒族(id:283926), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), HI(id:72996), STBot(id:137943), Ikizama(id:126094), Kamakura(id:472), Bue(id:237847), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), VolkovBot(id:105371), Rei-bot(id:94097), Chobot(id:20846), Sabkakusikaku(id:277058), 越中掾(id:149423), Alexbot(id:157199), Snowchild-152(id:265254), Sea of Japan(id:3230), V-ＳＳＫ(id:29127), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>