<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>納銭方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nosenkata (an institution to collect taxes from moneylenders and sake breweries)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nosenkata (an institution to collect taxes from moneylenders and sake breweries)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nosenkata (an institution to collect taxes from moneylenders and sake breweries)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>納銭方（のうせんかた/なっせんかた）とは、室町幕府が土倉役・酒屋役を徴収するために土倉・酒屋の有力者から任命した徴税委託の機関。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nosenkata was an organization commissioned to collect the dosoyaku (taxes imposed on pawnbroker and moneylender by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and sakayayaku (taxes imposed on sake brewery by the Muromachi bakufu), whose members were appointed by the Muromachi bakufu from among influence figures belonged to the doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) or the sakaya (sake breweries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nosenkata was an organization commissioned to collect the dosoyaku (taxes imposed on pawnbrokers and moneylenders by the Muromachi bakufu - Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and sakayayaku (taxes imposed on sake brewery by the Muromachi bakufu), whose members were appointed by the Muromachi bakufu from among influencial figures belonging to the doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) or the sakaya (sake breweries).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nosenkata was an organization commissioned to collect the dosoyaku (taxes imposed on pawnbrokers and moneylenders by the Muromachi bakufu - Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and sakayayaku (taxes imposed on sake brewery by the Muromachi bakufu), whose members were appointed by the Muromachi bakufu from among influential figures belonging to the doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) or the sakaya (sake breweries).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>室町幕府による土倉・酒屋への課税</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taxation on the doso and sakaya by the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taxation on the doso and sakaya by the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taxation on the doso and sakaya by the Muromachi bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>京都では鎌倉時代後期から土倉・酒屋が急速に発展してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, the doso and sakaya had developed rapidly since the latter part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, the doso and sakaya had developed rapidly since the latter part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, the doso and sakaya had developed rapidly since the latter part of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>延暦寺に代表される有力寺院や朝廷の造酒正（押小路家）などは、こうした土倉や酒屋を支配下においてそこから税を徴収していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leading Buddhist temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, as well as the miki no kami (Chief of the Sake Office, the Oshikoji family took charge for generations) in the Imperial Court, had collected taxes from the doso and sakaya by dominating them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leading Buddhist temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, as well as the miki no kami (Chief of the Sake Office, the Oshikoji family took charge for generations) in the Imperial Court, had collected taxes from the doso and sakaya by dominating them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leading Buddhist temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, as well as the miki no kami (Chief of the Sake Office, the Oshikoji family took charge for generations) in the Imperial Court, had collected taxes from the doso and sakaya by dominating them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>京都に成立した室町幕府は本来、御料所などからの収入に財政基盤を置いていたが、南北朝時代 (日本)の中で南朝 (日本)方によって占領されたり、自軍の武将への恩賞に宛てられるなどして次第に縮小していく傾向にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu, established in Kyoto, had originally put its financial base on the income from goryosho (land owned by the Emperor or bakufu) and others, however, the financial base gradually scaled down with the occupation of the goryosho by the South Court (Japan) during the Nanbokucho period (the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and with the appropriation of the goryosho for rewards allocated to their military commanders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi bakufu, established in Kyoto, had originally put its financial base on the income from goryosho (land owned by the Emperor or bakufu) and others, however, the financial base gradually scaled down with the occupation of the goryosho from the Southern Court (Japan) during the Nanbokucho period (the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and with the appropriation of the goryosho for rewards allocated to their military commanders.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu, established in Kyoto, had originally put its financial base on the income from goryosho (land owned by the Emperor or bakufu) and others, however, the financial base gradually scaled down with the occupation of the goryosho from the Southern Court (Japan) during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan) and with the appropriation of the goryosho for rewards allocated to their military commanders.</e>
<cmt>Nanbokucho period削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そこで幕府も土倉・酒屋からの徴税によって不足分を補う方針を採るようになり、軍事力による京都市中の掌握を背景に他の権門の影響力を排除しつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Muromachi bakufu tried to cover the financial shortage by collecting taxes from the doso and sakaya, and started to exclude the clout of other influential families using the military force employed for keeping the peace in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Muromachi bakufu tried to cover the financial shortage by collecting taxes from the doso and sakaya, and started to exclude the clout of other influential families using the military force employed for keeping the peace in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Muromachi bakufu tried to cover the financial shortage by collecting taxes from the doso and sakaya, and started to exclude the clout of other influential families using the military force employed for keeping the peace in Kyoto city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>3代征夷大将軍足利義満が在任していた応安4年（1371年）に後光厳天皇譲位のための諸経費を補うためとして京都の土倉より土倉役を徴収し、明徳4年（1393年）には「洛中辺土散在土倉并酒屋役条々」という5ヶ条からなる法令を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1371, during the third Seii taishogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA&apos;s service, the Muromachi bakufu collected the dosoyaku from the doso in Kyoto to supplement various expenses needed for Emperor Go-Kogon&apos;s abdication, and in 1393, the bakufu issued an ordinance comprised of five rules regarding doso and sakaya in and around Rakuchu (inside the capital Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>５ヶ条の法令について考えこのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1371, during the third Seii taishogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA&apos;s service, the Muromachi bakufu collected the dosoyaku from the doso in Kyoto to supplement various expenses needed for Emperor Go-Kogon&apos;s abdication, and in 1393, the bakufu issued an ordinance comprised of five rules regarding doso and sakaya in and around Rakuchu (inside the capital Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1371, during the third Seii taishogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA&apos;s service, the Muromachi bakufu collected the dosoyaku from the doso in Kyoto to supplement various expenses needed for Emperor Gokogon&apos;s abdication, and in 1393, the bakufu issued an ordinance comprised of five rules regarding doso and sakaya in and around Rakuchu (inside the capital Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>天皇の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これにおいて幕府は造酒正が朝廷財政に納入する分などを例外として、諸権門が土倉・酒屋より税を徴収することを禁じ、その代償として土倉・酒屋が年間6,000貫を幕府に納税することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this ordinance, the bakufu prohibited the influential families from collecting taxes from the doso and sakaya, except such taxes as the miki no tsukasa paid to the Court, instead, the bakufu imposed an annual payment of six-thousand kan on the doso and sakaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this ordinance, the bakufu prohibited the influential families from collecting taxes from the doso and sakaya, except for such taxes as the miki no tsukasa paid to the Court, instead, the bakufu imposed an annual payment of six-thousand kan on the doso and sakaya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this ordinance, the bakufu prohibited the influential families from collecting taxes from the doso and sakaya, except for such taxes as the miki no tsukasa paid to the Court, instead, the bakufu imposed an annual payment of 6,000 kan on the doso and sakaya.</e>
<cmt>six-thousand→6,000</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>納銭方の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the Nosenkata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the Nosenkata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the Nosenkata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>京都の土倉・酒屋を支配下に置いた幕府は当初は直接個々の業者より徴収を行おうとしたものの、徴収効率が悪かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dominating the doso and sakaya, the bakufu initially tried to collect taxes directly from individual traders, but the efficiency was poor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dominating the doso and sakaya, the bakufu initially tried to collect taxes directly from individual traders, but their efficiency was poor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dominating the doso and sakaya, the bakufu initially tried to collect taxes directly from individual traders, but their efficiency was poor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そこで、「衆中」と呼ばれていたそれぞれの業者内の有力者が責任者となって、数十軒単位で幕府に代わって徴税を行い、その収入を幕府に納付する方針に変更した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the bakufu adopted a new policy; the &quot;shuchu&quot; (leading figures among individual traders) takes responsibility in collecting taxes every tens of traders on behalf of the bakufu, and pays income generated by the taxation to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the bakufu adopted a new policy; the &quot;shuchu&quot; (leading figures among individual traders) takes responsibility in collecting taxes from every tens of traders on behalf of the bakufu, and pays income generated by the taxation to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the bakufu adopted a new policy; the &apos;shuchu&apos; (leading figures among individual traders) takes responsibility in collecting taxes from every tens of traders on behalf of the bakufu, and pays income generated by the taxation to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その責任者が納銭方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person responsible was Nosenkata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person responsible was Nosenkata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person responsible was Nosenkata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>納銭方には、土倉の担保用質物の員数に応じて土倉役を徴収する土倉の衆中と酒屋の醸造用酒壷の壷数に応じて酒屋役を徴収する酒屋の衆中が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two groups of shuchu in the Nosenkata, one was a group belonged to the doso, which collected the dosoyaku commensurate with the number of pawns for the mortgage, and the other was a group belonged to the sakaya, which collected the sakayayaku commensurate with the number of jars for brewing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two groups of shuchu in the Nosenkata, one was a group belonged to the doso, which collected the dosoyaku commensurate with the number of pawns for the mortgage, and the other was a group belonging to the sakaya, which collected the sakayayaku commensurate with the number of jars for brewing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two groups of shuchu in the Nosenkata, one was a group belonged to the doso, which collected the dosoyaku commensurate with the number of pawns for the mortgage, and the other was a group belonging to the sakaya, which collected the sakayayaku commensurate with the number of jars for brewing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、記録上において納銭方の中に法体の姿を取って｢○○坊｣と名乗っている者と普通に俗名を名乗っている者が存在するが、これは土倉が本来は延暦寺などの支配下にあったため、その一員である証としてそれらの寺院に属する僧侶の体裁を取った名残であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the existence of the priest-styled Nosenkata using Buddhist title and the Nosenkata using popular name is suggested in a record, the doso had originally been put under the control of temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, therefore the Buddhist title is regarded as remains of their work style as priest belonging to the Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the existence of the priest-styled Nosenkata using the Buddhist title and the Nosenkata using a popular name is suggested in a record, the doso had originally been put under the control of temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, therefore the Buddhist title is regarded as the remains of their work style as priest belonging to the Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the existence of the priest-styled Nosenkata using the Buddhist title and the Nosenkata using a popular name is suggested in a record, the doso had originally been put under the control of temples such as Enryaku-ji Temple, therefore the Buddhist title is regarded as the remains of their work style as priest belonging to the Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、当時の土倉役・酒屋役の幕府財政における重要性を反映して、本来は幕府直轄地を指していた料所（御料所と同義）を納銭方に対して用いる例もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reflecting the importance of the dosoyaku and sakayayaku on the bakufu finance in those days, the word &quot;goryosho&quot; was often used for the Nosenkata, though the &quot;goryosho&quot; originally indicated the territory directly controlled by bakufu.</e>
<cmt>「料所」という言葉が用いられるという意味と判断しましたが,文の意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reflecting the importance of the dosoyaku and sakayayaku on the bakufu finance in those days, the word &quot;goryosho&quot; was often used for the Nosenkata, though the &quot;goryosho&quot; and originally indicated the territory directly controlled by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reflecting the importance of the dosoyaku and sakayayaku on the bakufu finance in those days, the word &quot;goryosho&quot; was often used for the Nosenkata, though the &quot;goryosho&quot; originally indicated the territory directly controlled by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>and 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>こうした納銭方であった土倉の中には公方御倉に任じられる者も存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some doso in the Nosenkata were appointed to the officer of the Kubo-okura (finance branch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some doso in the Nosenkata were appointed to the officer of the Kubo-okura (finance branch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some doso in the Nosenkata were appointed to the officer of the Kubo-okura (finance branch).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>本来、幕府の財貨や文書を管理する倉奉行という役職が存在していたが、運搬の手間や安全を考えて納銭方に徴税だけではなく、幕府財政の出納実務をも特定の納銭方に一任するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, there was a post called kurabugyo in the bakufu, which had managed the property and documents belonged to the bakufu, however in the light of the labor in the shipment and security, some Nosenkata took charge not only of taxation but also of the business relating to revenue and expenditure for the bakufu finance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, there was a post called kurabugyo in the bakufu, which had managed the property and documents belonging to the bakufu, however, in the light of the labor involved in shipment and security, some Nosenkata took charge not only of taxation but also of business relating to revenue and expenditure for the bakufu finance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, there was a post called kurabugyo in the bakufu, which had managed the property and documents belonging to the bakufu, however, in the light of the labor involved in shipment and security, some Nosenkata took charge not only of taxation but also of business relating to revenue and expenditure for the bakufu finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>倉奉行は幕府に直接納付を許された特定の業者からの納税（直進）や幕府の特別会計（内裏造営経費である「造内裏棟別」など）及び小口の出納のみを扱う限定的な職務に縮小されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the kurabugyo was scaled down to deal with only restricted duties such as collecting taxes from specific traders who were approved to pay taxes directly to the bakufu, managing the special accounts including &quot;Zodairitobetsu (building expenses for Imperial Palace)&quot; and dealing with a small amount of revenue and expenditure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the kurabugyo was scaled down to deal with only restricted duties such as collecting taxes from specific traders who were approved to pay taxes directly to the bakufu, managing special accounts including &quot;Zodairitobetsu (building expenses for the Imperial Palace)&quot; and dealing with a small amount of revenue and expenditure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the kurabugyo was scaled down to deal with only restricted duties such as collecting taxes from specific traders who were approved to pay taxes directly to the bakufu, managing special accounts including &apos;Zodairitobetsu&apos; (building expenses for the Imperial Palace) and dealing with a small amount of revenue and expenditure.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>徳政令と財政再建</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) and fiscal reconstruction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokuseirei (ordering the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts) and fiscal reconstruction</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokuseirei (ordering the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts) and fiscal reconstruction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>ところが、6代将軍足利義教以後になると状況が変わってくることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There had been drastic changes since the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA&apos; period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There had been drastic changes since the period of the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There had been drastic changes since the period of the sixth shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>まず、土一揆などによって徳政令が出されると、それによって打撃を受けた土倉を救済するために土倉役を免除しなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whenever the Tokuseirei was issued after peasant uprisings, the bakufu had to exempt the seriously damaged doso from the dosoyaku payment to save them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whenever the Tokuseirei was issued after peasant uprisings, the bakufu had to exempt the seriously damaged doso from the dosoyaku payment to save them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whenever the Tokuseirei was issued after peasant uprisings, the bakufu had to exempt the seriously damaged doso from the dosoyaku payment to save them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その場合、納銭方からの収入が滞り、将軍の日々の生活にも影響が出る恐れも生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the income from the Nosenkata fell into arrears and shogun&apos;s daily life was threatened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the income from the Nosenkata fell into arrears and the shogun&apos;s daily life was threatened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the income from the Nosenkata fell into arrears and the shogun&apos;s daily life was threatened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そこで、「納銭所会所」と呼ばれる一種の座を結成させて同業者間の協力組織を確立させるとともに幕府による保護・監督体制を強化して土倉や酒屋の自由な営業・廃業を規制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the bakufu allowed the Nosenkata to form a za (guild) called &quot;Nosendokoro kaisho (納銭所会所)&quot; (meeting place for the Nosenkata) aiming to establish a cooperative system among the Nosenkata, and restricted the free trade and free closure of the doso and sakaya by strengthening the bakufu-led protection and supervision systems.</e>
<cmt>納銭方会所の読み方がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the bakufu allowed the Nosenkata to form a za (guild) called &quot;Nosendokoro kaisho (納銭所会所)&quot; (meeting place for the Nosenkata) aiming to establish a cooperative system among the Nosenkata, and restricted the free trade and free closure of the doso and sakaya by strengthening the bakufu-led protection and supervising systems.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the bakufu allowed the Nosenkata to form a za (guild) called &apos;Nosendokoro kaisho&apos; (meeting place for the Nosenkata) aiming to establish a cooperative system among the Nosenkata, and restricted the free trade and free closure of the doso and sakaya by strengthening the bakufu-led protection and supervising systems.</e>
<cmt>(納銭所会所)削除→読み方不明&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、分一徳政の導入による徳政令の手続に手数料を導入したり、新たに味噌屋や風呂屋なども対象に含めた馬上役を設定、更に納銭方に対して予め予定税収額を納付させた上での請負制を導入するなどの財政安定策が採られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the bakufu introduced the Bunichi Tokusei (borrowers are exempted from returning money to the doso and sakaya if they paid 10 to 20% of their debts to the bakufu) to impose a fee on the procedure for the issue of the Tokuseirei, and set up the bajoyaku (馬上役) (taxes imposed on the fermented soybean paste manufacturers, public bath managers and others), as well as introduced a contract system giving privilege to the Nosenkata under the condition that they paid the taxes in advance.</e>
<cmt>分一徳政は辞典で調べこのように書きました。馬上役の読み方がわかりません。「分一徳政の導入による徳政令」の意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the bakufu introduced the Bunichi Tokusei (borrowers are exempted from returning money to the doso and sakaya if they paid 10 to 20% of their debts to the bakufu) to impose a fee on the procedure for the issue of the Tokuseirei, and set up the bajoyaku (馬上役) (taxes imposed on the fermented soybean paste manufacturers, public bath managers and others), as well as introduced a contract system giving privileges to the Nosenkata under the condition that they paid the taxes in advance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the bakufu introduced the Bunichi Tokusei (borrowers are exempted from returning money to the doso and sakaya if they paid 10 to 20% of their debts to the bakufu) to impose a fee on the procedure for the issue of the Tokuseirei, and set up the bajoyaku (taxes imposed on the fermented soybean paste manufacturers, public bath managers and others), as well as introduced a contract system giving privileges to the Nosenkata under the condition that they paid the taxes in advance.</e>
<cmt>(馬上役)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これによって応仁の乱直前まで、幕府の権威低下にも関わらず幕府財政は比較的安定していたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, it is believed that the bakufu finance was kept comparatively stable until immediately before the Onin War despite losing its authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, it is believed that the bakufu finance was kept comparatively stable until immediately before the Onin War despite losing its authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, it is believed that the bakufu finance was kept comparatively stable until immediately before the Onin War despite losing its authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>室町幕府の衰退と納銭方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline of the Muromachi bakufu and the Nosenkata</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decline of the Muromachi bakufu and the Nosenkata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decline of the Muromachi bakufu and the Nosenkata</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、応仁の乱後には京都の荒廃や納税拒否の動きによって請負額に徴税額が達せずに赤字となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Onin War, with the devastation of Kyoto city and refusal of tax payment, the tax income did not reach the expected income calculated on the basis of the contract system, and as a result the bakufu finance went into the red.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Onin War, with the devastation of Kyoto city and refusal of tax payment, the tax income did not reach the expected income calculated on the basis of the contract system, and as a result the bakufu finances went into the red.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Onin War, with the devastation of Kyoto city and refusal of tax payment, the tax income did not reach the expected income calculated on the basis of the contract system, and as a result the bakufu finances went into the red.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>さらに納銭方を辞退する者が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, not a few people refused to be a Nosenkata.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, not a few people refused to be a Nosenkata.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, not a few people refused to be a Nosenkata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これに対して幕府は「請酒」と呼ばれる小売専門の酒屋や「日銭屋」と呼ばれる高利・日歩の新興金融業者に対しても課税を行うなどして税収低下を抑制しようとするが、税収回復は困難であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a countermeasure, the bakufu tried to curb the tax revenue decrease by imposing a tax on the&quot;請酒&quot; (sake retailer) and &quot;hizeniya&quot; (new money-lender which lends money at a high interest rate with daily interest), however the tax revenue was not restored.</e>
<cmt>請酒の読み方がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a countermeasure, the bakufu tried to curb the tax revenue decrease by imposing a tax on the&quot;請酒&quot; (sake retailer) and &quot;hizeniya&quot; (new money-lender which lends money at a high interest rate with daily interest), however the tax revenue was not restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a countermeasure, the bakufu tried to curb the tax revenue decrease by imposing a tax on the&apos;請酒&apos; (sake retailer) and &apos;hizeniya&apos; (new money-lender which lends money at a high interest rate with daily interest), however the tax revenue was not restored.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>天文 (日本)8年（1539年）に天文法華の乱の影響による土倉役・酒屋役の減少への対策として管領細川晴元が明徳以来度々納銭方や公方御倉を務めた延暦寺系の土倉｢正実坊｣による納銭方業務の請負一任（事実上の独占化）が決定されると、土倉や酒屋がこれに強く反対して幕府への直納（直進）要求するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Harumoto HOSOKAWA decided in 1539 to leave the monopolistic contract for the Nosenkata business entirely to &quot;Shojitsubo&quot; (a doso of Enryaku-ji Temple extraction), which had repeatedly taken charge of Nosenkata and Kubo-okura, as a measure against the dosoyaku and sakayayaku decrease due to the damage from the Tenbun Hokke War, the doso and sakaya strongly opposed his decision and requested direct tax payment to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>「細川晴元が明徳以来・・・・決定されると」の文の主語述語の関係が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Harumoto HOSOKAWA decided in 1539 to leave the monopolistic contract for the Nosenkata business entirely to &quot;Shojitsubo&quot; (a doso of Enryaku-ji Temple extraction), which had repeatedly taken charge of Nosenkata and Kubo-okura, as a measure against the dosoyaku and sakayayaku decrease due to the damage from the Tenbun Hokke War, the doso and sakaya strongly opposed his decision and requested direct tax payment to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Kanrei (shogunal deputy) Harumoto HOSOKAWA decided in 1539 to leave the monopolistic contract for the Nosenkata business entirely to &apos;Shojitsubo&apos; (a doso of Enryaku-ji Temple extraction), which had repeatedly taken charge of Nosenkata and Kubo-okura, as a measure against the dosoyaku and sakayayaku decrease due to the damage from the Tenbun Hokke War, the doso and sakaya strongly opposed his decision and requested direct tax payment to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>だが、晴元はこれを拒絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto, however, refused their request.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処確認を求めてという意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto however refused their request.</e>
<cmt>gｒammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto however refused their request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>同21年（1552年）には｢正実坊｣と同じく老舗業者であった「玉泉坊」も納銭方の地位確認を求めて訴訟を起こしたが、敗訴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1552, demanding the same privilege as &quot;Shojitsubo&quot;, &quot;Gyokusenbou&quot;, a long-established doso similar to &quot;Shojitsubo&quot;, filed a lawsuit only to lose.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1552, demanding the same privileges as &quot;Shojitsubo,&quot; &quot;Gyokusenbou,&quot; a long-established doso similar to &quot;Shojitsubo,&quot;,filed a lawsuit only to lose.</e>
<cmt>gｒammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1552, demanding the same privileges as &apos;Shojitsubo,&apos; &apos;Gyokusenbo,&apos; a long-established doso similar to &apos;Shojitsubo,&apos; filed a lawsuit only to lose.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>納銭方は天正元年（1573年）の室町幕府解体とともに廃止されるが、当時の正実坊の当主であった正実坊掟運は織田信長によってそのまま徴税担当に起用されており、その仕組みは織田政権によって吸収されていったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Nosenkata was abolished along with the dissolution of the Muromachi bakufu, the system of Nosenkata is thought to be absorbed by the Oda administration, because Shojitsubo Joun (正実坊掟運), the family head of Shojitsubo at that time, was continuously appointed by Nobunaga ODA to the post for collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>正実坊掟運の読み方がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Nosenkata was abolished along with the dissolution of the Muromachi bakufu, the system of Nosenkata is thought to be absorbed by the Oda administration, because Shojitsubo Joun (正実坊掟運), the family head of Shojitsubo at that time, was continuously appointed by Nobunaga ODA to the post for collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Nosenkata was abolished along with the dissolution of the Muromachi bakufu in 1573, the system of Nosenkata is thought to be absorbed by the Oda administration, because Shojitsubo Joun, the family head of Shojitsubo at that time, was continuously appointed by Nobunaga ODA to the post for collecting taxes.</e>
<cmt>in 1573補足 (正実坊掟運)削除→読み方不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fryed-peach(id:63402), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>