<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>悪党</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akuto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akuto</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akuto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>悪党（あくとう）とは、一般的に社会の秩序を乱す者ないし悪事をなす集団などを意味する用語であるが、日本の歴史においては中世に既存支配体系へ対抗した者・階層を悪党と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Akuto&quot; generally refers to a person who disturbs the order of society, or a group of people who commit wrongdoing, but in Japanese history, it refers to a person or class rebelling against the existing system in the middle ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Akuto&quot; generally refers to a person who disturbs the order of society, or a group of people who commit wrongdoing, but in Japanese history, it refers to a person or class rebelling against the existing system in the middle ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Akuto&quot; generally refers to a person who disturbs the order of society, or a group of people who commit wrongdoing, but in Japanese history, it refers to a person or class rebelling against the existing system in the middle ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本項では日本史上の悪党について詳述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this page, akuto in Japanese history is described in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this page, akuto in Japanese history is described in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section describes the details of akuto in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>&quot;On this page, akuto in Japanese history is described in detail.&quot; -&gt; &quot;This section describes the details of akuto in Japanese history.&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>発生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emergence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emergence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emergence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>史料における悪党の語の初出は 『続日本紀』 霊亀2年5月21日条（716年）の勅に見える「鋳銭悪党」であるが、2例目は12世紀後半の「占部安光文書紛失状案」（永万元年（1165年）3月21日付）まで遙かに下る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term akuto first appeared in historical materials as &apos;Jusen akuto&apos; in the oracle in the May 21, 716 section of &quot;Shoku-Nihongi&quot; (the second in a series of chronicles about Japan), but the second appearance is in the &apos;Senbuanko bunsho funshitsu joan&apos; (&apos;占部安光文書紛失状案&apos;) (March 21, 1165) in the late twelfth century, which is much later in history.</e>
<cmt>「占部安光文書紛失状案」→”Senbuanko bunsho funshitsu joan”[正確な読み・意味が確認できませんでした]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term akuto first appeared in historical materials as &apos;Jusen akuto&apos; in the oracle in the May 21, 716 section of &quot;Shoku-Nihongi&quot; (the second in a series of chronicles about Japan), but the second appearance is in the &apos;Senbuanko bunsho funshitsu joan&apos; (&apos;占部安光文書紛失状案&apos;) (March 21, 1165) in the late twelfth century, which is much later in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term akuto first appeared in historical materials as &apos;Jusen akuto&apos; in the imperial decree in the May 21, 716 section of &quot;Shoku-Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), but the second appearance is in the &apos;Senbuanko bunsho funshitsu joan&apos; (&apos;占部安光文書紛失状案&apos;) (March 21, 1165) in the late twelfth century, which is much later in history.</e>
<cmt>続日本紀の訳を変更勅は imperial decree としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、その後は悪党の語が頻繁に検出されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the term akuto is detected frequently from then on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the term akuto is detected frequently from then on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the term akuto is detected frequently from then on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>12世紀は中世の社会経済体制である荘園公領制がようやく確立した時期であるが、12世紀後半に見られた悪党の用例はいずれも荘園・国衙領における支配体制または支配イデオロギーを外部から侵した者を指して用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The twelfth century was a time when the public ownership system of manors, the medieval socioeconomic system, finally established, and the examples of akuto in the late twelfth century all referred to those who infringed upon the system or ideology of dominance in the manors and kokugaryo (government-owned land) from outside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelfth century was a time when the public ownership system of manors, the medieval socioeconomic system, finally established, and the examples of akuto in the late twelfth century all referred to those who infringed upon the system or ideology of dominance in the manors and kokugaryo (government-owned land) from outside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 12th century was a time when shoen koryo sei (The System of Public Lands and Private Estates), the medieval socioeconomic system, finally established, and the examples of akuto in the late 12th century all referred to those who infringed upon the system or ideology of dominance in shoen (manor in medieval Japan) and kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office).</e>
<cmt>荘園公領制、荘園、国衙領の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>例えば、安元元年（1175年）に東大寺領黒田荘（伊賀国名張郡）に乱入した名張郡司源俊方と興福寺僧らが、東大寺の文書において悪党とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the Gunji (district chief) of Nabari District, MINAMOTO no Toshikata, and the monks of Kofuku-ji Temple who broke into Kuroda no sho (Nabari District, Iga Province), a territory of Todai-ji Temple, in 1175 were referred to as akuto in documents of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the Gunji (district chief) of Nabari District, MINAMOTO no Toshikata, and the monks of Kofuku-ji Temple who broke into Kuroda no sho (Nabari District, Iga Province), a territory of Todai-ji Temple, in 1175 were referred to as akuto in documents of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the Gunji (district chief) of Nabari District, MINAMOTO no Toshikata, and the monks of Kofuku-ji Temple who broke into Kuroda no sho (Nabari District, Iga Province), a territory of Todai-ji Temple, in 1175 were referred to as akuto in documents of Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この例が示すように、荘園領主や荘官が維持していた支配体系に対し、荘園・公領の外部から侵入ないし妨害しようとした者が悪党として観念されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As seen in this example, those who attempted to invade or disturb the system maintained by manor lords and shokan (manor manager) from outside the manors and Imperial demesne, were considered akuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As seen in this example, those who attempted to invade or disturb the system maintained by manor lords and shokan (manor manager) from outside the manors and Imperial demesne, were considered akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As seen in this example, those who attempted to invade or disturb the system maintained by manor lords and shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)) from outside the manors and Imperial demesne, were considered akuto.</e>
<cmt>荘官の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ってからもこうした状況に大きな変化はなく、13世紀後半の文永年間（1264年-1275年）まで、本所（荘園領主）側から見て外部からの侵入者・侵略者を悪党と呼ぶ傾向が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation did not change largely in the Kamakura period, and until the Bunei years (1264 - 1275) in the late 13th century, the tendency to call external invaders and intruders from the point of view of the honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor) (manor lord) continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation did not change largely in the Kamakura period, and until the Bunei years (1264 - 1275) in the late 13th century, the tendency to call external invaders and intruders from the point of view of the honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor) (manor lord) continued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation did not change largely in the Kamakura period, and until the Bunei years (1264 - 1275) in the late 13th century, the tendency to call external invaders and intruders from the point of view of the honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor) (manor lord) continued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>悪党紛争の実態は、本所一円地同士または本所一円地と地頭層との所領紛争であり、一方の本所から見た悪党とは、その紛争相手たる本所一円地の領主だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The akuto conflict was in reality a territorial conflict among honjo-ichienchi (land collectively controlled by honjo) or between honjo-ichienchi and the jito (land steward) class, and the akuto from one honjo&apos;s viewpoint was the feudal lord of the honjo-ichienchi of the opponent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The akuto conflict was in reality a territorial conflict among honjo-ichienchi (land collectively controlled by honjo) or between honjo-ichienchi and the jito (land steward) class, and the akuto from one honjo&apos;s viewpoint was the feudal lord of the honjo-ichienchi of the opponent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The akuto conflict was in reality a territorial conflict among honjo-ichienchi (land collectively controlled by honjo) or between honjo-ichienchi and the jito (manager and lord of manor) class, and the akuto from one honjo&apos;s viewpoint was the feudal lord of the honjo-ichienchi of the opponent.</e>
<cmt>地頭の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>12世紀から本所は悪党活動に悩まされてきたが、悪党は他領へ逃亡するなど、本所による追捕から巧みに逃れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjo suffered from akuto activities since the 12th century, but akuto circumvented pursuit by honjo by escaping to other territories, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjo suffered from akuto activities since the 12th century, but akuto circumvented pursuit by honjo by escaping to other territories, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjo suffered from akuto activities since the 12th century, but akuto circumvented pursuit by honjo by escaping to other territories, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>本所はしばしば幕府へ悪党追捕を要請していたが、本所同士の紛争は本来、朝廷の管轄であるとして、幕府は悪党追捕に消極的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjo frequently requested the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to pursuit the akuto, but the bakufu was passive about it, pointing out that conflicts among honjo are originally under the jurisdiction of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjo frequently requested the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to pursuit the akuto, but the bakufu was passive about it, pointing out that conflicts among honjo are originally under the jurisdiction of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjo frequently requested the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) to pursuit the akuto, but the bakufu was passive about it, pointing out that conflicts among honjo were originally under the jurisdiction of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>are→were</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>13世紀前半に幕府が制定した御成敗式目第32条は、盗賊・悪党の所領内隠匿を罪科と定めているが、幕府には積極的に悪党を鎮圧する姿勢は特に見られなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Section thirty-two of the Goseibai shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), established in the early thirteenth century, specified that concealment of thieves and akuto in the territory was a crime, but bakufu was not active in suppressing the akuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Section thirty-two of the Goseibai shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), established in the early thirteenth century, specified that concealment of thieves and akuto in the territory was a crime, but bakufu was not active in suppressing the akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 32 of the Goseibai shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai), established by the bakufu in the early 13th century, specified that concealment of thieves and akuto in the territory was a crime, but bakufu was not active in suppressing the akuto.</e>
<cmt>「幕府が」制定した→by the bakufu を追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、正嘉年間（1257年-1258年）に入り、飢饉の深刻化による悪党活動の激化を受けて、幕府は悪党を夜討・強盗・山賊・海賊と同等視することに決め（正嘉2年、鎌倉幕府追加法320条）、その鎮圧にようやく乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Shoka years (1257 - 1258), when akuto activity increased due to worsening starvation, the bakufu decided to equate akuto with night burglars, robbers, bandits, and pirates (1258, Article 320 of the Kamakura bakufu tsuikaho (additional law)), and finally embarked on suppressing them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Shoka years (1257 - 1258), when akuto activity increased due to worsening starvation, the bakufu decided to equate akuto with night burglars, robbers, bandits, and pirates (1258, Article 320 of the Kamakura bakufu tsuikaho - additional law), and finally embarked on suppressing them.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Shoka years (1257 - 1258), when akuto activity increased due to worsening famine, the bakufu decided to equate akuto with night burglars, robbers, bandits, and pirates (1258, Article 320 of the Kamakura bakufu tsuikaho - additional law), and finally embarked on suppressing them.</e>
<cmt>starvation→famine</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>変化の背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of the change</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of the change</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background of the change</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>その一方で、13世紀半ば頃から中世社会の大規模な変動が始まっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, a major shift in medieval society began around the middle of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, a major shift in medieval society began around the middle of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, a major shift in medieval society began around the middle of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>12世紀末以来、武士階層を基盤とする鎌倉幕府は、数度の戦乱を通じて所領を基盤たる武士階層に再配分し、武士団の持つ自己増殖欲求に応えてきたが、宝治元年（1247年）の宝治合戦により得宗専制が完成して政治的安定が実現すると、所領再配分の機会となる戦乱の発生自体が見られなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the end of the twelfth century, Kamakura bakufu, which was based on samurai class, reallocated its territory to the base samurai class through several wars to meet the self-propagation desires of samurai forces, but when Tokuso sensei (autocracy by the shikken (regent for shogun) Hojo clan) completed with the Hoji Battle in 1247 and political stability was established, wars, which were opportunities for territory reallocation, stopped occurring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the end of the twelfth century, the Kamakura bakufu, based on the samurai class, reallocated its territory to the samurai through several wars to meet the self-propagating desires of the samurai forces, but when Tokuso sensei (autocracy by the shikken - regent for shogun - Hojo clan) ended the Hoji Battle in 1247 and political stability was established, wars, that presented opportunities for territory reallocation, stopped occurring.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness, redundancy, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the end of the 12th century, the Kamakura bakufu, based on the samurai class, had reallocated its territory to the samurai through several wars to meet the self-propagating desires of the samurai forces, but when the Hoji Battle of 1247 resulted in complete Tokuso sensei (autocracy by the shikken [regent for the shogun], who were members of the Hojo clan) and political stability was established, wars, that presented opportunities for territory reallocation, stopped occurring.</e>
<cmt>「宝治合戦により得宗専制が完成して」の部分を書き換えました。I have no idea what &quot;autocracy by the shikken - regent for shogun - Hojo clan&quot; is supposed to mean so I have had to guess a little.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ここに至り、惣領・庶子への分割相続により自己増殖を繰り返してきた武士団は分割すべき所領を得る機会を失い、惣領のみに所領を継承させる単独相続へと移行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, samurai forces which repeatedly self-propagated through divided succession to soryo (heir) and shoshi (child with no inheritance rights), lost opportunity to obtain territory for dividing, and shifted to single succession, where territory was inherited by the soryo only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, samurai forces that repeatedly self-propagated through succession and property division to soryo (heir) and shoshi (children without inheritance rights), lost the opportunity to obtain territory and shifted to single succession, where territory was inherited by the soryo only.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, samurai forces that repeatedly self-propagated through succession and property division to soryo (heir) and shoshi (child born out of wedlock), lost the opportunity to obtain territory and shifted to single succession, where territory was inherited by the soryo only.</e>
<cmt>庶子の説明変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>単独相続を契機として、惣領は諸方に点在する所領の集約化と在地での所領経営を進めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the single succession as a momentum, soryo consolidated their territories scattered in various quarters and engaged in the management of their residing territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the single succession as a momentum, soryo consolidated their territories scattered in various quarters and engaged in the management of their residing territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the single succession as a momentum, soryo consolidated their territories scattered in various quarters and engaged in the management of their residing territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この過程で、庶子を中心とする武士階層の没落が発生するとともに、本所（荘園領主）と在地武士との所領紛争が先鋭化していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process, the fall of the samurai class centered around shoshi occurred, while territorial conflict between honjo (manor lords) and the residing samurai became radical.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process, the fall of the samurai class centering around shoshi occurred, while territorial conflict between honjo (manor lords) and the residing samurai became radical.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the process, the fall of the samurai class centering around shoshi occurred, while territorial conflict between honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) and the residing samurai became radical.</e>
<cmt>本所(荘園領主）を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>荘園支配の内部に目を向けると、武士による侵略を防ぐために本所は荘園支配の強化に乗り出していたが、在地で荘園支配の実務にあたる荘官は自らの経営権を確立しようとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Focusing internally on manor governance, while honjo strengthened their control on the manor to prevent invasion by samurai, shokan who were in charge of the practical business of manor governance, were working to establish their own management authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Focusing internally on manor governance, while honjo strengthened their control on the manor to prevent invasions by samurai, shokan who were in charge of the practical business of manor governance, were working to establish their own management authority.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Focusing internally on manor governance, while honjo strengthened their control on the manor to prevent invasions by samurai, shokan who were in charge of the practical business of manor governance, were working to establish their own management authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ここに本所・荘官間の対立を惹起する条件が出揃っていたが、当時、急速に進展していた貨幣経済・流通経済の社会への浸透が両者の対立を激化させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conditions for the conflict between honjo and shokan to occur were all there, but their conflict intensified due to the spread of monetary economy and distribution economy in the society, which was progressing rapidly at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conditions for the conflict between honjo and shokan to occur were all there, but their conflict intensified due to the spread of a monetary and distribution economy, which was progressing rapidly at that time.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conditions for the conflict between honjo and shokan to occur were all there, but their conflict intensified due to the spread of a monetary and distribution economy, which was progressing rapidly at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>以上に見られる武士階層内部もしくは荘園支配内部における諸矛盾は中世社会の流動化へとつながっていき、13世紀後半からの悪党活動の活発化をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The various contradictions within the samurai class or manor governance led to the mobility of medieval society, and resulted in the increase in akuto activities in the late thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The various contradictions within the samurai class or manor governance led to the mobility of medieval society, and resulted in the increase in akuto activities during the late thirteenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The various contradictions within the samurai class or manor governance led to the mobility of medieval society, and resulted in the increase in akuto activities from the late thirteenth century onward.</e>
<cmt>during→from</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに同時期の元寇もこれらの諸矛盾をさらに増大させ、悪党活動の活発化を促したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, genko (Mongolian invasions of Japan), which occurred around this time also intensified the various contradictions, and induced the increase of akuto activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, genko (Mongolian invasions of Japan), which occurred around this time also intensified the various contradictions, and induced the increase of akuto activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, genko (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan), which occurred around this time also intensified the various contradictions, and induced the increase of akuto activities.</e>
<cmt>元寇の説明変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>展開</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>外部から荘園支配に侵入する悪党のほか、蝦夷や海賊的活動を行う海民なども悪党と呼ばれたが、これは支配体系外部の人々を悪党とみなす観念に基づいている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to akuto who invaded manor governance from the outside, ezo (northerners) and kaimin (people who lived and worked on the seas) who committed piracy were also called akuto, based on the concept of seeing outsiders of the system as akuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to akuto who invaded manor governance from the outside, ezo (northerners) and kaimin (people who lived and worked on the seas) who committed piracy were also called akuto, based on the concept of seeing outsiders of the system as akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to akuto who invaded manor governance from the outside, ezo (northerners) and kaimin (people who lived and worked on the seas) who committed piracy were also called akuto, which based on the concept of seeing outsiders of the system as akuto.</e>
<cmt>based の前に which を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>諸国を旅する芸能民や遊行僧などが悪党的性格を持つとされていたのも同様の理由からだと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this same reason, it is believed that entertainers and wandering monks who traveled in various provinces were considered to have akuto-like characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this same reason, it is believed that entertainers and wandering monks who traveled in various provinces were considered to have akuto-like characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this same reason, it is believed that entertainers and wandering monks who traveled in various provinces were considered to have akuto-like characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>蝦夷、海民、芸能民、遊行僧らはいずれも荘園公領制的な支配体系の外部に生きる漂泊的な人々であり、支配外部にいることを示す奇抜な服装、すなわち異形の者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ezo, kaimin, entertainers, and wandering monks were all people who drifted about, living outside of the system of private manor and public land system, and many had atypical appearance, with eccentric clothing indicating they are outside the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ezo, kaimin, entertainers, and wandering monks were all people who drifted about, living outside the system of private manors and public land system, and many had atypical appearance, with eccentric clothing indicating they were outside the system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ezo, kaimin, entertainers, and wandering monks were all people who drifted about, living outside the system of private manors and public land system, and many had atypical appearance, with eccentric clothing indicating they were outside the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>網野善彦は、これらの「悪党」が13世紀半ばから急速な成長を見せた流通経済・資本経済の担い手であり、中世社会の新たな段階を切り開いた主体の一つと説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiko AMINO described these &apos;akuto&apos; as bearers of distribution economy and capital economy, which developed rapidly from the mid-thirteenth century, and as one of the main constituents opening the way for a new phase in the medieval society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiko AMINO described these &apos;akuto&apos; as bearers of the distribution and capital economy, which developed rapidly from the mid-13th century, and as one of the main constituents opening the way for a new phase in medieval society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiko AMINO described these &apos;akuto&apos; as bearers of the distribution and capital economy, which developed rapidly from the mid-13th century, and as one of the main constituents opening the way for a new phase in medieval society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>支配体系外部からの侵略者のみを悪党と呼ぶ状況に変化が生じたのは弘安年間（1278年-1288年）のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Change in the situation where only outside intruders of the system were called akuto occurred during the Koan years (1278 - 1288).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Change in the situation where only outside intruders of the system were called akuto occurred during the Koan years (1278 - 1288).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Change in the situation where only outside intruders of the system were called akuto occurred during the Koan years (1278 - 1288).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この時期には荘園支配内部の対立関係がついに顕在化し、本所に対する荘官（在地領主）層の抵抗活動が抑えられなくなり、本所と対立した荘官・在地領主層は本所から悪党と呼ばれ始め、本所との所領紛争を展開していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, conflicting relationship within the manor governance finally became apparent, the resistance activities by the shokan (resident feudal lords) against the honjo could not be suppressed, shokan and the resident feudal lord class in conflict with the honjo began being called akuto by the honjo, and engaged in territorial conflicts with the honjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, conflicting relationships within the manor governance finally became apparent, resistance activities by the shokan (resident feudal lords) against the honjo could not be suppressed, shokan and the resident feudal lord class began being called akuto by the honjo, and engaged in territorial conflicts with the honjo.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, conflicting relationships within the manor governance finally became apparent, resistance activities by the shokan against the honjo could not be suppressed, shokan and the resident feudal lord class began being called akuto by the honjo, and engaged in territorial conflicts with the honjo.</e>
<cmt>荘官は既出ですので、荘官（在地領主）の括弧書きは削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>武士階層に目を向けても、単独相続などにより所領を失った無足御家人が旧領に残留し、新地頭の支配を妨害して悪党と呼ばれる事例が発生していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking at the samurai class, musoku (without land) gokenin (shogun&apos;s vassal) who lost their territory due to single succession, etc. remained in their old territory, and were called akuto when they disturbed the governance of the new jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking at the samurai class, musoku (without land) gokenin (shogun&apos;s vassal) who lost their territory due to single succession, etc. remained in their old territory, and were called akuto when they disturbed the governance of the new jito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking at the samurai class, musoku (without land) gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) who lost their territory due to single succession, etc. remained in their old territory, and were called akuto when they disturbed the governance of the new jito.</e>
<cmt>御家人の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これらの状況は、内部の者も「悪党」として扱うことを示しており、観念の非常に大きな変化の現れであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These affairs indicated that insiders were also treated as &apos;akuto,&apos; and was a sign of a major change in the concept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These affairs indicated that insiders were also treated as &apos;akuto,&apos; and this was a sign of a major change in the concept.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These affairs indicated that insiders were also treated as &apos;akuto,&apos; and this was a sign of a major change in the concept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>この段階において、本所と対立した荘官層には、上に挙げた漂泊的な悪党も含まれていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this stage, the shokan class in conflict with honjo is believed to have included the drifting akuto described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this stage, the shokan class in conflict with honjo is believed to have included the drifting akuto described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this stage, the shokan class in conflict with honjo is believed to have included the drifting akuto described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>彼らの中には、各地を往来しながら交易にたずさわり、流通経済の担い手として資本を蓄積し有徳人と呼ばれる者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them were involved in trade while traveling in various places, accumulated capital as a bearer of distribution economy, and were called utokujin (the rich).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them were involved in trade while traveling in various places, accumulated capital as a bearer of distribution economy, and were called utokujin (the rich).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them were involved in trade while traveling in various places, accumulated capital as a bearer of distribution economy, and were called utokujin (the rich).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そうした有徳人が経済力を背景として荘官に補任され、所領経営に乗り出す例もあったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, such utokujin were assigned as shokan due to their economic power, and became engaged in territory management.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, such utokujin were assigned as shokan due to their economic power, and became engaged in territory management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, such utokujin were assigned as shokan due to their economic power, and became engaged in territory management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、在地の荘官と対立した本所は、荘官に頼らず、独自に年貢物資を運搬する流通経路を確保する必要に迫られていたが、ここで年貢物資流通を担ったのが漂泊的な悪党なのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, honjo who were in conflict with the residing shokan had to secure their own distribution route to transport the annual tributes, and the ones who carried out this role of annual tribute distribution were the drifting akuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, honjo who were in conflict with the residing shokan had to secure their own distribution route to transport the annual tributes, and the ones who carried out this role of annual tribute distribution were the drifting akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, honjo who were in conflict with the residing shokan had to secure their own distribution route to transport the annual tributes, and the ones who carried out this role of annual tribute distribution were the drifting akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>13世紀後半以降、悪党は畿内・東北・九州などで活発に活動し、御成敗式目で禁止されている悪党と地頭の結合など見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the late thirteenth century, akuto were active in the Kinai, Tohoku, and Kyushu areas, and there were cases of akuto and jito unions prohibited in the Goseibai shikimoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the late thirteenth century, akuto were active in the Kinai, Tohoku, and Kyushu areas, and there were cases of akuto and jito unions prohibited in the Goseibai shikimoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the late 13th century, akuto were active in the Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), Tohoku, and Kyushu areas, and there were cases of akuto and jito unions prohibited in the Goseibai-shikimoku.</e>
<cmt>畿内の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>悪党の活動は支配体系の流動化を招き、幕府はこれに対応するため、13世紀末から悪党鎮圧へ積極的に取り組み始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The activities of akuto led to mobilization of the system, and to respond to this, the bakufu began actively suppressing the akuto from the end of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The activities of akuto led to mobilization of the system, and to respond to this, the bakufu began actively suppressing the akuto from the end of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The activities of akuto led to mobilization of the system, and to respond to this, the bakufu began actively suppressing the akuto from the end of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>元々、本所一円地における警察権・司法権は本所の所管であり、朝廷が裁定することとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, honjo held jurisdiction over law enforcement and judicial power at the honjo-ichienchi, and the Imperial Court would rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, honjo held jurisdiction over law enforcement and judicial power at the honjo-ichienchi, and the Imperial Court would rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, honjo held jurisdiction over law enforcement and judicial power at the honjo-ichienchi, and the Imperial Court would rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、悪党の著しい横行により本所は幕府へ鎮圧を強く要望していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the extreme infestation of akuto, honjo strongly requested their suppression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the extreme infestation of akuto, honjo strongly requested their suppression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the extreme infestation of akuto, honjo strongly requested the bakufu to suppress them.</e>
<cmt>「幕府へ」を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>そこで、1290年代前半になって確立されたのが次の鎮圧手続きである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, in the early 1290s, the following suppression procedure was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, in the early 1290s, the following suppression procedure was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, in the early 1290s, the following suppression procedure was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>まず本所が朝廷へ訴えを起こし、朝廷の召喚に被告人（悪党）が応じない場合は、違勅があったとして朝廷から幕府へ検断を命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, the honjo files a complaint to the Imperial Court, and if the accused (akuto) does not answer the summons, it is considered a disobedience against the Emperor, and the Imperial Court orders the bakufu for prosecution and conviction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, the honjo files a complaint to the Imperial Court, and if the accused (akuto) does not answer the summons, it is considered a disobedience against the Emperor, and the Imperial Court orders the bakufu to commence prosecution and conviction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, the honjo files a complaint to the Imperial Court, and if the accused (akuto) does not answer the summons, it is considered a disobedience against the Emperor, and the Imperial Court orders the bakufu to commence prosecution and conviction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このとき幕府が受ける命令を違勅綸旨または違勅院宣という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The order received by the bakufu is called ichoku rinji or ichoku inzen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The order received by the bakufu is called ichoku rinji or ichoku inzen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The order received by the bakufu is called ichoku rinji or ichoku inzen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>綸旨・院宣を受けた幕府は御家人2人を使節に任じた（両使）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon receiving the rinji (emperor&apos;s order) or inzen (Cloistered Emperor&apos;s declaration), the bakufu appointed two gokenin as envoys (ryoshi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon receiving the rinji (emperor&apos;s order) or inzen (Cloistered Emperor&apos;s declaration), the bakufu appointed two gokenin as envoys (ryoshi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon receiving the rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) or inzen (Cloistered Emperor&apos;s declaration), the bakufu appointed two gokenin as envoys (ryoshi).</e>
<cmt>綸旨の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>両使には、任務遂行のため、守護不入とされている本所一円地への入部が許されており、さらに本所側へ下地遵行を指示する権限が与えられていることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoshi were allowed to enter the honjo-ichienchi, which were off-limits to shugo (guardians), in order to execute their duties, and in some cases, were authorized to order shitaji jungyo (implementation of decisions regarding land) to the honjo side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshi were allowed to enter the honjo-ichienchi, which were off-limits to shugo (guardians), in order to execute their duties, and in some cases, were authorized to order shitaji jungyo (implementation of decisions regarding land) to the honjo side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshi were allowed to enter the honjo-ichienchi, which were off-limits to shugo (provincial constable), in order to execute their duties, and in some cases, were authorized to order shitaji jungyo (implementation of decisions regarding land) to the honjo side.</e>
<cmt>守護の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>悪党追捕のために始まったこの手続きは、室町時代の使節遵行権の根源となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This procedure which began as a way to pursuit akuto, became the root for shisetsu jungyo (process for implementing bakufu&apos;s decision on conflicts regarding property ownership) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This procedure which began as a way to pursue akuto, became the root for shisetsu jungyo (process for implementing bakufu&apos;s decision on conflicts regarding property ownership) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This procedure which began as a way to pursue akuto, became the root for the right of shisetsu jungyo (process for implementing bakufu&apos;s decision on conflicts regarding property ownership) during the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>「使節遵行権」のため the right of を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="45">
<j>この時期の著名な悪党が、12世紀から14世紀にかけて東大寺領黒田荘（伊賀国）で活躍した「黒田悪党」大江氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A prominent akuto from this period is the Oe clan, &apos;Kuroda akuto,&apos; who was successful in the Kuroda no sho (Iga Province), a territory of Todai-ji Temple, from the twelfth to fourteenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A prominent akuto from this period was the Oe clan, &apos;Kuroda akuto,&apos; who was successful in the Kuroda no sho (Iga Province), a territory of Todai-ji Temple, from the 12th to 14th century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A prominent akuto from this period was the Oe clan, &apos;Kuroda akuto,&apos; who was successful in the Kuroda no sho (Iga Province), a territory of Todai-ji Temple, from the 12th to 14th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>12世紀から代々と同荘下司職を勤める大江氏は、13世紀後半に黒田荘への支配権を強化しようと画策し、東大寺と対立してついに悪党と呼ばれるようになり、最終的には東大寺の要請を受けた六波羅探題に鎮圧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oe clan, who served as geshi (shokan in charge of practical business in the field) in this manor for generations since the twelfth century, planned to strengthen their rule over Kuroda no sho in the late thirteenth century until they were eventually called akuto after conflicting with Todai-ji Temple, and was ultimately suppressed by Rokuhara tandai which received a request from Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oe clan, who served as geshi (shokan in charge of practical business in the field) in this manor for generations since the twelfth century, planned to strengthen their rule over Kuroda no sho during the late thirteenth century until they were eventually called akuto after conflicting with Todai-ji Temple, and was ultimately suppressed by Rokuhara tandai which received a request from Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oe clan, who served as geshi (shokan in charge of practical business in the field) in this manor for generations since the 12th century, planned to strengthen their rule over Kuroda no sho during the late 13th century until they were eventually called akuto after conflicting with Todai-ji Temple, and was ultimately suppressed by Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) which received a request from Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>六波羅探題の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし、代わって同荘荘官職についた大江氏一族もまた、年貢納入を行わないなど東大寺との対立を深め、供御人と称して朝廷と直接結ぼうとし、これを鎮圧するはずの伊賀国守護、同御家人らと結んで、黒田荘を実質的に支配するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Oe clan family, who in turn was appointed as the shokan of the manor also became in conflict with Todai-ji Temple by not paying the annual tributes, called themselves kugonin (people serving the Imperial Palace and offering food and crafts to the Emperor) to try to directly connect with the Imperial Palace, and managed to practically rule Kuroda no sho by uniting with the shugo and gokenin of Iga Province who were supposed to suppress them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Oe clan family, who in turn was appointed as the shokan of the manor also came into conflict with the Todai-ji Temple by not paying the annual tributes, called themselves kugonin (people serving the Imperial Palace and offering food and crafts to the Emperor) to try to directly connect with the Imperial Palace, and managed to practically rule Kuroda no sho by uniting with the shugo and gokenin of Iga Province who were supposed to suppress them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Oe clan family, who in turn was appointed as the shokan of the manor also came into conflict with the Todai-ji Temple by not paying the annual tributes, called themselves kugonin (people serving the Imperial Palace and offering food and crafts to the Emperor) to try to directly connect with the Imperial Palace, and managed to practically rule Kuroda no sho by uniting with the shugo and gokenin of Iga Province who were supposed to suppress them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>結局大江氏は六波羅探題に再び鎮圧されたが、ともかくも、この事例は経済的な成長を果たそうとしている在地領主が荘園領主の抑圧を受けたときに悪党となることを示した典型例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, the Oe clan was suppressed by Rokuhara tandai once again, but in any case, this is a classic example of resident feudal lords, who were trying to grow financially, becoming akuto when faced with oppression by the manor lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the Oe clan was suppressed by Rokuhara tandai once again, but in any case, this is a classic example of resident feudal lords, who were trying to grow financially, becoming akuto when faced with oppression by the manor lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the Oe clan was suppressed by Rokuhara tandai once again, but in any case, this is a classic example of resident feudal lords, who were trying to grow financially, becoming akuto when faced with oppression by the manor lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>このほか、鎌倉幕府倒幕時に後醍醐天皇方についた楠木正成（河内国）、赤松氏（播磨国）、名和長年（伯耆国）、瀬戸内海の海賊衆らは、悪党と呼ばれた人々だったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is believed that Masashige KUSUNOKI (Kawachi Province), Akamatsu clan (Harima Province), Nagatoshi NAWA (Hoki Province), and the pirates of Seto Inland Sea, who took sides with Emperor Godaigo when the Kamakura bakufu collapsed, were so-called akuto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is believed that Masashige KUSUNOKI (Kawachi Province), Akamatsu clan (Harima Province), Nagatoshi NAWA (Hoki Province), and the pirates of Seto Inland Sea, who took sides with Emperor Godaigo when the Kamakura bakufu collapsed, were so-called akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is believed that Masashige KUSUNOKI (Kawachi Province), Akamatsu clan (Harima Province), Nagatoshi NAWA (Hoki Province), and the pirates of Seto Inland Sea, who took sides with Emperor Godaigo when the Kamakura bakufu collapsed, were so-called akuto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>悪党は南北朝時代 (日本)にも活動しているが、内乱が終わった14世紀後半、悪党活動によって荘園公領の支配体系が弱体化し、守護や国人らによる本所一円地（荘園）への侵略が進むとともに、本所側の対抗力が衰えてしまうと、本所の支配を侵す悪党という実態は、次第に見られなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akuto were also active in the period of South and North Courts (Japan), but when the civil war ended in the late fourteenth century, the manor and public land system was weakened due to akuto activities, and when the countervailing power of honjo weakened as invasion of honjo-ichienchi (manor) by shugo and kokujin (resident feudal lords and local samurai) increased, the picture of akuto invading honjo&apos;s rule gradually disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akuto were also active in the period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), but when the civil war ended in the late fourteenth century, the manor and public land system was weakened due to akuto activities, and when the countervailing power of honjo weakened as invasion of honjo-ichienchi (manor) by shugo and kokujin (resident feudal lords and local samurai) increased, the picture of akuto invading honjo&apos;s rule gradually disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akuto were also active in the period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), but when the civil war ended in the late fourteenth century, the manor and public land system was weakened due to akuto activities, and when the countervailing power of honjo weakened as invasion of honjo-ichienchi (manor) by shugo and kokujin (local samurai) increased, the picture of akuto invading honjo&apos;s rule gradually disappeared.</e>
<cmt>国人の定訳本所一円地（荘園）は、 (shoen) ではなく (manor) のままとしました。。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>研究史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>悪党概念は、1930年代に中村直勝によって提起され（『荘園の研究』 1939）、戦後になると石母田正（『中世的社会の形成』 1946）らによってその姿が明らかにされていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concept of akuto was presented by Naokatsu NAKAMURA in the 1930s (&quot;Shoen no Kenkyu&quot; (Studies of Shoen) 1939), and its aspects were revealed by Takashi ISHIMODA (&quot;Chuseiteki Shakai no Keisei&quot; (Formation of Medieval Society) 1946) and others after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concept of akuto was presented by Naokatsu NAKAMURA in the 1930s (&quot;Shoen no Kenkyu&quot; (Studies of Shoen) 1939), and its aspects were revealed by Takashi ISHIMODA (&quot;Chuseiteki Shakai no Keisei&quot; (Formation of Medieval Society) 1946) and others after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concept of akuto was presented by Naokatsu NAKAMURA in the 1930s (&quot;Shoen no Kenkyu&quot; (Studies of Shoen) 1939), and its aspects were revealed by Tadashi ISHIMODA (&quot;Chuseiteki Shakai no Keisei&quot; (Formation of Medieval Society) 1946) and others after the war.</e>
<cmt>Takashi→Tadashi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>戦後の歴史学において、悪党は封建領主のなかで位置づけられていたが、網野善彦、佐藤進一らが社会的基盤を農業以外に置く手工業民や芸能民などに着目した中世史像を提示すると、悪党の存在もそれらと関連付けて論じられるようになり、20世紀末からは海津一朗らによって元寇や徳政令等の社会変動における悪党の位置づけが試みられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In historical science after the war, akuto was positioned among feudal lords, but when Yoshihiko AMINO, Shinichi SATO, etc. introduced a picture of medieval history focused on craftsmen and entertainers whose social foundations were not agricultural, akuto was discussed in connection with them, and from the end of the twentieth century, Ichiro KAIZU and others are attempting to position akuto in the context of social change such as genko and Tokuseirei (an act by the Muromachi Bakufu ordering the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In historical science after the war, akuto was positioned among feudal lords, but when Yoshihiko AMINO, Shinichi SATO, etc. introduced a picture of medieval history focused on craftsmen and entertainers whose social foundations were not agricultural, akuto was discussed in connection with them, and from the end of the twentieth century, Ichiro KAIZU and others were attempting to position akuto in the context of social change such as genko and Tokuseirei (an act by the Muromachi Bakufu ordering the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In historical science after the war, akuto was positioned among feudal lords, but when Yoshihiko AMINO, Shinichi SATO, etc. introduced a picture of medieval history focused on craftsmen and entertainers whose social foundations were not agricultural, akuto was discussed in connection with them, and from the end of the 20th century, Ichiro KAIZU and others were attempting to position akuto in the context of social change such as genko and Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>徳政令の訳を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), らりた(id:1327), Tanuki Z(id:612), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 怪蘇(id:45514), Shimoxx(id:9332), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Tyanken(id:129245), まぬ(id:15285), SUMAKO(id:206516), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Chuta(id:10457), 堀五郎右衛門(id:84263), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>