<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>奏者番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sojaban (a governmental post in the bakufu)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies)</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>奏者番（そうじゃばん/そうしゃばん）は江戸幕府および藩の役職の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sojaban(or (修正候補なし)) was a governmental post in the bakufu or domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sojaban(or Soshaban) was a governmental post in the Edo bakufu or domains.</e>
<cmt>Soshaban追加、江戸追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sojaban (or Soshaban) was a governmental post in the Edo bakufu or domains.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>城中における武家の礼式を管理する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officers in this post managed etiquette of samurai in castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officers in this post managed etiquette of samurai in castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officers in this post managed etiquette of samurai in castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>具体的には大名・旗本が征夷大将軍に拝謁する際、あるいは在国の大名が献上品を使者に持たせて江戸城に派遣した場合に、その氏名と献上品の内容を確認して将軍に報告し、将軍が下賜を行う際にその伝達にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More specifically, when a daimyo or hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) was going to have an audience with seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who was to subdue the barbarians&quot;) or when a person bringing a present from a daimyo was sent to the Edo castle, these officers checked the person&apos;s name and the content of the present to report them to the shogun, and, when the shogun was going to give a grant, notified the person of the message.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, when daimyo or hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) were going to have an audience with seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who was to subdue the barbarians&quot;) or when a messenger taking a present from a daimyo was sent to the Edo castle, Sojaban checked the person&apos;s name and the content of the present to report them to the shogun, and, when the shogun gave a grant, notified the person of the message.</e>
<cmt>more削除、主語の明確化、was going to削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, when daimyo or hatamoto (a direct retainer of the bakufu) were going to have an audience with seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who was to subdue the barbarians&quot;) or when a messenger taking a present from a daimyo was sent to the Edo castle, Sojaban checked the person&apos;s name and the content of the present to report them to the shogun, and, when the shogun gave a grant, notified the person of the message.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>更に大名の転封などの重大な決定や大名家の不幸に際して上使として派遣されたり、徳川将軍家及び御三家の法要において、将軍が参列できない場合の代参を行うこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when a daimyo&apos;s territory was changed or someone of a daimyo family died, one of the officers was sent as the envoy of the shogun, and an officer in this post also participated sometimes in Buddhist memorial services at the Tokugawa shogun family or at gosanke (three privileged Tokugawa branch families) in place of the shogun when the shogun had to be absent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, when a daimyo&apos;s territory was changed or someone of a daimyo family died, one of the officers was sent as an envoy of the shogun, and an officer in this post sometimes participated in Buddhist memorial services of the Tokugawa shogun family or gosanke (three privileged Tokugawa branch families) in place of the shogun when the shogun had to be absent.</e>
<cmt>also削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, when a daimyo&apos;s territory was changed or someone of a daimyo family died, one of the officers was sent as an envoy of the shogun, and an officer in this post sometimes participated in Buddhist memorial services of the Tokugawa shogun family or gosanke (three privileged Tokugawa branch families) in place of the shogun when the shogun had to be absent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、将軍の御前で元服を行う大名・世子に礼儀作法を教える役目も担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officer was also in charge of teaching the etiquette concerned with the genpuku ceremony (the ceremony of celebrating the coming of age) for the heirs of daimyo who would hold the ceremony in front of shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officer was also in charge of teaching the etiquette concerned with the genpuku ceremony (the ceremony of celebrating the coming of age) for the heirs of daimyo who would attend the ceremony in front of shogun.</e>
<cmt>動詞変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officer was also in charge of teaching the etiquette concerned with the genpuku ceremony (the ceremony of celebrating the coming of age) for the heirs of daimyo who would attend the ceremony in front of shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>幕府では、定員の定めは特にないが20-30名とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the officers in this post was 20 to 30 customarily, though no specification existed in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Sojaban was 20 to 30 customarily, though no specification existed in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>主語の明確化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Sojaban was 20 to 30 customarily, though no specification existed in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>通説では慶長8年（1603年）の本郷信富の任命を最初とするが、それ以前に求める異説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a commonly accepted theory, Nobutomi HONGO was the first person appointed to the post (in 1603), but there is another theory insisting that he was not the first person to the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a commonly accepted theory, Nobutomi HONGO was the first person appointed to the post in 1603, but there is another theory insisting that he was not the first.</e>
<cmt>繰り返し部分削除、括弧削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a commonly accepted theory, Nobutomi HONGO was the first person appointed to the post in 1603, but there is another theory insisting that he was not the first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後に譜代大名が就任する役職となり、多くの場合初任の役職となるため大名にとっては出世の登竜門的な役職となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Sojaban became a post to be assumed by a Fudai daimyo (a daimyo who had belonged to the Tokugawa group from before the Sekigawara war), and, being mostly the first post to be assumed by a daimyo, became a post like a gateway to success.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Sojaban became a post for Fudai daimyo (a daimyo who had belonged to the Tokugawa group from the Battle of Sekigahara) as a gateway to success, being mostly the first post for them.</e>
<cmt>冠詞削除、譜代大名の説明が用語統一とは異なりますが、そのまま使用しました（ただし、fromを削除し、関ヶ原の戦いを訂正しました。）文の簡略化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Sojaban became a post for Fudai daimyo (a daimyo who had belonged to the Tokugawa group from the Battle of Sekigahara) as a gateway to success, being mostly the first post for them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、大名・旗本と将軍との連絡役となるため、大目付・目付と並ぶ枢要な役職でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As persons in the post worked as a liaison officer between a daimyo or hatamoto and the shogun, this post was an important one together with Ometsuke (an inspector: for details, refer to Ometsuke) and metuke (an inspector under Ometuke: for details, refer to Metsuke).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a liaison officer between a daimyo or a hatamoto and the shogun, this post was an important together with Ometsuke (an inspector) and metuke (an inspector under Ometsuke).</e>
<cmt>「for details, refer to Ometsuke（Ometsuke)」が原文にないため削除しました。スペルミス訂正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a liaison officer between a daimyo or a hatamoto and the shogun, this post was an important together with Ometsuke (an inspector) and metuke (an inspector under Ometsuke).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>奏者番の内4名は寺社奉行を兼任する（万治元年（1658年）以後）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four of the Sojaban officers also assumed the jisha-bugyo post (the post in charge of affairs concerned with shrines and temples) additionally (in 1658 and later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four of the Sojaban officers also assumed the jisha-bugyo post (the post in charge of affairs concerned with shrines and temples) concurrently (in 1658 and later).</e>
<cmt>additionallyを変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four of the Sojaban officers also assumed the jisha-bugyo post (the post in charge of affairs concerned with shrines and temples) concurrently (in 1658 and later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>詰衆からの登用が多く、江戸城内の詰席は芙蓉の間であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officers in this post were appointed mostly from Tsume-shu (the persons watching and serving the shogun family), who waited in the fuyo (cotton rose) room in the Edo castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officers in this post were appointed mostly from Tsume-shu (the persons watching and serving the shogun family), whose waiting room in the Edo castle was the fuyo (cotton rose) room.</e>
<cmt>詰席の表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officers in this post were appointed mostly from Tsume-shu (the persons watching and serving the shogun family), whose waiting room in the Edo castle was the fuyo (cotton rose) room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>文久2年（1862年）閏8月、江戸幕府の文久の改革により、廃止されたが翌年10月に復活している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This post was once abolished in uruu August (the second August) of 1862 (in the old calendar) due to Bunkyu Reform, but was restored again in October of the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This post was once abolished in August of 1862 due to Bunkyu Reform, but was restored again in October of the next year.</e>
<cmt>旧年の説明削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This post was once abolished in September of 1862 due to Bunkyu Reform, but was restored again in October of the next year.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変換</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Hyuuga(id:14767), ドルチェット(id:46458), Azusayumi7(id:21082), Loveless(id:129239), Nerimaman(id:61206), Point136(id:211299), Alexbot(id:157199), NDR(id:5500), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>