<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>阿闍梨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ajari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ajari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ajari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>阿闍梨（あじゃり、あざり、サンスクリット： アーチャーリャ、阿闍梨耶とも音写）は、サンスクリットで「軌範」を意味し、弟子たちの規範となり、法を教授する師匠のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ajari (also Azari, sanskrit: acarya, also transliterated as Ajariya) means a &quot;model/example&quot; in Sanskrit, and is a master who is an example to his disciples and teaches the dharma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ajari (also Azari, sanskrit: acarya, also transliterated as Ajariya) means a &quot;model/example&quot; in Sanskrit, and is a master who is an example to his disciples and teaches the dharma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ajari (also Azari, Sanskrit: acarya, also transliterated as Ajariya) means a &quot;model/example&quot; in Sanskrit, and is a master who is an example to his disciples and teaches the dharma.</e>
<cmt>sanskrit→Sanskrit</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>ヴェーダの宗教ではヴェーダにおける規範を伝授する指導者を、また部派仏教においては修行僧たちの規律を指導し、教義を伝授する高僧をいい、教団によって種類は異なるが、指導内容ごとに複数の阿闍梨がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In vedic religion it referred to a leader who instructs in the example of the vedas, while in the offshoot Buddhism it referred to a high-ranking monk who leads monks in training and instructs in the doctrine; so there were varying types depending on the group, but there were several Ajari all having to do with leadership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In vedic religion it referred to a leader who instructs in the example of the vedas, while in the offshoot Buddhism it referred to a high-ranking monk who leads monks in training and instructs in the doctrine; so there were varying types depending on the group, but there were several Ajari all having to do with leadership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the vedic religion, this term referred to a leader who instructed his followers using examples from the vedas, while in Nikaya Buddhism, it referred to a high-ranking monk who led monks in training and instructed them in doctrine; so while the exact meaning varied according to the particular religion, the term Ajari was used in several instances in the sense of leadership.</e>
<cmt>部派仏教 is a bit tricky to handle but a search for 部派仏教 and Buddhism on Google suggests that &quot;Nikaya Buddhism&quot; might work. Please check with someone knowledgeable in this field whether this is correct. Some of my revisions are a little 意訳.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>密教においては、大日如来等の諸仏を指すことがあるが、一般には衆僧の模範となるべき高位の僧侶の称号で、日本では天台宗および真言宗において高貴な身分の僧や、天皇の関わる儀式において修法を行う僧に特に与えられる職位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In esoteric Buddhism, it sometimes refers to Vairocana and the other Buddhas, but in general it is a title for priests in a high position who should be an example for the other monks; in Japan in the Tendai and Shingo sects, it is a position given to noble monks, especially to those who conduct rites in ceremonies involving the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In esoteric Buddhism, it sometimes refers to Vairocana and the other Buddhas, but in general it is a title for priests in a high position who should be an example for the other monks; in Japan in the Tendai and Shingo sects, it is a position given to noble monks, especially to those who conduct rites in ceremonies involving the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In esoteric Buddhism, it sometimes refers to Vairocana and the other Buddhas, but in general it is a title for priests in a high position who should be an example for the other monks; in Japan in the Tendai and Shingon sects, it is a position given to noble monks, especially to those who conduct rites in ceremonies involving the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Shingo→Shingon</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本で阿闍梨と称される僧には、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the monks called Ajari in Japan are:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the monks called Ajari in Japan are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the monks called Ajari in Japan are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>教授阿闍梨 法を教授する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoju Ajari – Teaches the Dharma;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoju Ajari – Teaches the Dharma;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoju Ajari – Teaches the Dharma;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>伝法阿闍梨（でんぽうあじゃり） 伝法（術・経文など維持発展に必要な総ての要素）の灌頂を受けた者がなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demp Ajari - Those who have received a kanjo of the denpo (all of the necessary elements for preservation and development of the techniques and sutras).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Demp Ajari - Those who have received a kanjo of the denpo (all of the necessary elements for preservation and development of the techniques and sutras).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Demp Ajari - Those who have received a kanjo (a ceremony to be the successor) of the denpo (all of the necessary elements for preservation and development of the techniques and sutras).</e>
<cmt>灌頂の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>七高山阿闍梨（しちこうざんあじゃり） 延暦寺・伊吹山・愛宕神社 (京都市)など特に朝廷から指定を受けて五穀豊穣を祈る儀式を行う寺院において祈願の勅命を与えられて導師を務める者がなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shichikozan Ajari – Especially at Enryaku-ji Temple, Mt. Ibuki, and Atago Jinja Shrine, one who has received a designation from the imperial court and has been given an imperial command to pray in a temple that conducts ceremonies to pray for abundant harvest, and works as an officiating monk;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichikozan Ajari – Especially at Enryaku-ji Temple, Mt. Ibuki, and Atago Jinja Shrine, one who has received a designation from the imperial court and has been given an imperial command to pray in a temple that conducts ceremonies to pray for abundant harvest, and works as an officiating monk;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichikozan Ajari – Especially at Enryaku-ji Temple, Mt. Ibuki, and Atago-jinja Shrine (Kyoto City), one who has received a designation from the imperial court and has been given an imperial command to pray in a temple that conducts ceremonies to pray for abundant harvest, and works as an officiating monk;</e>
<cmt>Atago Jinja Shrine→Atago-jinja Shrine京都市を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>一身阿闍梨（いっしんあじゃり） 皇族や摂関家の子弟から仏門に入り、貴種のゆえをもって若いうちに阿闍梨の称号を許された者がなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isshin Ajari – Members of the imperial family or a Regent family who enter the priesthood while young and are allowed the title of Ajari at a young age by virtue of their noble birth become this;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isshin Ajari – Members of the imperial family or a Regent family who enter the priesthood while young and are allowed the title of Ajari at a young age by virtue of their noble birth become this;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isshin Ajari – Members of the imperial family or Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents) who entered the priesthood while young and were allowed the title of Ajari at a young age by virtue of their noble birth became this;</e>
<cmt>摂関家の訳摂関家の子弟と言うことなので過去形にしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">et cetera.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">et cetera.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">et cetera.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、伝法阿闍梨のうち特に徳の高いものを大阿闍梨（だいあじゃり）といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a Denpo Ajari of especially great virtue was called a Great Ajari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, a Denpo Ajari of especially great virtue was called a Great Ajari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, a Denpo Ajari of especially great virtue was called a Great Ajari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>阿闍梨から派生した言葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Words Derived From Ajari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Words Derived From Ajari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Words Derived From Ajari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>京都名産の菓子「阿闍梨餅」は、比叡山の延暦寺千日回峰行の阿闍梨がかぶる網代笠を模したことからこの名がついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto&apos;s famous candy, Ajari-mochi, are so named because they resemble the wicker hats worn by the Ajari doing the 1000-day circumambulation at Enryaku-ji temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto&apos;s famous candy, Ajari-mochi, are so named because they resemble the wicker hats worn by the Ajari doing the 1000-day circumambulation at Enryaku-ji temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto&apos;s famous sweets, Ajari-mochi, are so named because they resemble the wicker hats worn by the Ajari doing the 1000-day circumambulation at Enryaku-ji temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>candy→sweets</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Avanzare(id:34657), Izayohi(id:13095), 新茶(id:157775), Tomzo(id:16777), Nnh(id:474), 午後紅茶(id:14285), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Kstigarbha(id:13376), R28Bot(id:177951), Authority(id:10737), Safkan(id:423), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>