<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大目付</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ometsuke (a governmental post in the Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ometsuke (inspector general)</e>
<cmt>用語統一に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ometsuke (inspector general)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大目付（おおめつけ）は、江戸幕府の役職のひとつで、職制上は老中に属し、大名・高家および朝廷を監視してこれらの謀反から幕府を守る監察官の役割を持った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ometsuke was a governmental post in the Edo period, and belonging to Roju (the second highest post in the Edo bakufu government) in the government system, played the role of an inspector who watched daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), koke (privileged families under Tokugawa Shogunate), and the Imperial court to protect the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) from rebellion of these powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ometsuke was a governmental post in the Edo period belonging to Roju (the second highest post in the Edo bakufu government) in the government system, and played a role of an inspector who watched daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), koke (privileged families under Tokugawa Shogunate), and the Imperial court to protect the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) from rebellion of these powers.</e>
<cmt>andを削除＆挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ometsuke was a governmental post in the Edo period belonging to Roju (the second highest post in the Edo bakufu government) in the government system, and played a role of an inspector who watched daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), koke (privileged families under Tokugawa Shogunate), and the Imperial court to protect the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) from rebellion of these powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>諸藩にもこれらの役職が置かれることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This post was also introduced some domains as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This post was also introduced some domains as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This post was also introduced some domains as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代初期には、柳生宗矩のような大名からも選ばれていたが、後に石高3千石〜5千石級の旗本から選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, an Ometsuke officer was selected from daimyo, as Munenori YAGYU was, but later, from Hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which was a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) earning a rice crop of 3000 to 5000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, Ometsuke officers were selected from daimyo, such as Munenori YAGYU, but later, from Hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which was a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) earning 3000 to 5000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku) rice yields.</e>
<cmt>語順変更、複数化、石高の表現変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, Ometsuke officers were selected from daimyo, such as Munenori YAGYU, but later, from Hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu, which was a form of Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) earning 3000 to 5000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku) rice yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大目付は、旗本の職の中でも江戸城留守居・御三卿家老に準ずる最高位とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ometuse was one of the highest post available for Hatamoto, being equivalent to Edojo-rusui (the post of housekeeping the Edo castle while the shogun was absent from the castle) and the Karo (the chief retainer) post at the gosankyo families (three privileged branch families of Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ometuse was one of the highest post among Hatamoto, being equivalent to Edojo-rusui (the post of housekeeping the Edo castle while the shogun was absent from the castle) and Karo (the chief retainer) of the gosankyo families (three privileged branch families of Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt>available forを変更、post削除、前置詞変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ometuse was one of the highest post among Hatamoto, being equivalent to Edojo-rusui (the post of housekeeping the Edo castle while the shogun was absent from the castle) and Karo (the chief retainer) of the gosankyo families (three privileged branch families of Tokugawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そして、旗本でありながら万石級（大名）を監視した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although being Hatamoto, the officer in this post watched daimyo earning a rice crop of at least 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Ometsuke was a Hatamoto, he watched daimyo, who earned a rice yield of at least 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>主語の挿入、混乱を避けるためwhoを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Ometsuke was a Hatamoto, he watched daimyo, who earned a rice yield of at least 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため、その在任中は万石級の格式を与えられ、○○守という称号が叙任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the social status being equivalent to that for a 10,000-class daimyo was given to the officer while being in the post, with the title of XX no kami conferred on as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, his social status in office was equivalent to that for a 10,000-koku class daimyo with the title of XX no kami conferred on him as well.</e>
<cmt>文の簡略化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, his social status in office was equivalent to that for a 10,000-koku class daimyo with the title of XX no kami conferred on him as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代中期になると、従来の監察官としての色彩よりも伝令（幕府の命令を全国の大名に伝える役）や殿中（江戸城）での儀礼官としての色彩が濃くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the middle era of the Edo period, the jobs of this post became more like Denrei (the post for informing daimyo of instructions from the bakufu) or Gireikan (the post in charge of etiquette) in Denchu (the Edo castle, rather than the original post for inspection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the middle of the Edo period, the jobs of this post became more like Denrei (the post for informing daimyo of instructions from the bakufu) or Gireikan (the post in charge of etiquette) in Denchu (the Edo castle), rather than the original post for inspection.</e>
<cmt>era削除、括弧挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the middle of the Edo period, the jobs of this post became more like Denrei (the post for informing daimyo of instructions from the bakufu) or Gireikan (the post in charge of etiquette) in Denchu (the Edo castle), rather than the original post for inspection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、兼帯といって道中奉行・宗門改役・鉄砲改役など5つの役を兼任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officers in this post also served five additional posts (called Kentai), including Dochu-bugyo (the post in charge of road-related matters), shumon aratame-yaku (the post in charge of the persecution of Christians), and teppo-aratame (the post for monitoring and checking guns owned by ordinary people).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officers in this post also took five additional posts (called Kentai), including Dochu-bugyo (the post in charge of road-related matters), shumon aratame-yaku (the post in charge of the persecution of Christians), and teppo-aratame (the post for monitoring and checking guns owned by ordinary people).</e>
<cmt>動詞の変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officers in this post also took five additional posts (called Kentai), including Dochu-bugyo (the post in charge of road-related matters), shumon aratame-yaku (the post in charge of the persecution of Christians), and teppo-aratame (the post for monitoring and checking guns owned by ordinary people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>定員は5名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of officers in this post was five.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of officers in this post was five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of officers in this post was five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>道中奉行を兼帯する大目付は、5人の中では筆頭格である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ometsuke officer in charge of Dochu-bugyo was placed at the head of the five officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ometsuke officer in charge of Dochu-bugyo was placed in the head of the five officers.</e>
<cmt>前置詞変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ometsuke officer in charge of Dochu-bugyo was placed in the head of the five officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、京都所司代・大坂城代等と同様に征夷大将軍を代理する立場にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officers were in the position of functioning as a deputy of seii-taishogun (literally, great general who was to subdue the barbarians), as Kyoto shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy) and Osaka jodai (the person sent for controlling the Osaka castle) were.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officers functioned as a deputy of seii-taishogun (literally, great general who was to subdue the barbarians), as Kyoto shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy) and Osaka jodai (the person sent for controlling the Osaka castle) did.</e>
<cmt>文の簡略化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officers functioned as a deputy of seii-taishogun (literally, great general who was to subdue the barbarians), as Kyoto shoshidai (the Kyoto deputy) and Osaka jodai (the person sent for controlling the Osaka castle) did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>若年寄に属する目付の上位に位置し、その権威だけはますます強くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ometsuke post was placed above the Metsuke post that belonged to the Wakadoshiyori post (a managerial post in Edo bakufu), and the authority itself became increasingly more stronger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ometsuke post was placed above the Metsuke post that belonged to the Wakadoshiyori post (a managerial post in Edo bakufu), and the Ometsuke&apos;s power became increasingly stronger.</e>
<cmt>moreの削除、主語の明確化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ometsuke post was placed above the Metsuke post that belonged to the Wakadoshiyori post (a managerial post in Edo bakufu), and the Ometsuke&apos;s power became increasingly stronger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>諸藩にあっては、おおむね中老・番頭・組頭より格下の藩士から選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a domain, the officers in the post were mostly selected from the retainers of the domain who were placed under Churo (the post immediately under Karo), Ban-gashira (a post in the domain government) and Kumi-gashira (also a post in the domain government)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a domain, the Ometsuke officers were mostly selected from the retainers of the domain who were placed under Churo (the post immediately under Karo), Ban-gashira (a post in the domain government) and Kumi-gashira (also a post in the domain government).</e>
<cmt>主語の明確化、コンマの挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a domain, the Ometsuke officers were mostly selected from the retainers of the domain who were placed under Churo (the post immediately under Karo), Ban-gashira (a post in the domain government) and Kumi-gashira (also a post in the domain government).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>薩摩藩では、はじめ横目頭と呼ばれ、藩では家老、若年寄に次ぐ役職であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Satsuma domain, the post was called Yokome-gashira, and was placed next to Karo and to Wakatoshiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Satsuma domain, the post was called Yokome-gashira, and was placed after Karo and to Wakatoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>next toをafterに変更、冠詞削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Satsuma domain, the post was called Yokome-gashira, and was placed after Karo and to Wakatoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一所持や一所持格といった上級武士から出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officers were appointed from samurai in such high classes as Issho-mochi (literally, a one-place holder) or Issho-mochi-kaku (the Issho-mochi level).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officers were appointed from samurai in such high classes as Issho-mochi (literally, a one-place holder) or Issho-mochi-kaku (the Issho-mochi level).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officers were appointed from samurai in such high classes as Issho-mochi (literally, a one-place holder) or Issho-mochi-kaku (the Issho-mochi level).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 DRKAWA(id:248054), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Azusayumi7(id:21082), 与左衛門(id:159462), Auf(id:633), Tetsusaburou(id:58913), 松茸(id:27535), くっちゃめ(id:86793), ジャニスカ(id:210715), Htk5346(id:70062), Big-KANA(id:195421), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>