<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>田守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamori (field administrator)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamori (field administrator)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamori (field administrator)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>田守（たもり）は、室町幕府が公領内の田畑の管理役として設置した職である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamori was a position in charge of managing fields in the public lands, which was set up by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamori was a position in charge of managing fields on public lands, which was set up by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamori was a position in charge of managing fields on public lands, which was set up by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に農民の中から技術に秀でた者が抜擢された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For most of the positions of tamori, peasants who had expertise in techniques were selected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For most of the tamori positions, peasants who had expertise in techniques were selected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For most of the tamori positions, peasants who had expertise in techniques were selected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>室町時代以前から守護や地頭に仕えて農業指導を行う者は存在したが、専業としての技術指導職は室町期になって初めて設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there existed some people who served shugo (provincial constable) or jito (manager and lord of manor) to be in charge of instructing in farming before the Muromachi period, a professional instructor in techniques was set up for the first time in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some people existed who served shugo (provincial constable) or jito (manager and lord of a manor) to be in charge of instruction in farming before the Muromachi period, a professional instructor of techniques was set up for the first time in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although provincial constables or manor lords gave instruction in farming before the Muromachi period, a position of professional instructor of farming techniques was set up for the first time in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代の農業技術の飛躍的な向上は田守たちの活躍によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo period saw a significant improvement of farming techniques thanks to the tamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo period saw a significant improvement of farming techniques thanks to the tamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo period saw a significant improvement of farming techniques thanks to the tamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>田守の起源は、鎌倉時代後期に北陸地方で行われていた、タンボモリという役務であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of tamori is supposedly tanbomori, a service provided in the Hokuriku region in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of tamori is supposedly tanbomori, a service provided in the Hokuriku region in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of tamori is supposedly tanbomori, a service provided in the Hokuriku region in the late Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このタンボモリは、主にイモチ病の発生を調べるため、水田およびその近辺の状況を毎日観察する役であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tanbomori was in charge of daily observation of paddy fields and their vicinity to mainly study rice blast fungus.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tanbomori was in charge of daily observations of paddy fields and their vicinity, to mainly study rice blast fungus.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tanbomori was in charge of daily observations of paddy fields and their vicinity, to mainly study rice blast fungus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>村内の各戸が毎年持ち回りで担当していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the families in the village took turns to be in charge of tanbomori each year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each yea the families in the village took their turn to be in charge of tanbomori.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each year the families in the village took their turn to be in charge of tanbomori.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後この役は持ち回りから特定の家が代々担当するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, only specific families came to be in charge of tanbomori for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, only specific families came to be in charge of tanbomori for some generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later this position called tanbomori was handed down among certain families for many generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>北陸地方に現存する田守姓は、タンボモリを専門職としていた家系の名残であると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the family name, tamori, that remains in the Hokuriku region is a remnant of families of professional tanbomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family name, tamori, that remains in the Hokuriku region is a remnant of families of professional tanbomori.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family name, tamori, that remains in the Hokuriku region is a remnant of families of professional tanbomori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>室町期に入ると、職業の分化・専門化が進み、タンボモリは田守という職業となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, occupations were specialized further, and the tanbomori became a profession called the tamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi period, occupations were further specialized, and the tanbomori became a profession called the tamori.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, occupations were further specialized, and the tanbomori became a profession called the tamori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それまで代々特定の家系が口伝で引き継いできた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that, the specific families succeeded the tanbomori by word of mouth for generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that, specific families succeeded the tanbomori by word of mouth for some generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that, specific families succeeded the tanbomori by word of mouth for some generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして応仁の乱で荒廃した農村を再興するべく、幕府が専門職として全国に田守職を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Onin War, the bakufu set up the profession of tamori across the country so as to restore the farming villages destroyed in the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Onin War, the bakufu set up the profession of tamori across the country to restore the farming villages destroyed in the war.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Onin War, the bakufu set up the profession of tamori across the country to restore the farming villages destroyed in the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>当初は公領内のみに田守が配置されたが、その後公領周辺の農村への技術指導も行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tamori was deployed only in the public lands at first, but later came to instruct the farming villages around the public lands in techniques.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tamori were deployed only on public lands at first, but later came to instruct the farming villages around the public lands, in techniques.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first the tamori only gave instruction within the area of public lands, but later came to instruct the neighboring farming villages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>室町時代後期には在地支配層である国人が独自に田守の任命を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Muromachi period, kokujin (local samurai), rulers of local lands, assigned the tamori in his own right.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Muromachi period, kokujin (local samurai), rulers of local lands, assigned the tamori in his own right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Muromachi period,local samurai assigned the tamori independently.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)の後期には、農村の多くで労働力が戦に駆り出されたため、農業生産力の低下が大きな問題となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Sengoku period (Japan), many peasants in farming villages were sent off to the war, which resulted in a critical problem of the decrease of agricultural production.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Sengoku period (Japan), many peasants in farming villages were sent off to war, and this resulted in a critical decrease in agricultural production.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan), many peasants in farming villages were sent off to war, and this resulted in a critical decrease in agricultural production.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代に英語の説明を補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このため、各地の戦国大名は優秀な田守を領国に呼び込んで厚遇する反面、領内の田守が他の土地へ移動することを厳しく制限した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period across the country treated good tamori well to attract them to their territories, while strictly inhibiting them from moving out to other territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period across the country treated good tamori well to attract them to their territories, while strictly inhibiting them from moving out to other territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku period across the country treated good tamori well to attract them to their territories,and tried to prevent them from moving away to other territories.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このことは田守が廃業する原因となり、一部の有力田守を除いて田守職に就くものは激減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to the discontinuance of tamori and the dramatic decrease in tamori except for some influential tamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to the discontinuance and a dramatic decrease of tamori except for some influential tamori.</e>
<cmt>redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to the extinction of tamori as an occupation except for a few influential tamori.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸時代に入り社会が安定化するとともに、田守が各地で復活するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With social stability in the Edo period, tamori came to be involved again across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With social stability in the Edo period, tamori came to be involved again across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As society gradually became more stable in the Edo period, the tamori profession was revived around the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>特に米所といわれた北陸地方では、冷害から稲を守るため各藩は大量の田守を雇い、稲作の安定化に力を入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the Hokuriku region, a rice-producing region, clans employed a number of tamori to protect paddy from being damaged by cold weather and focused on stabilization of rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the Hokuriku region, a rice-producing region, clans employed a number of tamori to protect their paddies from being damaged by cold weather and focused on stabilization of rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the Hokuriku region, a rice-producing region, clans employed a number of tamori to protect their paddies from being damaged by cold weather and focus on stabilization of rice cultivation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この時期には『農家益』や『農業全書』などの農業技術書が多く出版されたが、田守たちが伝承してきた技術が学問として体系化された時期でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period, many books of agricultural techniques, such as &quot;Noka eki (For the farmers&apos; benefit)&quot; and &quot;Nogyo zensho (Compendia of agricultural knowledge),&quot; were published and the techniques that had been handed down by the tamori were systematized as academics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this period, many books on agricultural techniques, such as &quot;Noka eki (For the farmers&apos; benefit)&quot; and &quot;Nogyo zensho (Compendia of agricultural knowledge),&quot; were published and the techniques that had been handed down by the tamori were systematized as academics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period, many books on agricultural techniques, such as &apos;Noka eki (farming handbook)&apos; and &apos;Nogyo zensho (Compendia of agricultural knowledge),&apos; were published and the techniques that had been handed down by the tamori were recorded systematically.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、田守職の一部は、植物に対する豊富な知識を生かして本草学へと流れていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, some of the tamori used the wealth of knowledge about plants and came to be involved in honso-gaku (materia medica).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, some of the tamori used their wealth of knowledge about plants and came to be involved in honso-gaku (materia medica).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, some of the tamori used their wealth of knowledge about plants and worked as herbalists.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、明治期に入ってからは政府の進めた工業化政策のため、多くの田守が廃業した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in the Meiji period, due to the industrialization policy proceeded by the government, many of the tamori gave up their businesses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in the Meiji period, due to the industrialization policy proceeded by the government, many tamori gave up their businesses.</e>
<cmt>wordiness</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in the Meiji period, due to the industrialization policy of the government, many tamori gave up their businesses.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), Nnh(id:474), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>