<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>管領</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanrei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanrei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanrei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>管領（かんれい）とは室町幕府の職名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanrei is the name of a post in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanrei is the name of a post in the Muromachi Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanrei is the name of a post in the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>室町幕府の表現を変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>もともとは役職や領地を管理・支配することの意味を持つ言葉で、鎌倉幕府の執権も管領とよばれることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally a word meaning to manage/rule an official post or fief, the regent to the Kamakura Shogunate was sometimes called Kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally a word meaning to manage/rule an official post or fief, the regent to the Kamakura Shogunate was sometimes called Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally a word meaning to manage/rule an official post or fief, the regent to the Kamakura bakufu was sometimes called Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>室町幕府の表現を変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>室町時代を通じて管領に任じられた斯波氏・畠山氏・細川氏の三管領家と、侍所頭人に任じられた四家である四職は、合わせて「三管四職」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Throughout the Muromachi period, the three families who were appointed Kanrei, the Shiba, Hatakeyama and Hosokawa clans, along with the four families that were appointed to Samuraidokoro Tonin, were collectively referred to as &quot;Sankan Yonshoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Throughout the Muromachi period, the three families who were appointed Kanrei, the Shiba, Hatakeyama, and Hosokawa clans, along with the four families that were appointed to Samuraidokoro Tonin, were collectively referred to as &quot;Sankan Yonshoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Throughout the Muromachi period, the three families who were appointed to Kanrei, the Shiba, Hatakeyama, and Hosokawa clans, along with the four families that were appointed to Samurai-dokoro tonin (Governor of the Board of Retainers), were collectively referred to as &quot;Sankan shishiki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>三管四職→Sankan shishiki侍所頭人の説明補足最初の appointed に to を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Outline&quot;→&quot;Summary &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元来は足利氏の家宰で秘書官的役割を担い、主従的な支配機構を司る執事がもとになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally filling a secretarial role in the management of the Ashikaga clan, it started as a steward who administered the mechanisms of feudal rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally filling a secretarial role in the management of the Ashikaga clan, it started as a steward who administered the mechanisms of feudal rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally filling a secretarial role in the management of the Ashikaga clan, it started as a steward who administered the mechanisms of feudal rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>足利尊氏が北朝を擁立して開いた武家政権（足利幕府、室町幕府）は、尊氏の弟の足利直義が政務を担当する二元的な統治機構を持ち、高師直・仁木頼章・細川清氏が幕府の執事職を務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The samurai administration that Takauji ASHIKAGA established in supported of the Norther Court (Ashikaga Shogunate, Muromachi Shogunate) had dual governing authorities that Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, was in charge of, KO no Moronao, Yoriaki NIKI and Kiyouji HOSOKAWA worked as stewards of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The samurai administration that Takauji ASHIKAGA established in support of the Norther Court (Ashikaga Shogunate, Muromachi Shogunate) had dual governing authorities that Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, was in charge of, KO no Moronao, Yoriaki NIKI and Kiyouji HOSOKAWA worked as stewards of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military government that Takauji ASHIKAGA established in support of the Northern Court (Ashikaga Shogunate, Muromachi bakufu) had dual governing authorities that Takauji&apos;s younger brother, Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, was in charge of, and KO no Moronao, Yoriaki NIKI and Kiyouji HOSOKAWA worked as stewards of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Norther→Northern室町幕府→Muromachi bakufu武家政権→military governmentwas in charge of, の後に接続詞補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>2代将軍足利義詮の頃には幕府内部の抗争で細川清氏が失脚するなど不安定で、義詮は一時的な将軍親政を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the second Shogun, because of instabilities such as Kiyouji HOSOKAWA falling from grace due to internal disputes in the Shogunate, Yoshiakira briefly conducted direct Shogunal rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the second Shogun, because of instabilities such as Kiyouji HOSOKAWA falling from grace due to internal disputes in the Shogunate, Yoshiakira briefly conducted direct Shogunal rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, the second Shogun, because of instabilities such as Kiyouji HOSOKAWA falling from grace due to internal disputes in the Shogunate, Yoshiakira briefly conducted direct Shogunal rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>義詮時代には領域的な支配機構を司る引付衆の役割を縮小して執事職の権限を強化し、一元化な統治機構の確立を目指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the era of Yoshiakira the role of the many who administered regional governing authorities was reduced and the power of the stewards was strengthened, with the aim of establishing a centralized governing authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of Yoshiakira the role of the many who administered regional governing authorities was reduced and the power of the stewards was strengthened, with the aim of establishing a centralized governing authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of Yoshiakira the role of Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court) who administered regional governing authorities was reduced and the power of the stewards was strengthened, with the aim of establishing a centralized governing authority.</e>
<cmt>era→period引付衆→Hikitsukeshu (Coadjustor of the High Court)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>1362年には13歳の斯波義将が任じられ、父の斯波高経が後見した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1362, the 13 year old Yoshimasa SHIBA was appointed, and his father Takatsune SHIBA was his guardian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1362, the 13 year old Yoshimasa SHIBA was appointed, and his father Takatsune SHIBA was his guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1362, the 13 year old Yoshimasa SHIBA was appointed, and his father Takatsune SHIBA was his guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1366年には反斯波派の佐々木道誉らによる貞治の政変で斯波氏が失脚し、道誉らの支持を得た細川頼之が執事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1366, in the Joji Incident spurred by the anti-Shiba Doyo SASAKI, the Shiba clan fell, and Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who had the support of Doyo and the others, became steward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1366, in the Joji Incident spurred by the anti-Shiba Doyo SASAKI, the Shiba clan fell, and Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who had the support of Doyo and the others, became steward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1366, in the Joji Incident spurred by the anti-Shiba Doyo SASAKI, the Shiba clan fell, and Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, who had the support of Doyo and the others, became steward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>執事から管領との転換は清氏から頼之の間であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the transition from steward to Kanrei was between Kiyouji and Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the transition from steward to Kanrei was between Kiyouji and Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the transition from steward to Kanrei was between Kiyouji and Yoriyuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以後は、政務は管領が統括し、足利将軍家の家政は政所へ移行するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, the Kanrei supervised government affairs, and management of the the Ashikaga Shogun household was transferred to a government office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, the Kanrei supervised government affairs, and management of the the Ashikaga Shogun household was transferred to a government office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, the Kanrei supervised government affairs, and management of the Ashikaga Shogun family was transferred to Mandokoro (Administrative Board).</e>
<cmt>household→family政所→Mandokoro (Administrative Board)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>細川頼之は康暦の政変で失脚し、斯波義将が復帰するが、その後も管領職をめぐり斯波氏と細川氏は対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA fell in the Koryaku Coup, and Yoshimasa SHIBA was rehabilitated, but even after that the Shiba and Hosokawa clans were opposed over the Kanrei position.</e>
<cmt>Koryaku Coupに変更</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA fell in the Koryaku Coup, and Yoshimasa SHIBA was rehabilitated, but even after that the Shiba and Hosokawa clans were opposed over the Kanrei position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA fell in the Koryaku Coup, and Yoshimasa SHIBA was rehabilitated, but even after that the Shiba and Hosokawa clans were opposed over the Kanrei position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1398年に畠山基国が管領になると、それ以降は足利一門の斯波家・畠山家・細川京兆家から交代で任じられることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1398, Motokuni HATAKEYAMA became Kanrei, and after that the Shiba, Hatakeyama and Hosokawa Keicho families related to the Ashikaga family were appointed in turns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1398, Motokuni HATAKEYAMA became Kanrei, and after that the Shiba, Hatakeyama and Hosokawa Keicho families related to the Ashikaga family were appointed in turns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1398, Motokuni HATAKEYAMA became Kanrei, and after that the Shiba, Hatakeyama and Hosokawa Keicho families related to the Ashikaga family were appointed in turns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>人事や評定を経た内容は管領奉書に書かれて諸国へ発せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personnell affairs and contents that passed assessment were written on Kanrei stationary and dispatched to the various provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personnell affairs and contents that passed assessment were written on Kanrei stationary and dispatched to the various provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personnell affairs and contents that passed assessment were written on Kanrei stationary and dispatched to the various provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>3代足利義満、4代将軍足利義持時代には宿老を中心とする合議制となり管領職の地位が低下し、経済的負担もあったことからまず斯波家が衰退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of the 3rd Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and the 4th Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, there was a conference system centered around the Shukuro, and the position of Kanrei was lowered; and the Shiba family first declined, not least because of financial burdens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the 3rd Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and the 4th Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, there was a conference system centered around the Shukuro, and the position of Kanrei was lowered; and the Shiba family first declined, not least because of financial burdens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the third Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA and the fourth Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA, there was a conference system centered around the Shukuro (chief vassal), and the position of Kanrei was lowered; and the Shiba family first declined, not least because of financial burdens.</e>
<cmt>宿老の補足説明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>6代将軍の足利義教は将軍権力の強化を目指し、管領の権限は縮小され、斯波氏や畠山氏の家督争いに介入し、その後の両家の衰退の遠因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 6th Shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, aimed to strengthen the authority of the Shogun, so the authority of the Kanrei was reduced, and intervened in disputes over inheritence in the Shiba and Hatakeyama clans, which later contributed to the decline of both houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 6th Shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, aimed to strengthen the authority of the Shogun, so the authority of the Kanrei was reduced, and intervened in disputes over inheritence in the Shiba and Hatakeyama clans, which later contributed to the decline of both houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth Shogun, Yoshinori ASHIKAGA, aimed to strengthen the authority of the Shogun, so the authority of the Kanrei was reduced, and intervened in disputes over inheritence in the Shiba and Hatakeyama clans, which later contributed to the decline of both families.</e>
<cmt>houses→families</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>8代将軍足利義政時代に起こった応仁の乱でははじめ管領の斯波義廉は山名宗全率いる西軍に属し、将軍義政らは細川勝元率いる東軍に確保されており、幕府における将軍と管領が分裂することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Onin War, which occurred during the time of the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, at first the Kanrei Yoshikado SHIBA joined the Western Army commanded by Sozen YAMANA, Shogun Yoshimasa and the others were protected by the Eastern Army commanded by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and the Shogun and Kanrei in the Shogunate split.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Onin War, which occurred during the time of the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, at first the Kanrei Yoshikado SHIBA joined the Western Army commanded by Sozen YAMANA, Shogun Yoshimasa and the others were protected by the Eastern Army commanded by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and the Shogun and Kanrei in the Shogunate split.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Onin War, which occurred during the time of the eighth Shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, at first the Kanrei Yoshikado SHIBA joined the Western Army commanded by Sozen YAMANA, Shogun Yoshimasa and the others were protected by the Eastern Army commanded by Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, and the Shogun and Kanrei in the Shogunate split.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1468年には東軍を率いる細川勝元が管領となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1468, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, who commaned the Eastern Army, became Kanrei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1468, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, who commanded the Eastern Army, became Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1468, Katsumoto HOSOKAWA, who commanded the Eastern Army, became Kanrei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>応仁の乱後は将軍権力及び斯波・畠山両家は衰退する一方で細川氏のみが権力を広げていき、やがて細川勝元の子・細川政元が細川氏による管領職の世襲化を確立、やがて明応の政変で将軍が廃立するなど幕府権力の全てを掌握した（細川京兆家政権の成立）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power of the Shogun, as well as the Shiba and Hatakeyama families, declined steadily after the Onin War, with only the Hosokawa clan expanding its power; before long Katsumoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s son, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, established heredity of the Kanrei post for the Hosokawa clan, and eventually, in the Meio Coup, overthrowing the Shogun and siezing all of the Shogunate&apos;s autority (establishment of the Hosokawa Keicho administration).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of the Shogun, as well as the Shiba and Hatakeyama families, declined steadily after the Onin War, with only the Hosokawa clan expanding its power; before long Katsumoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s son, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, established heredity of the Kanrei post for the Hosokawa clan, and eventually, in the Meio Coup, overthrowing the Shogun and siezing all of the Shogunate&apos;s authority (establishment of the Hosokawa Keicho administration).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power of the Shogun, as well as the Shiba and Hatakeyama families, declined steadily after the Onin War, with only the Hosokawa clan expanding its power; before long Katsumoto HOSOKAWA&apos;s son, Masamoto HOSOKAWA, established heredity of the Kanrei post for the Hosokawa clan, and eventually, in the Meio Coup, overthrowing the Shogun and siezing all of the Shogunate&apos;s authority (establishment of the Hosokawa Keicho administration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>だが、後継者を巡って政元が家臣に暗殺されると、細川氏は分裂して衰退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Masamoto was assassinated by vassals over succession, the Hosokawa clan split and declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Masamoto was assassinated by vassals over succession, the Hosokawa clan split and declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Masamoto was assassinated by vassals over succession, the Hosokawa clan split and declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1500年代には大内義興、三好長慶、六角定頼らが管領代として幕府に君臨し管領職は形骸化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 1500s, Yoshioki OUCHI, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, Sadayori ROKKAKU and others ruled the Shogunate as replacement Kanrei, the post of Kanrei became merely formal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1500s, Yoshioki OUCHI, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, Sadayori ROKKAKU and others ruled the Shogunate as replacement Kanrei, the post of Kanrei became merely formal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1500s, Yoshioki OUCHI, Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, Sadayori ROKKAKU and others ruled the Shogunate as deputy Kanrei, the post of Kanrei became merely formal.</e>
<cmt>replacement→deputy</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そして1563年の細川氏綱の死後、事実上の自然消滅という形で廃絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then after Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA&apos;s death in 1563, it in fact came to an end through natural lapse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then after Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA&apos;s death in 1563, it in fact came to an end through natural lapse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then after Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA&apos;s death in 1563, it in fact came to an end through natural lapse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Poe(id:16973), Ittyon(id:1348), Y7u67ut7677(id:193001), Aibot(id:104981), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), ふたりはGoki鰤MaxHeart(id:19635), Sanmari(id:1707), Mari(id:1553), でここ(id:9565), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Michey.M(id:906), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 海衛士(id:19229), Loveless(id:129239), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>