<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>揚名介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei no suke (a sinecure post as honorary deputy governor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei no suke (a sinecure post as honorary deputy governor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomei no suke (a sinecure post as honorary deputy governor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>揚名介（ようめいのすけ）とは、職掌及び給付のない名誉職としての国司の次官を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei no suke is a vice minister of kokushi (provincial governors), an honorary post without official duties and benefits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei no suke is a vice minister of kokushi (provincial governors), an honorary post without official duties and benefits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomei no suke is a vice minister of kokushi (provincial governors), an honorary post without official duties and benefits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>特にその官職及び官職にある者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei no suke indicates especially its government post and a person in the government post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei no suke indicates especially its government post and a person in the government post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates a person in a government post.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>年官年爵を有する者が、官職の給与を自らの所得とする一方、成功 (任官)により位階任官を求める者に対して官名のみ授けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A person having nenkan (a right granted as a stipend to members of the Imperial family (including the emperor), consorts of the emperor, some Court nobles, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain government post conferred to them on the occasion of the annual installation of them as government officials) and nenshaku (a right granted as a stipend to a retired emperor, the mother of the Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, the Empress, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain rank conferred to them on the occasion of the annual conferment of a rank to them) took salaries given to the government posts as his own earned income, while conferring only an official name of a government office on those who requested Ikai (Court rank) appointment for their success.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person having nenkan (a right granted as a stipend to members of the Imperial family (including the emperor), consorts of the emperor, some Court nobles, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain government post conferred to them on the occasion of the annual installation of them as government officials) and nenshaku (a right granted as a stipend to a retired emperor, the mother of the Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager, the Empress, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain rank conferred to them on the occasion of the annual conferment of rank) took the salaries given to the government posts as his own earned income, while conferring only the official name of a government office on those who requested Ikai (Court rank) appointment for their success.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person having nenkan (a right granted to members of the Imperial family and some Court nobles to nominate a person for a certain government post) and nenshaku (a right granted to a retired emperor, the mother of the Empress Dowager, the Empress Dowager and the Empress to nominate a person for a certain rank) took the salaries given to the government posts while conferring only the official name of a government office on those who requested a court rank appointment for their success.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このため、この制度を活用して名誉職として官職に任ぜられる事例が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a person was occasionally appointed to a government post as a honorary post by using this system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a person was occasionally appointed to a government post as an honorary post by using this system.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a person was occasionally appointed to a government post in an honorary capacity under this system.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これは単に「名を揚げる」だけで実を伴わない官職であったことから揚名（官）」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei(kan) (揚名（官）) was named after an honorary government post only for making a name for himself (名を揚げる).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei(kan) (揚名（官）) was named after an honorary government post only for making a name for himself (名を揚げる).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People in these honorary posts were called &apos;yomeikan&apos; as they had no power and were officials in name only.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後に財政の悪化に伴って揚名官として国司の介が任ぜられる事例が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, with the government&apos;s financial difficulties, a person was occasionally appointed to suke (vice governor of provincial offices) of kokushi as yomeikan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, with the government&apos;s financial difficulties, a person was occasionally appointed to suke (vice governor of provincial offices) of kokushi as yomeikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, as the government&apos;s financial position worsened, a person was occasionally appointed as vice governor of provincial offices (suke) in an honorary capacity.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これによって生じた名誉職としての介を揚名介といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The resulting honorary post of suke was called the yomei no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The resulting honorary post of suke was called the yomei no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The resulting honorary post of suke was called the yomei no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>『江談抄』には、揚名介の代表とされた山城介と水駅官（水駅の長）を併記して名だけの存在の代表としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Godansho&quot; (the Oe Conversations, with anecdotes and gossip) describes that Yamashiro no suke (assistant governor of Yamashiro) and Suieki kan (head of the waterway station), or typical examples of the yomei no suke, represent existence in name only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Godansho&quot; (the Oe Conversations, with anecdotes and gossip) describes that Yamashiro no suke (assistant governor of Yamashiro) and Suieki kan (head of the waterway station), or typical examples of the yomei no suke, represent existence in name only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Godansho&quot; (the Oe Conversations, with anecdotes and gossip) describes typical examples of honorary posts including Yamashiro no suke (assistant governor of Yamashiro) and Suieki kan (head of the waterway station).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、江戸時代の武家官位も名誉以上の権威を伴わないことから一種の揚名官であると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that Buke-kani (official court titles for samurai) in the Edo period was also one of yomeikan because it did not accompany authority other than honor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that Buke-kani (official court titles for samurai) in the Edo period were also one of yomeikan because it did not include authority other than honor.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that Buke-kani (official court titles for samurai) in the Edo period were also merely honorary titles.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>ただし、揚名介には本来もう1つ意味があったという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is a different hypothesis that Yomei no suke originally meant otherwise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is a different hypothesis that Yomei no suke originally meant otherwise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is a different hypothesis that Yomei no suke originally had a different meaning.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>『薩戒記』によれば、応永33年（1426年）に、後小松上皇から「揚名介」の任国を尋ねられた中山定親（『薩戒記』著者）と清原良賢が、「山城国・上野国・上総国・常陸国・近江国」を挙げたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot;(Diary), the retired Emperor Gokomatsu asked Sadachika NAKAYAMA (who wrote &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot;) and KIYOHARA no Yoshinari the places of duty of the &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; and they answered &apos;Yamashiro Province, Kozuke Province, Kazusa Province, Hitachi Province, and Omi Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot;(Diary), the retired Emperor Gokomatsu asked Sadachika NAKAYAMA (who wrote &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot;) and KIYOHARA no Yoshinari the places of duty of the &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; and they answered &apos;Yamashiro Province, Kozuke Province, Kazusa Province, Hitachi Province, and Omi Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot;(Diary), in 1426, the retired Emperor Gokomatsu asked Sadachika NAKAYAMA (who wrote &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot;) and KIYOHARA no Yoshinari the places of duty of the &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; and they answered &apos;Yamashiro Province, Kozuke Province, Kazusa Province, Hitachi Province, and Omi Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>山城国は平安京（京都）の所在地であり、山城介は内蔵助とともに賀茂祭の行列に必ず随従する決まりがあった（『官職難儀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamashiro Province was home to Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), where there was a rule that Yamashiro no suke, together with Kura no suke (Deputy chief of Kuraryo, Bureau of Palace Storehouses), had to follow the lead of a parade in the Kamo Festival (&quot;Kanshoku-nangi&quot;(book of government posts and criticism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamashiro Province was home to Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), where there was a rule that Yamashiro no suke, together with Kura no suke (Deputy chief of Kuraryo, Bureau of Palace Storehouses), had to follow the lead of a parade in the Kamo Festival (&quot;Kanshoku-nangi&quot;(book of government posts and criticism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamashiro Province was home to Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), where there was a rule that Yamashiro no suke, together with Kura no suke (Deputy chief of Kuraryo, Bureau of Palace Storehouses), had to take part in the parade in the Kamo Festival (&quot;Kanshoku-nangi&quot;(book of government posts and criticism).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>上野・上総・常陸は親王任国であり、介が現地において守の職務を代行する国であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kozuke, Kazusa, and Hitachi Provinces were shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes), where suke acted on kami&apos;s (vice governor of provincial offices) behalf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Kozuke, Kazusa, and Hitachi Provinces were shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes), where suke acted on kami&apos;s (vice governor of provincial offices) behalf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Kozuke, Kazusa, and Hitachi Provinces were shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes), where suke acted on behalf of the Vice Governor of the Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>近江国も畿内以外でもっとも平安京に近い国として、しばしば参議・八省卿級の高官や天皇側近などが守を兼務して介が守の職務を代行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Omi Province, which was the closest province to Heian-kyo other than the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), high officers, such as Sangi (councilor) and Hassho (eight ministries and agencies), or close advisers of the emperor frequently served concurrently as kami, while the suke acted on kami&apos;s behalf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Omi Province, which was the closest province to Heian-kyo other than the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), high officers, such as Sangi (councilor) and Hassho (eight ministries and agencies), or close advisers of the emperor frequently served concurrently as kami, while the suke acted on kami&apos;s behalf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in Omi Province, which was the closest province to Heian-kyo other than the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), high officers, such as Sangi (councilor) and Hassho (eight ministries and agencies), or close advisers of the Emperor frequently served concurrently as kami, while the suke acted on behalf of the Vice Governor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>つまり、いずれも実態を備えた名誉ある要職を指して（文字通り、一般の国の介とは違う名誉ある顕官という意味で）当初は「揚名介」という呼称が用いられていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, in all of the above cases, it is assumed that the name &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; originally indicated a honorary important post with reality (literally meaning a honorary high-ranking office that is different from the common suke in the country).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, in all of the above cases, it is assumed that the name &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; originally indicated a honorary important post with reality (literally meaning a honorary high-ranking office that is different from the common suke in the country).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, in all of the above cases, it is assumed that the name &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; originally indicated an important honorary post which also carried some authority.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>ところが、年官・年爵制度が横行して揚名官としての介が発生すると、両者の意味が混同された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the system of nenkan and nenshaku became common and the suke as yomeikan was created, the meanings of yomeikan and Yomei no suke were mixed together.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the system of nenkan and nenshaku became common and the suke as yomeikan was created, the meanings of yomeikan and Yomei no suke were mixed together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the system of nenkan and nenshaku became common and the suke as yomeikan was created, the meanings of yomeikan and Yomei no suke became confused.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>結果的に本来の顕官であった揚名介も揚名官の介の一種として見られるようになったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the Yomei no suke, which was originally a high-ranking office, came to be regarded as one of the yomeikan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the Yomei no suke, which was originally a high-ranking office, came to be regarded as one of the yomeikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the Yomei no suke, which was originally a high-ranking office, came to be regarded as a purely honorary role.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、『薩戒記』には著者・中山定親が後小松上皇からの質問を受けてその先例を調べた際に、以下の故事を伝聞記事として載せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, Sadachika NAKAYAMA described in his book &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot; the following historical event as hearsay when asked by the retired Emperor Gokomatsu and looked for the precedents of Yomei no suke:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, Sadachika NAKAYAMA described in his book &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot; the following historical event as hearsay when asked by the retired Emperor Gokomatsu and looked for the precedents of Yomei no suke:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, Sadachika NAKAYAMA described in his book &quot;Sakkai-ki&quot; the following historical event when asked by the retired Emperor Gokomatsu to look for the precedents of Yomei no suke:</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>鎌倉時代の一条家経が賀茂祭の山城介に向かって「揚名介が渡る」と口を滑らせてしまい、山城介が揚名介であるという秘事を漏らしたとして人々が騒然としたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, Ietsune ICHIJO blurted out &quot;Yomei no suke will go.&quot; to Yamashiro no suke who was in the Kamo Festival, thus disclosing a secret that Yamashiro no suke was Yomei no suke, and the people were thrown into an uproar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, Ietsune ICHIJO blurted out &quot;Yomei no suke will go.&quot; to Yamashiro no suke who was in the Kamo Festival, thus disclosing a secret that Yamashiro no suke was Yomei no suke, and the people were thrown into an uproar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, Ietsune ICHIJO accidentally said, as he faced Yamashiro no suke in the Kamo Festival, &apos;Yomei no suke will pass through&apos; thereby disclosing a secret that Yamashiro no suke was Yomei no suke, and this caused an uproar.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>『源氏物語』の揚名介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei no suke in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei no suke in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomei no suke in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>この「揚名介」という語は『源氏物語』の「夕顔 (源氏物語)」の巻に「揚名介なる人の家」という形で1ヶ所だけ現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; appears only once in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; in the volume &apos;Yugao&apos; as: &apos;a house of a person called Yomei no suke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; appears only once in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; in the volume &apos;Yugao&apos; as: &apos;a house of a person called Yomei no suke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; appears only once in &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; in the volume &apos;Yugao&apos; as: &apos;a house of a Yomei no suke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、『源氏物語』が古典・聖典となった鎌倉時代・室町時代期には揚名介の意味が分からなくなっていたらしく、『源氏物語』の古注釈書などで「源氏第一の難義」あるいは「源氏物語三ケの大事の一なり」等と呼んでとして秘伝扱いされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, when &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; was regarded as a Japanese classic, it seemed that the meaning of Yomei no suke could not be interpreted: commentaries of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; treated the term &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; as &apos;the most difficult part in the Tale of Genji&apos; or &apos;one of three critical matters in the Tale of Genji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, when &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; was regarded as a Japanese classic, it seemed that the meaning of Yomei no suke could not be interpreted: commentaries of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; treated the term &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; as &apos;the most difficult part in the Tale of Genji&apos; or &apos;one of three critical matters in the Tale of Genji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, when &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; was regarded as a Japanese classic, it seemed that the meaning of Yomei no suke was no longer understood and commentaries of &quot;The Tale of Genji&quot; treated the term &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; as &apos;the most difficult part in the Tale of Genji&apos; or &apos;;one of three critical matters in the Tale of Genji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>院政時代の世尊寺伊行でもすでに本来の意味が分からなくなっていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seemed that even Koreyuki SESONJI in the Insei period (the period of the government by a retired emperor) could not interpret the original meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seemed that even Koreyuki SESONJI in the Insei period (the period of government by a retired emperor) could not interpret the original meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seemed that even Koreyuki SESONJI in the Insei period (the period of government by a retired emperor) could not interpret the original meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『源氏釈』において「揚名介とは諸国の介なり、源氏の人のなるなり」と誤った説明を加えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, in &quot;Genji shaku&quot; (commentaries of the Tale of Genji) was added an incorrect explanation that &apos;Yomei no suke is suke appointed in the country, who was from Minamoto clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, in &quot;Genji shaku&quot; (commentaries of the Tale of Genji) was added an incorrect explanation that &apos;Yomei no suke is suke appointed in the country, who was from the Minamoto clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, in &quot;Genji shaku&quot; (commentaries of the Tale of Genji) an incorrect explanation was added that &apos;Yomei no suke is suke appointed in the country, who was from the Minamoto clan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鎌倉時代に入って藤原定家は『奥入』において「此の事源氏第一の難義なり、末代の人勘へ知るべき事に非ざるか」と意味が分からなくなっていることを正直に表明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, FUJIWARA no Sadaie honestly stated in &quot;Okuiri&quot; (Genji commentaries) that &quot;&apos;Yomei no suke&apos; is the most difficult part to understand in the Tale of Genji. People may not grasp the meaning for ever.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, FUJIWARA no Sadaie honestly stated in &quot;Okuiri&quot; (Genji commentaries) that &quot;&apos;Yomei no suke&apos; is the most difficult part to understand in the Tale of Genji. People may not grasp the meaning ever.&quot;</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, FUJIWARA no Sadaie frankly stated in &quot;Okuiri&quot; (Genji commentaries) that &quot;&apos;Yomei no suke&apos; is the most difficult part to understand in the Tale of Genji and that its meaning may never be understood. &quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の四辻善成になると『河海抄』において「当流両家深奥の説、殊なる秘事となるに依りて口伝にあり」と秘説化しており記録を残さず口伝で伝えるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI stated in &quot;Kakai-sho Commentary&quot; that: &quot;Thorough interpretations of each family are different secrets. Therefore, they are passed down by word of mouth.&quot; which means that the meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was made esoteric and passed down by word of month without keeping a record.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI stated in &quot;Kakai-sho Commentary&quot; that: &quot;Thorough interpretations of each family are different secrets. Therefore, they are passed down by word of mouth.&quot; which means that the meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was made esoteric and passed down by word of month without keeping a record.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Yoshinari YOTSUTSUJI stated in &quot;Kakai-sho Commentary&quot; that: &quot;Thorough interpretations of each family are different secrets. Therefore, they are passed down by word of mouth.&quot; which means that the meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was kept secret and passed down by word of month without keeping a record.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その後の中院通勝による『岷江入楚』では、「源氏物語三ケの大事の一なり、（中略）河海に載せたる事、皆誤れり、別に是を記すべし」として一般に見せる注釈書には掲載せず、別に存在する秘伝書のようなものの中に記しておいたことを述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in &quot;Mingo nisso&quot; (commentaries on the Tale of Genji) by Michikatsu NAKANOIN, it was stated that: &quot;&apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was one of three critical matters in the Tale of Genji. (omitted) The descriptions in &apos;Kakai-sho&apos; were completely incorrect. The interpretation of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; should be described separately.&quot; which means that the meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was not described in a commentary as usual, but in a kind of a book of secrets that was different from a commentary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in &quot;Mingo nisso&quot; (commentaries on the Tale of Genji) by Michikatsu NAKANOIN, it was stated that: &quot;&apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was one of three critical matters in the Tale of Genji. (omitted) The descriptions in &apos;Kakai-sho&apos; were completely incorrect. The interpretation of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; should be described separately.&quot; which means that the meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was not described in a commentary as usual, but in a kind of a book of secrets that was different from a commentary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in &quot;Mingo nisso&quot; (commentaries on the Tale of Genji) by Michikatsu NAKANOIN, it was stated that: &quot;&apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was one of three critical matters in the Tale of Genji. (omitted) The descriptions in &apos;Kakai-sho&apos; were completely incorrect. The interpretation of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; should be described separately.&quot; which means that the meaning of &apos;Yomei no suke&apos; was not described in a public commentary, but in a secret document.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>一条兼良になると1477年に著した『源語秘訣』（注解書『花鳥余情』で保留した15の論点を説明した秘伝書）の中で、以下のように正しい説明を加えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanera ICHIJO added correct explanations in his book &quot;Gengo hiketsu&quot;(Secrets of The Tale of Genji) (a book of secrets explaining 15 points which were put on hold in &quot;Kacho yojo&quot; (Aesthetic Impressions)) in 1477 as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanera ICHIJO added correct explanations in his book &quot;Gengo hiketsu&quot;(Secrets of The Tale of Genji) (a book of secrets explaining 15 points which were put on hold in &quot;Kacho yojo&quot; (Aesthetic Impressions)) in 1477 as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanera ICHIJO added correct explanations in his book &quot;Gengo hiketsu&quot; (Secrets of The Tale of Genji) (a book of secrets explaining 15 points which were put on hold in &quot;Kacho yojo&quot; (Aesthetic Impressions)) in 1477 as follows:</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「清慎公記云。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Seishinko-ki (diary) put.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Seishinko-ki (diary) put.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seishinko-ki (diary)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>康保4年7月22日。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 22, 967.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 22, 967.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 22, 967.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>揚名関白早可被停止之者也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yomei kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor only in name) is a person who should be retired soon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yomei kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor only in name) is a person who should be retired soon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yomei kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor only in name) is a person nearing retirement.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>今案、揚名の二字は諸国の介に限べからず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I think that Yomei should not be limited to suke of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I think that Yomei should not be limited to suke of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I think that Yomei should not be limited to suke of the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>故に揚名関白と清慎公はのたまへり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus Seishinko called the Yomei kanpaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus Seishinko called the Yomei kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus in the Seishinko Diary the Yomei are called the Yomei kanpaku.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>又揚名掾揚名目ともいへり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can also be said Yomei jo or Yomei sakan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Yomei jo or Yomei sakanの部分ははっきり確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can also be said Yomei jo or Yomei sakan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also referred to as Yomei jo or Yomei sakan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mark-zero(id:48822), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>