<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>四納言</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinagon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>四納言（しなごん）とは、平安時代中期一条天皇の時代に活躍した4人の公卿（源俊賢・藤原公任・藤原斉信・藤原行成）の称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinagon is a denomination referring to the four court nobles (MINAMOTO no Toshikata, FUJIWARA no Kinto, FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, and FUJIWARA no Yukinari), who were active in the era of Emperor Ichijo in the middle Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinagon refers to the four court nobles (MINAMOTO no Toshikata, FUJIWARA no Kinto, FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, and FUJIWARA no Yukinari) who were active in the era of Emperor Ichijo in the middle Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>deleted “donomination” and the comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shinagon&quot; refers to the four court nobles (MINAMOTO no Toshikata, FUJIWARA no Kinto, FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, and FUJIWARA no Yukinari) who were active in the era of Emperor Ichijo in the middle Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他 2009/6/29）の指示により、Shinagon にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原斉信が大納言、他の3名が権大納言まで昇ったことからこの称がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name, Shinagon (four nagons), derived from the fact that FUJIWARA no Tadanobu reached to &quot;Dai nagon&quot; or Dainagon (Major Counselor) and the other three achieved the post of &quot;Gon Dai nagon&quot; or Gon Dainagon (provincial major counselor).</e>
<cmt>納言を一つの意味ある塊として説明しているので、 &quot;Dai nagon&quot; or Dainagon (Major Counselor) ・ &quot;Gon Dai nagon&quot; or Gon Dainagon (provincial major counselor)のように、nagonの前にスペースを入れた表記を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name, Shinagon (four nagons), derived from the fact that FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was “Dainagon” (Major Counselor) and the other three served as &quot;Gon Dainagon&quot; (provincial major counselor).</e>
<cmt>the repetition of the titles seemed unnecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name, Shinagon (four nagons), derived from the fact that FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was Dainagon (chief councilor of state) and the other three served as Gon Dainagon (provisional chief councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>“Dainagon” (Major Counselor) を Dainagon (chief councilor of state) に変更しました。&quot;Gon Dainagon&quot; (provincial major counselor) を Gon Dainagon (a provisional chief councilor of state) に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「恪勤上達部」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakugon Kandachime (恪勤上達部) (warrior nobility whose rank is Third Rank or higher)</e>
<cmt>「恪勤上達部」→Kakugon Kandachime (恪勤上達部) [正しい読み方が不明です] 「恪勤上達部」→定訳不明：Kakugon Kandachime (恪勤上達部) (warrior nobility whose rank is Third Rank or higher)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakugon Kandachime (warrior nobility of Third Rank or higher)</e>
<cmt>whose rank is-&gt;of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakugon Kandachime&apos; (warrior nobility of Third Rank or higher)</e>
<cmt>Kakugon Kandachime にシングルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>「四納言」という言葉は、『十訓抄』（第一、四納言事）に由来し、漢の劉邦の時代に実在した「四皓」（『史記』留侯世家）と呼ばれる賢者に擬えられたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the word &quot;Shinagon&quot; was derived from &quot;Jukkinsho&quot; (A Miscellany of Ten Maxims) (Chapter 1: About Shinagon), and was taken after a wise man, a real figure in the era of Liu Bang in Han, called &quot;Shiko&quot; (Liuhou shijia (the Lord Liu Genealogy）, &quot;Shiki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>第一、四納言事→定訳不明：Chapter 1: About Shinagonとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the word &quot;Shinagon&quot; was derived from &quot;Jukkinsho&quot; (A Miscellany of Ten Maxims - Chapter 1: Shinagon), and was patterned after a wise man of the Liu Bang era of Han China, called &quot;Shiko&quot; (“Shiki,” the Lord Liu Genealogy).</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity, removed excess parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the word &apos;Shinagon&apos; was derived from &quot;Jukkinsho&quot; (A Miscellany of Ten Maxims - Chapter 1: Shinagon), and was patterned after a wise man of the Liu Bang era of Han China, called &quot;Shiko&quot; (&quot;Shiki,&quot; the Lord Liu Genealogy).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Shinagon&quot;をシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。“Shiki,” のダブルクォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、『続本朝往生伝』には当時この4人の他に5名（藤原実資・源扶義・平惟仲・藤原有国、他1名は不詳）を加えた「九卿」が存在したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Zoku Honcho-ojo-den,&quot; in addition to these four, originally there were another five persons (FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi, TAIRA no Korenaka, FUJIWARA no Arikuni, and the other unidentified person), and they were collectively called &quot;Kugyo&quot; (nine nobles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Zoku Honcho-ojo-den,&quot; in addition to these four there were originally another five (FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi, TAIRA no Korenaka, FUJIWARA no Arikuni, and one other), and they were collectively called &quot;Kugyo&quot; (nine nobles).</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Zoku Honcho-ojo-den,&quot; in addition to these four there were originally another five (FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, MINAMOTO no Sukeyoshi, TAIRA no Korenaka, FUJIWARA no Arikuni, and one other), and they were collectively called &quot;Kugyo&quot; (nine nobles).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>その一方で、四納言は藤原道長政権を積極的に支えた公卿であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Shinagon was the court nobles who actively supported the government of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Shinagon were the court nobles who actively supported the government of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>Noun-verb agreement (number)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Shinagon were the court nobles who actively supported the government of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>道長と距離を保っていた藤原実資の日記『小右記』寛弘2年5月14日（1005年6月23日）条には、「右衛門督以下恪勤上達部伺候云々、以七八人上達部世号恪勤上達部、朝夕致左府之勤歟」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article on July 23, 1005 of &quot;Shouki,&quot; a diary written by FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, who were keeping a certain distance with Michinaga, there is a description, as follows:</e>
<cmt>「右衛門督以下恪勤上達部伺候云々、以七八人上達部世号恪勤上達部、朝夕致左府之勤歟」は、次のセルに日本語訳を元に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a July 23, 1005, article in &quot;Shouki,&quot; a diary written by FUJIWARA no Sanesuke - who kept a certain distance with Michinaga - there is a description as follows:</e>
<cmt>Noun-verb agreement (number)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a July 23, 1005, article in &quot;Shouki,&quot; a diary written by FUJIWARA no Sanesuke - who kept a certain distance with Michinaga - there is a description as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「恪勤」には職務に精励するとともに、高官に仕える身分の低い従者（侍）の意味を持っており、実資は右衛門督（藤原斉信）以下の上達部（公卿、ここには俊賢・公任・行成を含む）が左府（左大臣藤原道長）の従者に成り下がったと嘲笑したと解されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kakugon&quot;(恪勤) means a lower-ranked retainer (samurai) who serves for a high rank official, while dedicating himself in his duties,&apos; and this comment can be interpreted that Sanesuke was ridiculing, saying that Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, and other Kandachimes (上達部) (court nobles, including Toshikata, Kinto, Yukinari in this context) had come down to be mere retainers of Safu (left ministry) (Sadaijin (minister of the left) FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>恪勤」→&quot;Kakugon&quot; (恪勤) [正しい読み方が不明です] 右衛門督→Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) 上達部→Kandachime(s) (上達部) [正しい読み方が不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kakugon&quot; means a lower-ranked retainer (samurai) who serves for a high-ranking official, dedicating himself to his duties, and this comment can be interpreted to mean that Sanesuke was ridiculing, saying that Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, and other Kandachimes (court nobles, including Toshikata, Kinto, Yukinari in this context) had been reduced to mere retainers of the Safu (left ministry, meaning minister of the left FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>edited for grammar, removed nested parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakugon&apos; means a lower-ranked retainer (samurai) who serves for a high-ranking official, dedicating himself to his duties, and this comment can be interpreted to mean that Sanesuke was ridiculing, saying that Saemon no kami (captain of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards) FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, and other Kandachimes (court nobles, including Toshikata, Kinto, Yukinari in this context) had been reduced to mere retainers of the Safu (left ministry, meaning minister of the left FUJIWARA no Michinaga).</e>
<cmt>&quot;kakugon&quot; をシングルクォーテーションに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>反対に「賢人右府」と呼ばれた実資がこの賢者の代表とされる四納言に含まれないのは、彼が右大臣に昇ったこともあるが、実資は有職故実に通じた賢人でかつ小野宮流の嫡流であったことから、道長の権勢に対抗することが可能な状況にあったところが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the reason why Sanesuke, although called &apos;Kenjin Ufu&apos; (Wise Right Ministry), was not included in Shinagon that was supposed to symbolize the men of wisdom, owed largely to the fact that Sanesuke was in a position that might threaten the power and influence of Michinaga, because Sanesuke was a person of wisdom with a vast knowledge of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquettes) and, moreover, a legitimate son of the Ononomiya family line.</e>
<cmt>「賢人右府」→定訳不明： &apos;Kenjin Ufu&apos; (Wise Right Ministry)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the reason why Sanesuke, although called &apos;Kenjin Ufu&apos; (Wise Right Ministry), was not included in Shinagon, was that he was in a position that might threaten the power and influence of Michinaga, because Sanesuke was a person of wisdom with a vast knowledge of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquettes) and, moreover, a legitimate son of the Ononomiya family line.</e>
<cmt>shortened to make it clearer</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the reason why Sanesuke, although called &apos;Kenjin Ufu&apos; (Wise Right Ministry), was not included in Shinagon, was that he was in a position that might threaten the power and influence of Michinaga, because Sanesuke was a person of wisdom with a vast knowledge of Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquettes) and, moreover, a legitimate son of the Ononomiya family line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>源俊賢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Toshikata,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Toshikata,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Toshikata,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>源俊賢は安和の変で失脚した左大臣源高明の子であり、高明が著した儀式書『西宮記』の継承者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Toshikata is a son of MINAMOTO no Takaakira, who fell from the position in the Anna Incident, and the successor to the exemplary book on rituals &quot;Saiguki&quot; written by Takaakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Toshikata was a son of MINAMOTO no Takaakira, who fell from his position in the Anna Incident, and the heir to the book of rituals &quot;Saiguki&quot; written by Takaakira.</e>
<cmt>verb tense, deleted “exemplary”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Toshikata was a son of MINAMOTO no Takaakira, who fell from his position in the Anna Incident, and the heir to the book of rituals &quot;Saiguki&quot; written by Takaakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>父の件が理由で叙爵が17歳と他の公卿が平均15歳で受けるのに比較して大きく出遅れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of his father&apos;s downfall, Toshikata&apos;s Joshaku (conferring a peerage) was largely delayed in comparison with other court nobles who were conferred a peerage at the age of 15 in average.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of his father&apos;s downfall, Toshikata&apos;s Joshaku (peerage) was delayed relative to other court nobles who were conferred peerage at an average age of 15.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity, removed unnecessary parts</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of his father&apos;s downfall, Toshikata&apos;s Joshaku (peerage) was at age of 17, delayed relative to other court nobles who were conferred peerage at an average age of 15.</e>
<cmt>「17歳と」訳漏れのため at age of 17, を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、妹の源明子が道長に嫁いだことで摂関家との関係を持ち、権大納言に昇ったのが59歳と昇進自体は決して順調とは言えなかったものの、道長との縁戚関係を利用して他の貴族・官人との仲介役を務め、道長のための政治資金の調達などの役割を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the marriage of his small sister MINAMOTO no Akiko to Michinaga, he gained a kinship relation with the Sessho/Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor) family, and he took charge of raising the political fund for Michinaga, working as an intermediary between Michinaga, and other nobles and officials by making use of his kinship connection with the Michinaga, although his promotion to Gon Dainagon took place when he was 59 years old, which was far from a smooth advancement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the marriage of his younger sister MINAMOTO no Akiko to Michinaga, he gained a kinship relation with the Sessho/Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor) family, and he took charge of raising political funds for Michinaga, working as an intermediary between Michinaga and other nobles and officials by making use of his kinship connection, although his promotion to Gon Dainagon took place when he was 59 years old - far from rapid advancement.</e>
<cmt>although “little sister” is a common phrase to refer to a younger female sibling, “small sister” would probably be taken to mean that she was physically diminutive</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the marriage of his younger sister MINAMOTO no Akiko to Michinaga, he gained a kinship relation with the Sessho/Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor) family, and he took charge of raising political funds for Michinaga, working as an intermediary between Michinaga and other nobles and officials by making use of his kinship connection, although his promotion to Gon Dainagon took place when he was 59 years old - far from rapid advancement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>藤原実資は俊賢を「貪欲謀略其聞共高之人也」（『小右記』寛弘8年7月26日条）と非難している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA Sanesuke criticized Toshikata, writing &quot;[h]e is notorious for his avarice and conspiracy&quot; (the article on September 2, 1011 of &quot;Shouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>「貪欲謀略其聞共高之人也」→定訳不明：&quot;he is notorious for his avarice and conspiracy&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA Sanesuke criticized Toshikata, writing &quot;he is notorious for his avarice and conspiracy&quot; (article on September 2, 1011, of &quot;Shouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>removed square brackets</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA Sanesuke criticized Toshikata, writing &quot;he is notorious for his avarice and conspiracy&quot; (article on September 2, 1011, of &quot;Shouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、寛仁3年（1019年）に発生した刀伊の賊の際に藤原実資と四納言が激しく議論したことで知られる朝議に彼の名前が無いのは、彼が既に権大納言の上表（辞表の提出）を行っていたため（同年10月に受理）に召集されなかったためであるが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the name of the Court Council members who were present at a fierce discussion held between Fujiwara Sanesuke and Shinagon, in the face of the Toi invasion that occurred in 1019, Toshikata&apos;s name was not included, because he had already submitted his Johyo (memorial to the Emperor) at that time to ask for his resignation from the post of Gon Dainagon (it was accepted in November 1019) and therefore, he was not called up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshikata&apos;s name was not included among the Court Council members present at a fierce debate between Fujiwara Sanesuke and Shinagon when faced with the Toi invasion in 1019, because he had already submitted his Johyo (memorial to the Emperor) at that time resign from the post of Gon Dainagon (his resignation was accepted in November 1019), and he was therefore not invited.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshikata&apos;s name was not included among the Court Council members present at a fierce debate between Fujiwara Sanesuke and Shinagon when faced with the Toi invasion in 1019, because he had already submitted his Johyo (letter of resignation) from the position of Gon Dainagon (which was accepted in November 1019), and he was therefore not invited.</e>
<cmt>「彼が既に権大納言の上表（辞表の提出）を行っていたため（同年10月に受理）」をbecause he had already submitted his Johyo (memorial to the Emperor) at that time resign from the post of Gon Dainagon (his resignation was accepted in November 1019) から　because he had already submitted his Johyo (letter of resignation) from the position of Gon Dainagon (which was accepted in November 1019) に修正しました。※「上表」の訳ですが、この場合は「君主に奉る意見書」ではなく「辞表」のため、上記のとおり修正しました。参考： http://kotobank.jp/word/%E4%B8%8A%E8%A1%A8</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後事情を知った俊賢は藤原実資に意見を具申している（『小右記』寛仁3年9月23日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, when Toshikata came to know that incident, he conveyed his clear-cut opinion to FUJIWARA Sanesuke (the article on October 29, 1019 of &quot;Shouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, when Toshikata found out about that incident, he conveyed his clear-cut opinion to FUJIWARA Sanesuke (article on October 29, 1019 of &quot;Shouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>came to know-&gt;found out</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, when Toshikata found out about that incident, he conveyed his clear-cut opinion to FUJIWARA Sanesuke (article on October 29, 1019 of &quot;Shouki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>藤原公任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Kinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Kinto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>藤原公任は『大鏡』に描かれた幼少期の藤原道長が強いライバル意識を持った相手として知られているものの、実際には寛和2年6月10日 (旧暦)の内裏歌合で若手貴族の代表として道長・斉信ともに選ばれるなど、青年時代から共に行動することが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the story of &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror), FUJIWARA no Kinto was known as a person with whom FUJIWARA no Michinaga had a strong rivalry in his infancy, however, in reality, he often worked with Michinaga in such cases as Dairi Utaawase (the palace poetry contest) on July 24, 986, in which he was selected and participated together with Michinaga and Tadanobu as a representative of the young nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the story of &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror), FUJIWARA no Kinto was known as a person with whom FUJIWARA no Michinaga had a strong rivalry in his childhood, however, in reality, he often worked with Michinaga in such cases as Dairi Utaawase (the palace poetry contest) on July 24, 986, in which he was selected and participated together with Michinaga and Tadanobu as a representative of the young nobles.</e>
<cmt>infancy-&gt;childhood</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the story of &quot;Okagami&quot; (The Great Mirror), FUJIWARA no Kinto was known as a person with whom FUJIWARA no Michinaga had a strong rivalry in his childhood, however, in reality, he often worked with Michinaga in such cases as Dairi Utaawase (the palace poetry contest) on July 24, 986, in which he was selected and participated together with Michinaga and Tadanobu as a representative of the young nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、関白藤原頼忠の子として天元3年2月15日に内裏にて円融天皇自らの加冠により元服して異例の正五位下が授けられる（『日本紀略』・『扶桑略記』、ただし後者には同3年条に誤って入れられている）など、将来が期待されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, as a son of Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Yoritada, his future was deemed promising by such an anecdote; he was convened Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), an irregularly high rank for his age, on March 9, 980 when he underwent genpuku (to celebrate his coming of age) in the Imperial Palace with the celebration of kakan (headgear wearing ceremony), a crown was put him on his head by the hand of Emperor Enyu (&quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; (Summary of Japanese chronologies) and &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A brief History of Japan), however, in the latter, this event was erroneously compiled in Sannenjo (the article in the year 980) of &quot;Fusoki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>同3年条→定訳不明：article in the year 980としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, as a son of Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Yoritada, his future was deemed promising; he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), an unusually high rank for his age, on March 9, 980, at his coming of age celebration in the Imperial Palace, and a crown was put on his head by Emperor Enyu, according to &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; (Summary of Japanese chronologies) and &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A brief History of Japan), although in the latter, this event was erroneously compiled in Sannenjo (the article in the year 980) of &quot;Fusoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>not sure where “by such an anecdote” came from or what it meansconvened-&gt;promoted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, as a son of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Yoritada, his future was deemed promising; he was promoted to Shogoinoge (Senior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade), an unusually high rank for his age, on March 9, 980, at his coming of age celebration in the Imperial Palace, and a crown was put on his head by Emperor Enyu, according to &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; (Summary of Japanese chronologies) and &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A brief History of Japan), although in the latter, this event was erroneously compiled in Sannenjo (the article in the year 980) of &quot;Fusoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Kanpaku に (chief adviser to the Emperor) を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>実際に四納言の中で唯一、藤原道長が政権の座に就く以前に参議に昇進している（正暦3年（992年）8月）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, he was the only one person among Shinagon, who became earlier a member of the Imperial Court before FUJIWARA no Michinaga came into power (September, 992)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, he was the only one of the Shinagon who became a member of the Imperial Court before FUJIWARA no Michinaga came to power in September, 992.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, he was the only one of the Shinagon who became a member of the Imperial Court before FUJIWARA no Michinaga came to power in September, 992.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、和歌・漢詩・管弦に優れ、『和漢朗詠集』・『北山抄』などの著作が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also good at waka (Japanese poetry), Chinese-style poetry, and music with string instruments, and he is also well known as a author of &quot;Wakan Roei Shu&quot; (Collection of Japanese and Chinese poems) and 『北山抄』&quot;Hokuzansho &quot;(Manual of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) among others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also good at waka (Japanese poetry), Chinese-style poetry, and music with string instruments, and he was well known as author of &quot;Wakan Roei Shu&quot; (Collection of Japanese and Chinese poems) and &quot;Hokuzansho &quot;(Manual of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), among others.</e>
<cmt>removed original Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also good at waka (Japanese poetry), Chinese-style poetry, and music with string instruments, and he was well known as author of &quot;Wakan Roei Shu&quot; (Collection of Japanese and Chinese poems) and &quot;Hokuzansho &quot;(Manual of court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette), among others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>政治的にはその後、九条流の台頭と小野宮流の劣勢に際しては従兄弟の実資とは違って道長と接近し、その子藤原教通を娘婿にすることで連携を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, he, different from his cousin Sanesuke, made approximation in political idea to Michinaga, in the face of the emergence of the Kujo line coupled with the downfall of Ononomiya line, and strengthened a tie with Michinaga by taking his son FUJIWARA no Norimichi as his son-in-law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, unlike his cousin Sanesuke, he came to agree with Michinaga on political issues, in the face of the emergence of the Kujo line coupled with the downfall of Ononomiya line, and strengthened ties with Michinaga by taking his son FUJIWARA no Norimichi as his son-in-law.</e>
<cmt>edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, unlike his cousin Sanesuke, he came to agree with Michinaga on political issues, in the face of the emergence of the Kujo line coupled with the downfall of Ononomiya line, and strengthened ties with Michinaga by taking his son FUJIWARA no Norimichi as his son-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>だが、寛仁年間に入ると、斉信に昇進を越されるようになり、娘の死も重なった結果、出家を決意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1017, he was overtaken by Tadanobu in promotion, and the death of his daughter that occurred at the around same time triggered him to make a decision to become a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1017, he was overtaken by Tadanobu in promotion, and the death of his daughter around same time caused him to decide to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1017, he was overtaken by Tadanobu in promotion, and the death of his daughter around same time caused him to decide to become a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『栄花物語』（巻27）では既に出家していた道長が公任のために衣装を贈る場面が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes) (27 vols.) there is a scene in which Michinaga, who had already been in religion, made a present of a priest robe to Kinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes, 27 vols.) there is a scene in which Michinaga, who had already taken vows, presented a priestly robe to Kinto.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity, removed excess parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Eiga Monogatari&quot; (A Tale of Flowering Fortunes, vol. 27) there is a scene in which Michinaga, who had already taken vows, presented a priestly robe to Kinto.</e>
<cmt>「栄花物語」は正続併せて40巻ありますので、（巻27）とは「第27巻目」のことと思われます。よって&quot;27vols.&quot; を &quot;vol. 27&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>結果的には四納言の中で最も長寿を保つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he lived the longest life among all the four of Shinagon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he lived the longest of all of the Shinagon.</e>
<cmt>added full stop</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he lived the longest of all of the Shinagon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>藤原斉信</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>藤原斉信は太政大臣藤原為光の子で道長の従兄弟にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was a son of Dajo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu and a cousin of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was a son of Dajo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu and a cousin of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Tadanobu was a son of Dajo-daijin (Grand minister of state) FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu and a cousin of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>前述のように寛和2年の歌合では道長・公任とともに招かれたが、道長・公任より1つ年下であった斉信は最年少の召人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described before, in the Utaawase (the poetry contest) held in 986, when he was invited to participate together with Michinaga and Kinto, he was one-year younger than Michinaga and Kinto, and was the youngest among all the invited participants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described before, in the Utaawase (poetry contest) held in 986, when he was invited to participate with Michinaga and Kinto, he was one year younger than them, and the youngest of all the invited participants.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described before, in the Utaawase held in 986, when he was invited to participate with Michinaga and Kinto, he was one year younger than them, and the youngest of all the invited participants.</e>
<cmt>the Utaawase (poetry contest) は、30行目のセルで説明済みのため、括弧内を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>同2年10月から1年間道長とともに左近衛少将を務めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the year 986, he served during one year as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) together with Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 986, he served one year as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) together with Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From November 986, he served one year as Sakone no shosho (Minor Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) together with Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>「同2年10月」の「10月」が役漏れのため、 &quot;November&quot; を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>蔵人頭時代に関白藤原道隆が重篤となり、息子である藤原伊周の内覧宣旨を巡る騒動が発生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he was Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Michitaka became seriously ill, and this provoked a disturbance in relation with nairan-senshi (a preliminary inspection of imperial decree) for Michitaka&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Korechika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Michitaka became seriously ill, and this provoked a disturbance in relation with nairan-senshi (a preliminary inspection of imperial decree) for Michitaka&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain), Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Michitaka became seriously ill, and this provoked a disturbance in relation with nairan-senshi (a preliminary inspection of imperial decree) for Michitaka&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Korechika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>四納言のうち、もっとも道長と親しかったのは斉信であったと考えられ、道長が出家後の万寿元年（1024年）に病気療養のために有馬温泉に向かった際に斉信も同行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that among Shinagon, Tadanobu was most familiar to Michinaga, and he also accompanied Michinaga, when Michinaga, who had already entered the priesthood, went to Arima-Onsen Hot Spring for his medical treatment and recuperation in 1024.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed that among the Shinagon, Tadanobu was closest to Michinaga, and he also accompanied Michinaga, who had already entered the priesthood, when he went to Arima-Onsen Hot Spring for medical treatment and recuperation in 1024.</e>
<cmt>edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed that among the Shinagon, Tadanobu was closest to Michinaga, and he also accompanied Michinaga, who had already entered the priesthood, when he went to Arima-Onsen Hot Spring for medical treatment and recuperation in 1024.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>更に道長の娘である藤原彰子・藤原威子の中宮大夫、外孫である敦成親王（後一条天皇）の東宮大夫に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he was appointed to be Chugu-daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s household) to Michinaga&apos;s two daughters, FUJIWARA no Shoshi and FUJIWARA no Ishi, and then to Togu-daifu (Lord Steward) to Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later Emperor Goichijo), who was a son of Michinaga&apos;s, that is, his grandchild.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he was appointed to be Chugu-daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s household) to Michinaga&apos;s two daughters, FUJIWARA no Shoshi and FUJIWARA no Ishi, and then to Togu-daifu (Lord Steward) to Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later Emperor Goichijo), who was a son of Michinaga&apos;s, that is, his grandchild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he was appointed to be Chugu-daibu (Master of the Consort&apos;s household) to Michinaga&apos;s two daughters, FUJIWARA no Shoshi and FUJIWARA no Ishi, and then to Togu-daifu (Lord Steward) to Imperial Prince Atsuhira (later Emperor Goichijo), who was a son of Michinaga&apos;s, that is, his grandchild.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>寛仁4年（1020年）に四納言中唯一の大納言に昇進し、その翌年に藤原実資が右大臣に転じた後は唯一の正官の大納言であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1020, he was promoted to Dainagon, as the only person who attained this post among Shinagon, and the next year, when FUJIWARA Sanesuke was appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right), he was the only Dainagon with the senior rank.</e>
<cmt>正官→定訳不明：senior rank.としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1020, he was promoted to Dainagon, as the only person who attained this post among Shinagon, and the next year, when FUJIWARA Sanesuke was appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right), he was the only Dainagon with the senior rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1020, he was promoted to Dainagon, as the only person who attained this post among Shinagon, and the next year, when FUJIWARA Sanesuke was appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right), he was the only Dainagon with the senior rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その後、斉信はあと一歩に迫った大臣の地位に就任することを願って度々祈祷を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, longing for the post of the minister which was only one step away, Tadanobu offered a prayer every day for the post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, longing for the ministerial post that was only one step away, Tadanobu prayed daily for it.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, longing for the ministerial post that was only one step away, Tadanobu frequently prayed for it.</e>
<cmt>「度々」を&quot;daily&quot; から &quot;frequently&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>彼と大臣の地位を争い先に就任した藤原実資は不快の念を『小右記』に記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, Fujiwara Sanesuke, who wan the post of the minister after having competed with Tadanobu, expressed his discomfort in his diary &quot;Shouki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this, Fujiwara Sanesuke, who won the post over Tadanobu, expressed his discomfort in his diary &quot;Shouki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this, Fujiwara Sanesuke, who won the post over Tadanobu, expressed his discomfort in his diary &quot;Shouki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>だが、若くして大臣となった藤原頼通・教通兄弟及び当時としては稀に見る長命を保った実資の3大臣を前に遂に斉信が大臣になることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tadanobu had never reached to be a minister, in the face of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and his brother Norimichi, who became ministers when they were still young, and Sanesuke, who enjoyed an exceptional longevity at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tadanobu never became a minister, in contrast to FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and his brother Norimichi, who became ministers when they were still young, and Sanesuke, who enjoyed exceptional longevity for that time.</e>
<cmt>in the face of-&gt;in contrast</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tadanobu never became a minister, in contrast to FUJIWARA no Yorimichi and his brother Norimichi, who became ministers when they were still young, and Sanesuke, who enjoyed exceptional longevity for that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>藤原行成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukinari</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yukinari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukinari</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>藤原行成は摂政藤原伊尹の孫であるが、幼くして祖父と父を失い、外祖父に育てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukinari is a grandchild of Sessho (regent) FUJIWARA Koretaka, but he lost his grandfather and father in his infancy and was brought up by his maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yukinari was a grandchild of Sessho (regent) FUJIWARA Koretaka, but he lost his grandfather and father in his infancy and was brought up by his maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yukinari was a grandchild of Sessho (regent) FUJIWARA no Koretada, but he lost his grandfather and father in his infancy and was brought up by his maternal grandfather.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA Koretaka を FUJIWARA no Koretada に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>後世に三蹟の1人として知られる書家として歴史に名を残すが、能吏としても知られており、天皇第一の側近として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he became a historically well known calligrapher as one of the three famous calligraphers, but at the same time he was know as an excellent official, and served actively as the closest adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。 家司別当→定訳不明：Keishi betto (the administrator of the household affaires)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he became famous as one of the three famous calligraphers, and at the same time was know as an excellent official, and served actively as the closest adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he became famous as one of the three famous calligraphers, and at the same time was know as an excellent official, and served actively as the closest adviser to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>一条天皇の蔵人頭を6年間にわたり務め、長保3年（1001年）2月には当時3歳で前年に生母藤原定子を失った第一皇子敦康親王の家司別当に任じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He worked in the post of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) to the Emperor during six years, and then he became Keishi betto (the administrator of the household affaires) to the first Imperial Prince Atsuyasu when the prince was three years old, as the prince lost his real mother FUJIWARA no Teishi one year before.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He worked in the post of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) to the Emperor for 6 years, and then became Keishi betto (administrator of household affairs) to the first Imperial Prince Atsuyasu when the prince was three years old, as the prince lost his real mother FUJIWARA no Teishi one year before.</e>
<cmt>during-&gt;for</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He worked in the post of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) to the Emperor for 6 years, and then became Keishi betto (administrator of household affairs) to the first Imperial Prince Atsuyasu when the prince was three years old, as the prince lost his real mother FUJIWARA no Teishi one year before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その一方で、藤原道長の政権確立のために行った2つの出来事は、いずれも道長の意向を受けた行成が一条天皇に迫ったことが行成の日記『権記』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he confessed in his diary &quot;Gonki&quot; that under the instruction of Michinaga, he pressured Emperor Ichijo to carry out the following two arrangements.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he confessed in his diary &quot;Gonki&quot; that under the instruction of Michinaga, he pressured Emperor Ichijo to carry out the following two arrangements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he confessed in his diary &quot;Gonki&quot; that under the instruction of Michinaga, he pressured Emperor Ichijo to carry out the following two arrangements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>中宮定子がいるにも関わらず道長の娘・彰子を一条天皇の后妃に立てて「一帝二后」を実現させたこと、第一皇子の敦康親王がいるにも関わらず道長の外孫である第二皇子の敦成親王（後一条天皇）を次期東宮に擁立したこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One was to set up the practice of &apos;two empresses for one emperor,&apos; by backing up the daughter of Michinaga, Shoshi, to be a wife of Emperor Ichijo, although the emperor already had the official wife, Empress Teishi, and the other was to put up the second Imperial Prince Atsunari (later Emperor Goichijo), who was a grandchild (a son of his daughter) of Michinaga for the next Togu (Crown Prince), in spite of the existence of the first Imperial Prince Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「一帝二后」→定訳不明：&apos;two empresses for one emperor&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One was to set up the practice of &apos;two empresses for one emperor,&apos; by backing up the daughter of Michinaga, Shoshi, to be a wife of Emperor Ichijo, although the emperor already had a wife, Empress Teishi, and the other was to set up the second Imperial Prince Atsunari (later Emperor Goichijo), who was a grandchild (a son of his daughter) of Michinaga as the next Togu (Crown Prince), in spite of the fact that there was already an Imperial Prince Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt>article usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One was to set up the practice of &apos;two empresses for one emperor,&apos; by backing up the daughter of Michinaga, Shoshi, to be a wife of Emperor Ichijo, although the emperor already had a wife, Empress Teishi, and the other was to set up the second Imperial Prince Atsunari (later Emperor Goichijo), who was a grandchild (a son of his daughter) of Michinaga as the next Togu (Crown Prince), in spite of the fact that there was already an Imperial Prince Atsuyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、道長が病気で一時重態になった際には行成を呼んで嫡男鶴君（頼通）の後見を依頼する程の信頼を得ていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also had earned Michinaga&apos;s great confidence in such grade that when Michinaga became seriously ill for a while, he called Yukinari to ask him to be Koken (guardian) of his legitimate son Tsuru gimi (鶴君) (Yorimichi）.</e>
<cmt>後見→Koken (guardian) 鶴君→Tsuru gimi (鶴君)[正しい読み方が不明です] 頼通　→Yorimichi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also earned Michinaga&apos;s trust to the point that when Michinaga became seriously ill, he called Yukinari to ask him to be Koken (guardian) of his legitimate son Tsuru gimi (Yorimichi）.</e>
<cmt>removed original Japanese</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also earned Michinaga&apos;s trust to the point that when Michinaga became seriously ill, he called Yukinari to ask him to be Koken (guardian) of his legitimate son Tsuru gimi (Yorimichi）.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>だが、その一方で一条天皇が死の床で最後まで側に置いたのも行成であり、また皇位継承から排除された敦康親王が20歳の若さで急死するまで親王家別当として最後まで親王を庇護したのは行成その人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Emperor Ichijo also kept Yukinari close to him, even on his deathbed until the end of his life, and it was also Yukinari that had protected Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, who had been excluded from the succession to the Imperial throne, until the prince&apos;s sudden death at the age of only 20, serving as Betto (the chief officer) for the Imperial Prince family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Emperor Ichijo also kept Yukinari close, even on his deathbed, and it was also Yukinari that protected Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, who was excluded from succession to the throne, until the prince&apos;s sudden death at the age of 20, while serving as Betto (chief officer) for the Imperial Prince family.</e>
<cmt>verb tense, shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Emperor Ichijo also kept Yukinari close, even on his deathbed, and it was also Yukinari that protected Imperial Prince Atsuyasu, who was excluded from succession to the throne, until the prince&apos;s sudden death at the age of 20, while serving as Betto (chief officer) for the Imperial Prince family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、公務に関しては時には強引な道長の方針と対立する場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, concerning to the matters of office, he sometimes opposed to the aggressive policy of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on official matters, he sometimes opposed the aggressive policies of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>deleted “to”, changed order to improve clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on official matters, he sometimes opposed the aggressive policies of Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>行成は道長から厚い信頼を受ける一方で、他の3名と道長との関係と比較すると、行成と道長の間には若干の距離があったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yukinari wan a great confidence of Michinaga, the personal relation of Yukinari and Michinaga seems to have been a little bit distant in comparison with the relation of Michinaga with the other three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yukinari won Michinaga&apos;s trust, their personal relationship seems to have been a little bit distant in comparison with that between Michinaga and the other three.</e>
<cmt>spelling, prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yukinari won Michinaga&apos;s trust, their personal relationship seems to have been a little bit distant in comparison with that between Michinaga and the other three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>なお、道長の子藤原長家の正室には初めは行成が娘が嫁いでいたが早世し、続いて斉信の娘が嫁いでいるがやはり早世している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Michinaga&apos;s son, FUJIWARA no Nagaie, at first a daughter of Yukinari was married off as the lawful wife, but she died early, and then Nagaie took Tadanobu&apos;s daughter as his wife, but she also died in early life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nagaie, Yukinari&apos;s daughter, was married to Michinaga&apos;s son, but she died early, and then Nagaie took Tadanobu&apos;s daughter as his wife, but she also died at a young age.</e>
<cmt>this one needed a lot of work</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nagaie, Yukinari&apos;s daughter, was married to Michinaga&apos;s son, but she died early, and then Nagaie took Tadanobu&apos;s daughter as his wife, but she also died at a young age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その後、行成は別の娘を嫁がせようとしたが道長から拒絶され、道長は実資の娘藤原千古との縁談を進めようとしたが、今度は長家が拒絶したためにともに実現しなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, when Yukinari tried to marry off another his daughter to Nagaie, Michinaga refused her, and when Michinaga tried to match his son with Sanesuke&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Chifuru, his son, Nagaie, refused her, and as a result any of the two marriages did not realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, when Yukinari tried to marry off another daughter to Nagaie, Michinaga refused her, and when Michinaga tried to match his son with Sanesuke&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Chifuru, his son, Nagaie, refused her, and as a result neither of the two marriages happened.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, when Yukinari tried to marry off another daughter to Nagaie, Michinaga refused her, and when Michinaga tried to match his son with Sanesuke&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Chifuru, his son, Nagaie, refused her, and as a result neither of the two marriages happened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>「四納言」の時代の終わり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End of the &apos;Shinagon&apos; era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End of the &apos;Shinagon&apos; era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End of the &apos;Shinagon&apos; era.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>寛仁3年（1019年）藤原道長が出家したその年に源俊賢が致仕、続いて万寿元年（1024年）に藤原公任も致仕して2年後に出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga entered the priesthood in 1019, in the same year, Minamoto no Toshikata retired from his official post, and successively, Fujiwara no Kinto also became a priest in 1024.</e>
<cmt>致仕→定訳不明：retired from his official postとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1019, the same year that FUJIWARA no Michinaga entered the priesthood, Minamoto no Toshikata retired from his official post, and FUJIWARA no Kinto also became a priest in 1024.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1019, the same year that FUJIWARA no Michinaga entered the priesthood, MINAMOTO no Toshikata retired from his official post, so did FUJIWARA no Kinto in 1024 consequently and Kinto became a priest two years later.</e>
<cmt>Minamoto no Toshikata を MINAMOTO no Toshikata に修正しました。藤原公任が致仕したのが1024年であって、出家したのはその2年後の1026年であるため、&quot;and FUJIWARA no Kinto also became a priest in 1024.&quot;を全文書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>万寿4年（1027年）6月に俊賢が死去すると、12月4日 (旧暦)に藤原道長と藤原行成が同日に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1027 Toshikata died, and in 1028, on the same day, January 9, FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Yukinari died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1027 Toshikata died, and in 1028, FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Yukinari both died on January 9.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1027 Toshikata died, and in 1028, FUJIWARA no Michinaga and FUJIWARA no Yukinari both died on January 9.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>長元8年（1035年）、最後まで大臣の地位に望みをつないでいた藤原斉信が死去、最後に公任が長久2年（1041年）に没している（なお、斉信が生前望んでいた大臣の空席が発生するのは、公任の死から更に5年後の藤原実資の死去に伴うものであった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1035, FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, who never gave up the hope to be the minister, died, and lastly Kinto died in 1041 (even after Kinto&apos;s death, it took five years more before the minister&apos;s vacant seat, for which Tadanobu had been longing in life, became finally available).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1035, FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, who never gave up hope of becoming minister, died, and lastly Kinto died in 1041 (even after Kinto&apos;s death, it was five years more before the minister&apos;s seat, for which Tadanobu had been longing in life, became finally available).</e>
<cmt>article usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1035, FUJIWARA no Tadanobu, who never gave up hope of becoming minister, died, and lastly Kinto died in 1041 (even after Kinto&apos;s death, it was five years more before the minister&apos;s seat, for which Tadanobu had been longing in life, became finally available).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>