<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八瀬童子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasedoji/Yasenodoji/Hasedoji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasedoji/Yasenodoji/Hasedoji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasedoji/Yasenodoji/Hasedoji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八瀬童子（やせどうじ、やせのどうじ、はせどうじ）は京都洛北八瀬郷（現在の京都府京都市左京区八瀬）に住み、室町時代から天皇の輿丁として奉仕した人々のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yasedoji,&quot; &quot;Yasenodoji,&quot; or &quot;Hasedoji&quot; was a group of people who lived in Rakuhoku Yasego, the Yase Village in the northern Kyoto (present day Yase, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) serving as Yotei (koshi carrier) for the Emperor from the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yasedoji,&quot; &quot;Yasenodoji,&quot; or &quot;Hasedoji&quot; was a group of people who lived in Rakuhoku Yasego, the Yase Village in the northern Kyoto (present day Yase, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) serving as Yotei (koshi carrier) for the Emperor from the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasedoji, Yasenodoji, or Hasedoji was a group of people who lived in Rakuhoku Yasego, the Yase Village in the northern Kyoto (present day Yase, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture) serving as Yotei (koshi carrier) for the Emperor from the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除Kyoto Prefecture補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>延暦寺の雑役に従事した童子村で伝教大師最澄が使役した鬼の子孫とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yasedoji were considered descendants of &quot;Oni&quot; (a creature from Japanese folklore) whom Dengyo Daishi Saicho (Buddhist Monk named Saicho with the posthumous title of Dengyo Daishi) employed in Doji mura (village) as a domestic laborer for the Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Doji mura か Doshi mura か確認できませんでした</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasedoji were considered descendants of &quot;Oni&quot; (a creature from Japanese folklore) whom Dengyo Daishi Saicho (Buddhist Monk named Saicho with the posthumous title of Dengyo Daishi) employed in Doji mura (village) as a domestic laborer for the Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasedoji were considered descendants of Oni (a creature from Japanese folklore) whom Dengyo Daishi Saicho (Buddhist Monk named Saicho with the posthumous title of Dengyo Daishi) employed in Doji mura (village) as a domestic laborer for the Enryaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>寺役に従事する者は結髪せず、長い髪を垂らしたいわゆる大童であり、履物も草履をはいた子供のような姿であったため童子と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who engaged in the temple chores had their hair hanging loose and disheveled; their features were like a child wearing sandals, so they were called Doji (a child).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who engaged in the temple chores had their hair hanging loose, were disheveled; and were like children wearing sandals, so they were called Doji (a child).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who engaged in the temple chores had their hair hanging loose, were disheveled; and were like children wearing sandals, so they were called Doji (a child).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>現在、八瀬童子の伝統を守るため関係者によって八瀬童子会が組織され、資料の収集保全が進められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To maintain the tradition of the Yasedoji, people involved established the Yasedoshi-kai (the association of the Yasedoji), which is collecting and keeping related materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To maintain the tradition of the Yasedoji, people involved established the Yasedoshi-kai (the association of the Yasedoji), which collects and keeps related materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To maintain the tradition of the Yasedoji, people involved established the Yasedoshi-kai (the association of the Yasedoji), which collects and keeps related materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、葵祭には輿丁の扮装で参加し、天皇の輿丁として奉仕した往時の姿をしのばせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Aoi Festival, members of the Yasedoshi-kai dress up as Yotei, which recalls the way the Yasedoji served as koshi carrier for the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Aoi Festival, members of the Yasedoshi-kai dress up as Yotei, recalling the way the Yasedoji served as koshi carriers for the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Aoi Festival, members of the Yasedoshi-kai dress up as Yotei, recalling the way the Yasedoji served as koshi carriers for the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>来歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>弘文天皇元年（672年）の壬申の乱の際、背中に矢を受けた大海人皇子がこの地にかま風呂を作り傷を癒したことから「矢背」または「癒背」と呼ばれ、転じて「八瀬」となったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Jinshin War in 672, Prince Oama, who had got an arrow in his back, built a steam bath there to heal his wound; the place was called &quot;Yase 矢背,&quot; in which &quot;ya&quot; means &quot;an arrow&quot; and &quot;se&quot; means &quot;the back,&quot; or &quot;癒背&quot; (healing the back), and then became known as &quot;Yase 八瀬.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Jinshin War in 672, Prince Oama, who was shot in the back with an arrow, built a steam bath to heal his wound; the place was called &quot;Yase 矢背,&quot; in which &quot;ya&quot; means &quot;an arrow&quot; and &quot;se&quot; means &quot;the back,&quot; or &quot;癒背&quot; (healing the back), it then became known as &quot;Yase 八瀬.&quot;</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Jinshin War in 672, Prince Oama, who was shot in the back with an arrow, built a steam bath to heal his wound; the place was called &apos;Yase&apos; (矢背) in which &apos;ya&apos; means &apos;an arrow&apos; and &apos;se&apos; means &apos;the back,&apos; or &apos;癒背&apos; (healing the back), it then became known as &apos;Yase&apos; (八瀬).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この伝承にちなんで後に多くの窯風呂が作られ、中世以降、主に公家の湯治場として知られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this legend, many steam baths were built later, and the place was known as a hot spring resort mainly for the Court nobles after the Japanese Middle ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this legend, many steam baths were later built, and were known as hot spring resorts, mainly for the Court nobles after the Middle ages in Japan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this legend, many steam baths were later built, and were known as hot spring resorts, mainly for the Court nobles after the Middle ages in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>歴史学的な見地からは大海人皇子に関する伝承はほぼ否定されており、八瀬の地名は高野川流域の地形によるものであるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From a historical viewpoint, the legend concerning Prince Oama is almost denied, and the name of Yase probably comes from a geographical features of the Takano River Basin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the historical viewpoint, the legend concerning Prince Oama is mostly denied, and the name of Yase probably comes from geographical features of the Takano River Basin.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the historical viewpoint, the legend concerning Prince Oama is mostly denied, and the name of Yase probably comes from geographical features of the Takano River Basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>比叡山諸寺の雑役に従事したほか座主の輿を担ぐ役割もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yasedoji were engaged in not only doing chores at several temples on Mt. Hiei but also carrying koshi (palanquin) for the head priests of other temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasedoji were engaged not only in chores at several temples on Mt. Hiei, but were also carrying koshi (palanquin) for the head priests of other temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasedoji were engaged not only in chores at several temples on Mt. Hiei, but were also carrying koshi (palanquin) for the head priests of other temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、参詣者から謝礼を取り担いで登山することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They sometimes carried temple visitors on a palanquin to the top of the mountain by charging fees.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They sometimes carried temple visitors on a palanquin to the top of the mountain and charged fees.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They sometimes carried temple visitors on a palanquin to the top of the mountain and charged fees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>延元元年（1336年）、京を脱出した後醍醐天皇が比叡山に逃れる際、八瀬郷13戸の戸主が輿を担ぎ、弓矢を取って奉護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo, who had escaped from Kyoto, fled to Mt. Hiei in 1336, the heads of thirteen families in the Yasego carried koshi and took up arrows to guard the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Godaigo, who had escaped from Kyoto, fled to Mt. Hiei in 1336, the heads of thirteen families in Yasego carried koshi and took up arrows to guard the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo, who had escaped from Kyoto, fled to Mt. Hiei in 1336, the heads of thirteen families in Yasego carried koshi and took up arrows to guard the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この功績により地租課役の永代免除の綸旨を受け、特に選ばれた者が輿丁として朝廷に出仕し天皇や太上天皇の行幸、葬送の際に輿を担ぐことを主な仕事とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these achievements, they received rinji (the Emperor&apos;s order) that they would have a permanent exemption from tax and labour duty, and only those chosen served the Court as Yotei, mainly going in for koshi carrier on the occasion of departure or a funeral of the Emperor and the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For these achievements, they received rinji (the Emperor&apos;s order) that they would be permanenly exemption from taxation and labour duties, and only those chosen served the Court as Yotei, mainly going in for koshi carrier on the occasion of departure or a funeral of the Emperor and the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For these achievements, they received rinji (the Emperor&apos;s order) that they would be permanently exemption from taxation and labor duties, and only those chosen served the Court as Yotei, mainly going in for koshi carrier on the occasion of departure or a funeral of the Emperor and the Cloistered Emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>延暦寺との境界争い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Border dispute with the Enryaku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Border dispute with the Enryaku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Border dispute with the Enryaku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>比叡山の寺領に入会権を持ち洛中での薪炭、木工品の販売に特権を認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Yasedoji had the right of common on the estate of the Enryaku-ji Temple, they enjoyed the privilege of selling firewood, charcoal or woodwork inside the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Yasedoji had common rights on the estate of Enryaku-ji Temple, they enjoyed the privilege of selling firewood, charcoal or woodwork inside the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Yasedoji had common rights on the estate of Enryaku-ji Temple, they enjoyed the privilege of selling firewood, charcoal or woodwork inside the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>永禄12年（1569年）、織田信長は八瀬郷の特権を保護する安堵状を与え、慶長8年（1603年）、江戸幕府の成立に際しても後陽成天皇が八瀬郷の特権は旧来どおりとする綸旨を下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1569, Nobunaga ODA issued a letter to secure the privileges of the Yasego, and in the establishment of the Edo bakufu in 1603, Emperor Goyozei also issued an order that the privileges of the Yasego would continue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1569, Nobunaga ODA issued a letter to secure the privileges of the Yasego, and the establishment of the Edo bakufu in 1603, Emperor Goyozei also issued an order ensuring the privileges of the Yasego would continue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1569, Nobunaga ODA issued a letter to secure the privileges of the Yasego, and the establishment of the Edo bakufu in 1603, Emperor Goyozei also issued an order ensuring the privileges of the Yasego would continue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>延暦寺と八瀬郷は寺領と村地の境界をめぐってしばしば争ったが、公弁法親王が天台座主に就任すると、その政治力を背景に幕府に八瀬郷の入会権の廃止を認めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yasego and the Enryaku-ji Temple often had a dispute over the border between the temple estate and the villege zone; however, after Monk Imperial Prince Koben became Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect), he urged the bakufu to acknowledge the abolition of the Yasego&apos;s right of common with his political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasego and the Enryaku-ji Temple often had disputes over the border between the temple estate and the villege zone; however, after Monk Imperial Prince Koben became Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect), he urged the bakufu to acknowledge the abolition of the Yasego&apos;s common rights with his political power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasego and the Enryaku-ji Temple often had disputes over the border between the temple estate and the village zone; however, after Monk Imperial Prince Koben became Tendai-zasu (head priest of the Tendai sect), he urged the bakufu to acknowledge the abolition of the Yasego&apos;s common rights with his political power.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これに対し八瀬郷は再三にわたり復活を願い出るが認められず、宝永4年（1707年）になってようやく老中、秋元喬朝が裁定を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, the Yasego repuested a retraction many times, but it was denied, and then in 1707, Senior councillor, Takatomo AKIMOTO, finally made a decision.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, the Yasego repuested a retraction many times, but it was denied, and then in 1707, Senior councillor, Takatomo AKIMOTO, finally made a decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, the Yasego requested a retraction many times, but it was denied, and then in 1707, Senior councillor, Takatomo AKIMOTO, finally made a decision.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>延暦寺の寺領を他に移し旧寺領・村地を禁裏領に付替えることによって、朝廷の裁量によって八瀬郷の入会権を保護するという方法で解決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was concluded in such a way that the Enryaku-ji Temple&apos;s estate was transferred to some other place, and the former temple&apos;s estate and the villege zone shifted to the sacred precincts of the Imperial Court; thus, the Yasego&apos;s right of common was secured by the Imperial Court&apos;s discretion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was concluded in such a way that the Enryaku-ji Temple&apos;s estate was transferred to some other place, and the former temple&apos;s estate and the villege zone shifted to the sacred precincts of the Imperial Court; thus, the Yasego&apos;scommon rights were secured by the Imperial Court&apos;s discretion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was concluded in such a way that the Enryaku-ji Temple&apos;s estate was transferred to some other place, and the former temple&apos;s estate and the village zone shifted to the sacred precincts of the Imperial Court; thus, the Yasego&apos;s common rights were secured by the Imperial Court&apos;s discretion.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>八瀬郷はこの恩に報いるため秋元を祭神とする秋元神社を建立し徳をたたえる祭礼を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People in the Yasego felt grateful for his decision, and erected the Akimoto-jinja Shrine dedicated to Takatomo AKIMOTO, and held a festival to praise his virtue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People in the Yasego felt grateful for his decision, and erected the Akimoto-jinja Shrine dedicated to Takatomo AKIMOTO, and held a festival to praise his virtue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People in the Yasego felt grateful for his decision, and erected the Akimoto-jinja Shrine dedicated to Akitomo, and held a festival to praise his virtue.</e>
<cmt>Takatomo原文に合わせ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この祭礼は「赦免地踊」と呼ばれる踊りの奉納を中心とするもので、現在でも続いている（毎年10月の第2月曜日の前日にあたる日曜日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This festival centering on a dedicatory dance called &quot;Shamenchi odori&quot; (the Shamenchi Dance) is now held (on Sunday preceding the second Monday in October every year).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This festival centering on a dedicatory dance called &quot;Shamenchi odori&quot; (the Shamenchi Dance) is now held (on Sunday preceding the second Monday in October every year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This festival centering on a dedicatory dance called &apos;Shamenchi odori&apos; (the Shamenchi Dance) is now held (on Sunday preceding the second Monday in October every year).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="22">
<j>葱華輦の輿丁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carrier for Sokaren (palanquin on which the Emperor&apos;s coffin is placed)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Carrier for Sokaren (palanquin on which the Emperor&apos;s coffin is placed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Carrier for Sokaren (palanquin on which the Emperor&apos;s coffin is placed)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="23">
<j>猪瀬直樹の『天皇の影法師』で紹介されて以来、歴代天皇の棺を担ぐ者として有名になったが、実際には後醍醐天皇以降の全ての天皇の棺を担いだわけではなく、特に近世においては長く断絶した期間もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Yasedoji were introduced in the book titled, &quot;Tenno no Kageboshi&quot; (A Silhuette of the Emperor) written by Naoki Inose, they have been well known for carrying coffins of successive Emperors; however, they did not carry all the Emperor&apos;s coffins from Emperor Godaigo onward in fact, and especially in the early-modern times, they discontinued their service for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Yasedoji were introduced in the book titled, &quot;Tenno no Kageboshi&quot; (A Silhouette of the Emperor) written by Naoki Inose, they have been well known for carrying coffins of successive Emperors; however, they did not carry all the Emperor&apos;s coffins from Emperor Godaigo onward in fact, and especially in the early-modern times, they discontinued their service for a long time.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Yasedoji were introduced in the book titled, &quot;Tenno no Kageboshi&quot; (A Silhouette of the Emperor) written by Naoki INOSE, they have been well known for carrying coffins of successive Emperors; however, they did not carry all the Emperor&apos;s coffins from Emperor Godaigo onward in fact, and especially in the early-modern times, they discontinued their service for a long time.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="24">
<j>大正元年（1912年）、明治天皇の葬送にあたり、喪宮から葬礼場まで棺を陸海軍いずれの儀仗兵によって担がせるかをめぐって紛糾し、その調停案として八瀬童子を葱華輦（天皇の棺を載せた輿）の輿丁とする慣習が復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the funeral of Emperor Meiji in 1912, there was a trouble over which military escort of the army or the navy should carry the coffin from the palace in mourning to the funeral hall; a compromise solution was that the custom of the Yasedoji serving as carrier for Sokaren (palanquin on which the Emperor&apos;s coffin is placed) was revived.</e>
<cmt>喪宮の読み方・意味がわかりませんでしたが、喪中の宮殿として訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the funeral of Emperor Meiji in 1912, there was some trouble over which military escort from the army or navy should carry the coffin from the palace in mourning to the funeral hall; a compromise was that the custom of the Yasedoji serving as carrier for Sokaren (palanquin on which the Emperor&apos;s coffin is placed) was revived.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the funeral of Emperor Meiji in 1912, there was some trouble over which military escort from the army or navy should carry the coffin from the palace in mourning to the funeral hall; a compromise was that the custom of the Yasedoji serving as carrier for Sokaren (palanquin on which the Emperor&apos;s coffin is placed) was revived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>明治維新後には地租免除の特権は失われていたが、毎年地租相当額の恩賜金を支給することで旧例にならった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration, they were deprived of the privilege of a land tax exemption; however, they could follow precedent, such that they granted money equivalent to the amount of land tax from the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, they were deprived of the privilege of a land tax exemption; however, they followed precedent, such that they were granted money equivalent to the amount of land tax from the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, they were deprived of the privilege of a land tax exemption; however, they followed precedent, such that they were granted money equivalent to the amount of land tax from the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この例は大正天皇の葬送にあたっても踏襲された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same process was applied to the funeral of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same principle was applied to the funeral of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same principle was applied to the funeral of Emperor Taisho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>平成元年（1989年）、昭和天皇の葬送では棺は車輌によって運ばれることとなり、葱華輦は式場内の移送にのみ用いられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the funeral of Emperor Showa in 1989, the coffin was carried by a car, and the Sokaren was used only for transfer of the coffin in the funeral hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the funeral of Emperor Showa in 1989, the coffin was carried in a car, and the Sokaren was used only to transfer the coffin to the funeral hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the funeral of Emperor Showa in 1989, the coffin was carried in a car, and the Sokaren was used only to transfer the coffin inside the funeral hall.</e>
<cmt>to→inside</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>八瀬童子会は旧例の通り八瀬童子に輿丁を任せるよう宮内庁に要請したが警備上の理由から拒否され、輿丁には皇宮護衛官が古式の装束を着てあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yasedoshi-kai requested that the role of Yotei be performed by the Yasedoji as in the past; however, it was rejected because of security reasons, and the Imperial guards became Yotei in historical costumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yasedoshi-kai requested that the role of Yotei be performed by the Yasedoji as in the past; however, it was rejected because of security reasons, and the Imperial guards became Yotei in historical costumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yasedoshi-kai requested that the role of Yotei be performed by the Yasedoji as in the past; however, it was rejected because of security reasons, and the Imperial guards became Yotei in historical costumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>八瀬童子会からは数名の代表者が車両から葱華輦に棺を乗せかえる際などに顧問として関与するに止まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Several members from the Yasedoshi-kai served as advisers only when the coffin was transferred from the car to the Sokaren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Several members from the Yasedoshi-kai served as advisers only when the coffin was transferred from the car to the Sokaren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Several members from the Yasedoshi-kai served as advisers only when the coffin was transferred from the car to the Sokaren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="30">
<j>八瀬童子の登場するフィクション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fiction in which the Yasedoji appear</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fiction in which the Yasedoji appear</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fiction in which the Yasedoji appear</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>『花と火の帝』 隆慶一郎 (著) 講談社文庫 上巻 ISBN 406185495X 下巻 ISBN 4061854968</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hana to Hi no Mikado&quot; (Emperor of A Flower and Fire) written by Keiichiro Ryu, Kodansha Bunko Vol. 1 ISBN 406185495X, Vol. 2 ISBN 4061854968</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hana to Hi no Mikado&quot; (Emperor of A Flower and Fire) written by Keiichiro Ryu, Kodansha Bunko Vol. 1 ISBN 406185495X, Vol. 2 ISBN 4061854968</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hana to Hi no Mikado&quot; (Emperor of A Flower and Fire) written by Keiichiro RYU, Kodansha Bunko Vol. 1 ISBN 406185495X, Vol. 2 ISBN 4061854968</e>
<cmt>名前の表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Murasagi(id:79122), Nnh(id:474), Oddmake(id:29591), Extrahitz(id:26245), こぶまき(id:38278), Sprinkler(id:14399), Nopira(id:29335), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>