<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>番衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>番衆（ばんしゅう）とは、番を編成して宿直警固にあたる者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banshu is a person to keep night watch by forming a vigilant team (ban).</e>
<cmt>番→定訳不明：vigilant team (ban)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banshu is a person who keeps watch at night as part of guard group (ban).</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not really happy with “guard group” but it makes more sense than “vigilant team” here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Banshu&quot;(a guard) is a person who keeps watch at night as part of guard group (ban).</e>
<cmt>統一リスト（その他 2009/6/29）の指示により、Banshu にダブルクォーテーションを追記し、(a guard) を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>狭義においては幕府に詰めて征夷大将軍及び御所の警固にあたる者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a more limited sense, it refers to a person who stationed in the office of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and stood guard for Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and his palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a more limited sense, it refers to a person stationed in an office of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) who stood guard for the Seii taishogun and his palace.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a more limited sense, it refers to a person stationed in an office of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) who stood guard for the seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and his palace.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍the Seii taishogun をthe seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>幕府の番衆の元は鎌倉幕府の源頼朝時代に弓矢に優れた側近の御家人を日夜身辺に置いたことに由来するとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Banshu in the bakufu originally derives from the fact that during the time of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura bakufu, he arranged gokenins (immediate vassals of the shogunate) with high qualification in bow and arrow to stay close to him night and day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Banshu in the bakufu originally derives from the fact that in the time of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and the Kamakura bakufu, he arranged for gokenins (immediate vassals of the shogunate) with skill in bow and arrow to stay close to him night and day.</e>
<cmt>qualification-&gt;skill</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Banshu in the bakufu originally derives from the fact that in the time of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and the Kamakura bakufu, he arranged for gokenins (immediate vassals of the shogunate) with skill in bow and arrow to stay close to him night and day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>源実朝の暗殺後、小侍所が設置され、6番制によって1日1番の小番が編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated, Kozamurai dokoro (an office of officers to guard Shogun in attendance) was set up, and a system of Koban (small vigilant team) was created, which was formed of 6 teams and each team took charge of 24 hours guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated, Kozamurai dokoro (the Shogun&apos;s guard) was set up, and a system of Koban (small watch teams) was created, which consisted of 6 teams on a rotating 24 hour watch.</e>
<cmt>edited for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated, Kozamurai dokoro (the Shogun&apos;s guard) was set up, and a system of Koban (small watch teams) was created, which consisted of 6 teams on a rotating 24 hour watch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>小番の中にも近習番・廂番・申次番などが設けられ、有力御家人の子弟が任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under Koban, there were several sub-teams such as Kinjuban (a bodyguard for the shogun), Hisashiban (a person who keeps the night watch staying under the eaves of building), and Moshitsugiban (a post to attend the visitors), and the powerful gokenins&apos; sons were appointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Koban, there were several sub-teams such as Kinjuban (a bodyguard for the shogun), Hisashiban (a person who keeps night watch under the eaves of building), and Moshitsugiban (a post to attend to visitors), and the powerful gokenins&apos; sons were appointed.</e>
<cmt>article usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Koban, there were several sub-teams such as Kinjuban (a bodyguard for the shogun), Hisashiban (a person who keeps night watch under the eaves of building), and Moshitsugiban (a post to attend to visitors), and the powerful gokenins&apos; sons were appointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>彼らは将軍近習層を形成して、時には執権勢力と対抗関係となり、政治的紛争の原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They formed a shogun kinshuso (a class of shogunal bodyguard), which sometimes becomes a counterweight to oppose the regent power, and provoked political conflicts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They formed a shogun kinshuso (a class of shogunal bodyguards), which sometimes became a counterweight to the regent&apos;s power, and provoked political conflicts.</e>
<cmt>article usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They formed a shogun kinshuso (a class of shogunal bodyguards), which sometimes became a counterweight to the regent&apos;s power, and provoked political conflicts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>室町幕府も同様の制度を整備し、後に5番制の奉公衆へと発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Muromachi bakufu, the same system was consolidated, and later it developed into Hokoshu, which was made up of five vigilant teams.</e>
<cmt>奉公衆→定訳不明：Hokoshuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi bakufu, the same system was used, and later it developed into Hokoshu, which was made up of five teams.</e>
<cmt>consolidated-&gt;used</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi bakufu, the same system was used, and later it developed into the Hokoshu (the shogunal military guard), which was made up of five teams.</e>
<cmt>奉公衆Hokoshu を the Hokoshu (the shogunal military guard) に修正しました。※出典：http://books.google.com/books?id=aiLYQ22ohmkC&amp;pg=PA40&amp;dq=hokoshu+guard&amp;as_brr=3&amp;hl=ja&amp;cd=2#v=onepage&amp;q=hokoshu%20guard&amp;f=false</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>彼らは将軍の警固のみならず、御料所の経営委任や自己の所領に対する段銭の京済（中間搾取の恐れのある守護などの中間者の関与を経ずに幕府へ直接納付を行う）や守護不入などの特権を得て将軍直属の軍事力の中核となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They not only guard the shogun but also played a central role in the military force directly controlled by the shogun, with the privileges granted from the shogun, such as, Kyosei (the right to direct tax payment of tansen (a kind of provisional tax in medieval Japan) imposed on the commission of goryosho (the Imperial or shogunate family&apos;s estate) and his private estate to the bakufu without any intermediaries such as Shugo (provincial constable) that would produce intermediate exploitation) and non-intervention of Shugo.</e>
<cmt>守護不入→定訳不明：non-intervention of Shugoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They not only guarded the shogun but also played a central role in the military force directly controlled by him, with privileges granted by the shogun, such as Kyosei (the right to direct tax payment of tansen, a kind of provisional tax imposed on the the Imperial or shogunate family&apos;s estate and his private estate and payed to the bakufu without any intermediaries such as Shugo) and sanctuary from interference by Shugo.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They not only guarded the shogun but also played a central role in the military force directly controlled by him, with privileges granted by the shogun, such as Kyosei (the right to direct tax payment of tansen, a kind of provisional tax imposed on the Imperial or shogunate family&apos;s estate and his private estate and paid to the bakufu without any intermediaries such as Shugo) and sanctuary from interference by Shugo.</e>
<cmt>on the the Imperial or shogunate family&apos;s estate の &quot;the&quot; を一つ削除しました。payed を paid に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>更に番衆の概念が武士の身分・家格づけにも応用され、相伴衆や御供衆、申次衆、内談衆などの呼称が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the concept of Banshu came to be applied to the status of samurais and their family ranking, and based on this concept, the job titles such as Shobanshu (officials who accompany the shogun), Otomoshu (an attendant group, who attended the shogun to go up to the ancient capital Kyoto), Moshitsugishu (a person in charge of conveying some information to the shogun), and Naidanshu (judges) were produced.</e>
<cmt>申次衆→定訳不明：Moshitsugishu (a person in charge of conveying some information to the shogun)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the concept of Banshu came to be applied to the status of samurais and their family ranking, and based on this concept job titles such as Shobanshu (officials who accompany the shogun), Otomoshu (a group that accompanied the shogun to Kyoto), Moshitsugishu (a person in charge of conveying messages to the shogun), and Naidanshu (judges) were created.</e>
<cmt>shortened a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the concept of Banshu came to be applied to the status of samurais and their family ranking, and based on this concept job titles such as Shobanshu (officials who accompany the shogun), Otomoshu (a group that accompanied the shogun to Kyoto), Moshitsugishu (a person in charge of conveying messages to the shogun), and Naidanshu (judges) were created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>江戸幕府においても室町幕府の制度は武家故実として尊重され、その一部は旗本・御家人制度にも導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Edo bakufu, the system of Muromachi bakufu was respected as one of the good practices of samurai family, and a part of it was transmitted to the Hatamoto (direct vassals of the shogun) /Gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) system</e>
<cmt>武家故実→定訳不明：good practice(s) of samurai familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in the Edo bakufu, the Muromachi system was retained as one of the good practices of samurai families, and part of it was used in the system of Hatamoto/Gokenin (direct vassals of the shogun and vassals of the shogunate, respectively).</e>
<cmt>articles, shortened for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the Edo bakufu, the Muromachi system was retained as one of the good practices of samurai families, and part of it was used in the system of Hatamoto/Gokenin (direct vassals of the shogun and vassals of the shogunate, respectively).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>すなわち、書院番・奏者番・使番などの将軍近侍・警固の役職に番衆制度が取り入れられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say, the Banshu system was incorporated into the valet and guard posts such as Shoinban (the castle guards), Sojaban (an official in charge of the ceremonies), Tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is to say, the Banshu system was incorporated into the valet and guard posts such as Shoinban (castle guards), Sojaban (an official in charge of ceremonies), and Tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield).</e>
<cmt>article usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is to say, the Banshu system was incorporated into the valet and guard posts such as Shoinban (castle guards), Sojaban (an official in charge of ceremonies), and Tsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>