<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>関東申次</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto moshitsugi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto moshitsugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto moshitsugi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>関東申次（かんとうもうしつぎ）は、関東執奏（かんとうしっそう）とも言い、鎌倉時代の朝廷に設けられた役職で鎌倉幕府側の六波羅探題とともに、朝廷・院政と幕府の間の連絡・意見調整を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto moshitsugi, also called Knato sisso, was a post introduced in the imperial court in the Kamakura period and played, together with the Rokuhara tandai on the Kamakura bakufu side, the role of doing communications and adjustments between the bakufu and the imperial court or the office of retired and priest Emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto moshitsugi, also called Knato sisso, was a post introduced in the imperial court during the Kamakura period and played, together with the Rokuhara tandai on the Kamakura bakufu side, the role of doing communications and adjustments between the bakufu and the imperial court or the office of retired priest Emperor</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto moshitsugi, also called Knato shisso, was a post introduced in the imperial court during the Kamakura period and played, together with the Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) on the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) side, the role of doing communications and adjustments between the bakufu and the imperial court or the government by cloistered emperors.</e>
<cmt>sisso→shisso幕府、六波羅探題の説明補足院政の訳変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>初めは幕府側の私的な指名を受けて特定の貴族が就任していたが、九条道家が失脚した寛元4年（1246年）以後は幕府による指名によって任命される正式な役職となり、源頼朝と婚姻関係（姪の嫁ぎ先）があった西園寺家当主による事実上の世襲となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, a specific court noble privately designated by the bakufu assumed the post, but after Iemichi KUJO lost his position in 1246, it became an official post designated by the bakufu and the post was hereditarily assumed effectevely by the Saionji family that had a marital relation with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (his niece entered the Saionji family through a marriage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, a specific court noble privately designated by the bakufu assumed the post, but after Iemichi KUJO lost his position in 1246, it became an official post designated by the bakufu and the post was hereditarily assumed effectevely by the Saionji family that had a marital relation with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (his niece entered the Saionji family through a marriage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, a specific court noble privately designated by the bakufu assumed the post, but after Michiie KUJO lost his position in 1246, it became an official post designated by the bakufu and the post was hereditarily assumed effectevely by the head of the Saionji family that had a marital relation with MINAMOTO no Yoritomo (his niece entered the Saionji family through a marriage).</e>
<cmt>Iemichi→Michiie「当主」を追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>承久の乱以後、原則として朝廷の重要事項の決定には関東申次を経由して幕府の許可を得る事になっており、大覚寺統と持明院統による皇位継承争いの激化に伴って、皇位継承問題や宮中の人事の是非も関東申次の一存がその帰趨を握るようになり、その権威は大きくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Jokyu War (the war in the Jokyu era), when the imperial court was going to decide an imprtant matter, it became basically necessary for the imperial court to get its persmission from the bakufu through the Kanto moshitsugi, and its power increased: For example, when the battle betwwen the Daikaku-ji line group and the Jimyo-in line group became serious concerning the imperial succession problem, the imperial succession problem or personel affairs in the imperial court became to be seriously affected by opinions of Kanto moshitsugi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Okyu War (the war in the Jokyu era), when the imperial court was going to decide an imprtant matter, it became basically necessary for the imperial court to get its persmission from the bakufu through the Kanto moshitsugi, and its power increased: For example, when the battle betwwen the Daikaku-ji line group and the Jimyo-in line group became serious concerning the imperial succession problem, the imperial succession problem or personel affairs in the imperial court became to be seriously affected by opinions of Kanto moshitsugi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Jokyu War (the war in the Jokyu era), when the imperial court was going to decide an imprtant matter, it became basically necessary for the imperial court to get its persmission from the bakufu through the Kanto moshitsugi, and its power increased: For example, when the battle betwwen Daikakuji-to (imperial lineage starting with Emperor Kameyama) and Jimyoin-to (imperial lineage from Emperor Gofukakusa to Emperor Gokomatsu) became serious concerning the imperial succession problem, the imperial succession problem or personel affairs in the imperial court became to be seriously affected by opinions of Kanto moshitsugi.</e>
<cmt>Okyu→Jokyu大覚寺統、持明院統を定訳に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>だが、西園寺家当主の個人的関係（大覚寺統側との不仲）から次第に持明院統よりの態度を取るようになると大覚寺統は申次を無視して幕府との直接交渉を展開するようになり、14世紀に入ると急速に求心力を失っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Kanto moshitsugi gradually sided more with the Jimyo-in line group due to a private relationship of the head of the Saionji family with the Daikaku-ji line group (the head was bad terms with the Daikaku-ji line group), the Daikaku-ji line group became to communicate with the bakufu directly, and Kanto moshitsugi came to lose its power rapidly when the 14-th century started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Kanto moshitsugi gradually sided more with the Jimyo-in line group due to a private relationship of the head of the Saionji family and the Daikaku-ji line group (the head was on bad terms with the Daikaku-ji line group), the Daikaku-ji line group came to communicate with the bakufu directly, and Kanto moshitsugi came to lose its power rapidly as the 14-th century started.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Kanto moshitsugi gradually sided more with Jimyoin-to due to a private relationship of the head of the Saionji family and Daikakuji-to (the head was on bad terms with Daikakuji-to), Daikakuji-to came to communicate with the bakufu directly, and Kanto moshitsugi came to lose its power rapidly as the 14-th century started.</e>
<cmt>大覚寺統、持明院統の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>やがて、大覚寺統の後醍醐天皇が鎌倉幕府を滅ぼすと西園寺家への風当たりが強くなり、最後の関東申次であった大納言西園寺公宗は謀反の疑いで処刑されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, after Daikaku-ji line Emperor Go-Daigo defeated the Kamakura bakufu, the Saionji family was criticized badly and Kinmune SAIONJI, who was in the Kanto moshitsugi post and in the Dainagon (Major Counselor) rank, was executed on suspicion of a rebelion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, after Daikaku-ji line Emperor Go-Daigo defeated the Kamakura bakufu, the Saionji family was badly criticized and Kinmune SAIONJI, who was in the Kanto moshitsugi post and in the Dainagon (Major Counselor) rank, was executed on suspicion of a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, after Daikakuji-to Emperor Godaigo defeated the Kamakura bakufu, the Saionji family was badly criticized, and Dainagon (chief councilor of state), Kinmune SAIONJI, who was the last Kanto moshitsugi, was executed on suspicion of a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>大覚寺統、後醍醐天皇の表記変更大納言を定訳に変更「最後の」を追記して、後半、書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 味っ子(id:17086), BAKU(id:55205), 水野白楓(id:22811), COCKY(id:19672), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>