<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>氏爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji no shaku (the annual promotion of one person from among the clans, the O, Minamoto, Fujiwara, Tachibana, and others from the sixth to the fifth rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji no shaku (the annual promotion of one person from among the clans, the O, Minamoto, Fujiwara, Tachibana, and others from the sixth to the fifth rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji no shaku</e>
<cmt>次セルに説明があるため補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>氏爵（うじのしゃく）とは、平安時代より、毎年正月6日に行われる叙位に際し、王氏、源氏、平氏、藤原氏、橘氏などの正六位上の者より、毎年1人ずつ従五位に叙すことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Uji no shaku refers to conferring a rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) on one person each annually from among persons ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) in the O clan, Minamoto clan, Taira clan, Fujiwara clan, Tachibana clan and others when the investiture was conducted on January 6 (old calendar) of every year from the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uji no shaku refers to conferring a rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) on one person each annually from among persons ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) in the O clan, Minamoto clan, Taira clan, Fujiwara clan, Tachibana clan and others when the investiture was conducted on January 6 (old calendar) of every year from the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uji no shaku refers to conferring a rank of Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) on one person each annually from among persons ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) in the O clan, Minamoto clan, Taira clan, Fujiwara clan, Tachibana clan and others when the investiture was conducted on January 6 (old calendar) of every year from the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従五位下に叙せられることを叙爵ということから、各氏に対する恒例人事として氏爵と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the conferment of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was called joshaku (conferring a peerage), the conferment of Jugoi was called uji no shaku as an annual promotion conducted to each clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the conferment of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was called joshaku (conferring a peerage), the conferment of Jugoi was called uji no shaku as an annual promotion conducted to each clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the conferment of Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) was called joshaku (conferring a peerage), this was called uji no shaku as an annual promotion conducted to each clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別称として氏挙（うじのきょ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its another name was uji no kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its other name was uji no kyo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its other name was uji no kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>氏爵は蔭位の制同様、有力氏族への特典であり、氏長者の推挙により、除目が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as Oni no sei (the automatic promotion of the persons at the age of 21, whose parents were from Imperial Prince to the fifth rank, or whose grandparents were upper than third rank), uji no shaku was a privilege to powerful clans, and Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) was held in accordance with a recommendation of uji no choja (the head of the clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as Oni no sei (the automatic promotion of the persons at the age of 21, whose parents were from Imperial Prince to the fifth rank, or whose grandparents were upper than third rank), uji no shaku was a privilege for powerful clans, and Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) was held in accordance with a recommendation of uji no choja (the head of the clan).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as Oni no sei (the automatic promotion of the persons at the age of 21, whose parents were from Imperial Prince to the fifth rank, or whose grandparents were upper than third rank), uji no shaku was a privilege for powerful clans, and Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) was held in accordance with a recommendation of uji no choja (the head of the clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>各氏とも正六位上の者は常に複数いるのが通常であり、新たな官途を得んとする者は、氏長者に対して申文という申請書を提出、氏長者がそのうちから適任者を選考したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each clan usually had more than one person ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) at any time, and it is considered that a person trying to newly acquire a post of government official submitted a request called moshibumi (general term for a request or petition submitted by a lower authority to a higher) to uji no choja, and uji no choja selected an eligible person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each clan usually had more than one person ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) at any time, and it is considered that a person trying to newly acquire a post of government official submitted a request called moshibumi (general term for a request or petition submitted by a lower authority to a higher) to uji no choja, and uji no choja selected an eligible person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each clan usually had more than one person ranked Shorokuinojo (Senior Sixth Rank, Upper Grade) at any time, and it is considered that a person trying to newly acquire a post of government official submitted a request called moshibumi (general term for a request or petition submitted by a lower authority to a higher) to uji no choja, and uji no choja selected an eligible person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そもそも、平安時代において氏長者の権限は低下傾向にあり、氏爵の制度に基づき同氏族への人事への影響力を有したことは、氏長者の権力が再強化されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first place, the authority of uji no choja was on a declining trend in the Heian period, and a possession of influence on personnel affairs for the said clans under the system of uji no shaku resulted in restrengthening of authority of uji no choja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first place, the authority of uji no choja was on a declining trend in the Heian period, and possessing influence on personnel affairs for the said clans under the system of uji no shaku resulted in restrengthening the authority of uji no choja.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first place, the authority of uji no choja was on a declining trend in the Heian period, and possessing influence on personnel affairs for the said clans under the system of uji no shaku resulted in restrengthening the authority of uji no choja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), MDR-SK(id:192066), Shimoxx(id:9332), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>