<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御家人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御家人（ごけにん）は、征夷大将軍の家人である武士の身分を指す語であるが、中世と近世では意味合いが異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin is a word used to describe the samurai retainers of the shogun but its meaning differed between the middle ages and early modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin is a word used to describe the samurai retainers of the shogun but its meaning differed between the middle ages and early modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin is a word used to describe the samurai retainers of the shogun but its meaning differed between the middle ages and early modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中世の御家人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin in the Middle Ages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin in the Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin in the Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代には、貴族や武家の棟梁に仕える武士を「家人」と呼んでおり、鎌倉幕府が成立すると鎌倉殿と主従関係を結び従者となった武士を、鎌倉殿への敬意を表す「御」をつけて御家人と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Heian period, samurai in the service of an aristocrat or samurai chief were called &apos;kenin&apos; (retainers) and with the establishment of the Kamakura period, those warriors who served as attendants to the Lord of Kamakura came to be called &apos;gokenin&apos; out of respect for the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>原文の「家人中世の家人」を「家人」に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Heian period, samurai in the service of an aristocrat or samurai chief were called &apos;kenin&apos; (retainers) and with the establishment of the Kamakura period, those warriors who served as attendants to the Lord of Kamakura came to be called &apos;gokenin&apos; out of respect for the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period, samurai in the service of an aristocrat or samurai chief were called &apos;kenin&apos; (retainers) and with the establishment of the Kamakura period, those warriors who served as attendants to the Lord of Kamakura came to be called &apos;gokenin&apos; out of respect for the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉殿御家人、関東御家人、鎮西御家人とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These retainers were also referred to as &apos;Kamakura-dono Gokenin&apos;, &apos;Kanto gokenin&apos; and &apos;Chinzei gokenin&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These retainers were also referred to as &apos;Kamakura-dono Gokenin&apos;, &apos;Kanto gokenin&apos; and &apos;Chinzei gokenin&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These retainers were also referred to as &apos;Kamakura-dono Gokenin,&apos; &apos;Kanto gokenin&apos; and &apos;Chinzei gokenin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>を&apos; にコンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>御家人の成立は、源頼朝による鎌倉幕府の樹立と密接に関連する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment of the position of gokenin was closely connected to the creation of the Kamakura Shogunate by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The establishment of the position of gokenin was closely connected to the creation of the Kamakura Shogunate by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The establishment of the position of gokenin was closely connected to the creation of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>流人だった頼朝の家人はごくわずかであり、1180年の挙兵の際、父源義朝の家人だった南関東の武士たちを「累代の御家人」として誘引した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exiled Yoritomo had very few retainers and when he raised an army in 1180, he drafted the south Kanto region samurai who served as retainers to his father, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, but the complex system of master-servant relationships that existed at the time meant that there were many who chose not to follow him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The exiled Yoritomo had very few retainers and when he raised an army in 1180, he drafted the south Kanto region samurai who served as retainers to his father, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, but the complex system of master-servant relationships that existed at the time meant that there were many who chose not to follow him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In exile Yoritomo had very few retainers to call upon so, when he raised an army in 1180, he attempted to entice samurai from the South Kanto region to serve as `inherited gokenin` on the basis they had previously served his father (MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo) as retainers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、当時の観念では主従関係は個々に結ぶものであり、頼朝に従属しない武士も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the relationships between leader and subordinate that existed previously were characterised by individual bonds and, many samurai subsequently elected not to subordinate themselves to Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後、鎌倉に東国政権を樹立すると、各地の武士が続々と頼朝支配下へと入っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As political power was later established in the east of Japan in Kamakura, samurai from throughout the country came under the control of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As political power was later established in the east of Japan in Kamakura, samurai from throughout the country came under the control of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the subsequent establishment in Kamakura of political power in the Eastern provinces, one by one the samurai in various provinces came under Yoritomo`s control.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>急速に増加した支配下の武士を秩序だって組織化するため、以仁王の令旨が利用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The order of Prince Mochihito was used to control and organize the rapidly increased number of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The order of Prince Mochihito was used to control and organize the rapidly increased number of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The order of Prince Mochihito was used to control and organize the rapidly increased number of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>すなわち、令旨に従って頼朝の支配に入った武士は、一律に「御家人」として組織された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those samurai who obeyed this order and came under the control of Yoritomo were all regarded as gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those samurai who obeyed this order and came under the control of Yoritomo were all regarded as gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those samurai who obeyed this order and came under the control of Yoritomo were all regarded as gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>治承・寿永の内乱期には、本拠である関東のみならず、各地の武士をより多く御家人として組織化する必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the turmoil of the Genpei War, it was necessary to designate as gokenin even more samurai from around the country as opposed to the shogunate&apos;s stronghold in the east of Japan, so all samurai who obeyed the order to kill members of the Taira clan were recognized as gokenin and many were given recognition and guarantees of ownership of their principal residences in an act known as Hontaku Ando.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the turmoil of the Genpei War, it was necessary to designate samurai as gokenin even more around the country as opposed to the shogunate&apos;s stronghold in the east of Japan, so all samurai who obeyed the order to kill members of the Taira clan were recognized as gokenin and many were given recognition and guarantees of ownership of their principal residences in an act known as Hontaku Ando.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the turmoil of the Jisho-Juei Civil War, it was necessary to designate samurai as gokenin (retainers of a shogun) even more around the country as opposed to the shogunate&apos;s stronghold in the east of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、平氏追討に従う武士を御家人として認定し本宅を安堵する「本宅安堵」が多く行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, those samurai who obeyed the order to kill members of the Taira clan were recognized as gokenin (shogun retainers) and many were given recognition and guarantees of ownership of their principal residences in an act known as `Hontaku Ando` (confirmation of a family&apos;s possession of its residence and the immediately adjacent land).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>関東の御家人の多くが頼朝の所領安堵を通じて御家人となっていたのに対し、本宅安堵の御家人に所領安堵する権限を有していたのは荘園領主たる本所や国司だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to the many Kanto region gokenin who achieved the status through Yoritomo&apos;s Shoryo Ando (act providing authorization of land ownership and guaranteeing feudal tenure), the Hontaku Ando retainers who had Shoryo Ando authority were all honjo or kokushi (provincial governors) who were lords of manors, so Yoritomo did not intrude on their jurisdiction but made them gokenin and guaranteed their status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the many Kanto region gokenin who achieved the status through Yoritomo&apos;s Shoryo Ando (act providing authorization of land ownership and guaranteeing feudal tenure), the Hontaku Ando retainers who had Shoryo Ando authority were all honjo or kokushi (provincial governors) who were lords of manors, so Yoritomo did not intrude on their jurisdiction but made them gokenin and guaranteed their status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the many gokenin (samurai retainers) in the Kanto region who achieved the status through Yoritomo&apos;s Shoryo Ando (act providing authorization of land ownership and guaranteeing feudal tenure), it was honjo (domain owning governors) or kokushi (provincial governors), and lords of manors, who had secure tenure of their territories and authority over the Hontaku Ando (residential tenure) retainers</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、頼朝は本所・国司の権限を侵すことなく、地位を安堵することで御家人を組織したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In light of this, Yoritomo did not impinge on the governors` jurisdiction but made retainers gokenin by guaranteeing status to these gokenin samurai retainers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>このように御家人は、鎌倉殿から直接、所領安堵を受ける御家人と、本宅安堵を受ける御家人に分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through these processes, gokenin consisted of those who received either Shoryo Ando rights or Hontaku Ando rights directly from the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through these processes, gokenin consisted of those who received either Shoryo Ando rights or Hontaku Ando rights directly from the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, gokenin retainers consisted of individuals in receipt of Shoryo Ando (feudal tenure) rights directly from the Lord of Kamakura or Hontaku Ando (residential tenure) rights.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>前者には東国に在住し、早い時期から頼朝に臣従していた者が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former resided in the east of Japan and consisted of many who had served Yoritomo from early on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former resided in the east of Japan and consisted of many who had served Yoritomo from early on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Previously many gokenin retainers resided in the eastern provinces of Japan and consisted of many veterans who had served under Yoritomo from early on.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>地頭に補任されるなどの厚い保護を受ける見返りに、有事には緊急に鎌倉に参集する義務を負っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While they received extensive protection such as being appointed manor lords, they were also duty bound to assemble in Kamakura during times of emergency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While they received extensive protection such as being appointed manor lords, they were also duty bound to assemble in Kamakura during times of emergency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While gokenin samurai retainers received extensive patronage (eg. being appointed manor lords), they were also obligated to muster in Kamakura during times of emergency.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>後者は、令制国を単位に編成され、「国御家人」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter were organized based on province and called &apos;kuni gokenin&apos; (literally meaning provincial retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter were organized based on province and called &apos;kuni gokenin&apos; (literally meaning provincial retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter gokenin samurai retainers were organized on province allegiances and called &apos;kuni gokenin&apos; (lit. provincial retainers).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>治承・寿永内乱終結後は、大番役への催促を通じて各地武士の国御家人化が進められ、西国武士の多くがこれにより国御家人へ編成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Genpei War, samurai throughout Japan were made kuni gokenin as a result of the drive toward obanyaku (guard service in Kyoto), and many warriors from western Japan became gokenin as a result of this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Genpei War, samurai throughout Japan were made kuni gokenin as a result of the drive toward obanyaku (guard service in Kyoto), and many warriors from western Japan became gokenin as a result of this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Jisho-Juei Civil War, samurai throughout Japan were made kuni gokenin (provincial samurai retainers) following service as obanyaku (guards in Kyoto), and many warriors from western Japan followed this path to becoming gokenin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>国御家人を統括するのは守護の任務であり、大番役を催促するとともに、大番役勤仕の御家人名簿を幕府へ提出していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shugo (Governor) of each province was responsible for the control of kuni gokenin, and would submit to the shogunate a register of gokenin who carried out obanyaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shugo (Governor) of each province was responsible for the control of kuni gokenin, and would submit to the shogunate a register of gokenin who carried out obanyaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shugo (Governor) of each province was responsible for the control of kuni gokenin (provincial samurai retainers), and submitted to the shogunate a register of gokenin who carried out obanyaku (Kyoto guard duty) as requests for guards increased.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>御家人は、上記のとおり直接所領安堵・本宅安堵の区分のほか、広大な所領を持ち数カ国の守護を兼ねる有力御家人から、ごく狭い所領しか持たない零細な御家人まで大小さまざまな規模であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As well as being classified according to Shoryo Ando or Hontaku Ando as described above, gokenin ranged from influential individuals with large territories and a position as shugo of a powerful province to insignificant gokenin with only small territories, but all were treated equally as subordinate to the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As well as being classified according to Shoryo Ando or Hontaku Ando as described above, gokenin ranged from influential individuals with large territories and a position as shugo of a powerful province to insignificant gokenin with only small territories, but all were treated equally as subordinate to the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As well as being classified according to Shoryo Ando (feudal tenure) or Hontaku Ando (residence tenure) as described above, the gokenin (samurai retainers) ranged from influential individuals with large territories holding shugo (governor) status in more than one province through to the other end of the spectrum: insignificant gokenin with only small territories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、鎌倉殿に等しく従属する家人として身分上は同格として扱われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, all were treated equally as subordinates of the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>頼朝以来、御家人相互の主従関係・支配関係は厳しく禁じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the time of Yoritomo, master-servant relationships and dominance-subservience relationships between gokenin were strictly forbidden, with direct relationships to the imperial court particularly harshly prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the time of Yoritomo, master-servant relationships and dominance-subservience relationships between gokenin were strictly forbidden, with direct relationships to the imperial court particularly harshly prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the time of Yoritomo, master-servant or dominant-subservient relationships between gokenin (samurai retainers) were strictly forbidden.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>特に朝廷と直接の関係を結ぶことは厳禁された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Direct relationships with the imperial court were in particular, strictly prohibited.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>御恩と奉公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goon to Hoko (Reward and Service)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goon to Hoko (Reward and Service)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Go-on to Hoko (Patronage and Service)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>御家人が鎌倉殿から受ける恩恵は、安堵と給与である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin received reassurances and a salary from the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin received reassurances and a salary from the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin (samurai retainers) received patronage and stipends from the Lord of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>安堵には前述のごとく所領安堵と本宅安堵がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These reassurances consisted of the above-mentioned Shoryo Ando and Hontaku Ando.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These reassurances consisted of the above-mentioned Shoryo Ando and Hontaku Ando.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Patronage consisted of the above-mentioned Shoryo Ando (feudal tenure) and Hontaku Ando (residential tenure).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>給与は、謀反追討などに勲功を挙げた御家人に対し、謀反人の所領などを新領として給与することである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin who killed traitors to the shogunate would be granted the traitor&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin who killed traitors to the shogunate would be granted the traitor&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin who killed traitors to the shogunate would be granted the traitor&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>所領安堵および新領給与は、地頭への補任という形で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A gokenin would be appointed as manor lord when receiving land through the Shoryo Ando act or when granted a new territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A gokenin would be appointed as manor lord when receiving land through the Shoryo Ando act or when granted a new territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin (samurai retainer) were appointed as lords of a manor when the beneficiary of land grants forming an act of Shoryo Ando (feudal tenure) or when granted a land holdings.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>承久の乱後には、後鳥羽上皇方の大量の所領が勲功を挙げた御家人へ新領給与されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Jokyu War, Retired Emperor Go-Toba&apos;s vast territory was granted to those gokenin who had served with distinction, and this was also carried out by appointing these individuals as manor lords which were called &apos;Shinpo Jito&apos; (literally meaning New Manor Lords).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Jokyu War, Retired Emperor Go-Toba&apos;s vast territory was granted to those gokenin who had served with distinction, and this was also carried out by appointing these individuals as manor lords which were called &apos;Shinpo Jito&apos; (literally meaning New Manor Lords).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Jokyu War, Retired Emperor Gotoba&apos;s vast territory was granted to gokenin who had served with distinction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この新領給与も地頭補任の形でなされており、この時に補任された地頭を特に新補地頭という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The granting of this new territory took the form of appointing lords to rule the manors within the territory, and those appointed were called &apos;Shinpo Jito&apos; (literally New Manor Lords).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>御家人は恩恵を受ける見返りとして、鎌倉殿へ軍事と公事の奉仕義務を負う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In return for remuneration, gokenin had a duty to serve the Lord of Kamakura both militarily and politically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In return for remuneration, gokenin had a duty to serve the Lord of Kamakura both militarily and politically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In return for patronage, gokenin (samurai retainers) had a duty to serve the Lord of Kamakura both militarily and politically.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>軍事とは、戦時の従軍参加はもちろんのこと、平時においての京都・鎌倉の大番役や異国警護役などの役を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to joining the ranks of the army during wartime, military service also included serving as obanyaku in Kyoto and Kamakura or guard service in other provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to joining the ranks of the army during wartime, military service also included serving as obanyaku in Kyoto and Kamakura or guard service in other provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to joining the ranks of the army during wartime, military service also included serving as obanyaku in Kyoto and Kamakura or guard service in other provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>公事は関東御公事（みくうじ）ともいい、幕府から御家人に賦課された米銭の納入義務のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Political service was also referred to as &apos;Kanto Mikuji&apos; and consisted of collecting the taxes of rice and money levied on gokenin by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Political service was also referred to as &apos;Kanto Mikuji&apos; and consisted of collecting the taxes of rice and money levied on gokenin by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Political service was also referred to as &apos;Kanto Mikuji&apos; and consisted of collecting the taxes of rice and money levied on gokenin by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="33">
<j>こうした鎌倉殿と御家人間の互恵関係を御恩と奉公という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This reciprocal relationship between the Lord of Kamakura and gokenin was called &apos;goon to hoko&apos; (literally meaning reward and service).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This reciprocal relationship between the Lord of Kamakura and gokenin was called &apos;goon to hoko&apos; (literally meaning reward and service).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This reciprocal relationship between the Lord of Kamakura and gokenin was called &apos;goon to hoko&apos; (literally meaning reward and service).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉中期以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Mid-Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Mid-Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the mid-Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>史料から検出される御家人の数は決して多くはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Few gokenin have been identified in historical sources.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>関東諸国を除き、一か国あたり概ね10名程度にとどまっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of Kanto Provinces, approximately ten gokenin (samurai retainers) have been identified in a few provinces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>関東諸国は他地域に比べて御家人が非常に多い地域であり、最も多い武蔵国の約80名をはじめ、各国とも数十名の御家人が在住していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to other areas, the provinces of the Kanto region had far more gokenin, with the highest count of approximately 80 identified in Musashi Province and several dozen known to reside in each of the other provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to other areas, the provinces of the Kanto region had far more gokenin, with the highest count of approximately 80 identified in Musashi Province and several dozen known to reside in each of the other provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to other areas, the provinces of the Kanto region had far more gokenin, with the highest count (approximately 80) identified in Musashi Province and several dozen known to reside in each of the other provinces.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1275年の史料によれば、全国の御家人の総数は約480名であり、御家人は武士の中でも非常に限られた階層だったことを物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A source from 1275 states the total number of Gokenin in the country was 480 and that their numbers were tightly restricted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A source from 1275 states the total number of Gokenin in the country was 480 and that their numbers were tightly restricted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a historical source dated from the year 1275, the total number of gokenin in the entire country was about 480 which indicates gokenin numbers were tightly restricted even within the elite samurai class.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>いっぽう、鎌倉幕府と御恩・奉公の契約関係にない「非御家人」の数も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there were also many so-called &apos;higokenin&apos; who did not have a contractual reward-and-service relationship with the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there were also many so-called &apos;higokenin&apos; who did not have a contractual reward-and-service relationship with the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there were also many so-called &apos;higokenin&apos; (non-samurai retainers) who did not have a contractual reward-for-service relationship with the Kamakura bakufu (shogunate).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>文永の役という対外危機に伴い、幕府は非御家人への指揮権も得ることになったが、幕府に従わぬ武士も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate obtained directive power over the higokenin as a result of the Mongol invasions of Japan but there were many samurai who did not obey the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate obtained directive power over the higokenin as a result of the Mongol invasions of Japan but there were many samurai who did not obey the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu (shogunate) obtained direct power over the higokenin (non-samurai retainers) as a result of the Mongol invasions of Japan however, there were many samurai who did not obey the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>永仁の徳政令以後は、非御家人に対する御家人への優遇策は顕著となり、非御家人の中には悪党となって幕府や公家・寺社への反抗を行う者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the Einin no Tokuseirei (a debt cancellation decree), the preferential treatment of gokenin over higokeinin became obvious and led to the development of rogue elements among higokenin who rebelled against the shogunate, imperial court nobles and religious institutions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the Einin no Tokuseirei (a debt cancellation decree), the preferential treatment of gokenin over higokeinin became obvious and led to the development of rogue elements among higokenin who rebelled against the shogunate, imperial court nobles and religious institutions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the Einin no Tokuseirei (debt cancellation decree), the preferential treatment of gokenin over higokenin became pronounced and led to rogue elements among higokenin rebelling against the bakufu, imperial court nobles and religious institutions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>鎌倉幕府の勢力が強まるにともなって、御家人は武士の身分を表す言葉となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Kamakura Shogunate became ever more powerful, the word &apos;gokenin&apos; came to mean &apos;samurai&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Kamakura Shogunate became ever more powerful, the word &apos;gokenin&apos; came to mean &apos;samurai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Kamakura bakufu became ever more powerful, the word &apos;gokenin&apos; came to mean &apos;samurai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufuピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>室町幕府は御家人制度を採らなかったが、御家人は将軍直参の武士の身分を示す用語としてしばしば用いられ、戦国時代 (日本)には転じて一部の戦国大名の家臣を指す言葉となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi Shogunate did not adopt the gokenin system but the word &apos;gokenin&apos; was frequently used for those samurai who were immediate followers of the shogun, and became used to refer to retainers of daimyo (feudal lords) during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi Shogunate did not adopt the gokenin system but the word &apos;gokenin&apos; was frequently used for those samurai who were immediate followers of the shogun, and became used to refer to retainers of daimyo (feudal lords) during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu did not adopt the gokenin (samurai retainer) system but the word &apos;gokenin&apos; was frequently used for those samurai who were immediate followers of the shogun, and was a term used to refer to retainers of some daimyo (feudal lords) during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>室町幕府・戦国大名の御家人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin of the Muromachi Shogunate and Warring States Period Daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin of the Muromachi Shogunate and Warring States Period Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin (samurai retainers) associated with daimyo (warrior generals) of the Muromachi bakufu and Warring States Period</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>鎌倉幕府の勢力が強まるにともなって、御家人は武士の身分を表す言葉となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Kamakura Shogunate became ever more powerful, the word &apos;gokenin&apos; came to mean &apos;samurai&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Kamakura Shogunate became ever more powerful, the word &apos;gokenin&apos; came to mean &apos;samurai&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Kamakura bakufu became ever more powerful, the word &apos;gokenin&apos; came to mean &apos;samurai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufuピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>室町幕府は御家人制度を採らなかったが、奉公衆を指して、古文書学上は、御家人という用語が、しばしば登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi Shogunate did not adopt the gokenin system but the word is frequently used as a paleographical term to refer to hokoshu (immediate retainers of the shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi Shogunate did not adopt the gokenin system but the word is frequently used as a paleographical term to refer to hokoshu (immediate retainers of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu did not adopt the gokenin system but the word is frequently used as a paleographical term to refer to hokoshu (immediate retainers of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>歴史教科書では、室町幕府の将軍家と、主従関係にある者を指して、御家人という用語は、使っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &apos;Gokenin&apos; is not used in history textbooks as a term for individuals who had a master-servant relationship with the Muromachi Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;Gokenin&apos; is not used in history textbooks as a term for individuals who had a master-servant relationship with the Muromachi Shogunate family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word Gokenin is not used in history textbooks as a term for individuals who had a master-servant relationship with the shogun family of Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>原文に「」のない&apos;を削除Muromachi Shogunate family→shogun family of Muromachi bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>御家人は将軍直参の武士の身分を示す用語としてしばしば用いられ、戦国時代 (日本)には転じて戦国大名の家臣を指す言葉として使用されることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is frequently used to refer to those samurai who were immediate followers of the shogun, and became used to refer to retainers of daimyo (feudal lords) during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is frequently used to refer to those samurai who were immediate followers of the shogun, and came to be used to refer to retainers of daimyo (feudal lords) during the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is frequently used to refer to those samurai who were direct vassals of the shogun, but also came to be used to refer to retainers of daimyo (feudal lords) during the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>特に著名なものとしては、武田氏・毛利氏などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly well-known Gokenin came from the 武田氏 and 毛利氏.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly well-known Gokenin came from the 武田氏 and 毛利氏.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly well-known Gokenin (samurai retainers) hailed from the Takeda and Mori clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>史料引用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical Source</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical Source</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical source</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>『勤年役御家人　二貫七百文　萩原弥兵門尉』云々と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kinnenyaku Gokenin, 2-kan 700-mon, Yaheimonju HAGIWARA&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kinnenyaku Gokenin, 2-kan 700-mon, Yaheimonju HAGIWARA&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">`Kinnenyaku (low rank) Gokenin, 2-kan 700-mon (pay rate), Yaheimonju HAGIWARA (name)` and so on.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>永禄6年（1513年）甲斐国恵林寺検地帳より引用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cited from a 1513 land survey list of Erin-ji Temple in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cited from a 1513 land survey list of Erin-ji Temple in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An entry in a land survey list in the year 1513 at Erin-ji Temple in Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この記述「御家人」について、新潟大学教授矢田俊は、地侍化した惣百姓と、武田氏のもともとの家臣であったものを区別するために行ったものであると説明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Professor Satoshi YADA of Niigata University explains that here &apos;Gokenin&apos; is used to differentiate village officials (sobyakusho) who became ji-zamurai (lords of smaller rural domains) and retainers who originally served the 武田氏.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Professor Satoshi YADA of Niigata University explains that here &apos;Gokenin&apos; is used to differentiate village officials (sobyakusho) who became ji-zamurai (lords of smaller rural domains) and retainers who originally served the 武田氏.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Professor Satoshi YADA of Niigata University explains that in this extracted reference, the term &apos;Gokenin&apos; was used to differentiate village officials (sobyakusho) who became ji-zamurai (lords of smaller rural domains) from retainers who originally served the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>近世の御家人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin of the Early Modern Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin of the Early Modern Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin of the early modern period</e>
<cmt>語頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他ファイルと合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>江戸時代には、御家人は知行が1万石未満の徳川将軍家の直参家臣団（直臣）のうち、特に御目見得以下（将軍に直接謁見できない）の家格に位置付けられた者を指す用語となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, the term &apos;gokenin&apos; became used to refer to immediate retainers to the Tokugawa Shogun family who held a fief worth less than 10,000-koku, especially those individuals not eligible to be granted an audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, the term &apos;gokenin&apos; came to be used to refer to immediate retainers to the Tokugawa Shogun family who held a fief worth less than 10,000-koku, especially those individuals not eligible to be granted an audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period the term &apos;Gokenin&apos; came refer to immediate retainers of the Tokugawa Shogun family who held lands of less than 10,000 koku (1 koku = 4.96 bushels): in particular, individuals lacking the rank to be granted a direct audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>御家人に対して、御目見得以上の家格の直参を旗本という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those retainers who were eligible to have an audience with the shogun were called &apos;hatamoto&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those retainers who were eligible to have an audience with the shogun were called &apos;hatamoto&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those retainers who were privileged enough to be granted face-to-face audiences with the shogun were called &apos;hatamoto.&apos; (direct retainers, lit `flag bearer`)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>近世の御家人の多くは、戦場においては徒士の武士、平時においては与力・同心として下級官吏としての職務や警備を務めた人々である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Gokenin of the early modern period were samurai who fought on foot during battle and held low-level policing positions as yoriki and doshin during peacetime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Gokenin of the early modern period were samurai who fought on foot during battle and held low-level policing positions as yoriki and doshin during peacetime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Gokenin (samurai retainers) in more recent times were foot-soldier samurai but, during peace time were low ranking government functionaries or held police roles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>御家人は、原則として、乗り物や、馬に乗ることは許されず、家に玄関を設けることができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was generally not permitted for Gokenin to ride vehicles or horses, or have an entrance hall on their house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was generally not permitted for Gokenin to ride vehicles or horses, or have an entrance hall on their house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin (samurai retainers) were generally not permitted to ride on vehicles or horses, or have an entrance hall (genkan) to their house.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>ここでいう乗り物には、扉のない篭は含まれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such vehicles did not included doorless palanquins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such vehicles did not included doorless palanquins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The definition of `vehicles` however, did not included doorless palanquins.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>例外として、奉行所の与力となると、馬上が許されることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriki of magistrates offices were exempt and permitted to ride horses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriki of magistrates offices were exempt and permitted to ride horses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Police attached to the magistrates offices were exempted from this rule and were permitted to ride horses.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>有能な御家人は旗本の就く上位の役職に登用されることもあり、原則として3代続けて旗本の役職に就任すれば、旗本の家格になりうる資格を得られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were situations in which skilled Gokenin were promoted to high positions usually held by hatamoto, and it was generally the case that a gokenin family would be granted hatamoto status if three generations were successively appointed to hatamoto positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were situations in which skilled Gokenin were promoted to high positions usually held by hatamoto, and it was generally the case that a gokenin family would be granted hatamoto status if three generations were successively appointed to hatamoto positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were situations in which skilled Gokenin were promoted to high positions usually held by Hatamoto (direct retainers), and it was generally the case that a gokenin family would be granted hatamoto status if three successive generations were appointed to hatamoto positions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>家格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family Status</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family Status</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family status</e>
<cmt>語頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>御家人の家格は譜代（ふだい）、二半場（にはんば）、抱席（かかえせき）の3つにわかれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status of a Gokenin family could be &apos;fudai&apos; (heredity daimyo), nihanba (the middle rank between fudai and kakaeseki) or kakaeseki (hereditary daimyo who were promoted in the periods of the fifth shogun and the succeeding shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of a Gokenin family could be &apos;fudai&apos; (heredity daimyo), nihanba (the middle rank between fudai and kakaeseki) or kakaeseki (hereditary daimyo who were promoted in the periods of the fifth shogun and the succeeding shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive generations of Gokenin families were divided into 3 classes: &apos;fudai&apos; (heredity daimyo), nihanba (the middle rank between fudai and kakaeseki), or kakaeseki (hereditary daimyo who were promoted in the periods of the fifth shogun and the succeeding shogun).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>譜代は江戸幕府草創の初代徳川家康から四代徳川家綱の時代に将軍家に与力・同心として仕えた経験のある者の子孫である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudai were the descendents of those who had served the Shogun family as yoriki or doshin from when the Edo Shogunate was founded by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA until the fourth shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, kakaeseki were families that were newly promoted to the status of Gokenin, and nihanba families occupied a status intermediate between the two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudai were the descendents of those who had served the Shogun family as yoriki or doshin from when the Edo Shogunate was founded by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA until the fourth shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, kakaeseki were families that were newly promoted to the status of Gokenin, and nihanba families occupied a status intermediate between the two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudai were the descendents of Gokenin who had served the Shogun family as police from when the Edo bakufu (shogunate) was founded by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA until the fourth shogun, Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>抱席（抱入（かかえいれ）とも）はそれ以降に新たに御家人身分に登用された者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">`Kakaeseki` (also called kakaeire) families were those families had been newly promoted to the status of Gokenin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>二半場はその中間の家格である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The so called `Nihanba` families occupied a status intermediate between the two preceding statuses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、譜代の中で、特に由緒ある者は、譜代席と呼ばれ、江戸城中に自分の席を持つことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among fudai, those with a long and distinguished history were called &apos;fudaiseki&apos; and held their own seats within Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among fudai, those with a long and distinguished history were called &apos;fudaiseki&apos; and held their own seats within Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudai who had a long and distinguished family history were called &apos;fudaiseki,&apos; and they had their own seats within Edo-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>譜代と二半場は、無役（幕府の公職に任ぜられていない状態）であっても、俸禄の支給を受け、惣領に家督を相続させて身分と俸禄を伝えることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even when fudai and nihanba did not hold an official position within the shogunate, they would receive a stipend and were granted inherited rights over their estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even when fudai and nihanba did not hold an official position within the shogunate, they would receive a stipend and were granted inherited rights over their estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when the Fudai and Nihanba ranked families did not hold an official position within the shogunate, they would receive a stipend and were granted inheritance rights to their estates.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>家督相続や叙任にあたっては、御家人は旗本のように将軍に謁見することはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereditary and appointed gokenin were not permitted to have an audience with the shogun as hatamoto could, whereas only fudaiseki were allowed an audience with superiors within the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereditary and appointed gokenin were not permitted to have an audience with the shogun as hatamoto could, whereas only fudaiseki were allowed an audience with superiors within the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Individuals inheriting or appointed to gokenin status were not granted audiences with the shogun (as a hatamoto (direct retainer) could expect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>譜代席のみは城中で若年寄や頭などの上司に謁見して申し渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of `Fudaiseki` (hereditary ranked families) were bestowed the title during a face-to-face meetings with superiors within the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>譜代席未満の御家人は、城中ではなく自分の所属する機関で、申し渡しがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin who were ranked lower than fudaizeki were not allowed an audience with superiors within the castle but were permitted to do so within their own institutions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin who were ranked lower than fudaizeki were not allowed an audience with superiors within the castle but were permitted to do so within their own institutions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin were ranked below Fudaizeki (hereditary retainers) and not granted audiences with superiors within the castle but, were granted the status within their own groupings.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>譜代と二半場に対して、抱席は一代限りの奉公で隠居や死去によって御家人身分を失うのが原則であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As opposed to fudai and nibanha, kakaeseki were restricted to serve for only a single generation and it was generally the case that the status of gokenin would be lost following retirement or death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As opposed to fudai and nibanha, kakaeseki were restricted to serve for only a single generation and it was generally the case that the status of gokenin would be lost following retirement or death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrasting with gokenin retainers holding Fudai and Nibanha status were the Kakaeseki retainers who were restricted to serving for one single generation and, usually relinquished the gokenin status upon retirement or death.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし、この原則は、次第に崩れていき、町奉行所の与力組頭（筆頭与力）のように、一代抱席でありながら、馬上が許され、230石以上の俸禄を受け、惣領に家督を相続させて身分と俸禄を伝えることが常態化していたポストもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this general rule was gradually eroded, and there were posts such as the leaders of yoriki at town magistrate&apos;s offices, known as Yoriki Kumigashira (a head of police), which were single generation kakaeseki but were also permitted to ride on horseback, received stipends of over 230-koku and were allowed to pass their status on to their successors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this general rule gradually eroded, and there were posts such as the leaders of yoriki at town magistrate&apos;s offices, known as Yoriki Kumigashira (a head of police), which were single generation kakaeseki but were also permitted to ride on horseback, received stipends of over 230-koku and were allowed to pass their status on to their successors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this rule of thumb waned over time and there were some posts (eg. a town magistrate&apos;s police chief) who were granted single generation kakaeseki status, but were also permitted to ride on horseback, received stipends of over 230-koku and were allowed to pass on their status to successors.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>これに限らず、抱席身分も実際には、隠居や死去したときは子などの相続人に相当する近親者が、新規取り立ての名目で身分と俸禄を継承していたため、江戸時代後期になると、富裕な町人や農民が困窮した御家人の名目上の養子の身分を金銭で買い取って、御家人身分を獲得することが広く行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only this, but in reality the status of kakaeseki and the applicable stipends were inherited by successors of those who retired or passed away through new titles, so in the latter part of the Edo period it became common for wealthy merchants and farmers to become gokenin paying to become the adopted son of impoverished gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only this, but in reality the status of kakaeseki and the applicable stipends were inherited by successors of those who retired or passed away through new titles, so in the latter part of the Edo period it became common for wealthy merchants and farmers to become gokenin paying to become the adopted son of impoverished gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only this, but in reality the status and stipends of Kakaeseki gokenin retainers were inherited by successors upon retirement or death, so in the latter part of the Edo period it became common for wealthy merchants and farmers to buy their way into gokenin ranks by paying to become the adopted son of an impoverished gokenin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>売買される御家人身分は御家人株と呼ばれ、家格によって定められた継承することができる役ごとに、相場が生まれるほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such traded gokenin titles were known as &apos;gokeninkabu&apos;, and market price was determined by whether or not the family status could be inherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such traded gokenin titles were known as &apos;gokeninkabu&apos;, and market price was determined by whether or not the family status could be inherited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A market for Gokenin titles was known as &apos;gokeninkabu&apos; (lit. Gokenin shares) with a market price determined by whether or not the family status could passed on to other generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>知行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fiefs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fiefs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fiefs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>御家人の大半は、知行地を持たない30俵以上、80俵取り未満の蔵米取で占められ、知行地を持つ者でも200石取り程度の小身であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The majority of gokenin were made up of those who did not hold fiefs but held kuramaidori (retainer ranks) of between 30-koku and 80-koku, while those who held fiefs had only small holdings of up to 200-koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The majority of gokenin were made up of those who did not hold fiefs but held kuramaidori (retainer ranks) of between 30-koku and 80-koku, while those who held fiefs had only small holdings of up to 200-koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The majority of gokenin were generally made up of individuals who either did not hold fiefs but held the rights to 30 to 80-koku in rice or, small land owners holding up to 200 koku of land.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>ただし、旗本と御家人の定義は直参のうち謁見できるかどうかであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, hatamoto and gokenin were defined by whether or not they had the right to an audience with the shogun, and family status did not dictate the value of the stipend as those hatamoto entitled the smallest stipends received only 50-koku - less than most gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, hatamoto and gokenin were defined by whether or not they had the right to an audience with the shogun, and family status did not dictate the value of the stipend as those hatamoto entitled the smallest stipends received only 50-koku - less than most gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, hatamoto (direct retainers) and gokenin (samurai retainers) were differentiated by whether or not they were granted audiences with the shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>家禄（俸禄）の高低は家格の決定に関係がなく、旗本で最も小禄であった者は50俵程度で、御家人の大半よりも少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The value of the stipend did not dictate family status: hatamoto entitled to the smallest stipends received only 50 koku - less than most gokenin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>200石（俵）取り以上の御家人もいたが、400石を越える御家人は存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were gokenin with estates of greater than 200-koku in value but none who&apos;s estates valued more than 400-koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were gokenin with estates of greater than 200-koku in value but none who&apos;s estates valued more than 400-koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some gokenin had estates exceeding 200 koku in value but none exceeded more than 400 koku.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>江戸時代中期以降は、地方知行制が崩れ、蔵米取に移行したり旗本に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the mid-Edo period, the fief system began to disappear and there came to be almost no gokenin who held fiefs as those who did became ranked according to kuramaidori or promoted to hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the mid-Edo period, the fief system began to disappear and there came to be almost no gokenin who held fiefs as those who did became ranked according to kuramaidori or promoted to hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the middle part of the Edo period, the fief system began to collapse and there was a shift to rights to rice (`kuramaidori`).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>そのため、知行地を持つ御家人はほとんどいなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin holding lands in the regions largely disappeared and in their place hatamoto were promoted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>御家人の多くは、江戸時代中期以降、非常に窮乏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many gokenin fell into severe poverty from the mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many gokenin fell into severe poverty from the mid-Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many gokenin found themselves slip into severe poverty from the middle of the Edo period onwards.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>諸藩の藩士は、家禄が100石（俵）あれば一応、安定した恵まれた生活を送れたとされるのに対し、幕府の御家人は100石（俵）取りであっても生活はかなり苦しかったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to the retainers who served the domains of Japan who could live a fairly comfortable lifestyle with a 100-koku stipend, gokenin belonging to the shogunate would have led a hard life even with a stipend of the same value.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the retainers who served the domains of Japan who could live a fairly comfortable lifestyle with a 100-koku stipend, gokenin belonging to the shogunate would have led a hard life even with a stipend of the same value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retainers serving in various domains of Japan who could live a fairly comfortable lifestyle with a 100 koku stipend, however, by comparison a gokenin belonging to the bakufu would have led a hard life even with a stipend of the same value.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>御家人は大都市の江戸に定住していたために常に都市の物価高に悩まされ、また諸藩では御家人と同じ程度の家禄を受けている微禄な藩士たちは給人地と呼ばれる農地を給付され、それを耕す半農生活で家計を支えることができたが、都市部の御家人にはそのような手段も取ることができなかったことが理由としてあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One reason given for this is that gokenin who resided in the large city of Edo were subjected to high urban prices, whereas domain retainers who received a stipend equally as small as gokenin would also be granted farmland on which they would work part-time in order to earn extra income - an option that was not available to gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One reason given for this is that gokenin who resided in the large city of Edo were subjected to high urban prices, whereas domain retainers who received a stipend equally as small as gokenin would also be granted farmland on which they would work part-time in order to earn extra income - an option that was not available to gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin who resided in metropolis of Edo faced high urban prices, whereas retainers in regional domains who received a small stipend on par with gokenin was also granted farmland on which they would work part-time to generate extra income - an option not available to gokenin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>窮乏した御家人たちは、内職を公然と行って家計を支えることが一般的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impoverished gokenin generally earned extra income by openly holding side jobs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impoverished gokenin generally earned extra income by openly holding side jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was common for impoverished gokenin to supplement the family income by secretly holding side jobs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), Albambot(id:195288), Tetsusaburou(id:58913), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), G.miyanomori(id:9984), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 梁山泊智多星呉用(id:127114), Information Center(id:151860), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), VolkovBot(id:105371), Michey.M(id:906), 玄史生(id:43670), 海衛士(id:19229), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), トホホ川(id:50502), Ponsaku(id:31417), 伏儀(id:142093), Safkan(id:423), Junger(id:10282), Kanbun(id:37114), Ssudo2002(id:22689), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>