<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>放免</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>放免（ほうめん）とは日本の令外官である検非違使の下部（しもべ）を指す名称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homen was the name of a shimobe (miscellaneous servants and attendants) of the kebiishi (officials with judicial and police powers) which were Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen was the name of Shimobe (miscellaneous servants and attendants) of Kebiishi (a official with judicial and police power) which was Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>大文字化、冠詞 削除、名詞の数を合わせるため一部単数化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen was the name of Shimobe (miscellaneous servants and attendants) of Kebiishi (a official with judicial and police power) which was Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「放免囚人」の義。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homen means &apos;released prisoner.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen means &apos;released prisoner.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen means &apos;released prisoner.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>検非違使庁の下級刑吏として、実際に犯罪者を探索し、捕縛したり、拷問や獄守を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Homen served as a minor officer in Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief), and practically took charge of searching, capturing, and torturing the criminals and a prison guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Homen served as a lower-level executioner in Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief), and practically took charge of searching, capturing, and torturing criminals; and guarding a prison.</e>
<cmt>「下級刑吏」を変更、冠詞削除、日本語に合わせ一部文変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Homen served as a lower-level executioner in Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief), and practically took charge of searching, capturing, and torturing criminals; and guarding a prison.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>放免の存在は、文献によると少なくとも11世紀前半には確実に遡って確認することが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existence of Homen can be surely confirmed in the literature at least back in the early 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existence of Homen can be surely confirmed in a document dated back to at least the early 11th century.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更、「文献」変更、一部文変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existence of Homen can be surely confirmed in a document dated back to at least the early 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元々は犯罪者の情報収集などの捜査の便を考慮し、前科のある者を検非違使庁に採用したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Kebiishicho recruited a person with a criminal record in view of convenience of investigation such as collecting information on criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Kebiishicho recruited a person with a criminal record in view of convenience of investigation such as collecting information on criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, Kebiishicho recruited a person with a criminal record in view of convenience of investigation such as collecting information on criminals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中には放免になった後も犯罪を起こしたりする者がいたようである（『今昔物語集』巻二十九「放免共、強盗ト為リ人ノ家ニ入リテ補ヘラルル語」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some homens committed crimes even after they became the homen (&quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; [The Tale of Times Now Past], volume 29, &apos;The tale of a homen who broke in a house as a robbery and was arrested.&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Homen committed crimes even after they became Homen (&quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; [The Tale of Times Now Past], volume 29, &apos;The tale of Homen who broke in a house to rob and were arrested.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>大文字化、単数化、冠詞削除,文を自然な流れになる様一部変更、複数化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Homen committed crimes even after they became Homen (&quot;Konjaku Monogatari Shu&quot; [The Tale of Times Now Past], volume 29, &apos;The tale of Homen who broke in a house to rob and were arrested.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>彼らの容姿には著しい特徴が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their appearance had remarkable characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their appearance had remarkable characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their appearance had remarkable characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当時は一般的でなかった口髭、顎鬚を伸ばし、特殊な祭礼や一部の女子にしか許されていなかった「綾羅錦繍」、「摺衣」と呼ばれる模様の付いた衣服を身につけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had mustache and beard, which were not common in that time, and wore clothes with patterns called &apos;Ryorakinshu&apos; (embroidered fine clothes) or &apos;Suriginu (Surigoromo)&apos; (plant dyeing cloth) that were allowed to wear only in the special rites and festivals or only a part of women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had mustaches and beards, which were not common at that time, and wore clothes with patterns called &apos;Ryorakinshu&apos; (embroidered fine clothes) or &apos;Suriginu (Surigoromo)&apos; (plant dyeing cloth) that were allowed to wear only in the special rites and festivals or only for a part of women.</e>
<cmt>複数化、前置詞変更、前置詞挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had mustaches and beards, which were not common at that time, and wore clothes with patterns called &apos;Ryorakinshu&apos; (embroidered fine clothes) or &apos;Suriginu (Surigoromo)&apos; (plant dyeing cloth) that were allowed to wear only in the special rites and festivals or only for a part of women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この模様については、「臓物出来するところの物を染め摺り文を成した衣袴」と同時代史料に記されており、佐藤進一は検非違使の得分を示唆していると解釈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This pattern was described as &apos;kinubakama (clothes and divided skirt) with stenciled patterns dyed by products from giblets&apos; in the historical material about that period, and Shinichi SATO interpreted that this description suggests the profit of kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>「臓物出来するところの物」は定訳不明でしたので、「臓物から出来た物」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These patterns were described as &apos;kinubakama (clothes and divided skirt) with stenciled patterns dyed by products from giblets in the historical material about that period, and Shinichi SATO interpretes that this description suggests the share of kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>複数化、アポストロフィ削除、現在形化、「得分」変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These patterns were described as &apos;kinubakama (clothes and divided skirt) with stenciled patterns dyed by products from giblets in the historical material about that period, and Shinichi SATO interpretes that this description suggests the share of kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、七曲がりの自然木の鉾を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, homen had a pike made with seven crooked natural wood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Homen had a pike made with seven crooked natural wood.</e>
<cmt>大文字化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Homen had a pike made with seven crooked natural wood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この鉾については僧兵の使用する撮棒などとの関連も指摘されており、いずれも穢れに対する呪術的な意味を持つものと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pike is thought to have some relation to a saibo (wooden stick as a weapon) used by the sohei (warrior monk), and both are estimated to have a magical meaning against kegare (impurity.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pike is thought to have some relation to a saibo (wooden stick as a weapon) used by the sohei (warrior monk), and both are assumed to have a magical meaning against impurity.</e>
<cmt>「けがれ」削除、「推定」変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pike is thought to have some relation to a saibo (wooden stick as a weapon) used by the sohei (warrior monk), and both are assumed to have a magical meaning against impurity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>これらの常民と区別される外見については、非人のため禁忌を憚らないためであるとする同時代史料があり、非人と見なされていたことが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the historical material about that period describing that these appearances to be distinguished from normal people were because they were hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank in the Japanese society, often ex-convicts or vagrants) and do not avoid taboos, so it can be understood that they were considered as hinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a historical material about that period describing that these appearances to be distinguished from normal people were because they were hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank in the Japanese society, often ex-convicts or vagrants) and did not avoid taboos, so it can be understood that they were assumed as hinin.</e>
<cmt>冠詞変更、過去形化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a historical material about that period describing that these appearances to be distinguished from normal people were because they were hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank in the Japanese society, often ex-convicts or vagrants) and did not avoid taboos, so it can be understood that they were assumed as hinin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ただし当時の非人は後世とは異なり、単に差別される対象ではなく畏怖される存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, hinin at that period is different from hinin of after ages, and they were not only the subject to be discriminated but also the awesome existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, hinin at that period were different from hinin of after ages, and they were not only the subject to be discriminated but also the awesome existence.</e>
<cmt>過去形化、複数化</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, hinin at that period were different from hinin of after ages, and they were not only the subject to be discriminated but also the awesome existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kotoito(id:21045), Tribot(id:186681), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>