<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>妻壁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gable Wall</e>
<cmt>翻訳漏れを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gable Wall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>妻壁（つまかべ）とは、妻側の妻梁以上の外装の壁を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gable wall is an exterior wall placed on the part of the gable side or pediment above the gable beam.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A gable wall is an exterior wall above the gable beam of a building.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A gable wall is an exterior wall above the gable beam of a building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、流通業界における輸送機器の壁の呼び名としても用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also used for the walls of a transport machine in the distribution industry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used to refer to the walls of transport machinery in the distribution industry.</e>
<cmt>・「for」→「to refer to」・「a」を削除・「machine」→「machinery」・注：本記事の「車両」の項は英語に適用しないと思います</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also used to refer to the walls of transport machinery in the distribution industry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>入母屋造りや切妻屋根等、棟付近に達する壁のあるものに見られ、宝形造や寄棟造の屋根にはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be seen in the structures that have a wall (walls) extended near the beam, such as Irimoya-zukuri style (an architectural style with a half-hipped roof) and Kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof), and it can not be seen in those with Hogyo-zukuri style (pyramidal style) and Yosemune-zukuri style (hipped roof style) roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gable walls can be seen in structures that have walls which reach the ridge such as Irimoya-zukuri style (a hip-and-gable roof) and Kirizuma-zukuri style (a gabled roof) buildings, but cannot be seen in those with the Hogyo-zukuri style (pyramidal style) or Yosemune-zukuri style (hipped roof style) roofs.</e>
<cmt>・「It」→「Gable walls」・「the」を削除・「a wall (walls)」→「walls」・「extended near the beam,」→「which reach the ridge」・「an architectural style with a half-hipped roof」→「a hip-and-gable roof」・「(an architectural style with a gabled roof」→「a gabled roof」・「buildings」を追加・「and it」→「but」・「and」→「or」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gable walls can be seen in structures that have walls which reach the ridge such as Irimoya-zukuri style (a hip-and-gable roof) and Kirizuma-yane style (a gabled roof) buildings, but cannot be seen in those with the Hogyo-zukuri style (pyramidal style) or Yosemune-zukuri style (hipped roof style) roofs.</e>
<cmt>原文に即して「Kirizuma-yane」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>形状は三角形である例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form is triangular in most cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many examples for which the shape is triangular.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many examples for which the shape is triangular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これに破風板などを含めて破風といいこれらを飾る意匠のことを妻飾り（つまかざり）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This style of wall including gable is called &apos;hafu&apos; and the design decorating it is called tsumakazari (embellishment of gable pediments).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a hafu-ita (bargeboard) is included, it is known as &quot;hafu&quot; and the designs adorning it are called tsumakazari.</e>
<cmt>・破風板 = gable ×・破風板 = bargeboard・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a hafu-ita (bargeboard) is included, it is known as &quot;hafu&quot; and the designs adorning it are called tsumakazari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>木構造の建築では、大壁の場合、漆喰やモルタルなどを塗り篭める塗壁（建築）や、木板や金属板などを張る張り壁、で仕上げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case of a large-sized wall of an architecture with wooden structure, coated walls are finished by plastering or cement plastering, and boarded walls by laying boards or metallic sheet.</e>
<cmt>塗り壁→定訳不明：coated wallsとしました。 張り壁→定訳不明：boarded wallsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of wooden buildings, large walls are plastered walls coated with lime plaster and mortar, or covered wooden boards or metal sheets.</e>
<cmt>・漆喰 = lime plaster・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of wooden buildings, large walls are plastered walls coated with lime plaster and mortar, or covered wooden boards or metal sheets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>屋根裏が閉鎖的な空間の場合は換気口が開けられ、屋根裏に人の立ち入ることができる空間や吹き抜けがある場合は窓やベランダ等が併設されることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a space where the attic is hermetically closed, a ventilation hatch is made, while if there is a space accessible by man or it is a vaulted attic, sometimes a window (windows) or balcony among others are also installed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the attic is a closed space, a ventilation hatch is opened, and when the attic is an accessible space or is vaulted, features such as windows and balconies may be installed.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the attic is a closed space, a ventilation hatch is opened, and when the attic is an accessible space or is vaulted, features such as windows and balconies may be installed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>日本の伝統的な建築のものとして、寺院建築では真壁 (建築)に仕上げることがあり、書院造等では木連格子（きづれごうし）とすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese traditional style of temple architecture is often finished with Makabe style, and in the Shoin-zukuri style (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a tokonoma) or others, sometimes kizure goshi (the gable pediments filled with boardbacked, crisscross lattice) is adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As traditional Japanese buildings, the gable walls of temples may be finished in the shinkabe style (the framing for the wall is set between pillars that remain exposed on both sides when the plastered wall is finished), and buildings in styles such as the Shoin-zukuri style (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a tokonoma) may have their gable walls finished using kizure goshi (gable pediments filled with boardbacked, crisscross lattice).</e>
<cmt>・真壁 = Makabe style ×・真壁 = Shinkabe style・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As traditional Japanese buildings, the gable walls of temples may be finished in the shinkabe style (the framing for the wall is set between pillars that remain exposed on both sides when the plastered wall is finished), and buildings in styles such as the Shoin-zukuri style (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a tokonoma) may have their gable walls finished using kizure goshi (gable pediments filled with boardbacked, crisscross lattice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>茅葺や藁葺のかまどを併設する農家や茶室建築の入母屋屋根の妻は、壁の変わりに開口し格子を設けて「煙ぬき」という換気口とすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gable of irimoya style roof used for farm houses and tea house architecture often install furnace thatched with grass or straw, secures an opening section with a crisscross lattice to make it as an air vent called &apos;kemurinuki ventilator.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「煙ぬき」→定訳不明：&apos;kemurinuki ventilator&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gables of irimoya style roofs used for farmhouse and tea house buildings with an attached furnace thatched with grass or straw have an opening made, a lattice attached and a kemurinuki ventilation chimney added.</e>
<cmt>・かまど = furnace thatched ×・かまど = cooking range・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gables of irimoya style roofs used for farmhouse and tea house buildings with an attached furnace thatched with grass or straw sometimes have an opening with a lattice for ventilation, called a &apos;kemurinuki,&apos; instead of the wall.</e>
<cmt>文意に合うよう書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>車両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rolling stock</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vehicles</e>
<cmt>・「Rolling stock」→「Vehicles」・注：本記事の「車両」の項は英語に適用しないと思います</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vehicles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>車両の進行・後退する方向（ナンバープレート (自動車)の付いている前後やストップランプの付いている側）にある壁を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means the wall facing the traveling direction or backing direction of a wagon (in case of a car, the front face or rear face, which carries the identification plate or the side on which the stop lump is installed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gable walls are the walls at the front and rear (where the number plates and brake lights are located) of vehicles.</e>
<cmt>注：原文を反映するように再翻訳しましたが、本記事の「車両」の項は英語に適用しないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gable walls are the walls at the front and rear (where the number plates and brake lights are located) of vehicles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>別名、妻側（つまがわ）・横手方向（よこてほうこう）とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, they are also called tumagawa (gable side) or yokotehoko (side direction).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called tumagawa (gable side) or yokotehoko (side direction).</e>
<cmt>・「Thus,」を削除・ペリオドを追加・注：本記事の「車両」の項は英語に適用しないと思います</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called tumagawa (gable side) or yokotehoko (side direction).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>物流業界では各種コンテナ・貨物自動車等の箱型の輸送機器の説明や表現方法として、よく用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the distribution industry, it is frequently used to explain or indicate box-shaped transportation machines, such as various type of containers and motor tracks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term is frequently used in the distribution industry to explain or indicate box-shaped transportation machines such as various types of container and trucks.</e>
<cmt>・再構成しました・「it」→「the term」・コンマを削除・「type」→「types」・「containers」→「container」・「motor tracks」→「trucks」・注：本記事の「車両」の項は英語に適用しないと思います</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term is frequently used in the distribution industry to explain or indicate box-shaped transportation machines such as various types of container and trucks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Loveless(id:129239), Rusk(id:9895), 夢の散歩(id:214093), Ik1973(id:293582), Goki(id:7107), Ws227(id:208643), ムカイ(id:72972), いそう規格(id:245135), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>