<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>金井沢碑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanaizawano-hi (Kanaizawano Stone Monument)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanaizawa no hi (Kanaizawa Stone Monument in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanaizawa no hi (Kanaizawa Stone Monument in Gunma Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>金井沢碑（かないざわのひ）は、群馬県高崎市山名町にある古碑であり、国の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanaizawano-hi is an ancient monument located in Yamana-cho, Takasaki City and designated as a historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanaizawa no hi is an ancient stone monument located in Yamana Town, Takasaki City and designated as a historic site.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanaizawa no hi is an ancient stone monument located in Yamana Town, Takasaki City and designated as a historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山ノ上碑、多胡碑とともに「上野三碑」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two other stone monuments - Yamanoue-hi and Tago-hi - in Gunma, and they are called generically, &quot;three stone monuments in Kozuke&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with Yama no Ue no hi (the monument on the mountain top) and Tago hi (Tago Stone Monument), they are collectively called &apos;Kozuke Sanpi&apos; (Three Monuments in Kozuke Province).</e>
<cmt>表現を合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with Yama no Ue no hi (the monument on the mountain top) and Tago hi (Tago Stone Monument), they are collectively called &apos;Kozuke Sanpi&apos; (Three Monuments in Kozuke Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>神亀3年(726年）2月29日建碑。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monument was built on February 29, 726.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monument was built on April 10, 726.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monument was built on April 10, 726.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>高さ110センチメートル、幅70センチメートル、厚さ65センチメートルの輝石安山岩に9行112文字が刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One hundred and twelve characters of nine lines are engraved on the pyroxene andesite 110cm in height, 70cm in width and 65cm in thickness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">112 characters of 9 lines are engraved on the pyroxene andesite 110 cm in height, 70 cm in width and 65 cm in thickness.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">112 characters of 9 lines are engraved on the pyroxene andesite 110 cm in height, 70 cm in width and 65 cm in thickness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>台石にはめこまれ、文はその表面に陰刻される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was set into the stone pedestal and the epigraph is engraved with incised characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was set into the stone pedestal and the epigraph is engraved with incised characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was set into the stone pedestal and the epigraph is engraved with incised characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>書体は古い隷書体の特徴が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The font type has characteristics of old Reisho Style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The font type has characteristics of old Reisho Style (clerical script).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The font type has characteristics of old Reisho Style (clerical script).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代の中ごろに出土し、かつては小川のほとりで付近の農家の洗濯板として使用されていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was unearthed in the middle of the Edo period and is said to have once been used as a washing board by a small river by farmers in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was unearthed in the middle of the Edo period and is said to have once been used as a washing board at the bank of a small river by farmers in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was unearthed in the middle of the Edo period and is said to have once been used as a washing board at the bank of a small river by farmers in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>その内容は、上野国群馬郡下賛（下佐野）郷高田里の三家（ミヤケ、屯倉）の子孫が、七世父母、現在の父母等のために天地に誓願して作る旨が記され、祖先の菩提と父母の安穏を仏に祈願している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The content shows that the descendants of the Miyake family in Takada-no-sato, Shimosanu (Shimosano)-go, Gunma-gun, Kozuke Province would build the monument, with prayers to heaven and earth, for the past and present parents and also prayed to Buddha for the salvation of their ancestors and safety of their parents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content shows that the descendants of the ruling family of the Miyake (Imperial-controlled territory) in Takada no sato, Shimosanu-go (also known as Shimosano-go), Gunma County, Kozuke Province would build the monument to pray to Buddha for the salvation of their ancestors and safety of their parents by pledging to the heaven and earth, for the parents of the seventh generation, those of the time, and so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The content shows that the descendants of the ruling family of the Miyake (Imperial-controlled territory) in Takada no sato, Shimosanu-go (also known as Shimosano-go), Gunma County, Kozuke Province would build the monument to pray to Buddha for the salvation of their ancestors and safety of their parents by pledging to the heaven and earth, for the parents of the seventh generation, those of the time, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ここから、郷里制の施行と奈良時代における民間への仏教信仰の浸透を知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These things tell us about the enforcement of Gori (Hometown) System and how Buddhism belief prevailed in people in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These things tell us about the enforcement of Gori-sei (Township-neighborhood system) and how Buddhism belief prevailed in people in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These things tell us about the enforcement of Gori-sei (Township-neighborhood system) and how Buddhism belief prevailed in people in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>金井沢碑に刻まれる「三家」は山ノ上碑に刻まれる「佐野三家」であると考えられてきたが、最近の発掘調査により史料上知られていないミヤケの存在が確実視されているため、「三家」が「佐野三家」とは別のミヤケである可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Miyake&quot; engraved on Kanaizawano-hi has been thought to be &quot;Sanomiyake&quot;, but with recent excavation research ensuring the existence of Miyake not found in historical records, &quot;Miiyake&quot; can be a different Miyake from &quot;Sanomiyake&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyake&apos; engraved on Kanaizawa no hi has been thought to be &apos;Sano no Miyake&apos; (ruling family of Miyake in Sano), but with recent excavation research ensuring the existence of Miyake not found in historical records, &apos;Miyake&apos; can be a different Miyake from &apos;Sano no Miyake.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyake&apos; engraved on Kanaizawa no hi has been thought to be &apos;Sano no Miyake&apos; (ruling family of Miyake in Sano), but with recent excavation research ensuring the existence of Miyake not found in historical records, &apos;Miyake&apos; can be a different Miyake from &apos;Sano no Miyake.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>1921年（大正10年）3月3日には国の史跡、1954年（昭和29年）には国の特別史跡に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1921 it was designated as a national historic site, and in 1954 a special national historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 3, 1921 it was designated as a national historic site, and in 1954 a special national historic site.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「3月3日には」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 3, 1921 it was designated as a national historic site, and in 1954 a special national historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), ReijiYamashina(id:29567), Nnh(id:474), 甲斐援隊員G(id:38820), Shin-改(id:9914), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>