<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaya (long house)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaya (long house)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaya (long house)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長屋（ながや）とは集合住宅の一形態である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaya is a style of collective housing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaya is a style of collective housing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaya is a style of collective housing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>定義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Definition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Definition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Definition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>複数の住戸が水平方向に連なり、壁を共有する物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a building where two or more dwelling units are placed horizonatally, with walls shared with those of adjacent units.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a building in which two or more dwelling units are situated horizontally, having walls shared with those of the adjacent units.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a building in which two or more dwelling units are situated horizontally, having walls shared with those of the adjacent units.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>あるいは（同じことだが）1棟の建物を水平方向に区分し、それぞれ独立した住戸とした物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or it is a building that is divided into a number of areas, with each of them used as a dwelling unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alternatively, it&apos;s a building divided into a number of areas, with each such area being used as a dwelling unit.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alternatively, it&apos;s a building divided horizontally into a number of areas, with each such area being used as a dwelling unit.</e>
<cmt>水平方向に　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それぞれの住戸に玄関が付いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An entrance is provided for each of the dwelling units.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An entrance is provided for each of the dwelling units.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An entrance is provided for each of the dwelling units.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>長屋の条件として必ず求められることは、各戸の玄関が直接接道など外界に接しており、その玄関を他の住戸と共有していてはならないことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An essential condition for a nagaya is that the entrance to each dwelling unit must be connected directly with an external road and must not be shared with those to other dwelling units.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An essential condition for a nagaya is that the entrance to each dwelling unit must connect directly to an external path, and this path must not be shared with those to the other dwelling units.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An essential condition for a nagaya is that the entrance to each dwelling unit must connect directly to an external path, and this entrance must not be shared with those to the other dwelling units.</e>
<cmt>「玄関を共有してはならない」ので、entrance　と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>近年ではテラスハウスと呼ぶことも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, it is often called terasu-hausu (a terrace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, it is often called terasu-hausu (a terrace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, it is often called a terrace house.</e>
<cmt>英語のみの表現でよいかと解釈しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>イギリスなどヨーロッパによく見られるタイプでセミデタッチト・ハウス（semi-detached house）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Semi-detached houses are often seen in Europe, for example, in England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Semi-detached houses are often seen in Europe, such as in England.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Semi-detached houses are often seen in Europe, such as in England.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1棟の建物（多くは2階建て）を中央で区分し、2軒の家が壁の一方向を共有する形式で、敷地や建設費を節約できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A building (mostly two-story) is divided into two parts at the middle of it, and one of the walls of each of the two parts, or tow houses, is shared with each other, enabling the necessary land space and building cost to be saved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A building (generally of two-story configuration) is divided into two parts at the midpoint, and one of the walls of each of the two parts, as in a row house, is shared by adjoining dwellings, thus economizing on land usage and the cost of construction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A building (generally of two-story configuration) is divided into two parts at the midpoint, and one of the walls of each of the two parts, as in a row house, is shared by adjoining dwellings, thus economizing on land usage and the cost of construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>二戸一棟とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called a building consiting of two houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also thought of as a building that comprises two houses.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also thought of as a building that comprises two houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（一戸建てはデタッチト・ハウス）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(An independently built house is called a detached house.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(An independently built house is called a detached house.)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(An independently built house is called a detached house.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>玄関を共有し、内部が複数の住戸に区分されている場合は、長屋とは区別される（アパートや下宿屋、寮のタイプ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A building where an entrance is shared with more than one dwelling unist is differentiated from a nagaya (is called, an apartment, boarding house or dormitory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A building where an entrance is shared with more than one dwelling unit is differentiated from a nagaya (it&apos;s called an apartment, boarding house or dormitory).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A building where an entrance is shared with more than one dwelling unit is differentiated from a nagaya (it&apos;s called an apartment, boarding house or dormitory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>2階建て以上で垂直方向にも区分したものは、アパート、マンションなどと呼ばれ、区別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A two or more story building in which dwelling units are divided vertially as well are aslo differentiated as an apato (in Japnaese pronouciation; actaully, an apartment) or a manshon (in Japnaese pronouciation; actaully, a condominium).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A building of two or more stories in which dwelling units are also divided vertically is further differentiated as an apato (in Japanese pronunciation; actually, an apartment) or a mansion (in Japanese usage; actually, a condominium).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A building of two or more stories in which dwelling units are also divided vertically is further differentiated as an apato (in Japanese pronunciation; actually, an apartment) or a mansion (in Japanese usage; in fact, a condominium).</e>
<cmt>actually→in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="14">
<j>日本における長屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaya in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaya in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaya in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>長屋という言葉で一般にイメージされるのは、下町の狭い路地に面して建てられた木造の住宅であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A general image of the term of nagaya would be wooden residential buildings built along narrow streets of shitamachi (the traditional shopping, entertaiment and residential districts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A general image of the term of nagaya would be a wooden residential building built along the narrow street of a shitamachi (the traditional shopping, entertainment and residential district).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term nagaya normally calls into mind a wooden residential building built along a narrow street of a shitamachi (the traditional shopping, entertainment and residential district).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>歴史的には、伝統的な都市住居として広く見られる形態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, the style was widely used for traditional urban residential buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, the style was widely used for traditional urban residential buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, the style was widely used for traditional urban residential buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>城郭においては、多門櫓と称す長屋を塁上に造り、防衛の建物として威力を発揮しながら一般の住宅としても活躍していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In castles, a nagaya called Tamon-yagura Turret was built on a mound, and was aslo used as general dwelling places while playing the role of a defensive building effectively as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In castles, a nagaya called the Tamon-yagura (turret) was built on a mound; it was used as a general dwelling place while effectively serving as a point of defense.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In castles, a nagaya called the Tamon-yagura (turret) was built on a mound and was used as ordinary residential houses while effectively serving as a point of defense.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>とくに御殿女中の居住施設は長局とよばれ、江戸城大奥では、戸別にトイレ・キッチン付二階建てで全長80mもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the dwelling facility for goten jochu (palace maids) was called Nagatsubone (attendants&apos; quarters), and the one in the innner palace of Edo Castle was a two-story 80 m-long buiding where a lavatory and kitchen were provided for each of the dwelling units.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the dwelling facility for the goten jochu (palace maids) was called the Nagatsubone (attendants&apos; quarters), and the one in the inner palace of Edo Castle was a two-story, 80-meter-long building in which a lavatory and kitchen were provided for each of the dwelling units.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the dwelling facility for the goten jochu (palace maids) was called the Nagatsubone (attendants&apos; quarters), and the one in the inner palace of Edo Castle was a two-story, 80-meter-long building in which a lavatory and kitchen were provided for each of the dwelling units.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>江戸時代の長屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaya in the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaya in the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaya in the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>江戸時代において、中層以上の商家などは表通りに独立した店を構えていたが、それ以外の町人、職人などはほとんどが裏町の長屋に借家住まいであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, merchants in middle or higher classes had their stores facing main streets, but most of the other merchants and craftmen rented a dwelling in a nagaya located along a back street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, merchants of the middle class or higher had their stores facing main streets, but most of the other merchants and craftsmen rented dwellings in nagaya located along the back streets.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, merchants of the middle class or higher had their stores facing main streets, but most of the other merchants and craftsmen rented dwellings in nagaya located along the back streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、大名屋敷の敷地内にも長屋が造られ、家臣らを住まわせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A nagaya was also built in the premises of daimyo yashiki (mansion of a feudal lord) as the dwellings of the vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A nagaya was also built on the premises of daimyo yashiki (mansion of a feudal lord) to accommodate the dwellings of vassals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A nagaya was also built on the premises of daimyo yashiki (mansion of a feudal lord) to accommodate the dwellings of vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に江戸時代、裏町に見られた長屋は落語や川柳の格好の題材になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the nagaya placed along back streets in the Edo period presented materials quite suited for rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) or Senryu (comic haiku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, the nagaya situated along back streets of the Edo period presented material very well suited for rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) or Senryu (comic haiku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, the nagaya situated along back streets of the Edo period presented material very well suited for rakugo (traditional comic storytelling) or senryu (comic haiku).</e>
<cmt>senryu　を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>密集した中で生活していたが、人情こまやかな生活を送っていた場合もみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they lived in a densely populated condition, there were also people who lived their lives in a heart-warming atmosphere.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they lived in a densely populated condition, there were also people who lived their lives in an atmosphere of warmth and hospitality.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they lived in a densely populated condition, people seemed to have lived in an atmosphere of warmth and hospitality.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸時代の長屋はほとんど平屋建てで、玄関を入るとすぐ台所であり、部屋はせいぜい2部屋程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the nagaya in the Edo period were one story building, and there was a kitchen immediated following an entrance, with only two rooms at the most.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the nagaya during the Edo period were one-story buildings in which there was a kitchen immediately following an entrance, with just two rooms at the most.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the nagaya during the Edo period were one-story buildings in which there was a kitchen immediately following an entrance, with just two rooms at the most.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>路地に共同トイレがあり、風呂は無い（火事の危険性が高く、防災上の理由で禁止されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lavatory to be shared was placed a nearby alley, and no bath was provided (the provision of a bath was prohibited for the possibility that a fire might be started there and for disaster prevention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lavatory to be shared was found in a nearby alley, but no bath was provided (the provision of a bath was prohibited due to the possibility that a fire might erupt and cause a disaster).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lavatory to be shared was found in a nearby alley, but no bath was provided (the provision of a bath was prohibited due to the possibility that a fire might erupt and cause a disaster).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>入浴は銭湯でする）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For bathing, public bathhouses were used.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For bathing, public bathhouses were used.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For bathing, public bathhouses were used.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>水は共同の井戸が有った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public wells were provided for water.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public wells were provided for water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public wells were provided for water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは地下水をくみ上げるものではなく、神田上水から供給されていた水道水の取水口である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they were for using underground water but intakes of water from Kanda Josui (Kanda water supply).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they weren&apos;t for the use of underground water but for the intake of water from Kanda Josui (Kanda water supply).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they weren&apos;t for the use of underground water but for the intake of water from Kanda Josui (Kanda water supply).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>そのため水が桶に溜まるまで多少の時間がかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, at a well, it took some time before enough water was stored in the tub.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, at a well it would take some time before the tub would be sufficiently full of water.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, at a well it would take some time before the tub would be sufficiently full of water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>それを待つ間に近所の者で世間話をする「井戸端会議」という言葉が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the waiting time, persons around the well chatted, generating the expression of &quot;idobata-kaigi (literally, a meeting beside a well).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the waiting time, persons around the well would chat, thus giving rise to the expression &quot;idobata-kaigi (literally, a meeting beside a well).&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While waiting, neighbors would chat, thus giving rise to the expression &quot;idobata-kaigi (literally, a meeting beside a well).&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションマークを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>江戸時代に「大家」と言えば、所有者（家主）とは異なり、住民の家賃を集めたり、管理を任されている者のことであった（現代で言うところの不動産管理会社に近い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Oya (literally, a big house)&quot; for a nagaya in the Edo period did not indicate the owner of the nagaya but a person who was entrusted with the work to collect the rents and to manage the nagaya (nearly equivalent to an estate-managing company at present).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;oya (big house)&quot; for a nagaya in the Edo period didn&apos;t indicate the owner of the nagaya but a person entrusted with the work of collecting rents and managing the nagaya (roughly equivalent to a property-management company of the present day).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;oya (big house)&quot; for a nagaya in the Edo period didn&apos;t indicate the owner of the nagaya but a person entrusted with the work of collecting rents and managing the nagaya (roughly equivalent to a property-management company of the present day).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>住民の相談相手になったり、何かと世話を焼いたり場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oya often became an adviser to a dweller or dwellers or als often handled a dweller&apos;s (or dwellers&apos;) affairs earnestly..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oya often became an adviser to a dweller or dwellers and would handle a dweller&apos;s (or dwellers&apos;) affairs earnestly.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oya often became an adviser to a dweller or dwellers and would handle a dweller&apos;s (or dwellers&apos;) affairs earnestly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>落語ではよく「大家といえば親も同然」などという台詞が聞かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the expression of &quot;Oya is almost the same as a parent&quot; frequently apeears in rakugo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the expression &quot;an oya is nearly the same as a parent&quot; frequently appears in rakugo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the expression &quot;an oya is nearly the same as a parent&quot; frequently appears in rakugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>狭い長屋暮らしに大量の所有物を収納するスペースは無く、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a dwelling unit of a nagaya, no space storing lots of belongings was available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a dwelling unit of a nagaya, there was insufficient space to store many belongings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was insufficient space to store many belongings in the small living space of nagaya.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>長屋には様々な生活物品を貸し出す損料屋（レンタル業に相当）が発達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, sonryo-ya (lender, equivalent to today&apos;s renting business) that lent various things necessary for living to persons dwelling in nagaya developed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus there emerged the sonryo-ya (a lender, equivalent to today&apos;s renting business), who lent various things necessary for living to persons dwelling in nagaya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, there emerged the sonryo-ya (a lender, equivalent to today&apos;s renting business), who lent various things necessary for living to people living in nagaya.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アポストロフィを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>1月分の家賃は1日の手間賃で稼げる程安かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rent of such a dwelling was so inexpensive that earnings for a day coud pay it</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rent for such a dwelling was so inexpensive that a day&apos;s earnings could cover it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rent for such a dwelling was so inexpensive that a day&apos;s earnings could cover it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="37">
<j>九尺二間の棟割長屋、割長屋（スタブ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyu(9)shaku-ni(2)ken-no munewai-nagaya, wari-nagaya (stub)</e>
<cmt>スタブ： stub としましたが、意味が理解できておりませんので、或いはstabかも知れません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyu(9)shaku-ni(2)ken-no munewai-nagaya, wari-nagaya (stub)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyu(9)shaku-ni(2)ken-no munewai-nagaya, wari-nagaya (stub)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>間口が9尺（約2.7m）、奥行きが2間（約3.6m）の住戸を連ねた長屋を九尺二間の長屋と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This term indicates a nagaya where dwelling unts, each ocupying a space of Kyu(9)shaku (approx. 2.7 m) in frontage by ni(2)ken (approx. 3.6 m) in depth, were placed in a row.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This term indicates a nagaya in which the dwelling units, each occupying a space of Kyu(9)shaku (approx. 2.7 m) in frontage by ni(2)ken (approx. 3.6 m) in depth, were placed in a row.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This term indicates a nagaya in which the dwelling units, each occupying a space of Kyu(9)shaku (approx. 2.7 m) in frontage by ni(2)ken (approx. 3.6 m) in depth, were placed in a row.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="39">
<j>九尺二間の長屋とは畳6畳の部屋とほぼ同規模の大きさでありそのうち約1畳半を土間として、4畳半を部屋として区画されているのが一般的。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The space of a dwelling unit in Kyu(9)shaku-ni(2)ken-no nagaya was almost equal to that of a six-tatami mat room, and generally, the space corresponding to approx. 1.5-tatami mat was used for earth floor and the remaining 4.5-tatami mat space for the room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The space of a dwelling unit in Kyu(9)shaku-ni(2)ken-no nagaya was roughly equal to that of a six-tatami-mat room, and generally the space corresponding to approximately 1.5-tatami mats was used for the earthen floor and the remaining 4.5-tatami-mat space was used for the room.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The space of a dwelling unit in Kyu(9)shaku-ni(2)ken-no nagaya was roughly equal to that of a six-tatami-mat room, and generally the space corresponding to approximately 1.5-tatami mats was used for the earthen floor and the remaining 4.5-tatami-mat space was used for the room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="40">
<j>棟割長屋は本来、建物の棟方向に壁を造って前後に区分してしまう物を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The munewari-nagaya indicated the nagaya in which walls were placed in the middle of the building in the direction of the ridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The munewari-nagaya indicated the nagaya in which walls were placed in the middle of the building parallel with the ridgeline.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munewari-nagaya indicated nagaya in which walls were placed in the direction parallel with the row, dividing the building into front and rear.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>このタイプでは開口部が一方向しか取れないため、通風・採光に難があり、住環境は劣悪になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the nagaya of this type, the area that can be opened outside was avaialbe only on one side. Therefore, it has shortcomings in ventilation and in taking natural light in, making the living environments unpreferrable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the nagaya of this type, only one side of the structure could be opened to the outside. Therefore, it had shortcomings in terms of ventilation as well as access to natural light, making the living environment undesirable.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the nagaya of this type, only one side of the structure had an entrance to the outside, leading to poor living environment due to a lack of poor air circulation and light.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="42">
<j>江戸時代の江戸の長屋は火事になってもすぐに再建できるようにと、板葺きに下見板という焼屋造りとよばれるつくりが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the nagaya in Edo in the Edo period, many yakiya-zukuri (flamable) style buildings with a single roof and clapboards were built to make it easier to reconstruct them after they were burnt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the nagaya in Edo of the Edo period, many yakiya-zukuri (flammable)-style buildings with shingled roofs and clapboards were built, so that in the event of a fire they could easily be replaced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the nagaya in Edo of the Edo period, many yakiya-zukuri (flammable)-style buildings with shingled roofs and clapboards were built, so that in the event of a fire they could easily be replaced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="43">
<j>近代の長屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaya in the modern era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagaya in the modern era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagaya in the modern era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>明治時代以降においても、都市住居としては長屋が一般的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the Meiji period and later, nagaya was generally used for dwellings in urban areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the Meiji period and later, nagaya were generally used as dwellings in urban areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the Meiji period and later, nagaya were generally used as dwellings in urban areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>2階建て（各住戸内に階段がある）長屋も次第に増え、各戸にトイレも造られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of two story nagaya (a stair was provided within each dwelling unit) increased gradually and a lavatory was installed within each dwelling unit as well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of two-story nagaya (a stair was provided within each dwelling unit) gradually increased, and a lavatory was installed within each dwelling unit.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of two-story nagaya (a stair was provided within each dwelling unit) gradually increased, and a lavatory was installed within each dwelling unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>風呂はまず無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, any bathing place was scarecely provided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, scarcely any space for bathing was provided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, scarcely any space for bathing was provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="47">
<j>現在でも、例えば東京の月島などには長屋が多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, many nagaya still exist, for example, in Tsukishima of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, many nagaya still exist, such as in the Tsukishima district of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, many nagaya still exist, such as in the Tsukishima district of Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>大阪・京都などでもよく見られる、一般的な住居形態であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagaya was a general dwelling style that existed widely in Osak and Kyoto as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nagaya was a general dwelling style that existed throughout Osaka and Kyoto as well.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nagaya was a general dwelling style that existed throughout Osaka and Kyoto as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="49">
<j>また見た目にはいわゆるマンションと同等の建築物でも建築基準法の要件に合致しているとその定義上、長屋となっている物も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many examples that a building is seemingly a condominium but actually a nagaya from the definitions of Building Standard Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many examples of buildings that are seemingly condominiums but are actually defined as nagaya according to the Building Standard Law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many examples of buildings that are seemingly condominiums but are in fact defined as nagaya according to the Building Standard Law.</e>
<cmt>actually →in factに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これは長屋の方が建築要件が緩いため、マンションでは建築不可となる場合でも長屋ならば建築可能となるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the conditions for building a nagaya are less strict and it happens that a building cannot be built meeting the conditions for a condominium but can be built meeting those for a nagaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the conditions for building a nagaya are less strict; for example, one could construct a building that doesn&apos;t meet the conditions for a condominium but can meet those of a nagaya.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because one can build a nagaya even if the building does not meet the conditions for a condominium because the conditions for building a nagaya are less strict.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この方法を用い、実質的にはマンションであるものを建築することにより周辺住民とトラブルを起こす例が報告されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a building that is a condominium effectivley is built using this method, troubles with people living around it can occur, and actually such examples are reported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a building that is effectively a condominium is built using this method, problems with people in surrounding dwellings can occur, and typically such examples are reported.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cases of trouble with nearby residents have been reported when a building that is effectively a condominium is built using this method.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。最後の have been reported を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 白拍子花子(id:244805), 住めら尊(id:173954), Unamu(id:14627), Xenix(id:199838), PATMAN(id:145791), Chobot(id:20846), Rikumio(id:99645), 663highland(id:18755), To-emon(id:23140), Ooyubari9201(id:27879), Avenafatua(id:102597), Corocororing(id:196761), Mishika(id:276), TAMA(id:25299), 在処(id:195599), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>