<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>桜井茶臼山古墳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakurai Chausuyama Kofun Tumulus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakurai Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus (a huge keyhole-shaped mound in the beginning of the early Kofun period [Tumulus period] in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakurai Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus (a huge keyhole-shaped mound in the beginning of the early Kofun period [Tumulus period] in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>桜井茶臼山古墳（さくらいちゃうすやまこふん）は、奈良県桜井市に所在する古墳時代前期初頭の巨大な前方後円墳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakurai Chausuyama Kofun is a huge keyhole-shaped tumulus constructed in the beginning of the early Kofun period located in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakurai Chausuyama Kofun is a huge keyhole-shaped mound constructed in the beginning of the early Kofun period located in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakurai Chausuyama Kofun is a huge keyhole-shaped mound constructed in the beginning of the early Kofun period located in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>外山茶臼山古墳（とびちゃうすやまこふん）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Tobi Chausuyama Kofun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Tobi Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Tobi Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>本古墳は、磐余の地に接した初瀬川の左岸にあり、墳丘長207メートル、前方部が柄鏡形をしている柄鏡式古墳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tumulus is a 207-meter long Ekagami-shiki kofun (hand mirror-type keyhole-shaped tumulus) with the hand-mirror-shaped front part located on the left bank of Hase-gawa River abutting on the Iware region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tumulus is a 207-meter long Ekagami-shiki tumulus (hand mirror-type keyhole-shaped mound) with the hand mirror-shaped front square part located on the left bank of the Hase-gawa River abutting on the Iware region.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tumulus is a 207-meter long Ekagami-shiki tumulus (hand mirror-type keyhole-shaped mound) with the hand mirror-shaped front square part located on the left bank of the Hase-gawa River abutting on the Iware region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>古墳時代初期の内でも比較的新しいものであり、箸墓に続いて造営された巨大な前方後円墳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is comparatively new one among the tumuli of the early Kofun period and is a huge keyhole-shaped tumulus constructed following Hashihaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is comparatively new one among the tumuli of the early Kofun period and is a huge keyhole-shaped tumulus constructed following Hashihaka Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is comparatively new one among the tumuli of the early Kofun period and is a huge keyhole-shaped tumulus constructed following Hashihaka Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この古墳は戦後しばらくたつころまで学界では知られていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tumulus was not known in the academic world for some time after the War.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tumulus was not known in the academic world for some time after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tumulus was not known in the academic world for some time after the World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>自然丘陵を利用し、柄鏡（えかがみ）式の前方後円墳で雑木林に覆われて、単なる丘陵の観を呈している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a hand mirror-type keyhole-shaped tumulus utilizing a natural hill and covered by trees, which looks like a mere hill.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a hand mirror-type keyhole-shaped tumulus utilizing a natural hill and covered by bush, which looks like a mere hill.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a hand mirror-type keyhole-shaped tumulus utilizing a natural hill and covered by bush, which looks like a mere hill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後円部の頂に高さ2メートル弱、１辺9.75×12.5メートルの貼石のある矩形壇があり、また方形に巡る有孔の壺形土器（二重口縁壺形土器）が壇の裾周りに巡らされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a slightly less than two-meter high, 9.75-meter and 12.5-meter Kukei-dan (rectangular platform) with stuck stones (bricks) located on the top of the rounded rear part and porous Tsubogata doki earthenware (Nijukoen tsubogata doki earthenware) are placed squarely surrounding the foot of the platform.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a slightly less than two-meter high, 9.75-meter and 12.5-meter Kukei-dan (rectangular platform) with stuck stones (bricks) located on the top of the back circular part and porous Tsubogata doki earthenware (Niju Koen tsubogata doki [earthenware in a shape like double rim pot]) are placed squarely surrounding the foot of the platform.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a slightly less than two-meter high, 9.75-meter and 12.5-meter Kukei-dan (rectangular platform) with stuck stones (bricks) located on the top of the back circular part and porous Tsubogata doki earthenware (Niju Koen tsubogata doki [earthenware in a shape like double rim pot]) are placed squarely surrounding the foot of the platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>上記を別にすると、墳丘に埴輪の使用がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from the above, Haniwa (clay figures) were not placed on the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from the above, Haniwa (clay figures) were not placed on the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from the above, Haniwa (clay figures) were not placed on the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>段築面には葺石がされている陪墳群がみられない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no subsidiary tumuli covered by Fuki-ishi stones on the terraced layers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no subsidiary tumuli covered by a fukiishi (a stone covering an old tomb) on the terraced layers.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no subsidiary tumuli covered by a fukiishi (a stone covering an old tomb) on the terraced layers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>この古墳の後円部の空濠の外に、宗像神社 (桜井市)がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Munakata-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City) located outside the dry moat of the rounded rear part of this tumulus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is Munakata-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City) located outside the dry moat of the back circular part of this tumulus.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is Munakata-jinja Shrine (Sakurai City) located outside the dry moat of the back circular part of this tumulus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>筑前国宗像郡の宗像神社と同神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shrine was dedicated to the same deity as Munakata-jinja Shrine in Munakata County, Chikuzen Province was.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shrine was dedicated to the same god as Munakata-jinja Shrine in Munakata County, Chikuzen Province was.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shrine was dedicated to the same god as Munakata-jinja Shrine in Munakata County, Chikuzen Province was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>宗像神社は、全国に散在していて、この大和にある神社は、いつ頃からの鎮座か、さらに社殿があるのは何時のことか分からない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the Munakata-jinja shrines found here and there throughout Japan, this particular Munakata Shrine in Yamato was unknown about when it was enshrined and when its Shaden (shrine building) was built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Munakata-jinja Shrines throughout Japan, this particular Shrine in Yamato was unknown about when it was enshrined and when the Shaden (shrine building) was built.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Munakata-jinja Shrines throughout Japan, this particular Shrine in Yamato was unknown about when it was enshrined and when the Shaden (shrine building) was built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、北部九州系の神社が大和にあることは注目に値する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the fact that one of the Munakata-jinja shrines originated from the northern Kyushu is located in Yamato is worthy of attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the fact that one of the Munakata-jinja Shrines originated from the northern Kyushu is located in Yamato is worthy of attention.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除するなど修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the fact that one of the Munakata-jinja Shrines originated from the northern Kyushu is located in Yamato is worthy of attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>墳丘にしみこんだ雨水を抜くための石組の地中排水溝があることが、レーダー探査による調査で2007年に確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A research by radar scan in 2007 confirmed the existence of a rockwork underground drain ditch for draining the rainwater sunk into the soil of the burial mound.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A research by radar scan in 2007 confirmed the existence of a rockwork underground drain ditch for draining the rainwater sunk into the soil of the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A research by radar scan in 2007 confirmed the existence of a rockwork underground drain ditch for draining the rainwater sunk into the soil of the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>埋葬施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burial facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burial facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burial facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>後円部の頂上には、高さ2メートル弱と推定される一辺9.75×12.5メートルの貼り石のある矩形壇が知られており、その壇の裾周りに二重口縁の壺形土器が巡らされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that there was a 9.75-meter and 12.5-meter Kukei-dan (rectangular platform) with the estimated height of a slightly less than two meters with stuck stones (bricks) located on the top of the rounded rear part, and Nijukoen Tsubogata doki earthenware were placed around the foot of the platform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that there was a 9.75-meter and 12.5-meter Kukei-dan with the estimated height of a slightly less than two meters with stuck stones located on the top of the back circular part, and Nijukoen Tsubogata doki earthenware were placed around the foot of the platform.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that there was a 9.75-meter and 12.5-meter Kukei-dan with the estimated height of a slightly less than two meters with stuck stones located on the top of the back circular part, and Nijukoen Tsubogata doki earthenware were placed around the foot of the platform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>さらに、その下に長さ6.7メートルの長大な棺を納めた竪穴式石室があり、既に盗掘を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, under the above platform, there was a vertical stone chamber in which a long coffin with the length of 6.7 meters was kept but the chamber had already been robbed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, under the above platform, there was a vertical stone chamber in which a long coffin with the length of 6.7 meters was kept but the chamber had already been robbed.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, under the above platform, there was a vertical stone chamber in which a long coffin with the length of 6.7 meters was kept but the chamber had already been robbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>副葬品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burial goods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burial goods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burial goods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>前期古墳の副葬品の典型的組合せ、つまり、銅鏡や玉類、剣や刀などの武器類をセットにしていることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a typical combination of burial goods of the early tumuli, which is characterized by making Dokyo (bronze mirror), gems and weapons including Ken (sword of sharpened two edges) and Katana (a sword) as a set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a typical combination of burial goods of the early tumuli, which is characterized by making bronze mirrors, gems and weapons including Ken (sword of sharpened two edges) and Katana (a sword) as a set.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a typical combination of burial goods of the early tumuli, which is characterized by making bronze mirrors, gems and weapons including Ken (sword of sharpened two edges) and Katana (a sword) as a set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>破片から復元すると斜縁二神二獣鏡、方格規矩四神鏡、獣帯鏡、平縁の神獣鏡各一面、内行花文鏡三面、三角縁神獣鏡四種6面、計9種類で少なくとも13面鏡が副葬されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At least, 13 pieces of mirrors in nine categories were buried, that is, one piece each of Shaen nishin niju kyo Mirror, Hokakukiku shishin kyo Mirror, Jutai kyo (round mirror of animal pattern) and Hirabuchi (listel) Shinju kyo Mirror, three pieces of Naiko Kamonkyo Mirror and six pieces of four types of Sankakubuchi Shinjukyo Mirror on the basis of the restored pieces from fragments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At least, 13 pieces of mirrors in 9 categories were buried, that is, 1 piece each of Shaen Nishin Niju-kyo (a mirror with raised edge and relief engraving of two animals and two gods), Hokakukiku shishin-kyo Mirror (a round mirror with a square pattern in the middle and engraving of four gods), Jutai kyo (round mirror of animal pattern) and Hirabuchi (listel) Shinju-kyo Mirror (a mirror with relief engraving of animals), 3 pieces of Naiko Kamon-kyo Mirror (a mirror with patterns like a flower-petal) and 6 pieces of four types of Sankakubuchi Shinju-kyo Mirror (a round mirror with raised edge and relief engraving of animals and gods) on the basis of the restored pieces from fragments.</e>
<cmt>用語補足し、一部アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At least, 13 pieces of mirrors in 9 categories were buried, that is, 1 piece each of Shaen Nishin Niju-kyo (a mirror with raised edge and relief engraving of two animals and two gods), Hokakukiku shishin-kyo Mirror (a round mirror with a square pattern in the middle and engraving of four gods), Jutai kyo (round mirror of animal pattern) and Hirabuchi (listel) Shinju-kyo Mirror (a mirror with relief engraving of animals), 3 pieces of Naiko Kamon-kyo Mirror (a mirror with patterns like a flower-petal) and 6 pieces of four types of Sankakubuchi Shinju-kyo Mirror (a round mirror with raised edge and relief engraving of animals and gods) on the basis of the restored pieces from fragments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>ヒスイの勾玉、ガラス製の管玉、小玉などの首飾り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Necklaces made of Hisui (jade) Magadama (comma-shaped beads), glass cylindrical beads, small beads and so on</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Necklaces made of Hisui (jade) Magadama (comma-shaped beads), glass cylindrical beads, small beads and so on</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Necklaces made of Hisui (jade) Magadama (comma-shaped beads), glass cylindrical beads, small beads and so on</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>鉄刀・鉄剣・銅鏃などの武器類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weapons including iron swords, iron swords of sharpened two edges and copper arrowhead</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weapons including iron swords, iron swords of sharpened two edges and copper arrowhead</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weapons including iron swords, iron swords of sharpened two edges and copper arrowhead</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>碧玉製の腕飾類、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bracelets made of Hekigyoku (jasper)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bracelets made of Hekigyoku (jasper)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bracelets made of Hekigyoku (jasper)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>玉杖（ぎょくじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyokujo (jasper cane)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyokujo (jasper cane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyokujo (jasper cane)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 貘(id:106080), Reggaeman(id:6214), Kansai explorer(id:48975), VanishingDuck(id:125995), Godaigo(id:133481), BAKU(id:55205), のりまき(id:53470), Ffokoob(id:259570), 胡亂堂(id:263343), タケル(id:10666), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>