<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豊楽院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Burakuin hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Burakuin hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Burakuin hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豊楽院（ぶらくいん）とは、宮城大内裏において朝廷の饗宴に用いられた施設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Burakuin hall is used for entertainments and banquets in Imperial Court of the palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Burakuin hall is used for entertainments and banquets in the Imperial Court of the palace</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Burakuin hall is used for entertainments and banquets in the Imperial Court of the palace.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>豊楽（ぶらく）とは和訓「とよのあかり」であり宴会を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">豊楽 is &quot;toyonoakari&quot; in the Japanese pronounciation which means a banquet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">豊楽 is &quot;toyonoakari&quot; in Japanese pronounciation which means a banquet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">豊楽 is &apos;toyonoakari&apos; in Japanese pronunciation which means a banquet.</e>
<cmt>pronunciationスペル訂正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>豊楽院はその名の通り、饗宴施設として平安京遷都直後、大内裏の正庁である朝堂院の西側に隣接して造営された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown in the name, the Burakuin hall was built as a facility for entertainments and banquets at a place immediate west of the Chodoin hall, the main govermant office of the palace, immediately after the capital was moved to Heian-kyo Capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown in the name, the Burakuin hall was built as a facility for entertainment and banquets at a place immediately west of the Chodoin hall, the main govermant office of the palace, righty after the capital was moved to Heian-kyo Capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown in the name, the Burakuin hall was built as a facility for entertainment and banquets at a place immediately west of the Chodoin hall, the main government office of the palace, righty after the capital was moved to Heian-kyo Capital.</e>
<cmt>governmentスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>四方を築地塀で囲まれ、南に正門である豊楽門を構えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was surrounded by walls made of solidified soil on the four sides, with Buraku-mon Gate, the official gate, placed in the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was surrounded by walls made of solidified soil on all four sides, with Buraku-mon Gate, the official gate, placed in the south.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was surrounded by walls made of solidified soil on all four sides, with Buraku-mon Gate, the official gate, placed in the south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>新嘗祭、大嘗祭の宴のほか、正月慶賀、節会（せちえ）、射礼（じゃらい）、饗応などが行われ、正殿である豊楽殿には天皇列席の際に高御座（たかみくら）が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Niinamesai (a harvest festival) and Daijosai (a grand thanksgiving festival), new year-celebrating ceremonies, seasonal ceremonies, shooting ceremonies and banquets were held there, with the seat for the emperor placed in the offical Burakuden hall when an emperor attended such a ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Niinamesai (a harvest festival) and Daijosai (a grand thanksgiving festival), new year-celebrating ceremonies, seasonal ceremonies, shooting ceremonies and banquets were held there, with the seat for the emperor placed in the offical Burakuden hall when an emperor attended such a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Niinamesai (a harvest festival) and Daijosai (a grand thanksgiving festival), new year-celebrating ceremonies, seasonal ceremonies, shooting ceremonies and banquets were held there, with the seat for the emperor placed in the official Burakuden hall when an emperor attended such a ceremony.</e>
<cmt>officialスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>朝廷の機能が徐々に内裏（天皇の私的住居）へ移行するに従って、朝廷の饗宴は紫宸殿で行われるようになり、その地位を低下させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the functions of the imperial court were gradually moved to Dairi (the emperor&apos;s private residence), entertainments and banquets became to be held in Shishinden (the main hall of Dairi), deminishing the importance of the Burakuden hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the functions of the imperial court were gradually moved to Dairi (the emperor&apos;s private residence), entertainment and banquets came to be held in the Shishinden (the main hall of Dairi), deminishing the importance of the Burakuden hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the functions of the Imperial Court were gradually moved to Dairi (the emperor&apos;s private residence), entertainment and banquets came to be held in the Shishinden (the main hall of Dairi), diminishing the importance of the Burakuden hall.</e>
<cmt>Imperial Court大文字にしました。diminishingスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>10世紀には廃墟同然のさまであったといわれ、1063年（康平6年）に全焼したのち、再建されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the hall was almost in ruins, and was never rebuilt after it was destroyed with a fire in 1063.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the hall was almost in ruins, and was never rebuilt after it was destroyed by fire in 1063.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the hall was almost in ruins, and was never rebuilt after it was destroyed by fire in 1063.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1987年から1988年にかけての発掘調査により、豊楽殿の遺構と遺物が発見され、国の史跡と重要文化財（考古資料）に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In academic excavations conducted in 1987 to 1988, structual and other remains of the Burakudenn hall were found, and the site has been desgnated as a national historical site, with the remains designated as cultural properties (archaeological materials).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In academic excavations conducted in 1987 to 1988, structual and other remains of the Burakudenn hall were found, and the site has been desgnated as a national historical site, with the remains designated as cultural properties (archaeological materials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In academic excavations conducted in 1987 to 1988, structural and other remains of the Burakuden hall were found, and the site has been designated as a national historical site, with the remains designated as cultural properties (archaeological materials).</e>
<cmt>n削除しました。structural、designatedスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>