<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大社造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taisha-zukuri style (a term concerning architecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taisha-zukuri Architectural Style</e>
<cmt>Made more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taisha-zukuri style (a term concerning architecture)</e>
<cmt>元に戻しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大社造（たいしゃづくり）は、日本の神社建築様式の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taisha-zukuri style is a style of shrine buildings in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The taisha-zukuri style is a style of shrine buildings in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Capital unnecessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The taisha-zukuri style is a style of shrine buildings in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>出雲大社（いずもおおやしろ）に代表される大社造は、伊勢神宮に代表される神明造や住吉大社に代表される住吉造と共に、もっとも古い神社建築様式とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the taisha-zukuri style, typically the style of the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building, is one of the oldest styles of shrine architecture, together with the shinmei-zukuri style, typically the style of the Ise-jingu shrine building, and the Sumiyoshi-zukuri style, typically the style of Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine buiding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the taisha-zukuri style, represented by the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building, is one of the oldest styles of shrine architecture, together with the shinmei-zukuri style, represented by the Ise-jingu shrine building, and the Sumiyoshi-zukuri style, represented by the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine buiding.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the taisha-zukuri style, represented by the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building, is one of the oldest styles of shrine architecture, together with the shinmei-zukuri style, represented by the Ise-jingu shrine building, and the Sumiyoshi-zukuri style, represented by the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine buiｌding.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>神明造が奥行きより幅が大きい長方形で、高床式倉庫から発展し穀物の代わりに神宝を納めるように変化したものと考えられ、住吉造が大嘗祭の建物に近似している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shinmei-zukuri style, with a rechtangular shape with its width longer than the depth, is considered developed from takayukashiki-soko (warehouses on stilts) and changed so that the building became more fitted for keeping shinpo (sacred treasures) rather than storing grain, and the sumiyosi-zukuri style is close to the style of the building where Daijosai (the first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) is held.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the shinmei-zukuri style buildings have a rectangular shape wider than they are deep, and the style is thought to have been developed from takayukashiki-soko (warehouses on stilts) and changed so that the building became more fitted for keeping shinpo (sacred treasures) than storing grain, and the sumiyoshi-zukuri style is close to the style of the building where Daijosai (the first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) is held.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the shinmei-zukuri style buildings have a rectangular shape with its width longer than the depth, and the style is thought to have been developed from takayukashiki-soko (warehouses on stilts) and changed so that the building became more fitted for keeping shinpo (sacred treasures) than storing grain, and the sumiyoshi-zukuri style is close to the style of the building where Daijosai (the first ceremonial offering of rice by newly-enthroned Emperor) is held.</e>
<cmt>「奥行きより幅が大きい」の部分を元に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これに対して、大社造はほぼ正方形の古典的な日本家屋に近い「田の字」形であることから、祭祀の場に使われていた宮殿が社殿に発展したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, taisha-zukuri style building use the shape of the Chinese character 田, which is square and close to that of traditional Japane houses, and therefore, it is considered that the shrine buildings using this style developed from palaces that had been used for religious services.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conversely, taisha-zukuri style buildings use the shape of the Chinese character 田, which is square and close to that of traditional Japanese houses, and accordingly it is considered that shrine buildings using this style developed from palaces that had been used for religious services.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conversely, taisha-zukuri style buildings use the shape of the Chinese character 田, which is square and close to that of traditional Japanese houses, and accordingly it is considered that shrine buildings using this style developed from palaces that had been used for religious services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その理由として、出雲大社の背後にある八雲山が神体であったとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a therory, the reason is because Mount Yakumo behind Izumo-oyashiro Shrine was shintai (an object of worship that was believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, the reason is because Mount Yakumo behind Izumo-oyashiro Shrine was a shintai (an object of worship that was believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, the reason is because Mount Yakumo behind Izumo-oyashiro Shrine was a shintai (an object of worship that was believed to contain the spirit of a deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>出雲大社の社殿に関しては鎌倉時代以降は記録が残されているが、それ以前に関しては不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the shrine building of Izumo-oyashiro Shrine, no record before the Kamakura period remains, and nothing is known about it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nothing is known about the shrine building of Izumo-oyashiro Shrine prior to the Kamakura Period as no records remain.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing is known about the shrine building of Izumo-oyashiro Shrine prior to the Kamakura Period as no records remain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このため、延享元年（1744年）建立の現社殿が基本形とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the present shrine buiding built in 1744 constitutes its basis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that the present shrine buiding built in 1744 constitutes its basic form.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the present shrine building built in 1744 constitutes its basic form.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>島根県隠岐郡隠岐の島町郡（こおり）にある水若酢神社の本殿は、大社造に分類される場合と、隠岐造と呼ばれる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honden of Mizuwakasu-jinja Shrine located in Kori, Okinoshima Town, Oki County Shimane Prefecture, is sometimes classified as a taisha-zukuri style building or is sometimed called a Oki-zukuri style building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honden of Mizuwakasu-jinja Shrine located in Kori, Okinoshima Town, Oki County Shimane Prefecture, is sometimes classified as a taisha-zukuri style building, yet is sometimes referred to as an Oki-zukuri style building.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honden of Mizuwakasu-jinja Shrine located in Kori, Okinoshima Town, Oki County, Shimane Prefecture, is sometimes classified as a taisha-zukuri style building, yet is sometimes referred to as an Oki-zukuri style building.</e>
<cmt>カンマ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>大社造の構造は掘建柱・切妻造・妻入であり、屋根には優美な曲線が与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A taisha-zukuri style building uses hottate bashira (earthfast posts), the kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof) and tsuma-iri (the style of the building which has the entrance on its short side), and is provided with a roof with graceful curved lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A taisha-zukuri style building uses hottate bashira (earthfast posts), elements of the the kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof) and tsuma-iri (the style of building which has the entrance on its shorter side), and has a roof with graceful curved lines.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A taisha-zukuri style building uses hottate bashira (earthfast posts), elements of the kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof) and tsuma-iri (the style of building which has the entrance on its shorter side), and has a roof with graceful curved lines.</e>
<cmt>重複するtheを削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この点で直線的な外観の神明造や住吉造と大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the point most different from the shinmei-zukuri style and Sumiyoshi-zukuri style whose external view gives an impression of being straight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the point most different from the shinmei-zukuri style and Sumiyoshi-zukuri style whose external view gives an impression of being straight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the point most different from the shinmei-zukuri style and Sumiyoshi-zukuri style whose external view gives an impression of being straight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>屋根</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roof</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roof</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roof</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>古来は萱葺（かやぶき）であったが、江戸時代以降は出雲大社が檜皮葺になるなどの変化が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thatch had been used for the roof from ancient times, but the situation has changed since the Edo period: For example, hiwadabuki (a cypress bark roof) has been used in the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thatch had been used for the roof since ancient times, but this changed during the Edo Period, and hiwadabuki (a cypress bark roof) was used for the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thatch had been used for the roof since ancient times, but this changed during the Edo Period, and hiwadabuki (a cypress bark roof) was used for the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>日本に仏教が伝来し、普及したころ神道では寺院建築を瓦屋根と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Buddhism was brought to Japan and became worshiped widely, temple buildings were called Kawara-yane (tiled roofs).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Buddhism was brought to Japan and became widely practiced, temple buildings were called Kawara-yane (tiled roofs).</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Buddhism was brought to Japan and became widely practiced, temple buildings were called Kawara-yane (tiled roofs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そうしたことから、神社建築においては瓦屋根は邪道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, use of tiled roofs in shrine buildings is wrong.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the use of tiled roofs in shrine buildings was seen as being wrong.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the use of tiled roofs in shrine buildings was seen as being wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>屋根を支える側面の破風（はふ）は、懸魚で修飾され優美な曲線を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hafu (bargeboard) supporting the roof on the side is shaped in a graceful curved line decorated with gegyo (decorative wooden board used to cover the ridge and purlin ends on a roof gable).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hafu (bargeboard) supporting the roof on the side is shaped in a graceful curved line decorated with a gegyo (decorative wooden board used to cover the ridge and purlin ends on a roof gable).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hafu (bargeboard) supporting the roof on the side is shaped in a graceful curved line decorated with a gegyo (decorative wooden board used to cover the ridge and purlin ends on a roof gable).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは中国大陸文化の影響であり、後世に変化したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that this was affected by continental Chinese culture and has been modified later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that this was influenced by continental Chinese culture and which has been later modified.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that this was influenced by continental Chinese culture and which has been later modified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>屋根に耐久性の低い萱や板を使うため、屋根の勾配をきつくして雨や雪が流れ落ちやすくしてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because less endurable thatch or shingles are used for the roof, the slope of the roof is made steep so that rain and snow drops along the roof more easily.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because less endurable thatch or shingles are used for the roof, the angle of the roof is made steep so that rain and snow falls down the roof more easily.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because less endurable thatch or shingles are used for the roof, the angle of the roof is made steep so that rain and snow falls down the roof more easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、切妻であるため軒出も大きく作る必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also necessary to make the eaves longer, because a kirizuma-style roof is used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also necessary to make the eaves longer, because a kirizuma-style roof is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also necessary to make the eaves longer, because a kirizuma-style roof is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>千木・鰹木は修飾目的で付けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) and Katsuogi (ornamental logs arranged orthogonal to the ridge of a Shinto shrine) are provided for a decorative purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) and Katsuogi (ornamental logs arranged perpendicular to the ridge of a Shinto shrine) are used for decorative purposes.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi (ornamental crossbeams on the gable of a Shinto shrine) and Katsuogi (ornamental logs arranged perpendicular to the ridge of a Shinto shrine) are used for decorative purposes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>柱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>古来は柱と地面の間には礎石も土台も与えられず掘立柱であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From ancient times, the pillars were earthfast, and neither base stones nor mud bases were provided between those pillars and the ground.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From ancient times the pillars were earthfast, and neither base stones nor mud bases were used between the pillars and the surface of the ground.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From ancient times the pillars were earthfast, and neither base stones nor mud bases were used between the pillars and the surface of the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、延享元年（1744年）建立の出雲大社社殿は礎石の上に柱が立てられ、耐久性を高めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building built in 1744, each pillar is placed on a base stone to increasie its duarability level.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building constructed in 1744, each pillar is placed on a base stone to increase its durability level.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building constructed in 1744, each pillar is placed on a base stone to increase its durability level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>田の字構造の社殿の中央に心の太柱が配され、垂木を支える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A big core pillar is placed at the center of the shrine building with the shape of Chinese character 田, supporting taruki (the rafters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A large core pillar is placed at the center of the shrine building which forms the shape of the Chinese character 田, supporting the taruki (rafters).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A large core pillar is placed at the center of the shrine building which forms the shape of the Chinese character 田, supporting the taruki (rafters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>妻中央の、やや外側に飛び出し棟へ達する柱を宇豆柱（うずばしら）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillar that is placed at the center of each tsuma side, a little outside of the wall, and that reaches the ridge is called a Uzu-bashira pillar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillar that is placed at the center of each tsuma side, a little outside of the wall, and that reaches the ridge is called the Uzu-bashira pillar.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillar that is placed at the center of each tsuma side, a little outside of the wall, and that reaches the ridge is called the Uzu-bashira pillar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>宇豆柱は心の太柱を補助する目的と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that a Uzu-bashira pillar is used for augmenting the strength of the big core pillar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that an Uzu-bashira pillar is used in order to augment the strength of the large core pillar.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that an Uzu-bashira pillar is used in order to augment the strength of the large core pillar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>壁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The walls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The walls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The walls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>神明造では壁は水平方向に板材を配するが、大社造では垂直方向に配する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The boards that are used for making a wall are provided horizontally in the shinmei-zukuri style, and vertically in the taisha-zukuri syle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The boards that are used for making the walls are placed horizontally in the shinmei-zukuri style, and vertically in the taisha-zukuri syle.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The boards that are used for making the walls are placed horizontally in the shinmei-zukuri style, and vertically in the taisha-zukuri sｔyle.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>妻の中央から右に外れた場所1か所のみに開口部が設けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An opening is provided only in a portion to the right of the center on a tsuma side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a single opening to the right of the center on the tsuma side.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a single opening to the right of the center on the tsuma side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="28">
<j>床</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The floors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The floors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The floors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="29">
<j>延享元年（1744年）建立の出雲大社の社殿には畳60帖が敷かれているが、いつから敷かれたのかは不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sixty tatami mats are laid in the shrine building of the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine built in 1744, but it is not known whhen they were laid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sixty tatami mats are laid in the shrine building of the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine built in 1744, but it is not known when they were laid.</e>
<cmt>Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sixty tatami mats are laid in the shrine building of the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine built in 1744, but it is not known when they were laid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>床は高く、神明造と同様に長い階段が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The floors are raised considerably and a long stair is needed as in the shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The floors are considerably raised and a long set of steps is needed as in the shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The floors are considerably raised and a long set of steps is needed as in the shinmei-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>大社造の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the taish-zukuri style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the taisha-zukuri style</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the taisha-zukuri style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>歴史は古いが、その創始については記録に残っていないため定かでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history started at ancient times, but its origin is unclear because no record remains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of this architectural style is long, but its exact beginnings are unknown.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of this architectural style is long, but its exact beginnings are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>弥生時代の遺跡の柱の遺構が大社造の柱の配置に似ているため、高床式住居が発展したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillar layout of remains in the Yayoi Period is similar to that of the taisha-zukuri style buildings, and therefore, it is considered that the taisha-zukuri style developed from takayukashiki jukyo (raised-floor houses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The layout of pillars in remains from the Yayoi Period is similar to that of taisha-zukuri style buildings, and so it is considered that the taisha-zukuri style developed out of takayukashiki-soko (raised-floor houses).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The layout of pillars in remains from the Yayoi Period is similar to that of taisha-zukuri style buildings, and so it is considered that the taisha-zukuri style developed out of takayukashiki-soko (raised-floor houses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>延享元年（1744年）建立の出雲大社の社殿の高さは、約24mと巨大である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The height of thee Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building built in 1744 is considerably high, 24 m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The height of the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building, constructed in 1744, is considerably high, at 24 m.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The height of the Izumo-oyashiro Shrine building, constructed in 1744, is considerably high, at 24 m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>以前はもっと大きく平安時代中期から鎌倉時代初期までの200年間に7回も倒壊したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bfore that, the shrine building was larger, and it is said that the building collapsed seven times during 200 years between the middle era of the Heian period and the early Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The previous shrine building was larger, and it is said that the building collapsed seven times during the 200 years between the middle of the Heian Period and the early Kamakura era.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The previous shrine building was larger, and it is said that the building collapsed seven times during the 200 years between the middle of the Heian Period and the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>era→period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>平安中期の長元5年（1032年）8月11日の倒壊は、地震や強風があったという記録はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the collapse on August 11, 1032, there is no recod indicating that an earthquake occurred or a strong wind blew on that day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the time of the collapse on August 11, 1032, there are no records indicating that an earthquake occurred or that a strong wind blew on that day.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the time of the collapse on August 11, 1032, there are no records indicating that an earthquake occurred or that a strong wind blew on that day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そうしたことから、自重に耐えられず倒壊したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it いｓ considered that the building collapsed due to its own weight.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is believed the building collapsed under its own weight.</e>
<cmt>Typo, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is believed the building collapsed under its own weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>山陰地方の社殿に大社造が多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many shｒine buidings in the taisha-zukuri style are found in the Sanin region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many shｒine buidings in the taisha-zukuri style are found in the Sanin region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many shｒine buidings in the taisha-zukuri style are found in the Sanin region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし、明治以降に建築された社殿の場合、名和神社のように大社造を採用しなかった例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the taisha-zukuri style was not adopted in some shrine buildings, for example, Nawa-jinja Shrine, built in the Meiji period or later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the taisha-zukuri style was not adopted for some shrine buildings built in or after the Meiji Period, such as Nawa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the taisha-zukuri style was not adopted for some shrine buildings built in or after the Meiji Period, such as Nawa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>21世紀に現存する大社造の社殿としては、山陰地方の島根県松江市大庭町にある神魂神社（かもすじんじゃ）の本殿が室町時代の正平元年（1346年）で最古である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the shrine buildings in the taisha-zukuri style remaining in the 21st century, Kamosu-jinja Shrine located in Oba-cho, Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture in the Sanin region, was built in 1346 in the Muromachi period and is the oldest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the shrine buildings in the taisha-zukuri style remaining in the 21st century, Kamosu-jinja Shrine located in Oba-cho, Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture in the Sanin region, was built in 1346 in the Muromachi Period and is the oldest.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the shrine buildings in the taisha-zukuri style remaining in the 21st century, Kamosu-jinja Shrine located in Oba-cho, Matsue City, Shimane Prefecture in the Sanin region, was built in 1346 in the Muromachi Period and is the oldest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>神魂神社本殿は、大社造の古式に則った最古の建造物であることから1952年（昭和27年）3月に国宝に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The honden (main hall) of Kamosu-jinja Shrine was designated as a national treasure in March of 1952, because it is the oldest building built based on ancient and orignal rules of the taisha-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honden (main hall) of Kamosu-jinja Shrine was designated a national treasure in March 1952, because it is the oldest building constructed based on the ancient original rules of the taisha-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>Spelling, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honden (main hall) of Kamosu-jinja Shrine was designated a national treasure in March 1952, because it is the oldest building constructed based on the ancient original rules of the taisha-zukuri style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mobnoboka(id:35218), N yotarou(id:60870), Urania(id:7213), アムネマチン(id:87480), Hangbak(id:120071), ブルクドルフ(id:84176), Korokoro(id:42329), Excavator(id:25917), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>