<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御薗橋801商店街</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misonobashi Hachimaruichi Shotengai (the Misonobashi 801 shopping street)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misonobashi Hachimaruichi Shotengai (the Misonobashi 801 shopping street)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misonobashi Hachimaruichi Shotengai (the Misonobashi 801 shopping street)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御薗橋801商店街（みそのばしはちまるいちしょうてんがい）は京都市北区御薗橋西詰から西へ800mの長さに渡って続く京都市最北の商店街である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in the northernmost place of Kyoto, Misonobashi Hachimaruichi Shotengai (the Misonobashi 801 shopping street) is a shopping street whose length is 800 m to the west from Misonobashi-nishizume (the west end of Misono-bashi Bridge), Kita Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in the northernmost place in Kyoto, Misonobashi Hachimaruichi Shotengai (the Misonobashi 801 shopping street) it&apos;s length is 800 m to the west from Misonobashi-nishizume (the west end of Misono-bashi Bridge), Kita Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in the northernmost place in Kyoto, Misonobashi Hachimaruichi Shotengai (the Misonobashi 801 shopping street) it&apos;s length is 800m to the west from Misonobashi-nishizume (the west end of Misono-bashi Bridge), Kita Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>商店街名は全長の800に未来への発展を意味して1を加えたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the shopping street comes from its length of 800 m plus 1 which was added intending a further expansion in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the shopping street comes from its length of 800 m plus 1 which was added intending further expansion in the future.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the shopping street comes from its length of 800m plus 1 which was added intending further expansion in the future.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>周囲には京都産業大学や世界文化遺産である上賀茂神社、西賀茂、神光院、賀茂川などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around there, Kyoto Sangyo University, Kamigamo-jinja Shrine, a world heritage property, Nishigamo, Jinko-in Temple and Kamo-gawa River exist</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nearby are the, Kyoto Sangyo University, Kamigamo-jinja Shrine, a world heritage property, Nishigamo, Jinko-in Temple and Kamo-gawa Rivert</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearby are the, Kyoto Sangyo University, Kamigamo-jinja Shrine, a world heritage property, Nishigamo, Jinko-in Temple and Kamo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Riverスペル訂正しました。ピリオド補足。余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>京都精華大学の学生によって京野菜のナスをイメージしてデザインされた同商店街のマスコット「801ちゃん」は女性向けの男性同性愛を扱った作品を意味する「やおい」と掛けた二次創作漫画『となりの801ちゃん』がヒットして今や同作品は商店街の公認を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;801-chan (pronounced as Yaoichi-chan),&quot; the mascot designed for the shopping street by students of Kyoto Seika University imaging a Kyoto-specific eggplant, has now been made offical by the street, because &quot;Tonari no 801 (Yaoi)-chan,&quot; a spin-out manga (cartoon) in which &quot;Yaoi&quot;is also used for suggesting &quot;Yaoi&quot;meaning a male-homosexual-love-dealing product for feamales, has become very popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;801-chan (pronounced as Yaoichi-chan),&quot; the mascot designed for the shopping street by students of Kyoto Seika University imaging a Kyoto-specific eggplant, has now been made offical by the street, because &quot;Tonari no 801 (Yaoi)-chan,&quot; a spin-off manga (cartoon) in which &quot;Yaoi&quot;is also used for suggesting &quot;Yaoi&quot;meaning a male-homosexual-love-dealing product for females, has become very popular.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">801-chan (pronounced as Yaoichi-chan),&apos; the mascot designed for the shopping street by students of Kyoto Seika University imaging a Kyoto-specific eggplant, has now been made official by the street, because &quot;Tonari no 801 (Yaoi)-chan,&quot; a spin-off manga (cartoon) in which &apos;Yaoi&apos; is also used for suggesting &apos;Yaoi&apos; meaning a male-homosexual-love-dealing product for females, has become very popular.</e>
<cmt>officialスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Si-take.(id:91094), 中二病の端くれ(id:137185), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>