<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>私のしごと館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Vocational Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Vocational Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Vocational Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>私のしごと館（わたしのしごとかん）は、若者を対象に職業体験の機会、職業情報、職業相談等を提供する施設である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Vocational Museum provides young people with experiences of work, recruit information, and vocational counseling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Vocational Museum provides young people with work experience, recruitment information, and vocational counseling.</e>
<cmt>「experiences of work」→「work experience」, 「recruit」→「recruitment」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Vocational Museum provides young people with work experience, recruitment information, and vocational counseling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>1989年（平成元年）度より施策の必要性の議論が始まり、1992年（平成4年）度には政府が施設の設置構想をまとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1989, discussions on its necessity started, and in 1992, the government completed a plan to establish the facility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1989, discussions on the need for such a facility started, and in 1992 the government completed the plan to establish it.</e>
<cmt>「on its necessity」→「on the need for such a facility」, 「a」→「the」, 「the facility」→「it」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1989, discussions on the need for such a facility started, and in 1992 the government completed the plan to establish it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1995年（平成7年）の閣議決定（開館準備の推進）及び1999年（平成11年）の閣議決定（設置の推進）を経て、厚生労働省の重点施策「若年者雇用対策の推進」の一つとして国により設置が推進及び促進された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the cabinet decided to prepare building the facility in 1995, and then in 1999, it decided to implement the plan to establish the facility, the government promoted and implemented the plan as one of the priority policies &quot;Promotion of Youth Employment Measures&quot; of the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following cabinet decisions to prepare for the building of the facility, taken in 1995, and to implement the plan to establish it, taken in 1999, the government promoted its creation as part of the policy surrounding the &quot;Promotion of Youth Employment Measures&quot; of the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following cabinet decisions to prepare for the building of the facility, taken in 1995, and to implement the plan to establish it, taken in 1999, the government promoted its creation as part of the policy surrounding the &apos;Promotion of Youth Employment Measures&apos; of the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>厚生労働省所管の独立行政法人雇用・能力開発機構が設置・運営する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is built and operated by the Employment and Human Resources Development Organization of Japan, an independent administrative institution under the jurisdiction of the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was built and is operated by the Employment and Human Resources Development Organization of Japan, an independent administrative institution under the jurisdiction of the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare.</e>
<cmt>「is」→「was」, 「is」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was built and is operated by the Employment and Human Resources Development Organization of Japan, an independent administrative institution under the jurisdiction of the Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>雇用保険法により定められている雇用保険事業のうちの能力開発事業として、若年者の失業予防のための事業を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It operates to prevent unemployment of young people as the development of vocational abilities, one of the employment insurance operations under the Unemployment Insurance Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It operates to prevent youth unemployment through the development of vocational abilities, one of the employment insurance related operations driven by the Unemployment Insurance Law.</e>
<cmt>「unemployment of young people」→「youth unemployment」, 「as」→「through」, 「related」挿入,「under」→「driven by」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It operates to prevent youth unemployment through the development of vocational abilities, one of the employment insurance related operations driven by the Unemployment Insurance Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>大阪府・京都府・奈良県にまたがる関西文化学術研究都市内にある、古代より木津川でつながる大阪、京都と奈良を結ぶ街道からそれほど離れていないところにあり、施設の行政的な所在地は京都府となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inside of Kyoto Prefecture and also in Kansai Science City which straddles Osaka, Kyoto, and Nara Prefectures, and is located not far from the route along Kizu-gawa river that has connected Osaka, Kyoto and Nara since ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is inside Kyoto Prefecture and is also part of Kansai Science City which straddles Osaka, Kyoto, and Nara Prefectures, and is located not far from the route following the Kizu-gawa river that has connected Osaka, Kyoto and Nara since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>「of」削除, 「is」挿入, 「in」→「part of」, 「along」→「following the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is inside Kyoto Prefecture and is also part of Kansai Science City which straddles Osaka, Kyoto, and Nara Prefectures, and is located not far from the route following the Kizu-gawa River that has connected Osaka, Kyoto and Nara since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>riverの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>2003年（平成15年）3月30日にプレオープン、同年10月4日にグランドオープンした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It partially opened on March 30, 2003, and started full operation on October 4 of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It partially opened on March 30, 2003, and began full operations on October 4 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>「started」→「began」, 「operation」→「operations」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It partially opened on March 30, 2003, and began full operations on October 4 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし2007年（平成19年）12月の閣議決定（独立行政法人整理合理化計画）において、運営を包括的に民間委託し、第三者委員会による外部評価結果を踏まえて１年以内に存廃を含めその在り方について検討を行うこととされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the cabinet&apos;s decision of December 2007 (plans to streamline independent administrative institutions) said that all its operations should be entrusted to the private sector, and based on an evaluation by the third- party committee, how it should be operated and whether it is necessary should be discussed within one year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the cabinet decision of December 2007 regarding plans to streamline independent administrative institutions stated that the running of the facility should be entrusted to the private sector, and based on an evaluation by an independent committee, proposals around how it should be operated and whether it is necessary should be made within a year.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the cabinet decision of December 2007 regarding plans to streamline independent administrative institutions stated that the running of the facility should be entrusted to the private sector, and based on an evaluation by an independent committee, proposals around how it should be operated and whether it was necessary should be made within a year.</e>
<cmt>時制の一致のため、it was necessaryとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その結果、2008年7月から運営が民間委託されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, its management was outsouced to the private sector in July 2008.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, its management was outsourced to the private sector in July 2008.</e>
<cmt>「outsouced」→「outsourced」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, its management was outsourced to the private sector in July 2008.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>目的</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Objectives</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Objectives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Objectives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>世界最大級の職業総合情報拠点として、失業予防のための若年者への職業意識啓発（職業教育、キャリア教育）を目的とする各種事業を実施する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It implements various programs to prevent unemployment by encouraging occupational aspirations of young people (vocational and career education) as one of the largest comprehensive occupational information centers in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It implements various programs to prevent unemployment by fostering the occupational aspirations of young people (vocational and career education) and is one of the largest comprehensive occupational information centers in the world.</e>
<cmt>「encouraging」→「fostering the」, 「as」→「and is」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It implements various programs to prevent unemployment by fostering the occupational aspirations of young people (vocational and career education) and is one of the largest comprehensive occupational information centers in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>中学生や高校生などの時から、仕事というものに親しみを持つことができるよう、また、いろいろな職業を体験することができるように、それら各種仕事の展示体験コーナーや、職業情報の提供、発信等を実施する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It presents displays of hands-on experience of various occupations, provides and announces occupational information so that high school or junior high school students can be familiar with jobs and experience them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It contains displays where the visitor can get hands-on experience relating to various types of work, and provides and announces information regarding occupations so that high school or junior high school students can become familiar with jobs and experience them firsthand.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It contains displays where the visitor can get hands-on experience relating to various types of work, and provides and announces information regarding occupations so that high school or junior high school students can become familiar with jobs and experience them firsthand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="13">
<j>労働意欲衰退は今や国際的社会問題であり、早期キャリア学習が世界各国で求められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Declining motivation for working is now international social problems, and there are growing calls for early career education in many countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Declining motivation for work is increasingly an international social problem, and there have been growing calls for early career education in many countries.</e>
<cmt>「working」→「work」, 「now」→「increasingly a」,「problems」→「problem」, 「are」→「have been」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Declining motivation for work is increasingly an international social problem, and there have been growing calls for early career education in many countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>博物館等の社会教育、心理学（キャリアカウンセリング）、職業訓練（職業能力開発）等の手法を組み合わせた方法により恒久的、継続的な問題解決をめざす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It aims to work out permanent and on-going solutions to these problems by using methods of social education by museums, psychology (career counseling), and occupational training (development of vocational abilities).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It aims to work out long-term and ongoing solutions to these problems through various techniques, such as social education by the museum, psychology (career counseling), and occupational training (development of vocational abilities).</e>
<cmt>「permanent」→「long-term」, 「on-going」→「ongoing」,「by using methods of」→「through various techniques, such as」, 「museums」→「the museum」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It aims to work out long-term and ongoing solutions to these problems through various techniques, such as social education by the museum, psychology (career counseling), and occupational training (development of vocational abilities).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>施設概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of the facility</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of the facility</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of the Facility</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>総敷地面積：83,000m2</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Site area: 83,000 m2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Site area: 83,000 m2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Site area: 83,000 square meters</e>
<cmt>m2→square metersとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>総延床面積：35,000m2</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Total floor space: 35,000 m2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Total floor space: 35,000 m2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Total floor space: 35,000 square meters</e>
<cmt>m2→square metersとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>総工費：581億円</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Total cost: \58.1 billion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Total cost: \58.1 billion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Total cost: 58.1 billion yen</e>
<cmt>\58.1 billion→58.1 billion yenとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>京都府精華町と木津川市等にまたがる関西文化学術研究都市にあり、二つの市と町にまたがっているためちょっと変わった住所になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its address is unusual because it is in Kansai Science City that straddles Seika Cho (Town) and Kizugawa City of Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its address is unusual because it is in Kansai Science City that straddles Seika Cho Town and Kizugawa City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Parentheses removed to avoid confusion, 「of」→「in」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its address is unusual because it is in Kansai Science City that straddles Seika-cho and Kizugawa City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Seika-choとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>住所は下記のとおり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The address is as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The addresses are as follows:</e>
<cmt>Changed to plural form.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The addresses are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>〒619-0282　関西文化学術研究都市（京都府　精華・西木津地区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansai Science City, Seika, Nishi-Kizu Area, Kyoto Prefecture 619-0282</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansai Science City, Seika, Nishi-Kizu Area, Kyoto Prefecture 619-0282</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansai Science City, Seika, Nishi-Kizu Area, Kyoto Prefecture 619-0282</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>（郵便物は上記住所で届く。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This address is valid for the mail delivery service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This address is used for correspondence.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This address is used for correspondence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>京都府木津川市木津川台9丁目6番</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">9-6 Kizugawadai, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefectur</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">9-6 Kizugawadai, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>「Prefectur」→「Prefecture」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">9-6 Kizugawadai, Kizugawa City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>京都府相楽郡精華町精華台7丁目5-1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">7-5-1 Seikadai, Seika Cho, Soraku Gun, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">7-5-1 Seikadai, Seika Cho, Soraku Gun, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">7-5-1 Seikadai, Seika-cho, Soraku-gun, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>住所表記を一部修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>機能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Functions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Functions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Functions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>世界最大の体験型職業労働博物館(しごと博物館）でもあり、職業意識啓発（職業教育、キャリア教育）を目的とした施設として、博物館、図書館、職業情報センター、その他イベント、セミナー、コンテンツ制作等の目的にも使用できる巨大複合施設の機能を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As world&apos;s largest hands-on occupational museum (jobs museum), and as a facility to encourage occupational aspirations (vocational and career education), it provides functions of a large composite establishment, including museums, libraries, occupational information centers, and other facilities for events, seminars, and contents creations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the world&apos;s largest hands-on occupational museum (employment museum), and as a facility encouraging occupational aspirations (relating to vocational and career education), it is a large composite establishment with many elements, including museums, libraries, occupational information centers, and other facilities for events, seminars, and craftmaking.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「jobs」→「employment」, 「to encourage」→「encouraging」, 「relating to」挿入,「provides functions of」→「is a」, 「with many elements」挿入,「contents creations」→「craftmaking」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the world&apos;s largest hands-on occupational museum (employment museum), and as a facility encouraging occupational aspirations (relating to vocational and career education), it is a large composite establishment with many elements, including museums, libraries, occupational information centers, and other facilities for events, seminars, and craftmaking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>関西文化学術研究都市の顔となる代表的な総合文化施設として、近くにあるけいはんなプラザ、国立国会図書館関西館などと並び、都市における中心的な機能と役割を果たすことが期待されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed to play a central role of a comprehensive cultural facility in an urban area representing Kansai Science City, along with nearby Keihanna Plaza and Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed to play a central role in a comprehensive cultural facility in the urban area representing Kansai Science City, along with nearby Keihanna Plaza and Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>「of」→「in」, 「an」→「the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed to play a central role in a comprehensive cultural facility in the urban area representing Kansai Science City, along with nearby Keihanna Plaza and Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>日本の中心は長い間畿内と呼ばれた近畿地方にあり、江戸時代においては上方文化の中心地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinki region had been the center of Japan called &quot;Kinai&quot; for ages, and was the center of Kamigata Bunka (Kinki Culture) in Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinki region, formerly called &quot;Kinai&quot;, was the center of Japan for an extended period, and was the center of Kamigata Bunka (Kinki Culture) during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinki region, formerly called &quot;Kinai&quot;, was the center of Japan for an extended period, and was the center of Kamigata Bunka (Kinki Culture) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>統一事項に基づき、Edo Period→Edo periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>今は阪神工業地帯を持つ近畿地方が中心となり、日本のみならず世界全体の若年者問題と、労働意欲低下問題解決のための機能を持つことで人々の士気向上をめざし、特に日本においては、ものづくりを中心とする経済発展に貢献することが期待されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, Kinki region with Hanshin Industrial Zone is hoped to lead lifting people&apos;s spirit by providing functions for solving youth problems and problems of declining motivation for working not only in Japan but in the world as well, especially to contribute to the economic development based on manufacturing in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the Kinki region, which contains Hanshin Industrial Zone, hopes to lift the human spirit by working towards building solutions to youth problems and tackling issues of declining motivation relating to working not only in Japan but in the world as well, with a particular focus on contributing to economic development based on manufacturing in Japan.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the Kinki region, which contains Hanshin Industrial Zone, hopes to lift the human spirit by working towards building solutions to youth problems and tackling issues of declining motivation relating to working not only in Japan but in the world as well, with a particular focus on contributing to economic development based on manufacturing in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>1989年（平成元年）- 「若年者等の職業意識に関する懇談会」を設置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1989: &quot;Council on Young People&apos;s Sense of Vocation&quot; was set up.</e>
<cmt>若年者等の職業意識に関する懇談会→Council on Young People&apos;s Sense of Vocation[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1989: The &quot;Council on Young People&apos;s Sense of Vocation&quot; was set up.</e>
<cmt>「In」削除, 「The」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1989: The &apos;Council on Young People&apos;s Sense of Vocation&apos; was set up</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>1992年（平成4年）- 「働きがいと技能尊重に関する有識者懇談会」を設置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1992: &quot;Advisory Panel of Well-informed Independent Personalities on Job Satisfaction and Respect for Skills&quot; was set up.</e>
<cmt>働きがいと技能尊重に関する有識者懇談会→Advisory Panel of Well-informed Independent Personalities on Job Satisfaction and Respect for Skills[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1992: The &quot;Advisory Panel of Well-informed Independent Personalities on Job Satisfaction and Respect for Skills&quot; was set up.</e>
<cmt>「In」削除, 「The」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1992: The &apos;Advisory Panel of Well-informed Independent Personalities on Job Satisfaction and Respect for Skills&apos; was set up</e>
<cmt>原文表記に合わせ、シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>1993年（平成5年）4月 - 新総合経済対策決定（経済対策閣僚会議決定）（公共投資、社会資本整備として、勤労体験プラザ（仮称）構想が具体化）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1993: the new package of economic stimulus measures were decided (the Ministerial Meeting&apos;s decision); a plan for establishing &quot;Work Experience Plaza&quot; (tentative) was presented as the public investment and the social capital improvement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1993: new package of economic stimulus measures decided by the Cabinet; tentative plan for establishing a &quot;Work Experience Plaza&quot; presented as public investment and social capital improvement.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1993: new package of economic stimulus measures decided by the Cabinet; tentative plan for establishing a &apos;Work Experience Plaza&apos; presented as public investment and social capital improvement</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、後出の表記にあわせシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>1993年（平成5年）6月8日 - 補正予算成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 8, 1993: the supplementary budget was passed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 8, 1993: supplementary budget passed.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 8, 1993: supplementary budget passed</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>1993年（平成5年）8月 - 関西文化学術研究都市に「勤労体験プラザ（仮称）」の建設計画発表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1993: the plan to build &quot;Work Experience Plaza (tentative)&quot; in Kansai Science City was announced.</e>
<cmt>勤労体験プラザ→Work Experience Plaza[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1993: tentative plan to build &quot;Work Experience Plaza&quot; in Kansai Science City announced.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1993: tentative plan to build &apos;Work Experience Plaza&apos; in Kansai Science City announced</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>1994年（平成6年）3月 - 用地取得</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1994: its land was aquired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1994: land aquired.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1994: land aquired</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>1995年（平成7年）6月 - 「勤労体験プラザ（仮称）基本計画」の策定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1995: &quot;Basic Plan of Work Experience Plaza (tentative)&quot; was drawn up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 1995: &quot;Work Experience Plaza Basic Plan (tentative)&quot; drawn up.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 1995: &apos;Work Experience Plaza Basic Plan&apos; (tentative) drawn up</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、(tantative)の位置を移動、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>1995年（平成7年）12月 - 「第8次雇用対策基本計画」の策定（閣議決定）（勤労体験プラザ（仮称）設置方針が盛り込まれる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1995: &quot;8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures&quot;was formulated (decision by the Cabinet); the policy to build Work Experience Plaza (tentative) was included.</e>
<cmt>第8次雇用対策基本計画→8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1995: &quot;8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures&quot; formulated (Cabinet decision); policy to build Work Experience Plaza (tentative) included.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「decision by the Cabinet」→「Cabinet decision」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1995: &apos;8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures&apos; formulated (Cabinet decision); policy to build Work Experience Plaza (tentative) included</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="35">
<j>1996年（平成8年）12月 - 展示・体験基本設計着手</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December 1996: basic designs for displays and experience started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 1996: basic designs for displays and work experience started.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 1996: basic designs for displays and work experience started</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="36">
<j>1997年（平成9年）4月 - 関西文化学術研究都市建設促進法に基づく基本方針改訂（内閣総理大臣決定）（勤労体験プラザ（仮称）の整備推進と情報提供施設としての位置付けが明記）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1997: the basic policy was revised (decision by the Prime Minister) under the Kansai Science City Construction Promotion Law; the promotion of building Work Experience Plaza (tentative) and its role as the information providing center were clearly stated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1997: basic policy revised by Prime Minister under Kansai Science City Construction Promotion Law - promotion of building Work Experience Plaza (tentative) and its role as information center clearly stated.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「:」→「-」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1997: basic policy revised by Prime Minister under Kansai Science City Construction Promotion Law - promotion of building Work Experience Plaza (tentative) and its role as information center clearly stated</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>1997年（平成9年）9月 - 建築基本設計着手</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1997: the basic architectural design started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 1997: basic architectural design started.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 1997: basic architectural design started</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="38">
<j>1998年（平成10年）3月 - 展示・体験実施設計着手</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1988: designs of the implementation of displays and experience started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 1998: designs of displays and work experience started.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「1988」→「1998」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 1998: designs of displays and work experience started</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="39">
<j>1998年（平成10年）8月 - 建築実施設計着手</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1998: designs of the implementation of building started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1998: building designs started.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1998: building designs started</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="40">
<j>1999年（平成11年）8月 - 「第9次雇用対策基本計画」の策定（閣議決定）（勤労体験プラザ（仮称）の設置が再度明記される）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1999: &quot;8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures&quot; (decision of the Cabinet); the policy to build Work Experience Plaza (tentative) was clearly stated again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1999: &quot;8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures&quot; (Cabinet decision) and policy to build Work Experience Plaza (tentative) clearly stated again.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1999: &apos;8th Basic Plan for Employment Measures&apos; (Cabinet decision) and policy to build Work Experience Plaza (tentative) clearly stated again</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>2000年（平成12年）2月 - 建設着工</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 2000: the construction started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 2000: construction started.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 2000: construction started</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="42">
<j>2001年（平成13年）1月 - 公募により名称を「私のしごと館」に決定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 2001: its official name was decided to be &quot;Watashi no Shigoto Kan&quot; (Vocational Museum) which was among the public applications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 2001: official name decided as &quot;Watashi no Shigoto Kan&quot; (Vocational Museum) selected from suggestions by the public.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list. 「to be」→「as」, 「which was among the public applications」→「selected from suggestions by the public」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 2001: official name decided as &apos;Watashi no Shigoto Kan&apos; (Vocational Museum) selected from suggestions by the public</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>2003年（平成15年）3月30日 - 私のしごと館プレオープン・辻村江太郎館長</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 30, 2003: the Vocational Museum was partially opened: the director was Kotaro TSUJIMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 30, 2003: Vocational Museum partially opened: director, Kotaro TSUJIMURA.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list. 「,」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 30, 2003: Vocational Museum partially opened: director, Kotaro TSUJIMURA</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="44">
<j>2003年（平成15年）4月1日 - 私のしごと館ライブラリィコーナー（図書館）開館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1 2003: the Vocational Museum Library Corner (a library) was opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 1 2003: Vocational Museum Library Corner opened.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list. 「(a library)」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1 2003: Vocational Museum Library Corner opened</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="45">
<j>2003年（平成15年）10月4日 - 私のしごと館グランドオープン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 4, 2003: Vocational Museum was fully opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 4, 2003: Vocational Museum fully opened.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 4, 2003: Vocational Museum fully opened</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="46">
<j>2006年（平成18年）3月10日 - プレオープン後入館者100万人達成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 10, 2006: the accumulated number of visitors since it partially opened reached one million.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 10, 2006: number of visitors since opening reached one million.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「accumulated」削除, 「partially opened」→「opening」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 10, 2006: number of visitors since opening reached one million</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="47">
<j>2006年（平成18年）3月31日 - 私のしごと館図書館コスト削減のため閉館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 31, 2006: the Vocational Museum Library was closed because of the cost reduction measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 31, 2006: Vocational Museum Library closed due to cost reduction measures.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「because of」→「due to」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 31, 2006: Vocational Museum Library closed due to cost reduction measures</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="48">
<j>2006年（平成18年）7月28日 - 川崎二郎厚生労働大臣来館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 28, 2006: Jiro KAWASAKI, the Minister of Health, Labour and Welfare visited this museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 28, 2006: Jiro KAWASAKI, Minister of Health, Labour and Welfare visit.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「visited this museum」→「visit」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 28, 2006: Jiro KAWASAKI, Minister of Health, Labour and Welfare visited the museum</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、他の表記に合わせ&quot;visited&quot;と過去形にし、目的語を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="49">
<j>2006年（平成18年）9月4日 – ILO（国際労働機関）事務局長マリア・A・ドゥッチ来館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 4, 2006: Maria-Angelica Ducci, Executive Director of the Office of the Director-General of International Labour Organization (ILO) visited this museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 4, 2006: Maria-Angelica Ducci, Executive Director of Office of Director-General of International Labour Organization (ILO) visit.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list.「visited this museum」→「visit」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 4, 2006: Maria-Angelica Ducci, Executive Director of Office of Director-General of International Labour Organization (ILO) visited the museum</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除、他の表記に合わせ&quot;visited&quot;と過去形にし、目的語を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="50">
<j>2007年（平成19年）12月24日 - 「独立行政法人整理合理化計画」の策定（閣議決定）（「私のしごと館」組織体制の抜本的見直し）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 24, 2007: &quot;Plans for Streamlining Independent Administrative Institutions&quot;was formulated (the Cabinet&apos;s decision); the organization of the Vocational Museum was to be drastically reviewed.</e>
<cmt>独立行政法人整理合理化計画→Plans for Streamlining Independent Administrative Institutions[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 24, 2007: &quot;Plans for Streamlining Independent Administrative Institutions&quot; formulated (Cabinet decision); organization of Vocational Museum to be overhauled.</e>
<cmt>Particles and unnecessary words removed as this and the following sentences are part of a list. 「drastically reviewed」→「overhauled」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 24, 2007: &apos;Plans for Streamlining Independent Administrative Institutions&apos; formulated (Cabinet decision); organization of Vocational Museum to be overhauled</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更、ピリオドを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Programs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Programs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Programs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>スローガンは「しごとの体験未来がかわる」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its slogan is &quot;Work experience makes your future.&quot;</e>
<cmt>しごとの体験未来がかわる→Work experience makes your future[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its slogan is &quot;Work experience makes your future.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its slogan is &apos;Work experience makes your future.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>国や研究機関等の長年にわたる研究成果を柱に、教育関係者や民間企業を含むあらゆる方々の知恵やノウハウを加え、「見て、触れて、感じて、学ぶ」を根本として各種事業を実施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the study achievement of the nation and research institutions, it borrows all the knowledge and wisdom of educational professionals and companies to carry out various programs with the basic idea &quot;Learn by seeing, touching, and feeling.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the collective study achievement of the nation and research institutions, it borrows all the knowledge and wisdom of educational professionals and companies to carry out various programs under the basic idea &quot;Learn by seeing, touching, and feeling.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「collective」挿入, 「with」→「under」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the collective study achievement of the nation and research institutions, it borrows all the knowledge and wisdom of educational professionals and companies to carry out various programs under the basic idea &apos;Learn by seeing, touching, and feeling.&apos;</e>
<cmt>“Learn by seeing, touching, and feeling.”のクォーテーションを半角およびシングルに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="53">
<j>日本のトロンプロジェクトに代表されるすぐれたバーチャルミュージアム、デジタルライブラリィ、アミューズメント施設の成果等をふんだんに取り入れているので、老若男女は問わず家族でも楽しめるが、主な対象はあくまで中高生を中心とする青少年であり、彼ら、彼女らが豊かで充実した職業人生を送れるためのあらゆる事業を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It provides wide variety of programs that help young people such as high school or junior high school students, who are main customers, to lead a rich life with satisfactory occupations, incorporating technologies of excellent virtual museum by the Tron Project in Japan, digital libraries, and amusement facilities, which are enjoyable by every generation and families as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It provides a wide variety of programs that help young people such as high school or junior high school students, who are the main participants, to lead a rich life with satisfying jobs, and incorporates technologies of the excellent virtual museum by the Tron Project in Japan, digital libraries, and amusement facilities, which are enjoyable by every generation and families as well.</e>
<cmt>「a」挿入, 「customers」→「participants」, 「satisfactory occupations」→「satisying jobs」,「and」挿入,「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It provides a wide variety of programs that help young people such as high school or junior high school students, who are the main participants, to lead a rich life with satisfying jobs, and incorporates technologies of the excellent virtual museum, digital libraries, and amusement facilities, as represented by the Tron Project in Japan, which are enjoyable by every generation and families as well.</e>
<cmt>「に代表される」という意味を明確にするため、by the Tron Project→as represented by the Tron Projectとし、位置を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="54">
<j>特に修学旅行、校外学習の誘致に力を入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is working hard to attract especially students on school excursions and extension courses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particular efforts are made to attract students on school excursions and extension courses.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particular efforts are made to attract students on school excursions and extension courses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="55">
<j>展示体験事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hands-on displays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hands-on displays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hands-on displays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="56">
<j>展示体験を通じ、楽しみながら職業人について学び、職業への動機づけを促す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hands-on experiences give visitors fun to learn about professionals and help them to have aspirations for jobs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hands-on experiences are fun for visitors to learn about professionals and help them to have aspirations in relation to jobs.</e>
<cmt>「give visitors fun」→「are fun for visitors」, 「for」→「in relation to」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hands-on experiences are fun for visitors to learn about professionals and help them to have aspirations in relation to jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="57">
<j>ライブラリィ事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Libraries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Libraries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Libraries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="58">
<j>個々の職業について、職業についての必要な情報の収集、コンテンツの制作を行い、書籍、視聴覚資料等を最新のICT技術を用い、しごと館内外に広く提供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This program collects information on every job, creates contents of them, and provides people over the world with those contents in the form of books, movies and other audio-visual media making use of the latest Information and Communication Technology (ICT).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This program collects information on every job, creates content relating to them, and provides people across the world with this content in the form of books, movies and other audio-visual media making use of the latest Information and Communication Technology (ICT).</e>
<cmt>「contents of」→「content relating to」, 「over」→「across」,「those contents」→「this content」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This program collects information on every job, creates content relating to them, and provides people across the world with this content in the form of books, movies and other audio-visual media making use of the latest Information and Communication Technology (ICT).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="59">
<j>相談・援助事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Counseling and support</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Counseling and support</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Counseling and support</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="60">
<j>自ら職業生活設計を行い適切な努力ができるよう、最新の研究成果をふまえたキャリアカウンセリングの実施、適職検査、職業探索、早期就職準備をはかるためのグループ活動等を行う機会を提供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to help young people to design appropriately their future career by themselves, this program provides them with career counseling based on the latest study achievements, vocational aptitude examinations, job search services, and opportunities to join groups for early preparations for finding jobs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to help young people to design their future career appropriately by themselves, this program provides them with career counseling based on the results of the latest research, vocational aptitude examinations, job search services, and opportunities to form groups to make early preparations for finding jobs.</e>
<cmt>「appropriately」箇所異動,「latest study achievements」→「results of the latest research」, 「join」→「form」,「for」→「to make」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to help young people to design their future career appropriately by themselves, this program provides them with career counseling based on the results of the latest research, vocational aptitude examinations, job search services, and opportunities to form groups to make early preparations for finding jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="61">
<j>研修・セミナー事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Training and seminars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Training and seminars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Training and seminars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="62">
<j>主に進路指導やキャリアカウンセリングにかかわる人に、自己啓発、職業選択、職業生活設計、能力開発等をテーマとした各種研修・セミナーを実施し、専門知識、技能を提供する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This program provides career counselors and career guides with professional skills and expertise by giving various trainings and seminars on self-development, job selection, career design, and ability development.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This program provides career counselors and career guides with professional skills and expertise by giving varied training and seminars on self-development, job selection, career design, and ability development.</e>
<cmt>「various trainings」→「varied training」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This program provides career counselors and career guides with professional skills and expertise by giving varied training and seminars on self-development, job selection, career design, and ability development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="63">
<j>企画・開発創造事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Planning and creative development</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Planning and creative development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Planning and creative development</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="64">
<j>各事業に係るツールの開発と制作、若年者を対象としたキャリアカウンセリングに係る企画、研究開発、その成果の普及活動を実施する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This program creates tools for other programs, makes plans for career counseling, carries out R&amp;D of them, and disseminates their products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This program creates tools for other programs, makes plans for career counseling, carries out R&amp;D, and disseminates products.</e>
<cmt>「of them」削除,「their」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This program creates tools for other programs, makes plans for career counseling, carries out R&amp;D, and disseminates products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>コンテンツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>展示、体験における職業体験手法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hands-on displays which provide work experiences</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hands-on displays which provide work experience</e>
<cmt>「experiences」→「experience」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hands-on displays which provide work experience</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>適性、適職検査</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vocational aptitude evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vocational aptitude evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vocational aptitude evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="67">
<j>研修・セミナー事業で活用される能力開発、キャリアカウンセリング手法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aptitude development and career counseling method used for vocational training and seminars</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aptitude development and career counseling method used for vocational training and seminars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aptitude development and career counseling method used for vocational training and seminars</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="68">
<j>しごとライブラリー（映像コンテンツ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Work Library (visual contents)</e>
<cmt>しごとライブラリー→Work Library（しごとライブラリー）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work Library (visual contents)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work Library (visual contents)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="69">
<j>仕事をテーマにし、703職種を集めた世界最大の職業映像コンテンツ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">World&apos;s largest visual contents of 703 jobs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">World&apos;s largest visual contents of 703 jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">World&apos;s largest visual contents of 703 jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>私のしごと館ホームページ「Job Job World」からも視聴できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are available to be seen at the web page of Vocational Museum &quot;Job Job World.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are available at the web page of Vocational Museum &quot;Job Job World.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「to be seen」削除,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are available at the web page of Vocational Museum &apos;Job Job World.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="71">
<j>しごとライブラリーテキスト</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Work Library texts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work Library texts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work Library texts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="72">
<j>しごとライブラリー（書籍版旺文社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Work Library (books published by Obunsha)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work Library (books published by Obunsha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work Library (books published by Obunsha)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="73">
<j>しごとライブラリーの書籍版、しごと百科全書のようなもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Work Library books, or encyclopedia of jobs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work Library books, or encyclopedia of jobs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work Library books, or encyclopedia of jobs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="74">
<j>しごとまなびシート、ワークシート</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learn work sheets: worksheets</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Work skill sheets: worksheets</e>
<cmt>「Learn work」→「Work skill」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Work skill sheets: worksheets</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="75">
<j>オリジナルビデオ「プロが語る職業のすべて」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Original video &quot;Professionals&apos; talks: what the job is all about.&quot;</e>
<cmt>プロが語る職業のすべて→Professionals&apos; talks: what the job is all about[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Original video &quot;Professionals&apos; talks: what the job is all about.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Original video &apos;Professionals&apos; talks: what the job is all about.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="76">
<j>「サクセスノート中学生・高校生の職業観・勤労観の形成支援ワークブック」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Success notebook: workbook for high school and junior high school students to help them develop career views and work views&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Success notebook: workbook for high school and junior high school students to help them develop career views and work views&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Success notebook: workbook for high school and junior high school students to help them develop career views and work views&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="77">
<j>その他順次制作、更新中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More are under construction or updating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More are under construction or are being updated.</e>
<cmt>「updating」→「are being updated」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More are under construction or are being updated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="78">
<j>コンテンツ制作、配信にあたっては、多数の展示ディスプレイ会社、広告代理店、映像制作会社、出版社、情報システム会社等との協力により行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Creation and distribution of these contents are conducted in corporation with many exhibition and display service companies, advertisement agents, video picture producers, publishers, and information systems companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The creation and distribution of this content is conducted in co-operation with many exhibition and display service companies, advertisement agents, video picture producers, publishers, and information systems companies.</e>
<cmt>「The」挿入, 「these contents are」→「this content is」, 「corporation」→「co-operation」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The creation and distribution of this content is conducted in co-operation with many exhibition and display service companies, advertisement agents, video picture producers, publishers, and information systems companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>キッザニアとの主な違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What are different from Kidzania:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main differences with Kidzania</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Differences with Kidzania</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>2006年10月、日本に民営施設であるキッザニア東京がオープンした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 2006, Kidzania Tokyo, a private facility, was opened in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 2006, Kidzania Tokyo, a private facility, was opened in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 2006, Kidzania Tokyo, a private facility, was opened in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>「私のしごと館」と「キッザニア」は未成年に仕事を体験させる点では共通しているが、両施設には以下のような違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Vocational Museum and Kidzania both provide minors with work experiences, there are differences between them as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Vocational Museum and Kidzania both provide minors with work experiences, there are differences between them as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Vocational Museum and Kidzania both provide minors with work experiences, there are differences between them as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>キッザニアはメキシコにおいて1999年に開館した「営利目的」の民間施設である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidzania is a &quot;for-profit&quot; private facility that opened in Mexico in 1999.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidzania is a &quot;for-profit&quot; private facility that opened in Mexico in 1999.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidzania is a &apos;for-profit&apos; private facility that opened in Mexico in 1999.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>私のしごと館はそれ以前より準備がなされていた「非営利」の公営施設である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Vocational Museum had been prepared before that and it is &quot;non-profit&quot; public facility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Vocational Museum has a longer history and is a &quot;non-profit&quot; public facility.</e>
<cmt>「had been prepared before that and it is」→「has a longer history and is a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Vocational Museum has a longer history and is a &apos;non-profit&apos; public facility.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>キッザニアは「こどもによる こどもたちの国」という宣言のとおり、児童を主な対象としており、特に日本においては「児童に社会体験の機会を与える」ことに重点を置く運営をめざしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidzania&apos;s main customers are children (sixth graders or smaller) as its declaration says, &quot;the country of children, and by children,&quot; and its operation in Japan aims at &quot;providing children with social experiences.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidzania&apos;s main customers are children (sixth graders or younger) as its declaration suggests, &quot;the country of children, and by children,&quot; and its operation in Japan aims at &quot;providing children with social experiences.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「smaller」→「younger」, 「says」→「suggests」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidzania&apos;s main customers are children (sixth graders or younger) as its declaration suggests, &apos;the country of children, and by children,&apos; and its operation in Japan aims at &apos;providing children with social experiences.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Kidzania’sのアポストロフィーを半角に変更、クォーテーションを半角およびシングルに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>また、職業体験には年齢制限（上限・下限）を設けるほか、職業体験中は保護者の介入を原則認めないなど、「こどもの街」としてのリアリティを徹底させる考え方をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidzania insists keeping its reality of &quot;children&apos;s town&quot; as real as possible by setting age limits (upper and lower limits) for work experiences, and asking parents to keep off their children during the experiences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidzania insists upon preserving the idea of the &quot;children&apos;s town&quot; by setting upper and lower age limits and encouraginging parents to remain apart from their children during the experience.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidzania insists upon preserving the idea of the &apos;children&apos;s town&apos; by setting upper and lower age limits and encouraginging parents to remain apart from their children during the experience.</e>
<cmt>“children’s town”→&apos;children&apos;s town&apos;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="85">
<j>私のしごと館は、雇用対策基本計画に基づいて設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Vocational Museum was established in accordance with the Basic Plan for Employment Measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Vocational Museum was established in accordance with the Basic Plan for Employment Measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Vocational Museum was established in accordance with the Basic Plan for Employment Measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>「しごと」に重点を置き、展示体験のみならず、「見て、触れて、感じて、学ぶ」ための各コーナーが設置され、「私のしごと」へとたどりつけるためあらゆる手法を用いた、若年者への総合的な職業意識啓発（職業教育、キャリア教育）をめざしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It places emphasis on &quot;work&quot; and provides various setups to &quot;learn by seeing, touching, and feeling,&quot; as well as hands-on displays, and it aims at the comprehensive promotion of vocational aspiration (occupational and career education) for young people using every method to help them find &quot;most fitted jobs.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It places emphasis on &quot;work&quot; and provides various setups to &quot;learn by seeing, touching, and feeling,&quot; as well as hands-on displays, and it aims at the comprehensive promotion of vocational aspirations (occupational and career education) for young people using every method to help them find the most appropriate jobs for them.</e>
<cmt>「aspiration」→「aspirations」, 「&quot;most fitted jobs&quot;」→「the most appropriate jobs for them」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It places emphasis on &apos;work&apos; and provides various setups to &apos;learn by seeing, touching, and feeling,&apos; as well as hands-on displays, and it aims at the comprehensive promotion of vocational aspirations (occupational and career education) for young people using every method to help them find the most appropriate jobs for them.</e>
<cmt>“ ”→すべてシングルクォーテーション、半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>「こどもの街」という考え方はなく、かわりに「しごとの街」というエリアがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It does not have any idea of &quot;children&apos;s town,&quot; but instead, it has an area called &quot;Jobs town.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It does not have any concept of a &quot;children&apos;s town,&quot; but instead, it has an area called &quot;Jobs town.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「idea」→「concept」, 「a」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It does not have any concept of a &apos;children&apos;s town,&apos; but instead, it has an area called &apos;Jobs town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>すべてシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="88">
<j>私のしごと館の娯楽性は、主な対象である学生・若年者に、「しごと」への興味をうながすため、最新の博物館学や、アミューズメント施設等の成果を応用したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It entertains young people and students, who are main targets, by using applications of the latest museology and amusement facilities to encourage them to have interest on &quot;jobs.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It entertains young people and students, who are main targets, by using applications of the latest museology and amusement facilities to encourage them to have interest in &quot;jobs.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「on」→「in」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It entertains young people and students, who are main targets, by using applications of the latest museology and amusement facilities to encourage them to have interest in &apos;jobs.&apos;</e>
<cmt>“jobs.”→&apos;jobs.&apos;に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="89">
<j>キッザニアの職業経験パビリオンはスポンサー企業から、実際の業務マニュアルの提供を受けた上で、子供向けの体験プログラムに落とし込んだものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kidzania&apos;s pavilion for work experience was made by reprogramming the real operation manuals provided by the sponsor company into experience programs for children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kidzania&apos;s pavilion for work experience was made by reprogramming real operation manuals provided by the sponsor company into experience programs for children.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kidzania&apos;s pavilion for work experience was made by reprogramming real operation manuals provided by the sponsor company into experience programs for children.</e>
<cmt>Kidzania’sのアポストロフィーを半角に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>また、子供の身の丈に合わせたリアリティの確保に力点を置いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It emphasizes on keeping the reality of jobs in children&apos;s world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It emphasizes keeping the reality of jobs in a children&apos;s world.</e>
<cmt>「on」削除, 「a」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It emphasizes keeping the reality of jobs in a children&apos;s world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="91">
<j>私のしごと館のしごと体験ゾーンのコーナー運営は、主に業界団体等が担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Vocational Museum&apos;s work experience zones are largely operated by industry organizations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Vocational Museum&apos;s work experience zones are largely operated by industry organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Vocational Museum&apos;s work experience zones are largely operated by industry organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By car:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By car:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="93">
<j>京奈和自動車道精華学研インターチェンジ下車すぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Close to Keinawa Expressway Seikagakken Interchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Close to Keinawa Expressway Seikagakken Interchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Close to Keinawa Expressway Seikagakken Interchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="94">
<j>鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By train:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By train:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By train:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="95">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道片町線祝園駅、近鉄京都線新祝園駅より奈良交通バス「私のしごと館」で下車後すぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Hosono Station of JR Katamachi Line or Shinhosono Station of Kintetsu Kyoto Line, take Nara Kotsu Bus, and get off at &quot;Watashino Shigoto Kan&quot; bus stop which is very close to the museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Hosono Station on the JR Katamachi Line or Shinhosono Station on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line, take Nara Kotsu Bus, and get off at &quot;Watashino Shigoto Kan&quot; bus stop which is very close to the museum.</e>
<cmt>「of」→「on the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Hosono Station on the JR Katamachi Line or Shinhosono Station on the Kintetsu Kyoto Line, take Nara Kotsu Bus, and get off at &apos;Watashino Shigoto Kan&apos; bus stop which is very close to the museum.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>所要時間約5分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Required time: approximately five minutes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Required time: approximately five minutes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Required time: approximately five minutes.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kikukikukikukikukiku(id:155913), ポポロ(id:119934), ROG(id:43532), 北大(id:110491), Ignis(id:28979), Crton(id:101494), Nichibi(id:163803), Cotatsu(id:90189), 野草(やそう）(id:97678), Rusk(id:9895), 準急三条(id:25072), Tsurugi(id:5534), ぱむ(id:24323), Hana-p(id:133035), T sawachan(id:29151), Pochacco562000(id:70889), Sorainu(id:64925), Imses(id:37755), Rikue(id:172140), Tamago915(id:11009), Cyberarts(id:52929), 野草(id:110313), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), ネッツ(id:150295), 野草(やそう)(id:93101), ホイップ(id:44812), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>