<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>八木城 (丹波国)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle (Tanba Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yagi-jo Castle (Tanba Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle (Tanba Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>八木城（やぎじょう）は京都府南丹市八木町八木および亀岡市宮前町神前周辺にあった城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was a castle which existed around Yagi, Yagi-cho, Mantan City, Kyoto Prefecture and Kozaki, Miyazaki-cho, Kameoka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yagi-jo Castle was a castle which existed in the vicinity of Yagi, Yagi-cho, Mantan City, Kyoto Prefecture and Kozaki, Miyazaki-cho, Kameoka City.</e>
<cmt>・「which」→「that」・「around」→「in the vicinity of」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was a castle which existed in the vicinity of Yagi, Yagi-cho, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture and Kozaki, Miyazaki-cho, Kameoka City.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>内藤ジョアンゆかりの城としても有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was famous as the castle associated with Joan NAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was famous as the castle associated with Joan NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was famous as the castle associated with Joan NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>丹波国三大城郭のひとつで、黒井城、八上城そして八木城が数えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was one of three major castles in Tanba Province; Kuroi Castle, yakami-jo Castle, Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was one of the three major castles of Tanba Province; Kuroi Castle, Yakami-jo Castle, Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「the」を補足・「in」→「of」・「yakami-jo」→「Yakami-jo」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was one of the three major castles of Tanba Province; Kuroi-jo Castle, Yakami-jo Castle, Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道八木駅の南西にある、標高344mにある城山にある複合梯格式の山城である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a multiple ladder type yama-jiro (castles built on the top of mountains or halfway up the mountains for defensive reasons) on Shiroyama, which was 344 meters in height, located in the southwest of JR West Yagi Station.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明ですが、複合梯格式→multiple ladder type と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a multiple teikaku-shiki (the central compound is placed adjacent to the castle walls, and additional compounds are placed surrounding the honmaru) mountain castle which stood at an altitude of 344m to the southwest of JR West Yagi Station.</e>
<cmt>・原文の「複合梯格式」を「複合梯郭式」に修正・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a multiple teikaku-shiki (the central compound is placed adjacent to the castle walls, and additional compounds are placed surrounding the honmaru) mountain castle which stood at an altitude of 344 m to the southwest of JR West Yagi Station.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>城郭施設の広さは広大で、山頂部に本丸、支尾根筋にも多数の曲輪などの防御施設が築かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle facility was vast; defense facilities such as Honmaru (the keep of a castle) on the mountain top, many Kuruwa (a space reserved for various purposes) along the ridge line were built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle was vast, with the central compound built on the top the mountain and various defenses such as additional compounds built on branching ridges.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle was vast, with the central compound built on the top of the mountain and various defenses such as additional compounds built on branching ridges.</e>
<cmt>of補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在でも、本丸、天守台、石垣といった遺構が地表面から確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient structural remnants including Honmaru, tenshu (main keep or tower of a castle) dai (platform), stone walls are seen on the land surface even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, remnants of the central copound, tenshudai (independent raised foundation upon which the castle keep was constructed) and stone walls can be seen on the surface of the ground.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, remnants of the central compound, tenshudai (independent raised foundation upon which the castle keep was constructed) and stone walls can be seen on the surface of the ground.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ただ、沿革についてはよく解っていない点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, its history was not well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are many unknown factors regarding the history of the castle.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are many unknown factors regarding the history of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>八木城の記載されている史料は多く、『太閤記』『明智軍記』『丹波風土記』『丹波興廃記』『籾井家日記』『内藤盛衰記』『八木町誌』等がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many historical materials that describe Yagi-jo Castle; &quot;Taikoki&quot; (Chronicle of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; (biography of Mitsuhide AKECHI), &quot;Tanba fudoki&quot; (Tanba record of local customs), &quot;丹波興廃記,&quot; &quot;Momi-ke nikki&quot; (Diary of Momi Family), Naito Seisuiki (The Rise and Fall of the Naito), &quot;Yagi-cho Journal&quot; etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。八木町誌→定訳不明ですが、→Yagi-cho Journal と訳出しました。丹波興廃記→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many historical sources that describe Yagi-jo Castle including &quot;Taikoki&quot; (Chronicle of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; (Biography of Mitsuhide AKECHI), &quot;Tanba Fudoki&quot; (Tanba Province Gazetteer), &quot;Tanba Kohaiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of Tanba), &quot;Momi-ke Nikki&quot; (Diary of the Momi Family), &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of the Naito Clan), and &quot;Yagi-cho Shi&quot; (Yagi Town Journal&quot;).</e>
<cmt>・「materials」→「sources」・「;」→「including」・「各書籍名を修正・「and」を補足・「etc」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many historical sources that describe Yagi-jo Castle including &quot;Taikoki&quot; (Chronicle of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), &quot;Akechi Gunki&quot; (Biography of Mitsuhide AKECHI), &quot;Tanba Fudoki&quot; (Tanba Province Gazetteer), &quot;Tanba Kohaiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of Tanba), &quot;Momi-ke Nikki&quot; (Diary of the Momi Family), &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of the Naito Clan), and &quot;Yagi-cho Shi&quot; (Yagi Town Journal&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『日本城郭大系』によるとこれらの史料は原史料の十分な考察がされないまま引用され、それらが更に孫引用され誤りが多いのではないかとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Japanese Castle History,&quot; these historical materials were cited from the sources which were cited from the original historical materials which were not well examined, thus, causing many mistakes.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。日本城郭大系→定訳不明のため暫定的に→Japanese castle history と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon Jokaku Taikei&quot; (Compendium of Japanese Castles) postulates that many mistakes have arisen due to the citation of these historical sources without sufficient examination of the original documents, and further secondary citations.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Jokaku Taikei&quot; (Compendium of Japanese Castles) postulates that many mistakes have arisen due to the citation of these historical sources without sufficient examination of the original documents, and further secondary citations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、内藤氏（丹波系）の居城であった他は、その存続期間や城主の系譜については明確でない点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many points which are unclear regarding its lifetime and the genealogy of the castellan, apart from the fact that it was the castle of the Naito clan (Tanba lineage).</e>
<cmt>内藤氏内藤氏→内藤氏と考え訳出しています。一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aside from the fact that it was the residence of the Naito clan (Tanba branch), there are many points which are unclear regarding the lifetime and genealogy of the castle.</e>
<cmt>・「its lifetime and the genealogy of the castellan」→「the lifetime and genealogy of the castle」・「apart」→「aside」・「castle]→「residence」・「lineage」→「branch」・再構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aside from the fact that it was the residence of the Naito clan (Tanba branch), there are many points which are unclear regarding the lifetime and genealogy of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>八木城は有名な山城ではあるが、不明な点も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was a famous yama-jiro (castles built on the top of mountains or halfway up the mountains for defensive reasons), but many points are not clear regarding Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yagi-jo Castle is a well-known mountain castle but there are many unclear points.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle is a well-known mountain castle but there are many unclear points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>元弘3年(1333年)足利尊氏が丹波篠村八幡宮での挙兵に応じた内藤顕勝（定房とも）が戦功により船井郡を与えられ建武 (日本)2年（1335年）に八木に入ったのが築城の始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the history of Yagi-jo Castle began when Takauji ASHIKAGA entered Yagi-jo in 1335 after he was granted the Funai district for the achievement in war he made with the cooperation of Akikatsu NAITO (may be called the Sadafusa) who agreed to rise in arm in Shinomura Tanba Hachiman-gu Shrine in 1333.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明ですが、内藤顕勝（定房とも）→Akikatsu NAITO (may be called the Sadafusa) と訳出しています。元弘3年(1333年)足利尊氏が丹波篠村八幡宮での挙兵に応じた内藤顕勝（定房とも）が戦功により→現状では文意が不明なため→元弘3年(1333年)足利尊氏が丹波篠村八幡宮での挙兵に応じた内藤顕勝（定房とも）との戦功によりと解釈し訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the history of Yagi-jo Castle began when Akikatsu NAITO (also called Sadafusa) entered Yagi having been granted the Funai district in 1335 because of his military exploits when his army fought alongside Takauji ASHIKAGA in Shinomura Tanba Hachiman-gu Shrine in 1333.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the history of Yagi-jo Castle began when Akikatsu NAITO (also called Sadafusa) entered Yagi having been granted the Funai district in 1335 because of his military exploits when his army fought alongside Takauji ASHIKAGA in Shinomura Tanba Hachiman-gu Shrine in 1333.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>『満済准后日記』の永享3年（1431年）7月24日に持之将軍義教ノ命ニヨリ守護代ヲ香西ヨリ内藤備前入道ニ替エルと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the section of July 24, 1431 of &quot;Mansai Jugo nikki diary,&quot; it is stated `Under the order of Yoshinori Shogun, Mochiyuki replaced KAZAI with Naito Bizen Nyudo as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable).&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the July 24, 1431 entry of &quot;Mansai Jugo Nikki&quot; it is stated that `Under the order of Shogun Yoshinori, Mochiyuki replaced KAZAI with Naito Bizen Nyudo as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo (provincial constable)).&apos;</e>
<cmt>・「In the section of July 24, 1431」→「In the July 24, 1431 entry」・「&quot;Mansai Jugo nikki diary,&quot;」→「&quot;Mansai Jugo Nikki&quot;」・「that」を補足・「Yoshinori Shogun」→「Shogun Yoshinori」・「the」を補足・括弧を補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the July 24, 1431 entry of &quot;Mansai Jugo Nikki&quot; it is stated that `Under the order of Shogun Yoshinori, Mochiyuki replaced Kazai with Naito Bizen Nyudo as Shugodai (deputy of Shugo (provincial constable)).&apos;</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>細川氏の被官となっていた内藤備前入道こと内藤信承が丹波国の守護代となったことにより、八木城は守護代である内藤氏の威勢を示すものとして本格的に拡張されはじめたものと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that the fact that Naito Bizen Nyudo, or Nobusuke NAITO who had been the hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of the Hosokawa clan became the Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Tanba Province facilitated to fully extend Yagi-jo as Yagi-jo was considered to indicate the power of the Naito clan that was Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that the fact that Naito Bizen Nyudo, also known as Nobusuke NAITO, who had been the hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of the Hosokawa clan became the Shugodai of Tanba Province facilitated the full-scale expansion of Yagi-jo Castle for the reason that Yagi-jo Castle displayed the power of the Naito clan which served as Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>・「or Nobusuke NAITO」→「also known as Nobusuke NAITO,」・「(deputy of Shugo, provincial constable)」を削除・「to fully extend Yagi-jo」→「the full-scale expansion of Yagi-jo Castle」・「as」→「for the reason that」・「Yagi-jo」→「Yagi-jo Castle」・「was considered to indicate」→「displayed」・「that was」→「which served as」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the fact that Naito Bizen Nyudo, also known as Nobusuke NAITO, who had been the hikan (low-level bureaucrat) of the Hosokawa clan became the Shugodai of Tanba Province facilitated the full-scale expansion of Yagi-jo Castle for the reason that Yagi-jo Castle displayed the power of the Naito clan which served as Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>信承は嘉吉2年（1442年）もしくは嘉吉3年（1443年）に死去あるいは更迭されたようで、嘉吉3年（1443年）6月には次の丹波国の守護代として内藤之貞が任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobusuke seemed to be dead or removed in 1442 or 1443, and Koresada NAITO was assigned as the subsequent Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Tanba Province in June 1443.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears as though Nobusuke had died or been replaced in 1442 or 1443, and Koresada NAITO was assigned as the subsequent Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Tanba Province in June 1443.</e>
<cmt>・「Nobusuke seemed to be dead or removed」→「It appears as though Nobusuke had died or been replaced」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears as though Nobusuke had died or been replaced in 1442 or 1443, and Koresada NAITO was assigned as the subsequent Shugodai (deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Tanba Province in June 1443.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また1449年（宝徳元年）-1452年（享徳元年）には内藤元貞と交替していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period from 1449 to 1452, he seemed to be replaced with Motosada NAITO.</e>
<cmt>また-には→1449年（宝徳元年）-1452年（享徳元年）として訳出しています。（wikipedia 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that he was replaced by Motosada NAITO between 1449 and 1452.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that he was replaced by Motosada NAITO between 1449 and 1452.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後上原元秀が文明 (日本)14年（1482年）12月に丹波国守護代になったようだ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, it seems that Motohide UEHARA became the Shugodai of Tanba Province in December, 1482.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Motohide UEHARA subsequently became the Shugodai of Tanba Province in December 1482.</e>
<cmt>・「Afterward,」を削除・「subsequently」を追加・コンマを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Motohide UEHARA subsequently became the Shugodai of Tanba Province in January 1483.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが、明応2年（1493年）10月に長塩弥六との刃傷沙汰があって、同年11月に死亡したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that he died in November 1493, after the knife fight with Yaroku NAGASHIO in October in the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it appears that he died in November 1493, after becoming wounded in a dispute with Yaroku NAGASHIO in October in the same year.</e>
<cmt>・「However,」を補足・「seems」→「appears」・「the knife fight」→「becoming wounded in a dispute」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it appears that he died in December 1493, after becoming wounded in a dispute with Yaroku NAGASHIO in November in the same year.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>『大乗院寺社雑事記』の明応4年（1495年）8月24日に、細川自丹波国上洛、守護代事内藤二返給了とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the section of August 24, 1495 of &quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine), it is stated that HOSOKAWA entered the Tanba province, and newly assigned NAITO to Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the August 24, 1495 entry of &quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine), it is stated that HOSOKAWA entered Tanba Province, and newly appointed NAITO as Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>・「In the section of August 24, 1495」→「In the August 24, 1495 entry」・「the」を削除・「province」→「Province」・「assigned NAITO to」→「appointed NAITO as」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the August 24, 1495 entry of &quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine), it is stated that Hosokawa entered Tanba Province, and newly appointed Naito as Shugodai.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>上原元秀の息子上原賢家の没落後は内藤元貞が再び守護代に戻ったものと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to it, Motosada NAITO came back to the post of Shugodai after Motohide UEHARA&apos;s son, Kataie UEHARA was downfallen..</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The text states that Motosada NAITO reassumed the position of Shugodai after the downfall of Motohide UEHARA&apos;s son, Kataie UEHARA.</e>
<cmt>・「According to it」→「The text states that」・「came back to」→「reassumed」・「the downfall of」を追加・「was downfallen.」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The text states that Motosada NAITO reassumed the position of Shugodai after the downfall of Motohide UEHARA&apos;s son, Kataie UEHARA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その後1505年（永正2年）-1521年（大永元年）迄は内藤貞正が守護代となり、続いて内藤国貞が守護となったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, it is regarded that Sadamasa NAITO had been Shugodai until the time of 1505-1521, and then Kunisada NAITO became a Shigodai.</e>
<cmt>その後-迄は→until the time of 1505-1521と訳しています。（wikipedia 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is regarded that Sadamasa NAITO subsequently became Shugodai until between 1505 and 1521, when he was succeeded by Kunisada NAITO.</e>
<cmt>・「Thereafter,」を削除・「subsequently」を追加・「became」→「served as」・「the time of 1505-1521」→「1505-1521」・「and then」→「followed by」・「became a Shigodai」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is regarded that Sadamasa NAITO subsequently became Shugodai until between 1505 and 1521, when he was succeeded by Kunisada NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし細川氏綱、三好長慶に味方して以降、八木城は幾度か戦場となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yagi-jo Castle turned out to be the battle area for several times, after Kunisada NAITO supported Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA and Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yagi-jo Castle came to serve as a battlefield several times, after Kunisada NAITO allied with Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA and Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>・「turned out to be the」→「came to serve as a」・「battle area」→「battlefield」・「for」を削除・「supported」→「allied with」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yagi-jo Castle came to serve as a battlefield several times, after Kunisada NAITO allied with Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA and Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>『細川両家記』等によると天文 (元号)22年（1553年）9月に落城し内藤国貞も討ち死にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hosokawa ryoke ki &quot; (Record of the two houses of Hosokawa), when Yagi-jo fell in September, 1553, Kunisada NAITO also died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to sources including &quot;Hosokawa Ryoke Ki &quot; (Record of the two houses of Hosokawa), when Yagi-jo fell in September, 1553, Kunisada NAITO also died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>・「sources including」を補足・「Hosokawa ryoke ki」→「Hosokawa Ryoke Ki」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to sources including &quot;Hosokawa Ryoke Ki &quot; (Record of the two houses of Hosokawa), when Yagi-jo Castle fell in October, 1553, Kunisada NAITO also died in the battle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後松永久秀の弟松永長頼が八木城を奪還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, Hisahide MATSUNAGA&apos;s younger brother, Nagayori MATSUNAGA recaptured Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Hisahide MATSUNAGA&apos;s younger brother, Nagayori MATSUNAGA regained Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「After that」→「Following this」・「regained」→「recaptured」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Hisahide MATSUNAGA&apos;s younger brother, Nagayori MATSUNAGA regained Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>松永長頼は三好氏軍の中で十河一存と並び早くから軍功をあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayori MATSUNAGA, on a par with Kazumasa SOGO, made achievement in war earlier than other members of the Miyoshi clan force</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayori MATSUNAGA, along with Kazumasa SOGO, achieved success in war earlier than other members of the Miyoshi clan force.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayori MATSUNAGA, along with Kazumasa SOGO, achieved success in war earlier than other members of the Miyoshi clan force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>三好長慶の信頼が厚かった人物であったと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was believed to be the person who was deeply trusted by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is believed to have been someone who was deeply trusted by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>・「was」→「is」・「be」→「have been」・「the person」→「someone」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is believed to have been someone who was deeply trusted by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『戦国三好一族』によると「丹波が13年間に亙って三好氏の版図であったのは、専ら彼（松永長頼）の軍略によるところが多い」と解説している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was stated in&quot;Sengoku Miyoshi ichizoku&quot; that `Tanba Province has been the territory of the Miyoshi clan for thirteen years, which was mainly attributed to his (Nagayori MATSUNAGA) strategic skills.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sengoku Miyoshi ichizoku&quot; states that &apos;It was mainly due to his (Nagayori MATSUNAGA) tactical skill that Tanba Province remained the territory of the Miyoshi clan for 13 years&apos;.</e>
<cmt>・「It was stated in&quot;Sengoku Miyoshi ichizoku&quot;」→「&quot;Sengoku Miyoshi ichizoku&quot; states」・「`Tanba Province has been the territory of the Miyoshi clan for thirteen years, which was mainly attributed to his (Nagayori MATSUNAGA) strategic skills.&apos;」→「&apos;It was mainly due to his (Nagayori MATSUNAGA) tactical skill that Tanba Province remained the territory of the Miyoshi clan for 13 years&apos;.」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sengoku Miyoshi ichizoku&quot; states that &apos;It was mainly due to his (Nagayori MATSUNAGA) tactical skill that Tanba Province remained the territory of the Miyoshi clan for 13 years.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その戦の天才も『多聞院日記』によると永禄8年（1565年）8月、赤井直正の反撃にあって討ち死にしたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Tamonin nikki diary,&quot; the expert of war seemed to be killed by attacks by Naomasa AKAI in August 1565.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Tamonin Nikki&quot;, it appears that this tactical genius was killed in an attack by Naomasa AKAI in August 1565.</e>
<cmt>・「&quot;Tamonin nikki diary,&quot;」→「&quot;Tamonin Nikki&quot;」・コンマを移動・ナチュラルに翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Tamonin Nikki,&quot; it appears that this tactical genius was killed in an attack by Naomasa AKAI in September 1565.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内藤ジョアン時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period of Joan NAITO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Period of Joan NAITO</e>
<cmt>Title caseにしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of Joan NAITO</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>八木城は、内藤ジョアン（内藤如安）の居城として厳しい禁教令（キリスト弾圧）を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was under the Ban on Christianity (Christianity oppression) as the castle of Joan NAITO.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the residence of Joan NAITO, Yagi-jo Castle was under the Kinkyo-rei (Edicts banning Christianity).</e>
<cmt>再構成・「castle」→「residence」・「Ban on Christianity (Christianity oppression)」→「Kinkyo-rei (Edicts banning Christianity)」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the residence of Joan NAITO, Yagi-jo Castle was under the Kinkyo-rei (Edicts banning Christianity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>後難を避けるため史料の多くが故意に書き換えられたり、記録が抹殺されてしまったようで、その真偽を鮮明にすることが非常に困難となってしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To avoid subsequent disasters, many historical materials were intentionally rewritten or some records were destroyed, which made it extremely difficult to ascertain the truth.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To avoid future trouble, it appears that many historical materials were intentionally rewritten and records were destroyed, making it extremely difficult to ascertain the truth.</e>
<cmt>・「subsequent disasters」→「future trouble」・「it appears that」を補足・「or」→「and」・「some」を」削除・「which made」→「making」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To avoid future trouble, it appears that many historical materials were intentionally rewritten and records were destroyed, making it extremely difficult to ascertain the truth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これが有名な城であるが「幻の八木城」と呼ばれる云われで、現在も歴史研究家の調査が継続されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why Yagi-jo Castle is called the `illusory Yagi-jo Castle,&apos; and the research regarding Yagi-jo Castle is still going on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why Yagi-jo Castle is called &quot;Maboroshi no Yagi-jo&quot; (lit. The Phantom Casle of Yagi-jo), and research into Yagi-jo Castle continues even now.</e>
<cmt>・「the `illusory Yagi-jo Castle,&apos;」→「&quot;Maboroshi no Yagi-jo&quot; (lit. The Phantom Casle of Yagi-jo)」・コンマを追加・「the」を削除・「regarding」→「into」・「is still going on.」→「continues even now」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why Yagi-jo Castle is called &apos;Maboroshi no Yagi-jo&apos; (lit. The Phantom Castle of Yagi-jo), and research into Yagi-jo Castle continues even now.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>内藤ジョアンの母は、内藤定房（八木玄夫の論文『丹波八木城と内藤如安』では、定房は内藤国貞の誤記ではないかとしている）の娘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mother of Joan NAITO was a daughter of Sadafusa NAITO (according to 八木玄夫&apos;s article, &quot;Tanba Yagi-jo Castle and Joan NAITO,&quot; Sadafusa might be a mistake, which meant to be Kunisada).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother of Joan NAITO was a daughter of Sadafusa NAITO (according to an article by Motoo YAGI entitled &quot;Tanba Yagi-jo Castle and Joan NAITO&quot;, Sadafusa may be an error for what should be Kunisada).</e>
<cmt>・「八木玄夫&apos;s article,」→「an article by Motoo YAGI entitled」・「might be a mistake which meant to」→「may be an error for what should」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mother of Joan NAITO was a daughter of Sadafusa NAITO (according to an article by Motoo YAGI entitled &quot;Tanba Yagi-jo Castle and Joan NAITO,&quot; Sadafusa may be an error for what should be Kunisada).</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>まず近江国の浅井氏に嫁ぎ一子を設けたが、夫が病死し子を連れて八木城に戻ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">She first married into the Azai clan in Omi Province, and had a child; she came back to Yagi-jo Castle after her husband died.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">She married into the Azai clan in Omi Province, and had a child but returned to Yagi-jo Castle with her child after her husband died.</e>
<cmt>・「first」を削除・「; she」→「but」・「came back」→「returned」・「with her child」を補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">She married into the Azai clan in Omi Province, and had a child but returned to Yagi-jo Castle with her child after her husband died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その子の名は八木玄蕃といい、内藤ジョアンの義兄となり後に家老職を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of her child was Genba YAGI, and he was the elder brother with a different father of Joan NAITO; later on he served as a chief retainer.</e>
<cmt>八木玄蕃→定訳不明ですが→Genba YAGIと訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of her child was Genba YAGI, and served as a karo (chief retainer) after becoming the brother-in-law of Joan NAITO.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of her child was Genba YAGI, and served as a karo (chief retainer) after becoming the brother-in-law of Joan NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後内藤ジョアンの母は細川氏と再婚したが、またしても夫と死別し八木城に戻ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the mother of Joan NAITO remarried the Hosokawa clan, but again her husband died and came back to Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mother of Joan NAITO subsequently remarried into the Hosokawa clan, but she once again returned to Yagi-jo Castle after her husband died.</e>
<cmt>・「After that,」を削除・「subsequently」を追加・「into」を補足・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mother of Joan NAITO subsequently remarried into the Hosokawa clan, but she once again returned to Yagi-jo Castle after her husband died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そのような中、内藤ジョアンの母は松永長頼と三度目になる再婚をし、二子を設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After such experiences, the mother of Joan NAITO remarried Nagayori MATSUNAGA for the third time, and had two children with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was under these circumstances that the mother of Joan NAITO remarried for the third time to Nagayori MATSUNAGA, with whom she had two children.</e>
<cmt>・「After such experiences,」→「It was under these circumstances that」・「for the third time」を移動・「to」を補足・「and had two children with him」→「with whom she had two children」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was under these circumstances that the mother of Joan NAITO remarried for the third time to Nagayori MATSUNAGA, with whom she had two children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>五郎丸後の内藤ジョアンと、妹の内藤ジュリアであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were Joan NAITO, and his younger sister, Julia NAITO.</e>
<cmt>五郎丸後の→定訳・文意ともに不明なため訳出していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were Joan NAITO, who later became Goromaru, and his sister Julia NAITO.</e>
<cmt>・翻訳漏れを修正・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were Joan NAITO, who later became Goromaru, and his sister Julia NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また『戦国三好一族』によると内藤ジョアンは松永長頼の「実子又は養嗣子と推定されている」と養嗣子の可能性も示唆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;Sengoku Miyoshi ichizoku&quot; stated that `Joan NAITO is assumed to be the birth child or the adopted child of Nagayori MATSUNAGA,&apos; indicating that he might be the adopted child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, &quot;Sengoku Miyoshi Ichizoku&quot; states that &apos;Joan NAITO is assumed to be the birth child or the adopted child of Nagayori MATSUNAGA&apos;, indicating the possibility that he may have been adopted.</e>
<cmt>・「ichizoku」→「Ichizoku」・「stated」→「states」・「that he might be the adopted child」→「indicating the possibility that he may have been adopted」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;Sengoku Miyoshi Ichizoku&quot; states that &apos;Joan NAITO is assumed to be the birth child or the adopted child of Nagayori MATSUNAGA,&apos; indicating the possibility that he may have been adopted.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>1553年（天文22年）頃から八上城の城主であった波多野元清の勢力が拡大していき、丹波国を侵し始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The force of Motokiyo HATANO, the castellan of Yagi-jo Castle had been expanding since around 1553, and it started to threaten Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>頃から→since around 1553と訳出しています。（wikipedia 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of Motokiyo HATANO, lord of Yagi-jo Castle had been expanding since circa 1553, and began to threaten Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>・「force」→「power」・「the castellan」→「lord」・「around」→「circa」・「it started」→「began」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power of Motokiyo HATANO, lord of Yagi-jo Castle had been expanding since circa 1553, and began to threaten Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>当時の八木城の城主であった内藤国貞は本梅郷の戦いで討死し、八木城で立て篭もっていた内藤定房も討ち取り、波多野元清軍を前に落城してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castellan of Yagi-jo Castle at that time, Kunisada NAITO was killed in the battle of Honbaigo, and Sadafusa NAITO who entrenched himself in Yagi-jo Castle was also killed, thus, the castle was fallen before the Motokiyo HATANO force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lord of Yagi-jo Castle at that time, Kunisada NAITO, was killed in the battle of Honbaigo, and Sadafusa NAITO who entrenched himself in Yagi-jo Castle was also killed, thus, the castle fell to the army of Motokiyo HATANO.</e>
<cmt>・「castellan」→「lord」・「that」→「the」・コンマを追加・「was fallen before」→「fell to」・「Motokiyo HATANO force」→「army of Motokiyo HATANO」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lord of Yagi-jo Castle at that time, Kunisada NAITO, was killed in the battle of Honbaigo, and Sadafusa NAITO who entrenched himself in Yagi-jo Castle was also killed, thus, the castle fell to the army of Motokiyo HATANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この時、内藤国貞の実子千勝丸は、湯浅宗貞が助け園部城でかくまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The birth child of Kunisada NAITO, 千勝丸 was saved and kept in Sonobe-jo Castle by Munesada YUASA.</e>
<cmt>千勝丸→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The birth child of Kunisada NAITO, Senkatsumaru, was saved and kept at Sonobe-jo Castle by Munesada YUASA.</e>
<cmt>・「千勝丸」→「Senkatsumaru」・コンマを追加・「in」→「at」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The birth child of Kunisada NAITO, Senkatsumaru, was saved and kept at Sonobe-jo Castle by Munesada YUASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>八木城が落城した事に対してに激怒した松永長頼は、出陣先から引き返し奮戦の末、八木城の奪還に成功したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayori MATSUNAGA who was furious when Yagi-jo Castle was fallen, and he came back from the other battle to fight, succeeding in regaining Yagi-jo Castle after the brave fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayori MATSUNAGA was enraged by the falling of Yagi-jo Castle, and left another battle, successfully retaking Yagi-jo Castle after a fierce fight.</e>
<cmt>・「who」を削除・「furious when Yagi-jo Castle was fallen」→「enraged by the falling of Yagi-jo Castle」・「he came back from the other battle」→「left another battle」・「succeeding in regaining」→「successfully retaking」・「the」→「a」・「brave」→「fight」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayori MATSUNAGA was enraged by the falling of Yagi-jo Castle, and left another battle, successfully retaking Yagi-jo Castle after a fierce fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>この時の奮戦ぶりを『足利季世記』によると、松永ハ内藤備前守ガ聟ナレバ、城中モ一入タノモシク思ヒケル、落武者カク計リケル事武功第一ナリト沙汰シケルと記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ashikaga Kiseiki&quot; (a military epic of Ashikaga) states that &apos;Matunaga is a son in low of Naito, a provincial governor of Bizen, and he is a dependable man in the castle particularly; the losers attempted to take over the castle, but he threw them over and took all the credit of war&apos; regarding the fierce fight at that time.</e>
<cmt>松永ハ内藤備前守ガ聟ナレバ、城中モ一入タノモシク思ヒケル、落武者カク計リケル事武功第一ナリト沙汰シケル→解釈については正しいかどうか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ashikaga Kiseiki&quot; (a military epic of Ashikaga) states that &apos;Matsunaga is a son-in-law of Naito - a provincial governor of Bizen, and he is a dependable man in the castle particularly; the losers attempted to take over the castle, but he threw them over and took all the credit of war&apos; regarding the fierce fight at that time.</e>
<cmt>・「Matunaga」→「Matsunaga」・「son in low」→「son-in-law」・「,」→「-」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ashikaga Kiseiki&quot; (a military epic of Ashikaga) states that &apos;Matsunaga is a son-in-law of Naito - a provincial governor of Bizen, and he is a dependable man in the castle particularly; the losers attempted to take over the castle, but he threw them over and took all the credit of war&apos; regarding the fierce fight at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その時の恩賞として征夷大将軍から内藤の姓を許され、内藤宗勝と改名したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family name, NAITO was granted by seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) for his achievement at that time, and he changed his name into Munekatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shogun granted him the family name &quot;Naito&quot; was a reward for his achievement, and it seems that he changed his name to Munekatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shogun granted him the family name &quot;Naito&quot; was a reward for his achievement, and it seems that he changed his name to Munekatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="45">
<j>一方内藤ジョアンは、山口県方面よりお家騒動で八木城を頼って逃げて来た女性がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Joan NAITO had a woman who escaped into Yagi-jo Castle from the direction of Yamagichi Prefecture due to the family feud.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Joan NAITO associated with a woman who had fled to Yagi-jo Castle from the direction of Yamagichi Prefecture due to a family feud.</e>
<cmt>・「had」→「associated with」・「had」を補足・「into」→「to」・「escaped」→「fled」・「a」→「the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Joan NAITO associated with a woman who had fled to Yagi-jo Castle from the direction of Yamaguchi Prefecture due to a family feud.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>名をカタリナといい、『郷土史八木』によると洗礼名しか判っていないとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Her name was katarina, and only her Christian name was known according to &quot;Local history Yagi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。カタリナ→定訳不明のため→katarina と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Her name was Katarina, and only her Christian name was known according to &quot;Kyodoshi Yagi&quot; (Local History of Yagi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>・「katarina」→「Katarina」・「&quot;Local history Yagi.&quot;」→「&quot;Kyodoshi Yagi&quot; (Local History of Yagi&quot;」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Her name was Katarina, and only her Christian name was known according to &quot;Kyodoshi Yagi&quot; (Local History of Yagi).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また『内藤如安の生涯』によると、山口で起きた「お家騒動」とはの陶隆房の反乱（大寧寺の変）ではないかと推察している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Naito Joan no shogai&quot; (The Life of Joan Naito), the `family feud&apos; in Yamagichi prefecture was assumed to be Rebellion of Sue Takafusa (Taineiji no hen, the revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Naito Joan no Shogai&quot; (The Life of Joan Naito), the &apos;family feud&apos; in Yamagichi Prefecture was assumed to be the Rebellion of Sue Takafusa (Taineiji no hen, the revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt>・「shogai」→「Shogai」・「prefecture」→「Prefecture」・「the」を補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Naito Joan no Shogai&quot; (The Life of Joan Naito), the &apos;family feud&apos; in Yamaguchi Prefecture was assumed to be the Rebellion of Sue Takafusa (Taineiji no hen, the revolt of Taineiji).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そのカタリナは、五郎丸と妹ジュリアをわが子のように育てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katarina brought up Goromaru and his younger sister, Julia in the same way as she would bring up her own children.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katarina brought up Goromaru and his younger sister, Julia as if they were her own children.</e>
<cmt>・「in the same way as she would bring up」→「as if they were」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katarina brought up Goromaru and his younger sister, Julia as if they were her own children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>五郎丸とジュリアもカタリナの影響からキリシタンの道に入っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goromaru and Julia was influenced by Katarina, and they went into the Christian path.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goromaru and Julia entered the Christian faith under the influence of Katarina.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goromaru and Julia entered the Christian faith under the influence of Katarina.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そして永禄8年（1565年）5月に、京の南蛮寺でルイス・フロイスより洗礼を受け、ジョアンという洗礼名を授かったのではないかと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was believed that in May 1565, they were christened by Luis Frois at Nanban-dera Temple in Kyoto and his Christian name, Joan was given at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that in May 1565, they were christened by Luis Frois at Nanban-dera Temple in Kyoto and his Christian name, Joan was given to him at that time.</e>
<cmt>・「was believed」→「is thought」・「to him」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that in June 1565, they were christened by Luis Frois at Nanban-dera Temple in Kyoto and his Christian name, Joan was given to him at that time.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="51">
<j>そのような中、黒井城の城主「丹波の赤鬼」と恐れられた赤井直正と、八上城の城主は波多野秀治に代わり、丹波国を手中に収めようと争乱を始めたので、同年8月松永長頼は700兵余りを引き連れ出軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the castellan of Kuroi Castle, Naomasa AKAI who was dreaded as `Red ogre of Tanba&apos; and the castellan of Yagami-jo Castle started a disturbance to conquer Tanba prefecture instead of Hideharu HATANO; in August 1565, Nagayori MATSUNAGA launched a battle with more than seven hundreds soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the lord of Kuroi-jo Castle, Naomasa AKAI who was dreaded as the &apos;Red Ogre of Tanba&apos; and the lord of Yagami-jo Castle started a revolt to conquer Tanba Province from Hideharu HATANO, and in August 1565, Nagayori MATSUNAGA led an expedition with more than 700 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>・「castellan」→「lord」 (x2)・「the」を追加・「ogre」→「Ogre」・「Kuroi Castle」→「Kuroi-jo Castle」・「disturbance」→「revolt」・「prefecture」→「Province」・「instead of」→「from」・「;」→「, and」・「launched a battle」→「led an expedition」・「seven hundreds」→「700」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the lord of Kuroi-jo Castle, Naomasa AKAI who was dreaded as the &apos;Red Ogre of Tanba&apos; and the lord of Yagami-jo Castle started a revolt to conquer Tanba Province from Hideharu HATANO, and in September 1565, Nagayori MATSUNAGA led an expedition with more than 700 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>氷上郡迄進んだところ、日暮れとなり豪雨となったので近くの寺に宿陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As they reached to Hikami-gun, they had a heavy rain at sundown, they stayed at a temple nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As they reached Hikami District, it began to rain heavily at dusk and they set up camp at a nearby temple.</e>
<cmt>・「to」を削除・「Hikami-gun」→「Hikami District」・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As they reached Hikami District, it began to rain heavily at dusk and they set up camp at a nearby temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、この寺の僧が赤井直正に密告し、夜中不意の夜襲をかけられてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the monk of the temple secretly communicated with Naomasa AKAI, and they had a sudden night attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a monk of the temple betrayed them to Naomasa AKAI, and they were suddenly attacked during the night.</e>
<cmt>・「the」→「a」・「secretly communicated with」→「betrayed them to」・「had a sudden night attack.」→「were suddenly attacked during the night」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a monk of the temple betrayed them to Naomasa AKAI, and they were suddenly attacked during the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>松永長頼も700兵を指揮し奮闘したが及ばす、ほぼ全員が玉砕したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayori MATSUNAGA led 700 soldiers and fought, but it appears that almost all of the soldiers killed themselves.</e>
<cmt>玉砕→自殺したと考え訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayori MATSUNAGA led 700 soldiers and fought hard, but it appears that almost all of the soldiers died with honor.</e>
<cmt>・「hard」を補足・「killed themselves」→「died with honor」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayori MATSUNAGA led 700 soldiers and fought hard, but it appears that almost all of the soldiers died with honor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>内藤ジョアンが洗礼を受けてから3ヵ月後に父を亡くしたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Joan NAITO lost his father three months after he was christened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Joan NAITO lost his father three months after he was christened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Joan NAITO lost his father three months after he was christened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="56">
<j>父を亡くした内藤ジョアンは、八木城の城主に収まったようで、八木城を中心として熱心な布教活動を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joan NAITO who lost his father seemed to become the castellan of Yagi-jo Castle, and he was actively involved in missionary work mainly at Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After losing his father, it seems that Joan NAITO became lord of Yagi-jo Castle, and actively conducted missionary work centered around Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After losing his father, it seems that Joan NAITO became lord of Yagi-jo Castle, and actively conducted missionary work centered around Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>そんな中、現在記録が明確になっているだけで三度日本人修道士ロレンソ了斎を招いたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As far as it is evident in the record today, it seems that he invited a Japanese missionary, Lorenzo RYOSAI, three times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As far as it is evident from current records, it seems that he invited the Japanese missionary, Lorenzo RYOSAI, on three occasions.</e>
<cmt>・「in the record today」→「from current records」・「a」→「the」・「three times」→「on three occasions」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As far as it is evident from current records, it seems that he invited the Japanese missionary, Lorenzo RYOSAI, on three occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>ロレンソ了斎とはルイス・フロイスの弟子で、九州から京都にかけて獲得した信者は6千人にものぼったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lorenzo RYOSAI was a disciple of Luis Frois, and he was said to have gained six thousands Christians throughout from Kyusyu to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lorenzo RYOSAI was a disciple of Luis Frois, and he was said to have converted as many as 6,000 people to Christianity from Kyusyu to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>・「gained six thousands Christians」→「converted as many as 6,000 people to Christianity」・「throughout」を削除c</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lorenzo RYOSAI was a disciple of Luis Frois, and he was said to have converted as many as 6,000 people to Christianity from Kyushu to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>八木城には1572年（元亀3年）-1573年（天正元年）にかけて2回訪問した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lorenzo RYOSAI visited Yagi-jo Castle twice during the period from 1572 to 1573.</e>
<cmt>-にかけて→1572 to 1573と訳出しています。（wikipedia 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lorenzo RYOSAI visited Yagi-jo Castle twice between 1572 and 1573.</e>
<cmt>「during the period from 1572 to 1573」→「1572 and 1573」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lorenzo RYOSAI visited Yagi-jo Castle twice between 1572 and 1573.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この1573年（天正元年）の初旬、2回目の訪問の様子をガスパル・ヴィレラの書簡によると、パードレ・オルガンチノはロレンソと共に約八日前三箇より当地に着きたり。内藤殿其部下説教を聞かん為め丹波の国に於てロレンソを待ち居れるが故に、彼を迎えに来たる人と共に一昨日当地を出発せりと記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the letter to Gaspar VILELA on his second visit in the early part of 1573, it is stated that Gaspar VILELA and Lorenzo arrived here from 三箇 eight days ago and Lorenzo left here on the day before the previous day with someone to take him to Tanba Province where NAITO and his subordinates had been waiting for Lorenzo to listen to his preaching.</e>
<cmt>2回目の訪問の様子をガスパル・ヴィレラの書簡によると、→、2回目の訪問の様子を記したガスパル・ヴィレラへの書簡によると、と解釈しました。三箇→定訳不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a letter from Gaspar VILELA, Lorenzo&apos;s second visit in the early part of 1573 is described as follows: Padre Organtino and Lorenzo arrived there from Sanga eight days ago, and because Naito and his subordinates visited Tanba Province to listen to his preaching, Lorenzo left there with the emissary the day before yesterday.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a letter from Gaspar VILELA, Lorenzo&apos;s second visit in the early part of 1573 is described as follows: Padre Organtino and Lorenzo arrived there from Sanga eight days ago, and because Naito and his subordinates visited Tanba Province to listen to his preaching, Lorenzo left there with the emissary the day before yesterday.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また1574年（天正2年）3回目の訪問の様子をルイス・フロイスの未刊の書簡では、時にフロイスは、ロレンソとともに都から丹波の山道をたどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the third visit in 1574, it is stated in the unpublished book of Luis Frois that `Frois and Lorenzo followed the mountain path of Tanba. After walking about five miles, Joan NAITO welcomed us with his chief retainer. A gorgeous altar was in his castle. Fourteen soldiers were christened after seventy soldiers were christened during eight days.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文が欠落しているようですが原文どおりとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An account of the third visit in 1574 in an unpublished correspondence by Luis Frois states that Frois and Lorenzo followed the mountain path from the capital to Tanba. After walking about five miles, Joan NAITO welcomed them with his retainer. A gorgeous altar was installed in his castle. Over eight days, 70 soldiers were baptised, followed by 14 more.</e>
<cmt>・「Regarding」→「An account of」・「, it is stated in the unpublished book of Luis Frois that」→「in an unpublished correspondence by Luis Frois states」・引用符を削除・「of Tanba」→「from the capital to Tanba」・「us」→「them」・「chief」を削除・「installed」を追加・最後の分を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An account of the third visit in 1574 in an unpublished correspondence by Luis Frois states that Frois and Lorenzo followed the mountain path from the capital to Tanba.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>約二里のところへ内藤ジョアンは家臣とともに出迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After walking about five miles, Joan NAITO welcomed them with his retainer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>城には豪華な祭壇が飾られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A gorgeous altar was installed in his castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>八日間に七十名の兵が、ついで十四名が受礼したと記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over eight days, 70 soldiers were baptized, followed by 14 more.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>八木城は丹波国におけるイエズス会布教活動の本拠地となりつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was becoming the base of missionary work by the Society of Jesus in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yagi-jo Castle was becoming the base of missionary work by the Society of Jesus in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was becoming the base of missionary work by the Society of Jesus in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="66">
<j>このころより内藤ジョアンこそ城主とすべき派と、内藤国貞の実子、千勝丸（後の内藤貞勝）の擁立を目指す一派とで内争となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, an infighting between the group claiming to install Joan NAITO as a load and the group aiming to back up the birth child of Kunisada NAITO, Senshomaru (later known as Sadakatsu NAITO) began.</e>
<cmt>千勝丸→Senshomaru 定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, infighting began between the group aiming to install Joan NAITO as a lord of the castle and the group backing the birth child of Kunisada NAITO, Senshomaru (later known as Sadakatsu NAITO).</e>
<cmt>・「an」を削除・「began」を移動・「claiming」→「aiming」・「load」→「lord of the castle」・「aiming to back up」→「backing」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, infighting began between the group aiming to install Joan NAITO as a lord of the castle and the group backing the birth child of Kunisada NAITO, Senshomaru (later known as Sadakatsu NAITO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>そのような中、内藤定房の兄弟は僧侶となっていたが、内藤氏の血縁でない松永長頼と事あるごとに反抗していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The brothers of Sadafusa NAITO were priests, and rebelled against Nagayori MATSUNAGA who didn&apos;t have a blood relationship with the Naito clan on various matters.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The brothers of Sadafusa NAITO were Buddhist monks, and rebelled at every opportunity against Nagayori MATSUNAGA who did not have a blood relationship with the Naito clan.</e>
<cmt>・「priests」→「Buddhist monks」・「at every opportunity」を追加・「didn&apos;t」→「did not」・「on various matters」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The brothers of Sadafusa NAITO were Buddhist monks, and rebelled at every opportunity against Nagayori MATSUNAGA who did not have a blood relationship with the Naito clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>内藤ジョアンの母にとっては伯父達から、内藤ジョアンを城主になる事を諦め、また内藤ジョアンの母もキリシタンに改宗するよう迫ったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that Joan NAITO&apos;s uncles forced Joan&apos;s mother to give up to install Joan as the lord and to become a Christian.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。内藤ジョアンの母にとっては→内藤ジョアンの母に対してはと解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that Joan NAITO&apos;s uncles forced his mother to abandon plans to install Joan as the lord and to convert to Christianity.</e>
<cmt>・「seems」→「appears」・「Joan&apos;s」→「his」・「give up」→「abandon」・「plans」を補足・「become a Christian」→「convert to Christianity」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that Joan NAITO&apos;s uncles forced his mother to abandon plans to install Joan as the lord and to convert to Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>しかし、内藤ジョアンの母は気丈な方であったらしく、頑としてこれに応じなかった為、僧侶に殺害されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Joan&apos;s mother seemed to be a strong willed person, and she was killed because she kept refusing their intentions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it seems that Joan&apos;s mother was strong willed, and she was killed by the monks because of her resolute refusal to comply.</e>
<cmt>・「it seems that」を追加・「seemed to be a strong willed person」→「was strong willed」・「by the monk」を補足・「she kept refusing their intentions」→「of her resolute refusal to comply」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it seems that Joan&apos;s mother was strong willed, and she was killed by the monks because of her resolute refusal to comply.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>内藤ジョアンは父に次ぎ、母も亡くしてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Joan NAITO subsequently lost his mother after he lost his father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore Joan NAITO lost his mother after previously losing his father.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore Joan NAITO lost his mother after previously losing his father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>『内藤如安の生涯』によると、母が殺されたのはの秋から暮れにかけてはでないかと推察している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Naito Joan no shogai&quot; (The Life of Joan Naito) assumed that his mother was killed between the autumn and the end of 1573.</e>
<cmt>の秋から暮れ→ between the autumn and the end of と訳出しています。（wikipedia 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Naito Joan no Shogai&quot; (The Life of Joan Naito) surmises that his mother was killed between autumn and the end of 1573.</e>
<cmt>・「ｓhogai」→「Shogai」・「assumed」→「surmises」・「the」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Naito Joan no Shogai&quot; (The Life of Joan Naito) surmises that his mother was killed between autumn and the end of 1573.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>『フロイス日本史』によると、母が亡くなってからの内藤ジョアンは城主の事など一向に気にかけなくなり、戦国の世を渡り歩き、ますます信仰の道に深く入っていた、と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Frois&apos;s History of Japan&quot; states that after his mother&apos;s death, Joan NAITO didn&apos;t care about his position as the lord at all, and went around the country, pursuing his faith further.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Frois&apos;s History of Japan&quot; states that after his mother&apos;s death, Joan NAITO did not care at all about his position as the lord of the castle, and drifted throughout the country, becoming increasingly involved in his faith.</e>
<cmt>・「didn&apos;t」→「did not」・「at all」を移動・「of the castle」を追加・「went around」→「drifted throughout」・「pursuing his faith further」→「becoming increasingly involved in his faith」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Frois&apos;s History of Japan&quot; states that after his mother&apos;s death, Joan NAITO did not care at all about his position as the lord of the castle, and drifted throughout the country, becoming increasingly involved in his faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="73">
<j>その後、内藤ジョアンは小西行長の客将となり、文禄・慶長の役で出兵し活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Joan NAITO became the Kyakusho (extra shogun) of Yukinaga KONISHI, and went to fight in the Bunroku-Keicho War, taking an active role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Joan NAITO became a guest commander of Yukinaga KONISHI, and went to fight in the Bunroku-Keicho War in which he played an active role.</e>
<cmt>・「the Kyakusho (extra shogun)」→「a guest commander」・「, taking」→「in which he played」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Joan NAITO became a guest commander of Yukinaga KONISHI, and went to fight in the Bunroku-Keicho War in which he played an active role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>また徳川幕府よりキリシタン禁教令で、高山右近と共にマニラに亡命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He escaped into Manila with Ukon TAKAYAMA after Tokugawa Bakufu promulgated Kirishitan Kinkyo-rei (Edicts banning Christianity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He fled to Manila with Ukon TAKAYAMA after the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) enacted the Kirishitan Kinkyo-rei (Edicts banning Christianity).</e>
<cmt>・「escaped into」→「fled to」・「Tokugawa Bakufu」→「the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)」・「promulgated」→「enacted」・「the」を補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He fled to Manila with Ukon TAKAYAMA after the Tokugawa shogunate enacted the Kirishitan Kinkyo-rei (Edicts banning Christianity).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>マニラでは「生き神」の如き歓待をうけ、地域の住民からも慕われたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Manila, he was welcomed and treated as the `living god,&apos; and he seemed to be loved by the local people.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Manila, he was welcomed and treated as if he were a living god, and seems to have been loved by the local people.</e>
<cmt>・「as the `living god,&apos;」→「as if he were a living god」・「he seemed to be」→「seems to have been」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Manila, he was welcomed and treated as if he were a living god, and seems to have been loved by the local people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>最後は妻マリア、妹ジュリアや子供達、地元の宣教師や修道士に見守れながら昇天したと語られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that he was accompanied with his wife Maria, younger sister Julia, his children, and the local missionaries and monks when he passed away.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that he was surrounded by his wife Maria, younger sister Julia, his children, and the local missionaries and monks when he passed away.</e>
<cmt>・「accompanied with」→「surrounded by」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that he was surrounded by his wife Maria, younger sister Julia, his children, and the local missionaries and monks when he passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>73歳であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He died at the age of seventy three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was aged 73.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was aged 73.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>八木城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle in Yagi-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Yagi-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>「Battle in Yagi-jo Castle」→「The Battle of Yagi-jo Castle」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Yagi-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="78">
<j>天正7年（1579年）織田信長軍は明智光秀を総大将に八上城や黒井城を中心に第二次丹波国征討戦に乗り出していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1579, Nobunaga Oda&apos;s army with Mitsuhide AKECHI as a supreme commander launched the second conquest of Tanba Province mainly based on Yagami-jo Castle or Kuroi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1579, Nobunaga Oda&apos;s army with Mitsuhide AKECHI as supreme commander launched the second campaign for the conquest of Tanba Province which focused on Yagami-jo Castle and Kuroi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「as」を削除・「campaign for the」を補足・「mainly based」→「which focused」・「or」→「and」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1579, Nobunaga Oda&apos;s army with Mitsuhide AKECHI as supreme commander launched the second campaign for the conquest of Tanba Province which focused on Yagami-jo Castle and Kuroi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>そのような中、同年5月に綾部城、玉巻城が落城すると、丹羽長秀、羽柴秀長らは羽柴秀吉からの要請をうけ三木合戦の援軍として転戦して行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ayabe-jo Castle and Tamaki-jo Castle were fallen in May 1579, Nagahide NIWA and Hidenaga HASHIBA were commanded by Hideyoshi HASHIBA to move to support Battle of the Miki-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the fall of Ayabe-jo Castle and Tamaki-jo Castle in May 1579, Nagahide NIWA and Hidenaga HASHIBA were commanded by Hideyoshi HASHIBA provide reinforcements for the Battle of the Miki-jo Castle, and fought in numerous battles.</e>
<cmt>・「When Ayabe-jo Castle and Tamaki-jo Castle were fallen」→「With the fall of Ayabe-jo Castle and Tamaki-jo Castle」・「move to support」→「provide reinforcements for the」・「and fought in numerous battles」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the fall of Ayabe-jo Castle and Tamaki-jo Castle in June 1579, Nagahide NIWA and Hidenaga HASHIBA were commanded by Hideyoshi HASHIBA provide reinforcements for the Battle of the Miki-jo Castle, and fought in numerous battles.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>同年6月、当時この地域の一定の勢力を保っていた八木城の城主内藤有勝に軍を向かわせ、八木城を攻城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June in the same year, they launched a battle against the castellan of Yagi-jo Castle, Arikatsu NAITO who had a measure of power, and attacked Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, they launched a battle against the lord of Yagi-jo Castle, Arikatsu NAITO who had a certain degree of power in the area at the time, and attacked Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「in」→「of」・「castellan」→「lord」・「measure of power」→「certain degree of power in the area at the time」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July of the same year, they launched a battle against the lord of Yagi-jo Castle, Arikatsu NAITO who had a certain degree of power in the area at the time, and attacked Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>八木城は自然の天険を利用した堅城であった為、容易に攻め落とすことが出来ず、明智光秀は和議を申し込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle, being a robust castle utilizing its rough landscape, made it difficult for them to capture, and Mitsuhide AKECHI offered a peace conference or negotiations to Arikatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yagi-jo Castle, being a robust castle utilizing its rough landscape, could not be taken easily, and Mitsuhide AKECHI offered peace negotiations to Arikatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt>・「made it difficult for them to capture」→「could not be taken easily」・「a」を削除・「conference or」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle, being a robust castle utilizing its rough landscape, could not be taken easily, and Mitsuhide AKECHI offered peace negotiations to Arikatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>しかし、内藤有勝はこれを拒否し、防戦に挑んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Arikatsu NAITO refused his offer, and continued a defense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Arikatsu NAITO refused his offer and continued to defend.</e>
<cmt>・コンマを削除・「a defense」→「to defend」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Arikatsu NAITO refused his offer and continued to defend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>そこで、明智光秀は八木城の城兵に内通謀反を工作し、これに応じる者があり、城内の本丸、二の丸に火を放った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhide AKECHI attempted to solicit someone as a betrayer within Yagi-jo Castle, and the one who accepted his offer set a fire in Honmaru (the keep of a castle) and Ninomaru (second defensive) of Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuhide AKECHI attempted to solicit someone as a betrayer within Yagi-jo Castle, and the person who accepted his offer set a fire in the honmaru (main compound) and the ninomaru (secondary compound) of Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「one」→「person」・「Honmaru (the keep of a castle)」→「the honmaru (main compound)」・「Ninomaru (second defensive)」→「the ninomaru (secondary compound)」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuhide AKECHI attempted to solicit someone as a betrayer within Yagi-jo Castle, and the person who accepted his offer set a fire in the honmaru (main compound) and the ninomaru (secondary compound) of Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>これを合図に明智光秀軍は大挙して攻め寄せ、ついに落城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the signal of the fire, Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s army attacked in full force, and Yagi-jo Castle eventually fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the fire serving as a signal, Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s army attacked in full force, and Yagi-jo Castle finally fell.</e>
<cmt>・「At the signal of the fire」→「With the fire serving as a signal」・「eventually」→「finally」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the fire serving as a signal, Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s army attacked in full force, and Yagi-jo Castle finally fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>同年6月27日であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was on June 27 in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was on June 27 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>・「It」→「This」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was on July 30 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この時に城主内藤有勝も戦死したものと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the lord of Yagi-jo Castle, Arikatsu NAITO died in the war at this time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the lord of Yagi-jo Castle, Arikatsu NAITO died in battle at this time.</e>
<cmt>・「seems」→「is thought」・「the war」→「battle」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the lord of Yagi-jo Castle, Arikatsu NAITO died in battle at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="87">
<j>内藤氏の一門であった内藤正勝は、明智光秀軍を突破し八田城へ向かおうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A family member of the Naito clan, Masakatsu NAITO tried to run through Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s army and head for Hatta-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A member of the Naito clan, Masakatsu NAITO, attempted to break through Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s forces and head for Hatta-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「family」を削除・コンマを補足・「tried」→「attempted」・「run」→「break」・「army」→「forces」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A member of the Naito clan, Masakatsu NAITO, attempted to break through Mitsuhide AKECHI&apos;s forces and head for Hatta-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>落ち延びる最中に、散り散りとなって自害する者も出て、内藤正勝は鴻ヶ獄城に入城したが、ここで没したと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way fleeing to Hatta-jo Castle, some of soldiers were separated from his army and killed themselves, Masakatsu NAITO entered into Kogadake-jo Castle, and it is believed that he died here.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While fleeing to Hatta-jo Castle, some soldiers were separated from his army and killed themselves, and Masakatsu NAITO entered Kogadake-jo Castle, where he is thought to have died.</e>
<cmt>・「On the way」→「While」・「of」を削除・「and」を追加・「into」を削除・「and it is believed that he died here」→「where he is thought to have died」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While fleeing to Hatta-jo Castle, some soldiers were separated from his army and killed themselves, and Masakatsu NAITO entered Kogadake-jo Castle, where he is thought to have died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>これにより室町時代から続いていた内藤氏は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the Naito clan who had been succeeded from the Muromachi period was demolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the Naito clan which had been existed since the Muromachi period died out.</e>
<cmt>・「who」→「which」・「succeeded from」→「existed since」・「was demolished」→「died out」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the Naito clan which had been existed since the Muromachi period died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="90">
<j>この戦いの様子は『内藤盛衰記』を中心に記載されているが、内藤有勝、内藤正勝という人物がどのような人物であったのかよく解っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle was mainly described in &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of the Naito), and it is not very clear regarding the personality of Arikatsu NAITO and Masakatsu NAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle was mainly described in &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of the Naito Clan), but it is not well understood what type of people Arikatsu NAITO and Masakatsu NAITO were.</e>
<cmt>・「The」→「This」・「Clan」を追加・「and」→「but」・「very clear regarding the personality of Arikatsu NAITO and Masakatsu NAITO」→「well understood what type of people Arikatsu NAITO and Masakatsu NAITO were」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle was mainly described in &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; (The Rise and Fall of the Naito Clan), but it is not well understood what type of people Arikatsu NAITO and Masakatsu NAITO were.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>八木玄夫の研究によると『内藤盛衰記』に記載されている「有勝は架空人物。この人物に如安の実績を移し、如安の名は消し去ったのだ」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to 八木玄夫&apos;s research, it is stated that `Arikatsu in &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; was fictional. The name and achievement of Joan was extinguished and shifted to Arikatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>八木玄夫→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。121と122は本来一文であると思われるため結合し、翻訳の作業上、一原文・一訳文の例外対処を行いました。一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Motoo YAGI&apos;s research, &apos;Arikatsu as described in &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; was fictional. The achievements of Joan were conferred upon Arikatsul, and the name of Joan exitinguished&apos;.</e>
<cmt>・「八木玄夫&apos;」→「Motoo YAGI」・「it is stated that」を削除・「as described」を補足・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Motoo YAGI&apos;s research, &apos;Arikatsu as described in &quot;Naito Seisuiki&quot; was fictional and achievements of Joan were conferred upon Arikatsu, and the name of Joan extinguished.&apos;</e>
<cmt>2文を1文にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>八木城落城の内藤有勝部分はノンフィクションの可能性も示唆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motoo YAGI pointed out the possibility that the part of Arikatsu NAITO in the fall of Yagi-jo was nonfictional.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the part when Yagi-jo Castle was fallen, Motoo YAGI expressed his view that it was not fictional.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the part when Yagi-jo Castle was fallen, Motoo YAGI expressed his view that it was not fictional.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>また松田毅一の論文『丹波八木城と内藤如庵について』では、同盟関係にあった織田信長と足利義昭が仲違いを生じると内藤ジョアンは「1574年（天正2年）の秋以降、和泉堺に移って以後、義昭のもとに走った」と、八木城の戦い時には八木城にいなかった可能性を指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kiichi MATSUDA&apos;s article, &quot;Tanba Yagi-jo Castle and Joan NAITO,&quot; he indicated that Joan NAITO was not present in the battle of Yagi-jo Castle, as `Joan moved to Izumi Sakai, and then went to Yoshiaki after the autumn of 1574 subsequent to the conflict between Nobunaga ODA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA that were in the alliance.</e>
<cmt>の秋→after the autumn of 1574と訳出しています。（wikipedia 参照）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kiichi MATSUDA&apos;s article, &quot;Tanba Yagi-jo Castle and Joan NAITO,&quot; he indicated that Joan NAITO was not present at the battle of Yagi-jo Castle because &apos;Joan moved to Izumi Sakai and then went to the place of Yoshiashi ASHIKAGA after the autumn of 1574 subsequent to the conflict between the allies Nobunaga ODA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>・「in」→「at」・「, as」→「because」・コンマ・「Yoshiaki」→「the place of Yoshiashi ASHIKAGA」・「Nobunaga ODA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA that were in the alliance」→「the allies Nobunaga ODA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kiichi MATSUDA&apos;s article, &quot;Tanba Yagi-jo Castle and Joan NAITO,&quot; he indicated that Joan NAITO was not present at the battle of Yagi-jo Castle because &apos;Joan moved to Izumi Sakai and then went to the place of Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA after the autumn of 1574&apos; subsequent to the conflict between the allies Nobunaga ODA and Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>1574年（天正2年）：原文に補足&apos;補足スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>いずれにしても、この時内藤ジョアンがどこにいたのか、改ざんされたりして明確な史料は残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anyway, any materials that evidence where Joan was in the battle of Yagi-jo Castle were unavailable, perhaps they were modified or whatever.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, any materials disclosing the whereabouts if Joan during this time were altered, and there are no definititive surviving sources.</e>
<cmt>・翻訳しなおし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, any materials disclosing the whereabouts if Joan during this time were altered, and there are no definitive surviving sources.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>廃城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Desertion of Yagi-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abandonment of Yagi-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>・「Desertion」→「Abandonment」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abandonment of Yagi-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>廃城の明確な時期は解っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The definitive time when Yagi-jo Castle was deserted was unclear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear exactly when Yagi-jo Castle was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear exactly when Yagi-jo Castle was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>福島克彦によると八木城は明智光秀による改修がなされている点を指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuhiko FUKUSHIMA pointed out that Yagi-jo Castle was renovated by Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuhiko FUKUSHIMA pointed out that Yagi-jo Castle was renovated by Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuhiko FUKUSHIMA pointed out that Yagi-jo Castle was renovated by Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>また、国道478号のバイパス工事に伴う発掘調査が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The excavation and research incidental to bypass line construction on National Route 478 was conducted.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excavations were conducted in conjunction with the construction of the National Route 478 bypass.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excavations were conducted in conjunction with the construction of the National Route 478 bypass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>『京都府遺跡調査概要』によると、発掘調査地点は特に明智光秀により大幅に手を加えられた可能性が高く、また遺物からも明智光秀時代の様相が高いと指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Kyoto Prefecture ruins research summary,&quot; it is probable that the site where the excavation was conducted was significantly doctored by Mitsuhide AKECHI, and the ruins that were found in the site, which appeared from the period of Mitsuhide AKECHI, also indicates it.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。『京都府遺跡調査→定訳不明のため→&quot;Kyoto Prefecture ruins research summary&quot; としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Kyoto Prefecture Ruins Investigation Summary,&quot; it is highly likely that the excavation site was heavily influenced by Mitsuhide AKECHI, and the artifacts that were found in the site, also indicate aspects strongly characteristic of the period of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>・「Kyoto Prefecture ruins research summary「→「Kyoto Prefecture Ruins Investigation Summary」・「probable」→「highly likely」・「site where the excavation was conducted」→「excavation site」・「significantly doctored」→「heavily influenced」・「ruins」→「artifacts」・「文」の後半を翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Kyoto Prefecture Ruins Investigation Summary,&quot; it is highly likely that the excavation site was heavily influenced by Mitsuhide AKECHI, and the artifacts that were found in the site, also indicate aspects strongly characteristic of the period of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>内藤氏は滅亡し、丹波国を平定した明智光秀は亀山城 (丹波国)を築城し、丹波国の中心も亀山城に移っていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Naito clan died out, and Mitsuhide AKECHI who conquered Tanba Province constructed Kameyama-jo Castle (Tanba province), and the center function of Tanba Province was shifted to Kameyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the demise of the Naito clan, Mitsuhide AKECHI who conquered Tanba Province constructed Kameyama-jo Castle (Tanba Province), and the center of Tanba Province shifted to Kameyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「After the Naito clan died out」→「After the demise of the Naito clan」・「and」を削除・「province」→「Province」・「function」を削除・「was」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the demise of the Naito clan, Mitsuhide AKECHI who conquered Tanba Province constructed Kameyama-jo Castle (Tanba Province), and the center of Tanba Province shifted to Kameyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>八木城は廃城を免れたようで亀山城の支城として存続していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yagi-jo Castle was not deserted, and still existed as a subsidiary castle of Kameyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that Yagi-jo Castle was not deserted, and continued to function as a subsidiary castle of Kameyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that Yagi-jo Castle was not deserted, and continued to function as a subsidiary castle of Kameyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>城郭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>「Castle」→「Structure」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>本丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmaru (the keep of a castle)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honmaru (Main Compound)</e>
<cmt>「Keep」とは欧州の城の中心にある塔のことを目指す」「(the keep of the castle)」→「Main Compound」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honmaru (Main Compound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>本丸は、馬屋敷曲輪の左手の一段高い台地が本丸跡である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmaru site was raised above and on the left side of the Kuruwa (walls of a castle) of umaya (horse stable).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The honmaru was situated on a plateau raised above the stable walls.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The honmaru was situated on a plateau raised above and left side of the stable walls.</e>
<cmt>and left side of補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>大きさは南北に10m、東西に13mある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was 10m from north to south, and was 13m from east to west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It measured 10m from north to south, and was 13m from east to west.</e>
<cmt>「was」→「measured」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It measured 10 m from north to south, and was 13 m from east to west.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>八木城はに木所佐左衛門、赤井藤右衛門らが測量作成した『八木城古絵図』が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yagi-jo Castle-ezu&quot; (pictorial diagram) which was measured and created by 木所佐左衛門 and Toemon AKAI was preserved in of Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>『八木城古絵図』→締約不明のため&quot;Yagi-jo Castle-ezu&quot; (pictorial diagram)と訳出しています。八木城はに→原文が欠落しているようですが原文どおりとしています。木所佐左衛門→読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a surviving &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot; (an old sketch map of Yagi-jo Castle) which was measured and created by Sazaemon KIDOKORO and Toemon AKAI.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a surviving &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot; (an old sketch map of Yagi-jo Castle) which was measured and created by Sazaemon KIDOKORO and Toemon AKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>この絵図には四方に牛蒡積みの石垣が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this ezu, stone walls (mound of stones) in gobo-zumi (long stones which are half buried into the mound are stacked) stacking pattern in four directions are described.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This depicts gobozumi (stone walls comprised of roughly cut or naturally formed rocks that are shaped like a burdock) stone walls on four sides.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This depicts gobozumi (stone walls comprised of roughly cut or naturally formed rocks that are shaped like a burdock) stone walls on four sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>現在この石垣は約60cmの土をかぶり石垣は見えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the stone walls are covered with about 60cm-thick mud, and they can&apos;t be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the stone walls are covered with about 60cm of mud, and cannot be seen.</e>
<cmt>・「-thick」→「of」・「they can&apos;t」→「cannot」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the stone walls are covered with about 60 cm of mud, and cannot be seen.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>先の八木城の戦いで落城はしたが、炎上はしなかったようで、灰燼の跡は確認されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yagi-jo Castle fell, it seems that they didn&apos;t burn given that the trace of embers was not found in there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though Yagi-jo Castle fell into the hands of the enemy during the battle, it seems that they didn&apos;t burn it down given that no traces of embers have been found there.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though Yagi-jo Castle fell into the hands of the enemy during the battle, it seems that they didn&apos;t burn it down given that no traces of embers have been found there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>金之間曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinnoma (Gold room) Kuruwa (walls of a castle)</e>
<cmt>金の間→定訳不明ですが→Kinnoma (Gold room) Kuruwa (walls of a castle)と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kin-no-Ma Compound</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kin-no-Ma Compound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>本丸の西側に突出してあるのが金之間曲輪。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinnoma (Gold room) Kuruwa (walls of a castle) projects from the west side of Honmaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kin-no-Ma compound projects from the west side of the honmaru.</e>
<cmt>・「Kinnoma (Gold room) Kuruwa (walls of a castle)」→「The Kin-no-Ma compound」・「Honmaru」→「the honmaru」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kin-no-Ma compound projects from the west side of the honmaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>名前の「金の間」から推察され、金蔵が想像されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kin-no-Ma Compound is assumed to be a trasure store from the name of `Kinnoma&apos; (Gold room).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Judging by its name, the Kin-no-Ma (lit. Gold Room), compound is assumed to have been a treasure store.</e>
<cmt>・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Judging by its name, the Kin-no-Ma (lit. Gold Room), compound is assumed to have been a treasure store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>『八木城古絵図』よると特別の石組みがなされていた一郭がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Yagi-jo Castle-ezu&quot; (pictorial diagram), stonewalls in which special stacking pattern was used were placed in a part of Yagi-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot;, there was one compound for which the stone walls were built using a special arangement of stones.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu,&quot; there was one compound for which the stone walls were built using a special arrangement of stones.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>金蔵との関連性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was associated with the store room to store gold.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has been associated with the treasure store.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has been associated with the treasure store.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>ただ、この曲輪はそのような名称より、城郭的に貴重な天守台の祖形が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, regarding this compound, aside from its name, the shape of tenshudai (raised foundation upon which the principal tower was constructed) which was an important part of a castle, has been remarked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the shape of the tenshudai (raised foundation upon which the principal tower was constructed), which was an important part of a castle, has been remarked upon as being more significant than the compound&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shape of the tenshudai (raised foundation upon which the principal tower was constructed), which was an important part of a castle, has been remarked upon as being more significant than the compound&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>これと似たような天守台が松永長頼方であった笑路城の発掘調査で確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other tenshu (main keep or tower of a castle) dai (platform) similar to the tenshu dai of Kinnoma (Gold room) Kuruwa (walls of a castle) was found in the excavation and research for Waroji-jo Castle of Nagayori MATSUNAGA.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another similar tenshudai (raised foundation upon which the the principal tower was constructed) has been unearthed in the excavation of Nagayori MATSUNAGA&apos;s Waroji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another similar tenshudai (raised foundation upon which the principal tower was constructed) has been unearthed in the excavation of Nagayori MATSUNAGA&apos;s Waroji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>重複削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>近世天守台の過渡期として『八木城古絵図』にも記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was contained in &quot;Yagi-jo Castle-ezu&quot; (pictorial diagram) as tenshudai (raised foundation upon which the principal tower was constructed) in transition to the modern tenshudai.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also included in &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot; as a transition toward early modern tenshudai.</e>
<cmt>・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also included in &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot; as a transition toward early modern tenshudai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>奥方屋敷曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okugata (wife) yashiki (residence) Kuruwa (walls of a castle)</e>
<cmt>奥方屋敷曲輪→定訳不明ですが→Okugata (wife) yashiki (residence) Kuruwa (walls of a castle) と訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okugata Yashiki Compound</e>
<cmt>・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okugata Yashiki Compound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="114">
<j>本丸の北東側に階段状の曲輪がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the northeast side of Honmaru, Kuruwa (walls of a castle) in a staircase pattern was placed.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stepped compound was located on the northeast side of the honmaru.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stepped compound was located on the northeast side of the honmaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>その中で一番広い場所が『八木城古絵図』に記載されている奥方屋敷曲輪ではないかと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest area in there was believed to be Okugata (wife) yashiki (residence) Kuruwa (walls of a castle) contained in &quot;Yagi-jo Castle-ezu&quot; (pictorial diagram).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The largest area of this was believed to be the okugata yashiki (lit. wives&apos; residence) compound described in &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot;).</e>
<cmt>・「biggest」→「largest」・「in there」→「of this」・「Okugata (wife) yashiki (residence) Kuruwa (walls of a castle)」→「the okugata yashiki (lit. wives&apos; residence) compound」・「contained」→「described」・「&quot;Yagi-jo Castle-ezu&quot; (pictorial diagram」→「&quot;Yagi-jo Koezu&quot;」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The largest area of this was believed to be the okugata yashiki (lit. wives&apos; residence) compound described in &quot;Yagi-jo Koezu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>)削除ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>名称から、領主の家族や家臣が山上生活を営んでいた場所ではないかと推察されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was assumed from its name that it was the place where family or chief retainers of feudal lord spent their time on mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed from its name that it was the place where the family members or retainers of feudal lords spent their time on the mountain.</e>
<cmt>・「was」→「is」・「the」を補足・「members」を追加・「chief」を削除・「lord」→「lords」・「mountains」→「the mountain」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed from its name that it was the place where the family members or retainers of feudal lords spent their time on the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>二の丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninomaru (second defensive)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninomaru (Secondary Compound)</e>
<cmt>・「Ninomaru (second defensive)」→「Ninomaru (Secondary Compound)」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninomaru (Secondary Compound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>本丸から西南側に一段低い場所が馬屋曲輪で、平坦地になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umaya (horse stable) Kuruwa (walls of a castle) is a flat place lower than and on the southwest side of Honmaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stable compound was located to the southwest of the honmaru on flat land one level below the honmaru.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stable compound was located to the southwest of the honmaru on flat land one level below the honmaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>そこから更に左側に進むと、3m程度の高い崖に突き当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Proceeding left further brings you to meet about 3-meter-high cliff.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further left is a 3m high cliff.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further left is a 3 m high cliff.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>それを登るとなだらかな平坦地がありこれが二の丸である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If you climb up the cliff further, reach the flat place that is Ninomaru.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon ascending this cliff, one will reach a flat area on which the ninomaru was located.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon ascending this cliff, one will reach a flat area on which the ninomaru was located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>かなりの広さがあり両側面は切り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninomaru is quite large, and both sides are sheer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninomaru is quite large, and both sides are sheer.</e>
<cmt>・「The」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninomaru is quite large, and both sides are sheer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>内藤五郎の居館があったのではないかと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The house of Goro NAITO might be in there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the residence of Goro NAITO may have been located here.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the residence of Goro NAITO may have been located here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>その他曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Kuruwas (walls of a castle)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Compounds</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Compounds</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>それ以外にも曲輪がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are Kuruwas other than those above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are other compounds in addition to those described above.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are other compounds in addition to those described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>八木玄蓄屋敷曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">八木玄蓄 Residence Kuruwa</e>
<cmt>八木玄蓄 →読み方不明のため原文のままとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">八木玄蓄 Residence Compound</e>
<cmt>「Kuruwa」→「Compound」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">八木玄蓄 Residence Compound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>二の丸を出て坂を下っていくと、小高い丘に突き当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting out of Ninomaru and going down the slope brings you to meet the hill.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon exiting the ninomaru and descending the slope, one will encounter a small hill.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon exiting the ninomaru and descending the slope, one will encounter a small hill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>そこが家老の八木玄蓄の屋敷跡と伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the hill was the place where the house of Joan&apos;s Karo (chief retainer), 八木玄蓄 was.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this is the site on which the residence of chief retainer 八木玄蓄 once stood.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this is the site on which the residence of chief retainer 八木玄蓄 once stood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>八木玄蓄は内藤のジョアンの義兄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">八木玄蓄 was the elder brother of Joan with a different father.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">八木玄蓄 was Joan&apos;s elder brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">八木玄蓄 was Joan&apos;s elder brother-in-law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>この曲輪は雑木が繁っており見通しも悪く、この台地が左手へ出張っているような形で、下にある谷は玄蓄谷と呼ばれている深い谷になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Kuruwa was covered in brush, and it was hard to see in there; its platform projected to the left, and a valley below the platform was a deep valley called the 玄蓄谷.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This compound was thickly wooded and difficult to see, and the platform projected out to the left while below was a deep valley known as 玄蓄谷.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This compound was thickly wooded and difficult to see, and the platform projected out to the left while below was a deep valley known as 玄蓄谷.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="128">
<j>三の丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sannomaru (outer part of the castle)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sannomaru (Tertiary Compound)</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sannomaru (Tertiary Compound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>八木玄蓄屋敷曲輪から更に尾根伝いに進むと、前方に一段高い峯が立ちはだかりこれが「烏帽子岳」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Proceeding further from 八木玄蓄 Residence Kuruwa along the ridge brings you to meet a higher crest that is called the Eboshi-dake Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Proceeding further along the ridge from 八木玄蓄&apos;s residence compound leads to a higher peak called the Eboshi-dake Mountain.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Proceeding further along the ridge from 八木玄蓄&apos;s residence compound leads to a higher peak called the Eboshi-dake Mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>ここに前城主の家老が居を構え居た三の丸がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sannomaru was where the chief retainer of the former castellan had his house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the sannomaru where the chief retainer of the former castle lord resided.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the sannomaru where the chief retainer of the former castle lord resided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>ここには大正時代のマンガン鉱を採掘した大きな洞窟が2つある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two large caves in there where manganese ore was mined in the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two large caves in which manganese ore was mined during the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>・「were」→「are」・「there where」→「which」・「in」→「during」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two large caves in which manganese ore was mined during the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="132">
<j>東の出丸（対面曲輪）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higasino (east) demaru (small castle or tower built onto and projecting from a larger castle) (Kuruwa (walls of a castle) for meetings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eastern Demaru (Opposing Compound)</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eastern Demaru (Opposing Compound)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>この東の出丸の側面に通っている道が表通であったため、この曲輪の周辺に大手門があったのではないかと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a road along the side of Higasino (east) demaru was a front road, an Otte-mon Gate (Main Gate) is thought to be near this Kuruwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the road that passed by this eastern demaru (small castle or tower built onto and projecting from a larger castle) was the main road, it is though that an otemon (main gate) once stod in the vicinity of this compound.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the road that passed by this eastern demaru (small castle or tower built onto and projecting from a larger castle) was the main road, it is though that an otemon (main gate) once stood in the vicinity of this compound.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>東の出丸には奏者番の詰所があったと伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that a sumesyo (a station) for sosha (a person in charge of informing a shogun or daimyo of the name of visitors to the residence before a meeting) was in Higasino (east) demaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that a sumesyo (station) for a sosha (an official in charge of informing a shogun or daimyo of the name of visitors to the residence before a meeting) was located in the eastern demaru.</e>
<cmt>・「a」を削除・「a person」→「an official」・「located」を補足・「the」を補足・「Higasino (east)」→「eastern」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that a tsumesyo (station) for a sosha (an official in charge of informing a shogun or daimyo of the name of visitors to the residence before a meeting) was located in the eastern demaru.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>まず使者や来客はここで待たされ、その間奏者番が、対面曲輪に赴いて御側使用人に報告し指示を受けていたのではないかと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that firstly, emissaries or guests waited in the sumesyo while sosha (an official in charge of informing a shogun or daimyo of the name of visitors to the residence before a meeting) went to the Opposing Compound to report and obtain instructions from the official of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that emissaries or guests would first wait in the sumesyo while the sosha went to the opposing compound to report to and obtain instructions from castle officials.</e>
<cmt>・「firstly」を削除・「would first」を追加・「waited」→「wait」・「the」を追加・「(an official in charge of informing a shogun or daimyo of the name of visitors to the residence before a meeting)」を削除・「Opposing Compound」→「opposing compound」・「to」を補足・「the official of the castle」→「castle officials」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that emissaries or guests would first wait in the tsumesyo while the sosha went to the opposing compound to report to and obtain instructions from castle officials.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>今もこの道は「奏者峠」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This road is still called the `sosha (a person in charge of informing a shogun or daimyo of the name of visitors to the residence before a meeting) Pass&apos; even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The road is called &quot;Sosha Pass&quot; even today.</e>
<cmt>・書き直し・括弧内の英語解釈は初出の場合のみ記載</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The road is called &apos;Sosha Pass&apos; even today.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="137">
<j>それ以外にも、北の出丸、北の丸口、屋敷曲輪の曲輪や、岩屋口、辰の口、虎松口、杉谷口などの虎口がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were Kuruwa (a space reserved for various purposes) such as Kitano (north) demaru, Kitano (north) maguchi (exit), Kuruwa of Residence Kuruwa, and Tora (tiger) guchi (exit) such as Iwaya (rock cave) guchi (exit), Tatsuno (dragon) guchi, Tora (tiger) matsu (pine) guchi, Sugi (cedar) tani (valley) guchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were also other compounds such as the northern demaru, the northern maguchi (exit) and the residential compound, as well as entrances including Iwaya-guchi (lit. Cave Gate), Tatsu-no-guchi (lit. Dragon Gate), Toramatsu-guchi (lit. Tiger and Pine Gate) and Sugitani-guchi (lit. Cedar Valley Gate).</e>
<cmt>・書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also other compounds such as the northern demaru, the northern maguchi (exit) and the residential compound, as well as entrances including Iwaya-guchi (lit. Cave Gate), Tatsu-no-guchi (lit. Dragon Gate), Toramatsu-guchi (lit. Tiger and Pine Gate) and Sugitani-guchi (lit. Cedar Valley Gate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>発掘調査</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excavation and research</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excavations</e>
<cmt>「Excavation and research」→「Excavations」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excavations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="138">
<j>八木城は国道478号のバイパス工事に伴う調査を含め、山麓の屋敷曲輪部分を中心とした発掘調査が何度か実施された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The excavation mainly subject to the Residence Compound in mountains including investigations for the bypass line construction of National Route 478 was conducted several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Numerous excavations focusing on the residential compound at the base of the mountain have been conducted including the investigation accompanying the construction the National Route 478 bypass.</e>
<cmt>・翻訳しなおし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Numerous excavations focusing on the residential compound at the base of the mountain have been conducted including the investigation accompanying the construction the National Route 478 bypass.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="139">
<j>この発掘調査から、遺構として石垣で護岸された屋敷跡や石組土抗、石組井戸、谷を埋めて作った段々状の平坦地、礎石の一部が発掘された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient structural remnants such as a residence protected by stone, small caves with rock arrangement, wells with rock arrangement, a platform with terraces created out of reclaimed valley, a part of a foundation stone were found.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These have unearthed structural remains of a residence protected by a stone wall, small caves with rock arrangements, stone wells, terraces created by digging into the valley walls, and some foundation stones.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These have unearthed structural remains of a residence protected by a stone wall, small caves with rock arrangements, stone wells, terraces created by digging into the valley walls, and some foundation stones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>遺物としては、土師皿、中国製磁器等か発掘された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relic such as Haji plates or Chinese ceramics were also mined.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Artifacts unearthed include Haji plates and Chinese porcelain.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Artifacts unearthed include Haji plates and Chinese porcelain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>またこの発掘調査で古墳時代後期の須恵器を焼いた窯跡を検出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of kiln in which unglazed (ceramic) ware were burnt were also mined in this excavation and research.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These excavations also discovered a kiln dating from the latter part of the Kofun period (tumulus period) that was used to fire sueki (unglazed ceramics).</e>
<cmt>・翻訳漏れを修正・原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These excavations also discovered a kiln dating from the latter part of the Kofun period (tumulus period) that was used to fire sueki (unglazed ceramics).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>城跡へのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access to castle site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access to the Castle Site</e>
<cmt>・「the」を追加・Title caseにしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access to the castle site</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="142">
<j>電車でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access by train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Train</e>
<cmt>[Access by train]→「By Train」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By train</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>JR西日本　嵯峨野線　八木駅　→　春日神社　徒歩約15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sagano Line Sagano Line Yagi station → Kasuga-jinja Shrine about 15minutes walk</e>
<cmt>全角文字→を残しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alight at Yagi Station on the JR West Sagano Line and walk for approximately 15 minutes from Kasuga-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alight at Yagi Station on the JR West Sagano Line and walk for approximately 15 minutes from Kasuga-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>車でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access by car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Car</e>
<cmt>[Access by car]→「By Car」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>京都縦貫自動車道　八木東インターチェンジ　→　国道9号　→　春日神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Jukan Expressway Yagi Higashi Interchange → National Route 9 → Kasuga-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>全角文字→を残しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take National Route 9 to Kasuga-jinja Shrine from the Yagi Higashi Interchange of the Kyoto Jukan Expressway.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take National Route 9 to Kasuga-jinja Shrine from the Yagi Higashi Interchange of the Kyoto Jukan Expressway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>近隣に駐車場無し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No parking lot available in the neighborhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No parking facilities available in the vicinity.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No parking facilities available in the vicinity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>徒歩でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access by walk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Foot</e>
<cmt>「Access by walk」→「On Foot」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On foot</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>春日神社　→　山頂本丸部分　徒歩約35分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasuga-jinja Shrine → Honmaru area on mountaintop about 35minutes walk</e>
<cmt>全角文字→を残しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approximately 35 minutes’ walk from Kasuga-jinja Shrine to the honmaru at the peak.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approximately 35 minutes&apos; walk from Kasuga-jinja Shrine to the honmaru at the peak.</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Caviler(id:256245), 子パンダ(id:178397), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Aotake(id:34929), 水野白楓(id:22811), 越中掾(id:149423), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Dvorak2008(id:254100), Volfgang(id:98768), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>