<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>福知山市都市緑化植物園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The botanical garden for increasing plants in urban areas in Fukuchiyama City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Botanical Garden for Increasing Plants in Urban aAreas in Fukuchiyama City</e>
<cmt>Capitalized as proper noun.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Botanical Garden for Increasing Plants in Urban Areas in Fukuchiyama City</e>
<cmt>aAreas → Areas</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>福知山市都市緑化植物園（ふくちやましとしりょくかしょくぶつえん）はスモール・テラ（SMALLTERRA・小さな地球）の愛称で呼ばれる、福知山市三段池公園にある植物園である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The botanical garden for increasing plants in urban areas in Fukuchiyama City, nicknamed Sumorutera (in Japanese pronounciation: perhaps indicates a small terrain, an small earth) is a botanical garden located in the Sandan-ike Pond park in Fukuchiayama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Botanical Garden for Increasing Plants in Urban Areas in Fukuchiyama City, nicknamed Sumorutera (the Japanese pronunciation of &apos;Small Terra&apos; or small Earth) is a botanical garden located in Sandan-ike Pond Park in Fukuchiyama City.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, spelling, grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Botanical Garden for Increasing Plants in Urban Areas in Fukuchiyama City, nicknamed &quot;Sumoru-tera&quot; (the Japanese pronunciation of &apos;Small Terra&apos; or small Earth) is a botanical garden located in Sandan-ike Pond Park in Fukuchiyama City.</e>
<cmt>指示書（その他　2009/6/29) に従い、Sumorutera をクォーテーションでくくりました。「スモール・テラ」と「・」がついているので、ハイフンを入れました。 Sumorutera → Smoru-tera</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道・KTR北近畿タンゴ鉄道福知山駅から、京都交通 (舞鶴)で三段池公園下車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Get on a bus of Kyoto Kotsu (based on Maizuru) from Fukuchiyama Station of West Japan Railway Company/Kitakinki tango Railway (KTR) and get off at the Sandan-ike Pond park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Fukuchiyama Station on the West Japan Railway Company/Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR) take the Kyoto Kotsu bus (Maizuru) and get off at Sandan-ike Pond Park.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Fukuchiyama Station on the West Japan Railway Company/Kitakinki Tango Railway (KTR) take the Kyoto Kotsu Bus (Maizuru) and get off at Sandan-ike Pond Park.</e>
<cmt>用語集の表記に合わせて修正Kyoto Kotsu bus → Kyoto Kotsu Bus</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), エアスマップIRE(id:13873), Blackbus(id:37164), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Suisui(id:69), FAT26(id:9460), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>