<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>箸墓古墳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>箸墓古墳（はしはかこふん、箸中山古墳とも）は、奈良県桜井市箸中に所在する箸中古墳群の盟主的古墳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus (also called Hashi Nakayama-kofun Tumulus) is the leading kofun (tumulus) of the Hashinaka-kofun Tumuli Group in Hashinaka, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus (also called Hashi Nakayama-kofun Tumulus) is the leading kofun (tumulus) of the Hashinaka-kofun Tumuli Group in Hashinaka, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus (also called Hashi Nakayama-kofun Tumulus) is the leading kofun (tumulus) of the Hashinaka-kofun Tumuli Group in Hashinaka, Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出現期古墳の中でも最古級と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered the oldest class of kofun of all the kofun that were made during the period in which they first appeared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered the oldest class of kofun of all the kofun that were made during the period in which they first appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered the oldest class of kofun of all the kofun that were made during the period in which they first appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>3世紀半ばすぎの大型の前方後円墳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a large-scale keyhole-shaped tumulus from after the mid-third century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s a large-scale, keyhole-shaped tumulus from after the mid-third century.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a large-scale, keyhole-shaped tumulus from after the mid-third century.</e>
<cmt>It&apos;s→It isとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>この古墳を、魏志倭人伝が伝える倭国の女王「卑弥呼」の墓とする（＝邪馬台国畿内説）向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a tendency to consider that the tumulus belongs to Himiko, the queen of Wa-koku (the oldest recorded name for Japan), described in Gishiwajin-den (the Wei Chronicle) (which is in accordance with the Yamatai-koku Kinai-setsu, which argues that the Yamatai-koku Kingdom was in Kinai, or the five central provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto, namely Yamato, Kawachi, Settsu, Izumi, and Yamashiro that are now the municipalities of Kyoto and Osaka and the prefectures of Nara and Hyogo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a tendency to consider that the tumulus belongs to Himiko, the queen of Wa-koku (the oldest recorded name for Japan), described in Gishiwajin-den (the Wei Chronicle) (in accordance with the Yamatai-koku Kinai-setsu, which argues that the Yamatai-koku Kingdom was in Kinai, or the five central provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto, namely Yamato, Kawachi, Settsu, Izumi and Yamashiro, which are now the municipalities of Kyoto and Osaka and the prefectures of Nara and Hyogo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a tendency to consider that the tumulus belongs to Himiko, the queen of Wa-koku (the oldest recorded name for Japan), described in the Gishiwajin-den (the Wei Chronicle) (in accordance with the Yamatai-koku Kinai-setsu, which argues that the Yamatai-koku Kingdom was in Kinai, or the five central provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto, namely Yamato, Kawachi, Settsu, Izumi and Yamashiro, which are now the municipalities of Kyoto and Osaka and the prefectures of Nara and Hyogo).</e>
<cmt>in the Gishiwajin-denとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従来、構築年代が3世紀末から4世紀初頭であり、卑弥呼が死亡したされる3世紀前半との時期にずれがあるため、その可能性は少ないといわれてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Traditionally, this has been considered unlikely, because there is a lag between the date of construction falling between the end of the third century and the early fourth century and that of her death, which is believed to be in the first half of the third century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditionally, this has been considered unlikely because there is a lag between the date of construction between the end of the third century and the early fourth century and that of her death, which is believed to be in the first half of the third century.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditionally, this has been considered unlikely because there is a lag between the date of construction between the end of the third century and the early fourth century and that of her death, which is believed to be in the first half of the third century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、最近、年輪年代学や放射性炭素年代測定による年代推定を反映して、古墳時代の開始年代を従来より早める説が有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, recently, the view advancing the beginning date of the Kofun Period has become influential, reflecting the age estimate using dendrochronology and radiocarbon dating.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, however, the view advancing the beginning date of the Kofun period has become influential, reflecting the age estimate using dendrochronology and radiocarbon dating.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, however, the view advancing the beginning date of the Kofun period has become influential, reflecting the age estimate using dendrochronology and radiocarbon dating.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>上記の箸墓古墳の築造年代は、研究者により多少の前後はある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above-mentioned construction date of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus moves slightly back and forth across scholars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above-mentioned construction date of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus varies slightly among scholars.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above-mentioned construction date of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus varies slightly among scholars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、卑弥呼の没年（248年頃）に近い3世紀の中頃から後半と見る説が一般的になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the predominant view is that it was built between the middle and the latter half of the third century around the year of Himiko&apos;s death (about 248).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the predominant view is that it was built between the middle and the latter half of the third century, in or around the year of Himiko&apos;s death (approximately 248).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the predominant view is that it was built between the middle and the latter half of the third century, in or around the year of Himiko&apos;s death (approximately 248).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして、箸墓古墳が卑弥呼の墓である蓋然性が高くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it has become more likely that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the tomb of Himiko.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it has become more likely that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the tomb of Himiko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it has become more likely that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the tomb of Himiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>現在は、宮内庁により第7代孝霊天皇の皇女、倭迹迹日百襲姫命大市墓（やまとととひももそひめのみことおおいちのはか）として管理されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, it is administered by the Imperial Household Agency as the tomb of Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto, the daughter of the seventh Emperor Korei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, it is administered by the Imperial Household Agency as the tomb of Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto, the daughter of the seventh emperor, Korei.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, it is administered by the Imperial Household Agency as the Oichi tomb (Oichi no haka) of Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto, the daughter of the seventh emperor, Korei.</e>
<cmt>「大市」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして、研究者や国民の墳丘への自由な立ち入りが禁止されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence, citizens and scholars are not permitted to freely enter the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, citizens and scholars are not permitted to freely enter the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, citizens and scholars are not permitted to freely enter the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>倭迹迹日百襲姫命とは、『日本書紀』では崇神天皇の祖父孝元天皇の姉妹である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicles of Japan), Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto is a sister of the Emperor Sujin, who is the grandfather of the Emperor Kogen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Nihon Shoki (The Chronicles of Japan),&quot; Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto is a sister of Emperor Sujin, who is the grandfather of Emperor Kogen.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (The Chronicles of Japan), Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto is a sister of Emperor Sujin, who is the grandfather of Emperor Kogen.</e>
<cmt>In the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大市は古墳のある地名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oichi is the name of the place where the kofun is located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oichi is the name of the place where the kofun is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oichi is the name of the place where the kofun is located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『古事記』では、夜麻登登母母曾毘売（やまととももそびめ）命である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Record of Ancient Matters), it is Yamatotomomosobime no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Kojiki (The Record of Ancient Matters),&quot; it is Yamatotomomosobime no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Record of Ancient Matters), it is Yamatotomomosobime no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>In the &quot;Kojiki&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>名の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Origin of the Name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Origin of the Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Origin of the Name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>『日本書紀』崇神天皇19月の条に、つぎのような説話が載せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following tale is recorded in the article concerning the nineteenth month of the Emperor Sujin of &quot;Nihon Shoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following tale is recorded in the article concerning the nineteenth month of Emperor Sujin in &quot;Nihon Shoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following tale is recorded in the article concerning the nineteenth month of Emperor Sujin in the &quot;Nihon Shoki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>In the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一般に「三輪山伝説」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally called &apos;Miwayama Densetsu&apos; (The Miwayama Legend).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally called &apos;Miwayama Densetsu (The Miwayama Legend).&apos;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally called &apos;Miwayama Densetsu&apos; (The Miwayama Legend).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>なお、箸が日本に伝来した時期（7世紀？）と説話の作成された時期とに大きなズレがあるところから、古墳を作成した集団である土師氏の墓、つまり土師墓から箸墓になった？という土橋寛の説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yutaka TSUCHIHASHI says Hashihaka (Chopsticks--which are called hashi in Japanese--Tomb) became Hajihaka, or the tomb of the Haji clan, which is the group that made the kofun, because there is a large gap between the period in which chopsticks were introduced into Japan (the seventh century?) and that in which the tale was made.</e>
<cmt>二つ目の「？」は省いてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yutaka TSUCHIHASHI says Hashihaka (Chopsticks--called hashi in Japanese--Tomb) became Hajihaka, or the tomb of the Haji clan, which is the group that made the kofun, because there is a large gap between the period in which chopsticks were introduced into Japan (possibly the seventh century) and that in which the tale was devised.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yutaka TSUCHIHASHI says Hashihaka (Chopsticks--called hashi in Japanese--Tomb) came from Hajihaka, or the tomb of the Haji clan, which is the group that made the kofun, because there is a large gap between the period in which chopsticks were introduced into Japan (possibly the seventh century) and that in which the tale was devised.</e>
<cmt>原文には「土師墓から箸墓になった」とあるため、Hashihaka became Hajihaka→Hashihaka came from Hajihakaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>墳形・規模</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shape and Scale</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shape and Scale</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shape and Scale</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>最古級の前方後円墳によくみられるように前方部が途中から撥型（ばちがた）に大きく開く墳形である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With regard to the shape of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, its square front starts to open like a plectrum in the middle, as it is observed in many of the oldest-class keyhole-shaped tumuli.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the shape of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, its square front starts to open like a plectrum in the middle, as is observed in many of the oldest-class, keyhole-shaped tumuli.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the shape of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, its square front starts to open like a plectrum in the middle, as is observed in many of the oldest-class, keyhole-shaped tumuli.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>測量図の等高線の様子から前方部正面が現状より拡がっていたことが分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The appearance of the contour on the survey map indicates that the front of the square front was wider than the actual state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The appearance of the contour on the survey map indicates that the front of the square front was wider than the actual state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appearance of the contour on the survey map indicates that the front of the square front was wider than the actual state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>前方部の先が撥形に開いている他の古墳は、兵庫県揖保川町の養久山（やくやま）1号墳、同県の権現山51号墳、京都府山城町の椿井大塚山古墳、岡山市の浦間茶臼山古墳などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Kofun with the square front whose tip opens like a plectrum include Yakuyama No. 1 Kofun Tumulus in Ibogawa-cho, Hyogo Prefecture, Gongenyama No. 51 Kofun Tumulus in the same prefecture, Tsubai Otuskayama-kofun Tumulus in Yamashiro-cho, Kyoto Prefecture, and Urama Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus in Okayama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other kofun with a square front whose tip opens like a plectrum include Yakuyama No. 1 Kofun Tumulus in Ibogawa-cho, Hyogo Prefecture; Gongenyama No. 51 Kofun Tumulus in the same prefecture; Tsubai Otuskayama-kofun Tumulus in Yamashiro-cho, Kyoto Prefecture; and Urama Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus in Okayama City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other kofun with a square front whose tip opens like a plectrum include Yakuyama No. 1 Kofun Tumulus in Ibogawa-cho, Hyogo Prefecture; Gongenyama No. 51 Kofun Tumulus in the same prefecture; Tsubai Otuskayama-kofun Tumulus in Yamashiro-cho, Kyoto Prefecture; and Urama Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus in Okayama City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ちなみに、浦間茶臼山古墳は箸墓古墳の二分の一の相似形といわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, Urama Chausuyama Tumulus is considered a half-size, similar figure to Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this regard, Urama Chausuyama Tumulus is considered to be half-size, with proportions similar to Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this regard, Urama Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus is considered to be half-size, with proportions similar to Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>Urama Chausuyama-kofun Tumulusとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>長さも幅も二分の一である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is half in length and width.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is half in length and width.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is half in length and width.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、前方部の頂の形は横長の長方形と台形の違いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the shape of its summit is different from that of Hashihaka-kofunTumulus, being a horizontally-long rectangle rather than a trapezoid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the shape of its summit is different from that of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, being a horizontally long rectangle rather than a trapezoid.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shape of its summit is different from that of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, being a horizontally long rectangle rather than a trapezoid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>現状での規模は、墳長およそ278ｍ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the actual size of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, its length is about 278 meters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to the actual size of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, its length is approximately 278 meters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to the actual size of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus, its length is approximately 278 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>後円部は、径約150ｍ、高さ約30ｍ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rounded rear is about 150 meters in diameter and about 30 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rear, which is rounded, is approximately 150 meters in diameter and about 30 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rear, which is rounded, is approximately 150 meters in diameter and about 30 meters in height.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>前方部は、前面幅約130ｍで高さ約16ｍを測る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the front width of the square front is about 130 meters and its height about 16 meters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The front width of the square front is approximately 130 meters, and its height about 16 meters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The front width of the square front is approximately 130 meters, and its height about 16 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その体積は約37万立方メートル。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its volume is about 370000 cubic meters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its volume is approximately 370,000 cubic meters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its volume is approximately 370,000 cubic meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>周辺地域の調査結果から、本来はもう一回り大きかったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The results of the investigation of the surrounding areas suggest that it was originally a size larger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The results of the investigation of the surrounding area suggest that it was originally a size larger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The results of the investigation of the surrounding area suggest that it was originally a size larger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>後円部は四段築成で、四段築成の上に小円丘（径約44～46メートル、高さ4メートルの土壇、特殊器台が置かれていたと考えられる）がのったものと指摘する研究者（近藤義郎等）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some scholars (like Yoshiro KONDO) point out that the rear has four terraces and a small knoll (on which it is believed that a clay platform, whose diameter and height were about 44-46 and 4 meters, respectively, and special vessel stands were placed) on top of the terraces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some scholars (such as Yoshiro KONDO) point out that the rear has four terraces and a small knoll (on which it is believed that a clay platform, whose diameter and height were approximately 44 to 46 and 4 meters, respectively, and special vessel stands were placed) on top of the terraces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some scholars (such as Yoshiro KONDO) point out that the rear has four terraces and a small knoll (on which it is believed that a clay platform, whose diameter and height were approximately 44 to 46 and 4 meters, respectively, and special vessel stands were placed) on top of the terraces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>前方部は、側面の段築は明瞭ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the square front, the terrace structure on the side is not obvious.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the square front, the terrace structure on the side is not obvious.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the square front, the terrace structure on the side is not obvious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、前面には四段の段築があるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is supposed that there is a four-terrace structure in the front.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is supposed that there is a four-terrace structure in the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is supposed that there is a four-terrace structure in the front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>ちなみに、5段築成（四段築成で、後円部に小円丘が載る）は箸墓古墳のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the only kofun that is a five-terrace construction (composed of four terraces and a small knoll on top of the rounded rear).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this regard, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the only kofun that&apos;s a five-terrace construction (composed of four terraces and a small knoll on top of the rounded rear).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this regard, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is the only kofun that is a five-terrace construction (composed of four terraces and a small knoll on top of the rounded rear).</e>
<cmt>that&apos;s→that isとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>4段築成（三段築成で、後円部に小円丘が載る）は西殿塚古墳（大和古墳群）、行燈山古墳（柳本古墳群）、渋谷向山古墳（柳本古墳群）、桜井茶臼山古墳（鳥見山古墳群）、メスリ山古墳（鳥見山古墳群）、築山古墳 (大和高田市)（馬見古墳群）等が考えらる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofun that is a four-terrace construction (comprising three terraces and a small knoll on top of the rounded rear) include Nishitonotsuka-kofun Tumulus (Oyamato-kofun Tumuli Group), Andonyama-kofun Tumulus (Yanagimoto-kofun Tumuli Group), Shibutani Mukaiyama-kofun Tumulus (Yanagimoto-kofun Tumuli Group), Sakurai Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus (Torimiyama-kofun Tumuli Group), Mesuriyama-kofun Tumulus (Tomiyama-kofun Tumuli Group), Tsukiyama-kofun Tumulus (Umami-kofun Tumuli Group) (in Yamato Takada City), and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofun that are of four-terrace construction (comprising three terraces and a small knoll on top of the rounded rear) include Nishitonotsuka-kofun Tumulus (Oyamato-kofun Tumuli Group); Andonyama-kofun Tumulus (Yanagimoto-kofun Tumuli Group); Shibutani Mukaiyama-kofun Tumulus (Yanagimoto-kofun Tumuli Group); Sakurai Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus (Torimiyama-kofun Tumuli Group); Mesuriyama-kofun Tumulus (Tomiyama-kofun Tumuli Group); Tsukiyama-kofun Tumulus (Umami-kofun Tumuli Group) (in Yamato Takada City); and so on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofun that are of four-terrace construction (comprising three terraces and a small knoll on top of the rounded rear) include Nishitonotsuka-kofun Tumulus (Oyamato-kofun Tumuli Group); Andonyama-kofun Tumulus (Yanagimoto-kofun Tumuli Group); Shibutani Mukaiyama-kofun Tumulus (Yanagimoto-kofun Tumuli Group); Sakurai Chausuyama-kofun Tumulus (Torimiyama-kofun Tumuli Group); Mesuriyama-kofun Tumulus (Torimiyama-kofun Tumuli Group); Tsukiyama-kofun Tumulus (Umami-kofun Tumuli Group) (in Yamato Takada City); and so on.</e>
<cmt>Tomiyama→Torimiyamaに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>そして、他の天皇陵クラスの古墳は全て三段築成（後円部も前方部も三段築成）とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All other kofun with an imperial-class mausoleum is a three-terrace construction (both in the rounded rear and in the square front).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All other kofun with imperial-class mausoleums are of three-terrace construction (both in the rounded rear and in the square front).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All other kofun with imperial-class mausoleums are of three-terrace construction (both in the rounded rear and in the square front).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>被葬者の格付けを表しているのかも知れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This might reflect the ranking of the buried individual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This might reflect the ranking of the buried individual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This might reflect the ranking of the buried individual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>奈良県立橿原考古学研究所や桜井市教育委員会の陵墓指定の範囲の外側を発掘した調査により、墳丘の裾に幅10メートルの周壕とさらにその外側に幅15メートル以上の外堤が存在していたことが確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The presence of a 10-meter-wide surrounding moat at the foot of the burial mound and a 15-meter-wide outer levee outside of it has been confirmed through the excavation research carried out in the vicinity of the area specified as the imperial mausoleum by the Nara Prefectural Archaeological Institute of Kashihara and the Sakurai City Board of Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The presence of a 10-meter-wide surrounding moat at the foot of the burial mound and a 15-meter-wide outer levee outside of it has been confirmed through the excavation research carried out in the vicinity of the area specified as the imperial mausoleum by the Nara Prefectural Archaeological Institute of Kashihara and the Sakurai City Board of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The presence of a 10-meter-wide surrounding moat at the foot of the burial mound and a 15-meter-wide outer levee outside of it has been confirmed through the excavation research carried out in the vicinity of the area specified as the imperial mausoleum by the Nara Prefectural Archaeological Institute of Kashihara and the Sakurai City Board of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>巨大な前方後円墳がその最古の時期から周壕を持つことが分かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, it has become clear that the huge keyhole-shaped tumulus had a surrounding moat from its earliest period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it has become clear that the huge keyhole-shaped tumulus had a surrounding moat from, its earliest period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it has become clear that the huge keyhole-shaped tumulus had a surrounding moat from, its earliest period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>外表施設・遺物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">External Facilities and Relics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">External Facilities and Relics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">External Facilities and Relics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>前方部先端の北側の墳丘の斜面には、川原石を用いた葺石が存在していることが確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuki-ishi (stones covering the surface of the burial mound) using river stones have been identified on the slope of the burial mound at the tip of the square front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuki-ishi (stones covering the surface of the burial mound) using river stones have been identified on the slope of the burial mound at the tip of the square front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuki-ishi (stones covering the surface of the burial mound) using river stones have been identified on the north slope of the burial mound at the tip of the square front.</e>
<cmt>「北側の」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="40">
<j>この時期には埴輪列はまだ存在していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A procession of haniwa (burial mound figurines) did not exist yet in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A procession of haniwa (burial mound figurines) didn&apos;t yet exist in that period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A procession of haniwa (burial mound figurines) did not yet exist in that period.</e>
<cmt>didn&apos;t→did notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、宮内庁職員によって宮山型特殊器台・特殊壺、最古の埴輪である都月型円筒埴輪、などが採集されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Miyayama-type special vessel stands and jars, the Totsuki-type cylindrical haniwa, and others have been collected by the staff of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Miyayama-type special vessel stands and jars, the Totsuki-type cylindrical haniwa and other items have been collected by the staff of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Miyayama-type special vessel stands and jars, the Totsuki-type cylindrical haniwa, which is the oldest type of haniwa, and other items have been collected by the staff of the Imperial Household Agency.</e>
<cmt>「最古の埴輪である」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これらが墳丘上に置かれていたことは間違いない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no doubt that they were put on the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no doubt that they had been placed on the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no doubt that they had been placed on the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>また、岡山市付近から運ばれたと推測できる特殊器台・特殊壺が後円部上でのみ認められるのに対して底部に孔を開けた二重口縁の壺形土師器は前方部上で採集されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the special vessel stands and jars that are presumed to have been brought from Okayama City and its environs are only seen in the rounded rear, the jar-shaped Haji pottery with a dual-rimmed mouth and holes on the bottom have been gathered in the square front.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the special vessel stands and jars, which are presumed to have been brought from Okayama City and its environs, are only seen in the rounded rear, the jar-shaped Haji pottery with a dual-rimmed mouth and holes on the bottom have been gathered from the square front.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the special vessel stands and jars, which are presumed to have been brought from Okayama City and its environs, are only seen in the rounded rear, the jar-shaped Haji pottery with a dual-rimmed mouth and holes on the bottom have been gathered from the square front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>器種によって置く位置が区別されていた可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is highly possible that vessel types determined their locations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is very possible that vessel types determined their locations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is very possible that vessel types determined their locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>特殊器台や特殊壺などの出土から古墳時代初頭に築造された古墳であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the unearthed special vessel stands and jars, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is considered a tumulus constructed in the early Kofun Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the unearthed special vessel stands and jars, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is considered to have been constructed in the early Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the unearthed special vessel stands and jars, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is considered to have been constructed in the early Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>埋葬施設は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A burial facility is unknown.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The burial facility isn&apos;t known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The burial facility is not known.</e>
<cmt>isn&apos;t→is notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし、墳丘の裾から玄武岩の板石が見つかっていることから竪穴式石室が作られていた可能性があるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is believed possible that it was equipped with a stone chamber dug into the earth, given that stone slabs were found on the foot of the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is believed possible that it was equipped with a stone chamber dug into the earth, given that stone slabs were found at the foot of the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is believed possible that it was equipped with a stone chamber dug into the earth, given that basaltic stone slabs were found at the foot of the burial mound.</e>
<cmt>「玄武岩の」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この石材は、大阪府柏原市の芝山の石であることが判明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been ascertained that they are the stones of Shibayama in Kashiwara City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been determined that they are the stones of Shibayama, in Kashiwara City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been determined that they are the stones of Shibayama, in Kashiwara City, Osaka Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>従って、崇神天皇に記す大坂山（二上山）の石ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence, they are not the stones of Mt. Osaka (Mt. Nijo) described in the tale of the Emperor Sujin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, they aren&apos;t the stones of Mt. Osaka (Mt. Nijo) described in the tale of Emperor Sujin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, they are not the stones of Mt. Osaka (Mt. Nijo) described in the tale of Emperor Sujin.</e>
<cmt>aren&apos;t→are notとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="50">
<j>周濠は、前方部と後円部の一部分の発掘調査から、幅10m前後の周濠と幅数十m前後の外堤の一部が見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With regard to the surrounding moat, some portions of the approximately 10-meter-wide surrounding moat and the 10-to-20-meter-wide outer levee have been found in the excavation research of some parts of the square front and the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With regard to the surrounding moat, some portions of the approximately 10-meter-wide surrounding moat and the 10-to-20-meter-wide outer levee have been found in the excavation research of portions of the square front and rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With regard to the surrounding moat, some portions of the approximately 10-meter-wide surrounding moat and the 10-to-20-meter-wide outer levee have been found in the excavation research of portions of the square front and rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>後円部の東南側の周濠部分では両側に葺き石を積み上げた渡り土手が見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A connecting bank that has a pile of fuki-ishi on both sides has also been found in a part of the surrounding moat that is on the southeast side of the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A connecting bank that has a pile of fuki-ishi on both sides has also been found in a part of the surrounding moat that is on the southeast side of the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A connecting bank that has a pile of fuki-ishi on both sides has also been found in a part of the surrounding moat that is on the southeast side of the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>築造時期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Construction Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Construction Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Construction Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>墳丘形態や出土遺物の内容から白石太一郎らによって最古級の前方後円墳であると指摘されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the basis of the shape of the burial mound and the contents of the unearthed relics, Taichiro SHIRAISHI and others indicated that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus was the oldest-class keyhole-shaped tumulus.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the shape of the burial mound and the contents of the unearthed relics, Taichiro SHIRAISHI and others have indicated that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is of the oldest class of keyhole-shaped tumulus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the shape of the burial mound and the contents of the unearthed relics, Taichiro SHIRAISHI and others have indicated that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is of the oldest class of keyhole-shaped tumulus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、陵墓指定範囲の外側の周辺部での発掘調査によって、墳丘の裾の幅10mの周濠の底から布留0式（ふるぜろしき）土器が出土した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Furu 0-style earthenware was excavated from the bottom of the 10-meter-wide surrounding moat on the foot of the burial mound in the excavation research in the vicinity outside the area specified as the imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Furu 0-style earthenware was excavated from the bottom of the 10-meter-wide surrounding moat at the foot of the burial mound in the excavation research, in the vicinity outside the area specified as the imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Furu 0-style earthenware was excavated from the bottom of the 10-meter-wide surrounding moat at the foot of the burial mound in the excavation research, in the vicinity outside the area specified as the imperial mausoleum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>そして、古墳時代前期初頭（3世紀半ば）の築造であることが確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it has been confirmed that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus was built at the beginning of the first half of the Kofun Period (in the middle of the third century).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it has been confirmed that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus was built at the beginning of the first half of the Kofun period (in the middle of the third century).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it has been confirmed that Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus was built at the beginning of the first half of the Kofun period (in the middle of the third century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>また、下記のことなど分かってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, things like what are written below have come to light.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。「下記の」を挿入してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, things such as the following have come to light:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, things such as the following have come to light:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>箸墓古墳よりも古いと考えられている纏向石塚墳丘墓などの突出部と箸墓古墳の前方部との形状が類似していること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The square front of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is similar in shape to the projecting portion of the Makimuku Ishizuka Tomb that is covered with a heap of earth, which is considered older than Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The square front of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is similar in shape to the projecting portion of the Makimuku Ishizuka Tomb, which is covered with a heap of earth and is considered older than Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The square front of Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is similar in shape to the projecting portion of the Makimuku Ishizuka Tomb, which is covered with a heap of earth and is considered older than Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>渡り土手を備えていること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is equipped with a connecting bank.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is equipped with a connecting bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is equipped with a connecting bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>周濠が墳丘の規模に比べ狭いこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And its surrounding moat is narrow, relative to the scale of its burial mound.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。ここまでが「下記のこと」です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its surrounding moat is narrow in relation to the scale of its burial mound.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its surrounding moat is narrow in relation to the scale of its burial mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>それらのことから箸墓古墳は、弥生時代の墳丘墓が飛躍的に巨大化したものであり、弥生時代の墳丘墓に続くものであると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of these findings, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is believed to be a dramatically enlarged version of and succeed the tombs covered with a heap of earth from the Yayoi Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of these findings, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is believed to be a dramatically enlarged version of (and successor of) the tombs covered with heaps of earth from the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of these findings, Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is believed to be a dramatically enlarged version of (and successor of) the tombs covered with heaps of earth from the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Significance</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Significance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Significance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>下記の点など、それまでの墳墓とは明らかに一線を画している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a clear distinction between Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus and the tombs protruding from the earth that precede it with respect to the points below.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。「下記の」を挿入してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a clear distinction between Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus and the tombs protruding from the earth that precede it with respect to the points mentioned below:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a clear distinction between Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus and the tombs protruding from the earth that precede it with respect to the points mentioned below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>墳丘の全長約280m、後円部の高さ約30mで自然にできた小山と錯覚するほどの規模、全国各地に墳丘の設計図を共有していると考えられる古墳が点在している点。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The country is dotted with kofun that are considered to share the blueprint of the burial mound, which is so big as to be mistaken as a naturally formed knoll, having a total length of about 280 meters and being about 30-meter-high in the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。用</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The country is dotted with kofun that are considered to share the blueprint of the burial mound, which is so big as to be mistaken as a naturally formed knoll, having a total length of about 280 meters and a height of approximately 30 meters at the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The country is dotted with kofun that are considered to share the blueprint of the burial mound, which is so big as to be mistaken as a naturally formed knoll, having a total length of about 280 meters and a height of approximately 30 meters at the rounded rear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>出土遺物に埴輪の祖形である吉備国系の土器が認められる点。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earthenware that belongs to the family of earthenware from the Kibi Province, which is the antecedent of haniwa, has been found among the unearthed relics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。ここまでが「下記の点」です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earthenware that belongs to the family of earthenware from Kibi Province, which is the antecedent of haniwa, has been found among the unearthed relics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earthenware that belongs to the family of earthenware from Kibi Province, which is the antecedent of haniwa, has been found among the unearthed relics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>また、規模、埴輪などは以後の古墳のモデルとなったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it is believed that its scale, haniwa, and so on acted as a model for the later kofun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is believed that its scale, haniwa and so on served collectively as a model for the later kofun.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is believed that its scale, haniwa and so on served collectively as a model for the later kofun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>そして、当古墳の築造をもって古墳時代の開始と評価する研究者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And many scholars evaluate the construction of that kofun as the beginning of the Kofun Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many scholars consider the construction of that kofun as the beginning of the Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many scholars consider the construction of that kofun as the beginning of the Kofun period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>被葬者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Buried Individual</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Buried Individual</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Buried Individual</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>宮内庁によって第7代孝霊天皇の皇女、倭迹迹日百襲姫命（やまとととひももそひめのみこと）の墓として管理されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is administered by the Imperial Household Agency as the tomb of Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto, the daughter of the seventh Emperor Korei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is administered by the Imperial Household Agency as the tomb of Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto, the daughter of the seventh emperor, Korei.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hashihaka-kofun Tumulus is administered by the Imperial Household Agency as the tomb of Yamatototohimomosohime no Mikoto, the daughter of the seventh emperor, Korei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>だが、この古墳を卑弥呼の墓とする研究者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some scholars claim that it is the tomb of Himiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some scholars claim that it&apos;s the tomb of Himiko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some scholars claim that it is the tomb of Himiko.</e>
<cmt>it&apos;s→it isとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>その根拠としては、下記の点などが挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The points below among others are cited as evidence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。後列をいったん統合させた後、5つに分割してあります。「下記の点」が挿入してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following points, among others, are cited as evidence:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following points, among others, are cited as evidence:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>この古墳の後円部の直径が『魏志倭人伝』にある卑弥呼の円墳の直径「百余歩」にほぼ一致すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The diameter of the round rear of this kofun almost matches that of the round barrow of Himiko, &apos;100 odd bu (a unit of volume),&apos; described in &quot;Gishiwajin-den.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The diameter of the round rear of this kofun nearly matches that of the round barrow of Himiko, &apos;a hundred odd bu (a unit of volume),&apos; described in &quot;Gishiwajin-den.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The diameter of the round rear of this kofun nearly matches that of the round barrow of Himiko, &apos;a hundred odd bu&apos; (a unit of volume), described in the &quot;Gishiwajin-den.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を移動、in the &quot;Gishiwajin-den&quot;としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>後円部にある段構造が前方部で消失することから、前方部が後世に付け加えられた可能性があること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is likely that the square front was later added, because the terrace structure that is found in the rounded rear vanishes in the square front.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is likely that the square front was added later, because the terrace structure that is found in the rounded rear vanishes in the square front.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is likely that the square front was added later, because the terrace structure that is found in the rounded rear vanishes in the square front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>大規模な古墳の中では、全国でももっとも早い時期に築造されたものであること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all the large-scale kofun, it was constructed in the earliest period in the entire country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all the large-scale kofun throughout the country, it was constructed in the earliest period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all the large-scale kofun throughout the country, it was constructed in the earliest period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>しかし、現時点では正確なことは分からない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the precise detail is unknown at this time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the precise details remain unknown at this time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the precise details remain unknown at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="72">
<j>ちなみに魏・晋時代の一里は300歩で、魏・晋時代の1里は76mとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, a ri (a unit of distance) in the Wei-Jin Period is believed to be 300 bu and 76 meters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, a ri (a unit of distance) of the Wei-Jin period is believed to equal 300 bu, or 76 meters.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, a ri (a unit of distance) of the Wei-Jin period is believed to equal 300 bu, or 76 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>よって、1歩はほぼ25cmとなり、100余歩は約30m弱となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence, a bu is about 25 centimeters and 100 odd bu about a little less than 30 meters.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, a bu is approximately 25 centimeters and 100 odd bu equal slightly less than 30 meters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, a bu is approximately 25 centimeters and 100 odd bu equal slightly less than 30 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>なお、桜井市教育委員会が2000年に実施した周辺部の発掘調査によって、周濠内の堆積土から木製の輪鐙（馬具）が発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, wooden Wa-abumi (round stirrups, which are horse gears) were found in the heaped earth inside the surrounding moat through the excavation research of the vicinity executed by the Sakurai City Board of Education in 2000.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, wooden Wa-abumi (round stirrups, which are equestrian gear) were found in the heaped earth within the surrounding moat through the excavation research of the vicinity executed by the Sakurai City Board of Education in 2000.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, wooden Wa-abumi (round stirrups, which are equestrian gear) were found in the heaped earth within the surrounding moat through the excavation research of the vicinity executed by the Sakurai City Board of Education in 2000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>同時に出土した布留1式土器により4世紀のものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is inferred to belong to the fourth century because of the Furu 0-style earthenware that was unearthed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inference is that it belongs to the fourth century, considering the Furu 0-style earthenware that was unearthed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inference is that it belongs to the fourth century, considering the Furu 1-style earthenware that was unearthed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>0-style→1-styleに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これにより日本列島内への騎馬文化の流入および東アジアにおける騎馬文化の伝播の理解が従来よりも古く修正されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this basis, understanding with regard to the inflow of the kiba culture (the equestrian culture) into the Japanese Islands as well as the diffusion of the kiba culture in East Asia has been modified in order to reflect their earlier occurrences.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that basis, the understanding with regard to the inflow of the kiba culture (the equestrian culture) into the Japanese archipelago, as well as the diffusion of the kiba culture in East Asia, has been modified in order to reflect their earlier occurrences.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that basis, the understanding with regard to the inflow of the kiba culture (the equestrian culture) into the Japanese archipelago, as well as the diffusion of the kiba culture in East Asia, has been modified in order to reflect their earlier occurrences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>ただし周濠内からの出土であることから、古墳本体の築造年代とは関わりのない後世の二次的な出土物である可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also possible that they are secondary artifacts belonging to later periods that have nothing to do with the construction period of the kofun itself, since they were unearthed from inside the surrounding moat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also possible that they are secondary artifacts belonging to later periods that have nothing to do with the construction period of the kofun itself, since they were unearthed from inside the surrounding moat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also possible that they are secondary artifacts belonging to later periods that have nothing to do with the construction period of the kofun itself, since they were unearthed from inside the surrounding moat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>尚、織田氏の統治下では、墳丘上にお茶室が設けられていたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it is reported that a tea-ceremony room was set up on the burial mound under the rule of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it is reported that a tea-ceremony room was set up on the burial mound under the rule of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it is reported that a tea-ceremony room was set up on the burial mound under the rule of the Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また、後円部南東の側面に測量図で溝が見られるのは、そのふもと近辺に江戸時代、箸中長者の経営する茶店がありその影響とも思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ditch that is found on the southeast side of the rounded rear on the survey map is supposed to be the influence of a teahouse that was run by a choja (millionaire), Hashinaka, around the foot in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ditch that is found on the southeast side of the rounded rear on the survey map is supposed to be associated with a teahouse that was run by a choja (millionaire), Hashinaka, around the foot during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ditch that is found on the southeast side of the rounded rear on the survey map is supposed to be associated with a teahouse that was run by a choja (millionaire), Hashinaka, around the foot during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>主に伊勢参りの旅人を相手に飴・甘味が名物として売られていた、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that candies and sweets were sold, mainly to the travelers going on a pilgrimage to Ise, as special products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that candies and sweets were sold, mainly to travelers on pilgrimages to Ise, as special products.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that candies and sweets were sold, mainly to travelers on pilgrimages to Ise, as special products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>また、周濠に掛かる外堤も少し東から検出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A portion of the outer levee of the surrounding moat has also been detected in the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A portion of the outer levee of the surrounding moat has also been detected in the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A portion of the outer levee of the surrounding moat has also been detected in the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="82">
<j>測量図を見て前方部と後円部の境目に斜めについた溝は、進入禁止になる前に村人が使用した道の跡である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ditch diagonally dividing the square front and the rounded rear on the survey map is the trail that the villagers used to use before the burial mound became inaccessible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ditch diagonally dividing the square front and rounded rear on the survey map is the trail the villagers used before the burial mound became inaccessible.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ditch diagonally dividing the square front and rounded rear on the survey map is the trail the villagers used before the burial mound became inaccessible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), Higashi(id:8842), BoB774(id:148281), Tomzo(id:16777), 123456(id:67803), Reggaeman(id:6214), 田中幹生(id:25312), Godaigo(id:133481), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), Ohigo(id:100474), Kurz(id:1601), Otraff(id:97860), 663highland(id:18755), 味波(id:103790), ５１６(id:45205), Ha～Ha(id:36403), Yosemite(id:5808), Chao35(id:34986), Aduma(id:32899), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>