<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>仏舎利</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s sariras</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB、新和英中辞典、およびhttp://jp.wordmind.com/ecmaster-cgi/Jsearch.cgi?kwd=buddha&amp;bool=and&amp;word=im</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddha&apos;s sariras</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s sariras</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>仏舎利（ぶっしゃり）とは、入滅した釈迦が荼毘に付された際の遺骨及び棺、荼毘祭壇の灰塵を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s sariras refer to the cremated ashes of Buddha&apos;s bones, and the remains of the coffin and alter which were used for the cremation of Buddha when he passed away.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB、プログレッシブ和英中辞典英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddha&apos;s sariras refer to the cremated ashes of Buddha&apos;s bones as well as the remains of the coffin and altar that were used for the cremation of Buddha when he passed away.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s sariras refer to the cremated ashes of Buddha&apos;s bones as well as the remains of the coffin and altar that were used for the cremation of Buddha when he passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>「舎利」は遺骨または遺体を意味する梵語シャリーラ(śarīra)の音写（śarīra शरीरの本義は単に「肉体」の意で、英語body同様に死体も指す）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;sarira&quot; (śarīra) is a loanword from Sanskrit which means the skeletal remains or body. (The term śarīra शरीर originally means &quot;body&quot; in Sanskrit and it also refers to &quot;dead body&quot; as in English.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;sarira&quot; (śarīra), a word borrowed from Sanskrit, means the skeletal remains or body (the term śarīra शरीर originally means &quot;body&quot; in Sanskrit and it also refers to &quot;dead body&quot; as in English).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;sarira&apos; (śarīra), a word borrowed from Sanskrit, means the skeletal remains or body (the term śarīra शरीर originally means &apos;body&apos; in Sanskrit and also refers to &apos;dead body&apos; as in English).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また、仏舎利と舎利は日本に於いてしばしば同義語で、「舎利」と言うことで聖者や釈迦のそれを他と区別する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Buddha&apos;s sarira is often used as a synonym of sarira, and the term sarira is used to distinguish the remains of others from those of the saints or Buddha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Buddha&apos;s sarira is often used as a synonym of sarira, and the term sarira is used to distinguish the remains of others from those of the saints or Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Buddha&apos;s sarira is often used as a synonym of sarira, and the term sarira is used to distinguish the remains of others from those of the saints or Buddha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ちなみに寿司で言う「シャリ」（飯／酢飯）の語源との説もあるが、これは誤り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this connection, some say that the term &quot;shari (rice/vinegared rice)&quot; for sushi derives from sarira, but that view is wrong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this connection, some say the term &quot;shari (rice/vinegared rice)&quot; for sushi derives from sarira, but that view is wrong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this connection, some say the term &apos;shari (rice/vinegared rice)&apos; for sushi is derived from sarira, but that view is wrong.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>詳しくは寿司用語を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, refer to the section for sushi terms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, refer to the section for sushi terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, refer to the section for sushi terms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>釈迦入滅の地クシナガラの統治部族マウラ族は当初仏舎利の専有を表明し、仏教を国教とする周辺国との間に仏舎利を巡って争いが発生する事態となったが、結果として8等分され、それに、容器と残った灰を加えて周辺内外の10か所の寺院に奉納された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, the Malla tribe which ruled Kushinagar (Kusinara) where Buddha died expressed their view that Buddha&apos;s sariras should be solely owned by them, and a dispute arose over Buddha&apos;s sariras between the Malla tribe and other countries which had Buddhism as the state religion. As a result of this dispute, Buddha&apos;s sariras were equally divided into eight pieces and along with the case and remaining ashes and dedicated to 10 temples in the surrounding countries inside and outside of Kushinagar.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。http://www.sacred-destinations.com/india/kushinagar.htmhttp://www.schoolsofbuddhism.com/SecondBuddhistCouncil/tabid/134/Default.aspx英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the Malla tribe that ruled Kushinagar (Kusinara), where Buddha died, expressed the view that Buddha&apos;s sariras should be solely owned by them, and a dispute arose over Buddha&apos;s sariras between the Malla tribe and other countries that had Buddhism as the state religion; consequently, Buddha&apos;s sariras were equally divided into eight pieces and, along with the case and remaining ashes, were dedicated to 10 temples in the surrounding countries within and outside Kushinagar.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the Malla tribe that ruled Kushinagar (Kusinara), where Buddha died, expressed the view that Buddha&apos;s sariras should be solely owned by them, and a dispute arose over Buddha&apos;s sariras between the Malla tribe and other countries that had Buddhism as the state religion; consequently, Buddha&apos;s sariras were equally divided into eight pieces and, along with the case and remaining ashes, were dedicated to 10 temples in the surrounding countries within and outside Kushinagar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>200年の後、インドの敬虔な仏教徒であったマウリヤ朝のアショーカ王はインド統一を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">200 years later, King Asoka of the Maurya Dynasty in India, who was a pious Buddhist, unified the whole land of India under his sway. He excavated seven out of eight places around the country where the Buddha&apos;s sariras had been dedicated, and pulverized the bones and divided grain by grain, and subdivided the ashes into minute quantities. At the end, he re-distributed them to an enormous number of temples inside and outside of the country, which were said to be some 80,000 temples including the ones in surrounding countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">200 years later, King Asoka of the Maurya Dynasty in India, who was a pious Buddhist, unified the whole land of India under his sway. He excavated seven out of eight places around the country where the Buddha&apos;s sariras had been dedicated, and pulverized the bones and divided them grain by grain, and subdivided the ashes into minute quantities; then he redistributed them to an enormous number of temples inside and outside the country, which were said to number some 80,000 temples including the ones in surrounding countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">200 years later, King Asoka of the Maurya Dynasty in India, who was a pious Buddhist, unified the whole land of India under his sway.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル16の原文を2文に分割し、セル17に移動し、あわせて訳文も移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>全国8個所に奉納されていた仏舎利のうち7か所の仏舎利を発掘し、遺骨は細かく粉砕しひと粒ひと粒に分け、灰塵は微量づつに小分けする作業を行って、最終的に周辺国も含めて8万余の膨大な寺院に再配布を実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He excavated seven out of eight places around the country where the Buddha&apos;s sariras had been dedicated, and pulverized the bones and divided them grain by grain, and subdivided the ashes into minute quantities; then he redistributed them to an enormous number of temples inside and outside the country; these were said to number some 80,000 temples, including the ones in surrounding countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル16の原文を2文に分割し、セル17に移動し、あわせて訳文も移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>仏教が後年に伝来する中国では、多くの僧が仏舎利の奉納されたインドやタイ王国に赴き、仏舎利の収められたストゥーパ（仏舎利を納骨する円すい形の仏塔。日本の卒塔婆のモデルであり語源である）の前で供養した宝石類を「仏舎利の代替品」として持ち帰り、それを自寺の仏塔に納めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many monks from China, to which Buddhism was introduced in late years, headed out to India and the Kingdom of Thailand, where Buddha&apos;s sariras had been dedicated.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB新和英中辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many monks from China, to which Buddhism was introduced in late years, headed out to India and the Kingdom of Thailand, where Buddha&apos;s sariras had been dedicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many monks from China, to which Buddhism was introduced in later years, headed out to India and the Kingdom of Thailand, where Buddha&apos;s sariras had been dedicated, and they held a memorial service with gems, etc., in front of stupa (a cone-shaped Buddhist monument in which Buddha&apos;s sariras were laid; a model and the origin of Japanese sotoba, or stupa); they took the gems as &apos;substitutes for Buddha&apos;s sariras&apos; to China and applied them to the pagodas of their temples.</e>
<cmt>原文が途中で切れ、セル20にまたがっていたので、1文に戻しました。訳文も1文に統合しました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この宝石を仏舎利の代用として奉納する手法は古くから日本でも行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This method of using gems as substitutes of Buddha&apos;s sariras was also used in Japan from old times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This method of using gems as substitutes for Buddha&apos;s sariras was also used in Japan in old times.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This method of using gems as substitutes for Buddha&apos;s sariras was also used in Japan in old times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>仏教公伝は538年とも552年とも伝えられており、このとき仏像や経典が渡来したとあるが、舎利についての記述はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan either in 538 or in 522, and that Buddhist statues and sutra were brought over at the same time, but there was no description on sariras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan either in 538 or in 522, and that Buddhist statues and sutra were brought over at the same time, but there was no description of sariras.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan either in 538 or in 552, and that Buddhist statues and sutra were brought over at the same time, but there was no description of sariras.</e>
<cmt>年号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>『日本書紀』には、推古元年正月15日（西暦593年）に、「仏の舎利を以て、法興寺の刹の柱の礎の中に置く」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a description in the &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot; that &quot;Buddha&apos;s sariras were placed in the cornerstone of a pillar of 刹 in Hoko-ji Temple&quot; in 593.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB「刹」　定訳不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description in the &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot; that &quot;Buddha&apos;s sariras were placed in the cornerstone of a pillar of 刹 in Hoko-ji Temple&quot; in 593.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description in the &quot;Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan)&quot; that &apos;Buddha&apos;s sariras were placed in the cornerstone of a pillar of 刹 in Hoko-ji Temple&apos; in January 15, 593 (in old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>1956年、飛鳥寺周辺の発掘調査により、法興寺（または元輿寺）の遺構が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1956, as a result of an excavation of the surrounding area of Asuka-dera Temple, an ancient foundation of Hoko-ji Temple (Gango-ji Temple) was found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1956, as a result of an excavation of the area surrounding Asuka-dera Temple, an ancient foundation of Hoko-ji Temple (Gango-ji Temple) was found.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1956, as a result of an excavation of the area surrounding Asuka-dera Temple, an ancient foundation of Hoko-ji Temple (Gango-ji Temple) was found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして今は失われた仏塔の芯礎から、木箱に収められた舎利容器が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A vessel for Buddha&apos;s sariras placed in a wooden box was found in a pillar foundation of the stupa, which does not exist anymore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A vessel for Buddha&apos;s sariras placed in a wooden box was found in a pillar foundation of the stupa, which no longer exists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A vessel for Buddha&apos;s sariras placed in a wooden box was found in a pillar foundation of the stupa, which no longer exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>舎利は593年に芯礎に安置されたが、完成した仏塔は1196年に落雷のため焼失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sariras were placed in the pillar foundation, but the stupa was burnt down in 1196 because of a lightning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sariras were placed in the pillar foundation, but the stupa was burned down in 1196 as the result of lightning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sariras were placed in the pillar foundation in 593, but the stupa was burned down in 1196 as the result of lightning.</e>
<cmt>年号の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>舎利は翌年いったん掘り出され、新しい舎利容器と木箱に入れて、ふたたび芯礎部分に埋めたものという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the sariras had been dug out next year, then put in a new vessel and a wooden box, and buried in the pillar foundation again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the following year the sariras were dug out, placed in a new vessel and a wooden box, and buried in the pillar foundation. again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the following year the sariras were dug out, placed in a new vessel and a wooden box, and buried in the pillar foundation again.</e>
<cmt>文中の余計なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>飛鳥時代には法興寺、斑鳩寺（現在の法隆寺）、現在の四天王寺など、立派な仏塔を備えた寺院が建立されているが、これらの仏塔は仏舎利を祭るものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Asuka Period, temples with an outstanding stupa, such as Hoko-ji Temple, Ikaruga-dera Temple (now Horyu-ji Temple), and the existing Shitenno-ji Temple, were built, whose stupa were dedicated to Buddha&apos;s sariras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Asuka period, temples with outstanding stupa, such as Hoko-ji Temple, Ikaruga-dera Temple (now Horyu-ji Temple), and the existing Shitenno-ji Temple, were built, whose stupa were dedicated to Buddha&apos;s sariras.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Asuka period, temples with outstanding stupa, such as Hoko-ji Temple, Ikaruga-dera Temple (now Horyu-ji Temple), and the existing Shitenno-ji Temple, were built, whose stupa were dedicated to Buddha&apos;s sariras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="19">
<j>『日本書紀』はまた、推古30年7月（西暦623年）に新羅の真平王が仏像・金塔・舎利などを贈ってきたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a description in the Nihonshoki that Buddhist statues, a golden stupa, and sariras were sent by Jinpyeong-wang of the Silla Kingdom in 623.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://jp.ipohang.org/Jp/Culture/?navi=DETAIL&amp;seq=93</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a description in the Nihon Shoki that Buddhist statues, a golden stupa and sariras were sent by Jinpyeong-wang of the Silla Kingdom in 623.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a description in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; that Buddhist statues, a golden stupa and sariras were sent by Jinpyeong-wang of the Silla Kingdom in July, 623 (in old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>&quot;を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この舎利は四天王寺に収められたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the sariras were dedicated to Shitenno-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>初期仏教では仏法（教え）を貴び、またインドの慣習儀礼に基づき像を造ることがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Buddhism in its early days, Buddhist doctrine was valued and statues were not created based on the Indian customs and religious observance. Therefore, Buddha&apos;s sariras were the only subject of religious belief with a concrete shape.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Buddhism&apos;s early days, Buddhist doctrine was valued so statues were not created based on the Indian customs and religious observance. Therefore, Buddha&apos;s sariras were the only subject of religious belief with a concrete shape.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Buddhism&apos;s early days, Buddhist doctrine was valued so statues were not created based on the Indian customs and religious observances.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル39の原文を2文に分割し、セル40に移動し、あわせて訳文も移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのため、仏舎利が唯一具体的な形を持った信仰対象となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Buddha&apos;s sariras were the only subjects of religious belief having a concrete shape.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル39の原文を2文に分割し、セル40に移動し、あわせて訳文も移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし日本へ伝来したときは最初から仏像があったので、仏舎利とそれを祭る仏塔は必ずしも信仰の中心ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Buddhism was introduced into Japan, Buddhist statues existed from the beginning, so Buddha&apos;s sariras and stupa which were dedicated to the sariras were not necessarily in the center of the religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Buddhism was introduced into Japan, Buddhist statues existed from the beginning, so Buddha&apos;s sariras and stupa, which were dedicated to the sariras, were not necessarily at the center of the religion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Buddhism was introduced into Japan, Buddhist statues existed from the beginning, so Buddha&apos;s sariras and stupa, which were dedicated to the sariras, were not necessarily at the center of the religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>754年に鑑真が仏舎利を携えて来日しているが、806年に空海らが真言密教とともに大量の仏舎利を持ち帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Jianzhen visited Japan with Buddha&apos;s sariras in 754, Kukai brought back a large amount of Buddha&apos;s sariras with Shingon Esoteric Buddhism in 806.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://jp.ipohang.org/Jp/Culture/?navi=DETAIL&amp;seq=93英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://opac.ndl.go.jp/articleid/9597727/jpn、およびhttp://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110002662703/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Jianzhen visited Japan with Buddha&apos;s sariras in 754, Kukai brought back a large number of Buddha&apos;s sariras with Shingon Esoteric Buddhism in 806.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Jianzhen visited Japan with Buddha&apos;s sariras in 754, Kukai brought back a large number of Buddha&apos;s sariras with Shingon Esoteric Buddhism in 806.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>以降、日本において仏舎利信仰が再燃し、仏塔だけでなく舎利容器に収めたものを室内でも礼拝するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, worship for Buddha&apos;s sariras was reignited in Japan and people started to worship not only sariras in stupa but also in a vessel for Buddha&apos;s sariras inside the building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, worship for Buddha&apos;s sariras was reignited in Japan and people started to worship not only sariras in stupa but also in a vessel for Buddha&apos;s sariras within the building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, worship for Buddha&apos;s sariras was reignited in Japan and people started to worship not only sariras in stupa but also in a vessel for Buddha&apos;s sariras within the building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>江戸時代の鎖国、明治の廃仏毀釈などで海外との交流は途絶えるが、明治末期の1900年以降、スリランカ、タイ王国などの上座部仏教圏との交流から仏舎利を贈与された例がいくつかある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the national seclusion in the Edo Period and the anti-Buddhist movement in the Meiji Period, interactions with overseas broke off, but there were a few cases where Buddha&apos;s sariras were given as a result of interactions with the countries with Theravada Buddhism such as Sri Lanka and Thailand after 1990, end of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB、プログレッシブ和英中辞典EXCEED和英辞典、およびhttp://jp.wordmind.com/ecmaster-cgi/Jsearch.cgi?kwd=%A4%CF%A4%A4&amp;word=im英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the national seclusion in the Edo period and the anti-Buddhist movement in the Meiji period, interactions with overseas countries broke off, but there were a few cases where Buddha&apos;s sariras were given as a result of interactions with the countries of Theravada Buddhism such as Sri Lanka and Thailand after 1890, at the end of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the national seclusion in the Edo period and the anti-Buddhism movement in the Meiji period, interactions with overseas countries broke off, but there were a few cases where Buddha&apos;s sariras were given as a result of interactions with the countries of Theravada Buddhism such as Sri Lanka and Thailand after 1900, at the end of the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>年号の訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>真贋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">True and False</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">True or False</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">True or False</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>仏舎利については不可思議な伝承が多く、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many mysterious traditions about Buddha&apos;s sariras.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many mysterious traditions about Buddha&apos;s sariras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many mysterious traditions about Buddha&apos;s sariras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「仏舎利を奉戴するに相応しくない者が持てば消滅する」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Buddha&apos;s sariras will disappear if owned by someone who does not deserve to have them.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Buddha&apos;s sariras will disappear if owned by someone who does not deserve to have them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s sariras will disappear if owned by someone who does not deserve to have them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>「仏舎利奉戴に相応しい者が持てば数も増え、大きくなったり、変色したりする」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Buddha&apos;s sariras will multiply in number, become bigger, or change its colors if owned by someone who deserve to have them.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Buddha&apos;s sariras will multiply in number, become bigger or change colors if owned by someone who deserves to have them.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha&apos;s sariras will multiply in number, become bigger or change colors if owned by someone who deserves to have them.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>といった、信心の深さによって変化が現れると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, it is said that there will be changes depending on the depth of faith.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, it is said that there will be changes depending on one&apos;s depth of faith.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, it is said that there will be changes depending on one&apos;s depth of faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この伝承が、宗教団体法の華三法行を主催した福永法源が「真性仏舎利を奉戴した後、超能力で100個に増えた」と言ったことからも分かるように、「仏舎利が増えるならビジネスになる」という悪智慧の温床にもなってしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This tradition has been a hotbed of craft such as &quot;If Buddha&apos;s sariras increase in number, it is a sign of good business,&quot; as seen in a comment by Hogen FUKUNAGA, founder of Ho-no-Hana Sampogyo, a religious organization, saying &quot;When I was given genuine Buddha&apos;s sariras, it multiplied by 100 by my supernatural power.&quot;</e>
<cmt>http://www.japantimes.co.jp/weekly/news/nn2005/nn20050723a6.htm、http://www.rickross.com/groups/ho_no_hana.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tradition has been a hotbed of craft such as, &quot;If Buddha&apos;s sariras increase in number, it is a sign of good business,&quot; as seen in a comment by Hogen FUKUNAGA, founder of Ho-no-Hana Sampogyo, a religious organization, who stated, &quot;When I was given genuine Buddha&apos;s sariras, they multiplied by 100 due to my supernatural power.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tradition has been a hotbed of craft such as, &apos;If Buddha&apos;s sariras increase in number, it is a sign of good business,&apos; as seen in a comment by Hogen FUKUNAGA, founder of Ho-no-Hana Sampogyo, a religious organization, who stated, &apos;When I was given genuine Buddha&apos;s sariras, they multiplied by 100 due to my supernatural power.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>一説には、現在アジア全土に自称仏舎利の合計は2トンにも達するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to another version, self-claimed Buddha&apos;s sariras spread throughout Asia amount to two tons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to another version, the so-called sariras of Buddha spread throughout Asia in a combined weight of two tons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to another version, the so-called sariras of Buddha spread throughout Asia in a combined weight of two tons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>仏舎利は、釈迦の遺骨・灰塵である真性の仏舎利のほか、宝石等による代替仏舎利が、時を経るごとに混乱して真・代いずれが何処の寺院に奉納されているのかが不明瞭になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are genuine Buddha&apos;s sariras which are the remains of Buddha&apos;s bones and ashes as well as substitutes such as gems, etc. Over the years, it has become confusing and unclear which genuine or substitutes of Buddha&apos;s sariras were dedicated in which temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are genuine Buddha&apos;s sariras that are the remains of Buddha&apos;s bones and ashes, as well as substitutes such as gems, etc; over the years it has become confusing and unclear which of Buddha&apos;s sariras, whether genuine or substitutes, were dedicated in which temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are genuine Buddha&apos;s sariras that are the remains of Buddha&apos;s bones and ashes, as well as substitutes such as gems, etc; over the years it has become confusing and unclear which of Buddha&apos;s sariras, whether genuine or substitutes, were dedicated in which temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そのため後年スリランカ政府が実態を調査し、回収可能なものは回収するなどして管理している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, the Sri Lankan government conducted a research on actual conditions and manage them by collecting Buddha&apos;s sariras where possible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Sri Lankan government conducted research on actual conditions and manages them by collecting Buddha&apos;s sariras where possible.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Sri Lankan government conducted research on actual conditions and manages them by collecting Buddha&apos;s sariras where possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>現在スリランカ政府は「仏舎利は金銭（布施）による取引で贈与することはなく、奉戴するに相応しい寺院団体を審査のうえで選出し、贈与している」としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sri Lankan government says, &quot;We do not give away Buddha&apos;s sariras as an exchange for money (donation), but give them to the temples which deserve to receive them based on our investigation and selection.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sri Lankan government says, &quot;We do not give away Buddha&apos;s sariras as an exchange for money (donation), but we give them to the temples that deserve to receive them based on our investigation and selection.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sri Lankan government says, &apos;We do not give away Buddha&apos;s sariras as an exchange for money (donation), but we give them to the temples that deserve to receive them based on our investigation and selection.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>考古学的に本物の釈迦の遺骨とされるものは、1898年にインドで発掘されたものであり、これは当時インドを支配していた英国からシャム国（現在のタイ王国）に譲渡されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is deemed as a true remains of Buddha&apos;s bones archaeologically is the one which was excavated in India in 1898, which was transferred by the United Kingdom which ruled India at that time to Siam (now Kingdom of Thailand).</e>
<cmt>プログレッシブ和英中辞典英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is deemed to be the true remains of Buddha&apos;s bones, archaeologically, was excavated in India in 1898 and subsequently transferred by the United Kingdom, which ruled India at that time, to Siam (now the Kingdom of Thailand).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is deemed to be the true remains of Buddha&apos;s bones, archaeologically, was excavated in India in 1898 and subsequently transferred by the United Kingdom, which ruled India at that time, to Siam (now the Kingdom of Thailand).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その一部はシャム国王ラーマ5世から日本国民へ贈られ、それを納めるために創建されたのが覚王山日暹寺（現在の覚王山日泰寺）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A portion of the sariras was given to the Japanese people by Rama V of Siam and Kakuozan Nissen-ji Temple (now Kakuo-zan Nittai-ji Temple) was built to deposit it.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A portion of the sariras was given to the Japanese people by Rama V of Siam, and Kakuozan Nissen-ji Temple (now Kakuo-zan Nittai-ji Temple) was built to deposit it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A portion of the sariras was given to the Japanese people by Rama V of Siam, and Kakuozan Nissen-ji Temple (now Kakuo-zan Nittai-ji Temple) was built to deposit it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="38">
<j>仏舎利崇敬の是非</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rights and Wrongs of Worship of Buddha&apos;s Sariras</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rights and Wrongs of Worshipping Buddha&apos;s Sariras</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rights and Wrongs of Worshipping Buddha&apos;s Sariras</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>釈迦は晩年、弟子らに対して「総てのものには必ず終わりがある／私の亡き後は私の遺した教えが皆の拠り所である。怠らず弁ぜよ」と語った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his later years, Buddha said to his disciples, &quot;All things must come to an end. When I am dead, my teachings will lead you. Never shirk, keep studying.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, Buddha said to his disciples, &quot;All things must come to an end; when I am dead, my teachings will lead you; never shirk, but keep studying.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddha, in his later years, said to his disciples, &apos;All things must come to an end; when I am dead, my teachings will lead you; never shirk, but keep studying.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。原文の最後が切れ、セル68の文頭に組み込まれていたので移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>諸行無常は必然とした上で、教義の伝承を最重要と説いていることから、後代の解釈では、物として実在する仏舎利を過度に崇拝崇敬することは釈迦の意向から逸脱している、と考える向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Buddha explained handing down the doctrine was the most important thing as Shogyo-mujo (All things are impermanent) was inevitable, in the interpretation in later years, there are those who believe that it deviates from Buddha&apos;s intention to worship and venerate Buddha&apos;s sariras, which exist as actual things, too much.</e>
<cmt>http://www.rk-world.org/ftp/basic.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Buddha explained that the handing down of the doctrine was the most important thing as Shogyo-mujo (all things are impermanent) and therefore inevitable, in the interpretations of later years there have been those who believed it deviates too far from Buddha&apos;s intention to worship and venerate Buddha&apos;s sariras, which exist as actual things.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Buddha explained that the handing down of doctrine was of the greatest importance as Shogyo-mujo (all things are impermanent) is inevitable, in later years there were some who believed that worshiping and venerating the Buddha&apos;s sariras, which exist as tangible things, deviates from the Buddha&apos;s intention.</e>
<cmt>I think it is more natural to say &quot;the Buddha&quot; than just &quot;Buddha&quot; so the rest of this page may need to be changed accordingly.</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>しかしながら、南伝の上座部仏教においては、上記で説明される通り、まぎれもなく仏舎利を信仰の対象としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Theravada Buddhism introduced from the south, Buddha&apos;s sarira was the object of worship undoubtedly, as explained above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Theravada Buddhism introduced from the south, Buddha&apos;s sarira was undoubtedly the object of worship, as explained above.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Theravada Buddhism introduced from the south, Buddha&apos;s sarira was undoubtedly the object of worship, as explained above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="42">
<j>また、北伝の大乗仏教においても、仏舎利は法身や仏性と同義と解釈する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in Mahayana [greater vehicle] Buddhism introduced from the north, Buddha&apos;s sariras are interpreted as the same as Truth Body or Buddha-nature.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in the Mahayana (greater vehicle) Buddhism introduced from the north, Buddha&apos;s sariras are interpreted as identical to &quot;Truth Body&quot; or &quot;Buddha-nature.&quot;</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in the Mahayana (greater vehicle) Buddhism introduced from the north, Buddha&apos;s sariras are interpreted as identical to &quot;Truth Body&quot; or &quot;Buddha-nature.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>涅槃経には以下のように説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nehan-gyo preaches as the following.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nehan-gyo preaches the following:</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nehan-gyo preaches the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="44">
<j>このように、仏塔や仏像を創設し、その中に宿る仏性を見つめていくことで、仏の世界へ近づくことが出来るという解釈が成立していることから、仏舎利への敬慕信仰という思想自体も正道から外れたものではない、と考える向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, there is an interpretation that people can get closer to the world of Buddha by creating stupas and Buddhist statues and staring into the eyes of Buddha-nature inside. Therefore, there are those who believe that the philosophy which respects and worships Buddha&apos;s sariras itself is not an unrighteous act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, there is an interpretation that people can get closer to the world of Buddha by creating stupas and Buddhist statues and staring into the eyes of Buddha-nature within; thus there are those who believe the philosophy that respects and worships Buddha&apos;s sariras is not an unrighteous act.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, there is an interpretation that people can get closer to the world of Buddha by creating stupas and Buddhist statues and staring into the eyes of Buddha-nature within; thus there are those who believe the philosophy that respects and worships Buddha&apos;s sariras is not an unrighteous act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MikeAz800o(id:58193), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 浩(id:70121), Raad(id:4918), Fluffy nns(id:601), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Taisyo(id:6896), PATMAN(id:145791), わがまま小皇帝(id:39717), Ag919(id:95805), 雲居雁乃(id:15842), Wiiii(id:59641), Makotozushi(id:4545), 死郎(id:1683), Kurz(id:1601), Akiyoshi&apos;s Room(id:146283), Shinobar(id:42025), Yukichin(id:725), Boca samba(id:137526), 木林森(id:10796), Ko-ken(id:49348), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Loveless(id:129239), Naoki123(id:70112), 踏蹟(id:51201), トホホ川(id:50502), Hat shop(id:3993), やすとし(id:63220), Corwin(id:973), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>