<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>和室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style Room</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style Room</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style Room</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>和室（わしつ）は、伝統的な日本の家屋に特有の、畳を敷き詰めた部屋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style room is a room on whose floor tatami mats are laid in a traditional Japanese house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Japanese-style room is a room on whose floor tatami mats are laid in a traditional Japanese house.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Japanese-style room is a room on whose floor tatami mats are laid in a traditional Japanese house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>畳の敷き方にもしきたりがあるが、その畳の敷かれた枚数で部屋の大きさを測るのもよく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The method of laying tatami mats depends on the tradition, and it is well known that the size of a room was measured by counting the number of tatami mats laid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The method of laying tatami mats depends on the tradition, and, as is well known, the size of a room was measured by counting the number of tatami mats laid.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The method of laying tatami mats depends on the tradition, and, as is well known, the size of a room was measured by counting the number of tatami mats laid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>家の中心になる部屋には、床の間がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed) is in a room located in the center of a house,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed) is in a room located in the center of a house,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed) is in a room located in the center of a house,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>空間は、障子や襖（ふすま）で囲まれ、特に障子は、空間が完全に断絶されているとも、いないともいえる曖昧な、おぼろげさを醸し出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Space is surrounded with shoji (a paper sliding door) or Fusuma (Japanese sliding door), and shoji especially generates fuzzy and dim effects allowing an impression which is ambiguous whether the space is completely partitioned or not.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Space is surrounded with shoji (paper sliding doors) or Fusuma (Japanese sliding doors), and shoji especially generate fuzzy and dim effects, giving an impression of ambiguity of whether or not the space is completely partitioned.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Space is surrounded with shoji (paper sliding doors) or Fusuma (Japanese sliding doors), and shoji especially generate fuzzy and dim effects, giving an impression of ambiguity of whether or not the space is completely partitioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そして、東洋的な幽玄な明かりを空間にもたらしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, a subtle and profound light is brought about.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, a subtle and profound light is brought about.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, a subtle and profound light is brought about.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>和室はさらに机や座布団、寝具などの出し入れで、会食から団欒、書斎、寝室とその用途をさまざまに変えることのできる多目的空間でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese style room offers a multi-purpose space that can be used for purposes from dining to a family get-together, a bedroom by taking out and putting in things such as a folding table, zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor), and Japanese-style bedding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Japanese style room offers a multi-purpose space that can be used for purposes from dining, to a family get-together, to a bedroom, achieved by taking out and putting in things such as a folding table, zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor), and Japanese-style bedding.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Japanese style room offers a multi-purpose space that can be used for purposes from dining, to a family get-together, a study or a bedroom, achieved by taking out and putting in things such as a folding table, zabuton (traditional Japanese cushions used to sit on the floor), and Japanese-style bedding.</e>
<cmt>study(書斎）を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかも、そこでは靴、上履きのような履物を必要としない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, shoes or slippers are not required in there.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, shoes or slippers are not required in a Japanese-style room.</e>
<cmt>omitted pronoun</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, shoes or slippers are not required in a Japanese-style room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>イグサという植物系の自然素材で作られ、素足で歩けばそのまま自然との一体感を味わえ、それがまた夏は涼しく、冬は暖かいという和室の特性を形作っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatami mats, being made of plants called rush, offers a sense of togetherness with nature and generates feelings of coolness in summer and warmth in winter, which are features of a Japanese-style room.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatami mats, being made of plants called rushes, offer a sense of togetherness with nature and generate feelings of coolness in summer and warmth in winter, which are features of a Japanese-style room.</e>
<cmt>plurals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatami mats, being made of plants called rushes, offer a sense of togetherness with nature and generate feelings of coolness in summer and warmth in winter, which are features of a Japanese-style room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>台湾の和室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style room in Taiwan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style room in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style room in Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>台湾は日本統治時代 (台湾)の遺風を残す、和室がある家屋も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiwan, there are quite a few houses with a Japanese-style room which have been succeeded from the period of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiwan, there are quite a few houses with Japanese-style rooms which have been passed down from the period of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiwan, there are quite a few houses with Japanese-style rooms which have been passed down from the period of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中国語で和室（ピンイン：héìshì/héshìh）と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called héìshì/héshìh (pinyin: indicating a pronunciation and tones) in Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called héìshì/héshìh (pinyin: indicating a pronunciation and tones) in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called héìshì/héshìh (pinyin: indicating a pronunciation and tones) in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし台湾の気候は畳に適しないので、和室地板（、和室の床のこと）という木の板で取って代わることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, tatami mats are not suitable for Japanese climates, they are often replaced with wood floor called héìshì de ban (wood floor in Japanese-style room) in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>héìshì de ban→中国語のpinyin を表記したのですが四声の部分（記号）については文字化けの可能性があると思われたため、表記しませんでした（正しくは dì bǎn)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, tatami mats are not suitable for the climate; they are often replaced with wood flooring called héìshì de ban (wood floor in Japanese-style room) in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>rewording, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, tatami mats are not suitable for the climate; they are often replaced with wood flooring called héìshì de ban (wood floor in Japanese-style room) in Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>台湾の和室は主に寝室として使っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiwan, a Japanese-style room is mainly used for a bedroom.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiwan, a Japanese-style room is mainly used for a bedroom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiwan, a Japanese-style room is mainly used for a bedroom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>仏堂．書斎の例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also used for a Buddhist hall and for a Shosai-zu (a drawing of a library).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used for a Buddhist hall and for a Shosai-zu (a drawing of a library).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also used for a Buddhist hall and for a Shosai (a study or a library).</e>
<cmt>書斎を書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>様々な和室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various Japanese-style rooms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Japanese-style rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Japanese-style rooms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SK(id:64397), ととりん(id:31982), Lombroso(id:20212), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Sina(id:10021), 663highland(id:18755), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Aixime(id:106780), Alexbot(id:157199), Mishika(id:276), FlaBot(id:30804), Koika(id:16738), Ws227(id:208643), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>