<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>醍醐寺三宝院庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboin Garden of Daigo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboin Garden of Daigo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanboin Garden of Daigo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>醍醐寺三宝院庭園（だいごじさんぽういんていえん）は、京都府京都市伏見区にある日本庭園である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboin Garden of Daigo-ji Temple is a Japanese style garden located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboin Garden of Daigo-ji Temple is a Japanese style garden located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanboin Garden of Daigo-ji Temple is a Japanese style garden located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>醍醐寺の院家である三宝院の庭園であり、1952年（昭和27年）に国の特別史跡および特別名勝に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the garden of Sanboin, an Inge (a branch temple to support services of the main temple) of Daigo-ji Temple, and was designated as a national historic site and a place of special scenic beauty in 1952.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the garden of Sanboin, an Inge (a branch temple to support services of the main temple) of Daigo-ji Temple, and was designated as a national historic site and a place of special scenic beauty in 1952.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the garden of Sanboin, an Inge (a branch temple to support services of the main temple) of Daigo-ji Temple, and was designated as a national historic site and a place of special scenic beauty in 1952.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>874年（貞観 (日本)16年）、空海の孫弟子にあたる理源大師聖宝が笠取山 (京都府)に醍醐寺を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 874, Rigen Daishi Shobo, Kukai&apos;s disciple in his two generations later, built Daigo-ji Temple on Kasatori-yama Mountain (located in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 874, Rigen Daishi Shobo, a second generation disciple of Kukai, built Daigo-ji Temple on Kasatori-yama Mountain (located in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>second generation disciple</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 874, Rigen Daishi Shobo, a second generation disciple of Kukai, built Daigo-ji Temple on Kasatori-yama Mountain (located in Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>山頂付近は「上醍醐」、山麓一帯は「下醍醐」と呼ばれ、堂塔伽藍が立ち並び繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area around the top of the mountain and the area around the foot of the mountain are called Kami-Daigo (the upper part of Daigo) and Shimo-Daigo (the lower part of Daigo), respectively, and both areas flourished, with dotogaran (the temple&apos;s halls, pagodas and cathedrals) built magnificently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The areas around the top and the foot of the mountain are called Kami-Daigo (upper Daigo) and Shimo-Daigo (lower Daigo), respectively, and both areas flourished with magnificent dotogaran (the temple&apos;s halls, pagodas and cathedrals).</e>
<cmt>shortened this a bit</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The areas around the top and the foot of the mountain are called &apos;Kami-Daigo&apos; (upper Daigo) and &apos;Shimo-Daigo&apos; (lower Daigo), respectively, and both areas flourished with magnificent dotogaran (the temple&apos;s halls, pagodas and cathedrals).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&apos; &apos;補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>三宝院は1115年（永久 (日本)3年）、醍醐寺第14代座主勝覚が開いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboin was established by Shokaku, the 14th zasu （head priest） of Daigo-ji Temple, and produced many zasu for generations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboin was established by Shokaku, the 14th zasu (head priest) of Daigo-ji Temple, and produced many zasu for generations.</e>
<cmt>removed double-Byte characters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanboin was established by Shokaku in 1115, the 14th zasu (head priest) of Daigo-ji Temple, and produced many zasu for generations.</e>
<cmt>「in 1115」補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>特に、歴代の座主を輩出し、1428年（応永35年）以降は三宝院主が醍醐寺座主の地位を独占した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the zasu at Daigo-ji Temple was monopolized by the zasu at Sanboin since 1428.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the zasu at Daigo-ji Temple was monopolized by the zasu at Sanboin since 1428.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the zasu at Daigo-ji Temple was monopolized by the zasu at Sanbo-in since 1428.</e>
<cmt>建物なので、「Sanbo-in」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし醍醐寺は1467年（応仁元年）に始まった応仁の乱の兵火に巻き込まれ、三宝院を含む多くの建物が焼失し、一帯は荒廃してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, many buildings of Daigo-JI Temple, including Sanboin, were burnt and lost in fires caused by fighting in Onin War started in 1467, making the temple lie in ruins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, many buildings of Daigo-JI Temple, including Sanboin, were lost in fires caused by fighting in the Onin War started in 1467, laying ruin to the temple.</e>
<cmt>burnt/lost in fire are redundant</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many buildings of Daigo-ji Temple, including Sanbo-in, were lost in fires caused by fighting in the Onin War started in 1467, laying ruin to the temple.</e>
<cmt>「Daigo-ji」とjiを小文字にしました。「Sanbo-in」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>荒廃した醍醐寺を復興したのが、1576年（天正4年）に第80代座主の地位に就いた義演であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ruined temple was reconstructed by Gien who assumed the post of the 80th zasu in 1574.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ruined temple was reconstructed by Gien, who assumed the post of the 80th zasu in 1574.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ruined temple was reconstructed by Gien, who assumed the post of the 80th zasu in 1576.</e>
<cmt>「1576」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義演は豊臣秀吉の手厚い庇護を受け、1598年（慶長3年）の醍醐の花見を醍醐寺の金剛輪院を中心として執り行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gien was considerably patronized by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and in 1598, held a cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo, centered on Kongorin-in of the Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gien had a great patron in Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and in 1598 held a cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo, centered on Kongorin-in of the Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>rephrased the patron part</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gien had a great patron in Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and in 1598 held a cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo, centered on Kongorin-in of the Daigo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、金剛輪院に「三宝院」の名称を受け継がせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, he had the title of &quot;Sanboin&quot; inherited by Kongorin-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, he had the title of &quot;Sanboin&quot; inherited by Kongorin-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, he had the title of &apos;Sanbo-in&apos; inherited by Kongorin-in.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。「Sanbo-in」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これが今日に伝わる三宝院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the start of present Sanboin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the start of present Sanboin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the start of present Sanbo-in.</e>
<cmt>「Sanbo-in」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>三宝院庭園は、この醍醐の花見に際して、豊臣秀吉が自らが基本設計を行ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboin Garden was basically designed by Hideyoshi himself when the cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo was held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboin Garden was basically designed by Hideyoshi himself when the cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanboin Garden was basically designed by Hideyoshi himself when the cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo was held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>作庭は醍醐の花見が終わった4月から始められ、その年の8月に秀吉が死去した後は義演の指導のもとで続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the garden started in April after the cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo ended, and, after Hideyoshi died in August, was continued under guidance of Gien.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the garden started in April after the cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo ended, and, after Hideyoshi died in August, was continued under guidance of Gien.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the garden started in April after the cherry blossom-viewing party at Daigo ended, and, after Hideyoshi died in August, was continued under guidance of Gien.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>義演は秀吉の基本設計をもとにさらに構想を発展させ、また当時一流の庭師を作庭に参画させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gien advanced the plan, based on Hideyoshi&apos;s basic design, and had first-class garden designers participated in building the garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gien advanced the plan, based on Hideyoshi&apos;s basic design, and had first-class garden designers participated in building the garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gien advanced the plan, based on Hideyoshi&apos;s basic design, and had first-class garden designers participated in building the garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>庭師の中には「天下一の石組の名手」と称された賢庭もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kentei, who was called &quot;the best rockwork expert in Japan,&quot; was also included in the garden designers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kentei, who was called &quot;the best rockwork expert in Japan,&quot; was also included in the garden designers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kentei, who was called &apos;the best rockwork expert in Japan,&apos; was also included in the garden designers.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>作庭は義演が亡くなる1624年（元和10年）までの27年間にわたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The work to construct the garden continued for 27 years until Gien died in 1624.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The work to construct the garden continued for 27 years until Gien died in 1624.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The work to construct the garden continued for 27 years until Gien died in 1624.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>当初、三宝院庭園は表書院から眺めるための鑑賞式庭園として設計された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboin Garden was initially designed as an a Kansho-shiki garden (a garden whose view is to be enjoyed) to be viewed from the omote shoin (main drawing room).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboin Garden was initially designed as a Kansho-shiki garden (a garden whose view is to be enjoyed) to be viewed from the omote shoin (main drawing room).</e>
<cmt>stray “an” and a whole bunch of extra spaces at the end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanbo-in Garden was initially designed as a Kansho-shiki garden (a garden whose view is to be enjoyed) to be viewed from the omote shoin (main drawing room).</e>
<cmt>「Sanbo-in」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、義演の死後に庭園内に茶室が置かれ、回遊もできるように造り変えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, after Gien died, a house for tea ceremony was built in the garden and the garden itself was modified so as to provide circulating walking-around paths.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after Gien died, a house for tea ceremony was built in the garden and the garden itself was modified so as to provide circulating walking paths.</e>
<cmt>deleted “around”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after Gien died, a house for tea ceremony was built in the garden and the garden itself was modified so as to provide circulating walking paths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>庭園の中心を占める池には「亀島」「鶴島」が配され、橋が架けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the pond at the center of the garden, a kame-shima island (literally, a tortoise island）and a tsuru-shima island (literally, a crane island) are placed, each connected with the land around the pond with a bridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the pond at the center of the garden, there are a kame-shima island (literally, a tortoise island）and a tsuru-shima island (literally, a crane island), each connected to the land around the pond with a bridge.</e>
<cmt>are placed-&gt;there arewith-&gt;to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the pond at the center of the garden, there are a &apos;kame-shima island&apos; (literally, a tortoise island) and a &apos;tsuru-shima island&apos; (literally, a crane island), each connected to the land around the pond with a bridge.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。原文の「」に合せて&apos;を補足しました。全角の）を半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>正面に据えられている「藤戸石」は、元々は管領家の細川氏の邸宅にあったもので、秀吉が聚楽第から運ばせたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Fujito-ishi&quot; (Fushito stone) placed on the front side was originally in the residence of the Hosokawa clan, a kanrei-ke family (a family in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), and Hideyoshi had the stone brought here from the Jurakudai residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Fujito-ishi&quot; (Fushito stone) placed on the front side was originally in the residence of the Hosokawa clan, a kanrei-ke family (a family in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), and Hideyoshi had the stone brought here from the Jurakudai residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Fujito-ishi&apos; (Fushito stone) placed on the front side was originally in the residence of the Hosokawa clan, a kanrei-ke family (a family in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), and Hideyoshi had the stone brought here from the Jurakudai residence.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>背後には水の音が変化するようにしつらえられた三段の滝石組が造られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the back side, a three-step fall made of artificially-placed rocks is provided so that the water-flow sound varies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the back side, a three-step fall made of artificially-placed rocks makes for varied sound of flowing water.</e>
<cmt>rephrased the bit about flowing water</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the back side, a three-step fall made of artificially-placed rocks makes for varied sound of flowing water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>三宝院庭園は、安土桃山時代の華やかな雰囲気を今日に伝える日本庭園として貴重なものであり、1952年（昭和27年）に国の特別史跡および特別名勝に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanboin Garden is precious as a Japanese garden where the gorgeous atmosphere of the Azuchi-Momoyama period can be felt, and was designated as a national special historic site and a place of special beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanboin Garden is precious as a Japanese garden where the gorgeous atmosphere of the Azuchi-Momoyama period can be felt, and was designated as a national special historic site and a place of special beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanbo-in Garden is precious as a Japanese garden where the gorgeous atmosphere of the Azuchi-Momoyama period can be felt, and was designated as a national special historic site and a place of special beauty in 1952.</e>
<cmt>「Sanbo-in」に訂正しました。in 1952を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), どんどん(id:172259), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>