<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>難波宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naniwa no Miya (an ancient palace in the Asuka and Nara periods in present Chuo Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya (an ancient palace in the Asuka and Nara periods in present Chuo Ward, Osaka City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>難波宮（なにわのみや）は、現在の大阪市中央区 (大阪市)にあった飛鳥時代・奈良時代の宮殿。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya was a palace that existed in the present Chuo Ward, Osaka City (Osaka City) in the Asuka and Nara periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naniwa no Miya was a palace located in the present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City in the Asuka and Nara periods.</e>
<cmt>原文には「(大阪市)」とありますが、リンク先の単語が抽出されるバグのようですので、訳出しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya was a palace located in the present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City in the Asuka and Nara periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>史書（『日本書紀』）には載っていたが、第二次世界大戦が終わるまでは所在地は不明なままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya was mentioned in a book of history (Nihonshoki, the Chronicles of Japan) but its location remained unknown until the end of the World War 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was mentioned in a history book (Nihonshoki [the Chronicles of Japan]), however, its location remained unknown until the end of the World War II.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mentioned in a history book (Nihonshoki [the Chronicles of Japan]), however, its location remained unknown until the end of the World War II.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1913年（大正2）大阪城外堀の南付近で数個の重圏文（じゅうけんもん）・蓮華文の瓦が発見されていたが、ほとんどの人は省みなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1913, several roof tiles with the jukenmon (concentric circle design) and rengemon (lotus flower patterns) patterns were found but were virtually ignored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1913, several roof tiles with the jukenmon (concentric circle design) and rengemon (lotus flower patterns) were found but were virtually ignored.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1913, several roof tiles with the jukenmon (concentric circle design) and rengemon (lotus flower patterns) were found but were virtually ignored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、1953年（昭和28）同所付近から鴟尾（しび）が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1953, however, Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile) was unearthed in the vicinity where the roof tiles had been found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1953, however, Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile) was unearthed in the vicinity where the roof tiles had been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1953, however, Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile) was unearthed in the vicinity where the roof tiles had been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このことがきっかけになり山根徳太郎を指導者とする難波宮址顕彰会の努力により発掘・調査が進み、奈良時代の宮の遺構が次第に明らかになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That discovery jump-started the excavation and study by Naniwakyushi Kenshokai under the leadership of Tokutaro YAMANE and, little by little, the remains of the palace in the Nara Period became unraveled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That discovery jump-started the excavation and study by Naniwakyushi Kenshokai (Association of honoring publicly for Naniwa-kyu Palace site) under the leadership of Tokutaro YAMANE and, little by little, the remains of the palace in the Nara period became unraveled.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That discovery jump-started the excavation and study by Naniwakyushi Kenshokai (Association of honoring publicly for Naniwa-kyu Palace site) under the leadership of Tokutaro YAMANE and, little by little, the remains of the palace in the Nara period became unraveled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そればかりでなく、1958年（昭和33）にはそれよりも一時代古いとみられる柱列跡が検出され、その柱穴に焦土が詰まっており、火災の跡であることが明らかになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1958, additionally, the remains of pillars believed to be a generation older than Shibi and, from the scorched earth that filled pillar holes, it became known that there had been a fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1958, additionally, the remains of pillars believed to be a generation older than Shibi and, from the scorched earth that filled pillar holes, it became known that there had been a fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1958, additionally, the remains of pillars believed to be a generation older than Shibi and, from the scorched earth that filled pillar holes, it became known that there had been a fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>つまり、686年（朱鳥元）正月「難波の宮室が全焼した」記録から、孝徳朝の宮室が焼失したと推定でき、その後に天武朝の宮室が建造されたのだと考えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, based on the record that the Naniwa no Miya Palace burnt down on New Year&apos;s Day of 686, it can be presumed that the palace of Emperor Kotoku was lost in fire whereby it came to be thus considered that a new palace was subsequently built for Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, based on the record that &apos;the Naniwa no Miya Palace burnt down&apos; in February 686, it can be presumed that the palace of Emperor Kotoku was lost in fire whereby it came to be thus considered that a new palace was subsequently built for Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしグレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, based on the record that &apos;the Naniwa no Miya Palace burnt down&apos; in February 686, it can be presumed that the palace of Emperor Kotoku was lost in fire whereby it came to be thus considered that a new palace was subsequently built for Emperor Tenmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらを「前期難波宮」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These palaces in the foregoing are referred to as &apos;Zenki Naniwa no Miya&apos; (the early Naniwa no Miya).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These palaces in the foregoing are referred to as &apos;the early Naniwa no Miya Palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除し用語を合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These palaces in the foregoing are referred to as &apos;the early Naniwa no Miya Palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>1961年（昭和36年）、山根徳太郎らの発掘により、聖武天皇時代の「後期難波宮」の大極殿跡が発見され、その存在が確認された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1961, the excavation work performed by Tokutaro YAMANE and his collaborators unearthed the remains of Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) in the late Naniwa no Miya from the era of Emperor Shomu and its existence was confirmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1961, the excavation work performed by Tokutaro YAMANE and his collaborators unearthed the remains of Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) in &apos;the late Naniwa no Miya Palace&apos; of the era of Emperor Shomu and its existence was confirmed.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1961, the excavation work performed by Tokutaro YAMANE and his collaborators unearthed the remains of Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) in &apos;the late Naniwa no Miya Palace&apos; of the era of Emperor Shomu and its existence was confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>山根は発見当時、「われ、幻の大極殿を見たり」という発言を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of this discovery, Yamane stated, &apos;I have seen the vision of Daigokuden.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of this discovery, Yamane stated, &apos;I have seen the vision of Daigokuden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of this discovery, Yamane stated, &apos;I have seen the vision of Daigokuden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>前期・難波宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Early Naniwa no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Early Naniwa no Miya Palace</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Early Naniwa no Miya Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>大化の改新の後、645年に孝徳天皇は難波に遷都し（難波長柄豊崎宮）、宮殿は652年に完成した、これは掘立柱、草葺屋根で造られたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 645, after the Taika Reforms, Emperor Kotoku relocated the capital city to Naniwa (Naniwa no Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace) whereby the earthfast and thatched-roof palace was completed in 652.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 645, after the Taika Reforms, Emperor Kotoku relocated the capital city to Naniwa (Naniwa no Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace) whereby the earthfast and thatched-roof palace was completed in 652.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 645, after the Taika Reforms, Emperor Kotoku relocated the capital city to Naniwa (Naniwa no Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace) whereby the earthfast and thatched-roof palace was completed in 652.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>孝徳天皇の没後、655年1月に斉明天皇が奈良の飛鳥板蓋宮で再び即位（重祚）し、遷都された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 655, after the passing of Emperor Kotoku, Emperor Saimei ascended to the throne for the second time at Asuka Itabuki no Miya palace in Nara whereby transferring the capital city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 655, after the passing of Emperor Kotoku, Empress Saimei ascended to the throne for the second time at Asuka Itabuki no Miya Palace in Nara whereby transferring the capital city.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 655, after the passing of Emperor Kotoku, Empress Saimei ascended to the throne for the second time at Asuka Itabuki no Miya Palace in Nara whereby transferring the capital city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>後期・難波宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Late Naniwa no Miya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Late Naniwa no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Late Naniwa no Miya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>奈良時代の神亀3年（726年）に聖武天皇が藤原宇合を知造難波宮事に任命して難波京の造営に着手させて離宮を設置する（平城京との複都制）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Nara Period (726), Emperor Shomu appointed FUJIWARA no Umakai as Chief of Construction of Naniwa no Miya to start the construction of Naniwa-kyo while having a detached palace in place (under the dual capital system in conjunction with Heijokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nara period (726), Emperor Shomu appointed FUJIWARA no Umakai as Chief of Construction of Naniwa no Miya to start the construction of Naniwa-kyo (an ancient capital of Naniwa) while having a detached palace in place (under the dual capital system in conjunction with Heijo-kyo[the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara]).</e>
<cmt>表記を変え、用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Nara period (726), Emperor Shomu appointed FUJIWARA no Umakai as Chief of Construction of Naniwa no Miya to start the construction of Naniwa-kyo (an ancient capital of Naniwa) while having a detached palace in place (under the dual capital system in conjunction with Heijo-kyo[the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>中国の技法である礎石建、瓦葺屋根の宮殿が造られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The palace was built with Chinese technique including cornerstones and tiled roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The palace was built with Chinese technique including cornerstones and tiled roofs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The palace was built with Chinese technique including cornerstones and tiled roofs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天平15年（744年）に遷都され、このとき難波京も成立していたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 744, the capital was transferred and it is considered that Naniwakyo was also in existence at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 744, the capital was transferred and it is considered that Naniwa-kyo was also in existence at that time.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 744, the capital was transferred and it is considered that Naniwa-kyo was also in existence at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>翌天平16年1月1日 (旧暦)、難波宮から紫香楽宮へ遷都した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 24, 744, the year following, the capital city was transferred from Naniwa no Miya to Shigaraki no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 24, 744, the following year, the capital city was transferred from Naniwa no Miya Palace to Shigaraki no Miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 24, 744, the following year, the capital city was transferred from Naniwa no Miya Palace to Shigaraki no Miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>784年、桓武天皇により長岡京に遷都された際、大極殿などの建物が長岡京に移築された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 784, concurrent with the relocation of capital to Nagaokakyo by Empeor Kanmu, buildings such as Daigokuden were dismantled and reconstructed in the new capital city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 784, concurrent with the relocation of capital to Nagaoka-kyo (an ancient capital of Nagaoka) by Emperor Kanmu, buildings such as Daigokuden were dismantled and reconstructed in the new capital city.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 784, concurrent with the relocation of capital to Nagaoka-kyo (an ancient capital of Nagaoka) by Emperor Kanmu, buildings such as Daigokuden were dismantled and reconstructed in the new capital city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>史跡難波宮跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya Historic Site</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naniwa no Miya Historic Site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naniwa no Miya Historic Site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>現在、難波宮の跡地の一部は、難波宮史跡公園となり、大阪城の南に整備されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, part of the remains of Naniwanomiya Palace has turned into Naniwa no Miya Historical Park which is being maintained to the south of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, part of the remains of Naniwa no Miya Palace has turned into Naniwa no Miya Historical Park which is being maintained to the south of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, part of the remains of Naniwa no Miya Palace has turned into Naniwa no Miya Historical Park which is being maintained to the south of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>難波宮の遺跡は周辺にも及んでおり、NHK大阪放送局・大阪歴史博物館のある一角も難波宮の跡である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of Naniwa no Miya extend over the surrounding area which includes the district where NHK Osaka and Osaka Museum of History are located.</e>
<cmt>同じ単語の重複を避けるために原文から少し変えてあります。意味は同じです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of Naniwa no Miya extend over the surrounding area which includes the district where NHK Osaka and Osaka Museum of History are located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of Naniwa no Miya extend over the surrounding area which includes the district where NHK Osaka and Osaka Museum of History are located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>大阪歴史博物館の地下1階では、地下遺跡の様子を見学することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the first basement level of the Osaka Museum of History, one can view the subterranean archaeological site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the first basement level of the Osaka Museum of History, visitors can view the subterranean archaeological site.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the first basement level of the Osaka Museum of History, visitors can view the subterranean archaeological site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>同博物館前にある茅葺きの高床倉庫は、法円坂遺跡で見つかった5世紀（古墳時代）の巨大高床倉庫群のうち1棟を復元したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thatched-roof stilt warehouse in front of that museum is a replica of one of the massive stilt warehouses existed in the 5th century that were found in the Hoenzaka Site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thatched-roof stilt warehouse in front of that museum is a replica of one of the massive stilt warehouses existed in the fifth century (Kofun period [Tumulus period]) that were found in the Hoenzaka Site.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thatched-roof stilt warehouse in front of that museum is a replica of one of the massive stilt warehouses existed in the fifth century (Kofun period [Tumulus period]) that were found in the Hoenzaka Site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>難波宮以前から重要な交通拠点となっていた難波津の遺構である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the ancient structural remnants of Naniwa no tsu which became the key transportation hub prior to the times of Naniwa no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the ancient structural remnants of Naniwa no tsu (Naniwa Port) which became the key transportation hub prior to the times of Naniwa no Miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the ancient structural remnants of Naniwa no tsu (Naniwa Port) which became the key transportation hub prior to the times of Naniwa no Miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>2006年には、万葉仮名で書かれたものとしては、最古とされる7世紀中ごろの木簡が出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, mokkan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written), from approximately the mid 7th Century, believed to be the oldest of its kind which was written in Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyo-shu or Collection of Myriad Leaves) was excavated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2006, mokkan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written), from approximately the mid seventh century, believed to be the oldest of its kind which was written in Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyoshu [Collection of Myriad Leaves]) was excavated.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2006, mokkan (a narrow strip of wood on which an official message is written), from approximately the mid seventh century, believed to be the oldest of its kind which was written in Manyo-gana (a form of syllabary used in the Manyoshu [Collection of Myriad Leaves]) was excavated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>木簡は長さ18.5センチ、幅2.7センチで、片面に墨で「皮留久佐乃皮斯米之刀斯」と書かれており、「はるくさ（春草）のはじめのとし」と読むとみられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mokkan measured 18.5 centimeters long and 2.7 centimeters wide with writings in ink on one side being &apos;皮留久佐乃皮斯米之刀斯&apos; which is believed to read &apos;Spring grass of the new year.&apos;</e>
<cmt>皮留久佐乃皮斯米之刀斯 －定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mokkan measured 18.5 centimeters long and 2.7 centimeters wide with writings in ink on one side being &apos;皮留久佐乃皮斯米之刀斯&apos; which is believed to read &apos;Harukusa no Hajime no toshi&apos; (Spring grass of the new year).</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにし表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mokkan measured 18.5 centimeters long and 2.7 centimeters wide with writings in ink on one side being &apos;皮留久佐乃皮斯米之刀斯&apos; which is believed to read &apos;Harukusa no Hajime no toshi&apos; (Spring grass of the new year).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>一緒に出土した土器や地層の状況から前期・難波宮の完成前後のものと考えられ、万葉仮名は天武・持統朝（672年-697年）に成立したと考える説に再考を促す発見であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on earthware excavated at the same time and the conditions of geological formation, it is considered that mokkan was made around the time when the early Naniwa no Miya was completed and it was the finding which urged reconsideration of the existing belief that Manyo-gana came into existence between 672 and 697.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on earthenware excavated at the same time and the conditions of geological formation, it is considered that mokkan was made around the time when the early Naniwa no Miya was completed and it was the finding which urged reconsideration of the existing belief that Manyo-gana came into existence between 672 and 697.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on earthenware excavated at the same time and the conditions of geological formation, it is considered that mokkan was made around the time when the early Naniwa no Miya was completed and it was the finding which urged reconsideration of the existing belief that Manyo-gana came into existence between 672 and 697.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="26">
<j>難波宮跡公園の北側を東西に通る阪神高速道路阪神高速13号東大阪線は、ほぼ全線が高架構造にもかかわらず、難波宮跡付近の部分だけ平面となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Virtually the entire Hanshin Expressway (No.13) Higashi Osaka Route which runs eat to west on the north side of Naniwa no Miya Historical Park is an elevated expressway except for the part near the remains of Naniwa no Miya which is at street level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Virtually the entire Hanshin Expressway (No.13) Higashi Osaka Route which runs east to west on the north side of Naniwa no Miya Historical Park is an elevated expressway except for the part near the remains of Naniwa no Miya Palace which is at street level.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正し、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Virtually the entire Hanshin Expressway (No.13) Higashi Osaka Route which runs east to west on the north side of Naniwa no Miya Historical Park is an elevated expressway except for the part near the remains of Naniwa no Miya Palace which is at street level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これは、建設に先立つ事前協議の結果、難波宮跡の遺構の保存と難波宮跡公園から大坂城跡への景観を確保するために「平面案」が採用されたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of pre-construction consultation, this &apos;street-level design&apos; was adopted to preserve the remains of the Naniwa no Miya ruins and to secure the scenery between Naniwa no Miya Historical Park and the ruins of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of pre-construction consultation, this &apos;street-level design&apos; was adopted to preserve the remains of the Naniwa no Miya Palace ruins and to secure the scenery between Naniwa no Miya Historical Park and the ruins of the Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>半角クォーテーションにし、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of pre-construction consultation, this &apos;street-level design&apos; was adopted to preserve the remains of the Naniwa no Miya Palace ruins and to secure the scenery between Naniwa no Miya Historical Park and the ruins of the Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、この突如として現れる急な勾配区間のために、事故や渋滞の原因となることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sudden steep inclination in this section of highway, however, often cause accidents and traffic congestions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sudden steep inclination in this section of the highway, however, often causes accidents and traffic congestions.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sudden steep inclination in this section of the highway, however, often causes accidents and traffic congestions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、平面部分の道路の基礎は、難波宮跡中心部の遺構を破壊しないよう、地下に杭を打ち込まないような特殊な構造となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A special structural design was used for the foundation of the street-level section of the expressway whereby no stakes were driven into the ground so as not to damage the center section of the Naniwa no Miya ruins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A special structural design was used for the foundation of the street-level section of the expressway whereby no stakes were driven into the ground so as not to damage the center section of the Naniwa no Miya Palace ruins.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A special structural design was used for the foundation of the street-level section of the expressway whereby no stakes were driven into the ground so as not to damage the center section of the Naniwa no Miya Palace ruins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Nnh(id:474), Championship2006(id:38664), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), Takumadaserikouy(id:252567), IP118.15.7.23(id:271353), Kansai explorer(id:48975), Trooper(id:213051), アスカ(id:9205), Saft(id:100518), Peachkiller(id:99202), 沢田(id:40580), BAKU(id:55205), Xqbot(id:273540), Villeneuve1982(id:22620), Ganman(id:96316), Joh shoh(id:9812), Otraff(id:97860), 663highland(id:18755), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Shimoxx(id:9332), Junger(id:10282), Nopira(id:29335), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>