<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>アートコンプレックス1928</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ART COMPLEX 1928</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ART COMPLEX 1928</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ART COMPLEX 1928</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>アートコンプレックス1928(ART COMPLEX 1928)は京都市中京区の旧毎日新聞社京都支局（現1928ビル）3階にある小劇場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ART COMPLEX 1928 is a small theater located on the third floor of the former Kyoto branch office of The Mainich Newspapers (present 1928 building) in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ART COMPLEX 1928 is a small theater located on the third floor of the former Kyoto branch office of The Mainich Newspaper (present 1928 building) in Nakagyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ART COMPLEX 1928 is a small theater located on the third floor of the former Kyoto branch office of The Mainichi Newspaper (present 1928 building) in Nakagyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>高さ5メートルのアーチ型の天井で、講堂風の舞台。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is provided with a 5 m-high arch ceiling and an auditorium-like stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is provided with a 5 m-high arch ceiling and an auditorium-like stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is provided with a 5 m-high arch ceiling and an auditorium-like stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>アートコンプレックス1928の名前は、芝居、音楽、ダンス、など様々なジャンル、芸術性、エンターテイメント性をコンプレックス（複合）したものを発信していきたいということから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of ART COMPLEX 1928 is used intending to generate and spread complex products of various art genres, such as play, music and dance, various artistic characteristics and various entertainment characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of ART COMPLEX 1928 is used intending to generate and spread complex products of various art genres, such as plays, music and dance, various artistic and entertainment characteristics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of ART COMPLEX 1928 is used intending to generate and spread complex products of various art genres, such as plays, music and dance, various artistic and entertainment characteristics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1999年にオープンし、エンジェルシステム、ファンドを導入したロングラン公演などの主催公演をおこなうなど意欲的に活動を続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It opened in 1999, and ambitious activities, for example, of hosting a long-run performance where an angel system/fund was introduced, have been conducted there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It opened in 1999, and ambitious activities, for example; the hosting of a long-run performance where an angel system/fund was introduced, has been conducted there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It opened in 1999, and ambitious activities, for example; the hosting of a long-run performance where an angel system or fund was introduced, has been conducted there.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>最大客席数は200席余。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The maximum number of seats is slightly more than 200.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The maximum number of seats is slightly more than 200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maximum number of seats is slightly more than 200.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>阪急電車河原町駅9番出口より北へ徒歩8分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hankyu Railway: eight minutes on foot from exit 9 of Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hankyu Railway: eight minutes on foot from exit 9 of Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hankyu Railway: Eight minutes on foot to the north from exit 9 of Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>京阪電車三条駅6番出口より西へ徒歩5分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway: five minutes on foot from exit 6 of Sanjo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keihan Electric Railway: five minutes on foot from exit 6 of Sanjo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keihan Electric Railway: Five minutes on foot to the west from exit 6 of Sanjo Station</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>地下鉄東西線烏丸線　御池駅5番出口より東へ徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Karasuma Line of Kyoto City subway: ten minutes on foot from exit 5 of Oike Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Karasuma Line of Kyoto City subway: ten minutes on foot from exit 5 of Oike Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tozai Line and the Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subway: Ten minutes on foot to the east from exit 5 of Oike Station</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nekosuki600(id:21263), Fuji-77(id:22233), Memeja(id:110500), Udk(id:42955), Harachang(id:176602), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>