<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamajiro (mountain castles)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamajiro (mountain castles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamajiro (mountain castles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山城（やまじろ）は、険阻な山を利用して築かれた城のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamajiro are castles that are built on steep mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamajiro are castles that are built on steep mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamajiro refers to castles built on steep mountains.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本においては、江戸時代の軍学者によって分類された地形による城の分類法の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, this is one of the castle classification systems that were determined by Edo period military strategists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, this is one of the castle classification systems that were determined by Edo period military strategists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Yamajiro was one of the castle classification methods determined by Edo period military strategists.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>中世ヨーロッパでの山城は「へーエンブルク（Hohenburg）」といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In medieval Europe, mountain castles were referred to as Hohenburg.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In medieval Europe, mountain castles were referred to as Hohenburg.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In medieval Europe, castles built on mountains were called as Hohenburg.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>高地は軍事的防御に有利であり、山に城郭を築く行為は場所と時代を問わず普遍的に行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of castles on mountains was a universal practice as high ground is beneficial from a military defensive standpoint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of castles on mountains was a universal practice as high ground is beneficial from a military defensive standpoint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of castles on mountains was a universal practice as high ground is beneficial from a military defensive standpoint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本以外に山城が多く築かれた時代には、日本の古代山城のモデルとなったと思われる三国時代 (朝鮮半島)の朝鮮、および中世の西ヨーロッパなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Japan, many mountain castles were constructed in both western Europe and Three Kingdoms period of Korea, from which the castles of ancient Japan are thought to have been modeled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Japan, many mountain castles were constructed in both western Europe and the Three Kingdoms period of Korea, from which the castles of ancient Japan are thought to have been modeled.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for Japan, many castles were built on mountains in Three Kingdoms period (of Korean history), from which the castles of ancient Japan are thought to have been modeled, and in medieval western Europe.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>近代の旅順要塞やマジノ要塞も山に築かれた要塞群である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Port Arthur stronghold and the Maginot Line also consisted of fortifications built on mountains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Port Arthur stronghold and the Maginot Line also consisted of fortifications built on mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Port Arthur stronghold and the Maginot Line also consisted of fortifications built on mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>要塞は、防御に有利な地形に築くことが望ましく、険しい山はその条件を満たすが、反面住むには不便で、守るべき対象である人の居住地から離れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It desirable for fortifications to be constructed on terrain that provides a defensive advantage and steep mountains fulfill this condition but there is also the disadvantage that such locations are inconvenient for human habitation, and these are therefore located distant from the settlements that they serve to defend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was desirable for fortifications to be constructed on terrain that provides a defensive advantage and steep mountains fulfill this condition but there is also the disadvantage that such locations are inconvenient for human habitation, and these were therefore located distant from the settlements that they served to defend.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although steep mountains are desirable to construct fortifications that are expected to be built on places effective for defence, they are difficult to live; thus, fortifications were established distant from the settlements that they served to defend.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、防御専用の要塞として造られることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore many were constructed as purely defensive installations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore many were constructed as purely defensive installations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many were constructed to serve as purely defensive installations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平時は麓に住民と共に城主が住み、敵が来襲すると山上の城に立て籠もる、といった使い方がなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During peace time, the lord of the castle would live at the foot of the mountain with the other residents but when an enemy invaded, everyone would barricade themselves within the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During peace time, the lord of the castle would live at the foot of the mountain with the other residents but when an enemy invaded, everyone would barricade themselves within the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In peacetime, the lord of the castle would often live with other people at the foot of the mountain while they moved to the castle on the mountain to barricade themselves in it when their enemies attacked them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本の山城は、飛鳥時代から奈良時代の近畿から九州北部にかけて築かれた朝鮮式山城、中世・戦国時代 (日本)までに築かれた中世山城、戦国末期の戦国山城、安土桃山時代後期から江戸時代までに築かれた近世山城がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese mountain castles consist of those Korean style mountain castles built from the Kinki region to the north of Kyushu since the Asuka period to the Nara period, medieval castles built during the middle ages and Warring States period (Japan), late Warring States period mountain castles, and early modern period mountain castles built from the latter part of the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese mountain castles consisted of these Korean style mountain castles built from the Kinki region to the north of Kyushu from the Asuka period to the Nara period, medieval castles built during the Middle ages and Warring States period (Japan), late Warring States period mountain castles, and early modern period mountain castles built from the latter part of the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese mountain castles include those of Korean style, which built from the Kinki region to the north of Kyushu from the Asuka period to the Nara period, those built in the late Sengoku period (period of warring states) and those built in the early modern period, from the latter part of the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このうち、朝鮮式山城については古代山城で述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of these, the Korean style mountain castles are considered to be the most ancient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of these, the Korean style mountain castles are considered to be the most ancient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the mentioned above, the mountain casltes of Korean style are discussed in the section on ancient mountain casltes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>中世の山城は、山上に城郭、麓に居館を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medieval mountain castles were constructed with a main castle building at the top of the mountain and a residence at the foot of the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Medieval mountain castles were constructed with a main castle building at the top of the mountain and a residence at the foot of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a medieval mountain castle was constructed, the castle itself was built on the top of a mountain and their residence at the foot of it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>山上の城は主に防御施設で、日常生活は麓の館で行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle on the mountain top served mainly as a defensive facility and everyday life was lived in the residence at mountain&apos;s base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle on the mountain top served mainly as a defensive facility and everyday life was lived in the residence at the mountain&apos;s base.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle on the mountain top served mainly as a defensive facility and the people there usually lived in the residence at the mountain&apos;s base.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>山上の城には掘立柱建築や簡易な櫓と塀を建てたのみで、長期間居住するための建物は建てられていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle at the peak was not meant for long-term habitation; consisting of only hottate bashira (earthfast posts), simple turrets and fences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle at the peak was not meant for long-term habitation; consisting of only hottate bashira (earthfast posts), simple turrets and fences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle at the peak was not meant for long-term habitation; consisting of structures with hottate bashira (earthfast posts), simple turrets and fences.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>小城の場合は、山の頂上に簡単な建物を造り、食料、武具を保管するだけで、後は自然の地形を利用して、適宜、山の各所に柵、堀、土塀を設けるといった程度であるが、中規模の城となると峰々に本丸、二の丸といった曲輪を造り、居住用の施設も備え、長期の籠城に耐えられるようにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Small castles would have a simple building that would serve only to store food and weapons, with the terrain being used for defense by constructing fences, moats and mud walls, whereas medium-size castles would have the main compound on the peak and the secondary compound district with residential facilities that made it possible to hold out against a long-lasting siege.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Small castles would have a simple building that would serve only to store food and weapons, with the terrain being used for defense by constructing fences, moats and mud walls, whereas medium-size castles would have the main compound on the peak and the secondary compound district with residential facilities that made it possible to hold out against a long-lasting siege.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding small castles, a simple building was made to store food and weapons and fences, moats and mud walls for defence were made by using natural terrain, whereas medium-size castles had Kuruwa (walls of a castle), a main compound on one peak and a secondary compound on another peak, and residential facilities that made it possible to hold out against a long-lasting siege.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大城となると周辺の山々に支城を設け、山系全体を要塞としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Large castles would have subsidiary castles on surrounding mountains, with the entire mountain range serving as a fortification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Large castles would have subsidiary castles on surrounding mountains, with the entire mountain range serving as a fortification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Large castles had subsidiary castles on surrounding mountains, making the entire mountain range serve as a fortification.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>堀はあまり深く掘らずに、槍が届く程度の深さに掘るのが一般的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moats were not deep and were generally dug to the depth of a spear&apos;s length.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moats were not deep and were generally dug to the depth of a spear&apos;s length.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usually moats were made deep just enough for a spear to reach the bottom of it.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>堀に落ちた攻城側の兵を、守城側の兵が槍で突いて攻撃が可能であるほうが、防衛上の利点が大きかったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because it was of greater defensive benefit that castle defenders were able to stab with spears those attacking soldiers that fell into the moat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because it was of greater defensive benefit that castle defenders were able to stab with spears those attacking soldiers that fell into the moat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was due to a greater defensive benefit, which meant that castle defenders were able to stab with spears attacking soldiers who fell into the moat.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>戦国期には、山上の城にも礎石建ての恒久的な建物を建てて、長期の滞在ができるように備えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Warring States period, permanent structures with foundations were built and able to accommodate long-term inhabitants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Warring States period, permanent structures with foundations were built and able to accommodate long-term inhabitants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Warring States period, permanent structures with foundations were built and able to accommodate long-term inhabitants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>典型例は、甲斐国武田氏の躑躅ヶ崎館（山梨県）や越前国朝倉氏の一乗谷朝倉氏遺跡（福井県）などがあり、一乗谷城は谷間に城下町と居館としての館を築き、有事に際しては山頂に築かれた城郭を拠点として防衛にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical examples of these include Tsutsuji-ga-saki Castle (Yamanashi Prefecture) of the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Ichijodani Asakura Family Historic Ruins (Fukui Prefecture) in Echizen Province, with Ichijodani Castle having a residence and castle town within the valley from which residents would seek refuge and defend themselves at the castle on the peak of the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical examples of these include Tsutsuji-ga-saki Castle (Yamanashi Prefecture) of the Takeda clan in Kai Province and the Ichijodani Asakura Family Historic Ruins (Fukui Prefecture) in Echizen Province, with Ichijodani Castle having a residence and castle town within the valley from which residents would seek refuge and defend themselves at the castle on the peak of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical examples of these include Tsutsuji-ga-saki Castle (Yamanashi Prefecture) of the Takeda clan in the Kai Province and Ichijodani Asakura Clan Ruins (Fukui Prefecture) in the Echizen Province; Ichijodani Castle had a residence and their castle town within the valley and defend themselves making the castle on the peak of the mountain as their base when enemies attacked them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>平城・平山城にくらべ、山城の絶対的な規模は小さい傾向があるが、一方で都市化を免れ、戦国山城の月山富田城や近世山城の竹田城（兵庫県）や高取城、岡城（大分県）などの広大な城域全体の遺構が保存されるケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared with hirajiro (flatland castles) and hirayamajiro (low mountain castles), yamajiro (mountain castles) tend to be of a smaller size, but these did not develop into cities and there are examples of the preserved ruins of large castles including the Warring States period yamajiro Gassantoda Castle, and the early modern period yamajiro Takeda Castle (Hyogo Prefecture), Takatori Castle and Oka Castle (Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared with hirajiro (flatland castles) and hirayamajiro (low mountain castles), yamajiro (mountain castles) tend to be of a smaller size, but these did not develop into cities and there are examples of the preserved ruins of large castles including the Warring States period yamajiro Gassantoda Castle, and the early modern period yamajiro Takeda Castle (Hyogo Prefecture), Takatori Castle and Oka Castle (Oita Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared with hirajiro (flatland castles) and hirayamajiro (low mountain castles), yamajiro (mountain castles) tended to be smaller and some of them did not develop into cities and have been preserved as whole ruins of large castles, including the Gassantoda Castle, a mountain castle in the Sengoku (civil war) period, and Takeda Castle (Hyogo Prefecture), Takatori Castle and Oka Castle (Oita Prefecture) in the early modern period.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その場合は、研究資料や観光資源として利用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These serve as both historical research sources and tourist attractions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These serve as both historical research sources and tourist attractions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These serve as both historical research sources and tourist attractions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>日本において初めて山に軍事的防御施設が築かれるのは弥生時代の高地性集落である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first defensive military facilities to be built on mountains in Japan were Yayoi period highland settlements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first defensive military facilities to be built on mountains in Japan were Yayoi period highland settlements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first defensive military facilities to be built on mountains in Japan were Yayoi period highland settlements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後、飛鳥時代から奈良時代にかけて、唐や新羅の侵攻に備えて西日本各地に古代山城（朝鮮式山城）が築かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Asuka period to the Nara period, invasions from Tang Dynasty China and the Korean Silla Kingdom led to the construction of the ancient mountain castles (Korean style mountain castles) throughout Western Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Asuka period to the Nara period, invasions from Tang Dynasty China and the Korean Silla Kingdom led to the construction of the ancient mountain castles (Korean style mountain castles) throughout Western Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Asuka to the Nara periods, invasions from the Tang Dynasty China and the Korean Silla Kingdom led to the construction of ancient mountain castles (Korean style mountain castles) throughout Western Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>中世には、鎌倉時代後期から南北朝時代 (日本)までに後醍醐天皇の率いる反幕府勢力が幕府に抵抗するため、山に城を築いたことで山城の築城が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle ages, castles began to be built on mountains by Emperor Go-Daigo in order to resist the power of the Shogunate from latter part of the Kamakura period to the Northern and Southern Courts period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Middle ages, castles began to be built on mountains by Emperor Go-Daigo in order to resist the power of the Shogunate from the latter part of the Kamakura period to the Northern and Southern Courts period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Middle ages, anti-Bakufu forces led by Emperor Godaigo started to build castles on mountains by in order to resist the power of the Bakufu from the latter Kamakura period to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。Go-DaigoをGodaigoに訂正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その初例と考えられているのは楠正成の千早城や赤坂城、または山岳寺院「金胎寺」を利用した金胎寺城がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early examples of these are considered to be Masashige KUSUNOKI&apos;s Chihaya Castle and Akasaka Castle, as well as the mountain temple &quot;Kontai-ji&quot; which was used as Kontaiji Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early examples of these are considered to be Masashige KUSUNOKI&apos;s Chihaya Castle and Akasaka Castle, as well as the mountain temple &quot;Kontai-ji&quot; which was used as Kontaiji Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that early examples of them were Masashige KUSUNOKI&apos;s Chihaya Castle and Akasaka Castle as well as Kontaiji Castle, which used the mountain temple &quot;Kontai-ji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その後、南朝はそれらに倣って各地に山城を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Court later imitated these and constructed mountain castles in various locations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Court later imitated these and constructed mountain castles in various locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court later imitated these and constructed mountain castles in various locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>武士が山麓の平地に居館を、背後の山に山城を築き、戦闘になると山城に立て篭もるといった様式が一般化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai would construct a residence on the flatlands at the base of a mountain and a castle on the mountain to the rear, and it became the norm that factions would hold up in castles at times of battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai would construct a residence on the flatlands at the base of a mountain and a castle on the mountain to the rear, and it became the norm that factions would hold up in castles in times of battle.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became common that warriors constructed their residence on the flatlands at the foot of a mountain and their castle on the mountain behind the residence, and barricade themselves in the castle when the battle started.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>戦国時代には、戦いが常態化したことから山上の城にも恒久的な施設を建てて長期の戦いに堪えられるように備えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As war became part of everyday life during the Warring States period, permanent facilities that allowed inhabitants to withstand long-term conflict were built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As war became part of everyday life during the Warring States period, permanent facilities that allowed inhabitants to withstand long-term conflict were built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As war became continuous during the the Sengoku period, permanent facilities that allowed inhabitants to withstand long-term battls were built.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>戦国後期には山上の主曲輪に領主の居館を構えて中腹に家臣たちと人質としてその一族を住まわせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter part of the Warring States period, the residence of the lord was constructed in the main compound at the top of the mountain, while he allowed his retainers and their families to live on the mountainside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter part of the Warring States period, the residence of the lord was constructed in the main compound at the top of the mountain, while he allowed his retainers and their families to live on the mountainside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter Sengoku period, a lord&apos;s residence was constructed within the main walls of their castle at the top of the mountain, while the lord made his vassals and their clans live on the mountainsideas as his hostages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>安土桃山時代後期から江戸初期には石垣を多用した城も現れ、山城にも導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the latter part of the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period, castles with stone walls began to appear and stone was also used for mountain castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the latter part of the Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period, castles with stone walls began to appear and stone was also used for mountain castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the latter Azuchi-Momoyama period to the early Edo period, they started to establish castles with stone walls and that type of castle was also used for mountain castles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>平山城と平城が中心になるのは、江戸時代の一国一城令以降のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the ikkoku-ichijo (lit. one castle per province) order that led hirayamajiro (low mountain castles) and hirajiro (flatland castles) to become the most common type of castle in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the ikkoku-ichijo (lit. one castle per province) order that led hirayamajiro (low mountain castles) and hirajiro (flatland castles) to become the most common type of castle in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was after the ikkoku-ichijo (lit. one castle per province) order that hirayamajiro (low mountain castles) and hirajiro (flatland castles) became the most common type of castles in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>山から平地への移行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shift from Mountains to Flatland</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shift from Mountains to Flatland</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shift from Mountains to Flatland</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>戦国後期になると城下町を伴う平山城、平城が主流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter part of the Warring States period, the castle towns that accompany flatland castles and low mountain castles became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter part of the Warring States period, the castle towns that accompany flatland castles and low mountain castles became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter Sengoku period, Hirayamajiro (castles built on a hill in a plain) and Hirajiro (castles built on flatland) with their castle towns became the mainstream.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。前出に合わせてハイフンとCastleを削除し、Hirayamajiroとしました。スペース補足しました。castlesとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その理由はいくつもあり、一通りではないが、以下に列挙する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several reasons for this, of which some examples are given below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several reasons for this, of which some examples are given below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several reasons for this and they will be mentioned below.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>戦の常態化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Normalization of Conflict</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Normalization of Conflict</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Normalization of Conflict</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>戦時にのみ山城に立てこもるという形態が不便になり、常時城に待機して戦に備える必要が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was inconvenient to hold up within a mountain castle only during war time, and the necessity arose to ordinarily remain in castles in preparation for conflict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was inconvenient to hold up within a mountain castle only during war time, and the necessity arose to ordinarily remain in castles in preparation for conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It became inconvenient to barricade themselves in a mountain castle only when enemies attacked them; it was necessary to stay there in preparation for battles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。余分なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そのため上述の通り山城に居住施設を設けるようになったが、今度は常時麓と往復する事になり、不便を生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, residential facilities came to be constructed at mountain castles but an inconvenience then arose from the need to often return to the foot of the mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, residential facilities came to be constructed at mountain castles but an inconvenience then arose from the need to often return to the foot of the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, residential facilities were constructed at mountain castles but it was inconvenient to travel back and forth between the foot of the mountain and the mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>戦国大名による支配の確立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of Control by Sengoku Period Daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of Control by Sengoku Period Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Established Control of the Sengoku Period Daimyo</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>大名の領地の支配を固めるためには、山上に築くのは交通の便が悪く問題があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Constructing castles on the tops of mountains meant that transport became inconvenient for daimyo (feudal lords) who wished to strengthen control over their territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Constructing castles on the tops of mountains meant that transport became inconvenient for daimyo (feudal lords) who wished to strengthen control over their territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was inconvenien in terms of transportation to construct a castle on the top of a mountain in order to strengthen the Daimyo&apos;s control over their territory.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、大名の支配の象徴として威容を見せつける必要が生じたため、険阻な山岳地でなく、目立つ場所に城が建てられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it became necessary to display castles as a symbol of a daimyo&apos;s power so they were constructed not on steep mountains but where they could be seen by all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it became necessary to display castles as a symbol of a daimyo&apos;s power so they were constructed not on steep mountains but where they could be seen by all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it became necessary to display castles as a symbol of a daimyo&apos;s power so they were constructed not on steep mountains but where they could be seen by all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="42">
<j>火縄銃の導入</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction of Firearms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction of Firearms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction of Firearms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>木柵と浅い堀で防御した山城は、火縄銃による攻撃に脆弱であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castles defended by wooden fences and shallow moats are vulnerable to attack by firearms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castles defended by wooden fences and shallow moats were vulnerable to attack by firearms.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castles defended by wooden fences and shallow moats were vulnerable to attack by firearms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため何重もの深い掘と塀によって防御するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, castles came to be defended by numerous deep moats and walls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, castles came to be defended by numerous deep moats and walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, castles came to be defended by numerous deep moats and walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また守城側も火縄銃で攻城側の兵を攻撃できるようになったため、堀の深さをあえて槍の届く程度にとどめる必要がなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castles were also designed to allow defenders to use firearms to fire on attackers, so there was no longer the need for the depth of moats to be restricted to the length of a spear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castles were also designed to allow defenders to use firearms to fire on attackers, so there was no longer the need for the depth of moats to be restricted to the length of a spear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castles were also designed to allow defenders to use firearms to fire on attackers, so there was no longer the need for the depth of moats to be restricted to the length of a spear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>そのため深い堀を掘るには、平山城や平城のほうが効率的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, castles were built on flatland or low mountains in order to allow deep moats to be dug.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, castles were built on flatland or low mountains in order to allow deep moats to be dug.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was more effective in Hirayamajiro Castle or Hirajiro Castle to make deep moats.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。前出に合わせてHirayamajiro、Hirajiroとしました。ハイフン削除。スペース補足。Castleを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>大規模化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Increasing Size of Castles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increasing Size of Castles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increased Size of Castles</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>戦国大名が支配権を確立するにつれ、各地に割拠していた国人領主などを完全に家臣として組み込むにあたり、城下町に集住させるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Warring States period daimyo (feudal lords) established sovereignty, they made the warlords of various provinces live within castle towns in order to ensure that they remained subservient retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Warring States period daimyo (feudal lords) established sovereignty, they made the warlords of various provinces live within castle towns in order to ensure that they remained subservient retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Sengoku Daimyo (feudal lords) established their sovereignty, they made their Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai lords) in various provinces live within the castle towns in order to ensure that the latter was completely obedient to the former.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。前出の表記に合わせて、ハイフン削除。Daimyoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>そのため城も大規模化する必要があり、山城では規模に限界があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was therefore necessary for castles to increase in size, but mountain castles had size limitations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was therefore necessary for castles to increase in size, but mountain castles had size limitations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was therefore necessary for castles to increase in size, but mountain castles had size limitations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>山城から平山城・平城に移行するにあたっては、麓に新たに主郭を築いて旧山城を詰の城（萩城など）とする例や、城地を低い丘や平地に移転する例（福山城 (備後国)など）があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the shift took place from mountain castles to flatland castles and low mountain castles, new main castles were constructed at the feet of mountains and there are cases in which the former mountain castle served as a tsume-no-shiro (a castle that guards the back of the main castle and serves as a retreat point when the main castle can no longer be defended) (such as Hagi Castle) or the castle site was relocated to a low hill or flatland (such as Fukuyama Castle (Higo Province)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the shift took place from mountain castles to flatland castles and low mountain castles, new main castles were constructed at the feet of mountains and there are cases in which the former mountain castle served as a tsume-no-shiro (a castle that guards the back of the main castle and serves as a retreat point when the main castle can no longer be defended) (such as Hagi Castle) or the castle site was relocated to a low hill or flatland (such as Fukuyama Castle (Higo Province)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a mountain castle was changed into a flatland castle or a low mountain castle, a new main castle was constructed at the foot of a mountains and a former mountain castle was used as a Tsume-no-shiro (a castle that guards the back of the main castle) (such as Hagi Castle) or a castle site was moved to a low hill or flatland (such as Fukuyama Castle (Bingo Province)).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>小田原城のように、元々は山城であったものが、城と麓の城下町が拡張を繰り返した結果両者が一体化し、城下町全体を惣構えで囲んだ大規模な平山城に発展した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As with Odawara Castle, there are examples of sites that were originally mountain castles but, as a result of the repeated expansion of the castle and castle town at the foot of the mountain, both became merged and the entire castle town became a large flatland castle surrounded by the sogamae (outer citadel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As with Odawara Castle, there are examples of sites that were originally mountain castles but, as a result of the repeated expansion of the castle and castle town at the foot of the mountain, both became merged and the entire castle town became a large flatland castle surrounded by the sogamae (outer citadel).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like Odawara Castle, as a result of the repeated expansion of a castle that was originally a mountain castle and castle town at the foot of the mountain, both merged and developed into a large flatland castle surrounding its entire castle town by the sogamae (outer citadel).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="52">
<j>ただし、こうした大規模化した平山城、平城によって、全ての山城を置き換えることは不可能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such flatland castles and low mountain castles that had expanded to such large sizes made it impossible to replace all mountain castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such flatland castles and low mountain castles that had expanded to such large sizes made it impossible to replace all mountain castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was not possible to replace all mountain castles with such expanded flatland castles and low mountain castles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>あくまで大名自身が居住する城にとどまり、各地の山城は健在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These remained the residential castles of the daimyo themselves, and the mountain castles throughout the country remained strong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These remained the residential castles of the daimyo themselves, and the mountain castles throughout the country remained strong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These remained the residential castles of the daimyo themselves, and the mountain castles throughout the country remained strong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また小大名の場合も、従来通りの山城形式のままで推移し、平山城、平城に移行できなかった場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, minor daimyo continued to construct traditional mountain castles, and there were circumstances in which it was not possible to move to a flatland castle or low mountain castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, minor daimyo continued to construct traditional mountain castles, and there were circumstances in which it was not possible to move to a flatland castle or low mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, some minor daimyo had to stay in their traditional mountain castles, unable to move to a flatland castle or low mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>こうした山城の中には、火縄銃などに対応するためにむしろ従来より発展した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these mountain castles are those that developed differently from previous mountain castles in order to increase defensive capability against firearms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these mountain castles are those that developed differently from previous mountain castles in order to increase defensive capability against firearms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these mountain castles are those that developed differently from previous mountain castles in order to increase defensive capability against firearms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>たとえば西国においては、放射状竪堀の導入が盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the introduction of radial moats became popular in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the introduction of radial moats became popular in the Kansai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, radial moats were often used in the western region.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また従来の木柵ではなく、平山城や平城の建築様式を取り入れ、狭間を持つ土塀で囲まれた、さながらトーチカのような鉄壁の要塞と化した山城もある（鷹取城など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there are examples where it was not traditional wooden fences that were used but the architectural styles of flatland castles and low mountain castles were incorporated and the castle surrounded by mud walls with portholes, as well as mountain castles with iron walls like those of bunkers (such as Takatori Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there are examples where it was not traditional wooden fences that were used but the architectural styles of flatland castles and low mountain castles were incorporated and the castle surrounded by mud walls with portholes, as well as mountain castles with iron walls like those of bunkers (such as Takatori Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some mountain castles stopped using their traditional wooden fences and started to use the architectural styles of flatland castles and low mountain castles, surrounded by mud walls with portholes, and became an impregnable fortification as if it were a pillbox (such as Takatori Castle).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="58">
<j>城のほとんどが平山城・平城に移行するのは、一国一城令によって各地の山城を破却する江戸時代以降の事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shift to flatland castles and low mountain castles as the major form of castle occurred after the Edo period as a result of the ikkoku-ichijo (lit. one castle per province) order which led to the demolition of mountain castles throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shift to flatland castles and low mountain castles as the major form of castle occurred after the Edo period as a result of the ikkoku-ichijo (lit. one castle per province) order which led to the demolition of mountain castles throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was after the Edo period when most castles became flatland castles or low mountain castles due to the Ikkoku Ichijo Rei (Law of One Castle per Province) that ordered to destroy mountain castles throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>もっとも江戸時代の大名の居城においても、山麓の居館と戦闘時に立て篭もる背後の山城の組み合わせという中世的様式を受け継いだ城も多く、岩国城、萩城、鹿児島城がこれにあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even among the residential castles of Edo period daimyo, there are many castles such as Iwakuni Castle, Hagi Castle and Kagoshima Castle which inherited the medieval style combination of both the residence at the foot of the mountain and the castle on the mountain to the rear in which safety would be sought during conflict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even among the residential castles of Edo period daimyo, there are many castles such as Iwakuni Castle, Hagi Castle and Kagoshima Castle which inherited the medieval style combination of both the residence at the foot of the mountain and the castle on the mountain to the rear in which safety would be sought during conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, many of the Daimyo&apos;s residential castles of the Edo period inherited the medieval style, which combined the residence at the foot of the mountain and the mountain castle behind the residence to barricade themselves in case they had a battle, including Iwakuni Castle, Hagi Castle and Kagoshima Castle.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。余分なinを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>仙台城のように江戸時代に入ってから山城を建造し、後に拡張により平山城に移行した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also examples such as Sendai Castle which were constructed as mountain castles during the Edo period but later went on to expand and undergo the transition to a low mountain castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also examples such as Sendai Castle which were constructed as mountain castles during the Edo period but later went on to expand and undergo the transition to a low mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also examples such as Sendai Castle which were constructed as mountain castles during the Edo period but later went on to expand and undergo the transition to a low mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Kazov(id:9237), Nnh(id:474), カテゴリ整理専用(id:146185), Luh(id:16361), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), Ｎｍ(id:62298), Nallimbot(id:230812), PATMAN(id:145791), 黄金もち(id:102311), Zorac(id:28001), Kotoito(id:21045), Miita(id:30561), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Hootaataa(id:199570), ムカイ(id:72972), Zzzz(id:16596), UME(id:8142), Rusk(id:9895), Yukichin(id:725), Kinori(id:443), GURAX(id:107578), Kone(id:377), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 史跡めぐり(id:95651), Miyakemasaru(id:236167), 弥(id:61590), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>