<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>茅葺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thatch</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thatch</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thatch</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>茅葺（かやぶき）とは、カヤ (草)（ススキやチガヤなど）を材料にして葺く家屋の屋根の構造の一つで、茅葺き屋根、茅葺屋根ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thatch is a roof structure of houses thached with kaya (grass) (Japanese pampas grass or cogon) as the material, and is also called a thatched roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thatch is a roof structure of houses thached with kaya (grass) (Japanese pampas grass or cogon) as the material, and is also called a thatched roof.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayabuki is a type of roof structure using kaya (grass) (Japanese pampas grass or cogon) as the material for thatching and is also called kaya-thatched roof.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>用いる材料により藁葺（わらぶき）・草葺（くさぶき）と呼び区別する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes called straw-thatching or grass-thaching depending on the material used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes called straw-thatching or grass-thatching depending on the material used.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes called straw-thatching or grass-thatching depending on the material used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>イギリスやドイツなど、世界で広く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thatch is seen worldwide, including England and Germany.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thatch is seen worldwide, including England and Germany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thatch is seen worldwide, including England and Germany.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>茅はススキの別名であるが、チガヤなどの総称でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaya is another name of Japanese pampas grass, but is sometimes used also for indicating a similar type of grasses totally, including cogon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaya is another name of Japanese pampas grass, but it is sometimes used also for indicating other similar types of grass, including cogon.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaya is an alternative name for susuki or Japanese pampas grass, but it is sometimes as a general term for chigaya (Imperata cylindrica).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>茅葺は世界各地でもっとも原初的な屋根とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that thatch is the most primitive roof in various areas of the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that thatch is the most primitive roof in various areas of the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that thatch is the most primitive roof in various areas of the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また日本でも縄文時代には茅を用いた屋根だけの住居が作られていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also considered that dwellings using only a thatched roof were built in the Jomon period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also thought that dwellings using only a thatched roof were built in the Jomon period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also thought that dwellings using only a thatched roof were built in the Jomon period of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>奈良時代以降の場合はこけら葺や樹皮葺であった可能性が検討されるが、弥生時代以前の遺跡（登呂遺跡など）で復元される竪穴式住居などの屋根は通常茅葺とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The posssibility that buildings might be single-roofed or bark-roofed in the Nara period or later is investigated, but it is said that the roofs of the pit dwellings restored at ruins in Yayoi or earlier periods (for example, Toro Ruins) are usually thatched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The posssibility that buildings might be single-roofed or bark-roofed in the Nara period or later has been investigated; but, it is said that the roofs of the pit dwellings restored at ruins in Yayoi or earlier periods (for example, Toro Ruins) were usually thatched.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The possibility that buildings in the Nara period onwards might have been kokera (bark tiles)-roofed or bark-roofed has been investigated; but restorations of the roofs of pit dwellings from Yayoi or earlier periods ruins (for example, Toro Ruins) are usually thatched.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>材料になる植物は水分が多い状態で屋根に使うとすぐに腐ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When used for roofs in a watery state, plant materials are rotten soon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When used for roofs in wet conditions, the plant material rots quickly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plant material for roofs quickly rots if they are used in a moist condition.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>したがって、通常冬になって枯れてから集める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, these materials are collected usually in the winter when they become dry.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, these materials are usually collected in the winter once they are dry.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, such material is usually collected in the winter after they die.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>春になるまで充分乾燥させてから使用するが、耐久性を高めるために使用前に燻したりすることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are dried adequately until spring and then are used, but are sometimes smoked before being used, to increase the durability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are dried adequately until spring and then used; but they are sometimes smoked before being used, to increase their durability.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are used after sufficient drying until spring but are sometimes smoked before being use to increase their durability.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>建物の内部で竈や囲炉裏を使用すると煙で燻されることにより耐久性が高められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a kamado(kitchen range, cooking stove) and/or a fireplace (a sunken hearth) is used within a building, the durability of such a roof is increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a kamado (kitchen range, cooking stove) and/or a fireplace (a sunken hearth) is used within a building, it increases the durability of such a roof.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a kamado (kitchen range, cooking stove) and/or a fireplace (a sunken hearth) is used within a building, it increases the durability of such a roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしながら、神社建築の場合は建物内部で火を使うことがまずないため、民家に比べると寿命が短くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because fire is rarely used inside shrine buildings, their fives are shorter than those of private houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because fire is rarely used inside shrine buildings, the fires are shorter-lived than those of private houses.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, shrine buildings are shorter-lived than private houses because fire is rarely used inside the building.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>基本的に雨漏りを防止するために急勾配の屋根にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, the steep roof is used to prevent rain from being seeped in.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The steep roof is used to prevent rain from seeping in.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Steep roofs are used to prevent rain from seeping in.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>使用する植物の茎などが太いと隙間が大きくなり雨漏りがしやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the plant materials with thick stalks are used for a roof, the spaces between the stalks become wider, making it easier for rain to seep in, and it becomes necessary to make the roof steeper to prevent rain from seeping in.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when plant materials with thick stalks are used for a roof, the spaces between the stalks increases, making it easier for rain to seep in. Thus, the roof must be made more steep to prevent rain from seeping in.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if plant materials with thick stalks are used, the gaps between the stalks are larger and tend to let the rain seep in.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このことから、より急勾配が要求される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the roof must be made steeper to prevent rain from seeping in.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>通気性・断熱性に優れる、雨音が小さいなどの長所を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roof is provided with a good air permeability and a good heat insulation ability and has a feature that the sound of rain dropping on it is smaller.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roof has good air permeability and good heat retention abilities. It also reduces the sound of rain falling on it.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roof has advantages such as good air permeability/heat retention abilities and also reduces the sound of falling rain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、寿命が短い・近隣で火災が生じた場合に容易に類焼してしまうといった短所を併せ持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it also has the disadvangate that the life is shorter and it is easily burnt from a fire started in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, its downside is its short life and flammability.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, its disadvantage is its short life and the fact that it may easily catch fire from neighboring fires.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>日本では集落が発展し、建物が密集する都市が形成されるにつれて火災に弱い短所が嫌われ、都市部や街道沿いの町屋などでは瓦の普及などにより早期に姿を消した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, as communities grew larger and the urban areas where buildings were built densely were formed, its fire-prone disadvantage was disliked, and such roofs disappered rapidly in urban areas, along roads and in Machiya (a traditional form of townhouse found mainly in Kyoto), when people started using tiled roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, as communities grew larger and densely-packed urban areas developed, its flammability was a serious disadvantage. Therefore, such roofs disappeared rapidly in urban areas, along roads and in Machiya (a traditional form of townhouse found mainly in Kyoto), to be replaced by tiled roofs.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, as communities grew larger and developed into densely-packed urban areas, its flammability was a serious disadvantage, therefore, such roofs disappeared rapidly in urban areas, and town houses along roads to be replaced by tiled roofs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>江戸の市街地などでは茅葺が禁じられていたエリアもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some urban areas of Edo, use of thatch was prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some urban areas of Edo, use of thatch was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thatch was prohibited in some urban areas of Edo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一方村落では材料のススキ・チガヤ・稲藁などの入手が容易であり、農閑期に共同作業で材料の入手と屋根の補修を行なうことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in villages, it was easier to obtain the materials, such as Japanese pampas grass, cogon or rice straws, and in the agricultural off-season, the villagers could obtain these materials and repair the roofs joinly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in villages it was easier to obtain the materials, such as Japanese pampas grass, cogon or rice straw, and in the agricultural off-season, the villagers could obtain these materials and repair the roofs jointly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it was easier to obtain the material such as Japanese pampas grass, cogon or rice straw in villages and it was possible to jointly gather these materials and repair roofs during the agricultural off-season.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。コンマを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのため20世紀中ごろまで日本各地の山間部の農村に茅葺が数多く残っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, many thatched houses remained in villages in mountaieous areas of Japan until around the middle of 20-th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, many thatched houses remained in villages in mountainous areas of Japan until around the middle of the 20th century.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, many thatched houses existed in villages in mountainous areas until around the middle of the 20th century in Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>台風の被害の大きい地域では、台風などによる強風に弱い短所が嫌われ、山間部に比べて早期に減少していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the areas where damage due to typhoons are serious, its shortcoming that is prone to strong wind of typhoons was disliked, and such roofs decreased in these areas earlier than those in mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the areas where typhoons are severe, thatched roofs could not withstand the strong winds. Thus, they fell into disfavor and decreased in number these areas earlier than those in mountainous areas.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to mountainous areas, thatched roofs decreased earlier in areas where typhoons are severe because thatched roofs cannot withstand strong winds.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>第二次世界大戦後は農村の過疎が進み、共同作業として行う葺き替えが困難になったこと、規制等により新たに建造することが簡便ではないこと、また、スギなどの木材価格が一時的に高騰し茅場が人工林化したことなどから急激に姿を消した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Second World War, thached roofs disappeared rapidly due to the following reasons: Popupation in farming areas has continued decreasing, maiking it difficult to do thached roof-renewing work jontly, it became not easy to build houses with such roofs due to the introduction of the regulations or other control concerned, and the prices of wood materials, such as Japanese cedar trees, increased drastically, making the kaya-growing places changed into articial forests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Second World War, thached roofs disappeared rapidly due to the following reasons: population in farming areas has continued decreasing, making it difficult to do thached roof-renewal work jontly; the introduction of regulations also complicated the building process; and, the price of wood materials, such as Japanese cedar trees, increased drastically, forcing kaya-growing areas to convert to articial forests.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Second World War, thatched roofs disappeared rapidly because of the decrease in population in farming areas made it difficult to jointly re-thatch roofs, introduction of regulations that complicated new buildings and the price of wood, such as Japanese cedar, temporarily increased and kaya-growing areas were converted to artificial forests.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>21世紀現在、もともと茅葺であった建物の大部分はトタンなどの金属葺屋根に改修されているが、わずかに茅葺が維持されている建物も残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present in the 21-th century, most of the thatched roofs of thatced houses were replaced with metal-made roofs, such as tin roofs, but few buildings maintaining thatched roofs still remain, though the number is very small.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present in the 21st century, most of the thatched roofs were replaced by metal roofs, such as tin roofs; however, a small amount of buildings with thatched roofs still remain.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present in the 21st century, most of the thatched roofs have been replaced by metal roofs, such as tin roofs; but a small number of buildings with thatched roofs still remain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>民家では新規に建築されることはほとんどなくなったが、伊勢神宮正宮・別宮などの寺社建築では古式に則り茅葺を維持している例が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has become rare that a thatched house is built privately, but many temple/shirine buildings, such as shogu and betsugu of Ise-jingu Shrine, maintain thatched roofs following old rules.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A privately-built thatched house has become a rarity, but many temple/shrine buildings, such as shogu and betsugu of Ise-jingu Shrine, maintain thatched roofs following old rules.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Newly built thatched private houses are extremely rare, but many temple/shrine buildings, such as the Shogu (main shrine) and Betsugu (sub-shrine) of Ise-jingu Shrine maintain thatched roofs according to old customs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>外観に特徴を与える意匠として商業施設などに採用される場合があるが、茅葺に見えるような繊維強化プラスチックなどの屋根が採用されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thatched roof designs are sometimes used in commercial facilities to give their external views a feature, but fiber reinforced plastic looking like thatch are used actually in some of such roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thatched roof designs are sometimes used in commercial facilities to give their external views a pleasant feature; however, reinforced plastic similar in appearance to thatch is used instead.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thatched roof designs are sometimes used in commercial facilities to give character to their exterior, but some use reinforced plastic that look similar to thatch instead.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>なお、宮城県石巻市では2006年11月1日より、建築基準法第22条1項の規制区域を緩和することによって、「茅葺き屋根」新築の道を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishinomaki City of Miyagi Prefecture loosened the conditions for the areas to be regulated based on Clouse 1, Article 22 of Building Standard Law starting on November 11, 2006, opening the way for building &quot;thached-roofs&quot; newly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishinomaki City of Miyagi Prefecture relaxed the regulations for thatched roofs based on Clause 1, Article 22 of the Building Standard Law starting on November 11, 2006, opening the way for building new thached roofs.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishinomaki City of Miyagi Prefecture relaxed the regulations for thatched roofs based on Clause 1, Article 22 of the Building Standard Law starting on November 1, 2006, opening the way for building new thatched roofs.</e>
<cmt>日付を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これは市内を流れる北上川特産のヨシを利用することにより、地場産業を活性化させることにつながる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has attracted attention from the viewpoints that this measure could activate local industries through use of reeds, a speciality on the Kitakami-gawa River flowing through the city, and making it possible to build thatched roofs, which are provided with a high cultural value, would induce people wanting to live in a rural area to live in Ishinomaki City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has attracted attention from the viewpoint that this measure could activate local industries through the use of reeds, a speciality on the Kitakami-gawa River flowing through the city. This would make it possible to build thatched roofs, which provide a high cultural value, and would induce people living in rural areas to live in Ishinomaki City.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has led to stimulation of local industries through the use of reeds, a specialty of the Kitakami-gawa River, which flows through the city.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また文化的価値が高い「茅葺き屋根」の新築を可能にすることによって、田舎暮らしを目指す人々を石巻市内に呼び込む道を開いたものとして注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also is attracting attention because it would induce people who wish to live in rural areas to live in Ishinomaki City by allowing new buildings with thatched roofs, which are of high cultural value.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ちなみに、当初石巻市は「茅葺き屋根」新築のための「特区」を国に申請していたが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, Ishinomaki City initially applied to the national government for &quot;a special area&quot;for enabling thatched roofs to be built newly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, Ishinomaki City initially applied to the national government for a special area to allow new thatched roofs to be built.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishinomaki City initially applied to the national government for a special area to allow new buildings with thatched roofs.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>国は市独自の判断で、火災の延焼防止を目的に住宅に不燃材使用を定めている建築基準法の２２条の指定を見直すことで、「茅葺き屋根」新築のための規制緩和に対応できるとの見解を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this, the national government expressed the view that the city could deal with, in tits own discretion, the deregulation for enabling thatched roofs to be bulit newly, through reviewing the speicificaiton in Articl 22 of Building Standard Law, which specifies use of nonflammable materials for preventing fire from being spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this, the national government expressed the view that the city could deal with, at its own discretion, the deregulation to allow the construction of new thatched roofs, through a review of the speicifications in Article 22 of the Building Standard Law, which specifies use of nonflammable materials for preventing the spread of fire.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The national government expressed the view that the city could deal with deregulation to allow the construction of new thatched roofs by redesignation of nonflammable materials for preventing the spread of fire specified in Article 22 of the Building Standard Law.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>日本以外では、西ヨーロッパ（ドイツ・デンマーク・オランダ等）においては一般民家等は少なくなってはいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside of Japan, use of such roofs in houses for the general public has decreased in West Europe (such as Germany, Denmark and Holland).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outside of Japan, use of such roofs in houses for the general public has decreased in West Europe (such as Germany, Denmark and Holland).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outside of Japan, use of such roofs in private houses has decreased in West Europe (such as Germany, Denmark and Holland).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、富裕層では裕福の象徴的な意味もあり、新築で建てるなど比較的数が多く、日本の職人も研修などで訪れたりもする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the area, relatively many thatched houses exist, partly because wealthy persons sometimes build such houses as a symbol of being rich, and Japanese craftmens concerned visit these countries for training or other purposes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, thatched houses are relatively numerous--partly because wealthy persons sometimes build such houses as a symbol of their wealth, and Japanese craftsmen concerned visit these countries for training or other purposes.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, newly built thatched houses are still relatively numerous because it is a symbol of wealth among the rich and Japanese craftsmen visit these countries for training.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本に於ける茅葺きの種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thatch types in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thatch types in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thatch types in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>屋根形状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roof shapes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roof shapes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Type of roof shapes</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>切妻造本を開いて伏せたような形状の屋根で、日本では高床式倉庫から発展したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof): This is a roof with the shape generated when a book is opened and placed facedown, and it is considered that in Japan, this type was developed from takayukashiki-soko (warehouse on stilts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof): This is a roof with a facedown opened book shape. It is considered that in Japan, this type was developed from takayukashiki-soko (warehouse on stilts).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirizuma-zukuri style (an architectural style with a gabled roof): The roof has a book opened facedown shape and is thought to have developed in Japan from takayukashiki-soko (warehouse on stilts).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>合掌造は通常切妻に分類されるが、妻の庇が大きい場合は入母屋とされる場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gassho-zukuri (a house built of wooden beams combined to form a steep thatched roof that resembles two hands together) is usually classified into Kiritzuma-zukuri, but when the eaves of a gable are large, it is sometimes classifed into irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gassho-zukuri (a house built of wooden beams combined to form a steep thatched roof that resembles two hands together) is usually classified as Kiritzuma-zukuri, but when the eaves of a gable are large, it is sometimes classifed into the irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gassho-zukuri (a house built of wooden beams combined to form a steep thatched roof that resembles two hands together): This type is usually classified as Kirizuma-zukuri, but is sometimes classified as irimoya style (building with a half-hipped roof) when the eaves of the gable are large.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>寺社建築の神明造では茅葺は必須とはされないが、切妻は必須とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, in the shinmei-zukuri style used in temple/shrine buildings, use of thatched roofs is not mandatory but use of kirizuma-zukuri is a must.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, in the shinmei-zukuri style used in temple/shrine buildings, the use of thatched roofs is not mandatory but the use of kirizuma-zukuri is a must.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinmei-zukuri style used in temple/shrine buildings require kirizuma-zukuri, but the use of thatched roofs is optional.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>寄棟造 竪穴式住居から発展したと考えられる形状で、日本各地で見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosemune-zukuri (a square or rectangular building, covered with a hipped roof): It is considered that this style was developed from pit dwellings, and is found in various areas in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosemune-zukuri (a square or rectangular building, covered with a hipped roof): It is considered that this style was developed from pit dwellings, and is found in various areas in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosemune-zukuri (a square or rectangular building, covered with a hipped roof): This style is found throughout Japan and is thought to have developed from prehistoric pit dwellings.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>入母屋造 切妻に大きな庇が一体化したものと、寄棟に明かり取り、煙出の窓を備えた構造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Irimoya style: It has the structure where a gable and the large eaves are integrated and where windows for taking light into and for outputting smoke are added to yosemune-zukuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Irimoya style: It has the structure where a gable and the large eaves are integrated and where windows for taking light into and for outputting smoke are added to yosemune-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Irimoya style: A structural style where a gable and large eaves are integrated into one with windows for taking in light and letting smoke out are added to yosemune-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>農村の民家のほか、寺社建築に多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many examples are found in temple/shrine buildings in addition to private farmer houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many examples are found in temple/shrine buildings in addition to private farm houses.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than private farm houses, many examples can be found amongst temple/shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="40">
<j>棟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ridges</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ridges</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ridges</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>竹簀巻き（たけすまき） 編んだ竹で棟の茅を巻く構造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takesumaki: The kaya ridge is wound by twined bamboos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takesumaki: The kaya ridge is wound by twined bamboos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takesumaki structure: The kaya ridge is wound around by woven bamboo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>日本各地で多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Found in various areas in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Found in various areas in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Found in various areas in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="43">
<j>置千木（おきちぎ） 木を組み合わせて棟を覆う構造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okichigi structure: Trees are assembled so as to cover a ridge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okichigi structure: Trees are assembled so as to cover a ridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okichigi structure: Wood is assembled so as to cover the ridge.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>木材の豊富な山間部に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Found in mountainous areas where plenty of wood materials are available.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Found in mountainous areas where plenty of wood materials are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Found in mountainous areas where plenty of wood materials are available.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="45">
<j>笄棟（こうがいむね） 茅を棟に積み重ね、屋根から突き出させた木材に締めて固定する構造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogaimune structure: Kaya is piled on a ridge and is fastened with wood materials protruded from the roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogaimune structure: Kaya is piled on a ridge and is fastened with wood materials protruding from the roof.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogaimune structure: Kaya is piled on the ridge and is fastened to wood protruding from the roof.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="46">
<j>芝棟（しばむね） 意図的に木や草を生やし、その根で棟の弛みをなくす構造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibamune structure: Trees and grasses are grown intentinally, to use their roots to work for preventing the ridge from being loosened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibamune structure: Trees and grasses are grown intentionally, to use their roots to work for preventing the ridge from being loosened.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibamune structure: Trees and grasses are grown intentionally to use their roots to prevent the ridge from loosening.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>葺き替え</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renewing thatch</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renewing thatch</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Re-thatching</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>場所や使用状態にもよるが20-40年程度で屋根全体を葺き替えることが多いようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although depending on where it is placed and how it is used, such a roof is likey to be renewed entirely in around 20 to 40 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although depending on where it is placed and how it is used, such a roof is likey to be renewed entirely in around 20 to 40 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending upon the location and usage, the entire roof is commonly renewed around once every 20 to 40 years.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>ただし頂点付近は傷みが激しいので定期的な補修が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the thatch around the top area is damaged fast and is needed to be repaired regularly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the thatch around the top area is damaged first and needs to be repaired regularly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, periodic repair is required around the top area because there is more damage to the thatch.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>材料の確保については、元来は村落周辺に茅場と呼ばれるススキ草原があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concering how to obtain the material, Japanese pampas grass fields called kayaba existed in the periphery of villages in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concering how to obtain the material, Japanese pampas grass fields called kayaba existed in the periphery of villages in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding securement of material, Japanese pampas grass fields called kayaba existed in the periphery of villages in the past.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これは、家畜の餌などとして定期的に刈り入れを行うことで、遷移 (生物学)の進行を止めてススキ草原を維持していたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These Japanese pampas grass fields were maintained by stopping (biological) transition through cutting the grass regularly, for example, as food for domestic livestock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Japanese pampas grass fields were maintained by stopping the (biological) transition through cutting the grass regularly, for example, as food for domestic livestock.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Japanese pampas grass fields were maintained by stopping the progress of transition (biology term) by cutting the grass regularly as food for domestic livestock.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>しかし、第二次大戦以降の生活の変化によって利用されなくなったことから、ほとんどが失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because people&apos;s lives have changed since the end of Second World War, use of them has been abandoned and most of them have been lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because daily life has changed since the end of the Second World War, use of them has been abandoned and most of them have been lost.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, use of the fields has been abandoned and most of them lost with the change in lifestyle since the end of the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>しかし、その後の減反や離農により茅場と化している場所も増えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the introduction of the acreage reduction policy and an increase in the persons who abandon farming, the places that have beccome like kayaba have increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the introduction of the acreage reduction policy and the number of people who abandon farming, kayaba areas have been on the rise.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the introduction of the acreage reduction policy and decrease in farming, areas that have become kayaba are on the rise.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>したがって、以前よりは苦労しなくなっているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that the materials for such roofs have become more easily available, compared with in the past.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is said that the materials for such roofs have become more easily available, compared to the past.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is said that finding material for such roofs has become easier than the past.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>職人の確保も、若手を育成している建築会社が出現するなど、減少に歯止めが掛かろうとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some buiding companies have started bringing up craftpersons to be engaed in thach-roofing work, and therefore, the trend that the number of such craftpersons descreases has begun stopping.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some buiding companies have started training craftspeople to be engaged in thatch-roofing work, and therefore, the decrease of craftspeople has begun to stop.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some building companies have started to train young craftspeople in thatch-roofing, and therefore, the decrease of craftspeople has begun slow.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>伊勢神宮では古来神路山など宮域周辺の各所で茅を集めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ise-jingu Shrine, kaya was collected in various places around the shrine, such as Kamiji-yama Mountain, from ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ise-jingu Shrine, kaya has been collected in various places around the shrine, such as Kamiji-yama Mountain, since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since ancient times, kaya has been collected at various places around the Ise-jingu Shrine, such as Kamiji-yama Mountain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>大正時代に茅を育成するための用地（神宮萱場）を度会郡度会町に確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Taisho period, the shrine obtained in Watarai-cho, Watarai-gun a place where kaya was to be grown (the kayaba for the shrine).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Taisho period, the shrine acquired land in Watarai-cho, Watarai-gun where kaya was to be grown (the kayaba for the shrine).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the shrine acquired land during the Taisho period in Watarai-cho, Watarai-gun especially for growing kaya (kayaba for the shrine).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この萱場では地元住民の奉仕により晩秋にススキが集められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this kayaba, Japanese pampas grass is collected in late autumn by getting voluntary cooperation of local people at that area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this kayaba, Japanese pampas grass is collected in late autumn by using the voluntary cooperation of local people at that area.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this kayaba, Japanese pampas grass is collected in late autumn by volunteers from the local residents.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>茅の屋根の縁は見た目を美しくするため切りそろえる場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To make the external view beautiful, the edges of many thatched roofs are cut cleanly so as to make a plane.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To make the external view beautiful, the edges of many thatched roofs are cut cleanly so as to make a plane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The edge of many thatched roofs are cut cleanly in a plane to make it look beautiful.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>しかし、切りそろえないほうが水はけはいい、とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also said that water drains more smoothly, if they are not cut cleanly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also said that water drains more smoothly, if they are not cut cleanly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also said that water drainage is better if the edge is not cut cleanly.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>住人が自ら葺く場合は穂の部分を下にした逆葺きが行われる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a person going to live in a thached house builds the thached roof by himself, it is usual that the sakabuki in which the ears of grass are placed on the lower level is used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a person going to live in a thatched house builds the thached roof by himself, it is usual that the sakabuki where the ears of grass are placed on the lower level is used.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the resident himself is thatching the roof, it is usually sakabuki (literally, reverse thatching), where the ears of grass are placed downwards.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>業者に頼んだ場合は穂を上に向けた本葺きが行われる事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the work is entrusted to a professional person, it is usual that the honbuki in which the ears of grass are placed on the higher level is used.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the work is entrusted to a professional person, it is usual that the honbuki is used where the ears of grass are placed on a higher level.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the work is entrusted to a professional, it is usually honbuki (literally, real thatching), where the ears of grass are placed upwards.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>前者は後者に比べ茅の使用量を2〜3分の1に押さえる事が出来、茅が滑り落ちない為施工が簡単である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the former method is used, only a half or third of kaya is needed, comapred with the latter method, and the thatch-roofing work is easier because kaya does not slide down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the former method is used, only a half or third of kaya is needed, compared with the latter method; and, the thatch-roofing work is easier because kaya does not slide down.</e>
<cmt>wording; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former method uses only a half or third of kaya compared with the latter method and is easier because kaya does not slide down.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>しかし、油分を含まない穂先が雨に曝される為耐久性に劣る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the ear part that does not possess oily contet is exposed to rain, and therefore, the roof built using the former method is inferior to that using the latter method in durability</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the ear part that does not possess an oily content is exposed to rain, and therefore, the roof built using the former method is inferior in durability to that using the latter method.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is less durable because the ear part, which has a low oil content, is exposed to rain.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="64">
<j>費用は地域差もあるが、大体1坪あたり12万円前後（屋根全体で500万円程度）掛かるのが相場という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the cost depends on the area, it is said that the typical market price is roughly around \120,000 per 3.3 square meters (aroung \5 M in total).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the cost depends on the area, it is said that the typical market price is roughly around \120,000 per 3.3 square meters (around \5 M in total).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the cost depends on the area, it is said that the typical market price is roughly around \120,000 per 3.3 square meters (around \5 M in total).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>茅葺の建物が集中してある場所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The places where thatcked building are concentrated</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Places where thatched building are concentrated</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Locations with many thatched building</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>白川郷・五箇山の合掌造り集落（岐阜県）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gassho-zukuri-concentrated areas in Shirakawago and Gokayama (located in Gifu Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gassho-zukuri-concentrated areas are in Shirakawago and Gokayama (located in Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gassho-zukuri-concentrated areas are in Shirakawago and Gokayama (located in Gifu Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>- 世界遺産（文化遺産）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- World heirtage (cultural heritage)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- World Heritage (cultural heritage) Site</e>
<cmt>wording, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">- World Heritage (cultural heritage) Site</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>大内宿（福島県南会津郡下郷町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ouchi juku (Shimogo-machi Town, Minami Aizu County, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ouchi juku (Shimogo-machi Town, Minami Aizu County, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ouchi juku (Shimogo-machi, Minami Aizu-gun, Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>住所の表現を統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>かやぶきの里・北村（京都府南丹市美山町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kayabuki-no-sato (thatched house village): Kitamura (Miyama-cho, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kayabuki-no-sato (thatched house village): Kitamura (Miyama-cho, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kayabuki-no-sato (thatched house village): Kitamura (Miyama-cho, Nantan City, Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>江戸東京たてもの園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">EDO TOKYO OPEN AIR ARCHITECTURALMUSEUM</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">EDO TOKYO OPEN AIR ARCHITECTURAL MUSEUM</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">EDO TOKYO OPEN AIR ARCHITECTURAL MUSEUM</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>日本民家園（神奈川県川崎市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon-minka-en (exhibits of trasitional private houses in Japan) (located in Kawasaki City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon-minka-en (exhibits of transitional private houses in Japan) (located in Kawasaki City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon-minka-en (exhibits of transitional private houses in Japan) (located in Kawasaki City, Kanagawa Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>奈良県立民俗博物館（奈良県大和郡山市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara Prefectural Museum of Folklore (located in Ymatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara Prefectural Museum of Folklore (located in Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara Prefectural Museum of Folklore (located in Yamatokoriyama City, Nara Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>三州足助屋敷（愛知県豊田市足助町）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanshu Asuke Yashiki (located in Asuke-cho, Toyota City, Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanshu Asuke Yashiki (located in Asuke-cho, Toyota City, Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanshu Asuke Yashiki (located in Asuke-cho, Toyota City, Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 アレシンロ(id:170344), Nnh(id:474), DragonBot(id:161936), Kansai explorer(id:48975), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Kumatora(id:16941), Kanahata(id:222427), Curry(id:71375), Wiiii(id:59641), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Dabofish(id:239582), PipepBot(id:146181), Call Tenderas(id:169753), Nisiguti(id:534), Dghshg(id:201354), Bandalgom(id:31841), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 茅葺屋根保存会(id:214489), Babi Hijau(id:40709), Ｋｓ(id:15319), M abe(id:37612), ArthurBot(id:265089), 白蛇の騎士(id:185121), G.miyanomori(id:9984), Nighthawks(id:36125), こおりやんま(id:108912), Yanahan(id:2437), Eveningmist(id:28648), Himetv(id:21833), L26(id:119681), Rusk(id:9895), Nnn(id:26535), Mochi(id:9489), N yotarou(id:60870), Bista(id:207887), Nekosuki600(id:21263), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>