<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宜陽殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giyoden storeroom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giyoden Hall (Treasure Hall)</e>
<cmt>「Giyoden storeroom」→「Giyoden Hall (Treasure Hall)」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giyoden Hall (Treasure Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宜陽殿（ぎようでん）とは、平安京の内裏における殿舎のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giyoden storeroom is one of buildings in dairi (Imperial Palace) of Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Giyoden Hall (Treasure Hall) was one of the halls of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Giyoden Hall (Treasure Hall) was one of the halls of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>内裏の南東にあり、紫宸殿の東南、綾綺殿の南、日華門を挟んで春興殿の北に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is southeasterly located in dairi, is in the east-south of Shishin-den Hall, is in the south of Ryokiden Hall, and is in the north from Shunkyo-den (a part of Heiankyo Palace) which is located beyond Nikka-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situated in the southeast of the Imperial Palace, this hall was located to southeast of Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall), south of Ryokiden Hall, and to the north of Shunkyoden Hall beyond Nikka-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situated in the southeast of the Imperial Palace, this hall was located to southeast of Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall), south of Ryokiden Hall, and to the north of Shunkyoden Hall beyond Nikka-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>南庭西側の校書殿とは東西に相対する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the opposite side of kyoshoden (a building in the Imperial Palace precincts) which is located on the west side of the southern country yard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stood opposite Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall) which was situated on the western side of the south garden.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stood opposite Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall), which was situated on the western side of the south garden, facing in an east-west direction.</e>
<cmt>「東西に」を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>母屋は天皇累代の御物・宝物を保管しておく納殿として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main housing was used for the storeroom to store imperial property or treasures that had been handed down for generations of emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The moya (core of the building) was used to store the imperial treasures that were handed down to successive emperors.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The moya (core of the building) was used to store the imperial treasures that were handed down to successive emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>西庇に左近衛陣座が置かれ、そこで陣定が盛んに行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Nishi-bisashi (western eaves), the position for Sakone no daisho (Major Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) was placed, and jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council) often took place there.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sakone (Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) court was located in the nishibisashi (western outer area) and was frequenly used to assemble the Jin no Sadame (Court Council).</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sakone (Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) court was located in the nishibisashi (western outer area) and was frequenｔly used to assemble the Jin no Sadame (Court Council).</e>
<cmt>frequenly→frequently</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>後に陣定の会場は紫宸殿につながる軒廊へと移っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, later, the place for the jin no sadame was shifted to Konro (roofed corridor with open sides) leading to the Shishin-den Hall.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meeting place of the Jin no Sadame later moved to the konro (roofed corridor with open sides) joined to Shishinden Hall.</e>
<cmt>・「However later」を削除・「meeting」を補足・「for」→「of」・「jin no sadame」→「Jin no Sadame」・「was shifted」→「later moved」・「the」を補足・「Konro」→「konro」・「leading to the」→「joined to」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meeting place of the Jin no Sadame later moved to the konro (roofed corridor with open sides) joined to Shishinden Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>現在の京都御所にも古式に則って再建されたものが伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The storerooms that were reconstructed in accordance with the old age have been preserved in the present day Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Giyoden Hall that was reconstructed according to the original design stands at the present Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Giyoden Hall that was reconstructed according to the original design stands at the present Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>