<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神尾山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>*統一用語リストにはKannosan-jo Castleとあったのですが、読みは「かんの・お・さんじょう」と「の・お」は長音ではないので、以下kannoosan-joと表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannoosan-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神尾山城（かんのおさんじょう）は、京都府亀岡市宮前町宮川にあった城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle was a castle existed in present Miyagawa, Miyazaki-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannoosan-jo Castle was a castle that existed in what is now Miyagawa, Miyazaki-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>・「that」を追加・「present」→「what is now」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle was a castle that existed in what is now Miyagawa, Miyazaki-cho, Kameoka City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>柳本賢治の居城で、その後明智光秀の丹波国攻めの基地になったのではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed to have been used by Kataharu YANAGOMOTO as his residence, and later by Mitsuhide AKECHI as a base to attack Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to have been used by Kataharu YANAGOMOTO as his residence, and later by Mitsuhide AKECHI as a base from which to attack Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>・「supposed」→「thought」・「from which」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to have been used by Kataharu YANAGOMOTO as his residence, and later by Mitsuhide AKECHI as a base from which to attack Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>神尾山城は金輪寺の裏山にあった山城で、金輪寺の周辺には、極楽坊跡、竹中坊跡、宝蔵坊跡、東柳坊跡など、数多い寺坊跡があり、天台宗天台密教の霊地で今も石垣がそのまま残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle was built on a mountain at the back of Kinrin-ji Temple, and in its surroundings inside the temple ground, there still remain the ruins of lodgings for visitors or pilgrims&apos; lodgings), such as Gokuraku-bo, Chikuchu-bo (竹中坊跡,), 宝蔵坊跡Hozo-bo, 東柳坊Toryu-bo (東柳).</e>
<cmt>寺坊跡→定訳不明：ruins of lodgings for visitors or pilgrims&apos; lodgings)としました。竹中坊→Chikuchu-bo (竹中坊) [正しい読み方不明です] 東柳坊→Toryu-bo (東柳) [正しい読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannoosan-jo Castle stood on a mountain behind Kinrin-ji Temple, in the surrounding area of which there remain the ruins of many temple living quarters for Buddhist monks and nuns such as Gokuraku-bo, Chikuchu-bo, Hozo-bo and Toryu-bo, and the site is also a sacred place of Tendai Esoteric Buddhism, with a stone wall that still stands.</e>
<cmt>再翻訳しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle stood on a mountain behind Kinrin-ji Temple, in the surrounding area of which there remain the ruins of many temple living quarters for Buddhist monks and nuns such as Gokuraku-bo, Chikuchu-bo, Hozo-bo and Toryu-bo, and the site is also a sacred place of Tendai Esoteric Buddhism, with a stone wall that still stands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>神尾山城はその聖地に築城され、巨石怪石を利用した特徴のある大形山城であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle was built in that sacred place, demonstrating a characteristic figure of a large-sized mountain castle constructed with strange-shaped big stones</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannoosan-jo Castle was built on this sacred site, and was a large structure which was distinctively constructed from large and strangely shaped stones.</e>
<cmt>・原文を反映するように再翻訳しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannoosan-jo Castle was built on this sacred site, and was a large structure which was distinctively constructed from large and strangely shaped stones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>亀岡市街地から西方約16km、西丹波の篠山市に抜ける山陰道に沿った山に築かれており、標高は359m、比高230mの山頂一帯にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was constructed on the crest of a mountain at 359m elevation and 230m relative elevation, 16km west from the center of Kameoka City, along the Sanin-do Road that leads to Shinoyama City in Nishi Tanba.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was constructed on the peak of a mountain with an altitude of 359m and a relative height of 230m that stands approximately 16km west of the center of Kameoka City, on the Sanin-do Road that led to Shinoyama City in Nishi Tanba.</e>
<cmt>読みやすくするように書換え</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was constructed on the peak of a mountain with an altitude of 359m and a relative height of 230m that stands approximately 16km west of the center of Kameoka City, along the Sanin-do Road that led to Shinoyama City in Nishi Tanba.</e>
<cmt>「沿った」on→along</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>神尾山城が史上に現れるのが桂川原の戦い八上・神尾山両城の戦いの時で、大永6年（1526年）の初旬、細川尹賢が摂津国で築城していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first appearance of the Kannoosan-jo Castle in a historical material can be found in the descriptions on the Battle of Katsuragawa River, and the Battles of Yagami-jo Castle and Kannoosan-jo Castle, and from there it can be understood that in the early 1529, Tadakata HOSOKAWA constructed a castle called Kannoosan-jo Castle in Settsu Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first reference to Kannoosan-jo Castle in historical sources can be found in the descriptions of the Battle of Katsuragawa River, and the Battles of Yagami-jo Castle and Kannoosan-jo Castle, which state that a castle called Kannoosan-jo Castle was built in Settsu Province by Tadakata HOSOKAWA in early 1526.</e>
<cmt>・「appearances of the」→「reference to」・「a historical material」→「historical sources」・「on」→「of」・文の後半を再構成ペリオドを補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first reference to Kannoosan-jo Castle in historical sources can be found in the descriptions of the Battle of Katsuragawa River, and the Battles of Yagami-jo Castle and Kannoosan-jo Castle, which state that a castle called Kannoosan-jo Castle was built in Settsu Province by Tadakata HOSOKAWA in early 1526.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この時の様子を『足利季世紀』では「尼崎ノ城」（大物城）と記述されているが、『新修　大阪市史第２巻』によると細川氏典厩家の本拠は中嶋で尼崎は含まれていないので、堀城の誤りではないかと指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Ashikaga kiseiki&quot; it was described as &apos;Amagasaki-no-jo&apos; (Daimotsu-jo), however, &quot;Shinshu Osaka-shi Shi&quot; (History of Osaka: new edition) Vol.2 pointed out that the Hosokawa Tenkyu family had its home base in Nakajima area but it did not cover Amagasaki area, therefore &apos;Amagasaki-jo Castle&apos; should be read as &apos;Hori-jo Castle.&apos;</e>
<cmt>『足利季世紀』→定訳不明： &quot;Ashikaga kiseiki&quot;としました。　「尼崎ノ城」（大物城）→定訳不明：&apos;Amagasaki-no-jo&apos; (Daimotsu-jo)としました。 『新修　大阪市史第２巻』→定訳不明：&quot;Shinshu Osaka-shi Shi&quot; (History of Osaka: new edition) Vol.2 としました。堀城 →定訳不明：&apos;Hori-jo Castle&apos; (堀城) [正しい読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Ashikaga Kiseiki&quot; it was recorded as &apos;Amagasaki-no-jo&apos; (Daimotsu-jo), but &quot;Shinshu Osaka-shi Shi&quot; (History of Osaka: new edition) vol. 2 describes that the Hosokawa Tenkyu family had its home base in Nakajima area but did not include the Amagasaki area, and it has therefore been identified that this may be an incorrect reference to Hori-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・「According to」→「In」・「kiseki」→「Kiseki」・「described」→「recorded」・「however,」→「but」・「Vol.2」→「vol. 2」・「pointed out」→「describes」・「it did not cover」→「did not include the」・「and it has」を追加・「been identified that」を追加・「&apos;Amagasaki-jo Castle&apos; should be read as」→「this may be an incorrect reference to」・引用符を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Ashikaga Kiseiki&quot; it was recorded as &apos;Amagasaki-no-jo&apos; (Daimotsu-jo), but &quot;Shinshu Osaka-shi Shi&quot; (History of Osaka: new edition) vol. 2 describes that the Hosokawa Tenkyu family had its home base in Nakajima area but did not include the Amagasaki area, and it has therefore been identified that this may be an incorrect reference to Hori-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この城の作事に香西元盛も加わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the construction of this castle, Motomori KOZAI was also involved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motomori KOZAI was also involved in the construction of this castle.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motomori KOZAI was also involved in the construction of this castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そんな中、細川尹賢の人夫と香西元盛の人夫が「土一簀」で口論となり、双方の人夫が喧嘩をはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, a quarrel between a laborer of Tadakata HOSOKAWA and a laborer of Motomori KOZAI about &apos;a basketful of dirt&apos; provoked a conflict between the laborers of the both party.</e>
<cmt>「土一簀」→定訳不明：&apos;a basketful of dirt&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, a quarrel between a laborer of Tadakata HOSOKAWA and a laborer of Motomori KOZAI about &apos;a basketful of dirt&apos; provoked a conflict between the laborers of the both party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, a quarrel between a laborer of Tadakata HOSOKAWA and a laborer of Motomori KOZAI about &apos;a basketful of dirt&apos; provoked a conflict between the laborers of the both party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>いったん両者とも引き分けたが、腹の虫が収まらなかった香西元盛の人夫が城中に瓦等投げ込んだりしたので、細川尹賢の憎悪感は頂点になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict ended in a draw at one time, but since some frustrated laborers of the Motomori KOZAI side threw roof tiles and other things into the Tadakata&apos;s castle, Tadakata HOSOKAWA became filled with resentment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two were briefly separated but Motomori KOZAI&apos;s laborers could not contain their anger and threw roof tiles and other objects within the castle, filling Tadakata HOSOKAWA with hatred.</e>
<cmt>書き直ししました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two were briefly separated but Motomori KOZAI&apos;s laborers could not contain their anger and threw roof tiles and other objects within the castle, filling Tadakata HOSOKAWA with hatred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>細川尹賢は香西元盛が無学であるのを利用して、偽の謀反書を細川高国に差出、驚いた細川高国は同年7月13日香西元盛を謀殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakata HOSOKAWA, taking advantage of Motomori KOZAI&apos;s ignorance, forwarded a falsified Motonari&apos;s letter of rebellion to Takakuni HOSOKAWA, and Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who was frightened, murdered Motomori KOZAI on July 31 of the same year (1529).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of Motomori KOZAI&apos;s ignorance, Tadakata HOSOKAWA forwarded a falsified letter of rebellion to a shocked Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who murdered Motomori KOZAI on July 31 of the same year (1529).</e>
<cmt>・「Motonari&apos;s」を削除・文の前半を再構成・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of Motomori KOZAI&apos;s ignorance, Tadakata HOSOKAWA forwarded a falsified letter of rebellion to Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who, astonished at the letter, murdered Motomori KOZAI on Autust 30 of the same year (1526).</e>
<cmt>書き換えました。同年7月13日はセル16から大永6年なので、グレゴリオ歴で1526年8月30日に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>逆に激怒した香西元盛の兄弟の波多野稙通と柳本賢治は細川高国に反旗を翻し、八上・神尾山城両城の戦い、桂川原の戦いに続いていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furious Motonari KOZAI&apos;s brothers, in return, rose in revolt against Takakuni HOSOKAWA, and this revolt subsequently lead to the Battles of Yagami-jo Castle and Kannoosan-jo Castle, and to the Battle of Katsurakawara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motonari KOZAI&apos;s brothers Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO were enraged and revolted against Takakuni HOSOKAWA, triggering a battle between Yagami-jo Castle and Kannoosan-jo Castle as well as the Battle of Katsurakawara.</e>
<cmt>翻訳漏れがありましたので、再翻訳しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motonari KOZAI&apos;s brothers Tanemichi HATANO and Kataharu YANAGIMOTO were enraged and revolted against Takakuni HOSOKAWA, triggering a battle between Yagami-jo Castle and Kannoosan-jo Castle as well as the Battle of Katsurakawara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、柳本賢治は中嶋の戦いで暗殺され、細川高国は大物崩れで自害、細川尹賢も殺害され、一旦城史は不明となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, as Kataharu YANAGIMOTO was assassinated in the Battle of Nakanoshima, Takakuni HOSOKAWA killed himself at Daimotsu-kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu), and Tadakata HOSOKAWA was also murdered, and since then the history of the castle became unknown for a while.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this, Kataharu YANAGIMOTO was assassinated in the Battle of Nakanoshima, Takakuni HOSOKAWA committed suicide at Daimotsu-kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu), Tadakata HOSOKAWA was also murdered, and the history of the castle became unknown for a brief period of time.</e>
<cmt>・「Afterwards」→「following this」・「killed himself」→「committed suicide」・「and」を削除・「since then」を削除・「while」→「brief period of time」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, Kataharu YANAGIMOTO was assassinated in the Battle of Nakanoshima, Takakuni HOSOKAWA committed suicide at Daimotsu-kuzure (the Battle of Daimotsu), Tadakata HOSOKAWA was also murdered, and the history of the castle became unknown for a brief period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>『証如上人日記』によると天文_(元号)15年（1546年）、細川晴元は三好長慶が擁立した細川氏綱（父は細川尹賢）に敗れ「丹波カンノチ」（神尾山城）へ没落と明記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shonyo Shonin nikki&quot; (Diary of Shonyo Shonin), in 1546, Harumoto HOSOKAWA was defeated by Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA (Tadakata HOSOKAWA is his father) backed up by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, and it is described clearly that he sought a refuge at &apos;Tanba-kannochi&apos; (that place in Tanba) （referring to Kannoosan-jo Castle）</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「丹波カンノチ」→定訳不明：&apos;Tanba-kannochi&apos; (that place in Tanba)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shonyo Shonin Nikki&quot; (the Diary of Shonyo Shonin) clearly describes that in 1546, Harumoto HOSOKAWA was defeated by Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA (son of Tadakata HOSOKAWA) supported by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, and that he sought a refuge at &apos;Tanba-kannochi&apos; (that place in Tanba) (referring to Kannoosan-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>・「nikki」→「Nikki」・「the」を補足・「Tadakata HOSOKAWA is his father」→「son of Tadakata HOSOKAWA」・「backed up」→「supported」・「described clearly」→「clearly described」・全角括弧→半角括弧（x2）・ペリオドを補足・再構成しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shonyo Shonin Nikki&quot; (the Diary of Shonyo Shonin) clearly describes that in 1546, Harumoto HOSOKAWA was defeated by Ujitsuna HOSOKAWA (son of Tadakata HOSOKAWA) supported by Nagayoshi MIYOSHI, and that he sought a refuge at &apos;Tanba-kannochi&apos; (that place in Tanba) (referring to Kannoosan-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは細川氏綱方の上野元治が足利義晴を迎え取ろうと同年9月13日に入京し、これに危機感を覚えた細川晴元が丹波国へ落ち延びており、この時の記述ではないかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It might be the description about the time when Harumoto HOSOKAWA went down to Tanba Province, when he felt threatened by Motoharu UENO, tsunakata of the Hosokawa clan, who entered in Kyoto on September 13 of the same year to conquer him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。綱方→定訳不明：tsunakata としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is though that this might be a description of the time when Harumoto HOSOKAWA fled to Tanba Province after feeling threatened by Motoharu UENO of the Hosokawa Ujitsuna faction who entered Kyoto on September 13 of the same year to conquer Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>再翻訳しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is though that this might be a description of the time when Harumoto HOSOKAWA fled to Tanba Province after feeling threatened by Motoharu UENO of the Hosokawa Ujitsuna faction who entered Kyoto on September 13 of the same year to conquer Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後細川晴元は丹波国を出国、摂津国に入国し神呪寺城、越水城へ移動し、更に舎利寺の戦いに繋がっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, Motoharu HOSOKAWA left Tanba Province and after entering to Settsu Province he directed himself to Kanno-ji Temple and Koshimizu-jo Castle, and finally he fought to death in the Battle of Shariji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motoharu HOSOKAWA subsequently left Tanba Province for Settsu Province where he relocated to Kannoji-jo Castle and Koshimizu-jo Castle, and became involved in the Battle of Shariji.</e>
<cmt>・「Afterwards,」を削除・「subsequently」を追加・「and after entering to」→「for」・「where」を補足・「directed himself」→「relocated」・「Kanno-ji Temple」→「Kannoji-jo Castle」・「finally he fought to death」→「became involved」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto HOSOKAWA subsequently left Tanba Province for Settsu Province where he relocated to Kannoji-jo Castle and Koshimizu-jo Castle, and became involved in the Battle of Shariji.</e>
<cmt>Motoharu→Harumoto</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>その次は天文22年（1553年）9月3日の『言継卿記』で、内藤国貞が本目城で討死にという記載が見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next appearance of the name is found in the article of September 3, 1553 of &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Diary of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA), in which there is a description that Sadakuni NAITO was killed in a battle at Honme-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>『言継卿記』→定訳不明：&quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Diary of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next appearance of the name is found in the article of September 3, 1553 of &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Diary of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA), in which there is a description that Sadakuni NAITO was killed in a battle at Honme-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next appearance of the name is found in the article of September 3, 1553 of &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Diary of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA), in which there is a description that Kunisada NAITO was killed in a battle at Honme-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Sadakuni→Kunisada</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>また『総見記』によると天正年間（1573年-1592年）明智光秀が八上城攻めの中継基地として「本目の城」を使った、との記載が見受けられるが、両文献に記載される本目城とは神尾山城を指すと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, according to the description of &quot;Sokenki,&quot; during the Tensho era (1573-1592), Mitsuhide Akechi used the &apos;Castle of Honme&apos; as a transit base to attack Yagami-jo Castle, and both of the castle named &apos;Honme&apos; are supposed to indicate Kannoosan-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, &quot;Sokenki&quot; describes that Mitsuhide Akechi used the &apos;Castle of Honme&apos; as a transit base from which to attack Yagami-jo Castle during the Tensho era (1573-1592), and it is supposed that the &apos;Honme Castle&apos; described in both writings refers to Kannoosan-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>・再構成しました・「from which」を補足・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, &quot;Sokenki&quot; describes that Mitsuhide Akechi used the &apos;Castle of Honme&apos; as a transit base from which to attack Yagami-jo Castle during the Tensho era (1573-1592), and it is supposed that the &apos;Honme Castle&apos; described in both writings refers to Kannoosan-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>城郭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure of the Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castle Structure</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castle Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>城郭は南北に約350m、東西に約70mで、丹波では大形に属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle extends about 350m from south to north, about 70m from east to west, and it is one of the large-sized castles in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle measures approximately 350m from south to north, approximately 70m from east to west, and it is one of the large castles of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>・「extends」 →「measures」・「about」→「approximately」（x2）・「-sized」を削除・「in」→「of」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle measures approximately 350m from south to north, approximately 70m from east to west, and it is one of the large castles of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>山稜線の主軸に根幹をなし、そこから派生した2つの支脈の稜線に曲輪が配され、下部の曲輪で横に繋がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foundation is situated on the chief axis of the mountain crest, and on the ridge line of each of the two feeder crests separates from the main axis, a kuruwa (the general term for a castle compound) is placed, and these compounds are connected horizontally with each other in the lower part of kuruwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foundation is situated on the chief axis of the mountain crest, and on the ridge line of each of the two feeder crests separates from the main axis, a kuruwa (the general term for a castle compound) is placed, and these compounds are connected horizontally with each other in the lower part of kuruwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foundation is situated on the main axis of the mountain ridge, and a kuruwa (the general term for a castle compound) is located on the ridgeline of each of the two feeder ridges (which are separated from the main axis); the lower parts of these kuruwa are connected to each other horizontally.</e>
<cmt>separates→separated,</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>主曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main compound of kuruwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main Compound</e>
<cmt>「Main compound of kuruwa」→「Main Compound」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main Compound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>主曲輪は、東西約27m、南北約60mで、そのほぼ中央部に底部5-6m、上部4m、高さ2.5m-3m、長さ7mの土塁跡があり北側、南側の曲輪を大きく区切られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main kuruwa compound extends about 27m from east to west, about 60m from south to north, and nearly in the middle of it, there is a remain of earthen mound, with the bottom size of 5-6m, topping size of 4m, height of 2.5-2m and the length of 7m, and by this mound the northern side and southern side of kuruwa are roughly divided.</e>
<cmt>主曲輪→定訳不明：main kuruwa compoundとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main compound extends about 27m from east to west, about 60m from south to north, and in the approximate center are the remains of an earthen mound measuring 5-6m at its base, 4m at its top, 2,5-3m in height and 7m in length; roughly dividing the compound into northern and southern areas.</e>
<cmt>・「kuruwa」を削除・「nearly in the middle of it」→「in the approximate center」「, there is a remain」→「are the remains」・「an」を補足・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main compound extends about 27m from east to west, about 60m from south to north, and in the approximate center are the remains of an earthen mound measuring 5-6m at its base, 4m at its top, 2,5-3m in height and 7m in length; roughly dividing the compound into northern and southern areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>『中世城郭辞典』によるとこの土塁跡に、多聞風櫓が建設されていた可能性を指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chusei Jokaku Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of medieval castles) pointed out the possibility that a vigilance tower (多聞風櫓) was constructed in the place where the earthen mound remains.</e>
<cmt>『中世城郭辞典』→定訳不明：&quot;Chusei Jokaku Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of medieval castles) としました。 多聞風櫓→vigilance tower (多聞風櫓) [正しい読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chusei Jokaku Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of Medieval Castles) states the possibility that a tamon yagura (long guard tower) once stood on the remains of the earthen mound.</e>
<cmt>・「medieval castles」→「Medieval Castles」・「pointed out」→「states」・「vigilance tower (多聞風櫓)」→「tamon yagura (long guard tower)」・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chusei Jokaku Jiten&quot; (Dictionary of Medieval Castles) states the possibility that a tamon yagura (long guard tower) once stood on the remains of the earthen mound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>北側曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">North side kuruwa compound</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Northern Compound</e>
<cmt>「North side kuruwa compound」→「Northern Compound」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Northern Compound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>北側曲輪は主曲輪より北側にあり、高低差が小さい、2つの大きな曲輪から成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The north side kuruwa compound is situated in the north of the main kuruwa and it contains two large-sized kuruwas, whose level of height have a slight difference.</e>
<cmt>北側曲輪→定訳不明：north side kuruwa compoundとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The northern compound stands to the north of the main compound and is comprised of two similarly sized sections.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The northern compound stands to the north of the main compound and is comprised of two similarly sized sections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>この北側曲輪や主曲輪には規則的に並んだ礎石跡が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the north side kuruwa as well as in the main kuruwa, the remains of neatly constructed foundation stone can be found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remains of neatly arranged foundation stones can be seen in both this northern compound and in the main compound.</e>
<cmt>・文法を修正・ナチュラルに書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remains of neatly arranged foundation stones can be seen in both this northern compound and in the main compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これにより、ある程度の規模の屋敷が想定でき、恒久的な山城の要素も考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this, it can be imagined that there was a residences with a certain scale, which might have been equipped with the elements of mountain castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From these, it can be assumed that fairly large residences once stood on the site, and that these were elements of a permanent mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>・「By this」→「From these」・「imagined」→「assumed」・原文を反映するように書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From these, it can be assumed that fairly large residences once stood on the site, and that these were elements of a permanent mountain castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、北側曲輪には亀岡市ではここだけにしか存在しない畝状空堀（竪掘跡）があり、形状から明智光秀時代の改修が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the north side kuruwa has a furrow-shaped dry canal (remains of pit), which indicates that it underwent a modification during the rule of Mitsuhide AKECHI, judging from the form.</e>
<cmt>畝状空堀（竪掘跡）→定訳不明： furrow-shaped dry canal (remains of pit)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the northern compound has a furrow-shaped dry moat (remains of a vertical-sided moat) that exists only in Kameoka City, which, judging from its form, appears to have undergone modification during the rule of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>・「north side kuruwa」→「northern compound」・「canal」→「moat」・「pit」→「a vertical-sided moat」・翻訳漏れを修正・「undewent」→「undergone」・「a」を削除・再構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the northern compound has a furrow-shaped dry moat (remains of a vertical-sided moat) that exists only in Kameoka City, which, judging from its form, appears to have undergone modification during the rule of Mitsuhide AKECHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、現在は南側曲輪から主曲輪にある土塁跡の脇を通過して北側曲輪への侵入は可能だが、当時は多聞風櫓が南北を遮断しており、西側にある曲輪帯曲輪・腰曲輪を通って北側曲輪と南側曲輪をいききしていたと思われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, it is possible to go to the north side kuruwa from the south side kuruwa, passing alongside the remain of earthen mound in the main kuruwa, but at that time, the vigilance tower (多聞風櫓) blocked the passing from south to north, and therefore, it is considered that to come and go between the north side and the south side kuruwa, the people were passing through the kuruwa compound in the west side consisted of obikuruwa (a long narrow castle compound) and koshiguruwa (the compound bounded by earthworks).</e>
<cmt>vigilance tower (多聞風櫓)→正しい読み方が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, it is possible to enter the northern compound from the southern compound, passing alongside the remains of the earthen mound in the main compound, but at the time of the castle&apos;s construction, the tamon yagura blocked passage from south to north, and it is therefore thought that people would pass between the northern and southern compounds by passing through the obikuruwa (a long narrow castle compound) and koshiguruwa (a compound bounded by earthworks) that comprised the western compound.</e>
<cmt>・「go to」→「enter」・「north side kuruwa」→「northern compound」・「south side kuruwa」→「southern compound」・「remain」→「remains」・「the」を追加・「kuruwa」→「compound」・「that time」→「the time of the castle&apos;s construction」・「vigilance tower (多聞風櫓)」→「tamon yagura」・「the passing」→「passage」・「and therefore, it is considered」→「and it is therefore thought」・文の後半を書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, it is possible to enter the northern compound from the southern compound, passing alongside the remains of the earthen mound in the main compound, but at the time of the castle&apos;s construction, the tamon yagura blocked passage from south to north, and it is therefore thought that people would pass between the northern and southern compounds by passing through the obikuruwa (a long narrow castle compound) and koshiguruwa (a compound bounded by earthworks) that comprised the western compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>南側曲輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">South side kuruwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Southern Compound</e>
<cmt>「South side kuruwa」→「Southern Compound」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Southern Compound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>南側曲輪は主曲輪より南側と南西側の2つ支脈の稜線に曲輪が配されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the south side kuruwa compound is constructed on the two feeding crests that extends from the main kuruwa to the south and to the southwest, respectively</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The southern compound is constructed on the two feeding crests that extend from the main compound to the south and to the southwest.</e>
<cmt>・「In the south side kuruwa compound」→「The southern compound」・「extends」→「extend」・「kuruwa」→「compound」・「, respectively」を削除・ペリオドを補足</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The southern compound is constructed on the two feeding crests that extend from the main compound to the south and to the southwest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>南側の曲輪は高低差があり7段の階段状になっており、その中ほどに上部3.5m、底部2m、高さ3mの堀切が存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The south side kuruwa, which has a difference in level, is a stepped ground with seven different levels, and in the middle of the compound there was a ditch of 3.5m in top 2m in bottom, and 3m in height.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The southern compound varies in height with seven stepped levels, and in the center is a dry moat which has a width of 3.5m at the top, 2m at the bottom and a height of 3m.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The southern compound varies in height with seven stepped levels, and in the center is a dry moat which has a width of 3.5m at the top, 2m at the bottom and a height of 3m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>南西側の尾根沿いにも3,4段程度の曲輪がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along the ridge in the southwest side, there is another with 3 or 4 levels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are also compounds with three and four levels along the southwestern ridge.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are also compounds with three and four levels along the southwestern ridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ここには「天狗岩」という巨石があり、霊場の景観を呈していることから、南西側の曲輪は金輪寺の寺院敷地を利用したとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, there is a huge stone called &apos;Tengu-iwa,&apos; (Tengu rock, or long-nosed goblin shaped rock), representing a mountain spirit, and therefore, it might be possible that the south west side kuruwa was constructed making use of the land of Kinrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「天狗岩」→定訳不明： &apos;Tengu-iwa,&apos; (Tengu rock, or long-nosed goblin shaped rock)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here there is a large rock called &apos;Tengu-iwa&apos; (Tengu rock, or long-nosed goblin shaped rock), representing a mountain spirit, and it is therefore thought that the southwestern compound was constructed on the grounds of Kinrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>・コンマを２つ削除・「huge stone」→「large rock」・文の後半を翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here there is a large rock called &apos;Tengu-iwa&apos; (Tengu rock, or long-nosed goblin shaped rock), representing a mountain spirit, and it is therefore thought that the southwestern compound was constructed on the grounds of Kinrin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>また、この南側と南西側の中間部分に「曲輪水の手曲輪」と丹波地方では珍しい曲輪跡がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there is a ruin of kuruwa that can be rarely seen in Tanba district, called &apos;mizu-no-te guruwa&apos; (a castle compound equipped with water withdrawal and storage facility for the castle), in the middle of the south and southwest sides.</e>
<cmt>「曲輪水の手曲輪」→「水の手曲輪」→&apos;mizu-no-te guruwa&apos; (a castle compound equipped with water withdrawal and storage facility for the castle)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In between the southern and southwestern sides is a &quot;mizu-no-te guruwa&quot; (castle compound built to protect the source of a castle&apos;s water) - rare in the Tanba region.</e>
<cmt>用語共有のデータベースに基づき、翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In between the southern and southwestern sides is the remains of &quot;mizu-no-te guruwa&quot; (castle compound built to protect the source of a castle&apos;s water) - rare in the Tanba region.</e>
<cmt>remains（跡）を追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これは4段目曲輪の最上部に1.5mの井戸跡があり、そこから湧水式の水路がほどこされ、水のはった曲輪になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There, a ruin of well with the dimension of 1.5m is found at the top of the kuruwa that has four levels, and from there a spring-fed canal leads to the kuruwa full of water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uppermost fourth level of this compound contains the remains of a well with a diameter of 1.5m from which a spring-fed aqueduct was built to provide the castle with water.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uppermost fourth level of this compound contains the remains of a well with a diameter of 1.5m from which a spring-fed aqueduct was built to provide the castle with water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その隣の南側曲輪、大手筋脇には石垣と盛土があり建物跡が推定され、「丹波国ではもっとも優れている水の手曲輪」と『中世城郭辞典』は指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The south side kuruwa next to it, along side Otesuji, there are remains of stonewall and a earthen mound, and these remains give the supposition that there was a building there, and according to &quot;Chusei Shokaku Jiten,&quot; it was &apos;the most excellent &apos;mizu-no-te guruwa&apos; in Tanba Province.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the adjacent southern compound and beside Otesuji are a stone wall and an earthen mound that are believed to be the remains of a building which &quot;Chusei Shokaku Jiten&quot; claims was &quot;the most excellent mizu-no-te guruwa in Tanba Province&quot;.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the adjacent southern compound and beside Otesuji are a stone wall and an earthen mound that are believed to be the remains of a building which &quot;Chusei Jokaku Jiten&quot; claims was &quot;the most excellent mizu-no-te guruwa in Tanba Province.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置、Shokaku→Jokaku</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>城跡へのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access to the ruins of the castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access to the Castle Ruins</e>
<cmt>「ruins of the castle」→「Castle Ruins」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access to the Castle Ruins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>電車でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By train</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Train</e>
<cmt>Title caseにしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Train</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>JR 山陰本線 千代川駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">JR Sanin Main Line Chiyokawa Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">JR Sanin Main Line Chiyokawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">JR Sanin Main Line Chiyokawa Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>バス　京阪京都交通 宮前下車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By bus, Keihan Kyoto Kotsu bus for Miyamae</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Take the Keihan Kyoto Kotsu bus for Miyamae</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Take the Keihan Kyoto Kotsu bus for Miyamae</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>車でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Car</e>
<cmt>Title caseにしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>京都縦貫自動車道 千代川インターチェンジ → 京都府道73号宮前千歳線 → 金輪寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto jukan jidoshado Chiyokawa Exit →Kyoto Prefectural highway No. 73 Miyamae Chitose Line→Kinrin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto-Jukan Expressway &gt; Chiyokawa Interchange &gt; Kyoto Prefectural Road 73 Miyazaki Chitose Route &gt; Kinrin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto-Jukan Expressway &gt; Chiyokawa Interchange &gt; Kyoto Prefectural Road 73 Miyazaki Chitose Route &gt; Kinrin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>近隣に駐車場無し（金輪寺に参拝者用駐車場有）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No parking area is available around the temple (parking space is provided only for worshippers at Kinrin-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no parking facilities nearby (parking facilities are provided for Kinrin-ji Temple worshippers).</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no parking facilities nearby (parking facilities are provided for Kinrin-ji Temple worshippers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>徒歩でのアクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On foot</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Foot</e>
<cmt>Title caseにしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Foot</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>金輪寺 → 主郭曲輪　徒歩約20分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinrin-ji Temple→Main kuruwa compound: about 20 minute walk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approximately 20 minute walk from Kinrin-ji Temple to the main compound.</e>
<cmt>翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approximately 20 minute walk from Kinrin-ji Temple to the main compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Kansai explorer(id:48975), 越中掾(id:149423), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>