<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>清涼殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiryoden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiryoden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiryoden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>清涼殿（せいりょうでん）とは、平安京の内裏における殿舎のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiryoden is one of the royal halls in the Inner Palace in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiryoden is one of the royal halls in the Inner Palace in Heiankyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiryoden is one of the royal halls in the Inner Palace in Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>仁寿殿の西、後涼殿の東。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">West of Jijuuden, East of Koryoden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">West of Jijuuden, East of Koryoden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">West of Jijuden (literally, &quot;hall of benevolence and longevity,&quot; which is the Emperor&apos;s residence), East of Koryoden Hall.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>紫宸殿が儀式を行う殿舎であるのに対し、天皇の日常生活の居所として使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Shishinden Hall was used for public ceremonies, the Seiryoden was used by the Emperor for daily life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Shishinden Hall was used for public ceremonies, the Seiryoden was used by the Emperor for daily life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Shishinden Hall was used for public ceremonies, the Seiryoden was used by the Emperor for daily life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし平安初期は仁寿殿や常寧殿が使用されたが、中期頃には清涼殿がもっぱら天皇の御殿となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in the early Heian Period the Jijuuden and Joneiden were used however from the middle of the Heian period the Seiryoden became the primary palace of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in the early Heian Period the Jijuuden and Joneiden were used however from the middle of the Heian period the Seiryoden became the primary palace of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in the early Heian period the Jijuden and Joneiden were used however from the middle of the Heian period the Seiryoden became the primary palace of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日常の政務の他、四方拝・叙位・除目などの行事も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from everyday affairs of State, rituals such as the Shiho-hai, Joi and Jimoku were done here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from everyday affairs of State, rituals such as the Shiho-hai, Joi and Jimoku were done here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from everyday affairs of State, rituals such as the Shihohai (a Shinto ceremony held on New Year&apos;s Day in which the Emperor pays respect to the deities in all quarters), Joi (the conferment of a court rank) and Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) were done here.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>建物の規模は九間四面（母屋（もや）が南北五間・東西二間で四方に廂、東に孫廂がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scale of the building is nine rooms and four sides (five rooms in the core north to south, two east to west, and a narrow corridor on all sides and an additional corridor on the East)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scale of the building is nine rooms and four sides (five rooms in the core north to south, two east to west, and a narrow corridor on all sides and an additional corridor on the East)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scale of the building is nine rooms and four sides (main housing has five rooms in the core north to south, two east to west, and hisashi (aisle room) on all sides and magohisashi (a narrow additional aisle room) on the east).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>屋根は檜皮葺の入母屋造。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roof is a hip and gable construction with Japanese cypress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roof is a hip and gable construction with Japanese cypress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roof is irimoya-zukuri style (building with a half-hipped roof) with hiwadabuki (cypress bark roof).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>正面は東で、東庭の北に呉竹台、南に河竹台がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The front faces the east and to the north of the eastern garden is the Kuretakenodai black bamboo garden and to the south is the Kawadakenodai bamboo garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The front faces the east and to the north of the eastern garden is the Kuretakenodai black bamboo garden and to the south is the Kawadakenodai bamboo garden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The front faces the east and to the north of the eastern garden is the Kuretake no dai (Wu Chinese bamboo) and to the south is the Kawatake no dai (Han Chinese bamboo).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>天皇が主に居住するのは中心の昼御座（ひのおまし、天皇出御の場）・夜御殿（よるのおとど、天皇の寝所の塗籠）で、その北には弘徽殿上御局・飛香舎上御局（后妃の伺候する部屋）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor mainly occupied the daytime living area (Hi-no-omashi, Shutsugyo-no-ba)and the night living area (called Yoru-no-otodo, Emperor&apos;s sleeping quarters or Nuri-gome) and to the north of this was the Kokiden-no-ue-no-mitsubone and the Higyosha-no-ue-no-mitsubone (rooms for waiting on the Empress).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor mainly occupied the daytime living area (Hi-no-omashi, Shutsugyo-no-ba)and the night living area (called Yoru-no-otodo, Emperor&apos;s sleeping quarters or Nuri-gome) and to the north of this was the Kokiden-no-ue-no-mitsubone and the Higyosha-no-ue-no-mitsubone (rooms for waiting on the Empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An emperor mainly occupied Hi-no-omashi (the daytime living area for shutsugyo (emperor&apos;s arrival (at his office, and so on)) and Yoru-no-otodo (emperor&apos;s sleeping quarters with nurigome (room surrounded with thick walls)) and to the north of this was the Kokiden-no-ue-no-mitsubone (room for dignified lady-in-waiting of Kokiden (one of the royal halls)) and the Higyosha-no-ue-no-mitsubone (room for dignified lady-in-waiting of Higyosha (one of the royal halls)) (both rooms for waiting on an empress).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>西側の廂には北から順に御湯殿上（天皇の食事を調理する）、御手水間（天皇の調髪を行う）、朝餉間（天皇が朝食を取る）、台盤所（食事を載せた台を置く）、鬼間（厨子などを置く）が並ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One the western corridor in order from the top was the Oyudono-no-ue room (where food was prepared for the Emperor), Ochozu-no-ma room (where the Emperor had his hair cut), Asagarei-no-ma room (where the Emperor ate breakfast), Daibandokoro (where the meal tray was placed), and Oni-no-ma (for placing miniature shrines etc.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One the western corridor in order from the top was the Oyudono-no-ue room (where food was prepared for the Emperor), Ochozu-no-ma room (where the Emperor had his hair cut), Asagarei-no-ma room (where the Emperor ate breakfast), Daibandokoro (where the meal tray was placed), and Oni-no-ma (for placing miniature shrines etc.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the western hisashi in order from the north was the Oyudono-no-ue room (where food was prepared for an emperor), Ochozu-no-ma room (where an emperor had his hair cut), Asagarei-no-ma room (where an emperor ate breakfast), Daibandokoro (where the meal tray was placed), and Oni-no-ma (for placing miniature shrines, and so on).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また南廂の殿上間は公卿・殿上人らが伺候する場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore the Tenjo-no-ma in the southern corridor was a place where the noble people and &apos;tenjobito&apos; (people of rank who were allowed into this room) waited on the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore the Tenjo-no-ma in the southern corridor was a place where the noble people and &apos;tenjobito&apos; (people of rank who were allowed into this room) waited on the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore the Tenjo-no-ma in Minami-bisashi (the southern aisle room) was a place where the noble people and &apos;tenjobito&apos; (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) waited on an emperor.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), ドラムスコ(id:40234), Masyu(id:31065), Pp976uu(id:181030), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 本屋(id:125948), BitBucket(id:30999), うぃき野郎(id:53567), 伏儀(id:142093), BAKU(id:55205), Dojo(id:32472), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>