<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都銀行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>株式会社京都銀行（きょうとぎんこう、The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.）は、京都府京都市下京区に本店を構え、京都府を中心に営業している地方銀行である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bank of Kyoto,Ltd., with its head office located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, does business in Kyoto Prefecture, and neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd., with its head office located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, does business in Kyoto Prefecture, and neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd., with its head office located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, does business in Kyoto Prefecture, and neighboring areas as a regional bank.</e>
<cmt>「regional bank」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Overview&quot;→&quot;Summary&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京都府の指定金融機関。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officially designated financial institution to do business with the prefectural government of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is officially designated as a financial institution in order to conduct business with the prefectural government of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is officially designated as a financial institution in order to conduct business with the prefectural government of Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>企業キャッチフレーズは「飾らない銀行」。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Corporate slogan: &quot;Keep natural attitude&quot;</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corporate slogan is, &quot;Keep a natural attitude.&quot;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The corporate slogan is, &quot;Keep a natural attitude.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>奇抜なTVCM「ながーい、おつきあい」シリーズでも知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its eccentric TV commercial &quot;Looong relationship&quot; (Nagaaai otsukiai) is well known.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明，　この場合はlooongのように，あえて変形語の作成が可能と思われます．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its eccentric TV commercial, &quot;Looong relationship (Nagaaai otsukiai),&quot; is well known.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its eccentric TV commercial, &quot;Looong relationship (Nagaaai otsukiai),&quot; is well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>英字表記は『The Bank of Kyoto』であるが、各店鋪やATMでは『The Bank for Kyoto』と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name in English is &quot;The Bank of Kyoto,&quot; but &quot;The Bank for Kyoto&quot; is posted in its branches and ATMs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name in English is &quot;The Bank of Kyoto,&quot; but &quot;The Bank for Kyoto&quot; is posted in its branches and ATMs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name in English is &quot;The Bank of Kyoto,&quot; but &quot;The Bank for Kyoto&quot; is posted in its branches and ATMs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>「京都銘柄」と称される京都企業の株式を多数保有し評価損益を多く抱えていること、バブル経済期にも比較的堅実な経営を続けていたことから、財務体質は良好で自己資本比率・信用格付けとも地方銀行の中で高水準にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bank has a sound financial status, keeping one of the highest levels both in capital-to-assetl ratio and credit rating among regional banks, because the bank&apos;s stock portfolio includes a significant number of stocks in renowned local companies called &quot;Kyoto Brands&quot; maintaining substantial appraisal profits, and it has been doing prudent business since before the &quot;bubble&quot; economy.</e>
<cmt>京都銘柄→[定訳不明]Kyoto Brands</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bank is financially sound, and it maintains one of the highest capital-to-asset ratios and credit ratings among regional banks, because the bank&apos;s stock portfolio includes a significant number of stocks in renowned local companies known as &quot;Kyoto brands,&quot; which maintain substantial appraisal profits, and it has been doing prudent business since before the &quot;bubble&quot; economy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bank is financially sound, and it maintains one of the highest capital-to-asset ratios and credit ratings among regional banks, because the bank&apos;s stock portfolio includes a significant number of stocks in renowned local companies known as &quot;Kyoto brands,&quot; which maintain substantial appraisal profits, and it has been doing prudent business since before the &quot;bubble&quot; economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>預金量は5兆1123億円。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Total Deposits: ¥5,112.3 billion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Total deposits: ¥5,112.3 billion</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Total deposits: ¥5,112.3 billion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>（2006年3月末）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(as of the end of March, 2006)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(as of the end of March 2006)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(as of the end of March 2006)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>2007年より、地元プロサッカークラブ京都サンガF.C.のユニフォーム袖スポンサーとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 2007, the bank&apos;s logo has been on the sleeves of uniform of Kyoto Sanga F.C., which is the professional football team in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 2007, the bank&apos;s logo has been on the sleeves of the uniforms of the Kyoto Sanga F.C., which is the professional football team in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 2007, the bank&apos;s logo has been on the sleeves of the uniforms of the Kyoto Sanga F.C., which is the professional football team in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>健全性指標</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soundness indicators</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soundness indicators</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soundness indicators</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>以下は2006年9月中間期の指標</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following are the data for the half-year ending September, 2006:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following data is for the half-year ending as of September 2006:</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following data is for the half-year ending as of September 2006:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>自己資本比率</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Capital-to-asset ratio</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Capital-to-asset ratio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Capital-to-asset ratio</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>単体：国内基準11.11%、国際統一基準14.66%</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Non-consolidated: 11.11% based on domestic standards: 14.66% based on International FinancialReporting Standards</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyotobank.co.jp/investor/annual/pdf_annual/ar2008_08.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Non-consolidated: 11.11% based on domestic standards, or 14.66% based on the International FinancialReporting Standards</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Non-consolidated: 11.11% based on domestic standards, or 14.66% based on the International FinancialReporting Standards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>連結：国内基準11.39%、国際統一基準14.91%</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consolidated: 11.39% based on domestic standards: 14.91% based on International Financial Reporting Standards</e>
<cmt>http://www.kyotobank.co.jp/investor/annual/pdf_annual/ar2008_08.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consolidated: 11.39% based on domestic standards, or 14.91% based on the International Financial Reporting Standards</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consolidated: 11.39% based on domestic standards, or 14.91% based on the International Financial Reporting Standards</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>（2006年9月30日現在）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(as of Septermber 30, 2006)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(as of September 30, 2006)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(as of September 30, 2006)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>格付け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Credit rating</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Credit rating</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Credit rating</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>格付投資情報センター：A+、スタンダード&amp;ampプアーズ：A</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rating and Investment Information, Inc. (R&amp;I): AStandard &amp; Poor&apos;s (S&amp;P): A</e>
<cmt>http://www.r-i.co.jp/eng/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rating and Investment Information, Inc. (R&amp;I): AStandard &amp; Poor&apos;s (S&amp;P): A</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rating and Investment Information, Inc. (R&amp;I): AStandard &amp; Poor&apos;s (S&amp;P): A</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（2006年11月1日現在）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(as of November 1, 2006)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(as of November 1, 2006)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(as of November 1, 2006)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>有価証券評価益（含み益）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gain on devaluation of marketable securities (unrealized gain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gain on devaluation of marketable securities (unrealized gain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gain on revaluation of marketable securities (unrealized gain)</e>
<cmt>「devaluation」では損失になってしまうと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>3,321億円（2006年9月30日現在）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">\332.1 billion (as of September 30, 2006)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">\332.1 billion (as of September 30, 2006)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">\332.1 billion (as of September 30, 2006)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>店舗政策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Branch management</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Branch management</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Branch management</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>京都府内の市町村と滋賀県・大阪府・奈良県・兵庫県・東京都に支店と出張所を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bank has branches and local offices in cities and villages in Kyoto Prefecture, as well as in Shiga Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture, and Tokyo Metropolis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bank has branches and local offices in cities and villages of Kyoto Prefecture, as well as in Shiga Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture and metropolitan Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bank has branches and local offices in cities and villages of Kyoto Prefecture, as well as in Shiga Prefecture, Osaka Prefecture, Nara Prefecture, Hyogo Prefecture and metropolitan Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>戦前までは、京都市内の銀行は東京市内（現、特別区）と同じくほとんどが都市銀行の支店であり、地元の地方銀行は小規模のものが数行存在していたに過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the prewar era, most bank offices were branches of major city banks just like in Tokyo City (now boroughs), and there were only a few regional banks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the prewar era, most bank offices were branches of major city banks, as was the case in Tokyo City (now boroughs), but there were only a few regional banks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the prewar era, most bank offices in Kyoto City were branches of major city banks, as was the case in Tokyo City (now boroughs), but there were only a few regional banks.</e>
<cmt>「in Kyoto City」を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかも、結局そのいずれもが大手銀行への併合の道をたどり、京都大内銀行が富士銀行（現在のみずほ銀行）と当時福知山市に本店を置いていた当行に分割譲渡されたのを最後に、戦時中京都市内では地元の地方銀行が消滅してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For worse, every one of them took the path to being merged by major banks, and eventually all regional banks in Kyoto City went extinct during the War, when the last bank, Kyoto Ouchi Bank, was split and transferred to The Fuji Bank, Limited (now Mizuho Bank, Limited) and Kyoto Bank, whose head office was located in Fukuchiyama City at that time.</e>
<cmt>京都大内銀行→[定訳不明]Kyoto Ouchi Bank（京都大内銀行）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unfortunately, every one of them took the path of merger into major banks, and during the war the regional banks in Kyoto City became defunct; eventually the last of them, Kyoto Ouchi Bank, was split and transferred to The Fuji Bank, Limited (now Mizuho Bank, Limited) and Kyoto Bank, whose head office was located in Fukuchiyama City at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unfortunately, every one of them took the path of merger into major banks, and during the war the regional banks in Kyoto City became defunct; eventually the last of them, Kyoto Ouchi Bank, was split and transferred to The Fuji Bank, Limited (now Mizuho Bank, Limited) and Kyoto Bank, whose head office was located in Fukuchiyama City at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>このため、戦後は地域産業発展のため地元資本の地方銀行を求める声が起こり、元来丹波国・丹後国地区での戦時中の統合銀行であった丹和銀行（本店・福知山市）が京都市内に進出することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, after the war, calls for creating regional banks with the local capital emerged, and Tanwa Bank (with its head office in Fukuchiyama City), which was originally an integrated bank during the war in regions of Tanba no Kuni and Tango no Kuni, launched business in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>丹和銀行→[定訳不明]Tanwa Bank（丹和銀行）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, after the war there was a call to create regional banks with the local capital, and Tanwa Bank (with its head office in Fukuchiyama City), which had originally been an integrated bank during the war in regions of Tanba no Kuni and Tango no Kuni, entered business in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, after the war there was a call to create regional banks with the local capital, and Tanwa Bank (with its head office in Fukuchiyama City), which had originally been an integrated bank during the war in regions of Tanba Province and Tango Province, entered business in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Tanba no Kuni and Tango no Kuni&quot;→&quot;Tanba Province and Tango Province&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>1953年には本店を京都市の現在地（旧高島屋跡）に移転、京都市内における店舗の拡張として、都市銀行をはじめとした他銀行の支店の譲受や自主出店により店舗数を増やした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1953, its head office moved to the current place (where previously old Takashimaya Company, Limited was located), and it acquired branches of other banks including city banks in a bid to increase its number of branches in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1953, its head office moved to the current location (formerly the site of the old Takashimaya Company, Limited), and it acquired the branches of other banks, including city banks, in a bid to increase its number of branches in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1953, the bank moved its head office to the current location (formerly the site of the old Takashimaya Company, Limited), and increased its number of branches in Kyoto City through acquisition of those of other banks, including city banks or opening up them independently.</e>
<cmt>自主出店が訳出されていませんでした。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その一方で1980年代に府外支店の大部分を整理している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, it abolished most of its branches outside Kyoto Prefecture in 1980s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the 1980s it abolished most of its branches outside Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the 1980s it abolished most of its branches outside Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>京都銀行はいわば後発であるため、京都市の指定金融機関にはなっておらず、また市内シェア（預金1兆円以上の金融機関のみで）も京都中央信用金庫や京都信用金庫、三菱東京UFJ銀行、三井住友銀行などと分け合っているのが現状である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bank has yet to be officially designated by Kyoto City administration because it is a new comer as it were, and its bank deposit share (among financial institutions with more than 1 trillion yen in deposit) in Kyoto City is comparable to those of Kyoto Chuo Shinkin Bank, The Kyoto Shinkin Bank, The Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi UFJ,Ltd, and Sumitomo Mitsui Banking Corporation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bank has yet to be officially designated by the Kyoto City administration because it&apos;s a newcomer relatively speaking and its bank-deposit share (among financial institutions with more than a trillion yen in deposits) in Kyoto City is comparable to those of Kyoto Chuo Shinkin Bank, The Kyoto Shinkin Bank, The Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi UFJ, Ltd. and Sumitomo Mitsui Banking Corporation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bank has yet to be officially designated by the Kyoto City administration because it&apos;s a newcomer relatively speaking and its bank-deposit share (among financial institutions with more than a trillion yen in deposits) in Kyoto City is comparable to those of Kyoto Chuo Shinkin Bank, The Kyoto Shinkin Bank, The Bank of Tokyo-Mitsubishi UFJ, Ltd. and Sumitomo Mitsui Banking Corporation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>（京都市内の預金は1兆円以下であるが、京都市内にはみずほ銀行や滋賀銀行、京都府南部には南都銀行も多店舗展開している）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It runs less than one trillion yen in deposit in Kyoto City, but there are other bank branches, such as Mizuho Bank and Shiga Bank n Kyoto City, and many branches of The Nanto Bank, Ltd. in the Southern part of Kyoto Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It accounts for less than a trillion yen in deposits in Kyoto City, but there are other bank branches, such as Mizuho Bank and Shiga Bank in Kyoto City, as well as many branches of The Nanto Bank, Ltd. in the southern part of Kyoto Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It accounts for less than a trillion yen in deposits in Kyoto City, but there are other bank branches, such as Mizuho Bank and Shiga Bank in Kyoto City, as well as many branches of The Nanto Bank, Ltd. in the southern part of Kyoto Prefecture.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>近年は新たな収益源を獲得するため、再び京都府外への出店を積極的に進めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, the bank has again started aggresively opening new branches outside Kyoto Prefecture,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, the bank has again started aggressively opening new branches outside Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, aiming to acquire new source of revenue, the bank has again started aggressively opening new branches outside Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「新たな収益源」が訳出されていません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>2000年以降、隣県の滋賀県や奈良県に加え、大阪府でも京阪間の鉄道沿線を中心に出店・融資攻勢を強め、大手銀行のほか、滋賀銀行、南都銀行などとしのぎを削っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 2000 it has heavily invested opening new branches in areas along the railway lines between Kyoto and Osaka in Osaka Prefecture in addition to neighboring Shiga Prefecture and Nara Prefecture, and it is actively competing with Shiga Bank and Nanto Bank, as well as major city banks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 2000 it has invested heavily, opening new branches in areas along the railway lines between Kyoto and Osaka in Osaka Prefecture in addition to neighboring Shiga and Nara prefectures, and it is actively competing with Shiga Bank and Nanto Bank as well as major city banks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 2000 it has invested heavily, opening new branches in areas along the railway lines between Kyoto and Osaka in Osaka Prefecture in addition to neighboring Shiga and Nara prefectures, and it is actively competing with Shiga Bank and Nanto Bank as well as major city banks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>兵庫県にも尼崎支店（2004年12月）、神戸支店（2005年9月）、川西支店（2007年10月）、六甲道支店（同11月）を開設するに至っているこれは旧兵庫銀行の経営破綻など、同県内に有力地銀が存在しない状況も大きく影響している（その為、京都銀行を含む県外地銀の進出攻勢が激しくなっている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It opened Amagasaki Branch (December, 2004), Kobe Branch (September, 2005), Kawanishi Branch (October,2007), and Rokkomich Branch in Hyogo Prefecture, encouraged by absence of other competitive regional banks in the prefecture after the bankruptcy of defunct Hyogo Bank (accelerating the increase of bank businesses from other prefectures including Kyoto Bank.)</e>
<cmt>兵庫銀行→[定訳不明]Hyogo Bank（兵庫銀行）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It opened the Amagasaki Branch (December, 2004), Kobe Branch (September, 2005), Kawanishi Branch (October,2007) and Rokkomich Branch in Hyogo Prefecture, encouraged by the absence of other competitive regional banks in the prefecture after the bankruptcy of the now-defunct Hyogo Bank (accelerating the increase of bank businesses from other prefectures, including Kyoto Bank).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It opened the Amagasaki Branch (December, 2004), Kobe Branch (September, 2005), Kawanishi Branch (October,2007) and Rokkomich Branch (November, 2005)in Hyogo Prefecture, encouraged by the absence of other competitive regional banks in the prefecture after the bankruptcy of the now-defunct Hyogo Bank (accelerating the increase of bank businesses from other prefectures, including Kyoto Bank).</e>
<cmt>「（同11月）」が訳出されていません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>ネット支店「京都銀行ネットダイレクト支店」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has an online branch &quot;The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Net Direct.&quot;</e>
<cmt>京都銀行ネットダイレクト支店→[定訳不明]The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Net Direct</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also operates an online branch called &quot;The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Net Direct.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also operates an online branch called &quot;The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Net Direct.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、京阪電気鉄道と提携してステーションATM「ステーションATMエキバンク」を主要駅に展開している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bank also operates ATMs at main stations &quot;The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Station ATM&quot;jointly with Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>ステーションATMエキバンク→[定訳不明]The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Station ATM</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bank operates ATMs carrying the name &quot;The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Station ATM&quot; at main stations jointly with Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bank operates ATMs carrying the name &quot;The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd. Station ATM&quot; at main stations jointly with Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>1884年（明治17年）：田中源太郎が亀岡銀行を設立（現在の亀岡市支店、楽々荘）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1884: Gentaro TANAKA founded Kameoka Bank (current Kameoka City Branch: Rakuraku So)</e>
<cmt>亀岡銀行→[定訳不明]Kameoka Bank（亀岡銀行） 楽々荘→[定訳不明]Rakuraku So（楽々荘）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1884: Gentaro TANAKA founded Kameoka Bank (currently Kameoka City Branch: Rakuraku So).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1884: Gentaro TANAKA founded Kameoka Bank (currently Kameoka City Branch: Rakuraku So).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>1941年（昭和16年）：両丹銀行（福知山）、宮津銀行（宮津）、丹後商工銀行（峰山）、丹後産業銀行（峰山）の4行合併により丹和銀行創立（本店福知山市）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1941: Ryotan Bank (in Fukuchiyama), Miyazu Bank (in Miyazu), Tango Shoko Bank (in Mineyama), and Tango Sangyo Bank emerged to establish Tanwa Bank (with its head office in Fukuchiyama City).</e>
<cmt>両丹銀行→[定訳不明]Ryotan Bank（両丹銀行）宮津銀行→[定訳不明]Miyazu Bank（宮津銀行）丹後商工銀行→[定訳不明]Tango Shoko Bank（丹後商工銀行）丹後産業銀行→[定訳不明]Tango Sangyo Bank（丹後産業銀行）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1941: Ryotan Bank (in Fukuchiyama), Miyazu Bank (in Miyazu), Tango Shoko Bank (in Mineyama) and Tango Sangyo Bank emerged to establish Tanwa Bank (with its head office in Fukuchiyama City).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1941: Ryotan Bank (in Fukuchiyama), Miyazu Bank (in Miyazu), Tango Shoko Bank (in Mineyama) and Tango Sangyo Bank emerged to establish Tanwa Bank (with its head office in Fukuchiyama City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>1943年（昭和18年）：京都支店（現、七条支店）を開設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1943: Opened Kyoto Branch (current Shichijo Branch).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1943: The Kyoto Branch (currently Shichijo Branch) was opened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1943: The Kyoto Branch (currently Shichijo Branch) was opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="38">
<j>1951年（昭和26年）：株式会社京都銀行に商号変更。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1951: Changed its corporate name to The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1951: The corporate name was changed to The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1951: The corporate name was changed to The Bank of Kyoto, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="39">
<j>1953年（昭和28年）：本店を京都市に移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1953: Moved its head office to Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1953: The head office was moved to Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1953: The head office was moved to Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="40">
<j>1982年（昭和57年）：ディーシーカードと共同で京都クレジットサービスを設立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1982: Founded Kyoto Credit Service Co., Ltd. jointly with DC Card (Mitsubishi UFJ NICOS Co., Ltd.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1982: Kyoto Credit Service Co., Ltd., was founded jointly with DC Card (Mitsubishi UFJ NICOS Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1982: Kyoto Credit Service Co., Ltd., was founded jointly with DC Card (Mitsubishi UFJ NICOS Co., Ltd.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 J o(id:26533), セルシオ越前(id:138322), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), KMT(id:1772), たね(id:10372), Myaataro(id:57164), SPR(id:141947), 砂場(id:27896), Cat94510(id:195661), Kisstory(id:43865), 愛佳と環姉(id:153537), Tan90deg(id:40673), ピン福(id:187138), Mochi(id:9489), Cimiquin(id:5516), 代言人(id:33675), Kyoto-u(id:96969), Jaku(id:19733), Jyb(id:160462), Wakkubox(id:30396), まったけ(id:130042), 三菱善次郎(id:21924), Yfuruhata(id:20926), 横東イン(id:141805), Sea of Japan(id:3230), ののっく(id:130566), 1029man(id:93235), Jade0416(id:104181), ケッチ１１(id:24089), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>