<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都スタジアム</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Stadium</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Stadium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Stadium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都スタジアム（きょうと-）は、京都府城陽市で建設予定だった球技場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoto Stadium is a stadium that was planned to be built in Joyo City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Stadium was planned to be built in Joyo City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Stadium was planned to be built in Joyo City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>仮称・木津川右岸スタジアム。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tentative name was the Kizugawa Ugan Stadium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tentative name was the Kizugawa Ugan Stadium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tentative name was the Kizugawa Ugan Stadium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>2002年に開催された2002 FIFAワールドカップの開催会場として建設される予定だったが、京都府が開催地から外れるなどしたため、計画自体が凍結された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stadium was scheduled to be constructed as the venue for the 2002 FIFA World Cup, which was cancelled because the Kyoto Prefecture was not selected as a host city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stadium was scheduled to be constructed as the venue for the 2002 FIFA World Cup, which was cancelled because Kyoto Prefecture was not selected as a host city.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stadium was scheduled to be constructed as the venue for the 2002 FIFA World Cup, which was cancelled because Kyoto Prefecture was not selected as a host city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>W杯の開催地に立候補した京都府は、城陽市の木津川 (京都府)右岸地域に、4万人程度が収容できる国際試合規格のサッカー専用スタジアムを建設することを計画していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bidding to host the World Cup, the Kyoto Prefecture planned to build a soccer-specific stadium which met the standard for the international games and could accommodate about 40,000 people on the right bank of the Kizu-gawa River in Joyo City (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bidding to host the World Cup, the Kyoto Prefecture planned to build a soccer-specific stadium which met the standard for the international games and could accommodate about 40,000 people on the right bank of the Kizu-gawa River in Joyo City (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bidding to host the World Cup, the Kyoto Prefecture planned to build a soccer-specific stadium which met the standard for the international games and could accommodate about 40,000 people on the right bank of the Kizu-gawa River in Joyo City (Kyoto Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかしW杯が大韓民国との共同開催となり、日本で開催地に立候補していた15自治体から開催地を10に絞り込む作業が行われた結果、京都府は落選した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After it had been decided, however, that Japan and Republic of Korea would jointly host the World Cup, 15 Japanese municipalities wishing to host the World Cup were narrowed down to 10 and the Kyoto Prefecture was eliminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After it had been decided, however, that Japan and Republic of Korea would jointly host the World Cup, 15 Japanese municipalities wishing to host the World Cup were narrowed down to 10 and Kyoto Prefecture was eliminated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After it had been decided, however, that Japan and Republic of Korea would jointly host the World Cup, 15 Japanese municipalities wishing to host the World Cup were narrowed down to 10 and Kyoto Prefecture was eliminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>府はその後、2008年開催のオリンピック誘致を目指した大阪府大阪市の大阪オリンピック構想に対応するため、サッカー競技の開催地として建設計画を見直し、スタンドの規模を3万人収容に縮小して建設することを一旦発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the prefecture once announced that it would respond to the Osaka Olympic Initiative of Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture, aimed at hosting the Olympic Games in 2008, by redesigning and downsizing the construction plan and building a stadium for the Olympic Football Tournament with 30,000 seats.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the prefecture once announced that it would respond to the Osaka Olympic Initiative of Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture, aimed at hosting the Olympic Games in 2008, by redesigning and downsizing the construction plan and building a stadium for the Olympic Football Tournament with 30,000 seats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the prefecture once announced that it would respond to the Osaka Olympic Initiative of Osaka City, Osaka Prefecture, aimed at hosting the Olympic Games in 2008, by redesigning and downsizing the construction plan and building a stadium for the Olympic Football Tournament with 30,000 seats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし、財政難に加え、大阪がオリンピック開催地から落選するなどしたことから、建設計画そのものが凍結となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, because of the financial difficulties as well as the fact that Osaka lost the bid for the Olympics, the construction plan itself was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, because of financial difficulties as well as the fact that Osaka lost the bid for the Olympics, the construction plan itself was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, because of financial difficulties as well as the fact that Osaka lost the bid for the Olympics, the construction plan itself was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="9">
<j>なおその後、京都市をホームタウンとする京都サンガF.C.の新たなホームスタジアムとして、京都市が横大路運動公園内に、球技専用のスタジアムを建設する構想を発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Kyoto City unveiled its plan to build a ball game stadium in the Yokooji Sports Park to use as a new home stadium of the Kyoto Sanga F.C. based in the Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Kyoto City unveiled its plan to build a ball game stadium at Yokooji Sports Park to use as a new home stadium of the Kyoto Sanga F.C. based inKyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kyoto City unveiled its plan to build a ball game stadium at Yokooji Sports Park to use as a new home stadium of the Kyoto Sanga F.C. based in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="10">
<j>2005年、京都市等によりスタジアム検討委員会が設置され、横大路運動公園ではアクセスの問題を解決するにあたり京阪電気鉄道の新駅を建設する必要がある等の問題があり、実現は2020年頃となるであろうと発表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stadium review committee which was organized by the Kyoto City and others in 2005 announced that the stadium would not be completed until around 2020 because measures had to be taken to improve the access to the Yokooji Sports Park, such as opening a new station of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A stadium review committee which was organized by Kyoto City and others in 2005 announced that the stadium would not be completed until around 2020 because measures had to be taken to improve the access to Yokooji Sports Park, such as opening a new station of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A stadium review committee which was organized by Kyoto City and others in 2005 announced that the stadium would not be completed until around 2020 because measures had to be taken to improve the access to Yokooji Sports Park, such as opening a new station of the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、横大路では新スタジアムの建設は困難であるとの判断となり、現実問題として京都市西京極総合運動公園陸上競技場兼球技場の改修を目指す方向で検討が進んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But they eventually concluded that it was difficult to build a new stadium in Yokooji and the more realistic idea of renovating the Kyoto Nishikyogoku Athletic Stadium is now being studied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But they eventually concluded that it was difficult to build a new stadium in Yokooji and the more realistic idea of renovating Kyoto Nishikyogoku Athletic Stadium is now being studied.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But they eventually concluded that it was difficult to build a new stadium in Yokooji and the more realistic idea of renovating Kyoto Nishikyogoku Athletic Stadium is now being studied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="12">
<j>その際、スタンドを可動席とすることで、臨場感を確保する案も発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this regard, the idea of installing movable seats to offer the sense of presence was announced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this regard, the idea of installing movable seats to offer the sense of presence was announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this regard, the idea of installing movable seats to offer the sense of presence was announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), MASA(id:2399), Championship2006(id:38664), Jaku(id:19733), レギオン(id:118724), Hitam1200(id:9578), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>