<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>舞鶴赤レンガ倉庫群</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Red Brick Warehouses</e>
<cmt>These buildings were built by the Japanese Navy as part of the Maizuru Naval Station. As brick buildings are a relative rarity in Japan, the place is said to feel like being in a foreign country</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Red Brick Warehouses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Red Brick Warehouses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>舞鶴赤レンガ倉庫群（まいづるあかレンガそうこぐん）は、京都府舞鶴市の旧舞鶴海軍軍需部本部地区（現・舞鶴港ウォーターフロント）にある12棟の赤煉瓦倉庫。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Red Brick Warehouses&quot; are 12 red brick warehouses located at former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Headquarters site (舞鶴海軍軍需部本部地区) (present Maizuru Port Waterfront) in Maizuru city, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>舞鶴海軍軍需部本部→Maizuru Imperial Navy Ordnance Corps Headquarters[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Red Brick Warehouses&quot; are 12 red brick warehouses located at the former headquarters of the Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps (舞鶴海軍軍需部本部地区) (now Maizuru Port Waterfront) in Maizuru city, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「The」挿入x2, 「headquarters of the」挿入,「Headquarters site」削除, 「present」→「now」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Red Brick Warehouses&quot; are 12 red brick warehouses located at the former headquarters of the Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps (舞鶴海軍軍需部本部地区) (now Maizuru Port Waterfront) in Maizuru city, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>北吸赤れんが倉庫群とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also called &quot;Kitasui Red Brick Warehouses.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called &quot;Kitasui Red Brick Warehouses.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called &quot;Kitasui Red Brick Warehouses.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>国の重要文化財および近代化産業遺産。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are Important Cultural Properties and a site of Heritage of Industrial Modernization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are Important Cultural Properties and a Heritage of Industrial Modernization site.</e>
<cmt>「site」箇所異動</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are Important Cultural Properties and a Heritage of Industrial Modernization site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1901年（明治34年）に舞鶴の地に舞鶴鎮守府が創設され、明治・大正時代を通じて大日本帝国海軍によって建てられた赤煉瓦造りの建築物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Japanese Navy had built red brick buildings through Meiji and Taisho Periods since Maizuru Chinjufu (Maizuru Naval District) was established in Maizuru in 1901.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Japanese Navy built red brick buildings throughout the Meiji and Taisho Periods, since Maizuru Chinjufu (Maizuru Naval District) was established in Maizuru in 1901.</e>
<cmt>「The」挿入, 「had」削除,「through」→「throughout the」,「,」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Japanese Navy built red brick buildings throughout the Meiji and Taisho periods, since Maizuru Chinjufu (Maizuru Naval District) was established in Maizuru in 1901.</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>なかでも、舞鶴市の東舞鶴・北吸地区に現存する倉庫群は12棟で、建造年代は1901年（明治34年）から1903年（明治36年）の明治期にかけて9棟建てられ、1918年（大正6年）から1921年（大正9年）の大正期にかけて3棟建てられたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among surviving 12 warehouses at Kitasui area of Higashi-maizuru, Maizuru City, nine warehouses were built during the period from1901 to 1903 in Meiji Era, and three were built during the period from 1918 to 1921 in Taisho Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the surviving 12 warehouses in the Kitasui area of Higashi-Maizuru, Maizuru City, nine warehouses were built during the period from 1901 to 1903 in the Meiji Era, and three were built between 1918 and 1921 in the Taisho Era.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入x3, 「at」→「in the」, 「Higashi-maizuru」→「Higashi-Maizuru」,「during the period from 1918 to 1921」→「between 1918 and 1921」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the surviving twelve warehouses in the Kitasui area of Higashi-Maizuru, Maizuru City, nine warehouses were built during the period from 1901 to 1903 in the Meiji period, and three were built between 1918 and 1921 in the Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>era →period としました。この文章中の西暦と年号ですが、合っていないようです。大正7年＝1918, 大正9年＝1920です。このセルは西暦のみをそのまま記載していますが、以降原文が年号で表されている箇所は、翻訳では全て正しい西暦に修正してあります。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">List</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">List</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">List</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠魚形水雷庫 - 明治36年竣工、現・赤れんが博物館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Fish-typeTorpedo Warehouse: completed in1903, present World Brick Museum</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠魚形水雷庫→The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Torpedo Warehouse[定訳不明, http://www.pref.kyoto.jp/visitkyoto/en/theme/sites/museums/brick/]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Fish-type Torpedo Warehouse: completed in 1903, now the World Brick Museum</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now the」, spaces added x2.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Fish-type Torpedo Warehouse: completed in 1903, now the World Brick Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠雑品庫並損兵器庫 - 明治35年竣工、現・舞鶴市政記念館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse: completed in1902, present Maizuru City Commemoration Hall</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠雑品庫並損兵器庫→The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse: completed in 1902, now Maizuru City Commemoration Hall</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」, space added, space removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse: completed in 1902, now Maizuru City Commemoration Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠弾丸庫並小銃庫 - 明治35年竣工、現・まいづる智恵蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Bullets and Rifles Warehouse: completed in1902, present Maizuru Wisdom Warehouse</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠弾丸庫並小銃庫→The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Bullets and Rifles Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Bullets and Rifles Warehouse: completed in 1902, now Maizuru Wisdom Warehouse</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」, space added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Bullets and Rifles Warehouse: completed in 1902, now Maizuru Wisdom Warehouse</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠予備艦兵器庫 - 明治35年竣工、現・舞鶴倉庫北吸六号倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Spare Warship Weapons Warehouse: completed in1902, present Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. Kitasui Warehouse No.6</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠予備艦兵器庫→The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Spare Warship Weapons Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Spare Warship Weapons Warehouse: completed in 1902, now Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. Kitasui Warehouse No.6</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」, space added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Spare Warship Weapons Warehouse: completed in 1902, now Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. Kitasui Warehouse No.6</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第三水雷庫 - 大正7年竣工、現・舞鶴倉庫北吸七号倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Torpedo Warehouse: completed in 1919, present Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. Kitasui Warehouse No.7</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第三水雷庫→The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Torpedo Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Torpedo Warehouse: completed in 1919, now Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. Kitasui Warehouse No.7</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Torpedo Warehouse: completed in 1918, now Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. Kitasui Warehouse No.7</e>
<cmt>1918 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需庫需品倉庫 - 明治35年竣工、現・近畿財務局倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in1902, present Kinki Finance Bureau&apos;s warehouse</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍軍需庫需品倉庫→The old Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1902, now owned by the Kinki Finance Bureau</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now owned by the」,「&apos;s warehouse」削除, space added. The following two sentences are identical. If they are three separate warehouses, it may be better to start with &apos;One of the three former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouses&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1902, now owned by the Kinki Finance Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需庫需品倉庫 - 明治35年竣工、現・近畿財務局倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in1902, present Kinki Finance Bureau&apos;s warehouse</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1902, now owned by the Kinki Finance Bureau</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now owned by the」,「&apos;s warehouse」削除, space added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1902, now owned by the Kinki Finance Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需庫需品倉庫 - 明治35年竣工、現・近畿財務局倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in1902, present Kinki Finance Bureau&apos;s warehouse</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1902, now owned by the Kinki Finance Bureau</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now owned by the」,「&apos;s warehouse」削除, space added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1902, now owned by the Kinki Finance Bureau</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第一需品庫 - 大正8年竣工、現・海上自衛隊舞鶴補給所No.17倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps First Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1920, present Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.17</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第一需品庫→The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps First Munitions Warehouse[定訳不明]海上自衛隊舞鶴補給所No.17倉庫→Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.17[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps First Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1920, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.17</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps First Munitions Warehouse: completed in 1919, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.17</e>
<cmt>1919 としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍経理部衣料科被服庫 - 明治34年竣工、現・海上自衛隊舞鶴補給所No.3倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse: completed in1901, present Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.3</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍経理部衣料科被服庫→The old Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse: completed in 1901, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.3</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」, space added, space removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse: completed in 1901, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.3</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍経理部衣料科被服庫 - 明治34年竣工、現・海上自衛隊舞鶴補給所No.2倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse: completed in1901, present Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse: completed in 1901, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.2</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」, space added, space removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Accounting Division Clothes Warehouse: completed in 1901, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.2</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第三被服庫 - 大正10年竣工、現・海上自衛隊舞鶴補給所No.4倉庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Clothes Warehouse: completed in1922, present Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.4</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第三被服庫→The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Clothes Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Clothes Warehouse: completed in 1922, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.4</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」, 「present」→「now」, space added.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Third Clothes Warehouse: completed in 1921, now Maritime Self-Defense Force Maizuru Depot Warehouse No.4</e>
<cmt>1921としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>現在</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>1903年（明治36年）に建てられた旧舞鶴海軍兵器廠魚形水雷庫であったものが現在は赤れんが博物館として活用されている他、旧雑品庫並損兵器庫も現在は舞鶴市政記念館として活用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Fish-typeTorpedo Warehouse built in1903 is now used as World Brick Museum, and the old Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse is used as Maizuru City Commemoration Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Fish-type Torpedo Warehouse, built in 1903, now forms the World Brick Museum, and the former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse is currently used as Maizuru City Commemoration Hall.</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」x2, 「,」挿入x2,「is now used as」→「now forms the」, spaces removed,「currently」挿入.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Fish-type Torpedo Warehouse, built in 1903, now forms the World Brick Museum, and the former Maizuru Naval Arsenal Miscellaneous Articles and Damaged Weapons Warehouse is currently used as Maizuru City Commemoration Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>さらに2007年（平成19年）4月には、舞鶴市政記念館横の一棟が、まいづる智恵蔵として建設当時の姿を再現した形でリニューアルオープンした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in April 2007, one warehouse at the side of the Maizuru City Commemoration Hall was renovated to open as Maizuru Wisdom Warehouse restoring its original appearances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in April 2007, one warehouse at the side of the Maizuru City Commemoration Hall was renovated and reopened as Maizuru Wisdom Warehouse with its original appearance restored.</e>
<cmt>「to open」→「and reopened」, 「restoring its original appearances」→「with its original appearance restored」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in April 2007, one warehouse at the side of the Maizuru City Commemoration Hall was renovated and reopened as Maizuru Wisdom Warehouse with its original appearance restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、舞鶴倉庫が3棟を倉庫として再利用し、残りの7棟は海上自衛隊・舞鶴総監部などの倉庫として使用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. uses three warehouses, and the rest seven buildings are now warehouses of Maizuru General Directorial Division of Maritime Self-Defense Force.</e>
<cmt>総監部→General Directorial Division[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. uses three warehouses, and the remaining seven buildings are now warehouses belonging to the Maizuru General Directorial Division of the Maritime Self-Defense Force.</e>
<cmt>「rest」→「remaining」, 「of」→「belonging to the」, 「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maizuru Warehouse Co., Ltd. uses three warehouses, and the remaining seven buildings are now warehouses belonging to the Maizuru General Directorial Division of the Maritime Self-Defense Force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>このような手付かずのものは、全国的に見て大変貴重で、近代化遺産として、映画やテレビドラマのロケーションに使用される事が数多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because these old buildings staying intact are most valuable as they are rare across the country, they have been used as locations of many movies and TV dramas as a heritage of Japan&apos;s modernization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rarity of these old buildings which remain intact makes them valuable, and they have been used as the backdrop for many movies and TV dramas as they represent Japan&apos;s modernization.</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rarity of these old buildings which remain intact makes them valuable, and they have been used as the backdrop for many movies and TV dramas as they represent Japan&apos;s modernization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>近年のロケ例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of recent year location shootings at these warehouses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of movies and TV programs using the warehouses as a backdrop in recent years</e>
<cmt>再構成しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of movies and TV programs using the warehouses as a backdrop in recent years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>バルトの楽園（2006年公開、映画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Baruto no Gakuen&quot;(バルトの楽園): movie released in 2006</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Baruto no Gakuen&quot;(バルトの楽園): movie released in 2006</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Baruto no Gakuen&quot;(バルトの楽園): movie released in 2006</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>男たちの大和/YAMATO（2005年公開、映画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Otokotachi no Yamato/YAMATO&quot; (The men&apos;s Yamato): movie released in 2005</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Otokotachi no Yamato/YAMATO&quot; (The men&apos;s Yamato): movie released in 2005</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Otokotachi no Yamato/YAMATO&quot; (The men&apos;s Yamato): movie released in 2005</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>エイジアン・ブルー（1995年公開、映画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Asian Blue&quot;: a movie released in 1995</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Asian Blue&quot;: a movie released in 1995</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Asian Blue&quot;: a movie released in 1995</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>寒椿（1992年公開、映画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kantsubaki&quot;(寒椿) (Camellia in the Winter): a movie released in 1992</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kantsubaki&quot;(寒椿) (Camellia in the Winter): a movie released in 1992</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kantsubaki&quot;(寒椿) (Camellia in the Winter): a movie released in 1992</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>夜汽車（1987年公開、映画）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yogisha&quot; (The Night Train): a movie released in 1987</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yogisha&quot; (The Night Train): a movie released in 1987</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yogisha&quot; (The Night Train): a movie released in 1987</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>歴史街道 ～ロマンへの扉～（帯番組）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Rekishi Kaido - Roman eno Tobira&quot; (Historic Roads -- A Door to Romantic Adventures): TV series</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Rekishi Kaido - Roman eno Tobira&quot; (Historic Roads -- A Door to Romantic Adventures): TV series</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Rekishi Kaido - Roman eno Tobira&quot; (Historic Roads -- A Door to Romantic Adventures): TV series</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By train:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By train:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By train:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道 舞鶴線 東舞鶴駅から徒歩約15分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Higashi-Maizuru Station of JR Maizuru Line, it is approximately 15 minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Higashi-Maizuru Station on the JR Maizuru Line it is approximately 15 minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt>「of」→「on the」, 「,」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Higashi-Maizuru Station on the JR Maizuru Line it is approximately 15 minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>タクシーなら約5分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A taxi will take you there in approximately 5 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A taxi will take you there in approximately 5 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A taxi will take you there in approximately 5 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>京都駅から特別急行列車「まいづる」「タンゴディスカバリー」で約1時間30分で東舞鶴駅着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kyoto Station, Limited Express &apos;Maizuru&apos; or &apos;Tango Discovery&apos; will take you to Higashi-Maizuru Station in approximately 90 minutes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kyoto Station, the Limited Express trains &apos;Maizuru&apos; or &apos;Tango Discovery&apos; will take you to Higashi-Maizuru Station in approximately 90 minutes.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「trains」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kyoto Station, the Limited Express trains &apos;Maizuru&apos; or &apos;Tango Discovery&apos; will take you to Higashi-Maizuru Station in approximately 90 minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="34">
<j>金沢駅から特急「サンダーバード」で敦賀駅乗換え、小浜線に乗り、約2時間で東舞鶴駅着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Kanazawa Station, take Limited Express &apos;Thunderbird&apos; and at Tsuruga Station transfer to Obama Line, then it will take you approximately 2 hours to reach Higashi-Maizuru Station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kanazawa Station, take the Limited Express &apos;Thunderbird&apos; and at Tsuruga Station transfer to the Obama Line, and it will take you approximately 2 hours to reach Higashi-Maizuru Station.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入x2, 「then」→「and」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kanazawa Station, take the Limited Express &apos;Thunderbird&apos; and at Tsuruga Station transfer to the Obama Line, and it will take you approximately 2 hours to reach Higashi-Maizuru Station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>自動車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By car:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By car:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="36">
<j>舞鶴若狭自動車道 舞鶴東インターチェンジから車で約15分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Maizurunishi Interchange of Maizuru-Wakasa Expressway, it will take approximately 15 minutes by car.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Maizurunishi Interchange on the Maizuru-Wakasa Expressway it takes approximately 15 minutes by car.</e>
<cmt>「of」→「on the」, 「, it will take」→「it takes」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Maizurunishi Interchange on the Maizuru-Wakasa Expressway it takes approximately 15 minutes by car.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="37">
<j>近隣の赤レンガ建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other red brick constructions in the neighborhood</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other red brick structures in the neighborhood</e>
<cmt>「constructions」→「structures」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other red brick structures in the neighborhood</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="38">
<j>北吸浄水場 - 配水池（明治34年築）と上屋（大正15年築）が国の重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitasui josuijo (Kitasui Water Filtration Plant) - distributing reservoir (built in 1901), and Uwaya (built in 1927) are National Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitasui josuijo (Kitasui Water Filtration Plant), a distributing reservoir (built in 1901), and Uwaya (built in 1927) are National Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>「-」→「, a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitasui josuijo (Kitasui Water Filtration Plant), a distributing reservoir (built in 1901), and Uwaya (built in 1926) are National Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>1926　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>旧軍港引込線北吸隧道 - 明治37年築、国登録有形文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitasui Tunnel of the old Naval Port Railroad Spur (built in 1904): National Registered Tangible Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitasui Tunnel on the old Naval Port Railroad Spur (built in 1904): National Registered Tangible Cultural Property</e>
<cmt>「of」→「on」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitasui Tunnel on the old Naval Port Railroad Spur (built in 1904): National Registered Tangible Cultural Property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第二気発油庫 - 明治35年築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Second Flammable Oil Warehouse: built in 1902</e>
<cmt>旧舞鶴海軍軍需部第二気発油庫→The old Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Second Flammable Oil Warehouse[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Second Flammable Oil Warehouse: built in 1902</e>
<cmt>「old」→「former」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Maizuru Navy Ordnance Corps Second Flammable Oil Warehouse: built in 1902</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), 竃馬(id:102733), Tmizuk(id:38161), ぱむ(id:24323), ポピュラーポプラ(id:157724), 663highland(id:18755), Ikespirit(id:120987), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>