<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蛤御門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hamaguri-Gomon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hamaguri-Gomon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hamaguri-Gomon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蛤御門（はまぐりごもん）は、現在の京都御苑西門の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hamaguri-Gomon gate is one of the west gates of Kyoto Gyoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hamaguri-Gomon gate is one of the west gates of Kyoto Gyoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hamaguri-Gomon Gate is one of the west gates of Kyoto Gyoen National Garden.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本来の正式名称は新在家御門であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official name of the gate originally was the Shinzaike-Gomon Gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official name of the gate originally was the Shinzaike-Gomon Gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official name of the gate originally was the Shinzaike-Gomon Gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>門の形状は高麗門型の筋鉄門である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gate is a sujigane-mon (iron girder gate) of the Korai-mon Gate style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gate is a sujigane-mon (iron girder gate) of the Korai-mon Gate style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gate is a sujigane-mon (iron girder gate) of the Korai-mon Gate style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>光格天皇の時に発生した天明の京都大火において御所が炎上した折に、滅多に開かなかったこの門がこの時だけは開いたというので蛤のような門、転じて蛤御門という俗称が付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gate came to be called by its nickname &apos;Hamaguri-Gomon Gate&apos; because it was the gate that rarely opened but it opened like a hamaguri (clam) when the imperial palace burned in the Great Kyoto Fire of the Tenmei period during the reign of Emperor Kokaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gate came to be called by its nickname &apos;Hamaguri-Gomon Gate&apos; because it was the gate that rarely opened, but it opened like a hamaguri (clam) when the imperial palace burned in the Great Kyoto Fire of the Tenmei period during the reign of Emperor Kokaku.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gate came to be called by its nickname Hamaguri-Gomon Gate because it was the gate that rarely opened, but it opened like a hamaguri (clam) when the imperial palace burned in the Great Kyoto Fire of the Tenmei period during the reign of Emperor Kokaku.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションをのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>結局今日まで正式名称となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has ended up being its official name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s name ended up being official.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s name ended up being official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>蛤御門の変では会津藩・桑名藩・薩摩藩連合軍の防衛拠点として位置づけられ、現在でも当時の弾痕を確認することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gate was the defense base for the Aizu, Kuwana, and Satsuma allied clans during the Conspiracy of Hamaguri-Gomon Gate, and the gate still has bullet marks made at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gate was the defense base for the Aizu, Kuwana, and Satsuma allied clans during the Conspiracy of Hamaguri-Gomon Gate, and the gate still has bullet holes made at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gate was the defense base for the Aizu, Kuwana, and Satsuma allied clans during the Conspiracy of Hamaguri-Gomon Gate, and the gate still has bullet holes made at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Korokoro(id:42329), 上田隼人(id:23104), ムカイ(id:72972), Takuan(id:29385), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>