<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>衣笠球場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinugasa Stadium</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinugasa Stadium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinugasa Stadium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>衣笠球場（きぬがさきゅうじょう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinugasa Stadium</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinugasa Stadium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinugasa Stadium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>かつて京都府京都市にあった野球場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a baseball stadium that used to be in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a baseball stadium that used to be in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A baseball stadium that used to be in Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>本項で詳述。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section describes the details of this stadium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section describes the details of this stadium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section describes the details of this stadium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>長崎県長崎市（旧三和町）元宮公園にある野球場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a baseball stadium in Motomiya Park in Nagasaki City (former Miwa-cho), Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a baseball stadium in Motomiya Park in Nagasaki City (former Miwa-cho), Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A baseball stadium in Motomiya Park in Nagasaki City (former Miwa-cho), Nagasaki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>衣笠祥雄に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stadium was named after Sachio KINUGASA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stadium was named after Sachio KINUGASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stadium was named after Sachio KINUGASA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>衣笠球場（きぬがさきゅうじょう）はかつて京都府京都市上京区（その後分区され、この地域は現在の北区 (京都市)に当たる）にあった野球場である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinugasa Stadium was a baseball stadium that used to be in Kamigyo Ward (the ward was later divided, and the area where the stadium once stood is in today&apos;s Kita Ward (Kyoto City)), Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinugasa Stadium was a baseball stadium that used to be in Kamigyo Ward (the ward was later divided, and the area where the stadium once stood is in today&apos;s Kita Ward - Kyoto City), Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinugasa Stadium was a baseball stadium that used to be in Kamigyo Ward (the ward was later divided, and the area where the stadium once stood is in today&apos;s Kita Ward, Kyoto City), Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>1946年、立命館専門学校工学科（立命館大学理工学部の前身）と同校馬術講習所の一部を開墾して造成を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the stadium began in 1946 on the cleared site which had been parts of the Department of Engineering, Ritsumeikan Vocational School (a predecessor of the College of Science and Engineering, Ritsumeikan University) and a horse riding school of the Ritsumeikan Vocational School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction of the stadium began in 1946 on a cleared site that had been part of the Department of Engineering, Ritsumeikan Vocational School (a predecessor of the College of Science and Engineering, Ritsumeikan University) and a horse riding school of the Ritsumeikan Vocational School.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction of the stadium began in 1946 on a cleared site that had been part of the Department of Engineering, Ritsumeikan Vocational School (a predecessor of the College of Science and Engineering, Ritsumeikan University) and a horse riding school of the Ritsumeikan Vocational School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1948年8月31日、立命館大学硬式野球部の専用球場として開設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 31, 1948, the stadium was opened as a stadium for Ritsumeikan University&apos;s baseball team.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 31, 1948, the stadium was opened as a stadium for Ritsumeikan University&apos;s baseball team.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 31, 1948, the stadium was opened as a stadium for Ritsumeikan University&apos;s baseball team.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>朝日新聞が立命館百年史編纂室に取材したところ、設立当初は立命館衣笠球場と呼ばれていたという（2008年11月16日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsumeikan 100-year History Compilation Office told the Asahi Shinbun that the stadium was called Ritsumeikan Kinugasa Stadium at its inception (November 16, 2008).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ritsumeikan 100-year History Compilation Office told the Asahi Shinbun that the stadium was called Ritsumeikan Kinugasa Stadium at its inception (November 16, 2008).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ritsumeikan 100-year History Compilation Office told the Asahi Shinbun that the stadium was called Ritsumeikan Kinugasa Stadium at its inception (November 16, 2008).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>京都市西京極総合運動公園野球場と並んで昭和戦後初期の京都府の主力球場として、建設翌年より大陽ロビンス戦を中心にプロ野球の公式戦でも使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinugasa Stadium, as well as the Nishikyogoku Baseball Stadium, is a main stadium in Kyoto Prefecture in the Showa early postwar period, and the stadium was also used for official games of professional baseball teams such as Taiyo Robins from the year following its construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinugasa Stadium, as well as the Nishikyogoku Baseball Stadium, is a main stadium in Kyoto Prefecture in the Showa early postwar period, and the stadium was also used for official games of professional baseball teams such as Taiyo Robins from the year following its construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinugasa Stadium, as well as the Nishikyogoku Baseball Stadium, is a main stadium in Kyoto Prefecture in early postwar period after 1945, and the stadium was also used for official games of professional baseball teams such as Taiyo Robins from the year following its construction.</e>
<cmt>和暦を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1950年には京都市を発祥地とする映画会社松竹がスポンサーとなって大陽ロビンスからチーム名を改めた松竹ロビンスの本拠地球場として使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Shochiku Co., Ltd., a film company that originated in Kyoto City, became the sponsor of Taiyo Robins in 1950, the team changed its name to Shochiku Robins and was based at the Kinugasa Stadium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Shochiku Co., Ltd., a film company that originated in Kyoto City, became the sponsor of Taiyo Robins in 1950, the team changed its name to Shochiku Robins and was based at Kinugasa Stadium.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Shochiku Co., Ltd., a film company that originated in Kyoto City, became the sponsor of Taiyo Robins in 1950, the team changed its name to Shochiku Robins and was based at Kinugasa Stadium.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし同年9月完成の大阪球場に1951年にナイター設備が完成すると、大阪球場での主催試合が増えてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Osaka Staidum was completed in September of that year, was fully equipped for night games in 1951, and hosted more games.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Osaka Staidum was completed in September of that year, was fully equipped for night games in 1951, and hosted more games.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Osaka Stadium was completed in September of the same year, was fully equipped for night games in 1951, and hosted more games.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため、プロ野球での使用はわずか数年で終わってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the Kinugasa Stadium was used by professional baseball teams only for several years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the Kinugasa Stadium was used by professional baseball teams only for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the Kinugasa Stadium was used by professional baseball teams only for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、松竹ロビンスが横浜ベイスターズに吸収され洋松ロビンスとなった1953年～1954年にかけては、実質的な準本拠地球場として使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Shochiku Robins was taken over by the YOKOHAMA BayStars to become the Yosho Robins from 1953 to 1954, the team used the Kinugasa Stadium, in effect, as a second home field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shochiku Robins was taken over by the YOKOHAMA BayStars to become Yosho Robins from 1953 to 1954, the team used the Kinugasa Stadium, in effect, as a second home field.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shochiku Robins was taken over by the YOKOHAMA BayStars to become Yosho Robins from 1953 to 1954, the team used the Kinugasa Stadium, in effect, as a second home field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>昭和30年代から40年代半ばにかけて、徐々に外野芝生席、一塁側内野スタンド、バックネット裏スタンドやフィールド自体も取り壊されて、やがて体育授業用のグランドや大学の建造物の敷地や広場や通路となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1955 to around 1969, grass bleachers, first-base stands, the stands behind the backstop, and the field itself were gradually demolished, and later replaced by the physical-education grounds, university&apos;s buildings, yards and passageways.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1955 to around 1969, grass bleachers, first-base stands, the stands behind the backstop, and the field itself were gradually demolished, and later replaced by physical-education grounds, university buildings, yards and passageways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1955 to around 1969, grass bleachers, first-base stands, the stands behind the backstop, and the field itself were gradually demolished, and later replaced by physical-education grounds, university buildings, yards and passageways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>現在は立命館大学衣笠キャンパスの一部として整備されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The site is now maintained as part of the Ritsumeikan University Kinugasa Campus.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The site is now maintained as part of the Ritsumeikan University Kinugasa Campus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The site is now maintained as part of the Ritsumeikan University Kinugasa Campus.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>かつての衣笠球場は、現在の第一体育館・学生会館・存心館・中央広場などの付近に位置し、第一体育館の南東辺りにホームベースがあったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kinugasa Stadium used to stand near where the Gymnasium 1, Student Center, Zonshinkan Hall, Central Square, and other facilities are located today, and the home plate is thought to have been placed somewhere to the southeast of Gymnasium 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kinugasa Stadium used to stand near where the Gymnasium 1, Student Center, Zonshinkan Hall, Central Square, and other facilities are located today, and the home plate is thought to have been placed somewhere to the southeast of Gymnasium 1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kinugasa Stadium used to stand near where the Gymnasium 1, Student Center, Zonshinkan Hall, Central Square, and other facilities are located today, and the home plate is thought to have been placed somewhere to the southeast of Gymnasium 1.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>周辺の電柱には、現在も「衣笠球場」と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Telephone poles around the site are labeled &quot;Kinugasa Stadium&quot; even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Telephone poles around the site are labeled &quot;Kinugasa Stadium&quot; even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Telephone poles around the site are labeled &apos;Kinugasa Stadium&apos; even today.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 大日本東京野球倶楽部(id:54102), Teru2005(id:15878), March Hare(id:256777), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), 崎宏(id:64519), Lcccn(id:48948), MASA(id:2399), 経済準学士(id:22656), Be jiro(id:213945), まったけ(id:130042), 春野秋葉(id:36725), 旅人の風(id:178849), Amikake3(id:89826), Suisui(id:69), Longlongsummer(id:211232), Himetv(id:21833), 独自路線組合(id:153732), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>