<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>花の御所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hana no gosho Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hana no gosho Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hana no gosho Palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>花の御所（はなの ごしょ）は、現在の京都市上京区の烏丸通・今出川通・上立売通・室町通に囲まれた東西一町南北二町の足利将軍家の邸宅の通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hana no gosho Palace is a popular name for the Ashikaga Shogun family residence which stretched over a space of 110 meters from east to west and 220 meters from north to south, which is surrounded by the current Karasuma-dori Street, Imadegawa-dori Street, Kamidachiuri-dori Street and Muromachi-dori Street in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hana no gosho Palace is a popular name for the Ashikaga Shogun family residence that stretched over a space of 110 meters from east to west and 220 meters from north to south, surrounded by the current Karasuma-dori Street, Imadegawa-dori Street, Kamidachiuri-dori Street and Muromachi-dori Street in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hana no gosho Palace is a popular name for the Ashikaga Shogun family residence that stretched over a space of 110 meters from east to west and 220 meters from north to south, surrounded by the current Karasuma-dori Street, Imadegawa-dori Street, Kamidachiuri-dori Street and Muromachi-dori Street in Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>一町110メートルで計算しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>室町家の花亭と、今出川家の菊亭を併せて一つの敷地としたため広大な敷地を有する邸宅となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It came to hold a large piece of land as the land of two residences, Hanatei (literally, flower residence) of the Muromachi family and Kikutei (literally, chrysanthemum residence) of the Imadegawa family, was merged together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This large piece of land came about because the land of two residences, Hanatei (literally, flower residence) of the Muromachi family and Kikutei (literally, chrysanthemum residence) of the Imadegawa family, were merged together.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This large piece of land came about because the land of two residences, Hanatei (literally, flower residence) of the Muromachi family and Kikutei (literally, chrysanthemum residence) of the Imadegawa family, were merged together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>現在の同志社大学今出川校地の烏丸通を挟んで向かい側の場所にある同志社大学・寒梅館以南に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located to the south of Doshisha University&apos;s Kambaikan, which is located across Karasuma-dori Street from the current Doshisha University Imadegawa Campus.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located to the south of Doshisha University&apos;s Kambaikan, across Karasuma-dori Street from the current Doshisha University Imadegawa Campus.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located to the south of Doshisha University&apos;s Kanbaikan, across Karasuma-dori Street from the current Doshisha University Imadegawa Campus.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>なごりとしては、邸内に建てられた岡松殿に始まる大聖寺が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of the palace&apos;s existing remains is the current Daisho-ji Temple, which started as Okamatsu dono (one of the buildings inside Hana no gosho Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A part of the palace&apos;s existing remains is the current Daisho-ji Temple, that started as Okamatsu dono (one of the buildings inside Hana no gosho Palace).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A part of the palace&apos;s existing remains is the current Daisho-ji Temple, that started as Okamatsu dono (one of the buildings inside Hana no gosho Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>室町通に面して正門が設けられたことから室町殿、室町第とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its main gate faced Muromachi-dori Street, it was also called &quot;Muromachi dono Palace&quot; and &quot;Muromachi dai Palace.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the main gate faced Muromachi-dori Street, it was also called &quot;Muromachi dono Palace&quot; and &quot;Muromachi dai Palace.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the main gate faced Muromachi-dori Street, it was also called Muromachi dono Palace and Muromachi dai Palace.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>古くより将軍の居所は「幕府」と呼ばれる事があり、すなわち「室町幕府」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a long-standing practice to call the residence of shogun &apos;bakufu,&apos; that is to say &apos;the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a long-standing practice to call it the residence of shogun &apos;bakufu,&apos; that is to say &apos;the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a long-standing practice to call it the residence of shogun &apos;bakufu,&apos; that is to say &apos;the Muromachi bakufu&apos; (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代中期より武家政権の名前として幕府の用語が使われるようになり、足利家の政権を「室町幕府」と呼称するのはこれに由来している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the mid Edo period, the term &quot;bakufu&quot; started to be used as a name of the samurai government, and this is the reason why the Ashikaga government is called &apos;the Muromachi bakufu&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the mid Edo period, the term &quot;bakufu&quot; started to be used as a name of the samurai government, and this is the reason why the Ashikaga government is called &apos;the Muromachi bakufu&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the mid Edo period, the term &quot;bakufu&quot; started to be used as a name of the samurai government, and this is the reason why the Ashikaga government is called &apos;the Muromachi bakufu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また北小路室町にあることから北小路亭とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it stood in Kitakoji Muromachi, it was also called Kitakojitei (Kitakoji residence).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it stood in Kitakoji Muromachi, it was also called Kitakojitei (Kitakoji residence).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it stood in Kitakoji Muromachi, it was also called Kitakojitei (Kitakoji residence).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ちなみに北小路とは現在の今出川通のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, Kitakoji is the current Imadegawa-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, Kitakoji is the current Imadegawa-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, Kitakoji is the current Imadegawa-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)、後醍醐天皇と対立して京都に武家政権を開いた足利尊氏は、北朝 (日本)を後見するため二条通高倉通に住み、2代将軍の足利義詮は三条坊門に住んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Takauji ASHIKAGA, confronting the Emperor Godaigo, established a samurai government in Kyoto and, while he lived on the Nijo-dori Takakura-dori to act as a guardian for the Northern Dynasty (Japan), the Second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA lived in Sanjo bomon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, Takauji ASHIKAGA, confronting Emperor Godaigo, established a samurai government in Kyoto and, while he lived on the Nijo-dori Takakura-dori to act as a guardian for the Northern Dynasty (Japan), the Second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA lived in Sanjo bomon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Takauji ASHIKAGA, confronting Emperor Godaigo, established a samurai government in Kyoto and, while he lived on the Nijo-dori Takakura-dori to act as a guardian for the Northern Court (Japan), the Second Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA lived in Sanjo bomon.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>花の御所と足利家との関係は足利義詮に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The connection between Hana no gosho Palace and the Ashikaga family began with Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The connection between Hana no gosho Palace and the Ashikaga family began with Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The connection between Hana no gosho Palace and the Ashikaga family began with Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>義詮は、室町季顕から、その邸宅である花亭を買上げ別邸とし、のちに足利家より崇光上皇に献上された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira bought Sueaki MUROMACHI&apos;s residence, Hatatei, as his second residence and it was later offered to the retired Emperor Suko from the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>室町季顕は、読み方が不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira bought Sueaki MUROMACHI&apos;s residence, Hatatei, as his second residence and it was later offered to the retired Emperor Suko from the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira bought Sueaki MUROMACHI&apos;s residence, Hatatei, as his second residence and it was later offered to the Retired Emperor Suko from the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。読みを確認しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>崇光上皇の御所となったことにより花亭は「花の御所」と呼ばれるようになったが、しばらくして使用されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hanatei became the gosho (Imperial Palace) of the retired Emperor Suko, people began to call it &apos;Hana no gosho Palace&apos; but soon it dropped out of use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Hanatei became the gosho (Imperial Palace) of the retired Emperor Suko, people began to call it the &apos;Hana no gosho Palace&apos; but soon it dropped out of use.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Hanatei became the gosho (Imperial Palace) of the Retired Emperor Suko, people began to call it the &apos;Hana no gosho Palace&apos; but soon it dropped out of use.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>3代将軍となった足利義満は1378年（天授4年/永和4年）に北小路通室町通の崇光天皇の御所跡と今出川公直の邸宅である菊亭の焼失跡地を併せた敷地（東西1町、南北2町）に足利家の邸宅の造営をはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1378, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun, started to build a new residence for the Ashikaga family in grounds stretching over a space of 110 meters from east to west and 220 meters from north to south, which included both sites of the Emperor Suko&apos;s gosho on Kitakoji-dori Muromachi-dori Street and of Kinnao IMADEGAWA&apos;s Kikutei, which had burned down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1378, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun, started to build a new residence for the Ashikaga family on grounds stretching over a space of 110 meters from east to west and 220 meters from north to south, which included both sites of the Emperor Suko&apos;s gosho on Kitakoji-dori Muromachi-dori Street and of Kinnao IMADEGAWA&apos;s Kikutei, which had burned down.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1378, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, the third Shogun, started to build a new residence for the Ashikaga family on grounds stretching over a space of 110 meters from east to west and 220 meters from north to south, which included both sites of the Emperor Suko&apos;s gosho on Kitakoji-dori Muromachi-dori Street and of Kinnao IMADEGAWA&apos;s Kikutei, which had burned down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1379年には寝殿が作られ、1381年に完成すると、それまでの三条坊門第から移住する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1379, the shinden (main house) was built and when the residence was completed in 1381, he moved there from the Sanjobomon dai Palace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1379, the shinden (main house) was built and when the residence was completed in 1381, he moved there from the Sanjobomon dai Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1379, the shinden (main house) was built and when the residence was completed in 1381, he moved there from the Sanjo bomon dai Palace.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>北小路通は土御門内裏に近く、敷地だけでも御所の2倍にも及ぶ規模の将軍邸は公家社会に対する義満のデモンストレーションを兼ねていたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Kitakoji-dori Street is near the Tsuchimikado dairi Palace and the Shogun&apos;s residence covered land twice as large as the gosho can be seen as Yoshimitsu showing off towards the court noble society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Kitakoji-dori Street is near Tsuchimikado dairi Palace and the Shogun&apos;s residence covered land twice as large as the gosho can be seen as Yoshimitsu showing off towards the court noble society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Kitakoji-dori Street is near Tsuchimikado dairi Palace and the Shogun&apos;s residence covered land twice as large as the gosho can be seen as Yoshimitsu showing off towards the court noble society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>庭内には鴨川 (淀川水系)から水を引き、各地の守護大名から献上された四季折々の花木を配置したと伝わり、「花の御所」とよばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in the garden, water was drawn in from the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and flowers and trees of every season offered by shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) were planted, resulting in the name &apos;Hana no gosho (literally, the flower palace).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in the garden, water was drawn in from the Kamo-gawa River (Yodo-gawa River system) and flowers and trees of every season offered by shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) were planted, resulting in the name &apos;Hana no gosho (literally, the flower palace).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in the garden, water was drawn in from the Kamo-gawa River (the Yodo-gawa River system) and flowers and trees of every season offered by shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese territorial lord) were planted, resulting in the name &apos;Hana no gosho&apos; (literally, the flower palace).</e>
<cmt>用語補足を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>義満はここに後円融天皇や関白二条師嗣などを招いて詩歌や蹴鞠の会などを催した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu held a range of events such as poetry events and kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) events, inviting the Emperor Goenyu, chief adviser to the Emperor, Morotsugu NIJO, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu held a range of events such as poetry events and kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) events, inviting the Emperor Goenyu, chief adviser to the Emperor, Morotsugu NIJO, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu held a range of events such as poetry events and kemari (a game played by aristocrats in the Heian period) events, inviting the Emperor Goenyu, kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), Morotsugu NIJO, and others.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>1394年に将軍職を息子の足利義持に譲ると、義満はここから新築した北山第（現鹿苑寺）へ移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he abdicated as Shogun in favor of his son, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA in 1394, Yoshimitsu moved from the gosho to the newly-built Kitayama dai (Kitayama residence) (the current Rokuon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he abdicated as Shogun in favor of his son, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA in 1394, Yoshimitsu moved from the gosho to the newly-built Kitayama dai (Kitayama residence) (the current Rokuon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he abdicated as Shogun in favor of his son, Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA in 1394, Yoshimitsu moved from the gosho to the newly-built Kitayama dai (Kitayama residence) (the current Rokuon-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>義満と不和であったとされる義持は義満の死後に室町第を離れるが、6代将軍の足利義教が住むなど長く将軍の邸宅であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yoshimochi, who was said to be on bad terms with Yoshimitsu, left Muromachi dai Palace after Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, the palace remained the residence of the Shogun for a long time, as the sixth Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA lived there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yoshimochi, who was said to be on bad terms with Yoshimitsu, left Muromachi dai Palace after Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, the palace remained the residence of the Shogun for a long time, as the sixth Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA lived there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yoshimochi, who was said to be on bad terms with Yoshimitsu, left Muromachi dai Palace after Yoshimitsu&apos;s death, the palace remained the residence of the Shogun for a long time, as the sixth Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA lived there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>8代将軍足利義政の頃に応仁の乱の戦火で焼失する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was burned down during the Onin war at the time of the eighth Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was burned down during the Onin war at the time of the eighth Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was burned down during the Onin War at the time of the eighth Shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、室町殿は何度か小規模なものであるが再建が繰り返されたが、13代将軍足利義輝が1559年に三管領家の斯波武衛家邸宅跡に二条御所を造営・移転したために廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Muromachi dono Palace was repeatedly rebuilt, although on a smaller scale, but it went completely out of use when the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA constructed Nijo gosho Palace in 1559 in the grounds where the residence of the Shiba Buei family, which was one of Sankanrei ke (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), and moved there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Muromachi dono Palace was repeatedly rebuilt, although on a smaller scale, but it went completely out of use when the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA constructed Nijo gosho Palace in 1559 in the grounds where the residence of the Shiba Buei family, which was one of Sankanrei ke (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), and moved there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Muromachi dono Palace was repeatedly rebuilt, although on a smaller scale, but it went completely out of use when the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA constructed Nijo gosho Palace in 1559 in the grounds where the residence of the Shiba Buei family, which was one of Sankanrei ke (three families in the post of kanrei, or shogunal deputy), and moved there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>花の御所の遺構</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remains of Hana no gosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remains of Hana no gosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remains of Hana no gosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>度重なる戦乱により幾度となく消失と再興を繰り返したため当時の建物は残っていないが、邸内に建てられた岡松殿より始まる尼門跡寺院の大聖寺が、ほぼ当時の場所に残る（元は岡松町にあったものと思われるが、現在は隣接する御所八幡町にある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After repeated destruction due to war and reconstructions, buildings from that time do not exist any more, but the Daisho-ji Temple, one of the Amamonzeki-ji Temples (a temple run by nuns of noble women), started as Okamatsu dono which was built inside the residence ground, remains on almost the same spot as in those days (Originally, it is considered to have been located in Okamatsu-cho but it is currently located in neighboring Gosho Hachiman-cho).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After repeated destruction due to war and reconstructions, the original buildings from that time do not exist any more, but the Daisho-ji Temple, one of the Amamonzeki-ji Temples (a temple run by nuns of noble women), started as Okamatsu dono which was built inside the residence ground, remains on almost the same spot as it was in those days (Originally, it is considered to have been located in Okamatsu-cho but it is currently located in neighboring Gosho Hachiman-cho).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After repeated destruction due to war and reconstructions, the original buildings from that time do not exist any more, but the Daisho-ji Temple, one of the Amamonzeki Temples (a temple run by nuns of noble women), started as Okamatsu dono which was built inside the residence ground, remains on almost the same spot as it was in those days (originally, it is considered to have been located in Okamatsu-cho Town but it is currently located in neighboring Gosho Hachiman-cho Town).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>大聖寺は足利義満が、正室の叔母（日野宣子、のちに岡松一品と称される）に花の御所内の岡松殿を与えて住まわせたことに始まるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Daisho-ji Temple began when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA gave Okamatsu dono in Hana no gosho Palace to his lawful wife&apos;s aunt (Nobuko HINO, later called Ippon OKAMATSU) as her residence.</e>
<cmt>岡松一品は、読み方が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daisho-ji Temple began when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA gave Okamatsu dono in Hana no gosho Palace to his lawful wife&apos;s aunt (Nobuko HINO, later called Ippon OKAMATSU) as her residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daisho-ji Temple began when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA gave Okamatsu dono in Hana no gosho Palace to his lawful wife&apos;s aunt (Nobuko HINO, later called Ippon OKAMATSU (岡松一品)) as her residence.</e>
<cmt>読みが確認できなかった漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Sat666(id:127263), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), PANYNJ(id:38638), Reggaeman(id:6214), Ishidashuji(id:114846), PATMAN(id:145791), Doskoi 8(id:1070), Lupinoid(id:68), VanishingDuck(id:125995), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kurz(id:1601), でここ(id:9565), Miyuki h(id:84952), VolkovBot(id:105371), 新芽(id:50924), 怪蘇(id:45514), Shimoxx(id:9332), Nalc(id:139567), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 伏儀(id:142093), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>