<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>今西家住宅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imanishi-ke Jutaku (Imanishi family&apos;s House)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imanishi-ke Jutaku (Imanishi family&apos;s House)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imanishi-ke Jutaku (Imanishi family&apos;s House)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>今西家住宅（いまにしけじゅうたく）は、重要伝統的建造物群保存地区に選定されていて奈良県の中部に位置する橿原市の今井町にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imanishi-ke Jutaku (今西家住宅) is in Imai-cho of Kashihara City which has been selected for Preservation Districts for Groups of Historic Buildings and is located in the central part of Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿は「選定されているの中部に」となっていたので、「の中部に」の前に「奈良県」を補って「選定されていて奈良県の中部に」と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imanishi-ke Jutaku is located in Imai-cho, Kashihara City, which has been selected as one of the Preservation Districts for Groups of Historic Buildings, in the central part of Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>日本語の表記を削除。文章の小修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imanishi-ke Jutaku is located in Imai-cho, Kashihara City, which has been selected as one of the Preservation Districts for Groups of Historic Buildings, in the central part of Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>慶安3年(1650年）に建てられた城郭のような構造で複雑な屋根の葺き方から別名「八つ棟」（やつむね）または「八つ棟造り」と呼ばれている建物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was built in a structure like a castle in 1650, and is a building called in another name &quot;Yatsumune&quot; (八つ棟) or &quot;Yatsumune-zukuri&quot; (八つ棟造り, complicated roof style with multiple ridges and bargeboards) because of its complicated roofing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a castle-like structure built in 1650 being also known as Yatsumune or Yatsumune-zukuri (a complicated roof style with multiple ridges and bargeboards) because of its complex roofing design.</e>
<cmt>誤訳を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a castle-like structure built in 1650 being also known as Yatsumune or Yatsumune-zukuri (a complicated roof style with multiple ridges and bargeboards) because of its complex roofing design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>東京大学による町屋 (商家)調査を経て、1957年6月18日に棟札とともに国の重要文化財に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being investigated as a machiya (a traditional form of townhouse found mainly in Kyoto) and a shoka (mercantile house) by the University of Tokyo, it was designated as a national important cultural property as well as its munafuda (construction plaque).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 18, 1957, after a machiya (a traditional form of townhouse found mainly in Kyoto) (or shoka, merchants&apos; house) (or shoka (mercantile house)) study conducted by the University of Tokyo, with posting of a munafuda (historical plaque on a building), it was designated as an Important Cultural Property in Japan.</e>
<cmt>誤訳・訳抜けを訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 18, 1957, after a machiya (a traditional form of townhouse found mainly in Kyoto) (or shoka, merchants&apos; house) (or shoka (mercantile house)) study conducted by the University of Tokyo, with posting of a munafuda (historical plaque on a building), it was designated as an Important Cultural Property in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>文化財保護法により根本修理に着手することとなり、奈良県教育委員会が今西家から委託を受けて昭和36年3月に起工し、同37年10月に竣工した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was decided to start to repair the house fundamentally under the Law of the Protection of Cultural Properties, Nara Prefectural Board of Education, entrusted by the Imanishi family, began the work of repair in March, 1961, and completed it in October, 1962.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was decided to undertake the fundamental repairs in accordance with the Law of the Protection of Cultural Properties whereby, commissioned by the Imanishi family, Nara Prefectural Board of Education commenced the work in March 1961 which was subsequently completed in October 1962.</e>
<cmt>冗漫・誤訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was decided to undertake the fundamental repairs in accordance with the Law of the Protection of Cultural Properties whereby, commissioned by the Imanishi family, Nara Prefectural Board of Education commenced the work in March 1961 which was subsequently completed in October 1962.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>今西家住宅は、棟札と呼ばれる上棟時の年号や施主名や大工棟梁を初めとする施工関係者の名を墨書きした細長い板や、屋根の棟の端部を飾る鬼瓦に刻まれた鬼瓦銘と呼ぶ刻銘によって慶安3年の建立年代が明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is evident that the Imanishi-ke Jutaku was built in 1650, since there remain a long and narrow plaque called munafuda on which the year when the framework was completed, the name of the client, and the names of the persons concerned with the construction including the master carpenter were written in India ink, and the inscription called onigawara-mei that was inscribed on the onigawara (Japanese gargoyle roof tile) with which the ends of the ridges of the roof were decorated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is clear that the Imanishi-ke Jutaku was built in 1650 because of a long and narrow board referred to as munafuda bearing the year when the framework was completed, name of the client and the other people concerned with the construction including the master carpenter written in ink as well as an inscription referred to as onigawara-mei that was carved on the onigawara (Japanese gargoyle roof tile) that are used to decorate the ends of the roof ridges.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭・冗漫を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is clear that the Imanishi-ke Jutaku was built in 1650 because of a long and narrow board referred to as munafuda bearing the year when the framework was completed, name of the client and the other people concerned with the construction including the master carpenter written in ink as well as an inscription referred to as onigawara-mei that was carved on the onigawara (Japanese gargoyle roof tile) that are used to decorate the ends of the roof ridges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>本建物の屋根形状は別名「八つ棟造り」ともいわれ、建物の妻面には複数の屋根の稜線が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roof form of this building is called &quot;Yatsumune-zukuri&quot; in another name, and several ridgelines of the roof can be seen from the gable side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roof style of this building is also known as &quot;Yatsumune-zukuri&quot; and several roof ridgelines can be seen on the gables.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭・冗漫を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roof style of this building is also known as &quot;Yatsumune-zukuri&quot; and several roof ridgelines can be seen on the gables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>妻面から見て、屋根の稜線が数多く見える状態を重ね妻の棟数の多い建物という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The state in which many ridgelines of the roof can be seen from the gable side is said to be the building with a large number of ridges of kasane-zuma (piled-up gables).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking from the gable side, if there are many roof ridgelines, it is referred to as a building with multiple ridges and overlapping gables.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正。「重ね妻の棟数の多い建物」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking from the gable side, if there are many roof ridgelines, it is referred to as a building with multiple ridges and overlapping gables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>漆喰による柱を隠した大壁を用いた雄大な外観は、一般庶民が住まう民家というよりは城郭建築を思い起こさせる建造物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The magnificent external appearance with okabe (extended large walls) in which pillars are hidden under shikkui (white plaster) is a building structure which makes one associate with a castle architecture rather than a folk dwelling where ordinary people live.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magnificent exterior with okabe (a style of wall construction) in which posts are hidden under shikkui (white plaster) is a building structure which reminds one of a castle rather than a private residence of ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>冗漫を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magnificent exterior with okabe (a style of wall construction) in which posts are hidden under shikkui (white plaster) is a building structure which reminds one of a castle rather than a private residence of ordinary people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>現在の今井町には今西家住宅と同様に外壁を大壁で包んだ古い町並が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In present-day Imai-cho, the old townscape in which the external walls are covered with okabe like Imanishi-ke Jutaku continues, and this is because the form of the townscape of Imai-cho handed down to now which used to be prosperous from the early Edo period when the construction of the town of jinai-cho (temple villages), Imai-cho, completed through to the mid and late Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Imai-cho today, old houses with their external walls being finished in the okabe style similar to that of Imanishi-ke Jutaku remain in existence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Imai-cho today, old houses with their external walls being finished in the okabe style similar to that of Imanishi-ke Jutaku remain in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これは寺内町今井の町造りが完成した江戸初期から中期・末期に栄えた今井町の町並の形態が現在まで残されてきたわけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of the townscape of Imai-cho, which was prosperous from the early Edo period when the construction of the temple town Imai-cho was completed to the mid- and late-Edo period, has been preserved to the present.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of the townscape of Imai-cho, which was prosperous from the early Edo period when the construction of the temple town Imai-cho was completed to the mid- and late-Edo period, has been preserved to the present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>この古い町並の外周には環濠跡を現在に残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are the remains of the moats left now around this old townscape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are the ruins of a surrounding moat that still remain in the perimeter of this old townscape.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are the ruins of a surrounding moat that still remain in the perimeter of this old townscape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この環濠は巾三間（約 5.45m）を有し、同環濠を掘り上げた際の建設発生土を盛り上げて土塁を築き、東西南北に九つの門を開けていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These moats are 5.45 meters in width, and the earth generated by construction when these moats were dug up was heaped up to constitute dorui (earthen walls), with the nine gates opened on the north, south, east, and west sides,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The surrounding moat is approximately 5.45 meters in width and the earth dug up during excavation of that moat was piled up to build dorui (earthen walls) which seemed to have a total of nine gates that serviced the north, south, east and west ends of the town.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The surrounding moat is approximately 5.45 meters in width and the earth dug up during excavation of that moat was piled up to build dorui (earthen walls) which seemed to have a total of nine gates that serviced the north, south, east and west ends of the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このような環濠集落を必要としたことは、中世未明から信奉してきた一向宗への弾圧からの自衛のために町造りの形態がそのまま残されてきたわけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why the town required to be surrounded by a moat like this is that the form of the town construction was handed down as it was to defend themselves against the oppression of the Ikkoshu sect which the townspeople had believed in since the opening of the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「一向宗への石山合戦からの自衛」では「石山合戦」への言及が唐突なので、Web原稿に合わせて「一向宗への弾圧からの自衛」に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background of Imai-cho being a village surrounded by a mot goes back to the days when that town was constructed for self-defense against attack by external forces cracking down on the Ikkoshu faith which the townspeople had embraced since before dawn of medieval times and that legacy with respect to the physical layout of the town remains intact today.</e>
<cmt>意味を明瞭にするため英訳を補足してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background of Imai-cho being a village surrounded by a mot goes back to the days when that town was constructed for self-defense against attack by external forces cracking down on the Ikkoshu faith which the townspeople had embraced since before dawn of medieval times and that legacy with respect to the physical layout of the town remains intact today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>現在の今西家住宅は、1650年建立以前に本陣及び住居が築かれていたことから2度目の普請であるが、前記集落の中の西端にあって、あたかも西の天守閣といった堂々たる風格を現していたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present-day Imanishi-ke Jutaku was the second building, because before it was built in 1650 a structure for the honjin (headquarters of army) and a dwelling house had already been built, and as it was located at the westernmost position of the town, it has been handed down to now that it appeared to have a stately air as if it were the western tenshukaku (keep or tower).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the honjin (headquarters of army) and family quarter had already existed prior to its construction in 1650, the present-day Imanishi-ke Jutaku was built in the second-phase but it has been told that, situated at the westernmost of the above village, it had a commanding air of a castle tower.</e>
<cmt>意味を明瞭にするため原文を補足または重複を省略してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the honjin (headquarters of army) and family quarter had already existed prior to its construction in 1650, the present-day Imanishi-ke Jutaku was built in the second-phase but it has been told that, situated at the westernmost of the above village, it had a commanding air of a castle tower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>このようにして今井の町造りが始まり、現在の今井町に変わってきたわけであるが、なぜこのような町造りが必要であったか、または今井町のおいたちなどを述べないと、当時の今西家住宅の存在がわからないと思われるので、それらのことから先に述べることにする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While in this way the town of Imai began to be constructed and it has turned into present-day Imai-cho, because it seems that the significance of existence of the then Imanishi-ke Jutaku cannot be understood, unless it is explained why the town needed to be constructed in this way or what was the history of Imai-cho, we will explain these first.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Town building of Imai thus began and has subsequently undergone changes to become Imai-cho as we know it today but as it seems difficult to understand the significance of Imanishi-ke Jutaku in those days unless some facts such as why it was necessary to develop the town in this fashion and the background of Imai-cho are explained, we will discuss these to begin with.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しましたしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Town building of Imai thus began and has subsequently undergone changes to become Imai-cho as we know it today but as it seems difficult to understand the significance of Imanishi-ke Jutaku in those days unless some facts such as why it was necessary to develop the town in this fashion and the background of Imai-cho are explained, we will discuss these to begin with.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>現在の橿原市は、ヤマト王権から飛鳥朝廷にかけ上代の発祥地として由緒ある土地柄であり、今井町はその北西方に東西に長く位置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The region which is now called Kashihara City has the historic character of the locality as the birthplace of the ancient times from Yamato Sovereignty to Asuka Imperial Court, and Imai-cho lies long from east to west in its northwest part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area known as Kashihara City today has a long and distinguished history, being the birthplace of ancient times from days of the Yamato Sovereignty to Asuka Imperial Court and Imai-cho stretches from east to west to the northwest of that city.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area known as Kashihara City today has a long and distinguished history, being the birthplace of ancient times from days of the Yamato Sovereignty to Asuka Imperial Court and Imai-cho stretches from east to west to the northwest of that city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この頃の地勢は地下の軟弱な状態からみて、あるいは泥地のような湿地帯でなかったかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judging from the soft state of the underground, the topography in these days seems to have been probably wetlands like swamps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the soft earth below ground, it seems that this area used to be a marshland such as mud flat.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the soft earth below ground, it seems that this area used to be a marshland such as mud flat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ところが今井町より東北 1.5 ㎞ の位置にある八木町は、奈良・京都・難波・伊勢・四日市・吉野・紀州路への交通の拠点で、八木周辺はその意味で古くから町屋化し、自然と商業も盛んになったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Yagi-cho which lies 1.5 kilometers to the northeast of Imai-cho was a footing for traffic bound for Nara, Kyoto, Naniwa, Ise, Yokkaichi, Yoshino, and Kishuji, and so it seems that the neighborhood of Yagi began to develop into machiya in that sense in the early times, and that the business activities also became promoted spontaneously there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Yagi-cho located 1.5 kilometers to the northeast of Imai-cho was a traffic hub linking routes to and from Nara, Kyoto, Naniwa, Ise, Yokkaichi, Yoshino, and Kishu whereby it seems that the area around Yagi developed into a merchant town from long ago and became a thriving business center over time.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Yagi-cho located 1.5 kilometers to the northeast of Imai-cho was a traffic hub linking routes to and from Nara, Kyoto, Naniwa, Ise, Yokkaichi, Yoshino, and Kishu whereby it seems that the area around Yagi developed into a merchant town from long ago and became a thriving business center over time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その結果、中世の今井町も隣接の八木の商業が入り込み、今井の町を形成してきたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, it seems that the business activities of adjoining Yagi had gotten into Imai-cho in the Medieval period, too, and formed the town of Imai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, it seems that business activities of the adjacent Yagi expanded into Imai-cho in the medieval period developing the latter into a town.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, it seems that business activities of the adjacent Yagi expanded into Imai-cho in the medieval period developing the latter into a town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、記録にはそう古いものはなく、今井の地名が見えるのは、至徳三年（1386年）に今井の地名が出てきて、この頃は興福寺寺領であったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But there are not so old descriptions about the place name Imai in records, and the place name Imai can be found in a record of 1386, when this town seemed to be a jiryo (estate belonging to a temple) of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Web原稿に合わせて「至徳 (日本)三年（1386年）」は「至徳三年（1386年）」に、「興福寺寺社領」は「興福寺寺領」に変更して解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are no older records on Imai before a document that mentioned a geographical name referred to as Imai in 1386 was found and it seems that this area was an estate of Kofuku-ji Temple in those days.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are no older records on Imai before a document that mentioned a geographical name referred to as Imai in 1386 was found and it seems that this area was an estate of Kofuku-ji Temple in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>今井については、中世末期において一向宗本願寺の進出によって一転機がおとずれ、俄然頭角を現すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imai received a turning point because the Hongan-ji Ikkoshu sect debouched into this area, and suddenly came to stand out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of medieval times, Imai reached a turning point when Ikkoshu Hongan-ji Temple branched out in this area and, thus, Imai suddenly became conspicuous.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of medieval times, Imai reached a turning point when Ikkoshu Hongan-ji Temple branched out in this area and, thus, Imai suddenly became conspicuous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>今井郷が都市的に発展したのは、本願寺一向宗の真宗の道場を建設して以来のことで、町並の整った寺内町今井が成立してきたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was since the Shinshu sect dojo (place of Buddhist practice or meditation) of the Hongan-ji Ikkoshu sect was constructed that Imai-go (Imai Village) had developed like a city, that is to say, jinai-cho Imai with the townscape arranged well seems to have been established since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was after a Shinshu sect dojo (place of Buddhist practice or meditation) of Ikkoshu Hongan-ji Temple had been constructed that Imai-go (Imai Village) developed into a city and it seems that the temple village Imai with organized townscape became established.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was after a Shinshu sect dojo (place of Buddhist practice or meditation) of Ikkoshu Hongan-ji Temple had been constructed that Imai-go (Imai Village) developed into a city and it seems that the temple village Imai with organized townscape became established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>このとき今井郷の形態は、外敵と郷民の自治を守るために、郷の周辺に濠を巡らし、土塁を設けた環濠集落で、現在もその濠跡が今井の周辺にその遺構を残している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the form of Imai-go was so-called Kango-shuraku, or a village surrounded by moats with dorui heaped, in order to protect the autonomy of the village people against external enemies, and at the present time too, the traces of the moats are left as the remains around Imai.</e>
<cmt>Excel原稿の「外敵と郷民の自治を守る」を「外敵から郷民の自治を守る」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Back then, Imai-go was a village surrounded by a moat and earthen walls for fortification to defend itself against enemies outside as well as to protect autonomy of the village people, and the ruins of that moat still remain in existence around Imai today.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Back then, Imai-go was a village surrounded by a moat and earthen walls for fortification to defend itself against enemies outside as well as to protect autonomy of the village people, and the ruins of that moat still remain in existence around Imai today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>また今井町の現道すじは、比較的に整然と残っているが、町の端から端までまっすぐ通ったものではなく、入り口部において道幅だけ屈曲しているか、少し入ったところで丁字型に突き当たっていて、外部より町中を見通すことの出来ない仕組みになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, although the streets in Imai-cho have remained in a comparatively well-ordered state up to now, they are not running straight from end to end through the town, but they bend like a crank in the width of a street at the entrance part, or come to a T-intersection at a short distance from the entrance, so that they are arranged not to allow the inside of the town to be seen through from the outside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The streets of Imai-cho have remained relatively in good condition today but, instead of running straight across town from one end to the other, they were designed to obstruct views of the town from outside with various features such as sharp turns at the town entrance and T-type intersections near the gate.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The streets of Imai-cho have remained relatively in good condition today but, instead of running straight across town from one end to the other, they were designed to obstruct views of the town from outside with various features such as sharp turns at the town entrance and T-type intersections near the gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>現に今西家北側の道路の本町筋では、本建物だけが北側の道路に突出していて、東西両端で道が大きく南に屈曲していて、前方の見通しが悪い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, in the case of Honmachi-suji, a street on the northern side of Imanishi-ke Jutaku, only this building juts out into the northern street, and that street bends greatly southward at both of the east and west ends to block the visibility of the forward view.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, along Honmachi-suji which is the street on the north side of Imanishi-ke Jutaku, thatbuilding juts out into the street on the north with sharp turn to the south at the eastern and western ends of the building, presenting blind corners.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, along Honmachi-suji which is the street on the north side of Imanishi-ke Jutaku, thatbuilding juts out into the street on the north with sharp turn to the south at the eastern and western ends of the building, presenting blind corners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これでは現在のように自動車が頻繁に通る都市としては不適当な町並である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an unsuitable townscape for a town in which a lot of cars go by frequently just like today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These streets are inappropriate for a city with busy vehicular traffic in these days.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These streets are inappropriate for a city with busy vehicular traffic in these days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>天正初年（1574年）、本願寺が織田信長に挑戦したとき、今井郷民のほとんどは商人であり武家は川井家の一族郎党を中心にした戦力であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1574, when Hongan-ji challenged Nobunaga ODA, although most of the people of Imai-go were merchants, and as buke (samurai family) the families and retainers of the Kawai family were the center of the fighting power, it seems that the people of Imai-go also rose up agreeing the honzan (head temple), and they deepened moats and re-heaped dorui to fight against the Nobunaga&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>用語集には「今井郷民」が「Gomi IMAI」と登録されています。この原稿の文脈には不適切だと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1574, when Hongan-ji Temple challenged Nobunaga ODA, most of the Imai-go residents were merchants and samurai families as war potential included mainly the family and retainers of the Kawai clan.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しましたしました。一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1574, when Hongan-ji Temple challenged Nobunaga ODA, most of the Imai-go residents were merchants and samurai families as war potential included mainly the family and retainers of the Kawai clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>本山に呼応して今井郷民も蹶起し、環濠を深くしたり、土塁を築き直したりして信長軍に対抗したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems, however, that the Imai-go residents rose in response to the head temple countermining Nogunaga&apos;s army by making the surrounding moat deeper and building the earthen walls over.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しましたしました。一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems, however, that the Imai-go residents rose in response to the head temple countermining Nogunaga&apos;s army by making the surrounding moat deeper and building the earthen walls over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ところが年余の抗戦も空しく、明智光秀の謀略で降伏し、武装は解除されたようであったが、町の存在だけは許されたようであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after resisting over a year in vain, they surrendered under Mitshuhide AKECHI&apos;s conspiracy, and they seemed to be disarmed, but it is said that only the existence of the town itself was allowed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After fighting back in resistance over a year without much result, however, they were ultimately outmaneuvered by Mitshuhide AKECHI and surrendered, and it seems that while they were disarmed, the town was allowed to remain in existence.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After fighting back in resistance over a year without much result, however, they were ultimately outmaneuvered by Mitshuhide AKECHI and surrendered, and it seems that while they were disarmed, the town was allowed to remain in existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのために北大和の奈良に対して、南大和随一の町として今井は発展してきたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, as opposed to Nara in northern Yamato, Imai seems to have been growing as the biggest town in southern Yamato.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that Imai has consequently developed into the largest town in southern Yamato, being the counterpart of Nara in northern Yamato.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that Imai has consequently developed into the largest town in southern Yamato, being the counterpart of Nara in northern Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="31">
<j>その後、江戸時代となり、世の中がおさまって町人の勢力が高まり、高度な自治を展開するにいたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in the Edo period, as the world was settled down peacefully and the chonin (townspeople) became more powerful, they came to expand high-level autonomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, in the Edo period, with Japan being a country at peace, townspeople became more powerful developing a high level of autonomy.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, in the Edo period, with Japan being a country at peace, townspeople became more powerful developing a high level of autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そこで幕府でも今井を町として認め、江戸・大阪・京都・奈良同様に惣会所を設け、町年寄などの町役人を指揮して町政に当たらせるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Tokugawa shogunate acknowledged Imai as an administrative town, set up a so-kaisho (meeting place of self-governed local community) like in Edo, Osaka, Kyoto, and Nara, and came to command machi-yakunin (municipal officials) such as machi-doshiyori (ward heads) to administer the affairs of the town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa shogunate consequently recognized Imai as a township whereby so-kaisho (meeting place of a municipality) as seen in Edo, Osaka, Kyoto and Nara was installed and machi-yakunin (municipal officials) such as machi-doshiyori (ward heads) began to manage affairs of the town under supervision of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa shogunate consequently recognized Imai as a township whereby so-kaisho (meeting place of a municipality) as seen in Edo, Osaka, Kyoto and Nara was installed and machi-yakunin (municipal officials) such as machi-doshiyori (ward heads) began to manage affairs of the town under supervision of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>今井町の惣年寄制は、慶長に始まったようで、初めは今西・尾崎両家が任命されたが、寛永に上田家が加えられて合計三人となり、今西家が筆頭になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that so-doshiyori (officers who worked under the town magistrate) system in Imai-cho started in the Keicho era (1596 - 1615), and at first both of the Imanishi family and the Ozaki family were appointed so-doshiyori, but in the Kanei era (1624 - 1644) the Ueda family was added so that three persons in total were appointed so-doshiyori, of which the Imanishi family was the head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the so-doshiyori (officers who worked under the town magistrate) system in Imai-cho started in the Keicho era (1596 - 1615) and the Imanishi family and the Ozaki family were originally appointed to that position but, during the Kanei era (1624 - 1644), the Ueda family was added to make up a group of three so-doshiyori with the Imanishi family being at the head of that group.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the so-doshiyori (officers who worked under the town magistrate) system in Imai-cho started in the Keicho era (1596 - 1615) and the Imanishi family and the Ozaki family were originally appointed to that position but, during the Kanei era (1624 - 1644), the Ueda family was added to make up a group of three so-doshiyori with the Imanishi family being at the head of that group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この惣年寄の下に町年寄十一人（当時六つの町があり、各町二人ずつ、北町のみ一人）・町代六人・肝煎六人（いずれも各町一人ずつ）都合二十六人の町役人が、自治的に町の支配に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under these so-doshiyori were eleven machi-doshiyori (in those days there were six towns, so two persons were appointed from each town, and one from only Kita-cho), six cho-dai and six kimoiri (one person from each town, respectively), and so 26 machi-yakunin in total were responsible to the management of the town in self-governed style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under so-doshiyori, there were a total of twenty-six machi-yakunin including eleven machi-doshiyori (two representatives per township for five of the six towns that existed in those days and one representative for the remaining Kita-cho, six cho-dai (one representative per township) and six kimoiri (one representative per township) who had autonomous control over administration of the municipality.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under so-doshiyori, there were a total of twenty-six machi-yakunin including eleven machi-doshiyori (two representatives per township for five of the six towns that existed in those days and one representative for the remaining Kita-cho, six cho-dai (one representative per township) and six kimoiri (one representative per township) who had autonomous control over administration of the municipality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="35">
<j>この頃の惣年寄の仕事はどのようなことをしていたかというと、今西家の古文書には以下のように書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What so-doshiyori in those days were doing as their duties was written in the old documents of the Imanishi family as follows:</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。原稿の「今西家の古文書には」の後に「以下のように書かれている」を補い、そこで文を切断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to tasks performed by so-doshiyori in those days, there is a description in ancient documents written by the Imanishi family as follows:</e>
<cmt>Additionally, the handcuffs used in those days remain in the possession of the Imanishi family today.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to tasks performed by so-doshiyori in those days, there is a description in ancient documents written by the Imanishi family as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「惣年寄義ハ古来より六町之〆括り取捌役ニ而勤来、公事訴訟願等の義は勿論御上より被仰渡候御用町年寄へ申渡。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;We so-doshiyori have been working since old times to put together the six towns and settle their problems; we have been working to tell to machi-doshiyori not only the suit applications but also the directions and orders given by the town magistrate, and about what people report to the government officials, no matter what it might be, if it is a suit application, we have been working to consult the persons concerned or machi-doshiyori, and settle what could be solved between the parties concerned, or report to the government officials in charge what was unsolved; when the land was awarded to us for these services, we were allowed to meet the jito (manager and lord of manor) just like retainers of the clan, and we did as we were told to.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。原稿の最後の「、」を「。」に変えました。原稿の内容を3つに分けてセミコロン（;）で区切りました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;We, so-doshiyori, have long been performing the role of supervisors over the six townships which, in addition to addressing the matters concerning taxes, lawsuits and petitions, includes communicating instructions from the Shogunate to machi-doshiyori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We, so-doshiyori, have long been performing the role of supervisors over the six townships which, in addition to addressing the matters concerning taxes, lawsuits and petitions, includes communicating instructions from the Shogunate to machi-doshiyori.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に 」 追加 &quot; → &apos;&apos; を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「尤下より申上候義、何事ニ不依、公事訴訟之義ハ当人又は町年寄江改相談、相済候義ハ埒明、滞申義者御役迄申上候義ニ而勤来候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to the bottom-to-top communication, there are no restrictions on the subject matter to be brought up and, as to the affairs in relation to taxes, lawsuits and petitions, we have first sufficiently discussed the issue with the party concerned as well as machi-doshiyori but, if no solution was reached, we have then presented the matter to the government officials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to the bottom-to-top communication, there are no restrictions on the subject matter to be brought up and, as to the affairs in relation to taxes, lawsuits and petitions, we have first sufficiently discussed the issue with the party concerned as well as machi-doshiyori but, if no solution was reached, we have then presented the matter to the government officials.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に「 」 追加 &apos; &apos; を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>「依之御給地之時分、御地頭様へ御目見等も御家中並ニ被仰付相勤申候。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We have, thus, been diligently serving as so-doshiyori whereby we have been given various privileges such as receiving land from the government and having access to jito (manager and lord of manor) being treated like samurai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>NC_check 一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We have, thus, been diligently serving as so-doshiyori whereby we have been given various privileges such as receiving land from the government and having access to jito (manager and lord of manor) being treated like samurai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に 「 追加スペース調整&quot; → &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>このように今井六町の締括り役であって、領主・代官の町方支配の一翼を担っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like this, the role of so-doshiyori was to put together the six towns of Imai, and so they played a part in the domination of the people in town by the feudal lord or daikan (local governor).</e>
<cmt>前の文の文末の変更に伴って原稿の「とあるように」を「このように」に変えて解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The role of so-doshiyori was to supervise the affairs of the six townships of Imai playing a role in the overall administration of the towns by the feudal lord or daikan (local governor).</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The role of so-doshiyori was to supervise the affairs of the six townships of Imai playing a role in the overall administration of the towns by the feudal lord or daikan (local governor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>公事・訴訟の取りさばきが主な任務であるが、商売繁盛の町方のことで「町中家屋敷・同地売買借入証文奥書印形」の責務があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To deal with the suit applications was a main task of so-doshiyori, but relating to the people in town who had achieved prosperous trade, they also had a duty of &quot;standing surety for and putting their seal to a bond to buy and sell or borrow a mansion and/or its premises in town.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原稿の「奥書印形」を「保証人になって捺印する」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main duties of so-doshiyori included addressing matters concerning taxes and petitions but, with townspeople being affluent with flourishing business, they were also responsible for &apos;giving stamp of approval on inscription on contract for sale, purchase or rent of residence and/or land in town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main duties of so-doshiyori included addressing matters concerning taxes and petitions but, with townspeople being affluent with flourishing business, they were also responsible for &apos;giving stamp of approval on inscription on contract for sale, purchase or rent of residence and/or land in town.&apos;</e>
<cmt>‘ ’ → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>今西家の西側面には、もと牢屋が最近まであったこと、またいぶし牢などの現存していることから、悪質犯人を拘留するといった警察権も行使していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there used to be a jail cell on the western side of the Imanishi-ke Jutaku until recently, and a smoking jail cell exists actually in the house, it is thought that so-doshiyori exercised the police power such as custody of malicious criminals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the facts that the former jail existed until recently and that ibushi-ro (smoke torture chamber) still exists today on the west side of the Imanishi-ke residence, it seems that so-doshiyori exercised police authority such as holding hold heinous criminals in custody as well.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the facts that the former jail existed until recently and that ibushi-ro (smoke torture chamber) still exists today on the west side of the Imanishi-ke residence, it seems that so-doshiyori exercised police authority such as holding hold heinous criminals in custody as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また当時使われていた手錠も今西家に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the handcuffs which were used those days have handed down to the Imanishi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the handcuffs used in those days remain in the possession of the Imanishi family today.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the handcuffs used in those days remain in the possession of the Imanishi family today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="43">
<j>今西家は江戸初期から幕末まで前述のように惣年寄役として勤めてきたのであるが、これは現位置すなわち慶安三年に本建物が創立されてからのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imanishi family had worked as so-doshiyori since the early Edo period until the last days of the Tokugawa Shogunate as stated above, but it was when this building was founded on the present location, that is in 1650, that they began to perform this role.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned earlier, the Imanishi family had worked as so-doshiyori between the early Edo period and the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate but it was after Imanishi-ke Jutaku was first established at the present location in 1650 that they began to perform this role.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned earlier, the Imanishi family had worked as so-doshiyori between the early Edo period and the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate but it was after Imanishi-ke Jutaku was first established at the present location in 1650 that they began to perform this role.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この任地に着任するまでに既に今井町の住人であり、前述の一向宗の戦いにおいて、信長から武装解除される際に今井郷民を危険から回避させ、単独で交渉にあたるなど相当の功績があったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before they moved to this place of their assignment, they had already lived in Imai-cho, and when they were disarmed by Nobunaga in the aforesaid battle of the Ikkoshu sect, they seemed to make considerable achievements such as making the people of the Imai-go avoid the crisis and negotiating with the enemy alone, and such achievements were recognized so that they were allowed to construct a splendid building sometimes called Tenshukaku of Imai at the present location, which is said to be the beginning of the Imanishi-ke Jutaku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imanishi had been living in Imai-cho before arriving at his post at that location and when disarmament was ordered by Nobunaga after the battle of the Ikkoshu sect, it seems that Imanishi made considerable contributions to the community such as helping the Imai-go residents to escape from danger and subsequently negotiating with the enemy side on his own.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。読みやすく修正しましたしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imanishi had been living in Imai-cho before arriving at his post at that location and when disarmament was ordered by Nobunaga after the battle of the Ikkoshu sect, it seems that Imanishi made considerable contributions to the community such as helping the Imai-go residents to escape from danger and subsequently negotiating with the enemy side on his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>その功績が認められ、現位置に今井の天守閣ともいわれる豪壮な建築の行われたのが始まりのようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the construction of the magnificent building also known as the castle tower of Imai at the present location in recognition of Imanishi&apos;s achievements marked the beginning of Imanishi-ke Jutaku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。読みやすく修正しましたしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the construction of the magnificent building also known as the castle tower of Imai at the present location in recognition of Imanishi&apos;s achievements marked the beginning of Imanishi-ke Jutaku.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィ ’→ &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="46">
<j>江戸初期の今井の町勢の概略は、東西 610m、南北 310m、大体長方形の地形で東西南北方眼状に道路を配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An approximate extent of the town of Imai in the early Edo period was 610 meters from east to west and 310 meters from north to south, that was a rectangular configuration on the whole, in which streets were laid from east to west and from north to south like a grid sheet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general landform of Imai-cho in the early Edo period was by and large a rectangle in shape measuring 610 meters east to west and 310 meters north to south with a grid of straight streets running north-south and east-west.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general landform of Imai-cho in the early Edo period was by and large a rectangle in shape measuring 610 meters east to west and 310 meters north to south with a grid of straight streets running north-south and east-west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>その地形や街路の形状は、町造りの始められた頃からの形状がほぼ残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That configuration and the shapes of streets have been handed down to now as they were at the time when the town began to be constructed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That landform and shape of the streets have generally remained unchanged from the days when the town began to be built.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That landform and shape of the streets have generally remained unchanged from the days when the town began to be built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="48">
<j>以上のようにして町の外郭が出来上がり、その中に街路を配し現在の町並みに近い区画が出来上がるわけであるが、街路は前述のように町の端から端まで通り抜けのものではなく、入口で屈曲、あるいは途中でＴ字型に組んで見通しのできないように配備されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, the outline of the town was completed, and streets were laid there to finish dividing it into the blocks close to the present townscape, though the streets were not for passing through the town from one end to the other end as mentioned before, but they were designed to bend at the entrance or come to a T-intersection on the way in order that their layout would prevent anyone from seeing through the town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the outline being completed as described above, the town was built with blocks divided by streets but, as mentioned earlier, those are not straight streets running across the town from one end to the other but, rather, they were laid out to obstruct views of the town with sharp turns at the town entrance and T-type intersections near the gate.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the outline being completed as described above, the town was built with blocks divided by streets but, as mentioned earlier, those are not straight streets running across the town from one end to the other but, rather, they were laid out to obstruct views of the town with sharp turns at the town entrance and T-type intersections near the gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="49">
<j>その上、街路の端々の東西南北に９つの門があったようで、夜は４つの門のみを開け、外来者が町中にみだりに入ることを拒んでいたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is more, it was thought that there were nine gates at the north, south, east, and west ends of the streets, and that only four gates were opened at night to prevent external persons from getting into the town without good reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it seems that there were a total of nine gates at the north, south, east, and west ends of the streets and that only four gates were open as required at night to keep strangers from arbitrarily entering the town.</e>
<cmt>意味を明瞭にするため補足してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it seems that there were a total of nine gates at the north, south, east, and west ends of the streets and that only four gates were open as required at night to keep strangers from arbitrarily entering the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>もし、外来者が今井町内で宿泊する必要のあるときは、その都度、町年寄へ届出を必要としていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When external persons needed to stay in Imai-cho, they were required to hand in a notification to machi-doshiyori every time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When outlanders needed to stay in Imai-cho overnight, they were required to notify machi-doshiyori accordingly each time.</e>
<cmt>不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When outlanders needed to stay in Imai-cho overnight, they were required to notify machi-doshiyori accordingly each time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="51">
<j>このような形態で今井の町造りが始まり、惣年寄制によって自治権を確立した町並みが出来上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the town of Imai started in this way, the townscape in which the autonomy was established through the so-doshiyori system were completed, and folk dwellings from the early Edo period through to the end of the Edo period stood side by side, among which Imanishi-ke Jutaku was located at the present position from the beginning and seems to have risen stately there exceptionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of Imai-cho thus began and the town run by the so-doshiyori system with an established autonomy came into existence.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しましたしました。一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of Imai-cho thus began and the town run by the so-doshiyori system with an established autonomy came into existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>江戸初期から末期にかけての民家が軒を連ね、そのうちでも今西家住宅は、当初から現位置にあって、ひときわその威容を示していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private residences built between the beginning and the end of Edo period stood side by side and it seems that Imanishi-ke Jutaku, which was located at the present from the start, stood out in the townscape with its stately air.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しましたしました。一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private residences built between the beginning and the end of Edo period stood side by side and it seems that Imanishi-ke Jutaku, which was located at the present from the start, stood out in the townscape with its stately air.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>特質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>本建物の特質としては、棟札があって創立年代がはっきりしていて、民家というよりは城郭を思わせる構造形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of this building are that the year when it was founded is clear because there is a munafuda left, and that it has a structural style which is associated with a castle rather than a folk dwelling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the characteristics of this house, there is an existing munafuda identifying the year in which that building was originally built and that it has a structural style which reminds someone of a castle rather than a private house.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the characteristics of this house, there is an existing munafuda identifying the year in which that building was originally built and that it has a structural style which reminds someone of a castle rather than a private house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>平面形式は土間と座敷が折半、同境に一本引き雨戸があり、座敷内部では、帳台構え、各間仕切の敷居・鴨居が突き止めであることなどが一階平面の特質である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of the first floor flat are that the flat has a style divided in half for doma (dirt floor) and zashiki (Japanese style tatami room), that there is ipponbiki-amado (wooden sliding doors aligned on one straight groove) separating these two areas, that inside of the zashiki chodaigamae (a built-in ornamental doorway found in the raised area of a formal style reception suite) is equipped, and that shikii (threshold) and kamoi (the deeply grooved upper beam) of each majikiri (partition) between zashiki have a stopper fixed at their ends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of the main floor plan are that the floor is divided in half between doma (dirt floor area) and zashiki (Japanese style tatami rooms) by ipponbiki-amado (wooden sliding storm doors mounted on one straight track) and, inside the zashiki area, there are chodaigamae (a built-in ornamental doorway found in the raised area of a formal style reception suite), shikii (threshold) and kamoi (door lintel) of each majikiri (partition) between zashiki are designed to stop the sliding door at the specific point.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of the main floor plan are that the floor is divided in half between doma (dirt floor area) and zashiki (Japanese style tatami rooms) by ipponbiki-amado (wooden sliding storm doors mounted on one straight track) and, inside the zashiki area, there are chodaigamae (a built-in ornamental doorway found in the raised area of a formal style reception suite), shikii (threshold) and kamoi (door lintel) of each majikiri (partition) between zashiki are designed to stop the sliding door at the specific point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>二階には床の間付きの座敷のあることが注目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the second floor is a zashiki with tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed) built in, which is worthy of attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is worthy of attention that there is a zashiki with tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art objects or flowers are displayed) on the second floor.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is worthy of attention that there is a zashiki with tokonoma (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art objects or flowers are displayed) on the second floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>二階にこのような座敷を造ることは、階級意識が強かったこの頃では、上から人を見下げるということで、一般民家には用いられなかったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Building such a zashiki on the second floor didn&apos;t seem to be applied to a general folk dwelling, because it resulted in looking down on people from the upper room in those days when class consciousness was high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days of class consciousness, it did not seem to be a practice among private citizens to build a zashiki with tokonoma on the second floor of their houses as it could be construed as looking down on the other people.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days of class consciousness, it did not seem to be a practice among private citizens to build a zashiki with tokonoma on the second floor of their houses as it could be construed as looking down on the other people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>ところが今西家の先祖は武家出身であって、その上、一向宗の騒動には相当功績のあった人で、その功績が買われて現位置に建てられたことが伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But an ancestor of the Imanishi family was originally a samurai, and what is more, he was a man who made a considerable achievement in the riot of Ikkoshu sect, so it has been said that this house was built at the present place because that achievement was evaluated high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancestor of the Imanishi family, however, was originally of the samurai class in addition to making a major contribution during the incidence of the Ikkoshu sect whereby it has been said that this house was built at the present location in recognition of his achievements.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancestor of the Imanishi family, however, was originally of the samurai class in addition to making a major contribution during the incidence of the Ikkoshu sect whereby it has been said that this house was built at the present location in recognition of his achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="58">
<j>現在、本建物が建っている位置は、旧環濠集落の西端にあって、西の要といったことから外敵を威嚇、あるいは防禦する意味において、城郭を思わせる建築様式を備えさせたものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present location where this building stands is the westernmost point of the former village surrounded by a moat, that is to say, the western key place, and so, it is thought that in order to mean the intention for threatening the external enemies or protecting from them, the architectural style which made people associate with a castle was provided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present location where this building stands is the westernmost of the former village surrounded by a moat being, in a manner of speaking, the western key strategic point of that village and, hence, it is considered that the house was built in an architectural style which reminds one of a castle intended to intimidate enemies and to defend the community.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present location where this building stands is the westernmost of the former village surrounded by a moat being, in a manner of speaking, the western key strategic point of that village and, hence, it is considered that the house was built in an architectural style which reminds one of a castle intended to intimidate enemies and to defend the community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="59">
<j>したがって、本建物は故意に北側の道路上（本町筋）に突出していて、二階座敷北と東の両面に塗籠（ぬりごめ）の連子窓を設け、外敵の見張りあるいは町内の動向をさぐるに格好の場所であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, this building is protruded on the northern street (Honmachi-suji) intentionally, and renjimado (a window with vertical or horizontal wooden laths or bamboo) with nurigome (painting walls, etc. with thick plaster) is installed on both of the north and east sides of the zashiki on the second floor, and so, it is inferred that this was a suitable place to watch the external enemies or spy on the movements in the town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is, therefore, considered that this building was deliberately built to jut out in the street (Honmachi-suji) in the north with renjimado (window with vertical or horizontal wooden laths or bamboo) of nurigome (painting walls, etc. with thick plaster) style being installed on the northern and eastern sides of zashiki on the second floor making it an ideal place to look out for enemies and to watch movements in town.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is, therefore, considered that this building was deliberately built to jut out in the street (Honmachi-suji) in the north with renjimado (window with vertical or horizontal wooden laths or bamboo) of nurigome (painting walls, etc. with thick plaster) style being installed on the northern and eastern sides of zashiki on the second floor making it an ideal place to look out for enemies and to watch movements in town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="60">
<j>なお元禄以前に二階部屋があったことから、この家の別格であることの証しとなっているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, that there were rooms on the second floor before the Genroku era proves that this house was treated exceptionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there were rooms on the second floor that existed before the Genroku era proving that this was no ordinary house.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there were rooms on the second floor that existed before the Genroku era proving that this was no ordinary house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="61">
<j>内方高さが現行内方高さに合っており、畳寸法についても旧尺貫法で長さ 6尺3寸、巾 3尺1寸5分の現行京間の畳が使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The heights of the inside of the house correspond with the present-day heights, and the size of a tatami mat in the former shakkanho (old Japanese system of weights and measures) is 6 shaku 3 sun (190.89 centimeters) long and 3 shaku 1 sun 5 bu (95.445 centimeters) wide, so the tatami mats of the present-day kyoma (a standard measurement used for bay size in the Kansai region) have been used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The internal height of the house meets the current interior height requirements and the dimensions of the tatami mats measure, in the former shakkanho system (old Japanese measuring system), 6 shaku 3 sun (190.89 centimeters) long and 3 shaku 1 sun 5 bu (95.445 centimeters) wide being equivalent of that for Kyoma tatami used today.</e>
<cmt>誤訳および回りくどさを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The internal height of the house meets the current interior height requirements and the dimensions of the tatami mats measure, in the former shakkanho system (old Japanese measuring system), 6 shaku 3 sun (190.89 centimeters) long and 3 shaku 1 sun 5 bu (95.445 centimeters) wide being equivalent of that for Kyoma tatami used today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="62">
<j>以上の特質のうち二階座敷を除けば、今井町に現存する古い民家に共通した構造形式を用いているが、その中でも旧形をよく保存されてきたのは今西家住宅のみで、他の建物では随時改変されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the above characteristics, except for the second floor zashiki, the structural style common to the old minka now existing in Imai-cho have been used, but among them all, the old style has been well preserved in only Imanishi-ke Jutaku, and in the other buildings changes have been made on demand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the above characteristics, except for the second floor zashiki, the structural style of Imanishi-ke Jutaku has a commonality with that for the other existing old private residences in Imai-cho but only the former has maintained its original shape while the other houses have been altered as needed.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the above characteristics, except for the second floor zashiki, the structural style of Imanishi-ke Jutaku has a commonality with that for the other existing old private residences in Imai-cho but only the former has maintained its original shape while the other houses have been altered as needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="63">
<j>本建物東南隅すなわち仏間南に二階屋（別間）が接続しているが、この二階屋も後補のものではなく、本建物と同期のものであることがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the south-east corner of this building, that is, on the south of the butsuma (room for Buddha statue), a two-storied building (betsuma [detached rooms]) is connected, which has turned out to be as old as the main building, not to be added later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A two story building (betsuma or another building) is attached to the south-east corner of this building which is the south of the butsuma (room for Buddha statue) but it has been found that the two story building was built in the same year as the main building and was not an addition.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A two story building (betsuma or another building) is attached to the south-east corner of this building which is the south of the butsuma (room for Buddha statue) but it has been found that the two story building was built in the same year as the main building and was not an addition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="64">
<j>この二階屋は改変がはげしかったために、昭和32年本建物指定調査の際は、一応保留という形になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because this two-storied building has been changed extremely, when the investigation of cultural property designation of this building was carried out in 1957, it was decided to defer judgment for the time being.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As this two story building has been drastically altered, during the investigation for cultural property designation in 1957, the judgment on that building was deferred.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As this two story building has been drastically altered, during the investigation for cultural property designation in 1957, the judgment on that building was deferred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>再度の調査で本建物と同期のものであり、当然追加指定ということも考えられたが、内部改造のはげしかったことと、当主の希望などもあって指定しないことにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second investigation proved that it was as old as the main building, so the additional designation of it was taken into consideration of course, but in the end it was agreed that it would not be designated, because the inside of the building has been changed extremely, and the head of the family desired not to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of another investigation, the two story building was determined to have been built in the same year when the main building was constructed and was considered for additional designation but due to various factors such as drastic alterations of the interior of the house that had taken place and the wishes of the family head, it was decided that no designation was to be given.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of another investigation, the two story building was determined to have been built in the same year when the main building was constructed and was considered for additional designation but due to various factors such as drastic alterations of the interior of the house that had taken place and the wishes of the family head, it was decided that no designation was to be given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="66">
<j>別間の構造形式は、主屋と大差はないが、各部材の大きさの比例関係である木割りの小さいことと、一階南端柱間には書院のような痕跡のあることから、南八畳間の座敷はあるいは書院形式のものではなかったかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the structural style of the betsuma is almost as same as the omoya (main building), because kiwari (a system for measuring out the wooden component to be used in architecture or statuary) which is a direct proportion relationship among the sizes of each component is small, and because there are vestiges like shoin (reception room) in hashirama (bay, space or distance between two pillars) at the south end of the first floor, it is thought that zashiki of the south eight-tatami room was probably that of shoin style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the structural style of betsuma is much the same as that of omoya (main building), because kiwari (a system for measuring out the wooden component to be used in architecture or statuary) which is in a direct proportional relationship with the size of each component is small, and because there are the shoin-like (reception room) marks in hashirama (bay, space or distance between two pillars) at the south end of the main floor, it is considered that the eight-tatami room in the south side of the betsuma was probably built in the shoin style.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the structural style of betsuma is much the same as that of omoya (main building), because kiwari (a system for measuring out the wooden component to be used in architecture or statuary) which is in a direct proportional relationship with the size of each component is small, and because there are the shoin-like (reception room) marks in hashirama (bay, space or distance between two pillars) at the south end of the main floor, it is considered that the eight-tatami room in the south side of the betsuma was probably built in the shoin style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="67">
<j>仏間南現在押し入れのある個所は、もと東西に長い四畳間であって、この四畳間から二階に上がっていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The south space of butsuma where oshiire (closet) is now installed was originally a four-tatami room which was long in east and west direction, and it seems that people went up to the second floor from this four-tatami room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The south side of the butsuma where oshiire (closet) is located now was originally a long four-tatami room stretching from east to west which seems to have been used as an access way to upstairs.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The south side of the butsuma where oshiire (closet) is located now was originally a long four-tatami room stretching from east to west which seems to have been used as an access way to upstairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>二階は現在前記四畳間上部は現昇降口及び押入れ・南に八畳間の座敷を有しているが、もとは厨子形式のものでなかったかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the second floor, there are a present entrance and oshiire just above the aforesaid four-tatami room, and zashiki of eight-tatami room in the south, which is suspected to have been originally a room of zushi (a cupboard-like case with double doors in which an image of the Buddha, a sutra, or some other revered object is kept at a temple) style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the second floor, there are a hatch and closet above the four-tatami room mentioned earlier and on there is an eight-tatami room the south side but it is speculated the upstairs was originally a tsushiarea (storage).</e>
<cmt>「厨子」は「ツシ」と読み、 ここでは「物置」のような意味で、&apos;loft&apos;あるいは &apos;storage&apos; が適切と思われます。http://www.city.kawasaki.jp/88/88bunka/home/top/stop/zukan/z0017.htm</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the second floor, there are a hatch and closet above the four-tatami room mentioned earlier and on there is an eight-tatami room the south side but it is speculated the upstairs was originally a tsushiarea (storage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="69">
<j>この別間と向い合って西に三階蔵があったが、昭和初年の地震で倒壊したようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facing this betsuma, there used to be a three-storied kura (storehouse) in the west, but it is said to have been destroyed by the earthquake in the early years of Showa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a three story kura (storehouse) facing the betsuma on the west side but it seems to have been destroyed by an earthquake in 1926.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a three story kura (storehouse) facing the betsuma on the west side but it seems to have been destroyed by an earthquake in 1926.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="70">
<j>本建物の沿革については、解体修理の際発見された瓦銘や刻銘から述べることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of this building can be described based on kawara-mei (inscription on tile) or the other inscriptions which were discovered when it was taken apart and repaired.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possible to describe the history of this building from kawara-mei (inscriptions on tile) or the other inscriptions found when this building which were discovered when it was dismantled and repaired.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possible to describe the history of this building from kawara-mei (inscriptions on tile) or the other inscriptions found when this building which were discovered when it was dismantled and repaired.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>平瓦の中に明暦2年（1656年）の刻銘のあるものがあり、明暦2年は創立から7年後のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among hiragawara (broad, concave tiles), there are those with an inscription of the year 1656, which was seven years after the construction of this building.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of hiragawara (broad, concave tiles) used for this building have the inscription indicating the year 1656 which was 7 years after its construction.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of hiragawara (broad, concave tiles) used for this building have the inscription indicating the year 1656 which was 7 years after its construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>もし、この頃に屋根葺が行われたとすれば、銘のある瓦と同種の瓦が相当数出てこなくてはならないが、それらの資料の得られないところから考えると、何かの災害によって応急的に一部の瓦が補足されたのではなかろうかと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If roofing had been carried out in those days, a considerable number of tiles of the same kind as the inscribed tile should have been discovered, but considering that such materials can not be gained in fact, it is suspected that some tiles were added to make temporary repairs for damages by some disaster.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the roof had been put on around that time, quite a few tiles that are the same type as those with inscriptions had to be found but, in view of their absence, it is considered that some of the tiles may have been added to address an emergency situation due to some disaster or another.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the roof had been put on around that time, quite a few tiles that are the same type as those with inscriptions had to be found but, in view of their absence, it is considered that some of the tiles may have been added to address an emergency situation due to some disaster or another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>次に元禄6年（1693年）の瓦銘については、慶安3年に創立されてから43年後で相当数の平瓦が補足されており、また文政8年（1825年）の瓦銘のある瓦と同種類の瓦が半数近くあり、これらのときに屋根の葺き替えの行われていることがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, judging from the kawara-mei of the year 1693, which was 43 years after the construction in 1650, it is certain that a considerable number of hiragarawa were added this year, and almost half of the whole tiles are those of the same kind as the tile with the kawaramei of the year 1825, so it has turned out that reroofing was carried out in each of these years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next off, with respect to the kawara-mei of the year 1693 which was 43 years after the initial construction in 1650, it has been found that a fair number of hiragarawa were added that year and nearly half of all tiles are the same type as those with the kawara-mei of the year 1825 indicating that the building was reroofed in those years.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next off, with respect to the kawara-mei of the year 1693 which was 43 years after the initial construction in 1650, it has been found that a fair number of hiragarawa were added that year and nearly half of all tiles are the same type as those with the kawara-mei of the year 1825 indicating that the building was reroofed in those years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>元禄と文政の修理は屋根だけでなく、外部大壁および軒裏の塗りかえ、内部間仕切の改変など相当大規模な修理が行われてきたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1693 and 1825 repairs, not only reroofing but also repainting the external okabe and the downward surfaces of eaves, changing the internal partitions, and the like were included, and therefore, considerably large-scale repairs seem to have been carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the renovations in 1693 and 1825, it seems that fairly extensive repairs were performed including repainting of exterior walls as well as soffits and modifications of interior partitions in addition to reroofing.</e>
<cmt>誤訳・意味不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the renovations in 1693 and 1825, it seems that fairly extensive repairs were performed including repainting of exterior walls as well as soffits and modifications of interior partitions in addition to reroofing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="75">
<j>その後、昭和初年までは記録的には何の資料も得られなかったが、内部の壁が3回くらい塗りかえられているところから、文政以降にも破損の都度修理が行われてきたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that time, no data was found as the records of repairs until the first years of Showa, but considering that the internal walls were repainted three times or so, it is suspected that repairs have been carried out every time damages were found also since 1825.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No records were found as to the subsequent repairs until 1926 but, considering that the interior walls have been repainted approximately three times; it seems that additional repairs have been performed to address damages as required since 1825.</e>
<cmt>誤訳・意味不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No records were found as to the subsequent repairs until 1926 but, considering that the interior walls have been repainted approximately three times; it seems that additional repairs have been performed to address damages as required since 1825.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="76">
<j>昭和2年（1927年）の北丹後地震により、本建物西に接続していた牢屋と、南の三階倉が倒壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the earthquake at the northern Tango Province occurred in 1927, the jail connecting to the west of the main building and the three-storied storehouse in the south were destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Northern Tango Earthquake in 1927, the jailhouse connected to the west side of the main building and the three story storehouse located on the south side of that building were destroyed.</e>
<cmt>誤訳・意味不明瞭を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Northern Tango Earthquake in 1927, the jailhouse connected to the west side of the main building and the three story storehouse located on the south side of that building were destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="77">
<j>この頃には本建物も相当破損していたようで、特に西南隅の地盤沈下に伴い、本建物が西に大きく傾いていたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, this building seemed to be considerably damaged, and especially because of the ground sinkage at the south-west corner, this building seemed to lean to the west a lot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, it seems that this building had fallen into disrepair to the considerable degree and that, specifically, due to land subsidence occurred at the southwest corner of the premise, the building was visibly tilting westward.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, it seems that this building had fallen into disrepair to the considerable degree and that, specifically, due to land subsidence occurred at the southwest corner of the premise, the building was visibly tilting westward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="78">
<j>江戸時代であれば、この程度の修理は官費で賄えたであっただろうが、明治維新後は廃藩置県によって、長年勤めてきた惣年寄の役職もなく、一市民としては簡単な修理も覚束ないといった窮状に達していたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the repair of this level could have been paid for with government expense, but after Meiji Restoration, the family lost a post of so-doshiyori that they had served as for a long time, and as an ordinary citizen they seemed to have fallen into so terrible a distress that they could not afford to pay for the simple repair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the repair of this magnitude could have been paid for at the public expense but, with abolition of clans and establishment of prefectures coming to effect after the Meiji Restoration, the family no longer had a post of so-doshiyori which they had long served and it seems that, being just ordinary townspeople, they were in desperate straits whereby finding it difficult to afford to keep up with simple repairs.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the repair of this magnitude could have been paid for at the public expense but, with abolition of clans and establishment of prefectures coming to effect after the Meiji Restoration, the family no longer had a post of so-doshiyori which they had long served and it seems that, being just ordinary townspeople, they were in desperate straits whereby finding it difficult to afford to keep up with simple repairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="79">
<j>当主によると明治維新後、男爵位を政府から薦められたものの手続き費も儘ならないほど窮迫していたようで、ご先祖が権力に驕ることの無かった事に誇りを持っているとおっしゃっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the family said that although he was recommended to get a title of Baron by the government after Meiji Restoration, the family were so poverty-stricken that they could not afford to pay the procedure charge, and that he was proud that his ancestors had not been arrogant with power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the head of the family, although he was nominated for a barony by the government after the Meiji Restoration, the family was so destitute that they could not afford the processing fee for the peerage and he also mentioned that he was proud of ancestors for not having been arrogant about their power.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the head of the family, although he was nominated for a barony by the government after the Meiji Restoration, the family was so destitute that they could not afford the processing fee for the peerage and he also mentioned that he was proud of ancestors for not having been arrogant about their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="80">
<j>それで牢屋や三階蔵の復旧は行われなかったが、牢屋接続部の屋根の修理と、これ以上本建物が西に倒れないよう土間西側から斜めに支柱を入れて補強した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the jail and the three-storied storehouse were not restored, but the roof of the connection part between the jail and the main building were repaired, and in order that the main building would not lean more to the west, it was reinforced with a prop which was installed diagonally from the west side of the doma.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, no restoration work was performed on the jail or three story storehouse but the roof over the area where the jail and main building joined was repaired and, to stop its further tilting westward, the main building was reinforced by installing braces on a slant from the west side of doma.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, no restoration work was performed on the jail or three story storehouse but the roof over the area where the jail and main building joined was repaired and, to stop its further tilting westward, the main building was reinforced by installing braces on a slant from the west side of doma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>別間も本建物と平行して傾斜していたので、本建物と接続する桁・母屋などの横架材を切り離し、別間だけ独立して傾斜を復旧していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the betsuma also leaned in parallel with the main building, the crossbeam connecting with the main building and the plate of the main housing were cut off, and only the betsuma was restored from the leaning independently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the betsuma was also tilting in parallel with the main building, crossbeams and joists connecting the two buildings were severed to correct tilting of the betsuma by itself.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the betsuma was also tilting in parallel with the main building, crossbeams and joists connecting the two buildings were severed to correct tilting of the betsuma by itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="82">
<j>このとき仏間南旧４畳間の中央東西に筋違い用の壁を新しく設け、同壁の北に仏間側からの押入れ・南間西に二階昇降口、東に別間座敷側の押入れを、それぞれ新設し、二階も現在風に改変されたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, a new diagonally opposite wall was made in the east and west direction at the center of the former 4-tatami room on the south of the butsuma, and a closet for the butsuma on the north of the wall, an entrance to the second floor on the west of the south room, and a closet for the betsuma zashiki on the east were newly built in respectively, and the second floor was also changed into the present style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this restoration, it seems that the second floor was modernized by various improvements including; a new bearing wall running in an east-west direction at the center of the former four-tatami room on the south side of the butsuma, a closet in the butsuma on the north side of that wall, a hatch for going up and down between the main floor and upstairs installed on the west side of the room on the south side and another closet in zashiki in the betsuma on the east side.</e>
<cmt>誤訳を修正および読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this restoration, it seems that the second floor was modernized by various improvements including; a new bearing wall running in an east-west direction at the center of the former four-tatami room on the south side of the butsuma, a closet in the butsuma on the north side of that wall, a hatch for going up and down between the main floor and upstairs installed on the west side of the room on the south side and another closet in zashiki in the betsuma on the east side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="83">
<j>このようにして別間の創立年代が明らかになり、昭和初年には立ちを直し、締め直しも行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the construction year of the betsuma became clear, and in the early years of Showa, tachi (stand) was fixed and re-fastening was also executed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction year of the betsuma thus became known and, in 1926, the building was straightened and re-nailed.</e>
<cmt>誤訳を修正および読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction year of the betsuma thus became known and, in 1926, the building was straightened and re-nailed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>しかし、軸部の弛緩激しく、東大壁の弛緩が特に目立ち、本建物に並行して修理の必要があったのであるが、予算の都合で壁の応急修理のみにとどめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the loosening of the axis parts was intense, and especially the loosening of the east okabe was remarkable, so it was necessary to repair them simultaneously with the main building, but only temporary repairs of the walls were done because of the limited budget.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The frame, however, had become severely loosened and the condition of okabe on the east side was particularly was noticeable being in a desperate need for repairs in concurrence with the main building but, due to the budget constraint, only the walls were repaired as a temporary measure.</e>
<cmt>誤訳を修正および読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The frame, however, had become severely loosened and the condition of okabe on the east side was particularly was noticeable being in a desperate need for repairs in concurrence with the main building but, due to the budget constraint, only the walls were repaired as a temporary measure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="85">
<j>今西家現在の宅地は、北・東とも道路に面して旧状どおり、南面は、県道までになっているが、児童公園南春日神社境内一円も旧宅地であったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present residential land of the Imanishi-ke Jutaku borders the streets on the north and the east as it was, and stretches to the Prefectural Road on the south, but it is said that all over the precincts of Kasuga-jinja Shrine to the south of the Children&apos;s Park was the former residential land, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present residential site of the Imanishi-ke Jutaku faces streets on the north and east sides as it originally did and stretches to a prefectural highway to the south but it seems that the area around the grounds of Kasuga-jinja Shrine to the south of the Children&apos;s Park used to be a part of that property as well.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present residential site of the Imanishi-ke Jutaku faces streets on the north and east sides as it originally did and stretches to a prefectural highway to the south but it seems that the area around the grounds of Kasuga-jinja Shrine to the south of the Children&apos;s Park used to be a part of that property as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="86">
<j>また南を東西に走る県道（御堂筋）は明治天皇ご行幸の際に県に寄贈して開通したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the Prefectural Road (Midosuji) running east and west on the south of this building was donated to the prefecture and opened when Emperor Meiji came here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the prefectural road (Midosuji) running in an east-west direction to the south of this building was donated to the prefecture by the Imanishi family which was inaugurated to mark the occasion of the royal visit by Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the prefectural road (Midosuji) running in an east-west direction to the south of this building was donated to the prefecture by the Imanishi family which was inaugurated to mark the occasion of the royal visit by Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="87">
<j>県道が付設される以前は、現道路上東端に南側借家が南北に建っており、もとは今西家の附属建物の敷地であったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Prefectural Road was constructed, the southern rented houses stood north and south at the east end of the present road, and it is thought that the plot had been originally the premises of the attached buildings of the Imanishi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the prefectural highway was constructed, the south-side rental houses stood north and south at the east end of that road and it seems that this area was originally the site of buildings owned by the Imanishi family.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the prefectural highway was constructed, the south-side rental houses stood north and south at the east end of that road and it seems that this area was originally the site of buildings owned by the Imanishi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>また第二次大戦以前までここに信長公陣屋跡が建っていたが火事を危惧し撤去したとのことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it is said that here stood the vestige of jinya (regional government office) of Lord Nobunaga before World War II, but it was removed for fear that fire might broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that there was the former jinya (regional government office) of Nobunaga ODA at this site before the World War II which has subsequently been removed out of concern for fire danger.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that there was the former jinya (regional government office) of Nobunaga ODA at this site before the World War II which has subsequently been removed out of concern for fire danger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="89">
<j>市に寄贈された西側の現児童公園には、今西家の茶室があったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that there was a chashitsu (tea-ceremony house) of the Imanishi family in the western Children&apos;s Park which was donated to the city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that there was a chashitsu (tea-ceremony house) of the Imanishi family in the present Children&apos;s Park on the west side which was donated to the city.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that there was a chashitsu (tea-ceremony house) of the Imanishi family in the present Children&apos;s Park on the west side which was donated to the city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>今西家の由緒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the Imanishi Family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the Imanishi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the Imanishi Family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>今西家の先祖は、十市城主民部太夫遠武の次男十市治良太夫遠正が廣瀬大社の社司樋口太夫正之の婿養子となり八千余石を領して川井城を築き川井民部少輔中原遠正と称したのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancestor of the Imanishi family started with Jiro Dayu Tomasa TOCHI, the second son of the lord of Tochi-jo Castle, Minbu Dayu Totake, and Tomasa was adapted by his wife&apos;s father, Dayu Masayuki HIGUCHI, a shashi (chief Shinto priesthood) of Hirose-taisha Shrine, and owned a territory of 8000 koku and constructed Kawai-jo Castle, and changed his name to Minbu Shoyu Nakahara Tomasa KAWAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of the Imanishi family began when Jiro Dayu Tomasa TOCHI, born the second son of the lord of Tochi-jo Castle Minbu Dayu Totake, became the adoptive son of his father-in-law Dayu Masayuki HIGUCHI who was a shashi (chief Shinto priesthood) of Hirose-taisha Shrine whereby Jiro Dayu Tomasa became the owner of a territory over 8,000 koku where he built Kawai-jo Castle and began to refer himself as Minbu Shoyu Nakahara Tomasa KAWAI.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of the Imanishi family began when Jiro Dayu Tomasa TOCHI, born the second son of the lord of Tochi-jo Castle Minbu Dayu Totake, became the adoptive son of his father-in-law Dayu Masayuki HIGUCHI who was a shashi (chief Shinto priesthood) of Hirose-taisha Shrine whereby Jiro Dayu Tomasa became the owner of a territory over 8,000 koku where he built Kawai-jo Castle and began to refer himself as Minbu Shoyu Nakahara Tomasa KAWAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>十市遠勝が筒井順慶に圧迫されて今井に亡命した後を追って、永禄九年（1566年）に一族である四代目の川井助衛門尉正治が家臣と共に当地に移住した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tokatsu TOCHI was oppressed by Junkei TSUTSUI and exiled himself to Imai in 1566, the family descendant in the fourth generation Sukeemonnojo Masaharu KAWAI ran after him and immigrated to this place with his vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1566, following Tokatsu TOCHI who was aggrieved by the oppressive Junkei TSUTSUI and went into exile in Imai, Sukeemonnojo Masaharu KAWAI, the fourth head of the family who was an Imanishi clansman and his retainers moved to that location.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1566, following Tokatsu TOCHI who was aggrieved by the oppressive Junkei TSUTSUI and went into exile in Imai, Sukeemonnojo Masaharu KAWAI, the fourth head of the family who was an Imanishi clansman and his retainers moved to that location.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="92">
<j>五代目の川井長左衞門正冬のとき十市氏と川井氏を恃んできた河瀬新左衛門氏兼を石山本願寺顕如上人光佐の門流に属させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the fifth generation Nagazaemon Masafuyu KAWAI was the head of the family, Shinzaemon Ujikane KAWASE came to turn to the Tochi clan and the Kawai clan, and so, they made him belong to mon-ryu (school of sect) of Ishiyama Hongan-ji Kennyo Shonin Kosa to be Nyudo Hyobubo KAWASE, and built a new dojo in Imai-go and appointed him jushoku (a chief priest).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the time of the fifth head of the family Nagazaemon Masafuyu KAWAI, counting on the Tochi clan and Kawai clan, Shinzaemon Ujikane KAWASE moved to Imai-go where Kawase was subsequently made a disciple of the school of Ishiyama Hongan-ji Kennyo Shonin Kosa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the time of the fifth head of the family Nagazaemon Masafuyu KAWAI, counting on the Tochi clan and Kawai clan, Shinzaemon Ujikane KAWASE moved to Imai-go where Kawase was subsequently made a disciple of the school of Ishiyama Hongan-ji Kennyo Shonin Kosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>河瀬入道兵部房とし、新しく今井郷に道場を営立して住職とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawase assumed the Buddhist name of Nyudo Hyobubo KAWASE and built a new dojo of which he was appointed jushoku (the resident priest) in Imai-go.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawase assumed the Buddhist name of Nyudo Hyobubo KAWASE and built a new dojo of which he was appointed jushoku (the resident priest) in Imai-go.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="94">
<j>一向宗と結んで、時の権力者織田信長と闘うために街の周囲に環濠土塁をうがち、西から今井を守るべく櫓などを備えた城構え（現今西家住宅地）を築き城塞都市化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to cooperate with Ikkoshu sect and fight against the then person of power Nobunaga ODA, they dug moat and heaped dorui around the town, and to protect Imai against attacks from the west, they constructed a building like a castle (present-day Imanishi-ke Jutaku) with towers and made the town a fortified city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banding together with the Ikkoshu sect in the fight against the then powerful Nobunaga ODA, Imai-go was turned into a fortress whereby a moat as well as earthen walls were built around the town and, to guard the westernmost of that town, a castle-like structure (the present Imanishi-ke Jutaku site) equipped with various appropriate features such as turret was constructed.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banding together with the Ikkoshu sect in the fight against the then powerful Nobunaga ODA, Imai-go was turned into a fortress whereby a moat as well as earthen walls were built around the town and, to guard the westernmost of that town, a castle-like structure (the present Imanishi-ke Jutaku site) equipped with various appropriate features such as turret was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="95">
<j>信長に対して天正二年（1574年）十市氏および川井氏家臣が中心となって今井郷民が蹶起したが、天正三年（1575年）冬に信長と和した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1574, the people of Imai-go rose against Nobunaga with the vassals of the Tochi clan and the Kawai clan as the main fighting forces, but in the winter of 1575, they made peace with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1574, the people of Imai-go rose against Nobunaga with vassals of the Tochi clan and the Kawai clan playing a key role, but, in the winter of 1575, they made peace with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1574, the people of Imai-go rose against Nobunaga with vassals of the Tochi clan and the Kawai clan playing a key role, but, in the winter of 1575, they made peace with Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="96">
<j>所謂、土民なみになる（武力放棄）という条件で武装が解除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On condition that they should become the same as so-called ordinary peasants (that is, abandon arms), they were disarmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The condition of disarmament was that they should become the same as so-called natives (which means to abandon arms).</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The condition of disarmament was that they should become the same as so-called natives (which means to abandon arms).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="97">
<j>その後、自治都市として海の堺と同じく陸の今井として栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, as autonomous cities, Imai of the land flourished just like Sakai of the sea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town subsequently flourished as a municipal borough being referred to as the inland Imai as opposed to Sakai along the sea.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town subsequently flourished as a municipal borough being referred to as the inland Imai as opposed to Sakai along the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="98">
<j>徳川時代になって、高度の自治を展開したので幕府は今井を町として認め、江戸、大阪、京都、奈良と同様に惣年寄、町年寄をおき町制にあたらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tokugawa period, because Imai had developed high-level autonomy, the bakufu acknowledged Imai as a town, and appointed so-doshiyori and machi-doshiyori and made them govern the town just like Edo, Osaka, Kyoto, and Nara.</e>
<cmt>原稿に「町制にあたらせた」とある部分は、前方の意味を考慮すると「町政にあたらせた」と言いたかったのではないかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the head of the family, although he was nominated for a barony by the government after the Meiji Restoration, the family were so destitute that they could not afford the processing fee for the peerage and he also mentioned that he was proud of his ancestors for not having been arrogant about their power.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the head of the family, although he was nominated for a barony by the government after the Meiji Restoration, the family were so destitute that they could not afford the processing fee for the peerage and he also mentioned that he was proud of his ancestors for not having been arrogant about their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="99">
<j>今井町に惣年寄制がしかれたのは慶長年間（1600年頃）で初めに川井長左衞門正冬（後改め今西氏）、河瀬入道兵部房（後改め今井氏）、尾崎源兵衛、あと上田忠右衛門、を加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was around 1600 when the so-doshiyori system was applied to Imai-cho, and at first Nagazaemon Masafuyu KAWAI (later changed to the Imanishi clan), Nyudo Hyobubo KAWASE (later changed to the Imai clan), and Genbei OZAKI were appointed, and later Chuemon UEDA was added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was around 1600 when the so-doshiyori system was implemented in Imai-cho with Nagazaemon Masafuyu KAWAI (later assumed the new family name of Imanishi), Nyudo Hyobubo KAWASE (later assumed the new family name of Imai) and Genbei OZAKI initially being appointed as so-doshiyori and Chuemon UEDA subsequently joined this team at a later date.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was around 1600 when the so-doshiyori system was implemented in Imai-cho with Nagazaemon Masafuyu KAWAI (later assumed the new family name of Imanishi), Nyudo Hyobubo KAWASE (later assumed the new family name of Imai) and Genbei OZAKI initially being appointed as so-doshiyori and Chuemon UEDA subsequently joined this team at a later date.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="100">
<j>五代目川井長左衞門正冬のとき大坂夏の陣の功により元和七年（1621年）５月郡山城主松平下総守忠明（徳川家康の外孫）より今井の西口にあることから今西姓を名乗るようにすすめられ、その時に薙刀 銘来国俊を拝領している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the fifth generation Nagazaemon Masafuyu was the head of the family, thanks to the achievement in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), he was recommended to change his family name to Imanishi (今西) because his house was at the western entrance (西口) of Imai (今井) by the lord of Koriyama-jo Castle Shimousanokami Tadaaki MATSUDAIRA in June or July, 1621, and then Naginata (a Japanese halberd) with the signature of Kunitoshi RAI was bestowed on him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In late June or July 1621 during the time of the fifth family head Nagazaemon Masafuyu, in recognition of his achievement in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), Masafuyu was given recommendation by the lord of Koriyama-jo Castle Shimousanokami Tadaaki MATSUDAIRA (a grandson of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) to assume the new surname of Imanishi deriving from his house being located at the west (nishi in Japanese) entrance of the town of Imai and, in addition, received a gift of naginata (Japanese halberd) made by the grand master swordsmith Kunitoshi on that occasion.</e>
<cmt>訳抜けを修正、および読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In late June or July 1621 during the time of the fifth family head Nagazaemon Masafuyu, in recognition of his achievement in Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka), Masafuyu was given recommendation by the lord of Koriyama-jo Castle Shimousanokami Tadaaki MATSUDAIRA (a grandson of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA) to assume the new surname of Imanishi deriving from his house being located at the west (nishi in Japanese) entrance of the town of Imai and, in addition, received a gift of naginata (Japanese halberd) made by the grand master swordsmith Kunitoshi on that occasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="101">
<j>2階正面の壁には、向かって右方に川の字の井桁枠で囲み川井氏の定紋を入れ、左には菱形3段に重ねた当家の旗印を付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the front wall on the second floor, Jomon (family crest) of the Kawai clan which is a Chinese character 川 (kawa) surrounded by igetawaku (a figure similar to a Chinese character 井 [i]) is painted on the right half, and Hatajirushi (emblem on flag) of this family which is three lozenges piled vertically is put on the left half.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the front wall on the second floor, jomon (family crest) of the Kawai clan, consisting of three vertical lines to assimilate the Chinese character delineating river (kawa in Japanese) in the igetawaku (similar to the Oxford frame) and hatajirushi (war banners used on the medieval Japanese battlefield) of the family composed of three vertically stacked diamonds are painted in black on the right and left hand sides, respectively.</e>
<cmt>訳抜けを修正、および読みやすく修正しました。また、「旗印」の訳を分かりやすく補足してあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the front wall on the second floor, jomon (family crest) of the Kawai clan, consisting of three vertical lines to assimilate the Chinese character delineating river (kawa in Japanese) in the igetawaku (similar to the Oxford frame) and hatajirushi (war banners used on the medieval Japanese battlefield) of the family composed of three vertically stacked diamonds are painted in black on the right and left hand sides, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="102">
<j>『棟上げ慶安参年参月廿参日』の棟札銘（重要文化財）により、慶安3年（1650年）の建立であることが知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the munafuda-mei (Important Cultural Property) that says &quot;Frameworks were raised on April 23, 1650,&quot; it is known that this building was erected in 1650.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the inscription on munafuda-mei (Important Cultural Property) which reads &quot;Framework was completed on April 23, 1650,&quot; it is understood that the building was erected in 1650.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the inscription on munafuda-mei (Important Cultural Property) which reads &quot;Framework was completed on April 23, 1650,&quot; it is understood that the building was erected in 1650.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="103">
<j>今井町では最も古い民家で、また主屋南隅に接続する角座敷および二階部屋も同期のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the oldest minka in Imai-cho, and kado-zashiki (corner room) which is connected to the south corner of the omoya (main building) and the rooms on the second floor were constructed almost at the same time as the main building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the oldest private residence in Imai-cho and kado-zashiki (corner room) connected to the south corner of the main building as well as the rooms on the second floor were also constructed during the same period as that building.</e>
<cmt>読みやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the oldest private residence in Imai-cho and kado-zashiki (corner room) connected to the south corner of the main building as well as the rooms on the second floor were also constructed during the same period as that building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="104">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>奈良県橿原市今井町3丁目9番25号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">9-25, 3 chome, Imai-cho, Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">9-25, 3 chome, Imai-cho, Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">9-25, 3 chome, Imai-cho, Kashihara City, Nara Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Koba-chan(id:860), Point136(id:211299), Tantal(id:74335), 伊藤ていじ(id:293393), 辻恭三(id:293182), Fromm(id:71291), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>