<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>月華門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekka-mon Gate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekka-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekka-mon Gate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>月華門（げっかもん）は、内裏を構成する内閤門のうちの一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekka-mon Gate is one of naikakumon-gates that make up dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekka-mon Gate was one of the naikaku-mon gates that comprised the dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>・「is」→「was」・「make up」→「comprised」・「the」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekka-mon Gate was one of the naikaku-mon gates that comprised the dairi (Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>紫宸殿南庭（なんてい・だんてい）の西側の門である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a western gate of Shishinden Dan-tei (southern courtyard of Shishin-den Hall).</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was located on the west side of the south garden of the Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall).</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was located on the west side of the south garden of the Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>現在の京都御所にも古式に則って再建されたものが伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gates that were reconstructed in accordance with the old age have been preserved in the present day Kyoto Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gekka-mon Gate that stands in the present Kyoto Imperial Palace was rebuilt according to the ancient design.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gekka-mon Gate that stands in the present Kyoto Imperial Palace was rebuilt according to the ancient design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>校書殿と安福殿との間にあり、南庭東側の日華門とは東西に相対する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located between yoshoden (a building in the Imperial Palace precincts) and Anpukuden Hall, and it is located on the opposite side of Nikka-mon Gate on the east side of the southern courtyard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located between Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall) and Anpukuden Hall, the gate faced Nikka-mon Gate on the east side of the south garden.</e>
<cmt>「日華門」の記事と統一して書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located between Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall) and Anpukuden Hall, the gate faced Nikka-mon Gate on the east side of the south garden in an east-west direction.</e>
<cmt>「東西に」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>西の中門ともいい、右近衛府の陣に充てられたため、右近陣（うこんのじん）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as chumon (inner gate) on the west side or Ukon no (right division) jin (position) that was the position of guards for Sayu Konoefu (the right division of the Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called &quot;Nishi no Chu-mon&quot; (lit. western inner gate) and &quot;Ukonfu no Jin&quot; (lit. Post of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) because it was assigned to serve as a post for the Ukonfu (Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called &quot;Nishi no Chu-mon&quot; (lit. western inner gate) and &quot;Ukon no Jin&quot; (lit. Post of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) because it was assigned to serve as a post for the Ukonfu (Right Division of Inner Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Ukonfu no Jin&quot; → &quot;Ukon no Jin&quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>