<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>難波長柄豊崎宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naniwa no Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naniwa Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace (a palace in the ancient capital of Japan in the Asuka period)</e>
<cmt>原文に読みを合わせ、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naniwa Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace (a palace in the ancient capital of Japan in the Asuka period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>難波長柄豊碕（埼）宮（なにわながらのとよさきのみや）は、飛鳥時代の日本の首都の宮殿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naniwa Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace is a palace in the capital of Japan in the Asuka Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naniwa Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace was a palace in the capital of Japan in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naniwa Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace was a palace in the capital of Japan in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>前期難波宮とも呼ばれ、日本最初の本格的な首都の宮殿建築とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also referred to as the early Naniwa no Miya Palace, Naniwa no Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace is considered to be Japan&apos;s first full-scale palace architecture of the capital city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also referred to as the early Naniwa no Miya Palace, it is considered to be Japan&apos;s first full-scale palace architecture of the capital city.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also referred to as the early Naniwa no Miya Palace, it is considered to be Japan&apos;s first full-scale palace architecture of the capital city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>乙巳の変（645年）の後、天智天皇らによって企画され、652年に完成し、孝徳天皇が遷都した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Isshi-no-hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) (645), Naniwa no Nagara no Toyosaki no Miya Palace was designed by Emperor Tenchi and the other concerned parties and Emperor Kotoku relocated the capital when that palace was completed in 652.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Isshi Incident (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) (645), the Palace was designed by Emperor Tenchi and others and Emperor Kotoku relocated the capital when that palace was completed in 652.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Isshi Incident (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) (645), the Palace was designed by Emperor Tenchi and others and Emperor Kotoku relocated the capital when that palace was completed in 652.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>建物は、686年（朱鳥元）の正月に全焼するまで、現在の大阪市中央区 (大阪市)に34年の間存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until it was burnt down on New Year&apos;s Day of 686, the building existed for 34 years in Chuo Ward, Osaka City as we know it today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until it was burnt down in February 686, the building existed for 34 years in present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until it was burnt down in February 686, the building existed for 34 years in present-day Chuo Ward, Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>654年（白雉5）孝徳帝の没後、斉明天皇（皇極天皇が重祚）により飛鳥板蓋宮に遷宮された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 654, after the passing of Emperor Kotoku, Emperor Saimei (a second accession of Emperor Kogyoku) transferred the deity to Asuka Itabuki no Miya palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 654, after the passing of Emperor Kotoku, Empress Saimei (a second accession of Empress Kogyoku) moved to Asuka Itabuki no Miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 654, after the passing of Emperor Kotoku, Empress Saimei (a second accession of Empress Kogyoku) moved to Asuka Itabuki no Miya Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後は、744年（天平16）になって同じ場所に聖武天皇によって宮殿が築かれた（「後期難波宮」 難波京参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another palace was subsequently built by Emperor Shomu at the same location in 744 (See &apos;the late Naniwa no Miya Palace&apos; under Naniwa-kyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another palace was subsequently built by Emperor Shomu at the same location in 744 (See the article of &apos;the late Naniwa no Miya Palace&apos; under Naniwa-kyo [an ancient capital of Naniwa]).</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another palace was subsequently built by Emperor Shomu at the same location in 744 (See the article of &apos;the late Naniwa no Miya Palace&apos; under Naniwa-kyo [an ancient capital of Naniwa]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>この宮は、上町台地の上にあり、大正2年(1913)に陸軍の倉庫建築中に数個の重圏文・蓮華文の瓦が発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This palace was located on the Uemachi plateau and, in 1913, several roof tiles with the jukenmon (concentric circle design) and rengemon (lotus flower patterns) patterns were found during the construction of an army warehouse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This palace was located on the Uemachi plateau and, in 1913, several roof tiles with the jukenmon (concentric circle design) and rengemon (lotus flower patterns) were found during the construction of an army warehouse.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This palace was located on the Uemachi plateau and, in 1913, several roof tiles with the jukenmon (concentric circle design) and rengemon (lotus flower patterns) were found during the construction of an army warehouse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>昭和28年、同地付近から鴟尾（しび）が発見されたのがきっかけで、難波宮址顕彰会の発掘・調査が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1953, in the wake of the discovery of Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile) in the vicinity of the location where the roof tiles were found, excavation and study by Naniwakyushi Kenshokai got underway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1953, in the wake of the discovery of Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile) in the vicinity of the location where the roof tiles were found, excavation and study by Naniwakyushi Kenshokai (Association of honoring publicly for Naniwa Palace site) got underway.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1953, in the wake of the discovery of Shibi (ornamental ridge-end tile) in the vicinity of the location where the roof tiles were found, excavation and study by Naniwakyushi Kenshokai (Association of honoring publicly for Naniwa Palace site) got underway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>現在、難波宮の跡地の一部は、難波宮史跡公園となり、大阪城の南に整備されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, part of the remains of Naniwanomiya Palace has turned into Naniwa no Miya Historical Park which is being maintained to the south of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, part of the remains of Naniwa no Miya Palace has turned into Naniwa no Miya Historical Park which is being maintained to the south of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, part of the remains of Naniwa no Miya Palace has turned into Naniwa no Miya Historical Park which is being maintained to the south of Osaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>前期・後期の遺跡を元に建物の基壇などが設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that park, some exhibits such as foundations of the buildings constructed based on the remains of the early and late Naniwanomiya Palace have been installed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that park, some exhibits such as foundations of the buildings constructed based on the remains of the early and late Naniwa no Miya Palace have been installed.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that park, some exhibits such as foundations of the buildings constructed based on the remains of the early and late Naniwa no Miya Palace have been installed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), けふこえて(id:17107), Straysheep(id:42448), E-tns(id:138039), Takumadaserikouy(id:252567), 663highland(id:18755), うぃき野郎(id:53567), アスカ(id:9205), 明日香(id:82152), Peachkiller(id:99202), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>