<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>京都府立総合資料館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>京都府立総合資料館（きょうとふりつそうごうしりょうかん）は、京都市左京区にある、図書館、文書館、博物館の機能を兼ね備えた総合文化施設である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in Sakyo Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives is a comprehensive cultural facility that serves as a library, documents archives, and a museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in Sakyo Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives is a comprehensive cultural facility that serves as a library, document archives, and a museum.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in Sakyo-ku Ward of Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives is a comprehensive cultural facility that serves as a library, document archives, and a museum.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都府に関する図書、古文書（こもんじょ）、美術工芸資料などを収集・保管、研究、公開することを目的としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its objectives are collecting, storing, studying, and publishing of books, ancient documents, and materials of arts and crafts related to Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its objectives are collecting, storing, studying, and publishing of books, ancient documents, and materials of arts and crafts related to Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its objectives are collecting, storing, studying, and publishing of books, ancient documents, and materials of arts and crafts related to Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>収蔵品には一般図書のほか、京都府発足以来の行政文書、国宝の「東寺百合文書」（とうじひゃくごうもんじょ）のような貴重な歴史資料も数多く含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its collections include the administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture since it was inaugurated, and many valued historical materials such as &apos;Toji Hyakugomonjo Document,&apos;as well as general books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its collections include the administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture since it was inaugurated, and many valued historical materials such as the &apos;Toji Hyakugomonjo Document,&apos;as well as general books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its collections include the administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture since it was inaugurated, and many valued historical materials such as the &apos;To-ji Hyakugo Monjo&apos; (100 case documents, of the To-ji Temple), a National Treasure, as well as general books.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>総合資料館は京都市街の北部に位置し、近隣には京都府立植物園、京都府立大学、京都コンサートホールなどの文化施設が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives is located in the north of the Kyoto City urban area, and in its neighborhood are many cultural facilities such as the Kyoto Botanical Garden, Kyoto Prefectural University, and Kyoto Concert Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives is located in the north of the Kyoto City urban area, and in its neighborhood are many cultural facilities such as the Kyoto Botanical Garden, Kyoto Prefectural University, and Kyoto Concert Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives is located in the north of the Kyoto City urban area, and in its neighborhood are many cultural facilities such as the Kyoto Botanical Garden, Kyoto Prefectural University, and Kyoto Concert Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>総合資料館の開館は1963年（昭和38年）で、京都府立図書館（京都市左京区岡崎成勝寺町）のその当時の蔵書21万冊のうち18万冊を引き継いでスタートした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It opened in 1963, taking over 180,000 books out of 210,000 books stored in Kyoto Prefectural Library (Okazaki Seishoji Cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It opened in 1963, taking over 180,000 books out of 210,000 books stored in Kyoto Prefectural Library (Okazaki Seishoji Cho, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It opened in 1963, taking over 180,000 books out of 210,000 books stored in Kyoto Prefectural Library (Okazaki Seishoji-cho, Sakyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City) at that time.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このように、総合資料館自体の開館は比較的新しいが、その蔵書は1898年（明治31年）に発足した府立図書館のものを引き継いでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is relatively new, its collections include books that had been stored by Kyoto Prefectural Library opened in 1898.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is relatively new, its collections include books that had been stored by Kyoto Prefectural Library opened in 1898.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is relatively new, its collections include books that had been stored by Kyoto Prefectural Library opened in 1898.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>府立図書館の歴史をさらにさかのぼれば、その前身は三条東洞院（現在の京都市中京区、中京郵便局あたり）に1873年（明治6年）に設置された、府立の「集書院」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of Kyoto Prefectural Library dates back to the prefectural &apos;Shushoin Library&apos; established at Sanjo Higashinotoin (neighborhood of the Nakagyo Post Office in Nakagyo Ward of Kyoto City) in 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of Kyoto Prefectural Library dates back to the prefectural &apos;Shushoin Library&apos; established at Sanjo Higashinotoin (neighborhood of the Nakagyo Post Office in Nakagyo Ward of Kyoto City) in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of Kyoto Prefectural Library dates back to the prefectural &apos;Shushoin Library&apos; established at Sanjo Higashinotoin (neighborhood of the Nakagyo Post Office in Nakagyo-ku Ward of Kyoto City) in 1873.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>総合資料館には、一般図書約32万冊のほか、京都府の行政資料、社寺や旧家伝来の古文書、美術工芸品、玩具、人形、民俗資料などの実物資料などが収蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stores tangible real materials, such as the administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture, ancient documents of temples, shrines and old families, arts and crafts, toys, dolls, folk materials, as well as 320,000 items of general books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stores real tangible materials, such as the administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture, ancient documents of temples, shrines and old families, arts and crafts, toys, dolls, folk materials, as well as 320,000 general books.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stores real tangible materials, such as the administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture, ancient documents of temples, shrines and old families, arts and crafts, toys, dolls, folk materials, as well as 320,000 general books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このうち、実物資料については財団法人京都文化財団にその管理が委託されているが、総合資料館内の展示室でも折りにふれて展示公開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The management of those real materials is entrusted to Kyoto Cultural Foundation, and there are occasional exhibitions of them at the display room of this library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The management of these real materials is entrusted to the Kyoto Cultural Foundation, and there are occasional exhibitions of them in the library display room.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The management of these real materials is entrusted to the Kyoto Cultural Foundation, and there are occasional exhibitions of them in the library display room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>館の建物は地上4階、地下1階建で、図書閲覧室、文書閲覧室のほか、学生用の学習室、古文書、実物資料などの展示会が行われる展示室などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its building has four stories above ground with one basement floor, housing a study room for students, exhibition rooms for ancient documents and real historical materials, as well as reading rooms of books and documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building has four stories above ground with one basement floor, housing a study room for students, exhibition rooms for ancient documents and real historical materials, as well as reading rooms for books and documents.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building has four storeys above ground with one basement floor, housing a study room for students, exhibition rooms for ancient documents and real historical materials, as well as reading rooms for books and documents.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>コレクション</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collections</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collections</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>図書資料は、京都府に関するものを中心に収集され、蜷川虎三（元京都府知事、1897 - 1981）や、吉田光邦（元京都文化博物館長、京都大学名誉教授、1921 – 1991）などの旧蔵書がまとまって収蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of its book collections are related to Kyoto Prefecture, including the whole old book stocks of Torazo NINAGAWA (former governor of Kyoto Prefecture, 1897 - 1981) and Mitsukuni YOSHIDA (former director of the Museum of Kyoto, emeritus professor of Kyoto University, 1921 - 1991).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of its book collections are related to Kyoto Prefecture, including the whole old book stocks of Torazo NINAGAWA (former governor of Kyoto Prefecture, 1897 - 1981) and Mitsukuni YOSHIDA (former director of the Museum of Kyoto, emeritus professor of Kyoto University, 1921 - 1991).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of its book collections are related to Kyoto Prefecture, including the whole old book stocks of Torazo NINAGAWA (former governor of Kyoto Prefecture, 1897 - 1981) and Mitsukuni YOSHIDA (former director of the Museum of Kyoto, emeritus professor of Kyoto University, 1921 - 1991).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このほかに、歌人・作家の吉井勇（1886 - 1960）の蔵書、遺品などからなる「吉井勇資料」、マルクス経済学者河上肇の著書や彼に関する資料、原稿、遺品などからなる「河上肇文庫」などのコレクションもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also has &apos;Yoshii Isamu Shiryo Materials&apos; consisting of the book collection and relics of Isamu YOSHII (a poet and novelist, 1886 - 1960), and &apos;Kawakami Hajime Bunko (Hajime Kawakami Library)&apos; consisting of Marxist Economist Hajime KAWAKAMI&apos;s books, related materials to him, his manuscripts, and relics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also has &apos;Yoshii Isamu Shiryo Materials&apos; consisting of the book collection and relics of Isamu YOSHII (a poet and novelist, 1886 - 1960), and &apos;Kawakami Hajime Bunko (Hajime Kawakami Library)&apos; consisting of Marxist Economist Hajime KAWAKAMI&apos;s books, related materials to him, his manuscripts, and relics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also has &apos;Yoshii Isamu Shiryo Materials&apos; consisting of the book collection and relics of Isamu YOSHII (a poet and novelist, 1886 - 1960), and &apos;Kawakami Hajime Bunko&apos; (Hajime Kawakami Library) consisting of Marxist Economist Hajime KAWAKAMI&apos;s books, related materials to him, his manuscripts, and relics.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>行政資料は、京都府発足以来の府庁文書のほか、旧郡役所、豊岡県、宮津県などからの引き継ぎ文書も保管されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its administrative documents include Kyoto Prefectural documents since it was inaugurated, as well as transferred materials from former county offices, former Toyooka Prefecture, and former Miyazu Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its administrative documents include Kyoto Prefectural documents since it was inaugurated, as well as transferred materials from former county offices, former Toyooka Prefecture, and former Miyazu Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its administrative documents include Kyoto Prefectural documents since it was inaugurated, as well as transferred materials from former county offices, former Toyoka Prefecture, and former Miyazu Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>古文書関係では、京都市南区にある空海ゆかりの寺院・東寺（教王護国寺）に伝来した国宝の「東寺百合文書」をはじめ、東寺の子院・観智院に伝来した「観智院伝来文書典籍類」、「革嶋家文書」が重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its collection of ancient documents includes &apos;To-ji Hyakugomonjo Document,&apos; a National Treasure, which had been handed down at To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) that is associated with Kukai, a well-known Buddhist priest, in Minami Ward of Kyoto City, and &apos;Ancient documents and books of Kanchi-in Temple&apos; that had been handed down at Kanchi-in, a sub temple of To-ji, and &apos;Kawashimake Bunsho (the Kawashima family documents),&apos; which are both designated as Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>観智院伝来文書典籍類→Ancient documents and books of Kanchi-in Temple[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its collection of ancient documents includes the &apos;To-ji Hyakugomonjo Document,&apos; a National Treasure, which had been handed down at To-ji Temple (Kyoogokoku-ji Temple) that is associated with Kukai, a well-known Buddhist priest, in Minami Ward of Kyoto City, and &apos;Ancient documents and books of Kanchi-in Temple&apos; that had been handed down at Kanchi-in, a sub temple of To-ji, and &apos;Kawashimake Bunsho (the Kawashima family documents),&apos; which are both designated as Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its collection of ancient documents includes the &apos;To-ji Hyakugo Monjo Document,&apos; a National Treasure, which had been handed down at To-ji Temple (also known as Kyogokoku-ji Temple) that is associated with Kukai, a well-known Buddhist priest, in Minami-ku Ward of Kyoto City, and &apos;Ancient documents and books of Kanchiin Temple&apos; that had been handed down at Kanchiin Temple, a sub temple of To-ji Temple, and &apos;Kawashimake Bunsho&apos; (the Kawashima family documents), which are both designated as Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>実物資料としては、日本画家で風俗史家でもあった吉川観方（1894 - 1979）が収集した衣服、玩具などの風俗資料、古典楽器の佐竹コレクション（和楽器師・佐竹藤三郎らの収集）、郷土玩具の朏（みかづき）コレクション（朏健之助収集）などが著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its famous real objects collections: folk materials such as clothes and toys collected by Kanpo YOSHIKAWA (1894 - 1979) who was a Japanese-style painter and a folk historian; Satake Collection of traditional musical instruments (by Tozaburo SATAKE, a craftsman of Japanese musical instruments, and others); and &apos;Mikazuki Collection&apos; of folk toys (by Kennosuke MIKAZUKI).</e>
<cmt>佐竹コレクション→Satake Collection（佐竹コレクション）[定訳不明]朏コレクション→Mikazuki Collection（朏コレクション）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its famous real objects collections: folk materials such as clothes and toys collected by Kanpo YOSHIKAWA (1894 - 1979) who was a Japanese-style painter and a folk historian; Satake Collection of traditional musical instruments (by Tozaburo SATAKE, a craftsman of Japanese musical instruments, and others); and &apos;Mikazuki Collection&apos; of folk toys (by Kennosuke MIKAZUKI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its famous real objects collections: Folk materials such as clothes and toys collected by Kanpo YOSHIKAWA (1894 - 1979) who was a Japanese-style painter and a folk historian; Satake Collection of traditional musical instruments (by Tozaburo SATAKE, a craftsman of Japanese musical instruments, and others); and &apos;Mikazuki Collection&apos; of folk toys (collected by Kennosuke MIKAZUKI).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、これら実物資料の管理は、京都文化博物館を運営する財団法人京都文化財団が行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Culture Foundation that operates the Museum of Kyoto takes care of these objects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Culture Foundation that operates the Museum of Kyoto takes care of these objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Culture Foundation that operates the Museum of Kyoto takes care of these objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>国指定文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>東寺百合文書（国宝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To-ji Hyakugomonjo Document (National Treasure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To-ji Hyakugomonjo Document (National Treasure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To-ji Hyakugo Monjo Document (National Treasure)</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>東寺の宝蔵に伝来した膨大な文書群で、奈良時代（8世紀）から江戸時代末期に至る24,067通が国宝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a set of huge amount of documents that had been stored in the treasure house of To-ji, of which 24,067 items of the Nara period (the eighth century) through the Edo period are designated as National Treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This set includes a huge amount of documents that had been stored in the treasure house of To-ji, of which 24,067 items from the Nara period (the eighth century) through the Edo period were designated as National Treasures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This set includes a huge amount of documents that had been stored in the treasure house of To-ji, of which 24,067 items from the Nara period (the eighth century) through the Edo period were designated as National Treasures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>荘園関係文書をはじめとして、多岐にわたる文書が含まれ、経済史、仏教史のみならず、日本史研究全般にとって貴重な史料を多く含んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It includes many historical documents of a variety of kinds such as Shoen (manor) related ones, which are very important not only for economical history and Buddhism history, but also for the whole study of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This includes many varieties of historical documents such as those related to Shoen (manor), that are very important not only for the history of economics and Buddhism, but also for the whole study of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This includes many varieties of historical documents such as those related to Shoen (manor), that are very important not only for the history of economics and Buddhism, but also for the whole study of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>掛軸・巻物等に改装されずに作成当初の形態を保ったまま保存されている文書が多いことも、史料としての価値を高めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are valued as historical materials because they are preserved as they were made without being redecorated into scrolls or hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are valued as historical materials because they are preserved as they were originally made without being converted into scrolls or hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are valued as historical materials because they are preserved as they were originally made without being converted into scrolls or hanging scrolls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸時代の加賀藩主前田綱紀は、この文書の価値を認め、保存のための文書箱100合を1685年（貞享2年）に寄進している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunanori MAEDA, a lord of Kaga han (feudal domain), recognizing the values of these documents, donated a hundred Go of document boxes for preservation of them to the temple in 1685.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunanori MAEDA, a lord of Kaga han (feudal domain), recognizing the value of these documents, donated a hundred Go of document boxes for preservation to the temple in 1685.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunanori MAEDA, a lord of Kaga clan, recognizing the value of these documents, donated a hundred of document boxes for preservation to the temple in 1685.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「合」は蓋と身からなる容器を数える際の単位で、「百合文書」の名はここに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Hyakugomonjo&apos;(literally, a hundred Go of documents) comes from this &apos;Go&apos; which is a unit for counting containers consisting a box and a lid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name &apos;Hyakugomonjo&apos;(literally, a hundred Go of documents) comes from this &apos;Go&apos; which is a unit for counting containers consisting of a box and a lid.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name &apos;Hyakugo Monjo&apos;(literally, a hundred of documents) comes from this &apos;go&apos; which is a unit for counting containers consisting of a box and a lid.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>東寺観智院伝来文書典籍類（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient documents and books of Kanchi-in Temple (東寺観智院伝来文書典籍類) (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient documents and books of Kanchi-in Temple (東寺観智院伝来文書典籍類) (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient documents and books of Kanchiin Temple of To-ji Temple (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>漢字をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>東寺の子院・観智院に伝来したもので、「東寺百合文書」と混在していたが、総合資料館による調査の結果、分離されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These documents had been handed down at Kanchi-in Temple, a sub temple of To-ji, and they had been mixed with &apos;To-ji Hyakugomonjo Document,&apos; but the research of this library separated them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These documents had been handed down at Kanchi-in Temple, a sub temple of To-ji, and they had been mixed with the &apos;To-ji Hyakugomonjo Document,&apos; but the research of this library separated them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These documents had been handed down at Kanchiin Temple, a sub temple of To-ji Temple, and they had been mixed with the &apos;To-ji Hyakugo Monjo Document,&apos; but the research of this library separated them.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>革嶋家文書（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawashimake Bunsho (the Kawashima family documents) (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawashimake Bunsho (the Kawashima family documents) (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawashimake Bunsho (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>前出補足をのぞきました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>京都市西京区川島の旧家・革嶋家に伝来した文書類で、2,459通が重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are the hereditary documents of the Kawashima family, an old family in Kawashima of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, and a set of 2,459 items of them is designated as Important Cultural Property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are the hereditary documents of the Kawashima family, an old family in Kawashima of Nishikyo Ward, Kyoto City, and among them, a set containing 2,459 items is designated as Important Cultural Property.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are the hereditary documents of the Kawashima family, an old family in Kawashima of Nishikyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, and among them, a set containing 2,459 items is designated as Important Cultural Property.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>鎌倉時代から大正時代に至る800年に亘って作成された家文書がまとまって伝存する点で貴重である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variable because a set of 800 family&apos;s document written from the Kamakura period to the Taisho period exist today.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>京都府行政文書（重要文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administrative documents of Kyoto Prefecture (Important Cultural Property)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="29">
<j>府庁文書12,641点、府庁史料2,110点、郡役所資料249点、豊岡県第14・15大区区務所文書18点、宮津藩政記録389点が重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties: 12,641 items of prefectural government documents: 2,110 items of prefectural government historical materials: 249 items of county government materials: eighteen items of local administrative offices documents of the fourteenth and the fifteenth Wards of former Toyooka Prefecture: 389 items of the administrative records of Miyazu han.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties: 12,641 items of prefectural government documents: 2,110 items of prefectural government historical materials: 249 items of county government materials: eighteen items of local administrative offices documents of the fourteenth and the fifteenth Wards of former Toyooka Prefecture: 389 items of the administrative records of Miyazu han.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties: 12,641 items of prefectural government documents: 2,110 items of prefectural government historical materials: 249 items of county government materials: eighteen items of local administrative offices documents of the fourteenth and the fifteenth Wards of former Toyoka Prefecture: 389 items of the administrative records of Miyazu clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>時代的には、1867年（慶応3年）の京都町奉行所廃止から、1947年（昭和22年）の地方自治法施行までのものが文化財指定対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of the documents designated as Cultural Properties: from the year 1867 when Kyoto Machibugyo (Kyoto City Magistrate) was abolished to the year 1947 when the Local Autonomy Law was put into effect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of the documents designated as Cultural Properties: from the year 1867 when Kyoto Machibugyo (Kyoto City Magistrate) was abolished to the year 1947 when the Local Autonomy Law was put into effect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of the documents designated as Cultural Properties: From 1867 when Kyoto Machibugyo (Kyoto City Magistrate) was abolished to 1947 when the Local Autonomy Law was put into effect.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>豊岡県第14・15大区区務所文書と宮津藩政記録とは、それぞれ豊岡県、宮津県（いずれも明治時代初期に廃止）の旧蔵文書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local administrative offices documents of the fourteenth and the fifteenth Wards of former Toyooka Prefecture and the administrative records of Miyazu han used to be stored in Toyooka Prefecture and Miyazu Prefecture (both of them were abolished in the early years of the Meiji period), respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local administrative offices documents of the fourteenth and the fifteenth Wards of former Toyooka Prefecture and the administrative records of Miyazu han used to be stored in Toyooka Prefecture and Miyazu Prefecture (both of them were abolished in the early years of the Meiji period), respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local administrative offices documents of the fourteenth and the fifteenth Wards of former Toyoka Prefecture and the administrative records of Miyazu clan used to be stored in Toyoka Prefecture and Miyazu Prefecture (both of them were abolished in the early years of the Meiji period), respectively.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>出版物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Publications</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Publications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Publications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>京都府資料目録 - 京都府立総合資料館編集・刊行、1984年（昭和59年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Catalogue of documents of Kyoto Prefecture: edited and published by Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives in 1984</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Catalogue of documents of Kyoto Prefecture: edited and published by Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives in 1984</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Catalogue of documents of Kyoto Prefecture: Edited and published by Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives in 1984</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>1984年以降の収蔵品については、随時「追録」が刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Addenda&apos; of the catalogue of items collected in and after 1984 are published as needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Addenda&apos; of the catalogue of items collected in and after 1984 are published as needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Addenda&apos; of the catalogue of items collected in and after 1984 are published as needed.</e>
<cmt>半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>京都府関係雑誌論文目録 - 京都府立総合資料館編集・刊行、1971年（昭和46年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Catalogue of articles in magazines on Kyoto Prefecture: edited and published by Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives in 1971</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Catalogue of articles in magazines on Kyoto Prefecture: edited and published by Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives in 1971</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Catalogue of articles in magazines on Kyoto Prefecture: Edited and published by Kyoto Prefectural Library and Archives in 1971</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>以上のほか、京都府史に関する図書、特別展図録などを刊行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also publishes books on the history of Kyoto Prefecture and picture records of its special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also publishes books on the history of Kyoto Prefecture and picture records of its special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also publishes books on the history of Kyoto Prefecture and picture records of its special exhibitions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>所在地・利用情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location and access information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location and access information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location and Access Information</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>住所京都府京都市左京区下鴨半木町1-4 北山通に面す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located at Shimogamohangi Cho 1-4, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, it faces Kitayama-dori Street.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located at Shimogamohangi Cho 1-4, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, it faces Kitayama-dori Street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located: Faced Kitagawa-dori Street, 1-4 Shimogamohangi-cho, Sakyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>交通京都市営地下鉄京都市営地下鉄烏丸線北山駅下車、すぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is close to Kitayama Station of Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is close to Kitayama Station of Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is close to Kitayama Station of Kyoto City Subway Karasuma Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="38">
<j>開館時間午前9時00分～午後4時30分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opening hours: 9:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opening hours: 9:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opening hours: 9:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>休館日毎月第2水曜、祝日（日曜と重なる場合は翌日）、年末年始、資料整理期間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Closed: the second Wednesday every month: National Holidays (if it comes on Sunday, then the next day): the year end and the New Year days: inventory period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Closed: the second Wednesday every month: National Holidays (if it comes on Sunday, then the next day): the year end and the New Year days: inventory period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Closed: The second Wednesday every month; National Holidays (if it comes on Sunday, then the next day); the year end and the New Year days; inventory period</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>周辺情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighborhood information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neighborhood information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearby Attractions</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="40">
<j>京都府立大学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural University</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Prefectural University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Prefectural University</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>京都府立陶板名画の庭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Garden of Fine Art, Koto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Garden of Fine Art, Koto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Garden of Fine Art, Kyoto</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>京都コンサートホール</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Concert Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Concert Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Concert Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ＋－(id:17104), BoB774(id:148281), 目白梅(id:141468), Rusk(id:9895), Miyuki h(id:84952), 味村(id:128437), Miya(id:1881), Urania(id:7213), うぃき野郎(id:53567), 663highland(id:18755), Ikespirit(id:120987), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>