<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>アサヒビール大山崎山荘美術館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asahi Beer Oyamazaki Villa Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asahi Beer Oyamazaki Villa Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asahi Beer Oyamazaki Villa Museum of Art</e>
<cmt>ホームページに合わせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>アサヒビール大山崎山荘美術館（あさひびーる・おおやまざきさんそうびじゅつかん）は、アサヒビール運営による私立美術館である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asahi Beer Oyamazaki Villa Museum is a private art museum operated by Asahi Breweries, Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asahi Beer Oyamazaki Villa Museum is a private art museum operated by Asahi Breweries, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asahi Beer Oyamazaki Villa Museum of Art is a private art museum operated by Asahi Breweries, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都府乙訓郡大山崎町に立地。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in Oyamazaki Cho of Otokuni Gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located in Oyamazaki Cho, Otokuni Gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located in Oyamazaki-cho, Otokuni-gun, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>大阪府と京都府の境にある天王山の山腹に位置し、真下に木津川・淀川・桂川の三川が淀川へと合流する美しい風景を見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is builtd at the mountainside of Tenno-zan Mountain which is on the border of Osaka Prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture, and it overlooks beautiful scenery that Kizu-gawa River, Uji-gawa River, and Katsura-gawa River join together to make Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>原文は，「木津川・宇治川・桂川の三川が淀川へと」と解釈するのが地理の事実に即していると思われます．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is built on the mountainside of Tenno-zan Mountain which is on the boundary of Osaka Prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture, and overlooks beautiful scenery where Kizu-gawa River, Uji-gawa River, and Katsura-gawa River join together to make Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Error, grammar and word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is built on the mountainside of Mt. Tenno which is on the boundary of Osaka Prefecture and Kyoto Prefecture, and overlooks beautiful scenery where the Kizu-gawa River, the Uji-gawa River, and the Katsura-gawa River join together to make the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>大山崎山荘美術館のコレクションの中核は、朝日麦酒株式会社（現アサヒビール）の創業者として知られる関西の実業家・山本為三郎の収集したコレクションである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The core of the collection of Oyamazaki Villa Museum is the one that was collected by Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO, a businessman in the Kansai region who was known as the founder of Asahi Breweries, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>英語名は朝日麦酒株式会社のときから，Asahi Breweries, Ltd. だったようです．(アサヒビール英語website: http://www.asahibeer.co.jp/english/companye/history.html)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The centerpiece of the collection of Oyamazaki Villa Museum is the items collected by Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO, a businessman in the Kansai region who was known as the founder of Asahi Breweries, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The centerpiece of the collection of Oyamazaki Villa Museum of Art is the items collected by Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO, a businessman in the Kansai region who was known as the founder of Asahi Breweries, Ltd.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>彼は大正から昭和初期に柳宗悦らが提唱した「日本民藝運動」の賛同者であり支援者でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He agreed to and supported &apos;Nihon Mingei Undo&apos; (Japanese folk art movement) that Muneyoshi YANAGI and others set up in Taisho and in the beginning of the Showa Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He agreed to and supported the &apos;Nihon Mingei Undo&apos; (Japanese folk art movement) that Muneyoshi YANAGI and others set up from the Taisho to the beginning of the Showa Period.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He agreed to and supported the &apos;Nihon Mingei Undo&apos; (Japanese folk art movement) that Muneyoshi YANAGI and others set up from the Taisho period to the beginning of the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>大山崎山荘には民芸運動にかかわる河井寛次郎、バーナード・リーチ、濱田庄司、富本憲吉、棟方志功および芹沢けい介といった作家たちとの交流の中で収集された作品が展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyamazaki Villa Museum exhibits works he collected when he interacted with artists who were involved in the movement, such as Kanjiro KAWAI, Bernard LEACH, Shoji HAMADA, Kenkichi TOMIMOTO, Shiko MUNAKATA, and Keisuke SERIZAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyamazaki Villa Museum exhibits works he collected through his interaction with artists who were involved in the movement such as Kanjiro KAWAI, Bernard LEACH, Shoji HAMADA, Kenkichi TOMIMOTO, Shiko MUNAKATA and Keisuke SERIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural, and punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyamazaki Villa exhibits works collected through his interaction with artists who were involved in the movement such as Kanjiro KAWAI, Bernard LEACH, Shoji HAMADA, Kenkichi TOMIMOTO, Shiko MUNAKATA and Keisuke SERIZAWA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>陶磁器・染織・絵画などの作品や、彼らにインスピレーションを与えた朝鮮王朝の古陶磁、イギリスのスリップウェアなどの古陶磁といった、生活用品でもあった美術品がおさめられているが、これらは山本自身が日常親しく愛用したものばかりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stores not only art works of ceramic ware, dyed fabrics, and paintings, but also artistic livingware such as old ceramics of Korean Dynasties that inspired them and pieces of Slipware that is the old pottery of England, which Yamamoto himself loved to use daily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection contains not only art works including ceramic ware, dyed fabrics and paintings, but also everyday pieces which are considered works of art and which inspired him, such as ancient ceramics from the time of the Korean Dynasties, and pieces of Slipware, a type of ancient English pottery, which Yamamoto himself loved to use daily.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for clarity and to improve word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection contains not only art works including ceramic ware, dyed fabrics and paintings, but also everyday pieces which are considered works of art and which inspired him, such as ancient ceramics from the time of the Korean Dynasties, and pieces of Slipware, a type of ancient English pottery, which Yamamoto himself loved to use daily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ほかにも、クロード・モネの絵画『睡蓮』連作を複数所有するほか、モーリス・ド・ヴラマンク、アメデオ・モディリアーニ、パウル・クレー、イサム・ノグチ、アルベルト・ジャコメッティ、ヘンリー・ムーアなど、第二次世界大戦前後の近現代美術も展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it owns more than one pieces of &quot;Water Lilies&quot; by Claude MONET, and it exhibits modern works of artists in and around the time of the Second World War, such as Maurice de VLAMINCK, Amedeo MODIGLIANI, Paul KLEE, Isamu NOGUCHI, Alberto GIACOMETTI, and Henry MOORE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it contains more than one of the series of paintings entitled &quot;Water Lilies&quot; by Claude MONET, and it exhibits modern works of artists in and around the time of the Second World War, such as Maurice de VLAMINCK, Amedeo MODIGLIANI, Paul KLEE, Isamu NOGUCHI, Alberto GIACOMETTI and Henry MOORE.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it contains more than one of the series of paintings entitled &quot;Water-Lilies&quot; by Claude MONET, and it exhibits modern works of artists in and around the time of the Second World War, such as Maurice de VLAMINCK, Amedeo MODIGLIANI, Paul KLEE, Isamu NOGUCHI, Alberto GIACOMETTI and Henry MOORE.</e>
<cmt>美術館ホームページの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>建物は実業家・加賀正太郎が1932年の昭和初期に完成させた三階建てのイギリス・チューダー様式の山荘である本館と、それとは別に隣接して地下に作られた安藤忠雄設計の現代建築の新館「地中の宝石箱」からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its building consists of a main hall built as a three-storey English Tudor-style villa which was completed by a businessman Shotaro KAGA in 1932, and an adjacent underground new hall &apos;Jewelry Box in the Ground&apos; (地中の宝石箱) which is a modern piece of architecture designed by Tadao ANDO.</e>
<cmt>「地中の宝石箱」→“Jewelry Box in the Ground” (地中の宝石箱)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The building consists of a main hall built as a three-storey English Tudor-style villa which was completed by a businessman Shotaro KAGA in 1932, and an adjacent newer building underground called &apos;Jewelry Box in the Ground&apos; (地中の宝石箱) which is a modern piece of architecture designed by Tadao ANDO.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and word order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The building consists of a main hall built as a three-storey English Tudor-style villa which was completed by a businessman Shotaro KAGA in 1932, and an adjacent newer building underground called &apos;Underground Jewelry Box&apos; which is a modern piece of architecture designed by Tadao ANDO.</e>
<cmt>地中の宝石箱、の訳は山崎山荘美術館ホームページから引用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>山荘は戦後に荒廃していたが、保存運動が高まり1996年に今日のように私立美術館として再生された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The villa had been dilapidated after the War, but growing calls for preservation of it led to restore it as a private museum in 1996 as it is today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The villa had become dilapidated after the War, but growing calls for its preservation led to it being restored as a private museum in 1996, in the form it is today.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The villa had become dilapidated after the War, but growing calls for its preservation led to it being restored as a private museum in 1996, in the form it is today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大山崎山荘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyamazaki Villa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyamazaki Villa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyamazaki Villa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>大山崎山荘は加賀正太郎という人物の建物だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oyamazaki Villa used be owned by Shotaro KAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyamazaki Villa used be owned by Shotaro KAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyamazaki Villa used be owned by Shotaro KAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>1888年、大阪船場の株相場師の息子として生まれた彼は、現在の一橋大学を卒業するとイギリスを中心に欧州へ遊学し、アルプス山脈の山々に登頂した日本人のさきがけとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born to a stock speculator at Senba, Osaka in 1888, after graduating Hitotsubashi University, he went to study abroad in Britain and other European countries, and he was one of the first Japanese who climbed mountains of the Alps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born to a stock speculator in Senba, Osaka in 1888, after graduating from Hitotsubashi University he went to study abroad in Britain and other European countries, and was one of the first Japanese to climb the Alps.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born to a stock speculator in Senba, Osaka in 1888, after graduating from present Hitotsubashi University he went to study abroad in Britain and other European countries, and was one of the first Japanese to climb the Alps.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本帰国後は証券会社（加賀証券）を設立したほか、1934年にはサントリーの前身壽屋で山崎工場を立ち上げたもののオーナーとの路線対立から独自でウイスキー製造に乗り出した竹鶴政孝を支援して大日本果汁（後のニッカウヰスキー）創立に参加するなど、イギリスから持ち帰ったモダンな生活様式を日本に定着させようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After returning home, he founded a securities firm (Kaga Securities), and also he tried to introduce the modern lifestyle that he learned in Britain into Japan by taking part in the foundation of Dai Nippon Kaju (Japan Fruit Juice, and later Nikka Whisky) in 1934 supporting Masataka TAKETSURU who started producing whisky on his own after disagreeing with the owner of Yamazaki factory Taketsuru helped to set up working for Kotobukiya, later Suntory Holdings Ltd.</e>
<cmt>加賀証券→Kaga Securities （加賀証券）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After returning home he founded a securities firm (Kaga Securities), and tried to introduce elements of the modern lifestyle he learned in Britain into Japan by taking part in the foundation of Dai Nippon Kaju (Japan Fruit Juice, later Nikka Whisky) in 1934. In this he supported Masataka TAKETSURU who started producing whisky on his own after disagreeing with the owner of the Yamazaki factory Taketsuru helped to set up, working for Kotobukiya, later Suntory Holdings Ltd.</e>
<cmt>Sentence split for clarity. Changes to grammar and punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After returning home, he tried to introduce elements of the modern lifestyle he learned in Britain into Japan by founding a securities firm (Kaga Securities) and, in 1934, by taking part in the foundation of Dai Nippon Kaju (Japan Fruit Juice, later Nikka Whisky) supporting Masataka TAKETSURU who started up Yamazaki Factory of Kotobukiya, former Suntory Holdings Ltd., but tried to start producing whisky on his own by disagreeing with the owner.</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、1文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>彼は天王山山麓の淀川の流れを見下ろすこの場所に、テムズ川を見下ろすウィンザー城の風景を重ねあわせ、ここに山荘を作りたいと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He decided to build his villa at this site on the Tenno-zan mountainside overlooking Yodo-gawa River comparing it with the scenery of Windsor Castle overlooking the Thames.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He decided to have a villa built on this site on the Tenno-zan mountainside overlooking Yodo-gawa River, comparing it to the scenery of Windsor Castle overlooking the Thames.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He decided to have a villa built on this site at the foot of Mt. Tenno overlooking the Yodo-gawa River, comparing it to the scenery of Windsor Castle overlooking the Thames.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1912年に建設に着手、1915年には最初の木造の望楼「白雲楼」が、さらに増築を重ね1932年には現在見る本館である「霽景楼（せいけいろう）」が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1912, he started the construction, completed the wooden observation tower &apos;Hakuunro&apos; (literally White Cloud Tower) (白雲楼) in 1915, and expanded the building several more times to complete &apos;Seikeiro&apos; (literally Clear Scenery Tower) (霽景楼), the main hall today, in 1932.</e>
<cmt>白雲楼→ “Hakuunro” (literally White Cloud Tower) (白雲楼)霽景楼→Seikeiro→“Seikeiro” (literally Clear Scenery Tower) (霽景楼)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He began work on the construction in 1912, completed the wooden observation tower &apos;Hakuunro&apos; (literally White Cloud Tower) (白雲楼) in 1915, and expanded the building several more times to complete &apos;Seikeiro&apos; (literally Clear Scenery Tower) (霽景楼), the main hall today, in 1932.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He began work on the construction in 1912, completed the wooden observation tower &apos;Haku-unro&apos; (literally White Cloud Tower) in 1915, and expanded the building several more times to complete &apos;Seikeiro&apos; (literally Clear Scenery Tower), the main hall today, in 1932.</e>
<cmt>漢字を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは構造は鉄筋コンクリート造であったが、外観は木の柱を露出させその間にレンガ壁を組んだハーフティンバー工法で、淀川を見渡すテラスが備えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its frame structure was made of ferroconcrete, and the exterior was half-timbered with brick walls between exposed wooden pillars, equipped with a terrace overlooking Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its frame structure is made of ferroconcrete, and the exterior half-timbered with brick walls between exposed wooden pillars, equipped with a terrace overlooking Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Tense changed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its frame structure is made of ferroconcrete, and the exterior half-timbered with brick walls between exposed wooden pillars, equipped with a terrace overlooking the Yodo-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>内部はがっしりとしたイギリス風の調度がそなえられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Massive English furniture was installed inside.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He equipped the inside of the building with solid English-style furnishings.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He equipped the inside of the building with solid English-style furnishings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>加賀は併設された温室でイギリス時代以来夢中だった洋蘭の研究や品種改良を進め、『蘭花譜』という図録を出版し、1954年に死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the attached greenhouse, he devoted his time to study and improvement of orchids he had been obsessed with since he was in Britain, and finally published a picture book of flowers called &quot;Rankafu&quot; (Genealogy of Orchids) before he died in 1954.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the attached greenhouse he devoted his time to study and the selective breeding of orchids he had been obsessed with since his time in Britain, and he finally published a picture book of flowers called &quot;Rankafu&quot; (Genealogy of Orchids) before he died in 1954.</e>
<cmt>Changed for grammar, punctuation and word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the attached greenhouse Kaga devoted his time to study and the selective breeding of orchids he had been obsessed with since his time in Britain, and he finally published a picture book of flowers called &quot;Rankafu&quot; (Genealogy of Orchids) before he died in 1954.</e>
<cmt>加賀を明記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>保存運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movement for preservation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movement for preservation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movement for Preservation</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>山荘は後に加賀家の手を離れ、様々な所有者の手に移り一時は会員制レストランなどに再利用されるが年々老朽化が進み、バブル経済末期には建設業者が買収し、一帯を更地に地上げするマンション開発計画を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This villa later left the hands of the Kagas to change its ownership several times, was once used as a members-only restaurant, but became older year after year, and at the end of the bubble economy, a construction firm bought it to project a plan to scrap it and build condominiums in a bid to raise prices of lands around this place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This villa later left the hands of the Kagas and its ownership changed several times, once being used as a members-only restaurant, but becoming older year after year at the end of the bubble economy a construction firm bought it as part of a plan to have it demolished and build condominiums in a bid to raise land prices around the area.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and for natural flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This villa later left the hands of the Kaga family and its ownership changed several times, once being used as a members-only restaurant, but becoming older year after year at the end of the bubble economy a construction firm bought it as part of a plan to have it demolished and build condominiums in a bid to raise land prices around the area.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天王山の横腹に大きなマンション群が林立し景観が一変することに反対する地元住民は山荘の価値を見直し、山荘と周囲の森林の保全を訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local residents opposed the plan saying large condominiums on the mountainside of Tenno-zan would harm the scenery, and demanded reevaluation of the villa and preservation of it and the forest around it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local residents opposed the plan, claiming large condominiums on the mountainside of Tenno-zan would harm the scenery, and demanded a reevaluation of the villa and the preservation of it and the surrounding forest.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, punctuation and grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local residents opposed the plan, claiming large condominiums on the side of Mt. Tenno would harm the scenery, and demanded a reevaluation of the villa and the preservation of it and the surrounding forest.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>これが大山崎町や京都府を動かし、さらに当時の知事荒巻禎一の友人だったアサヒビールの社長樋口廣太郎が知事の申し出に応じて企業メセナ活動として保存に協力することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This moved Oyamazaki Cho and Kyoto Prefecture to reach an agreement that Hirotaro HIGUCHI, who was the president of Asahi breweries and a friend of then governor Teiichi ARAMAKI, would help to preserve the villa as cooperate mecenat in response to the governor&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This moved Oyamazaki Cho and Kyoto Prefecture to reach an agreement where Hirotaro HIGUCHI, who was the president of Asahi breweries and a friend of then governor Teiichi ARAMAKI, would help to preserve the villa in a form of corporate patronage in response to the governor&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>Changed for grammar, and French &apos;mecenat&apos; removed as not in standard English usage.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This moved Oyamazaki-cho Town and Kyoto Prefecture to reach an agreement where Hirotaro HIGUCHI, who was the president of Asahi Breweries and a friend of then governor Teiichi ARAMAKI, would help to preserve the villa in a form of corporate patronage in response to the governor&apos;s request.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>アサヒビールは加賀の作ったニッカウヰスキーを子会社にしており、さらにアサヒビール初代社長の山本為三郎と加賀正太郎は交友があり、両者の縁が深かったことが幸いした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fortunately, Shotaro Kaga left good personal connection that Asahi Breweries was a parent company of Nikka Whisky that Kaga helped to found, and Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO, the first president of Asahi Breweries, was a friend of Kaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was fortunate that Shotaro Kaga and Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO, the first president of Asahi Breweries, had a deep personal connection through their friendship and the fact that Asahi Breweries was a parent company of Nikka Whisky that Kaga helped to found.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was fortunate that Shotaro KAGA and Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO, the first president of Asahi Breweries, had a deep personal connection through their friendship and the fact that Asahi Breweries was a parent company of Nikka Whisky that Kaga helped to found.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>こうして土地は京都府や大山崎町などが業者から買い取り、山荘はアサヒビール運営の山本コレクションの美術館となることが決まり、後には安藤忠雄が建築設計・監修に選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Kyoto Prefecture and Oyamazaki Cho bought the land from the construction firm, and the villa was decided to be turned to an art museum of Yamamoto&apos;s collection operated by Asahi Breweries, with Tadao ANDO later selected as the designer and supervisor of its new buiding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Kyoto Prefecture and Oyamazaki Cho bought the land from the construction firm, and it was decided that the villa was to be turned into an art museum for Yamamoto&apos;s collection operated by Asahi Breweries, with Tadao ANDO later selected as the designer and supervisor of its new building.</e>
<cmt>Changed for grammar and spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Kyoto Prefecture and Oyamazaki-cho Town bought the land from the construction firm, and it was decided that the villa was to be turned into an art museum for Yamamoto&apos;s collection operated by Asahi Breweries, with Tadao ANDO later selected as the designer and supervisor of its new building.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>山荘の建物や内装は建設当時のクラシックな姿に修復される一方、山荘に付属する形で廊下で結ばれたシリンダー状の新展示室は、周囲の自然環境や山荘の落ち着いた調和を乱さぬよう、地下に計画された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The building of this villa and its interior were refurbished to restore its original classic appearances, and the cylinder type new subsidiary exhibition room was planned to be built in the ground connected with the villa by a corridor in order not to disturb the natural environment and the calm atmosphere of the villa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The structure of this villa and its interior were refurbished to restore its original classic appearance, and the cylinder type new subsidiary exhibition room was planned to be constructed underground, connected with the villa by a corridor in order not to disturb the natural environment and the calm atmosphere of the villa.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The structure of this villa and its interior were refurbished to restore its original classic appearance, and the cylinder type new subsidiary exhibition room was planned to be constructed underground, connected with the villa by a corridor in order not to disturb the natural environment and the calm atmosphere of the villa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>階段状の廊下はガラス張りで光があふれ、階段を下りた薄暗い地下にある展示室は光量を落とされ静謐な空間となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The corridor is a stairway shielded by glass to be full of light, and at the foot of the stairway, the underground exhibition room makes a serene space with dim light.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The corridor is a stairway shielded by glass to create a space full of light, and at the foot of the stairway the underground exhibition room makes a serene space with dim light.</e>
<cmt>Changed for flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The corridor is a stairway shielded by glass to create a space full of light, and at the foot of the stairway the underground exhibition room makes a serene space with dim light.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>円形シリンダーの中央には四角い部屋が設けられ、天窓から自然光が降り注ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the center of the cylinder room, there is a square room illuminated by natural light from a skylight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the center of the cylinder room, there is a square room illuminated by natural light from a skylight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the center of the cylinder room, there is a square room illuminated by natural light from a skylight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>保存・修復された山荘は、1996年に美術館として開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The villa was refurbished and preserved, and was opened to the public as an art museum in 1996.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The villa was refurbished and preserved, and was opened to the public as an art museum in 1996.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The villa was refurbished and preserved, and was opened to the public as an art museum in 1996.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>以来多くの観光客を受け入れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There have been many visitors ever since.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been many visitors ever since.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been many visitors ever since.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>鑑賞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appreciation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appreciation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appreciation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>コレクション、ほか展示企画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collections and exhibitions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collections and exhibitions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collections and Exhibitions</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>実業家の山本為三郎は1893年に大阪で生まれ、後にホテル経営（後のリーガロイヤルホテル）をまとめる一方、芸術家の支援も行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Born in Osaka in 1893, the businessman Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO operated hotels (later Rihga Royal Hotels), and supported artists as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Born in Osaka in 1893, the businessman Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO operated hotels (later Rihga Royal Hotels), and supported artists as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Born in Osaka in 1893, the businessman Tamesaburo YAMAMOTO operated hotels (later Rihga Royal Hotels), and supported artists as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>特に日本民芸運動とは関係が深く、それにまつわる作家の美術作品や、彼らが手本とした古い生活雑器、古美術品の収集も行い、大阪の北の三国にはこれらの作品を収めた邸宅・三国荘があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He had close relationship especially with Japanese folk art movement, and collected art works of them, old livingware they admired, and antique art works, which he stored in his mansion &apos;Mikuni-so&apos; villa in Mikuni north to Osaka City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He had an enspecially close relationship with the Japanese folk art movement, and collected works of art by them, old everyday ornaments they admired, and antique art works, which he stored in his mansion &apos;Mikuni-so&apos; villa in Mikuni north of Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>Changed for word choice and grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He had an especially close relationship with the Japanese folk art movement, and collected works of art by them, old everyday ornaments they admired, and antique art works, which he stored in his mansion &apos;Mikuni-so&apos; villa in Mikuni, north of Osaka City.</e>
<cmt>カンマを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また近現代の西洋美術なども収集しており、これが美術館のもう一つのコレクションの柱となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also collected modern Western art works, which make the other main collection of this museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also collected modern Western artwork, which make up the other main collection of this museum.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also collected modern Western artwork, which make up the other main collection of this museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>現在は民芸運動関係作品が山荘に、『睡蓮』他の絵画作品が地下展示室に展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, works related to Japanese folk art movement are exhibited at the villa, and pieces of &quot;Water Lilies&quot; and other paintings at the underground exhibition hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, works related to the Japanese folk art movement are exhibited at the villa, and works such as &quot;Water Lilies&quot; and other paintings in the underground exhibition hall.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, works related to the Japanese folk art movement are exhibited at the villa, and works such as &quot;Water-Lilies&quot; and other paintings in the underground exhibition hall.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これが季節ごとに展示換えされるほか、これらのコレクションから受けた印象をもとに現代美術作家が制作を行い、展示を行う企画展や、来館者を相手にしたワークショップなども精力的に行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They not only put these on display in seasonal rotation, they also work energetically to hold special exhibitions that display works created by present artists being inspired by these collections, and to conduct workshops inviting visitors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They not only put these on display in seasonal rotation, but they also work energetically to hold special exhibitions that display works created by artists of the present day who have been inspired by these collections, and to conduct workshops inviting visitors.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They not only put these on display in seasonal rotation, but they also work energetically to hold special exhibitions that display works created by artists of the present day who have been inspired by these collections, and to conduct workshops inviting visitors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>カフェ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coffee shop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coffee shop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coffee Shop</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>テラスに面した部屋は、淀川や京都盆地を見下ろすカフェになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a coffee shop with a terrace overlooking Yodo-gawa River and Kyoto Basin.</e>
<cmt>「京都盆地」は日本語として分離可能と思います．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a coffee shop with a terrace overlooking Yodo-gawa River and Kyoto Basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a coffee shop with a terrace overlooking the Yodo-gawa River and Kyoto Basin.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>ケーキは大阪のリーガロイヤルホテルから運ばれてくる焼き菓子が中心。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the cake it serves is baked confectionery from Rihga Royal Hotels in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the cakes it serves are baked confectionery from Rihga Royal Hotels in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Made plural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the cakes it serves are baked confectionery from Rihga Royal Hotels in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other</e>
<cmt>Made singular.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>ミュージアムショップはモネの睡蓮をあしらったバッグ・手帳などアイテムが豊富である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its museum shop sells variety of items such as bags and notebooks with a small copy of Water Lilies of Monet on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The museum shop sells a variety of items such as bags and notebooks with a small motif of Water Lilies of Monet.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The museum shop sells a variety of items such as bags and notebooks with a small motif of Water-Lilies of Monet.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、山荘の外は大きな庭園となっており、周囲をめぐる散歩道がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside the villa is a large garden with a walkway around it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outside the villa is a large garden with a walkway around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outside the villa is a large garden with a walkway around it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>周囲・交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neighborhood and Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local Area and Access</e>
<cmt>Word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local Area and Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道JR京都線の山崎駅からも、阪急京都本線大山崎駅からも徒歩10分と駅から徒歩圏内にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is within a walking distance of ten minutes from Yamazaki Station of JR Kyoto Line and from Oyamazaki Station of Hankyu Railway Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is within ten minutes walking distance of Yamazaki Station on the JR Kyoto Line and from Oyamazaki Station on the Hankyu Railway Kyoto Line.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is within ten minutes walking distance of Yamazaki Station on the JR West Kyoto Line and from Oyamazaki Station on the Hankyu Railway Kyoto Main Line.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>ただし美術館までの勾配がきついため、駅と美術館を往復する送迎バスも利用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the road to the museum is a steep slope, so it provides a pickup shuttle bus service between the stations and the museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the road to the museum is steep, so a pickup shuttle bus service between the stations and the museum is provided.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the road to the museum is steep, so a pickup shuttle bus service between the stations and the museum is provided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>駐車場はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has no parking space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are no parking facilities.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are no parking facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>周囲は宝積寺や山崎聖天などの寺社仏閣が多く桜の時期は特に美しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples and shrines are in the neighborhood such as Hoshaku-ji Temple and Yamazaki-shoten Temple which are beautiful especially in spring with cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several temples and shrines in the local area, such as Hoshaku-ji Temple and Yamazaki-shoten Temple which are especially beautiful in spring with cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>Made more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several temples and shrines in the local area, such as Hoshaku-ji Temple and Yamazaki-shoten Temple which are especially beautiful in spring with cherry blossoms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>また天王山登山コースの途中にもあるため、ハイキングで建物を見に来る来館者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People visit this museum to see its building on their way of hiking because it is on the course of climbing Tenno-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People visit the museum to see the building when hiking because it is on the way to the summit of Tenno-zan Mountain.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People visit the museum to see the building when hiking because it is on the way to the summit of Mt. Tenno.</e>
<cmt>前出に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Bakkai(id:7233), 0null0(id:582), Imses(id:37755), 663highland(id:18755), You-kan(id:33117), Hide-sp(id:145562), Norio-abc(id:106785), Nopira(id:29335), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>