<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>亀石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameishi (Turtle Rock)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameishi (Turtle Rock in Ise-jingu Shrine Geku [the outer shrine])</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameishi (Turtle Rock in Ise-jingu Shrine Geku [the outer shrine])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊勢神宮外宮境内にある石。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A stone in the precincts of Ise Jingu Shrine Geku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A rock in the precincts of Ise-jingu Shrine Geku.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A rock in the precincts of Ise-jingu Shrine Geku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>高倉山の天岩戸の入り口の岩を運んだと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition says that it carried a rock for the entrance of Ama-no-Iwato in Takakurayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to legend, the rock, which was used as the entrance of Ama-no-Iwato in Mt. Takakura, was carried to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to legend, the rock, which was used as the entrance of Ama-no-Iwato in Mt. Takakura, was carried to the shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良県明日香村川原にあるカメの形をした遺構。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a turtle-shaped relic Kawahara, Asuka-mura, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A turtle-shaped relic in Kawahara, Asuka Village, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A turtle-shaped relic in Kawahara, Asuka Village, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>長さ3.6メートル、幅2.1メートル、高さ1.8メートルの巨大な花崗岩に亀に似た彫刻が彫られていることからこの名前で呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because this huge stone of granite 3.6 meters in length, 2.1 meters in width, and 1.8 meters in height has a turtle-like carving on it, it is called by this name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because this huge granite with 3.6 meters in length, 2.1 meters in width, and 1.8 meters in height has a turtle-like carving on it, it is called by this name.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because this huge granite with 3.6 meters in length, 2.1 meters in width, and 1.8 meters in height has a turtle-like carving on it, it is called by this name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ユーモラスな顔つきから明日香村観光のシンボルともなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its humorous face has made itself a symbol of sightseeing in Asuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its humorous face has made itself a symbol of sightseeing in Asuka Village.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its humorous face has made itself a symbol of sightseeing in Asuka Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ここでは後者について述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here we will describe the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here we will describe the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here we will describe the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>建造時期・目的</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Time of Construction and Its Purpose</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Time of Construction and Its Purpose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Time of Construction and Its Purpose</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>いつ、なんの目的で作られたかは謎で、川原寺の所領の四隅を示す石標、猿石を含めた古墳に関連する遺物、斉明天皇の時代にグリフィン像を造ろうとしたが加工途中で放棄されたものなど、いくつかの説がだされているが結論は出ていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When and why it was made remains a mystery, and there are several theories that it was a marker of one of the four corners of the Kawahara Temple territory, a relic related to a kofun (ancient tomb) including Saruishi (Stone Monkey) or an unfinished product in the process of making a griffin statue in the Emperor Saimei period, but no conclusion has been made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When and why it was made is a mystery; any theories, such as a marker of one of the four corners of the Kawahara-ji Temple&apos;s territory, a relic related to a kofun (tumulus) including Saruishi (Stone Monkey), or an unfinished product in the process of making a griffin statue in the era of Emperor Saimei, don&apos;t draw a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When and why it was made is a mystery; any theories, such as a marker of one of the four corners of the Kawahara-ji Temple&apos;s territory, a relic related to a kofun (tumulus) including Saruishi (Stone Monkey), or an unfinished product in the process of making a griffin statue in the era of Emperor Saimei, don&apos;t draw a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>形状</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shape</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shape</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>亀石と呼ばれているが、顔が三角形であることや目が上に飛び出しているなど、亀というよりはカエルの特徴をとらえていると見る人もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it is called Kameishi, some people think it has an feature of a frog rather than a turtle because of the triangle shaped face and eyes protruding upward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is called Kameishi, some people think it has a feature of a frog rather than a turtle because of the triangle shaped face and eyes protruding upward.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is called Kameishi, some people think it has a feature of a frog rather than a turtle because of the triangle shaped face and eyes protruding upward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>上部が自然石のままで下部のみが加工されていることから、現在の下面が本来の上面で実は上下逆であったという説も奈良国立文化財研究所の報告書で出されてはいるが、有力視はされていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because its upper part remains a natural stone, while the lower part alone is processed, Nara National Cultural Properties Research Institute introduced in their report a theory suggesting a topsy-turvy state, i.e., the present bottom should have been intended for the top, which is not strongly supported.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the upper part remains a natural stone, while the lower part alone is processed, Nara National Cultural Properties Research Institute introduced in their report a theory suggesting a topsy-turvy state, i.e., the present bottom should have been intended for the top, which is not strongly supported.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the upper part remains a natural stone, while the lower part alone is processed, Nara National Cultural Properties Research Institute introduced in their report a theory suggesting a topsy-turvy state, i.e., the present bottom should have been intended for the top, which is not strongly supported.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>下部には石矢の跡が見られるが、建造当初からあったものなのか酒船石遺跡のように後世になって石を割ろうとした跡なのかも分かっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the lower part traces of stone arrows are seen, and it remains unknown whether the traces were there from the beginning of the construction or they were made in later years when it was tried to be divided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown that traces of stone arrows seen in the lower part were made in its earliest days, or in later years when the rock was tried to be broken.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown that traces of stone arrows seen in the lower part were made in its earliest days, or in later years when the rock was tried to be broken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>もし当初から残された跡だとすれば亀石は未完成品であるとの証拠にもなり、後世に割られたとしたら本来は現在よりもかなり高さのある石だった可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If they are traces made at the beginning, it proves that Kameishi is an unfinished product, or if it was broken in later years, the original stone might be much taller than the present one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If they are traces made at the beginning, it proves that Kameishi is an unfinished product, or if it was broken in later years, the original stone might be much taller than the present one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If they are traces made at the beginning, it proves that Kameishi is an unfinished product, or if it was broken in later years, the original stone might be much taller than the present one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>伝説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>言い伝えによれば、奈良盆地一帯が湖であった頃、対岸の当麻（たいま）のヘビと川原のナマズの争いの結果、当麻に水を吸い取られ、川原あたりは干上がってしまい、湖の亀はみんな死んでしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend says that when the area around Nara Basin was a lake, as a result of a battle between the snakes in Taima across the lake and the Catfish in Kawahara, the water was taken by Taima and the Kawahara area was dried up, leading to the death of all turtles in the lake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend says that when the area around Nara Basin was a lake, in a battle between the snakes in Taima on the opposite shore and the catfish in Kawahara, sucked the water by Taima caused Kawahara area to be dried up and all the turtle in the lake to be killed.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend says that when the area around Nara Basin was a lake, in a battle between the snakes in Taima on the opposite shore and the catfish in Kawahara, sucked the water by Taima caused Kawahara area to be dried up and all the turtle in the lake to be killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>亀を哀れに思った村人たちは、「亀石」を造って亀の供養をしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that villagers who pitied the turtles built &quot;Kameishi&quot; for the repose of their souls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that villagers who pitied the turtles built &apos;Kameishi&apos; for the repose of their souls.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that villagers who pitied the turtles built &apos;Kameishi&apos; for the repose of their souls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>亀石は、以前は北を向き、次に東を向いたと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They say Kameishi formerly faced north and then east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They say Kameishi formerly faced north and then east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They say Kameishi formerly faced north and then east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そして、今は南西を向いているが、西に向き、当麻のほうを睨みつけると、奈良盆地は一円泥の海と化す、と伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now it faces southeast, and legend says that if it faces west and stares at Taima, Nara Basin will be a sea of mud.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now it faces southeast, and legend says that if it faces west and stares at Taima, Nara Basin would be a sea of mud.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now it faces southeast, and legend says that if it faces west and stares at Taima, Nara Basin would be a sea of mud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), ＋－(id:17104), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Nighthawks(id:36125), Kansai explorer(id:48975), TEy(id:32722), VanishingDuck(id:125995), Ponsaku(id:31417), Ｈｉｒｏ２００６(id:59115), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>