<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊根の舟屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ine no Funaya Houses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ine no Funaya Houses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ine no Funaya Houses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊根の舟屋（いねのふなや） は、京都府与謝郡伊根町の伊根地区にある民家の種類のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in the Ine area of Ine Town, Yosa County, Kyoto Prefecture, the Ine no funaya houses are private houses of a type.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in the Ine area of Ine Town, Yosa County, Kyoto Prefecture, the Ine no funaya houses are private houses..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ine no Funaya (a large cluster of traditional fishermen houses) houses are private houses, located in the Ine area of Ine-cho Town, Yosa-gun County, Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>舟屋から見る海の景観、海から見る舟屋の景観が美しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The view of sea from funaya houses and that of funaya houses from sea are beautiful.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The views of sea from the funaya houses and that of funaya houses from sea are beautiful.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The views of sea from the funaya houses and that of funaya houses from sea are beautiful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そのため、伊根町の代表的な観光スポットとして観光客が多く訪れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the area is a well-known sightseeing spot in Ine Town and is visited by many tourists.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the area is a well-known sightseeing spot in Ine Town and is visited by many tourists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the area is a well-known sightseeing spot in Ine Town and is visited by many tourists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、近年では伊根町内での映画やドラマのロケがあり、全国に名が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, areas in Ine Town have recently been used for locations for movies or dramas, making the name of Ine known nationally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, areas in Ine Town have recently been used for locations for movies or dramas, making the name of Ine known nationally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, areas in Ine Town have recently been used for locations for movies or dramas, making the name of Ine known nationally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>舟屋は江戸時代中期頃から存在しているものと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the funaya houses have existed since around the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the funaya houses have existed since around the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the funaya houses have existed since around the middle of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>舟屋は2000年現在、238棟が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is ascertained that 234 funaya houses existed as of 2000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is confirmed that 234 funaya houses existed as of 2000.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is confirmed that 238 funaya houses existed as of 2000.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特徴としては基本的に「海への開口」、「妻入り」の2点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features of these houses are basically as follows: They are provided with a space open to the sea and are built using the tsuma-iri (the entrance is provded on a gable side) style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features of these houses are basically as follows: They are provided with a space open to the sea and are built using the tsuma-iri (entrance is provded on the gable side) style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features of these houses are basically as follows: They are provided with a space open to the sea and are built using the tsuma-iri (entrance is provided on the gable side) style.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>こうした特徴が評価され、国の重要伝統的建造物群保存地区の選定を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These features have been evaluated highly, and the area was designated as one of the national preservation dstricts for groups of historic buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These features have been highly evaluated, and the area was designated as one of the national preservation dstricts for groups of historic buildings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These features have been highly evaluated, and the area was designated as one of the national preservation districts for groups of historic buildings.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>漁村では全国で初めて</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a designation is the first for the fishing villages in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a designation is the first for a fishing village in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a designation is the first for a fishing village in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>舟屋は伊根湾の海面すれすれに建築されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A funaya house is built close to the sea surface of the Ine bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A funaya house is built close to the sea surface of the Ine bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A funaya house is built close to the sea surface of the Ine-wan bay.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1階には船揚場、物置、作業場があり、出漁の準備、漁具の手入れ、魚干物の乾場や農産物の置き場などと幅広く活用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provided with a non-sea area where a boat is to be placed, a storage room and a working space, the first floor is used for various purposes, such as maintaining fishing gears, drying fishes to make dried fishes and placing agricaltural products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provided with a non-sea area where a boat is to be placed, a storage room and a working space, the first floor is used for various purposes, such as for maintaining fishing gear, for drying fish and for storing agricultural products.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provided with a non-sea area where a boat is to be placed, a storage room and a working space, the first floor is used for various purposes, such as for maintaining fishing gear, for drying fish and for storing agricultural products.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、2階は居室、民宿といった生活の場となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second floor is used for living, such as a living room and/or rooms for minshuku operation (providng lodging and measls to tourists in a private house).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second floor is used for living, includes a living room and/or rooms for minshuku operation (providng lodging and meals for tourists in a private house).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second floor is used for living, includes a living room and rooms for minshuku operation (providing lodging and meals for tourists in a private house).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Su-no-G(id:52744), Sapphire123(id:147732), Peachkiller(id:99202), にゃんにゃんこ(id:128119), Wakkubox(id:30396), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>