<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>千木・鰹木</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi (a roof material) and Katsuogi (a roof material)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi (a roof material) and Katsuogi (a roof material)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi (a roof material) and Katsuogi (a roof material)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>千木（ちぎ）・鰹木（かつおぎ）は、今日では神社建築にのみ見られる、建造物の屋根に設けられた部材である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi/katsuogi is a material provided on roofs of buildings, but nowadays is found only in shirine buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi/katsuogi is a material provided on roofs of buildings, but nowadays is found only in shirine buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi/katsuogi is a material provided on roofs of buildings, but nowadays is found only in shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>千木は屋根の両端で交叉させた木であり、鰹木は屋根の上に棟に直角になるように何本か平行して並べた木である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi indicates crossed trees placed at each end of a roof, and katsuogi is a number of trees placed in parallel with each other but perpendicularly to the ridge of a roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi indicates crossed trees placed at each end of a roof, and katsuogi is a number of trees placed in parallel with each other but perpendicularly to the ridge of a roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi indicates crossed trees placed at each end of a roof, and katsuogi is a number of trees placed in parallel with each other but perpendicularly to the ridge of a roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>どちらも元々は上流階級の邸宅にも用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, both of them were used in the residences of persons in the upper class.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, both of them were used in the residences of persons of the upper class.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, both of them were used in the residences of persons of the upper class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、今日では神社にのみ用いられ、神社建築の象徴のようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they are nowadays seen only in shirines, becoming like a symbol of shirine buildings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they are nowadays seen only in shrines, and have become symbolic of shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they are nowadays seen only in shrines and have become symbolic with shrine buildings.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>千木は古代、屋根を作るときに木材2本を交叉させて結びつけ、先端を切り揃えずにそのままにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ancient times, two wooden materials were simply crossed to make a roof, without their tips cut neatly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times, two wooden materials were simply crossed to make a roof, without their tips being cut neatly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times, two wooden logs were simply crossed and tied together to make a roof without their tips being cut neatly.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その名残りと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigi is considered to reflect such a practice in the past.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigi is considered to reflect such a practice in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigi is considered to reflect such past practice.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>千木・鰹木ともに元々は建物の補強のためのものであったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that both chigi and katsuogi were for reinforcing the structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that both chigi and katsuogi were to reinforce the structure.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that both chigi and katsuogi were to reinforce the structure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鰹木は、形が鰹節に似ていることが名前の由来であると云われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the term of katsuogi originated in that its shape resembled a dried bonito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the term of katsuogi originated in that its shape resembled a dried bonito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the term katsuogi originates from its shape which resembles a dried bonito.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>鰹木は「堅緒木」「堅魚木」「勝男木」「葛尾木」などとも書く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsuogi (鰹木) is also written as &quot;堅緒木,&quot; &quot;堅魚木,&quot; &quot;勝男木&quot; or &quot;葛尾木.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsuogi (鰹木) is also written as &quot;堅緒木,&quot; &quot;堅魚木,&quot; &quot;勝男木&quot; or &quot;葛尾木.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsuogi (鰹木) is also written as &apos;堅緒木,&apos; &apos;堅魚木,&apos; &apos;勝男木&apos; or &apos;葛尾木.&apos;</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>出雲大社を始めとして出雲諸社は、祭神が男神の社は千木を外削ぎ（先端を地面に対して垂直に削る）に、女神の社は内削ぎ（水平に削る）にしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In shrines in the Izumo area including Izumo Taisha Shrine, the sotosogi style (both ends of chigi were cutted vertically against the ground) is used for the shirnes whose god is male, and the uchisogi style (both ends of chigi were cutted in parallel with the ground) for the shrines whose god is female.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In shrines in the Izumo area including Izumo Taisha Shrine, the sotosogi style (both ends of chigi were cut vertically against the ground) is used for the shrines whose god is male, and the uchisogi style (both ends of chigi were cut parallel with the ground) for the shrines whose god is female.</e>
<cmt>wording; verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In shrines in the Izumo area including Izumo Taisha Shrine, the sotosogi style (both ends of chigi are cut vertically) is used for the shrines whose god is male and the uchisogi style (both ends of chigi are cut horizontally) for the shrines whose god is female.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>他の神社でもこれに倣っているものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other shrines follow these styles.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また鰹木の数は、奇数は陽数・偶数は陰数とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that an odd number was cheerful and an even number gloomy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that an odd number was cheerful and an even number gloomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also considered that for the number of katsuogi, an odd number is yang and an even number is yin.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのために、それぞれ男神・女神の社に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is considered that a katsuogi with tress whose number was odd was used for a male-god shrine and a katsuogi with tress whose number was even was used for a female-god shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is considered that a katsuogi with tress whose number was odd was used for a male-god shrine and a katsuogi with tress whose number was even was used for a female-god shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, an odd number of katsuogi was used for male-god shrines and an even number for female-god shrines.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ピリオドを追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし、伊勢神宮の場合、皇大神宮の祭神天照大神、豊受大神宮の祭神トヨウケビメとともに主祭神が女神であるのにもかかわらず、内宮では千木・鰹木が内削ぎ・10本、外宮は外削ぎ・9本である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, although, in Ise-jingu shrine, both main gods of Kotai-jingu Shrine and Toyouke Dai-jingu Shrine are female, with Amaterasu Omikami in the former shrine and Toyoukebime in the latter, the chigi is the uchisogi style and the number of trees of the katsugi is 10, for the inner shrine, and the chigi is the sotosogi style and the number of trees of the katsugi is 9, for the outer shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, although, in Ise-jingu shrine, both main gods of Kotai-jingu Shrine and Toyouke Dai-jingu Shrine are female, with Amaterasu Omikami in the former shrine and Toyoukebime in the latter, the chigi is the uchisogi style and the number of trees of the katsuogi is 10, for the inner shrine, and the chigi is the sotosogi style and the number of trees of the katsuogi is 9, for the outer shrine.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at Ise-jingu shrine, the main god of Kotai-jingu Shrine and Toyouke Dai-jingu Shrine are female, Amaterasu Omikami and Toyoukebime, respectively, but the chigi is cut in the uchisogi style and the number of katsuogi is ten for the inner shrine, and the chigi is cut in the sotosogi style and the number of katsuogi is nine for the outer shrine.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同様に、別宮では、次のように見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar situations are also found concerning betsugu (a shrine built separated from the main shrine) as in the following: For examples, both main gods of 月讀宮 (Tsukiyominomiya), betsugu in the inner shrine and 月夜見宮 (Tsukiyomi no miya), betsugu in the outer shrine, are the same male, Tsukiyomi (the expression of 月夜見尊 (Tsukiyomi no mikoto) is used for the betsugu for the outer shrine, clearly indicating that the god is a male), but regardless of the sex of the shrine gods, the chigi is the uchisogi style and the number of trees of the katsuogi is even, for the betsugu of the inner shrine, and the chig is sotosogi and the number of trees of the katsuogi is odd, for the betsugu of the outer shirine, with the similar relationships maintained for Sessha (shrine where the gods connected to the gods in the main shrine are worshipped), Massha (small shrine belonging to the main shrine) and Shokansha (shrine where the gods of clothing, food and housing are worshipped) as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar situations are also found concerning betsugu (a shrine built separated from the main shrine) as in the following: For example, both main gods of 月讀宮 (Tsukiyominomiya), betsugu in the inner shrine and 月夜見宮 (Tsukiyomi no miya), betsugu in the outer shrine, are the same male, Tsukiyomi (the expression of 月夜見尊 (Tsukiyomi no mikoto) is used for the betsugu for the outer shrine, clearly indicating that the god is a male); However, regardless of the sex of the shrine gods, the chigi is the uchisogi style and the number of trees of the katsuogi is even, for the betsugu of the inner shrine, and the chig is sotosogi and the number of trees of the katsuogi is odd, for the betsugu of the outer shirine, with the similar relationships maintained for Sessha (shrine where the gods connected to the gods in the main shrine are worshipped), Massha (small shrine belonging to the main shrine) and Shokansha (shrine where the gods of clothing, food and housing are worshipped) as well.</e>
<cmt>This is an extreme example of a run-on sentence and needs to be re-translated. I attempted to break it up into two sentences (in red lettering), but I think the meaning is lost. Upon re-translating, try breaking it up into many (6 or more) discrete sentences to represent single ideas. Otherwise, the reader gets completely lost after the first 2 or 3 ideas are thrown out in succession.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar situations are also found in the betsugu (shrines built separately from the main shrine) as follows.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>例えば、内宮別宮の月讀宮、外宮別宮の月夜見宮は主祭神はともに同じ祭神であるツクヨミ（外宮別宮は「月夜見尊」と表記している）と男神である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Tsukiyomi no miya (literally, &quot;moon-reading palace&quot;), which is a betsugu in the inner shrine, and Tsukiyomi no miya (literally, &quot;moon night-viewing palace&quot;), which is a betsugu in the outer shrine, are dedicated to the same male god whose name is Tsukuyomi (written Tsukuyomi no mikoto at the betsugu in the outer shrine, literally, &quot;moon night-viewing male god&quot;).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションマークを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしながら、祭神の男女を問わず内宮別宮は内削ぎ・偶数の鰹木、外宮別宮は外削ぎ・奇数の鰹木である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, regardless of whether the main god is male or female, betsugu in the inner shrine have uchisogi-style chigi and an even number of katsuogi, whereas betsugu in the outer shrine have sotosogi-style chigi and an odd number of katsuogi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また摂社・末社・所管社も同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same rule applies to Sessha (shrines where gods related to the gods in the main shrine are worshiped), Massha (small shrines belonging to the main shrine) and Shokansha (shrines where the gods of clothing, food and housing are worshiped).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この理由には諸説あり、外宮の祭神がもともと男神的性格を帯びたものではなかったとする議論もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many theories for the reason, and it has also been discussed that the god of betsugu might not have been provided with a male-like character originally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many theories on the reason for this. It has also been speculated that the god of betsugu might not have been provided with a male-like character originally.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories regarding an explanation for this rule, but it has been speculated that the main god in the outer shrine may originally not have had masculine properties.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Nnh(id:474), Fg2(id:216015), N yotarou(id:60870), Matsubara-kou(id:41153), ChibaRagi(id:68046), Alexbot(id:157199), Wiiii(id:59641), Excavator(id:25917), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>