<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>安福殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anpukuden Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anpukuden Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anpukuden Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>安福殿（あんぷくでん）とは、平安京の内裏における殿舎のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anpukuden Hall is one of buildings in dairi (Imperial Palace) of Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anpukuden Hall was one of the halls of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anpukuden Hall was one of the halls of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>紫宸殿の西南、月華門を挟んで校書殿の南に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is located in the southwest of Shishin-den Hall (hall for state ceremonies), and is in the south of Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archives) which is located beyond Gekka-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situated in the southeast of the Imperial Palace, this hall was located to the south of Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall) beyond Gekka-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situated in the southeast of the Imperial Palace, this hall was located to the south of Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall) beyond Gekka-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>南庭東側の春興殿とは東西に相対する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the opposite side of Shunkyo-den (a part of Heiankyo Palace) which is located on the east side of the southern country yard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stood opposite Shunkyoden which was situated on the eastern side of the south garden.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stood opposite Shunkyoden, which was situated on the eastern side of the south garden, facing in an east-west direction.</e>
<cmt>「東西に」を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>侍医や薬生（やくしょう）が控えていたので薬殿（くすどの）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called as the Kusudono (Physician&apos;s Hall) as jii (a doctor for the Emperor and the Imperial family) or Medical students stayed in there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Kusudono (Physician&apos;s Hall) because court physicians and medical students resided there.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Kusudono (Physician&apos;s Hall) because court physicians and medical students resided there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>