<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>校書殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kyosho-den Hall (a building in Imperial Palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall)</e>
<cmt>用語共有に基づき、書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoshoden Hall (Palace Archive Hall)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>校書殿（きょうしょでん）とは、平安京の内裏における殿舎のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">kyosho-den Hall was a building in Imperial Place in the Heian-kyo capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoshoden Hall was one of the halls of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoshoden Hall was one of the halls of the dairi (Imperial Palace) in the city of Heian-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>内裏の南西にあり、紫宸殿の西、清涼殿の南に位置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being in the southeast area within Imperial Place, this hall was placed in the west of Shishin-den Hall and in the south of Seiryo-den Hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situated in the southwest of the Imperial Palace, this hall was located to west of Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall) and to the south of Seiryoden Hall.</e>
<cmt>・「Being」→「Situated」・「southeast area within」→「southwest of the」・「placed」→「located」・「in」→「to」　（x2）・「Shishin-den Hall」→「Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall)」・「Seiryo-den」→「Seiryoden」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situated in the southwest of the Imperial Palace, this hall was located to west of Shishinden Hall (Throne Hall) and to the south of Seiryoden Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>校書殿西廂の北には蔵人所が置かれ、西廂の南には書籍、文書を整理する校書所が置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kurododokoro (the chamberlain&apos;s office) was placed in the north of the seiso (the room attached to the west side) of kyosho-den Hall, and the Kyosho dokoro bureau for taking care of documents was placed in the south of the seiso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kurododokoro (Chamberlain&apos;s Office) was located in the north of the nishibisashi (western outer area) and the Kyoshodokoro Bureau which was responsible for the organization of documents was located in the south of the nishibisashi of Kyoshoden Hall.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kurododokoro (Chamberlain&apos;s Office) was located in the north of the nishibisashi (western outer area) and the Kyoshodokoro Bureau which was responsible for the organization of documents was located in the south of the nishibisashi of Kyoshoden Hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、東廂の南には右近衛府の職員の詰め所である右近陣座（うこんのじんのざ）が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the south of the toso (the room attached to its east side), Ukono-jinnoza, where the officers at the headquarters of the right division of Inner Palace guards worked, was placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the south of the Higashibisashi (eastern outer area) was the Ukon-no-Jin-no-Za which served as an office for Ukonefu (Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) officers.</e>
<cmt>ナチュラルに再翻訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the south of the Higashibisashi (eastern outer area) was the Ukon-no-Jin-no-Za which served as an office for Ukonefu (Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>文書の管理が行われていたので文殿とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Fumi-dono Hall (literally, a hall for documents), because documents were managed in the hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoshoden Hall was also called Fumidono Hall (lit. Document Hall) because it was where the administration of documents was conducted.</e>
<cmt>・「It」→「Kyoshoden Hall」・「(literally, a hall for documents」→「lit. Document Hall」・コンマを削除・「documents were managed in the hall」→「it was where the administration of documents was conducted」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoshoden Hall was also called Fumidono Hall (lit. Document Hall) because it was where the administration of documents was conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Blue-comet(id:192801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>