<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>国立国会図書館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Diet Library (NDL)</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Diet Library (NDL)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Diet Library (NDL)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>国立国会図書館（こくりつこっかいとしょかん）は、日本の国会議員の調査研究、行政、ならびに日本国民のために奉仕を提供する図書館である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The National Diet Library (NDL) is a library which provides services for members of Japan&apos;s Diet in their research and study, the executive agencies of the government, and the general public in Japan.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The National Diet Library (NDL) provides services for members of Japan&apos;s Diet in their research and study, as well as the executive agencies of the government and the general public in Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The National Diet Library (NDL) provides services for members of Japan&apos;s Diet in their research and study, as well as the executive agencies of the government and the general public in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、納本制度に基づいて、日本国内で出版されたすべての出版物を収集・保存する日本唯一の法定納本図書館である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the NDL is the only legal deposit library in Japan which acquires all materials published in Japan and preserve them based on the Legal Deposit System.</e>
<cmt>法定納本図書館：　legal deposit libraryhttp://www.ndl.go.jp/en/aboutus/outline_1.htmltsujikeita.hp.infoseek.co.jp/JSLIS-08_Kikawada.pdf、http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/cdnlao/newsletter/056/563.html#01</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the NDL is the only legal deposit library in Japan that acquires all materials published in Japan and preserves them based on the Legal Deposit System.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL is also the only legal deposit library in Japan that acquires all materials published in Japan and preserves them based on the Legal Deposit System.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>英語表記は。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name in English is..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name in English is:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name in English is:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>&quot;Overview&quot;→&quot;Summary&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>国立国会図書館は、日本の立法府である国会に属する国の機関であり、国会の立法行為を補佐することを第一の目的とする議会図書館である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL is an organ of the State which belongs to the Diet, a legislative body of Japan, and serves as a parliamentary library with a primary objective of assisting legislative activities of the Diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL, an organ of the State, belongs to the Diet, a legislative body of Japan, and serves as a parliamentary library with the primary objective of assisting in the legislative activities of the Diet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL, an organ of the State, belongs to the Diet, a legislative body of Japan, and serves as a parliamentary library with the primary objective of assisting in the legislative activities of the Diet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同時に、納本図書館として日本で唯一の国立図書館としての機能を兼ねており、行政・司法の各部門および日本国民に対するサービスも行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL also possesses a function as the only national legal deposit library in Japan, and provides services to the executive and judicial agencies of the government as well as to the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL also possesses a function as the only national legal deposit library in Japan, and provides services to the executive and judicial agencies of the government as well as to the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL also possesses a function as the only national legal deposit library in Japan, and provides services to the executive and judicial agencies of the government as well as to the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>施設は、「中央の図書館」として東京本館（東京都千代田区永田町）および国立国会図書館関西館（京都府相楽郡精華町精華台）が置かれ、「支部図書館」として国際子ども図書館（東京都台東区上野公園）、東洋文庫（東京都文京区本駒込）のほか、行政機関・司法機関などに26館が置かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its facilities consist of the &quot;Main Libraries&quot; which include the Tokyo Main Library (Nagata-cho, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and the Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library (Seikadai, Seika-cho, Soraku-gun, Kyoto Prefecture), as well as the &quot;Branch Libraries&quot; which include the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature (Ueno-koen, Taito Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), the Toyo Bunko (Oriental Library) (Honkomagome, Bunkyo Ward) and 26 libraries in the executive and judicial agencies of the government, etc.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/service/tokyo/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its facilities consist of the &quot;main libraries,&quot; which include the Tokyo Main Library (Nagata-cho, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and the Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library (Seikadai, Seika-cho, Soraku-gun, Kyoto Prefecture), as well as the &quot;branch libraries,&quot; which include the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature (Ueno-koen, Taito Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), the Toyo Bunko (Oriental Library) (Honkomagome, Bunkyo Ward) and 26 libraries in the executive and judicial agencies of the government, etc.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its facilities consist of the &quot;main libraries,&quot; which include the Tokyo Main Library (Nagata-cho, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and the Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library (Seikadai, Seika-cho, Soraku-gun, Kyoto Prefecture), as well as the &quot;branch libraries,&quot; including the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature (Ueno-koen, Taito Ward, Tokyo Prefecture), the Toyo Bunko (Oriental Library) (Honkomagome, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) and 26 libraries in the executive and judicial agencies of the government, etc.</e>
<cmt>東洋文庫のTokyo Prefectureを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>国立国会図書館の淵源は、大日本帝国憲法下の帝国議会各院に置かれていた衆議院図書館、貴族院図書館、および文部省に付属していた帝国図書館の3館にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL has its origins in the following three libraries: the Library of the House of Representatives and the Library of the House of Peers, both of which were established in each house of the Imperial Diet under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan; and the Imperial Library established under the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://www.ndl.go.jp/en/aboutus/outline_2seal.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL has its origins in the following three libraries: the Library of the House of Representatives and the Library of the House of Peers, both of which were established in each house of the Imperial Diet under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan; and the Imperial Library established under the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL has its origins in the following three libraries: the Library of the House of Representatives and the Library of the House of Peers, both of which were established in each house of the Imperial Diet under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan; and the Imperial Library established under the Ministry of Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>貴衆各院の図書館は、1891年（明治24年）に設立された各院の図書室を起源としており、また、帝国図書館は1872年（明治5年）に設立された書籍館をその前身とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers have their origins in the libraries of each house established in 1891, and the Imperial Library developed out of a bibliotheca established in 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers have their origins in the libraries of each respective house, as established in 1891, while the Imperial Library developed out of a bibliotheca established in 1872.</e>
<cmt>grammar, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers have their origins in the libraries of each respective house, as established in 1891, while the Imperial Library developed out of a bibliotheca established in 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>第二次世界大戦後、1947年（昭和22年）に施行された日本国憲法は、国会を唯一の立法機関と定め、国会を構成する衆議院・参議院の両議院は「全国民を代表する選挙された議員」（国会議員）で組織されると定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the World War II, the Constitution of Japan, which came into force in 1947, defined the Diet as the sole law-making organ of the State, and that the House of Representatives and the House of Councillors, which compose the Diet, shall consist of &quot;elected members, representative of all the people&quot; (the member of the Diet).</e>
<cmt>プログレッシブ和英中辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After World War II, the Constitution of Japan, which came into force in 1947, defined the Diet as the sole law-making organ of the State, and that the House of Representatives and the House of Councilors, which comprise the Diet, should consist of &quot;elected members, representative of all the people&quot; (as the member of the Diet).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After World War II, the Constitution of Japan, which came into force in 1947, defined the Diet as the sole law-making organ of the State, and that the House of Representatives and the House of Councilors, which comprise the Diet, should consist of &quot;elected members, representative of all the people&quot; (as the member of the Diet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして、国会が民主的に運営され、国会議員が十分な立法活動を行うためには、国会議員のための調査機関として議会図書館の拡充が必要とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An expansion of the parliamentary library as a research organ for Diet members was deemed vital for the democratic operation of the Diet and for assisting Diet members to fully perform their legislative duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An expansion of the parliamentary library as a research organ for Diet members was deemed vital for the democratic operation of the Diet and for assisting Diet members to fully perform their legislative duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An expansion of the parliamentary library as a research organ for Diet members was deemed vital for the democratic operation of the Diet and for assisting Diet members to fully perform their legislative duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>このため、日本国憲法の施行とともに施行された国会法（昭和22年法律第79号）130条は「議員の調査研究に資するため、別に定める法律により、国会に国立国会図書館を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Article 130 of the National Diet Act (Act No. 79 of 1947) which came into force along with the enforcement of the Constitution of Japan, stipulated, &quot;The National Diet Library shall be established in the Diet by a separate law, in order to assist Diet members in their research and study.&quot;</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB、プログレッシブ和英中辞典</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Article 130 of the National Diet Act (Act No. 79 of 1947), which came into force along with the enforcement of the Constitution of Japan, stipulated, &quot;The National Diet Library shall be established in the Diet by a separate law so as to assist Diet members in their research and study.&quot;</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Article 130 of the National Diet Act (Act No. 79 of 1947), which came into force along with the enforcement of the Constitution of Japan, stipulated, &quot;The National Diet Library shall be established in the Diet by a separate law so as to assist Diet members in their research and study.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>」と定め、あわせて国会図書館法（昭和22年法律第84号）を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Diet Library Act (Act No. 84 of 1947) was enacted at the same time.</e>
<cmt>法なび法令用語和英辞書 (http://waei.hounavi.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Diet Library Act (Act No. 84 of 1947) was enacted at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Diet Library Act (Act No. 84 of 1947) was enacted at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これにより、貴衆両院の図書館を合併した国会図書館の設立が定められたが、この体制では国会議員の調査研究には不十分であるとみられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resulted in an establishment of the National Library which combined the libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers, however, the structure appeared to be insufficient for assisting Diet members in their research and study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted in the establishment of the National Library, which combined the libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers; however, the structure appeared to be insufficient as a means to assist Diet members in their research and study.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted in the establishment of the National Library, which combined the libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers; however, the structure appeared to be insufficient as a means to assist Diet members in their research and study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>そこで、アメリカ合衆国から図書館使節団が招かれ、国会はその意見を取り入れて、翌1948年（昭和23年）、国立国会図書館法（昭和23年法律第5号）を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given this, a library mission was invited by the Diet from the United States of America, and the National Diet Library Act (Act No. 5 of 1948) was enacted in 1948 based on the advice of the U.S. library mission.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given this, a library mission from the United States of America was invited by the Diet, and the National Diet Library Act (Act No. 5 of 1948) was enacted based on the advice of the U.S. library mission.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given this, a library mission from the United States of America was invited by the Diet, and the National Diet Library Act (Act No. 5 of 1948) was enacted based on the advice of the U.S. library mission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>同法はアメリカ図書館使節団の強い影響下に誕生したため、国立国会図書館はアメリカ議会図書館 (Library of Congress) をモデルとして、議会図書館であると同時に国立図書館（国立中央図書館）の機能も兼ね、国内資料の網羅的収集と整理を目的とした法定納本制度をもつこととされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Act came into force under a strong influence of the U.S. library mission, it was decided that the NDL would be established based on the U.S. Library of Congress, combining functions as a national library (national central library) as well as a parliamentary library, and having the Legal Deposit System with the purpose of acquiring and classifying a comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Act came into force under the strong influence of the U.S. library mission, it was decided that the NDL should be established based on the U.S. Library of Congress, combining the functions of a national library (national central library) and a parliamentary library, and having the Legal Deposit System for the purpose of acquiring and classifying a comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Act came into force under the strong influence of the U.S. library mission, it was decided that the NDL should be established based on the U.S. Library of Congress, combining the functions of a national library (national central library) and a parliamentary library, and having the Legal Deposit System for the purpose of acquiring and classifying a comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>同法の制定とともに、国会図書館の設立準備が進められ、初代国立国会図書館長には憲法学で日本国憲法制定時の憲法担当国務大臣だった金森徳次郎が迎えられて、1948年（昭和23年）2月25日に国立国会図書館は発足した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Along with the enactment of said Act, preparations for the establishment of a national library progressed, and the National Diet Library was established on February 25, 1948, with Tokujiro KANAMORI, a constitutional scholar who served as the Minister of State at the enactment of the Constitution of Japan, as the first Chief Librarian of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>「憲法学」の部分は、「憲法学者」の意味であると解釈し、翻訳いたしました。英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the enactment of the Act, preparations for the establishment of a national library progressed, and the National Diet Library was established on February 25, 1948, with Tokujiro KANAMORI, a constitutional scholar who had served as the Minister of State at the enactment of the Constitution of Japan, as the first Chief Librarian of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the enactment of the Act, preparations for the establishment of a national library progressed, and the National Diet Library was established on February 25, 1948, with Tokujiro KANAMORI, a constitutional scholar who had served as the minister of state at the enactment of the Constitution of Japan, as the first chief librarian of the NDL..</e>
<cmt>最後のピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>続いて、初代副館長に美学で尾道市立図書館長だった中井正一が任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following this, Masakazu NAKAI, an aesthetics scholar who had been Chief Librarian of the Onomichi City Library, was appointed the first Deputy Chief Librarian of the NDL. The NDL was officially　opened to the public on June 5, 1948 in a temporary building using the former Akasaka Detached Palace (Akasaka rikyu) (now known as the State Guest House or Geihinkan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「美学」の部分は、「美学学者」の意味であると解釈し、翻訳いたしました。http://www.docoja.com:8080/jisho/mainword?dbname=geog&amp;mainword=Akasaka_palacehttp://www.infomapjapan.com/sight_Tokyo.phtml、および英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Masakazu NAKAI, an aesthetics scholar who had been Chief Librarian of the Onomichi City Library, was appointed the first Deputy Chief Librarian of the NDL. The NDL was officially opened to the public on June 5, 1948 in a temporary building using the former Akasaka Detached Palace (Akasaka rikyu) (now known as the State Guest House or Geihinkan).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Masakazu NAKAI, an aesthetics scholar who had been the chief librarian of the Onomichi City Library, was appointed the first deputy chief librarian of the NDL..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル30の原文を分割し、セル31に移動。それにあわせ、訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>同年6月5日、旧赤坂離宮（現迎賓館）を仮庁舎として、国立国会図書館は正式に開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL was officially opened to the public on June 5, 1948 in a temporary building using the former Akasaka Detached Palace (Akasaka rikyu), which is now known as the State Guest House (or the Geihinkan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル30の原文を分割し、セル31に移動。それにあわせ、訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>翌1949年（昭和24年）には、国立国会図書館法の定めた方針に基づき、出版法（明治26年法律第15号。出版法及び新聞紙法を廃止する法律（昭和24年法律第95号）により廃止）に基づいて納本された出版物を所蔵していた上野の国立図書館（1947年（昭和22年）に帝国図書館から改称）が統合された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year (in 1949), pursuant to the policies specified in the National Diet Library Act,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year (1949), pursuant to the policies specified in the National Diet Library Act,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year (1949), pursuant to the policies specified in the National Diet Library Act, the NDL merged with the National Library in Ueno (the name was changed from the Imperial Library in 1947), which housed publications deposited in accordance with the Publishing Act (Act No. 15 of 1893, an act to abolish the Publishing Act and Newspaper Act (Act No. 95 of 1949)).</e>
<cmt>セル33とセル34に分割されていた原文をセル33にまとめ、あわせて、訳文もまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これにより、国立国会図書館は名実ともに日本唯一の国立図書館となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the NDL merged with the National Library in Ueno (renamed from the Imperial Library in 1947) which housed publications deposited in accordance with the Publishing Act (Act No. 15 of 1893; abolished by an Act to abolish the Publishing Act and Newspaper Act (Act No. 95 of 1949)). As a result of this, the NDL became the only national library in Japan, both nominally and virtually.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the NDL merged with the National Library in Ueno (renamed from the Imperial Library in 1947), which housed publications deposited in accordance with the Publishing Act (Act No. 15 of 1893; abolished by an act to abolish the Publishing Act and Newspaper Act (Act No. 95 of 1949)). As a result of this, the NDL became the only national library in Japan, both nominally and virtually.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, the NDL became the only national library in Japan, both nominally and virtually.</e>
<cmt>セル33で1文にまとめた文章の最後を分割し、セル34に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>旧帝国図書館の蔵書と施設はそのまま上野に残され、同館は国立国会図書館の支部図書館である国立国会図書館支部上野図書館とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collections and facilities of the former Imperial Library were preserved untouched in Ueno, and it became the NDL Ueno Brach Library, one of the branch libraries of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/aboutus/outline_2.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collections and facilities of the former Imperial Library were preserved untouched in Ueno, and it became the NDL Ueno Branch Library, one of the branches of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collections and facilities of the former Imperial Library were preserved untouched in Ueno, and it became the NDL Ueno Branch Library, one of the branches of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>組織の発足より建設が遅れていた国立国会図書館の本館庁舎は、国立国会図書館法と同時に公布された国立国会図書館建築委員会法（昭和23年法律第6号）に基づいて検討が進められ、国会議事堂の北隣にあった旧ドイツ大使館跡地（東京都千代田区永田町）に建設されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the NDL Main Building had been delayed since the establishment of the organization, but the discussion progressed based on the Act on Construction Committee for National Diet Library (Act No. 6 of 1948) which was promulgated along with the National Diet Library Act. It was decided that the Main Building shall be build on the site of the former Embassy of Germany (Nagata-cho, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) located directly north of the Diet Building.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。法なび法令用語和英辞書 (http://waei.hounavi.jp/)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the NDL Main Building had been delayed since the establishment of the organization, but the discussion progressed based on the Act on the Construction Committee for National Diet Library (Act No. 6 of 1948), which was promulgated along with the National Diet Library Act; thus it was decided that the Main Building should be build on the site of the former Embassy of Germany (Nagata-cho, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) located directly north of the Diet Building.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the NDL Main Building had been delayed since the establishment of the organization, but the discussion progressed based on the Act on the Construction Committee for the National Diet Library (Act No. 6 of 1948), which was promulgated along with the National Diet Library Act; thus it was decided that the Main Building should be built on the site of the former Embassy of Germany (Nagata-cho, Chiyoda Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) located directly north of the Diet Building.</e>
<cmt>build→built</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>本館庁舎（現在の東京本館）は建築設計競技により前川國男の案が選ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A design submitted by Kunio MAEKAWA was selected in the architectural design competition for the Main Building (now known as the Tokyo Main Library). Upon the completion of the first phase of the library construction in 1961, the collection of books started to be housed in the new building.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A design submitted by Kunio MAEKAWA was selected in the architectural design competition for the Main Building (now known as the Tokyo Main Library). Upon the completion of the first phase of library construction in 1961, the collection of books started to be housed in the new building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A design submitted by Kunio MAEKAWA was selected in the architectural design competition for the Main Building (now known as the Tokyo Main Library).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル38の原文をセル39に分割し、訳文もそれにあわせて分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1961年（昭和36年）に第一期工事を完了し、図書が収蔵され始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the completion of the first phase of library construction in 1961, the new building began to house the collection of books.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル38の原文をセル39に分割し、訳文もそれにあわせて分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>収蔵された図書は、貴衆両院図書館からの引継書と戦後の収集分からなる赤坂の国会図書館仮本館蔵書が約100万冊、帝国図書館による戦前収集分を基礎とする上野図書館の蔵書が約100万冊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection of books included a stock of approximately one million volumes previously housed in the NDL&apos;s temporary Main Library in Akasaka, which consisted of those transferred from the Libraries of the House of Representatives and the House of Peers, and those acquired after the war, as well as another approximately one million volumes previously housed in the Ueno Branch Library most of which had been acquired prior to the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection of books included a stock of approximately a million volumes previously housed in the NDL&apos;s temporary main library in Akasaka, which consisted of those transferred from the libraries of the houses of Representatives and Peers along with those acquired after the war, as well as approximately a million volumes previously housed in the Ueno Branch Library, most of which had been acquired prior to the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection of books included a stock of approximately a million volumes previously housed in the NDL&apos;s temporary main library in Akasaka, which consisted of those transferred from the libraries of the houses of Representatives and Peers along with those acquired after the war, as well as approximately a million volumes previously housed in the Ueno Branch Library, most of which had been acquired prior to the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ここに、別々の歴史をもつ2館の蔵書は1館に合流し、同年11月1日、国立国会図書館本館は蔵書205万冊をもって開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Combing the collection of books from the two libraries with different histories, the NDL Main Library opened on November 1, 1961 with a total collection of 2,050,000 volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Combining the collections of books from the two libraries, with their different histories, the NDL Main Library opened on November 1, 1961 with a total collection of 2,050,000 volumes.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Combining the collections of books from the two libraries, with their different histories, the NDL Main Library opened on November 1, 1961 with a total collection of 2,050,000 volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>本館の工事は開館後も続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the Main Library continued after the opening of the NDL. As the extension work progressed, the Diet Service Section, which was located in the Miyakezaka temporary building on the site of the former General Staff Office Building (now known as the Kensei-Kinenkan (Constitution Memorial Center) located in the North Area of the Front Garden of the Diet Building), merged into the NDL Main Library, completing the consolidation of the NDL&apos;s functions previously spread among three areas: Akasaka, Ueno and Miyakezaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the Main Library continued after the opening of the NDL. As the extension work progressed, the Diet Service Section--which was located in the Miyakezaka temporary building on the site of the former General Staff Office Building (now known as the Kensei-Kinenkan (Constitution Memorial Center) located in the North Area of the Front Garden of the Diet Building)--merged into the NDL Main Library, completing the consolidation of the NDL&apos;s functions previously spread among three areas: Akasaka, Ueno and Miyakezaka.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the Main Library continued after the opening of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル43の原文をセル44に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>増築の進捗にともなって旧参謀本部庁舎跡地（現国会前庭北地区・憲政記念館）の三宅坂仮庁舎に置かれていた国会サービス部門も本館内に移転し、赤坂・上野・三宅坂の3地区に分かれていた国会図書館の機能は最終的な統合をみる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the extension work progressed, the Diet Service Section--which was located in the Miyakezaka temporary building on the site of the former General Staff Office Building (now known as the Kensei-Kinenkan (Constitution Memorial Center) located in the north area of the front garden of the Diet Building)--merged into the NDL Main Library, completing the consolidation of the NDL&apos;s functions previously spread among three areas: Akasaka, Ueno and Miyakezaka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル43の原文をセル44に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>本館は、開館から7年後の1968年（昭和43年）に竣工し、地上6階・地下1階の事務棟と17層の書庫棟からなる施設が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The construction of the Main Building was completed in 1968, seven years after the initial opening, creating a facility which consisted of an Administration Building with six floors aboveground and one floor underground, as well as a Library Building with 17 floors aboveground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the Main Building was completed in 1968, seven years after the initial opening, thereby creating a facility that consisted of an administration building with six floors above ground and one floor underground, as well as a library building with 17 floors above ground.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the Main Building was completed in 1968, seven years after the initial opening, thereby creating a facility that consisted of an administration building with six floors above ground and one floor underground, as well as a library building with 17 floors above ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="30">
<j>1970年代には蔵書の順調な増大、閲覧者の増加が進み、本館の施設は早くも手狭になりつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the collection steadily expanded and the number of library users increased during the 1970&apos;s, it became already apparent that more space would be required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the collection steadily expanded and the number of library users increased during the 1970s, it became readily apparent that more space would be required.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the collection steadily expanded and the number of library users increased during the 1970s, it became readily apparent that more space would be required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このため本館の北隣に新館が建設されることになり、1986年（昭和61年）に開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, it was decided to build an Annex building directly north of the Main Building. The Annex was opened to the public in 1986.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, it was decided to build an annex building directly north of the main building. The annex was opened to the public in 1986.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, it was decided to build an annex building directly north of the main building, and the annex was opened to the public in 1986.</e>
<cmt>2文を1文に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>設計は本館と同じく前川國男が担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Annex was designed by Kunio MAEKAWA, an architect of the Main Building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The annex was designed by Kunio MAEKAWA, an architect of the main building.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The annex was designed by Kunio MAEKAWA, an architect of the main building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>地上4階地下8階で広大な地下部分をすべて書庫にあてた新館の完成により、国立国会図書館は全館合計で1200万冊の図書を収蔵可能な巨大図書館となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With a completion of the Annex with four floors aboveground and eight floors underground, with all of the underground floors allocated for the stack space, the NDL grew to a massive library which could accommodate a combined total of 12 million volumes. It was expected, however, that the NDL will reach its full storage capacity at the beginning of the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the completion of the annex, including four floors aboveground and eight floors underground, with all of the underground floors allocated for the stack space, the NDL grew to a massive library that could accommodate a combined total of 12 million volumes. It was expected, however, that the NDL will reach its full storage capacity at the beginning of the twenty-first century.</e>
<cmt>grammar, number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the completion of the annex, including four floors above ground and eight floors underground, with all of the underground floors allocated for the stack space, the NDL grew to a massive library that could accommodate a combined total of 12 million volumes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル50の原文をセル51に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、これも21世紀初頭に所蔵能力の限界に達することが予測された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was expected, however, that the NDL would reach its full storage capacity at the beginning of the twenty-first century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル50の原文をセル51に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>このため1980年代以降、第二国立国会図書館を建設する計画が浮上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to a plan to build the second facility of the NDL after the 1980&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to a plan, after the 1980s, to build the second facility of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to a plan, after the 1980s, to build the second facility of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>第二の国会図書館は増えつづける蔵書を東京本館と分担して保存し、関西文化学術研究都市に建設されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was decided that the second facility of the NDL would be built in Kansai Science City and that the new facility would share the responsibility of preserving the increasing number of collections with the Tokyo Main Library. It was also decided that the new facility would specialize in providing information responded to the development of telecommunications accompanied by the advancement of computer technology, as well as services as a digital library for remote users. The new facility, named the Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library, was opened to the public in 2002.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was decided that the second facility of the NDL would be built in Kansai Science City and that the new facility would share the responsibility of preserving the increasing number of collections with the Tokyo Main Library. It was also decided that the new facility would specialize in providing information corresponding to the development of telecommunications accompanied by the progress of computer technology, as well as services as a digital library for remote users. The new facility, named the Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library, was opened to the public in 2002.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was decided that the second facility of the NDL would be built in Kansai Science City and that the new facility would share the responsibility of preserving the increasing number of collections with the Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル54の原文を3文に分割し、セル55、56に移動。それにあわせ、訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また当館は、コンピュータ技術の発達にともなう情報通信の発展に対応する情報発信、非来館型サービスに特化した図書館と位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also decided that the new facility would specialize in providing information corresponding to the development of telecommunications accompanied by the progress of computer technology, as well as services as a digital library for remote users.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル54の原文を3文に分割し、セル55、56に移動。それにあわせ、訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>そして、国立国会図書館関西館として、2002年（平成14年）に開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new facility, named the Kansai-kan of the National Diet Library, was opened to the public in 2002.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル54の原文を3文に分割し、セル55、56に移動。それにあわせ、訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>関西館には科学技術関連資料、アジア言語資料、国内論文などが移管され、東京本館とともに国立国会図書館の中央館を構成する一角となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the transferred collections of scientific and technological materials, materials in Asian languages, and Japanese doctoral dissertations, etc., the Kansai-san has become a vital part of the NDL Main Library along with the Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the transferred collections of scientific and technological materials, materials in Asian languages and Japanese doctoral dissertations, etc., the Kansai-san became a vital part of the NDL Main Library along with the Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the transferred collections of scientific and technological materials, materials in Asian languages and Japanese doctoral dissertations, etc., the Kansai-kan became a vital part of the NDL Main Library along with the Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt>Kansai-san→kansai-kan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>また、関西館の開館に前後して、支部上野図書館の施設を改築の上、国際子ども図書館として活用する計画が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the time of the opening of the Kansai-san, there was an ongoing plan to refurbish the facility of the Ueno Branch Library and utilize it as the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the time of the opening of the Kansai-san, there was an ongoing plan to refurbish the facility of the Ueno Branch Library and use it as the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the time of the opening of the Kansai-kan, there was a plan to refurbish the facility of the Ueno Branch Library and use it as the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature.</e>
<cmt>Kansai-san→kansai-kan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>国際子ども図書館は国立国会図書館の蔵書のうち児童書（主に18歳未満を対象とする図書館資料）を分担して所蔵する児童書のナショナルセンターとして位置付けられ、2000年（平成12年）に部分開館、2002年（平成14年）に全面開館した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, positioned as a national center of children&apos;s literature which is in charge of storing children&apos;s literature (library materials primarily targeting readers under 18 years of age) among the collection of books housed in the NDL., was partly opened in 2000 and was fully opened in 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, positioned as a national center for children&apos;s literature in charge of storing children&apos;s literature (library materials primarily targeting readers under 18 years of age) among the collection of books housed in the NDL, was partly opened in 2000 and was fully opened in 2002.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, positioned as a national center for children&apos;s literature in charge of storing children&apos;s literature (library materials primarily targeting readers under 18 years of age) among the collection of books housed in the NDL, was partly opened in 2000 and was fully opened in 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>近年は、電子図書館事業の拡充に力が注がれる一方、2005年（平成17年）の国立国会図書館法における館長の国務大臣待遇規定の削除、2006年（平成18年）の自由民主党行政改革推進本部の国会事務局改革の一環としての独立行政法人化の提言、2007年（平成19年）の国会関係者以外からは初めてとなる長尾真（元京都大学総長）の館長任命など、国立国会図書館の組織のあり方をめぐる動きが相次いでいる状況である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, while the NDL has been focusing on the expansion of the electronic library projects, there have been a number of movements related to the organization of the NDL including the following: removal of the Minister of State status for the Chief Librarian of the NDL under the National Diet Library Act in 2005; a suggestion on the transformation into an independent administrative institution as part of the National Diet Administrative Reforms by the Administrative Reform Promotion Headquarters of Liberal Democratic Party in 2006; and an appointment of Makoto NAGAO (a former President of Kyoto University) as Chief Librarian of the NDL, the first appointment of a non-Diet related member in 2007, etc.</e>
<cmt>http://www.jimin.jp/jimin/english/Organs/index.html英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://www.kyoto-u.ac.jp/ja</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, while the NDL has focused on the expansion of the electronic library projects, there have been numerous movements related to the organization of the NDL, such as the following: removal of the &quot;minister of state&quot; status for the chief librarian of the NDL under the National Diet Library Act in 2005; a suggestion on the transformation into an independent administrative institution as part of the National Diet Administrative Reforms by the Administrative Reform Promotion Headquarters of the Liberal Democratic Party in 2006; and the appointment of Makoto NAGAO (a former president of Kyoto University) as the chief librarian of the NDL in 2007, the first appointment of a non-Diet member, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, while the NDL has focused on the expansion of the electronic library projects, there have been numerous movements related to the organization of the NDL, such as the following: removal of the &quot;minister of state&quot; status for the chief librarian of the NDL under the National Diet Library Act in 2005; a suggestion on the transformation into an independent administrative institution as part of the National Diet Administrative Reforms by the Administrative Reform Promotion Headquarters of the Liberal Democratic Party in 2006; and the appointment of Makoto NAGAO (a former president of Kyoto University) as the chief librarian of the NDL in 2007, the first appointment of a non-Diet member, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>理念</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Philosophy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Philosophy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Philosophy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>国立国会図書館法の前文は、「国立国会図書館は、真理がわれらを自由にするという確信に立って日本国憲法の誓約する日本の民主化と世界平和とに寄与することを使命としてここに設立される」と、その設立理念を明らかにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The philosophy of the NDL&apos;s establishment is specified in the preamble of the National Diet Library Act as follows: &quot;National Diet Library is hereby established as a result of the firm conviction that truth makes us free and with the object of contributing to international peace and the democratization of Japan as promised in our Constitution.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The philosophy of the NDL&apos;s establishment is specified in the preamble of the National Diet Library Act, as follows: &quot;The National Diet Library is hereby established as a result of the firm conviction that truth makes us free and with the object of contributing to international peace and the democratization of Japan, as promised in our Constitution.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The philosophy of the NDL&apos;s establishment is specified in the preamble of the National Diet Library Act, as follows: &apos;The National Diet Library is hereby established through the firm conviction that truth makes us free and with the objective of contributing to international peace and the democratization of Japan, as promised in the Constitution.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>前文の一節「真理がわれらを自由にする」は、図書館が公平に資料を提供してゆくことで国民に知る自由を保障し、健全な民主社会を育む礎となっていかねばならないとする国立国会図書館の基本理念を明らかにしたものであると解釈されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A paragraph from its preamble &quot;truth makes us free&quot; has been interpreted as an illumination of the NDL&apos;s principles which state that libraries should guarantee the freedom of knowledge for the Japanese people by an equal provision of materials, and should be the foundation for realizing the sound democratic society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A paragraph from its preamble, &quot;Truth Makes Us Free,&quot; has been interpreted as an illumination of the NDL&apos;s principles, which state that libraries should guarantee freedom of knowledge for the Japanese people through the equal provision of materials, and should be the foundation for realizing a sound democratic society.</e>
<cmt>g, art</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A paragraph from its preamble, &apos;Truth Makes Us Free,&apos; has been interpreted as an illumination of the NDL&apos;s principles, which state that libraries should guarantee freedom of knowledge for the Japanese people through the equal provision of materials, and should be the foundation for realizing a sound democratic society.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>国立国会図書館法はアメリカ図書館使節団の原案をもとに起草されたと言われているが、この前文は歴史家で国会議員の羽仁五郎（当時の参議院図書館運営委員長）が挿入したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it is said that the National Diet Library Act was drawn up based on the original plan by the U.S. library mission, this preamble is believe to have been inserted by Goro HANI, a historian and a Diet member (Chairman of the Steering Committee of the Library of the House of Councillors back then).</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/aboutus/outline_2seal.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it is said that the National Diet Library Act was drawn up based on the original plan by the U.S. library mission, this preamble is believed to have been inserted by Goro HANI, a historian and a Diet member (who was then the chairman of the Steering Committee of the Library of the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it is said that the National Diet Library Act was drawn up based on the original plan by the U.S. library mission, this preamble is believed to have been inserted by Goro HANI, a historian and a Diet member (who was then the chairman of the Steering Committee of the Library of the House of Councilors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>「真理がわれらを自由にする」の句は羽仁五郎の創案になるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The phrase &quot;truth makes us free&quot; originated with Goro HANI. It is believed that when HANI was in Germany for his study, he was inspired by an inscription &quot;(truth makes people free)&quot; engraved on the library building of University of Freiburg (Albert-Ludwigs-Universitat Freiburg) where he was studying. The origin of the verse is said to have been a phrase in the New Testament &quot;(truth make you free)&quot; (8-32 of The Gospel According to St. John).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。http://www.uni-freiburg.de/index_en.php 英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phrase &quot;truth makes us free&quot; originated with Goro HANI. It is believed that when HANI was in Germany for his study, he was inspired by an inscription &quot;(truth makes people free)&quot; engraved on the library building of University of Freiburg (Albert-Ludwigs-Universitat Freiburg), where he was studying; the origin of the verse is said to have been a phrase in the New Testament &quot;(truth make you free)&quot; (8-32 of the Gospel According to St. John).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phrase &apos;truth makes us free&apos; originated with Goro HANI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル70の原文をセル71に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>羽仁がドイツに留学していた当時、留学先のフライブルク大学の図書館の建物に刻まれているのを見て感銘を受けたという銘文「（真理は人を自由にする）」をもとにしたといい、その句は『新約聖書』の「（真理はあなたたちを自由にする）」（ヨハネによる福音書 8-32）に由来していると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that when HANI was in Germany for his study, he was inspired by an inscription &apos;(truth makes people free)&apos; engraved on the library building of University of Freiburg (Albert-Ludwigs-Universitat Freiburg), where he was studying; the origin of the verse is said to have been a phrase in the New Testament &apos;(the truth shall make you free)&apos; (8-32 of the Gospel according to St. John).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル70の原文をセル71に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="48">
<j>1961年（昭和36年）に開館した国立国会図書館東京本館では、本館2階目録ホールの壁に金森初代館長の筆になる「真理がわれらを自由にする」の句が大きく刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the NDL Tokyo Main Library which was opened to the public in 1961, the phrase &quot;truth makes us free&quot; drawn by KANAMORI, the first Chief Librarian, has been engraved in large letters on the wall of the Book Catalog Hall on the second floor of the Main Building. This phrase has been seen by many people and came to be known as a principle of not only the NDL but also libraries in general.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the NDL Tokyo Main Library which was opened to the public in 1961, the phrase &quot;truth makes us free&quot; drawn by KANAMORI, the first Chief Librarian, has been engraved in large letters on the wall of the Book Catalog Hall on the second floor of the main building. This phrase has been seen by many people and has become known as a principle not only of the NDL but also of libraries in general.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the NDL Tokyo Main Library which was opened to the public in 1961, the phrase &apos;truth makes us free&apos; drawn by KANAMORI, the first chief librarian, has been engraved in large letters on the wall of the book-catalog hall on the second floor of the main building.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル73の原文をセル74に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この句は多くの人の目にとまるようになるとともに、ひとり国立国会図書館のみならず図書館一般の原理として理解されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phrase has been seen by many people and has become known as a principle not only of the NDL but also of libraries in general.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル73の原文をセル74に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>戦後日本の図書館運動・図書館界の発展においてこの句が与えた影響は少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This phrase had a significant influence on library movements and development of libraries in postwar Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This phrase had a significant influence on library movements and the development of libraries in postwar Japan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This phrase had a significant influence on library movements and the development of libraries in postwar Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>組織</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>国立国会図書館は日本の立法府である国会に属する独立した国の機関で、衆議院および参議院の議長及び両議院に置かれる常任委員会である議院運営委員会の監督のもと自立して運営される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL is an organ of the State which belongs to the Diet, a legislative body of Japan, and is operated independently under the supervision of the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the House of Councillors, as well as the Committees on Rules and Administration, which are the Standing Committee of both houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL, an organ of the State, belongs to the Diet, a legislative body of Japan, and is operated independently under the supervision of the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the House of Councilors, as well as the Committees on Rules and Administration, which comprise the standing committees of both houses.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL, an organ of the State, belongs to the Diet, a legislative body of Japan, and is operated independently under the supervision of the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the House of Councilors, as well as the Committees on Rules and Administration, which comprise the standing committees of both houses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>図書館の事務を統理する国立国会図書館長は、両議院の議長によって任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chief Librarian of the NDL, who supervises the administration of the library, is appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the House of Councillors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chief Librarian of the NDL, who supervises the administration of the library, is appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the House of Councillors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chief Librarian of the NDL, who supervises the administration of the library, is appointed by the Speaker of the House of Representatives and the President of the House of Councillors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="53">
<j>その組織は国立国会図書館法に基づき、中央の図書館と支部図書館からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the National Diet Library Act, its organization consists of Main Libraries and Branch Libraries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the National Diet Library Act, its organization consists of the main libraries and branches.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the National Diet Library Act, its organization consists of the main libraries and branches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>中央の図書館には、東京・永田町の東京本館と京都府の関西館があり、支部図書館のひとつである国際子ども図書館の扱うものを除き、国会図書館の所蔵する各種の資料を分担して保管している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Main Libraries comprise of the Tokyo Main Library in Nagata-cho, Tokyo Prefecture, and the Kansai-san in Kyoto Prefecture, and the two Libraries share the responsibility of storing various materials owned by the National Library, except for those fall under the category of the responsibility of the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Main Libraries comprise the Tokyo Main Library in Nagata-cho, Tokyo Prefecture, and the Kansai-san in Kyoto Prefecture; additionally, the two Libraries share the responsibility for storing various materials owned by the National Library, except for those falling under the category of the responsibility of the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main libraries comprise the Tokyo Main Library in Nagata-cho, Tokyo Prefecture, and the Kansai-kan in Kyoto Prefecture; additionally, the two libraries share the responsibility for storing various materials owned by the National Library, except for those falling under the category of the responsibility of the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature.</e>
<cmt>Kansai-san→Kansai-kan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、国会議事堂内には、中央の図書館に付属する国立国会図書館国会分館がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the NDL Diet Branch Library, which belongs to the Main Libraries, is located inside the Diet Building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the NDL Diet Branch Library, which belongs to the Main Libraries, is located inside the Diet Building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the NDL Diet Branch Library, which belongs to the Main Libraries, is located inside the Diet Building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>支部図書館は、国際子ども図書館、東洋文庫そして行政および司法の各部門におかれる図書館がこれに該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, the Toyo Bunko, and libraries in each of the executive and judicial agencies fall under the category of Branch Libraries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, the Toyo Bunko, and libraries in each of the executive and judicial agencies are classified as branch libraries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, the Toyo Bunko, and libraries in each of the executive and judicial agencies are classified as branch libraries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>このうち国際子ども図書館は、納本制度によって国会図書館に集められた日本国内の出版物や購入・国際交換によりもたらされた日本国外の出版物のうち、18歳未満を読者の主たる対象とする資料の保存・提供を分担している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature is in charge of preservation and provision of materials primarily targeting readers under 18 years of age, out of the materials published in Japan which have been acquired by the National Library based on the Legal Deposit System, as well as the materials published outside Japan which have been brought to the National Library by international exchanges. Therefore, the substantial nature of the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature is closer to a branch library which belongs to the Main Libraries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature is in charge of preservation and provision of materials primarily targeting readers under 18 years of age, out of the materials published in Japan that have been acquired by the National Library based on the Legal Deposit System, as well as the materials published outside Japan that have been brought to the National Library via international exchanges. Therefore, the substantial nature of the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature is closer to a branch library belonging to the Main Libraries.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature is in charge of the preservation and provision of materials primarily targeting readers under 18 years of age, out of the materials published in Japan that have been acquired by the National Library based on the Legal Deposit System, as well as the materials published outside Japan that have been brought to the National Library via purchase and international exchanges.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル87の原文をセル88に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割。「購入」の訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その性格は実質的には中央の図書館の分館に近い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the substantial nature of the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature is closer to a branch library belonging to the main libraries.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また、支部東洋文庫はアジア研究専門の図書館兼研究所である財団法人東洋文庫の寄託を受け、文庫の図書館奉仕部門を国立国会図書館の支部として国会図書館の組織内においたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the Toyo Bunko Branch Library is a Library Service Department of the Toyo Bunko, which has been designated as a branch of the NDL and placed under the organization of the National Library, deposited by the Toyo Bunko, a library and research institute dedicated to Asian studies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the Toyo Bunko Branch Library is a Library Service Department of the Toyo Bunko, which has been designated as a branch of the NDL and placed under the organization of the National Library, deposited by the Toyo Bunko, a library and research institute dedicated to Asian studies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the Toyo Bunko Branch Library is a Library Service Department of the Toyo Bunko, which has been designated as a branch of the NDL and placed under the organization of the National Library, deposited by the Toyo Bunko, a library and research institute dedicated to Asian studies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="60">
<j>行政および司法の各部門、すなわち日本の行政機関および最高裁判所に置かれる図書館については行政・司法に対するサービスで改めて詳しくあつかうが、各省庁や裁判所に置かれる付属図書館を制度上国立国会図書館の支部とすることで、日本唯一の国立中央図書館である国立国会図書館と各図書館を一体のネットワークに置いたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The libraries in the executive and judicial agencies, or the executive branches of the Japanese government and the Supreme Court of Japan will be explained in detail in the section on the Services to the Executive and Judicial Agencies of the Government. By designating libraries affiliated to the executive agencies and courts as branches of the NDL in a system, the NDL, the only national main library in Japan, and other libraries mentioned above have been integrated within a single network.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。http://www.courts.go.jp/english/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The libraries in the executive and judicial agencies, or the executive branches of the Japanese Government and the Supreme Court of Japan, will be explained in detail in the section covering the services to the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government; moreover, by designating libraries affiliated to the executive agencies and courts as branches of the NDL in a system, the NDL, as the only national main library in Japan, and other libraries mentioned above have been integrated within a single network.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The libraries in the executive and judicial agencies, or the executive branches of the Japanese Government and the Supreme Court of Japan, will be explained in detail in the section covering the services to the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government; moreover, by designating libraries affiliated to the executive agencies and courts as branches of the NDL in a system, the NDL, as the only national main library in Japan, and other libraries mentioned above have been integrated within a single network.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>これらの図書館は、設置主体は各省庁や裁判所であるが、同時に国立国会図書館の支部図書館として、中央の図書館とともに国立国会図書館の組織の一部とされる特別な位置付けにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though established by the executive agencies or courts, these libraries are in a special position as Branch Libraries of the NDL, comprising a part of the NDL organization along with the Main Libraries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though established by the executive agencies or courts, these libraries are in a special position as branch libraries of the NDL, comprising a part of the NDL organization along with the main libraries.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though established by the executive agencies or courts, these libraries are in a special position as branch libraries of the NDL, comprising a part of the NDL organization along with the main libraries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="62">
<j>東京と関西の2つの施設に分かれた中央の図書館はおよそ900人の職員を擁しており、業務ごとに部局に細分化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Main Libraries, consisting of two separate facilities in Tokyo and Kansai, have some 900 staff and are subdivided into departments. The only special department established pursuant to the National Diet Library Act is the &quot;Research and Legislative Reference Bureau.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。http://opac.ndl.go.jp/recordid/000009378564/jpn</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Main Libraries, consisting of two separate facilities in Tokyo and Kansai, have some 900 staff and are subdivided into departments. The only special department established pursuant to the National Diet Library Act is the &quot;Research and Legislative Reference Bureau.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main libraries, consisting of two separate facilities in Tokyo and Kansai, have some 900 staff and are subdivided into departments.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル94 の原文をセル95に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>そのうち唯一国立国会図書館法を設置の根拠とする特別な部局として「調査及び立法考査局」がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only special department established pursuant to the National Diet Library Act is the &apos;Research and Legislative Reference Bureau.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル94 の原文をセル95に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>調査及び立法考査局は国会に対する図書館奉仕に加えて、国会からの要望に応じた調査業務を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the library services for the Diet, the Research and Legislative Reference Bureau provide research services based on the request from the Diet. Such researches are conducted mainly by senior specialists with a special position for conducting highly advanced researches in the fields of interest of the Standing Committees of both houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the library services for the Diet, the Research and Legislative Reference Bureau provide research services based on the request from the Diet. Such researches are conducted mainly by senior specialists with a special position for conducting highly advanced research in the fields of interest of the standing committees of both houses.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the library services for the Diet, the Research and Legislative Reference Bureau provide research services as requested by the Diet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル96 の原文をセル97に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>これらの調査は、衆参両院の常任委員会が必要とする分野に関する高度な調査を行う特別職として置かれる専門調査員を中心に行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such research is conducted mainly by senior specialists with a special position for conducting highly advanced research in the fields of interest of the standing committees of both houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル96 の原文をセル97に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>サービス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>国立国会図書館のサービスは、以下の3本の柱から成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL&apos;s services are comprised of the following three main areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL&apos;s services are comprised of the following three main areas:</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL&apos;s services are comprised of the following three main areas:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>国会へのサービス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services for the Diet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services for the Diet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services for the Diet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>立法の際に必要となる資料の収集と分析、提供を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collects, analyzes and provides materials required in the preparation of legislation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collects, analyzes and provides materials required in the preparation of legislation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collects, analyzes and provides materials required in the preparation of legislation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="69">
<j>行政・司法へのサービス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services to the Executive and Judicial Agencies of the Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services to the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services to the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>各府省庁と最高裁判所に支部図書館を設置し、図書館サービスを行なう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishes Branch Libraries in the executive and judicial agencies of the government and the Supreme Court of Japan, and provides library services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishes branch libraries in the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government and the Supreme Court of Japan, and provides library services</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provides library services and establishes branch libraries in the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government and the Supreme Court of Japan.</e>
<cmt>I have reversed the order because otherwise the number of times that &quot;and&quot; appears makes the sentence a little difficult to follow,</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>国民一般へのサービス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services to the General Public</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services to the General Public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services to the General Public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>一般利用者が直接、または他の公共図書館などを通じて間接的に受けるサービス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services that the general public users receive directly or indirectly through other public libraries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services that users from the general public receive directly or indirectly through other public libraries</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services that users from the general public receive directly or indirectly through other public libraries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また、地方の議会や公務員へのサービスもここに含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services to prefectural and other local assemblies and government officials are included in this category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services to prefectural and other local assemblies, as well as government officials, are included in this category.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services to prefectural and other local assemblies, as well as government officials, are included in this category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="74">
<j>「国会図書館」という名称から明らかなように、国会へのサービスを第一義とするが、国民一般へのサービスも国立国会図書館の重要な要素である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the NDL&apos;s original mandate is the services for the Diet, as obvious from its name of &quot;Diet Library,&quot; services to the general public is also an important function of the NDL.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the NDL&apos;s original mandate was to serve the Diet, as obvious by its name &quot;Diet Library,&quot; services to the general public are also important functions of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the NDL&apos;s original mandate was to serve the Diet, as obvious by its name &quot;Diet Library,&quot; services to the general public are also important functions of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>国民へのサービスは日本の国立図書館としての機能であり、納本制度に基づく国内出版物の網羅的収集や全国書誌の作成が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services to the general public is a function as a Japanese National Library, and the NDL is engaged in acquiring comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan based on the Legal Deposit System, and creating a national bibliography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The service to the general public is to function as a Japanese National Library; thus the NDL is engaged in acquiring comprehensive collections of materials published in Japan based on the Legal Deposit System, and to create a national bibliography.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB; grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The service to the general public is to function as a Japanese National Library; thus the NDL is engaged in acquiring comprehensive collections of materials published in Japan based on the Legal Deposit System, and to create a national bibliography.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>また、図書館間協力や国際協力にも力を入れており、国際協力では資料の国際交換、資料の貸出・複写・レファレンス、日本語図書を扱う外国人司書の研修などを行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the NDL is focused on collaboration among libraries and international cooperation, and exchanges publications internationally, provides international loan, copying and reference services, as well as training for foreign librarians who deal with Japanese-language books as part of international cooperation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the NDL is focused on collaboration among libraries as well as international cooperation; it exchanges publications internationally, provides international lending, copying and reference services along with training for foreign librarians who deal with Japanese-language books as part of international cooperation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the NDL is focused on collaboration among libraries as well as international cooperation; it exchanges publications internationally, provides international lending, copying and reference services along with training for foreign librarians who deal with Japanese-language books as part of international cooperation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>一般利用者へのサービス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services for the General Public Users</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services for General Public Users</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services for General Public Users</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>一般利用者へのサービスは、来館利用、利用者の身近にある図書館などを通じた間接的な利用、そして後述するインターネットを通じた電子図書館サービスの提供などから成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services for the General Public Users consist of on-site use, indirect use through a user&apos;s nearby library, and a provision of digital library via the Internet which will be explained in detail below, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services for users from the general public consist, among others, of on-site use, indirect use through the user&apos;s nearby library, and a provision of digital library via the Internet, which will be explained in detail below.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services for users from the general public consist, among others, of on-site use, indirect use through the user&apos;s nearby library, and a provision of digital library via the Internet, which will be explained in detail below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>国立国会図書館の各サービスポイント、すなわち東京本館、関西館、国際子ども図書館などを利用者が直接訪れる来館利用では、利用に許可の必要な貴重書や特別の事情があって利用の制限されている資料を除き、国立国会図書館の所蔵する膨大な資料が利用者の求めに応じて提供される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In on-site user services, which is the services for the users who physically visit each of the NDL service points (i.e. the Tokyo Main Library, the Kansai-kan, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, etc)., an enormous amount of materials possessed by the NDL is made available based on users&apos; request, except for rare books which require special approval for viewing and materials whose usage is limited for special reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In on-site user services, meaning the services for users who physically visit each of the NDL service points (i.e. the Tokyo Main Library, the Kansai-kan, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, etc.), enormous amounts of materials possessed by the NDL are made available based on user request, except for rare books that require special approval for viewing and materials whose usage is limited for special reasons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In on-site user services, meaning the services for users who physically visit each of the NDL service points (i.e. the Tokyo Main Library, the Kansai-kan, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, etc.), enormous amounts of materials possessed by the NDL are made available based on user request, except for rare books that require special approval for viewing and materials whose usage is limited for special reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>国立国会図書館の所蔵する資料は現在では3館に分散しているが、それぞれに取り寄せて来館利用することが可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the holdings of the NDL are separately held in three libraries, it is possible for the users to order materials held in a particular library to be sent to another library where the users wish to read such materials (inter-site request).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the holdings of the NDL are held in three separate libraries, it is possible for a user to order materials held in a particular library to be sent to another library where the user wants to read such materials (inter-site request).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the holdings of the NDL are held in three separate libraries, it is possible for a user to order materials held in a particular library to be sent to another library where the user wants to read such materials (inter-site request).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="80">
<j>間接的な利用では、一般の図書館利用者が最寄の図書館では入手できなかった資料を網羅的なコレクションをもつ国会図書館から図書館間貸出で取り寄せたり、最寄の図書館では解決できなかったレファレンス（図書館員の行う参考調査）を国立国会図書館に依頼したりすることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using the indirect user services, a general public library user can order materials which were not available at the user&apos;s nearby library to be sent from the NDL with a comprehensive collection, or to request a reference service (reference research conducted by a librarian) of issues which could not solved at a nearby library to the NDL.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using the indirect user services, a general public library user can order materials that were not available at the user&apos;s nearby library to be sent from the NDL with a comprehensive collection, or to request a reference service (reference research conducted by a librarian), to the NDL, of issues that could not solved at a nearby library.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using the indirect user services, general public library users can order materials that are not available at their local library from the NDL&apos;s comprehensive collection of books or make use of the NDL&apos;s reference service (reference research conducted by a librarian) to resolve an issue that could not be resolved at their local library.</e>
<cmt>to sent from ---から以下を訳しなおしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="81">
<j>図書館間貸出は、利用者の身近にある公共図書館、大学図書館や各種の資料室（ただし国立国会図書館の図書館間貸出制度に加入申請し、承認を受けた機関のみ）を窓口として、国立国会図書館の資料を利用できる制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Interlibrary Loan is a system in which a user can use materials held in the NDL through the user&apos;s nearby public library, university library, or a reference room (institutions which applied for and have been approved as a registered user of the NDL&apos;s Interlibrary Loan Services only).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Interlibrary Loan is a system in which a user can use materials held in the NDL through the user&apos;s nearby public library, university library or a reference room (institutions that have applied for and have been approved as registered users of the NDL&apos;s Interlibrary Loan Services only).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Interlibrary Loan is a system in which a user can use materials held in the NDL through the user&apos;s nearby public library, university library or a reference room (institutions that have applied for and have been approved as registered users of the NDL&apos;s Interlibrary Loan Services only).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>ただし、あくまで図書館間貸し出しであるため借り出し先の図書館の館外に持ち出すことはできず、図書館資料を所蔵館外で複写することを禁じた著作権法の規定のため複写も認められない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this is an Interlibrary loan, however, the borrowed materials cannot be taken outside the library where the materials have been loaned, and cannot be copied or duplicated by any means in accordance with the Copyright Act which prohibits library materials from being copied or duplicated outside the library which holds such materials.</e>
<cmt>http://www.japaneselawtranslation.go.jp/law/detail_main/?id=56&amp;vm=4&amp;re=</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because this is an interlibrary loan the borrowed materials cannot be taken outside the library where the materials have been loaned, nor can the materials be copied or duplicated by any means in accordance with the Copyright Act, which prohibits library materials from being copied or duplicated outside the library that holds such materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because this is an interlibrary loan the borrowed materials cannot be taken outside the library where the materials have been loaned, nor can the materials be copied or duplicated by any means in accordance with the Copyright Act, which prohibits library materials from being copied or duplicated outside the library that holds such materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>国立国会図書館は資料の保存を大原則としているため、利用者の身近にある多くの図書館と違い、来館利用でも個人に対する貸出を行っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the NDL&apos;s main principle is to preserve materials, unlike many other libraries in users&apos; neighborhood, the materials held in the NDL are not to be lent out to any individuals even for on-site services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given that the NDL&apos;s main principle is to preserve materials, unlike many neighborhood libraries, the materials held in the NDL cannot be lent out to any individual, even for on-site services.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given that the NDL&apos;s main principle is to preserve materials, unlike many neighborhood libraries, the materials held in the NDL cannot be lent out to any individual, even for on-site services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>また、所蔵する資料が膨大であり、サービスの対象とする地域も日本全国から諸外国にまで及んでいるため、個人からの利用には数多くの制約がかけられていたり、不便に感じられる点も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, since the NDL holds an enormous amount of materials, and the scope of its services encompasses across the nation as well as foreign countries, there are many restrictions and inconvenient points for individual users.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, because the NDL holds an enormous amount of materials, and the scope of its services encompasses the nation as well as foreign countries, there are many restrictions and inconvenient points for individual users.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, because the NDL holds an enormous amount of materials, and the scope of its services encompasses the nation as well as foreign countries, there are many restrictions and inconvenient points for individual users.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>そのため、利用者は求める資料の入手をはかる場合、身近な公共図書館や大学図書館を利用した場合のほうが容易に資料に達することができることがしばしばであり、他の図書館で見当たらない資料のみに限って国立国会図書館を利用すべきとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, when a user is looking to obtain a specific material, there are many cases where it is easier to obtain such material from a nearby public library or a university library. Therefore, it is said that a user should use the NDL only for the material which cannot be found in other libraries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, when a user wants to obtain a specific material, there are many cases where it is easier to obtain such material from a nearby public library or a university library; therefore, it is said that a user should use the NDL only for the material that cannot be found in other libraries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, when a user wants to obtain a specific material, there are many cases where it is easier to obtain such material from a nearby public library or a university library; therefore, it is said that a user should use the NDL only for the material that cannot be found in other libraries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>このような国立国会図書館の性格を指して、「国会図書館は資料の最後のよりどころ」という言い方がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reference to such nature of the NDL, is often said that &quot;the NDL is the final resource for materials.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reference to such nature of the NDL, is often said that &quot;the NDL is the final resource for materials.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reference to such nature of the NDL, it is often said that &apos;the NDL is the final resource for materials.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>国会に対するサービス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services for the Diet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services for the Diet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services for the Diet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>国立国会図書館の国会に対するサービスは、資料の提供、貸し出しなどの一般的な図書館サービスに加えて、議会図書館に特有の立法調査を兼ね備えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL&apos;s Services for the Diet include legislative research specific to the parliamentary library, in addition to general library services such as provision of materials and loan services.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL&apos;s services for the Diet include legislative research specific to the parliamentary library, in addition to general library services such as the provision of materials and loan services.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL&apos;s services for the Diet include legislative research specific to the parliamentary library, in addition to general library services such as the provision of materials and loan services.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>東京本館と国会議事堂内の国会分館には国会議員専用の議員閲覧室があり、本館議員閲覧室には議員研究室も付設されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Reading Rooms dedicated for the Diet members are situated in the Tokyo Main Library and the Diet Branch Library inside the Diet Building. The Diet Members&apos; Study Room is attached to the Diet Members&apos; Reading Room in the Main Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reading rooms dedicated for the Diet members are situated in the Tokyo Main Library and the Diet Branch Library inside the Diet Building. The Diet Members&apos; Study Room is attached to the Diet Members&apos; Reading Room in the Main Library.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reading rooms dedicated for the Diet members are situated in the Tokyo Main Library and the Diet Branch Library inside the Diet Building, as well as the Diet Members&apos; Study Room, which is attached to the Diet Members&apos; Reading Room in the Main Library.</e>
<cmt>2文を1文に統合しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>議員閲覧室、議員研究室は政治家の政策勉強のほか、政治家同士の密談に使われているといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the Diet Member&apos;s Reading Room and Study Room are used by Diet members for their study of policies, as well as for confidential talks among politicians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the Diet Member&apos;s Reading Room and Study Room are used by Diet members for the study of policies, as well as for confidential talks among politicians.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the Diet Member&apos;s Reading Room and Study Room are used by Diet members for the study of policies, as well as for confidential talks among politicians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>また、国会議員と国会職員に対しては国会分館を中心に貸し出しサービスも行われており、図書館への貸し出しと異なって貸し出しの冊数制限も存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, loan services are available for Diet members and Diet staff primarily in the Diet Branch Library, and unlike loans to other libraries, there is no restrictions on the number of books to be loaned to Diet members and Diet staff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, loan services are available for Diet members and Diet staff primarily in the Diet Branch Library; but unlike loans to other libraries there is no restriction on the number of books to be loaned to Diet members and Diet staff.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, loan services are available for Diet members and Diet staff primarily in the Diet Branch Library; but unlike loans to other libraries there is no restriction on the number of books to be loaned to Diet members and Diet staff.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="91">
<j>国立国会図書館の組織において、国会に対するサービスの主体となるのは国立国会図書館法第15条によって規定された調査及び立法考査局（「調査局」と略称される）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main body which provides the Services for the Diet in the NDL organization is the Research and Legislative Reference Bureau (referred to as the &quot;Research Bureau&quot; in short) specified in Article 15 of the National Diet Library Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main body within the NDL organization that provides the services for the Diet is the Research and Legislative Reference Bureau (referred to as the &quot;Research Bureau&quot;), as specified in Article 15 of the National Diet Library Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main body within the NDL organization that provides the services for the Diet is the Research and Legislative Reference Bureau (referred to as the &quot;Research Bureau&quot;), as specified in Article 15 of the National Diet Library Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>調査局は、同法の規定に基づいて、国会のための調査や立法に関連する資料の収集・提供を行うこととされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Research Bureau shall conduct researches for the Diet and collect and provide materials related to legislation, pursuant to the same Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Research Bureau shall conduct research for the Diet and collect and provide materials related to legislation, pursuant to the same Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Research Bureau shall conduct research for the Diet and collect and provide materials related to legislation, pursuant to the same Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="93">
<j>このために調査局には国会のための調査を行う部門と立法関連の資料提供サービスを行う部門が置かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this purpose, in the Research Bureau, there are divisions which are assigned to research execution for the Diet and to provision of materials related to legislation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that purpose, in the Research Bureau there are divisions assigned to research execution for the Diet and the provision of materials related to legislation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that purpose, in the Research Bureau there are divisions assigned to research execution for the Diet and the provision of materials related to legislation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>調査部門の各課はおおむね国会両院の常任委員会の構成に対応する主題別に細分されており、国会議員の問い合わせに応じて調査を行う立法レファレンス業務や、時事的な問題についての予備調査を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Divisions of the Research Bureau are mostly divided into smaller groups by topics which correspond to the structure of the Standing Committees of both houses, and legislative reference activity based on requests from Diet members and anticipatory research on current issues are conducted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The divisions of the Research Bureau are mostly divided into smaller groups by topics that correspond to the structure of the standing committees of both houses, and legislative reference activity based on requests from Diet members and anticipatory research on current issues are conducted.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The divisions of the Research Bureau are mostly divided into smaller groups by topics that correspond to the structure of the standing committees of both houses, and legislative reference activity based on requests from Diet members and anticipatory research on current issues are conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="95">
<j>また、調査局は国立国会図書館の国民向けサービスのための資料収集・整理とは独立して資料の収集・整理も行っており、最新の情報を収集して立法業務の補佐に役立てている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, separately from the collection and classifications of materials by the NDL for the Services for the General Public, the Research Bureau gathers and classifies materials to utilize the latest information in assisting the legislative activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, separately from the collection and classifications of materials by the NDL for services for the general public, the Research Bureau gathers and classifies materials so that the latest information can be used to assist the legislative activities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, separately from the collection and classifications of materials by the NDL for services for the general public, the Research Bureau gathers and classifies materials so that the latest information can be used to assist the legislative activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>この他、調査局を通じて行われる国会向けのサービスには国立国会図書館の一般の所蔵資料のうちの議会・法令関係資料の管理・提供や法令の索引作成、国会会議録のデータベース化などがあり、これらは国立国会図書館の閲覧室、出版活動、インターネット送信などを通じて、一般の国民に対しても提供されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Services for the Diet conducted by the Research Bureau include the management and provision of parliamentary and regulatory related materials among general materials housed in the NDL, preparation of indexes of laws, regulations, and bills, and creation of database for Minutes of the Diet, etc. These services have been made available to the general public in the reading rooms of the NDL, through publications, and via the Internet, etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Services for the Diet conducted by the Research Bureau include the management and provision of parliamentary and regulatory related materials among the general materials housed in the NDL; the preparation of indexes of laws, regulations and bills; and the creation of database for the minutes of the Diet, etc.; these services have been made available to the general public in the reading rooms of the NDL, through publications, via the Internet, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Services for the Diet conducted by the Research Bureau include the management and provision of parliamentary and regulatory related materials among the general materials housed in the NDL; the preparation of indexes of laws, regulations and bills; and the creation of database for the minutes of the Diet, etc.; these services have been made available to the general public in the reading rooms of the NDL, through publications, via the Internet, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>行政・司法に対するサービス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Services to the Executive and Judicial Agencies of the Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Services to the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Services to the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>国立国会図書館のサービス対象のもうひとつの柱は国の行政・司法に対してである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another main service provided by the NDL is for the executive and judicial agencies of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another main service provided by the NDL is for the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another main service provided by the NDL is for the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>これらに対し国立国会図書館は図書館サービス資料の貸し出し、複写、レファレンスなどの図書館サービスを行っているが、その窓口となるのが国の行政・司法の各部門に設けられた支部図書館である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL provides them with loan, copying and reference services of library service materials, through Branch Libraries in the executive and judicial agencies.</e>
<cmt>「図書館サービス資料」は「図書館資料」のタイポの可能性があるかもしれませんが、ここでは原文に忠実に「library service materials」と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL provides them with lending, copying and reference services of library service materials, through branch libraries in the Executive and Judicial agencies.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL provides them with lending, copying and reference services of library service materials, through branch libraries in the Executive and Judicial agencies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>行政・司法各部門の附属図書館（支部内閣府図書館、支部最高裁判所図書館など）は、設置母体の省庁の刊行物を収めたり業務上必要な資料を収集し所蔵しており、それぞれの省庁の予算によって運営されるが、同時に制度上で国立国会図書館の支部図書館として国立国会図書館の組織に包括されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Affiliated Libraries of the executive and judicial agencies of the government (Cabinet Office Library, Branch of the NDL; Supreme Court Library, Branch of the NDL, etc). deposit materials published by the agencies they belong to, and collect and store necessary materials for their duties. Though these libraries are operated under the budget of each agency, they are included in the NDL organization as Branch Libraries of the NDL in the system.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/aboutus/admin_list_add.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The affiliated libraries of the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government (Cabinet Office Library, branch of the NDL; Supreme Court Library, branch of the NDL, etc). deposit materials published by the agencies to which they belong, and collect and store the materials necessary for their duties; though these libraries are operated under the budget of each agency, they are included in the NDL organization as branch libraries of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The affiliated libraries of the Executive and Judicial agencies of the government (Cabinet Office Library, branch of the NDL; Supreme Court Library, branch of the NDL, etc.) deposit materials published by the agencies to which they belong, and collect and store the materials necessary for their duties; although these libraries are operated under the budget of each agency, they are included in the NDL organization as branch libraries of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の中に移動&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>また、支部図書館同士は国立国会図書館の中央館を中心にネットワークを形成し、各省庁出版物の相互交換、資料の相互貸借、図書館職員の共通研修などを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Branch Libraries comprise a network centered around the Main Libraries of the NDL, and exchange materials published by agencies, loan the materials, and provide joint trainings for librarians with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, branch libraries comprise a network centered around the main libraries of the NDL; they exchange materials published by agencies, lend the materials and collectively provide joint training for librarians.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, branch libraries comprise a network centered around the main libraries of the NDL; they exchange materials published by agencies, lend the materials and collectively provide joint training for librarians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="101">
<j>行政・司法各部門支部図書館の館長はそれぞれの事務官・技官から任命されるが、その任命権は立法府の職員である国立国会図書館長に与えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chief Librarians of Branch Libraries of the executive and judicial agencies are appointed from among the administrative and technical officers, but the appointive poser is given to the Chief Librarian of the NDL who is a staff of the legislative branch of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief librarians of the branch libraries of the Executive and Judicial agencies are appointed from among the administrative and technical officers, but the position of appointment is given to the chief librarian of the NDL, who is a staff of the Legislative branch of the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief librarians of the branch libraries of the Executive and Judicial agencies are appointed from among the administrative and technical officers, but the position of appointment is given to the chief librarian of the NDL, who is a staff of the Legislative branch of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>このように三権をまたぐ支部図書館制度は世界の国立図書館の中でもきわめて珍しく、国立国会図書館のもつ大きな特色のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, the Branch Library System across the three powers is extremely rare among national libraries around the world, and is regarded as one of the most prominent characteristics of the NDL.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, the Branch Library System across the three powers is extremely rare among the national libraries of the world, and it is regarded as one of the most prominent characteristics of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, the Branch Library System across the three powers is extremely rare among the national libraries of the world, and it is regarded as one of the most prominent characteristics of the NDL.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>国立国会図書館の特色</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics of the NDL</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics of the NDL</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics of the NDL</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>資料の収集・整理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Acquisition and Classification of Materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acquisition and Classification of Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acquisition and Classification of Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>世界各国の国立中央図書館は、法律などによって定められた納本制度によって出版者に特定の図書館に出版物を納めることを義務付け、一国内の出版物を網羅的に収集することを重要な役割としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the primary functions of national libraries around the world is to mandate that all publications must deposited in designated libraries based on the Legal Deposit System as stipulated in a law, etc., and collect a comprehensive collection of materials published in their respective countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the primary functions of national libraries around the world is to mandate that all publications must be deposited in designated libraries based on the Legal Deposit System as stipulated in a law, etc., and to compile a comprehensive collection of materials published in their respective countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar, usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the primary functions of national libraries around the world is to mandate that all publications must be deposited in designated libraries based on the Legal Deposit System as stipulated in a law, etc., and to compile a comprehensive collection of materials published in their respective countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>日本の国立中央図書館である国立国会図書館においては、国立国会図書館法が、国内全ての官公庁、団体と個人に出版物を国立国会図書館に納本することを義務付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the NDL, the national main library of Japan, it is mandated that copies of all publications must be sent by all government and municipal agencies, groups, and individuals in Japan to the NDL in accordance with the National Diet Library Law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the NDL, Japan&apos;s national main library, it is mandated that copies of all publications must be sent by all government and municipal agencies, groups and individuals in Japan to the NDL, in accordance with the National Diet Library Law.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the NDL, Japan&apos;s national main library, it is mandated that copies of all publications must be sent by all government and municipal agencies, groups and individuals in Japan to the NDL, in accordance with the National Diet Library Law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>納本の対象となる出版物は、図書、小冊子、逐次刊行物（雑誌や新聞、年鑑）、楽譜、地図、マイクロフィルム資料、点字資料およびCD-ROM、DVDなどパッケージで頒布される電子出版物（音楽CDやゲームソフトも含む）などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The applicable publications include books, pamphlets, serials (magazines, newspapers, and periodicals), music scores, maps, microfilm materials, materials published in Braille, and electronic publications distributed in packages such as CD-ROM, DVD, etc. (including music CDs, and gaming software).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The applicable publications include books, pamphlets, serials (magazines, newspapers and periodicals), musical scores, maps, microfilm materials, materials published in Braille, and electronic publications distributed in formats such as CD-ROM, DVD, etc. (including music CDs and gaming software).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The applicable publications include books, pamphlets, serials (magazines, newspapers and periodicals), musical scores, maps, microfilm materials, materials published in Braille, and electronic publications distributed in formats such as CD-ROM, DVD, etc. (including music CDs and gaming software).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>納本を求められる部数は、官公庁では2部から30部までの複数部であり、民間の出版物は1部である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of copies required to be deposited is between two and 30 copies for publications of government and municipal agencies, and 1copy for private publications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of copies required to be deposited is between two and 30 copies for publications of government and municipal agencies, while one copy is required for private publications.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of copies required to be deposited is between two and 30 copies for publications of government and municipal agencies, while one copy is required for private publications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="107">
<j>納本以外の資料収集手段としては、寄贈、購入や、出版物の国際交換がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Means for acquisition of materials other than by deposit, are by gift, purchase, and international exchange of publications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The means for acquisition of materials other than by deposit are by gift, purchase and the international exchange of publications.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The means for acquisition of materials other than by deposit are by gift, purchase and the international exchange of publications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>購入を通じては、古書・古典籍など納本の対象とならないものや、百科事典、辞典、生活暦など参考図書としてきわめて利用の多い資料の複本、そして学術研究に有用であると判断され選択された外国資料が収集される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old books and rare books and old materials which do not fall into the category of deposit, duplicates of frequently used materials as reference books such as encyclopedias, dictionaries, almanacs, etc., and foreign materials which have been designated and selected as useful materials for academic studies, are acquired by purchase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old books, rare books, old materials that do not fall into the category of deposits, duplicates of frequently used materials as reference books such as encyclopedias, dictionaries, almanacs, etc., and foreign materials that have been designated as useful materials for academic studies are acquired by purchase.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old books, rare books, old materials that do not fall into the category of deposits, duplicates of frequently used materials as reference books such as encyclopedias, dictionaries, almanacs, etc., and foreign materials that have been designated as useful materials for academic studies are acquired by purchase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>国際交換は、他国の国立図書館・議会図書館に対し、納本制度によって複数部が受け入れられた官公庁出版物を主に提供することにより、交換で入手の難しい外国の官公庁資料等を収集するのに用いられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">International exchanges are used to acquire official materials of foreign government offices which are difficult to be obtained from national libraries and parliamentary libraries of other countries, as an exchange primarily for a copy of materials published by the government and municipal agencies of Japan whose copies have been acquired through the Legal Deposit System.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">International exchanges are used to acquire official materials of foreign government offices that are difficult to obtain from the national and parliamentary libraries of other countries, as an exchange primarily for copies of materials published by the government and municipal agencies of Japan, whose copies have been acquired through the Legal Deposit System.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">International exchanges are used to acquire official materials of foreign government offices that are difficult to obtain from the national and parliamentary libraries of other countries, as an exchange primarily for copies of materials published by the government and municipal agencies of Japan, whose copies have been acquired through the Legal Deposit System.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="110">
<j>こうして国立国会図書館に新たに収集された資料は、一件一件についてその書名、著者、出版者、出版年などの個体同定情報が記述された書誌データが作成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">bibliographic data which describes identification information for each material including the title, author, publisher, year of publication, etc. is created for each of new materials acquired by the NDL as described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bibliographic data that describes the identification information for each material (including the title, author, publisher, year of publication, etc.) is created for each of the new materials acquired by the NDL, as described above.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bibliographic data that describes the identification information for each material (including the title, author, publisher, year of publication, etc.) is created for each of the new materials acquired by the NDL, as described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>また国立国会図書館の書誌データには同館独自の国立国会図書館分類表 (NDLC) によって分類番号がつけられ、国立国会図書館件名標目表 (NDLSH) によって件名が付与されて、目録に登録される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the NDL&apos;s bibliographic data is registered in the catalogs after given a classification number by the National Diet Library Classification (NDLC), a unique classification for the NDL, as well as a headline by the National Diet Library Subject Headings (NDLSH).</e>
<cmt>http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~ax2s-kmtn/ref/classification.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the NDL&apos;s bibliographic data is registered in the catalogs after it is given a classification number by the National Diet Library Classification (NDLC), a unique classification for the NDL and a headline by the National Diet Library Subject Headings (NDLSH).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the NDL&apos;s bibliographic data is registered in the catalogues after it is given a classification number by the National Diet Library Classification (NDLC), a unique classification for the NDL and a headline by the National Diet Library Subject Headings (NDLSH).</e>
<cmt>catalogs→catalogues</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>現在では目録の大半は NDL-OPACとしてオンライン化されており、その蔵書のうちのかなり部分はインターネット上から検索することが可能になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of catalogs are now available on online via NDL-OPAC (National Diet Library Online Public Access Catalog), and most of the holdings can be searched for on the Internet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the catalogues are now available online via NDL-OPAC (National Diet Library Online Public Access Catalogue), and most of the holdings can be searched via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the catalogues are now available online via NDL-OPAC (National Diet Library Online Public Access Catalogue), and most of the holdings can be searched via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="113">
<j>なお、国立国会図書館の蔵書構築など図書館技術に関する運用は、1948年（昭和23年）にGHQ民間情報教育局特別顧問ダウンズによって提出された勧告（ダウンズ勧告）に基づく面が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The NDL&apos;s operation of library technologies such as establishment of its collection, etc. is largely based on the recommendations submitted by Robert Bringham Downs, a special advisor of the Civil Information and Education Section, GHQ/SCAP, in 1948 (the Downs Report).</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/data/kensei_shiryo/senryo/CIE.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL&apos;s operation of library technologies such as establishment of its collection, etc., is largely based on the recommendations submitted by Robert Bringham Downs, a special advisor of the Civil Information and Education Section, GHQ/SCAP, in 1948 (the Downs Report).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL&apos;s operation of library technologies such as establishment of its collection, etc., is largely based on the recommendations submitted by Robert Bringham Downs, a special advisor of the Civil Information and Education Section, GHQ/SCAP, in 1948 (the Downs Report).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>図書の整理は、開館当初はダウンズ勧告に基づいて、和漢書は日本国内の図書館で一般的な日本十進分類法 (NDC)、洋書は世界的に使われる国際十進分類法 (UDC) によって行れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early days after the opening, Japanese and Chinese book were classified by the Nippon Decimal Classification (NDC) and western books were classified by the Universal Decimal Classification (UDC), based on the recommendations of the Downs Report.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early days after the opening, Japanese and Chinese book were classified by the Nippon Decimal Classification (NDC) and Western books were classified by the Universal Decimal Classification (UDC), based on the recommendations of the Downs Report.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early days after the opening, Japanese and Chinese books were classified by the Nippon Decimal Classification (NDC) and Western books were classified by the Universal Decimal Classification (UDC), based on the recommendations of the Downs Report.</e>
<cmt>book→books</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>しかし、膨大な蔵書を書架に配架して利用していく上で十進分類法に不便がみられたため、1960年代に国立国会図書館分類表が考案され、適用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the NDC was not convenient for storing an enormous collection of book in the bookshelves, the NDLC was invented and in the 1960&apos;s and adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the NDC was not convenient for storing an enormous collection of books in the bookshelves, the NDLC was invented and adopted in the 1960s.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the NDC was not convenient for storing an enormous collection of books in the bookshelves, the NDLC was invented and adopted in the 1960s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>ただし、和図書についてはそれ以降も書誌データには日本十進分類表による分類番号は付与されており、日本十進分類法を日常に利用している他の図書館や一般利用者の便にも備えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after that, classification numbers based on the NDC have been included in the bibliographic data for Japanese books, for the convenience of other libraries which use the NDC regularly and general public users.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after that, classification numbers based on the NDC have been included in the bibliographic data for Japanese books, for the convenience of other libraries that use the NDC regularly, as well as for users from the general public.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after that, classification numbers based on the NDC have been included in the bibliographic data for Japanese books, for the convenience of other libraries that use the NDC regularly, as well as for users from the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>書誌データの提供</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provision of bibliographic data</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provision of bibliographic data</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provision of bibliographic data</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>納本制度により、国立国会図書館は原則としてすべての出版物が継続的に揃うことになるため、理論的には国会図書館の編成する自館所蔵資料の目録は、日本で出版された全ての出版物の書誌情報を収めた目録となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a rule, all publications continued to be acquired by the NDL based on the Legal Deposit System, theoretically speaking, the catalog of materials housed in its libraries which is composed by the NDL, is a catalog which include bibliographic information of all materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a rule, the acquisition of all publications continued by the NDL based on the Legal Deposit System, which, theoretically speaking, is the catalogue of materials housed in its libraries that comprise the NDL, such catalogue including the bibliographic information of all materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a rule, the acquisition of all publications continued by the NDL based on the Legal Deposit System, which, theoretically speaking, is the catalogue of materials housed in its libraries that comprise the NDL, such catalogue including the bibliographic information of all materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>こうして作成された目録に収められる、全国の出版物に関する網羅的な書誌情報を全国書誌という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comprehensive bibliographic information on all publications in Japan to be included in the catalog created as mentioned above is called a national bibliography. In the NDL, bibliographic information of materials which arrive based on the Legal Deposit System is summarized in the &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; once a week.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/publication/jnbwl/jnb_top.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comprehensive bibliographic information on all publications in Japan to be included in the catalogue created mentioned above is called a national bibliography. In the NDL, the bibliographic information of materials that arrive based on the Legal Deposit System is summarized in the &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comprehensive bibliographic information on all publications in Japan, for inclusion in the above-mentioned catalogue, is called a national bibliography.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル187 の原文をセル188に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>国立国会図書館においては毎週一度、その週に納本制度によって受け入れられた資料の書誌情報が『日本全国書誌』としてまとめられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the NDL, the bibliographic information of materials that arrive based on the Legal Deposit System is summarized once a week in the &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル187 の原文をセル188に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。毎週一度の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="120">
<j>『日本全国書誌』はインターネット上で公開されるほか、冊子体で刊行・頒布される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; is published on the Internet, as well as issued and distributed as a booklet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; is published on the Internet and is issued and distributed as a booklet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; is published on the Internet and is issued and distributed as a booklet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>また、電子情報・データベース化したものが『JAPAN/MARC』として頒布され、CD-ROM版やDVD-ROM版でも販売されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its contents are processed into a database for circulation as &quot;JAPAN/MARC (Machine Readable Cataloging)&quot; and recorded on CD-ROM and DVD-ROM discs for sale.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。http://www.ndl.go.jp/jp/data/opac_syoshiqa_teikyo.html#a3</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its contents are processed into a database for circulation as &quot;JAPAN/MARC (Machine Readable Cataloguing)&quot;and recorded on CD-ROM and DVD-ROM discs for sale.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its contents are processed into a database for circulation as &quot;JAPAN/MARC (Machine Readable Cataloguing)&quot; and recorded on CD-ROM and DVD-ROM discs for sale.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>その基本的な機能は、日本において出版された出版物を検索調査する際の総合的・統一的な索引である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its basic function is comprehensive and uniformed indexing when searching materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its basic function is to ensure comprehensive, uniform indexing when searching materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its basic function is to ensure comprehensive, uniform indexing when searching materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="123">
<j>また、各図書館は、自館で所蔵する資料の目録を作成するにあたって、自館で書誌データを作成せずとも、『日本全国書誌』を利用してコピーカタロギング（書誌情報を複製して自館の目録を作成すること）することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, when compiling a catalog of materials they own, other libraries can copy-catalog (create a catalog of a library by copying bibliographic information) using the &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; without creating a bibliographic data by themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, when compiling a catalogue of materials they own, other libraries can copy-catalogue (create a catalogue of a library by copying bibliographic information) using the &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; without having to create their own bibliographic data.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, when compiling a catalogue of materials they own, other libraries can copy-catalogue (create a catalogue of a library by copying bibliographic information) using the &quot;Japanese National Bibliography Weekly List&quot; without having to create their own bibliographic data.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>これには各図書館の目録作成の労力の軽減、および国内各図書館の間での書誌データの共有というメリットがあるが、国立国会図書館の目録の作成には刊行からタイムラグがあり、新刊の検索に向かないことが欠点として指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though this has merits such reduced efforts for other libraries for creating catalogs and sharing of bibliographic data among libraries, there is a time lag in the NDL&apos;s creating a catalog from the publication, which has been pointed out as a fault that it is not suitable for searching newly published materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though this has merits such as reduced effort for other libraries in creating catalogues and sharing bibliographic data among libraries, there is a time lag in the NDL&apos;s creation of a catalogue from the publication, which has been pointed out as a fault that makes the system unsuitable for searching newly published materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though this has merits such as reduced effort for other libraries in creating catalogues and sharing bibliographic data among libraries, there is a time lag in the NDL&apos;s creation of a catalogue from the publication, which has been pointed out as a fault that makes the system unsuitable for searching newly published materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>これは、他の図書館が新規に受け入れて目録化する資料の多くは新刊書であるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an issue since most of materials that other libraries acquire and make catalogs of are newly published books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is an issue, since most of the materials that other libraries acquire and make catalogues of are newly published books.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an issue because most of the materials that other libraries acquire and make catalogues of are newly published books.</e>
<cmt>This is an issue, が後部とつながらないため、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>このため、公共図書館の多くは『JAPAN/MARC』よりも民間の取次会社の作成する書誌データベースを目録作成に用いることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, most public libraries use bibliographic database created by private distributors rather than &quot;JAPAN/MARC&quot; when creating their catalogs. Therefore &quot;JAPAN/MARC&quot; has not been used as a national bibliography for copy-cataloging purposes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason most public libraries use bibliographic database created by private distributors rather than &quot;JAPAN/MARC&quot; when creating their catalogues. Therefore, &quot;JAPAN/MARC&quot; has not been used as a national bibliography for copy-cataloguing purposes.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason most public libraries use bibliographic database created by private distributors rather than &quot;JAPAN/MARC&quot; when creating their catalogues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル197の原文をセル198に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>そのため、コピーカタロギングのための全国書誌としての役割はあまり活用されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, &quot;JAPAN/MARC&quot; has not been used as a national bibliography for copy-cataloguing purposes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル197の原文をセル198に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="128">
<j>また、国立国会図書館は全国書誌の作成とともに開館以来『雑誌記事索引』を作成、頒布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the NDL compiles the &quot;Japanese Periodicals Index&quot; for circulation as well as the national bibliographies since its opening.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The NDL has, since its opening, also compiled the &quot;Japanese Periodicals Index&quot; for circulation as well as the national bibliographies.</e>
<cmt>syntax</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL has, since its opening, also compiled the &quot;Japanese Periodicals Index&quot; for circulation as well as the national bibliographies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>これは国内の主要な雑誌の収録記事を目録化したもので、索引の範囲は主に学術誌など調査上の利用に対する要求が大きい雑誌に限定されているものの、通常の目録では検索されにくい雑誌記事の目録として貴重なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a catalog of articles of major Japanese periodicals, and is valued as a catalog for periodicals which cannot be easily searched using other regular catalogs, even though its scope of indexing is primarily limited to the periodicals with high demand for searching such as academic periodicals, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a catalogue of articles of major Japanese periodicals, and is valued as a catalogue for periodicals that cannot be easily searched using other regular catalogues, even though its scope of indexing is primarily limited to periodicals with high demand for searching, such as academic periodicals, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a catalogue of articles of major Japanese periodicals, and is valued as a catalogue for periodicals that cannot be easily searched using other regular catalogues, even though its scope of indexing is primarily limited to periodicals with high demand for searching, such as academic periodicals, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>蔵書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>国立国会図書館の所蔵する資料の基礎となる部分は、戦前の帝国議会両院付属図書館が議会の審議をたすけるために収集した資料と、当時の日本唯一の国立図書館であった帝国図書館の蔵書の二つから成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basis of materials housed in the NDL comprise the materials that affiliated libraries in both houses of the pre-war Imperial Diet collected to assist deliberations in the Diet, and materials housed in the Imperial Library, the only national library in Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basis of materials housed in the NDL constitutes the materials that affiliated libraries in both houses of the pre-war Imperial Diet collected to assist deliberations in the Diet, as well as the materials housed in the Imperial Library, which was at that time the only national library in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis of materials housed in the NDL constitutes the materials that affiliated libraries in both houses of the pre-war Imperial Diet collected to assist deliberations in the Diet, as well as the materials housed in the Imperial Library, which was at that time the only national library in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>特に帝国図書館の蔵書は出版法の納本制度に基づいて網羅的に収集された戦前の和図書や、貴重な古書、洋書などを含み、きわめて価値が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, the materials housed in the Imperial Library such has a collection of great value, including pre-war Japanese books, rare old books, and Western books, which were acquired comprehensively based on the Legal Deposit System under the Publishing Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, the materials housed in the Imperial Library comprise a collection of great value, including pre-war Japanese books, rare old books and Western books, which were acquired comprehensively based on the Legal Deposit System under the Publishing Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, the materials housed in the Imperial Library comprise a collection of great value, including pre-war Japanese books, rare old books and Western books, which were acquired comprehensively based on the Legal Deposit System under the Publishing Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="132">
<j>国立国会図書館の成立以降は一国の網羅的な収集と全国書誌の作成を目的とした本格的な納本制度が導入されたので、この図書館には原則として日本で出版されたすべての出版物が所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a full-fledged Legal Deposit System was introduced with a purpose of acquiring a comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan and compiling national bibliographies after the establishment of the NDL, as a rule, all materials published in Japan have been stored in the NDL.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a full-fledged Legal Deposit System was introduced for the purpose of acquiring a comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan and compiling national bibliographies after the establishment of the NDL, as a rule all materials published in Japan have been stored within the NDL.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a full-fledged Legal Deposit System was introduced for the purpose of acquiring a comprehensive collection of materials published in Japan and compiling national bibliographies after the establishment of the NDL, as a rule all materials published in Japan have been stored within the NDL.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>外国資料については、国際交換や購入により、学術研究や参考調査に有用な人文・社会科学資料や、科学技術資料、日本関係資料などを中心に収集している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for foreign materials, the NDL collects primarily materials on humanities and social science, materials on science and technology, and materials on Japan, which are useful for academic study and reference researches through international exchanges and purchases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding foreign materials, the NDL collects primarily materials on humanities and social science, materials on science and technology, and materials on Japan, which are useful for academic study and reference research through international exchanges and purchases.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding foreign materials, the NDL collects primarily materials on humanities and social science, materials on science and technology, and materials on Japan, which are useful for academic study and reference research through international exchanges and purchases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="134">
<j>国会図書館の蔵書の中には、旧帝国図書館時代を含め図書館がまとまって受け入れた特色あるコレクションが含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stock of the NDL include unique and substantial collections that the library acquired including the days of the former Imperial Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stock of the NDL includes the unique and substantial collections that the library has acquired, including those from the days of the former Imperial Library.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stock of the NDL includes the unique and substantial collections that the library has acquired, including those from the days of the former Imperial Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>これらの特殊コレクションは、資料的に価値の高いものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of these rare collections have great values as materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of these rare collections have great value as materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of these unique collections have great value as materials.</e>
<cmt>「特殊な」はrareでは不適切なため、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>代表的なコレクションとして、帝国図書館から引き継いだ旧藩校蔵書、江戸幕府引継書類、本草学関連の古書からなる伊藤文庫・白井文庫や、戦後の国会図書館が議会のための図書館であるという性格から重点的に受け入れた近代政治史関連史資料からなる憲政資料、国内外の議会・法令関係資料、支部上野図書館で旧蔵していたバレエ・シャンソン関連資料の蘆原英了コレクション、出版文化史資料を中心とする布川文庫（布川角左衛門旧蔵書）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major collections include the following: stock of the old han schools (schools of the feudal domains) and the Tokugawa Shogunate Succession Documents that were inherited from the former Imperial Library; the Ito Bunko (Ito collection) and the Shirai Bunko (Shirai collection) consisting of old books on herbalism; the Modern Political and Constitutional History, comprising of materials on the modern political history which were collected as a high priority considering the nature of a post-war national library as a library for the Diet; collection of official gazettes and statutes of Japan and foreign countries; the Ashihara Eiryo Collection, a collection of materials related to ballet and chanson inherited from the Ueno Branch Library; the Nunokawa Bunko (Nunokawa collection) (the collection formerly possessed by Kakuzaemon NUNOKAWA) which concentrated on materials related to the history of publications and culture.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://www.ndl.go.jp/en/aboutus/outline_7.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major collections include the following: stock of the old Han schools (schools of the feudal domains) and the Tokugawa Shogunate Succession Documents that were inherited from the former Imperial Library; the Ito Bunko (Ito collection) and the Shirai Bunko (Shirai collection), consisting of old books on herbalism; the Modern Political and Constitutional History, comprising materials on the modern political history, which were collected as a high priority considering the nature of a post-war national library as a facility for the Diet; the collection of official gazettes and statutes of Japan and foreign countries; the Ashihara Eiryo Collection, a collection of materials related to ballet and chanson inherited from the Ueno Branch Library; and the Nunokawa Bunko (Nunokawa collection) (the collection formerly possessed by Kakuzaemon NUNOKAWA), which concentrated on materials related to the history of publications and culture.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major collections include the following: stock of the old Han schools (schools of the feudal domains) and the Tokugawa Shogunate Succession Documents that were inherited from the former Imperial Library; the Ito Bunko (Ito collection) and the Shirai Bunko (Shirai collection), consisting of old books on herbalism; the Modern Political and Constitutional History, comprising materials on the modern political history, which were collected as a high priority considering the nature of a post-war national library as a facility for the Diet; the collection of official gazettes and statutes of Japan and foreign countries; the Ashihara Eiryo Collection, a collection of materials related to ballet and chanson inherited from the Ueno Branch Library; and the Nunokawa Bunko (Nunokawa collection) (the collection formerly possessed by Kakuzaemon NUNOKAWA), which concentrated on materials related to the history of publications and culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>また、戦前に発禁処分を受けた書籍・雑誌もコレクションに含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection also include banned books and magazines in prewar days. The banned books previously housed in the Imperial Library are made available as part of general materials, and the banned books previously held by the former Ministry of Home Affairs are categorized as valuable books and made available for reading with a certain level of restrictions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection also includes books and magazines that had been banned in prewar days. The banned books previously housed in the Imperial Library are made available as part of the general materials, and the banned books previously held by the former Ministry of Home Affairs are categorized as valuable books and made available for reading with a certain level of restriction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection also includes books and magazines that had been banned in prewar days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル214の原文をセル215に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>旧帝国図書館所蔵の発禁図書は一般資料の一部として、旧内務省保管の発禁図書は貴重書扱いのため一定の制限下で閲覧に供されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The banned books previously housed in the Imperial Library are made available as part of the general materials, and the banned books previously held by the former Ministry of Home Affairs are categorized as valuable books and made available for reading with a certain level of restriction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル214の原文をセル215に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="139">
<j>2004年度（平成16年度）末の統計によれば、国立国会図書館の所蔵資料は図書8,369,233冊、雑誌176,961タイトル、新聞10,351タイトルで、ほかにマイクロフィルムや地図、電子資料といった図書形態以外の資料を1,200万点以上所蔵している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the statistics as of the end of fiscal year 2004, the NDL possesses 8,369,233 volumes of books, 176,961 titles of magazines, 10,351 titles of newspapers, as well as more than 12 million items of materials in a format other than a book such as microfilms, maps, digital materials, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the statistics as of the end of fiscal year 2004, the NDL possesses 8,369,233 volumes of books, 176,961 titles of magazines, 10,351 titles of newspapers, as well as more than 12 million items of materials in various non-book formats, such as microfilm, maps, digital materials, etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the statistics as of the end of fiscal year 2004, the NDL possesses 8,369,233 volumes of books, 176,961 titles of magazines, 10,351 titles of newspapers, as well as more than 12 million items of materials in various non-book formats, such as microfilm, maps, digital materials, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>電子図書館事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Digital Library Projects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Digital Library Projects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Digital Library Projects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>1990年代以降には、情報通信の発展に対応し、国立国会図書館は主にインターネット上のウェブサイトを通じた電子図書館機能拡充を模索し始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1990&apos;s, the NDL started to expand its digital library functions primarily via websites on the Internet, responding to development of telecommunications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the 1990s the NDL started to expand its digital library functions, primarily via websites on the Internet, in response to developments in telecommunications.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the 1990s the NDL started to expand its digital library functions, primarily via websites on the Internet, in response to developments in telecommunications.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="141">
<j>2002年（平成14年）には関西館の開館に伴ってウェブサイトが大幅に刷新された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2002, the website was renewed substantially to coincide with the opening of the Kansai-kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2002 the website was substantially renewed to coincide with the opening of the Kansai-kan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2002 the website was substantially renewed to coincide with the opening of the Kansai-kan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>国立国会図書館蔵書検索・申込システム「NDL-OPAC」は機能を大幅に拡充され、国会図書館の所蔵する資料のほとんどがインターネットを通じて世界のどこからでも検索することが可能になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Functions of the &quot;NDL-OPAC&quot; (National Diet Library Online Public Access Catalog), a search and request system for the materials housed in the NDL, were expanded significantly, and it became possible to search most of materials in the possession of the NDL from anywhere in the world via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>http://opac.ndl.go.jp/index_e.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Functions of the &quot;NDL-OPAC&quot; (National Diet Library Online Public Access Catalogue), a search-and-request system for the materials housed in the NDL, were expanded significantly, and it became possible to search most of materials in the possession of the NDL from anywhere in the world via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Functions of the &apos;NDL-OPAC&apos; (National Diet Library Online Public Access Catalogue), a search-and-request system for the materials housed in the NDL, were expanded significantly, and it became possible to search most of materials in the possession of the NDL from any location worldwide via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>国立国会図書館の所蔵する国内出版物は納本制度を通じて収集された日本国内の出版物の網羅的コレクション、その目録は週刊でまとめられてきた全国書誌の集積である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese publications housed in the NDL is a comprehensive collection of all the materials published in Japan which are acquired through the Legal Deposit System, and its catalogs are an accumulation of national bibliographies which have been compiled on a weekly basis. Therefore, the provision of bibliographic data through the NDL-OPAC is a service not only to deliver the information of the stock of the NDL only but also to provide the general public with a broad and comprehensive bibliographical data on every conceivable kind of materials published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese publications housed in the NDL make up a comprehensive collection of all the materials published in Japan, which are acquired through the Legal Deposit System, and its catalogues are an accumulation of national bibliographies that have been compiled on a weekly basis. Therefore, the provision of bibliographic data through the NDL-OPAC is a service not only to deliver the information of the stock of the NDL but also to provide the general public with broad-based, comprehensive bibliographical data on every conceivable kind of material published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese publications housed in the NDL make up a comprehensive collection of all the materials published in Japan, which are acquired through the Legal Deposit System, and its catalogues are an accumulation of the national bibliographies that have been compiled on a weekly basis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル225の原文をセル226に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>そのため、NDL-OPACを通じた書誌データの提供は、単に国会図書館一館の資料所蔵情報の公開にとどまらず、日本におけるありとあらゆる出版物の書誌データを網羅的に広く国民に提供するサービスでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the provision of bibliographic data through the NDL-OPAC is a service intended not only to deliver the information of the stock of the NDL but also to provide the general public with broad-based, comprehensive bibliographical data on every conceivable kind of material published in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル225の原文をセル226に分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="145">
<j>また、同じく雑誌記事索引もNDL-OPACを通じてインターネット検索が可能とされ、現在では国立国会図書館開館以来50年以上にわたって蓄積された雑誌記事索引のデータベースが公開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Periodicals Index became also available for searching on the Internet via the NDL-OPAC, and a database of Japanese Periodicals Index which has been accumulated for more than 50 years since the opening of the NDL is now available for a public use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Periodicals Index also became available for searching on the Internet via the NDL-OPAC, and a database of the Index, which has been accumulated for more than 50 years since the opening of the NDL, is now available for a public use.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Periodicals Index also became available for searching on the Internet via the NDL-OPAC, and a database of the Index, which has been accumulated for more than 50 years since the opening of the NDL, is now available for a public use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="146">
<j>このほか、国立国会図書館が所蔵する資料のうち歴史的な貴重書や浮世絵の画像を公開する「貴重書画像データベース」、国立国会図書館の所蔵する明治期に出版された資料をスキャニングした画像を提供する「近代デジタルライブラリー」、インターネット上の情報を文化資産として保存することを目的とする「WARP（インターネット情報選択的蓄積事業）」（旧称 インターネット資源選択的蓄積実験事業）など、様々な電子図書館コンテンツが公開されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the above, various digital library contents have been made available to the public including the &quot;Rare Books Image Database&quot; which reveals rare historical book and image data of Ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) among materials housed in the NDL, the &quot;Digital Library from the Meiji Era&quot; which provides scanned image data of the NDL&apos;s materials published during the Meiji period, and &quot;WARP&quot; (Web Archiving Project) (Project of selective accumulation of Internet based information; formerly the Experimental project of selective accumulation of Internet based information), etc.</e>
<cmt>英辞郎 on the WEB、プログレッシブ和英中辞典http://kindai.ndl.go.jp/information/aboutKDL.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the above, various kinds of digital library content have been made available to the public, including the &quot;Rare Books Image Database,&quot; which reveals rare historical book and image data of Ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) among the materials housed in the NDL; the &quot;Digital Library from the Meiji Era,&quot; which provides scanned image data of the NDL&apos;s materials published during the Meiji period; and &quot;WARP&quot; (Web Archiving Project) (project of selective accumulation of Internet-based information; formerly an experimental project of selective accumulation of Internet-based information), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the above, various kinds of digital library content have been made available to the public, including the &apos;Rare Books Image Database,&apos; which reveals rare historical book and image data of Ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints) among the materials housed in the NDL; the &apos;Digital Library from the Meiji Era,&apos; which provides scanned image data of the NDL&apos;s materials published during the Meiji period; and &apos;WARP&apos; (Web Archiving Project) (project of selective accumulation of Internet-based information; formerly an experimental project of selective accumulation of Internet-based information), etc.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="147">
<j>近代デジタルライブラリーは、公開範囲は著作権の保護期間が満了していることが確認される資料や著作権者の許諾が得られた資料に限られるものの、インターネットを通じて明治・大正時代の出版物をいつでもどこからでも見ることができ、その文化的、歴史的な資料価値は極めて高いとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Digital Library from the Meiji Era&quot; makes it possible for anyone, at any time or place, to access digitized contents of materials published during the Meiji/Taisho period and its cultural and historical value as materials is deems extremely high, though its scope is limited to the materials whose copyright protection period can be confirmed to have been expired, or the materials with approval of a copyright holder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Digital Library from the Meiji Era&quot; makes it possible for anyone, at any time or place, to access the digitized contents of materials published during the Meiji/Taisho period; thus its cultural and historical value as materials is deems extremely high, though its scope is limited to the materials for which the copyright protection period can be confirmed as expired, or materials with the approval of a copyright holder.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Digital Library from the Meiji Era makes it possible for anyone, at any time or place, to access the digitized contents of materials published during the Meiji/Taisho period; thus its cultural and historical value as materials is deemed extremely high, although its scope is limited to the materials for which the copyright protection period can be confirmed as having expired, or materials with the approval of a copyright holder.</e>
<cmt>&quot;取るdeems→deemed&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="148">
<j>WARP は、インターネットを通じて公開されていた学術雑誌や、政府省庁などのウェブページそのものを、管理者の許諾を得た上で国立国会図書館のサーバに保存し、インターネットを通じて一般に公開するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through WARP, academic periodicals published on the Internet and actual websites of the government agencies, etc. are archived in the NDL&apos;s server and made available to the public over the Internet, upon obtaining approval of respective administrators of such contents. It is an experimental project that a library, in the same manner as paper-medium materials, collects, classifies, preserves, and makes available to the public the digital information on the Internet (networked digital information) whose contents can be alternated by its administrators anytime and anyways, unlike the packaged digital information such as CD-ROM discs whose contents cannot be altered.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through WARP, academic periodicals published on the Internet and the actual websites of government agencies, etc., are archived in the NDL&apos;s server and made available to the public over the Internet, upon obtaining the approval of the respective administrators of such contents. It is an experimental project that a library, in the same manner as paper-medium materials, collects, classifies, preserves and makes available to the public the digital information on the Internet (networked digital information) whose contents can be alternated by its administrators anytime and in any manner, unlike packaged digital information such as CD-ROM discs, the contents of which cannot be altered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through WARP, academic periodicals published on the Internet and the actual websites of government agencies, etc., are archived in the NDL&apos;s server and made available to the public over the Internet, upon obtaining the approval of the respective administrators of such contents.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル234の原文をセル235ﾆに分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>CD-ROMのように変更されないようパッケージ化された電子情報と違い、管理者によっていつでも自由に改変することの可能なインターネット上の電子情報（ネットワーク系電子情報）を図書館が紙媒体の資料と同じように収集、整理、保存、公開する実験的な試みである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an experimental project that a library, in the same manner as paper-medium materials, collects, classifies, preserves and makes available to the public the digital information on the Internet (networked digital information) whose contents can be alternated by its administrators anytime and in any manner, unlike packaged digital information such as CD-ROM discs, the contents of which cannot be altered.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル234の原文をセル235ﾆに分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="150">
<j>今後の動きとしては、一国の情報資源の網羅的収集を役割とする国立図書館として、国立国会図書館がインターネット上で流通するネットワーク系電子情報をも網羅的に収集して保存することが検討されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a future project, it has been considered that the NDL, as a national library with a mission of acquiring a comprehensive collection of the nation&apos;s information resources, will also collect and preserve networked digital information circulated through the Internet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a future project, it has been considered that the NDL, as a national library with the mission of acquiring a comprehensive collection of the nation&apos;s information resources, will also collect and preserve networked digital information circulated via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a future project, it has been considered that the NDL, as a national library with the mission of acquiring a comprehensive collection of the nation&apos;s information resources, will also collect and preserve networked digital information circulated via the Internet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>国立国会図書館の納本制度の運用について調査と審議を行う諮問機関である納本制度審議会は、2004年（平成16年）に行ったネットワーク系電子出版物の収集に関する答申において、インターネット情報の収集と保存、提供を制度化するよう勧告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Legal Deposit System Council, an advisory council to conduct researches and deliberations on the operation of the Legal Deposit System, proposed that a system to acquire, preserve, and provide the information on the Internet should be established in its report on &quot;Concept of the Acquisition System for the Networked Electronic Publications&quot; submitted in 2004.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/publication/ndl_newsletter/143/436.html、www.ndl.go.jp/jp/information/data/nakai_jpn.ppt</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Legal Deposit System Council, an advisory council to conduct research and deliberations on the operation of the Legal Deposit System, proposed that a system intended to acquire, preserve and provide the information on the Internet should be established in its report on &quot;Concept of the Acquisition System for the Networked Electronic Publications,&quot; as submitted in 2004.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Legal Deposit System Council, an advisory council to conduct research and deliberations on the operation of the Legal Deposit System, proposed that a system intended to acquire, preserve and provide the information on the Internet should be established in its report on &quot;Concept of the Acquisition System for the Networked Electronic Publications,&quot; as submitted in 2004.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>国立国会図書館はこれにもとづき、日本国内で発信されたウェブページを年に一度程度の頻度で自動的・非選択的に収集し、一定の制限のもとで保存、提供などを行う事業の制度化を検討している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this report, the NDL is considering the institutionalization of a project to collect websites transmitted in Japan at a pace of once a year or so automatically and non-selectively, and to preserve and make available such websites under a certain restriction. The NDL revealed its plan to start with the acquisition of websites of a public nature with domain names such as go.jp, ac.jp, ed.jp, etc., and make available such websites in its report on the &quot;Concept of Institutionalization of Acquisition and Utilization of Internet-based Information&quot; (revised edition).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this report, the NDL is considering the institutionalization of a project to collect websites transmitted in Japan at a pace of approximately once a year, being automatic and non-selective, and to preserve and make available such websites under a certain restriction. The NDL revealed its plan to start with the acquisition of websites of a public nature with domain names such as go.jp, ac.jp, ed.jp, etc., and to make available such websites in its report on the &quot;Concept of Institutionalization of Acquisition and Utilization of Internet-based Information&quot; in its revised edition.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this report, the NDL is considering the institutionalization of a project to collect websites transmitted in Japan at a pace of approximately once a year, being automatic and non-selective, and to preserve and make available such websites under a certain restriction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル239の原文をセル240ﾆに分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>まず go.jp、 ac.jp、 ed.jp など公的な性格をもつドメイン名のページを収集、公開するとの方針を「インターネット情報の収集・利用に関する制度化の考え方」（改訂版）において明らかにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The NDL revealed its plan to start with the acquisition of websites of a public nature with domain names such as go.jp, ac.jp, ed.jp, etc., and to make available such websites in its report on the &apos;Concept of Institutionalization of Acquisition and Utilization of Internet-based Information&apos; in its revised edition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル239の原文をセル240ﾆに分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>このような動きは、自由民主党e-Japan 重点計画特命委員会の『世界最先端のIT国家実現のための申入れ』（2004年（平成16年））を契機として注目された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These developments caught the public&apos;s attention in tandem with the &quot;Proposal on Realization of the World&apos;s Most Advanced IT Nation&quot; by the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP)&apos;s Special Mission Committee on e-Japan Focused Plan in 2004.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These developments caught the public&apos;s attention in 2004, in tandem with the &quot;Proposal on Realization of the World&apos;s Most Advanced IT Nation&quot; by the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP)&apos;s Special Mission Committee on the e-Japan Focused Plan.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These developments caught the public&apos;s attention in 2004, in tandem with the &quot;Proposal on Realization of the World&apos;s Most Advanced IT Nation&quot; by the Liberal Democratic Party (LDP)&apos;s Special Mission Committee on the e-Japan Focused Plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>しかしその後、同申入れを検討した自民党デジタルアーカイブ小委員長の野田聖子衆議院議員や山口俊一衆議院議員が2005年（平成17年）に同党から離党しており（のちに復党）、また国立国会図書館が将来的に行うとしている網羅的収集は、同時にわいせつ物、児童ポルノ、プライバシー侵害情報の流布などによる違法行為の助長が指摘されていることから、実現は困難であるともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the House of Representatives member Seiko NODA and the House of Representatives member Shunichi YAMAGUCHI who suggested this proposal left the LDP in 2005 (rejoined the LDP later). Furthermore, it has been pointed out that the NDL&apos;s future plan of comprehensive collection of information could promote illegal acts by the circulation of obscene products, child pornography, and privacy infringing information. Therefore, it is said that the realization of the proposal will be quite difficult.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the House of Representatives member Seiko NODA and the House of Representatives member Shunichi YAMAGUCHI, who suggested this proposal, left the LDP in 2005 (but rejoined later); it has also been pointed out that the NDL&apos;s future plan for the comprehensive collection of information could promote illegal acts through the circulation of obscene products, child pornography and privacy-infringing information, so it is said that the realization of the proposal will be quite difficult.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the House of Representatives member Seiko NODA and the House of Representatives member Shunichi YAMAGUCHI, who suggested this proposal, left the LDP in 2005 (but rejoined later); it has also been pointed out that the NDL&apos;s future plan for the comprehensive collection of information could promote illegal acts through the circulation of obscene products, child pornography and privacy-infringing information, so it is said that the realization of the proposal will be quite difficult.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>国立国会図書館の利用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usage of the NDL</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Usage of the NDL</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Usage of the NDL</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="156">
<j>この節では、一般利用者として国立国会図書館の東京本館を来館利用する場合を中心に述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This section mainly explains about the cases when a general public user visit and use the NDL Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This section mainly explains the case in which a general public user visits and uses the NDL Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This section mainly explains the case in which a general public user visits and uses the NDL Tokyo Main Library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>国立国会図書館関西館および国際子ども図書館についての詳細は、それぞれの記事を参照されたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details on the Kansai-kan of the NDL and the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, please refer to the article on each topic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details on the Kansai-kan of the NDL and the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, please refer to the article on each topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details on the Kansai-kan of the NDL and the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, please refer to the article on each topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>入退館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Visiting and Leaving the Library</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Visiting and Leaving the Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Visiting and Leaving the Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="158">
<j>東京本館、関西館は満18才以上ならば誰でも利用できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anybody eighteen years of age or older is eligible to use services for the Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anyone 18 years of age or older is eligible to use services for the Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anyone 18 years of age or older is eligible to use services for the Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>これに対し国際子ども図書館は、児童に対するさまざまな個別的サービスを行っており、児童書に関する専門文献を集めた資料室を除き誰でも利用することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature which provides a wide range of specific services targeted children, can be used by anybody except for the reference room for specialized documents related to children&apos;s literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, which provides a wide range of specific services targeted toward children, can be used by anyone, except for the reference room for specialized documents related to children&apos;s literature.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the International Library of Children&apos;s Literature, which provides a wide range of specific services targeted toward children, can be used by anyone, except for the reference room for specialized documents related to children&apos;s literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="160">
<j>入退館ゲートでは複数の国会職員や委託業者が常時監視している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gate that visitors of the library pass through when entering or leaving the library, is constantly monitored by several Diet members or outsourced guards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gate through which library visitors pass when entering or leaving the library is constantly monitored by several Diet members or outsourced guards.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gate through which library visitors pass when entering or leaving the library is constantly monitored by several Diet members or outsourced guards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>入館にあたっては、カード発行機を利用して、資料の検索、請求、受取、複写などに用いる当日限りのICカード型の「館内利用者カード」の発行を受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon entering the library, a user is required to obtain a &quot;User Card,&quot; an IC card which is valid only on the day of issue, from the User Card Issuing Machine. The card is required when searching, requesting, collecting and copying materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon entering the library, a user is required to obtain a user card, which is an IC card that is valid only on the day of issuance, from the User Card Issuing Machine; the card is required when searching, requesting, collecting and copying materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon entering the library, a user is required to obtain a user card, which is an IC card that is valid only on the day of issuance, from the User Card Issuing Machine; the card is required when searching, requesting, collecting and copying materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>館内利用者カードの発行にあたっては氏名や住所、電話番号などの入力作業が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When obtaining a User Card, a user is required to input his/her name, address, telephone numbers, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When obtaining a user card, the user is required to input his/her name, address, telephone number(s), etc.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When obtaining a user card, the user is required to input his/her name, address, telephone number(s), etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>あらかじめ利用者登録を行って交付された登録利用者カード（館内利用者カードとは別。左画像参照）を持参すれば、パスワードの入力のみで館内利用者カードの発行を受けることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the user brings his/her Registered User Card (which is different from the User Card; see the picture shown to the left), however, he/she can obtain the User Card by inputting his/her password only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if the user brings his/her registered user card (which is different from the user card; see the picture shown to the left), he/she can obtain the user card by inputting only his/her password.</e>
<cmt>grammar, case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if the user brings his/her registered user card (which is different from the user card; see the picture shown to the left), he/she can obtain the user card by inputting only his/her password.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>こうして発行された館内利用者カードを用いて鉄道駅の自動改札機に類似のゲートを通過し、入館する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By using the User Card issued in this way, a user passes through the gate which is similar to an automatic ticket gate at train stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By using the card thus issued, a user passes through the gate that is similar to an automatic ticket gate at a train station.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By using the card thus issued, a user passes through the gate that is similar to an automatic ticket gate at a train station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>なお、東京本館と関西館では、鞄などの不透明な袋類の持込を禁止しているため、入館前に荷物は入口脇にあるロッカーに預けなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As opaque bags such as a briefcase cannot be brought into the Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan, a user is required to deposit his/her baggage in a locker located next to the entrance before entering the library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because opaque bags such as briefcases cannot be brought into the Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan, before entering the library the user is required to deposit his/her baggage in a locker located next to the entrance.</e>
<cmt>structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because opaque bags such as briefcases cannot be brought into the Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan, before entering the library the user is required to deposit his/her baggage in a locker located next to the entrance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="166">
<j>利用が終わった後は、まず受け取った資料をすべてカウンターに返却する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a user finishes using materials, he/she is required to return all the materials to the counter where he/she received them before leaving the library. The User Card is collected automatically when a user inserts the card into the gate and leaves the library.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a user finishes using materials, he/she is required to return all the materials to the counter where he/she received them before leaving the library. The user card is collected automatically when a user inserts the card into the gate and leaves the library.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a user finishes using materials, he/she is required to return all the materials to the counter where he/she received them before leaving the library.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル261の原文をセル262ﾆに分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>館内利用カードをゲートに通すとカードが回収され、退館できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The user card is collected automatically when a user inserts the card into the gate and leaves the library.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処セル261の原文をセル262ﾆに分割し、あわせて訳文も分割しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>資料を返却しない限り、退館はできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No one is allowed to leave the library without returning the materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No one is allowed to leave the library without returning the materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No one is allowed to leave the library without returning the materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>開館時間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Library Open Hours</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Library Open Hours</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Library Open Hours</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="169">
<j>東京本館 - 9時30分から19時（土曜日は17時）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Main Library - 9:30-19:00 (17:00 on Saturday)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Main Library: 9:30-19:00 (17:00 on Saturday)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Main Library: 9:30-19:00 (17:00 on Saturday)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="170">
<j>関西館 - 10時から18時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansai-kan - 10:00-18:00</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansai-kan: 10:00-18:00</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansai-kan: 10:00-18:00</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="171">
<j>国際子ども図書館 - 9時30分から17時</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">International Library of Children&apos;s Literature - 9:30-17:00</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">International Library of Children&apos;s Literature: 9:30-17:00</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">International Library of Children&apos;s Literature: 9:30-17:00</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>休館日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Days Closed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Days Closed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Days Closed</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>東京本館および関西館 - 日曜・祝日、毎月第三水曜と年末年始</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan - Sundays, National holidays, the third Wednesday of the month, and year-end and New Year&apos;s holidays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan: Sundays, national holidays, the third Wednesday of the month, and the Year-End/New Year holidays</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Main Library and the Kansai-kan: Sundays, national holidays, the third Wednesday of the month, and the Year-End/New Year holidays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="173">
<j>国際子ども図書館 - 月曜・祝日（ただし「こどもの日」の5月5日を除く）・毎月第3水曜・年末年始</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">International Library of Children&apos;s Literature - Mondays, public holidays (except Children&apos;s Day on May 5), the third Wednesday of the month, and year-end and New Year&apos;s holidays</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">International Library of Children&apos;s Literature: Mondays, public holidays (except Children&apos;s Day on May 5), the third Wednesday of the month, and the Year-End/New Year holidays</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">International Library of Children&apos;s Literature: Mondays, public holidays (except Children&apos;s Day on May 5), the third Wednesday of the month, and the Year-End/New Year holidays</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>資料の配置と閲覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Arrangement and Reading of Materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arrangement and Reading of Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arrangement and Reading of Materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="174">
<j>東京本館は、膨大な資料を管理するため原則としてすべての資料を利用者が直接触れられない書庫に配架する閉架式図書館をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For its management of an enormous amount of materials, as a rule, the Tokyo Main Library applies a closed stack system for its materials, with which all materials are stored in the closed stack room where a user cannot access directly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the management of an enormous amount of materials, as a rule the Tokyo Main Library applies a closed-stack system for its materials, with which all materials are stored in a closed stack room that is not directly accessible by the user.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the management of an enormous amount of materials, as a rule the Tokyo Main Library applies a closed-stack system for its materials, with which all materials are stored in a closed stack room that is not directly accessible by the user.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>このため利用者は、まず NDL-OPAC （国立国会図書館蔵書検索・申込システム）で必要とする資料を検索し、システムを通じて資料の申込を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, a user is required to search the materials he/she needs on the NDL-OPAC (a search and request system for materials housed in the NDL) first and request the materials via the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason the user is first required to search for the materials he/she needs on the NDL-OPAC (a search-and-request system for materials housed in the NDL) and then request the materials via the system.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason the user is first required to search for the materials he/she needs on the NDL-OPAC (a search-and-request system for materials housed in the NDL) and then request the materials via the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>書庫からはNDL-OPACの申込データをもとに資料が出納されるが、膨大な数の資料を広大な書庫から出納するため、利用者は本の受け取りに数十分程度の時間を要する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the request data on the NDL-OPAC, the materials will be taken out from the stack room, but it takes about 20-30 minutes before a user can collect the requested materials since an enormous amount of materials are taken out from the extremely large stack room.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the request data on the NDL-OPAC, the materials will be taken out from the stack room; however, it takes about 20-30 minutes before a user can collect the requested materials because enormous amounts of materials are taken out of the extremely large stack room.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the request data on the NDL-OPAC, the materials will be taken out from the stack room; however, it takes about 20-30 minutes before a user can collect the requested materials because enormous amounts of materials are taken out of the extremely large stack room.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>また、1人1回請求する冊数も制限されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a limit on the number of materials that can be requested by an individual at one time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a limit to the number of materials that can be requested by an individual at one time.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a limit to the number of materials that can be requested by an individual at one time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="178">
<j>東京本館は本館と新館の2棟から成り立っており、基本的に本館2階カウンターが図書、新館2階カウンターが雑誌の出納を担当している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokyo Main Library consists of two buildings (the Main Building and the Annex). Generally, the counter on the second floor of the Main Building is in charge of taking out books, and the counter on the second floor of the Annex is in charge of taking out periodicals.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokyo Main Library consists of two buildings (the main building and the annex), but generally the counter on the second floor of the main building is in charge of lending books and the counter on the second floor of the annex is in charge of lending periodicals.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokyo Main Library consists of two buildings (the main building and the annex), but generally the counter on the second floor of the main building is in charge of lending books and the counter on the second floor of the annex is in charge of lending periodicals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>また、主題別の特殊な資料や、国会図書館として特色的な資料については、それぞれに専門室が設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Special Materials Rooms exist for special materials by topics, as well as for unique materials as a national library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, special materials rooms exist for special materials by topics, as well as for materials that are unique among national libraries.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, special materials rooms exist for special materials by topics, as well as for materials that are unique among national libraries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>専門室では利用の多い参考資料は開架されているため、そこでは百科事典、辞典、統計、生活暦、新聞などの一部は書架から直接手にとって利用することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As some of the materials in the Special Materials Rooms are available in open stacks, users can read some of the materials on open shelves such as encyclopedias, dictionaries, statistics, almanacs, newspapers, etc. directly in their hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because some of the materials in the special materials rooms are available in open stacks, users can read some of the materials on open shelves such as encyclopedias, dictionaries, statistics, almanacs, newspapers, etc., and hold them in their hands.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because some of the materials in the special materials rooms are available in open stacks, users can read some of the materials on open shelves such as encyclopedias, dictionaries, statistics, almanacs, newspapers, etc., and hold them in their hands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="181">
<j>現在東京本館にある専門室は、本館2階に科学技術・経済情報室（科学技術及び経済社会関係の参考図書、科学技術関係の抄録・索引誌）と人文総合情報室（総記・人文科学分野の参考図書類、図書館・図書館情報学関係の主要雑誌等）、本館3階に古典籍資料室（貴重書、準貴重書、江戸期以前の和古書、清代以前の漢籍等）、本館4階に地図室（一枚ものの地図、住宅地図等）と憲政史料室（日本近現代政治史料、日本占領関係資料、日系移民関係資料）、新館1階に音楽・映像資料室（レコード、CD、ビデオ、DVD等）と電子資料室（CD-ROMなどの電子資料、電子ジャーナル等）、新館3階に議会官庁資料室（内外の議会会議録・議事資料、官公報、法令集、判例集、条約集、官庁刊行資料目録・要覧・年次報告、統計資料類、政府間国際機関刊行資料、法律・政治分野の参考図書等）、新館4階に新聞資料室（新聞の原紙、縮刷版・復刻版、マイクロフィルム、新聞切抜資料）、の計9室である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Special Materials Rooms currently available in the Tokyo Main Library are the following nine rooms: the Business, Science and Technology Room (Reference books on business and social science, science and technology, and abstracts and indexes of science and technology) and the Humanities Room (Reference books on general subjects and humanities, core journals of library &amp; information science) on the second floor of the Main Building; the Rare Books and Old Materials Room (Rare books, semi-rare books, Japanese old books up to Edo Period, Chinese old books up to the Qing Dynasty, etc.) on the third floor of the Main Building; the Map Room (Single-sheet maps (topographical maps, geological maps and hydrographical charts etc.), residential maps) and the Modern Japanese Political History Materials Room (Kensei-shiryoshitsu) (Documents and microfilms related to modern Japanese political history, microfilms of GHQ documents, materials related to Japanese immigrants) on the fourth floor of the Main Building; the Audio-Visual Materials Room (Phonographic records, CDs, DVDs, and VHSs, etc. issued in Japan) and the Electronic Resources Room (Electronic resources such as CD-ROMs, Electronic journals, etc.) on the first floor of the Annex; the Parliamentary Documents and Official Publications Room (Parliamentary documents, official gazettes, statutes, court reports and treaties of Japan and other countries.Publication catalogues, directories, annual reports, statistics of Japanese and foreign government offices and publications of international organizationsReference books on law and politics, etc.) on the third floor of the Annex; and the Newspaper Reading Room (Newspapers (original, reduced edition and microfilm), newspaper clippings) on the fourth floor of the Annex.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/service/tokyo/readinginfo.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nine special materials rooms currently available in the Tokyo Main Library, as follows: the Business, Science and Technology Room (reference books on business and social science, science and technology; abstracts and indexes of science and technology) and the Humanities Room (reference books on general subjects and humanities; core journals of library and information science) on the second floor of the main building; the Rare Books and Old Materials Room (rare books, semi-rare books, Japanese old books up to the Edo period, Chinese old books up to the Qing dynasty, etc.) on the third floor of the main building; the Map Room (single-sheet maps (topographical maps, geological maps and hydrographical charts, etc., and residential maps) and the Modern Japanese Political History Materials Room (Kensei-shiryoshitsu) (documents and microfilms related to modern Japanese political history, microfilms of GHQ documents and materials related to Japanese immigrants) on the fourth floor of the main building; the Audio-Visual Materials Room (phonograph records, CDs, DVDs, VHS tapes, etc., issued in Japan) and the Electronic Resources Room (electronic resources such as CD-ROMs, electronic journals, etc.) on the first floor of the annex; the Parliamentary Documents and Official Publications Room (parliamentary documents, official gazettes, statutes, court reports and treaties of Japan and other countries.Publication catalogues, directories, annual reports, statistics of Japanese and foreign government offices and publications of international organizationsReference books on law and politics, etc.) on the third floor of the Annex; and the Newspaper Reading Room (Newspapers (original, reduced edition and microfilm), newspaper clippings) on the fourth floor of the Annex.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nine special materials rooms are currently available in the Tokyo Main Library, as follows: the Business, Science and Technology Room (reference books on business and social science, science and technology; abstracts and indexes of science and technology) and the Humanities Room (reference books on general subjects and humanities; core journals of library and information science) on the second floor of the main building; the Rare Books and Old Materials Room (rare books, semi-rare books, Japanese old books up to the Edo period, Chinese old books up to the Qing dynasty, etc.) on the third floor of the main building; the Map Room (single-sheet maps and residential maps) and the Modern Japanese Political History Materials Room (Kensei-shiryoshitsu) (documents and microfilms related to modern Japanese political history, microfilms of GHQ documents and materials related to Japanese immigrants) on the fourth floor of the main building; the Audio-Visual Materials Room (phonograph records, CDs, DVDs, VHS tapes, etc.) and the Electronic Resources Room (electronic resources such as CD-ROMs, electronic journals, etc.) on the first floor of the Annex; the Parliamentary Documents and Official Publications Room (parliamentary documents, official gazettes, statutes, court reports and treaties of Japan and other countries, publication catalogues, directories, annual reports, statistics of Japanese and foreign government offices and publications of international organizations, reference books on law and politics, etc.) on the third floor of the Annex; and the Newspaper Reading Room (Newspapers (original, reduced and reprinted edition and microfilm), newspaper clippings) on the fourth floor of the Annex.</e>
<cmt>原文にない「topographical maps, geological maps and hydrographical charts, etc.,」、「, issued in Japan」を削除しました。annex→Annex改行を削除「復刻版」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>かつてはアジア・北アフリカ諸国の諸言語資料を専門とするアジア資料室も東京本館に置かれていたが、関西館の開館にともなってその蔵書とともに関西館に移転し、アジア情報室と改称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asian Materials Room, specialized in materials written in Asian and North African languages, used to be situated in the Tokyo Main Library, but the room was transferred to the Kansai-kan with its collection and renamed as the Asian Resources Room when the Kansai-san was opened to the public.</e>
<cmt>http://www.ndl.go.jp/en/service/kansai/collection/outline.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Asian Materials Room, specializing in materials written in Asian and North African languages, was formerly situated in the Tokyo Main Library, but it was transferred to the Kansai-kan with its collection and renamed as the Asian Resources Room when the Kansai-san was opened to the public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Asian Materials Room, specializing in materials written in Asian and North African languages, was formerly situated in the Tokyo Main Library, but when the Kansai-kan was opened to the public it was transferred to the Kansai-kan with its collection and renamed as the Asian Resources Room.</e>
<cmt>Kansai-san→Kansai-kan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>複写サービス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Copying Services</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Copying Services</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Copying Services</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="183">
<j>複写（コピー）は、利用者自身がコピー機でコピーを取ることはできず、複写カウンターに申し込んで行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A user cannot copy materials using a photocopier by himself/herself, but is required to make a request at the Copying Center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A user cannot copy materials alone using a photocopier but is instead required to make a request at the Copying Center.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A user cannot copy materials alone using a photocopier but is instead required to make a request at the Copying Center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>利用者の自由な複写を許さないのは、国立国会図書館が納本図書館として資料保全を図る必要があり、また図書館一般における利用者の複写は、原則として著作権法第31条の定める著作権者の許諾を得ない複写の範囲などに限られていることから、同館は複写する部分を図書館側がチェックすることになっているためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Free copying by a user is not allowed in the NDL because the NDL has an obligation of preservation of materials as a deposit library, and the NDL is required to confirm the portions to be copied as copying by a user in libraries in general is limited to the portion which can be copied without obtaining approval of a copyright holder as specified in Article 31 of the Copyright Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Free copying by a user is not allowed in the NDL because the NDL has an obligation to preserve materials as a deposit library, and the NDL is required to confirm the portions to be copied because copying by library users in general is limited to the portion that can be copied without obtaining the approval of a copyright holder as specified in Article 31 of the Copyright Act.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Free copying by a user is not allowed in the NDL because the NDL has an obligation to preserve materials as a deposit library, and the NDL is required to confirm the portions to be copied because copying by library users in general is limited to the portion that can be copied without obtaining the approval of a copyright holder as specified in Article 31 of the Copyright Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>このため、たとえ国立国会図書館にしか所蔵されていない貴重な資料であろうとも、逐次刊行物の最新号や著作権の存続している資料の全頁を複写することはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, a user cannot copy full pages of the latest edition of serials and materials protected by copyright, even if they are valuable materials only available in the NDL.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason a user cannot copy full pages of the latest editions of serials and materials protected by copyright, even if they are valuable materials only available in the NDL.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason a user cannot copy full pages of the latest editions of serials and materials protected by copyright, even if they are valuable materials only available in the NDL.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="186">
<j>セルフコピーができないために、混雑時にはコピーの申込みをしてから複写製品を受け取るまでに、数十分の時間がかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since self copying is not available, it takes between 10-30 minutes before photoduplicates can be collected after a request for photoduplication is made, depending on the level of usage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because self-copying is not available, it takes between 10-30 minutes before photoduplicates can be collected after a request for photo-duplication is made, depending on the level of usage.</e>
<cmt>usage</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because self-copying is not available, it takes between 10-30 minutes before photoduplicates can be collected after a request for photo-duplication is made, depending on the level of usage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>資料出納の待ち時間に複写に要する待ち時間を加えると、目的の資料の複写物を入手するまでに相当の時間がかかり、待ち時間の長さは国会図書館利用の上で、利用者への大きな負担となっている部分である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Waiting time for the materials to be taken out from the stack room, combined with the waiting time required for the photoduplication, a considerable amount of time is required for a user to collect photoduplicates of target materials. The length of waiting time is one of the burdens for a user when using the NDL.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the waiting time for the materials to be taken out from the stack room, combined with the waiting time required for the photo-duplication, a considerable amount of time is required for a user to collect photoduplicates of target materials. The length of waiting time is one of the burdens for a user when using the NDL.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the waiting time for the materials to be taken out from the stack room, combined with the waiting time required for photo-duplication, a considerable amount of time is required for a user to collect photoduplicates of target materials and the length of waiting time is one of the burdens for a user when using the NDL.</e>
<cmt>2文を1文に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="188">
<j>ただし、関西館にはセルフコピー機があり、参考資料の一部を利用者自身で複写することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are self-service photocopiers in the Kansai-kan, and a user can copy a part of reference materials by himself/herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are self-service photocopiers in the Kansai-kan, and the user can copy portions of reference materials by himself/herself.</e>
<cmt>better</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are self-service photocopiers in the Kansai-kan, and the user can copy portions of reference materials by himself/herself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>この場合も、図書館担当者による複写箇所の確認は受けなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in this case, a user is required to have the portion he/she copied in materials confirmed by a library staff.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in this case the user is required to have the portion he/she has copied in materials confirmed by a library staff person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in this case the user is required to have the portion he/she has copied in materials confirmed by a library staff person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="190">
<j>また、あらかじめ利用者登録をすれば、インターネット上でNDL-OPACから資料を特定し、郵送でのコピーサービスを実費のみで受けることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a registered user can look up and identify a material on the NDL-OPAC system via the Internet, and request a copying service by mail by paying actual costs only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, a registered user can look up and identify a material on the NDL-OPAC system via the Internet and request a copying service by mail by paying the actual costs only.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, a registered user can look up and identify a material on the NDL-OPAC system via the Internet and request a copying service by mail by paying the actual costs only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>遠隔コピーサービスは雑誌記事索引と連動し、検索した雑誌の特定の記事を指定してコピーを受け取ることも可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the remote copying service is connected with the Japanese Periodicals Index system, it is possible for a user to specify the article to be copied within the searched magazines and request a copy of such article to be sent to him/her.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the remote copying service is connected with the Japanese Periodicals Index system, it is possible for a user to specify the article to be copied within the searched magazines and request that a copy of such article be sent to him/her.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the remote copying service is connected with the Japanese Periodicals Index system, it is possible for a user to specify the article to be copied within the searched magazines and request that a copy of such article be sent to him/her.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Okura(id:23087), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Ideal(id:236), CommonsDelinker(id:84593), Charles&apos;s Wain(id:41263), Opponent(id:720), Zekkezeke(id:24857), 釣本直紀(id:85142), 新芽(id:50924), Sanctuary-jp(id:166066), 誤字鳥(id:48736), Fukumitu(id:113236), あなん(id:6904), Yas(id:739), Component(id:146478), Sumaru(id:20609), Kouko0515(id:100370), Kuga(id:33569), 翰林硯士(id:99377), BoB774(id:148281), 目白梅(id:141468), Oxhop(id:2551), Albambot(id:195288), 貿易風(id:85487), たんじゅんそぼく(id:61057), Pruqsa(id:190960), L III (N)(id:72793), Hrs885(id:104160), Docile-jp(id:14825), Album(id:74976), Ef3(id:84901), Vantey(id:22521), Futy(id:195), McRash-F4(id:146046), Tietew(id:4054), R28Bot(id:177951), 上(id:14148), RedStar(id:18409), Sug(id:5245), Hareno(id:9960), Ligar(id:12623), KISS(id:28504), BOTarate(id:185620), 田無稲子(id:63575), Urania(id:7213), Charenji(id:7908), MelancholieBot(id:31942), Ttwo(id:82880), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Charon(id:9162), Yoppi(id:21994), Johncapistrano(id:969), BBG(id:124711), 呉(id:90996), 竹麦魚(id:11012), あばさー(id:95106), Okc(id:17021), Amagase(id:108940), J o(id:26533), 西村崇(id:162006), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Transpassive(id:12204), G.miyanomori(id:9984), NORITO,S(id:30100), Carkuni(id:79281), 竃馬(id:102733), VolkovBot(id:105371), Miya(id:1881), Falcosapiens(id:221), Fievarsty(id:201483), Bossa(id:41241), Safkan(id:423), Chatama(id:16156), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), っ(id:4481), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>