<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>杉山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugiyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugiyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugiyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>杉山城（すぎやまじょう）は、埼玉県比企郡嵐山町にあった城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugiyama-jo Castle was located in Ranzan-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugiyama-jo Castle is located in Ranzan-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugiyama-jo Castle was located in Ranzan-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>is→was（もう存在しない城なので過去形でよいと判断しました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名は初雁城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Hatsukari-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Hatsukari-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Hatsukari-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>市野川左岸の山の上に築かれた山城である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle was constructed on top of the mountain on the left bank of Ichino-kawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle was constructed on top of a mountain above the left bank of Ichino-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>Grammar. I think &apos;left-bank&apos; is inappropriate as it would depend on which direction you were facing - perhaps &apos;west bank&apos; would be better?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle was constructed on top of a mountain above the bank of Ichino-kawa River.</e>
<cmt>元原稿が不十分です。どちらを向いていたかわからないと「左岸」では意味がないので単に「bank」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>築城主は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The owner of the castle is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original owner of the castle is unknown.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original owner of the castle is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>地元豪族の金子主水の築城によるとの伝承はあるが、文献資料 (歴史学)にはあらわれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a tradition that the castle was built by Mondo KANEKO (金子主水), local Gozoku (local ruling family,) but there are no supporting descriptions in literatures and documents (history.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is widely believed that the castle was built by Mondo KANEKO (金子主水), from a local gozoku (local ruling family,) but there are no supporting historical documents to confirm this.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is widely believed that the castle was built by Mondo KANEKO (金子主水), from a gozoku (local ruling family,) but there are no supporting historical documents to confirm this.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>従来、城の縄張りの観点から後北条氏の時代に造築されたものではないかとの見方が有力であったが、発掘調査にもとづく考古学的な知見からは山内上杉家時代の城である可能性が非常に強くなってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, there had been a leading view that the castle was built in the era of the Gohojo clan from the castle&apos;s Nawabari (the castle&apos;s ground plan) view points, but according to the archaeological findings based on the excavation research, the likelihood that the castle was built in the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi family has been become much higher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, the prevailing view was that the castle was built in the era of the Gohojo clan based on the evidence of the castle&apos;s nawabari (ground plan), but according to archaeological findings from excavation research the likelihood that the castle was built in the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi family has become much stronger.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, the prevailing view was that the castle was built in the era of the Gohojo clan based on the evidence of the castle&apos;s nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures), but according to archaeological findings from excavation research the likelihood that the castle was built in the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi family has become much stronger.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、この縄張りを主とする城郭史的観点と考古学的観点の見解の相違を「杉山城問題」と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The difference between the view point of castle walls history mainly based on this Nawabari and the archaeological view point can be called &apos;Sugiyama-jo Castle issue.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Differences in opinion between proponents of the nawabari-based theory and the archaelogy-based theory are referred to as the &apos;Sugiyama-jo Castle issue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Differences in opinion between proponents of the nawabari-based theory and the archaelogy-based theory are referred to as the &apos;Sugiyama-jo Castle issue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>検出遺構・出土遺物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discovered ancient structural remnants and excavated relics (of the past)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient structural remnants and excavated relics</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient structural remnants and excavated relics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>検出遺構としては、土塁、曲輪、井戸跡などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discovered ancient structural remnants include Dorui, Kuruwa, well ruins, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient structural remnants that have been discovered include the dorui (earthen walls), kuruwa (enclosure) and well ruins, among others.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar. It would be better if &apos;dorui&apos; and &apos;kuruwa&apos; were translated I think.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient structural remnants that have been discovered include the dorui (earthen walls), kuruwa (walls of a castle) and well ruins, among others.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>出土遺物には、かわらけ（中世土器）や古瀬戸様式がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excavated relics include Kawarake (earthen cups in the Middle Ages) and Koseto style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excavated relics include kawarake (medieval earthen cups) and Koseto style artefacts.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excavated relics include kawarake (medieval earthen cups) and Koseto style artefacts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>史跡指定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designated historical sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designated historical sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designated historical sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>2008年（平成20年）3月28日、すでに国の史跡に指定されていた菅谷館（嵐山町）に、松山城 (武蔵国)（吉見町）、小倉城 (武蔵国)（ときがわ町・嵐山町・小川町）とともに杉山城が追加指定され、「比企城館跡群」の名称で一括して国の史跡に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 28, 2008, in addition to Sugaya-yakata Castle (Ranzan-machi) already designated as a national historic site, Matsuyama-jo Castle (Musashi Province) (Yoshimi-machi,) Ogura-jo Castle (Musashi Province) (Tokigawa-machi, Ranzan-machi, Ogawa-machi) and Sugiyama-jo Castle were designated as national historic sites and all these castles were collectively designated as national historic sites at the name of &apos;Hiki-jo Castle Ruins.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 28, 2008, in addition to Sugaya-yakata Castle (Ranzan-machi), already designated as a national historic site, Matsuyama-jo Castle (Musashi Province) (Yoshimi-machi), Ogura-jo Castle (Musashi Province) (Tokigawa-machi, Ranzan-machi, Ogawa-machi) and Sugiyama-jo Castle were designated as national historic sites and all these castles were collectively designated as national historic sites under the name of &apos;Hiki-jo Castle Ruins.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar. I am unsure as to what （ときがわ町・嵐山町・小川町） means. Is the castle part of three sections of a city?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 28, 2008, in addition to Sugaya-yakata Castle (Ranzan-machi), already designated as a national historic site, Matsuyama-jo Castle (Musashi Province) (Yoshimi-machi), Ogura-jo Castle (Musashi Province) (Tokigawa-machi, Ranzan-machi, Ogawa-machi) and Sugiyama-jo Castle were designated as national historic sites and all these castles were collectively designated as national historic sites under the name of &apos;Hiki-jo Castle Ruins.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>杉山城問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugiyama-jo Castle issue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugiyama-jo Castle issue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugiyama-jo Castle issue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>杉山城の築城を山内上杉家によるものとする根拠は、山内上杉氏滅亡以前の時代的特徴を有する土器（かわらけ）の出土、古瀬戸の甕などの遺物の編年が山内上杉氏時代に属すること、他の城から出土するかわらけの分布を検討しても山内上杉氏の城として違和感がないこと、16世紀代の後北条氏時代の遺物が出土しないこと、さらに、後北条氏の時代の鎌倉街道を調査すると杉山の地は必ずしも要衝の地ではないのに対し、逆に山内上杉氏の時代だと要衝として重要視されるという立地条件などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basis of claiming that the erection of Sugiyama-jo Castle was by the Yamauchi Uesugi family is: discovery of earthwares (Kawarake) representing the characteristics of the period before the Yamauchi Uesugi clan was destroyed, the ruins such as earthenware pots of Koseto style were made in years included in the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi clan, it is not unreasonable to think it was the Yamauchi Uesugi clan&apos;s castle from considering the distributions of Kawarake dig out at other castles, no discovery of ruins representing the era of the Gohojo clan in the 16th century, and the locations in which as a result of research of Kamakura kaido in the era of the Gohojo clan, the place of Sugiyama was not necessarily an important spot, but it was considered important as a key spot during the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The claim that the erection of Sugiyama-jo Castle was by the Yamauchi Uesugi family rests on the following: the discovery of kawarake earthenware representing the characteristics of the period before the Yamauchi Uesugi clan was destroyed, the fact that Koseto style earthenware pots were made during the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi clan, that kawarake excavated from other castles have been considered to indicate a connection with the Yamauchi Uesugi clan, the lack of artefacts pointing to the era of the Gohojo clan in the 16th century, and the location of the castle itself, which as a result of research into the Kamakura kaido was found to be strategically unimportant in the era of the Gohojo clan, but was considered important as a key spot during the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The claim that the erection of Sugiyama-jo Castle was by the Yamauchi Uesugi family rests on the following: the discovery of kawarake earthenware representing the characteristics of the period before the Yamauchi Uesugi clan was destroyed, the fact that Koseto style earthenware pots were made during the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi clan, that kawarake excavated from other castles have been considered to indicate a connection with the Yamauchi Uesugi clan, the lack of artefacts pointing to the era of the Gohojo clan in the 16th century, and the location of the castle itself, which as a result of research into the Kamakura kaido was found to be strategically unimportant in the era of the Gohojo clan, but was considered important as a key spot during the era of the Yamauchi Uesugi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>発掘調査はほぼ完全発掘に相当し、杉山城の築城が後北条氏によるものである可能性はきわめて低くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The excavation research was almost equal to a comprehensive one, and the likelihood that Sugiyama-jo Castle was built by the Gohojo clan has become very low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The excavation research project was comprehensive, and the likelihood that Sugiyama-jo Castle was built by the Gohojo clan has declined.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The excavation research project was comprehensive, and the likelihood that Sugiyama-jo Castle was built by the Gohojo clan has declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>近年、『足利高基書状写』に「椙山之陣」と記されている事が判明し、この書状の原本が天文 (元号)15年（1546年）の河越夜戦以前の史料であることは明白なことから、上記の調査成果とも合致する内容となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the recent year, it was found that &apos;椙山之陣&apos; was noted in &quot;Copy of Takiamoto ASHIKAGA Letter (足利高基書状写,)&quot;and it is obvious that the original of this letter was a historical material prior to Kawagoe Night Battle in 1546, supporting the outcomes of the research above mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, it has been discovered that the phrase &apos;椙山之陣&apos; was written in the &quot;Copy of the Letters of Takamoto ASHIKAGA&quot; (足利高基書状写) and as the original manuscript was a historical document created prior to the Kawagoe Night Battle of 1546, the assertions of the research above are reinforced.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, spelling, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, it has been discovered that the phrase &apos;椙山之陣&apos; was written in the &quot;Copy of the Letters of Takamoto ASHIKAGA&quot; (足利高基書状写) and as the original manuscript was a historical document created prior to the Kawagoe Night Battle of 1546, the assertions of the research above are reinforced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>一方、一部の縄張り研究者は、杉山城の縄張りが詳細な設計プランがないと施工不可能なことや、後北条氏の滝山城における3つの虎口との類似性から、後北条氏の築城であると主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other side, some of Nawabari researchers insist that Sugiyama-jo Castle was erected by the Gohojo clan since the it was not possible to construct Nawabari in Sugiyama-jo Castle without detailed design plans and Sugiyama-jo Castle&apos;s Koguchi gate was similar to the three Koguchi gates in Takiyama-jo Castle of the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some supporters of the nawabari-based theory insist that Sugiyama-jo Castle was erected by the Gohojo clan since the construction of the nawabari in Sugiyama-jo Castle would be impossible without detailed design plans and Sugiyama-jo Castle&apos;s koguchi gate is similar to the three koguchi gates in Takiyama-jo Castle belonging to the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some supporters of the nawabari-based theory insist that Sugiyama-jo Castle was erected by the Gohojo clan since the construction of the nawabari in Sugiyama-jo Castle would be impossible without detailed design plans and Sugiyama-jo Castle&apos;s koguchi gate is similar to the three koguchi gates in Takiyama-jo Castle belonging to the Gohojo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>今後も、歴史学、考古学、城郭史など様々な観点からの議論の深化が望まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is expected that this issue will be more deeply discussed from various view points including history, archaeology and castle history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hoped that this issue will be more deeply discussed from historical, and archaelogical view points and through analysis of castle history.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hoped that this issue will be more deeply discussed from historical, and archaelogical view points and through analysis of castle history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>埼玉県比企郡嵐山町杉山614番地外</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugiyama 614, Ranzan-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugiyama 614, Ranzan-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugiyama 614, Ranzan-machi, Hiki-gun, Saitama Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>0.5キロメートルほど北西に関越自動車道の嵐山小川インターチェンジがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is Ranzan Ogawa Interchange in Kanetsu Expressway, located about five hundred meters north west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranzan Ogawa Interchange on the Kanetsu Expressway is located about five hundred meters to the north west.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranzan Ogawa Interchange on the Kanetsu Expressway is located about five hundred meters to the north west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), E-castle(id:161139), Makos(id:314663), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), КОЛЯ(id:59429), Urania(id:7213), Salmoides(id:156586), Nyao148(id:93723), 目蒲東急之介(id:34741), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>