<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>楼閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokaku (a multi-layered building)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokaku (a multi-storied building)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokaku (a multi-storied building)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>楼閣（ろうかく）とは、重層の建築物をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A rokaku indicates a multi-storied building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokaku indicates a multi-storied building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokaku indicates a multi-storied building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>たかどの、高楼のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its meaning is the same as that of &quot;takadono&quot; or &quot;Koro (高楼).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its meaning is the same as that of &quot;takadono&quot; or &quot;Koro (高楼).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its meaning is the same as that of &quot;takadono&quot; or &quot;Koro (高楼).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>塔と類義であるが、塔は本来仏塔を指し、entower の訳語としての塔は近代に入っての用法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its meaning is similar to that of 塔 (a tower), but 塔 indicated a Buddhist tower originally and it is in modern days that 塔 has become to be used as the translated word of &quot;entower.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its meaning is similar to that of 塔 (a tower), but 塔 originally indicated a Buddhist tower and iin modern days 塔 has come to be used as translated word&quot;entower.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its meaning is similar to that of a tower, but &quot;tower&quot; originally indicated a Buddhist tower in ancient times and in modern days &quot;tower&quot; has come to be used as translated word &quot;entower.&quot;</e>
<cmt>inスペル訂正しました、漢字の表記は不要と考え削除しました。&quot;tower&quot;補足しました。in ancient times補足しました。スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>それ以前の高層建築は一般に楼閣、高楼という呼称が用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that, a multi-storied building was generally called a rokaku or a koro (high building).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that, a multi-storied building was generally called a rokaku or a koro (tall building).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that, a multi-storied building was generally called a rokaku or a koro (tall building).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>「楼」（＝樓）とは重層の建物、「閣」とは御殿や櫓など高所の建造物を意味し、これらを総称して楼閣という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">楼 (=樓) (rou) indicates a multi-storied building and 閣 (kaku) a building located in a high place, such as a palace or a turret, with a building meeting both of these conditions called 楼閣 (rokaku) generally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">楼 (=樓) (rou) indicates a multi-storied building and 閣 (kaku) a building located in a high place, such as a palace or a turret, with a building meeting both of these conditions generally called 楼閣 (rokaku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">楼 (=樓) (rou) indicates a multi-storied building and 閣 (kaku) a building located in a high place, such as a palace or a turret, with a building meeting both of these conditions generally called 楼閣 (rokaku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>中国では国家的大事業の記念や政治的示威の目的をもって、多くが河畔、臨海に建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, many rokakus were built on the riverside or on the seaside for commemorating national big enterprises or for political demonstration purposes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, many rokakus were built on the riverside or on the seaside for commemorating big national events or for political demonstration purposes.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, many rokakus were built on the riverside or on the seaside for commemorating big national events or for political demonstration purposes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、城門には望楼が併設されるのが常であったため、これらも貴重な楼閣遺構として見ることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was also customary that a boro (watch tower) is placed in a castle gate, you can see boroes as important relics of rokakus as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was also customary that a boro (watch tower) was placed in a castle gate, you can see boroes as important relics of rokakus as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was also customary that a boro (watch tower) was placed in a castle gate, you can see boroes as important relics of rokakus as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>木造のものとして最古の遺構は984年、遼代に建立された独楽寺観音閣（天津市薊（けい）県）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lodest wooden relic of a rokaku is the Kannon-kaku of Dokuraku-ji Temple (located in Kei Ken, Tenshin City), built in 984 of the Lia era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest wooden rokaku relic is the Kannon-kaku of Dokuraku-ji Temple (located in Kei Ken, Tenshin City), built in 984 of the Lia era.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest wooden rokaku relic is the Kannon-kaku of Dokuraku-ji Temple (located in Ji County, Tianjin City), built in 984 of the Liao era.</e>
<cmt>天津市薊（けい）県→Ji County, Tianjin遼代→Liao era訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>河畔に佇む楼閣の大廈高楼たるさまは多くの詩家にも好まれ、李白の「黄鶴楼送孟浩然之広陵」や、崔顥（約704年-754年）の「黄鶴楼」など興趣に富んだ佳作を生むこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sight that a large and lofty tower stands still on a riverside was liked by many poets, producing many masterpieses of interesting and tasteful poems, for example, 黄鶴楼送孟浩然之広陵 (Sending off 孟浩然 (Mokonen) for 広陵 (Koryo) at 黄鶴楼 (Kokakuro)) by Rihaku and 黄鶴楼 (Kokakuro) by Saiko (around 704 to 754).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sight of a large, lofty tower still standing on a riverside was admired by many poets, who produced many masterpieses of interesting and tasteful poems, for example, 黄鶴楼送孟浩然之広陵 (Sending off 孟浩然 (Mokonen) for 広陵 (Koryo) at 黄鶴楼 (Kokakuro)) by Rihaku and 黄鶴楼 (Kokakuro) by Saiko (around 704 to 754).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sight of a large, lofty tower still standing on a riverside was admired by many poets, who produced many masterpieces of interesting and tasteful poems, for example, &apos;黄鶴楼送孟浩然之広陵&apos; (Sending off Haoran MENG for Yangju at Yellow Crane Tower) by Li Bai and &apos;黄鶴楼&apos; (Yellow Crane Tower) by Hao Cui (around 704 - 754).</e>
<cmt>masterpiecesスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&apos;を補足しました。下記の英語読みに訂正しました、孟浩然→Haoran MENG 広陵→Yangju(楊州) [http://www2.ttcn.ne.jp/~hasegawahiroyuki/koukakurou.htm]黄鶴楼→Yellow Crane Tower 李白→Li Bai崔顥→Hao Cui toをハイフンに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鼓楼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>鼓楼（ころう）は時報を告げるために用いられた楼閣で南京市のものが著名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A koro is a rokaku used for informing people of time, and the one in Nankin City is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A koro is a rokaku used for informing people the time, and the one in Nankin City is famous.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A koro is a rokaku used for informing people the time, and the one in Nanjing City is famous.</e>
<cmt>南京市→Nanjing</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>（→鼓楼）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(=&gt;Koro)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(=&gt;Koro)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(=&gt;Koro)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>中国の著名な楼閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous rokakus in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous rokakus in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous rokakus in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>黄鶴楼（湖北省武漢市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokakuro (in Bukan City, Kohoku-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokakuro (in Bukan City, Kohoku-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yellow Crane Tower (in Wuhan, Hubei Province)</e>
<cmt>黄鶴楼→Yellow Crane Tower湖北省武漢市→Wuhan, Hubei Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>滕王閣（江西省南昌市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokaku (in Nansho City, Kosei-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokaku (in Nansho City, Kosei-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pavilion of Prince Teng (in Nanchang, Jiangxi Province)</e>
<cmt>滕王閣→Pavilion of Prince Teng江西省南昌市→Nanchang, Jiangxi Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>岳陽楼（湖南省岳陽市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakuyoro (in Gakuyo City, Konan-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gakuyoro (in Gakuyo City, Konan-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yueyang Tower (in Yueyang City, Hunan Province)</e>
<cmt>岳陽楼→Yueyang Tower湖南省岳陽市→Yueyang City, Hunan Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>以上は「江南の三大名楼」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above three buildings are called the three great towers in Konan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above three buildings are called the three great towers in Konan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above three buildings are called the three great towers in Jiangnan.</e>
<cmt>江南→Jiangnan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>これに蓬莱閣を加えて「中国四大名楼」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Horaikaku was added to the above three buildings, they are called four great towers in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Horaikaku was added to the above three buildings, they are called four great towers in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Penglai Pavilion was added to the above three buildings, they are called four great towers in China.</e>
<cmt>蓬莱閣→Penglai Pavilion</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>蓬莱閣（山東省蓬莱市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horaikaku (in Horai Cit,. Santo-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horaikaku (in Horai Cit,. Santo-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Penglai Pavilion (in Penglai City, Shandong Province)</e>
<cmt>蓬莱閣→Penglai Pavilion 山東省蓬莱市→Penglai City, Shandong Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>真武閣（広西チワン族自治区）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinbuen (Kosei autonoumous region of the Chiwan tribe)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinbuen (Kosei autonoumous region of the Chiwan tribe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zhenwu Pavillon (Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region)</e>
<cmt>autonomousスペル訂正しました。真武閣→Zhenwu Pavillon広西チワン族自治区→Guangxi Zhuang Autonomous Region</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>煙雨楼（浙江省嘉興市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienu-ro (in Kako-City, Sekko-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienu-ro (in Kako-City, Sekko-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yanyulou Pavillon (in Jiaxing City, Zhejiang Province)</e>
<cmt>煙雨楼→Yanyulou Pavillon浙江省嘉興市→Jiaxing City, Zhejiang Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>鎮海楼（広東省広州市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinkairo (in Koshu City, Kanton-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinkairo (in Koshu City, Kanton-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zhenhai Tower (in Guangzhou, Guangdong Province)</e>
<cmt>鎮海楼→Zhenhai Tower 広東省広州市→Guangzhou, Guangdong Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>閲江楼（江蘇省南京市）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Etsukoro (in Nankin City, Koso-sho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Etsukoro (in Nankin City, Koso-sho)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuejianglou Pavillon (in Nanjing City, Jiangsu Province)</e>
<cmt>閲江楼→Yuejianglou Pavillon江蘇省南京市→Nanjing City, Jiangsu Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>本邦における楼閣建築の始まりは弥生時代の望楼（見張り台）に求められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first rokaku building in Japan is boroes (watching towers) in the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first rokaku building in Japan is boroes (watch towers) during the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first rokaku building in Japan is boroes (watch towers) during the Yayoi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし一般的には重層の建築物はほとんど利用されず、外見上重層である仏塔も一階のみに部屋を設け二階以上は屋根だけをかける場合が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, mult-storied buildings were scarcely used generally, and in many of Buddhist towers which are seemingly muti-storied, the rooms were provided only on the ground level floor, with only roofs constructed for the higher portion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, mult-storied buildings were scarcely used, and in many of Buddhist towers which are seemingly muti-storied, rooms were provided only on the ground level, with only roofs constructed for the higher portion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, multi-storied buildings were scarcely used, and in many of Buddhist towers which are seemingly multi-storied, rooms were provided only on the ground level, with only roofs constructed for the higher portion.</e>
<cmt>multi-スペル訂正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>貴族の邸宅に見られる寝殿造、書院造も平屋建てを前提とした様式であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinden-zukuri style buildings and shoin-zukuri style buildings for nobelpersons&apos; residences were also one-storied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinden-zukuri style buildings and shoin-zukuri style buildings for nobelpersons&apos; residences were also one-storied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinden-zukuri style buildings and shoin-zukuri style buildings for noblepersons&apos; residences were also one-storied.</e>
<cmt>noblepersons&apos;スペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>室町期以後、禅宗の隆盛とともに大陸風の楼閣寺院、茶室が出現する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period and later eras, temples and tea rooms employing a continental-syle rokaku increased corresponding to the increasing popularity of the zen sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period and later eras, temples and tea rooms employing a continental-style rokaku increasingly corresponded to the increasing popularity of the zen sect.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period and later eras, temples and tea rooms employing a continental-style rokaku increasingly corresponded to the increasing popularity of the zen sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>重層建築は意匠として重要であったほか、眺望が利く高層部は天下を睥睨する意図も併せ持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Multi-storied buildings were important not only from the viewpoint of the design but were also built intending for looking down the people from the higher-placed position that provided a commanding view of the area around them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Multi-storied buildings were important not only from the viewpoint of the design, but were also built intended for looking down at people from a higher position that provided a commanding view of the area around them.</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Multi-storied buildings were important not only from the viewpoint of the design, but were also built intended for looking down at people from a higher position that provided a commanding view of the area around them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>京の鹿苑寺、慈照寺はその代表であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical such examples are Rokuon-ji Temple and Jisho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical of such examples are Rokuon-ji Temple and the Jisho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical of such examples are Rokuon-ji Temple and the Jisho-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>一方、軍事的必要性、及び戦国大名の一円支配強化から望楼を起源とする「天守」（天守閣）が現れ、城郭建築の象徴として一世を風靡することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, due to military necessity and also for the necessity of warring loads strengthening the control of their territories, &quot;tenshu (also tenshukaku: castle turret)&quot; was designed based on boroes, with many such turrets built as a symbol of castle buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, due to military necessity and also for the necessity of warring loads strengthening the control of their territories, &quot;tenshu (also tenshukaku: castle turret)&quot; was designed based on boroes, with many such turrets built as a symbol of castle buildings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, due to military necessity and also for the necessity of warring loads strengthening the control of their territories, &apos;tenshu&apos; (also tenshukaku: castle turret) was designed based on boroes, with many such turrets built as a symbol of castle buildings.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正します。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>他方、寺院における楼閣建築も本邦独自の発展を見せ、西本願寺の飛雲閣など優れた木造楼閣が現れることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, rokaku buildings in temples in Japan developed independently of those in the continet, and many superior wooden rokakus, such as Hiunkaku in Nishihongan-ji Temple, were designed and built.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, rokaku buildings in temples in Japan developed independently of those on the continet, and many superior wooden rokakus, such as Hiunkaku in Nishihongan-ji Temple, were designed and built.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, rokaku buildings in temples in Japan developed independently of those on the continent, and many superior wooden rokakus, such as Hiunkaku in Nishihongan-ji Temple, were designed and built.</e>
<cmt>continentスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>近世に至ると都市部の旅館（旅籠）では土地の有効利用の目的もあって二階に客間を設けるものが多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the modern period, guest rooms of inns in urban areas became to be built on the second floor to make the land space available used more effectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the modern period, guest rooms of inns in urban areas came to be built on the second floor to make land space available and to be used more effectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the modern period, guest rooms of inns in urban areas came to be built on the second floor to make land space available and to be used more effectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>老舗旅館の「○○楼」や「○○閣」といった名称はその名残であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Long-established inns&apos; names of &quot;--楼 (ro)&quot; or &quot;--閣 (kaku)&quot; would be reminiscent of those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Long-established inns&apos; names of &quot;--楼 (ro)&quot; or &quot;--閣 (kaku)&quot; would be reminiscent of those days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Long-established inns&apos; names of &apos;--楼 (ro)&apos; or &apos;--閣 (kaku)&apos; would be reminiscent of those days.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正します。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>明治維新を迎えると浅草凌雲閣（浅草十二階）など煉瓦造のものが現れるが、これはもはや「高層ビル」といっていいものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Meiji era, brick-made rokakus, such as Ryounkaku (so-called Asakusa Twelve Stories), were built, but these buildings would be more appropriate to be called high-rise buildings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entering the Meiji era, brick-made rokakus, such as Ryounkaku (so-called Asakusa Twelve Stories), were built, but these buildings would be more appropriately called high-rise buildings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entering the Meiji era, brick-made rokakus, such as Ryounkaku (so-called Asakusa Twelve Stories), were built, but these buildings would be more appropriately called high-rise buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="33">
<j>鹿苑寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>慈照寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jisho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jisho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jisho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>飛雲閣（西本願寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiunkaku (in Nishihongan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiunkaku (in Nishihongan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiunkaku (in Nishihongan-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>以上を「京の三閣」といい、これに</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These buildings described above were called &quot;the three kakus in Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These buildings described above were called &quot;the three kakus in Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These buildings described above were called &apos;the three kakus in Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正します。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>呑湖閣（どんこかく、芳春院〈大徳寺塔頭〉）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Donkokaku (in Hoshun-in Temple, a tacchu (sub-temple) of Daitoku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Donkokaku (in Hoshun-in Temple, a tacchu (sub-temple) of Daitoku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Donkokaku (in Hoshun-in Temple, a tacchu (sub-temple) of Daitoku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>を加えて「京の四閣」といい、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the building described immediately above is added to the three above, they are called &quot;the four kakus in Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the building described immediately above is added to the three above, they are called &quot;the four kakus in Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the building described immediately above is added to the three above, they are called &apos;the four kakus in Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正します。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>東福寺伽藍（でんねかく、東福寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The big building of Tofuku-ji Temple (Dennekaku in Tofuku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The big building of Tofuku-ji Temple (Dennekaku in Tofuku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The big building of Tofuku-ji Temple (Dennekaku in Tofuku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>を加えると「京の五閣」と称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the building described immediately above is added to the four above, they are called &quot;the five kakus in Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the building described immediately above is added to the four above, they are called &quot;the five kakus in Kyoto.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the building described immediately above is added to the four above, they are called &apos;the five kakus in Kyoto.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正します。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="41">
<j>聴秋閣（三渓園）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choshukaku (in Sankei-en Garden)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choshukaku (in Sankei-en Garden)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choshukaku (in Sankei-en Garden)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>栖鳳楼（せいほうろう）　平安京大内裏にあった四楼の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seihoro: one of the four roes (towers) that were located in the palace in Heian-kyo Capital</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seihoro: one of the four roes (towers) that were located in the palace in Heian-kyo Capital</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seihoro: one of the four roes (towers) that were located in the palace in Heian-kyo Capital</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>森陣屋にある茶屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tea ceremony room in the Mori jinya (a regional government office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tea ceremony room in the Mori jinya (a regional government office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tea ceremony room in the Mori jinya (a regional government office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>慣用句</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Idiomatic phrases</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Idiomatic phrases</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Idiomatic phrases</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>空中楼閣 - 実現不可能なことから架空のことを意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuchu-rokaku (a rokau in the air): This phrase is used for meaning an imarginary thing, because such a rokaku cannot be built actually,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuchu-rokaku (a rokau in the air): This phrase is used for meaning an imaginary thing, because such a rokaku cannot in fact be built,</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuchu-rokaku (a rokau in the air): This phrase is used for meaning an imaginary thing, because such a rokaku cannot in fact be built,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>あるいは蜃気楼のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">or for meaning a mirage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">or for meaning a mirage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">or for meaning a mirage.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>砂上の楼閣 - 一見立派であるが基礎が柔らかいためすぐに崩壊してしまうこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sajo-no-rokaku (building a rokaku on sand): &quot;A thing is Sajo-no-rokaku&quot; means that it looks magnificient seemingly but will be broken down easily because its base is not solid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sajo-no-rokaku (building a rokaku on sand): &quot;Sajo-no-rokaku&quot; means that it looks magnificient, but will be broken down easily because its foundation is not solid.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sajo no rokaku (building a rokaku on sand): This phrase means that it looks magnificent, but will be broken down easily because its foundation is not solid.</e>
<cmt>magnificentスペル訂正しました。ハイフン削除、スペース補足。This phraseに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="47">
<j>摩天楼 - 天にもとどきそうな高い建物のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matenro: skyscrapers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matenro: skyscrapers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matenro: skyscrapers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>超高層ピルのことを俗にそういう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Super-high buildings are called &quot;matenro&quot; popularly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Super-high buildings are popularly called &quot;matenro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Super-high buildings are popularly called &quot;matenro.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), A-Taul(id:41790), こおりやんま(id:108912), ムカイ(id:72972), 鏡水蒼月(id:142300), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>