<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寄棟造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosemunezukuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosemunezukuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosemune-zukuri</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寄棟造（よせむねづくり）は、建築物の屋根形式のひとつで、4方向に傾斜する屋根面をもつものをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosemunezukuri refers to the form of roof of the buildings and has the four-way sloping roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosemunezukuri is a form of roof which has four sloping faces.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosemune-zukuri is a form of roof which has four sloping faces.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>広義では同様の屋根をもつ建物のことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, it also refers to the buildings which have the same type of roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, it also refers to buildings which have this type of roof.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, it also refers to buildings which have this type of roof.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>屋根の形式を指す場合には、単に寄棟ということも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it refers to the form of roof, it is often called &quot;yosemune&quot; simply.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When referring to the style of roof itself it is often abbreviated to &quot;yosemune&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When referring to the style of roof itself it is often abbreviated to &quot;yosemune&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>四注（しちゅう）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;shichu.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;shichu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;shichu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では、切妻造に次いで多く用いられている形式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it is the form which is the second most used to the “kirizumazukuri” (the form which has the two-way sloping roofs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan it is the second most widely-used form after “kirizumazukuri” which has two sloping faces).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan it is the second most widely-used form after &quot;kirizuma-zukuri&quot; which has two sloping faces.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一“ ”→&quot; &quot;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>寄棟造は、世界各地の住宅などで見られる一般的な屋根の造りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosemunezukuri is a general form of roof of the houses and so on around the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosemunezukuri is a general form of roof for houses and other buildings throughout the world.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosemune-zukuri is a general form of roof for houses and other buildings throughout the world.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>日本では、最上部に大棟をもち、長方形の平面である屋根を日本語で寄棟造というのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the roof which has an &quot;omune&quot; (horizontal member of the building) at the highest point and the rectangle flat form is generally called &quot;yosemunezukuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan the form of roof which has an &quot;omune&quot; (horizontal section) at the highest point and has a rectangular flat form is generally called &quot;yosemunezukuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan the form of roof which has an &quot;omune&quot; (horizontal section) at the highest point and has a rectangular flat form is generally called &quot;yosemune-zukuri.&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>歴史的には、東日本に多く見られ、古代には「東屋」（あずまや）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, it is common in the eastern Japan and called &quot;azumaya&quot; in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, it was more common in eastern Japan and was called &quot;azumaya&quot; in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, it was more common in eastern Japan and was called &quot;azumaya&quot; in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>明治時代の一時期には、宝形造も混同して呼ばれていたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometime during the Meiji period, &quot;hogyozukuri&quot; (four-triangles-roof form) was also called as such confusingly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometime during the Meiji Period, &quot;hogyozukuri&quot; (four-triangles-roof form) was confusingly also called by the same name.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometime during the Meiji Period, &quot;hogyo-zukuri&quot; (four-triangles-roof form) was confusingly also called by the same name.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>屋根の構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The structure of roof</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roof structure</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roof structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>典型的な構成の寄棟造の屋根は、4方向に勾配を持ち、長方形の平面で妻側の三角形の屋根と平側の台形の屋根からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical structure of the roof of yosemunezukuri has four-way sloping roofs which consist of two triangle-shape roofs at &quot;tsumagawa&quot; (the side vertical to omune) and two trapezoid-shape roofs at &quot;hiragawa&quot; (the side parallel to omune).</e>
<cmt>「4方向」ということは4枚の屋根があるということなので、妻側と平側にそれぞれ2つずつ、つまり2+2=4と考えて、和文にはない2をtwoと明記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical structure of a yosemunezukuri roof has four sloping faces which consist of two triangle-shape roofs at &quot;tsumagawa&quot; (the side vertical to the omune) and two trapezoid-shape roofs at &quot;hiragawa&quot; (the side parallel to the omune).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical structure of a yosemune-zukuri roof has four sloping faces which consist of two triangle-shape roofs at &quot;tsumagawa&quot; (the side vertical to the omune) and two trapezoid-shape roofs at &quot;hiragawa&quot; (the side parallel to the omune).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>4方に傾斜を持つことから、切妻造と比較して、雨の流れがよく雨仕舞いに優れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As yosemunezukuri has four-way sloping roofs, the flow of rainwater drains well compared to the kirizumazukuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As yosemunezukuri have four-way sloping roofs, the flow of rainwater drains well compared to the kirizumazukuri.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As yosemune-zukuri have four-way sloping roofs, the flow of rainwater drains well compared to the kirizuma-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その一方で、屋根部に垂直面がないために、切妻造や入母屋造と比較して小屋裏の換気が悪くなりがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as it has no vertical plane, it is likely to be badly ventilated compared to kirizumazukuri or irimoyazukuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as it has no vertical plane, it is likely to be badly ventilated compared to kirizumazukuri or irimoyazukuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as it has no vertical plane, it is likely to be badly ventilated compared to kirizuma-zukuri or irimoya-zukuri.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、複数の寄棟が組み合わされて、複雑な形状の屋根が造られることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, sometimes several yosemunes are combined to form complicated-shape roofs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, sometimes several yosemune are combined to form roofs of a complex shape.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, sometimes several yosemune are combined to form roofs of a complex shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>宝形造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogyozukuri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogyozukuri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogyo-zukuri</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>正方形の平面で寄棟を造ろうとした場合には、大棟ができず、4枚の屋根がすべて三角形になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To try to make yosemune with square-shape planes, omune cannot be put and all the four roofs become triangles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not possible to form an omune if you attemp to create a yosemune using square-shaped flat sections, as the four sections would need to be triangular.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not possible to form an omune if you attempt to create a yosemune using square-shaped flat sections, as the four sections would need to be triangular.</e>
<cmt>スペルミス修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このような造りを特に方形造、宝形造（ほうぎょうづくり）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This kind of structure is called hogyozukuri (方形造, 宝形造) in particular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This particular kind of structure is called hogyozukuri (方形造, 宝形造).</e>
<cmt>Order changed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This particular kind of structure is called hogyo-zukuri (方形造, 宝形造).</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これが、六角形であれば六注、八角形であれば八注という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If this is a hexagonal shape, it is called rokuchu and if an octagon shape, hacchu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If this is a hexagonal shape, it is called rokuchu and if an octagon shape, hacchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If this is a hexagonal shape, it is called rokuchu and if an octagon shape, hacchu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>代表的な建築物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Typical architectures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Typical examples of this form of architecture</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Typical examples of this form of architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>正倉院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>唐招提寺金堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshodaiji temple kindo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshodaiji temple kindo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshodai-ji Temple Kondo (main building with a principal image of the temple)</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>東大寺大仏殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Todaiji temple daibutsuden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Todaiji temple daibutsuden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Todai-ji Temple Daibutsu-den Hall (the Great Buddha hall)</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>元興寺極楽坊本堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gangoji temple gokurakubohondo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gangoji temple gokurakubohondo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gango-ji Temple Gokuraku-bo Hondo</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nhatbon(id:120517), Urania(id:7213), Metatron(id:64025), OiOiO(id:94238), PixelBot(id:166734), アルキテクトニケー(id:172676), Eveningmist(id:28648), ムカイ(id:72972), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>