<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>フランソア喫茶室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cafe François</e>
<cmt>[URL(http://www.francois1934.com/)]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OK</e>
<cmt>Thank you for providing the URL. That really is very useful.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>フランソア喫茶室（ふらんそあきっさしつ）は、京都府京都市下京区にある喫茶店で、国の登録有形文化財（建造物）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">cafe François, located in Shimogyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, is a government-registered tangible cultural property (building).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Cafe François is a government-registered tangible cultural property (building).</e>
<cmt>I think we are only transliterating Japanese place names in actual addresses, so there is no need for &quot;-ku&quot; before &quot;Ward&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Located in Shimogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture, Cafe François is a government-registered tangible cultural property (building).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>創業者の故・立野正一が1934年（昭和9年）に創業した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe was founded by the late Shoichi TATENO in 1934.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe was founded by the late Shoichi TATENO in 1934.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe was founded by the late Shoichi TATENO in 1934.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後に購入した北隣の木造二階建ての民家を現在に残る店の姿に改築したのは1941年（昭和16年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he purchased a two-storied wooden private house adjacent to the cafe on its north side, and in 1941 changed it into a cafe, one that has been used to the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He later purchased a two-story wooden private house adjacent to the cafe on its north side, and in 1941 converted it into a cafe, which is still there to this day.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He later purchased a two-story wooden private house adjacent to the cafe on its north side, and in 1941 converted it into a cafe, which is still there to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>改築前は、明治から大正時代に建てられた京都の伝統的な町屋だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before it was remodeled, the private house was one of the machiya traditional townhouses mainly found in Kyoto which had been built during the Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>[参考URL(http://www.kansai.gr.jp/culture_e/build/living/machiya1.htm)]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before it was remodeled, the house had been a machiya, a traditional townhouse found mainly in Kyoto that was built during the Meiji or Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before it was remodeled, the house had been a machiya, a traditional townhouse found mainly in Kyoto that was built during the Meiji or Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>戦争への足跡が聞こえる中、思想や芸術について自由に語り合える場を作ろうと、創業者の立野正一が友人のイタリア人（京大建築科の留学生ベンチ・ベニ）に改築を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the war was looming ahead, TATENO asked Benci Beni, an Italian student, who was the founder&apos;s friend and studying architecture at Kyoto University, to remodel the private house in order to provide a place where people could talk about thought and art freely.</e>
<cmt>「ベンチ・ベニ（Benci Beni）」の訳は任意のものです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With war looming, TATENO asked Benci Beni, an Italian studying architecture at Kyoto University who was a friend of his, to remodel the private house in order to provide a place where people could talk about ideas and art freely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With war looming, Tateno asked Benci BENI, an Italian studying architecture at Kyoto University who was a friend of his, to remodel the private house in order to provide a place where people could talk about ideas and art freely.</e>
<cmt>Tatenoとしました。BENI大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ベンチ・ベニは建物を洋風に設計。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When remodeling the house, Benci Beni designed it in Western style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While remodeling the house, Benci Beni designed it in Western style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While remodeling the house, Benci BENI designed it in Western style.</e>
<cmt>BENI大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>豪華客船のキャビンをイメージした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interior represents a luxury passenger liner&apos;s cabin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interior represents a luxury passenger liner cabin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interior represents a luxury passenger liner cabin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>設計はベンチ・ベニだが、施工は当時の日本の大工（日銀の内装を手がけた大工）や、家具の装飾を手がける指物師（木の道の匠）が作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe was designed by Benci Beni, but the construction work itself was undertaken by Japanese carpenters, who had done interior finishing work for the Bank of Japan building, and by sashimonoshi (cabinetmakers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe was designed by Benci Beni, but the construction work itself was undertaken by Japanese carpenters, who had done interior finishing work for the Bank of Japan building, and by sashimonoshi (cabinet makers).</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe was designed by Benci BENI, but the construction work itself was undertaken by Japanese carpenters, who had done interior finishing work for the Bank of Japan building, and by sashimonoshi (cabinet makers).</e>
<cmt>BENI大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>木造2階建、瓦葺、建築面積40㎡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A two-storied, tile-roofed wooden structure, the cafe has a building area of 40 m2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A two-storied, tile-roofed wooden structure, the cafe has a building area of 40 m2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A two-storied, tile-roofed wooden structure, the cafe has a building area of 40 square meters.</e>
<cmt>square metersに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>室内には、ヨーロッパで17世紀頃に流行したバロック様式を取り入れた華やかな装飾が施され、壁や窓は色鮮やかなステンドグラスで飾られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interior is gorgeously decorated in the Baroque style, which flourished in Europe around the 17th century, and colorful stained glass is fitted in the walls and windows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interior is gorgeously decorated in the Baroque style, which flourished in Europe around the 17th century, and colorful stained glass is fitted in the walls and windows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interior is gorgeously decorated in the Baroque style, which flourished in Europe around the 17th century, and colorful stained glass is fitted in the walls and windows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>最大の特徴は白いドームの天井。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The greatest feature of the cafe is its domed ceiling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The greatest feature of the cafe is its domed ceiling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The greatest feature of the cafe is its domed ceiling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>柱は中央に膨らみのあるルネサンス調のエンタシス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The columns incorporate Renaissance-style entasis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The columns incorporate Renaissance-style entasis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The columns incorporate Renaissance-style entasis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その上部や店内の調度品に至るまで、華やかな彫刻が施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Splendid patterns are carved onto everything from the upper part of the columns to furniture and furnishings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Splendid patterns are carved onto everything from the upper part of the columns to furniture and furnishings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Splendid patterns are carved onto everything from the upper part of the columns to furniture and furnishings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>壁にはパブロ・ピカソや竹久夢二などの絵画が掛かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the wall hang paintings of Pablo PICASSO, Yumeji TAKEHISA, and other artists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the walls hang paintings of Pablo PICASSO, Yumeji TAKEHISA, and other artists.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the walls hang paintings of Pablo PICASSO, Yumeji TAKEHISA, and other artists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ヨーロッパの古いランプや赤いビロードのいすなどがあり、これらは開店当初から変わらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other features include old European lamps and chairs with a velvet-covered seat, which have remained unchanged since the cafe opened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other features include old European lamps and chairs with a velvet-covered seats, which have remained unchanged since the cafe opened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other features include old European lamps and chairs with a velvet-covered seats, which have remained unchanged since the cafe opened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>店名はフランスの画家、ジャン＝フランソワ・ミレーにちなんでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe was named after Jean-François MILLET, a French painter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe was named after Jean-François MILLET, a French painter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe was named after Jean-François MILLET, a French painter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>創業者の立野正一は、絵描きを目指して美術学校へ通っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The founder TATENO attended an art school aiming to be an artist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The founder TATENO attended an art school aiming to be an artist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The founder Shoichi TATENO attended an art school aiming to be an artist.</e>
<cmt>Shoichi補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>国が軍国主義へ傾倒していくなかで、それに反発し、社会主義を啓蒙する場所として作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japan became increasingly militaristic, he opposed such a tendency and opened the cafe as a place for enlightening people on socialism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japan became increasingly militaristic, he opposed such a tendency and opened the cafe as a place for enlightening people on socialism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japan became increasingly militaristic, he opposed such a tendency and opened the cafe as a place for enlightening people on socialism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>思想や芸術について自由に語り合うための場所としての意味合い、思想の拠点という役割も、喫茶店にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe was intended to provide a place where people could talk about thought and art freely, and also had the function of serving as a center of thinkers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe was intended to provide a place where people could talk about thought and art freely, and also had the function of serving as a center for thinkers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe was intended to provide a place where people could talk about thought and art freely, and also had the function of serving as a center for thinkers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>立野は、志賀直哉や武者小路実篤といった自然主義文学の作家たちに影響を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TATENO was influenced by such writers as Naoya SHIGA and Saneatsu MUSHANOKOJI, who advocated naturalist literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TATENO was influenced by such writers as Naoya SHIGA and Saneatsu MUSHANOKOJI, who advocated naturalist literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tateno was influenced by such writers as Naoya SHIGA and Saneatsu MUSHANOKOJI, who advocated naturalist literature.</e>
<cmt>Tatenoとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その彼ら自身もバルビゾン派という画家たちの思想を受け継いでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These writers had taken over the thoughts of painters of the Barbizon school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These writers had taken over the thoughts of painters of the Barbizon school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These writers had taken over the thoughts of painters of the Barbizon school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>そのバルビゾン派の代表格がフランソワ・ミレーで店名の由来となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most prominent artist in the school was MILLET, the origin of the cafe&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most prominent artist in the school was MILLET, the origin of the cafe&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most prominent artist in the school was François MILLET, the origin of the cafe&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>François 補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただ、太平洋戦争が始まるとコーヒーを出せなくなり、店名も「都茶房」と変え、番茶や干しバナナを提供しながら、幸運にも戦火をくぐりぬけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after the Pacific War broke out, the cafe could not afford to serve coffee, but fortunately survived the war while offering bancha (coarse tea) and dried banana under the different name &quot;Miyako Sabo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But after the Pacific War broke out, the cafe could not afford to serve coffee, but fortunately survived the war while offering bancha (coarse tea) and dried bananas under the different name of &quot;Miyako Sabo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But after the Pacific War broke out, the cafe could not afford to serve coffee, but fortunately survived the war while offering bancha (coarse tea) and dried bananas under the different name of &apos;Miyako Sabo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>2002年（平成14年）10月18日には、国の登録有形文化財（建造物）に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe was designated by the national government as a registered tangible cultural property (building) on October 18, 2002.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe was designated by the national government as a registered tangible cultural property (building) on October 18, 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe was designated by the national government as a registered tangible cultural property (building) on October 18, 2002.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>喫茶店が登録文化財になったのは同店が全国で始めてである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">François became the first cafe in Japan to be designated as such.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">François became the first cafe in Japan to be designated as such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">François became the first cafe in Japan to be designated as such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>昭和の初期という時代に、和と洋を組み合わせた革新性、その後も改装されることなく建物が当時のままの姿で残っている点が高く評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe was innovative in that its designs combined Japanese and Western style in the early Showa period, and retains its original structure without being renovated subsequently, and these are highly rated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe was innovative in that its designs combined Japanese and Western style in the early Showa period, and retains its original structure without being renovated, and these are highly rated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe was innovative in that its designs combined Japanese and Western style in the early Showa period, and retains its original structure without being renovated, and these are highly rated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>現在は、2代目店長の今井香子氏が経営している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cafe is currently run by Ms. Kyoko IMAI, the second-generation manager.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cafe is currently run by Ms. Kyoko IMAI, the second-generation manager.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cafe is currently run by Ms. Kyoko IMAI, the second-generation manager.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>京都府京都市下京区西木屋町通四条下る船頭町184</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">184, Sendocho, Nishikiyamachi-dori Street, Shijo Kudaru, Shomogyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">184, Sendocho, Nishikiyamachi-dori Street, Shijo Kudaru, Shomogyo-ku Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">184, Sendo-cho, Shijo Sagaru, Nishikiyamachi-dori Street, Shomogyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足しました。四条下る→Shijo Sagaru住所表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>京阪四条駅より徒歩5分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five minutes&apos; walk from Keihan Electric Railway Shijo Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five minute walk from Keihan Electric Railway Shijo Station</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five minute walk from Keihan Electric Railway Shijo Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>阪急河原町駅より南木屋町出口徒歩1分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One minute&apos;s walk from the Minamikiyamachi Exit of Hankyu Railway Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One minute walk from the Minamikiyamachi Exit of Hankyu Railway Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One minute walk from the Minamikiyamachi Exit of Hankyu Railway Kawaramachi Station</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), Rusk(id:9895), Gappei2006(id:69935), Dragon2850(id:183907), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>