<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>船岡山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funaokayama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funaokayama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funaokayama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>船岡山城（ふなおかやまじょう）は京都市内にある中世の山城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funaokayama-jo Castle is a yamashiro (a castle on a mountain) in the medieval period, located in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funaokayama-jo Castle was a yamashiro (a castle on a mountain) in the medieval period, located in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>verb tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funaokayama-jo Castle was a yamashiro (a castle on a mountain) in the medieval period, located in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>船岡山全体が国の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funaoka-yama Mountain as a whole is designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funaoka-yama Mountain as a whole is designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funaoka-yama Mountain as a whole is designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>別名、船崗山城、山名城とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also named 船崗山城 (Funaokayama-jo Castle) or is called Yamana-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written as 船崗山城, or is called Yamana-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>changed to “written” to clarify that this is an alternative way to write the name</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written as 船崗山城, or is called Yamana-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>船岡山は京都市北区紫野北舟岡町にある標高112m、面積2万5千坪の小山である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funaoka-yama Mountain is a hill at 112 meters above sea level and an area size of 83.5 thousand square meters, located in Murasakino Kitafunaoka-cho, Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funaoka-yama Mountain is a hill of 112 meters above sea level, with an area of 83,500 square meters, located in Murasakino Kitafunaoka-cho, Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>prepositions, number notation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funaoka-yama Mountain is a hill of 112 meters above sea level, with an area of 82,644.63 square meters, located in Murasakino Kitafunaoka-cho, Kita Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>「面積2万5千坪」の表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>陰陽五行思想、風水思想に基づいて、船岡山は大地の気が溢れ出る、玄武の小山と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, based on the Inyo [Onmyo] gogyo shiso (Yin-Yang Wu-Hsing Idea) and on the feng shui (wind-water) theory, Funaoka-yama Mountain is a hill of Genbu God (a Chinese god) where vital energy of the earth overflows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, based on the Inyo gogyo shiso (Yin-Yang Wu-Hsing theory) and on feng shui theory, Funaoka-yama Mountain is a hill of the god Genbu (a Chinese god) where vital energy of the earth overflows.</e>
<cmt>idea-&gt;theorydeleted “wind water” because it doesn&apos;t really clarify the concept</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, based on the Inyo gogyo shiso (Yin-Yang Wu-Hsing theory) and on feng shui theory, Funaoka-yama Mountain is a hill of the god Genbu (a Chinese god) where vital energy of the earth overflows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>船岡山城は、応仁元年（1467年）に始まる応仁の乱の西軍の城として築造された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funaokayama-jo Castle was built as a castle for the troops of the west-side group in Onin War that started in 1467.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funaokayama-jo Castle was built as a castle for the troops of the western group in the Onin War that started in 1467.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funaokayama-jo Castle was built as a castle for the troops of the western group in the Onin War that started in 1467.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌年、東軍によって落城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, this castle fell to a troop of the east-side group.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, this castle fell to an army from the east.</e>
<cmt>troop-&gt;army</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, this castle fell to an army from the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は東西両軍とも利用しなかったため、廃城となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, neither of the east-side nor west-side troops used it, and therefore, the castle was abolished</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, neither of the eastern nor wester armies used it, and therefore, the castle was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>abolished-&gt;abandonedpunctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, neither of the eastern nor western armies used it, and therefore, the castle was abandoned.</e>
<cmt>westernスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>臨戦用の陣城と推定されており、恒久的な城郭施設の存在は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that the castle was a temporary fort provided for fighting, and it is unclear whether permanent castle facilities were provided there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed that the castle was a temporary fort provided for fighting, and it is unclear whether permanent castle facilities were provided there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed that the castle was a temporary fort provided for fighting, and it is unclear whether permanent castle facilities were provided there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>遺構としては山腹に横堀が掘られており、堀の外側土塁が積みあがっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its remains, horizontal trenches are dug on the slopes of the mountain, and mud walls exist outside these trenches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As its remains, horizontal trenches are dug on the slopes of the mountain, and mud walls exist outside these trenches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its remains, horizontal trenches are dug on the slopes of the mountain, and mud walls exist outside these trenches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また山頂部にはかなり広い削平面が確認でき、典型的な中世の山城であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, existence of a considerably large flattened area is confirmed on the top of the mountain, indicating that it was a typical yamashiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a large, flattened area on top of the mountain, indicating that it was a typical yamashiro.</e>
<cmt>shortened for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a large, flattened area on top of the mountain, indicating that it was a typical yamashiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>応仁の乱で、備前国守護の山名教之や丹後国守護の一色義直らが船岡山城で立てこもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Onin War, Noriyuki YAMANA, a military governor of Bizen Province, and Yoshinao ISSHIKI, a military governor of Tango Province, barricaded themselves in this castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Onin War, Noriyuki YAMANA, a military governor of Bizen Province, and Yoshinao ISSHIKI, a military governor of Tango Province, barricaded themselves in this castle.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Onin War, Noriyuki YAMANA, a military governor of Bizen Province, and Yoshinao ISSHIKI, a military governor of Tango Province, barricaded themselves in this castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この時に、西軍は船岡山一帯を陣地としたため、その後「西陣」の名で呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, a troop of the west-side group used the area including Funaoka-yama Mountain as a whole for its encampment, and therefore, the area became called &quot;Nishijin&quot; (the encampment of the west-side group) later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, a western army used the area around Funaoka-yama Mountain for its encampment, and therefore the area later came to be called &quot;Nishijin&quot; (the encampment of the western army group).</e>
<cmt>rephrased for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, a western army used the area around Funaoka-yama Mountain for its encampment, and therefore the area later came to be called &apos;Nishijin&apos; (the encampment of the western army group).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>次は、永正8年（1511年）に細川政賢と大内義興の間で繰り広げられた有名な船岡山合戦が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, the castle was the site of Funaokayama-no-kassen (battle at Mt. Funaoka), the famous battle fought between Masayoshi HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI in 1511.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, the castle was the site of Funaokayama-no-kassen (battle at Mt. Funaoka), the famous battle fought between Masayoshi HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI in 1511.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, the castle was the site of Funaokayama no kassen (battle at Mt. Funaoka), the famous battle fought between Masayoshi HOSOKAWA and Yoshioki OUCHI in 1511.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除して、「Funaokayama no kassen」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>文化財等指定</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designation as cultural properties or others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designation of cultural properties, etc.</e>
<cmt>or others-&gt;etc.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designation of cultural properties, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>日本の歴史の重要な舞台にしばしば登場した船岡山（城）の全体が国の史跡に指定されている（昭和43年2月15日指定）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entire area of Funaoka-yama Mountain (Castle), which appear on many important scenes in Japanese history, has been designated as a national historic site (designated on February 15, 1968).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entire area of Funaoka-yama Mountain (Castle), which was important in many instances in Japanese history, has been designated as a national historic site (designated on February 15, 1968).</e>
<cmt>scenes-&gt;instances</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entire area of Funaoka-yama Mountain (Castle), which was important in many instances in Japanese history, has been designated as a national historic site (designated on February 15, 1968).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>また、京都の自然200選（平成7年3月27日京都府指定）、風致地区（昭和6年7月14日京都市指定）にも指定され、地形や現状の変更が行われないように保護が計られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the area was included in the 200 selected Kyoto treasures of nature (designated on March 27, 1995, by Kyoto Prefecture) and was also designated as a scenic area (on July 14, 1931 by Kyoto City), to protect the geographical shape and present state of the area from being altered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the area was included in the 200 selected Kyoto treasures of nature (designated on March 27, 1995, by Kyoto Prefecture) and was also designated as a scenic area (on July 14, 1931 by Kyoto City), to protect the geographical shape and present state of the area from being altered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the area was included in the 200 selected Kyoto treasures of nature (designated on March 27, 1995, by Kyoto Prefecture) and was also designated as a scenic area (on July 14, 1931 by Kyoto City), to protect the geographical shape and present state of the area from being altered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線北大路駅より京都市営バス乗車、船岡山バス停または建勲神社前バス停下車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Get on a Kyoto City bus at Kitaoji Station on the Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subway, and get off the bus at the Funaokayama bus stop or at the bus stop in front of Kenkun-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Get on a Kyoto City bus at Kitaoji Station on the Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subway, and get off the bus at the Funaokayama bus stop or at the bus stop in front of Kenkun-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Get on a Kyoto City bus at Kitaoji Station on the Karasuma Line of Kyoto City Subway, and get off the bus at the Funaokayama bus stop or at the bus stop in front of Kenkun-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 黄金もち(id:102311), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Urania(id:7213), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Kagetudo(id:163875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>