<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藤井斉成会有鄰館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yurinkan Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yurinkan Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yurinkan Museum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>藤井斉成会有鄰館（ふじいさいせいかいゆうりんかん）は、京都府京都市左京区岡崎にある、中国の古美術が中心の私立美術館。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yurinkan Museum is a private art museum mainly dedicated to Chinese ancient art works, and is located in Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yurinkan Museum, located in Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, is a private facility that is mainly dedicated to ancient Chinese art works.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yurinkan Museum, located in Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, is a private facility that is mainly dedicated to ancient Chinese art works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>財団法人藤井斉成会は、滋賀県出身の実業家藤井善助（1873－1943、藤井紡績（後の藤井 (繊維会社)となる）創業者）の東洋美術コレクションを保存展示するための機関として大正15年（1926）に設立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujii Saiseikai Foudation was founded in 1926 to store and exhibit Oriental art collections of Zensuke FUJII (1873-1943) from Shiga Prefecture, who was the founder of Fujii Boseki (later, Fujii, a textile company).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fujii Saiseikai Foundation was founded in 1926 to store and exhibit the Oriental art collections of Zensuke FUJII (1873-1943) from Shiga Prefecture, who was the founder of Fujii Boseki (later, Fujii, a textile company).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fujii Saiseikai Foundation was founded in 1926 to store and exhibit the Oriental art collections of Zensuke FUJII (1873-1943) from Shiga Prefecture, who was the founder of Fujii Boseki (later, Fujii, a textile company).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本の私立美術館としては草分けの1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the private art museums that were opened in the earliest stage of their history in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is among the private art museums that were opened in the earliest stage of their history in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is among the private art museums that were opened in the earliest stage of their history in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>京都市登録文化財の建物は地上3階建てで、屋上に朱塗りの八角堂を乗せた東洋風の展示館は設立当初からのもので、展示室内部も昭和初期の雰囲気をとどめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its three-story building is registered to Kyoto City as a cultural property, and its oriental exhibition hall topped with a red-lacquered octagonal tower has been there since foundation, with the interior maintaining atmosphere of early Showa Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its three-story building is registered with Kyoto City as a cultural property; its Oriental exhibition hall topped with a red-lacquered octagonal tower has been there since its establishment, while the interior retains the atmosphere of the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its three-story building is registered with Kyoto City as a cultural property; its Oriental exhibition hall topped with a red-lacquered octagonal tower has been there since its establishment, while the interior retains the atmosphere of the early Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>国宝 1件、国の重要文化財 9件を含む所蔵品は、中国の殷（商）から清まで各時代の青銅器、仏像、書画、陶磁器など多彩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection has many different kinds of art works, including one National Treasure, nine National Important Cultural Properties, bronze pieces, Buddha statues, paintings, calligraphy, porcelains, and ceramics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection has many different kinds of art works, including one national treasure, nine national important cultural properties, bronze pieces, Buddha statues, paintings, calligraphy, porcelains and ceramics.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection has many different kinds of art works, including one national treasure, nine national important cultural properties, bronze pieces, Buddha statues, paintings, calligraphy, porcelains and ceramics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>珍しい収蔵品として人口に膾炙しているものは、科挙試の際に使用されたとされる、カンニング用の下着である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its well known rare collection item is an underwear allegedly used to cheat at Kakyo Examination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A well-known rare item in the collection is an undergarment that was allegedly used to cheat at the Kakyo Examination.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A well-known rare item in the collection is an undergarment that was allegedly used to cheat at the Kakyo Examination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一般公開は原則として、2～7月、9～11月毎月2回（第1・第3日曜）1200-1500のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is open to public only on two days per month (first and third Sundays), 12:00 pm - 15:00 pm, and closed for January, August and December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is open to the public just two days per month (first and third Sundays) from 12:00 noon to 3:00 p.m., and is closed in January, August and December.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is open to the public just two days per month (first and third Sundays) from 12:00 noon to 3:00 p.m., and is closed in January, August and December.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>主な収蔵品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main collection</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main collection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>春秋経伝集解（しゅんじゅうけいでんしっかい）巻第二残巻－中国唐代の写本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fragment of Commentary on the Spring and Autumn Annals, Volume II (Transcription during Tang Period of China)</e>
<cmt>春秋経伝集解→[定訳不明]Shunju Keiden Shikkai→Fragment of Commentary on the Spring and Autumn Annals, Volume II[定訳不明, 参考http://www.emuseum.jp/cgi/bunsyutu.cgi?SyoID=5&amp;ID=w027&amp;SubID=s120&amp;Link=w027x001]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fragment of Commentary on the Spring and Autumn Annals, Volume II (Transcription during China&apos;s Tang period)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fragment of Commentary on the Spring and Autumn Annals, Volume II (Transcription during China&apos;s Tang Dynasty)</e>
<cmt>Tang Dynastyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>絹本淡彩毛詩大雅蕩之什図　（中国・南宋時代）　伝馬和之筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenpon Tansai Moshitaiga Toshiju Zu (Nangsong Period of China) by Ma Hezhi</e>
<cmt>絹本淡彩毛詩大雅蕩之什図→[定訳不明]Kenpon Tansai Moshitaiga Toshiju Zu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenpon Tansai Moshitaiga Toshiju Zu (the Nangsong period of China), by Ma Hezhi</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenpon Tansai Moshitaiga Toshiju Zu (a picture of Moshitaiga Toshiju light-colored painting on silk) (the Nangsong period of China), by Ma Hezhi</e>
<cmt>(a picture of Moshitaiga Toshiju light-colored painting on silk)を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>絹本墨画秋山肅寺図　（中国・北宋時代）　伝許道寧筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenpon Bokuga Shuzan Shukuji Zu (Beisong Period of China) by Xu Daoning</e>
<cmt>絹本墨画秋山粛寺図→[定訳不明]Kenpon Bokuga Shuzan Shukuji Zu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenpon Bokuga Shuzan Shukuji Zu (the Beisong period of China), by Xu Daoning</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenpon Bokuga Shuzan Shukuji Zu (a picture of Shuzan Shuku-ji Temple monochrome ink painting on silk) (the Beisong period of China), by Xu Daoning</e>
<cmt>(a picture of Shuzan Shuku-ji Temple monochrome ink painting on silk)を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>紙本墨画幽竹枯槎図　（中国・金時代）　王庭筠筆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihon Bokuga Yuchiku Kosa Zu (Jin Period of China) by Wang Tingyun</e>
<cmt>紙本墨画幽竹枯槎図→[定訳不明]Shihon Bokuga Yuchiku Kosa Zu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihon Bokuga Yuchiku Kosa Zu (the Jin period of China), by Wang Tingyun</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihon Bokuga Yuchiku Kosa Zu (a picture of Yuchiku Kosa monochrome ink painting on paper) (the Jin period of China), by Wang Tingyun</e>
<cmt>(a picture of Yuchiku Kosa monochrome ink painting on paper)を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>銅造菩薩立像（中国・五胡十六国時代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dozo Bosatsu Ryu Zo (Wuhu Shiliuguo Period of China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dozo Bosatsu Ryu Zo (the Wuhu Shiliuguo period of China)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dozo Bosatsu Ryu Zo (a standing statue of Dozo Bosatsu) (the Wuhu Shiliuguo period of China)</e>
<cmt>(a standing statue of Dozo Bosatsu)を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>石造金剛力士立像　2躯（旧天龍山石窟仏）（隋時代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekizo Kongo Rikishi Zo, two bodies (Tenryu-san Mountain Sekkutsu Butsu) (Sui Period of China)</e>
<cmt>石造金剛力士立像→[定訳不明]Sekizo Kongo Rikishi Zo天龍山石窟仏→[定訳不明]Tenryu-san Mountain Sekkutsu Butsu</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekizo Kongo Rikishi Zo, two bodies (Tenryu-san Mountain Sekkutsu Butsu) (the Sui period of China)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekizo Kongo Rikishi Zo (a standing statue of Kongo Rikishi made of stone), two bodies (Tenryu-san Mountain Sekkutsu Butsu) (the Sui period of China)</e>
<cmt>(a standing statue of Kongo Rikishi made of stone)を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>石造菩薩及両脇侍立像（三尊菩薩立像）1基 台座框に河清三年の銘がある（北斉時代、564年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekizo Bosatsu and Ryouwaki Samurai Ryuzo(Three Stone-made Standing Bodhisattva), or Sanzon Bosatsu Ryuzo (Three Standing Bodhisattva), one set, with its base frame being signed third year of Seika (564, Northern Qi of China)</e>
<cmt>石造菩薩及両脇侍立像→[定訳不明]Sekizo Bosatsu and Ryouwaki Haberi Ryuzo(Three Stone-made Standing Bodhisattva)三尊菩薩立像→[定訳不明]Three Standing Bodhisattva</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekizo Bosatsu and Ryouwaki Samurai Ryuzo (Three Standing Bodhisattva Made of Stone), or Sanzon Bosatsu Ryuzo (Three Standing Bodhisattva), one set, the base frame of which was signed in the third year of Seika (564, Northern Qi of China)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekizo Bosatsu and Ryouwaki Samurai Ryuzo (Three Standing Bodhisattva Made of Stone), or Sanzon Bosatsu Ryuzo (Three Standing Bodhisattva), one set, the base frame of which was signed in the third year of Seika (564, Northern Qi of China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>石造弥勒仏及両脇侍立像 1基　台座正面に□魏天平二年の銘がある（東魏時代、535年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sekizo Miroku Bosatsu oyobi Ryokyojiryu Zo (Three Stone-made Standing Maitreya Bodhisattva), with front surface of the base being signed the second year of Gi-Tenpyou) (535, Eastern Wei of China)</e>
<cmt>石造弥勒仏及両脇侍立像→[定訳不明]Sekizo Miroku Bosatsu oyobi Ryokyojiryu Zo (Three Stone-made Standing Maitreya Bodhisattva)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sekizo Miroku Bosatsu oyobi Ryokyojiryu Zo (Three Standing Maitreya Bodhisattva Made of Stone), with the front surface of the base signed in the second year of Gi-Tenpyou) (535, Eastern Wei of China)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sekizo Miroku Bosatsu oyobi Ryokyojiryu Zo (Three Standing Maitreya Bodhisattva Made of Stone), with the front surface of the base signed in the second year of Gi-Tenpyou) (535, Eastern Wei of China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>張即之書李伯嘉墓誌銘 （中国・南宋時代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rihaku Kaboshi by Sokushi Cho (Nangsong Period of China)</e>
<cmt>李伯嘉墓誌→[定訳不明]Rihaku Kaboshi</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rihaku Kaboshi by Sokushi Cho (the Nangsong period of China)</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rihaku Kaboshi by Sokushi Cho (the Nangsong period of China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>朝鮮通信使関係資料（朝鮮国書 2通、徳川将軍返書控（金銀箔料紙）6通、朝鮮国東莱府使書契　1通、 附 朝鮮国礼曹参議書契 3通）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Materials related to Chosentsushinshi (Joseon Korea Diplomatic Mission to Tokugawa Japan): two letters of Joseon sovereign&apos;s message: Six replies from Tokugawa Shogun (gold-silver-leaf paper): Shokei (a note) by Joseon Toraifu mission: Three notes by Joseon Reiso Sangi)</e>
<cmt>朝鮮通信使→[定訳不明]Chosentsushinshi (Joseon Korea Diplomatic Mission to Tokugawa Japan)朝鮮国礼曹参議→[定訳不明]Joseon Reiso Sangi書契→[定訳不明]Shokei (note)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Materials related to Chosentsushinshi (Joseon Korea Diplomatic Mission to Tokugawa, Japan): two letters of Joseon sovereign&apos;s message; six replies from Tokugawa Shogun (gold- and silver-leaf paper); shokei (a note) from the Joseon Toraifu mission; three notes by Joseon Reiso Sangi)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Materials related to Chosentsushinshi (Joseon Korea Diplomatic Mission to Tokugawa, Japan): two letters of Joseon sovereign&apos;s message; six replies from Tokugawa Shogun (gold- and silver-leaf paper); one shokei (note) from the Joseon Toraifu mission; three notes by Joseon Reiso Sangi</e>
<cmt>「shokei(a note)」→「one shokei(note)」としました。最後の余分なカッコを取りました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>建築概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview of the building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview of the building</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview of the building</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>設計者― 武田五一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designer: Goichi TAKEDA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designer: Goichi TAKEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designer: Goichi TAKEDA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>竣工― 1926年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Completed in 1926</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completed in 1926</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completed in 1926</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>延床面積 ― 1,264㎡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gross Floor Area: 1,264 m2</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Total floor area: 1,264 square meters</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Total floor area: 1,264 square meters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>所在地― 京都府京都市左京区岡崎円勝寺44</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location: 44 Enshoji, Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: 44 Enshoji, Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: 44 Enshoji, Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>Kyoto Prefectureを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道 京都駅 から市バス46番で東山仁王門下車、徒歩3分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kyoto Station of West Japan Railway Company, take City Bus 46, get off at &quot;Higashiyama Nio Mon,&quot; and three minutes on foot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kyoto Station of West Japan Railway Company, take City Bus 46, get off at &quot;Higashiyama Nio Mon&quot; and walk three minutes.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kyoto Station of West Japan Railway Company, take City Bus 46, get off at &quot;Higashiyama Nio Mon&quot; and walk three minutes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>JR 京都駅 から市バス5番で京都会館美術館前下車、徒歩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Kyoto Station of JR, take City Bus 5, get off at &quot;Kyoto Kaikan Bijutsu Kan Mae,&quot; and walk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Kyoto Station of JR, take City Bus 5, get off at &quot;Kyoto Kaikan Bijutsu Kan Mae&quot; and walk.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Kyoto Station of JR, take City Bus 5, get off at &quot;Kyoto Kaikan Bijutsu Kan Mae&quot; and walk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>京阪電気鉄道 三条駅 (京都府)下車、徒歩10分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ten minutes on foot from Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) of Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is located ten minutes on foot from Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) of Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is located ten minutes on foot from Sanjo Station (Kyoto Prefecture) of Keihan Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yt(id:7522), ちょるや氏(id:88738), Rusk(id:9895), らりた(id:1327), ReijiYamashina(id:29567), KMT(id:1772), Urania(id:7213), Imses(id:37755), 663highland(id:18755), Wei Yuan(id:13342), Lupinoid(id:68), Kaznov17(id:68122), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>