<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>六波羅館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuhara yakata (Rokuhara residences)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuhara yakata (Rokuhara residences)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuhara Yakata Residences</e>
<cmt>大文字にして、タイトルなので括弧説明を削除しました。Residences補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>六波羅館（ろくはらやかた）は京都の東山山麓にかつて存在した邸宅群の総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuhara yakata is the term for indicating the residences once existed at the foot of Higashi-yama Mountain as a whole.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuhara yakata is the term for indicating the residences that once existed at the foot of Higashi-yama Mountain as a whole.</e>
<cmt>that</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuhara yakata is the term for indicating the residences that once existed at the foot of Higashi-yama Mountain as a whole.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>はじめ伊勢平氏の居館として築かれ、伊勢平氏が滅亡した後には六波羅探題が入居した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, the residence of Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) was built there, and then Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) used the place after Ise-Heishi was ruined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the residence of Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) was built there, and then Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) used the place after Ise-Heishi was ruined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the residence of Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) was built there, and then Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) used the place after Ise-Heishi was ruined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>この地に伊勢平氏が根拠地を築くきっかけとなったのは、平正盛建立の阿弥陀堂である（現在の常光院）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started with Amida-do Hall (a temple hall having an enshrined image of Amitabha) (present Joko-in Temple) built by TAIRA no Masamori that this place became the base site of Ise-Heishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started with Amida-do Hall (a temple hall enshrining an image of Amitabha, present Joko-in Temple) built by TAIRA no Masamori, and this place became the base of Ise-Heishi.</e>
<cmt>removed excess parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It started with Amida-do Hall (a temple hall enshrining an image of Amitabha, present Joko-in Temple) built by TAIRA no Masamori, and this place became the base of Ise-Heishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>六波羅館と呼ばれる邸宅群の範囲は時代により異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of the residences called Rokuhara yakata was different depending on the era.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of the residences called Rokuhara yakata was different depending on the era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of the residences called Rokuhara yakata was different depending on the era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしながら、伊勢平氏が繁栄を謳歌した最盛期には、北側が平安京の五条大路を東に延長した通り（現在の松原通）、東側が車大路、南側が平安京の六条大路を東に延長した通りであったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is considered that, in the best era of Ise-Heishi when the clan was most prosperous, the north side border was the street that was extended to the east from the Gojo-oji Street (literally, the fifth big street in the east-west direction) in Heian-kyo Capital (present Matsubara-dori Street), the east side border was Kuruma-oji Street (literally, a big street for vehicles), and the south side border was the street that was extended to the east from he Rokujo-oji Street (literally, the sixth big street in the east-west direction) in Heian-kyo Capital.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is considered that in the best era of Ise-Heishi when the clan was most prosperous, the north side border was the street that extended east from Gojo-oji Street (the fifth major east-west street) in Heian-kyo Capital (present Matsubara-dori Street), the east side border was Kuruma-oji Street (literally, a big street for vehicles), and the south side border was the street extended east from Rokujo-oji Street (the sixth major east-west street).</e>
<cmt>shortened this some</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is considered that in the best era of Ise-Heishi when the clan was most prosperous, the north side border was the street that extended east from Gojo-oji Street (the fifth major east-west street) in Heian-kyo Capital (present Matsubara-dori Street), the east side border was Kuruma-oji Street (literally, a big street for vehicles), and the south side border was the street extended east from Rokujo-oji Street (the sixth major east-west street).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>南北はおよそ500メートル、東西はおよそ600メートルであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The size of the area was about 500 meters in the north-south direction and about 600 meters in the east-west direction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The size of the area was about 500 meters north to south, and about 600 meters east to west.</e>
<cmt>shortened this some</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The size of the area was about 500 meters north to south, and about 600 meters east to west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>周囲は塀を巡らせ、内部には伊勢平氏の惣領家の邸宅「泉殿（いずみどの）」を中心として「屋敷三千二百余宇」が立ち並んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area was surrounded by walls, and inside, there were 3,200 and plus houses built with &quot;Izumi-dono,&quot; the residence of the Soryo (government) family, as its center.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area was surrounded by walls, and inside there were 3,200 or more houses built with &quot;Izumi-dono,&quot; the residence of the Soryo (government) family, at the center of them.</e>
<cmt>plus-&gt;more</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area was surrounded by walls, and inside there were 3,200 or more houses built with &apos;Izumi-dono,&apos; the residence of the Soryo (government) family, at the center of them.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこには伊勢平氏の一族郎党が起居していたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that all of the families and retainers of the Ise-Heishi clan lived there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that all of the families and retainers of the Ise-Heishi clan lived there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that all of the families and retainers of the Ise-Heishi clan lived there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>平忠盛、平清盛らの居館となった泉殿は、太田静六の研究によると、それ以前の寝殿造に較べて極端に小さいものであったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a research by Seiroku OTA, the Izumi-dono residence was extremely smaller than Shinden-zukuri style residences built before the era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to research by Seiroku OTA, the Izumi-dono residence was much smaller than Shinden-zukuri style residences built before then.</e>
<cmt>articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to research by Seiroku OTA, the Izumi-dono residence was much smaller than Shinden-zukuri style residences built before then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また泉殿の南には、平頼盛の居館である池殿があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ike-dono,&quot; the residence of TAIRA no Yorimori, was located on the south side of the Izumi-dono residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ike-dono,&quot; the residence of TAIRA no Yorimori, was located on the south side of the Izumi-dono residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ike-dono, the residence of TAIRA no Yorimori, was located on the south side of the Izumi-dono residence.</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて&quot; &quot;削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>泉殿は氏長者の邸宅と位置づけられており、1169年に清盛が福原に移ると、この邸宅は後継者の平重盛に譲られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumi-dono was positioned as the residence of the clan head, and therefore, when Kiyomori moved to Fukuhara in 1169, this residence was handed over to TAIRA no Shigemori, his heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumi-dono was positioned as the residence of the clan head and, therefore, when Kiyomori moved to Fukuhara in 1169, this residence was handed over to TAIRA no Shigemori, his heir.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumi-dono was positioned as the residence of the clan head and, therefore, when Kiyomori moved to Fukuhara in 1169, this residence was handed over to TAIRA no Shigemori, his heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、清盛が上京した際にも清盛は泉殿ではなく、西八条にあった妻の平時子の邸宅に滞在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, even when Kiyomori visited Kyoto, he did not stay at Izumi-dono but at the residence of his wife, TAIRA no Tokiko, in Nishi-hachijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, even when Kiyomori visited Kyoto, he did not stay at Izumi-dono but at the residence of his wife, TAIRA no Tokiko, in Nishi-hachijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, even when Kiyomori visited Kyoto, he did not stay at Izumi-dono but at the residence of his wife, TAIRA no Tokiko, in Nishi-hachijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>ちなみに清盛の時代、六波羅館のすぐ南には後白河法皇の住んだ法住寺があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, at the era of Kiyomori, Hoju-ji Temple where Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa lived existed just on the south side of Rokuhara-yakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On a related note, in the era of Kiyomori, Hoju-ji Temple where Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa lived existed just on the south side of Rokuhara-yakata.</e>
<cmt>“by the way” is too conversational for this context</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On a related note, in the era of Kiyomori, Hoju-ji Temple where Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa lived existed just on the south side of Rokuhara yakata.</e>
<cmt>Rokuhara yakataのハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Peachkiller(id:99202), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>