<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>福知山城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>福知山城（ふくちやまじょう）は、京都府福知山市にある平山城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama-jo is a hirayama-jo castle (a castle built on a hill in a plain) located in Fukuchiyama City of Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama-jo is a hirayama-jo castle (a castle built on a hill on a plain) located in Fukuchiyama City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>「in」→「on」, 「of」→「in」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle is a hirayamajiro (flatland-mountain castle) located in Fukuchiyama City in Kyoto Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Fukuchiyama-jo Castleとし、「平山城」の表記を修正 (参照; http://www.jcastle.info/resources/view/14-Japanese-Castles)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸時代には福知山藩の居城であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a residential castle to govern Fukuchiyama han (domain) in Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a residential castle built to govern the Fukuchiyama han (domain) in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>「built」挿入,「the」挿入x2</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a residential castle built to govern the Fukuchiyama Domain in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Fukuchiyama Domain, Edo periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>もとは小笠原長清の末裔とされる塩見頼勝が、室町時代後期に同地に築城した横山城という掻上城であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was originally a kakiage type castle (a simple and small castle on a stamped mound of soil and rocks) called Yokoyama-jo Castle built by Yorikatsu SHIOMI who is said to have been a descendant of Nagakiyo OGASAWARA in the late Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was originally a kakiage type castle (a simple and small castle on a stamped mound of soil and rocks) called Yokoyama-jo Castle built by Yorikatsu SHIOMI who is said to have been a descendant of Nagakiyo OGASAWARA of the late Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt>「in」→「of」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was originally a kakiage type castle (a simple and small castle on a stamped mound of soil and rocks) called Yokoyama-jo Castle built by Yorikatsu SHIOMI who is said to have been a descendant of Nagakiyo OGASAWARA of the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Muromachi periodに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1579年(天正7年)に明智光秀は丹波国を平定すると、これを福智山城と改名、近世城郭へと大修築したものである（城代は藤木権兵衛・明智秀満）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhide AKECHI, after conquring Tanba no kuni, changed its name to Fkuchiyama-jo Castle (福智山城), and made a major renovation to turn it into a new structure of his time (its castellan was Gonbee FUJIKI and later, Hidemitsu AKECHI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuhide AKECHI, after conquring Tanba no kuni, changed its name to Fukuchiyama-jo Castle (福智山城), and embarked on major renovations to turn it into a new structure of the time (its castellan was Gonbee FUJIKI and later, Hidemitsu AKECHI).</e>
<cmt>「Fkuchiyama」→「Fukuchiyama」, 「made a major renovation」→「embarked on major renovations」,「his」→「the」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuhide AKECHI, after conquring Tanba Province, changed its name to Fukuchiyama-jo Castle (福智山城), and embarked on major renovations to turn it into a new structure of the time (its castellan was Gonbee FUJIKI and later, Hidemitsu AKECHI).</e>
<cmt>Tanba no kuni→Tanba Provinceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>尚、江戸時代の城主、朽木氏により「福知山」に改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in Edo Period, its castellan Kutsuki clan changed the Chinese character of its name from &quot;福智山&quot; (Fukuchiyama) to &quot;福知山&quot; (Fukuchiyama).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in the Edo Period, its castellan of the Kutsuki clan changed the Chinese character of its name from &quot;福智山&quot; (Fukuchiyama) to &quot;福知山&quot; (Fukuchiyama).</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「from the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in the Edo period, its castellan of the Kutsuki clan changed the Chinese character of its name from &apos;福智山&apos; (Fukuchiyama) to &apos;福知山&apos; (Fukuchiyama).</e>
<cmt>Edo periodとし、原文に合わせシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>現在は、福知山城公園として整備され、天守は1985年(昭和60年)に復元されたもので、福知山市郷土資料館の施設となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Tenshu (donjon) was restored in 1985 and is now a facility of Fukuchiyama City Folk Museum in Fukuchiyamajo-koen Park which used be the castle compound.</e>
<cmt>福知山市郷土資料館→Fukuchiyama City Folk Museum（福知山市郷土資料館）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Tenshu (donjon) was restored in 1985 and is now a facility of Fukuchiyama City Folk Museum in Fukuchiyamajo-koen Park which used be the castle compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Tenshu (donjon) was restored in 1985 and is now a facility of Fukuchiyama City Folk Museum in Fukuchiyamajo-koen Park which used be the castle compound.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ほか、公園入口には隅櫓風城郭建築様式の福知山市佐藤太清記念美術館がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the side of the entrance of the park stands Fukuchiyama municipal Taisei Sato Memorial Museum whose structure is Sumiyagura (turret) Style Castle Architecture.</e>
<cmt>隅櫓風城郭建築様式→Sumiyagura (turret) Style Castle architecture（隅櫓風城郭建築様式）[定訳不明] 福知山市佐藤太清記念美術館→Fukuchiyama Municipal Taisei Sato Memorial Art Museum（福知山市佐藤太清記念美術館）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the side of the entrance of the park stands Fukuchiyama municipal Taisei Sato Memorial Museum whose structure is of Sumiyagura (turret) Style Castle Architecture.</e>
<cmt>「of」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the side of the entrance of the park stands Fukuchiyama City Sato Taisei Memorial Art Museum whose structure is of Sumiyagura (turret) Style Castle Architecture.</e>
<cmt>「福知山市佐藤太清記念美術館」→公式ウェブの表記に修正 (参照: http://fukuchiyama-artmuseum.jp/en.html)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>市街地を一望する福知山盆地の中央に突き出た丘陵地にあり、その地形の姿から臥龍城の別名を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Garyu-jo Castle&quot; (a lying dragon castle), because it is on a hill protruding in Fukuchiyama basin looking over the urban area, and the hill looks like a lying dragon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Garyu-jo Castle&quot; (lying dragon castle), because it is on a hill protruding from Fukuchiyama basin overlooking the surrounding urban area, and the hill looks like a lying dragon.</e>
<cmt>「a」削除, 「in」→「from」,「looking over」→「overlooking」,「surrounding」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Garyu-jo Castle&quot; (lying dragon castle), because it is on a hill protruding from Fukuchiyama basin overlooking the surrounding urban area, and the hill looks like a lying dragon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天守は国道9号走行中やJR福知山線の列車内からうかがえ、夜間はライトアップもされ、シンボリックである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Tenshu can be seen from a car on National Route 9 or from a train of JR Fukuchiyama Line, illuminated at night to make a symbol of the city.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Tenshu can be seen from both National Route 9 and the JR Fukuchiyama Line, and is illuminated at night as a symbol of the city.</e>
<cmt>「a car on」→「both」,「or from a train of」→「and」, 「and is」挿入, 「to make」→「as」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Tenshu can be seen from both National Route 9 and the JR Fukuchiyama Line, and is illuminated at night as a symbol of the city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また多数の桜が城周辺に植林されており、春には桜が満開となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many cherry trees around the castle are magnificent when in full bloom in spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many cherry trees around the castle are magnificent when in full bloom in spring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many cherry trees around the castle are magnificent when in full bloom in spring.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>曲輪は、福知山盆地に突き出た丘陵地の先端から、本丸、二ノ丸、伯耆丸、内記丸と続く連郭式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Kuruwa (walls of a castle and the regions surrounded by them) lies from the tip of the hill, which proturdes to Fukuchiyama basin, to Honmaru (the core of the castle) linking Ninomaru (second bailey), Hokimaru (third bailey), and Naikimaru (fourth bailey) forming Renkaku style (連郭式) (serial Kuruwa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Kuruwa (the walls of the castle and the regions surrounded by them) lies from the tip of the hill, which protrudes from Fukuchiyama basin, to the Honmaru (the core of the castle) linking the Ninomaru (second bailey), Hokimaru (third bailey), and Naikimaru (fourth bailey) forming a Renkaku style (連郭式) serial Kuruwa.</e>
<cmt>「walls of a」→「the walls of the」,「proturdes to」→「protrudes from」,「the」挿入x2, 「a」挿入, 「()」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Kuruwa (the walls of the castle and the regions surrounded by them) lies from the tip of the hill, which protrudes from Fukuchiyama basin, to the Honmaru (the core of the castle) linking the Ninomaru (second bailey), Hokimaru (third bailey), and Naikimaru (fourth bailey) forming a Renkaku style (連郭式) serial Kuruwa.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>本丸と二ノ丸にはそれぞれ御殿があったが、城の中央に位置し規模の大きい二ノ丸御殿が中心施設であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honmaru and Ninomaru had a Goten (palace), and as Ninomaru was largest at the center of the castle, it was probably the central facility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Honmaru and Ninomaru had a Goten (palace), and as the Ninomaru was largest at the center of the castle it was probably the central facility.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入x2, 「,」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Honmaru and Ninomaru had a palace, and as the Ninomaru was largest at the center of the castle it was probably the central facility.</e>
<cmt>「御殿」→辞書にも&quot;palace&quot;という訳語が記載されており、ローマ字表記を削除し英訳のみとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、その両側面の平地に設けた堀の内には、大手門のある北側に対面所や武家屋敷を、南側には蔵、馬屋、鷹部屋、庭園を配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Horinouchi (inside the moat) at the both sides in a plain land, there were meeting terrace and samurai houses at the north where Otte-mon Gate was, and at the south, Kura (storehouse), Umaya (horse stable), Takabeya (falcon house), and a garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Horinouchi (inside the moat) where the land on both sides is flat, there was a meeting terrace and samurai houses to the north where Otte-mon Gate was, and to the south, Kura (storehouses), Umaya (horse stables), Takabeya (falcon house), and a garden.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「at the both sides in a plain land」→「where the land on both sides is flat」, 「were」→「was a」,「at」→「to」x2, 「storehouse」→「storehouses」,「stable」→「stables」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Horinouchi (inside the moat) where the land on both sides is flat, there was a meeting terrace and samurai houses to the north where Ote-mon Gate (main gate) was, and to the south, Kura (storehouses), Umaya (horse stables), Takabeya (falcon house), and a garden.</e>
<cmt>Otte-mon Gate→Ote-mon Gateに修正、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>更に内記丸に続く郭外の台地には、平侍の長屋等があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also there were Nagaya (long houses) for Hurazamurai (lower-ranked samurai) on a terrace land beyond Naikimaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also there were Nagaya (long houses) for Hurazamurai (lower-ranked samurai) on a terrace beyond the Naikimaru.</e>
<cmt>「land」削除, 「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also there were Nagaya (long houses) for Hirazamurai (lower-ranked samurai) on a terrace beyond the Naikimaru.</e>
<cmt>Hurazamurai→Hirazamuraiに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>現在、本丸以外の曲輪は残っておらず、廃城後の「切り通し」や鉄道敷設によって、これらのあった丘陵地形は分断されてしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Carved out pathways after it was abandoned and the railroad construction have divided the hill on which the castle structures used to be, and only walls of Honmaru remain today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Carved out pathways after it was abandoned and railroad construction have divided the hill on which the castle structures used to be, and only the walls of the Honmaru remain today.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除, 「the」挿入x2</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Carved out pathways after it was abandoned and railroad construction have divided the hill on which the castle structures used to be, and only the walls of the Honmaru remain today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>尚、現在の復元天守へ登るための通路は、本丸に移された朝暉神社への参道として後に作られたものあり、本来の城道は現在住宅地として利用されている二の丸側から通じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pathway to climb the present donjon was built later to visit Asahi-jinja Shrine which was transferred to Honmaru, and the original main street was connected with Ninomaru which is now residential area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pathway to climb the present donjon was built later to access Asahi-jinja Shrine which was transferred to the Honmaru, and the original main street was connected with the Ninomaru which is now a residential area.</e>
<cmt>「visit」→「access」, 「the」挿入x2,「a」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pathway to climb the present donjon was built later to access Asahi-jinja Shrine which was transferred to the Honmaru, and the original main street was connected with the Ninomaru which is now a residential area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>石垣は穴太衆による野面積みである（福知山市指定文化財）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ano shu (groups of stone walls technicians) built its stone wall by Nozura-dumi (an old method of building robust stone walls) (Cultural Property designated by Fukuchiyama City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ano shu (groups of stone wall technicians) built its stone wall by Nozura-dumi (an old method of building robust stone walls), and this is a Cultural Property designated by Fukuchiyama City.</e>
<cmt>「walls」→「wall」, 「and this is a」挿入, 「()」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ano shu (groups of stone wall technicians) built its stone wall by Nozura-zumi (an old method of building robust stone walls), and this is a Cultural Property designated by Fukuchiyama City.</e>
<cmt>Nozura-dumi→Nozura-zumiとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>石材に墓石や石仏が使用されるのは、織田信長やその家臣ゆかりの城には多々見られることであるが、その使用数の夥しさとしては、郡山城跡に並び珍しい例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga Oda and his retainers commonly used some gravestones and stone-made Buddhist images to build walls, but the large number of those stones found in the walls of this castle is outstanding along with Koriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga Oda and his retainers commonly used gravestones and stone Buddhist images to build walls, but the large number of those stones found in the walls of this castle is outstanding, only matched by Koriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>「some」削除,「-made」削除,「along with」→「, only matched by」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA and his retainers commonly used gravestones and stone Buddhist images to build walls, but the large number of those stones found in the walls of this castle is outstanding, only matched by Koriyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Nobunaga ODAに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これはただ単に石材や、時間が不足していたためだとか、権力の強さをほかの国々に誇示するため、等さまざまな説があり、正しいことはまだはっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for this is not known yet, but there are some explanations such as that it was only because of shortage of time or materials, or that it was to show off the builders&apos; power to other war lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for this is not known, but there are some suggested explanations such as that it was due to a shortage of time or materials, or that it was to show off the builders&apos; power to other war lords.</e>
<cmt>「yet」削除, 「suggested」挿入, 「only because of」→「due to a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for this is not known, but there are some suggested explanations such as that it was due to a shortage of time or materials, or that it was to show off the builders&apos; power to other war lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>本丸の井戸「豊磐井」（とよのいわい）は、城郭内の井戸として日本一の深さ（50m、海面下に達する）を誇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The well called &quot;Toyonoiwai&quot; of Honmaru boasts Japan&apos;s deepest well inside a castle (50 meters deep reaching below sea level).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The well called &quot;Toyonoiwai&quot; in the Honmaru is Japan&apos;s deepest well inside a castle (50 meters deep, and reaching below sea level).</e>
<cmt>「of Honmaru boasts」→「in the Honmaru is」,「, and」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The well called &apos;Toyonoiwai&apos; in the Honmaru is Japan&apos;s deepest well inside a castle (50 meters deep, and reaching below sea level).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>復元天守は、大天守（3層4階）、続櫓、小天守が連結された形で、近世初期の望楼型である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The restored Tenshu (donjon or keep) is Boro type (top tower keep placed on the main structure) of the era of Nobunaga with Dai-tenshu (large keep of three roofs and four stories), Tsuduki-yagura (linking turrets), and connected Sho-tenshu (small keep).</e>
<cmt>続櫓→Tsuduki-yagura (linking turrets)[定訳不明]望楼型→Boro type (top tower keep placed on the main structure)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The restored Tenshu (donjon or keep) is of Boro type (with the top tower keep placed on the main structure) of the era of Nobunaga with a Dai-tenshu (large keep of three roofs and four stories), Tsuduki-yagura (linking turrets), and connected Sho-tenshu (small keep).</e>
<cmt>「of」挿入, 「with the」挿入, 「a」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The restored Tenshu (donjon or keep) is of Boro type (with the top tower keep placed on the main structure) of the era of Nobunaga with a Dai-tenshu (large keep of three roofs and four stories), Tsuzuki-yagura (linking turrets), and connected Sho-tenshu (small keep).</e>
<cmt>Tsuduki-yagura→Tsuzuki-yaguraとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>外観は忠実に再現されているが、構造は鉄筋コンクリート造である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its exterior looks like its original appearance but the structure is of ferroconcrete.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its exterior looks like its original appearance but the structure is of ferroconcrete.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its exterior looks like its original appearance but the structure is of ferroconcrete.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>遺構</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>本丸を残して二の丸以下の郭は開発により失われたが、本丸には石垣および井戸が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stone walls of Honmaru and the well remain today, but its walls of Ninomaru and other outer structures are lost due to land developments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stone walls of the Honmaru and the well remain today, but the walls of the Ninomaru and other outer structures are lost due to land development.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入x2, 「its」→「the」, 「developments」→「development」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stone walls of the Honmaru and the well remain today, but the walls of the Ninomaru and other outer structures are lost due to land development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>建造物としては、二の丸から本丸に移築された銅門脇番所（多聞櫓）が現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As architecture, there remains Bansho (guard station) at the side of Akagane-mon Gate (Tamonyagura, or hall turrets) which has been transferred to Honmaru from Ninomaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As extant architecture, there remains the Bansho (guard station) at the side of Akagane-mon Gate (Tamonyagura, or hall turrets) which has been transferred to the Honmaru from the Ninomaru.</e>
<cmt>「extant」挿入,「the」挿入x3</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As extant architecture, there remains the Bansho (guard station) at the side of Akagane-mon Gate (Tamonyagura, or hall turrets) which has been transferred to the Honmaru from the Ninomaru.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、観瀧寺、正眼寺、法鷲寺、明覚寺、および瑞林寺の山門として、それぞれ城門が移築され現存する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of the castle gates was transferred to build each Sanmon Gate of Kanryu-ji Temple, Shogen-ji Temple, Hosho-ji Temple, Myokaku-ji Temple, and Zuirin-ji Temple, and they remain today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the castle gates was transferred in order to build each Sanmon Gate of Kanryu-ji Temple, Shogen-ji Temple, Hosho-ji Temple, Myokaku-ji Temple, and Zuirin-ji Temple, and they remain today.</e>
<cmt>「in order」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the castle gates was transferred in order to build each San-mon Gate (main gate of a Buddhist Temple) of Kanryu-ji Temple, Shogen-ji Temple, Hosho-ji Temple, Myokaku-ji Temple, and Zuirin-ji Temple, and they remain today.</e>
<cmt>San-mon Gateとし、補足を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>福知山城と福知山音頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle and Fukuchiyama Ondo (Fukuchiyama folk tune)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle and Fukuchiyama Ondo (Fukuchiyama folk tune)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama-jo Castle and Fukuchiyama Ondo (Fukuchiyama folk tune)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>福知山音頭は江戸時代に出来上がった盆踊りの曲で、「ドッコイセ～、ドッコイセ～｣という特徴的なフレーズがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Ondo, established during Edo Period, is for Bon Festival Dance with a unique phrase &quot;Dokkoi-see, Dokkoi-see.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama Ondo, established during the Edo Period, is a Bon Festival Dance with a unique phrase &quot;Dokkoi-see, Dokkoi-see.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「for」→「a」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Ondo, established during the Edo period, is a Bon Festival Dance with a unique phrase &apos;Dokkoi-see, Dokkoi-see.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edo periodとし、シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これは、福知山城の築城中に石垣を運ぶ際、このような掛け声をかけて運んでいたことに由来すると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend has it that this comes from the construction work of the castle at which workers rhythmically called out like this when carrying stones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend has it that this comes from the construction work of the castle during which workers rhythmically called out like this when carrying stones.</e>
<cmt>「at」→「during」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend has it that this comes from the construction work of the castle during which workers rhythmically called out like this when carrying stones.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>交通アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>JR福知山線・山陰本線・北近畿タンゴ鉄道 福知山駅 徒歩15分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is 15 minutes on foot from Fukuchiyama Station of JR Fukuchiyama Line, or JR Sanin Line, or Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is 15 minutes on foot from Fukuchiyama Station on the JR Fukuchiyama Line, JR Sanin Line, and Kitakinki Tango Railway.</e>
<cmt>「of」→「on the」,「or」削除, 「or」→「and」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">15 minutes on foot from Fukuchiyama Station on the JR Fukuchiyama Line, JR Sanin Main Line, and Kitakinki Tango Railway</e>
<cmt>JR Sanin Main Lineとし、原文に合わせピリオド削除、一部文章を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>周辺情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tourist information around the castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tourist information around the castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tourist Information around the Castle</e>
<cmt>頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>明智藪　由良川の流れを曲げ、度重なる氾濫防止と水運交易発展のために築いた堤防。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akechiyabu (dike): this dike bends the stream of Yura-gawa River to control frequent floods and for the development of trades by water transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akechiyabu (dike): this dike bent the stream of Yura-gawa River to prevent frequent floods and for the development of trade by water transportation.</e>
<cmt>「bends」→「bent」, 「control」→「prevent」,「trades」→「trade」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akechiyabu (dike): this dike bent the stream of the Yura-gawa River to prevent frequent floods and for the development of trade by water transportation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Yura-gawa River&quot; -&gt; &quot;the Yura-gawa River&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>御霊神社　光秀を合祀する神社。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goryo-jinja Shrine: it enshrines Mitsuhide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goryo-jinja Shrine: it enshrines Mitsuhide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goryo-jinja Shrine: it enshrines Mitsuhide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>「明智光秀家中軍法」等、直筆の書状を所蔵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stores letters written by Mitsuhide such as &quot;Akechi Mitsuhide Kachu Gunpo&quot; (明智光秀家中軍法) (Mitsuhide AKECHI Family&apos;s Military Law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stores letters written by Mitsuhide such as &quot;Akechi Mitsuhide Kachu Gunpo&quot; (明智光秀家中軍法) (Mitsuhide AKECHI Family&apos;s Military Law).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stores letters written by Mitsuhide such as &apos;Akechi Mitsuhide Kachu Gunpo&apos; (Mitsuhide AKECHI Family&apos;s Military Law).</e>
<cmt>(明智光秀家中軍法) を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>佐藤太清記念美術館（福知山市立美術館）　城址公園内にあり、意匠を城にあわせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taisei Sato Memorial Art Museum (Fukuchiyama Municipal Art Museum): it stands in Fukuchiyamajo-koen Park and it is modeled after the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taisei Sato Memorial Art Museum (Fukuchiyama Municipal Art Museum): it stands in Fukuchiyamajo-koen Park and is modeled after the castle.</e>
<cmt>「it」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sato Taisei Memorial Art Museum (Fukuchiyama City Art Museum): it stands in Fukuchiyamajo-koen Park and is modeled after the castle.</e>
<cmt>佐藤太清記念美術館（福知山市立美術館）→公式ウェブの表記に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>松村家住宅（京都府指定文化財）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsumuras&apos; house(松村家住宅) (Cultural Property designated by Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>松村家住宅→Matsumura&apos;s house（松村家住宅）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsumuras&apos; house(松村家住宅) (Cultural Property designated by Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsumuras&apos; house(松村家住宅) (Cultural Property designated by Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>丹波生活衣館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanba Traditional Yarn-Dyed Fabric Museum(丹波生活衣館)</e>
<cmt>丹波生活衣館→Tanba Traditional Yarn-Dyed Fabric Museum（丹波生活衣館）[定訳不明,参考URL(http://www.city.fukuchiyama.kyoto.jp/modules/weblinks/singlelink.php?lid=157)]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanba Traditional Yarn-Dyed Fabric Museum(丹波生活衣館)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanba Traditional Yarn-Dyed Fabric Museum(丹波生活衣館)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>福知山市役所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama City Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama City Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama City Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>福知山市武道館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Municipal Budokan (gymnasium for martial arts)</e>
<cmt>福知山市武道館→Fukuchiyama Municipal Budokan (gymnasium for martial arts)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuchiyama Municipal Budokan (gymnasium for martial arts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuchiyama Municipal Budokan (gymnasium for martial arts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Monado(id:53906), Suguri F(id:11127), カテゴリ整理専用(id:146185), Reggaeman(id:6214), 078(id:28534), Jt noSke(id:32855), FAT26(id:9460), Qje(id:160294), 663highland(id:18755), Tagaru(id:30411), BAKU(id:55205), Roga246(id:53246), Sea of Japan(id:3230), ムカイ(id:72972), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>