<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>南座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minamiza Theater</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minamiza Theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minamiza Theater</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>南座（みなみざ）は京都市東山区にある劇場。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minamiza is a theater located in Higashiyama Ward of Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minamiza is a theater located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minamiza is a theater located in Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正式名称は京都四條南座（きょうとしじょうみなみざ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its official name is Kyoto Shijo Minamiza Theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its official name is Kyoto Shijo Minamiza Theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its official name is Kyoto Shijo Minamiza Theater.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>松竹が経営する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochiku Co. Ltd. runs this theater.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is run by Shochiku Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>Changed to improve flow.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is run by Shochiku Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代から続く歌舞伎の劇場で毎年11月末日より12月末まで行われる顔見世公演は京都の風物詩となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kaomise (a face-showing ceremony) performance is a seasonal tradition staged from the end of November to the end of December every year at this Kabuki theater that has been showing Kabuki since the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Kabuki theater has been showing Kabuki since the Edo Period, and every year from the end of November to the end of December a seasonal tradition called the Kaomise (a face-showing ceremony) is staged.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to make more natural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) theater has been showing Kabuki since the Edo period, and every year from the end of November to the end of December a seasonal tradition called the Kaomise (a face-showing ceremony) is staged.</e>
<cmt>「歌舞伎」の補足を追加、Edo Period→Edo periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このときには役者の名前を勘亭流で書いた「まねき」と呼ばれる、白木の看板が劇場の入り口上にずらりと並べられることで有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is well known that Many plain wooden boards called &apos;Maneki&apos; with each actor&apos;s name written in Kanteiryu (a special calligraphy style for Kabuki) are lined up above the entrance of the theater during this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The many plain wooden boards called &apos;Maneki&apos; having each actor&apos;s name written in Kanteiryu (a special calligraphy style for Kabuki) arranged above the entrance of the theater during this period are well-known.</e>
<cmt>Changed for punctuation and clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The many plain wooden boards called &apos;Maneki&apos; having each actor&apos;s name written in Kanteiryu (a special calligraphy style for Kabuki) arranged above the entrance of the theater during this period are well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>2007年現在では、歌舞伎以外の演劇も上演されている（松竹制作の新劇など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plays other than Kabuki, such as Shingeki (literally New Play) of Shochiku, are also staged as of 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, plays other than Kabuki such as Shingeki (literally &apos;New Play&apos;) created by Shochiku, are also staged (as of 2007).</e>
<cmt>Changed for punctuation and clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, plays other than Kabuki such as Shingeki (literally &apos;New Play&apos;) created by Shochiku, are also staged (as of 2007).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>現存する安土桃山時代文化の劇場建築は1929年に竣工、1991年に外観を残しつつ最新設備を備えた劇場として改装されたもので、登録有形文化財である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its present architecture in the style of the Azuchi-Momoyama Period is a Registered Tangible Cultural Property which was completed in 1929 and renovated in 1991 keeping its old exterior and equipped with the latest facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is in the style of the Azuchi-Momoyama Period and is a Registered Tangible Cultural Property, completed in 1929 and renovated in 1991 keeping its former exterior yet being equipped with the latest facilities.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity and grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is in the style of the Azuchi-Momoyama period and is a Registered Tangible Cultural Property, completed in 1929 and renovated in 1991 keeping its former exterior yet being equipped with the latest facilities.</e>
<cmt>Azuchi-Momoyama periodとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>〒605-0075 京都府京都市東山区四条通大和大路通西入中之町198</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">198 Shijo-dori Yamato-oji Nishiiru Nakano Cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture 605-0075</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">198 Shijo-dori Yamato-oji Nishiiru Nakano Cho, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture 605-0075</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">198 Nakano-cho, Shijo Street Yamatooji Street Nishi-iru, Higashiyama Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture 605-0075</e>
<cmt>仕様書に基づき住所表記を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>四条大橋東詰（四条川端東入る南側）に位置し、四条河原町から鴨川にかかる四条大橋を渡って八坂神社方面へ行く途中にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is at the east end of Shijo-ohashi Bridge (at the south side of Shijo-dori on the east side of the river), or you can find it on your way from Shijo Kawaramachi over Shijo-ohashi Bridge toward Yasaka-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is at the east end of Shijo-ohashi Bridge (at the south side of Shijo-dori on the east side of the river), or you can find it on your way from Shijo Kawaramachi over Shijo-ohashi Bridge toward Yasaka-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is at the east end of Shijo-ohashi Bridge (Minami-gawa, Shijo-Kawabata Higashi-iru), or you can find it on your way from Shijo Kawaramachi over Shijo-ohashi Bridge toward Yasaka-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>四条川端東入る南側→住所表記のため、Minami-gawa, Shijo-Kawabata Higashi-iruとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>最寄り駅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Closest railway stations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Closest railway stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Closest railway stations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>京阪電気鉄道 四条駅すぐ上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is just above Shijo Station of Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is just above Shijo Station on the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is just above Gion-shijo Station on the Keihan Electric Railway.</e>
<cmt>四条駅→「祇園四条駅」に変更されているため現在の名称に修正しました。(参照: http://www.okeihan.net/eki/detail.php?station_no=39)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>阪急電鉄 河原町駅徒歩3分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is three minutes on foot from Kawaramachi Station of Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is three minutes on foot from Kawaramachi Station on the Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is three minutes on foot from Kawaramachi Station on the Hankyu Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>定紋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emblem</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emblem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emblem</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>松竹マークが使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It uses the trademark of Shochiku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trademark of Shochiku is used as its emblem..</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trademark of Shochiku is used as its emblem.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドを削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tomomarusan(id:17060), Miyuki h(id:84952), Rusk(id:9895), Matsukaze(id:51778), ととりん(id:31982), COCKY(id:19672), こぶまき(id:38278), You-kan(id:33117), Savasa(id:118123), Memeja(id:110500), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>