<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>岡崎公園 (京都市)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okazaki-koen Park (Kyoto Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okazaki-koen Park (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>・「Prefecture」→「City」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okazaki-koen Park (Kyoto City)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>岡崎公園（おかざきこうえん）は、京都市左京区岡崎にある都市型の公園である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okazaki-koen Park (Kyoto Prefecture) was a urban-type park in Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okazaki-koen Park is an urban park in Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>・「(Kyoto Prefecture)」を削除・「was」→「is」・「a」→「an」・「urban-type」→「urban」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okazaki-koen Park is an urban park in Okazaki, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>六勝寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rikusho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rikusho-ji Temples</e>
<cmt>「Temple」→「Temples」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rikusho-ji Temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>この地は、平安時代に法勝寺等、六勝寺と総称される6ヶ寺の大寺が建立された故地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the place where six major temples that were collectively called the Hossho-ji Temple and Rikusho-ji Temple were built during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was here that the six great temples collectively known as the &quot;Rikusho-ji&quot; (lit. Six Victorious Temples) including Hossho-ji Temple were built during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was here that the six great temples collectively known as the &quot;Rikusho-ji&quot; (lit. Six Victorious Temples) including Hossho-ji Temple were built during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その名は、現在でも各寺の故地に町名となって残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their names have been remained until today as the name of towns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of each of these temples has remained as the name of the cho (district) located where the temple once stood.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of each of these temples has remained as the name of the cho (district) located where the temple once stood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内国博覧会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The National Exhibition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The National Exhibition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The National Exhibition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>壮麗を極めた往時の六勝寺の伽藍も、その後の戦乱で灰燼に帰してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pomp-filled Buddhist temple of Rikusho-ji Temple was burned to the ground through subsequent wars.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The magnificent Rikusho-ji temple complex was burned to the ground through subsequent wars.</e>
<cmt>・「pomp-filled」→「magnificent」・「Buddhist temple of Rikusho-ji Temple」→「Rikusho-ji temple complex」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The magnificent Rikusho-ji temple complex was burned to the ground through subsequent wars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幕末維新の頃には、岡崎には人家も疎らで、空き地が広がっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, there were only few houses, and fields were in every direction.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Meiji Restoration at the end of the Edo period, Okazaki consisted of only a few houses and vacant land.</e>
<cmt>翻訳漏れを修正、翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Meiji Restoration at the end of the Edo period, Okazaki consisted of only a few houses and vacant land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治時代、東側に隣接する蹴上の地域に、琵琶湖疏水が引かれ、日本初の水力発電所が建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Lake Biwa Canal was drawn to the Keage region adjacent to the east side, and the first hydroelectric power station in Japan was constructed.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, the Lake Biwa Canal was extended to the Keage area which bordered Okazaki to the east, and Japan&apos;s first hydroelectric power station was constructed.</e>
<cmt>・「drawn」→「extended」・「region」→「area」・「adjacent to the east side」→「which bordered Okazaki to the east」・「the first hydroelectric power station in Japan」→「Japan&apos;s first hydroelectric power station」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Lake Biwa Canal was extended to the Keage area which bordered Okazaki to the east, and Japan&apos;s first hydroelectric power station was constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>インクラインを利用した水運も発達すると、岡崎の地を琵琶湖疏水の本流が西流するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the transportation by water using Incline was developed, the mainstream of the Lake Biwa Canal was drawn to the west across the place of Okazaki.</e>
<cmt>一原文・一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the development of water transportation using inclines, the main trunk of the Lake Biwa Canal was drawn to the west across the Okazaki area.</e>
<cmt>・「After the transportation by water using Incline was develop」→「With the development of water transportation using inclines」・「mainstream」→「main trunk」・「place of Okazaki」→「Okazaki area」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the development of water transportation using inclines, the main trunk of the Lake Biwa Canal was drawn to the west across the Okazaki area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>こうして、疏水の北側の地域を会場として、内国博覧会が開催されるようなり、賑わいを取り戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the region on the north side of the canal was used for the venue of The National Exhibition, and it regained popularity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the area on the north side of the canal was used for the venue for The National Exhibition and regained prosperity.</e>
<cmt>・「region」→「area」・「of」→「for」・コンマを削除・「it」を削除・「popularity」→「prosperity」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the area on the north side of the canal was used for the venue for The National Exhibition and regained prosperity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その会場あとに造営されたのが、平安神宮であり、その他、文化施設も建設され、公園として整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the Heian-jingu Shrine that was built in the place that used to be the venue for the National Exhibition, and cultural facilities were additionally constructed, and was maintained as a park.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the exhibition, Heian-jingu Shrine was constructed on the former exhibition site, other cultural institutions were built, and the area was maintained as a park.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the exhibition, Heian-jingu Shrine was constructed on the former exhibition site, other cultural institutions were built, and the area was maintained as a park.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>文化施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural Institutions</e>
<cmt>・「facilities」→「Institutions」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural Institutions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>京都市美術館、京都国立近代美術館、京都会館、京都市勧業館（みやこめっせ）、岡崎グラウンド、京都府立図書館、京都市動物園、平安神宮など、京都の文化・観光・産業施設が集まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cultural facilities, tourist facilities, and industrial facilities of Kyoto such as Kyoto Municipal Museum of Art, The National Museum of Modern Art, Kyoto, Kyoto Kaikan Hall, Kyoto International Exhibition Hall (Miyako Messe), Okazaki baseball ground, Kyoto Prefectural Library, Kyoto City Zoo, and Heian-jingu Shrine are concentrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area is the location of Kyoto&apos;s cultural, tourism and industrial institutions including the Kyoto Municipal Museum of Art, National Museum of Modern Art, Kyoto, Kyoto Kaikan Hall, Kyoto International Exhibition Hall (Miyako Messe), Okazaki baseball ground, Kyoto Prefectural Library, Kyoto City Zoo, and Heian-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>再構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area is the location of Kyoto&apos;s cultural, tourism and industrial institutions including the Kyoto Municipal Museum of Art, National Museum of Modern Art, Kyoto, Kyoto Kaikan Hall, Kyoto International Exhibition Hall (Miyako Messe), Okazaki baseball ground, Kyoto Prefectural Library, Kyoto City Zoo, and Heian-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>公園の南端、西端には、琵琶湖から引かれた琵琶湖疎水の水路がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The canal drawn from the Lake Biwa Canal was at the southern and the western tip of the park..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the southern and western extremes of the park are the Lake Biwa Canal waterway dug from Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the southern and western extremes of the park are the Lake Biwa Canal waterway dug from Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>この広範なエリアをしばしば岡崎公園と呼ぶが、狭義には、同名の公園が平安神宮の南側にあり、テニスコートが隣接している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This wide area is often called the Okazaki-koen Park, but in a narrow sense, the other park adjacent to the tennis court with the same name was located on the south side of Heian-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This wider area is often called Okazaki-koen Park, but the park with this name is more narrowly defined as the park located on the southern side of Heian-jingu Shrine, adjacent to the tennis courts.</e>
<cmt>原文を反映するように翻訳し直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This wider area is often called Okazaki-koen Park, but the park with this name is more narrowly defined as the park located on the southern side of Heian-jingu Shrine, adjacent to the tennis courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mooko(id:36162), Mishika(id:276), Tatata(id:110870), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>