<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土間</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doma (literally, earth floor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doma (literally, earth floor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doma (earthen floor)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>土間（どま）とは日本建築に於ける家屋内の一部を構成する間取りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doma is a space constituting the inside of a Japanese style house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A doma is a space constituting the inside of a Japanese-style house.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A doma is a space constituting the inside of a Japanese-style house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の伝統的な民家や納屋の屋内空間は、人間の生活面が柱によって地面より高くしつらえられ、木の板などが敷かれた「床（ゆか）」という装置が敷かれた部分と、地面と同じ高さの部分とに分けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inner space of a traditional private Japanese house or barn consits of the area where the living space is placed above the ground by using so-called &quot;yuka,&quot; flat wooden plates or something like that which are supported by pillars, and the area that is placed on the ground level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inner space of a traditional private Japanese house or barn consists of the area where the living space is placed above the ground by using so-called &quot;yuka&quot; (flat wooden plates) or something similar, which are supported by pillars, and the area that is placed at ground level.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inner space of a traditional private Japanese house or storehouse consists of an area called &quot;yuka&quot; where living space is placed above the ground using flat wooden plates supported by pillars, and an area that is placed at ground level.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションマークを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この後者が土間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter area consititutes a doma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter area constitutes a doma.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter area constitutes a doma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>土間の仕上げには、三和土（漆喰を塗り固めた床）、珪藻土、コンクリート・タイルなどが用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For finishing a doma, tataki (a floor hard-packed with plaster, diatomite or concrete tiles9 are used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For finishing a doma, a tataki (a floor hard-packed with plaster, diatomite or concrete tiles) is used.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tataki (a floor hard-packed with plaster), diatomite or concrete tiles are used for finishing a doma,</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>古い民家では単純に地面が露出している屋内の場所に過ぎない様式のものもあり、この辺りが語源といえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In old private houses, an area sometimes exists where earth is simply exposed, and this would be the origin of this term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In old private houses, there is sometimes an area where the earth is simply exposed, and this would be the origin of the term.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In old private houses, there is sometimes an area where the earth is simply exposed, and this would be the origin of the term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>地面とほぼ同じ高さで、生活空間である廊下・居間・寝室といったようなその他の部屋よりも一段低くなっており、屋外と連絡するための・人が出入りする、大きく開く扉ないし引き戸が必ず設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is placed almost at the ground level and lower than the other rooms constituting the living space, such as passages, a living room and bed rooms, and wide doors or sliding doors are always provided for it to connect the insdie and outside of the house, enabling persons to enter or exit from the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is placed nearly at ground level and lower than the other rooms constituting the living space, such as passages, a living room and bedrooms, and wide doors or sliding doors are always provided for it to connect the inside and outside of the house, enabling persons to enter or exit the area.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is placed nearly at ground level and lower than the other rooms constituting living space, such as corridors, living room and bedrooms, and wide doors or sliding doors are always built to allow people to come and go between the inside and outside of the house.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以下に述べるが、現在では縮小化されたものが同じように呼ばれているが、本来は「地面と同じ扱いの屋内の部屋」という性格があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described below, although now the same term is also used for itsscaled-down versions, it originaly had the nature of &quot;a indoor room used in the same way as for ground.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described below, although now the same term is also used for its scaled-down versions, it originally had the nature of &quot;an indoor room used in the same way as for the ground.&quot;</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described below, although the same term is now used for a scaled-down version, it originally had the nature of &quot;an indoor room used in the same way as the ground.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションマークを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>用途上、防水性があるものが使われることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering usage, water-proofing materials are mostly used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the purpose of use, water-resistant materials are generally employed.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water-resistant materials are generally employed considering the purpose of use,</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>現代では旧家などに伝統的な形態のものが多く保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, many traditional style doma are preserved, for example, in houses for old established families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, many traditional-style doma are preserved, for example, in houses for old established families.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, many traditional-style doma are preserved in houses of old established families.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>日本の民家は古来柱に支えられた高床式の床敷き部分と、土間の部分が対等な存在であり、この二つの要素が一つの建築物として結合した形態が基本となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In private Japanes houses, the raised foor area supported by pillars and the doma area were valued equally from ancient times, and connecting these two factors constitutes the basic style of these houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In private Japanese houses, the raised floor area supported by pillars and the doma area have been valued equally ancient times, and connecting these two factors constitutes the basic style of such houses.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In private Japanese houses, the raised floor area supported by pillars and the doma area have been valued equally since ancient times, and connecting these two factors constitutes the basic style of such houses.</e>
<cmt>古来　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>両者の結合部位の要の部分にある柱が大黒柱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillar placed at the important position connecting these two parts is called a daikoku-bashira (central pollar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillar placed at the critical position connecting these two parts is called a daikoku-bashira (central pillar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillar placed at the critical position connecting these two parts is called a daikoku-bashira (central pillar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>現代の民家建築では、土間は単なる屋外と屋内の境にある玄関の狭小な空間に縮小している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contemporary private house buildings, a doma was reduced only to a small space in the entrance hall provided at a boundary between the inside and outside of a house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contemporary private houses, a doma was reduced to a small space in the entrance hall provided at a boundary between the inside and outside of the house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contemporary private houses, the doma has become reduced to a small space in the entrance hall provided and is simply at the boundary between the inside and outside of the house.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>単純に靴を脱ぐための場所と位置付けられ、伝統的な土間の重要な機能であった生業の作業空間という要素は、生活家屋内から排除されていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is positioned as a place simply for taking off shoes, and the factor that it provides a work space for gaining earings, constituting an important function of traditional doma, is mostly excluded from the living quarters in the house.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is positioned as a place simply to remove shoes, and the fact that it provides a work space for gaining earnings, constituting an important function of the traditional doma, is generally excluded from the living quarters in the house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is simply a place to remove shoes and the important function of the traditional doma, which was to provide work space for gaining earnings, is now generally excluded from the living quarters in the house.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>現代では農家や手工業者のように、伝統的に土間で行われていた作業を家内産業として営む者は、庭など屋外の別空間を簡易的な屋根で覆うことにより、その役割を代替する事が多くなっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the persons who traditionally did their work on the doma of their own houses, such as farmers and craftmen, have more and more become to replace the doma function with an outdoor space, for example, in their yards, which is covered with a simplified roof.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the person who traditionally did his work in the doma of his own house, such as a farmer or a craftsman, would have increasingly come to replace the doma function with an outdoor space, such as in the yard, which would be covered with a simple roof.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, people who traditionally did their work in the doma of their own house, such as farmers and craftsmen, have increasingly come to replace the role of doma with a separate outdoor space, such as the yard, covered with a simple roof.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>旧来のものは作業場として十二分な広さを持つ場所であったが、現在のものでは広くて半畳程度（住宅規模によっても異なる）の玄関の付帯物扱いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An original doma has a space wide enough for doing work there, but the sizes of the comtemporaty ones become around 0.825 square meters at the most (depending on the size of a house), and a doma has become a part of an entrance hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An original doma has a space wide enough to allow work, but the sizes of contemporary ones become around 0.825 square meters at the most (depending on the size of the house), and the doma has become a part of the entrance hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original doma has a space wide enough to allow work, but contemporary ones are considered part of the entrance hall, which is around 0.825 square meters at most (depending on the size of the house).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>主な用途</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major usages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major usages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major usages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>土間は戸外と屋内の中間的な場所にあたり、日本家屋では「屋内では靴を脱ぐ」という生活習慣があるが、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A doma is positioned as a place intermediate between outdoors and indoors, and Japanese have a living habit of &quot;taking off shoes indoors&quot; in Japanese houses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A doma is positioned as a place intermediate between the outdoors and indoors, and the Japanese have a living habit of &quot;taking off shoes indoors&quot; in their houses.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The doma is positioned as a place intermediate between outdoor and indoor, and it is a custom in Japanese houses &quot;to take off shoes indoors.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。クォーテーションマークを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>土間に限っては土足のままでもかまわない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was allowed to enter doma alone without taking off shoes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was permissible to enter the doma alone without taking off one&apos;s shoes.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was permissible to enter the doma alone without taking off one&apos;s shoes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このため現代住宅でも「靴を履いたり脱いだりする場所」という位置付けで存続している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the doma continues existing as a place where shoes are to be taken off or on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the doma continues to exist as a place where shoes are to be taken off or put on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the doma continues to exist as a place where shoes are to be taken off or put on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>日本家屋の玄関、学校の昇降口も、土間の一種と考えることも出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The entance halls of Japanese houses and the entrance/exit places of schools are also considered to be a kind of doma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The entrance halls of Japanese houses and the entrances/exits of schools are also considered to be doma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The entrance halls of Japanese houses and the entrances/exits of schools are also considered to be doma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>土間は基本的に戸外と同じ扱いであるため、一時的に土間に下りる場合でも、サンダルなど簡易的な履物をはく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since a doma is handled as an outdoor place, a simple footwear is taken on even when descending to a doma temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a doma is treated as an outdoor place, a simple footwear is put on, even when descending to a doma temporarily.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a doma is treated as an outdoor place, even if descending to a doma temporarily, simple footwear such as sandals are put on.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。is を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>作業場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Woring place</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A working place</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Working place</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>雨天などの際に農機具や漁具の手入れを行う作業場として活用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, when it rains, a doma is used as a place for maintaining agricultural machines or fishing gear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, during periods of rain a doma is used as a place in which to maintain agricultural machines or fishing gear.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The doma is used as a work place to take care of agricultural machines or fishing gear on rainy days.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>数畳から十数畳程度の広さを持ち、ござやすのこを敷いて座ったり、あるいは靴を脱いでそれらの上に立ったりもする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A doma is provided with a space of several joes (approx. 1.65 square meters per jo) to ten plus several joes, and people sit on a straw mat or sunoko (a board made of horizontarily placed thin plates) placed on the doma, or take off their shoes and stand on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A doma is provided with a space of several joes (approx. 1.65 square meters per jo) to ten-odd joes; people will sit on a straw mat or sunoko (a board made of thin plates positioned horizontally) placed on the doma, or will take off their shoes and stand on it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The doma provided a space of several joes (approx. 1.65 square meters per jo) to about 15 joes and people would sit on a straw mat or sunoko (a board made of thin plates positioned horizontally) or take off their shoes to stand on it.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>ごみや埃の出易い作業をする上で、掃除の簡単に済ませられる土間を利用したと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that, in doing the work in which lots of trash and dust was generated, use of a doma was considered to make it easier to clean up the trash and dust generated there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that, in doing the work in which considerable trash and dust was generated, the use of a doma was thought to make it easier to clean up the trash and dust thus generated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that the use of a doma convenient for cleaning up after doing tasks that generate trash and dust.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その一方で古い農村部の日本家屋では、板の間がそのまま生活居住空間で作業場所は特別に設置しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in Japanese houses in villages in old times, a room with a wooden floor was used for daily household activities and no specific work place was provided indoors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the Japanese houses of villages in old times, a room with a wooden floor was used for daily household activities but no specific workplace was provided indoors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in old Japanese houses of agricultural villages, the room with a wooden floor was used for daily household activities and there was no designated workplace.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのため、汎用性のあるスペースとして利用されていたようだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it seems that a doma was used as a general-purpose place in these houses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it seems that the doma was used as a general-purpose place in such houses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the doma was probably used as a general-purpose area in such houses.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、伝統的農村家屋では用途によって板をはめて板の間として使用したり、板をはずして土間として使用したりするスペースが設けられていることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in some traditional houses in rural areas, there was a place used sometimes as a wooden floor room by laying wooden plates there wall to wall or some other times as a doma by removing these plates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in some traditional houses in rural areas, there was a place used sometimes as a wooden floor room by laying wooden plates there wall to wall or some other times as a doma by removing these plates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a space which can be used as a wooden floor room by laying wooden plates but also used as a doma without the wooden plates are found in some traditional houses in rural areas.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>炊事場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitchens</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitchens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitchens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>調理では火や水を多く使うことから、床が腐る心配がない・燃え移るものの少ない土間が必然的に利用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A doma was naturally used for cooking, because use of a doma made it unnecessary to worry about that the foor might be rotten and there were few flammable things in a doma as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A doma was naturally used for cooking because the use of a doma made it unnecessary to worry that the floor might be rotten, and there were few flammable items in a doma as well.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the doma floor cannot rot and has few flammable items, the doma was naturally used for cooking, which requires much water and fire.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また竈など火を使う設備を設置する上でも、土間の方が設置がし易く、火災予防の観点からも有効である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a doma is a place where fire-using equipment, such as a furnance, can be installed more easily, and is also a place effective from the viewpoint of fire prevention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, a doma is a place where flame-generating, such as a furnace, can be installed more easily, and it&apos;s also effective from the standpoint of fire prevention.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, flame-generating equipment, such as a furnace, could be installed more easily in the doma and this is also effective from the standpoint of fire prevention.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この為旧家などは炊事場が土間となっている事が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in many old established familiy houses, their kitchens are placed on a doma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the kitchens of many old established family houses are placed on doma.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the kitchens of many old established family houses are located at the doma.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>伝統的な農村家屋では、便所や風呂は母屋から離れた別小屋になっていることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many traditional houses in rural areas, the lavatory and bathing place are placed in a hut separated from the main building.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many traditional houses in rural areas, the lavatory and bathing place are placed in a hut that stands apart from the main building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many traditional rural houses, the lavatory and bathing place are located in a hut separate from the main building.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>炊事場に関しても、母屋の中ではなく外に設置し、屋根をかけて作っているケースも少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in not a few such houses, the kitchen is also installed at a roofed place outside of the main building,.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in many such houses the kitchen is also installed at a roofed place outside the main building,.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kitchen is also located at a roofed place outside the main building.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>構造的には軒下の一種であるが、風雨を避けるための簡易的な壁を回しているため、屋外なのか屋内なのか、判断が難しいところである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structurally, the kichen is an under-eaves type, but because simplified walls were provided around it, it is difficult to judge whether the kitchen is placed outdoors or indoors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structurally, the kichen is an under-eaves type, but because simplified walls were provided around it, it is difficult to judge whether the kitchen is placed outdoors or indoors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kitchen is a type of under-eave structure, but because simple walls surround it, it is difficult to judge whether the kitchen is outdoors or indoors.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>こうした構造から、炊事場を釜屋（かまや）と呼ぶ地方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With such a structure provided, a kitchen is called a kamaya (furnance hut) in some regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With such a structure provided, a kitchen is called a kamaya (furnace hut) in some regions.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kitchen is called kamaya (furnace hut) in some regions because fo such structure.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>軍艦島の集合住宅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collective buildings in the Gunkan-jima Island</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collective buildings of Gunkan-jima Island</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collective buildings of Gunkan-jima Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>端島 (長崎県)（長崎県）の集合住宅は密集した団地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collective buildings in Hashima Island (located in Nagasaki Prefecture) are a densely-built housing complex.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collective buildings of Hashima Island (located in Nagasaki Prefecture) comprise a densely built housing complex.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collective housing in Hashima Island (Nagasaki Prefecture) is a densely built housing complex.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかしながら、作られた時代を反映して玄関に土間に相当する広い空間をもつものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, reflecting the age when it was built, some of the dwelling units were provided with a rather spacious area equivalent to a doma in their entrance halls</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, reflecting the age when it was built, some of the dwelling units were provided with a rather spacious area equivalent to a doma in their entrance halls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, reflecting the age when it was built, some of the dwelling units have a rather spacious area equivalent to a doma in their entrance halls.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、ビルであるにも関わらず地面から床面までの段差を大きくしてあるなど、過渡期の姿をとどめている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In additio, although they are large buildings, the step between the surface of that spacious area and the gound level is made large, keeping the style employed in the transitional period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, although they&apos;re large buildings, the step between the surface of that spacious area and the ground level is made large, thus retaining the style employed during the transitional period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, although they are large buildings, there is a large difference in the height between the ground level and the floor level, thus showing a transitional style.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Youtetsu(id:7844), Tawashi2006(id:95112), Sina(id:10021), Okztosh(id:27983), Muyo(id:14948), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Toto-tarou(id:16648), Yatobi(id:9686), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>