<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>角屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>角屋（すみや）はもと京都、嶋原遊廓の揚屋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiya was originally ageya of Shimabara Yukaku (redlight district).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiya was originally an ageya of Shimabara Yukaku (red-light district).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiya was originally an ageya of Shimabara Yukaku (red-light district).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>天正17年（1589年）、豊臣秀吉によって柳馬場二条に遊郭「柳町」が開かれ、初代徳右衛門が角屋の営業を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI started yukaku, &quot;Yanagimachi&quot; in Yanaginobanba Nijo, and first Tokuemon launched business of Sumiya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI started a yukaku, &quot;Yanagimachi,&quot; in Yanaginobanba Nijo, and the first Tokuemon launched the Sumiya business.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI started a yukaku, &quot;Yanagimachi,&quot; in Yanaginobanba Nijo, and the first Tokuemon launched the Sumiya business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>慶長7年（1602年）、柳町は突然の移転を強いられ、角屋も六条三筋町へ移動を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1602, Yanagimachi was abruptly forced to move out, and Sumiya had no other option but to move to Rokujo Misuji machi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1602, Yanagimachi was abruptly forced to move out, so Sumiya had no choice but to move to Rokujo Misuji machi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1602, Yanagimachi was abruptly forced to move out, so Sumiya had no choice but to move to Rokujo Misuji machi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>更に寛永18年（1641年）、再度柳町は移転となり、角屋は二代目徳右衛門によって現在地の嶋原へ移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in 1641, Yanagimachi was forced to move again, and second Tokuemon moved Sumiya to Shimabara where it is currently located.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in 1641 Yanagimachi was forced to move again, and the second Tokuemon moved Sumiya to Shimabara, where it is currently located.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in 1641 Yanagimachi was forced to move again, and the second Tokuemon moved Sumiya to Shimabara, where it is currently located.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>尚、六条三筋町の所在地（新町五条下ル）は現在も角屋が所有している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiya still owns its building in Rokujo Misuji machi (Shinmachi Gojo Kudaru).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiya still owns its building in Rokujo Misuji machi (Shinmachi Gojo Kudaru).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiya still owns its building in Rokujo Misuji machi (Shinmachi Gojo Kudaru).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>明治5年（1872年）まで営業した後、お茶屋に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It conitnued its business until 1872, when it was incorporated into Ochaya.</e>
<cmt>お茶屋→[定訳不明]Ochaya</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The business continued until 1872, when it was incorporated into Ochaya.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The business continued until 1872, when it was incorporated into Ochaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>昭和60年（1985年）まで「松の間」を宴会に使用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its &quot;Matsuno-ma Room&quot; had been used for banquets until 1985.</e>
<cmt>松の間→[定訳不明]Matsuno-ma Room（松の間） 下記の焼失の記事と矛盾しますが，立て直し等の記述がないので，そのまま訳しました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its &quot;Matsuno-ma&quot; room was used for banquets until 1985.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its &quot;Matsuno-ma&quot; room was used for banquets until 1985.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>昭和27年（1952年）、嶋原が開かれて以来現存する唯一の揚屋の遺構として国の重要文化財に指定された（ただし「松の間」のみは大正末期、火事により焼失してしまい指定されていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1952, Sumiya&apos;s building was designated as a national Important Cultural Property by the government based on the fact that it was the only surviving building of ageya that was built when Sumiya moved to Shimabara (except for &quot;Matsuno-ma Room&quot; which was destroyed by fire at the end of Taisho Era).</e>
<cmt>前記の　1985年まで「松の間」を使用した，という記述に矛盾しますが，原文の通りに訳しました．</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1952, Sumiya&apos;s building was designated as a national important cultural property by the government, based on the fact that it was the only surviving ageya structure that was built when Sumiya moved to Shimabara (except for the Matsuno-ma room, which was destroyed by fire at the end of the Taisho period).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1952, Sumiya&apos;s building was designated as a national important cultural property by the government, based on the fact that it was the only surviving ageya structure that was built when Sumiya moved to Shimabara (except for the Matsuno-ma room, which was destroyed by fire at the end of the Taisho period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>平成元年（1989年）より1日30人限定で内部を公開していたが、更に平成10年（1998年）4月より「角屋もてなしの文化美術館」として開館された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had been open to public since 1989, up to 30 visitors a day, and in April 1998, it was opened as a cultural art museum, SUMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had been open to the public since 1989, receiving up to 30 visitors a day, and in April 1998 it was opened as SUMIYA, a cultural art museum.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had been open to the public since 1989, receiving up to 30 visitors a day, and in April 1998 it was opened as SUMIYA, a cultural art museum.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>平成19年（2007年）現在家名は十四代目に継承されており、当代が館長を勤めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2007, the fourteenth family head has succeeded the family name, and he is the head curator of the museum.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2007, the fourteenth family head has succeeded to the family name, and he serves as the museum&apos;s head curator.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2007, the fourteenth family head has succeeded to the family name, and he serves as the museum&apos;s head curator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現在一般公開は1階部分のみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, only the first floor is open to general bublic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, only the first floor is open to the general public.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, only the first floor is open to the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>損傷部分の保存を考え、2階座敷見学には事前予約が必要となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To see sashiki on the second floor, you are required to make advanced reservations, because preservation of damaged parts is planned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An advance reservation is required in order to see the sashiki on the second floor, considering the planned restoration of damaged portions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An advance reservation is required in order to see the zashiki on the second floor, considering the planned preservation of damaged portions.</e>
<cmt>sashiki -&gt; zashikirestoration -&gt; preservationとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>所蔵品は約1万1千点にのぼる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its collection includes as many as 11 thousand items.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its collection includes as many as 11,000 items.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its collection includes as many as 11,000 items.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>江戸時代中期には島原でも俳諧が盛んになり当時の角屋当主（七代目、俳名徳屋）は与謝蕪村を師として招いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle period of Edo Era, Haikai, or seventeen-syllable verse, became popular in Shimabara, and the head of Sumiya then (seventh head, Haimyo Tokuya) invited Buson YOSA as a teacher of Haikai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid-Edo period, haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) became popular in Shimabara, and the head of Sumiya (the seventh head, Haimyo Tokuya) invited Buson YOSA as a teacher of haikai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid-Edo period, haikai (seventeen-syllable verse) became popular in Shimabara, and the head of Sumiya (the seventh head, Haimyo Tokuya) invited Buson YOSA as a teacher of haikai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その蕪村がここに残した「紅白梅図」は国の重要文化財として当美術館に展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This museum exhibits &quot;Kohaku Bai Zu&quot; as a national Important Cultural Property which was drawn and left here by Buson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This museum exhibits &quot;Kohaku Bai Zu,&quot; which was drawn and left here by Buson, as a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This museum exhibits &quot;Kohaku Bai Zu&quot; (Red and White Plum Blossoms), which was drawn and left here by Buson, as a national important cultural property.</e>
<cmt>(Red and White Plum Blossoms)を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>他、天明年間前後に制作された円山応挙、石田幽汀などの襖絵も残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection also includes decorated fusuma doors drawn by Okyo MARUYAMA and Yutei ISHIDA in Tnmei Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection also includes decorated fusuma doors drawn by Okyo MARUYAMA and Yutei ISHIDA in the Tnmei period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection also includes decorated fusuma doors drawn by Okyo MARUYAMA and Yutei ISHIDA in the Tnmei period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>幕末には久坂玄瑞、西郷隆盛などの勤王の志士が密議を交わしたり、豪商からの資金調達のために接待に使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Bakumatsu, Genzui KUSAKA, Takamori SAIGO and other royalist political reformers called Kino no Shishi used Sumiya to hold secret meetings or to entertain rich merchants for fund raising.</e>
<cmt>勤王の志士→[定訳不明]Kino no Shishi→[定訳不明]royalist political reformers</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Bakumatsu, Genzui KUSAKA, Takamori SAIGO and other royalist political reformers called &quot;Kino no Shishi&quot; used Sumiya to hold secret meetings or entertain wealthy merchants for the purpose of fundraising.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Bakumatsu, Genzui KUSAKA, Takamori SAIGO and other royalist political reformers called &quot;Kino no Shishi&quot; used Sumiya to hold secret meetings or entertain wealthy merchants for the purpose of fundraising.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、新選組もここでの遊興を楽しんだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsengumi members also enjoyed entertainment here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsengumi members also enjoyed entertainment here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsengumi members also enjoyed entertainment here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>特に芹沢鴨との関わり合いは深く、文久3年（1863年）6月ここで角屋での暴挙をはたらき、その際に出来た刀傷が今でも残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, Kamo SERIZAWA&apos;s involvement in Sumiya was serious, and his violent behavior here at Sumiya in June, 1863 made some sword-cuts on its furniture which remains today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, Kamo SERIZAWA&apos;s involvement in Sumiya was serious, and his violent behavior here at Sumiya in June 1863 resulted in some sword cuts on the furniture, which can still be seen today.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, Kamo SERIZAWA&apos;s involvement in Sumiya was serious, and his violent behavior here at Sumiya in June 1863 resulted in some sword cuts on the furniture, which can still be seen today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、芹沢が殺害される直前にここで酒宴を開いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SERIZAWA gave a feast here immediately before he was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SERIZAWA gave a feast here immediately before he was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SERIZAWA gave a feast here immediately before he was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>中には名物の「臥龍松」という枝の長い松が生えていたが枯れてしまい、現在は2代目にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A famous long pine tree like a lying dragon called &quot;Gayumatsu&quot; was once in its compound, but it died and another pine tree has replaced it to the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A famous long pine tree reminiscent of a reclining dragon, called &quot;Gayumatsu,&quot; was once in its compound, but it died and was replaced by another pine, which still exists today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A famous long pine tree reminiscent of a reclining dragon, called &quot;Gayumatsu,&quot; was once in its compound, but it died and was replaced by another pine, which still exists today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MD242(id:11277), K-kazumasa(id:9265), BAKU(id:55205), 上田隼人(id:23104), 今紫(id:9521), Reggaeman(id:6214), Moraykaita(id:125554), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>