<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>同志社大学今出川校地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha University Imadegawa-kochi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha University Imadegawa-kochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha University Imadegawa-kochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>同志社大学今出川校地（どうししゃだいがくいまでがわこうち）は同志社大学のキャンパス。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha University Imadegawa-kochi is the campus of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha University Imadegawa-kochi is the campus of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha University Imadegawa-kochi is the campus of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>同志社大学ではキャンパスのことを「校地」と呼んでいるため、この記事の名称も今出川校地となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Doshisha University calls its campus &quot;kochi&quot;, Imadegawa-kochi is used as the title of this article.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Doshisha University calls its campus &quot;kochi&quot;, Imadegawa-kochi is used as the title of this article.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Doshisha University calls its campus &apos;kochi,&apos; Imadegawa-kochi is used as the title of this article.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>今出川校地は旧薩摩藩邸の跡地で、隣接して冷泉家時雨亭文庫がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imadegawa-kochi was the site of Satsuma domain&apos;s residence in the past, and Reizeike Shiguretei Bunko is located adjacently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imadegawa-kochi was the site of the Satsuma domain residence in the past, and Reizeike Shiguretei Bunko is located adjacently.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imadegawa-kochi was the site of the Satsuma domain residence in the past, and Reizeike Shiguretei Bunko (Shiguretei bunko library of the Reizei family) is located adjacently.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、南に京都御所、北に相国寺がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Kyoto Imperial Palace and Shokoku-ji Temple are located its south and north side respectively.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the Kyoto Imperial Palace and Shokoku-ji Temple are located at its north and south sides respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the Kyoto Imperial Palace and Shokoku-ji Temple are located at its north and south sides respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>今出川校地内では同志社礼拝堂、クラーク記念館など、5棟が国の重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five buildings located at Imadegawa-kochi, including Doshisha Chapel and Clarke Memorial Hall, are designated as national important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five buildings located at Imadegawa-kochi, including Doshisha Chapel and Clarke Memorial Hall, are designated as national important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five buildings located at Imadegawa-kochi, including Doshisha Chapel and Clarke Memorial Hall, are designated as national important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これらの建物は現在でも講義・事務所・礼拝等に使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These buildings are being used for lecture, office and worship even at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These buildings are being used for lectures, offices, and worship even at present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These buildings are being used for lectures, offices, and worship even at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>校地内には同志社中学校が存在しているが、2010年度に岩倉校地にある同志社高等学校との統合と中学校跡地を大学が利用することが決定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Junior High School is currently located at Imadegawa-kochi, but the decision was made to integrate it with Doshisha High School, which is located at Iwakura-kochi, in 2010 and use the site of junior high school for university&apos;s facility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Junior High School is currently located at Imadegawa-kochi, but the decision was made to integrate it with Doshisha High School, which is located at Iwakura-kochi, in 2010 and use the site of junior high school for the university&apos;s facility.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Junior High School is currently located at Imadegawa-kochi, but the decision was made to integrate it with Doshisha High School, which is located at Iwakura-kochi, in 2010 and use the site of junior high school for the university&apos;s facility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、同志社女子大学今出川校地、同志社幼稚園、同志社女子中学校・高等学校が隣接。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts Imadegawa-kochi, Doshisha Kindergarten and Doshisha Girl&apos;s Junior &amp; Senior High School are also located adjacently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts Imadegawa-kochi, Doshisha Kindergarten and Doshisha Girl&apos;s Junior &amp; Senior High School are also located adjacently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Women&apos;s College of Liberal Arts Imadegawa-kochi, Doshisha Kindergarten and Doshisha Girl&apos;s Junior and Senior High School are also located adjacently.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>今出川・同志社大学新町校地・同志社大学室町校地の3校地は近接しており、ほぼ一体として利用されており、3校地を併せて今出川校地と呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Doshisha University&apos;s Imadegawa-kochi, Shinmachi-kochi and Muromachi-kochi are located in proximity, these three campuses are being used in an integrated fashon and they are often collectively called Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Doshisha University&apos;s Imadegawa-kochi, Shinmachi-kochi and Muromachi-kochi are located in proximity, these three campuses are being used in an integrated fashon and they are often collectively called Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Doshisha University&apos;s Imadegawa-kochi, Shinmachi-kochi and Muromachi-kochi are located in proximity, these three campuses are being used in an integrated fashion and they are often collectively called Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>同志社大学の前身・同志社英学校時代以来の校地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was initially the campus of Doshisha English School, the predecessor of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was initially the campus of Doshisha English School, the predecessor of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was initially the campus of Doshisha English School, the predecessor of Doshisha University.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕末の1862年以降この地（当時は相国寺二本松と呼ばれた）には薩摩藩京都藩邸が置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1862, the end of Edo period, Kyoto residence of Satsuma domain was located at this place (this place was called Shokoku-ji Temple Nihonmatsu at the time).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since 1862, the end of the Edo period, the Kyoto residence of the Satsuma domain was located at this place (this place was called Shokoku-ji Temple Nihonmatsu at the time).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since 1862, the end of the Edo period, the Kyoto residence of the Satsuma domain was located at this place (this place was called Shokoku-ji Temple Nihonmatsu at the time).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>洋学者・山本覚馬（のち同志社英学校の創立者・新島襄の義兄・協力者となる）が明治維新の混乱の中で藩邸跡地を購入していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the state of confusion resulted from Meiji Restoration, Western learning scholar Kakuma YAMAMOTO (the brother-in- law and collaborator of Jo NIIJIMA, the founder of Doshisha English School) purchased the site of domain&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the state of confusion resulting from the Meiji Restoration, Western learning scholar Kakuma YAMAMOTO (the brother-in- law and collaborator of Jo NIIJIMA, the founder of Doshisha English School) purchased the site of the domain&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the state of confusion resulting from the Meiji Restoration, Western learning scholar Kakuma YAMAMOTO (the older brother-in-law and collaborator of Jo NIIJIMA, the founder of Doshisha English School) purchased the site of the domain&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除、補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同志社英学校が1875年11月29日に開校した時には京都市上京区寺町丸太町上ルの高松保実の屋敷（現在は新島旧邸）の一角を借り、教室として寄宿舎として利用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Doshisha English School was opened on November 29, 1875, it rented a part of Sasuzane TAKAMATSU&apos;s residence (current Niijima&apos;s former residence) for classrooms and dormitories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Doshisha English School was opened on November 29, 1875, it rented a part of Sasuzane TAKAMATSU&apos;s residence (current Niijima&apos;s former residence) for classrooms and dormitories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Doshisha English School was opened on November 29, 1875, it rented a part of Sasuzane TAKAMATSU&apos;s residence (current Niijima&apos;s former residence) for classrooms and dormitories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのおよそ半年後の1876年山本からの寄贈をうけた現・今出川校地に建物が竣工し英学校が移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1876, about a half year after its opening, the land of current Imadegawa-kochi was donated by Yamamoto and the school constructed buildings and moved there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1876, about a half year after opening, the land of the current Imadegawa-kochi was donated by Yamamoto and the school moved there and constructed buildings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1876, about a half year after opening, the land of the current Imadegawa-kochi was donated by Yamamoto and the school moved there and constructed buildings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>当初は2棟（第一寮､第二寮）の建物で1階を教室、2階を寄宿舎として使用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two buildings (first building, second building) initially, and the first floor was used as classrooms while the second floor was used as dormitories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two buildings (first building, second building) initially, and the first floor was used as classrooms while the second floor was used as dormitories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two buildings (first dormitory, second dormitory) initially, and the first floor was used as classrooms while the second floor was used as dormitories.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、同志社はキリスト教主義であるが、当時の京都ではキリスト教を排除する傾向にあり、住民の反対運動が相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Doshisha was a school which believed in Christianity, opposition movements were vigorously organized by residents since the social environment in Kyoto was not in favor of Christianity at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Doshisha was a school that believed in Christianity, opposition movements were vigorously organized by residents since the social environment in Kyoto was not in favor of Christianity at the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Doshisha was a school that believed in Christianity, opposition movements were vigorously organized by residents since the social environment in Kyoto was not in favor of Christianity at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、今出川校地において教育を行う際に聖書を教えてはいけないとの契約を京都府とも結んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the school concluded the agreement with Kyoto Prefecture which prohibited it from teaching Bible at Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, the school concluded an agreement with Kyoto Prefecture which prohibited it from teaching the Bible at Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the school concluded an agreement with Kyoto Prefecture which prohibited it from teaching the Bible at Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そこで新島襄は現在のアーモスト館あたりにあった元豆腐屋を新島名義で買い上げ、学校外のその場所で聖書を教えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Jo NIIJIMA bought a bean curd shop located near current Amherst House under his name and taught Bible at this place instead of at school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Jo NIIJIMA bought a bean curd shop located near current Amherst House under his name and taught the Bible at this place instead of at the school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Jo NIIJIMA bought a bean curd shop located near current Amherst House under his name and taught the Bible at this place instead of at the school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、実際には学校内で聖書を教えていたところを京都府の役員に発見されて新島が始末書を書いたこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, however, there was a case where the scene of teaching Bible at school was found by an official of Kyoto Prefecture and Niijima wrote a letter of apology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, however, there was a case where teaching the Bible at school was discovered by an official of Kyoto Prefecture and Niijima wrote a letter of apology.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, however, there was a case where teaching the Bible at school was discovered by an official of Kyoto Prefecture and Niijima wrote a letter of apology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>レンガ造りの建物がほとんどを占める同志社の建物だが最初に建てられたものは木造であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although current buildings of Doshisha are mostly brick-build ones, the original buildings were wooden buildings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although current buildings of Doshisha are mostly brick, the original buildings were wooden.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although current buildings of Doshisha are mostly brick, the original buildings were wooden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>同志社に初めて登場するレンガ造りの建物は1884年に完成したアメリカン・ボードより寄付された彰栄館（京都で現存する最古のレンガ造り）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha&apos;s first brick-build building was Shoei-kan (the oldest brick-build building in existence in Kyoto), which was completed in 1884 and donated by the American Board.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha&apos;s first brick building was Shoei-kan (the oldest brick building in existence in Kyoto), completed in 1884 and donated by the American Board.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha&apos;s first brick building was Shoeikan (the oldest brick building in existence in Kyoto), completed in 1884 and donated by the American Board.</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>第二寮はその後1970年代に京田辺校地に移築された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second building was moved and reconstructed at Kyotanabe-kochi in 1970&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second building was moved and reconstructed at Kyotanabe-kochi in 1970&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second dormitory was moved and reconstructed at Kyotanabe-kochi in 1970&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>使用学部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faculties using Imadegawa-kochi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faculties using Imadegawa-kochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faculties using Imadegawa-kochi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>学部：神、文、社会、法、経済、商学部の各3～4年次および政策学部全学年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under graduate schools : Third and fourth academic year of School of Theology, Faculty of Letters, Faculty of Social Studies, Faculty of Law, Faculty of Economics and Faculty of Commerce as well as all academic years of Faculty of Policy Studies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under graduate schools: Third and fourth academic years of the School of Theology, Faculty of Letters, Faculty of Social Studies, Faculty of Law, Faculty of Economics, and Faculty of Commerce as well as all academic years of the Faculty of Policy Studies</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under graduate schools: Third and fourth academic years of the School of Theology, Faculty of Letters, Faculty of Social Studies, Faculty of Law, Faculty of Economics, and Faculty of Commerce as well as all academic years of the Faculty of Policy Studies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>研究科：神学、文学、社会学、法学、経済学、商学、アメリカ、総合政策科学研究科</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Graduate schools : Graduate School of Theology, Graduate School of Letters, Graduate School of Social Studies, Graduate School of Law, Graduate School of Economics, Graduate School of Commerce, Graduate School of American Studies and Graduate School of Policy and management</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Graduate schools: Graduate School of Theology, Graduate School of Letters, Graduate School of Social Studies, Graduate School of Law, Graduate School of Economics, Graduate School of Commerce, Graduate School of American Studies, and Graduate School of Policy and management</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Graduate schools: Graduate School of Theology, Graduate School of Letters, Graduate School of Social Studies, Graduate School of Law, Graduate School of Economics, Graduate School of Commerce, Graduate School of American Studies, and Graduate School of Policy and management</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>神学部、社会学部は2009年度に今出川校地へ統合。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">School of Theology and Faculty of Social Studies were moved to Imadegawa-kochi in 2009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">School of Theology and Faculty of Social Studies were moved to Imadegawa-kochi in 2009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">School of Theology and Faculty of Social Studies were moved into Imadegawa-kochi in 2009.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>文学部心理学科は心理学部として改組され2009年度に全学年京田辺校地へ移転。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Psychology Department of Faculty of Letters was reorganized into Faculty of Psychology and was moved to Kyotanabe-kochi in 2009.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Psychology Department of Faculty of Letters was reorganized into Faculty of Psychology and was moved to Kyotanabe-kochi in 2009.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Psychology Department of Faculty of Letters was reorganized into Faculty of Psychology and its all academic years was moved to Kyotanabe-kochi in 2009.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>文学部、法学部、経済学部、商学部も2013年度までに今出川校地に統合が予定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Faculty of Letters, Faculty of Law, Faculty of Economics and Faculty of Commerce are also expected to be moved to Imadegawa-kochi by 2013.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Faculty of Letters, Faculty of Law, Faculty of Economics, and Faculty of Commerce are also expected to be moved to Imadegawa-kochi by 2013.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Faculty of Letters, Faculty of Law, Faculty of Economics, and Faculty of Commerce are also expected to be moved into Imadegawa-kochi by 2013.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>教育施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Education facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Education facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Education facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>弘風館 （こうふう-かん 略称K）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofu-kan (an abbreviated title is K)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofu-kan (the abbreviated title is K)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofukan (the abbreviated title is K)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>経済学部事務室、法学部事務室、教室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Office of Faculty of Economics, Office of Faculty of Law, classrooms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Office of the Faculty of Economics, Office of the Faculty of Law, classrooms</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Office of the Faculty of Economics, Office of the Faculty of Law, classrooms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>至誠館 （しせい-かん 略称S）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shisei-kan (an abbreviated title is S)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shisei-kan (the abbreviated title is S)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiseikan (the abbreviated title is S)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>商学部事務室、教室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Office of Faculty of Commerce, classrooms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Office of the Faculty of Commerce, classrooms</e>
<cmt>grammr</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Office of the Faculty of Commerce, classrooms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>神学館 （しんがく-かん 略称G）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shingaku-kan (an abbreviated title is G</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shingaku-kan (an abbreviated title is G)</e>
<cmt>added)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shingakukan (an abbreviated title is G)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>神学部事務室、教室、神学館礼拝堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Office of School of Theology, classrooms, Shingaku-kan Chapel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Office of the School of Theology, classrooms, Shingaku-kan Chapel</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Office of the School of Theology, classrooms, Shingakukan Chapel</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>クラーク記念館 （略称CL）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clarke Memorial Hall (an abbreviated title is CL)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clarke Memorial Hall (the abbreviated title is CL)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clarke Memorial Hall (the abbreviated title is CL)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>キリスト教文化センター、教室、クラークチャペル</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Center for Christian Culture, classrooms, Clarke Chapel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Center for Christian Culture, classrooms, Clarke Chapel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Center for Christian Culture, classrooms, Clarke Chapel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>明徳館 （めいとく-かん 略称M）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meitoku-kan (an abbreviated title is M)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meitoku-kan (the abbreviated title is M)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meitokukan (the abbreviated title is M)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>食堂、購買、教室、教育開発センター、研究支援課、学生ラウンジ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dining room, shopping booth, classrooms, Education Development Center, Research Support Division, students lounge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dining room, shopping booth, classrooms, Education Development Center, Research Support Division, student lounge</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dining room, shopping booth, classrooms, Education Development Center, Research Support Division, student lounge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>徳照館 （略称T）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokusho-kan (an abbreviated title is T)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokusho-kan (the abbreviated title is T)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokushokan (the abbreviated title is T)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>文学部・文学研究科事務室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Office of Department of Literature, Faculty of Letters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Office of the Department of Literature, Faculty of Letters</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Office of the Department of Literature, Faculty of Letters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>博遠館 （はくえん-かん 略称H）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakuen-kan (an abbreviated title is H)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakuen-kan (the abbreviated title is H)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakuenkan (the abbreviated title is H)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>教室、大学院共同図書室、アメリカ研究所・アメリカ研究科事務室、総合政策科学研究科事務室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classrooms, library of graduate schools, office of International Institutes of American Studies, office of Graduate School of Policy and Management</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classrooms, library of graduate schools, office of International Institutes of American Studies, office of the Graduate School of Policy and Management</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classrooms, library of university and graduate schools, office of International Institutes of American Studies, office of the Graduate School of Policy and Management</e>
<cmt>スペース削除など変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>今出川図書館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imadegawa Library</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imadegawa Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imadegawa Library</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>EU情報センターがあり、EU関連の書物やレポートも充実している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">EU Information Center is set at the library and it possesses a lot of books and reports relating EU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">EU Information Center is set at the library and it possesses a lot of books and reports relating EU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">EU Information Center is set at the library and it possesses a lot of books and reports relating EU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>扶桑館 （ふそう-かん 略称F）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuso-kan (an abbreviated title is F)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuso-kan (the abbreviated title is F)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fusokan (the abbreviated title is F)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>ワールドワイドビジネス研究センター、ヒューマンセキュリティ研究センター、社会的共通資本研究センター、国際センター（国際課）、日本語・日本文化教育センター（国際教育課）、生協書籍部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Research Center for World Business, Research Center for Human Security, Research Center for Social Common Capital, International Center (International Division), Center for Japanese Language and Culture (International Education Division), co-op bookshop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Research Center for World Business, Research Center for Human Security, Research Center for Social Common Capital, International Center (International Division), Center for Japanese Language and Culture (International Education Division), co-op bookshop</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Research Center for World Wide Business, Research Center for Human Security, Research Center for Social Common Capital, International Center (International Division), Center for Japanese Language and Culture (International Education Division), co-op bookshop</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>啓明館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keimei-kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keimei-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keimeikan</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>人文科学研究所、同志社社史資料センター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Institute for the Study of Humanities and Social Sciences, Doshisha Archives Center</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Institute for the Study of Humanities and Social Sciences, Doshisha Archives Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Institute for the Study of Humanities and Social Sciences, Doshisha Archives Center</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>講武館 （こうぶ-かん 略称KB）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobun-kan (an abbreviated title is KB)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobun-kan (the abbreviated title is KB)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobunkan (the abbreviated title is KB)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>寧静館 （ねいせい-かん 略称N）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neisei-kan (an abbreviated title is N)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neisei-kan (the abbreviated title is N)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neiseikan (the abbreviated title is N)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>待辰館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taishin-kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taishin-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taishinkan</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>一神教学際研究センター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Center for Interdisciplinary Study of Monotheistic Religions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Center for the Interdisciplinary Study of Monotheistic Religions</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Center for the Interdisciplinary Study of Monotheistic Religions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>光塩館 （略称KE）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koen-kan (an abbreviated title is KE)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koen-kan (the abbreviated title is KE)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koenkan (the abbreviated title is KE)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>啓明館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keimei-kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keimei-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keimeikan</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>運動施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Athletic facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Athletic facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Athletic facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>なし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nil</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nil</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nil</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>その他施設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other facilities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other facilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>ハリス理化学館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harris Science Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harris Science Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harris Science Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>入試センター、広報課、アドミッションズオフィス、校友課</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entrance Examination Center, Public Relations Division, Admissions Office, Alumni Association Division</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entrance Examination Center, Public Relations Division, Admissions Office, Alumni Association Division</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entrance Examination Center, Public Relations Division, Admissions Office, Alumni Association Division</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>有終館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushu-kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushu-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushukan</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>庶務課</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General Affairs Division</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">General Affairs Division</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General Affairs Division</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>致遠館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chien-kan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chien-kan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chienkan</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>人事課、経理課、資金課、学事課、企画課</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Personnel Division, Accounting Division, Finance Division, Student Affairs Division, Planning Division</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Personnel Division, Accounting Division, Finance Division, Student Affairs Division, Planning Division</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Personnel Division, Accounting Division, Finance Division, Student Affairs Division, Planning Division</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>今出川校地には以下の文化財建造物がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are the buildings located at Imadegawa-kochi that are designated as cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are the buildings located at Imadegawa-kochi that are designated as cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are the buildings located at Imadegawa-kochi that are designated as cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National important cutural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important national cutural properties</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important national cultural properties</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>同志社大学今出川校地にある日本国政府指定の重要文化財は以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are the national important cultural properties designated by the Government of Japan which are located at Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following are important national cultural properties designated by the Government of Japan which are located at Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following are important national cultural properties designated by the Government of Japan which are located at Imadegawa-kochi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>建造物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="64">
<j>同志社礼拝堂 （今出川校地）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Chapel (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Chapel (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Chapel (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="65">
<j>指定書・台帳番号1575</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of designation : registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter of designation: registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter of designation: Registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>種別近代・学校建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification : modern school building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification: modern school building</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification: Modern school building</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>指定年月日1963年7月1日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of designation : July 1, 1963</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of designation: July 1, 1963</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of designation: July 1, 1963</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>年代1886年（明治19年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1886</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1886</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1886</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>構造形式煉瓦造、建築面積316.0㎡、一階建、一部中二階及び地下室付、鉄板葺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick-build structure, 316.0 square meters, one-storied building with partial mezzanine and basement, steel sheet roofing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick structure, 316.0 square meters, one-storied building with partial mezzanine and basement, steel sheet roofing</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick structure, 316.0 square meters, one-storey building with partial mezzanine and basement, steel sheet roofing</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>D.C.グリーンが設計し、1886年に竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by D.C Green and completed in 1886.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designed by D.C Green and completed in 1886.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designed by D.C Green and completed in 1886.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>アメリカン・ゴシック調の鉄板葺き煉瓦造り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the American Gothic style brick-build building with steel sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">American Gothic style brick-build building with steel sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">American Gothic style brick-build building with steel sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>アメリカン・ボードの寄付によって建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was constructed thanks to the donation by the American Board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Constructed thanks to donations by the American Board.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Constructed thanks to donations by the American Board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>日本におけるプロテスタント派の煉瓦造りの礼拝堂としては現存する最古のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the oldest brick-build Protestant chapel in existence in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the oldest brick Protestant chapel in existence in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the oldest brick Protestant chapel in existence in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>施工は有終館も請け負った三上吉兵衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its construction work was conducted by Kichibei MIKAMI, who also constructed the construction work of Yushu-kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its construction was conducted by Kichibei MIKAMI, who also built the Yushu-kan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its construction was conducted by Kichibei MIKAMI, who also built the Yushukan.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>ステンドグラスが美しく、徳冨蘆花の小説、『黒い眼と茶色の目』の中で「五色の光線」が降ると形容された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its stained glass is so beautiful, Roka TOKUTOMI described in his novel &quot;Black eyes and brown eyes&quot; as &quot;five-colored rays are falling&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stained glass is so beautiful, Roka TOKUTOMI described in his novel &quot;Black eyes and brown eyes&quot; as &quot;five-colored rays are falling.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stained glass is so beautiful, Roka TOKUTOMI described in his novel &quot;Black eyes and brown eyes&quot; as &apos;five-colored rays are falling.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>1963年に国の重要文化財に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national important cultural property in 1963.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated as an important national cultural property in 1963.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated as an important national cultural property in 1963.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>1987年から1990年まで半解体修理工事が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was partly dismantled and repaired from 1987 to 1990.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was partly dismantled and repaired from 1987 to 1990.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was partly dismantled and repaired from 1987 to 1990.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>現在も礼拝堂として使用されており、毎週礼拝も行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is still used as a chapel at present and worship is conducted every week.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is still used as a chapel at present and worship is conducted every week.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is still used as a chapel at present and worship is conducted every week.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>また、週末には同志社関係者に限り結婚式を挙げることもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Persons who are related to Doshisha can use it for wedding ceremony during a weekend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Persons who are related to Doshisha can use it for wedding ceremonies during the weekend.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Persons who are related to Doshisha can use it for wedding ceremonies during the weekend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>同志社の礼拝堂としては2代目（初代は木造）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the second Doshisha Chapel (the first one was wooden building).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the second Doshisha Chapel (the first one was a wooden building).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the second Doshisha Chapel (the first one was a wooden building).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="81">
<j>有終館 （今出川校地）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushu-kan (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushu-kan (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushu-kan (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="82">
<j>指定書・台帳番号1575</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of designation : registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter of designation : registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter of designation: Registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>スペース削除などしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>種別近代・学校建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification : modern school building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification: modern school building</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification: Modern school building</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>指定年月日1979年5月21日（内装は指定外）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of designation : May 21, 1979 (exclusive of interior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of designation: May 21, 1979 (exclusive of interior)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of designation: May 21, 1979 (exclusive of interior)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>年代1887年（明治20年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1887</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1887</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1887</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>構造形式煉瓦造、建築面積352.3㎡、二階建、地下一階、桟瓦葺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick-build structure, 352.3 square meters, two stories above ground and one below, sangawara tile roofing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick structure, 352.3 square meters, two stories above ground and one below, sangawara tile roofing</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick structure, 352.3 square meters, two-storey above ground and one below, sangawara-buki (clay Sangawara tile roofing)</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>1887年に、書籍館（しょじゃくかん）として竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 1887 as Shojaku-kan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in 1887 as Shojaku-kan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in 1887 as Shojakukan Library.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>竣工した当時は日本最大の学校図書館建築物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of its completion, it was the biggest school library building in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of its completion, it was the biggest school library building in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of its completion, it was the biggest school library building in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>設計はD.Cグリーン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by D.C. Green.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designed by D.C. Green.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designed by D.C. Green.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>施工は三上吉兵衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its construction work was conducted by Kichibei MIKAMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its construction work was conducted by Kichibei MIKAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its construction work was conducted by Kichibei MIKAMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>初代大学図書館。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the university&apos;s first library.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the university&apos;s first library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the university&apos;s first library.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>1928年昭和天皇が即位式で在京の折、この有終館が出火した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fire broke out at Yushu-kan in 1928 when the Emperor Showa was staying in Kyoto for the enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fire broke out at Yushu-kan in 1928 when Emperor Showa was staying in Kyoto for the enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fire broke out at Yushukan in 1928 when Emperor Showa was staying in Kyoto for the enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>前出表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>即位式典の場所である御所は、同志社今出川校地に隣接しており、大学当局は即位式の間、全学あげて構内の警備をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Imperial Palace, the venue of enthronement ceremony, was adjacent to Doshisha Imadegawa-kochi, the authority of university was in full alert during the period of enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Imperial Palace, the venue of enthronement ceremony, was adjacent to Doshisha Imadegawa-kochi, the authority of university was on full alert during the period of enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Imperial Palace, the venue of enthronement ceremony, was adjacent to Doshisha Imadegawa-kochi, the authority of university was on full alert during the period of enthronement ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>ところがその詰所にしていた部屋の木製の大火鉢が加熱して出火してしまったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, a fire broke out because a big wooden hibachi (heating appliance) in the guard station was overheated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, a fire broke out because a big wooden hibachi (heating appliance) in the guard station overheated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, a fire broke out because a big wooden hibachi (heating appliance) in the guard station overheated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>これにより当時の総長および理事、監事は引責辞職。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The president, directors and auditors of the university at the time resigned from their posts to take responsibility for the above incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The president, directors and auditors of the university at the time resigned from their posts to take responsibility for the above incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The president, directors and auditors of the university at the time resigned from their posts to take responsibility for the above incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>燃え残った有終館の駆体は撤去の予定であったが、当時隣の同志社女学校の建築を手がけていた武田五一が修理・保存を勧告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Yushu-kan&apos;s framework that survived the fire was expected to be demolished, Goichi TAKEDA, who was engaged in the construction of adjacent building of Doshisha Girl&apos;s school, recommended to repai and preserve it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Yushu-kan&apos;s framework that survived the fire was expected to be demolished, Goichi TAKEDA, who was engaged in the construction of an adjacent building of Doshisha Girl&apos;s school, recommended repairing and preserving it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Yushukan&apos;s framework that survived the fire was expected to be demolished, Goichi TAKEDA, who was engaged in the construction of an adjacent building of Doshisha Girl&apos;s School, recommended repairing and preserving it.</e>
<cmt>前出表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>結局外壁の内部に15cmの鉄筋コンクリートの壁を作る方法で保存した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, it was preserved by means of installing ferroconcrete wall of 15-centimeter thick on the inside of outer wall.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, it was preserved by means of installing ferroconcrete walls, 15-centimeter thick on the inside of outer walls.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, it was preserved by means of installing ferroconcrete walls, 15-centimeter thick on the inside of outer walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>有終館の名は図書館としての役目を終えた際に当時の総長であった海老名弾正が命名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This building was named Yushu-kan by Danjo EBINA when its role as library ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This building was named Yushu-kan by Danjo EBINA when its role as a library ended.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This building was named Yushukan by Danjo EBINA when its role as a library ended.</e>
<cmt>前出表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="99">
<j>ハリス理化学館 （今出川校地）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harris Science Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harris Science Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harris Science Hall (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="100">
<j>指定書・台帳番号1575</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of designation : registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter of designation: registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter of designation: Registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>種別近代・学校建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification : modern school building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification: modern school building</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification: Modern school building</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>指定年月日1979年5月21日（階段以外の内装は指定外）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of designation : May 21, 1979 (exclusive of interior other than stairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of designation: May 21, 1979 (exclusive of interior other than stairs)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of designation: May 21, 1979 (exclusive of interior other than stairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>年代1890年（明治23年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1890</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1890</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1890</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>構造形式煉瓦造、建築面積587.0㎡、東北隅実験室付、桟瓦葺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick-build structure, 587.0 square meters, a laboratory is attached to the northeast corner, asagawara tile roofing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick-build structure, 587.0 square meters, a laboratory is attached to the northeast corner, asagawara tile roofing</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick-build structure, 587.0 square meters, a laboratory is attached to the northeast corner, sangawara-buki roofing</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>アメリカ合衆国コネティカット州ニューロンドン (コネチカット州)のハリス(JONATHAN N. HARRIS)の寄付によって建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was constructed by the donations of Harris (JONATHAN N. HARRIS) of New London (Connecticut), Connecticut, U.S.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was constructed with the donations of Harris (JONATHAN N. HARRIS) of New London (Connecticut), Connecticut, U.S.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was constructed with the donations of Harris (Jonathan N. HARRIS) of New London, Connecticut, U.S.</e>
<cmt>重複する文字を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>設計者は英国王立建築家協会員のハンセル(ALEX N. HANSELL)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by Hansell (ALEX N. HANSELL), a member of Royal Institute of British Architects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designed by Hansell (ALEX N. HANSELL), a member of Royal Institute of British Architects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designed by Hansell (Alex N. HANSELL), a member of Royal Institute of British Architects.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>1890年の竣工で、イギリス積みの煉瓦建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 1890, and it is a British-style brick-build building.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in 1890, and it is a British-style brick building.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in 1890, and it is a British-style brick building.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>1979年5月21日に重要文化財に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national important cultural property as of May 21, 1979.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated as an important national cultural property as of May 21, 1979.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated as an important national cultural property as of May 21, 1979.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="109">
<j>クラーク記念館 （今出川校地）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clarke Memorial Hall</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clarke Memorial Hall</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clarke Memorial Hall (Imadegawa-kochi)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="110">
<j>指定書・台帳番号1575</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of designation : registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter of designation: registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter of designation: Registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>種別近代・学校建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification : modern school building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification: modern school building</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification: Modern school building</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>指定年月日1979年5月21日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of designation : May 21, 1979</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of designation: May 21, 1979</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of designation: May 21, 1979</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>年代1894年（明治27年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1894</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1894</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1894</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>構造形式煉瓦造、建築面積389.4㎡、桟瓦葺、西南隅塔屋付、銅板葺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick-build structure, 389.4 square meters, asagawara tile roofing, a tower is attached to the southwest corner, copper sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick-build structure, 389.4 square meters, asagawara tile roofing, a tower is attached to the southwest corner, copper sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick-build structure, 389.4 square meters, asagawara-buki roofing, a tower is attached to the southwest corner, copper sheet roofing</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>附指定建築仕様書等1冊、建築設計図1巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A copy of architetural specification and a volume of architectural plan were also designated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A copy of the architectural specifications and a volume of architectural blueprints were also designated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A copy of the architectural specifications and a volume of architectural blueprints were also designated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>ドイツのネオ・ゴシックを基調とする建築物で、「印象的な尖塔は同志社大学のシンボル的存在」と同志社大学関係者は考えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a German neo-gothic style building, and people relating Doshisha University think that &quot;its impressive spire is something like a symbol of Doshisha University&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a German neo-gothic style building, and people relating Doshisha University think that &quot;its impressive spire is something like a symbol of Doshisha University.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a German neo-gothic style building, and people relating Doshisha University think that &apos;its impressive spire is something like a symbol of Doshisha University.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>27歳でこの世を去った息子（バイロン・ストーン・クラーク）のためにとB.W.クラーク夫妻より6000ドル寄付され建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was constructed with the donation of 6.000 dollars by Mr. and Mrs. Clarke, who donated this amount in memory of their son Byron Stone Clarke who died at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was constructed with the donations of 6.000 dollars by Mr. and Mrs. Clarke, who donated this amount in memory of their son Byron Stone Clarke who died at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was constructed with the donations of 6,000 dollars by Mr. and Mrs. Clarke, who donated this amount in memory of their son Byron Stone Clarke who died at the age of 27.</e>
<cmt>カンマにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>そのため1階の壁面に「THE STUDY OF THE WORD OF GOD WAS DEAR TO HIM」（神の言葉の研究は彼にとって大切であった、の意）と刻まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a phrase &quot;THE STUDY OF THE WORD OF GOD WAS DEAR TO HIM&quot; was engraved on the wall of first floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the phrase &quot;THE STUDY OF THE WORD OF GOD WAS DEAR TO HIM&quot; was engraved on the wall of the first floor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the phrase &apos;THE STUDY OF THE WORD OF GOD WAS DEAR TO HIM&apos; was engraved on the wall of the first floor.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>1894年の開館当時はクラーク神学館と呼ばれ、神学教育・研究の中心として使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called Clarke Divinity Hall at the time of its opening, and it was used as a center for the education and study of theology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called Clarke Divinity Hall at the time of its opening, and it was used as a center for the education and study of theology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called Clarke Divinity Hall at the time of its opening in 1894, and it was used as a center for the education and study of theology.</e>
<cmt>年号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>1979年5月に「設計図」、「建築仕様書」とともに重要文化財に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national important cultural property in May 1979 together with its &quot;architectural plan&quot; and &quot;architectural specification&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated as an important national cultural property in May 1979 together with its &quot;architectural bluprints&quot; and &quot;architectural specifications.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated as an important national cultural property in May 1979 together with its &apos;architectural blueprints&apos; and &apos;architectural specifications.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>2003年1月から2008年2月まで10億1760万円をかけ改修工事が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its renovation work was conducted from January 2003 to February 2008 at a cost of 1,017.6 M\.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its renovation work was conducted from January 2003 to February 2008 at a cost of 1,017.6 M\.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its renovation work was conducted from January 2003 to February 2008 at a cost of 1,017.6 million yen.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>この際、後世に改造された部分などは撤去され、当初の姿に復元された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, the building was restored to its original state by removing portions that were alterated after its completion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, the building was restored to its original state by removing portions that were alterated after its completion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, the building was restored to its original state by removing portions that were alternated after its completion.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>2006年度に行われた同志社EVEにおいて、補修工事に使われた土居葺板に寄せ書きを行うイベントが開催された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Doshisha EVE held in 2006, an event was held in which participants wrote words on doibuikiita (roofing material) which was used for restoration work.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Doshisha EVE held in 2006, an event was held in which the participants wrote words on doibuikiita (roofing material) used for the restoration work.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Doshisha EVE held in 2006, an event was held in which the participants wrote words on doibukiita (a base board for tile roofing) used for the restoration work.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="124">
<j>彰栄館 （同志社中学校）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoei-kan (Doshisha Junior High School)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoei-kan (Doshisha Junior High School)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoeikan (Doshisha Junior High School)</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="125">
<j>指定書・台帳番号1575</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of designation : registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter of designation: registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter of designation: Registration No. 1575</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>種別近代・学校建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Classification : modern school building</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Classification: modern school building</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Classification: Modern school building</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>指定年月日1979年5月21日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of designation : May 21, 1979</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of designation: May 21, 1979</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of designation: May 21, 1979</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>年代1884年（明治17年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1884</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1884</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1884</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>構造形式煉瓦造、建築面積276.2㎡、2階建、桟瓦葺、東面塔屋付、南面玄関ポーチ付、鉄板葺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick-build structure, 276.2 square meters, two-storied, asagawara tile roofing, a tower is attached to the east corner, a porch is attached to the south entrance, steel sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick structure, 276.2 square meters, two-storied, asagawara tile roofing, a tower is attached to the east corner, a porch is attached to the south entrance, steel sheet roofing.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick structure, 276.2 square meters, two-storey, asagawara-buki roofing, a tower is attached to the east corner, a porch is attached to the south entrance, steel sheet roofing</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>附指定時計機械1台 MAY 5, 1887の銘板がある</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A clock mechanism with a plate bearing an inscription of MAY 5, 1887 was also designated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A clock mechanism with a plate bearing an inscription of MAY 5, 1887 was also designated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A clock mechanism with a plate bearing an inscription of MAY 5, 1887 was also designated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>D.C.グリーンが設計し、1884年に竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by D.C. Green and was completed in 1884.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designed by D.C. Green and completed in 1884.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designed by D.C. Green and completed in 1884.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>アメリカン・ゴシック調の瓦葺きの煉瓦造り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an American-gothic style brick-build building with kawara tile roofing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an American-gothic style brick building with kawara tile roofing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an American-gothic style brick building with kawara tile roofing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>アメリカン・ボードの寄付によって建築。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was constructed with the donations of the American Board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was constructed with the donations of the American Board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was constructed with the donations of the American Board.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>京都市内に現存する煉瓦建築の中では最古のもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the oldest brick-build building in existence in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the oldest brick building in existence in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the oldest brick building in existence in Kyoto City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>登録有形文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Registered tangible cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registered tangible cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registered tangible cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="135">
<j>同志社大学今出川校地にある日本国政府によって登録された登録有形文化財は以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are the registered tangible cultural properties located at Imadegawa-kochi that are registered by the Government of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following are registered tangible cultural properties located at Imadegawa-kochi that are registered by the Government of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following are registered tangible cultural properties located at Imadegawa-kochi that are registered by the Government of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="136">
<j>建築物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buildings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="137">
<j>アーモスト館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amherst House</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amherst House</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amherst House</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="138">
<j>登録番号26-0200</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Registratio No. 26-0200</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registratio No. 26-0200</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registration Number: 26-0200</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>構造鉄筋コンクリート造地上3階地下1階建、スレート葺、建築面積343㎡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : reinforced concrete structure, three stories above ground and one below, slate roofing, 343 square meters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: reinforced concrete structure, three stories above ground and one below, slate roofing, 343 square meters</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Reinforced concrete structure, three-storey above ground and one below, slate roofing, 343 square meters</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>年代1932年（昭和7年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1932</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1932</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1932</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>所在地京都府京都市上京区今出川通烏丸東入相国寺門前町632</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location : 632 Imadegawa-dori Karasumahigashi-iru, Shokokuji-Monzen-cho, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: 632 Imadegawa-dori Karasumahigashi-iru, Shokokuji-Monzen-cho, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: 632 Shokokuji-Monzen-cho, Karasuma Higashi-iru, Imadegawa-dori Street, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>原簿記載年月日2005年11月10日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of registration : November 10, 2005</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of registration: November 10, 2005</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of registration: November 10, 2005</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>官報告示年月日2005年12月5日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette : December 5, 2005</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of notice through official gazette : December 5, 2005</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette: December 5, 2005</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>1931年11月29日定礎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its construction work started on November 29, 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction work started on November 29, 1931.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction work started on November 29, 1931.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>1932年3月20日竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed on March 20, 1932.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Completed on March 20, 1932.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Completed on March 20, 1932.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>ニューイングランド・ジョージア様式で、左右対称の概観が特徴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a New England Georgia style building and its characteristic is bilaterally symmetric appearance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a New England Georgia style building and its characteristic is bilaterally symmetric appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a New England Georgia style building and its characteristic is bilaterally symmetric appearance.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>2005年11月10日に登録有形文化財（建造物）に登録。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was registered as a registered tangible cultural property on November 10, 2005.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registered as a tangible cultural property on November 10, 2005.</e>
<cmt>redundance</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registered as a tangible cultural property on November 10, 2005.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>学生寮（アーモスト寮）として使用されているが、現在は改修工事中。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is being used as students dormitory (Amherst dormitory), but renovation work is being conducted at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is being used as a students dormitory (Amherst dormitory), but renovation work is being conducted at present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is being used as a students dormitory (Amherst dormitory), but renovation work is being conducted at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>設計はウィリアム・メレル・ヴォーリズ(W.M.Vories)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W.M. Vories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W.M. Vories).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W. M. Vories).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>施工は清水組。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Constructio work was done by Shimizu Gumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction work was done by Shimizu Gumi.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction work was done by Shimizugumi.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="151">
<j>同志社啓明館本館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Keimei-kan Honkan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Keimei-kan Honkan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Keimeikan Honkan</e>
<cmt>同志社ウェブサイトでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="152">
<j>登録番号26-0256</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Registratio No. : 26-0256</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registratio No: 26-0256</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registration Number: 26-0256</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>構造煉瓦及び鉄筋コンクリート造5階建、スレート葺、建築面積406㎡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick and reinforced concrete structure, five stories, slate roofing, 406 square meters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick and reinforced concrete structure, five stories, slate roofing, 406 square meters</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick and reinforced concrete structure, five-storey, slate roofing, 406 square meters</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>年代1920年（大正9年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1920</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1920</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1920</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>所在地京都府京都市上京区今出川通烏丸東入玄武町602-1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location : 602-1 Imadegawa-dori, Karasumahigashi-iru, Genbu-cho, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: 602-1 Imadegawa-dori, Karasumahigashi-iru, Genbu-cho, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: 602-1 Genbu-cho, Karasuma Higashi-iru, Imadegawa Street, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>原簿記載年月日2007年7月31日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of registration : July 31, 2007</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of registration: July 31, 2007</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of registration: July 31, 2007</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>官報告示年月日2007年8月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette : August 13, 2007</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of notice through official gazette: August 13, 2007</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette: August 13, 2007</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>1920年図書館（2代目大学図書館）として竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 1920 as a library (university&apos;s second university).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in 1920 as a library (university&apos;s second university).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in 1920 as a library (university&apos;s second university).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>設計はウィリアム・メレル・ヴォーリズ(W.M.Vories)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W.M. Vories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designed by William Merrell Vories (W.M. Vories).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designed by William Merrell Vories (W. M. Vories).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>第二次大戦中、ラングドン・ウォーナー博士が米陸軍当局に提出した「爆撃してはならない日本の文化財目録」の中に入っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was include in &quot;The list of Japanese cultural properties which U.S shouldn&apos;t bomb&quot;, which Dr. Langdon Warner submitted to the U.S Army authority during the Second World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was include in &quot;The list of Japanese cultural properties which U.S shouldn&apos;t bomb,&quot; which Dr. Langdon Warner submitted to the U.S Army authority during the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>O</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was include in &apos;The list of Japanese cultural properties which U.S shouldn&apos;t bomb,&apos; which Dr. Langdon Warner submitted to the U.S Army authority during the World War II.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変え統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>1973年12月 に現在の図書館（3代目大学図書館）の竣工により、「啓明館」と改称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was renamed &quot;Keimei-kan&quot; when the existing library (university&apos;s third library) was completed in December 1973.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was renamed &quot;Keimei-kan&quot; when the existing library (university&apos;s third library) was completed in December 1973.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was renamed &apos;Keimeikan&apos; when the existing library (university&apos;s third library) was completed in December 1973.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>2007年7月31日に登録された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was registered as of July 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was registered as of July 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was registered as of July 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="163">
<j>同志社啓明館西館</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Keimei-kan Nishikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Keimei-kan Nishikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Keimeikan Nishikan</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="164">
<j>登録番号26-0257</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Registratio No. : 26-0257</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registratio No: 26-0257</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registration No: 26-0257</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>構造煉瓦及び鉄筋コンクリート造4階建、スレート葺、建築面積153㎡、渡廊下付</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : brick and reinforced concrete structure, four stories, slate roofing, 153 square meters, a roofed passage is attached</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: brick and reinforced concrete structure, four stories, slate roofing, 153 square meters, a roofed passage is attached</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Brick and reinforced concrete structure, four-storey, slate roofing, 153 square meters, a roofed passage is attached</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>年代1915年（大正4年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : 1915</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: 1915</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: 1915</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>所在地京都府京都市上京区今出川通烏丸東入玄武町602-1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location : 602-1 Imadegawa-dori, Karasumahigashi-iru, Genbu-cho, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: 602-1 Imadegawa-dori, Karasumahigashi-iru, Genbu-cho, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: 602-1 Genbu-cho, Karasuma Higashi-iru, Imadegawa, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>原簿記載年月日2007年7月31日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of registration : July 31, 2007</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of registration: July 31, 2007</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of registration: July 31, 2007</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>官報告示年月日2007年8月13日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette : August 13, 2007</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of notice through official gazette: August 13, 2007</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette: August 13, 2007</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>1915年図書館（2代目大学図書館）として竣工。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was completed in 1915 as a library (university&apos;s second library).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was completed in 1915 as a library (university&apos;s second library).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was completed in 1915 as a library (university&apos;s second library).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>設計はウィリアム・メレル・ヴォーリズ(W.M.Vories)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W.M. Vories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W.M. Vories).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designed by William Merrell Vories (W. M. Vories).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>1973年12月 に現在の図書館（3代目大学図書館）の竣工により、「啓明館」と改称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was renamed &quot;Keimei-kan&quot; when the existing library (university&apos;s third library) was completed in December 1973.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was renamed &quot;Keimei-kan&quot; when the existing library (university&apos;s third library) was completed in December 1973.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was renamed &apos;Keimeikan&apos; when the existing library (university&apos;s third library) was completed in December 1973.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>2007年7月31日に登録された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was registered as of July 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was registered in July 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was registered in July 31, 2007.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="174">
<j>同志社フレンドピースハウス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doshisha Friend Peace House</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doshisha Friend Peace House</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doshisha Friend Peace House</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="175">
<j>登録番号26-0206</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Registratio No. : 26-0206</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Registratio No: 26-0206</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Registration No: 26-0206</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>構造木造2階建、瓦葺、建築面積248㎡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure : two-storied wooden building. Kawara tile roofing, 248 square meters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure: two-storied wooden building. Kawara tile roofing, 248 square meters</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure: Two-storey wooden building, kawara tile roofing, 248 square meters</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>年代明治中期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Age : middle of Meiji era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Age: middle of Meiji era</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Age: Around 1883 to 1897</e>
<cmt>西暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>所在地京都府京都市上京区寺町通石薬師下る染殿町665-1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Location : 665-1 Somedono-cho, Teramachi-dori Ishiyakushi-sagaru Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Location: 665-1 Somedono-cho, Teramachi-dori Ishiyakushi-sagaru Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Location: 665-1 Somedono-cho, Ishiyakushi-sagaru, Teramachi Street, Kamigyo Ward, Kyoto City, Kyoto Prefecture</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>原簿記載年月日2006年3月2日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of registration : March 2, 2006</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of registration: March 2, 2006</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of registration: March 2, 2006</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>官報告示年月日2006年3月23日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette : March 23, 2006</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Date of notice through official gazette: March 23, 2006</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Date of notice through official gazette: March 23, 2006</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>以前同志社大学の布哇寮であり、現在は同志社フレンドピースハウスとして活用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be Hawai Dormitory of Doshisha University, and it is currently used as Doshisha Friend Peace House.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be the Hawai Dormitory of Doshisha University, and it is currently used as Doshisha Friend Peace House.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be the Hawaii Dormitory of Doshisha University, and it is currently used as Doshisha Friend Peace House.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="182">
<j>京都市営地下鉄烏丸線今出川駅下車すぐ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nearby Imadegawa Station of the Karasuma Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nearby Imadegawa Station of the Karasuma Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nearby Imadegawa Station of the Karasuma Line of Kyoto Municipal Subway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>京阪鴨東線出町柳駅から徒歩5~6分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A 5-6 minute-walk from Demachiyanagi Station of Keihan Oto Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A 5-6 minute-walk from Demachiyanagi Station of Keihan Oto Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A five to six minute-walk from Demachiyanagi Station of Keihan Oto Line.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Yukke123(id:178302), Akinoniji(id:56111), Straysheep(id:42448), Showhead(id:206754), AEONseven&amp;i(id:89677), Urania(id:7213), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>