<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>亭子院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teiji-in (a building)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teiji-in</e>
<cmt>・「(a building)」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teiji-no-in</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>亭子院（ていじのいん）は、西洞院通の西側、左京七条二坊の十三町十四町に位置した平安時代に在位した宇多天皇の譲位後の後院である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Located in 13th cho and 14th cho of seventh-jo and second-bo (Jo: a street in the east-west direction; bo: a street in the north-south direction) in the left side area of the Heian-kyo capital, Teiji-in was Goin Palace (the palace for a retired emperor) of the retired Emperor Uda who was an emperor in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teiji-in is the palace in which Emperor Uda who reigned during the Heian period resided after his abdication located on the western side of Nishinotoin-dori Street, in 13-cho and 14-cho, 7-jo/2-bo (where a &quot;jo&quot; is row of sections running east-west and a &quot;bo&quot; is a column of sections running north-south) in Sakyo (the left (eastern) side of the city).</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくように書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teiji-no-in is the palace in which Emperor Uda who reigned during the Heian period resided after his abdication located on the western side of Nishinotoin-dori Street, in 13-cho and 14-cho, 7-jo/2-bo (where a &quot;jo&quot; is row of sections running east-west and a &quot;bo&quot; is a column of sections running north-south) in Sakyo (the left (eastern) side of the city).</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>亭子院歌合、亭子院酒合戦など著名な文人や大宮人を召いては宴や催しが行われたことで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that banquets and other events where famous men of literature and/or omiyabito (courtiers at the Imperial Court) participated in, such as Teijiin Uta-awase (a waka poem contest at Teijiin) and Teijiin sake kassen Contest (a sake wine-drinking contest at Tenji-in), were held there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that banquets and other events such as Teijiin Uta-awase (a waka poem contest held at Teijiin) and Teijiin Sake Kassen (a sake drinking contest held at Tenji-in) in which famous men of literature and omiyabito (courtiers at the Imperial Court) would participate were held there.</e>
<cmt>再構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that banquets and other events such as Teijinoin Uta-awase (a waka poem contest held at Teijinoin) and Teijinoin Sake Kassen (a sake drinking contest held at Teiji-no-in) in which famous men of literature and omiyabito (courtiers at the Imperial Court) would participate were held there.</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>条坊制による区画名により東七条宮とも称し、宇多天皇の中宮藤原温子の御所としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the block-naming method based on the Jo-bo system, the place was also called Higashi shichijo no Miya (the palace located on the seventh-jo on the east side), and is also known as the place of FUJIWARA no Onshi, chugu (the second consort of an emperor) of Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Higashi Shichijo no Miya (lit. Palace the seventh jo on the east side) according to the jo-bo system of naming sections of the city, and is also known as the palace of Emperor Uda&apos;s wife FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>再構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Higashi Shichijo no Miya (lit. Palace the seventh jo on the east side) according to the jo-bo system of naming sections of the city, and is also known as the palace of Emperor Uda&apos;s wife FUJIWARA no Onshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>池の中に亭(亭子）を設けていたことから、亭子院と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because tei (or teishi) (an arbor) was placed in the pond, the place became called Teiji-in (a palace with Teishi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because a tei (or teishi) (pavilion) was placed in the pond, the place became called Teiji-in.</e>
<cmt>・「arbor」→「pavilion」・「(a palace with Teishi)」を削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because a tei (or teishi) (pavilion) was placed in the pond, the place became called Teiji-no-in.</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>また宇多法皇在命中の間は、法皇自身を指す人称として、日本紀略をはじめとして著名な大宮人らの日記、歌集等に広く記されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Cloistered Emperor Uda was alive, Teiji-in was widely used as the term for indicating the Cloistered Emperor himself as well, and many of the term appear in diaries or collections of waka poems by famous omiyabito, in addition to &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; (Summary of Japanese Chronologies).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the lifetime of Cloistered Emperor Uda, the word &quot;Teiji-in&quot; was widely used to refer to the cloistered emperor in the diaries and poetry collections written by famous courtiers, as well as in &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; (Summary of Japanese Chronologies).</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the lifetime of Cloistered Emperor Uda, the word &quot;Teiji-no-in&quot; was widely used to refer to the cloistered emperor in the diaries and poetry collections written by famous courtiers, as well as in &quot;Nihongi Ryaku&quot; (Summary of Japanese Chronologies).</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>亭子院に関する記録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Records concerning Teiji-in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Records Relating to Teiji-in</e>
<cmt>「concerning」→「Relating to」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Records Relating to Teiji-no-in</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>昌泰2年（899年）、宇多法皇が、東七条宮を後院とすべく区画内に新たな建物を加えようとした際、古井戸から不動尊像がみつかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Cloistered Emperor Uda was going to add new buildings in the premises to make Higashi shichijo no Miya his Goin Palace, a statue of Fudo-son was found in an old well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Cloistered Emperor Uda was going to add new buildings in the premises to make Higashi shichijo no Miya his Goin Palace, a statue of Fudo-son was found in an old well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Cloistered Emperor Uda was going to add new buildings in the premises to make Higashi shichijo no Miya his Goin Palace in 899, a statue of Fudo-son was found in an old well.</e>
<cmt>in 899を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これは、当該の区画が古くは弘法大師空海が賜った東寺の鬼門にあたり、空海自身が発見した霊力ある石に不動尊像を掘り付け、人目に触れぬよう埋めたものだと判った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was found that, because this block corresponded to the Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction) of Toji-Temple Kobo-Daishi Kukai had been awarded, Kukai sculpted a Fudo-son image out of a strange power-provided stone he found and buried the image there so that it could not be seen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was found that, because this block corresponded to the kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction) of Toji-Temple which had been granted to Kobo Daishi (Kukai), Kukai sculpted a Fudo-son image out of a stone possessing spiritual force that he had found, and buried the image there so that it could not be seen.</e>
<cmt>・「Kimon」→「kimon」・「Kobo-Daishi Kukai had been awarded」→「which had been granted to Kobo Daishi (Kukai)」・「strange power-provided stone he found」→「stone possessing spiritual force that he had found」・コンマを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was found that, because this block corresponded to the kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction) of Toji-Temple which had been granted to Kobo Daishi (Kukai), Kukai sculpted a Fudo-son image out of a stone possessing spiritual force that he had found, and buried the image there so that it could not be seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、法皇は勅令でその井戸を封じたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that, therefore, the cloistered emperor issued an imperial edict to close the well.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that, therefore, the cloistered emperor issued an imperial edict to close the well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that, therefore, the cloistered emperor issued an imperial edict to close the well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>菅原道真の死去した延喜3年（903年）8月に、「皇太夫人藤原温子、東七条宮に遷御あらせらる」という記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following description is recorded in August, 903, when SUGAWARA no Michizane died: FUJIWARA no Onshi, Kotaifujin (the title for the wife of a retired emperor), moved to Higashi shichijo no Miya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 903 when SUGAWARA no Michizane died, it was recorded that &quot;Kotaifujin (the title for the wife of a retired emperor) FUJIWARA no Onshi moved to Higashi shichijo no Miya.</e>
<cmt>再構成</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 903 when SUGAWARA no Michizane died, it was recorded that &quot;Kotaifujin (the title for the wife of a retired emperor) FUJIWARA no Onshi moved to Higashi shichijo no Miya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>承平 (日本)元年7月19日 (旧暦)（931年9月3日）の宇多法皇崩御後、後院として使われることはなく寺院となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Cloistered Emperor Uda died on September 3, 931, the place became used not as Goin Palace but as a temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Cloistered Emperor Uda died on September 3, 931, Teiji-in became used not as goin palace but as a temple.</e>
<cmt>・「the place」→「Teiji-in」・「Goin Palace」→「goin palace」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Cloistered Emperor Uda died on September 8, 931, Teiji-no-in became used not as goin palace but as a temple.</e>
<cmt>原文の読みに合わせましたグレゴリオ歴に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>今は、址跡として明王院不動堂がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, Fudo-do Hall of Myo-o-in Temple is placed at the site.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fudo-do Hall of Myo-o-in Temple currently stands on the site.</e>
<cmt>書き直し</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fudo-do Hall of Myo-o-in Temple currently stands on the site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sotaro.Hikosaka(id:181201), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>