<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>清戸迫横穴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave tomb</e>
<cmt>「横穴」は「よこあな」とも「おうけつ」とも読みますので（広辞苑）、「Yokoana」「Oketsu」を文脈に応じて使い分けます。あえて統一いたしません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave Tumulus (a horizontal decorated cave tumulus in Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave Tumulus (a horizontal decorated cave tumulus in Fukushima Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>清戸迫横穴（きよとさくおうけつ）は、福島県双葉郡双葉町大字新山にある横穴式装飾古墳。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu is a Yokoanashiki Soshoku kofun (decorated cave tomb) located in Oaza Shinzan Futaba-machi, Futaba-gun, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyotosaku Oketsu is a horizontal decorated cave tumulus located in Oaza Shinzan, Futaba-machi, Futaba County, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu is a horizontal decorated cave tumulus located in Oaza Shinzan, Futaba-machi, Futaba County, Fukushima Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>奥壁に人や動物、うずまきを描いた壁画が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There remains mural paintings of persons, animals and a spiral on the inner wall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There remain mural paintings of persons, animals and a spiral on the inner wall.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There remain mural paintings of persons, animals and a spiral on the inner wall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>国の史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was designated as a national historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>装飾壁画の発見</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discovery of the decorative mural paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discovery of the decorative mural paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discovery of the decorative mural paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>清戸迫横穴は300基以上ある横穴墓群の一つで、正式名称は「清戸迫76号横穴墓」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu is one of over 300 Yokoana cave tombs and officially called &apos;Kiyotosaku 76th Oketsu Cave Tomb,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave is one of more than 300 horizontal decorated cave tumuli cluster and officially called &apos;Kiyotosaku 76th Oketsu Cave Tomb.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave is one of more than 300 horizontal decorated cave tumuli cluster and officially called &apos;Kiyotosaku 76th Oketsu Cave Tomb.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>古くから清戸迫丘陵地にその存在が知られていた円墳・横穴群のうちの76号で、1967年（昭和42年）11月、双葉町立南小学校の新築に伴う敷地造成工事にかかる発掘調査がおこなわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the 76th Tomb, one of the round tumulus and Yokoana cave tombs which were known from long ago to be existing on the Kiyotosaku Hills, excavation researches were conducted in November 1967, using the opportunity of a site preparation work for a new school building of the Futaba Town Municipal Minami Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the 76th Tomb, one of the round tumulus and a horizontal cave tombs which were known since ancient times to be existing on the Kiyotosaku Hills, excavation researches were conducted in November 1967, using the opportunity of a site preparation work for a new school building of the Futaba Municipal Minami Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>半角英字にし、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the 76th Tomb, one of the round tumulus and a horizontal cave tombs which were known since ancient times to be existing on the Kiyotosaku Hills, excavation researches were conducted in November 1967, using the opportunity of a site preparation work for a new school building of the Futaba Municipal Minami Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同年11月、敷地内に存在していた横穴墓群の一部を発掘調査した際に76号横穴墓からベンガラ（赤色顔料）によって描かれた壁画が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November in the same year, a mural painting drawn with Bengara (iron oxide red pigment) was discovered in the 76th Oketsu Cave Tomb when some of the Yokoana cave tombs on the site were excavated and researched.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the same year, a mural painting drawn with Bengara (iron oxide red pigment) was discovered in the 76th Oketsu Cave Tomb when some of the horizontal cave tombs on the site were excavated and researched.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, a mural painting drawn with Bengara (iron oxide red pigment) was discovered in the 76th Oketsu Cave Tomb when some of the horizontal cave tombs on the site were excavated and researched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>同横穴墓は、南東を開口部とし、全長約2.6メートルの玄室の奥壁に渦巻文（うずまきもん）を中心に人物2名などが両側に描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yokoana cave tomb has its openings on the southeast side and a painting of Uzumaki mon (spiral) design in the center and two persons and so on on both sides of it was drawn on the inner wall of the burial chamber with a total length of about 2.6 meters.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The horizontal cave tomb has its openings on the southeast side and a painting of Uzumaki-mon (a decorative spiral pattern) in the center of which two persons and others on both sides were drawn on the inner wall of the burial chamber with a total length of approximately 2.6 meters.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The horizontal cave tomb has its openings on the southeast side and a painting of Uzumaki-mon (a decorative spiral pattern) in the center of which two persons and others on both sides were drawn on the inner wall of the burial chamber with a total length of approximately 2.6 meters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>壁画は、現在判明している彩色壁画のうちの北限にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This painting is the northernmost one among the decorative mural paintings discovered so far.</e>
<cmt>「一原文一訳文の例外対処」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This mural painting is the northernmost among the decorative mural paintings discovered so far.</e>
<cmt>用語等を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This mural painting is the northernmost among the decorative mural paintings discovered so far.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、昭和42年(1967年)11月、翌年には国の史跡に指定され、現在は双葉町立南小学校の敷地内に保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it was designated as a national historic site in the following year of November 1967 and is presently preserved in the site of the Futaba Town Municipal Minami Elementary School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it was designated as a national historic site in November 1967 of the following year and is presently preserved in the premise of the Futaba Municipal Minami Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>半角英字にし、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it was designated as a national historic site in November 1967 of the following year and is presently preserved in the premise of the Futaba Municipal Minami Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>横穴墓の構造と壁画について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure of Yokoana cave tomb and mural paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure of a horizontal cave tomb and mural paintings</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure of a horizontal cave tomb and mural paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>横穴は入口から奥壁まで3.15メートル、高さは1.56メートル、奥壁の横幅は2.34メートルである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yokoana is 3.15 meters long from the entrance to the inner wall, 1.56 meters high and 2.34 meters wide on the inner wall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cave is 3.15 meters long from the entrance to the inner wall, 1.56 meters high and 2.34 meters wide on the inner wall.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cave is 3.15 meters long from the entrance to the inner wall, 1.56 meters high and 2.34 meters wide on the inner wall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>壁画に描かれているものについてでは、正面左側の人物は冠帽や美豆良が見られ、袴を着用し靴を履いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the objects of the painting, a person on the left hand side of the painting wears a hat and Mizura (an ancient hair style, bunch of hair is wrapped round and hangs beside the ears), Hakama (formal men&apos;s divided skirt) and shoes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the objects of the mural painting, a person on the left hand side of the painting wears a hat and Mizura (an ancient hair style, bunch of hair is wrapped round and hangs beside the ears), Hakama (formal men&apos;s divided skirt) and shoes.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the objects of the mural painting, a person on the left hand side of the painting wears a hat and Mizura (an ancient hair style, bunch of hair is wrapped round and hangs beside the ears), Hakama (formal men&apos;s divided skirt) and shoes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>正面中央には渦巻文が描かれているが、これが何を象徴しているのかはまだ不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a spiral drawn in the center, but what it symbolizes has not been known yet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What the Uzumaki-mon pattern drawn in the center symbolizes has not been known.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What the Uzumaki-mon pattern drawn in the center symbolizes has not been known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>渦巻文右側の人物は兜をかぶって左手を挙げており、その左側に馬を従えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A person on the right of the spiral wears Kabuto (helmet) raising its left hand and take a horse along on its left side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A person on the right of the Uzumaki-mon wears Kabuto (helmet) raising its left hand and take a horse along on its left side.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A person on the right of the Uzumaki-mon wears Kabuto (helmet) raising its left hand and take a horse along on its left side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その他、弓矢を射ている人物をはじめ、イノシシ、鹿、犬などが描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, a person shooting an arrow, a wild boar, a deer and a dog and so on are drawn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a person shooting an arrow, a wild boar, a deer and a dog and so on are drawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a person shooting an arrow, a wild boar, a deer and a dog and so on are drawn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、この横穴墓の築造年代は7世紀前半と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is likely that this Yokoana cave tomb was constructed in the early 7th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is likely that this horizontal cave tomb was constructed in the early seventh century.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is likely that this horizontal cave tomb was constructed in the early seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>一般公開</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Open to the public</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Open to the public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Open to the public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>清戸迫横穴は現在は覆屋の中に保存されており、維持管理の問題のため限られた日のみの公開となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu is presently preserved under the covering roof and open to the public only limited number of days due to the problem of maintenance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave is presently preserved under the covering roof and opens to the public only limited number of days due to the problem of maintenance.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyotosaku Oketsu Cave is presently preserved under the covering roof and opens to the public only limited number of days due to the problem of maintenance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>公開日は4月・5月・7月・10月の第2日曜日で、時間は900-1200、1300-1500となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is open to the public on the second Sunday in April, May, July and October during 9:00-12:00 and 13:00-15:00.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is open to the public on the second Sunday in April, May, July and October from 9 am to noon and from 1 pm to 3 pm.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is open to the public on the second Sunday in April, May, July and October from 9 am to noon and from 1 pm to 3 pm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Knua(id:66861), Nnh(id:474), 貘(id:106080), Greenland4(id:114494), Reggaeman(id:6214), Sadaharu(id:85339), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>