<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平桟橋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taira-sanbashi Bridge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taira-sanbashi Bridge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taira-sanbashi Bridge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平桟橋（たいらさんばし）は舞鶴港にある桟橋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taira-sanbashi is a landing bridge at Maizuru Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taira-sanbashi is a landing bridge at Maizuru Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taira-sanbashi is a landing bridge at Maizuru Port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中華人民共和国からの帰還者や、ソビエト連邦に不法抑留された引揚者が夢にまでみた祖国の土を踏んだ地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is where repatriates from People&apos;s Republic of China and people who had been illegally detained in the Soviet Union stepped onto their home country they so eagerly hoped to return to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is where repatriates from the People&apos;s Republic of China and people who had been illegally detained in the Soviet Union set foot in the home country they so eagerly hoped to return to.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「stepped onto their home country」→「set foot on the home territory」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is where repatriates from the People&apos;s Republic of China and people who had been illegally detained in the Soviet Union set foot in the home country they so eagerly hoped to return to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>引揚桟橋とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Hikiage-sanbashi&quot; (Repatriation Bridge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Hikiage-sanbashi&quot; (Repatriation Bridge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Hikiage-sanbashi&quot; (Repatriation Bridge).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>太平洋戦争(大東亜戦争)が終結した当時、海外に残された日本人は660万人以上といわれ、その引揚げのために舞鶴港の他9港が指定され、引揚援護局を設置して業務を開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of Japanese expatriates stranded overseas was estimated to be more than 6.6 million when the Pacific War ended, and Maizuru port and other nine ports were designated repatriation ports and the Repatriation Support Bureau was set up to help them return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>引揚援護局→Repatriation Support Bureau（引揚援護局）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Pacific War the number of Japanese expatriates stranded overseas was estimated to be more than 6.6 million, and Maizuru port and another nine ports were designated repatriation ports and the Repatriation Support Bureau was set up to help them return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>「when the Pacific War ended」→「At the end of the Pacific War」(箇所異動), 「other」→「another」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Pacific War the number of Japanese expatriates stranded overseas was estimated to be more than 6.6 million, and Maizuru port and another nine ports were designated repatriation ports and the Repatriation Support Bureau was set up to help them return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>舞鶴港では当初は舞鶴西港が引揚げ港に指定されたが、ソ連地域からの引揚げが開始された1947年（昭和22年）には舞鶴東港の平桟橋へ変更され、その後13年にわたって多くの引揚者が祖国への一歩を平桟橋に記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Maizuru-nishi Port (west port) was initially designated for the repatriation, later the designation was changed to Taira-sanbashi landing bridge at Maizuru-higashi Port (east port) in 1947 when the repatriation from Soviet Union started, and many repatriates had arrived at Taira-sanbashi for thirteen years ever since.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Maizuru-nishi Port (west port) was initially designated for the repatriation, later the designation was changed to Taira-sanbashi landing bridge at Maizuru-higashi Port (east port) in 1947 when the repatriation from the Soviet Union started, and many repatriates arrived at Taira-sanbashi during the following thirteen years.</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入, 「had」削除,「for thirteen years ever since」→「during the following thirteen years」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Maizuru-nishi Port (west port) was initially designated for the repatriation, later the designation was changed to Taira-sanbashi Bridge at Maizuru-higashi Port (east port) in 1947 when the repatriation from the Soviet Union started, and many repatriates arrived at Taira-sanbashi Bridge during the following thirteen years.</e>
<cmt>前出の表記に合わせ、Taira-sanbashi Bridgeとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>現在では平桟橋は復元され、記念碑が立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A monument stands at the landing bridge which is restored today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A monument stands at the landing bridge which has been restored to its original state.</e>
<cmt>「is」→「has been」, 「today」→「to its original state」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A monument stands at the landing bridge which has been restored to its original state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また付近には引揚の記録を残した舞鶴引揚記念館がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Close to this bridge is Maizuru Repatriation Memorial Museum which stores the records of the repatriation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Close to this bridge is Maizuru Repatriation Memorial Museum which stores the records of repatriation.</e>
<cmt>「the」削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Close to this bridge is Maizuru Repatriation Memorial Museum which stores the records of repatriation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、2005年（平成17年）は海外引揚60周年に当たる年であり、当地では海外引揚第1船の入港した11月7日とその周辺に記念行事が開催されることになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the year 2005 comes upon the 60th anniversary of the repatriation, several memorial events are planned to be held on and around November 7, which was the date the first repatriation ship arrived in the port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because 2005 is the 60th anniversary of the repatriation, several memorial events are planned to be held on and around November 7, which was the date the first repatriation ship arrived in the port.</e>
<cmt>「the year」削除, 「comes upon」→「is」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because 2005 is the 60th anniversary of the repatriation, several memorial events are planned to be held on and around November 7, which was the date the first repatriation ship arrived in the port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>アクセス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Access</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鉄道・バス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By train and by bus:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By train and by bus:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By train and by bus:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>西日本旅客鉄道東舞鶴駅より、京都交通の路線バス三浜線もしくは田井・野原線で約15分、「引揚記念公園前バス停」下車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From JR Higashi Maizuru Station, take the bus of Mihama Route or Tai Nohara Route of Kyoto Kotsu, and get off at the &quot;Hikiage Kinen Koen Mae Bus Stop&quot; (time required: approximately 15 minutes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From JR Higashi Maizuru Station, take a Mihama Route or Tai Nohara Route bus owned by Kyoto Kotsu, and get off at the &quot;Hikiage Kinen Koen Mae Bus Stop&quot; (time required: approximately 15 minutes).</e>
<cmt>「take the bus of」→「take a」, 「of」→「bus owned by」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From JR Higashi Maizuru Station, take a Mihama Route or Tai Nohara Route bus owned by Kyoto Kotsu, and get off at the &apos;Hikiage Kinen Koen Mae Bus Stop&apos; (time required: approximately 15 minutes).</e>
<cmt>原文の表記に合わせシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>Jr東舞鶴駅より、舞鶴観光周遊バスで「引揚記念館バス停」下車。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From JR Higashi Maizuru Station, take Maizuru Sightseeing Bus, and get off at the &quot;Hikiage Kinenkan Bus Stop.&quot;</e>
<cmt>舞鶴観光周遊バス→Maizuru Sightseeing Bus（舞鶴観光周遊バス）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From JR Higashi Maizuru Station, take the Maizuru Sightseeing Bus, and get off at the &quot;Hikiage Kinenkan Bus Stop.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「the」挿入</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From JR Higashi Maizuru Station, take the Maizuru Sightseeing Bus, and get off at the &apos;Hikiage Kinenkan Bus Stop.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の表記に合わせシングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>車</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By car</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By car</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>舞鶴若狭自動車道・舞鶴東インターチェンジより、京都府道28号小倉西舞鶴線、(京都府道51号舞鶴和知線)、国道27号を経て京都府道・福井県道21号舞鶴野原港高浜線を大浦半島方面へ約20分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Maizuru Higashi Interchange of Maizuru-Wakasa Expressway, take Kyoto Prefectural road 28 Kokura Nishi Maizuru Route, (Kyoto Prefectural road 51 Maizuru Wachi Route), National Route 27, and drive headed for Oura Peninsula through Kyoto Prefectural road and Fukui Prefectural Route 21 Maizuru Noharako Takahama Route (time required: approximately 20 minutes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Maizuru Higashi Interchange on the Maizuru-Wakasa Expressway, take Kyoto Prefectural Road 28 Kokura Nishi Maizuru Route, (Kyoto Prefectural Road 51 Maizuru Wachi Route), National Route 27, and drive heading for Oura Peninsula on Kyoto Prefectural Road and Fukui Prefectural Route 21 Maizuru Noharako Takahama Route (time required: approximately 20 minutes).</e>
<cmt>「of」→「on the」, 「road」→「Road」x3,「headed」→「heading」, 「through」→「on」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Maizuru Higashi Interchange on the Maizuru-Wakasa Expressway, take Kyoto Prefectural Road 28 Kokura Nishi Maizuru Route, (Kyoto Prefectural Road 51 Maizuru Wachi Route), National Route 27, and drive heading for Oura Peninsula on Kyoto Prefectural Road/Fukui Prefectural Road 21 Maizuru Noharako Takahama Route (time required: approximately 20 minutes).</e>
<cmt>「京都府道・福井県道」の表記修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ぱむ(id:24323), Blackbus(id:37164), 編集しても良いですか?(id:14251), Sea of Japan(id:3230), Singing(id:134656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>