<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>内閣官制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei (Cabinet organization order)</e>
<cmt>http://www.kantei.go.jp/foreign/cabinet_system/2.html首相官邸のＨＰではNaikaku-kanseiとハイフンがついてるため、訳語でつけましたが不要の場合削除してください。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naikaku-kansei (Cabinet organization order)</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei (Cabinet organization order)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>内閣官制（ないかくかんせい）とは、広義には内閣 (日本)の設置・廃止、名称、組織、権限等に関する定めをいい、狭義には1889年に定められた日本の法令、明治22年勅令第135号をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei is regulations for the Japanese Cabinet about its establishment, abolition, naming, organization, authority and so on in a broad sense and the Imperial Ordinance no. 135 of 1889 in a narrow sense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term naikaku-kansei refers in the broadest sense to the set of regulations for the Cabinet of Japan that govern its establishment, abolition, naming, organization, authority and so on, while more narrowly the term refers specifically to Imperial edict no. 135, a law passed in 1889.</e>
<cmt>word choice, grammar (&quot;is regulations&quot;)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Naikaku-kansei refers in the broadest sense to the set of regulations for the Cabinet of Japan that govern its establishment, abolition, naming, organization, authority and so on, while more narrowly the term refers specifically to Imperial edict no. 135, a law passed in 1889.</e>
<cmt>内閣官制の頭文字を大文字に修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>広義の内閣官制には、1885年（明治18年）に制定され、内閣制度を初めて定めた明治18年太政官布告・太政官達第69号や、内閣職権を含める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the broad sense of Naikaku-kansei, it includes Dajokan Fukoku (a decree issued by the Grand Council of State) and Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) no. 69 of 1885, which are the first regulations for the Cabinet system, and Naikaku-shokken (Official powers of the Cabinet).</e>
<cmt>Naikaku-shokkenも上記に同じくハイフンをつけました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The broadest sense of Naikaku-kansei includes the 1885 Dajokan Fukoku (a decree issued by the Grand Council of State) and Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) no. 69, which were the first regulations governing the Cabinet system, and it also includes the Naikaku-shokken (Official powers of the Cabinet).</e>
<cmt>Awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The broadest sense of Naikaku-kansei includes the 1885 Dajokan Fukoku (a decree issued by the Grand Council of State) and Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) no. 69, which were the first regulations governing the Cabinet system, and it also includes the Naikaku-shokken (Official powers of the Cabinet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>1947年（昭和22年）の日本国憲法施行後に、内閣法（昭和22年法律第5号）が施行されたことにより、内閣官制は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the effectuation of the Constitution of Japan in 1947, Naikaku-kansei was abolished as the Cabinet Law (Act No. 5 of 1947) was enacted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the 1947 promulgation of the Constitution of Japan, the Cabinet Law (Act no. 5 of 1947) was enacted, which led to the Naikaku-kansei being abolished.</e>
<cmt>awkward phrasing &quot;A as B&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the 1947 promulgation of the Constitution of Japan, the Cabinet Law (Act no. 5 of 1947) was enacted, which led to the Naikaku-kansei being abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prehistory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prehistory of the Naikaku-kansei</e>
<cmt>Inadequate explanation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prehistory of the Naikaku-kansei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1868年（慶応4年）の五箇条の御誓文に示された政治方針は、太政官制度によって実現が図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The political policy stated in Gokajo no Goseimon (Charter Oath of Five Articles) of 1868 was aimed to be realized by the system of Dajokan (the Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Daijokan (Grand Council of State) system was intended to make the political policies elucidated in the Charter Oath of 1868 a reality.</e>
<cmt>Poor structure, phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Daijokan (Grand Council of State) system was intended to make the political policies elucidated in the Charter Oath of 1868 a reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、太政官に立法・司法・行政の全機能を集中させ、太政大臣に強力な権限を与えるこの制度は、近代国家の国政運営に適さないと考えられ、また、太政大臣の負担が大きく、かえって国家運営の停滞と責任の所在の不明確さを招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the system that concentrated all the functions of legislation, judiciary and administration on Dajokan and gave broad authority to the Dajo-daijin (Grand Minister) was considered to be unsuited for the state administration of a modern nation, and Dajo-daijin&apos;s broad responsibilities caused delays in the national management and an obscure locus of responsibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this system, which concentrated all the state&apos;s legislative, judiciary and administrative functions in the Daijokan and gave broad authority to the Dajo-daijin (High Chancellor) was thought to be ill-suited for the political management of a modern nation; the High Chancellor&apos;s extensive responsibilities caused delays in the political management of the nation and invited confusion over who had responsibility for which tasks.</e>
<cmt>Poor structure, phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this system, which concentrated all the state&apos;s legislative, judiciary and administrative functions in the Daijokan and gave broad authority to the Dajo-daijin (Grand Minister) was thought to be ill-suited for the political management of a modern nation; the High Chancellor&apos;s extensive responsibilities caused delays in the political management of the nation and invited confusion over who had responsibility for which tasks.</e>
<cmt>Dajo-daijin (High Chancellor)→Dajo-daijin (Grand Minister) に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そこで新たな制度を構築する必要に迫られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was when the government had to build the new regulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was at this point that the government recognized the necessity of creating a new set of regulations.</e>
<cmt>Poor phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was at this point that the government recognized the necessity of creating a new set of regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>明治18年太政官達第69号と内閣職権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dajokan tasshi no. 69 of 1885 and Naikaku-shokken</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 1885 Daijokan tasshi no. 69 and the Naikaku-shokken</e>
<cmt>Minor structural problems, missing definite article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 1885 Daijokan tasshi no. 69 and the Naikaku-shokken</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1885年（明治18年）、新しい国家運営の制度である合議体の内閣が定められた（明治18年太政官達第69号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1885, the Cabinet as a collegiate body, the new system for the national administration, was set up (Dajokan tasshi no. 69 of 1885).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1885 the government created a new system to manage the nation: a Cabinet as a collegiate body (as stipulated in the 1885 Daijokan tasshi no. 69).</e>
<cmt>Structure, phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1885 the government created a new system to manage the nation: a Cabinet as a collegiate body (as stipulated in the 1885 Daijokan tasshi no. 69).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その内容は、おおむね次のとおり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The content is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The particulars were as follows:</e>
<cmt>Structure, phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The particulars were as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>太政大臣、左右大臣、参議及び各省卿の職制を廃し、新たに内閣総理大臣並びに宮内省、外務省、内務省 (日本)、大蔵省、陸軍省、海軍省、司法省、文部省、農商務省 (日本)及び逓信省の各大臣を置くこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To abolish government posts of the Grand Ministers of State, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry, and establish posts of the Prime Minister and the Ministers of Imperial Household, Foreign Affairs, Interior, Finance, Army, Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Posts and Telecommunications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cabinet positions of High Chancellor, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry were abolished, while the post of Prime Minister and that of the various government Ministers, namely of the Imperial Household, Foreign Affairs, the Interior, Finance, the Army, the Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Communications and Transportation, were established.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cabinet positions of High Chancellor, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry were abolished, while the post of Prime Minister and that of the various government Ministers, namely of the Imperial Household, Foreign Affairs, the Interior, Finance, the Army, the Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Communications and Transportation, were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>内閣総理大臣及び各大臣（宮内大臣を除く。）をもって、内閣 (日本)を組織すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To form the Cabinet with the Prime Minister and Ministers (excluding Imperial Household Minister).</e>
<cmt>「）をもって、内閣 (日本)を組織すること。」で文章が分割されていましたので、一文に統合致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Cabinet consisting of the Prime Minister and the various Ministers (excluding the Imperial Household Minister) was formed.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Cabinet consisting of the Prime Minister and the various Ministers (excluding the Imperial Household Minister) was formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>これにより、宮中（宮廷）と府中（政府）の別が明定され、行政責任を各省大臣が個別に負う体制の基礎が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the distinction between the Imperial court and the government offices was clarified and the basis of the system that an administrative responsibility was taken individually by each minister was originated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These steps clarified the separation between the Imperial court and the government, and created the foundation of a governmental system in which each minister took a share of administrative responsibility.</e>
<cmt>Unnecessary passive voice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These steps clarified the separation between the Imperial court and the government, and created the foundation of a governmental system in which each minister took a share of administrative responsibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>初代の内閣総理大臣には、参議であった伊藤博文が任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirobumi ITO, a former Councillor, was appointed as the first Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirobumi ITO, a former Councillor, was appointed as the first Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirobumi ITO, a former Councillor, was appointed as the first Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="15">
<j>また、同時に定められた内閣職権（全7条）によって、内閣機構の運営基準、主として内閣総理大臣の職務権限が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, a guideline for the management of the Cabinet system, mainly about the Prime Minister&apos;s controlling power, was stipulated in Naikaku-shokken (seven articles in all), that was established at the same time as Dajokan tasshi no. 69 of 1885.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, with passage of the Naikaku-shokken (&quot;the powers of each Cabinet position,&quot; which had seven articles in all), put in place at the same time as the Daijokan tasshi no. 69., guidelines--mainly concerned with defining the limits of the Prime Minister&apos;s power--for the management of the Cabinet system were established.</e>
<cmt>Awkward structure, phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, with passage of the Naikaku-shokken (&quot;the powers of each Cabinet position,&quot; which had seven articles in all), put in place at the same time as the Daijokan tasshi no. 69, guidelines--mainly concerned with defining the limits of the Prime Minister&apos;s power--for the management of the Cabinet system were established.</e>
<cmt>不要なピリオドを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>内閣総理大臣は「内閣ノ首班トシ機務ヲ奏宣シ旨ヲ承テ大政ノ方向ヲ指示」（2条）し、また「行政全部ヲ統督」（4条）すると定められ、少なくとも形式上は強力な権限を与えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Naikaku-shokken, it was written that the Prime Minister &apos;shall report state affairs to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instruction, and direct the course of policies as a chief among ministers&apos; (Article no. 2) and &apos;maintain the unity among the different branches of the administration&apos; (Article no. 4), thus at least the Prime Minister was formally given wide authorities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-shokken stipulated that the Prime Minister &quot;shall report state affairs to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instructions, and direct the course of policies as the first among ministers&quot; (Article 2) and &quot;maintain unity among the different branches of the administration&apos; (Article 4); the Prime Minister, therefore, possessed extensive authority, at least formally.</e>
<cmt>Poor phrasing, grammar/word choice (&quot;authorities&quot;)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-shokken stipulated that the Prime Minister &quot;shall report state affairs to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instructions, and direct the course of policies as the first among ministers&quot; (Article 2) and &quot;maintain unity among the different branches of the administration&quot; (Article 4); the Prime Minister, therefore, possessed extensive authority, at least formally.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし実際には、藩閥が対立均衡している下で、内閣が十分に力を発揮することは難しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in reality, it was difficult for the Cabinet to function effectively under the circumstance that the domain cliques were at feud.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet in reality, given the context of feuding among the domainal cliques, it was quite difficult for the Cabinet to function effectively.</e>
<cmt>Awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet in reality, given the context of feuding among the domainal cliques, it was quite difficult for the Cabinet to function effectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="18">
<j>法文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of the Law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Text of the Law</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation (&quot;letter of the law&quot; has a special meaning)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Text of the Law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>太政大臣左右大臣参議各省卿ノ職制ヲ廃シ内閣総理大臣及各省諸大臣ヲ置キ内閣ヲ組織ス（明治18年太政官達第69号）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To abolish government posts of the Grand Ministers of State, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry, and establish posts of the Prime Minister and the Ministers of each ministry to form the Cabinet (Dajokan tasshi no. 69 of 1885).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government posts of High Chancellor, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry shall be abolished, and the posts of Prime Minister and the Ministers of each ministry, whom together shall form the Cabinet, shall be established (the 1885 Daijokan tasshi no. 69).</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government posts of High Chancellor, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry shall be abolished, and the posts of Prime Minister and the Ministers of each ministry, whom together shall form the Cabinet, shall be established (the 1885 Daijokan tasshi no. 69).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>今般太政大臣左右大臣参議各省卿ノ職制ヲ廃シ更ニ内閣総理大臣及宮内外務内務大蔵陸軍海軍司法文部農商務逓信ノ諸大臣ヲ置ク</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To abolish government posts of the Grand Ministers of State, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry, and establish posts of the Prime Minister and the Ministers of Imperial Household, Foreign Affairs, Interior, Finance, Army, Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Posts and Telecommunications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government posts of High Chancellor, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry shall be abolished, and the posts of Prime Minister and the Ministers of Imperial Household, Foreign Affairs, the Interior, Finance, the Army, the Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Communications and Transportation shall be established.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government posts of High Chancellor, the Ministers of the Left and Right, the Councillors and the Lords of each Ministry shall be abolished, and the posts of Prime Minister and the Ministers of Imperial Household, Foreign Affairs, the Interior, Finance, the Army, the Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Communications and Transportation shall be established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>内閣総理大臣及外務内務大蔵陸軍海軍司法文部農商務逓信ノ諸大臣ヲ以テ内閣ヲ組織ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To form the Cabinet by the Prime Minister and the Ministers of Foreign Affairs, Interior, Finance, Army, Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Posts and Telecommunications.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cabinet shall be formed, and shall consist of the Prime Minister and the Ministers of Foreign Affairs, the Interior, Finance, the Army, the Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Communication and Transportation.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cabinet shall be formed, and shall consist of the Prime Minister and the Ministers of Foreign Affairs, the Interior, Finance, the Army, the Navy, Justice, Education, Agriculture and Commerce, and Communication and Transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>内閣職権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-shokken</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-shokken</e>
<cmt>Missing definite article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-shokken</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>第一條　内閣天皇ノ直轄ニ屬シ大權ノ施行ニ關シ國務大臣輔弼ノ任ヲ致ス所トス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 1 The Cabinet shall be placed under the direct control of the Emperor and the State Ministers shall make advices to the Emperor with full responsibility of the results when the prerogative is to be exercised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 1: The Cabinet shall be under the direct control of the Emperor, and when appropriate, the State Ministers shall advise the Emperor and shall have full responsibility for the outcome.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 1: The Cabinet shall be under the direct control of the Emperor, and when appropriate, the State Ministers shall advise the Emperor and shall have full responsibility for the outcome.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>第二條　内閣總理大臣ハ内閣ノ首班トシ機務ヲ奏宣シ旨ヲ承テ大政ノ方向ヲ指示スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 2 The Prime Minister shall report state affairs to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instruction and direct the course of policies as a chief among ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 2: The Prime Minister shall report on the affairs of state to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instructions and direct the course of policies as the first among ministers.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 2: The Prime Minister shall report on the affairs of state to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instructions and direct the course of policies as the first among ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>第三條　内閣總理大臣ハ内閣ノ會議ヲ總括シ議事ヲ整理スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 3 The Prime Minister shall control the Cabinet meetings and organize proceedings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 3: The Prime Minister shall be in charge of Cabinet meetings and direct the proceedings.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 3: The Prime Minister shall be in charge of Cabinet meetings and direct the proceedings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>第四條　内閣總理大臣ハ行政全部ヲ統督シ各部ノ成績ニ付説明ヲ求メ及ヒ之ヲ檢明スルコトヲ得</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 4 The Prime Minister shall supervise all the administrations and has the right to demand the explanation of each minister&apos;s result and to examine it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 4: The Prime Minister shall oversee the entire administration and shall possess the right to demand an explanation of and investigate into each minister&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 4: The Prime Minister shall oversee the entire administration and shall possess the right to demand an explanation of and investigate into each minister&apos;s performance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>第五條　凢ソ法律勅令ニハ内閣總理大臣之ニ副署シ、其各省主任ノ事務ニ屬スルモノハ内閣總理大臣及主任大臣之ニ副署スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 5 Laws and ordinances shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and each ministry&apos;s duties shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and the State Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 5: Laws and ordinances shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister, and the work of each ministry shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and the Cabinet Minister of the ministry in question.</e>
<cmt>Minor phrasing problem</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 5: Laws and ordinances shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister, and the work of each ministry shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and the Cabinet Minister of the ministry in question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>第六條　各國務大臣ノ任免ハ内閣總理大臣之ヲ奏宣シ、内閣總理大臣ノ任免ハ首席國務大臣之ヲ奏宣ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 6 The appointment and dismissal of a State Minister shall be reported to the Emperor by the Prime Minister, and the appointment and dismissal of the Prime Minister shall be reported to the Emperor by the chief State Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 6: Any appointments or dismissals of Cabinet Ministers shall be reported to the Emperor by the Prime Minister, and the appointment or dismissal of the Prime Minister shall be reported to the Emperor by the ranking Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>Minor phrasing problem</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 6: Any appointments or dismissals of Cabinet Ministers shall be reported to the Emperor by the Prime Minister, and the appointment or dismissal of the Prime Minister shall be reported to the Emperor by the ranking Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>第七條　各大臣事故アルトキハ臨時命ヲ承ケテ他ノ大臣其事務ヲ管理スルコトアルヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 7 The duties of a disabled State Minister shall be performed by another State Minister on temporary order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 7: In the event a Minister of State is incapacitated, a temporary order shall be issued assigning his or her duties to another Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>Minor phrasing problem</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 7: In the event a Minister of State is incapacitated, a temporary order shall be issued assigning his or her duties to another Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="30">
<j>内閣官制（明治22年勅令第135号）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei (the Imperial Ordinance no. 135 of 1889)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 135, of 1889)</e>
<cmt>Missing definite article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 135, of 1889)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1889年（明治22年）、大日本帝国憲法が公布された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1889, the Constitution of the Empire of Japan was promulgated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1889, the Constitution of the Empire of Japan was promulgated.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1889, the Constitution of the Empire of Japan was promulgated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この憲法では、天皇が統治権を総攬するものとし、「国務各大臣ハ天皇ヲ輔弼シ其ノ責ニ任ス」（55条1項）と定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this Constitution, the Emperor had the complete right of sovereignty, and it was stated that &apos;the respective State Ministers shall give their advice to the Emperor, and be responsible for it&apos; (First paragraph of Article no. 55).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under this constitution, the Emperor had the right of absolute sovereignty, and it was stated that &quot;the respective State Ministers shall advise the Emperor, and shall be held responsible for the outcome of their advice&quot; (first paragraph of Article no. 55).</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under this constitution, the Emperor had the right of absolute sovereignty, and it was stated that &quot;the respective State Ministers shall advise the Emperor, and shall be held responsible for the outcome of their advice&quot; (first paragraph of Article no. 55).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、内閣についての規定は、憲法にはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was no stipulation on the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 1889 constitution did not, however, include any regulations on the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 1889 constitution did not, however, include any regulations on the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>行政権は国務各大臣の輔弼により天皇が自ら行うものとされ、内閣は国務各大臣の協議と意思統一のための組織体にすぎないものとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor himself exercised the administrative power, enlisting the aid of State Ministers, and the Cabinet was therefore established merely as a consultative body where State Ministers engaged in discussion to ensure that their opinions were consistent with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The executive power of the government was under the personal control of the Emperor, who was assisted by the Ministers of State, and so the Cabinet was originally established merely as a consultative body, within which Ministers of State engaged in discussion to ensure that their opinions were consistent with each other.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The executive power of the government was under the personal control of the Emperor, who was assisted by the Ministers of State, and so the Cabinet was originally established merely as a consultative body, within which Ministers of State engaged in discussion to ensure that their opinions were consistent with each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>同年12月24日、内閣制度運営の基準として、内閣官制（明治22年勅令第135号）が公布される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 24 of the same year, Naikaku-kansei (the Imperial Ordinance no. 135 of 1889) was promulgated as a guideline for management of the Cabinet system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 24 of the same year (1889), the government promulgated the Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 135, of 1889), a set of guidelines for managing the Cabinet system.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing, passive voice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 24 of the same year (1889), the government promulgated the Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 135, of 1889), a set of guidelines for managing the Cabinet system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>その内容はほぼ内閣職権を引き継いだが、内閣総理大臣の権限は弱められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Naikaku-kansei largely took over the contents of its predecessor, Naikaku-shokken, it weakened the controlling power of the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although in terms of content the Naikaku-kansei largely continued along the same lines as those of its predecessor, the Naikaku-shokken, it did weaken the power and authority of the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although in terms of content the Naikaku-kansei largely continued along the same lines as those of its predecessor, the Naikaku-shokken, it did weaken the power and authority of the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「内閣総理大臣ハ各大臣ノ首班トシテ機務ヲ奏宣シ旨ヲ承ケテ行政各部ノ統一ヲ保持ス」（2条）と定めていたが、この「首班」とは「同輩中の首席」を意味すると解された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei stated that &apos;the Prime Minister shall report state affairs to the Emperor as a chief among ministers, receive the Emperor&apos;s instruction, and maintain the unity among the different branches of the administration&apos; (Article no. 2), however, in the above, &apos;chief&apos; just meant &apos;prima inter pares.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-kansei stipulated that &quot;as the head among the ministers, the Prime Minister shall report affairs of state to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instructions, and maintain unity among the different branches of the administration&apos; (Article no. 2), but the abovementioned &apos;head&apos; meant simply &apos;prima inter pares&apos; (first among equals).</e>
<cmt>Phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-kansei stipulated that &quot;as the head among the ministers, the Prime Minister shall report affairs of state to the Emperor, receive the Emperor&apos;s instructions, and maintain unity among the different branches of the administration&quot; (Article no. 2), but the abovementioned &quot;head&quot; meant simply &quot;prima inter pares&quot; (first among equals).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="38">
<j>法文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of the Law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Text of the Law</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Text of the Law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>内閣官制(明治22年勅令第135号)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei (the Imperial Ordinance no. 135 of 1889)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 135, of 1889)</e>
<cmt>Unnecessary definite article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 135, of 1889)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>第一条　内閣ハ国務各大臣ヲ以テ組織ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 1 The Cabinet shall be organized by each Minister of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 1: The several Ministers of State shall form the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 1: The several Ministers of State shall form the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>第二条　内閣総理大臣ハ各大臣ノ首班トシテ機務ヲ奏宣シ旨ヲ承ケテ行政各部ノ統一ヲ保持ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 2 The Prime Minister shall report state affairs to the Emperor, receive his instruction, direct the course of policies, and supervise each organ of the administration as a chief among ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 2: The Prime Minister, as the head among the ministers, shall report affairs of state to the Emperor, receive his instructions, direct the course of policies, and supervise each organ of the administration.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 2: The Prime Minister, as the head among the ministers, shall report affairs of state to the Emperor, receive his instructions, direct the course of policies, and supervise each organ of the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>第三条　内閣総理大臣ハ須要ト認ムルトキハ行政各部ノ処分又ハ命令ヲ中止セシメ勅裁ヲ待ツコトヲ得</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 3 The Prime Minister has the right to cancel proceedings or orders of each organ of the administration and to request the Emperor&apos;s decision when necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 3: The Prime Minister has the right to cancel proceedings or orders of any organ of the administration and when necessary to request the Emperor make a decision.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 3: The Prime Minister has the right to cancel proceedings or orders of any organ of the administration and when necessary to request the Emperor make a decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>第四条　凡ソ法律及一般ノ行政ニ係ル勅令ハ内閣総理大臣及主任大臣之ニ副署スヘシ　勅令ノ各省專任ノ行政事務ニ屬スル者ハ主任ノ各省大臣之ニ副署スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 4 Ordinances concerning laws and general administration shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and the State Minister, and ordinances concerning each ministry&apos;s duties shall be countersigned by the State Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 4: Imperial edicts concerning laws and general administration shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and the State Minister, and imperial edicts concerning each ministry&apos;s duties shall be countersigned by the Minister of State of the ministry in question.</e>
<cmt>Slight problem at the end of the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 4: Imperial edicts concerning laws and general administration shall be countersigned by the Prime Minister and the State Minister, and imperial edicts concerning each ministry&apos;s duties shall be countersigned by the Minister of State of the ministry in question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>第五条　左ノ各件ハ閣議ヲ経ヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 5 The matters below shall be submitted to the Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 5: All the items described below shall be discussed at a Cabinet meeting:</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 5: All the items described below shall be discussed at a Cabinet meeting:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>一　法律案及予算決算案</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 Draft laws and budget proposals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1) Legislative bills and budget proposals</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1) Legislative bills and budget proposals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>二　外国条約及重要ナル国際条件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2 Foreign treaties and important international terms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2) Foreign treaties and critical international matters</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2) Foreign treaties and critical international matters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>三　官制又ハ規則及法律施行ニ係ル勅令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3 Ordinances concerning government-regulated organizations or regulations and enforcement of laws</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3) Imperial edicts concerning government-regulated organizations, regulations, or enforcement of laws</e>
<cmt>Word choice (chokurei should be translated &quot;imperial edicts/decrees&quot;)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3) Imperial edicts concerning government-regulated organizations, regulations, or enforcement of laws</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>四　諸省ノ間主管権限ノ争議</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4 Inter-ministerial disputes over authority</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4) Inter-ministry disputes over authority</e>
<cmt>Slight phrasing problem</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4) Inter-ministry disputes over authority</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>五　天皇ヨリ下付セラレ又ハ帝国議会ヨリ送致スル人民ノ請願</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5 Popular petitions sent by the Emperor or Imperial Diet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5) Popular petitions submitted by the Emperor or the Imperial Diet</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5) Popular petitions submitted by the Emperor or the Imperial Diet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>六　予算外ノ支出</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">6 Extrabudgetary expenditures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">6) Extrabudgetary expenditures</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">6) Extrabudgetary expenditures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>七　勅任官及地方長官ノ任命及進退</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">7 Appointment and dismissal of imperial appointees and local governors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">7) Any appointments or dismissals of imperial appointees or local governors</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">7) Any appointments or dismissals of imperial appointees or local governors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>其ノ他各省主任ノ事務ニ就キ高等行政ニ関係シ事体稍重キモノハ総テ閣議ヲ経ヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, each minister shall be engaged in their office matters and all the important matters concerning high administration shall be discussed at a Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note also that each minister shall handle the general tasks facing his or her ministry, while any important matters concerning high-level administration shall be discussed at a Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note also that each minister shall handle the general tasks facing his or her ministry, while any important matters concerning high-level administration shall be discussed at a Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>第六条　主任大臣ハ其ノ所見ニ由リ何等ノ件ヲ問ハス内閣総理大臣ニ提出シ閣議ヲ求ムルコトヲ得</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 6 Ministers have the right to submit any matter of his responsibility to the Prime Minister and to request to hold a Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 6: Each minister has the right to submit any matter for which he or she is responsible to the Prime Minister, and may request a Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 6: Each minister has the right to submit any matter for which he or she is responsible to the Prime Minister, and may request a Cabinet meeting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>第七条　事ノ軍機軍令ニ係リ奏上スルモノハ天皇ノ旨ニ依リ之ヲ内閣ニ下付セラルルノ件ヲ除ク外陸軍大臣海軍大臣ヨリ内閣総理大臣ニ報告スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 7 Military orders and strategies in wartime shall be reported to the Emperor, and except the ones sent to the Cabinet by order of the Emperor, they shall be reported to the Prime Minister by Minister of Army or Navy.</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため、下記ＨＰの解釈を参考にしました。http://ww1.m78.com/topix-2/meiji%20constitution.html「戦時における作戦は参謀総長が天皇に直接報告することがあるが、それ以外は陸軍大臣を通して首相に直ちに報告し、また戦時の作戦についても天皇への報告後直ちに首相に報告する」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 7: In wartime, military strategy and orders shall be reported to the Emperor, and with the exception of any directives sent to the Cabinet by order of the Emperor, all such military decisions shall be reported to the Prime Minister by the Minister of the Army or Navy.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 7: In wartime, military strategy and orders shall be reported to the Emperor, and with the exception of any directives sent to the Cabinet by order of the Emperor, all such military decisions shall be reported to the Prime Minister by the Minister of the Army or Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>第八条　内閣総理大臣故障アルトキハ他ノ大臣臨時命ヲ承ケ其ノ事務ヲ代理スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 8 The duties of the disabled Prime Minister shall be performed by a State Minister on temporary order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 8: In the event the Prime Minister is incapacitated, a temporary order shall be issued assigning his or her duties to another Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 8: In the event the Prime Minister is incapacitated, a temporary order shall be issued assigning his or her duties to another Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>第九条　各省大臣故障アルトキハ他ノ大臣臨時摂任シ又ハ命ヲ承ケ其ノ事務ヲ管理スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 9 The duties of a disabled State Minister shall be performed by another State Minister, or his office matters shall be managed by order by another State Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 9: In the event the Prime Minister is incapacitated, either a temporary order shall be issued transferring his or her duties to another Minister of State or an order shall be issued assigning the tasks of his office to be managed by another State Minister.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 9: In the event the State Minister is incapacitated, either a temporary order shall be issued transferring his or her duties to another Minister of State or an order shall be issued assigning the tasks of his office to be managed by another State Minister.</e>
<cmt>主語がPrime Ministerになっていたので、State Ministerに修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>第十条　各省大臣ノ外特旨ニ依リ国務大臣トシテ内閣員ニ列セシメラルルコトアルヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 10 Ministers without portfolio shall be a member of the Cabinet by special order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 10: Ministers of State not placed in charge of any ministries may be made members of the Cabinet by special order.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 10: Ministers of State not placed in charge of any ministries may be made members of the Cabinet by special order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="58">
<j>内閣官制中改正ノ件(明治40年勅令第7号)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amendment of Naikaku-kansei (Ordinance no. 7 of 1907)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amendment to the Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 7, of 1907)</e>
<cmt>Missing &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amendment to the Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 7, of 1907)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>1907年（明治40年）公文式 (勅令)廃止・公式令制定に伴って内閣官制を改正した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei was amended in 1907 at the same time as the abolition of Kobunshiki (Imperial ordinance) and the establishment of Koshikirei (renewed version of Kobunshiki).</e>
<cmt>公式令（くしきりょう）とは違う公式令（こうしきれい）のため用語例を使用していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-kansei was amended in 1907 with the abolition of the Kobunshiki (an Imperial edict) and the passage of the Koshikirei (an amended version of the Kobunshiki).</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-kansei was amended in 1907 with the abolition of the Kobunshiki (an Imperial edict) and the passage of the Koshikirei (an amended version of the Kobunshiki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この改正では、内閣官制第四条にあった勅令副署規定を公式令に移し、公文式にあった内閣総理大臣の閣令制定権をここに移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this amendment, Chokurei fukusho kitei (Imperial ordinance for the rules of countersignature) stipulated in Naikaku-kansei Article no. 4 was moved to Koshikirei, and the Prime Minister&apos;s right to issue a cabinet order in Kobunshiki was moved to Naikaku-shokken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this amendment, the Chokurei fukusho kitei (an Imperial edict on the rules of countersignature), stipulated in Article 4 of the Naikaku-kansei, was moved to the Koshikirei, while the right of the Prime Minister to issue cabinet orders, as recorded in the Kobunshiki, was moved to the Naikaku-shokken.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this amendment, the Chokurei fukusho kitei (an Imperial edict on the rules of countersignature), stipulated in Article 4 of the Naikaku-kansei, was moved to the Koshikirei, while the right of the Prime Minister to issue cabinet orders, as recorded in the Kobunshiki, was moved to the Naikaku-shokken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>その際、各省大臣の単独副署の制度が廃止され、全ての勅令に内閣総理大臣が副署することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, the rule of each minister&apos;s single countersignature had been abolished and it was decided that all the Imperial ordinances had to be countersigned by the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, the rule that each minister could countersign laws and so forth by him or herself was abolished, and it was decided that all Imperial edicts had to be countersigned by the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, the rule that each minister could countersign laws and so forth by him or herself was abolished, and it was decided that all Imperial edicts had to be countersigned by the Prime Minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また、第四条ノニにおいて、内閣総理大臣の地方官庁に対する職権を明確にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the Prime Minister&apos;s administrative power over local governments was clarified in Article no. 4-2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Article 4 section two clarified the extent of the Prime Minister&apos;s administrative power over local governments.</e>
<cmt>Slightly awkward phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Article 4 section two clarified the extent of the Prime Minister&apos;s administrative power over local governments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>ともに内閣総理大臣の権限を強化するものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both of the above were to strengthen the Prime Minister&apos;s public authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both of the above changes were enacted in order to strengthen the Prime Minister&apos;s power and authority.</e>
<cmt>Minor phrasing issue</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both of the above changes were enacted in order to strengthen the Prime Minister&apos;s power and authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="64">
<j>法文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter of the Law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Text of the Law</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Text of the Law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>内閣官制中改正ノ件(明治40年勅令第7号)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amendment of Naikaku-kansei (Ordinance no. 7 of 1907)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amendment to the Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 7, of 1907)</e>
<cmt>Structure, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amendment to the Naikaku-kansei (Imperial edict no. 7, of 1907)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>内閣官制中左ノ通改正ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naikaku-kansei has been amended as below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naikaku-kansei was amended as follows:</e>
<cmt>Grammar (unnecessary present perfect)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naikaku-kansei was amended as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>第四条　内閣総理大臣ハ其ノ職権又ハ特別ノ委任ニ依リ閣令ヲ発スルコトヲ得</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 4 The Prime Minister has the right to issue a cabinet order according to his authority or special commission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 4: The Prime Minister has the right, either through his own authority or by special commission, to issue cabinet orders.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 4: The Prime Minister has the right, either through his own authority or by special commission, to issue cabinet orders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>第四条ノ二　内閣総理大臣ハ所管ノ事務ニ付警視総監、北海道庁長官府県知事ヲ指揮監督ス若シ其ノ命令又ハ処分ノ成規ニ違ヒ、公益ヲ害シ又ハ権限ヲ犯スモノアリト認ムルトキハ之ヲ停止シ又ハ取消スコトヲ得</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 4-2 The Prime Minister shall control and supervise the Chief Commissioner of the Metropolitan Police and the director general and prefectural governor of the Hokkaido government, but if his order or proceeding is against the regulations and is considered to harm the public interest or authority, it shall be stopped or cancelled.</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため、わかる範囲で訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 4, section two: The Prime Minister shall oversee and supervise the Chief Commissioner of the Metropolitan Police (of Tokyo) and the Director-general and prefectural governor of the government of Hokkaido, but if any of the Prime Minister&apos;s orders or directives is found to be against regulations or considered harmful to the public interest or authority, it shall be suspended or revoked.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 4, section two: The Prime Minister shall oversee and supervise the Chief Commissioner of the Metropolitan Police (of Tokyo) and the Director-general and prefectural governor of the government of Hokkaido, but if any of the Prime Minister&apos;s orders or directives is found to be against regulations or considered harmful to the public interest or authority, it shall be suspended or revoked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>附則　本令ハ公布ノ日ヨリ之ヲ施行ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Supplementary provision This ordinance shall be in force on or after the date of its promulgation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supplementary provision: This ordinance shall be in force from the date of its promulgation.</e>
<cmt>Slight phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supplementary provision: This ordinance shall be in force from the date of its promulgation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 春野秋葉(id:36725), ペトチザン(id:19878), 磯多申紋(id:36455), 俊平太郎(id:34056), PPP(id:22924), 無言雀師(id:13124), MIsogi(id:20599), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>