<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>尊王攘夷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sonno Joi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sonno Joi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonno Joi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>尊王攘夷（そんのうじょうい、尊攘）とは、王を尊び外圧・外敵を撃退しなければならないとする思想。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sonno Joi is a philosophy of respect for the Emperor and rejection of external pressures and foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sonno Joi is a philosophy of respect for the Emperor and rejection of external pressures and foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonno Joi is a philosophy of respect for the Emperor and rejection of external pressures and foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では、幕末に朝廷から一般民衆まで熱く論じられ、反体制運動の合言葉ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, at the end of the Edo period, everyone from Chotei Court officials to the general public were talking about it passionately and the phase became a watchword for the anti-establishment movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it was discussed passionately among people from Chotei Court officials to the general public at the end of the Edo period and became a watchword for the anti-establishment movement.</e>
<cmt>主語を合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it was discussed passionately among people from Chotei Court officials to the general public at the end of the Edo period and became a watchword for the anti-establishment movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>国の存在の根拠としての尊王と、侵掠・侵入してくる外敵に対抗する攘夷が結びついたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The phase was coined from two separate words - Sonno as the base of the country, and Joi to stand against foreign invaders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The phase was coined from Sonno as the base of the country and Joi to stand against foreign invaders.</e>
<cmt>簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The phase was coined from Sonno as the base of the country and Joi to stand against foreign invaders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「王（きみ＝天子）を尊び、夷（い＝外国人）を攘（はら）う」の意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means &apos;Son 尊(respect) O 王 (Emperor) jo 攘(expel) i 夷 (foreigners)&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It means &apos;Son 尊(respect) O 王 (Emperor) jo 攘(expel) i 夷 (foreigners)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It means &apos;Son 尊(respect) O 王 (Emperor) jo 攘(expel) i 夷 (foreigners)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>古代中国の春秋時代において、周王朝の天子（王）を尊び、王朝を守るため侵入する夷狄（いてき＝周辺諸民族。この時代の夷狄は南方の楚を指していた）を打ち払う、という意味で覇者が用いた標語を、国学者が輸入して流用したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Chunqiu period in China, a leader used a slogan meaning &apos;To respect (尊) the Emperor (王) and protect Zhou Dynasty, we have to expel the iteki (夷狄 [which at that time meant unfamiliar tribes of the Chu Dynasty, to the south of Zhou Dynasty]); and a scholar of Japanese classic literature imported and used this catchphrase.</e>
<cmt>「覇者」は&quot;hegemon&quot;としても一般に分かる単語かどうか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Chunqiu period in China, the leader used the slogan meaning &apos;To respect (尊) the Emperor (王) and protect Zhou Dynasty, we have to expel the iteki (夷狄 [unfamiliar tribes, at that time the Chu Dynasty to the south of Zhou Dynasty]),&apos; and scholars of Japanese classic literature imported to use it.</e>
<cmt>「覇者」をthe rulerとし、「夷狄」の説明も変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Chunqiu period in China, the leader used the slogan meaning &apos;To respect (尊) the Emperor (王) and protect Zhou Dynasty, we have to expel the iteki (夷狄 [unfamiliar tribes, at that time the Chu Dynasty to the south of Zhou Dynasty]),&apos; and scholars of Japanese classic literature imported to use it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>斉 (春秋)の桓公 (斉)は、周室への礼を失せず、諸侯を一致団結させて、楚に代表される夷狄を討伐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duke Huan of Qi (a state in Zhou Dynasty), noted the disrespect to the Zhou royal house and gathered lords to attack iteki, including Chu, together and put them down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lord Huan of Qi (a state in Zhou Dynasty) held other lords together to subdue iteki including Chu without being disrespectful to the Zhou court.</e>
<cmt>「桓公」をLordに変更し、全体も言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lord Huan of Qi (a state in Zhou Dynasty) held other lords together to subdue iteki including Chu without being disrespectful to the Zhou court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、尊王攘夷を声高に唱えたのは、宋学の儒学者たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the scholars of Sung-period neo-Cunfucianism who talked loudly about Sonno Joi after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the scholars of Sung-period Neo-Cunfucianism who raised a loud voice about Sonno Joi after that.</e>
<cmt>動詞を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the scholars of Sung-period Neo-Cunfucianism who raised a loud voice about Sonno Joi after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なお、中国では、周の天子（王）を「王」のモデルとしていたことから、本来「尊王」と書くが、尊王論が日本に受容されるに際して「王」とは天皇のことであるという読み換えが行われたことから、天皇は単なる国王ではなく皇帝であるという優越意識を踏まえて「尊皇」に置き換えて用いることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, the model of the &apos;O&apos; (王) was the Emperor of the Chu, so they use the character &apos;王&apos; in &apos;尊王&apos; (Sonno) but when Sonnoron (Imperialism) was accepted in Japan, because &apos;王&apos; in Japan means the &apos;Emperor&apos; (皇) and the Japanese Emperor was not just a King but someone more revered, Sonno is sometimes written as &apos;尊皇&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Chinese character &apos;王&apos; was used in &apos;尊王&apos; (Sonno) in China because &apos;O&apos; (王) was modeled after the Emperor of the Zhou, Sonno was also written as &apos;尊皇&apos; because &apos;王&apos; had meant the &apos;Emperor&apos; (皇) in Japan who was not just a King but someone more revered since Sonnoron (Imperialism) was accepted in Japan</e>
<cmt>全体的に言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Chinese character &apos;王&apos; was used in &apos;尊王&apos; (Sonno) in China because &apos;O&apos; (王) was modeled after the Emperor of the Zhou, Sonno was also written as &apos;尊皇&apos; because &apos;王&apos; had meant the &apos;Emperor&apos; (皇) in Japan who was not just a King but someone more revered since Sonnoron (Imperialism) was accepted in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>尊王論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sonnoron (Imperialism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sonnoron (Imperialism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sonnoron (Imperialism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本における尊王論とは、『古事記』・『日本書紀』が日本という国家の根拠を示したことに基づいて、日本国の存在の根拠を天皇（神）に依ろう、とする考え方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, Sonnoron is, based on the concept of Japan as a nation defined in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), a philosophy that held that the existence of Japan should be rooted in the belief that it was the will of the Emperor (God).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, Sonnoron is, based on the concept of Japan as a nation defined in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), a philosophy that the existence of Japan would have its origin from the will of the Emperor (God).</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, Sonnoron is a philosophy that, based on the concept of Japan as the nation defined in the &quot;Kojiki&quot; (The Records of Ancient Matters) and the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), claims that Japan exists because of the will of the Emperor (God).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>文化・民族・国の根拠を神に依ろうとする発想は世界共通のもので、王の権威は神から授かったのだという考えに依拠する王権神授説などその流れは多様。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The search to establish the relationship of culture, people and country with God occurred in nations all over the world but its history developed differently: for instance, there was the theory of the divine right of kings in which the authority of kings was thought to be granted by God.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The idea that the cultures, ethnic groups and nations originate in God is universal and developed differently, such as a theory of the divine right of kings in which the authority of kings is thought to be granted by God.</e>
<cmt>意訳と思われますので、前半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The idea that the cultures, ethnic groups and nations originate in God is universal and developed differently, such as a theory of the divine right of kings in which the authority of kings is thought to be granted by God.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>神に民族・国の根拠を依拠する思想は、その国・民族が危機に面するほど過激になるのも世界共通。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also the same all over the world, that the more a nation and its people face risks, the stronger the belief to put faith, and reason for being, in God become.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also the same all over the world that the idea that the ethnic groups and nations originate in God becomes radical as a nation and its people are in crisis.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also the same all over the world that the idea that the ethnic groups and nations originate in God becomes radical as a nation and its people are in crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>攘夷論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joiron (principle of excluding foreigners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joiron (principle of excluding foreigners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joiron (principle of excluding foreigners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>日本では、200年余り続いた江戸の太平の世の中では、外国のどこかへ行って物を取ってこよう、外国のどこかが日本に来て何かを持って行ってしまうかもしれない、という発想・実感はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, during the peaceful Edo period which lasted more than 200 years, people never thought about going overseas to get something or that someone might ever come to Japan one day to steal from them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, during the peaceful Edo period which had lasted more than 200 years, people never thought that they would go abroad to get something or that foreigners might ever come to Japan to steal something from them.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正し、後半を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, during the peaceful Edo period which had lasted more than 200 years, people never thought that they would go abroad to get something or that foreigners might ever come to Japan to steal something from them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが大航海時代以降世界に進出、支配領域を拡大したヨーロッパ、続く帝国主義の波に乗ったアメリカ合衆国によるアフリカ・アジア進出・侵略・植民地化は、東アジア各国にとっても脅威となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, European countries started to explore the world after the Age of Geographical Discovery to expand their areas of dominance, and the USA rode on the wave of continuous Imperialism. They travelled - from both sides of the world - toward Africa and Asia for incursions and colonization which became a threat for East Asian countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, European countries which started to explore the world after the Age of Geographical Discovery to expand their areas of dominance and the USA which rode on the wave of continuous Imperialism and made a foray into Africa and Asia for incursions and colonization became a threat for East Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文が二訳文になっていたため、一訳文に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, European countries which started to explore the world after the Age of Geographical Discovery to expand their areas of dominance and the USA which rode on the wave of continuous Imperialism and made a foray into Africa and Asia for incursions and colonization became a threat for East Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>アメリカ合衆国の東インド艦隊司令長官ペリーが来航した時には「泰平の眠りを覚ます上喜撰（蒸気船）、たった四杯で夜も眠れず」という狂歌が読まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Admiral Perry of the the East India Squadron visited Japan, this Kyoka (comic Tanka) was created: &quot;Jokisen woke me up from a long peaceful sleep, only four of them but kept me awake all night&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Admiral Perry of the the East India Squadron visited Japan, this Kyoka (comic Tanka) was created: &quot;Jokisen woke me up from a long peaceful sleep, only four of them but kept me awake all night&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Admiral Perry of the the East India Squadron visited Japan, this Kyoka (comic Tanka) was created: &apos;Jokisen woke me up from a long peaceful sleep, only four of them but kept me awake all night.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>＜上喜撰＞とは当時の玉露茶の商品名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&lt;Jokisen&gt; was also a name of Gyokuro green tea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&lt;Jokisen&gt; was also a name of Gyokuro green tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&lt;Jokisen&gt; was also a name of Gyokuro green tea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>上喜撰を飲んで「たった四杯で夜も眠れなくなる」ことと、異国の蒸気船が来航して「たった四杯（隻）で国中が蜂の巣をつついたような騒ぎとなり夜も眠れないでいる」こととをかけて世の騒動を揶揄している訳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Tanka was ambiguous with double meanings of &apos;four cups of Jokisen tea kept me awake all night&apos; and &apos;four steamboats created chaos in the whole country and the noise kept us from sleeping all night&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Tanka was cynical about the confusion by a double meaning of &apos;four cups of Jokisen tea kept us awake all night&apos; and &apos;four Jokisen (steamboats) created chaos in the whole country which kept us from sleeping all night&apos;.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Tanka was cynical about the confusion by a double meaning of &apos;four cups of Jokisen tea kept us awake all night&apos; and &apos;four Jokisen (steamboats) created chaos in the whole country which kept us from sleeping all night&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>中国南部では清国がイギリスと戦争（アヘン戦争）となり香港を奪われ、日本でも北海道でゴローウニン事件、九州でフェートン号事件といった例などの摩擦が起こり始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In southern China, Qing Dynasty went into the Opium War with England and lost Hong Kong, while in Japan, tension was building up after the several incidents such as the Golovnin Affair in Hokkaido and the Phaeton Incident in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Qing Dynasty went into the Opium War with England in southern China and lost Hong Kong, Japan began to face growing tension after the incidents such as the Golovnin Affair in Hokkaido and the Phaeton Incident in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>前半を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Qing Dynasty went into the Opium War with England in southern China and lost Hong Kong, Japan began to face growing tension after the incidents such as the Golovnin Affair in Hokkaido and the Phaeton Incident in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これに対応するためには、「開国」して外来者を受け入れ自らも外へ出て行くか、外来者を追い払って（これまでの）平和を維持するかのどちらかであるが、「攘夷」は後者の発想・考え方。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To deal with the situation, they could either accept foreign visitors by &apos;Kaikoku&apos; (opening the country to the world) and go overseas themselves, or expel the visitors to keep the (previous) peace but &apos;Joi&apos; was the idea and concept of the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although, to deal with the situation, they could either accept foreign visitors by &apos;Kaikoku&apos; (opening the country to the world) and go overseas themselves, or expel the visitors to keep the (previous) peace, &apos;Joi&apos; was the idea and concept of the latter.</e>
<cmt>butでの繋ぎをalthoughに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although, to deal with the situation, they could either accept foreign visitors by &apos;Kaikoku&apos; (opening the country to the world) and go overseas themselves, or expel the visitors to keep the (previous) peace, &apos;Joi&apos; was the idea and concept of the latter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、国内では国学 (学問)の普及にともなって民族意識がとみに高まった時代でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within Japan, it was a time that ethnic consciousness was rising rapidly together with the spread of Kokugaku (study of Japanese literature and culture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Japan, it was a time that ethnic consciousness was rising rapidly together with the spread of Kokugaku (study of Japanese literature and culture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Japan, it was a time that ethnic consciousness was rising rapidly together with the spread of Kokugaku (study of Japanese literature and culture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ことは複雑で事態は単純ではないが、大きな流れとしては、江戸幕末では「開国」を主張する徳川幕府や薩摩藩と、「攘夷」を主張する長州藩の対立となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the whole situation was very complex the major trend at the end of the Edo period was that the Tokugawa Shogunate and the Satsuma Domain who insisted on &apos;Kaikoku&apos; were ranged against the Choshu Domain who insisted on &apos;Joi&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the whole situation was very complex, the major trend at the end of the Edo period was that the Tokugawa Shogunate and the Satsuma Domain who insisted on opening Japan to the world were at odds with the Choshu Domain who insisted on expelling foreigners.</e>
<cmt>「開国」「攘夷」をそれぞれ訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the whole situation was very complex, the major trend at the end of the Edo period was that the Tokugawa Shogunate and the Satsuma Domain who insisted on opening Japan to the world were at odds with the Choshu Domain who insisted on expelling foreigners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ところが、欧米列国の圧力により修好通商条約に天皇が勅許を出した（1865年）ことにより「尊王」と「攘夷」は結びつかなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, under pressure from some European countries and America, the Emperor agreed to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce in 1865, which made it impossible for &apos;Sonno&apos; and &apos;Joi&apos; to be joined together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, under pressure from some European countries and America, the Emperor agreed to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce in 1865, which made it impossible for &apos;Sonno&apos; and &apos;Joi&apos; to be joined together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, under pressure from some European countries and America, the Emperor agreed to the Treaty of Amity and Commerce in 1865, which made it impossible for &apos;Sonno&apos; and &apos;Joi&apos; to be joined together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、津和野藩の大国隆正らによって、欧米列強の圧力を排するためには一時的に外国と開国してでも国内統一や富国強兵を優先すべきだとする大攘夷論が唱えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principle of Daijoiron was supported by some samurai such as Takamasa OKUNI of Tsuwano Domain and it was the concept that, to resist pressure from the allied western powers, it would be best to temporarily open the country to the world and give priority to uniting the whole country and fukoku kyohe (strengthening the military).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some samurai such as Takamasa OKUNI of Tsuwano Domain supported the principle of Daijoiron, which was the concept that, to resist pressure from the allied western powers, it would be best to temporarily open the country to the world and give priority to uniting the whole country and fukoku kyohei (strengthening the military).</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正し、能動態で言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some samurai such as Takamasa OKUNI of Tsuwano Domain supported the principle of Daijoiron, which was the concept that, to resist pressure from the allied western powers, it would be best to temporarily open the country to the world and give priority to uniting the whole country and fukoku kyohei (strengthening the military).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これは、「開国」と「攘夷」という相反する対外思想が「討幕」という一つの行動目的へと収斂される可能性を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused the conflicting principles of &apos;Kaikoku&apos; (opening the country and &apos;Joi&apos;(expelling foreigners) to converge and created the possibility of the goal of attacking the shogunate&apos;to be attained.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This created the possibility for the conflicting principles of opening the country and expelling foreigners to converge toward the goal of attacking the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>「開国」「攘夷」をそれぞれ訳出し、動詞をcreatedのみで言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This created the possibility for the conflicting principles of opening the country and expelling foreigners to converge toward the goal of attacking the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>土佐藩の坂本龍馬らの斡旋・仲介・手助けもあって、幕末日本の薩摩と長州の二大地方勢力は討幕へと向かっていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then later, with the intercession and help of Rhoma SAKAMOTO of Tosa Domain, two large local forces of Satsuma and Choshu Domains attacked the shogunate at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「斡旋・仲介・手助け」の３語を&quot;intercession/mediation/help&quot;と並べるとおかしいとネイティブに言われました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then later, with the intercession and help of Rhoma SAKAMOTO of Tosa Domain, two large local forces of Satsuma and Choshu Domains turned toward attacking the shogunate at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>intercessionのみで「斡旋・仲介」を表現できると思います。「向かっていく」の意を訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then later, with the intercession and help of Rhoma SAKAMOTO of Tosa Domain, two large local forces of Satsuma and Choshu Domains turned toward attacking the shogunate at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), JYOQ2(id:7240), Straysheep(id:42448), 経済準学士(id:22656), Punipico(id:25163), Aibot(id:104981), 味っ子(id:17086), Tector(id:139418), Qazzx(id:8772), Kinori(id:443), IwaimBot(id:190695), ぎぼうし(id:139427), Chobot(id:20846), Shimoxx(id:9332), Gewagewa(id:40129), Maakun(id:16735), Jpatokal(id:1566), Higashi(id:8842), BoB774(id:148281), しるふぃ(id:11247), Chi-Ham(id:143515), Law soma(id:45202), ZZZ(id:9462), BuxWV(id:169145), 右.翼団体幹部候補生(id:274325), 平成の光源氏(id:146498), 廿粁(id:219234), ＫｏＺ(id:48584), LaaknorBot(id:220851), 呆庵入道(id:74721), MDR-SK(id:192066), SilvonenBot(id:190970), YurikBot(id:18605), R28Bot(id:177951), Okippa(id:120238), 羊鶴(id:7557), Sug(id:5245), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>