<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Heian Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heian Period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>平安時代（へいあんじだい、794年-1185年頃）とは、794年に桓武天皇が平安京（京都）に都（首都）を移してから、鎌倉幕府の成立までの約390年間を指す日本の歴史の時代区分の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Heian period is a period of Japanese history of about 390 years, running from 794 when emperor Kanmu moved its capital to Heian Kyo (ancient Kyoto) to the establishment of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heian period denotes a period of Japanese history spanning roughly 390 years, from 794 when Emperor Kanmu moved the capital to Heian Kyo (ancient Kyoto) to the establishment of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heian period denotes a period of Japanese history spanning roughly 390 years, from 794 when Emperor Kanmu moved the capital to Heian Kyo (ancient Kyoto) to the establishment of the Kamakura Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in 1185.</e>
<cmt>年号を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>京都市におかれた平安京が、鎌倉幕府が成立するまで政治上の唯一の中心だったことから平安時代と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the period is named after the fact that Heian-Kyo in Kyoto City was the only political center before the establishment of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period is named so due to the fact that Heian-Kyo in Kyoto City was the only political center before the establishment of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period is named so due to the fact that Heian-Kyo in Kyoto City was the only political center before the establishment of the Kamakura Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安前期は、前代（奈良時代）からの中央集権的な律令制を、部分的な修正を加えながらも、基本的には継承していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Heian period, the Ritsuryo system of centralized governance structure from the former period (the Nara period) was basically continued with partial amendments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Heian period, the Ritsuryo system of centralized governance structure from the former period (the Nara period) was basically continued with partial amendments.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Heian period, the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) of centralized governance structure from the former period (the Nara period) was basically continued with partial amendments.</e>
<cmt>律令制の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、律令制と現実の乖離が大きくなっていき、9世紀末～10世紀初頭ごろ、政府は税収を確保するため、律令制の基本だった人別支配体制を改め、土地を対象に課税する支配体制へと大きく方針転換した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the the Ritsuryo system lost touch with the realities, the government changed its policy from the individual-based ruling system, which was the base of the the Ritsuryo system to a land-based ruling system in order to secure tax revenue from the end of the 9th century to the beginning of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the the Ritsuryo system lost touch with reality, the government changed its policy from an individual-based ruling system, which was the base of the the Ritsuryo system to a land-based ruling system in order to secure tax revenue from the end of the 9th century to the beginning of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the the Ritsuryo system lost touch with reality, the government changed its policy from an individual-based ruling system, which was the base of the the Ritsuryo system to a land-based ruling system in order to secure tax revenue from the end of the 9th century to the beginning of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>th の表記の変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この方針転換は、民間の有力者に権限を委譲してこれを現地赴任の筆頭国司（受領）が統括することにより新たな支配体制を構築するものであり、これを王朝国家体制という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this change was conducted to establish the new ruling system by delegating some power to local influential people under the control of the head of the provincial governors (the head of Kokushi, Zuryo), who were dispatched there, and the system is called the dynasty state system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This change was conducted to establish the new ruling system by delegating some power to local influential people under the control of the head of the provincial governors (the head of Kokushi, Zuryo), who were dispatched there: the system was called the dynasty state system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This change was conducted to establish the new ruling system by delegating some power to local influential people under the control of the head of the provincial governors (the head of Kokushi, Zuryo), who were dispatched there: the system was called the dynasty state system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>王朝国家体制期は、通常古代の末期に位置づけられるが、分権的な中世の萌芽期と位置づけることも可能であり、古代から中世への過渡期と理解されている（日本文学史研究においては「中古」という表現も用いられている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the dynasty system is usually placed at the end of the ancient times, it can be placed in groundbreaking years and interpreted as a transient period. (In the historical study of Japanese literature, the expression of &apos;Heian era&apos; is used.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the dynasty system is usually placed as having existed during the end of ancient times, it is also possible to place it during the early years of the middle age having a decentralized system and it is generally accepted as a transient period from the ancient period to the middle age (the expression &apos;Heian era&apos; is used in the historical study of Japanese literature).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flowRobert: Highlighted portion does not make sense - Edited to make more sense… however &quot;分権的な中世の萌芽期と位置づけること&quot; should probably be checked closely…and see if a more clearer translation could be made.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the dynasty system is usually placed as having existed during the end of ancient times, it is also possible to place it during the early years of the middle age having a decentralized system and it is generally accepted as a transient period from the ancient period to the middle age (the expression &apos;Chuko&apos; (literally, middle old) is used in the historical study of Japanese literature).</e>
<cmt>内容を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>王朝国家体制の下では、国家から土地経営や人民支配の権限を委譲された有力百姓（田堵・名主）層の成長が見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under this system, influential farmers, (Tato: farm managers who lease public fields from provincial lords and produce agricultural products; and Myoshu: owners of rice fields) to whom the power of managing land and controlling people was transmitted from the government, became powerful.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under this system, influential farmers, (Tato: farm managers who lease public fields from provincial lords and produce agricultural products; and Myoshu: owners of rice fields) to whom the management of land and control of people was transmitted from the government, became powerful.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under this system, influential farmers, (Tato: farm managers who lease public fields from provincial lords and produce agricultural products; and Myoshu: owners of rice fields) to whom the management of land and control of people was transmitted from the government, became powerful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>彼らの統制の必要からこの権限委譲と並行して、国家から軍事警察権を委譲された軍事貴族層や武芸専門の下級官人層もまた、武士として成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to govern the farmers, the government transmitted military and police power to military aristocracy and military art-specialized lower-ranking government officials. they developed into warriors (Bushi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to govern the farmers, the government transmitted military and police power to military aristocracy and military art-specialized lower-ranking government officials. these persons developed into warriors (Bushi).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to govern the farmers, the government transmitted military and police power to military aristocracy and military art-specialized lower-ranking government officials, who developed into warriors (Bushi).</e>
<cmt>二文を一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>国家権限の委譲とこれによる中央集権の過大な負担の軽減により、中央政界では政治が安定し、官職が特定の家業を担う家系に世襲される家職化が進み、貴族の最上位では摂関家が確立し、中流貴族に固定した階層は中央においては家業の専門技能によって公務を担う技能官人として行政実務を、地方においては受領となって地方行政を担った（平安貴族）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the transmission of governmental power and authority reduced the burden of the government, which enabled political stabilization in the central government, and facilitated heredity transfer of government posts: among the aristocracy, the highest became regents and advisers, the middle-class carried out administrative affairs based on the specialized skills related with their family businesses in the central government and carried out administration as Zuryo in the local regions (Nobles in the the Heian period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the transmission of governmental power and authority reduced the burden of the government, which enabled political stabilization of the central government, and facilitated the transfer of government posts according to heredity: among the aristocracy, the highest became regents and advisers, the middle-class carried out administrative affairs based on the specialized skills related with their family businesses in the central government and carried out administration as Zuryo in the local regions (Nobles in the the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transmission of governmental power and authority reduced the burden of the government, which enabled political stabilization of the central government, and facilitated the transfer of government posts according to heredity: among the aristocracy, the highest became Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents), the middle-class carried out administrative affairs based on the specialized skills related with their family businesses in the central government and carried out administration as Zuryo in the local regions (Nobles in the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>the the→theout の後のスペース短縮摂関家の定訳を入れるために変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この時期は摂関家による摂関政治が展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, regency performed by regents and advisers developed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理摂関政治：（ジーニアスに「摂政政治」とあるのを参考に）regencyとしました。権門：内容から考えてinfluential familiesとしました。荘園はShoen (private estate)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, regency performed by regents and advisers developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, regency performed by Sekkan-ke developed.</e>
<cmt>「摂関家」の表現変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>特定の権門が独占的に徴税権を得る荘園が、時代の節目ごとに段階的に増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen (private estate), where particular influential families exclusively obtained the power to levy taxes, increased gradually in accordance with each milestone of the time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen (private estate), where particular influential families exclusively obtained the power to levy taxes, increased gradually in accordance with each milestone of the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoen (manor in medieval Japan), where particular influential families exclusively obtained the power to levy taxes, increased gradually in accordance with each milestone of the time.</e>
<cmt>荘園の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>受領が徴税権を担う国衙領と勢力を二分していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen shared the power with Kokugaryo (provincial lands), where zuryo were responsible for levying taxes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen shared the power with Kokugaryo (provincial lands), where zuryo were responsible for levying taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoen shared the power with Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office), where zuryo were responsible for levying taxes.</e>
<cmt>国衙領の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>11世紀後期からは太上天皇が治天の君（事実上の君主）となって政務に当たる院政が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the 11th century, the Cloister Government started, whereby Daijo Tenno (retired Emperor) became the Chiten no kimi (supreme ruler) and influenced political affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the 11th century, the Cloister Government started, whereby Daijo Tenno (retired Emperor) became the Chiten no kimi (supreme ruler) and influenced political affairs.</e>
<cmt>Eliminated space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the 11th century, the Cloister Government started, whereby Daijo Tenno (retired Emperor) became the Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power) and influenced political affairs.</e>
<cmt>治天の君の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>院政の開始をもって中世の開始とする見解が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is usually interpreted that the initiation of the cloister government means the start of the Medieval Age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is usually interpreted that the initiation of the cloister government signaled the start of the Medieval Age.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is usually interpreted that the initiation of the cloister government signaled the start of the Medieval Age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>院政期には荘園の一円領域的な集積と国衙領（公領）の徴税単位化が進み、荘園公領制と呼ばれる体制へ移行することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Cloister Government time, a lot of private estates were collected together and Kokugaryo became a tax unit, which led to the new system called shoen koryo sei (the System of Public Lands and Private Estates).</e>
<cmt>貴社のInternet上の用語集に従って荘園公領制はshoen koryo sei (the System of Public Lands and Private Estates)としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of the Cloister Government, many private estates were collected together and Kokugaryo formed into a tax unit, which led to the new system dubbed shoen koryo sei (the System of Public Lands and Private Estates).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Cloister Government, many shoen (manors in medieval Japan) were collected together and Kokugaryo formed into a tax unit, which led to the new system dubbed shoen koryo sei (the System of Public Lands and Private Estates).</e>
<cmt>荘園の定訳 (many shoen なので manors としました。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>12世紀中期頃には貴族社会内部の紛争が武力で解決されるようになり、そのために動員された武士の地位が急速に上昇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the middle of the 12th century, conflicts among the aristocracy were solved by sword, leading to the rapidly increased status of warriors who were recruited solely for the purpose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the middle of the 12th century, conflicts among the aristocracy were solved by force, which increased the status of warriors who were recruited solely for this purpose.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the middle of the 12th century, conflicts among the aristocracy were solved by force, which increased the status of warriors who were recruited solely for this purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>こうした中で最初の武家政権である平氏政権が登場するが、この時期の社会矛盾を一手に引き受けたため、程なくして同時多発的に全国に拡大した内乱により崩壊してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the first Samurai government, the Taira clan administration came to the forefront, but soon collapsed due to simultaneously-occurring, nation-wide civil wars since they shouldered the social contradiction of that time all by themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the first Samurai government, the Taira clan administration came to the forefront, but soon collapsed due to simultaneous nation-wide civil wars, brought upon their attempt to single handledly shoulder the social contradictions of the times by themselves.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the first Samurai government, the Taira clan administration came to the forefront, but soon collapsed due to simultaneous nation-wide civil wars, brought upon their attempt to single handledly shoulder the social contradictions of the times by themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>平氏政権の崩壊とともに、中央政府である朝廷とは別個に、内乱を収拾して東国の支配権を得た鎌倉幕府が登場し、平安時代は幕を下ろした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the collapse of the Taira clan administration, the Kamakura bakufu came to power after sorting out the civil wars and gaining the right to rule the Eastern provinces, leading to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the collapse of the Taira clan administration, the Kamakura bakufu came to power after sorting out the civil wars and gained the right to rule the Eastern provinces, leading to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the collapse of the Taira clan administration, the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) came to power after sorting out the civil wars aside from the Imperial Court, and the central govenment gained the right to rule the Eastern provinces, leading to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>幕府の定訳「中央政府である朝廷とは別個に」を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>政治史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Political history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Political history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Political history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>平安前期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The early Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The early Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>奈良末期の宝亀元年（770年）の称徳天皇が崩御し、天智天皇系の光仁天皇が60前後という高齢ながらに即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 770, at the end of the Nara period, Emperor Shotoku passed away and Emperor Konin, a descendent of Emperor Tenchi, ascended the throne although he was already around 60 years old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 770, at the end of the Nara period, Emperor Shotoku passed away and Emperor Konin, a descendent of Emperor Tenchi, ascended the throne although he was already around 60 years old.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 770, at the end of the Nara period, Emperor Shotoku passed away and Emperor Konin, a descendent of Emperor Tenchi, ascended the throne although he was already around 60 years old.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>天武天皇以来の皇統は、以前より盛んだった天武系皇族間での相次ぐ政争によって継承順で繰り上がった天智天皇系の白壁王（光仁天皇）が継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the imperial line had succeeded from Emperor Tenmu, there had been a string of struggles for power and Shirakabe no okimi (Prince Shirakabe), a descendent of Emperor Tenchi became Emperor Konin following the order of succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the imperial line had succeeded from Emperor Tenmu, there had been a string of power struggles and Shirakabe no okimi (Prince Shirakabe), a descendent of Emperor Tenchi became Emperor Konin following the order of succession.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the imperial line had succeeded from Emperor Tenmu, there had been a string of power struggles and Shirakabe no okimi (Prince Shirakabe), a descendent of Emperor Tenchi became Emperor Konin following the order of succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>未だ天武系の皇族の影響があるなか、光仁天皇崩御後に桓武天皇が即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Emperor Konin passed away,Emperor Kanmu ascended the throne, when the Tenmu-descendent imperial family was still influential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Emperor Konin passed away, Emperor Kanmu ascended the throne while the Tenmu-descendent imperial family was still influential.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Emperor Konin passed away, Emperor Kanmu ascended the throne while the Tenmu-descendent imperial family was still influential.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>桓武天皇は歴代天皇の中でも遷都を二回も行うほどの強権を誇ったが、光仁天皇即位まではあまり恵まれた境遇ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu showed such authority as to relocate the capital twice although he had not been in such preferential circumstances until Emperor Konin&apos;s ascension.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu possessed enough authority to allow him to relocate the capital twice, although he had not experienced such privileged circumstances until Emperor Konin&apos;s ascension.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu possessed enough authority to allow him to relocate the capital twice, although he had not experienced such privileged circumstances until Emperor Konin&apos;s ascension.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>天武系でなければ即位すら出来なかった時代に天智系の光仁天皇（当時は白壁王）の第一皇子として生まれ、立太子は行われなかった（通常、継承順位が高ければ生まれると同時に行われた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a time when only a Tenmu-descendent prince could ascend the throne, Emperor Kanmu was born as the first prince of Tenchi-descendent Emperor Konin (Prince Shirakabe at that time) but Rittaishi (investiture of the Crown Prince) was not conducted, although it was normally done at the time of birth if the order of succession was high.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a time when only a Tenmu-descendent prince could ascend the throne, Emperor Kanmu was born as the first prince of Tenchi-descendent Emperor Konin (Prince Shirakabe at that time) but Rittaishi (investiture of the Crown Prince) was not conducted, although it was normally done at the time of birth if the person&apos;s order of succession was high.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At a time when only a Tenmu-descendent prince could ascend the throne, Emperor Kanmu was born as the first prince of Tenchi-descendent Emperor Konin (Prince Shirakabe at that time) but Rittaishi (investiture of the Crown Prince) was not conducted, although it was normally done at the time of birth if the person&apos;s order of succession was high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>日々の暮らしに困憊するほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He subsequently lived in near poverty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently he lived in near poverty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently he lived in near poverty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>以後、時の権力者となった桓武天皇の影響により、現在まで天武系の皇族は皇位に即いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, because of the influence of Emperor Kanmu, the power of the day, no Tenmu-descendent emperor has ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, no Tenmu-descendent emperor has ascended the throne, due to th influennce of Emperor Kanmu, who was in power during this period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, no Tenmu-descendent emperor has ascended the throne, due to the influence of Emperor Kanmu, who was in power during this period.</e>
<cmt>th→theinfluennce→influence</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>奈良時代は天武系の、平安時代は桓武天皇に続く天智系の時代であったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be said that the Nara period was the time of Tenmu-descendent emperors and the Heian was the time of Tenchi-descendent emperors who succeeded the line of Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that the Nara period was a time of Tenmu-descendent emperors and the Heian was a time of Tenchi-descendent emperors who succeeded the line of Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that the Nara period was a time of Tenmu-descendent emperors and the Heian was a time of Tenchi-descendent emperors who succeeded the line of Emperor Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>桓武天皇は新王朝の創始を強く意識し、自らの主導による諸改革を進めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu was strongly aware of the initiation of the new dynasty and promoted various reformations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu was strongly aware of the start of the new dynasty and promoted various reformations.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu was strongly aware of the start of the new dynasty and promoted various reformations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>桓武の改革は律令制の再編成を企図したものであり、その一環として桓武は平城京から長岡京、さらには平安京への遷都（794年）を断行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His reformations were intended to reorganize the Ritsuryo system and as a part of the reformations, he forcibly relocated the capital from Heijo kyo (ancient Nara) to Nagaoka kyo and then from Nagaoka kyo to Heian kyo (in 794).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His reformations were intended to reorganize the Ritsuryo system and as a part of these reformations, he forcibly relocated the capital from Heijo kyo (ancient Nara) to Nagaoka kyo and then from Nagaoka kyo to Heian kyo (in 794).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His reformations were intended to reorganize the Ritsuryo system and as a part of these reformations, he forcibly relocated the capital from Heijo kyo (ancient Nara) to Nagaoka kyo and then from Nagaoka kyo to Heian kyo (in 794).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>平安遷都は、前時代の旧弊を一掃し、天皇の権威を高める目的があったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that transfer of the national capital to Kyoto was conducted in order to sweep out old wrongs of the former times and to enhance the authority of the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the transfer of the national capital to Kyoto was conducted in order to erase outdated thinking and concepts, and enhance the authority of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the transfer of the national capital to Kyoto was conducted in order to erase outdated thinking and concepts, and enhance the authority of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、その様式には強く唐風の物があり、奈良とは異なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Heian style was strongly influenced by Tang in contrast to the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the Nara period, the Heian style was strongly influenced by the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the Nara period, the Heian style was strongly influenced by the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>桓武（781年～806年）以下数代においては、天皇が直接に政治を行う天皇親政の時代だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu (from 781 to 806) and several later generations conducted Tenno shinsei (direct rule by emperors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu (from 781 to 806) and several later generations conducted Tenno shinsei (direct rule by emperors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu (from 781 to 806) and several later generations conducted Tenno shinsei (direct rule by emperors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>政治を司る太政官の筆頭官も親王らが占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Princes were the heads of Daijokan (councils of state) who discharged policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Princes were the heads of Daijokan (councils of state) who carried out policy.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Princes were the heads of Daijokan (Grand Council of State) who carried out policy.</e>
<cmt>太政官の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この時期は、律令制の再建へ積極的な取り組みがなされ、形骸化した律令官職に代わって令外官などが置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Positive efforts were made in order to reestablish the Ritsuryo system, placing Ryoge no kan (extra statutory office) instead of Ritsutyo government service, which lost importance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Positive efforts were made to reestablish the Ritsuryo system, putting in place Ryoge no kan (extra statutory office) instead of the Ritsutyo government service, which lost importance.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Positive efforts were made to reestablish the Ritsuryo system, putting in place Ryoge no kan (class outside of the Ritsuryo system) instead of the Ritsutyo government posts, which lost importance.</e>
<cmt>令外官の定訳service→posts</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、桓武は王威の発揚のため、当時日本の支配外にあった東北地方の蝦夷征服に傾注した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in order to display the empror&apos;s prestige, Emperor Kanmu concentrated on conquering Ezo in Tohoku district.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in order to display the empror&apos;s prestige, Emperor Kanmu concentrated on conquering Ezo in Tohoku district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in order to display the empror&apos;s prestige, Emperor Kanmu concentrated on conquering Ezo in Tohoku region.</e>
<cmt>district→region</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>坂上田村麻呂が征夷大将軍として蝦夷征服に活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro succeeded in conquering Ezo as Seii taishogun (great general who subdued the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro succeeded in conquering Ezo as Seii taishogun (great general who subdued the barbarians).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro succeeded in conquering Ezo as seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>称徳天皇で断絶した天武皇統の教訓を踏まえ、桓武は多数の皇子をもうけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu, having learned a lesson from the fact that the stream of Tenmu-descendent emperors was extinguished after the death of Emperor Shotoku, put up many princes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu, having learnt a lesson from the fact that the stream of Tenmu-descendent emperors was extinguished after the death of Emperor Shotoku, had many princes of his own.</e>
<cmt>Robert: OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu, having learnt a lesson from the fact that the stream of Tenmu-descendent emperors was extinguished after the death of Emperor Shotoku, had many princes of his own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>桓武の死後、皇子らは順番に皇位につくこととし、桓武の次代の平城天皇は桓武に劣らぬ積極的な改革を遂行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Kanmu, the princes ascended the throne in order and Emperor Heizei, the next emperor after Kanmu, conducted no less positive renovations than Kanmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Emperor Kanmu, the princes ascended the throne in order. the renovations by Emperor Heizei, the next emperor after Kanmu, were no less positive renovations than Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Emperor Kanmu, the princes ascended the throne in order; the renovations by Emperor Heizei, the next emperor after Kanmu, were no less positive renovations than Kanmu.</e>
<cmt>NCが二文に分けたのを一文にしましたのでご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>平城は弟の嵯峨天皇に譲位した後も執政権を掌握し続けようとしたが、それを嫌った嵯峨との間に対立が深まり、最終的には軍事衝突により嵯峨側が勝利した（810年、薬子の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Emperor Heizei tried to keep the ruling power after abdicating the throne to his brother, Emperor Saga, the latter did not welcome it, which led to a serious conflict between them, and finally to a military confrontation, in which Emperor Saga won Kusuko no hen (Kusuko Incident) in 810).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Emperor Heizei tried to keep the ruling power after abdicating the throne to his brother, Emperor Saga did not welcome it, which led to a serious conflict between the two, and finally a military confrontation, in which Emperor Saga won Kusuko no hen (Kusuko Incident) in 810).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Emperor Heizei tried to keep the ruling power after abdicating the throne to his brother, Emperor Saga did not welcome it, which led to a serious conflict between the two, and finally a military confrontation, in which Emperor Saga won (Kusuko Incident in 810).</e>
<cmt>Kusuko no hen を削除し、従って括弧内の括弧を一つ削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>この事件以降、12世紀中葉の平治の乱まで中央の政治抗争は武力を伴わず、死刑も執行されない非武力的な政治の時代が永らく続くこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that incident, until Heiji no ran (Heiji Rebellion), the non-violent political age continued, during which central political conflicts didn&apos;t lead to military confrontations or the carrying out of the death penalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, until Heiji no ran (Heiji Rebellion), the non-violent political age continued, during which central political conflicts did not lead to military confrontations or the execution of the death penalty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, until the Heiji War in the middle of 12th century, the non-violent political age continued, during which central political conflicts did not lead to military confrontations or the execution of the death penalty.</e>
<cmt>平治の乱の表現変更12世紀追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="40">
<j>嵯峨治世初期は、太政官筆頭だった藤原園人の主導のもと、百姓撫民（貧民救済）そして権門（有力貴族・寺社）抑制の政策がとられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of the reign of Emperor Saga, FUJIWARA no Sonohito, the head council of state, lead the policy to rescue farmers (relief of the poor) and control power (influential aristocracy, temples and shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the reign of Emperor Saga, FUJIWARA no Sonohito, the head council of state, lead a policy to rescue farmers (relief of the poor) and control power (influential aristocracy, temples and shrine).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the reign of Emperor Saga, FUJIWARA no Sonohito, the head council of state, lead a policy to rescue farmers (relief of the poor) and control power (influential aristocracy, temples and shrines).</e>
<cmt>shrine→shrines</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これは、律令の背景思想だった儒教に基づく政策であったが、園人の後に政権を握った藤原冬嗣は一変して墾田開発の促進を政策方針とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this policy was based on Confucianism, the background idea of the Ritsuryo system but FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu changed the policy drastically, making facilitation of reclaimed land development the policy line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">this policy was based on Confucianism, a key idea of the Ritsuryo system, but FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu changed the policy drastically, making it policy to facilitate the development of reclaimed land.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This policy was based on Confucianism, a key idea of the Ritsuryo system, but FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu, who took over Sonohito, changed the policy drastically, making it policy to facilitate the development of reclaimed land.</e>
<cmt>「園人の後に政権を握った」追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>律令制の根幹は人別課税だったが、冬嗣は土地課税を重視した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Ritsuryo system was based on the individual-based tax system, but Fuyutsugu count on the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ritsuryo system was based on an individual-based tax system, while the Fuyutsugu count was a land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ritsuryo system was based on an individual-based tax system, while the Fuyutsugu count was a land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>なおかつ権門有利を志向したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, his policy was beneficial for the influential.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, his policy benefited those with influence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, his policy benefited those with influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>820年代から多数設定され始めた勅旨田や同時期に大宰府管内で施行された公営田も、冬嗣路線に則ったものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Chokushiden (proprietorships and imperial land) started in the 820&apos;s on a large scale and Kueiden (lands directly managed by the government to secure revenues) was implemented inside Dazaifu around the same time according to Fuyutsugu&apos;s policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Chokushiden (proprietorships and imperial land) started in the 820&apos;s on a large scale and Kueiden (lands directly managed by the government to secure revenues) was implemented inside Dazaifu around the same time according to Fuyutsugu&apos;s policy.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Chokushiden (proprietorships and imperial land) started in the 820&apos;s on a large scale and Kueiden (lands directly managed by the government to secure revenues) was implemented inside Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) around the same time according to Fuyutsugu&apos;s policy.</e>
<cmt>大宰府の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>冬嗣は嵯峨天皇の蔵人頭として活躍し、それを足掛かりとして台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuyutsugu flourished as kurodo no to (head chamberlain) of Emperor Saga and gained power by it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyutsugu flourished as kurodo no to (head chamberlain) of Emperor Saga, and thus gained power.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyutsugu flourished as kurodo no to (head chamberlain) of Emperor Saga, and thus gained power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>また、嵯峨治世期には、各種法令の集大成である弘仁格式が編纂・施行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Saga, Konin kakushiki (amendments to penal and administrative law), the integration of various laws was compiled and put into practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Emperor Saga, Konin kakushiki (amendments to penal and administrative law), various laws were compiled, integrated and put into practice.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Emperor Saga, Konin kyakushiki code (amendments to penal and administrative law compiled in 820), which was the integration of various laws, was compiled and put into practice.</e>
<cmt>弘仁格式の定訳NCの文章が原文と違うと考え書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>冬嗣の子、藤原良房も冬嗣の路線を継承し、開墾奨励政策をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, the son of Fuyutsugu followed his father&apos;s policy line and encouraged developing reclaimed land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, the son of Fuyutsugu, followed his father&apos;s policy and encouraged the development of reclaimed land.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, the son of Fuyutsugu, followed his father&apos;s policy and encouraged the development of reclaimed land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>当時、課税の対象だった百姓らの逃亡・浮浪が著しく、租税収入に危機が迫っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, peasants on whom the tax was imposed frequently ran away and wandered about, which lowered the yield of tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, peasants on whom tax was imposed frequently ran away and wandered about, which lowered tax yields.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, peasants on whom tax was imposed frequently ran away and wandered about, which lowered tax yields.</e>
<cmt>tax の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>冬嗣・良房は墾田開発を促進し、土地課税にシフトすることで状況に対応しようとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Fuyutsugu and Yoshifusa tried to deal with the situation by taxing the land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Fuyutsugu and Yoshifusa tried to deal with the situation by taxing the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Fuyutsugu and Yoshifusa tried to deal with the situation by taxing the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>良房は、政治権力の集中化も進めていき、そうした中で応天門の変（866年）が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshifusa promoted the concentration of political power, when the Otenmon no hen (Otemon Incident) happened (866).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshifusa promoted the concentration of political power, when the Otenmon no hen (Otemon Incident) happened (866).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshifusa promoted the concentration of political power, when the Otemon Incident happened (866).</e>
<cmt>Otenmon no hen 削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この事件は、藤原氏による他氏排斥と理解されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the incident is often interpreted as the Fujiwara clan&apos;s excluding other clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the incident is often interpreted as the Fujiwara clan&apos;s exclusion of other clans.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the incident is often interpreted as the Fujiwara clan&apos;s exclusion of other clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>良房執政期を中心とした時期は、政治も安定し、開発奨励政策や貞観格式編纂などの成果により、貞観の治と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this era is called Jogan no chi (glorius Jogon rule) since the political situation became stable and development support policy and Jogan-kyakushiki (ammendments to the Konin compilation) became successful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">this era is called Jogan no chi (glorius Jogon rule) due to the political situation having become stable and the success of the development support policy and Jogan-kyakushiki (ammendments to the Konin compilation).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">this era is called Jogan no chi (glorious Jogan rule) due to the political situation having become stable and the success of the development support policy and Jogan Kyakushiki Code (Regulations and Procedures of the Jogan Era).</e>
<cmt>貞観格式の訳変更glorius→gloriousJogon→Jogan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="53">
<j>良房の養子、藤原基経もまた、良房路線を継承し土地課税重視の政策をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mototsune, an adopted child of Yoshifusa, also followed Yoshifusa&apos;s policy line, counting on the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Mototsune, an adopted child of Yoshifusa, also followed Yoshifusa&apos;s policy line, and carried out counting based on the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Mototsune, an adopted child of Yoshifusa, also followed Yoshifusa&apos;s policy line, and carried out counting based on the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>基経執政期で特徴的なのが、官田の設置である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Mototsune administration is characterized by the establishment of Kanden (imperial estates).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mototsune administration is characterized by the establishment of Kanden (imperial estates).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mototsune administration is characterized by the establishment of Kanden (imperial estates).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>それまで中央行政の経費は地方からの調・庸によっていたが、畿内に設定した官田の収益を行政経費に充てることとしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the profit from Kanden in Kinai was used for administrative costs but until that time, the expenditure had depended on the tax collected from the countryside, Cho (tributes) and Yo(labor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the profit from Kanden in Kinai was used for administrative costs but until that time, the expenditure had depended on the tax collected from the countryside, Cho (tributes) and Yo(labor).</e>
<cmt>Erased spaces</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The profit from Kanden in Kinai (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) was used for administrative costs but until that time, the expenditure had depended on the tax collected from the countryside, Cho (tributes) and Yo (labor).</e>
<cmt>畿内の説明補足Yo の後にスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="56">
<j>887年に即位した宇多天皇は、その数年後に基経が死去すると天皇主導の政治を展開するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Uda, who ascended the throne in 887, began to develop emperor-led policies when Mototsune passed away a few years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Uda, who ascended the throne in 887, began to develop emperor-centric policies when Mototsune passed away a few years later.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Uda, who ascended the throne in 887, began to develop emperor-centric policies when Mototsune passed away a few years later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>冬嗣から基経まで、権門に有利な政策が実施されてきたが、宇多は権門抑制策そして小農民保護策を進めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the policy which was advantageous for influential families had been conducted from Fuyutsugo to Mototsune, Emperor Uda promoted controlling such families and protecting the peasants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although policy which was advantageous for influential families had been conducted from Fuyutsugo to Mototsune, Emperor Uda promoted the control of such families and protected the peasants.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although policy which was advantageous for influential families had been conducted from Fuyutsugo to Mototsune, Emperor Uda promoted the control of such families and protected the peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>宇多のもとでは藤原時平と菅原道真の両者が太政官筆頭に立ち、協力しながら宇多を補佐していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under Emperor Uda, FUJIWARA no Tokihira and SUGAWARA no Michizane were Daijokan hitto (head councils of state), cooperating with the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Emperor Uda, FUJIWARA no Tokihira and SUGAWARA no Michizane were Daijokan hitto (head councils of state), who cooperated with the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Emperor Uda, FUJIWARA no Tokihira and SUGAWARA no Michizane were the heads of Daijokan, who cooperated with the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Daijokan hitto (head councils of state)→the heads of Daijokan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>この宇多治世は寛平の治という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Uda administration is called Kanpyo no chi (Glorious Kanpyo rule).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Uda administration is called Kanpyo no chi (Glorious Kanpyo rule).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the Uda administration is called Kanpyo no chi (Glorious Kanpyo rule).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>宇多が醍醐天皇に譲位するとにわかに時平・道真の対立が深まり、道真が失脚することとなった（901年昌泰の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after Emperor Uda abdicated from the throne to Emperor Daigo, the conflict between Tokihira and Michizane became serious, leading to Michizane&apos;s downfall (the Shotai no hen; Shotai Conspiracy in 901).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Emperor Uda abdicated the throne to Emperor Daigo, leading to the conflict between Tokihira and Michizane becoming serious, resulting in Michizane&apos;s downfall (the Shotai no hen; Shotai Conspiracy in 901).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Emperor Uda abdicated the throne to Emperor Daigo, leading to the conflict between Tokihira and Michizane becoming serious, resulting in Michizane&apos;s downfall (the Shotai Incident in 901).</e>
<cmt>昌泰の変の表現変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="61">
<j>実権を握った時平は宇多路線を引継ぎ、権門抑制と小農民保護を遂行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tokihira took charge, he followed Uda&apos;s line, controlling influential families and protecting peasants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tokihira took charge, he followed Uda&apos;s policy and controlled influential families and protected peasants.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tokihira took charge, he followed Uda&apos;s policy and controlled influential families and protected peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>宇多以来の路線は律令制への回帰を志向したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the post-Uda policy was oriented to the return to the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post-Uda policy was aimed at returning to the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post-Uda policy was aimed at returning to the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>時平執政期の902年に発布された班田励行令は、まさに律令回帰を顕著にあらわしているが、これが史上最後の班田実施となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the law to encourage allotment of farmland, which was issued in 902, was a prominent example of the return to the Ritsuryo system and the law was the last policy to put allotment of farmland into practice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law to encourage the allotment of farmland, which was issued in 902, was a prominent example of the return to the Ritsuryo system and the law was the last policy to carry out the allotment of farmland.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law to encourage the allotment of farmland, which was issued in 902, was a prominent example of the return to the Ritsuryo system and the law was the last policy to carry out the allotment of farmland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>また、律令回帰を目指す法令群である延喜格式が編纂されたのもこの時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in this era, Engi no kyakushiki (regulations and laws of the Engi era), which was oriented to the return to the Ritsuryo system, was made.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理延喜の治には、貴社の用語集より（研究社新和英辞典）のthe peaceful era of Engiを使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, in this era, Engi no kyakushiki (regulations and laws of the Engi era), which were aimed at a return to the Ritsuryo system, were made.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, in this era, Engi no kyakushiki (regulations and laws of the Engi era), which were aimed at a return to the Ritsuryo system, were made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>これら諸施策は後代、理想的な政治とされ、延喜の治と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">these measures and policies were considered ideal in later times, and the then-policy was called Engi no chi (the peaceful era of Engi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">these measures and policies were considered ideal in later times, and the then-policy was called Engi no chi (the peaceful era of Engi).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These measures and policies were considered ideal in later times, and the then-policy was called Engi no chi (glorious Engi rule).</e>
<cmt>「延喜の治」を他の何々の治にならって変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>平安中期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the mid- Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mid- Heian period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mid- Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>時平の死後、弟の藤原忠平が太政官首班となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tokihira&apos;s death, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, his younger brother became Daijokan Shuhan (Chief Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tokihira&apos;s death, his younger brother,FUJIWARA no Tadahira, became Daijokan Shuhan (Chief Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tokihira&apos;s death, his younger brother, FUJIWARA no Tadahira, became the chief of Daijokan.</e>
<cmt>FUJIWARA の前にスペース挿入太政官首班の表現変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>忠平は律令回帰路線に否定的であり、土地課税路線を推進していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadahira was not in favor of the return to Ritsuryo system, and promoted the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadahira was not in favor of a return to the Ritsuryo system, and promoted the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadahira was not in favor of a return to the Ritsuryo system, and promoted the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>忠平執政期ごろに、有力百姓層（富豪層）へ土地経営と納税を請け負わせる名田もしくは負名が開始していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the time of Tadahira&apos;s administration, Myoden (rice field lots under the control of nominal holders) or Fuka (tillers of public rice fields) started; under either system, nominal farmers undertook management of rice fields and tax payments.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理名田は内容から考えてrice field lots under the control of nominal holdersとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the time of Tadahira&apos;s administration, Myoden (rice field lots under the control of nominal holders) or Fuka (tillers of public rice fields) were started; under either system, nominal farmers undertook management of rice fields and tax payments.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the time of Tadahira&apos;s administration, Myoden (rice field lots under the control of nominal holders) or Fumyo (tillers of public rice fields) were started; under either system, powerful farmers (the rich class) undertook management of rice fields and tax payments.</e>
<cmt>Fuka→Fumyonominal farmers→powerful farmers「（富豪層）」追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この時期が律令国家体制から新たな国家体制、すなわち王朝国家体制へ移行する転換期だったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this time is considered to have been the turning point from the Ritsuryo system to a new state system, the system of the dynasty state.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This time is considered to have been the turning point from the Ritsuryo system to a new state system, the system of the dynasty state.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This time is considered to have been the turning point from the Ritsuryo system to a new state system, the system of the dynasty state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>忠平期を摂関政治の成立期とするのが通説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadahira&apos;s administration period is usually considered the time of the establishment of regency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadahira&apos;s administration period is usually considered the time during which the regency was established.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadahira&apos;s administration period is usually considered the time during which the regency was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>それ以前の藤原良房の時から藤原北家が摂政・関白に就いて執政してきたが、発展段階の摂関政治だったとして初期摂関政治と区別されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan had conducted policy as a regent or advisor since the time of FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, their regency is considered to have still been in the development stage and distinguished from the early regency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan had conducted policy as a regent or advisor since the time of FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, their regency is considered to have still been in the developmental stage and was distinguished from the early regency.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan had conducted policy as a regent or chief adviser to the Emperor since the time of FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, their regency is considered to have still been in the developmental stage and was distinguished from the early regency.</e>
<cmt>関白の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>忠平以降は朝政の中心としての摂関が官職として確立し、忠平の子孫のみが摂関に就任するという摂関政治の枠組みが確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadahira, a regent to the emperor was established as a central post in the government and also the framework in which only descendents of Tadahira were able to become a regent was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadahira, a regent to the emperor was established as a central post in the government and also the framework in which only descendents of Tadahira were able to become a regent was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadahira, Sekkan (regents and advisers) was established as a central post in the government and also the framework in which only descendents of Tadahira were able to become Sekkan was established.</e>
<cmt>摂関の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>ただし、摂関政治においても摂関が全ての決定権を握っていたのではなく、議政官が衆議する陣定の場でほとんどの政治決定が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, regents didn&apos;t decide everything even in that system but almost all the policies were discussed and determined by Giseikan (Legislatures) at &apos;Jin no sadame.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even in this system, regents didn&apos;t decide everything, yet almost all policies were discussed and determined by Giseikan (Legislatures) at &apos;Jin no sadame.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even in this system, Sekkan didn&apos;t decide everything, yet almost all policies were discussed and determined by Giseikan (Legislatures) at Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council).</e>
<cmt>陣定の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>ところで、9世紀ごろから関東地方を中心として、富豪層による運京途中の税の強奪など、群盗行為が横行し始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the 9th century on, especially in the Kanto region, while millionaires were bringing taxes to Kyoto, they were assaulted and robbed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the 9th century onwards especially in the Kanto region, millionaires who brought taxes to Kyoto were assaulted and robbed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the 9th century onwards especially in the Kanto region, millionaires who brought taxes to Kyoto were assaulted and robbed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>群盗の活動は9世紀を通じて活発化していき、朝廷は群盗鎮圧のために東国などへ軍事を得意とする貴族層を国司として派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After robbery became more common, the Imperial Court sent military aristocrats to Togoku (eastern part of Japan) as kokushi (provincial governors) to discourage robbery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After robbery became more common in 9th century, the Imperial Court sent military aristocrats to Togoku (eastern part of Japan) as kokushi (provincial governors) to discourage such acts.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After robbery became more common in 9th century, the Imperial Court sent military aristocrats to Togoku (eastern part of Japan) as kokushi (provincial governors) to discourage such acts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>それとともに、従前の軍団 (古代日本)に代えて国衙に軍事力の運用権限を担わせる政策をとっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Court also took the policy to leave military force to Kokuga (provincial government office compounds) instead of the previous army group (of ancient Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Court also made the policy to leave the discretion of military force up to the Kokuga (provincial government office compounds) instead of the previous army group (of ancient Japan).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Court also made the policy to leave the discretion of military force up to the kokuga (provincial government offices) instead of the previous army group (of ancient Japan).</e>
<cmt>国衙の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>この政策が結実したのが9世紀末～10世紀初頭の寛平・延喜期であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this idea was brought to fruition in Kanpyo and Engi eras, from the end of the 9th century to the beginning of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This idea was brought to fruition in Kanpyo and Engi eras, from the end of the 9th century to the beginning of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This idea was brought to fruition in Kanpyo and Engi eras, from the end of the 9th century to the beginning of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>この時期の勲功者が武士の初期原型となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">those who distinguished themselves in that time were ancestors of warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who distinguished themselves at this time were the ancestors of warriors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who distinguished themselves at this time were the ancestors of warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>彼らは自らもまた名田経営を請け負う富豪として、また富豪相互あるいは富豪と受領の確執の調停者として地方に勢力を扶植していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the warriors became influential in the country as rich farmers who undertook the management of Myouden (rice field lots under the nominal holder), or as mediators to solve conflicts between millionaires and zuro or those between millionaires.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the warriors became influential as rich farmers who undertook the management of Myouden** (rice field lots under the nominal holder), or as mediators to solve conflicts between millionaires and zuro or between millionaires.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The warriors became influential in rural areas as rich farmers who undertook the management of Myoden, or as mediators to solve conflicts between millionaires and zuryo or between millionaires.</e>
<cmt>Myouden**→Myoden　そして既出のため説明削除。「地方に」追記しました。zuro→zuryo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>彼ら同士の対立や受領に対する不平が叛乱へ発展したのが、忠平執政期の940年前後に発生した承平天慶の乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, conflicts among warriors and disaffectedness toward zuryo developed into a rebellion, the Johei-Tenga no ran (Johei-Tengyo War in 940, during Tadahira&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, conflicts among warriors and disaffectedness toward zuryo turned into a rebellion, the Johei-Tenga no ran (Johei-Tengyo War in 940, during Tadahira&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, conflicts among warriors and disaffectedness toward zuryo turned into a rebellion, the Johei-Tengyo War, during Tadahira&apos;s administration around 940.</e>
<cmt>文頭のスペース削除Johei-Tenga no ran 削除in→around後半、書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>朝廷の側に立ち、反乱側に立った自らと同じ原初の武士達を倒して同乱の鎮圧に勲功のあった者の家系は、承平天慶勲功者、すなわち正当なる武芸の家系と認識された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the warriors who conquered the rebellion for the Court, fighting against those in the same social class were considered distinguished in Johei and Tengyo War and their descendents were admitted as the right family line of military art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warriors who took the side of the Court and fought against those in the same social class in order to suppress the war, were recognized as being valorous during Johei-Tengyo war and thus were also considered as being a proper warrior line.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warriors who took the side of the Court and fought against those in the same social class in order to suppress the war, were recognized as performing a deed of valor and thus were also considered as being a proper warrior line.</e>
<cmt>「承平天慶勲功者」のNCの表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>当時、成立した国衙軍制において、「武芸の家系」は国衙軍制を編成する軍事力として国衙に認識された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokuga established its military force and admitted &apos;the family line of military art&apos; as part of the military force.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokuga established its military force and admitted &apos;the family line of military art&apos; as being a part of the military force.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokuga admitted &apos;the warrior line&apos; as being a part of the Kokuga force system, which was established at that time.</e>
<cmt>国衙が国衙軍制を作ったのではないので訂正しました。「武芸の家系」は上文で「warrior line」のため変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>このように国衙によって公認された者が武士へと成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">those military people authorized by kokuga became warriors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those military people authorized by kokuga became warriors.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those military people authorized by kokuga became warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="84">
<j>忠平の死後、10世紀中葉に村上天皇が親政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadahira&apos;s death, Emperor Murakami conducted direct Imperial rule in the middle of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadahira&apos;s death, Emperor Murakami conducted direct Imperial rule in the middle of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadahira&apos;s death, Emperor Murakami conducted direct Imperial rule in the middle of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これを天暦の治といい、延喜の治と並んで聖代視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Tenryaku no chi(glorious Tenryaku rule), and along with Engi no chi, is regarded as sacred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">this rule was called Tenryaku no chi(glorious Tenryaku rule), and along with Engi no chi, is regarded as being sacred.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This rule was called Tenryaku no chi (glorious Tenryaku rule), and along with Engi no chi, was regarded as being sacred.</e>
<cmt>括弧の前にスペース挿入is→was</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="86">
<j>10世紀中葉から後期にかけて、ある官職に伴う権限義務を特定の家系へ請け負わせる官司請負制が中央政界でも地方政治でも著しく進展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the middle to the end of the 10th century, the government official contract system developed in the national political arena as well as in regional politics: specific family lines were given contracts to have authority and duties associated with certain government posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the middle to the end of the 10th century, the government official contract system developed in the national political arena as well as in regional politics: specific family lines were given contracts to have authority and duties associated with certain government posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the middle to the end of the 10th century, the government official contract system developed in the national political arena as well as in regional politics: specific family lines were given contracts to have authority and duties associated with certain government posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>この体制を担う貴族や官人の家組織の中では、子弟や外部から能力を見込んだ弟子に対し、幼少期から家業たる専門業務の英才教育をほどこして家業を担う人材を育成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aristocrats and government officials who undertook such authority and duty developed human resources: they pampered their children as well as gifted disciples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aristocrats and government officials who undertook such authority and duty developed human resources: they pampered their children as well as gifted disciples.</e>
<cmt>Erased space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aristocrats and government officials who undertook such authority and duty developed human resources: they pampered their children as well as gifted disciples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>先述の武士の登場も、武芸の家系に軍事警察力を請け負わせる官司請負制の一形態とみなせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the appearance of warriors is considered a type of government office contract system: families of military art undertook military and police force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the appearance of warriors is considered a type of government office contract system: families of military arts undertook military and police force.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The appearance of warriors is considered a type of government office contract system: families of military arts undertook military and police force.</e>
<cmt>of の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="89">
<j>朝廷の財政は、地方からの収入によっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court&apos;s finances depended on income from the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court&apos;s finances depended on income from the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court&apos;s finances depended on income from the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>特に地方政治においては、国司へ大幅な行政権を委任する代わりに一定以上の租税進納を義務づける政治形態が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In regional politics, the Court delegated much administrative authority to Kokushi and in return, they had responsibilities to pay taxes above a certain level to the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In regional politics, the Court delegated much administrative authority to Kokushi and in return, they bore the responsibility to pay taxes above a certain level to the government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In regional politics, the Court delegated much administrative authority to Kokushi and in return, they bore the responsibility to pay taxes above a certain level to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>このとき、行政権が委任されたのは現地赴任した国司の筆頭者であり、受領と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, administrative authority was delegated to kokushi, who were called Zuryo (career provincial officials).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, administrative authority was delegated to kokushi, who were called Zuryo (career provincial officials).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, administrative authority was delegated to the heads of kokushi who were dispatched to provinces, and they were called Zuryo.</e>
<cmt>kokushi→the heads of kokushi受領、既出のため説明削除「現地赴任した」追記して書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>受領は、大きな権限を背景として富豪層からの徴税によって巨富を蓄え、また恣意的な地方政治を展開したとされ、その現れが10世紀後期～11世紀中期に頻発した国司苛政上訴だったと考えられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Zuryo saved a large amount of money by collecting taxes from millionaires due to their authority and developed arbitrary regional politics, leading to Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against Kokushi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Zuryo saved a large amount of money by collecting taxes from millionaire, due to their authority and developed arbitrary regional politics, leading to Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against Kokushi).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Zuryo saved a large amount of money by collecting taxes from millionaires, due to their authority and developed arbitrary regional politics, leading to Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against Kokushi) which often happened from the end of the 10th century to the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>「10世紀後期～11世紀中期に頻発した」追記しました。millionaire→millionaires</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>一方で受領は勘解由使や受領考過定など監査制度の制約も受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, they had some restrictions through an auditing system such as Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners) and Zuryo kokatei (Evaluation of Zuryo).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理受領考過定＝Evaluation of Zuryo (定訳不明です)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, they had some restrictions through an auditing system such as Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners) and Zuryo kokatei (Evaluation of Zuryo).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, they had some restrictions through an auditing system such as Kageyushi (Board of Discharge Examiners) and Zuryo kokatei (Evaluation of Zuryo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>いずれにせよ、受領は名田請負契約などを通じて富豪層を育成する存在であるとともに、富豪から規定の税を徴収しなければならない存在でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At any rate, zuryo had to develop millionaires through the Myoden contract system and collect set taxes from them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At any rate, zuryo had to develop millionaires through the Myoden contract system and collect set taxes from them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At any rate, zuryo had to develop millionaires through the Myoden contract system and collect set taxes from them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>また富豪層は受領との名田請負契約に基づいて巨富を築くと同時に中央官界とも直接結びついて受領を牽制するなど、受領の統制を超えて権益拡大を図る存在でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Millionaires made enormous fortunes through the Myoden contract system and tried to increase their interest beyond the zuryo&apos;s control by directly connecting to central official circles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Millionaires made enormous fortunes through the Myoden contract system and tried to increase their interest beyond the zuryo&apos;s control by directly connecting to central official circles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Millionaires made enormous fortunes through the Myoden contract system and tried to increase their interest beyond the zuryo&apos;s control by directly connecting to central official circles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="96">
<j>また、荘園が拡大し始めたのもこの時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time private estates began expanding.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time private estates began expanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time shoen began expanding.</e>
<cmt>private estates→shoen</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>10世紀前期に従来の租税収取体系が変質したことに伴い、権門層（有力貴族・寺社）は各地に私領（私営田）を形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the change in the tax collecting system in the 10th century, influential classes (influential aristocracy, temples and shrines) took over Private land (shieiden: lands directly governed by such powers) in many places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the change in the tax collecting system in the 10th century, influential classes (influential aristocracy, temples and shrines) took over private land (shieiden: lands directly governed by such powers) in many places.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the change in the tax collecting system in the 10th century, influential classes (influential aristocracy, temples and shrines) took over private land (shieiden: lands directly governed by such powers) in many places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>このように荘園が次第に発達していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, private estates were gradually formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, private estates were gradually formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, shoen was gradually formed.</e>
<cmt>private estates→shoenwere→was</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>権門層は、荘園を国衙に収公されないよう太政官、民部省や国衙の免許を獲得し、前者を官省符荘といい後者を国免荘という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the influential obtained licenses from Dajokan, Minbusho(Ministry of Popular Affairs) to prevent Kokuga from confiscating their private estates, (such estates were called Kanshofu sho: a shoen enjoying immnity from taxation by virtue of havingofficial documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) or to protect their estates from Kokuga (such estates were called Kokumen sho: (a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in bempo or binho system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the influential obtained licenses from Dajokan, Minbusho(Ministry of Popular Affairs) to prevent Kokuga from confiscating their private estates, (such estates were called Kanshofu sho: a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) or to protect their estates from Kokuga (such estates were called Kokumen sho: (a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in bempo or binho system).</e>
<cmt>Spelling and space errors</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influential obtained licenses from Daijokan, Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) or Kokuga to prevent Kokuga from confiscating their shoen, (the former was called Kanshofu sho: a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs, and the latter was called Kokumen sho: a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in bempo or binho system).</e>
<cmt>Minbusho の前後のスペース調整private estates→shoenDajokan→Daijokan「太政官、民部省や国衙」から免許を獲得しているので、書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>こうした動きに対し、10世紀後期に登場した花山天皇は権門抑制を目的として荘園整理令などの諸政策を発布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the 10th century, Emperor Hanayama issued several policies including Private estate Regulation Acts in order to control the influential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the 10th century, Emperor Hanayama issued several policies including Private estate Regulation Acts in order to control the influential.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the 10th century, Emperor Hanayama issued several policies including Private estate Regulation Acts in order to control the influential.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>この花山新制はかなり大規模な改革を志向していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">that new system conducted by Emperor Hanayama aimed to create large-scale reformations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That new system conducted by Emperor Hanayama aimed to create large-scale reformations.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That new system conducted by Emperor Hanayama aimed to create large-scale reformations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>しかし反発した摂関家によって数年のうちに花山は退位に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Emperor Hanayama was forced to abdicate the throne by an anti-reformation line of regents and advisers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Emperor Hanayama was forced to abdicate the throne due to a line of regents and advisors who opposed such reform.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Emperor Hanayama was forced to abdicate the throne due to Sekkan-ke who opposed such reform.</e>
<cmt>a line of regents and advisors→Sekkan-ke</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>とはいえ、その後の摂関政治は権門優遇策をとった訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the later regency did not take a pro-influential family policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the later regency did not adopt a policy which favored influential families.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the later regency did not adopt a policy which favored influential families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>摂関政治で最大の栄華を誇った藤原道長の施策にはむしろ抑制的な面も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the policies conducted by FUJIWARA no Michinaga, who himself lived most extravagantly while in power, had aspects of controlling the influential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The policies conducted by FUJIWARA no Michinaga, who himself lived most extravagantly while in power, contained aspects of controlling the influential.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The policies conducted by FUJIWARA no Michinaga, who himself lived most extravagantly while in power, contained aspects of controlling the influential.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>摂関政治の最大の課題は、負名体制と受領行政との矛盾、そして権門の荘園整理にどう取り組むかという点にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the largest problems for the regency were how to deal with the contradiction between the Fumyo&apos;s tax managing system and the Zuryo administration, and how to restrict private estates owned by the influential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the largest problems for the regency were how to deal with the contradiction between the Fumyo&apos;s tax managing system and the Zuryo administration, and how to restrict private estates owned by the influential.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The largest problems for the regency were how to deal with the contradiction between the Fumyo&apos;s tax managing system and the Zuryo administration, and how to restrict shoen owned by the influential.</e>
<cmt>private estates→shoen</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="106">
<j>摂関政治による諸課題への取り組みに成果が見られ始めたのが、11世紀前期～中期にかけての時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early to middle of the 11th century, the regency&apos;s approaches of the various problems began to pay off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early to middle of the 11th century, the regency&apos;s approaches of the various problems began to pay off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early to middle of the 11th century, the regency&apos;s approaches of the various problems began to pay off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>この期間、国内税率を一律固定化する公田官物率法が導入されたり、小規模な名田に並行して広く領域的な別名が公認されるようになったり、大規模事業の財源として一国単位で一律に課税する一国平均役が成立するなど、社会構造に変革を及ぼすような政策がとられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During that period, some policies, which affected the social structure, were developed: the Koden kanmotsu rippo, which fixed the domestic tax rate, was introduced; another large territorial name was authorized in parallel with small-sized Myoden; Ikkoku heikinyaku (taxes and labor uniformly imposed on every private estate in one province) in order to get financial resources for large-scale projects.</e>
<cmt>公田官物率法を、ほぼ直訳しております。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, some policies, which affected the social structure, were developed: the Koden kanmotsu rippo, which fixed the domestic tax rate, was introduced; another large territorial name was authorized alongside small-sized Myoden; Ikkoku heikinyaku (taxes and labor uniformly imposed on every private estate in one province) in order to get financial resources for large-scale projects.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, some policies, which affected the social structure, were developed: the Koden kanmotsu rippo, which fixed the domestic tax rate, was introduced; bechimyo (large territories including mountains and forests) was authorized alongside small-sized Myoden; Ikkoku heikinyaku (taxes and labor uniformly imposed on every private estate in one province) in order to get financial resources for large-scale projects.</e>
<cmt>「別名」→another name ではなく、&quot;bechimyo&quot;ですので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>このため、10世紀前期に始まった王朝国家体制はより中世的な形態へ移行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the dynasty state, which started in the early 10th century, changed into a more-medieval form.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dynasty state, which started in the early 10th century, changed into a more-medieval form.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dynasty state, which started in the early 10th century, changed into a more-medieval form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>11世紀中期を画期として以前を前期王朝国家、以後を後期王朝国家と区分する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the dynasty state before the mid-11th century is distinguished as the early dynasty state and that after the mid-11th century as the later dynasty state.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dynasty state before the mid-11th century is noted as the early dynasty state and the period after the mid-11th century as the later dynasty state.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dynasty state before the mid-11th century is noted as the early dynasty state and the period after the mid-11th century as the later dynasty state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="110">
<j>11世紀前期には、女真族が北部九州に来襲する事変が発生した（1019年、刀伊の入寇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first stage of the 11th century, the Joshin tribe attacked Northern Kyushu (Toi no nyuko: Toi invasion in 1019).</e>
<cmt>女真「族」なので、the Joshin tribeとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first stage of the 11th century, the Joshin tribe attacked Northern Kyushu (Toi no nyuko: Toi invasion in 1019).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first stage of the 11th century, the Joshin (a people lived in eastern China and northern Korea) attacked Northern Kyushu (Toi invasion in 1019).</e>
<cmt>Toi no nyuko: →削除「女真族」を訂正しましたのでご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>平安後期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The later Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The later Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The later Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>11世紀後期からは、中世に移行したと考えてよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Japan moved into the Medieval Ages in the latter half of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan is considered to have moved into the Medieval Ages in the latter half of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan is considered to have moved into the Medieval Ages in the latter half of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>この時期までに郡司・郷司・負名層が自ら墾田して領主となる開発領主が登場しており、彼らは自領を権門へ寄進することで権利を確保していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By that time, Gunji(local magistrates), Goji(local government officials under the ritsuryo system), Fumyo (tillers of public rice fields) developed new rice fields and owned those fields. they ensured their powers by donating such fields to the influential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, Gunji(local magistrates), Goji(local government officials under the Ritsuryo system), Fumyo (tillers of public rice fields) developed new rice fields and owned these fields. they ensured their power by donating such fields to the influential.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, Gunji (local magistrates), Goji (local government officials under the Ritsuryo system), Fumyo (tillers of public rice fields) developed new rice fields, owned these fields, and ensured their power by donating such fields to the influential.</e>
<cmt>二文を一文に繋げました。スペースを削除・挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>これを寄進地系荘園という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">these private estates are called donated private estates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">these private estates were called donated private estates.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These fields were called donated-type shoen.</e>
<cmt>寄進地系荘園の訳、変更。Private estates→fields</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>これに対応して、国衙領内部も郡・郷・保・条などに再編成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to the increase in donated private estates, the lands in the Kokugaryo were reorganized into the following districts such as Gun(county), Go(district), Ho, Jo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the increase in donated private estates, the lands in the Kokugaryo were reorganized into districts such as Gun(county), Go(district), Ho, Jo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, the lands in the Kokugaryo were reorganized into districts such as Gun (county), Go (district), Ho, Jo.</e>
<cmt>to the increase in donated private estates→削除スペース挿入・削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>これら荘園や公領は特定の領主が私有地として独占的な支配権を持つのではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various interests were related with these private estates and public lands: specific owners did not hold land ownership.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various interests were related with these private estates and public lands: specific owners did not hold land ownership.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specific owners did not hold land ownership for these shoen and public lands.</e>
<cmt>private estates→shoenVarious interests were related with はこの項の原文にはないので削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>支配単位ごとに上は収税権をもつ朝廷、権門から在地領主として地域に根を下ろした武士などを経て、下は名主層に至る、複数者の権利が重層的にからんでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rather, the Imperial Court, the influential who had the authority to collect taxes, warriors who lived there as local lords, as well as myoshu had interests in those lands in a multilayered way.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather, the Imperial Court, the influential who had the authority to collect taxes, warriors who lived there as local lords, as well as myoshu had multilayered interests in these lands.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather, the Imperial Court, the influential who had the authority to collect taxes, warriors who lived there as local lords, as well as myoshu had multilayered interests in these lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>各主体が保有する権利は「職」（しき）とよばれ、職が重層的な体系をなしていたことから、これを職の体系という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the land ownership was called &apos;Shiki&quot; and since Shiki had a multilayered system, this system is called the Shiki system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land ownership was known as &quot;Shiki&quot; (literally means profession) and since Shiki was comprised of a multilayered system, this system was called the Shiki system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land ownership was known as &apos;Shiki&apos; (literally means profession) and since Shiki was comprised of a multilayered system, this system was called the Shiki system.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>そして職の体系を基盤として11世紀後期～12世紀に成立した体制を荘園公領制という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the system established from the late stage of the 11th century to the 12th century based on the Shiki system is called Shoen Koryo Sei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system established from the late stage of the 11th century to the 12th century based on the Shiki system is called Shoen Koryo Sei.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system established from the late stage of the 11th century to the 12th century based on the Shiki system is called Shoen Koryo Sei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>平安後期の政治・経済史は、この荘園公領制の成立と深く関わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the political and economic history in the latter half of the Heian period is strongly associated with the establishment of this system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The political and economic history in the latter half of the Heian period is strongly associated with the establishment of this system.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The political and economic history in the latter half of the Heian period is strongly associated with the establishment of this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="120">
<j>11世紀中期までは摂関政治がある程度機能していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up to the middle of the 11th century, the regency functioned to some extent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up to the middle of the 11th century, the regency functioned to some extent.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up to the middle of the 11th century, the regency functioned to some extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>社会の変動に対応する政治的イニシアチブを摂関家と天皇のいずれもがとりえないという摂関政治の欠陥が露呈し、機能不全に陥っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that time, neither regents and advisers nor emperors could take the political initiative, leading to a lack of direction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that time, neither regents and advisers nor emperors could take the political initiative, leading to a lack in direction.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that time, defect in the regency that neither Sekkan-ke nor emperors could take the political initiative for social changes was exposed, leading to a lack of function.</e>
<cmt>regents and advisers→Sekkan-kedirection→function「社会の変動に対応する」「摂関政治の欠陥が露呈し」追記して書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>同後期に登場した、外戚に藤原氏を持たない後三条天皇は天皇親政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo, who had no maternal relative from the Fujiwaras, directly ruled the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理記録荘園券契所→Kiroku shoen Kenkeijoという表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Gosanjo, who had no maternal relative from the Fujiwaras, directly ruled the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gosanjo, who had no maternal relatives from the Fujiwara clan, directly ruled the country.</e>
<cmt>relative→relativesthe の後のスペース短縮Fujiwaras→Fujiwara clan</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>記録荘園券契所を設置して実効的な荘園整理を進める（延久の荘園整理令）など、当時の社会変動に伴う課題に自ら取り組んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He coped with the challenges associated with social changes in those days. For example, he promoted effective regulations of private estates by establishing theKiroku shoen kenkeijo (office for the investigation of estate documents) (Enkyu Order for the Reform of &quot;Shoen&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He coped with the challenges associated with social changes in those days such as promoting effective regulation of private estates by establishing theKiroku shoen kenkeijo (office for the investigation of estate documents) (Enkyu Order for the Reform of &quot;Shoen&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He coped with the challenges associated with social changes in those days such as promoting effective regulation of shoen by establishing the Kiroku shoen kenkeijo (office for the investigation of estate documents) (Enkyu Manor Regulation Acts).</e>
<cmt>private estates→shoenKiroku の前にスペース挿入延久の荘園整理令の訳、変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>後三条の子、白河天皇も積極的に政治に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Shirakawa, a son of Emeror Gosanjo, positively coped with political challenges.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Shirakawa, a son of Emeror Gosanjo, positively coped with political challenges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Shirakawa, a son of Emeror Gosanjo, positively coped with political challenges.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>退位して上皇となった後は天皇家の長という立場で独自の政策を展開していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the abdication from the crown, the retired Emperor Shirakawa developed his own policies from the viewpoint of the head of the Emperor&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the abdication from the crown, the retired Emperor Shirakawa developed his own policies from the viewpoint of the head of the Emperor&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the abdication, the retired Emperor Shirakawa developed his own policies from the viewpoint of the head of the Emperor&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt>from the crown→削除　（crown ではなく emperor だと思いますが、abdication のみで十分と考えます。）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>これが院政の開始であり、院政を行う上皇を治天の君という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the beginning of the cloister government, and a retired emperor who organized policy is called &apos;chiten no kimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the beginning of the cloister government, and a retired emperor who organized policy is called &apos;chiten no kimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the beginning of the cloister government, and a retired emperor who organized policy is called &apos;chiten no kimi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>白河上皇は、自らの政策を企画・遂行するために中流貴族を院司とし、また院独自の軍事力として北面の武士を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the retired Emperor Shirakawwa, in order to design and carry out his policy, made middle-class aristocracy Inshi (official of the In no cho, or Retired Emperor&apos;s Office), placed Hokumen no Bushi&apos; (the Imprerial Palace Guards) as his own military force.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the retired Emperor Shirakawwa, in order to design and carry out his policy, made middle-class aristocracy Inshi (official of the In no cho, or Retired Emperor&apos;s Office), and placed Hokumen no Bushi&apos; (the Imprerial Palace Guards) as his own military force.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retired Emperor Shirakawa, in order to design and carry out his policy, made middle-class aristocracy Inshi (official of the In no cho, or Retired Emperor&apos;s Office), and placed Hokumen no Bushi (the Imprerial Palace Guards) as his own military force.</e>
<cmt>Shirakawwa→Shirakawahis の前のスペース短縮Bushi&apos;→Bushi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>また当時、河内源氏に代わって武士の棟梁となりつつあった伊勢平氏を院司としたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also made Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) Inshi, the head of warriors instead of Kawachi-genji (Genji clan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also made Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) Inshi, the head of warriors instead of Kawachi-genji (Genji clan).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also made Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) Inshi, the head of warriors instead of Kawachi-genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>Genji→Minamoto</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="129">
<j>白河に続く鳥羽天皇も、白河以上の専制を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the retired Toba Emperor, the successor of Shirakawa, dominated more strongly than Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the retired Toba Emperor, the successor of Shirakawa, dominated more strongly than Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Toba, the successor of Shirakawa, dominated more strongly than Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>鳥羽天皇が鳥羽上皇となっているので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>伊勢平氏を実行部隊として日宋貿易に力を入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He put his efforts into the trade between Japan and Sung Dynasty in China, placing Ise-Heishi in charge.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He put his efforts into trade between Japan and the Sung Dynasty in China, placing Ise-Heishi in charge.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He put his efforts into trade between Japan and the Sung Dynasty in China, placing Ise-Heishi in charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>また荘園公領制の進展に伴って各地の荘園を集積するなど、経済的な支配力も強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also put private estates in many places under his control with the development of shoen koryo sei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also put private estates in many places under his control with the development of shoen koryo sei.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also put shoen in many places under his control with the development of shoen koryo sei.</e>
<cmt>private estates→shoen</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="132">
<j>12世紀に入ると、有力貴族などが特定の国の租税収取権を保有する知行国制がひろく実施されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 12th century, Chigyo kokusei (proprietary province system) was widely performed: in this system, influential aristocrats owned the authority to collect taxes from certain provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 12th century, Chigyo kokusei (proprietary province system) was widely performed: in this system, influential aristocrats owned the authority to collect taxes from certain provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 12th century, Chigyo kokusei (proprietary province system) was widely performed: in this system, influential aristocrats owned the authority to collect taxes from certain provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>知行国制は、荘園公領制の進展と軌を一にしたものであり、経済的利得権が権門勢家へ集中していったことを表している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chigyo kokusei developed together with shoen koryosei, which means only the influential could get economic profits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chigyo kokusei developed together with shoen koryosei, which means only the influential could derive economic profits.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chigyo kokusei developed together with shoen koryosei, which means only the influential could derive economic profits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="134">
<j>12世紀中期に鳥羽上皇が没すると、治天の君の座を巡って天皇家・摂関家を巻き込む政争が起こり、軍事衝突によって解決した（保元の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of the retired Emperor Toba in the middle of the 12th century, a political fight occurred, which involved the Emperor&apos;s family, regents and advisers, and was resolved after a military confrontation (Hogen Distrubance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of the retired Emperor Toba in the middle of the 12th century, a political fight occurred, which involved the Emperor&apos;s family, regents and advisers, and was resolved after a military confrontation (Hogen Distrubance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of the retired Emperor Toba in the middle of the 12th century, a political fight for the seat of chiten no kimi occurred, which involved the Emperor&apos;s family and Sekkan-ke, and was resolved after a military confrontation (the Hogen War).</e>
<cmt>regents and advisers→and Sekkan-keHogen Disturbance→the Hogen War「治天の君の座を巡って」追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>続いて、数年後に再び政争が軍事衝突によって終結し（平治の乱）、両乱を通じて武士の政治的地位が上昇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some years later, a military confrontation brought another political fight (Heiji Disturbance) to an end and through those two wars, the warriors&apos; political status rose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some years later, a military confrontation brought another political fight (Heiji Disturbance) to an end and through these two wars, the warriors&apos; political status rose.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some years later, a military confrontation brought another political fight (the Heiji War) to an end and through these two wars, the warriors&apos;political status rose.</e>
<cmt>political の前のスペース短縮Disturbance→War</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>保元以前、武力で政争が解決した事例は平安初期の平城上皇の変にまで遡り、三百数十年ぶりの異変だったため、当時の人々に大きな衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">those two wars astounded people of that time because they had not had a political fight involving a military force for three hundred years and several decades since Heizeijoko no hen (retired Emperor Heizei Disturbance), which occurred in the early the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">these wars astounded people of the time because they had not had a political fight which involved a military force for three hundred years and several decades since Heizeijoko no hen (retired Emperor Heizei Disturbance), in the early the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These wars astounded people of the time because they had not had a political fight which involved a military force for 300 years and several decades since the War of retired Emperor Heizei, in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>the Heian→HeianHeizeijoko no hen (retired Emperor Heizei Disturbance)→the War of retired Emperor Heizei数字変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>両乱で大きな勲功のあった平清盛は異例の出世を遂げ、後白河天皇の院政を支えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Kiyomori, who distinguished himself in the two wars, exceptionally developed his career and supported Goshirakawa&apos;s cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Kiyomori, who distinguished himself during these two wars, developed his career and supported Goshirakawa&apos;s cloister government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Kiyomori, who distinguished himself during these two wars, developed his career and supported Goshirakawa&apos;s cloister government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし、次第に後白河と清盛との間に対立が見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, conflicts between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori became serious.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, conflicts between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori became serious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, conflicts between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori became serious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>清盛は後白河院政を停止して、自らの政権を打ち立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori put an end to the cloister government and established his own government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori put an end to the cloister government and established his own government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori put an end to the cloister government and established his own government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>これを平氏政権という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>平氏政権は、貴族社会の中で成立したが、各地に地頭や国守護人を設置するなど最初の武家政権としての性格を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Taira clan government was established in the aristocratic society, it had some similarities to the first military government, such as setting up Jito (estate stewards) and Province bakufu officers in many places.</e>
<cmt>地頭：estate stewardsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Taira clan government was established under an aristocratic society, it had some similarities to the first military government, such as the setting up of Jito (estate stewards) and Province bakufu officers in many places.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Taira clan government was established under an aristocratic society, it had some similarities to the first military government, such as the setting up of jito (manager and lord of manor) and provincial officers in many places.</e>
<cmt>地頭の定訳国守護人の定訳不明ですが、provincial officers としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>平氏政権の支配に対して、貴族・寺社層から反発が出されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aristocracy, temples and shrines rebelled against the Taira clan government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="143">
<j>そうした不満を背景として1180年に後白河の皇子以仁王が反平氏の兵を挙げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aristocracy, temples and shrines were against the Taira clan government. With such complaints in the background, Prince Mochihito, a son of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, rose in arms to subjugate the Taira clan in 1180.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aristocracy, temples and shrines rebelled against the Taira clan government. With such complaints in the background, Prince Mochihito, a son of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, rose in arms to subjugate the Taira clan in 1180.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With such complaints in the background, Prince Mochihito, a son of the retired Emperor Goshirakawa, rose in arms to subjugate the Taira clan in 1180.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>この挙兵はすぐに鎮圧されたが、平家支配に潜在的な不満を抱いていた各地の武士・豪族層が次々に挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was soon crushed, many warriors and powerful regional who had been discontented with the Taira government rose in arms one after another.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was soon crushed, many warriors and powerful regionals who had been discontent with the Taira government rose in arms one after another.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was soon crushed, many warriors and powerful regionals who had been discontent with the Taira government rose in arms one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>平氏勢力や各地の勢力の間で5年に渡る内乱が繰り広げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Civil war continued for five years between Taira clans and regional clans.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Civil war continued for five years between the Taira and regional clans.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Civil war continued for five years between the Taira and regional clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>最終的に関東に本拠を置いた武家政権、すなわち鎌倉幕府の勝利によって内乱は終結した（治承・寿永の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the war finally ended in the victory of the first military government, Kamakura bakufu, which placed its headquarters office in Kanto region (Jisho-Juei no ran: Jisho-Juei War).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the war finally ended in the victory of the first military government, Kamakura bakufu, which placed its headquarters in the Kanto region (Jisho-Juei no ran: Jisho-Juei War).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war finally ended in the victory of the first military government, Kamakura bakufu, which placed its headquarters in the Kanto region (the Jisho-Juei War).</e>
<cmt>Jisho-Juei no ran 削除Jisho-Juei War 定冠詞追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>この乱の過程で鎌倉幕府は朝廷から東国の支配権、軍事警察権を獲得し、朝廷から独立した地方政権へと成長していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the war, Kamakura bakufu obtained the right to rule Togoku and military and police authorities, becoming a local government independent of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the war, the Kamakura bakufu obtained the right to rule Togoku as well as military and police authorities, becoming a local government independent of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war, the Kamakura bakufu obtained the right to rule Togoku as well as military and police authorities, becoming a local government independent of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>鎌倉幕府の成立をもって新たな時代区分が開始したとされ、この時点が平安時代の終期とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the new period of history is considered to have started with the establishment of Kamakura bakufu and this point is regarded as the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This new period of history is considered to have started with the establishment of Kamakura bakufu and this point is regarded as the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This new period of history is considered to have started with the establishment of Kamakura bakufu and this point is regarded as the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>社会・経済史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Socio-economic history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Socio-economic history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Socio-economic history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="149">
<j>8世紀に本格的に始まった律令制の根幹は、戸籍・計帳によって人民を把握し、課税の対象とする人別支配であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the foundation of the Ritsuryo system, which officially started in the 8th century, an individual-controlling system: rulers determined the number of people, according to family register and the yearly tax registers, and taxed those people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the foundation of the Ritsuryo system, which officially started in the 8th century, an individual-controlling system: rulers determined the number of people, according to family register and the yearly tax registers, and taxed those people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foundation of the Ritsuryo system, which officially started in the 8th century, was an individual-controlling system: rulers determined the number of people, according to family register and the yearly tax registers, and taxed those people.</e>
<cmt>century の後に was 追記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>しかし、奈良時代後期（8世紀後期）ごろから、課税から逃れたい人民らの偽籍・逃亡・浮浪が次第に顕著となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it became apparent that a lot of people who wanted to escape from paying taxes began falsifying the register, then escaping and wandering about in the latter stage of the Nara period (the latter stage of the 8th century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it became apparent that many people who wanted to escape evade taxation began falsifying the register, then escapted and wandered about during the latter stage of the Nara period (the latter stage of the 8th century).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it became apparent that many people who wanted to escape taxation began falsifying the register, escaping and wandering about during the latter stage of the Nara period (the latter stage of the 8th century).</e>
<cmt>escape evade→escape「偽籍・逃亡・浮浪」は並列なので訂正しました。ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="151">
<j>平安時代に入ってからその状況は一層進展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">that tendency developed further in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This tendency was exacerbated further during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This tendency was exacerbated further during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>平安時代初期の右大臣藤原園人は、貧民救済を主要政策として精力的に取り組んだが、貧民層の増大が課題となっていたことを物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sonohito, Udaijin, (the Minister of the Right) in the early part of the Heian period, made positive efforts to rescue the poor, which showed that the increase in poor people was problematic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sonohito, Udaijin, (the Minister of the Right) in the early part of the Heian period, made positive efforts to rescue the poor, which showed that there was a problematic increase in the number of poor people.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sonohito, Udaijin (Mnister of the Right) in the early part of the Heian period, made positive efforts to rescue the poor, which showed that there was a problematic increase in the number of poor people.</e>
<cmt>the→the&quot;Udaijin, (the Minister&quot;→&quot;Udaijin (Mnister&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>平安前期には、人民内部で少数の富豪層と大多数の貧困層（一般百姓層）へと階層の二極分化が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the earlier part of the Heian period, people were divided into a few millionaires and a majority of poor people (common peasants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the earlier part of the Heian period, people were divided into a few millionaires and a majority of poor people (common peasants).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the earlier part of the Heian period, people were divided into a few millionaires and a majority of poor people (common peasants).</e>
<cmt>the→the</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>富豪層は院宮王臣家（皇族、有力貴族）と墾田開発などを通じて関係を結び、一般百姓層を自らの影響下へ置き始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the millionaires became related with Engu oshinke (imperial families and nobles) through the reclaimed land development, and began to put common peasants under their influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the millionaires became related with Engu oshinke (imperial families and nobles) through the reclaimed land development, and began to put common peasants under their influence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The millionaires became related with Ingu oshinke (imperial families and nobles) through the reclaimed land development, and began to put common peasants under their influence.</e>
<cmt>Engu→Ingu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>貧困層は、富豪層の影響下に入ることで、偽籍・逃亡・浮浪をより容易なものとし、人別支配に基づく課税制度は破綻を迎えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the poor were under the influence of the millionaires, the former could falsify the register, escape and wander about more easily than before, which lead to the downfall of the individual-based tax system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the poor were under the influence of the millionaires, the former could falsify the register, escape and wander about more easily than before, which lead to the downfall of the individual-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the poor were under the influence of the millionaires, the former could falsify the register, escape and wander about more easily than before, which lead to the downfall of the individual-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="156">
<j>平安中期のはじめごろ、朝廷は人別支配を放擲し、土地課税を基調とした支配へと移行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the early part of the Heian period, the Imperial Court gave up the individual-based tax system, and moved into the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the early part of the Heian period, the Imperial Court gave up the individual-based tax system, and moved into the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the early part of the Heian period, the Imperial Court gave up the individual-based tax system, and moved into the land-based tax system.</e>
<cmt>the→the</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>それに伴って、地方に土着した貴族や郡司らに出自する富豪層は、国衙から名田経営と租税収取を請け負う田堵負名へ成長し、より一層経済力をつけていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Millionaires who were descents from aristocracy who had settled in the country or local magistrates grew into Tato fumyo(cultivator/tax manager): they undertook cultivation of Myoden and tax collection from kokuga and expanded their economic power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Millionaires who were descents from aristocracy who had settled in the country or local magistrates grew into Tato fumyo(cultivator/tax manager): they undertook cultivation of Myoden and tax collection from kokuga and expanded their economic power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Millionaires who were descents from aristocracy who had settled in the country or local magistrates grew into Tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager): they undertook cultivation of Myoden and tax collection from kokuga and expanded their economic power.</e>
<cmt>括弧の前にスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>富豪層と一般百姓層の格差はますます増大し、一般百姓は次第に富豪の支配下に組み込まれていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the gap between millionaires and common peasants was becoming bigger and bigger; the latter were gradually put under the former&apos;s influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gap between millionaires and common peasants gew larger and larger; the latter gradually came under the former&apos;s influence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gap between millionaires and common peasants gew larger and larger; the latter gradually came under the former&apos;s influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>文化・宗教史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Culture and religious history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Culture and religious history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Culture and religious history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="159">
<j>平安初期の中央文化は、唐の影響を強く受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the central culture of the early Heian period was strongly affected by Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The central culture of the early Heian period was strongly affected by the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The central culture of the early Heian period was strongly affected by the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>桓武天皇は中国皇帝にならい郊天祭祀を行うなど、中国への志向が強かったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Emperor Kanmu strongly admired China; he, followed Tang emperors and performed Koten saishi (a sacred ceremony that acknowleges an Emperor as son of heaven).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Emperor Kanmu strongly admired China; he, followed Tang emperors and performed Koten saishi (a sacred ceremony that acknowleges an Emperor as son of heaven).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Emperor Kanmu strongly admired China; he followed Tang emperors and performed Koten saishi (a sacred ceremony that acknowleges an Emperor as son of heaven).</e>
<cmt>he の後のカンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>桓武期には従来の日本に見られない中国仏教（天台宗、密教）が最澄、空海によって伝来された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his reign, Chinese Buddhism (Tendai sect and Esoteric Buddhism), was introduced to Japan by Saicho and Kukai, respectively, for the first time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During his reign, Chinese Buddhism (Tendai sect and Esoteric Buddhism), was introduced to Japan by Saicho and Kukai, respectively, for the first time.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During his reign, Chinese Buddhism (Tendai sect and Esoteric Buddhism), was introduced to Japan by Saicho and Kukai, respectively, for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>以降の日本仏教の方向性を大きく規定づけることとなった（平安仏教）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It decided the direction of Japanese Buddhism from that time on (Heian Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳語例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was to decide the direction of Japanese Buddhism (Heian Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was to decide the direction of Japanese Buddhism (Heian Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>こうした仏教の影響を日本古来の信仰も受けて、本地垂迹説があらわれて神仏習合が進んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese traditional religion was influenced by Buddhism, Han-honji-suijaku setsu (theory of original reality and manifested traces) was introduced, leading to Syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese traditional religion was influenced by Buddhism, Han-honji-suijaku setsu (theory of original reality and manifested traces) was introduced, leading to the Syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese traditional religion was influenced by Buddhism, Honji-suijaku setsu (theory of original reality and manifested traces) was introduced, leading to the Syncretism of Shinto and Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>本地垂迹説の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>嵯峨天皇から清和天皇にかけての時期は、凌雲集などの漢文詩集が編纂されたり、唐風の書がはやるなど、唐風文化が花開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Emperor Saga to Emperor Seiwa, Tang-way culture was in full bloom; poetry books of Chinese classics, including Ryounshu (Cloud-borne collection), were compiled and Tang-way calligraphy was popular.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Emperor Saga to Emperor Seiwa, the Tang-way culture was in full bloom; poetry books of Chinese classics, including Ryounshu (Cloud-borne collection), were compiled and Tang-way calligraphy was popular.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Emperor Saga to Emperor Seiwa, the Tang-way culture was in full bloom; poetry books of Chinese classics, including Ryounshu (Cloud-borne collection), were compiled and Tang-way calligraphy was popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>この唐風が非常に強い文化を弘仁・貞観文化という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the culture with a strong influence from Tang is called Konin-Jogan Culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The culture which was strongly influenced by the Tang dynasty is called Konin-Jogan Culture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The culture which was strongly influenced by the Tang dynasty is called Konin-Jogan Culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="166">
<j>文化の国風化（日本化）の萌芽は、奈良時代から見られていたが、平安初期は唐風文化の影に隠れるかのようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although beginnings of Kokufubunka (Japanized culture: aristocratic culture) were seen in the Nara period, it was hidden under the shadow of Tang-way culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the beginnings of Kokufubunka (Japanized culture: aristocratic culture) were seen in the Nara period, it was hidden under the shadow of Tang-way culture.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the beginnings of Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture) were seen in the Nara period, it was hidden under the shadow of Tang-way culture.</e>
<cmt>「文化の国風化」を「国風文化」としていますので、215で出てくる国風文化の定訳をここで記入します。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>しかし、唐風化の波が沈静化すると、ふたたび日本的な要素が文化の前面へと現れてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the influence of Tang weakened, factors with Japanese characteristics became apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the influence of the Tang dynasty weakened, factors which were uniquely Japanese became apparent.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the influence of the Tang dynasty weakened, factors which were uniquely Japanese became apparent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>これが、平安中期ごろの国風文化である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">this is the Kokufubunka (aristocratic culture) in the mid- Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">this is the Kokufubunka (aristocratic culture) in the mid- Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the Kokufu Bunka in the mid-Heian period.</e>
<cmt>国風文化の説明削除Kokufubunka→Kokufu BunkaHeian の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>特徴としては、平仮名・片仮名の発明で中古日本語の表記が容易になったことによる、和歌・日記・物語文学の隆盛、官衣束帯の登場（官服の国風化）、寝殿造の登場などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is characterized by the following: the prosperity of waka, diaries, chronicles, which occurred because description of ancient and medieval Japanese became easier following the invention of Hiragana and Katakana; the appearance of Kan-i-sokutai (official uniform in aristocratic culture), and the appearance of Shinden-zukuri style (the palace style of the Fujiwara period architecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is characterized by the following: the prosperity of waka, diaries, chronicles, which occurred because description of ancient and medieval Japanese became easier following the invention of Hiragana and Katakana; the appearance of Kan-i-sokutai (official uniform in aristocratic culture), and the appearance of Shinden-zukuri style (the palace style of Fujiwara period architecture).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is characterized by the following: the prosperity of waka, diaries, chronicles, which occurred because description of ancient and medieval Japanese became easier following the invention of hiragana (Japanese syllabary characters) and katakana (one of the Japanese syllabaries); the appearance of Kan-i-sokutai (official uniform in aristocratic culture), and the appearance of Shinden-zukuri style (architecture representative [characteristic] of a nobleman&apos;s residence in the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>平仮名の定訳と片仮名の説明補足寝殿造を登録の多い説明に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>また、平安中期は、仏教の末法思想が人々に広く浸透し、浄土思想・浄土教が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid- Heian period, Mappo-shiso, the &quot;Pessimism due to decadent-age theory&quot; belief was prevalent, and Pure Land Buddhism, Jodo (Pure Land) sect was widely accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid-Heian period, Mappo-shiso, the &quot;Pessimism due to decadent-age theory&quot; belief was prevalent, and Pure Land Buddhism, the Jodo (Pure Land) sect was widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid-Heian period, Mappo-shiso (the &quot;end of the world&quot; belief) was prevalent, and Pure Land Buddhism, the Jodo (Pure Land) sect was widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>末法思想の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>民衆に仏教信仰が拡がったのもこの時期であり、空也や融通念仏の良忍などの僧が民衆の中で活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was during that time that Buddhism was widely accepted among ordinary people and Kuya as well as Ryonin of Yuzu nenbutsu (reciting the name of Amida Buddha) was active among them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was during this time that Buddhism was widely accepted among ordinary people and Kuya as well as Ryonin of Yuzu nenbutsu (reciting the name of Amida Buddha) was active among them.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was during this time that Buddhism was widely accepted among ordinary people and Kuya as well as Ryonin of Yuzu nenbutsu (reciting the name of Amida Buddha) was active among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="172">
<j>平安末期になると歴史物語・軍記物語などの時代を顧みる文学が芽生えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Heian period, literature that looked back over the past, such as historical tales and war chronicles, was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Heian period, literature was born that looked back over the past, such as historical tales and war chronicles.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Heian period, literature was born that looked back over the past, such as historical tales and war chronicles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>天台仏教・山岳仏教が日本各地へ広がり、豊後国東半島（豊貴寺大堂など）や北陸地方（平泉寺など）などで動きが顕著であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tendai Buddhism and Mountain Buddhism spread all over Japan and the regions where this was prominent was Kunisaki peninsula in the Fungo Province (including Main Hall in Fuki-ji Temple) and Hokuriku District (including Heisen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tendai Buddhism and Mountain Buddhism spread all over Japan and the regions where this was prominent included Kunisaki peninsula in the Fungo Province (including Main Hall in Fuki-ji Temple) and Hokuriku District (including Heisen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tendai Buddhism and Mountain Buddhism spread all over Japan and the regions where this was prominent included Kunisaki peninsula in the Bungo Province (including Main Hall in Fuki-ji Temple) and Hokuriku Region (including Heisen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>Fungo→BungoDistrict→Region</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>その他の地域でも三仏寺投入堂などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nageire do (thrown-in temple) of Sanbutsu-ji Temple was also famous for Buddhism activity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nageire do (thrown-in temple) of Sanbutsu-ji Temple was also famous for Buddhism activity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nageire-do (thrown-in temple) of Sanbutsu-ji Temple was also famous for Buddhism activity.</e>
<cmt>Nageire do→Nageire-do</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>当時、民衆の間に今様という歌謡が流行し、後白河上皇により今様を集成した『梁塵秘抄』が編まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the songs and ballads called imayo were popular among ordinary people and &quot;Ryojinhi-sho&quot; (folk song collection, which literarly means &quot;Songs to Make the Dust Dance on the Beams&quot;) was compiled under the order of retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Songs and ballads called imayo were popular among ordinary people and &quot;Ryojinhi-sho&quot; (a folk song collection, which literarly means &quot;Songs to Make the Dust Dance on the Beams&quot;) was compiled under the order of retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Songs and ballads called imayo were popular among ordinary people and &quot;Ryojin hisho&quot; (folk song collection) was compiled under the order of retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>梁塵秘抄の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>覚猷（鳥羽僧正）筆と伝えられ、人々の様子をユーモラスかつ活き活きとした姿で描いた鳥獣人物戯画もこの時代の作品である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choju-Jinbutsu-Giga Emaki (Scrolles of frolicking Animals) was drawn in that period which is said to have been drawn by Kakuya (Toba Sojo (high Buddhist priest) and it shows vivid and humorous pictures of people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choju-Jinbutsu-Giga Emaki (Scrolles of frolicking Animals) was drawn during this period which is said to have been drawn by Kakuya (Toba Sojo (high Buddhist priest) and shows vivid and humorous pictures of people.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choju-Jinbutsu-giga (scrolls of frolicking animals and humans) was drawn during this period which is said to have been drawn by Kakuya (Toba Sojo (high-ranking Buddhist priest)) and shows vivid and humorous pictures of people.</e>
<cmt>鳥獣人物戯画、僧正の定訳priest)→priest))</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 唐変木(id:17050), Wushi(id:107127), Y.Sanada(id:36926), Idioma-bot(id:129667), MIsogi(id:20599), Eskimbot(id:29676), Shikire(id:1623), Extrahitz(id:26245), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Damdamdamd(id:109603), Mintleaf(id:2216), Robert De Smith(id:28533), OKBot(id:143139), Ghaz(id:1137), でここ(id:9565), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), Redattore(id:30931), 代言人(id:33675), Kinori(id:443), Rei-bot(id:94097), 十月之交(id:586), Chobot(id:20846), Tenko(id:102318), Shimoxx(id:9332), 李(id:10582), ASAMA501(id:91947), Yosemite(id:5808), Kzhr(id:131), TARBOT(id:73059), Lonicera(id:20638), Kussy(id:3128), Forestfarmer(id:59407), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tongpoo(id:2900), 葉月(id:25674), Sh(id:2707), 榎(id:91458), Synthetik(id:30), MDR-SK(id:192066), Carkuni(id:79281), Xandi(id:36691), Miri(id:164), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Kyube(id:9866), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 伏儀(id:142093), 史跡めぐり(id:95651), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Junger(id:10282), Louperibot(id:128971), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>