<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雲図抄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unzusho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unzusho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unzusho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>雲図抄（うんずしょう）は、平安時代後期に描かれた儀式書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unzusho is a book on rites that was written in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unzusho is a book on rites that was written in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unzusho is a book on rites that was written in the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>書名は「雲上（清涼殿）での（儀式の）指図」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title of the book literally means &apos;an instruction for rites of Unjo (in other words, Seiryoden or the imperial court)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title of the book literally means &apos;an instruction for rites of Unjo (in other words, Seiryoden or the imperial court)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of the book literally means &apos;an instruction for rites of Unjo (in other words, Seiryoden or the imperial court).&apos;</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>それは、清涼殿における儀式の際の配置を彩色付の図を付して解説したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It illustrates arrangements of rites in Seiryoden with colored pictures.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It illustrates the arrangements of rites in Seiryoden with colored pictures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It illustrates the arrangements of rites in Seiryoden with colored pictures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>『本朝書籍目録』では著者は藤原朝隆とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The author was identified as FUJIWARA no Tomotaka in &quot;Honchoshojaku mokuroku&quot;(the oldest list of Japanese books in existence written in the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The author was identified as FUJIWARA no Tomotaka in &quot;Honchoshojaku mokuroku&quot;(the oldest list of Japanese books in existence written during the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The author was identified as FUJIWARA no Tomotaka in &quot;Honchoshojaku mokuroku&quot; (the oldest list of Japanese books in existence written during the Kamakura period).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、近代に和田英松が著者をその兄の藤原重隆として編纂年代を1110年代後半と推定してからは通説であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in mordern times, since Hidematsu WADA presumed that the author had been his elder brother, FUJIWARA no Shigetaka, and that the year of compilation had been the late 1110&apos;s, this presumption has been widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in mordern times, since Hidematsu WADA presumed that the author had been his elder brother, FUJIWARA no Shigetaka, and that the year of compilation had been the late 1110&apos;s, this presumption has been widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in modern times, since Hidematsu WADA presumed that the author had been his elder brother, FUJIWARA no Shigetaka, and that the year of compilation had been the late 1110&apos;s, this presumption has been widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、江戸時代に藤原為隆の子孫である坊城俊将が、重隆・朝隆の弟藤原親隆を著者とする説を立てている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, in the Edo period, Toshimasa BOJO, who was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Tametaka, advanced a new theory that FUJIWARA no Chikataka, who was a younger brother of aforementioned Shigetaka and Tomotaka, was the author.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, during the Edo period, Toshimasa BOJO, who was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Tametaka, advanced a new theory that FUJIWARA no Chikataka, who was a younger brother of aforementioned Shigetaka and Tomotaka, was the author.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, during the Edo period, Toshimasa BOJO, who was a descendant of FUJIWARA no Tametaka, advanced a new theory that FUJIWARA no Chikataka, who was a younger brother of aforementioned Shigetaka and Tomotaka, was the author.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>藤原為隆は重隆・朝隆・親隆の実兄であり、坊城家にかつてその由来が伝わっていた可能性もあるが、不詳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since FUJIWARA no Tametaka was a real brother of Shigetaka, Tomotaka and Chikataka, there was a possibility that the history of the book had been handed down in the BOJO family, but the truth remains unclear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since FUJIWARA no Tametaka was a real brother of Shigetaka, Tomotaka and Chikataka, there was a possibility that the history of the book had been handed down in the BOJO family, but the truth remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since FUJIWARA no Tametaka was a real brother of Shigetaka, Tomotaka and Chikataka, there was a possibility that the history of the book had been handed down in the Bojo family, but the truth remains unclear.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>