<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>末期養子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsugo Yoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsugo Yoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsugo Yoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>末期養子（まつごようし）とは、養父が死に瀕したときに縁組された養子。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsugo yoshi was an adopted son on the adoptive father&apos;s deathbed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。それに伴い、原文を変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsugo yoshi was adopted on his adoptive father&apos;s deathbed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Matsugo yoshi&quot; refers to a son who was adopted on his adoptive father&apos;s deathbed.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションおよびアポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>末期養子（まつごようし）とは、江戸時代、武家の当主で嗣子のない者が事故・急病などで死に瀕した場合に、家の断絶を防ぐために緊急に養子縁組をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Edo era, when a head of samurai family who didn&apos;t have a son was on his deathbed because of accidents or disease, he adopted a son urgently to prevent from forfeiting a family name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。それに伴い、原文を変更。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo era, when a head of a samurai family who didn&apos;t have a son was on his deathbed due to accidents or disease, he would adopt a son to prevent forfeiting the family name.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, when a head of a samurai family, without a son to carry on the family name, was on his deathbed due to an accident or disease, a son was urgently adopted in order to prevent the extinction of the family name.</e>
<cmt>家の断絶は the extinction of the family nameとしました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当主が既に死亡しているにもかかわらず、周囲のものがそれを隠して当主の名において養子縁組を行うこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a head of family had already been dead, people around him concealed his death and pursued an adoption under the head&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the head of the family was already dead, people around him concealed his death and pursued an adoption under the head&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when the head of the family had been already dead, sometimes an adoption was carried out in the name of the family head by concealing his death for some time.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これも末期養子という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is also called Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also called Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a practice is also called &quot;Matsugo yoshi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Matsugo yoshi にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、これは一種の緊急避難の措置であり、危篤状態にあった当主が奇跡的に回復した場合などには、当主がその縁組を取り消すことも可能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Matsugo yoshi was a kind of emergency measure and when the head of family who was on his deathbed recovered miraculously, he could cancel the adoption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Matsugo yoshi was an emergency measure and if the head of family managed to recover miraculously, he could cancel the adoption.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Matsugo yoshi was an emergency measure, if the family head managed to recover miraculously, he was able to cancel the adoption.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>禁止と解禁の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Putting and Lifting a Ban</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Putting and Lifting a Ban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circumstance concerning the prohibition and lifting a ban</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>江戸時代初期には、大名の末期養子は江戸幕府によって禁じられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo era, Matsugo yoshi of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) was banned by Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo era, Matsugo yoshi of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) was banned by the Edo shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early Edo period, the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) prohibited the daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) to carry out the practice of Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>武家の家督を継ぐためには、主家（大名にとっては徳川将軍家が主家ということになる）に事前に届出をして嫡子たることを認められる必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To take over as head of the samurai family, a successor had to notify beforehand and had to be approved as the heir and son by a master (daimyo&apos;s master was the Tokugawa Shogun family).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To take over as head of the samurai family, a successor had to notify beforehand and had to be approved as the heir and son by a master (daimyo&apos;s master was the Tokugawa Shogun family).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To take over as the reign of a samurai family, a successor was required to notify and to be approved as the heir and son by the head family beforehand (the family of the Tokugawa Shogun was the head family of all the daimyo families).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。the daimyo famies を the daimyo families に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>末期養子はこの条件を満たすことができない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsugo yoshi didn&apos;t meet this condition.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsugo yoshi didn&apos;t meet this condition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsugo yoshi did not meet this requirement.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>御目見以上の格の大名家においては、さらに将軍との謁見を済ませておくことも必要とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A successor of daimyo family whose rank was Omemie (be received in audience) or higher had to have an audience with the Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A successor of daimyo family whose rank was Omemie (be received in audience) or higher had to have an audience with the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A successor of a daimyo family whose rank was Omemie (a rank with the privilege to have an audience with one&apos;s lord or a dignitary) or higher had to have an audience with the Shogun before the adoption took place.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>末期養子がこのように厳しく禁じられたのは、次のような事情による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason that Matsugo yoshi was banned was as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason that Matsugo yoshi was banned was as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circumstance concerning the prohibition of Matsugo yoshi was as follows.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>まず、末期養子においては当主の意思を確認する事が困難であった事による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the reasons was that it was difficult to confirm the willingness of the lord about Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the reasons was that it was difficult to confirm the willingness of the lord concerning Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Primarily, it was difficult to confirm the will of the family head by that time the Matsugo yoshi was required.</e>
<cmt>当主の訳はthe family head として統一しました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>家臣などが当主を暗殺して、自分の都合の良い当主に挿げ替えるなどの不法が行われる事態を危惧したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was worried that vassals might assassinate their lord and replace with a convenient person for them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was worried that vassals might assassinate their lord and replace him with person convenient to their needs.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was feared that retainers might assassinate the family head and replace him with someone convenient to their needs.</e>
<cmt>当主の訳はthe family head として統一しました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>だが最も重要な理由として、幕府が大名の力を削ぎ統制を強めることに大いに意を用いていた事にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the most important reason was that the bakufu wanted to reduce the daimyo&apos;s power and control it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the most important reason was that the bakufu wanted to reduce the daimyo&apos;s power and control them.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the most important purpose for the prohibition was in the bakufu&apos;s motivation to weaken the influence of daimyo in order to control them more easily.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。アポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>末期養子の禁止もその手段のひとつとして活用されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ban of Matsugo yoshi was one of the measure for that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ban of Matsugo yoshi was one such measure.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The banning of Matsugo yoshi was one such measure.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>支配体制のいまだ確立していない江戸時代初期には特に顕著で、幕府の成立から三代征夷大将軍徳川家光の治下にかけて、嗣子がないために取り潰される大名家が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early Edo era when the regime had not been established yet, especially between the formation of the bakufu and regime of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, many daimyo families were forfeited because of no heir and son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early Edo era when the regime had not been established yet, especially between the formation of the bakufu and regime of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, many daimyo families were forfeit due to the lack of an heir and son.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early Edo period when the control system had not been established yet, especially the period between the foundation of the bakufu and the regime of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, many daimyo families became extinct due to the lack of an heir.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは幕藩体制を確立するために大いに役立った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This measure worked very well to establish the shogunate system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This measure worked very well in establishing the shogunate system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This measure worked very well in establishing the shogunate system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしその反面、それらの大名家に仕えていた武士たちは浪人となる他なく、社会不安も増すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the other hand, the samurais who served for the forfeited daimyo families became ronin(masterless samurai) and that caused social instability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the samurais who served the forfeit daimyo families became ronin(masterless samurai) and caused social instability.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the samurais who served the extinct daimyo families became ronin(the masterless samurai), which caused a social instability.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>それが極致に達したのが、慶安4年（1651年）に起きた慶安の変、いわゆる由井正雪の乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eminent example of the social instability was the Keian Incident, in 1651, so-called Incident of Shosetsu YUI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A prime example of this kind of social instability was the Keian Incident, in 1651, or so-called Incident of Shosetsu YUI.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most telling example of such a case was the Keian Incident of 1651, or so-called the Incident of Shosetsu YUI.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>浪人が徒党を組んで幕府転覆を図ったこの事件は、幕府の大名統制策が新たな不安定要因を生み出していたことをはっきりと示していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident that ronin banded together and attempted to overthrow the bakufu showed the growing political unrest as a result of strict controls which the shogunate enforced on daimyos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident involved ronin who banded together in an atempt to overthrow the bakufu, and was a sign of the growing political unrest as a result of strict controls which the shogunate enforced on daimyos.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident involved ronins who banded together in an attempt to overthrow the bakufu, and was a sign of the growing political unrest as a result of strict controls which the shogunate enforced on daimyos.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。ronins　と複数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、これより前、寛永14年（1637年）から翌年にかけて起こった島原の乱においても、多くの浪人が一揆に加わったことが、その鎮定を困難にしたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Shimabara War (1637 - 1638) which occurred before this incident, many ronins participated in the uprising and that made suppression hard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Shimabara War (1637 - 1638) which occurred before this incident, many ronin participated in the uprising and which made supression difficult.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the earlier Shimabara War (1637 - 1638), many ronins participated in the uprising which made its suppression difficult.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>このような事情と、幕府の支配体制が一応の完成を見たことから、慶安4年、幕府は末期養子の禁を解いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering these situations and the control of the shogunate had been consolidated, the shogunate lifted a ban of Matsugo yoshi in 1651.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the situation and consolidation of the control of the shogunate, the shogunate lifted the ban on Matsugo yoshi in 1651.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the circumstance described above, and together with the fact that the control system of the shogunate was considered complete and secure for the time being, in 1651, the shogunate lifted the ban on Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>とはいえ、末期養子の認可のためには、幕府から派遣された役人が直接当主の生存と養子縁組の意思を確かめる判元見届（はんもとみとどけ）という手続きが必要であり、無制限に認められたわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, to be accepted Matsugo yoshi, the procedure of &quot;Hanmoto Mitodoke&quot; that officials delivered from the bakufu confirmed the living of lord and the willingness of adoption directly was necessary and it was not unrestricted approval.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, to be accepted Matsugo yoshi, the procedure of &quot;Hanmoto Mitodoke,&quot; where officials from the bakufu confirmed the willingness by lord who was alive to proceed with the adopotion was required, and was not carried out lightly.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even after the lifting of a ban, for Matsugo yoshi to be given approval, the procedure of &quot;Hanmoto Mitodoke&quot;, in which the family head was confirmed as alive and his will for adoption was certified by a bakufu official, had to be carried out, which made it not always as straightforward as it could have been.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>（ただし、のち当主生存の確認は儀式化する）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Later, the confirmation of the lord as alive became a mere event.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Later, the confirmation of the lord&apos;s life turned into a mere formality.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Later, however, the procedure in which the family head was confirmed as alive became a matter of formality.)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。「しかし」訳漏れのため、however, を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、末期養子を取る当主の年齢は17歳以上50歳以下とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the age of the lord who planned adoption was to be between 17 and 50.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionaly, it was decreed that the age of the to be lord was to be between 17 and 50.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it was decreed that the family head must be aged between 17 and 50 in order to be entitled for an adoption of Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>それ以外の年齢の当主は末期養子は認められていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lord with the age outside the range could not be accepted to adopt Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lord outside this age bracket could not be accepted to be adopted as Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A family head who fell outside this age bracket could not adopt a Matsugo yoshi.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>17歳未満の者が許可されるのは寛文3年（1663年）、50歳以上の者が許可されるのは天和 (日本)3年（1683年）になってからであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The adoption by the age under 17 was permitted in 1663 and the adoption by the age over 50 was permitted in 1683.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adoption of a lord under 17 was permitted in 1663 and the adoption by the age over 50 was permitted in 1683.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The permission for the adoption of Matsugo yoshi by family heads aged less than 17 was decreed in 1663, and the permission for those aged over 50 was decreed in 1683.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), An-chan(id:14590), Extrahitz(id:26245), 難民(id:4644), BAKU(id:55205), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), Turtlization(id:199715), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>