<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>移郷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Igo</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Igo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Igo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>移郷（いごう）は、奈良時代、平安時代の刑罰のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Igo is a kind of punishment in Nara and Heian periods to remove a criminal to another province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Igo is a kind of punishment carried out during the Nara and Heian periods to remove a criminal to another province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Igo is a kind of punishment carried out during the Nara and Heian periods to remove a criminal to another province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>例えば人を殺して死刑に処せられるべき者が赦に浴してその罪を許された場合で、殺された人の父母兄弟姉妹などによって復讐されるおそれのある時、罪人を他国に移して1戸を立てさせ、難を逃れさせることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a mandatory removal of a criminal sentenced to death for murder to another province to build a house in order to get of trouble if this criminal at risk of being revenged by parents, a brother, a sister etc. of the person who has been murdered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is the mandatory removal of a criminal sentenced to death for murder to another province to build a house in order to get out of trouble if this criminal at risk of revenge from parents, a brother, a sister etc. of the person he has been murdered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is the mandatory removal of a criminal sentenced to death for murder to another province to build a house in order to get out of trouble if this criminal at risk of revenge from parents, a brother, a sister etc. of the person he has been murdered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>「法曹至要抄」によれば、もし群盗共殺の時は、下手人および頭首人を移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Hossoshiyosho, if a gang of robbers committed a murder, the murderer and its boss shall be removed to a province. If the person who been murdered do not have no relation and therefore is not at any risk of being revenged, the criminal shall be affected to a group of technicians, Ryoko, Kanko, Kenin or Nuhi. However, if the criminal is a woman or if a Kenin or Nuhi of a another house is murdered, the criminal shall not be removed to another province.</e>
<cmt>下手人　http://ci.nii.ac.jp/naid/110000438038/頭首人（頭首）　http://www.eudict.com/?word=%E9%A0%AD%E9%A6%96&amp;lang=jpkeng陵戸　http://www.lub.lu.se/luft/diss/hum119.pdf官戸、家人、奴婢　http://www.e-shrine.org/images/NovNewsletter.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Hossoshiyosho, if a gang of robbers commit a murder, the murderer and his boss shall be removed to a province. If the person murdered does not have any relations and therefore is not at any risk of being revenged, the criminal shall be affected to a group of technicians, Ryoko, Kanko, Kenin or Nuhi. However, if the criminal is a woman or if a Kenin or Nuhi of a another house is murdered, the criminal shall not be removed to another province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;the Hossoshiyosho,&apos; if a gang of robbers commit a murder, the murderer and his boss shall be removed to a province.</e>
<cmt>補足一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただしもし死家に父子祖孫伯叔兄弟等なくして、復讐される憂がないものは、あるいは他国の雑戸および陵戸、官戸、家人、奴婢に充てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the person murdered does not have any relations and therefore is not at any risk of being revenged, the criminal shall be affected to a group of technicians, Ryoko, Kanko, Kenin or Nuhi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>もし婦人が犯あり、あるいは他主の家人奴婢を殺す者は移す限りでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if the criminal is a woman or if a Kenin or Nuhi of a another house is murdered, the criminal shall not be removed to another province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>もし移すべきを移さず、移すべからざるを移さば、官司を徒1年に処すという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If a criminal to be removed is not removed or vice versa, a government official is sentenced to one-year penalty.</e>
<cmt>従1年　定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If a criminal to be removed is not removed or vice versa, a government official is sentenced to one-year penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If a criminal to be removed is not removed or vice versa, a government official is sentenced to one-year penalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 竹麦魚(id:11012), 経済準学士(id:22656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>