<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>家相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaso (physiognomy of the house).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaso (physiognomy of the house).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaso (physiognomy of the house)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>家相（かそう）とは、風水や気学などと通じる開運学の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaso refers to one of the study of good-luck which has a similarity to feng shui and so on.</e>
<cmt>「気学」、意味不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaso refers to the study of fortune telling which is similar to Feng Shui etc.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaso refers to the study of fortune telling which is similar to Feng Shui, Kigaku (fortune telling based on Chinese 12 year cycle) and etc.</e>
<cmt>「気楽」:Kigaku (fortune telling based on Chinese 12 year cycle) として補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後天的運命学と分類されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes classified in the study of posteriori destiny.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes classified as the study of posteriori destiny.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes classified as the study of posteriori destiny.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>宮内貴久の著物では、良い地相の土地に、陽宅と隠宅によって、住まう人々の幸福を願う思想あるいは、思想に基づく実践のことと定義している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Takahisa MIYAUCHI&apos;s books, it refers to the philosophy or practice where the happiness for dwellers is pursued in the good physiognomy of land or a bright house and dark house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to books written by Takahisa MIYAUCHI, the idea of happiness is sought by pursuing the good physiognomy of land or Yang (bright) and Yin (dark) houses.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to books written by Takahisa MIYAUCHI, it refers to the idea or practice of the Yang (bright) and Yin (dark) houses on a good physiognomy of land, upon the desire for happiness of ones living.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。原文の下の段にあった「と定義しており、」は文脈、訳文から考えてこちらに組み入れたほうが意味が通るとし、この段へ組み入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では、このうち陽宅風水が家相という形で普及したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As defined like the above in Japan, in particular, the bright house feng shui became spread as a form of kaso.</e>
<cmt>「陽宅風水」を、bright house feng shuiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, Yang (bright) Feng Shui spread in Japan in the form of Kaso.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, in Japan, Yang (bright) Feng Shui spread as the form of Kaso.</e>
<cmt>in→as と修正しました。オーダーを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし日本においては、「地相」と「家相」の別個の定義に対して、包括的に「家相」として用いられてきたとも述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in Japan, regarding separate definitions of &apos;chiso&apos; (physiognomy of the land) and &apos;kaso,&apos; the one of &apos;kaso&apos; has been applied comprehensively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However in Japan, though &apos;Chiso (physiognomy of the land)&apos; and &apos;Kaso&apos; are separately defined, comprehensively &apos;Kaso&apos; is applied.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However in Japan, although &apos;Chiso&apos; (physiognomy of the land) and &apos;Kaso&apos; are separately defined, comprehensively &apos;Kaso&apos; is applied.</e>
<cmt>though→although と修正しました。クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>宮内貴久の著物によれば、住居とは生存の拠り所として、最も根本的な施設であり古来より生命や財産を守るための工夫を重ねてきたが天災によって、当時としては不可解な被害(例えば地震)に見舞われていたことから災いの要因を含めた「世界を支配し統括する原理を知りたい」という欲求に晒された結果、住宅に対して、人々が居住生活に求める概念を実体化させて、長い年月を経て培われた知見が規範化され影響力を持ち家相の世界観が生み出されたと述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Takahisa MIYAUCHI&apos;s books, houses are the most fundamental center as home of living and have made efforts to protect life or fortune from ancient times, but natural disasters, disasters (for example, earthquake) which were mysterious in those days, sometimes happened and thus they &apos;wish to understand the principle governing and controling the world,&apos; including the factor of disasters, as a result of which, they materialize the concept for living space and give rise to the perspective of the world from kaso, where the long-time developed knowledge has norm and influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahisa MIYAUCHI, houses are the most fundamental center of one&apos;s existence and from ancient times people have made efforts to protect life or fortune, but natural disasters (eg.earthquakes) were mysterious in those days so they desired to understand &apos;the principles governing and controlling the world&apos; including factors for disasters, as a result of which the concept of living space materialize, over the years cultivated through knowledge, a standard influencing the construction of a house, from an outlook of the world was produced.</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a book of Takahisa MIYAUCHI, houses are the most fundamental center of one&apos;s existence and from ancient times people have made efforts to protect life or fortune, but natural disasters (eg. earthquakes) were mysterious in those days so they desired to understand &apos;the principles governing and controlling the world&apos; including factors for disasters, as a result of which the concept of living space materialize, over the years cultivated through knowledge, a standard influencing the construction of a house, from an outlook of the world was produced.</e>
<cmt>「の著物によれば」を補いました。スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>江口征男の著書によれば、彰国社「建築大辞典」の家相の項目では、冒頭にて「民間俗説の一」と位置づけており四神相応との発生を同じくするものであり禁忌や呪術による信仰的存在が関係していると定義されていると述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Yukio EGUCHI&apos;s book, kaso is positioned as &apos;one of folk common sayings&apos; in the opening of kaso section in &apos;Dictionary of architecture&apos; by Shokokusha publishing company and has the same origin with Shijin-soo and has relation with religious faith by taboo or magic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yukio EGUCHI&apos;s book, the relation of taboos or magic to the existence of magical beliefs are similarly described and defined in Shokokusha publication&apos;s &apos; Dictionary of Architecture&apos; in an item on Kaso at the beginning, as well as in the &apos;Popular beliefs of the folks&apos; of Shijin-soo.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yukio EGUCHI&apos;s book, the relation of taboos or magic to the existence of magical beliefs are similarly described and defined in Shokokusha publication&apos;s &apos;Dictionary of Architecture&apos; in an item on Kaso at the beginning, as &apos;a popular beliefs of the folks&apos; which has the same origin of Shijin-soo.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本での歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Japan</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Kaso in Japan</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>以下、日本における江戸時代以降の歴史について触れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereafter, the history after the Edo period in Japan will be mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereafter, Japanese history after the Edo era is mentioned</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hereafter, Japanese history after the Edo period is mentioned</e>
<cmt>era→period と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>松平英明、本間五郎の著書では、天明から寛政の時代にかけて急増し、享和から化政にかけて再盛期を迎えたと考えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA says that kaso increased from Tenmei era to Kansei era and faced the peak from Kyowa era to Kasei era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, there was a sudden increase in the practice of Kaso from the Tenmei era to Kasei era, and peaked during the Kyowa era to Kasei era.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, there was a sudden increase in the practice of Kaso from the Tenmei era to Kasei era, and peaked during the Kyowa era to Kasei era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>それには、刊行年月の特定が出来るものと出来ないものが100冊あったとする内藤昌の集計(ref.内藤昌,1961)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In it there is a tally by Akira NAITO that there were 100 books whose publishing years and months could be specified or not (ref. Akira NAITO, 1961).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akira NAITO claims there are 100 books, of which the year and month of publication may or maynot be specified. (ref. Akira NAITO, 1961).</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akira NAITO claims that there were 100 books, of which the year and month of publication could or could not be specified (ref. Akira NAITO, 1961).</e>
<cmt>are→were,may→could,maynot→could not と修正しました。that を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>特定可能が50冊あったとする横山敬の集計(ref.横山敬,1981)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A tally by Takashi YOKOYAMA that there were 50 books whose publishing years and months could be specified (ref. Takashi YOKOYAMA, 1981).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A tally by Takashi YOKOYAMA shows that there are 50 books in which the year and month is specified.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A tally by Takashi YOKOYAMA shows that there were 50 books in which the year and month were specified (ref. Takashi YOKOYAMA, 1981).</e>
<cmt>are→were,is→were と修正しました。(ref. Takashi YOKOYAMA, 1981) を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>176冊の中から文化、文政、天保の年に多く出版されているという村田あがの分析結果。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The research result by Aga MURATA that many were published in the year of Bunka, Bunsei and Tenpo era among 176 books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The research results by Aga MURATA, of 176 books most were published in the Bunka, Bunsei and Tenpo eras.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The research results by Aga MURATA, of 176 books most were published in the Bunka, Bunsei and Tenpo eras.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらを、根拠としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The books think these as grounds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These books were taken as a basis.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These books were taken as a basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>また江戸時代での出版規制の事実も松平英明、本間五郎の著物では、以下の事例について、述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as for the regulation for publishing during Edo period, in the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, the following examples are mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for regulations regarding publishing during the Edo period, the following examples are mentioned in the books by Hideaka MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for regulations regarding publishing during the Edo period, the following examples are mentioned in the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA.</e>
<cmt>Hideaka→Hideaki と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>1696年、風水について触れた著物の1つ、陳畊山「三才発秘」は、1696年に、卯川四番船で中国から輸入されたものであるが一部墨消しと差返しの処分を受けるだけに止まらず1685年以降は禁書の指定を受けた(ref.大庭脩,1967)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The secret of the three powers: heaven, earth and man&apos; by Chin Kyosan, one of the books which dealt with the year and feng shui, was imported from China by Fourth Usen Ship in 1696, but a part of it was deleted with ink and returned and after 1685 was banned (ref. Osamu OBA, 1967).</e>
<cmt>年抜け、ウィキペディアで確認しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In one of the books on Feng Shui, Chin KYOSAN stated &apos;The secret of the three powers (heaven, earth and man)&apos; was imported from China by the Fourth Unsen Ship in 1969, but a part of it was deleted with ink, after 1685 the book was banned (ref. Osamu OBA, 1967).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In one of the books on Feng Shui, Chin KYOSAN stated &apos;The secret of the three powers [heaven, earth and man]&apos; was imported from China by the Fourth Unsen Ship in 1969, but a part of it was deleted with ink, after 1685 the book was banned (ref. Osamu OBA, 1967).</e>
<cmt>年号を原文に補いました。クォーツ内のカッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>1801年9月、大阪南宝寺の板元 河内屋八兵衛が出願した松倉東鶏の著書「方鑑精義大成」が風儀を乱すとの理由で不許可となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1801, &apos;Hokanshogitaisei&apos; by Tokei MATSUKURA, which Hachibei KAWACHIYA, a cook in Osaka Minami-Kyuhoji Temple, filed for, was banned because of being injurious to public morals.</e>
<cmt>年抜け、ウィキペディアで確認しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of 1801, Hachibei KAWACHIYA, a cook from a Minami-Kyuhoji Temple in Osaka filed against the book &apos;Horsemanship&apos; by Tokei MATSUKURA, which was banned due to debasement of morals.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of 1801, Hachibei KAWACHIYA, a publisher from a Minami-Kyuhoji Temple in Osaka filed the book &apos;Horsemanship&apos; by Tokei MATSUKURA, which was banned due to debasement of morals.</e>
<cmt>年号を原文に補いました。ここでの「板元」は「はんもと：図書などを出版する所」であると思われ、修正しました。filed against→filed と修正しました。また、文脈より「南宝寺」は地名ではないかと思われるのですが、確認が取れずそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ただし翌年5月に再出願を行った結果7月に許可が下りた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in next May it was approved in July after filed again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the following May it was filed again, but approved only in July.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the following May it was filed again, and approved in July as a result.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>1802年9月、大阪長堀心斎町の板元 播磨屋五兵衛が出願した「弁惑書口訣」「天分捷径平天儀図解」の2冊に対して、暦に差支えないか問題となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1802, as for the two books &apos;Benwaku book oral instruction&apos; and &apos;Tenwakeshokeiheitengi graphic illustration&apos; filed by Gohei HARIMA, a cook in Nagahori Shinsaibashi cho, Osaka, the problem arouse on the calendar.</e>
<cmt>年抜け、ウィキペディアで確認しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, in September of 1802, Gohei HARIMA, a cook in Nagahori Shinsaibashi cho, Osaka, filed that some problems may arise in the calendar from the books &apos;Benwaku book oral instruction&apos; and &apos;Tenwakeshokeiheitengi graphic illustration&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, in September of 1802, Gohei HARIMA, a publisher in Nagahori Shinsaibashi cho, Osaka, filed that some problems may arise in the calendar from the two books &apos;Benwaku book oral instruction&apos; and &apos;Tenwakeshokeiheitengi graphic illustration.&apos;</e>
<cmt>年号を原文に補いました。ここでの「板元」は「はんもと：図書などを出版する所」であると思われ、修正しました。books→two books と修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これらの本は、当時著名な暦学者であった麻田立達の鑑別と証言により許可が下りた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These books were approved by the identification and testimony by Ryutatsu ASADA who was a famous calendar scholar in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryutatsu ASADA, who was a famous scholar of the calendar in those days testified and approved the books.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryutatsu ASADA, who was a famous scholar of the calendar in those days testified and approved the books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>明治・大正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji and Taisho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji and Taisho period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji and Taisho period</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>宮内貴久の著物によれば、政府から各府県に対して、民族調査を命じ生活細部に影響を及ぼす禁令を敷いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the books by Takahisa MIYAUCHI, the government ordered each prefecture to do ethnic survey and issue interdicts on the details of life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Takahisa MIYAUCHI, the government ordered a detailed survey to see how far the prohibition had influenced the daily life.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a literally work of Takahisa MIYAUCHI, the government ordered a detailed survey to each prefecture to see how far the prohibition had influenced the daily life.</e>
<cmt>「著物」、「各府県に対し」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>特に、 1872年には、教部省により淫祠邪教の類として家相も直接的に禁止されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in 1872, kaso was directly forbidden as a kind of Inshi jakyo (evil heresies) by Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion).</e>
<cmt>年抜け、ウィキペディアで確認しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially as in 1872, Kaso was forbidden as it was considered to be a kind of Inshi jakyo (evil heresies) by Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially as in 1872, Kaso was forbidden as it was considered to be a kind of Inshi jakyo (evil heresies) by Kyobusho (Ministry of Religion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>と述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It explains the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As explained earlier.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As explained earlier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>そして、この流れを受け継いだ大正時代には、学会誌「建築雑誌」や各種新聞雑誌の類などを行い、この運動は昭和初期まで続くこととなり民俗学において、民家研究や民族宗教研究といった研究分野での進展がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And during Taisho period following the trend, an academic journal &apos;Architecture Magazine&apos; or various newspapers or magazines and so on were published and this movement continued until the early Showa period and there was no advancement in folklore such as the study on folk dwelling or folk religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, following the trend during the Taisho period and academic journal &apos;Architecture Journal&apos; and similar journals published this movement which continued until the early Showa period, with regard to folklore there has been no progress in the study of folk dwelling, religion and related fields.</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, following the trend during the Taisho period and academic journal &apos;Architecture Journal&apos; and similar journals published this movement which continued until the early Showa period, with regard to folklore there has been no progress in the study of folk dwelling, religion and related fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>とも分析している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He analyzed like the above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been analyzed similarly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been analyzed similarly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>昭和</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Showa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Showa period</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>松平英明、本間五郎の著書には、「所が目下市中で家相方位鑑定の看板を掲げている大部分の易筮（えきざい）家は、兎角職業的な意識から脱することが出来ないため、何等かの欠点を見出すと必ず其れに乗じて何ら彼のと難癖をつけたがるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, there are comments lamenting the world such as, &apos;However, most of fortune-tellers which put up the sign of kaso direction appraisal in cities can not get out of professional consciousness and thus they are always likely to criticize the faults whatever they are.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, commented &apos;By the way, signboards put up in downtown city, which give the orientation of Kaso, could not escape any professional consciousness as some faults were always attributed.</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, commented &apos;By the way, signboards put up in downtown city, which give the orientation of Kaso, could not escape any professional consciousness as some faults were always attributed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これは余程御注意なさらないといけない」「高島嘉右衛門「占い」は「売らない」が東京だけで数十軒も看板を揚げて、ついに警視庁に召喚されたことは...（中略）...こうした横着者が市中にたくさんなるのである」と世の中を憂いだ記述がある（鉤括弧部は引用。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You must be careful of this,&apos; &apos;Dozens of Kaemon TAKASHIMA&apos; shops &apos;uranai (fortune-telling)&apos; is &apos;uranai (not selling)&apos; put up the sign only in Tokyo and finally themetropolitan police department recalled them … Thus, such drones have increased in the city.&apos; (the part in quotation marks are citation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This must be carefully noted&apos;. &apos;Several dozens of signboards in Kaemon TAKASHIMA, in Tokyo alone, indicating the pun, &apos;uranai&apos; (fortune-telling) and &apos;uranai&apos; (sold out) were put up, finally the police were summoned (omitted), such kind of pickers were many in the city&apos; which was a pity. (the part in quotation mark is a citation).</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This must be carefully noted.&apos; &apos;Several dozens of signboards in Kaemon TAKASHIMA, in Tokyo alone, indicating the pun, &apos;uranai&apos; (fortune-telling) and &apos;uranai&apos; (not selling) were put up, finally the police were summoned (omitted), such kind of pickers were many in the city&apos; which was a pity (the part in quotation mark is a citation).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正しました。スペースを修正しました。「売らない」はnot selling に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>一部現代漢字への変換あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them are converted to present-day kanji (Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Part of it is converted to modern-day Kanji (Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Part of it is converted to modern-day Kanji (Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>1931年、内田寛一が地理学の観点から認識された自然を考慮すべきだと主張するも研究は、進展しなかったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the study by Kanichi UCHIDA who emphasized nature recognized from the standpoint of geography did not advance in 1931.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1931, Kanichi UCHIDA, insisted on recognizing from the view point of nature and geography, but could make no progress.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1931, Kanichi UCHIDA, insisted on recognizing from the view point of nature and geography, but could make no progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>1946年、文部省迷信調査協議会によれば「鬼門を避けるか」という問いに関して、信じるかどうかを別として「避ける」という回答が2/3に及んでいると報告された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the superstition survey council of Ministry of Education in 1946, as for the question &apos;Do you avoid Kimon (the northeastern (unlucky) direction, person or thing to be avoided)?&apos; it was reported that the answer &apos;I do&apos; dominated the two-thirds of all, apart from believing or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1946, the Ministry of Education, council for superstition took a survey &apos;Is Kimon (demon&apos;s gate) to be avoided&apos;, surprisingly one may believe or not, two thirds of the reply was &apos;Yes&apos;.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1946, the Ministry of Education, council for superstition took a survey &apos;Is Kimon [demon&apos;s gate] to be avoided,&apos; surprisingly one may believe or not, two thirds of the reply was &apos;Yes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>年号を原文に補いました。クォーツを修正しました。カッコを修正しました。カンマ、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>1960年代末、清家清によって、建築計画学、建築史学、地理学の3分野から研究が進められることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late 1960s, Kiyoshi SEIKE advanced the study from the three fields such as architectural planning study, architectural history and geography.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late 1960&apos;s, Kyoshi SEIKE applied three fields of architectural planning, architectural history and geography to further this study.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late 1960&apos;s, Kyoshi SEIKE applied three fields of architectural planning, architectural history and geography to further this study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>清家は、建築学の観点からある一定の科学性が認められると論じたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SEIKE seems to have argued that kaso had a certain level of scientific nature from a viewpoint of architecture study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SEIKE seems to have argued that Kaso had a certain level of scientific nature from the viewpoint of architectural study.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seike seems to have argued that Kaso had a certain level of scientific nature from the viewpoint of architectural study.</e>
<cmt>SEIKE→Seike と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>1981年には、宮野秋彦によって、家相の方位吉凶と自然環境との相関性について研究が進められ中国の西安や洛陽の自然環境に一致すると報告されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1981 Akihiko MIYANO advanced the study on the correlation between directional fortune in kaso andnatural environment and reported that the correlationcorresponds to the natural environment in Xian andLuoyang in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1981, Akihiko MIYANO studied the correlation between directional fortune in Kaso and natural environment and reported that there was no correlation with respect to the natural environment in Xian and Luoyang in China.</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1981, Akihiko MIYANO studied further the correlation between directional fortune in Kaso and natural environment and reported that it matched the natural environment in Xian and Luoyang in China.</e>
<cmt>年号を原文に補いました。原文に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various theories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various theories</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="33">
<j>佐久間象山は、一般的な家相に使われる基準に対して異を唱えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozan SAKUMA opposed to the standard used in common kaso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozan SAKUMA opposed the standards used in general Kaso.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozan SAKUMA opposed the standards used in general Kaso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>「由来日本の地湿潤の気多く燥気甚き支那の気象と相異す。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because he considered that the kaso theory cultivated in China should not be applied to Japan, saying that &apos;Traditionally climate of Japan is very humid, which is different from that of China that is very dry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally the climate of Japan is very humid, which is different from that in China which is mostly dry.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally the climate of Japan is very humid, which is different from that in China which is mostly dry.&apos;</e>
<cmt>記号の修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>「故に支那の建築と日本の家宅とは自ずから其の形態洋式と異にせり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, naturally, the architecture in China and that in Japan differ in their form and style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the architecture in China and Japan differ in form and style accordingly.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the architecture in China and Japan differ in form and style accordingly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>「仍って庇の出様、縁側の造り方等、まったく日本国特殊のものにして、而も其形似すべからず。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the form of eaves or veranda-like porches is totally peculiar to Japan and the form should not be similar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the form of eaves and veranda-like porches are completely peculiar to Japan, besides the form need not be similar.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the form of eaves and the construction of veranda-like porches are completely peculiar to Japan, and also the shape need not be similar.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「造り方」を補いました。besides→and also （ここでの「而も」は前述を受けて、”その上”との意味で修正しました。）、form→shape と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>「猥に之を改むるは寧ろ気候国土に反すると知るべし。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is rather contradictory for our climate to change it&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is rather contradictory to change the climate of the country&apos;, this statement remained, because the theory of Kaso cultivated in China should not be adopted in Japan.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One should know that changing the style goes against the climate and the land.&apos;</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。文脈に応じて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>このような言葉を残し支那で培われてきた家相説を日本に適用すべきではないという考えによるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statement such as this remained, because he believed that the theory of Kaso cultivated in China should not be adopted in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>佐久間象山は例示として、納屋や穀倉、便所等を本宅の東あるいは東南に配置するのは、東の光線と冬の東南の光線を遮断するので離れに構えるかするべきで母屋につづけるべきではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Shozan SAKUMA argued that barn, granary, lavatory and so on should not be positioned in the east or southeast of the main house because they block the light from east and the winter light from southeast and thus should be positioned in the annex and should not be positioned in the main house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Shozan SAKUMA argued that the barn, granary, lavatory, etc. should not be positioned in the east or southeast of the main house as the light from the east and the winter light from the southeast is blocked.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Shozan SAKUMA argued that the barn, granary, lavatory, etc. should be detached, not be positioned in the east or southeast of the main house as the light from the east and the winter light from the southeast is blocked.</e>
<cmt>「離れに構えるかすべきで」を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>鬼門の方角(東北)のスミに少し寄せた位置に、納屋や物置を配置することは、夏の強烈な朝日を避けることができるとしており太陽光線と四季の関係からこのような配置に差し支えなしと断定したと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is said to have asserted that it is good for a barn or storeroom to be positioned in the corner of the direction of Kimon (northeast) because the house can avoid strong summer light in the morning and such a positioning is not problematic because of the relation between sunlight and the four season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is said to have asserted that the barn or storeroom is to be positioned in the corner of Kimon (northeast) to avoid the strong summer light entering the house in the morning and in this particular position neither the solar rays nor the four seasons can cause any hindrance.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is said to have asserted that the barn or storeroom is to be positioned in the corner of Kimon (northeast) to avoid the strong summer light entering the house in the morning, and in this particular position is approved upon the condition of the solar rays and four seasons.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>流派と考え方</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools and their way of thinking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools and Thoughts</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools and Thoughts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>松平英明、本間五郎は、家相の流派を、大きく3つに分けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA divided the school of kaso roughly into the three.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA divided the school of Kaso roughly into three.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA divided the school of Kaso roughly into three.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>神谷古暦派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiya old calendar school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiya, the old school calendar.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiya Koreki (old calender) school</e>
<cmt>old school calender とすると全く別の意味に取られかねないため、こちらに修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>神谷古暦派は、易学を基本として家相を鑑る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiya old calendar school checked kaso based on the art of divination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamiya old school calendar, based the study of Kaso on the art of divination.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamiya-Koreki school, based the study of Kaso on the art of divination.</e>
<cmt>Kamiya old school calender→Kamiya-Koreki school と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>方位には、九星を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its direction Kyusei (nine stars having own color, respectively, used for astrology) was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The orientation of Kyusei (nine stars having own color, respectively, used for astrology) was applied.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyusei (nine stars having own color, respectively, used for astrology) was applied for the orientation.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="44">
<j>村田あがの著物によれば、江戸時代の家相学では、畳数に陰陽五行での「木」「火」「土」「金」「水」を割り当て、相生、相剋を判断していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the books by Aga MURATA, in the kaso study during Edo period, &apos;wood,&apos; &apos;fire,&apos; &apos;earth,&apos; &apos;metal&apos; and &apos;water&apos; in inyogogyo (the cosmic dual forces (yin and yang) were applied to the number of jo(counter for tatami mats; measure of room size) and synastry or rivalry were judged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Aga MURATA, in the study of Kaso during the Edo period, Inyogogyo(the cosmic dual forces(yin and yang)) and the five elements &apos;wood&apos;, &apos;fire&apos;, earth&apos;, &apos;metal&apos; and &apos;water&apos; was assigned by the number of jo(counter for tatami mats; measure of room size) which could predict a synastry or rivalry.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the books of Aga MURATA, in the study of Kaso during the Edo period, Inyogogyo (the cosmic dual forces [yin and yang]) and the five elements &apos;wood,&apos; &apos;fire,&apos; &apos;earth,&apos; &apos;metal&apos; and &apos;water&apos; was assigned by the number of jo (counter for tatami mats; measure of room size) which could predict a synastry or rivalry.</e>
<cmt>「著物」を補いました。スペース、カッコ内のカッコを修正しました。カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>村田あがによれば江戸時代の家相説では、その一例として「九畳八畳の続き間の如きは、土生金の吉相なり」（かぎ括弧部は村田あがの著物より引用）といったように使われていたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Aga MURATA, in the kaso theory during Edo period, as an example, it is said to have been used like, &apos;something like the following space of 9 jo or 8 jo have a luck of earth giving rise to metal.&apos; (the part in the quotation marks is cited from the book by Aga MURATA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Aga MURATA, in the kaso theory during Edo period, as an example, it is said to have been used like, &apos;something like the following space of 9 jo or 8 jo have a luck of earth giving rise to metal.&apos; (the part in the quotation marks is cited from the book by Aga MURATA.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Aga MURATA, in the kaso theory during the Edo period, as an example, it is said to have been used such as, &apos;something like the adjoining rooms of nine jo (counter for tatami mats) or eight jo have a luck of earth giving rise to metal&apos; (the part in the quotation marks is cited from the book by Aga MURATA).</e>
<cmt>「）といったように使われていたとされている。」を原文のセルに組み入れました。the を補いました。following space→adjoining rooms,like→such as,9→nine,8→eight と修正しました。(counter for tatami mats) を補いました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>ただし典拠となる漢籍には、このような考え方は存在しないとも述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, he wrote that such a way of thinking does not exist. in Chinese books as the source.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is mentioned with some authority that such an idea does not to exist in the Chinese book.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is mentioned that such an idea does not to exist in the Chinese book as an authority.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="47">
<j>松平英明、本間五郎の著物によれば、神谷古暦派が畳数の鑑定法に肯定的であったと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, Kamiya old calendar school was positive for the way of appraisal of the number of jo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the books by Hideaka MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, the Kamiya the old school calendar, could positively appraise by the number of mats in a room.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, the Kamiya-Koreki school, could positively appraise by the number of mats in a room.</e>
<cmt>Hideaka→Hideaki,Kamiya the old school calender→Kamiya-Koreki school と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>松平東鳩派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudaira Tohato school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudaira Tohato school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudaira Tohato school</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>松平東鳩派は、風水理気学を基本として家相を鑑る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudaira Tohato school checked kaso based on feng shui dynamics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudiara Tohato school applied the basics of Feng shui dynamics for the study of Kaso.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudiara Tohato school applied the basics of Feng shui dynamics for the study of Kaso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>方位には、干支方を用いる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As its direction the Oriental zodiac was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for orientation, the Oriental zodiac was utilized.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for orientation, the Oriental zodiac is utilized.</e>
<cmt>was→is と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>松平琴鶴派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudaira Kinkaku school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudaira Kinkaku school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudaira Kinkaku school</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="50">
<j>松平琴鶴派は、風水理気学と九星を用いることから折衷派とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matsudaira Kinkaku school was called eclectic school because it used feng shui dynamics and Kyusei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matsudaira Kinkaku school was called an eclectic school as it utilized a combination of Feng Shui and Kyusei.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matsudaira Kinkaku school was called an eclectic school as it utilized a combination of Feng Shui and Kyusei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>また松平英明、本間五郎の著物によれば、流水法に否定的であったと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And according to the books by Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, it was negative for the way of running water.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And according the Hideaka MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, running water indicates a negative influence.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And according to the documents of Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA, the Matsudaira Kinkaku school had a negative stance towards the running water method.</e>
<cmt>Hideaka→Hideaki と修正しました。文脈より修正しました。「流水法」の定訳が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>運用の相違</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Difference of practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Difference of practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Difference of practice</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>流水法、八宅法などの多種多様な鑑定法の存在、各流派で採用する鑑定法や主張の相違などにより代表的なものに、以下のような相違が生じていると松平英明、本間五郎は、主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA asserted that there existed many and various ways of appraisal such as the way of running water, the way of Hattaku school and so on, and the differences of the way of appraisal adopted by each school and affirmation, and thus the following differences arose as the representative ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA emphasized that there existed various ways of appraisal, each school adapted different methods giving rise to the following differences.</e>
<cmt>Sentence pattern changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideaki MATSUDAIRA and Goro HONMA emphasized that there are differences of practice produced upon existing various ways of appraisal such as the ryusui (running water) method, the way of Hattaku school, each school adapted different methods giving rise to the following differences.</e>
<cmt>文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>家の中心点</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The center of the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Center Point of House</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Center Point of House</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>家の中心は、大まかに3つの考え方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the center of the house, there roughly exist three ways of thinking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are roughly three ways in selecting the center of the house.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are roughly three ways in selecting the center of the house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>敷地の中心を取る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The center of the premises.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selecting the center of the whole premise.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selecting the center of the whole premise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>家屋の形から中心を点を取る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The center as a point seen from the form of the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Selecting the center by the shape of the house.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Selecting the center by the shape of the house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>家主の居間、奥居間を中心とする</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The living room or inner living room for the house owner as the center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The living quarters of the owner or the living room is selected as the center.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The living quarters of the owner or the living room is selected as the center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="57">
<j>村田あがによれば、江戸時代では、家主の居間奥居間を元とする考えが多いと述べており、家主が長期不在の場合は、一家の吉凶を敷地中心点で取りつつも同敷地内にて生活する留守居番の吉凶は、留守居の住まいの中心で判断するなど中心が2箇所とる考え方があったと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aga MURATA wrote that during Edo period, many thought the living room or inner living room of the house owner as the center and when the house owner was in long-term absence the house&apos;s fortune was to be the center of the premises, but the fortune of rusuiban (a person representing the master during his absence), who lived in the same premises, was to be the center of the living space of rusuiban and so on, there was a way of thinking which took the two centers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aga MURATA wrote that during the Edo period, the living room of the owner or the inner living room is considered as the center of the house, in the case of an owner being absent for a long period of time, it becomes necessary to protect one&apos;s fortune by selecting one more center of the premise with a caretaker who serves as an owner, in which case one can think of a house having two centers.</e>
<cmt>sentence changed to make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aga MURATA wrote that during the Edo period, the living room of the owner or the inner living room is considered as the center of the house, in the case of an owner being absent for a long period of time, it becomes necessary to protect one&apos;s fortune by selecting one more center of the premise with a caretaker who serves as an owner, in which case one can think of a house having two centers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>方位の判断方法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How to judge the direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Methods to determine the orientation</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Methods to determine the orientation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>九星、干支方、八方、二十四方など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyusei, the Oriental zodiac, Happo (eight directions), 24 directions and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyusei, the Oriental zodiac, Happo (eight directions), 24 directions and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyusei, the Oriental zodiac, Happo (8 directions), 24 directions and so on.</e>
<cmt>eight→8 と修正しました。（「用語統一：その他：31項」に従い）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>年回り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cycle of the Years</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cycle of the Years</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>本命星など個人に付随するもの</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Luck star and so on, belonging to individuals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each individual is accorded his own favorite stars.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Things accompany with individuals such as one&apos;s birth star</e>
<cmt>本命星:one&apos;s birth star として修正しました。文脈に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>張り、欠けの判断</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Judgment of fulfillment or lack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tension, Lack of judgement.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Determination of protrusion and depression</e>
<cmt>「張り」とは家相でいうところの&quot;出っ張り&quot;、「欠け」同じく&quot;引っ込んだところ”ということから、修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispute</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>家相を迷信であるとする主張には、文献間の吉凶統一性の欠如、水周りと鬼門に関する客観的記述と科学的データの欠如、水周り部の科学的根拠の希薄性があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who insist that kaso is a superstition raise the lack of unity for fortunes among documents, the lack of objective description and scientific data concerning water running and Kimon and the weakness of scientific basis of the water running part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The insistence that Kaso is a superstition, raises a lack of unity in literature regarding one&apos;s fortune, lack of objective description and weak scientific data regarding surrounding water and Kimon, indicates a dilution of the theory of Kaso.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The insistence that Kaso is a superstition, raises a lack of unity in literature regarding one&apos;s fortune, lack of objective description and weak scientific data regarding surrounding water and Kimon, indicates a dilution of the theory of Kaso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>これに対して、宮内貴久は、合理性が明らかにしたところで無意味で住宅観を明らかにすることが重要であると述べており、佐久間象山は、諸説の節で記載しているとおり「支那で培われてきた家相説を日本に適用すべきではない」と述べておりこれらが統一性の欠如を示唆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Takahisa MIYAUCHI said that clear rationality is meaningless but the clear philosophy of house is important and Shozan SAKUMA said &apos;the kaso theory cultivated in China should not be applied to Japan,&apos; as described in some sections, which suggests the lack of unity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As regards to this, Takahisa MIYAUCHI revealed that rationality is meaningless but it is important to clarify the outlook of a house, also Shozan SAKUMA describes in some sections &apos;the Kaso theory cultivated in China should not be applied to Japan&apos; which suggests a lack of unity.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As regards to this, Takahisa MIYAUCHI revealed that rationality is meaningless but it is important to clarify the outlook of a house, also Shozan SAKUMA describes in some sections &apos;the Kaso theory cultivated in China should not be applied to Japan&apos; which suggests a lack of unity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>以下に、学術的な見地から支持あるいは反支持の立場であったとされる人物を述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereafter, we will mention the people who were for or against kaso from the academic point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereafter, person&apos;s supporting or opposing is described from an academic point of view.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hereafter, person&apos;s supporting or opposing is described from an academic point of view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>支持者ら</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were for kaso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supporters</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supporters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>高野富文 （長野県上田地方の家相観の報告、1963）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomifumi TAKANO (the report of kaso philosophy in Ueda region, Nagano Prefecture, 1963).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomifumi TAKANO (a report on the physiognomy of Kaso in the Ueda region, Nagano Prefecture, 1963).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomifumi TAKANO (a report on the physiognomy of Kaso in the Ueda region, Nagano Prefecture, 1963).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="63">
<j>佐藤勘、佐藤力次郎 （力次郎による鬼門と戌亥信仰に関する論考、1976）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kan SATO, Rikijiro SATO (the thesis on Kimon and Inui faith by Rikijiro, 1976).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kan SATO, Rikijiro SATO (a debate on the beliefs in relation to Inui and Kimon (the northeastern unlucky) direction, person, a thing to be avoided).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kan SATO, Rikijiro SATO (a debate on the beliefs in relation to Inui and Kimon [the northeastern unlucky] direction, person, a thing to be avoided by Rikijiro in 1976).</e>
<cmt>「力次郎による」、「1976」を補いました。カッコ内のカッコを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>反支持者ら</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were against kaso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anti-supporters</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anti-supporters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="64">
<j>須貝高 （- 不明 - 1985年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takashi SUGAI (the birth year unknown - 1985)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takashi SUGAI (the birth year unknown - 1985)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takashi SUGAI (the birth year unknown - 1985)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>大下一司 （- 不明 - 1985年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazushi OSHITA (the birth year unknown - 1985)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazushi OSHITA (the birth year unknown - 1985)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazushi OSHITA (the birth year unknown - 1985)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>西園苧 （- 不明 - 1986年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cho NISHIZONO (the birth year unknown - 1986)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cho NISHIZONO (the birth year unknown - 1986)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cho NISHIZONO (the birth year unknown - 1986)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="67">
<j>大熊喜邦 （学会誌「建築雑誌」家相の話、- 不明 -）中国からの伝来であり多くは迷信であるとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiho OKUMA (academic journal &apos;Architecture Magazine&apos; the story of kaso, unknown) thought that kaso came from China and was mostly a superstition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiho OKUMA, (academic journal &apos;Archetecture Journal&apos;, Story of Kaso – Unknown) stated that Kaso is mostly a superstition, introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiho OKUMA, (academic journal &apos;Archetecture Journal,&apos; Story of Kaso – Unknown) stated that Kaso is mostly a superstition, introduced from China.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="68">
<j>伊藤忠太 （学会誌「建築雑誌」方位家相について、- 不明 -）化政期から日本でも流行しだした説であるとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuta ITO (academic journal &apos;Architecture Magazine&apos; on directional kaso, unknown) thought that kaso was a theory which became popular from Kasei era even in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuta ITO (academic journal &apos;Archetecture Journal&apos;, on the orientation of Kaso – Unknown) states that in Japan, Kaso was a popular theory from the Kasei era.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuta ITO (academic journal &apos;Archetecture Journal,&apos; on the orientation of Kaso – Unknown) states that in Japan, Kaso was a popular theory from the Kasei era.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Chiether(id:77421), チロチロ(id:107137), Law soma(id:45202), ムカイ(id:72972), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>