<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朝鮮寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korean Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chosen-dera Temple (Korean Temple)</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朝鮮寺（ちょうせんでら）とは、おもに在日韓国・朝鮮人ら、特にその婦人層において信仰されている寺院の通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean Temple (Chosendera in Japanese) refers to the common name of the temples worshipped by korean people living in Japan, particularly, the women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korean Temple (Chosendera in Japanese) refers to the common name of the temples worshipped by korean people living in Japan, particularly, the women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chosen-dera Temple (Korean Temple) refers to the common name of the temples worshipped by korean people living in Japan, particularly, the women.</e>
<cmt>読みを補足し、説明を括弧に入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>多くの朝鮮寺は生駒山麓周辺に集中している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A lot of Korean Temples are concentrated at the foot of Mt. Ikoma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A lot of Korean Temples are concentrated at the foot of Mt. Ikoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A lot of Korean Temples are concentrated at the foot of Mt. Ikoma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この名称は研究者らによって便宜的に付与されているものであり、該当の寺院およびその信者はこの名称を用いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This name is conveniently given by researchers, so the temples and the devotees don&apos;t use this name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This name is conveniently given by researchers, and are not used by the temples or devotees.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This name is conveniently given by researchers, and are not used by the temples or devotees.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>地域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Region</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Region</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1981年の統計においては、在日韓国朝鮮人の三割が大阪府に居住している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the statistics of 1981, the thirty persent of the korean people living in Japan are residing in Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According 1981 statistics, the thirty percent of the korean people living in Japan resided in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According 1981 statistics, the 30 percent of the korean people living in Japan resided in Osaka.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>さらに範囲を兵庫県、京都府、大阪へと広げると、割合は半数近くにも達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If further spreading the target area to Hyogo Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture and Osaka Prefecture, the ratio reaches nearly half.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increasing the scope to include Hyogo Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture and Osaka Prefecture increases this number to 50 percent.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increasing the scope to include Hyogo Prefecture, Kyoto Prefecture and Osaka Prefecture increases this number to 50 percent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これらの人々の信仰の対象として、生駒山周辺には60程度の朝鮮寺が存在すると報告されていたが、現在ではその数は20程度にまで減少している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be reported about sixty Korean Temples were located around the foot of Mt. Ikoma as the object of worship of these people, but these days, the number has decreased to about twenty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be reported that sixty Korean Temples were located around the foot of Mt. Ikoma as the object of worship of these people, but these days, the number has decreased to about twenty.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be reported that 60 Korean Temples were located around the foot of Mt. Ikoma as the object of worship of these people, but these days, the number has decreased to about 20.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>生駒山中でも大阪に面した西側南北10kmほどの地域、北から順に辻子谷（づしだに）、額田谷（ぬかただに）、鳴川谷（なるかわだに、以上いずれもハイキングコースとして知られる）、山畑・服部川地区、黒谷など、互いに平行に走る谷沿いにそれぞれ数個の寺院が連なって存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the area spreading 10km from north to south on the west side of Mt. Ikoma viewing Osaka, specifically, from north, Zushidani Valley, Nukatadani Valley, Narukawadani Valley, all of these known as hiking trail, Yamahata and Hattorigawa Area, and Kurotani, a few temples are closely located in line along each valley running in parallel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the area spreading 10km from north to south on the west side of Mt. Ikoma viewing Osaka, specifically, from north, Zushidani Valley, Nukatadani Valley, Narukawadani Valley, all of which are known as hiking trails, Yamahata and Hattorigawa Area, and Kurotani, a few temples are closely located in line along each valley running in parallel.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the area spreading 10km from north to south on the west side of Mt. Ikoma viewing Osaka, specifically, from north, Zushidani Valley, Nukatadani Valley, Narukawadani Valley, all of which are known as hiking trails, Yamahata and Hattorigawa Area, and Kurotani, a few temples are closely located in line along each valley running in parallel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらは行政区では四条畷市、大東市、東大阪市、八尾市に該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These correspond to Shijonawate City, Daito City, Higashiosaka City and Yao City in public administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These correspond to Shijonawate City, Daito City, Higashiosaka City and Yao City in public administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These correspond to Shijonawate City, Daito City, Higashiosaka City and Yao City in public administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この地域の中心には大きな信仰を集める宝山寺が存在し、この存在が朝鮮寺がこの地域に集中して創設されたことに影響を及ぼしていると見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the center of this area located is Hozan-ji Temple visited by so many devotees, and the presence of this temple seems to have influenced on the foundation of Korean Temples concentrated in this area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the center of this area located is Hozan-ji Temple visited by so many devotees, and the presence of this temple seems to have influenced the foundation of Korean Temples concentrated in this area.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the center of this area located is Hozan-ji Temple visited by so many devotees, and the presence of this temple seems to have influenced the foundation of Korean Temples concentrated in this area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>寺の概観</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview of temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview of temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Overview of temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>多くの朝鮮寺においては本堂および七星堂、賽神場が設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Korean Temples have Hondo (main hall), Shichiseido (hall to worship Septentrions) and Sainokami (guardian deity).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Korean Temples have Hondo (main hall), Shichiseido (hall to worship Septentrions) and Sainokami (guardian deity).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Korean Temples have Hondo (main hall), Shichiseido (hall to worship Septentrions) and Sainokami (guardian deity).</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>前者二つは朝鮮半島における仏教寺院中における大雄殿、三聖閣に該当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first and the second correspond to Daiyuden and Sanseikaku in Buddhist temples of Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>「三聖閣」は、韓国語読みで「サムソンカク」というようですが、ここでは日本語読みにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first and the second correspond to Daiyuden and Sanseikaku in Buddhist temples of Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first and the second correspond to Daeungjeon Hall and Samseonggak Hall in Buddhist temples of Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>大雄殿→Daeungjeon Hall [http://www.dangjin.go.kr/html/jp/culture/culture_03_02_t10.html]三聖閣→Samseonggak Hall [http://sca.seoul.go.kr/english/culturalAsset.jsp?sCode=100528&amp;sClssCode=7&amp;sClssCode2=24]</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>本尊および諸菩薩を祀る本堂は日本の通常の仏教寺院本堂の外観とは異なり、一見して民家または集会所と区別が付かない場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) and main hall enshrining Bosatsu (Buddhist saint) were different from the general Buddhist temples of Japan in terms of appearance, and they would be almost mistaken for folk dwelling or gathering place at the first visit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) and main hall enshrining Bosatsu (Buddhist saint) were different from the general Buddhist temples of Japan in terms of appearance, and they would be almost mistaken for folk dwelling or gathering place on first visit.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its Honzon (principal object of worship at a temple) and main hall enshrining Bosatsu (Buddhist saint) were different from the general Buddhist temples of Japan in terms of appearance, and they would be almost mistaken for folk dwelling or gathering place on first visit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>寺としての表札も控えめである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name plate of temple is modest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The temple&apos;s name plate is fairly modest.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The temple&apos;s name plate is fairly modest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>七星堂では星神を中心にして、山神、海神などが祀られ、いずれの寺院でも本堂よりも地理的に高い箇所に設けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Shichiseido, God of the mountain, God of the sea and so on are enshrined with God of the star in the center, and all Shichiseido is located on geographically higher place than main hall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Shichiseido, God of the mountain, God of the sea and so on are enshrined with God of the stars in the center, and all Shichiseido is located on a geographically higher location than the main hall.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Shichiseido, God of the mountain, God of the sea and so on are enshrined with God of the stars in the center, and all Shichiseido is located on a geographically higher location than the main hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>星神と山神については朝鮮半島においても同様に信仰されており、それぞれ現世での幸福と金銭を祈祷する習合性を現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">God of the star and God of the sea are also worshipped in Korean Peninsula to pray for happiness and wealth respectively, that shows syncretization in their belief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">God of the stars and God of the sea are also worshipped in Korean Peninsula to pray for happiness and wealth respectively, which shows syncretization in their beliefs.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">God of the stars and God of the sea are also worshipped in Korean Peninsula to pray for happiness and wealth respectively, which shows syncretization in their beliefs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>賽神場は通常は飾りつけなどの無い数畳の空間である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sainokami-jo (place of guardian deity) is generally a space with a width of a few tatami, without ornaments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sainokami-jo (place of guardian deity) is generally a space with a width of a few tatami, without ornaments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sainokami-jo (place of guardian deity) is generally a space with a width of a few tatami, without ornaments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>賽神場は、朝鮮においてクッ（賽神）と称されるシャーマニズム的現世信仰が行われる場所であり、諸神および諸仏に巫女（男も存在する）が信者の現世における利益をかなえさせる儀式が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sainokami-jo is a place where the belief in material benefits like Shamanism is carried on, and miko (shrine maiden or male attendant) holds a ceremony dedicated to gods or Buddha to pray for devotees&apos; benefits of this world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sainokami-jo is a place where the belief in material benefits like Shamanism is carried on, and miko (shrine maiden or male attendant) holds a ceremony dedicated to gods or Buddha to pray for devotees&apos; benefits of this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sainokami-jo is a place where the belief in material benefits like Shamanism is carried on, and miko (shrine maiden or male attendant) holds a ceremony dedicated to gods or Buddha to pray for devotees&apos; benefits of this world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この賽神場とそこでの現世信仰が朝鮮寺の大きな特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sainokami-jo and the belief in material benefits are outstanding features of Korean Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sainokami-jo and the belief in material benefits are outstanding features of Korean Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sainokami-jo and the belief in material benefits are outstanding features of Korean Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>数多くの朝鮮寺における信仰において、仏教と賽神が占める重要度は各々の寺院によって異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In numerous believes in Korean Temple, the importance of Buddhism and Sainokami is different depending on each temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In numerous believes in Korean Temple, the importance of Buddhism and Sainokami differs depending on each temple.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In numerous believes in Korean Temple, the importance of Buddhism and Sainokami differs depending on each temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>境内には地形を利用して祠や行場としての滝などが併設されている場合が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the precincts, hokora (small shrine) and fall used for gyoba (ascetic practice place) are usually situated, making use of natural landform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the precincts, hokora (small shrine) and fall used for gyoba (ascetic practice place) are usually situated, making use of natural landform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the precincts, hokora (small shrine) and fall used for gyoba (ascetic practice place) are usually situated, making use of natural landform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>それらの多くおよび本堂などには不動明王が祭られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In many of them and main hall, Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the five Wisdom Kings) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In many of them and the main hall, Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the five Wisdom Kings) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In many of them and the main hall, Fudo Myoo (Acala, one of the five Wisdom Kings) is enshrined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>宗派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Religious school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Religious school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Religious school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>多くの朝鮮寺は、朝鮮および日本における仏教の宗派を名乗っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Korean Temples use the name of any religious school of Buddhism in Korea or Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Korean Temples use the name of any religious school of Buddhism in Korea or Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Korean Temples use the name of any religious school of Buddhism in Korea or Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>朝鮮系では曹渓宗、日本系では天台宗、真言宗などの修験系が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The popular Korean religious school is Jogye sect, and that of Japanese is Shugen-related school such as Tendai sect and Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A popular Korean religious school is the Jogye sect, and that of Japanese is Shugen-related school such as Tendai sect and Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A popular Korean religious school is the Jogye sect, and that of Japanese is Shugen-related school such as Tendai sect and Shingon sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>前項に示したような実際の寺院の概観において、その朝鮮寺が属する宗派による違いは存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The actual overview of temple mentioned above doesn&apos;t vary according to any religious school that Korean Temple belongs to.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The actual overview of temple mentioned above doesn&apos;t vary according to any religious school that a Korean Temple belongs to.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The actual overview of temple mentioned above doesn&apos;t vary according to any religious school that a Korean Temple belongs to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>このように体系性、宗派性が低い事実とあわせ、朝鮮寺は死者儀礼とも無関係であることがほとんどであり、現世利益の祈祷仏教に属すると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the fact that they are not affected by any systematic and religious influence, Korean Temple has no relation to the ceremony for dead, therefore, it can be considered belonging to Buddhism for prayer, worshipping material benefits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the fact that they are not affected by any systematic or religious influence, Korean Temples have no relation to the ceremony for dead, therefore, it can be considered to belong to Buddhism for prayer, worshipping material benefits.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the fact that they are not affected by any systematic or religious influence, Korean Temples have no relation to the ceremony for dead, therefore, it can be considered to belong to Buddhism for prayer, worshipping material benefits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="29">
<j>儀式</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremony</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceremony</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>代表的な年中行事としては4月8日の仏生会、7月7日の七星祭、冬至の節分など（暦はいずれも旧暦）において数十人の信者が集まり、儀式、祭が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative annual event is Bussho-e (Buddhist mass celebrating Buddha&apos;s Birthday) of April 8, Shichiseisai Festival of July 7 and Setsubun (the traditional end of winter) of winter solstice (all date in the old calendar) where dozens people gather to take part in ceremony or festival.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The representative annual event is Bussho-e (Buddhist mass celebrating Buddha&apos;s Birthday) of April 8, Shichiseisai Festival of July 7 and Setsubun (the traditional end of winter) of winter solstice (all date in the old calendar) where dozens people gather to take part in ceremony or festival.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The representative annual event is Bussho-e (Buddhist mass celebrating Buddha&apos;s Birthday) of April 8, Shichiseisai Festival of July 7 and Setsubun (the traditional end of winter) of winter solstice (all date according to old lunar calendar) where dozens people gather to take part in ceremony or festival.</e>
<cmt>(all date according to old lunar calendar)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これらの年中行事においては呪術的な要素はあまり見られず、自身の家族における家内安全の祈願が中心となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these annual events, any magical element is rarely seen, and prayer for family&apos;s safety is core.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these annual events, any magical element is rarely seen, and prayer for family&apos;s safety remains at the core..</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these annual events, any magical element is rarely seen, and prayer for family&apos;s safety remains at the core.</e>
<cmt>不要なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>これに対して、災いが生じた信者が寺院と巫女（ポサル）に依頼してその都度行われる賽神の儀式は、明らかにシャーマニックな特徴を備えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, ceremony of sainokami conducted by temple and miko upon request by devotee who suffered disaster is equipped with features of shamanism.</e>
<cmt>「ポサル」というのは韓国語のようなので、ここでは訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, ceremony of sainokami conducted by temple and miko upon request by devotees who suffered through a disaster has features of shamanism.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, ceremony of sainokami conducted by temple and miko upon request by devotees who suffered through a disaster has features of shamanism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この儀式は、家族の災いの原因である祖先の霊を呼び寄せ、舞や供物、供銭などでそれをもてなして災いをかけないように頼み、最後に霊を送り届ける一連の過程にそって執り行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ceremony takes a process in the following way; at first, calling the ancestor&apos;s spirit that caused the family disaster, then, asking it to stop torturing in exchange of danse, offerings or money, finally sending it back to the original place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ceremony carries out the process in the following way; at first, calling the ancestor&apos;s spirit that caused the family disaster, then, asking it to stop the torture in exchange of for dance, offerings or money, finally sending it back to its original place.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ceremony carries out the process in the following way; at first, calling the ancestor&apos;s spirit that caused the family disaster, then, asking it to stop the torture in exchange of for dance, offerings or money, finally sending it back to its original place.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>複数の霊が登場することも多く、数日の儀式では15万円、一週間ほどのものになると100万円以上の費用が依頼者から支払われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, more than two spirits show up, so a-few-day ceremony costs 150 thousands yen, and a-week ceremony does one million yen, that paid by devotee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, more than two spirits show up, so a-few-day ceremony costs 150 thousands yen, and a-week ceremony costs one million yen, that is paid by a devotee.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, more than two spirits show up, so a-few-day ceremony costs 150,000 yen, and a-week ceremony costs 1,000,000 yen, that is paid by a devotee.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この費用は、儀式の際に寺院に泊り込む巫女の飲食費や交通費、そして賽銭として儀式中で繰り返し供えられる金銭が含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The expense includes food, drink and transportation fee for miko who stays over nights at the temple during the ceremony, and money offering repeatedly done during the ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expense includes food, drink and transportation fee for miko who stays overnight at the temple during the ceremony, and money offerings repeatedly done during the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expense includes food, drink and transportation fee for miko who stays overnight at the temple during the ceremony, and money offerings repeatedly done during the ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>後者の供銭についてもポサルの収入となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The money offering also joins miko&apos;s income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The money offering also joins miko&apos;s income.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The money offering also joins miko&apos;s income.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="37">
<j>賽神の儀式においては僧侶とポサルが並び、ポサルは舞や交霊をとりおこなう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ceremony, monk and miko stay side by side, and miko perfoms dance and exchange of spirits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ceremony, monk and miko stay side by side, and miko perfoms dance and exchange of spirits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ceremony, monk and miko stay side by side, and miko performs dance and exchange of spirits.</e>
<cmt>performsスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ポサルは信者から強い尊敬の念を持って遇されており、「先生」、「ポサル様」等の敬称で呼称されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miko is highly respected by devotees and called with the title of honor.</e>
<cmt>「先生」「ポサル様」は実際の韓国語の呼びかけだと思うので、ここでは訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miko is highly respected by devotees and called by a title of honor.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miko is highly respected by devotees and called by a title of honor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>それにたいして僧侶は一般的な僧服等を身に着けているものの、賽神を仏教によって権威付ける存在として扱われ、宗派による儀式の違いなども存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, although Buddhist monks wear general uniforms of monk, they are only expected to serve for authorizing sainokami with Buddhism, so there is no difference in the ceremony each religious school carries on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, although Buddhist monks wear general uniforms of a monk, they are only expected to serve to authorize sainokami with Buddhism, so there is no difference in the ceremony carried out between each religious school.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, although Buddhist monks wear general uniforms of a monk, they are only expected to serve to authorize sainokami with Buddhism, so there is no difference in the ceremony carried out between each religious school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>数十人存在すると見られるポサルの多くは中年から老年の女性であり、住職として朝鮮寺に居住する者のほかに自宅に祭壇を設け巫行を行っているものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many miko supposedly exising dozens are middle-aged or old-age women, and some of them reside as chief monk in Korean Temple, and the others are living in their own residence equipped with an altar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many existing miko are supposedly dozens of middle-aged or old-age women, and some of them reside as chief monk in Korean Temple, and the others are living in their own residence equipped with an altar.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many existing miko are supposedly dozens of middle-aged or old-age women, and some of them reside as chief monk in Korean Temple, and the others are living in their own residence equipped with an altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>その多くは血縁や師弟関係で結ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them are tied by blood-related or master-and-pupil relationship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them are tied by blood-related or master-and-pupil relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of them are tied by blood-related or master-and-pupil relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>信者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Devotees</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Devotees</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Devotees</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>朝鮮寺の信者は在日朝鮮韓国人の女性が中心となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Devotees of Korean Temple are mainly korean women living in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Devotees of Korean Temples are mainly korean women living in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Devotees of Korean Temples are mainly korean women living in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>一般的には、一家の家長である男性が儒教にのっとった葬祭を領分とするのに対して、主婦は朝鮮寺における信仰を奉じている場合が多いとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In genral, men, the head of family, serve for holding funerals and festivals in consistency with Confucianism, while women show their belief by visiting Korean Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, men, the head of family, serve to hold funerals and festivals in consistency with Confucianism, while women show their belief by visiting Korean Temples.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, men, the head of family, serve to hold funerals and festivals in consistency with Confucianism, while women show their belief by visiting Korean Temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>檀家制度が存在する寺はほとんど存在せず、現世利益がどの程度あったかというポサルの評判を聞き集まった信者が中心となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Danka seido (parishioner system) is not familiar in most of Korean Temples, and devotees come to join hearing the reputation of miko how much she could bring in material benefits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Danka seido (parishioner system) is not familiar to most Korean Temples, and devotees come to join hearing the reputation of miko how much she could bring in material benefits.</e>
<cmt>&quot;come to join hearing the reputation of miko how much she could bring in material benefits. &quot; doesn’t make sense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Very few temples in Korea participated in the danka seido (parishioner system), and most devotees of such temples assembled after hearing of the reputation miko had for providing this-worldly benefits.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Call Tenderas(id:169753), 間久部香織(id:142582), Amagase(id:108940), Opponent(id:720), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Saintjust(id:21864), Ajax(id:11202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>