<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>蔵前入用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuranyuyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuramae nyuyo</e>
<cmt>「前」が抜けていました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuramae nyuyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>蔵前入用（くらまえにゅうよう）とは、江戸時代に江戸幕府直轄領（天領）に対してかけられた高掛三役と呼ばれる特別税のうちの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuranyuyo was a national tax imposed by the Edo bakufu during Edo period, and was one of the 3 major taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuramae nyuyo was one of the three major taxes called Takagakari Sanyaku that were imposed on the direct control territories of the Edo bakufu (Shogunal demesne) during Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「直観領～特別税」までにあたる訳が抜けていました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuramae nyuyo was one of the three major taxes called Takagakari Sanyaku that were imposed on the direct control territories of the Edo bakufu (Shogunal demesne) during Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>直轄領の年貢の納付先である浅草御蔵をはじめとする幕府御蔵の維持・運営経費の捻出を名目とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It provided income to maintain and manage territories under direct control of the government such as the Asakusa okura (rice storage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The revenue from this tax subsidized the expense of maintenance and management of bakufu okura (rice storehouses of the Edo shogunate) such as the Asakusa okura where nengu (land tax) from direct control territories were delivered to.</e>
<cmt>「幕府御蔵の維持・・・」が「直観領の維持・・・」と訳されているので誤訳です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The revenue from this tax subsidized the expense of maintenance and management of bakufu okura (rice storehouses of the Edo shogunate) such as the Asakusa okura where nengu (land tax) from direct control territories were delivered to.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元禄2年（1689年）に関東地方では村高100石につき金1分（1/4両）、上方では村高100石につき銀15匁納付が命じられ、5年後の元禄7年（1694年）に勘定奉行によって公式に規定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1689, in Kanto region, the tax rate was 1gold bun (edo era money) per 100 koku (measure of rice). In areas near Edo, it was 15silver monme (edo era money) per 100 koku. 5 years later, it was made official by the tax office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1689, the tax rate was one bu (a quarter of one ryo) of gold per 100 koku (measure of rice) of Muradaka (total yields of a village) in Kanto region and 15 monme of silver per 100 koku of Muradaka in Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka) area, and these orders were made official by the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) five years later in 1694.</e>
<cmt>英文を1文に修正しました。上方はareas near Edoではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1689, the tax rate was one bu (a quarter of one ryo) of gold per 100 koku (measure of rice) of Muradaka (total yields of a village) in Kanto region and 15 monme of silver per 100 koku of Muradaka in Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka) area, and these orders were made official by the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) five years later in 1694.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、五街道や脇往還の宿場町及び助郷義務を負っていた村に対しては免除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the inn towns located along Go-kaido Road (a major road used for travel) and Wakiokan (main roads other than Gokaido Road), as well as villages that offered aid to surrounding areas in need were waived from the tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the inn towns located along Go-kaido Road (five major roads used for travel) and Wakiokan (main roads other than Gokaido Road), as well as villages that had a duty of sukego (labor service which was imposed to the neighboring village of the inn towns) were waived from the tax.</e>
<cmt>五街道はfive major roadsに修正しました。助郷の訳も追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the inn towns located along Go-kaido Road (five major roads used for travel) and Wakiokan (main roads other than Gokaido Road), as well as villages that had a duty of sukego (labor service which was imposed to the neighboring village of the inn towns) were waived from the tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、宝暦6年（1756年）以後には5割以下の不作となった地域に対しても免除されたが、基本的には江戸幕府滅亡後の明治5年（1872年）の廃止までの182年にわたって元禄7年の制がそのまま維持された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After 1756, the districts with a crop yield below 50% were also exempt, but until 1872 after the fall of the Edo bakufu, this tax was enforced for 182 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After 1756, the districts with poor crop yields below 50% were also exempt, but in principle this tax system of 1694 had survived for 182 years into the Meiji Period, until it was abolished in 1872.</e>
<cmt>「基本的には」以降の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After 1756, the districts with poor crop yields below 50% were also exempt, but in principle this tax system of 1694 had survived for 182 years into the Meiji Period, until it was abolished in 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 味っ子(id:17086), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>