<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>文禄・慶長の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunroku-Keicho War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bunroku-Keicho War</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bunroku-Keicho War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>文禄・慶長の役（ぶんろく・けいちょうのえき）は1592年（日本：文禄元年、明および李氏朝鮮：万暦20年）から1598年（日本慶長3年、明および朝鮮万暦26年）にかけて行われた戦役。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bunroku-Keicho War was a war conducted in the period from 1592 (Japan: Bunroku 1; Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea: Banreki 20) to 1598 (Japan: Keicho 3; Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea: Banreki 26).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bunroku-Keicho War was a war conducted during the period from 1592 (Japan: Bunroku one; Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea: Banreki twenty) to 1598 (Japan: Keicho three; Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea: Banreki twenty-six).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bunroku-Keicho War was a war conducted during the period from 1592 (Japan: Bunroku one; Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea: Banreki twenty) to 1598 (Japan: Keicho three; Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea: Banreki twenty-six).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の豊臣秀吉が主導する遠征軍と李氏朝鮮および明の軍との間で交渉を交えながら朝鮮半島を戦場にして戦われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expeditionary force from Japan headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and military force of Yi Dynasty Korea and Ming combated with each other in Korean Peninsula carrying out intermittent negotiations in parallelism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An expeditionary force from Japan headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and military forces of the Yi Dynasty Korea and Ming fought each other on the Korean Peninsula carrying out intermittent negotiations in parallel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An expeditionary force from Japan headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and military forces of the Yi Dynasty Korea and Ming fought each other on the Korean Peninsula carrying out intermittent negotiations in parallel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>名称について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the name</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>豊臣政権時から江戸時代後期に至るまでは、この戦役が日本が明の征服を目指す途上の朝鮮半島で行われたものであることから唐入り・唐御陣、あるいは高麗陣・朝鮮陣などの呼称が用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the time of the Toyotomi Government to the late Edo Period, as Japan carried out this war in Korean Peninsula on its way to conquer Ming, it was called &quot;karairi (literally, entering China),&quot;&quot;karagojin (literally, China war),&quot;or &quot;Korai jin (Goryeio war),&quot; and &quot;chosen jin (literally, Korea wa).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the time of the Toyotomi Government to the late Edo Period, as Japan carried out this war on the Korean Peninsula on the way to conquer Ming, it was called &quot;karairi (literally, entering China),&quot; &quot;karagojin (literally, China war),&quot;or &quot;Korai jin (the Goryeio war),&quot; and &quot;chosen jin (literally, Korea wa).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the time of the Toyotomi Government to the late Edo period, as Japan carried out this war on the Korean Peninsula on the way to conquer Ming, it was called &quot;karairi&quot; (literally, entering China), &quot;karagojin&quot; (literally, China war), or &quot;Korai jin&quot; (the Goryeio war), and &quot;Chosen jin&quot; (literally, Korea wa).</e>
<cmt>用語統一&quot;位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>幕末から明治初期にかけては朝鮮征伐、征韓などと呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the Edo Period to the beginning of the Meiji Period, it was called &quot;chosen seibatsu (punitive expedition to Korea)&quot; or &quot;seikan (punitive expedition to Korea).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the Edo Period to the beginning of the Meiji Period, it was called &quot;chosen seibatsu (punitive expedition to Korea)&quot; or &quot;seikan (punitive expedition to Korea).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the Edo period to the beginning of the Meiji period, it was called &quot;chosen seibatsu&quot; (punitive expedition to Korea) or &quot;seikan&quot; (punitive expedition to Korea).</e>
<cmt>用語統一&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1910年（明治43年）の日韓併合以後は朝鮮人が日本人となったことから朝鮮征伐の表現は避けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Japanese Annexation of Korea in 1910, because Koreans became Japanese citizens, the expression of chosen seibatsu was avoided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Japanese Annexation of Korea in 1910, because Koreans became Japanese citizens, the expression of chosen seibatsu was avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Japanese Annexation of Korea in 1910, because Koreans became Japanese citizens, the expression of chosen seibatsu was avoided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>代わって第一次出兵を文禄の役、第二次出兵を慶長の役、併せて文禄・慶長の役という呼称が定着した（他にも朝鮮出兵や朝鮮役・征韓の役という呼び方もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, the names &quot;the Bunroku War&quot; for the first war and &quot;the Keicho War&quot; for the second war have come to stay (Furthermore, there are name &quot;chosen shuppei (literally despatching troops to Korea),&quot; &quot;chosen eki (literally, Korea war),&quot; and &quot;seikan no eki (war for punitive expedition to Korea)&quot;.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, names like &quot;the Bunroku War&quot; for the first war and &quot;the Keicho War&quot; for the second war have come to stay (Furthermore, there are name &quot;chosen shuppei (literally despatching troops to Korea),&quot; &quot;chosen eki (literally, Korea war),&quot; and &quot;seikan no eki (war for punitive expedition to Korea).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, names like &quot;the Bunroku War&quot; for the first war and &quot;the Keicho War&quot; for the second war and &quot;the Bunroku-Keicho War&quot; for both have come to stay (Furthermore, there are name &quot;chosen shuppei&quot; (literally dispatching troops to Korea), &quot;chosen eki&quot; (literally, Korea war), and &quot;seikan no eki&quot; (war for punitive expedition to Korea).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。&quot;位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近年では、朝鮮半島が戦場となったため、朝鮮側が受けた被害に関心をもつ研究者を中心に朝鮮侵略と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, in certain cases, it is called chosen shinryaku (literally, invasion into Korea) by people centering on researchers who are interested in damages which the Korean side suffered because the Korean Peninsula was the battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, in certain cases, it has been called chosen shinryaku (literally, invasion into Korea) by people centering on researchers who are interested in damage the Korean side suffered because the Korean Peninsula was the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, in certain cases, it has been called chosen shinryaku (literally, invasion into Korea) by people centering on researchers who are interested in damage the Korean side suffered because the Korean Peninsula was the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし豊臣秀吉はあくまで明を征服することを目指しており、朝鮮そのものの侵略が目的ではなく、あくまで明への出兵の途上での戦役であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI absolutely aimed to conquer Ming and invasion into Korea itself was not the purpose and, therefore, it was a war on the way to sending military force to Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI absolutely aimed to conquer Ming and invasion into Korea itself was not the purpose and, therefore, it was a war on the way to sending military forces to Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI absolutely aimed to conquer Ming and invasion into Korea itself was not the purpose and, therefore, it was a war on the way to sending military forces to Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>文禄の役は1592年（文禄元年）に始まって翌1593年（文禄2年）に休戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bunroku War began in 1592 and it was suspended in the next year, 1593.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bunroku War began in 1592 and it was suspended during the next year, 1593.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bunroku War began in 1592 and it was suspended during the next year, 1593.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、慶長の役は1597年（慶長2年）講和交渉決裂によって始まり、1598年（慶長3年）の秀吉の死を受けた日本軍の撤退をもって終結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Keicho War began in 1597 because of collapse of peace negotiation and ended in 1598 with retreat of Japanese force because of Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keicho War began in 1597 because of the collapse of peace negotiations and ended in 1598 with the retreat of Japanese force because of Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keicho War began in 1597 because of the collapse of peace negotiations and ended in 1598 with the retreat of Japanese force because of Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>朝鮮民主主義人民共和国・大韓民国では文禄の役を壬辰倭乱（じんしんわらん、、イムジンウェラン、戦役総称として使う場合もあり）、慶長の役を丁酉倭乱（ていゆうわらん、、チョンユウェラン）または丁酉再乱（ていゆうさいらん、、チョンユヂェラン）と呼んでいる（北朝鮮では壬辰祖国戦争（じんしんそこくせんそう、、イムジンチョグクチョンジェン）と呼ばれる場合もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea and Republic of Korea, the Bunroku War is called Imjin Waeran (It is also used as the generic name of the Wars), and the Keicho War is called Chonyu Ueran or Chonyu Jeran (In the North Korea, in certain cases it is also called Imjin chogukuchonjen).</e>
<cmt>「丁酉倭乱」、「丁酉再乱」、「壬辰祖国戦争」は仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea and the Republic of Korea, the Bunroku War is called Imjin Waeran (It is also used as the generic name of the Wars), and the Keicho War is called Chonyu Ueran or Chonyu Jeran (In the North Korea, in certain cases it is also called Imjin chogukuchonjen).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea and the Republic of Korea, the Bunroku War is called Imjin Waeran (It is also used as the generic name of the Wars), and the Keicho War is called Chonyu Ueran or Chonyu Jeran (In the North Korea, in certain cases it is also called Imjin chogukuchonjen).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>中華人民共和国では万暦朝鮮戦争（ばんれきちょうせんせんそう、）もしくは朝鮮壬辰衛国戦争（ちょうせんじんしんえいこくせんそう、）と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, it is called &quot;万暦朝鮮戦争&quot; or &quot;朝鮮壬辰衛国戦争.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「万暦朝鮮戦争」および「朝鮮壬辰衛国戦争」の読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, it is called &quot;万暦朝鮮戦争&quot; or &quot;朝鮮壬辰衛国戦争.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the People&apos;s Republic of China, it is called &quot;万历朝鲜战争&quot; or &quot;朝鲜壬辰卫国战争.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「万暦朝鮮戦争」および「朝鮮壬辰衛国戦争」の読みが確認できませんでしたのでWebの中国語を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、文禄元年への改元は12月8日（グレゴリオ暦1593年1月10日）に行われたため、4月12日の釜山上陸で始まった戦役初年の1592年のほとんどの出来事は元号的には天正20年の出来事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name of era was changed to &quot;Bunroku&quot; on December 8 (January 10, 1593 by the Gregorian calendar), almost all events in 1592, the first year of the War, which began with landing at Busan on April 12, occurred in Tensho 20 as far as name of the era is concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name of era changed to &quot;Bunroku&quot; on December 8 (January 10, 1593 by the Gregorian calendar), almost all events in 1592, the first year of the War, that began with landing at Busan on April 12, occurred in Tensho 20 as far as name of the era is concerned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name of era changed to &quot;Bunroku&quot; on December 8 (January 10, 1593 by the Gregorian calendar), almost all events in 1592, the first year of the War, that began with landing at Busan on April 12, occurred in Tensho 20 as far as name of the era is concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦役前の状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations before the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situation before the war</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situation before the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>明の征服を企図していた豊臣秀吉は、天正15年（1587年）九州征伐に際し、臣従した対馬の領主・宗氏を通じて「李氏朝鮮の服属と明遠征の先導（征明嚮導）」を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who had intended to conquer Ming required through So clan who was the feudal lord of Tsushima and rendered homage and service to Hideyoshi on the occasion of the Kyushu Conquest in 1587, &quot;Yi Dynasty Korea&apos;s yielding allegiance to Hideyoshi and guidance for expedition to Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who had intended to conquer Ming required through So clan who was the feudal lord of Tsushima and rendered homage and service to Hideyoshi on the occasion of the Kyushu Conquest in 1587, &quot;Yi Dynasty Korea&apos;s yielding allegiance to Hideyoshi and guidance for expedition to Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who had intended to conquer Ming required through So clan who was the feudal lord of Tsushima and rendered homage and service to Hideyoshi on the occasion of the Kyushu Conquest in 1587, &apos;Yi Dynasty Korea&apos;s yielding allegiance to Hideyoshi and guidance for expedition to Ming.&apos;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>元来、朝鮮との貿易に経済を依存していた宗氏は対応に苦慮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The So clan of which economy had basically been dependent on trade with Korea racked its brains how to cope with the situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（不適切に分割されていた二つの原文を連結し、三つに分割し直しました。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The So clan had basically been dependent upon trade with Korea and they racked their brains on how to cope with the situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The So clan had basically been dependent upon trade with Korea and they racked their brains on how to cope with the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>李氏朝鮮に対しこの要求を直接伝えず、日本統一を祝賀する朝鮮通信使の派遣を要求して穏便に済まそうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It did not convey these requirements directly to Yi Dynasty Korea and tried to settle the situation peacefully by requiring dispatch of Chosen Tsushinshi (the Korean Emissary) to celebrate unification of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（不適切に分割されていた二つの原文を連結し、三つに分割し直しました。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It did not convey these requirements directly to the Yi Dynasty in Korea and tried to settle the situation peacefully by requiring dispatch of Chosen Tsushinshi (the Korean Emissary) to celebrate the unification of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It did not convey these requirements directly to the Yi Dynasty in Korea and tried to settle the situation peacefully by requiring dispatch of Chosen Tsushinshi (the Korean Emissary) to celebrate the unification of Japan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>明の冊封国であった李氏朝鮮に征明嚮導の意思はなく、秀吉は明への遠征のため先ず朝鮮の制圧を決め、文禄元年（1592年）4月（和暦。漢数字表記の月は以下同じ）、16万人の大軍を送ることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yi Dynasty Korea, which had been Sakuho-koku (countries to confer a peerage with a Saku paper) of Ming, did not have intention of guiding troops to conquer Ming and Hideyoshi decided to conquer Korea at first in order to make the expedition to Ming and a large army of 160,000 were sent in April 1592 (by traditional Japanese calendar).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（不適切に分割されていた二つの原文を連結し、三つに分割し直しました。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yi Dynasty Korea, which had been Sakuho-koku (countries to confer a peerage with a Saku paper) of Ming, did not have the intention of leadding troops to conquer Ming and Hideyoshi decided to conquer Korea at first in order to make a successful expedition to Ming and a large army of 160,000 were sent in April 1592 (according to the traditional Japanese calendar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yi Dynasty Korea, which had been Sakuho-koku (countries to confer a peerage with a Saku paper) of Ming, did not have the intention of leading troops to conquer Ming and Hideyoshi decided to conquer Korea at first in order to make a successful expedition to Ming and a large army of 160,000 were sent in May 1592 (according to the traditional Japanese calendar).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>李氏朝鮮王朝では日本へ派遣した使節が帰国し、その報告が西人派（正使の黄允吉は戦争が近いことを警告）と東人派（副使の金誠一は日本の侵略はあったとしても先の話と否定）で別れ、政権派閥の東人派が戦争の警告を無視した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yi Dynasty Korea, delegates who were dispatched to Japan returned and Seijinha group (黄允吉, who was seishi (senior envoy), warned that war would occur in the near future) and the Tojinha group (金誠一, who was the vice envoy, denied telling that invasion by Japan would not be in the near future) made different reports and the Tojinha group, which was the fraction in power, ignored the warning against war.</e>
<cmt>「西人派」、「東人派」、「黄允吉」、「金誠一」は読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Yi Dynasty Korea, delegates dispatched to Japan returned and the Seijinha group (黄允吉, who was seishi (senior envoy), warned that war would occur in the near future) and the Tojinha group (金誠一, who was the vice envoy, denied saying that invasion by Japan would not be in the near future) made different reports and the Tojinha group, the fraction in power, ignored the warning about the potential of war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Yi Dynasty Korea, delegates dispatched to Japan returned and the Seijinha group (黄允吉, who was seishi (senior envoy), warned that war would occur in the near future) and the Tojinha group (金誠一, who was the vice envoy, denied saying that invasion by Japan would not be in the near future) made different reports and the Tojinha group, the fraction in power, ignored the warning about the potential of war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、秀吉は開戦後も李氏朝鮮が降参するならこれを許し、明遠征への先導役を果たさせる考えを捨てていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi still maintained the intention that, if Yi Dynasty Korea would surrender, he would accept it and make it a guide for expedition to Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi still maintained the intention that, if Yi Dynasty Korea would surrender, he would accept it and make it a stepping stone for an expedition to Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi still maintained the intention that, if Yi Dynasty Korea would surrender, he would accept it and make it a stepping stone for an expedition to Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>先鋒と交渉役を務めた小西行長や宗義智の日本軍一番隊は、しばしば秀吉が考える「李氏朝鮮の服属と明遠征の先導（征明嚮導）」を「朝鮮に明への道を借りる（假途入明）」に言い換えた上で李氏朝鮮に求めに応じるよう交渉を呼びかけている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Division of the Japanese army of Yukinaga KONISHI and Yoshitomo SO, who acted as the spearhead and negotiators by changing Hideyoshi&apos;s idea &quot;subjection of Yi Dynasty Korea and guiding expedition to Ming&quot; to &quot;to borrow roads to Ming from Korea&quot; and asked Yi Dynasty Korea to negotiate to accept the requests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Division of the Japanese army of Yukinaga KONISHI and Yoshitomo SO, who acted as the spearhead and negotiators by changing Hideyoshi&apos;s idea &quot;subjection of Yi Dynasty Korea and guiding expedition to Ming&quot; to &quot;to borrow roads to Ming from Korea&quot; and asked Yi Dynasty Korea to negotiate to accept the requests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Division of the Japanese army of Yukinaga KONISHI and Yoshitomo SO, who acted as the spearhead and negotiators by changing Hideyoshi&apos;s idea &apos;subjection of Yi Dynasty Korea and guiding expedition to Ming&apos; to &apos;to borrow roads to Ming from Korea&apos; and asked Yi Dynasty Korea to negotiate to accept the requests.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;全角削除スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>なお、戦力に自信のあった日本軍は上陸後も戦国の常識に従って何度も李氏朝鮮を交渉により服属させようと試みており、朝鮮の武力制圧が既定路線であるかのような認識は間違いである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese army which was confident of their war potential tried, even after their landing, to subjugate Yi Dynasty Korea by negotiation in accordance with common sense in the Warring States period and, therefore, it is wrong to understand that subjugation of Korea by military power was the predetermined policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army, confident of their war potential, tried, even after their landing, to subjugate Yi Dynasty Korea by negotiation in accordance with common sense in the Warring States period and, therefore, it is wrong to conclude that subjugation of Korea by military power was the predetermined policy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army, confident of their war potential, tried, even after their landing, to subjugate Yi Dynasty Korea by negotiation in accordance with common sense in the Warring States period and, therefore, it is wrong to conclude that subjugation of Korea by military power was the predetermined policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>戦術に於いても攻城戦の開始前と落城寸前の場面で降伏勧告を行っており、自軍被害も低減できる無血開城の交渉を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In tactics, summons to surrender were given before starting a siege and just before fall of the castle and carried out negotiation for bloodless surrender which enabled them to minimize the damage to their own troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In tactics, a choice to surrender was given before starting a siege and just before fall of the castle and negotiations were carried out for a bloodless surrender which enabled them to minimize the damage to their own troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In tactics, a choice to surrender was given before starting a siege and just before fall of the castle and negotiations were carried out for a bloodless surrender which enabled them to minimize the damage to their own troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、異文化間の戦争のため明・朝鮮の指揮官は民衆を巻き込んだ籠城に徹し、守将の降伏による無血開城よりも民衆を巻き込んだ落城を選ぶケースが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was a war between different cultures, however, commanders of Ming and Korea devoted themselves to tact of holding the castle involving common people and, in many cases, they chose the fall of the castle involving common people rather than bloodless surrender by surrender of the defense general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was a war between different cultures, however, commanders of Ming and Korea devoted themselves to the tact of holding the castle involving common people and, in many cases, they chose the fall of the castle involving common people rather than bloodless surrender of a defense general.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was a war between different cultures, however, commanders of Ming and Korea devoted themselves to the tact of holding the castle involving common people and, in many cases, they chose the fall of the castle involving common people rather than bloodless surrender of a defense general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>文禄の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunroku War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bunroku War</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bunroku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>4月12日、釜山に上陸した日本軍は翌13日より攻撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese army landed in Busan on April 12 (Japanese calendar) and commenced attack from the next day, on April 13 (Japanese calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army landed in Busan on April 12 (Japanese calendar) and commenced attack from the next day, on April 13 (Japanese calendar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army landed in Busan on May 23 and commenced attack from the next day, on May 24.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>侵攻に対応が遅れた朝鮮軍は連戦連敗や無血撤退・逃散を重ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean army, which was late to cope with invasion, repeated a succession of defeats and bloodless retreats and fleeing in every direction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean army, which was late to cope with invasion, repeated a succession of defeats and bloodless retreats fleeing in every direction.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean army, which was late to cope with invasion, repeated a succession of defeats and bloodless retreats fleeing in every direction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>釜山鎮の戦い（鄭撥戦死）、東莱城の戦い（宋象賢戦死）、尚州の戦い（李鎰敗走）、弾琴台の戦い（申砬戦死）などで日本軍は勝利を重ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese army won victory after victory in the Battle of Busanjin (Chonparu died in war), the Battle of Tonne castle (Son Sanhyon died in war.), the Battle of Sangju (Yi Iru took to flight.), the Battle of Tangumdae (Shin Ritsu died in war.) and so on.</e>
<cmt>地名および人名のアルファベット表記は確認できず、すべて仮訳です。また「弾琴台の戦い」について、原文では「申砬（戦死）」が欠落していたため、補って訳出しました。ただし「Shin Ritsu」は朝鮮語での表記不明のため、日本での読みをローマ字表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army won victory after victory in the Battle of Busanjin (Chonparu died in the war), the Battle of Tonne castle (Son Sanhyon died in the war.), the Battle of Sangju (Yi Iru took to flight.), the Battle of Tangumdae (Shin Ritsu died in the war.) and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army won victory after victory in the Battle of Busanjin (Chonparu died in the war), the Battle of Tonne castle (Son Sanhyon died in the war), the Battle of Sangju (Yi Iru took to flight), the Battle of Tangumdae (Shin Ritsu died in the war) and so on.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>一番隊（小西行長、他）、二番隊（加藤清正、他）、三番隊（黒田長政、他）を先鋒に三路に分かれて急進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made a rapid advance by deviding themselves into three ways having the First Division (Yukinaga KONISHI and others), the Second Division (Kiyomasa KATO and others) and the Third Division (Nagamasa KURODA and others) as spearheads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They made a rapid advance by deviding themselves into three ways having the First Division (Yukinaga KONISHI and others), the Second Division (Kiyomasa KATO and others) and the Third Division (Nagamasa KURODA and others) as spearheads.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They made a rapid advance by dividing themselves into three ways having the First Division (Yukinaga KONISHI and others), the Second Division (Kiyomasa KATO and others) and the Third Division (Nagamasa KURODA and others) as spearheads.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ソウルに日本軍が迫ると李氏朝鮮の宣祖は平壌へ遷都して避難した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japanese army approached to Seoul, Sonjo, who was the emperor of Yi Dinasty Korea, transferred the caipital and fleed to Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japanese army approached Seoul, Sonjo, who was the emperor of Yi Dinasty Korea, transferred the capital and fled to Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japanese army approached Seoul, Sonjo, who was the emperor of Yi Dynasty Korea, transferred the capital and fled to Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>翌5月には首都・漢城（漢陽・現在のソウル特別市）を日本軍が占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next month, May, Japanese army occupied the capital, Hancheng (Hanyang; present Seoul Special City).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next month, May, the Japanese army occupied the capital, Hancheng (Hanyang; present Seoul Special City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next month, June, the Japanese army occupied the capital, Hancheng (Hanyang; present Seoul Special City).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>容易に李氏朝鮮の首都である漢城が陥落すると、日本の諸将は5月に漢城にて軍議を開き、各方面軍による八道国割と呼ばれる制圧目標を決めた（平安道から一番隊小西行長他、咸鏡道から二番隊加藤清正他、黄海道から三番隊黒田長政他、江原道から四番隊毛利吉成他、忠清道から五番隊福島正則他、全羅道から六番隊小早川隆景他、慶尚道から七番隊毛利輝元他、京畿道から八番隊宇喜多秀家他）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hancheong, which had been the capital of Yi Dynasty Korea, fell easily, Japanese commanders held a war council in May in Hancheong and determined targets of subjugation called Hachidokuniwari (literally, dividing countries into eight routes) by each corps (the First Division of Yukinaga KONICHI and others from Pyeongan Province, the Second Division of Kiyomasa KATO and others from Hangyong Province, the Third Division of Nagamasa KURODA and others from Hwanghae Province, the Forth Division of Yoshinari MORI and others from Gangwon Province; the Fifth Division of Masanori FUKUSHIMA and others from Chungcheong Province; the Sixth Division by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA and others from Jeolla Province, the Seventh Division by Terumoto MORI and others from Gyeongsang Province, and the Eighth Division of Hideie UKITA and others from Gyeonggi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hancheong, which had been the capital of Yi Dynasty Korea, fell easily, Japanese commanders held a war council in May in Hancheong and determined targets of subjugation called Hachidokuniwari (literally, dividing the country into eight routes) by each corps (the First Division of Yukinaga KONICHI and others from Pyeongan Province, the Second Division of Kiyomasa KATO and others from Hangyong Province, the Third Division of Nagamasa KURODA and others from Hwanghae Province, the Forth Division of Yoshinari MORI and others from Gangwon Province; the Fifth Division of Masanori FUKUSHIMA and others from Chungcheong Province; the Sixth Division by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA and others from Jeolla Province, the Seventh Division by Terumoto MORI and others from Gyeongsang Province, and the Eighth Division of Hideie UKITA and others from Gyeonggi Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hancheong, which had been the capital of Yi Dynasty Korea, fell easily, Japanese commanders held a war council in June in Hancheong and determined targets of subjugation called Hachidokuniwari (literally, dividing the country into eight routes) by each corps (the First Division of Yukinaga KONISHI and others from Pyeongan Province, the Second Division of Kiyomasa KATO and others from Hangyong Province, the Third Division of Nagamasa KURODA and others from Hwanghae Province, the Forth Division of Yoshinari MORI and others from Gangwon Province; the Fifth Division of Masanori FUKUSHIMA and others from Chungcheong Province; the Sixth Division by Takakage KOBAYAKAWA and others from Jeolla Province, the Seventh Division by Terumoto MORI and others from Gyeongsang Province, and the Eighth Division of Hideie UKITA and others from Gyeonggi Province).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>日本軍の進撃が平壌に迫ると宣祖は遼東との国境である北端の平安道・義州へと逃亡し、冊封に基づいて明に救援を要請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Japanese army marched close to Pyongyang, Sonjo fled to Uiju in Pyeongan Province which was located at the north end and on the border to Liaodong and asked Ming for help based on sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japanese amy marched close to Pyongyang, Sonjo fled to Uiju in Pyeongan Province located at the north end and on the border of Liaodong and asked Ming for help based on sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japanese army marched close to Pyongyang, Sonjo fled to Uiju in Pyeongan Province located at the north end and on the border of Liaodong and asked Ming for help based on sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その間にさらに北上した日本の一番隊と三番隊は平壌を占領して進撃を停止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mean time, the First and Third Divisions marched further to the north and occupied Pyongyang and suspended their marching.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mean time, the First and Third Divisions marched further to the north and occupied Pyongyang and suspended their marching.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mean time, the First and Third Divisions marched further to the north and occupied Pyongyang and suspended their marching.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>なお、開城の攻略まで行動を共にしていた二番隊は鏡道へ進路を転じ、日本軍は北西部の平安道の平壌より北方と全羅道を除く朝鮮全土を制圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Second Division, which acted with them until attack on Kaesong, switched their course to Hamgyong Province and the Japanese army occupied whole Korea excluding the part of Pyeongan Province in the northwestern area to the north of Pyongyang and Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Second Division, acting with them until the attack on Kaesong, switched their course to Hamgyong Province and the Japanese army occupied all of Korea excluding part of Pyeongan Province in the northwestern area to the north of Pyongyang and Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Division, acting with them until the attack on Kaesong, switched their course to Hamgyong Province and the Japanese army occupied all of Korea excluding part of Pyeongan Province in the northwestern area to the north of Pyongyang and Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>加藤清正の一隊は威力偵察のため国境を越えて明領・オランカイ（兀良哈）へ攻め入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO and his troops invaded into Orangkai in Ming&apos;s territory surpassing the border for the purpose of reconnaissance in force.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa KATO and his troops invaded Orangkai in Ming&apos;s territory surpassing the border for the purpose of reconnaissance in force.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO and his troops invaded Orangkai in Ming&apos;s territory surpassing the border for the purpose of reconnaissance in force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>「宣祖実録（せんそじつろく、ソンジョシルロク）宣祖二十五年壬辰五月條」によると、このとき朝鮮の民衆は既に王や大臣を見限り、日本軍に協力する者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;the record for May of the 25th year of Sonjo in &apos;Senso Jitsuroku&apos; (literally, factual stories in the era of Sonjo),&quot; Korean people had already given up on Sonjo and many persons who cooperated with the Japanese army appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>「宣祖実録」の朝鮮語読みの表記が確認できないため訳文のとおりとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;the record for May of the 25th year of Sonjo in &apos;Senso Jitsuroku&apos; (literally, factual stories in the era of Sonjo),&quot; The Korean people had already given up on Sonjo and many persons who cooperated with the Japanese army appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;the record for May of the 25th year of Sonjo in &apos;Senso Jitsuroku&apos; (literally, factual stories in the era of Sonjo),&quot; The Korean people had already given up on Sonjo and many persons who cooperated with the Japanese army appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>これは、宣祖実録の「人心怨叛，與倭同心耳」、「我民亦曰：倭亦人也，吾等何必棄家而避也？」で伺い知ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We can guess this by &quot;人心怨叛，與倭同心耳&quot; and &quot;我民亦曰:倭亦人也，吾等何必棄家而避也？&quot; in Senso Jitsuroku.</e>
<cmt>漢文記事の内容を正確に確認することができませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We can guess this by &quot;人心怨叛，與倭同心耳&quot; and &quot;我民亦曰:倭亦人也，吾等何必棄家而避也？&quot; in Senso Jitsuroku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We can guess this by &apos;人心怨叛，與倭同心耳&apos; and &apos;我民亦曰:倭亦人也，吾等何必棄家而避也？&apos; in Senso Jitsuroku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;漢文記事の内容を正確に確認することができませんでしたので、そのまま表記しております。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>また、明の朝鮮支援軍が駆けつけると、辺りに散らばる首の殆どが朝鮮の民であったと書かれてある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written that, when the army of Ming to support Korea rushed and arrived, almost all heads which were scattered were those of Korean people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written that, when the Ming army supporting Korea rushed forward and arrived, almost all heads which were scattered were those of Korean people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written that, when the Ming army supporting Korea rushed forward and arrived, almost all heads which were scattered were those of Korean people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>景福宮・昌徳宮・昌慶宮の三王宮は、日本軍の入城前にはすでに灰燼となっており、奴婢（ぬひ、奴隷の一種）は、日本軍を解放軍として迎え、奴婢の身分台帳を保管していた掌隷院に火を放った、とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is described that three palaces, Gyeongbokgung Palace, Changdeokgung and Changgyeonggung, had been reduced to ashes before the Japanese army entered the castle and nuhi (a type of slave) welcomed the Japanese army as liberation forces and set fire to changnye won in which status ledgers for nuhi had been kept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been described that three palaces, Gyeongbokgung Palace, Changdeokgung and Changgyeonggung, had been reduced to ashes before the Japanese army entered the castle and nuhi (a type of slave) welcomed the Japanese army as liberation forces and set fire to changnye won in which status ledgers for nuhi had been kept.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been described that three palaces, Gyeongbokgung Palace, Changdeokgung and Changgyeonggung, had been reduced to ashes before the Japanese army entered the castle and nuhi (a type of slave) welcomed the Japanese army as liberation forces and set fire to changnye won in which status ledgers for nuhi had been kept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="39">
<j>日本軍に大きく後れを取った李氏朝鮮であったが、釜山を基点として支配領域を広げていた日本軍後方部隊のうち、海岸移動を行っていた船団に対して李舜臣率いる朝鮮水軍が4月と5月の二回の出撃で積極的に攻撃を加え、備えのない日本船団は被害を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yi Dynasty Korea had been beaten by the Japanese army, the Korean navy headed by Yi Sun-sin attacked, twice in April and May, actively groups of ships that had been moving along the coast among troops at the rear of the Japanese army that had been expanding the area under its control based at Busan, and the Japanese groups of ships that had not prepared for suffered damages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yi Dynasty Korea had been beaten by the Japanese army, the Korean navy headed by Yi Sun-sin attacked, twice in April and May, actively fleet of ships that had been moving along the coast among troops at the rear of the Japanese army that had been expanding the area under its control based at Busan, and the Japanese fleet of ships that had not prepared for the damages suffered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yi Dynasty Korea had been beaten by the Japanese army, the Korean navy headed by Yi Sun-sin attacked, twice in May and June, actively fleet of ships that had been moving along the coast among troops at the rear of the Japanese army that had been expanding the area under its control based at Busan, and the Japanese fleet of ships that had not prepared for the damages suffered.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>海戦用の水軍や朝鮮沿岸を西進する作戦を持たなかった日本軍は、陸戦部隊や後方で輸送任務にあたっていた部隊から急遽水軍を編成して対抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army that did not have navy for naval battle and a plan to proceed to the west along the coast of Korean organized hastily a navy with troops for land combats and troops that had been engaifed in transportation in the rear to cope with Korean navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army that did not have a navy for fighting on the sea nor a plan to proceed to the west along the coast of Korea, they hastily organized a navy with troops for land combat and troops that had been engulfed in transportation in the rear to cope with the Korean navy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army that did not have a navy for fighting on the sea nor a plan to proceed to the west along the coast of Korea, they hastily organized a navy with troops for land combat and troops that had been engulfed in transportation in the rear to cope with the Korean navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="41">
<j>こうして編成された水軍は脇坂安治の抜け駆けが閑山島海戦にて敗北した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With respect to the navy which had been organized in such way, stealing a march by Yasuharu WAKISAKA was defeated in the Battle of Hansan Island.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With respect to a navy organized in such a way, stealing a march by Yasuharu WAKISAKA, it was defeated in the Battle of Hansan Island.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With respect to a navy organized in such a way, stealing a march by Yasuharu WAKISAKA, it was defeated in the Battle of Hansan Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>続いて援護のために進出した加藤嘉明と九鬼嘉隆の水軍が李舜臣の泊地攻撃に耐えかねて後退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the navy headed by Yoshiakira KATO and Yoshitaka KUKI, that debouched to back up, retreated as they could not stand up against attacks to their mooring places by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the navy headed by Yoshiakira KATO and Yoshitaka KUKI, that debouched to back up, retreated as they could not stand up against attacks on their mooring places by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the navy headed by Yoshiakira KATO and Yoshitaka KUKI, that debouched to back up, retreated as they could not stand up against attacks on their mooring places by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>日本軍は海戦の不利を悟って、積極的な出撃戦術から消極的な水陸共同防御戦術へ方針を変更した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army woke up their disadvantages in naval battles and switched their policy from positive sally tactics to passive joint defense by navy and army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army woke up their disadvantages in naval battles and switched their methods from positive sally tactics to passive joint defense by navy and army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army woke up their disadvantages in naval battles and switched their methods from positive sally tactics to passive joint defense by navy and army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これは長年の倭寇対策で船体破壊のための遠戦指向の朝鮮水軍に対して、船員制圧のための近戦指向の日本水軍では装備や戦術の差もあって、正面衝突の海戦をすると日本水軍が不利であったことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because that direct naval battles were unfavorable to the Japanese navy because of the differences in equipage and tactics between the Korean navy that was oriented to distant combat (battles with missiles) to break vessel&apos;s body because of their experiences in long period in coping with wako (Japanese pirates) and Japanese navy that was oriented to close combat to suppress sailors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because direct naval battles were unfavorable to the Japanese navy because of the differences in equipment and tactics between the Korean navy that was oriented to distant combat (battles with missiles) to break the vessel&apos;s body because of their experiences over a long period in coping with wako (Japanese pirates) and the Japanese navy that was oriented to close combat to suppress sailors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because direct naval battles were unfavorable to the Japanese navy because of the differences in equipment and tactics between the Korean navy that was oriented to distant combat (battles with missiles) to break the vessel&apos;s body because of their experiences over a long period in coping with wako (Japanese pirates) and the Japanese navy that was oriented to close combat to suppress sailors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>しかし当時の船は航海力も攻撃力も未熟であり、陸上への依存が強いため水陸共同防御戦術は有効に機能し、以降の李舜臣の攻撃は戦果があがらず精彩を欠くようになり、出撃も滞ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as vessels at that time were immature both in capability for navigation and combat power and they were dependent to support from the land, the joint defense by navy and army worked effectively and, after that, attacks by Yi Sun-sin could not achieve good results in battle and became lackluster and the number of sorties decreased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as vessels at that time were immature both in capability for navigation and combat power and they were dependent to support from the land, the joint defense by navy and army worked effectively and, after that, attacks by Yi Sun-sin could not achieve good results in battle and became lackluster and the number of sorties decreased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as vessels at that time were immature both in capability for navigation and combat power and they were dependent to support from the land, the joint defense by navy and army worked effectively and, after that, attacks by Yi Sun-sin could not achieve good results in battle and became lackluster and the number of sorties decreased.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="46">
<j>7月、援軍に来た祖承訓率いる遼東の明軍が最前線の平壌を急襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, the army of Ming from Liaodong which was headed by Zu Chengxun and sent as reinforcement made an assault on Pyongyang in the forefront.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, the army of Ming from Liaodong headed by Zu Chengxun, sent as reinforcements made an assault on Pyongyang at the forefront.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, the army of Ming from Liaodong headed by Zu Chengxun, sent as reinforcements made an assault on Pyongyang at the forefront.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これは小西行長によって撃退するものの、明の救援によって交渉優先の状況となり戦況は膠着することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This assault was beaten back by Yukinaga KONISHI, but, because of help by Ming, the situations changed to prioritize negotiation and war situation got stuck.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This assault was beaten back by Yukinaga KONISHI, but, because of assistance from Ming, the situations changed to prioritize negotiation and war situation got stuck.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This assault was beaten back by Yukinaga KONISHI, but, because of assistance from Ming, the situations changed to prioritize negotiation and war situation got stuck.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="48">
<j>朝鮮へ派遣された諸将は八道国割を目標に要衝を制圧していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commanders dispatched to Korea conquered strategic points in accordance with Hachidokuniwari strategy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commanders dispatched to Korea conquered strategic points in accordance with Hachidokuniwari strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commanders dispatched to Korea conquered strategic points in accordance with Hachidokuniwari strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>前述のとおり小西行長は当初は李氏朝鮮、後には明との和平交渉を優先して平壌で北進を停止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described above, Yukinaga KONISHI gave a priority to peace talks with Yi Dynasty Korea, at first, and, then, with Ming and stopped the move to the north at Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described above, Yukinaga KONISHI put priority on peace talks with Yi Dynasty Korea, at first, and, then, with Ming and stopped any further movments north, stopping at Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described above, Yukinaga KONISHI put priority on peace talks with Yi Dynasty Korea, at first, and, then, with Ming and stopped any further movements north, stopping at Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>また小早川隆景は忠清道方面から全羅道に侵入したが権慄の反撃によって進撃を阻まれ、直後に南下する明軍の攻撃に対応するために漢城へ転出したため、全羅道の制圧は進まなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA invaded into Jeolla Province from Chungcheong Province, but his advance was blocked off by counterattack by Gwon Yul and, as he moved out immediately after that to Hancheng in order to cope with attack by the army of Ming, that moved down to the south, conquering Jeolla Province did not progress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA invaded Jeolla Province from Chungcheong Province, but his advance was blocked off by a counterattack by Gwon Yul and, as he moved out immediately after that to Hancheng in order to cope with attack by the Ming army that moved down to the south, the attempt at conquering Jeolla Province did not progress.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA invaded Jeolla Province from Chungcheong Province, but his advance was blocked off by a counterattack by Gwon Yul and, as he moved out immediately after that to Hancheng in order to cope with attack by the Ming army that moved down to the south, the attempt at conquering Jeolla Province did not progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="51">
<j>日本軍は釜山西方の制圧を画策して、第一次晋州城攻防戦（1592年9月、細川忠興指揮の日本軍対金時敏指揮の朝鮮軍）を生起させるが苦戦したうえ、攻城に失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Intending to conquer the west of Busan, the Japanese army caused the first Siege of Jinju (the Japanese army commanded by Tadaoki HOSOKAWA versus the Korean army commanded by Kim Si-min) and, after hard battles, failed in attack on the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Intending to conquer the area west of Busan, the Japanese army caused the first Siege of Jinju (the Japanese army commanded by Tadaoki HOSOKAWA versus the Korean army commanded by Kim Si-min) and, after hard battles, failed in attack on the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Intending to conquer the area west of Busan, the Japanese army caused the first Siege of Jinju (in September 1592, the Japanese army commanded by Tadaoki HOSOKAWA versus the Korean army commanded by Kim Si-min) and, after hard battles, failed in attack on the castle.</e>
<cmt>日付補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>ちなみに、この戦闘は閑山島海戦（1592年7月、脇坂安治指揮の日本軍対李舜臣指揮の朝鮮軍）・幸州山城攻防戦（1593年2月、宇喜多秀家指揮の日本軍対権慄指揮の朝鮮軍）とあわせて韓国では「壬辰倭乱の三大捷」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, this batter is called in the Republic of Korea &quot;three major victories in Imjin Waeran&quot; together with the Naval Battle of Hansan Island (July 1592, the Japanese army commanded by Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus the Korean army commanded by Yi Sun-sin) and the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) (the Japanese army commanded by Hideie UKITA versus the Korean army commanded by Gwon Yul).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, this battle are called in the Republic of Korea &quot;three major victories in Imjin Waeran&quot; together with the Naval Battle of Hansan Island (July 1592, the Japanese army commanded by Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus the Korean army commanded by Yi Sun-sin) and the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) (the Japanese army commanded by Hideie UKITA versus the Korean army commanded by Gwon Yul).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, this battle are called in the Republic of Korea &apos;three major victories in Imjin Waeran&apos; together with the Naval Battle of Hansan Island (July 1592, the Japanese army commanded by Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus the Korean army commanded by Yi Sun-sin) and the Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju) (the Japanese army commanded by Hideie UKITA versus the Korean army commanded by Gwon Yul).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="53">
<j>翌文禄2年（1593年）1月、李如松率いる明軍4万3,000人余が平壌に進攻し奪還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January (old calendar) in the next year (1593), the army of Ming of 43,000 soldiers headed by Li Ru-song attached Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January (old calendar) during the next year (1593), the Ming Army of 43,000 soldiers headed by Li Ru-song attacked Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February during the next year (1593), the Ming Army of 43,000 soldiers headed by Li Ru-song attacked Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし日本軍は漢城郊外の碧蹄館の戦いに勝利する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army, however, won the Battle of Byeokjegwan in the suburb of Hancheng.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army, however, won the Battle of Byeokjegwan in the suburbs of Hancheng.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army, however, won the Battle of Byeokjegwan in the suburbs of Hancheng.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>この段階で両者の戦線が行き詰まり、和平交渉が始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this stage, the battle lines for the both parties seemed fixed, and peace talk was commenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this stage, the battle lines for the both parties seemed fixed, and peace talks commenced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this stage, the battle lines for the both parties seemed fixed, and peace talks commenced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="56">
<j>占領各地では義兵の決起が生じ、このため武器・兵糧不足に悩まされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various occupied areas, rises by volunteer soldiers occurred and they suffered from insufficient weapons and provisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In various occupied areas, volunteer soldiers arose and they suffered from insufficient weapons and provisions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In various occupied areas, volunteer soldiers arose and they suffered from insufficient weapons and provisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この義兵は流民も多く、朝鮮の民衆や軍隊も襲う事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such volunteer soldiers included many displaced persons and sometimes attacked Korean people or army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such volunteer soldiers included many displaced persons and sometimes attacked Korean people or the army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such volunteer soldiers included many displaced persons and sometimes attacked Korean people or the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>漢城に集結して和平交渉を始めていた日本軍だが、本土から釜山までの海路の補給は維持していたが、釜山から漢城までの陸路の治安が悪化して食糧などの補給が滞りがちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army that had assembled in Hancheng and commenced a peace talk, maintained the route for supply by sea from Japan to Busan, but the security of the land route from Busan to Hancheng had been deteriorated and, therefore, supply of food etc. had got stacked up.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army that had assembled in Hancheng and commenced peace talks, maintained the route for supplies by sea from Japan to Busan, but the security of the land route from Busan to Hancheng had deteriorated and, therefore, supplies of food etc. were stacking up.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army that had assembled in Hancheng and commenced peace talks, maintained the route for supplies by sea from Japan to Busan, but the security of the land route from Busan to Hancheng had deteriorated and, therefore, supplies of food etc. were stacking up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>そのため、加藤清正が捕虜にした李氏朝鮮の2人の王子（臨海君・順和君）の返還と引き替えに釜山周辺の南部へ4月頃までに移陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they moved their camps to the southern areas around Busan by April in exchange of return of two princes (Prince Imhaegun and Prince Sunhwagun) of Yi Dynasty Korea who had been captured by Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they moved their camps to the southern areas around Busan by April in exchange of two princes (Prince Imhaegun and Prince Sunhwagun) of Yi Dynasty Korea who had been captured by Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they moved their camps to the southern areas around Busan by May in exchange of two princes (Prince Imhaegun and Prince Sunhwagun) of Yi Dynasty Korea who had been captured by Kiyomasa KATO.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="60">
<j>こうして兵力と補給に余裕が出てきたことにより朝鮮南部の支配を既定事実とするため、朝鮮南部へ布陣した諸将を動員して第二次晋州城攻防戦で晋州城を攻略した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, as they could have leeway both in troop strength and supply, in order to make control of the southern Korea established fact, commanders camped in the southern Korea were called up to attack the Jinju Castle (the second Siege of Jinju).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, as they could gain some leeway both in troop strength and supplies, in order to control southern Korea an established fact, commanders camped in southern Korea were called up to attack Jinju Castle (the second Siege of Jinju).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, as they could gain some leeway both in troop strength and supplies, in order to control southern Korea an established fact, commanders camped in southern Korea were called up to attack Jinju Castle (the second Siege of Jinju).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>（当初は漢城戦線を維持したまま日本本土からの新戦力を投入する計画であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(At the beginning, it was planned to use the new troops from Japan while maintaining the front line of Hancheng.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(At the beginning, it was planned to use the new troops from Japan while maintaining the front line at Hancheng.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(At the beginning, it was planned to use the new troops from Japan while maintaining the front line at Hancheng.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>更に全羅道を窺うも明軍の進出によって戦線は膠着し、長い休戦期に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, although they tried to advance to Jeolla Province, the front got stuck and long-lasting truce period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, although they tried to advance to Jeolla Province, the front got stuck and there was a long-lasting truce period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, although they tried to advance to Jeolla Province, the front got stuck and there was a long-lasting truce period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>休戦期の和平交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peace talk in the truce period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peace talks during the truce period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peace talks during the truce period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>この時期、豊臣秀吉は明が降伏したという報告を受け、反対に明の朝廷では日本が降伏したという報告を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI received a report of surrender of Ming and, to the contrary, the court of Ming Dynasty received a report of surrender of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI received a report of the surrender of Ming and, to the contrary, the court of the Ming Dynasty received a report of the surrender of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI received a report of the surrender of Ming and, to the contrary, the court of the Ming Dynasty received a report of the surrender of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これは日本・明双方の講和担当者が穏便に講和を行うためにそれぞれ偽りの報告をした為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because persons in charge of peace talk of both Japan and Ming made false reports in order to realize peace smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because the persons in charge of peace talk of both Japan and Ming made false reports in order to smoothly realize peace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because the persons in charge of peace talk of both Japan and Ming made false reports in order to smoothly realize peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>このため秀吉は和平に際し、明の皇女を天皇に嫁がせる事や、朝鮮南部の割譲など、到底明側には受け入れられない講和条件を提示し、明の降伏使節の来朝を要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in negotiating peace, Hideyoshi proposed conditions of peace which were unacceptable to Ming, such that a princess of Ming marry the emperor of Japan and cession of the southern part of Korea and required dispatch of envoy to surrender from of Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, while negotiating peace, Hideyoshi proposed conditions of peace unacceptable to Ming, such that a princess of Ming marry the emperor of Japan and the cession of the southern part of Korea and required the dispatch of an envoy to surrender from Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, while negotiating peace, Hideyoshi proposed conditions of peace unacceptable to Ming, such that a princess of Ming marry the emperor of Japan and the cession of the southern part of Korea and required the dispatch of an envoy to surrender from Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>一方、明の朝廷も日本が降伏したという証を要求したが、これも秀吉にとっては到底受け入れられるものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the court of Ming Dynasty required proof of surrender of Japan and this was not acceptable for Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the court of Ming Dynasty required proof of surrender of Japan and this was not acceptable to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the court of Ming Dynasty required proof of surrender of Japan and this was not acceptable to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>結局、日本の交渉担当者は「関白降表」という偽りの降伏文書を作成し、明側には秀吉の和平条件は「勘合貿易の再開」という条件のみであると伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last, the person in charge of negotiation of Japan prepared a false instrument of surrender titled &quot;Kanpaku kohyo (literally, letter of surrender by Kanpaku)&quot; and it was reported to Ming that Hideyoshi&apos;s only condition for peace was &quot;restart of the tally trade (between Japan and the Ming Dynasty).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At last, the person in charge of negotiations for Japan prepared a false instrument of surrender titled &quot;Kanpaku kohyo (literally, letter of surrender by Kanpaku)&quot; and it was reported to Ming that Hideyoshi&apos;s only condition for peace was &quot;restart of the tally trade (between Japan and the Ming Dynasty).&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last, the person in charge of negotiations for Japan prepared a false instrument of surrender titled &apos;Kanpaku kohyo&apos; (literally, letter of surrender by Kanpaku) and it was reported to Ming that Hideyoshi&apos;s only condition for peace was &apos;restart of the tally trade&apos; (between Japan and the Ming Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>「秀吉の降伏」を確認した明は朝議の結果「封は許すが貢は許さない」（明の冊封体制下に入る事は認めるが勘合貿易は認めない）と決め、秀吉に対し日本国王の称号と金印を授けるため日本に使節を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After confirming &quot;Hideyoshi&apos;s surrender,&quot; Ming decided by deliberation of the court that &quot;&apos;Ho&apos; is allowed but &apos;Ko&apos; is not allowed (It is allowed to join the sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors) system of Ming, but tally trade is not allowed),&quot; and dispatched an envoy to Japan to confer the title of the king of Japan and a gold seal on Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After confirming &quot;Hideyoshi&apos;s surrender,&quot; Ming decided by deliberation of the court that &quot;&apos;Ho&apos; is allowed but &apos;Ko&apos; is not allowed (It is allowed to join the sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors) system of Ming, but tally trade is not allowed),&quot; and dispatched an envoy to Japan to confer the title of the king of Japan and a gold seal on Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After confirming &apos;Hideyoshi&apos;s surrender,&apos; Ming decided by deliberation of the court that &apos;Ho is allowed but Ko is not allowed&apos; (It is allowed to join the sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors) system of Ming, but tally trade is not allowed), and dispatched an envoy to Japan to confer the title of the king of Japan and a gold seal on Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>文禄5年（1596年）9月、秀吉は来朝した明使節と謁見。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1596, Hideyoshi had an audience with the envoy of Ming who visited Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1596, Hideyoshi had an audience with the envoy of Ming who visited Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1596, Hideyoshi had an audience with the envoy of Ming who visited Japan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>自分の要求が全く受け入れられていないのを知り激怒。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He found that his requests were totally refused and got very angry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He found that his requests were totally refused and he got very angry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He found that his requests were totally refused and he got very angry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>使者を追い返し朝鮮への再度出兵を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He turned the envoy back and determined to send troops again to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sent the envoy back and was determined to send troops again to Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sent the envoy back and was determined to send troops again to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>慶長の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Keicho War</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Keicho War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）2月、和平交渉で無視された朝鮮南部割譲を実力で果たすという名目で、秀吉は14万人の軍を再び朝鮮に送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1597, Hideyoshi sent troops of 140,000 to Korea with a pretext to achieve by force the cession of the southern Korea which was ignored in the peace talk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1597, Hideyoshi sent 140,000 troops to Korea with a pretext to achieve by force the cession of southern Korea which was ignored in the peace talks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1597, Hideyoshi sent 140,000 troops to Korea with a pretext to achieve by force the cession of southern Korea which was ignored in the peace talks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>李氏朝鮮王朝では釜山に集結中の日本軍を朝鮮水軍で攻撃するように命令したが、度重なる命令無視のために三道水軍統制使の李舜臣は罷免され、後任には元均が登用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yi Dynasty Korea ordered to Korean navy to attack the Japanese army that had assembled in Busan, Yi Sun-sin, who was the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces, was removed from his post because of repeatedly ignoring orders and Won Gyun was appointed to the successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yi Dynasty Korea ordered the Korean navy to attack the Japanese army that had assembled in Busan, Yi Sun-sin, who was the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces, was removed from his post because of repeatedly ignoring orders and Won Gyun was appointed the successor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yi Dynasty Korea ordered the Korean navy to attack the Japanese army that had assembled in Busan, Yi Sun-sin, who was the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces, was removed from his post because of repeatedly ignoring orders and Won Gyun was appointed the successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>朝鮮水軍を引き継いだ元均も攻撃を渋ったが、ついに7月に出撃を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Won Gyun, who succeeded the Korean navy, was also reluctant to make such attacked but, finally in July he departed for attacking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Won Gyun, who succeeded the Korean navy, was also reluctant to attacked but, finally in July he did attack.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Won Gyun, who succeeded the Korean navy, was also reluctant to attacked but, finally in August he did attack.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>しかし攻撃は失敗し、帰路に巨済島で停泊していたところを水陸から攻撃され、朝鮮水軍は幹部指揮官、元均、李億祺、崔湖の戦死と共に壊滅的打撃を被った（漆川梁海戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this attack failed and, when they anchored at Geoje Island on their way back, they were attacked both from the land and sea and the Korean navy suffered catastrophic damages including death in war of senior commanders, Won Gyun, Lee Eokgi and 崔湖 (the Naval Battle of Chilcheollyang).</e>
<cmt>「崔湖」のアルファベット表記が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the attack failed and, when they anchored at Geoje Island on their way back, they were attacked both from the land and sea and the Korean navy suffered catastrophic damage including deaths of senior commanders, Won Gyun, Lee Eokgi, and 崔湖 (the Naval Battle of Chilcheollyang).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the attack failed and, when they anchored at Geoje Island on their way back, they were attacked both from the land and sea and the Korean navy suffered catastrophic damage including deaths of senior commanders, Won Gyun, Lee Eokgi, and 崔湖 (the Naval Battle of Chilcheollyang).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>翌8月、日本軍は右軍と左軍（及び水軍）の二隊に別れ慶尚道から全羅道に向かって進撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next month, August, the Japanese army was separated into two troops, the Right Troop and Left Troop (and navy) and started marching from Gyeongsang Province to Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the next month, August, the Japanese army was separated into two groups, the Right group and Left group (and navy) and started marching from Gyeongsang Province to Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the next month, Seｐtember, the Japanese army was separated into two groups, the Right group and Left group (and navy) and started marching from Gyeongsang Province to Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>対する明・朝鮮軍は道境付近の黄石山城と南原市城で守りを固めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To cope with this attack the troops of Ming and Korea built up defenses at Hwangsoksan Castle and Namwon Castle near the border of Provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To cope with this attack the troops of Ming and Korea built up defenses at Hwangsoksan and Namwon Castles near the border of the Provinces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To cope with this attack the troops of Ming and Korea built up defenses at Hwangsoksan and Namwon Castles near the border of the Provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>日本の右軍は黄石山城を、左軍は南原市城を攻撃、たちまち二城を陥落させ全州市城に進むと、ここを守る明軍が逃走したため無血占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Right Troops of Japan attacked Hwangsoksan Castle while the Left Troop attacked Namwon Castle and they took immediately both castles by assault and advanced to and occupied without blood Jeonju Castle, because the troops of Ming that had been defending the castle fled when they came close to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Right group of Japan attacked Hwangsoksan Castle while the Left attacked Namwon Castle and they immediately took both castles in the assaults and advanced to and occupied without blood Jeonju Castle, because the Ming army that had been defending the castle fled when they came close to it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Right group of Japan attacked Hwangsoksan Castle while the Left attacked Namwon Castle and they immediately took both castles in the assaults and advanced to and occupied without blood Jeonju Castle, because the Ming army that had been defending the castle fled when they came close to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>日本の諸将は全州で軍議を行い、右軍、中軍、左軍、水軍に別れ諸将の進撃路と制圧する地方の分担を行い、守備担当を決め全羅道・忠清道を瞬く間に占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese commanders held a council of war in Jeonju and divided themselves into the Right Troop, the Middle Troop, the Left Troop and the Navy and allocated marching routes and districts to conquer, and determined the troops in charge of defense and occupied Jeolla Province from Chungcheong Province immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese commanders held a council of war in Jeonju and divided themselves into the Right, Middle, and Left groups and the Navy and allocated marching routes and districts to conquer, and determined which troops were in charge of defense and immediately occupied Jeolla Province after marching from Chungcheong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese commanders held a council of war in Jeonju and divided themselves into the Right, Middle, and Left groups and the Navy and allocated marching routes and districts to conquer, and determined which troops were in charge of defense and immediately occupied Jeolla Province after marching from Chungcheong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>北上した日本軍に一時は漢城の放棄も考えた明軍であったが、結局南下しての抗戦を決意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of march of the Japanese army to the north, the army of Ming once considered to give up Hanchen, but they made finally their mind up to resist going down to the south.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the Japanese army marching north, the Ming army once considered to give up Hanchen, but they finally decided to resist going down south.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the Japanese army marching north, the Ming army once considered to give up Hanchen, but they finally decided to resist going down south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>9月に先遣隊の明将・解生と黒田長政の部隊が天安市で遭遇戦を行い双方が後退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, advance troops, troops of kaisei, who was the commander of Ming and troops Nagamasa KURODA conducted an encounter in Cheonan City and both troops retreated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, advancing troops of kaisei, the commander of Ming and Nagamasa KURODA&apos;s army had an encounter in Cheonan City and both retreated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, advancing troops of kaisei, the commander of Ming and Nagamasa KURODA&apos;s army had an encounter in Cheonan City and both retreated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="82">
<j>同じく9月には南原城から南下した後に西進した日本水軍の先鋒を三道水軍統制使に返り咲いた李舜臣が鳴梁海戦で破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September also, Yi Sun-sin, who came back to the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces, defeated the advance troops of the Japanese navy, which at first moved to the south from the Namwon Castle and then moved to the west, in the Naval Battle at Meiryo.</e>
<cmt>「鳴梁」の朝鮮語読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During September also, Yi Sun-sin, who returned to the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces, defeated the advancing Japanese navy, which at first moved to the south from the Namwon Castle and then moved west, in the Naval Battle at Meiryo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During October also, Yi Sun-sin, who returned to the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces, defeated the advancing Japanese navy, which at first moved to the south from the Namwon Castle and then moved west, in the Naval Battle at Meiryo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし、日本軍により全羅道西岸が制圧されると朝鮮水軍は制海権を失い、李舜臣も全羅道北端まで後退し、日本水軍は全羅道西岸まで進出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Korean navy lost the naval supremacy after the west coast of Jeolla Province was conquered and Yi Sun-sin also retreated to the northern border of Jeolla Province and the Japanese navy advanced to the west coast of Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Korean navy lost naval supremacy after the west coast of Jeolla Province was conquered and Yi Sun-sin also retreated to the northern border of Jeolla Province and the Japanese navy advanced to the west coast of Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Korean navy lost naval supremacy after the west coast of Jeolla Province was conquered and Yi Sun-sin also retreated to the northern border of Jeolla Province and the Japanese navy advanced to the west coast of Jeolla Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="84">
<j>京畿道まで進出した日本軍は、冬の訪れを前にして寒冷期の漢江渡河の困難さを鑑み、慶尚道から全羅道の沿岸部へ撤収し、文禄の役の際に築かれた城郭群域の外縁部（東は蔚山から西は順天市に至る範囲）に新たな城郭群を築いて久留の計を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the winter came, taking into consideration difficulty to cross Han-gang in the cold season, the Japanese army, which advanced to Gyeonggi Province, retreated from Gyeongsang Province to the coastal area of Jeolla Province and tried to execute the plan of the perpetuation of camp by construction of groups of new castles in the outer border of the area of castles constructed during Bunroku war (ranging from Ulsan in the east to Suncheon-si in the west).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before winter, taking into consideration the difficulty of crosing Han-gang during the cold season, the Japanese army, which advanced to Gyeonggi Province, retreated from Gyeongsang Province to the coastal area of Jeolla Province and tried to build a permanent camp by constructing a number of new castles on the outer border of the area of castles constructed during Bunroku war (ranging from Ulsan in the east to Suncheon-si in the west).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before winter, taking into consideration the difficulty of crossing Han-gang during the cold season, the Japanese army, which advanced to Gyeonggi Province, retreated from Gyeongsang Province to the coastal area of Jeolla Province and tried to build a permanent camp by constructing a number of new castles on the outer border of the area of castles constructed during Bunroku war (ranging from Ulsan in the east to Suncheon-si in the west).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>城郭群が完成後は各城の在番軍以外は帰国する予定で、翌慶長3年（1598年）中は攻勢を行わない方針を立てていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was planned that, after the completion of the castles troops other than those staying in each castle returned to Japan and no attack would not be conducted in the next year, 1598.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan was after the completion of the castles, the troops other than those staying to defend each castle, would return to Japan and no attacks would be conducted during the next year, 1598.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan was after the completion of the castles, the troops other than those staying to defend each castle, would return to Japan and no attacks would be conducted during the next year, 1598.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="86">
<j>築城を急ぐ日本軍に対して、明軍と朝鮮軍は攻勢をかける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Troops of Ming and Korea attacked the Japanese army which had been hurrying up construction of castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming and Korea armies attacked the Japanese army which had been busy constructing the castles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming and Korea armies attacked the Japanese army which had been busy constructing the castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>12月22日、完成直前の蔚山倭城（日本式城郭）を明・朝鮮連合軍5万6,900人が襲撃し、攻城戦を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 22, allied forces of Ming and Korea consisting of 56,900 soldiers attacked Ulsan Waeseong (Japanese style castle), which was just before its completion, and began a siege.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 22, allied forces of Ming and Korea consisting of 56,900 soldiers attacked Ulsan Waeseong (Japanese style castle), just before its completion, and began a siege.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 29, 1598, allied forces of Ming and Korea consisting of 56,900 soldiers attacked Ulsan Waeseong (Japanese style castle), just before its completion, and began a siege.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>急遽入城した加藤清正を初め日本軍の堅い防御の前に大きな損害を被り苦戦を強いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, the allied forces suffered a big damage and faced an uphill battle because of strong defense by the Japanese army including Kiyomasa KATO who hurried to enter the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, the allied forces suffered a large casualties and faced an uphill battle because of the strong defense by the Japanese army including Kiyomasa KATO who hurried to enter the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, the allied forces suffered a large casualties and faced an uphill battle because of the strong defense by the Japanese army including Kiyomasa KATO who hurried to enter the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>そのため明・朝鮮連合軍は強襲策を放棄し、包囲戦に切り替える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the allied forces of Ming and Korea gave up smart attack and switched to a battle of encirclement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the allied forces of Ming and Korea gave up the attack and switched to a battle of encirclement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the allied forces of Ming and Korea gave up the attack and switched to a battle of encirclement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>このとき蔚山城は未完成であり、食料準備も出来ていないままの籠城戦で日本軍は苦境に陥る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the Ulsan Castle had not yet been completed and therefore the Japanese army was put in a difficult position with tact of holding the castle in which sufficient food had not been prepared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the Ulsan Castle had not yet been completed and therefore the Japanese army was put in a difficult position trying to hold the castle with insufficient food supplies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the Ulsan Castle had not yet been completed and therefore the Japanese army was put in a difficult position trying to hold the castle with insufficient food supplies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>年が明けた翌慶長3年（1598年）1月になると蔚山城は飢餓により落城寸前まで追いつめられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January of the next year (1598), the Ulsan Castle was run down to just before falling because of starving.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During January the following year (1598), Ulsan Castle was run down to just about to fall because of starvation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During February the following year (1598), Ulsan Castle was run down to just about to fall because of starvation.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし、1月3日毛利秀元等が率いる援軍が到着し、翌4日水陸から明・朝鮮連合軍を攻撃敗走させ2万人の損害を与えて勝利した（蔚山城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 3, however, rescue forces headed by Hidemoto MORI and so on arrived and, on the next day, January 4, attacked and routed the allied forces of Ming and Korea and caused a damage of 20,000 soldiers and won the battle (the Battle of Ulsan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 3, however, rescue forces headed by Hidemoto MORI and so on arrived and, on the next day, January 4, attacked and routed the allied Ming and Korean forces and caused 20,000 casualties and won the battle (the Battle of Ulsan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 8, however, rescue forces headed by Hidemoto MORI and so on arrived and, on the next day, February 9, attacked and routed the allied Ming and Korean forces and caused 20,000 casualties and won the battle (the Battle of Ulsan).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>戦いの後、宇喜多秀家など13人は、立地上突出している蔚山・順天・梁山の三城を援軍の困難さを理由として放棄する案を豊臣秀吉に上申しているが、秀吉はこれを却下し上申者を叱責した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this battle, thirteen commanders including Hideie UKITA submitted a proposal to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI on their plan to give up three castles, Ulsan, Suncheon and Yangsan, which were located in projecting positions, because of difficulty in sending a recue force, but Hideyoshi rejected this proposal and scolded those who made the proposal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this battle, thirteen commanders including Hideie UKITA submitted a proposal to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI on their plan to give up three castles, Ulsan, Suncheon, and Yangsan, located in projecting positions, because of the difficulty in sending a recue force, but Hideyoshi rejected this proposal and scolded those who made the proposal.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this battle, thirteen commanders including Hideie UKITA submitted a proposal to Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI on their plan to give up three castles, Ulsan, Suncheon, and Yangsan, located in projecting positions, because of the difficulty in sending a rescue force, but Hideyoshi rejected this proposal and scolded those who made the proposal.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="94">
<j>秀吉は翌慶長4年（1599年）の攻勢計画を発表していたが、秀吉が8月18日に死去すると戦役を続ける意義は失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hideyoshi announced the plan of attack in the next year, 1599, Hideyoshi died on August 18 and the significance of continuing the war disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hideyoshi announced the plan of attack during the next year, 1599, Hideyoshi died on August 18 and the significance of continuing the war disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hideyoshi announced the plan of attack during the next year, 1599, Hideyoshi died on October 7 and the significance of continuing the war disappeared.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>そのため五大老や五奉行を中心に、密かに朝鮮からの撤収準備が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the situations, preparations for retreat from Korea were commenced in secrecy by the Gotairo (Five Elders) and Gobugyo (five major magistrates).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under this situation, preparations for retreat from Korea were commenced in secrecy by the Gotairo (Five Elders) and Gobugyo (five major magistrates).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under this situation, preparations for retreat from Korea were commenced in secrecy by the Gotairo (Five Elders) and Gobugyo (five major magistrates).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>もっとも、秀吉の死は秘匿され朝鮮に派遣されていた日本軍にも知らされなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi&apos;s death was kept in secrecy and it was not informed to the Japanese army which had been dispatched to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Hideyoshi&apos;s death was kept secret and it was not even informed to the Japanese army which had been dispatched to Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Hideyoshi&apos;s death was kept secret and it was not even informed to the Japanese army which had been dispatched to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="97">
<j>9月に入ると明・朝鮮連合軍は蔚山、泗川市、順天へ総力を挙げた攻勢に出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, the allied forces of Ming and Korea began all-out attacks to Ulsan, Sacheon and Suncheon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, the Ming and Korean allied forces began all-out attacks to Ulsan, Sacheon and Suncheon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, the Ming and Korean allied forces began all-out attacks to Ulsan, Sacheon and Suncheon.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>迎え撃つ日本軍は沿岸部に築いた城の堅固な守りに助けられ、蔚山城の戦い第二次蔚山城の戦いでは明・朝鮮連合軍を撃退し防衛に成功。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The intercepting Japanese army was helped by strong defense with castles constructed in the coastal area and, in the second Battle of Ulsan, succeeded defense by beating back the allied forces of Ming and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The intercepting Japanese army was helped by the strong defense with castles constructed in the coastal area and, in the second Battle of Ulsan, succeeded by beating back the Ming and Korean forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The intercepting Japanese army was helped by the strong defense with castles constructed in the coastal area and, in the second Battle of Ulsan, succeeded by beating back the Ming and Korean forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>泗川の戦いは島津氏軍が明軍の火薬の暴発事故による混乱に乗じて一斉に突撃し、明・朝鮮連合軍に大打撃を与え潰走させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Suncheon, the troops of Shimazu clan made a rush by taking a chance in the confusion caused by accident of burst of gun powder of the troops of Ming and gave a big damage to and sent the allied forces of Ming and Korea. flying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Suncheon, the troops of the Shimazu clan made a rush by taking a chance in the confusion caused by an accidental burst of gun powder on the Ming side and inflicted large scale damage sending the Ming and Korean forces. flying.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Suncheon, the troops of the Shimazu clan made a rush by taking a chance in the confusion caused by an accidental burst of gun powder on the Ming side and inflicted large scale damage sending the Ming and Korean forces flying.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="100">
<j>順天を守っていたのは小西行長であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI was in charge of defense of Suncheon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinaga KONISHI was in charge of defense of Suncheon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI was in charge of defense of Suncheon.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>日本軍最左翼に位置するためあらたに派遣された明水軍が加わり水陸からの激しい攻撃を受けるが防衛に成功し、明・朝鮮連合軍を後退させた（順天城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was located in the extreme left wing of the Japanese camp, it was attacked fiercely both from the sea and land, but he succeeded the defense and made the allied forces of Ming and Korea retreat (the Battle of the Suncheon Castle).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was located in the extreme left wing of the Japanese camp, it was attacked fiercely both from sea and land, but he succeeded in defending their position and forced the Ming and Korean forces to retreat (the Battle of Suncheon Castle).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was located in the extreme left wing of the Japanese camp, it was attacked fiercely both from sea and land, but he succeeded in defending their position and forced the Ming and Korean forces to retreat (the Battle of Suncheon Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>明・朝鮮連合軍は順天倭城を遠巻きに監視するのみとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The allied forces of Ming and Korea changed their tactics to just watch Suncheon Waeseong without getting too close.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming and Korean forces changed their tactics to just watch Suncheon Waeseong without getting too close.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming and Korean forces changed their tactics to just watch Suncheon Waeseong without getting too close.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="103">
<j>蔚山、泗川、順天への攻勢を退けた日本軍であったが、既に秀吉は8月に死去しており戦争を継続する意義は失われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army repulsed attacks to Ulsan, Sacheon and Suncheon, but, as Hideyoshi had already died in August, the significance of continuing the war had been lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army repulsed attacks to Ulsan, Sacheon, and Suncheon, but, since Hideyoshi had already died in August, the significance of continuing the war had been lost.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army repulsed attacks to Ulsan, Sacheon, and Suncheon, but, since Hideyoshi had already died in October, the significance of continuing the war had been lost.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>そこでついに10月15日、秀吉の死は秘匿されたまま五大老による撤退命令が発令された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finally, on October 15, a withdrawal order in the name of Gotairo was issued keeping Hideyoshi&apos;s death in secrecy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finally, on October 15, a withdrawal order in the name of Gotairo was issued keeping Hideyoshi&apos;s death a secret.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finally, on December 2, a withdrawal order in the name of Gotairo was issued keeping Hideyoshi&apos;s death a secret.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>撤退命令を受領した小西行長は11月、明・朝鮮の陸水諸将と交渉や買収で無血撤退の約束を取り付ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having received the withdrawal order, Yukinaga KONISHI succeeded in November to obtain a promise of bloodless withdrawal through negotiations with and bribing of commanders of the army and navy of Ming and Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having received the withdrawal order, Yukinaga KONISHI succeeded in November to obtain a promise of bloodless withdrawal through negotiations with and by bribing the Ming and Korean commanders of the army and navy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having received the withdrawal order, Yukinaga KONISHI succeeded in December to obtain a promise of bloodless withdrawal through negotiations with and by bribing the Ming and Korean commanders of the army and navy.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>実際には明・朝鮮水軍は後退せずに海上封鎖を継続しており、海路撤退を妨害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, the navy of Ming and Korea did not retreat and continued naval blockage and obstructed withdrawal by sea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, the Ming and Korean navy did not retreat, but continued the naval blockage and obstructed withdrawal by sea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, the Ming and Korean navy did not retreat, but continued the naval blockage and obstructed withdrawal by sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="107">
<j>小西軍の脱出が阻まれてていることが確認されると泗川から撤退してきた島津義弘の他、立花宗茂、寺沢広高、宗義智らの諸将は救援に向かうために水軍を編成して進撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After confirming that the troops of Konishi clan was obstructed, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who had retreated from Sacheon, and other commanders such as Muneshige TACHIBANA, Hirotaka TERASAWA and Yoshitomo SO organized naval troops and made an attack to rescue the troops of Konichi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After confirming the Konishi clan troops ware obstructed, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who had retreated from Sacheon, and other commanders such as Muneshige TACHIBANA, Hirotaka TERASAWA and Yoshitomo SO organized the naval troops and made an attack to rescue the Konichi clan troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After confirming the Konishi clan troops were obstructed, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who had retreated from Sacheon, and other commanders such as Muneshige TACHIBANA, Hirotaka TERASAWA and Yoshitomo SO organized the naval troops and made an attack to rescue the Konishi clan troops.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>島津義弘の救援軍が近づくのを知ると明・朝鮮水軍は順天の海上封鎖を解いて迎撃を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing that Yoshihiro SHIMAZU&apos;s rescue forces were approaching, the navy of Ming and Korea lifted naval blockade of Suncheon and intercepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that Yoshihiro SHIMAZU&apos;s rescue forces were approaching, the Ming and Korean navy lifted their naval blockade of Suncheon and intercepted them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that Yoshihiro SHIMAZU&apos;s rescue forces were approaching, the Ming and Korean navy lifted their naval blockade of Suncheon and intercepted them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="109">
<j>この露梁海戦で島津水軍は苦戦したが、明・朝鮮も明水軍の副将、や朝鮮水軍の三道水軍統制使の李舜臣を含む複数の幹部が戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The navy of Shimazu clan had a hard time in this Naval Battle of Noryang, but, on the side of Ming and Korea, multiple top officials including the adjutant general of the navy of Ming and Yi Sun-sin, who was the Naval Commander of the Three Provinces of the navy of Korea died in war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu clan&apos;s navy had a hard time in the Naval Battle of Noryang, but on the side of Ming and Korea, multiple top officials including the adjutant general of the navy of Ming and Yi Sun-sin, who was the Naval Commander of Three Provinces of the navy of Korea died in this war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimazu clan&apos;s navy had a hard time in the Naval Battle of Noryang, but on the side of Ming and Korea, multiple top officials including the adjutant general of the navy of Ming and Yi Sun-sin, who was the Naval Commander of Three Provinces of the navy of Korea died in this war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>また、明・朝鮮水軍の出撃で順天の海上封鎖が解けたことを知った小西行長は海戦海域を避けて海路脱出に成功している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing that naval blockade of Suncheon was lifted because of sortie of the navy of Ming and Korea, Yukinaga KONISHI succeeded to escape by sea avoiding the marine area of the naval battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing that naval blockade of Suncheon was lifted because of the sorties of the Ming and Korean navies, Yukinaga KONISHI succeeded to escape by sea avoiding the area of the on-going naval battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing that naval blockade of Suncheon was lifted because of the sorties of the Ming and Korean navies, Yukinaga KONISHI succeeded to escape by sea avoiding the area of the on-going naval battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="111">
<j>こうして、日本の出征大名達は朝鮮を退去して日本へ帰国し、豊臣秀吉の画策した明遠征、朝鮮征服計画は成功に至らぬまま、秀吉の死によって終結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, daimyo who went war from Japan withdrew and returned to Japan and expedition to Ming and conquest of Korea intended by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was not achieved and ended by Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the daimyo that went to war from Japan withdrew and returned to Japan and the expedition to Ming and the conquest of Korea intended by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was not achieved and was ended by Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the daimyo that went to war from Japan withdrew and returned to Japan and the expedition to Ming and the conquest of Korea intended by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was not achieved and was ended by Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>戦役後の和平</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peace talk after the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peace talks after the war</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peace talks after the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>和平交渉は徳川家康によって委任を受けた対馬の宗氏と朝鮮当局の間で進められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peace talks were carried out between So clan in Tsushima, who was entrusted by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and the government of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peace talks were carried out between the So clan in Tsushima, who was entrusted by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and the government of Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peace talks were carried out between the So clan in Tsushima, who was entrusted by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and the government of Korea.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>断絶していた李氏朝鮮との国交を回復すべく、日本側から朝鮮側に通信使の派遣を打診したことにはじまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It began with approach to restoring diplomatic relations with Yi Dynasty Korea from Japan to Korea for sounding for dispatch of Tsushinshi (Emissary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It began with the approach to restore diplomatic relations with the Yi Dynasty in Korea from Japan to Korea for sounding out the dispatch of Tsushinshi (Emissary).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It began with the approach to restore diplomatic relations with the Yi Dynasty in Korea from Japan to Korea for sounding out the dispatch of Tsushinshi (Emissary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>征夷大将軍徳川家康と朝鮮側の使節との会見が実現したのは日本軍撤兵から6年後の慶長9年（1604年）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in 1604, six years after withdrawal of the Japanese army, that interview by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who was seii taishogun (lieterally, great general who subdues the barbarians), with an envoy from Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in 1604, six years after the withdrawal of the Japanese army, that an interview of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA took place, who was seii taishogun (lieterally, great general who subdues the barbarians), with an envoy from Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in 1604, six years after the withdrawal of the Japanese army, that an interview of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA took place, who was seii taishogun (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians), with an envoy from Korea.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>江戸幕府に対する朝鮮通信使が派遣されて正式の和平が果たされたのは慶長12年（1607年）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in 1607 that Chosen Tsushinshi to Edo bakufu (shogunate by Tokugawa clan) was despatched and formal peace was made.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in 1607 that Chosen Tsushinshi to Edo bakufu (shogunate by Tokugawa clan) was despatched and formal peace was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in 1607 that Chosen Tsushinshi to Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was dispatched and formal peace was made.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>明は日本と国交を結ばないまま滅亡し、明に代わって中国を支配するようになった清は、すでに日本が鎖国を取ったため貿易は行うが、正式な国交を持とうとはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ming was ruined without having diplomatic relations with Japan and Qing, which began to control China after Ming, because Japan adopted national isolation policy, conducted only tarade but had no official diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ming was ruined without having diplomatic relations with Japan and Qing, which began to control China after Ming, because Japan adopted a national isolation policy, conducted only trade, but had no official diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ming was ruined without having diplomatic relations with Japan and Qing, which began to control China after Ming, because Japan adopted a national isolation policy, conducted only trade, but had no official diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impacts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>休戦を挟んで6年に及んだ戦争は、朝鮮・日本・明の三国に重大な影響を及ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war which lasted for six years including a cease-fire period, effected serious impacts on Korea, Japan and Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war which lasted for six years including a cease-fire period, made a serious impact on Korea, Japan, and Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war which lasted for six years including a cease-fire period, made a serious impact on Korea, Japan, and Ming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>朝鮮半島への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impacts on Korean Peninsula</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact on the Korean Peninsula</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact on the Korean Peninsula</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>戦場となった朝鮮半島では日本軍、朝鮮軍、明軍の戦闘や駐留の他、統治不全によって治安が悪化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Korean Peninsula, which was the battle field, public safety was deteriorate because of disorderly governance in addition to battles between troops of Japan, Korea and Ming as well as their stay.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Korean Peninsula, which was the battle field, public safety deteriorate because of disorderly governance in addition to battles between troops of Japan, Korea, and Ming as well as their presence there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Korean Peninsula, which was the battle field, public safety deteriorate because of disorderly governance in addition to battles between troops of Japan, Korea, and Ming as well as their presence there.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>その為、不平両班や被差別階級、困窮した農民、盗賊による反乱、蜂起、及び朝鮮軍によるその鎮圧、また朝鮮王朝内部の政争による粛正や処刑などが行われ、混乱は戦災を更に悲惨なものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, revolts and uprising of discontented yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea), discriminated class, impoverished farmers and robbers occurred and got depressed by the army of Korea and cleanup and execution because of struggles for power in the Korean court were conducted and the such turmoil made war damages further miserable.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, revolts and uprising of discontented yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea), discriminated classes, impoverished farmers, and thieves occurred and got suppression by the Korean army during their cleanup and executions occurred out of struggles for power in the Korean court were conducted and the such turmoil created further misery in the midst of the war damage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, revolts and uprising of discontented yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea), discriminated classes, impoverished farmers, and thieves occurred and got suppression by the Korean army during their cleanup and executions occurred out of struggles for power in the Korean court were conducted and the such turmoil created further misery in the midst of the war damage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="120">
<j>李氏朝鮮は階級差別と搾取によって農民が春窮と呼ばれる毎年春に飢える状況が常態となっているほど生産性の低い統治を行っており、国土開発を怠っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Productivity of governance by Yi Dynasty Korea was so low that such situations as called shunkyu (literally, poverty in springtime) in which farmers starved in the spring time by class discrimination and exploitation and national land development was neglected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Productivity of governance by Yi Dynasty Korea was so low that such situations called shunkyu (literally, poverty in springtime) in which farmers starved in the spring time because of class discrimination and exploitation and national land development was neglected.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Productivity of governance by Yi Dynasty Korea was so low that such situations called shunkyu (literally, poverty in springtime) in which farmers starved in the spring time because of class discrimination and exploitation and national land development was neglected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>また、流通経済が発達しなかったため銀などの貨幣による売買が成立せず自給自足が基本の朝鮮民とは物々交換などで食料の調達を行わなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, as distribution economy had not developed, selling and buying using currency such as silver did not exist and procurement of food had to be conducted by barter exchange with Korean people who had been living by self-sufficient economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, as distribution economy had not developed, selling and buying using currency such as silver did not exist and procurement of food had to be conducted by barter exchange with Korean people who had been living by self-sufficient economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, as distribution economy had not developed, selling and buying using currency such as silver did not exist and procurement of food had to be conducted by barter exchange with Korean people who had been living by self-sufficient economy.</e>
<cmt>全角削除ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="122">
<j>戦争が開始され、日本軍・明軍・朝鮮軍による現地調達による食料消費と治安悪化のために農民が耕作を放棄することで流民が流民を生み、飢えた民衆は敵味方より略奪することで飢えを凌ごうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war began, because of consumption of foods by local procurement by troops of Japan, Ming and Korea and deteriorated safety, famers gave up cultivation and roaming people created further roaming people, and starved people tried to keep hunger at bay by robbing both from enemies and favors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war began, because of the consumption of food locally procured by troops of Japan, Ming, and Korea and the deteriorated safety, famers gave up cultivation and roaming people created further roaming people, and starved people tried to keep hunger at bay by robbing both from enemies and by obtaining favors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war began, because of the consumption of food locally procured by troops of Japan, Ming, and Korea and the deteriorated safety, farmers gave up cultivation and roaming people created further roaming people, and starved people tried to keep hunger at bay by robbing both from enemies and by obtaining favors.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>また、明軍と李氏朝鮮との交渉により鴨緑江より朝鮮側の兵糧供給は李氏朝鮮側の調達及び輸送と取り決められたため、自軍と政府の維持も含めて李氏朝鮮は民衆から過酷な食料調達を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it was decided in the negotiation between the army of Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea that, with respect to supply of provisions to the area on the Korea side from Yalu River, Yi Dynasty Korea was responsible for procurement and transportation, Yi Dynasty Korea conducted cruel procurement of goods from common people including maintenance of both their own army and the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it was decided in negotiations between the armies of Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea that, with respect to supply of provisions to the area on the Korea side from the Yalu River, Yi Dynasty Korea was responsible for procurement and transportation, Yi Dynasty Korea cruely conducted confiscation of goods and services from common people including maintenance of both their own army and the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it was decided in negotiations between the armies of Ming and Yi Dynasty Korea thet, with respect to supply of provisions to the area on the Korea side from the Yalu River, Yi Dynasty Korea was responsible for procurement and transportation, Yi Dynasty Korea cruelly conducted confiscation of goods and services from common people including maintenance of both their own army and the government.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>そのため、明軍の略奪と合わせて日本軍が一歩も足を踏み入れていない平安道も荒廃して開戦当初の人口を養いきれずに人口が激減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, together with despoliation by troops of Ming, even Pyeongan Province, in which no Japanese troops entered, went to pot and could not feed the population just before the commencement of the war and the population decreased drastically.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, together with despoliation by troops of Ming, even Pyeongan Province, in which no Japanese troops entered, went to pot and could not feed the population just before the commencement of the war and the population decreased drastically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, together with despoliation by troops of Ming, even Pyeongan Province, in which no Japanese troops entered, went to pot and could not feed the population just before the commencement of the war and the population decreased drastically.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="125">
<j>民衆は無秩序に食料を求めて朝鮮・明軍・日本軍を襲い、食料調達が不足した日本軍・明軍・朝鮮軍は朝鮮民衆から現地徴発を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common people attacked the troops of Korea, Ming and Japan disorderly looking for foods and the latter, which suffered short supply of foods, conducted local procurement from common people of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common people attacked the troops of Korea, Ming and Japan disorderly looking for food and the latter, which suffered short supply of food, conducted local procurement from common people of Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common people attacked the troops of Korea, Ming and Japan disorderly looking for food and the latter, which suffered short supply of food, conducted local procurement from common people of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>明軍に優先的に食料供給が行われたことから、朝鮮軍の戦意低下は少なからぬものがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As foods were supplied to the troops of Ming preferentially, fight of the Korean troops was degraded more than a little.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As food was preferentially supplied to the Ming troops, Korean troops ability to wage battle was quite degraded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As food was preferentially supplied to the Ming troops, Korean troops ability to wage battle was quite degraded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>戦役の後期から戦後の安全保障のための明軍の朝鮮駐屯による略奪なども横行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last stage of the war and, after the war, despoliation by the troops of Ming, which stationed for assuring safety even after the war widespread.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last stage of the war and, after the war, despoliation by the Ming troops, stationed for assuring security even after the war, was widespread.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last stage of the war and, after the war, despoliation by the Ming troops, stationed for assuring security even after the war, was widespread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>そのため、後に朝鮮の民衆の中には日本を一番の侵略者としながらも、明軍に対しても第二の侵略者として評する人間も出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, later, there were certain persons among Korean common people who, while naming Japan as the top invader, criticized the army of Ming as the second invader.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, later, there were certain persons among Korean common people who, while naming Japan as the top invader, criticized the Ming army as the second invader.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, later, there were certain persons among Korean common people who, while naming Japan as the top invader, criticized the Ming army as the second invader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="129">
<j>また戦時下での混乱により諸勢力による宮殿・王陵、官庁、文化財の破壊や略奪が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During confusion in wartime, various powers destroyed and despoiled palaces, tombs of kings, governmental offices and cultural properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During confusion in wartime, various powers destroyed and despoiled palaces, tombs of kings, governmental offices and cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During confusion in wartime, various powers destroyed and despoiled palaces, tombs of kings, governmental offices and cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>特に身分差別に苦しんだ朝鮮民衆は緒戦の混乱に乗じて官庁や被差別身分を示す書類を焼き払った例が朝鮮側資料により知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known from materials in Korea that Korean common people who suffered from discrimination by class set fire on the governmental offices and documents showing discriminated classes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known from materials in Korea that Korean common people who suffered from class discrimination set fire to governmental offices and documents on discriminated classes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known from materials in Korea that Korean common people who suffered from class discrimination set fire to governmental offices and documents on discriminated classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>また日本軍は治安を乱しゲリラ攻撃を仕掛ける義勇軍の抵抗に手を焼いたため、治安確保のために住民の虐殺や村の焼き討ちなどを行うことも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as Japanese troops had a hard time with resistance by voluntary army that disturbed the peace and conducted guerrilla attack, it often slaughtered inhabitants and burned villages in order to ensure security.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as Japanese troops had a hard time with the resistance that disturbed the peace and conducted guerrilla attacks, it often slaughtered inhabitants and burned villages in order to ensure security.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as Japanese troops had a hard time with the resistance that disturbed the peace and conducted guerrilla attacks, it often slaughtered inhabitants and burned villages in order to ensure security.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>戦功の証明として行われたはなそぎによってその後しばらくの間朝鮮に鼻のない人間が多く見られたということが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that, because of mutilation of nose conducted to prove military exploits, there were many persons in Korea who lost their nose for certain period after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is known from the mutilation of a person&apos;s nose done as evidence of their military exploits, there were many persons in Korea who lost their noses for certain period after that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is known from the mutilation of a person&apos;s nose done as evidence of their military exploits, there were many persons in Korea who lost their noses for certain period after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>しかしこれらは不穏民衆を一揆と認識して討伐した慶長の役が始まった後の話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this was conducted :only after the Keicho war began when disruptive people were recognize as insurgency.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this was conducted :only after the Keicho war began when disruptive people were recognized as members of the insurgency.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this was conducted only after the Keicho war began when disruptive people were recognized as members of the insurgency.</e>
<cmt>:削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>当初は朝鮮は戦後には支配下に繰り入れられるべき領土であり、日本の国内戦同様に非戦闘員である民衆は保護の対象であり殺戮は禁止されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, it was understood that Korea was the territory which should be included in the territories under control of Japan and, same as a war in Japan, common people who were noncombatants should be the object of protection and it was prohibited to kill them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, it was understood that Korea was a territory that should be included in the territories under control of Japan and, same as a war in Japan, common people who were noncombatants should be the object of protection and it was prohibited to kill them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, it was understood that Korea was a territory that should be included in the territories under control of Japan and, same as a war in Japan, common people who were noncombatants should be the object of protection and it was prohibited to kill them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>はなそぎも1597年の慶長の役の頃が主体であるが、これまで戦争全般を通じた蛮行であるがごとく語られてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutilation of nose was conducted mainly at the time of the Keicho War in 1597, but it has been told that it was act ob barbarism conducted throughout the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mutilation of a person&apos;s nose was conducted mainly during the time of the Keicho War in 1597, but it has been said that it was act of barbarism conducted throughout the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutilation of a person&apos;s nose was conducted mainly during the time of the Keicho War in 1597, but it has been said that it was act of barbarism conducted throughout the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>また戦後に咸鏡道に建てられた日本軍撃退記念碑の北関大捷碑には加坡の戦闘で斬殺した日本兵から左耳825個を切り取って朝鮮王へ送った記録が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Hokkantaishohi, which is a monument raised in Hangyong Province after the war to commemorate repulsion of the Japanese army, it is recorded that 825 left ears were cut from Japanese soldiers killed by sword in the battle in Kaba to the King of Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処；「加坡」の読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Hokkantaishohi, which is a monument raised in Hangyong Province after the war to commemorate repulsion of the Japanese army, it is recorded that 825 left ears were cut from Japanese soldiers killed by the sword in the battle in Kaba for the King of Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Hokkantaishohi, which is a monument raised in Hangyong Province after the war to commemorate repulsion of the Japanese army, it is recorded that 825 left ears were cut from Japanese soldiers killed by the sword in the battle in Kaba for the King of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>さらに、日本兵の首に賞金を掛けたため都市部で朝鮮軍・明軍による朝鮮領民の首無し死体が続出するなど荒廃した状況が伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as prize was offered for heads of Japanese soldier, it is reported blighted situations in which a large number of bodies without head of Korean people by the troops of Korea and Ming in urban district.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as a prize was offered for the heads of Japanese soldiers, it is reported there were situations in which a large number of bodies without heads of Korean people taken by the Korean and Ming troops in urban districts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as a prize was offered for the heads of Japanese soldiers, it is reported there were situations in which a large number of bodies without heads of Korean people taken by the Korean and Ming troops in urban districts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="138">
<j>戦役以後、総じて朝鮮人の間では日本に対する敵意が生まれ、平和な貿易関係を望む対馬の宗氏も朝鮮王朝に強く警戒され、日本使節の上京は禁じられ、貿易に訪れた日本人も釜山に設けられた倭館に行動を制限された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war in general, among Korean people, hostility against Japan was generated and the So clan which wished peaceful trade relationship was taken strong precautions, visit of Japanese diplomat to the capital was prohibited and Japanese people visited with the purpose of trading also restricted their activities and forced to stay in Wakan (consular office) established in Busan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war in general, among Korean people, hostility against Japan was generated and the So clan which wished a peaceful trade relationship took strong precautions, the visit of a Japanese diplomat to the capital was prohibited and Japanese people visited for the purpose of trading were also restricted in their activities and were forced to stay in Wakan (consular office) established in Busan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war in general, among Korean people, hostility against Japan was generated and the So clan which wished a peaceful trade relationship took strong precautions, the visit of a Japanese diplomat to the capital was prohibited and Japanese people visited for the purpose of trading were also restricted in their activities and were forced to stay in Wakan (consular office) established in Busan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>また日本人捕虜（降倭）の多くは、鉄輪をはめられ逃げ出すことも出来ない状態にされたうえで、その身分を賎民とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Japanese captives (kowa (literally, surrendered Japanese)) were put iron rings to prevent escaping and made their status as humble person.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Japanese captives (kowa - literally, surrendered Japanese) were put in iron rings to prevent them from escaping and this made their status as a humble person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Japanese captives (kowa - literally, surrendered Japanese) were put in iron rings to prevent them from escaping and this made their status as a humble person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="140">
<j>一方、朝鮮の両班階層（支配層）の間では明の援軍のおかげにより朝鮮は滅亡を免れたのだという意識（「再造之恩」）が強調され、明への恩義を重視する思想が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, among yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea) (ruling class) of Korea, understanding that Korea could narrowly avoid ruin thanks to reinforcement forces from Ming (&quot;再造之恩&quot;) was underscored and a thought to attach importance to gratitude to Ming spread widely.</e>
<cmt>「再造之恩」の意味不明につき、漢字のまま、表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, among yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea) (ruling class) of Korea, understanding that Korea could narrowly avoid ruin thanks to reinforcements from Ming (&quot;再造之恩&quot;) was underscored and the thought to attach importance to gratitude towards Ming spread widely.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, among yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea) (ruling class) of Korea, understanding that Korea could narrowly avoid ruin thanks to reinforcements from Ming (&quot;再造之恩&quot;) was underscored and the thought to attach importance to gratitude towards Ming spread widely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>これは後の明清交代期に於いて、清朝と明との間での朝鮮外交の針路に多大な影響を与えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later period of shifting from Ming to Quin, this gave an important impact on the track of foreign diplomacy between the Quin Dynasty and Ming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the later period in the shift from Ming to Quin, this made an important impact on the track of foreign diplomacy between the Quin Dynasty and Ming.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the later period in the shift from Ming to Quin, this made an important impact on the track of foreign diplomacy between the Quin Dynasty and Ming.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="142">
<j>また、文化面でも朝鮮半島に多大な影響をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the cultural aspects, great impacts were given to the Korean</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the cultural aspects, a great impact was given to the Koreans</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the cultural aspects, a great impact was given to the Koreans.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>南蛮貿易により日本にもたらされた唐辛子は、文禄・慶長の役の日本軍によって朝鮮半島にももたらされ、キムチ等の韓国・朝鮮料理の礎を築いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Red pepper, which was brought to Japan through trade with Spain and Portugal, was introduced to Korean Peninsula by the troops of Japan in the Bunroku-Keicho War and established the basis of Korean cuisine such as kimchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Red pepper, brought to Japan through trade with Spain and Portugal, was introduced to the Korean Peninsula by the troops of Japan in the Bunroku-Keicho War and established the basis of Korean cuisine such as kimchi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Red pepper, brought to Japan through trade with Spain and Portugal, was introduced to the Korean Peninsula by the troops of Japan in the Bunroku-Keicho War and established the basis of Korean cuisine such as kimchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>日本国内情勢への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impacts on domestic situations in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact on domestic situations in Japan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact on domestic situations in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="144">
<j>留守中の大名領地に太閤検地が行われ、豊臣政権の統治力と官僚的な集団が強化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiko kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey) was conducted for territories of daimyo who were absent and governing power and the bureaucratic group of the Toyotomi government ere strengthened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiko kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey) was conducted for territories of daimyo who were absent and the governing power and bureaucratic group of the Toyotomi government were strengthened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiko kenchi (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s nationwide land survey) was conducted for territories of daimyo who were absent and the governing power and bureaucratic group of the Toyotomi government were strengthened.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>しかし戦後にはこの戦争に過大な兵役を課せられた西国大名が疲弊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, however, Saigoku Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in western Japan), who suffered from too heavy military service for the war, were impoverished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, however, Saigoku Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in western Japan), having suffered from too heavy a military service for the war, was impoverished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, however, Saigoku Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in western Japan), having suffered from too heavy a military service for the war, was impoverished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>家臣団が分裂したり内乱が勃発する大名も出るなど、かえって豊臣政権の基盤を危うくする結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For certain daimyo, vassals were disunited, or internal insurrection occurred resulting in weakening the foundation of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For certain daimyo, vassals were disunited, or internal insurrection occurred resulting in weakening the foundation of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For certain daimyo, vassals were disunited, or internal insurrection occurred resulting in weakening the foundation of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="147">
<j>一方で、諸大名中最大の石高を持ちながら、関東移封直後で新領地の整備のために九州への出陣止まりで朝鮮への派兵を免れた徳川家康が隠然たる力を持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had the largest Kokudaka (assessed yield; tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain) among daimyo but as he had been moved to Kanto just before, he only headed troops to Kyushu but was exempted from going to Korea to fight in order to consolidate new territory, became to have latent powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had the largest Kokudaka (assessed yield; tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain) among daimyo, but as he had been moved to Kanto just before, he only headed troops to Kyushu, but was exempt from going to Korea to fight in order to consolidate new territory, came to have latent powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had the largest Kokudaka (assessed yield; tax system based on rice, measured by reference to the rated annual yield of the domain) among daimyo, but as he had been moved to Kanto just before, he only headed troops to Kyushu, but was exempt from going to Korea to fight in order to consolidate new territory, came to have latent powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>派兵を免れたことが徳川家康が後に天下を取る要因の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was exempted from sending troops to Korea was one of factors for Ieyasu to conquer the whole country</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was exempted from sending troops to Korea was one of factors allowing Ieyasu to conquer the whole country</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was exempted from sending troops to Korea was one of factors allowing Ieyasu to conquer the whole country.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="149">
<j>五大老の筆頭となった家康は秀吉死後の和平交渉でも主導権を握り、実質的な政権運営者へとのし上がってゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu, who became the top of Gotairo, gained the control of the peace talks after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and pushed his way up to the virtual operator of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu, who became the top of Gotairo, gained the control of the peace talks after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and pushed his way up to the virtual operator of the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu, who became the top of Gotairo, gained the control of the peace talks after Hideyoshi&apos;s death and pushed his way up to the virtual operator of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>この官僚集団と家康の急成長は、豊臣政権存続を図る官僚集団と次期政権を狙う家康との対立に発展し、関ヶ原の戦い（1600年）に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such rapid growth of the bureaucratic group and Ieyasu developed to confrontation between the beaurocratic group that tried to maintain the Toyotomi government and Ieyasu who had been lookin for the next government resulting in the Battle of Sekigahara (1600).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such rapid growth of the bureaucratic group and Ieyasu developed to confrontation between the beaurocratic group that tried to maintain the Toyotomi government and Ieyasu who had been looking to the next government resulting in the Battle of Sekigahara (1600).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such rapid growth of the bureaucratic group and Ieyasu developed to confrontation between the bureaucratic group that tried to maintain the Toyotomi government and Ieyasu who had been looking to the next government resulting in the Battle of Sekigahara (1600).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>戦いに圧勝した家康は日本国内で不動の地位を得、1603年に征夷大将軍に任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having achieved overwhelming victory, Ieyasu secured an impregnable position in Japan and he was apponted in 1603 to seii taishogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having achieved overwhelming victory, Ieyasu secured an impregnable position in Japan and he was apponted in 1603 to seii taishogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having achieved overwhelming victory, Ieyasu secured an impregnable position in Japan and he was appointed in 1603 to seii taishogun.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>こうして太平の江戸時代が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, peaceful Edo Period commenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, peaceful Edo Period commenced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, peaceful Edo period commenced.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="153">
<j>また、出兵に参加した大名たちによって連れてこられた朝鮮人儒学者との学問や書画文芸での交流、そして陶工が大陸式の磁器の製法、瓦の装飾などを伝えたことで日本の文化に新たな一面を加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New aspects were added to Japanese culture by intercommunion in scholarship and calligraphy and painting as well as creative writing with Korean Confucians who were brought to Japan by daimyo who took part in dispatch to Korea and transmission by potters of manufacturing process of continental ceramics and decoration of roof tiles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New aspects were added to Japanese culture by intercommunion in scholarship and calligraphy and painting as well as creative writing with Korean Confucians who were brought to Japan by daimyo who took part in dispatch to Korea and transmission by potters of manufacturing process of continental ceramics and the decoration of roof tiles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New aspects were added to Japanese culture by intercommunion in scholarship and calligraphy and painting as well as creative writing with Korean Confucians who were brought to Japan by daimyo who took part in dispatch to Korea and transmission by potters of manufacturing process of continental ceramics and the decoration of roof tiles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>その一方、多くの朝鮮人捕虜が戦役で失われた国内の労働力を補うために使役され、また奴隷として海外に売られたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, many Korean captives were roped into working as replacement of lost domestic labor for the war and some were sold overseas as slaves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, many Korean captives were roped into working as replacements of lost domestic labor for the war and some were sold overseas as slaves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, many Korean captives were roped into working as replacements of lost domestic labor for the war and some were sold overseas as slaves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>開国後の大陸進出への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impact of advance into the continent after opening of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact of the advance into the continent after opening of Japan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact of the advance into the continent after opening of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>江戸時代末期・明治時代の開国による外交関係の樹立から大陸情勢への関係が不回避となると、当時の武将達が三韓征伐を想起したように、秀吉の朝鮮出兵もクローズ・アップされるようになり、大陸への進出は豊臣秀吉公の遺志を継ぐ行いだと考えるものも多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When involvement in situations in the continent became inevitable as a result of establishment of diplomatic relationships by opening Japan in the last days of the Edo Period and the Meiji Period, same as commanders at the time of war were reminded of sankan-seibatsu (the conquest of three countries in old Korea), dispatch of troops by Hideyoshi became to be closed up and many became to consider advance into the continent was a conduct to follow Hideyoshi&apos;s wish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When involvement in situations in the continent became inevitable as a result of the establishment of diplomatic relationships by opening Japan in the last days of the Edo and the Meiji Periods, same as commanders at the time of war were reminded of sankan-seibatsu (the conquest of three countries in old Korea), dispatch of troops by Hideyoshi came to be closed up and many came to consider advancing into the continent was conduct following Hideyoshi&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When involvement in situations in the continent became inevitable as a result of the establishment of diplomatic relationships by opening Japan in the last days of the Edo and the Meiji periods, same as commanders at the time of war were reminded of sankan-seibatsu (the conquest of three countries in old Korea), dispatch of troops by Hideyoshi came to be closed up and many came to consider advancing into the continent was conduct following Hideyoshi&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>朝鮮併合がなった際、初代総督寺内正毅は『小早川、加藤、小西が世にあれば、今宵の月をいかにみるらむ（秀吉公の朝鮮征伐に参加された小早川・加藤・小西の諸将が今生きていれば、朝鮮を日本のものとしたこの夜の月をどのような気持ちでみられるだろうか）』と歌を詠み、外務部長だった小松緑はこれに返歌して、『太閤を地下より起こし見せばやな高麗（こま）やま高くのぼる日の丸（太閤殿下を蘇らせ見せ申し上げたいものだ、朝鮮の山々に高く翻る日の丸を）』と歌い、共に太閤の成し得なかった朝鮮の編入が成功したことを喜んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When annexation of Korea was completed, Masatake TERAUCHI who was the first Governor-General of Korea, composed a waka, &quot;If Kobayakawa, Kato and Konishi are alive, how they look the moon of tonight (If Kobayakawa, Kato and Koshinich, who were commanders took part in the war by Hideyoshi to conquer Korea are still alive, how they look the moon of today after obtaining Korea for Japan)&quot; and Midori KOMATSU who was the secretary of foreign affairs, composed in reply to it &quot;I would like to awake Taiko (Hideyoshi) from the underground and make him look at Hinomaru (national flag of Japan) above the mountains of Korea (I would like to revive Taiko and show him Hinomaru flaunting above mountains of Korea)&quot; and they were delighted at success to make annexation of Korea which Hideyoshi could not achieve.</e>
<cmt>「外務部長」は当時の正式英文表記が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When annexation of Korea was completed, Masatake TERAUCHI who was the first Governor-General of Korea, composed a waka, &quot;If Kobayakawa, Kato, and Konishi were alive, how would they look the moon of tonight (If Kobayakawa, Kato, and Koshinich, who were commanders took part in the war by Hideyoshi to conquer Korea were still alive, how would they look at the moon of tonight after obtaining Korea for Japan)&quot; and Midori KOMATSU who was the secretary of foreign affairs, composed in reply to it &quot;I would like to awake Taiko (Hideyoshi) from the underground and make him look at Hinomaru (national flag of Japan) above the mountains of Korea (I would like to revive Taiko and show him Hinomaru flaunting above mountains of Korea)&quot; and they were delighted at success to annex of Korea which Hideyoshi could not achieve.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When annexation of Korea was completed, Masatake TERAUCHI who was the first Governor-General of Korea, composed a waka, &quot;If Kobayakawa, Kato, and Konishi were alive, how would they look the moon of tonight&quot; (If Kobayakawa, Kato, and Konishi, who were commanders took part in the war by Hideyoshi to conquer Korea were still alive, how would they look at the moon of tonight after obtaining Korea for Japan) and Midori KOMATSU who was the secretary of foreign affairs, composed in reply to it &quot;I would like to awake Taiko (Hideyoshi) from the underground and make him look at Hinomaru (national flag of Japan) above the mountains of Korea&quot; (I would like to revive Taiko and show him Hinomaru flaunting above mountains of Korea) and they were delighted at success to annex of Korea which Hideyoshi could not achieve.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動スペル全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>明への影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Impacts on Ming</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Impact on Ming</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Impact on Ming</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>朝鮮への援兵を、同時期に行われた寧夏のボバイ、播州（四川省）の楊応龍の二人の辺境地方の地元民族首長反乱の鎮圧とあわせて、「万暦の三征」と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reinforcement troops for Korea was called &quot;Three Expeditions in Banreki Period&quot; together with suppressing two other concurrent uprisings by local ethnic chiefs, Bobai in Ningxia and You Ouryu in Banshu (Sichuan Province).</e>
<cmt>「ボバイ」、「楊応龍」、「播州」は正しい読み、綴りが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reinforcement troops for Korea were called &quot;Three Expeditions in the Banreki Period&quot; together with suppressing two other concurrent uprisings by local ethnic chiefs, Bobai in Ningxia and You Ouryu in Banshu (Sichuan Province).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reinforcement troops for Korea were called &apos;Three Expeditions in the Banreki Period&apos; together with suppressing two other concurrent uprisings by local ethnic chiefs, Bobai in Ningxia and You Ouryu in Banshu (Sichuan Province).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="158">
<j>これらの軍事支出と皇帝万暦帝の奢侈は明の財政を悪化させ、17世紀前半の女真の強大化に耐え切れないほどの、明の急速な弱体化の重要な原因となったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such military expenditure and extravagance by the emperor, Banreki, worsened financial conditions of Ming and it is considered to be the serious cause of rapid weakening of Ming that could not bear growth of Jurchen in the first half of the seventeenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such military expenditure and extravagance by the emperor, Banreki, worsened the financial conditions of Ming and it is considered to be a serious cause of rapid weakening of Ming that could not bear growth of Jurchen during the first half of the seventeenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such military expenditure and extravagance by the emperor, Banreki, worsened the financial conditions of Ming and it is considered to be a serious cause of rapid weakening of Ming that could not bear growth of Jurchen during the first half of the seventeenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>主な戦い（日付＝旧暦）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important battles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important battles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important battles (Date according to old lunar calendar)</e>
<cmt>以下旧暦の日付が続きますので、（日付＝旧暦）を補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="159">
<j>1592年（文禄元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1592</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1592</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1592</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>4月28日 忠州の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 28: Battle of Chungju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 28: Battle of Chungju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 28: Battle of Chungju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="160">
<j>小西行長対申リツ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Shin Ritsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Shin Ritsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Shin Ritsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>5月18日 臨津江の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 18: Battle of Imjin River</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 18: Battle of Imjin River</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 18: Battle of Imjin River</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>加藤清正対李陽元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO versus Yi Yanwon</e>
<cmt>「李陽元」は現地でのローマ字表記不明なため、仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa KATO versus Yi Yanwon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO versus Yi Yanwon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>6月5日 龍仁の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 5: Battle of Yongin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 5: Battle of Yongin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 5: Battle of Yongin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>脇坂安治対李洸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus Yi Gwang</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus Yi Gwang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus Yi Gwang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>7月8日 閑山島海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 8: Naval Battle of Hansan Island</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 8: Naval Battle of Hansan Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 8: Naval Battle of Hansan Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="163">
<j>脇坂安治対李舜臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuharu WAKISAKA versus Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>7月8日 梨峙の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 8: Battle of 梨峙</e>
<cmt>「梨峙」の読み、綴り共に確認できず、漢字表記のまま残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 8: Battle of 梨峙</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 8: Battle of 梨峙</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="164">
<j>小早川隆景対権慄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA versus Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA versus Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA versus Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>7月9日 （第1次）錦山の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 9: (First) Battle of Kumsan</e>
<cmt>「錦山」のローマ字綴りが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 9: (First) Battle of Kumsan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 9: (First) Battle of Kumsan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="165">
<j>小早川隆景対高敬命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA versus Ko Gyonmin</e>
<cmt>「高敬命」のローマ字綴りが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA versus Ko Gyonmin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA versus Ko Gyonmin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>7月17日 （第1次）平壌城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 17: (First) Battle of Pyeongyang Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 17: (First) Battle of Pyeongyang Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 17: (First) Battle of Pyeongyang Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="166">
<j>小西行長対祖承訓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Zu Chengxun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Zu Chengxun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Zu Chengxun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>8月18日 （第2次）錦山の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 18: (Second) Battle of Kumsan</e>
<cmt>「錦山」のローマ字綴りが確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 18: (Second) Battle of Kumsan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 18: (Second) Battle of Kumsan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="167">
<j>小早川隆景,立花宗茂,安国寺恵瓊対趙憲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Ekei ANKOKUJI versus</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Ekei ANKOKUJI versus</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Ekei ANKOKUJI versus 趙憲</e>
<cmt>原文からハイフン削除趙憲→表記不明</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>10月5日 晋州城攻防戦第一次攻防戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 5: First Battle of the Siege of Jinju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 5: First Battle of the Siege of Jinju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 5: First Battle of the Siege of Jinju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="168">
<j>細川忠興、長谷川秀一対金時敏,郭再祐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Hidekazu HASEGAWA versus Kim Si-min and Kwoak Che-u</e>
<cmt>「郭再祐」のローマ字綴りは確認できておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Hidekazu HASEGAWA versus Kim Si-min and Kwoak Che-u</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadaoki HOSOKAWA and Hidekazu HASEGAWA versus Kim Si-min and Kwoak Che-u</e>
<cmt>全角削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="169">
<j>1593年（文禄2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1593</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1593</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1593</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>1月6日 (第2次)平壌城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 6: (Second) Battle of Pyeongyang Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 6: (Second) Battle of Pyeongyang Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 6: (Second) Battle of Pyeongyang Castle</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="170">
<j>小西行長対李如松</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Li Ru-song</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Li Ru-song</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Li Ru-song</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>1月26日 碧蹄館の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 26: Battle of Byeokjegwan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 26: Battle of Byeokjegwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 26: Battle of Byeokjegwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="171">
<j>小早川隆景,立花宗茂,宇喜多秀家対李如松,查大受, 高彦伯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Hideie UKITA versus Li Ru-song, Cha Da Sho and 高彦伯</e>
<cmt>「高彦伯」の読み、ローマ字綴り共に確認できないため、漢字表記のまま残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Hideie UKITA versus Li Ru-song, Cha Da Sho and 高彦伯</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage KOBAYAKAWA, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Hideie UKITA versus Li Ru-song, Cha Da Sho and 高彦伯</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>2月12日 幸州山城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 12: Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 12: Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 12: Battle of Henju-Sanson (the Battle of Haengju)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>宇喜多秀家、石田三成対権慄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideie UKITA, Mitsunari ISHIDA versus Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideie UKITA, Mitsunari ISHIDA versus Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideie UKITA, Mitsunari ISHIDA versus Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>6月19日 晋州城攻防戦第二次攻防戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 19: Second Battle of the Siege of Jinju</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 19: Second Battle of the Siege of Jinju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 19: Second Battle of the Siege of Jinju</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="173">
<j>宇喜多秀家,黒田長政,加藤清正対崔慶会,金千鎰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideie UKITA, Nagamasa KURODA and Kiyomasa KATO versus 崔慶会 and 金千鎰,</e>
<cmt>「崔慶会」、「金千鎰」の読みが確認できないため、漢字表記のまま残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideie UKITA, Nagamasa KURODA and Kiyomasa KATO versus 崔慶会 and 金千鎰,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideie UKITA, Nagamasa KURODA and Kiyomasa KATO versus 崔慶会 and 金千鎰</e>
<cmt>原文からハイフン削除カンマ削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="174">
<j>1597年（慶長2年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1597</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1597</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1597</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>7月15日 漆川梁海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 15: Naval Battle of Chilcheollyang</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 15: Naval Battle of Chilcheollyang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 15: Naval Battle of Chilcheollyang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="175">
<j>藤堂高虎対元均</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatora TODO versus Won Gyun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatora TODO versus Won Gyun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatora TODO versus Won Gyun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>8月13日 南原城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 13: Battle of Namwon Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 13: Battle of Namwon Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 13: Battle of Namwon Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="176">
<j>宇喜多秀家対楊元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideie UKITA versus 楊元</e>
<cmt>「楊元」の読みが確認できないため、漢字表記のまま残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideie UKITA versus 楊元</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideie UKITA versus 楊元</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>9月7日 稷山の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 7: Battle of Jiksan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 7: Battle of Jiksan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 7: Battle of Jiksan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="177">
<j>黒田長政対解生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA versus 解生</e>
<cmt>「解生」の読みが確認できないため、漢字表記のまま残しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa KURODA versus 解生</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA versus 解生</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>9月17日 鳴梁海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 17: Naval Battle of Meiryo</e>
<cmt>「鳴梁」の読みが確認できないため、Wikipediaの日本読みにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 17: Naval Battle of Meiryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 17: Naval Battle of Meiryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="178">
<j>- 藤堂高虎対李舜臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatora TODO versus Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatora TODO versus Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatora TODO versus Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>12月21日（翌1月4日まで） 蔚山城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December 21 (until January 4, next year): Battle of Ulsan Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December 21 (until January 4, next year): Battle of Ulsan Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 21 (until January 4, next year): Battle of Ulsan Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="179">
<j>加藤清正,毛利秀元,黒田長政,小早川秀秋対楊鎬,麻貴,権慄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO, Hidemoto MORI, Nagamasa KURODA and Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA versus Yang Hao, Ma Gui and Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa KATO, Hidemoto MORI, Nagamasa KURODA and Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA versus Yang Hao, Ma Gui and Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO, Hidemoto MORI, Nagamasa KURODA and Hideaki KOBAYAKAWA versus Yang Hao, Ma Gui and Gwon Yul</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="180">
<j>1598年（慶長3年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1598</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1598</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1598</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>9月18日 順天の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 18: Battle of Suncheon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 18: Battle of Suncheon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 18: Battle of Suncheon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="181">
<j>小西行長対劉テイ,陳リン</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Ryu Tei and Chin Rin</e>
<cmt>「劉テイ、陳リン」のアルファベット表記が確認できないため、日本読みをローマ字表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Ryu Tei and Chin Rin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukinaga KONISHI versus Ryu Tei and Chin Rin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="33">
<tit>
<j>9月22日 （第2次）蔚山城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 22: (Second) Battle of Ulsan Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 22: (Second) Battle of Ulsan Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 22: (Second) Battle of Ulsan Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="182">
<j>- 加藤清正対麻貴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO versus Ma Gui</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomasa KATO versus Ma Gui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomasa KATO versus Ma Gui</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="34">
<tit>
<j>10月1日 泗川の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1: Battle of Sacheon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1: Battle of Sacheon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 1: Battle of Sacheon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="183">
<j>島津義弘対董一元</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU versus Ton Yi Yuan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU versus Ton Yi Yuan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU versus Ton Yi Yuan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="35">
<tit>
<j>11月18日 露梁海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 18: Naval Battle of Noryang</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 18: Naval Battle of Noryang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 18: Naval Battle of Noryang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="184">
<j>島津義弘,立花宗茂,宗義智対陳璘,李舜臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Yoshitomo SO versus Chin Rin and Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>「陳璘」のアルファベット表記が確認できず、Wikipediaの読みをローマ字表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Yoshitomo SO versus Chin Rin and Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, Muneshige TACHIBANA and Yoshitomo SO versus Chin Rin and Yi Sun-sin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 冬月(id:30384), Yasumi(id:44933), 経済準学士(id:22656), Jjok(id:55405), Eskimbot(id:29676), Dedede(id:30060), HI(id:72996), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), 直正(id:13317), Kamakura(id:472), Alex K(id:86829), Redpepper(id:58488), ＋－(id:17104), Swind(id:30993), らりた(id:1327), Jessew07(id:84758), Lulusuke(id:44392), Point136(id:211299), Bow(id:16755), Gowish(id:11130), Tsiyon Nassi(id:62513), DumZiBoT(id:230315), MystBot(id:224584), Yuno(id:36108), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Haeha(id:9372), 松茸(id:27535), Takehope(id:125033), 曹洞(id:110074), SSIG33(id:66434), Escarbot(id:59151), Applepeeler(id:75846), Necromania2(id:58921), TakuyaMurata(id:156), Sionnach(id:21673), Metatron(id:64025), Psfdiugw(id:216058), Mer du Japon(id:3789), Haiji(id:164968), Hotsuregua(id:99069), TT(id:46431), Resto1578(id:168692), Straysheep(id:42448), Reggaeman(id:6214), Caomengde(id:36165), Complement(id:245164), Rikumio(id:99645), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Kumatora(id:16941), Cap-001r(id:24379), Nakaoka7675(id:39645), Johncapistrano(id:969), Uraios(id:72687), Snow steed(id:9428), A6M4(id:14155), Dondokken(id:246411), Real Madrid(id:27490), An-chan(id:14590), Chobot(id:20846), Loveless(id:129239), Furansowakun2(id:211707), Kuranojoe(id:227801), Tenko(id:102318), Ryoske(id:34653), こぶまき(id:38278), VSA-itama(id:25395), Inori(id:90350), Jinzuu(id:60495), Tatsujin28(id:9300), LERK(id:4460), Izayohi(id:13095), Kcm367(id:97653), 水野白楓(id:22811), LaaknorBot(id:220851), Cave cattum(id:41235), Ongakutai(id:34103), Dent2000q(id:57770), 新茶(id:157775), VolkovBot(id:105371), Newport8865(id:71168), ソーセージ(id:30121), ウィキ太郎(id:81560), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 巴投(id:181114), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), Safkan(id:423), Tokugawa(id:61656), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>