<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小倉事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogura Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogura Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogura Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小倉事件（おぐらじけん）とは、延宝9年（天和_(日本)元年・1681年）に霊元天皇が皇位継承を巡って第1皇子である一宮（後の済深法親王）を強引に出家させてその外戚に当たる小倉家一族を粛清した事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ogura Incident was a dispute over succession of the imperial throne in which Emperor Reigen forced Ichinomiya (later Cloistered Imperial Prince Saishin), his oldest son, to become a Buddhist priest in 1681, and purged the greater imperial houosehold of the Ogura family, Ichinomiya&apos;s maternal relatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ogura Incident was a dispute over succession of the imperial throne in which Emperor Reigen forced Ichinomiya (later Cloistered Imperial Prince Saishin), his oldest son, to become a Buddhist priest in 1681, and purged the greater imperial houosehold of the Ogura family, Ichinomiya&apos;s maternal relatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ogura Incident was a dispute over succession of the imperial throne in which Emperor Reigen forced Ichinomiya (later Cloistered Imperial Prince Saishin), his oldest son, to become a Buddhist priest in 1681, and purged the greater imperial household of the Ogura family, Ichinomiya&apos;s maternal relatives.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>霊元天皇の正妃である女御（後に中宮）鷹司房子には男子がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyogo (a rank of imperial consort) Fusako TAKATSUKASA (later promoted to Chugu rank), legitimate spouse of Emperior Reigen, had no son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyogo (a rank of imperial consort) Fusako TAKATSUKASA (later promoted to Chugu rank), legitimate spouse of Emperior Reigen, had no son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyogo (a rank of imperial consort) Fusako TAKATSUKASA (later promoted to Chugu rank), legitimate spouse of Emperor Reigen, had no son.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そこで当時院政を敷いていた後水尾法皇と江戸幕府との間で密かに万が一鷹司房子に男子が生まれないままに天皇が崩御された場合の時には小倉実起の娘（中納言典侍・実名不詳）が生んだ第1皇子である一宮が継承するという合意が出来ており、天皇や摂関家などの有力公家の合意を取り付けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There had been an agreement between Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo, then taking the virtual reins of the court, and the Edo Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a nominally emperor-appointed Shogun) that, if Emperor Reigen died before Fusako TAKATSUKASA delivered a son, the Emperor&apos;s oldest son Ichinomiya born to a daughter (an unidentified Chunagon Naishi (a maid of honor to the Deputy Chief of the Councilor of State)) of Saneoki OGURA would inherit the throne, and this agreement had won consent of the Emperor and influential noble families including Sekkanke (families qualified for appointment as Prince Regent or Chief Advisor to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There had been an agreement between Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo, then taking the virtual reins of the court, and the Edo Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a nominally emperor-appointed Shogun) that, if Emperor Reigen died before Fusako TAKATSUKASA delivered a son, the Emperor&apos;s oldest son Ichinomiya born to a daughter (an unidentified Chunagon Naishi (a maid of honor to the Deputy Chief of the Councilor of State)) of Saneoki OGURA would inherit the throne, and this agreement had won consent of the Emperor and influential noble families including Sekkanke (families qualified for appointment as Prince Regent or Chief Advisor to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There had been an agreement between Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo, then taking the virtual reins of the court, and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a nominally emperor-appointed Shogun) that, if Emperor Reigen died before Fusako TAKATSUKASA delivered a son, the Emperor&apos;s oldest son Ichinomiya born to a daughter (an unidentified Chunagon Naishi (a maid of honor to the Vice-Councilor of State)) of Saneoki OGURA would inherit the throne, and this agreement had won consent of the Emperor and influential noble families including Sekkanke (families qualified for appointment as Prince Regent or Chief Advisor to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>スペルスペース削除&quot;Deputy Chief of the Councilor of State&quot;→&quot;Vice-Councilor of State&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>ところが、延宝3年（1674年）に第4皇子である五宮（後に朝仁親王と命名、後の東山天皇）が誕生すると、天皇は当時4歳の一宮よりも五宮に皇位を継がせたいと考えるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Gonomiya, the Emperor&apos;s fourth son (later Imperial Prince Asahito and still later Emperor Higashiyama) was born in 1674, the Emperor began to think of having Gonomiya, rather than four years old Ichibnomiya, succeed his throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Gonomiya, the Emperor&apos;s fourth son (later Imperial Prince Asahito and still later Emperor Higashiyama) was born in 1674, the Emperor began to think of having Gonomiya, rather than four years old Ichibnomiya, succeed his throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Gonomiya, the Emperor&apos;s fourth son (later Imperial Prince Asahito and still later Emperor Higashiyama) was born in 1674, the Emperor began to think of having Gonomiya, rather than four years old Ichinomiya, succeed his throne.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、一宮の生母である中納言典侍が皇子誕生以来体調を崩して実家に戻ったままになっていることも天皇の不満を抱かせていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor was also dissatisfied with the absence of Chunagon Naishi, Ichinomiya&apos;s real mother, who had returned to her native home after the birth of the prince and remained there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor was also dissatisfied with the absence of Chunagon Naishi, Ichinomiya&apos;s real mother, who had returned to her native home after the birth of the prince and remained there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor was also dissatisfied with the absence of Chunagon Naishi, Ichinomiya&apos;s real mother, who had returned to her native home after the birth of the prince and remained there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>延宝6年（1677年）、天皇は幕府の意向を確かめるべく江戸に使者を派遣するが、当時の征夷大将軍徳川家綱は法皇やその正妃東福門院（家綱の叔母）の同意のないこの提案には反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1677, the Emperor sent an envoy to Edo to know what the Bakufu&apos;s intention was, but Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, then Seii Taishogun (literally &quot;generalissimo who subdues the barbarians&quot;) objected to this proposal, which had not been approved by the Cloistered Emperor and his legitimate consort Tofukumonin (Ietsuna&apos;s aunt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1677, the Emperor sent an envoy to Edo to know what the Bakufu&apos;s intention was, but Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, then Seii Taishogun (literally &quot;generalissimo who subdues the barbarians&quot;) objected to this proposal, which had not been approved by the Cloistered Emperor and his legitimate consort Tofukumonin (Ietsuna&apos;s aunt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1677, the Emperor sent an envoy to Edo to know what the Bakufu&apos;s intention was, but Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, then Seii Taishogun (literally &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) objected to this proposal, which had not been approved by the Cloistered Emperor and his legitimate consort Tofukumonin (Ietsuna&apos;s aunt).</e>
<cmt>&quot;generalissimo&quot;→&quot;great general &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが、この年に東福門院が死去し、3年後に後水尾法皇と将軍家綱が相次いで病死すると、天皇は大覚寺にいた法皇の弟・性真法親王に一宮の弟子入りを新将軍徳川綱吉には一宮の出家と五宮への皇位継承を承諾を求める勅使を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Tofukumonin died in that year followed by successive deaths of Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo and Shogun Ietsuna from illness three years later, the Emperor sent imperial messengers to Cloistered Imperial Prince Shoshin, a younger brother of the Cloistered Emperor who was at the Daikaku-ji Temple then and to the new Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to obtain the former&apos;s acceptance of Ichinomiya as a disciple and the latter&apos;s consent to Gonomiya&apos;s proposed inheritance of the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Tofukumonin died in that year followed by the successive deaths of Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo and Shogun Ietsuna from illness three years later, the Emperor sent imperial messengers to Cloistered Imperial Prince Shoshin, a younger brother of the Cloistered Emperor who was at the Daikaku-ji Temple then and to the new Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to obtain the former&apos;s acceptance of Ichinomiya as a disciple and the latter&apos;s consent to Gonomiya&apos;s proposed inheritance of the throne.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Tofukumonin died in that year followed by the successive deaths of Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo and Shogun Ietsuna from illness three years later, the Emperor sent imperial messengers to Cloistered Imperial Prince Shoshin, a younger brother of the Cloistered Emperor who was at the Daikaku-ji Temple then and to the new Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to obtain the former&apos;s acceptance of Ichinomiya as a disciple and the latter&apos;s consent to Gonomiya&apos;s proposed inheritance of the throne.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>法親王は当初は反対したものの押し切られ、綱吉は就任早々の朝廷との関係悪化を嫌ってこれを承諾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cloistered Imperial Prince, at first against the proposal, was eventually persuaded and Tsunayoshi, wishing to avoid worsening of relations with the Imperial Court in the early days of his new position, also consented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cloistered Imperial Prince, at first against the proposal, was eventually persuaded and Tsunayoshi, wishing to avoid worsening relations with the Imperial Court in the early days of his new position, also consented.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cloistered Imperial Prince, at first against the proposal, was eventually persuaded and Tsunayoshi, wishing to avoid worsening relations with the Imperial Court in the early days of his new position, also consented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして延宝9年4月に一宮の大覚寺入りが正式に決定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in April 1670, it was formally decided to let Ichinomiya enter Daikaku-ji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in April 1670, it was formally decided to let Ichinomiya enter Daikaku-ji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in May and June 1670, it was formally decided to let Ichinomiya enter Daikaku-ji.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、外祖父にあたる小倉実起はこれに反対して一宮を自邸に匿ってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Howeer, Saneoki OGURA, maternal grandfather of Ichinomiya, sheltered the prince in his residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Saneoki OGURA, maternal grandfather of Ichinomiya, sheltered the prince in his residence.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Saneoki OGURA, maternal grandfather of Ichinomiya, sheltered the prince in his residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後も天皇は小倉家に決定の履行を迫るが小倉家側はこれを拒んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Emperor urged the Ogura family to honor the decision, but they refused to do so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Emperor urged the Ogura family to honor the decision, but they refused to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Emperor urged the Ogura family to honor the decision, but they refused to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>9月16日_(旧暦)、勅使阿野季信は小倉邸に赴き、直ちに一宮を参内させて天皇に出家の挨拶をするようにという趣旨の勅命を伝えるが小倉実起はこれを拒絶、9月17日_(旧暦)に再度訪れた阿野は一宮を連れ出そうとするも、事の異常さに気付いた一宮に感づかれて失敗に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 16th day of the 9th month (by old calendar), imperial messenger Toshinobu ANO visited Ogura&apos;s residence, and conveyed the mperial command to the effect that Ichinomiya should immediately visit the Imperial Palace and report his entrance into priesthood to the Emperor, only to meet an outright refusal by Saneoki OGURA; on his revisit on the 17th day of the 9th month (by old calendar), Ano tried to take Ichinomiya with him, but his attempt failed as the prince sensed the abnormality of the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 16th day of the 9th month (by old calendar), imperial messenger Toshinobu ANO visited Ogura&apos;s residence, and conveyed the imperial command to the effect that Ichinomiya should immediately visit the Imperial Palace and report his entrance into priesthood to the Emperor, only to be met by an outright refusal by Saneoki OGURA; on his revisit on the 17th day of the 9th month (by old calendar), Ano tried to take Ichinomiya with him, but his attempt failed as the prince sensed the abnormality of the situation.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 27, imperial messenger Toshinobu ANO visited Ogura&apos;s residence, and conveyed the imperial command to the effect that Ichinomiya should immediately visit the Imperial Palace and report his entrance into priesthood to the Emperor, only to be met by an outright refusal by Saneoki OGURA; on his revisit on October 28, Ano tried to take Ichinomiya with him, but his attempt failed as the prince sensed the abnormality of the situation.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これに激怒した天皇は阿野を閉門処分にして宮中警護の武士を小倉邸に派遣して同邸を制圧、一宮を飛鳥井雅豊邸に幽閉した上、幕府に対し小倉実起への処分を要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furiously angered by this outcome, the Emperor ordered to place Ano under house arrest, sent warriors guarding the Imperial Place to Ogura&apos;s residence, which was occupied by the warriors, confined Ichinomiya in the residence of Masatoyo ASUKAI, and requested the Bakufu to punish Saneoki OGURA and Saneoki&apos;s younger brother</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furious at this outcome, the Emperor ordered Ano under house arrest, sent warriors guarding the Imperial Place to Ogura&apos;s residence, which was occupied by the warriors, confined Ichinomiya in the residence of Masatoyo ASUKAI, and requested the Bakufu to punish Saneoki OGURA and Saneoki&apos;s younger brother</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furious at this outcome, the Emperor ordered Ano under house arrest, sent warriors guarding the Imperial Place to Ogura&apos;s residence, which was occupied by the warriors, confined Ichinomiya in the residence of Masatoyo ASUKAI, and requested the Bakufu to punish Saneoki OGURA.</e>
<cmt>and Saneoki&apos;s younger brother 原文にないので削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>綱吉は小倉の勅命違反の事実を重視して小倉実起と嫡男の小倉公連、その弟の竹淵季件を佐渡国へと流刑を命じ、藪家や中園家といった小倉家の同族に対しても逼塞を命じた（なお、この処分が決定する直前に天和への改元が以前からの予定通りに実施されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking Ogura&apos;s failure to obey the imperial command seriously, Tsunayoshi ordered to banish Saneoki OGURA, his legitimate son Kintsura OGURA and Kintsura&apos;s younger brother Kiken TAKEBUCHI to Sado Province, and relatives of Ogura including the Yabu and Nakazono families to block themselves in their respective houses (incidentally, immediately before these punishments, the imperial era name had been changed to Tenwa as scheduled beforehand).</e>
<cmt>竹淵季件の正しい読み方が分る資料が見つからないので、仮の読み方を記載します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking Ogura&apos;s failure to obey the imperial command seriously, Tsunayoshi ordered Saneoki OGURA banished, his legitimate son Kintsura OGURA and Kintsura&apos;s younger brother Kiken TAKEBUCHI to Sado Province, and relatives of Ogura including the Yabu and Nakazono families under house arrest (incidentally, immediately before these punishments, the imperial era name had been changed to Tenwa as scheduled beforehand).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking Ogura&apos;s failure to obey the imperial command seriously, Tsunayoshi ordered to banish Saneoki OGURA, his legitimate son Kintsura OGURA and Kintsura&apos;s younger brother Kiken TAKEBUCHI to Sado Province, and relatives of Ogura including the Yabu and Nakazono families under house arrest (incidentally, immediately before these punishments, the imperial era name had been changed to Tenwa as scheduled beforehand).</e>
<cmt>banishの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、この事態に後水尾法皇の側近であった左大臣近衛基熙と権大納言中院通茂が天皇に激しく抗議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this situation invived strong protests to the Emperor by Sadaijin (minister of the left) Motohiro KONOE and Gondainagon (Junior Chief of the Councilor of State) Michishige NAKANOIN, both close aides to Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this situation invited strong protests to the Emperor by Sadaijin (minister of the left) Motohiro KONOE and Gondainagon (Junior Chief of the Councilor of State) Michishige NAKANOIN, both close aides to Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this situation invited strong protests to the Emperor by Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Motohiro KONOE and Gondainagon (Junior Chief of the Councilor of State) Michishige NAKANOIN, both close aides to Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;minister of the left&quot;→&quot;Minister of the Left&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>特に以前武家伝奏として皇位継承問題に関与していた中院は天皇本人を前にして後水尾法皇と前将軍家綱が死んでから1年余りでその意向をひっくり返した天皇と綱吉を公然と罵ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially Nakanoin, who had been involved in the issue of imperial throne succession as a Buke Tenso (liaison officer between the Imperial Court and the Bakufu), abused the Emperor and Tsunayoshi, openly in the presence of the Emperor himself, for reversing the intention of Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo and former Shogun Ietsuna in only a little over one year after the deaths of both.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially Nakanoin, who had been involved in the imperial throne succession as a Buke Tenso (liaison officer between the Imperial Court and the Bakufu), abused the Emperor and Tsunayoshi, openly in the presence of the Emperor himself, for reversing the intention of Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo and former Shogun Ietsuna in only a little over one year after the deaths of both.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially Nakanoin, who had been involved in the imperial throne succession as a Buke Tenso (liaison officer between the Imperial Court and the Bakufu), abused the Emperor and Tsunayoshi, openly in the presence of the Emperor himself, for reversing the intention of Cloistered Emperor Gomizunoo and former Shogun Ietsuna in only a little over one year after the deaths of both.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>更に性真法親王もこの事態に驚いて弟子入りの拒絶を通告してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, surprised by this development, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shoshin himself refused to become an apprentice priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, surprised by this development, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shoshin himself refused to become an apprentice priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, surprised by this development, Cloistered Imperial Prince Shoshin himself refused to become an apprentice priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>だが、霊元天皇は年が明けて天和2年（1682年）に入ると、積極的に行動に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the turn of the year to 1682, however, Emperor Reigen took an offensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the turn of the year to 1682, however, Emperor Reigen took the offensive.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the turn of the year to 1682, however, Emperor Reigen took the offensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>2月14日_(旧暦)、空席になっていた関白の後任に左大臣近衛基熙ではなく、それより下位の右大臣一条冬経を任命する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 14 (old calendar), he filled the vacant position of Kampaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) with, instead of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Motohiro KONOE, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Fuyutsune ICHIJO, lower in rank than Konoye.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 14 (old calendar), he filled the vacant position of Kampaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) with, instead of Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) Motohiro KONOE, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Fuyutsune ICHIJO, lower in rank than Konoye.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 22, he filled the vacant position of Kanpaku (Chief Adviser to the Emperor) with, instead of Sadaijin Motohiro KONOE, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) Fuyutsune ICHIJO, lower in rank than Konoe.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル&quot;Sadaijin (Minister of the Left)&quot;→&quot;Sadaijin&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>続いて、3月25日_(旧暦)には五宮の次期皇位継承者（儲君）と鷹司房子の中宮擁立が発表され、その一方で8月16日_(旧暦)に一宮を大覚寺の代わりに勧修寺に入れて出家させされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then on March 25 (old calendar), nomination of Gonomiya as Chokun (heir to the Imperial Throne) and of Fusako TAKATSUKASA as Chugu was announced, while Ichinomiya was forced to become a priest at the Kaju-ji Temple, instead of Daikaku-ji, on August 16 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then on March 25 (old calendar), the nomination of Gonomiya as Chokun (heir to the Imperial Throne) and of Fusako TAKATSUKASA as Chugu was announced, while Ichinomiya was forced to become a priest at the Kaju-ji Temple, instead of Daikaku-ji, on August 16 (old calendar).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then on May 2, the nomination of Gonomiya as Chokun (heir to the Imperial Throne) and of Fusako TAKATSUKASA as Chugu was announced, while Ichinomiya was forced to become a priest at the Kaju-ji Temple, instead of Daikaku-ji Temple, on September 17.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にTemple補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>12月2日_(旧暦)には四宮の親王宣下が行われて「朝仁親王」の名が与えられ、翌3年（1683年）2月9日_(旧暦)には中世以来断絶していた立太子式が行われて朝仁親王が正式に皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 12 (old calendar), an imperial proclamation to nominate Shinomiya was issued, renaming him Imperial Prince Asahito, who was officially invested in crown princedom in the ceremony of investiture of the Crown Prince next year, on February 9 (old calendar), 1683, the first such rite after a long interval since the (Japanese) Medieval Age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 12 (old calendar), an imperial proclamation to nominate Shinomiya was issued, renaming him Imperial Prince Asahito, who was officially invested in crown princedom in the ceremony of investiture of the Crown Prince next year, on February 9 (old calendar), 1683, the first such rite after a long interval since the (Japanese) Medieval Age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 30, an imperial proclamation to nominate Shinomiya was issued, renaming him Imperial Prince Asahito, who was officially invested in crown princedom in the ceremony of investiture of the Crown Prince next year, on March 7, 1683, the first such rite after a long interval since the (Japanese) Medieval Age.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これは、崇光天皇の皇太子直仁親王（正平一統の際に吉野朝廷に捕えられて廃位）以来三百数十年ぶりの立太子であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the first such ceremony in well over 300 years since Emperor Suko&apos;s heir Imperial Prince Naohito had been invested in crown princedom (though this prince was arrested by the Yoshino Court on the occasion of Shohei Itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts) and dethroned).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first such ceremony in well over 300 years since Emperor Suko&apos;s heir Imperial Prince Naohito had been invested in crown princedom (though this prince was arrested by the Yoshino Court on the occasion of Shohei Itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts) and dethroned).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first such ceremony in well over 300 years since Emperor Suko&apos;s heir Imperial Prince Naohito had been invested in crown princedom (although this prince was arrested by the Yoshino Court on the occasion of Shohei Itto (temporal unification of the Northern and Southern Courts) and dethroned).</e>
<cmt>&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>貞享元年（1684年）佐渡にて小倉実起・公連父子が相次いで病死、さすがの霊元天皇もこれを憐れんで翌年に竹淵季件を赦免して小倉熙季と改名させて小倉家を再興する事を許した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1684, Saneoki and Kintsura OGURA, father and son, successively died of illness in Sado, a sad enough circumstance to tempt Emperor Reigen to remit Kiken TAKEBUCHI and had him change the name to Hirosue OGURA, who was permitted to restore the Ogura family.</e>
<cmt>前出同様、竹淵季件については仮の読み方を記載します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1684, Saneoki and Kintsura OGURA, father and son, successively died of illness in Sado, a sad enough circumstance to tempt Emperor Reigen to remit Kiken TAKEBUCHI and had him change the name to Hirosue OGURA, who was permitted to restore the Ogura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1684, Saneoki and Kintsura OGURA, father and son, successively died of illness in Sado, a sad enough circumstance to tempt Emperor Reigen to remit Kiken TAKEBUCHI and had him change the name to Hirosue OGURA, who was permitted to restore the Ogura family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>だが、貞享4年（1687年）中院通茂が先年の暴言の事実と皇太子への悪意の疑いで追放され（ただし、後年許されて霊元上皇と東山天皇の推挙で幕府から加増を受けている）、直後に朝仁親王（東山天皇）への譲位と院政開始を宣言する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1687, Michishige NAKANOIN was expelled for his abusive remark in the earlier year and suspected ill itention toward the Crown Prince (though he was remitted afterwards and his salaries from the Bakufu were increased at the recommendation of the retired Emperor Reigen and Emperor Higashiyama), and immediately after that the incumbent emperor declared the abdication of his throne in favor or Imperial Prince Asahito (now Emperor Higashiyama) and the start of his assumption of the virtual reins of the court as retired emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1687, Michishige NAKANOIN was expelled for his abusive remark earlier in the year and was suspected of ill intentions toward the Crown Prince (though he was remitted afterwards and his salaries from the Bakufu were increased at the recommendation of the retired Emperor Reigen and Emperor Higashiyama), and immediately after that the incumbent emperor declared the abdication of his throne in favor or Imperial Prince Asahito (now Emperor Higashiyama) and the start of his assumption of the virtual reins of the court as retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1687, Michishige NAKANOIN was expelled for his abusive remark earlier in the year and was suspected of ill intentions toward the Crown Prince (although he was remitted afterwards and his salaries from the Bakufu were increased at the recommendation of the Retired Emperor Reigen and Emperor Higashiyama), and immediately after that the incumbent emperor declared the abdication of his throne in favor or Imperial Prince Asahito (now Emperor Higashiyama) and the start of his assumption of the virtual reins of the court as retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;though&quot;→&quot;although &quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>ここに至って近衛基熙や江戸幕府は、霊元天皇による四宮擁立の真意が皇子可愛さだけではなく、院政を開始して摂家や幕府の干渉を排して思いのままの政治を行うための長期計画の一環であり、すぐに成人を迎えてしまう年長の一宮に皇位を譲る事が不都合であったからであった事に気付くのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This development made Motohiro KONOE and the Bakufu in Edo realize that the true motive underlying Emperor Reigen&apos;s insistence on succession by Shinomiya had not only been love of his own son but part of his long-cherished scheme to assume the virtual reins of the court as retired emperor and exercising ruling authority without allowing interference by the Sekkanke or the Bakufu, to whom handing over the imperial throne to the older Ichinomiya, who would soon become of age, would have been a disadvantage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This development made Motohiro KONOE and the Bakufu in Edo realize that the true motive underlying Emperor Reigen&apos;s insistence on succession by Shinomiya had not only been love of his own son but part of his long-cherished scheme to assume the virtual reins of the court as retired emperor and exercising ruling authority without allowing interference by the Sekkanke or the Bakufu, to whom handing over the imperial throne to the older Ichinomiya, who would soon become of age, would have been a disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This development made Motohiro KONOE and the Bakufu in Edo realize that the true motive underlying Emperor Reigen&apos;s insistence on succession by Shinomiya had not only been love of his own son but part of his long-cherished scheme to assume the virtual reins of the court as retired emperor and exercising ruling authority without allowing interference by the Sekkanke or the Bakufu, to whom handing over the imperial throne to the older Ichinomiya, who would soon become of age, would have been a disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>以後、院政を展開しようとする霊元上皇とこれを阻もうとする近衛基熙や江戸幕府との長い確執が始まる事になるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There ensued a prolonged feud between former Emperor Reigen, attempting to exercising virtual ruling authority as retired emperor, on one hand and Motohiro KONOE and the Bakufu in Edo trying to obstruct the retired Emperor&apos;s intention on the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There ensued a prolonged feud between former Emperor Reigen, attempting to exercising virtual ruling authority as retired emperor, on one hand and Motohiro KONOE and the Bakufu in Edo trying to obstruct the retired Emperor&apos;s intention on the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There ensued a prolonged feud between the Retired Emperor Reigen, attempting to exercising virtual ruling authority as retired emperor, on one hand and Motohiro KONOE and the Bakufu in Edo trying to obstruct the retired Emperor&apos;s intention on the other.</e>
<cmt>&quot;former Emperor Reigen&quot;→&quot;the Retired Emperor Reigen&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 踏蹟(id:51201), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>