<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東山御物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama gyomotsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama gyomotsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama gyomotsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東山御物（ひがしやまぎょもつ/ひがしやまごもつ）とは、室町幕府8代征夷大将軍足利義政によって収集された絵画・茶器・花器・文具などの称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; (it can be pronounced &quot;Higashiyama gomotsu&quot;) refers to the paintings, chaki (tea utensils), kaki (flower vase), stationery and other items collected by Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the eighth Sei taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; (it can be pronounced &quot;Higashiyama gomotsu&quot;) refers to the paintings, chaki (tea utensils), kaki (flower vase), stationery and other items collected by Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the eighth Sei taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama gyomotsu (Higashiyama gomotsu) refers to the paintings, chaki (tea utensils), kaki (flower vase), stationery and other items collected by Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, the eighth seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>文頭のクォーテーションマークを削除しました。幕府　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「東山」は、義政が山荘を営んだ東山の地に因む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama&apos; was taken from the name of place Higashiyama where Yoshimasa kept a mountain villa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama&apos; was taken from the name of the place Higashiyama where Yoshimasa kept a mountain villa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;Higashiyama&apos; was taken from the name of the place Higashiyama where Yoshimasa kept a mountain villa.</e>
<cmt>文頭に翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし、その中には室町幕府歴代将軍から継承された物が多数含まれ、また、江戸幕府歴代将軍の収集物が「柳営御物」と呼ばれるのに対する意味で、室町幕府歴代将軍の収集物全体を指して「東山御物」と呼ぶ場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the whole collection of the successive shoguns of the Muromachi bakufu is sometimes called &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu,&apos; as opposed to the collection of the successive shoguns of the Edo bakufu, which is called (Ryuei Gomotsu&apos; (the works of art for the tea ceremony passed down from the Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the whole collection of the successive shoguns of the Muromachi bakufu is sometimes called &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu,&apos; as opposed to the collection of the successive shoguns of the Edo bakufu, which is called (Ryuei Gomotsu&apos; (the works of art for the tea ceremony passed down from the Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the whole collection of the successive shoguns of the Muromachi bakufu is sometimes called &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu,&apos; as opposed to the collection of the successive shoguns of the Edo bakufu, which is called &apos;Ryuei gomotsu&apos; (the works of art for the tea ceremony passed down from the Tokugawa family).</e>
<cmt>括弧をクォーテーションマークに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、明治以前には「東山殿御物」・「東山殿之御物」・「東山殿御所持」などの呼称が用いられており、「東山御物」の4文字表記が出現するのは明治に入ってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Meiji era, names such as &apos;Higashiyama dono gyomotsu&apos; (東山殿御物), &apos;Higashiyama dono no gyomotsu&apos; (東山殿之御物), and &apos;Higashiyama dono goshoji&apos; (東山殿御所持) were used, and the four-character name &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; (東山御物) came into being in the early Meiji era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Meiji era, names such as &apos;Higashiyama dono gyomotsu&apos; (東山殿御物), &apos;Higashiyama dono no gyomotsu&apos; (東山殿之御物), and &apos;Higashiyama dono goshoji&apos; (東山殿御所持) were used, and the four-character name &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; (東山御物) came into being during the early Meiji era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Meiji period, names such as &apos;Higashiyama dono gyomotsu&apos; (東山殿御物), &apos;Higashiyama dono no gyomotsu&apos; (東山殿之御物), and &apos;Higashiyama dono goshoji&apos; (東山殿御所持) were used, and the four-character name &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; (東山御物) came into being during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>era →period としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、東山御物の称が普及したのは、創元社『茶道全集』（1936年発行）によるところが大きいとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a theory, the name &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; became familiar largely due to &quot;Sado Zenshu&quot; published by Sogensha (in 1936).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a theory, the name &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; became familiar largely due to &quot;Sado Zenshu&quot; published by Sogensha (in 1936).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a theory, the name &apos;Higashiyama gyomotsu&apos; became familiar largely due to &quot;Sado Zenshu&quot; (complete collection of Japanese tea ceremony) published by Sogensha (in 1936).</e>
<cmt>茶道全集→complete collection of Japanese tea ceremony　としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>義政の祖父にあたる足利義満や父の足利義教ら歴代将軍は唐物志向が強く、日明貿易により宋 (王朝)・元 (王朝)などの中国絵画（唐物）を収集し、「天山」「道有」などの鑑蔵院が押された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the successive shoguns including Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA (Yoshimasa&apos;s grandfather) and Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (Yoshimasa&apos;s father) had a strong taste for Karamono (things imported from China), they collected Chinese paintings (Karamono) through trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty, and the paintings were affixed a seal of Kango in (a collector&apos;s seal, which was impressed on Sung and Yuan period paintings) such as &apos;Tenzan&apos; and &apos;Doyu&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the successive shoguns including Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA (Yoshimasa&apos;s grandfather) and Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (Yoshimasa&apos;s father) had a strong taste for Karamono (things imported from China), they collected Chinese paintings (Karamono) through trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty, and the paintings were affixed with the seal of Kango in (a collector&apos;s seal, which was impressed on Sung and Yuan period paintings) such as &apos;Tenzan&apos; and &apos;Doyu&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the successive shoguns including Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA (Yoshimasa&apos;s grandfather) and Yoshinori ASHIKAGA (Yoshimasa&apos;s father) had a strong taste for Karamono (things imported from China), they collected Chinese paintings (Karamono) of Sung (dynasty), Yuan (dynasty), etc., through trade between Japan and the Ming Dynasty, and the paintings were affixed with the seal of Kanzo in (a collector&apos;s seal, which was impressed on Sung and Yuan period paintings) such as &apos;Tenzan&apos; and &apos;Doyu&apos;</e>
<cmt>宋、元　を追加しました。鑑蔵院　読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>義政期には唐物の管理や鑑定を行っていた同朋衆能阿弥にが「御物御画目録」（280幅、東京国立博物館所蔵）を編纂し、材質・形態別の分類を行い、画家や画題、賛者などを記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of reign of Yoshimasa, Noami, the doboshu (the shogun&apos;s attendants in charge of entertainment), who was responsible for the maintenance and appraisal of Karamono, compiled &apos;Gomotsu One Mokuroku&apos; (an inventory of selected Chinese paintings in the Ashikaga collection) (280 sets, owned by Tokyo National Museum), sorting the works by materials and styles, and recording the names of the painters, the subjects of the paintings and sanja (an assistant to a shonagon (minor councilor) in the Heian period)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of reign of Yoshimasa, Noami, the doboshu (the shogun&apos;s attendants in charge of entertainment), who was responsible for the maintenance and appraisal of Karamono, compiled &apos;Gomotsu One Mokuroku&apos; (an inventory of selected Chinese paintings in the Ashikaga collection) (280 sets, owned by Tokyo National Museum), sorting the works by materials and styles, and recording the names of the painters, the subjects of the paintings and sanja (an assistant to a shonagon (minor councilor during the Heian period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of reign of Yoshimasa, Noami, the doboshu (the shogun&apos;s attendants in charge of entertainment), who was responsible for the maintenance and appraisal of Karamono, compiled &apos;Gomotsu One Mokuroku&apos; (an inventory of selected Chinese paintings in the Ashikaga collection) (280 sets, owned by Tokyo National Museum), sorting the works by materials and styles, and recording the names of the painters, the subjects of the paintings and sanja (person who appreciates the work and writes appraisal in it).</e>
<cmt>賛者→「作品を鑑賞し、賛辞などを作品に書き込んだ人」という意味のようですので、sanja (person who appreicates the work and writes appraisal in it)　と変更しました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、能阿弥は他にも東山御物について撰述した『君台観左右帳記』を著している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noami also wrote &quot;Kumidaikansochoki&apos; (book of secrets about zashiki-kazari (decoration of room or study with shoin (one of Japan&apos;s most important residential architectural styles, established in Momoyama era))).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noami also wrote &quot;Kumidaikansochoki&apos; (book of secrets about zashiki-kazari or decorations of a room or study with shoin - one of Japan&apos;s most important residential architectural styles, established during the Momoyama era).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noami also wrote &quot;Kumidaikansochoki&apos; (book of secrets about zashiki-kazari or decorations of a room or study with shoin - one of Japan&apos;s most important residential architectural styles, established during the Momoyama era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>だが、応仁・文明の乱により散逸した物や諸大名に下賜されたり、幕府財政難のために土倉に売却されるなどして、地方に移ったものやそのまま行方不明になった物も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, quite a few works were moved to various provinces or gone missing, because they were scattered and ultimately lost during the Onin-Bunmei Wars, given away to territorial lords, or sold to doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) due to the economic difficulties of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, quite a few works were moved to various provinces or gone missing, because they were scattered and ultimately lost during the Onin-Bunmei Wars, given away to territorial lords, or sold to doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) due to the economic difficulties of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, quite a few works were moved to various provinces or gone missing, because they were scattered and ultimately lost during the Onin-Bunmei Wars, given away to territorial lords, or sold to doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders) due to the economic difficulties of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>安土桃山時代に入ると、義政を「茶道の祖」として崇敬する風潮が茶人の間で生まれ、東山御物の茶器が重んじられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Azuchi Momoyama period, a trend to revere Yoshimasa as the &apos;founder of tea ceremony&apos; started among the masters of tea ceremony, and the chaki (tea utensils) of Higashiyama gyomotsu came to be valued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Azuchi Momoyama period, a trend to revere Yoshimasa as the &apos;founder of tea ceremony&apos; started among the masters of tea ceremony, and the chaki (tea utensils) of Higashiyama gyomotsu came to be valued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Azuchi-Momoyama period, a trend to revere Yoshimasa as the &apos;founder of tea ceremony&apos; started among the masters of tea ceremony, and the chaki of Higashiyama gyomotsu came to be valued.</e>
<cmt>Azuchi-Momoyama としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>現代に残る東山御物の多くが国宝や重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the existing Higashiyama gyomotsu are designated as National Treasures or Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the existing Higashiyama gyomotsu are designated as National Treasures or Important Cultural Properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the existing Higashiyama gyomotsu are designated as national treasures or important cultural properties.</e>
<cmt>national treasures, important cultural properties 小文字で統一しています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>現存品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Existing works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Existing works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Existing works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>春景山水図（国宝、金地院所蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">View of spring landscape (National Treasure, owned by Konchi-in Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">View of spring landscape (National Treasure, owned by the Konchi-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunkei Sansui-zu (a drawing of spring landscape) (a national treasure, owned by the Konchi-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>national treasures, important cultural properties 小文字で統一しています。日本語を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>夏景山水図（国宝、久遠寺所蔵、東京国立博物館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakei Sansui-zu (a drawing of summer landscape) (National Treasure, owned by Kuon-ji Temple, deposition, Tokyo National Museum)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakei Sansui-zu (a drawing of summer landscape) (National Treasure, owned by the Kuon-ji Temple, deposition, Tokyo National Museum)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakei Sansui-zu (a drawing of summer landscape) (a national treasure, owned by the Kuon-ji Temple, deposition, Tokyo National Museum)</e>
<cmt>national treasures, important cultural properties 小文字で統一しています。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>冬景山水図（国宝、金地院所蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shukei Tokei Sansui-zu (drawings of autumn and winter landscape) (National Treasure, owned by Konchi-in Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokei Sansui-zu (drawings of autumn and winter landscape) (National Treasure, owned by the Konchi-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokei Sansui-zu (drawings of winter landscape) (a national treasure, owned by the Konchi-in Temple)</e>
<cmt>autumn は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>ほか</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>