<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>傀儡子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugutsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>傀儡子（くぐつ、傀儡とも言う）とは、9世紀頃から各資料に現れだした、諸国を旅し、芸能によって生計を営んでいた集団の事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugutsu is a group of people who traveled across the nation and made a living by performing arts, appearing on the records from around the nineth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugutsu were groups of people who traveled around the country and made a living in the performing arts, appearing on the records from around the 9th century.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugutsu were groups of people who traveled around the country and made a living in the performing arts, appearing on the records from around the ninth century.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>呪術等を用い、色々な芸能を行うことが出来、また特に人形を操っていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are said to have been able to make various performances, and especially, to have maneuvered puppets, using magic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are said to have used magic to conduct various performances, particularly the control of puppets.</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to reflect the source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are said to have used magic to conduct various performances, particularly the control of puppets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>傀儡師とも書き、女性の場合は傀儡女（くぐつめ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugutsu can be written in a different form of Kanji and the females were called Kugutsume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were also referred to as &apos;Kugutsushi&apos; and females were called &apos;kugutsume,&apos;</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to reflect the source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also written as kugutsushi (傀儡師) and females were called &apos;kugutsume.&apos;</e>
<cmt>漢字を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>その生活体系から、後の時代の、巫女、歌舞伎、市子、イタコ等との関連性が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given their way of living, their relevance with subsequent Miko (ladies serving the god), Kabuki (Japanese drama play), Ichigo(psychic ladies) and Itako(ladies with special religious ability) has been pointed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to their livelihood, their relationship to subsequent groups such as miko (shrine maidens), kabuki (Japanese classical drama) performers and ichigo (female fortune-tellers) has been identified.</e>
<cmt>Retranslated to reflect the source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to their livelihood, their relationship to subsequent groups such as miko (shrine maidens), Kabuki (traditional drama performed by male actors) performers, ichigo (female fortune-tellers) and Itako (The Japanese shaman) has been identified.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Libertas(id:40611), 与左衛門(id:159462), BAKU(id:55205), Suisui(id:69), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>