<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>太政官符</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijokan-pu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijokan-pu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijokanpu</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>太政官符（だいじょうかんぷだじょうかんぷ）は、日本の律令制のもとで太政官が管轄下の諸官庁・諸国衙へ発令した正式な公文書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijokan-pu was official documents issued by Daijokan (Department of State) to its lower agencies and Kokuga (local offices of the state) under the Ritsuyo system (ancient government system.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daijokan-pu were official documents issued by Daijokan (Department of State) to lower agencies and Kokuga (local offices of the state) under the Ritsuyo system (ancient government system.)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daijokanpu (also known as Dajokanpu) were official documents issued by Daijokan (Grand Council of State) to lower agencies and Kokuga (local offices of the state) under the Ritsuyo system (ancient government system).</e>
<cmt>補足を用語集に合わせ、ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>官符とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Kan-pu (official documents.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Kan-pu (official documents.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Kanpu (official documents).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>符とは、元来官庁が自己の管轄下にある下位の官庁に出す命令文書を指し、太政官以外の官庁でもこれを出すことが出来たが、太政官は原則として他の全ての官庁に対して符が出せたこと、格式のような重要な法令も太政官符の書式を用いて出されることがあったことから、極めて重みを有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;符&quot; (fu or pu) originally indicated the documents of orders and instructions that government agencies gave to their lower rank agencies, which meant that any agencies, including Daijokan, were able to issue it, but because Daijokan, in principle, was able to issue it to all the other agencies and the important laws like Kyakushiki (supplementary laws of Ritsuryo) were sometimes issued in the form of Daijokan-pu, it was taken very seriously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;符&quot; (fu or pu) originally indicated the documents of orders and instructions that government agencies gave to their lower rank agencies, which meant that any agencies, including Daijokan, were able to issue it, but because Daijokan, in principle, was able to issue it to all the other agencies and the important laws like Kyakushiki (supplementary laws of Ritsuryo) were sometimes issued in the form of Daijokan-pu, it was taken very seriously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pu (符, also referred as fu) originally indicated the documents of orders and instructions that government agencies gave to their lower rank agencies, which meant that any agencies, including Daijokan, were able to issue it, but because Daijokan, in principle, was able to issue it to all the other agencies and the important laws like Kyakushiki (supplementary laws of Ritsuryo code) were sometimes issued in the form of Daijokanpu, it was taken very seriously.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>この文書が各官庁、国衙などの政務機関に送られ、実務上の効力を発揮した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These documents were sent to the agencies and Kokuga and became practically effective.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These documents were sent to the agencies and Kokuga and became practically effective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These documents were sent to the agencies and Kokuga and became practically effective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>例えば、平安時代において荘園新立の承認を受けるには太政官符及び民部省符が必要とされており、こうした荘園を官省符荘と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, during Heian Period Daijokan-pu or Minbusho (ministry of taxation)-fu was needed to get approval to establish a new Shoen (manor) and these manors were called Kansho-fu-sho (government-approved) manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, during the Heian Period Daijokan-pu or Minbusho (ministry of taxation)-fu was needed to get approval to establish a new Shoen (manor) and these manors were called Kansho-fu-sho (government-approved) manors.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, during the Heian period Daijokanpu and Minbushofu (official documents issued by Minbusho [Ministry of Popular Affairs]) was needed to get approval to establish a new Shoen (manor) and these manors were called Kanshofu no sho (government-approved manors).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>太政官符は、天皇の裁可もしくは国政の枢要を担う太政官会議（議政官会議、公卿会議とも）での決定を受けて、弁官局で文書が作成され諸司諸国へ発給されるのが律令上の原則だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system, in principal, the draft of government&apos;s official documents was approved by the Emperor or Daijokan Conference (Giseikan-top bureaucrats or Kugyo-the noble Conference), then the document was produced by Benkankyoku (the agency directly belonged to Daijokan) and were delivered to central agencies and local government offices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Ritsuryo system, in principal, the drafts of government official documents were approved by the Emperor or Daijokan Conference (Giseikan-top bureaucrats or Kugyo-the noble Conference), then the document was produced by Benkankyoku (the agency that directly belonged to Daijokan) and were delivered to central agencies and local government offices.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system, in principal, the drafts of government official documents were approved by the emperor or Daijokan Conference (also referred as Giseikan [top bureaucrats] or Kugyo [court nobles] Conference), then the document was produced by Benkankyoku (the agency that directly belonged to Daijokan) and were delivered to central agencies and local government offices.</e>
<cmt>指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>律令初期は原則どおり議政官会議における決定を受けて太政官符が発給されたと考えられているが、平安中期頃になると、上卿（太政官筆頭）が主宰する陣定での決定をもとに太政官符が発給されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the early period under the Ritsuryo system, it is considered that Daijokan-pu was issued in accordance with the principles following the decision of Giseikan Conference, but in the middle of Heian Period Daijokanpu came to be issued based on Jin-no-sadame (one of the Imperial conferences) hosted by Shokei (the top official of Daijokan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the early period under the Ritsuryo system, it is considered that Daijokan-pu was issued in accordance with the principles following the decision of the Giseikan Conference, but in the middle of the Heian Period, Daijokanpu came to be issued based on Jin-no-sadame (one of the Imperial conferences) hosted by Shokei (the top official of Daijokan)</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the early period under the Ritsuryo system, it is considered that Daijokanpu was issued in accordance with the principles following the decision of the Giseikan Conference, but in the middle of the Heian period, Daijokanpu came to be issued based on Jin no Sadame (one of the Imperial conferences) hosted by Shokei (court novels who work at Imperial Court as high rank post) (the top official of Daijokan).</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>平安後期になると、官符よりも簡易な形態の官宣旨（かんせんじ）や院政下での院宣が主流となり、官符は廃れていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Heian period Kansenji (simplified Kan-pu) and Inzen (decree of cloistered government) under Insei (the cloistered government) became popular and Kanpu fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Heian period, Kansenji (simplified Kan-pu) and Inzen (decree of cloistered government) under Insei (the cloistered government) became popular and Kanpu fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Heian period, Kansenji (simplified Kanpu) and Inzen (decree of cloistered government) under Insei (the cloistered government) became popular and Kanpu fell into disuse.</e>
<cmt>用語表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 李(id:10582), BAKU(id:55205), MIsogi(id:20599), Greenland4(id:114494), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>