<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陸奥石川氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutsu Ishikawa clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mutsu Ishikawa clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutsu Ishikawa clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>石川氏（いしかわし）は、平安時代中期から戦国時代 (日本)の武家。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ishikawa clan was a samurai family from the mid-Heian period to the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ishikawa clan was a samurai family from the mid-Heian period to the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ishikawa clan was a samurai family from the mid-Heian period to the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は源氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original surname was Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original surname was Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan&apos;s original surname was Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家系は清和源氏の一流・大和源氏の一門、源頼親の子源頼遠を祖とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family was descended from a branch of Seiwa-Genji, a line of Yamato Genji, with MINAMOTO no Yorito, a son of MINAMOTO no Yorichika, the progenitor of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family was descended from a branch of Seiwa-Genji, a line of Yamato Genji, with MINAMOTO no Yorito, a son of MINAMOTO no Yorichika, the progenitor of the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family was descended from MINAMOTO no Yorito, a son of MINAMOTO no Yorichika, as the progenitor of the clan, in a line of Yamato Genji, a branch of Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>他氏との混同を避けるために陸奥石川氏と呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ishikawa clan was often called Mutsu Ishikawa clan so as not to be confused with other Ishikawa clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ishikawa clan was often called Mutsu Ishikawa clan so as not to be confused with other Ishikawa clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ishikawa clan was often called the Mutsu Ishikawa clan so as not to be confused with other Ishikawa clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>永承6年（1051年）、頼遠は子の源有光とともに陸奥守源頼義に従って奥州に下向、前九年の役に従軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1051, Yorito, together with his son MINAMOTO no Arimitsu, went down to Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces) following the Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi to serve in Zen Kunen no Eki (Former Nine Years&apos; Campaign)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1051, Yorito, together with his son MINAMOTO no Arimitsu, went down to Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces) following the Mutsu no kami (the governor of Mutsu Province) MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi to serve in Zen Kunen no Eki (Former Nine Years&apos; Campaign)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1051, Yorito, together with his son MINAMOTO no Arimitsu, went to Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces) following the Governor of Mutsu Province, MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi, to serve in Zen Kunen no Eki (Former Nine Years&apos; Campaign.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>厨川に戦死した頼遠に代わって有光が軍を指揮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yorito died in the battlefield of Kuriyagawa, Arimitsu headed the army in the place of Yorito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yorito died in the battlefield of Kuriyagawa, Arimitsu directed the army in place of Yorito.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arimitsu directed the army in place of Yorito, who was killed in the battlefield of Kuriyagawa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>康平6年（1063年）、有光はその軍功により従五位下安芸守に任じられ、陸奥国（後の磐城国）白河郡の地を下賜された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1063, Arimitsu was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Aki no kami (governor of Aki Province) and granted the land of Shirakawa-gun County in Mutsu Province (later Iwaki no kuni) for distinguished war service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1063, Arimitsu was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Aki no kami (governor of Aki Province) and granted the land of Shirakawa-gun County in Mutsu Province (later Iwaki no kuni) for distinguished war service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1063, Arimitsu was appointed to Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, Governor of Aki Province and granted the land of Shirakawa-gun County in Mutsu Province (later Iwaki no kuni) for distinguished war service.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>石川郷に三芦城を築城して居住し、それ以来石川氏を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He constructed Miyoshi-jo Castle in Ishikawa-go district and lived there, since then he had borne the family name Ishikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He constructed Miyoshi-jo Castle in Ishikawa-go district and lived there, since then he bore the family name Ishikawa.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He constructed Miyoshi-jo Castle in Ishikawa-go district and lived there, when he took the family name Ishikawa.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>第6代石川広季は、伊豆で源頼朝が平家討伐の兵を挙げたことを知り、寿永2年（1183年）、伯父光治率いる軍を鎌倉に送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the sixth head of the family Hirosue ISHIKAWA heard that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo raised the army of defeating the Taira family, he dispatched the army headed by his uncle Mitsuharu to Kamakura in 1183.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the sixth head of the family Hirosue ISHIKAWA heard that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo raised an army to defeat the Taira family, he dispatched an army headed by his uncle Mitsuharu to Kamakura in 1183.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the sixth head of the family Hirosue ISHIKAWA heard that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo raised an army to defeat the Taira family in Izu, he dispatched an army headed by his uncle Mitsuharu to Kamakura in 1183.</e>
<cmt>in Izu補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>文治4年（1188年）、奥州藤原氏攻めの為に白河関に到った頼朝は、石川の地にある川辺八幡宮に戦勝祈願を行い、三日間の滞在後に伊達郡厚樫山の戦場に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1188, when Yoritomo advanced to Shirakawa no seki (Shirakawa Barrier) for attacking the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, he visited the Kawabe Hachiman-gu Shine in the land of Ishikawa and prayed for a victory, and after three days&apos; stay, he headed for the battlefield of Atsukashi yama Mt. in Date-gun County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1188, when Yoritomo advanced to Shirakawa no seki (Shirakawa Barrier) to attack the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, he visited the Kawabe Hachiman-gu Shine in the land of Ishikawa and prayed for a victory, and after three days&apos; stay, headed for the battlefield of Atsukashi yama Mt. in Date-gun County.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1188, when Yoritomo advanced to the Shirakawa Barrier to attack the Oshu-Fujiwara clan, he visited the Kawabe Hachiman-gu Shrine in the land of Ishikawa and prayed for a victory, and after three days&apos; stay, headed for the battlefield of Mt. Atsukashi in Date-gun County.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>奥州を平定し、凱旋する途上で神料を寄進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo suppressed Oshu, and on his way of returning in triumph, he visited the shrine and offered a donation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo suppressed Oshu, and on his triumphant returh, visited the shrine and offered a donation.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo suppressed Oshu, and visited the shrine on his triumphant return to offer a donation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>第13代石川時光は、新田義貞による倒幕の軍に長子石川義光率いる軍を従わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thirtieth head of the family Tokimitsu ISHIKAWA sent the army headed by his eldest son Yoshimitsu ISHIKAWA to join the shogunate overthrowing army headed by Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thirtieth head of the family Tokimitsu ISHIKAWA sent an army headed by his eldest son Yoshimitsu ISHIKAWA to join the shogunate overthrowing army headed by Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimitsu ISHIKAWA, the thirtieth head of the family, sent an army headed by his eldest son Yoshimitsu ISHIKAWA to join the shogunate government overthrowing army headed by Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元弘3年（1333年）、鎌倉幕府が滅亡して建武の新政が成ると、上洛して新政権から従五位下宮内大輔に、翌建武 (日本)元年（1334年）に従四位下大膳大夫に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333, when the Kamakura shogunate fell and the Kenm Restoration started, Tokimitsu ISHIKAWA went up to Kyoto and was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Kunai-taifu (post of Imperial Household Ministry) by the new government, and Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) Daizen no daibu (Master of the Palace Table) in 1334.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333, when the Kamakura shogunate fell and the Kenm Restoration started, Tokimitsu ISHIKAWA went up to Kyoto and was appointed to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade) Kunai-taifu (post of Imperial Household Ministry) by the new government, and Jushiinoge (Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade) Daizen no daibu (Master of the Palace Table) in 1334.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) fell and the Kenmu Restoration started in 1333, Tokimitsu ISHIKAWA went up to Kyoto and was appointed to Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, the Imperial Household Secretary by the new government, and Junior Fourth Rank, Lower Grade, the Master of the Palace Table in 1334.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、鎌倉幕府との結びつきが強かったことを理由に新政府に冷遇され、第14代石川貞光の時、陸奥守北畠顕家は古来から石川氏が治めていた領地を結城家や和地氏に与える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, Ishikawa clan was coldly treated by the new government for the reason that it was closely tied with the Kamakura shogunate, and in the time of the fourteenth head of the family Sadamitsu ISHIKAWA, Akiie KITABATAKE distributed the fief traditionally inherited and controlled by Ishikawa clan to Yuki family and Wachi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, Ishikawa clan was coldly treated by the new government for the reason that it was closely tied with the Kamakura shogunate, and in the time of the fourteenth head of the family Sadamitsu ISHIKAWA, Akiie KITABATAKE distributed the fief traditionally inherited and controlled by Ishikawa clan to Yuki family and Wachi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the Ishikawa clan was treated coldly by the new government for the reason that it was tied closely with the Kamakura bakufu, and in the time of Sadamitsu ISHIKAWA, the fourteenth head of the family, the Governor of Mutsu Province, Akiie KITABATAKE, distributed the fief traditionally succeeded and controlled by Ishikawa clan to the Yuki family and the Wachi clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>貞光はこれを迎え撃つために軍を挙げるが敗れ、建武2年（1335年）に足利尊氏に従って北朝 (日本)方に属した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadamitsu raised the army to make a stand against that and got a defeat, and in 1335, he followed Takauji ASHIKAGA and took the side of Hokucho (the Northern Court) (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadamitsu raised the army to make a stand but was instead defeated, and in 1335, he followed Takauji ASHIKAGA and took the side of Hokucho (the Northern Court) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadamitsu raised the army to make a stand but was defeated instead, and in 1335, followed Takauji ASHIKAGA and took the side of the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>義光は足利軍の将として湊川の戦いに参戦、比叡山坂本の合戦において討ち死にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu participated in the Battle of Minatogawa as a leader of the Ashikaga army and died in the battlefield in the Battle of Hieizan Sakamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu participated in the Battle of Minatogawa as a leader of the Ashikaga army and died in the battlefield in the Battle of Hieizan Sakamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu participated in the Battle of Minatogawa as a leader of the Ashikaga army and was killled in the Battle of Hieizan Sakamoto.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>以後は旧領奪還を目指す石川氏と結城氏の間で激しい争いが繰り返された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, fierce battles were repeated between Ishikawa clan which aims to recover the former fief and Yuki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, fierce battles were repeated between Ishikawa clan which aimed to recover the former fief and Yuki clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, fierce battles were repeated between the Ishikawa clan, which aimed to recover the former fief, and the Yuki clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>第25代石川晴光は、永禄6年（1563年）、伊達晴宗の四男小二郎（後に石川昭光と改名）を養子に受け、家督を譲って隠居した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1563, the twenty-fifth head of the family Harumitsu ISHIKAWA adopted the fourth son of Harumune DATE, Kojiro (later, he was renamed to Akimitsu ISHIKAWA) and handed over the headship of the family to him and retired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1563, the twenty-fifth head of the family Harumitsu ISHIKAWA adopted the fourth son of Harumune DATE, Kojiro (later, he was renamed to Akimitsu ISHIKAWA) and handed over the head of the family to him and retired.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1563, Harumitsu ISHIKAWA, the twenty-fifth head of the family, adopted Kojiro (later, he was renamed Akimitsu ISHIKAWA), the fourth son of Harumune DATE and handed over the head of the family to him and retired.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>第26代昭光は天正18年（1590年）、豊臣秀吉による小田原攻めに参陣しない伊達政宗を憚って自らも援軍の派兵を見送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1590, the twenty-sixth head of the family Akimitsu ISHIKAWA shelved sending the reinforcements to the Invasion of Odawara headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, being afraid of Masamune DATE who did not participated in the invasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1590, the twenty-sixth head of the family Akimitsu ISHIKAWA shelved sending the reinforcements to the Invasion of Odawara headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, as he was afraid of Masamune DATE and did not participate in the invasion.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1590, Akimitsu, the twenty-sixth head of the family, postponed sending the reinforcements to the Invasion of Odawara headed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, as he was afraid of Masamune DATE who did not participate in the invasion.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし秀吉に恨まれ、奥州仕置によって領地は蒲生氏郷に与えられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi bore resentment against Akimitsu and transferred the fief of Ishikawa clan to Ujisato GAMO on the pretext of Oshu Shioki (approach to punish the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi bore resentment against Akimitsu and transferred the fief of Ishikawa clan to Ujisato GAMO on the pretext of Oshu Shioki (an approach to punish the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, and prevent them from strengthening their power).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi bore resentment against Akimitsu and transferred the fief of the Ishikawa clan to Ujisato GAMO on the pretext of punishment of the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu to prevent them from strengthening their power.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>老臣溝井六郎は秀吉に対して異心のないことを闡明することを主張するが、秀吉軍が迫る中で賛同する者はなく、ついに伊達家に仕えることを余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a senior vassal Rokuro MIZOI insisted on Akimitsu&apos;s clear assertion of harboring no treacherous designs to Hideyoshi, no one agreed on that as they had Hideyoshi&apos;s army gained ground on them; and at last, they were forced to serve the Date family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a senior vassal Rokuro MIZOI insisted on Akimitsu&apos;s clear assertion that he bear no treacherous designs against Hideyoshi, no one would agree on the matter; and at last, they were forced to serve the Date family.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A senior vassal Rokuro MIZOI insisted on Akimitsu&apos;s clear assertion that he bear no treacherous intentions against Hideyoshi, but nobody agree to that opinion; and at last, they were obliged to serve the Date family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>溝井は独り城に籠り、火を放って自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MIZOI entrenched himself in the castle by himself, set fire to the castle and committed suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MIZOI entrenched himself in the castle by himself, set fire to the castle and committed suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MIZOI entrenched himself in the castle alone, set fire to the castle and committed suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>昭光は慶長3年（1598年）、伊具郡角田1万石の領主となり、石川家の碑所である長泉寺を石川から移し、守護神である八幡神を石川から勧請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1598, Akimitsu became the lord of Kakuda in Igu-gun County for a million koku, moved Chosen-ji Temple which was ihaijo (site of a Buddhist mortuary tablet) of Ishikawa family from Ishikawa to the fief and did kanjo (ceremonial transfer of a divided tutelary deity to a new location) of Hachiman-shin (God of War) which was a guardian deity of the Ishikawa family from Ishikawa to the fief.</e>
<cmt>「牌所」は「位牌所」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1598, Akimitsu became the lord of Kakuda in Igu-gun County for a million koku, moved Chosen-ji Temple which was ihaijo (site of a Buddhist mortuary tablet) of Ishikawa family from Ishikawa to the fief and did kanjo (ceremonial transfer of a divided tutelary deity to a new location) of Hachiman-shin (God of War) which was a guardian deity of the Ishikawa family from Ishikawa to the fief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1598, Akimitsu became the lord of Kakuda in Igu-gun County, the land worthwhile a million koku of rice, moved Chosen-ji Temple, which was the site of a Buddhist mortuary tablet of Ishikawa family, from Ishikawa to the new fief, and did the ceremonial transfer of a divided tutelary deity to a new location of God of War, which was a guardian deity of the Ishikawa family, from Ishikawa to the new fief.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>この時、一族の中には昭光に従い角田に移ったものと、刀を捨て農民・商人として残るものとに分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On this occasion, some of the clan followed Akimitsu and moved to Kakuda, the others abandon swords and remained as farmers and merchants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, some of the clan followed Akimitsu and moved to Kakuda, the others abandoned the clan and remained as farmers and merchants.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, some members of the clan followed Akimitsu and moved to Kakuda, the others abandoned the samurai status and remained in Ishikawa as farmers and merchants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>慶長8年（1603年）、家督を嫡男石川義宗に譲るが、慶長15年（1610年）、義宗が34歳で没すると、昭光は角田城に戻って政務を執る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1603, Akimitsu handed over the headship of the family to his legitimate son Yoshimune ISHIKAWA, but in 1610 when Yoshimitsu died at the age of 34, Akimitsu returned to Kakuda Castle and attended to government affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1603, Akimitsu handed over the headship of the family to his legitimate son Yoshimune ISHIKAWA, but in 1610 when Yoshimitsu died at the age of 34, Akimitsu returned to Kakuda Castle and attended to government affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1603, Akimitsu handed over the headship of the family to his legitimate son Yoshimune, but in 1610 when Yoshimitsu died at the age of 34, Akimitsu returned to Kakuda-jo Castle and attended to government affairs.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>一族・庶流の分立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Separation of the Clan and the Illegitimate lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Separation of the Clan and the Illegitimate lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Separation of the clan and the illegitimate lineage</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>尊卑文脈によれば、有光～四代目の世代（鎌倉前期）の頃に、陸奥石川氏は一族・庶流の分立を進め、城・館を築き石川庄の村々に一族の地頭を配置していったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Sonpi Bunmyaku (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), in the period of the generations from Arimitsu to the fourth head of the clan (the early Kamakura period), Mutsu Ishikawa clan seems to have promoted separation of the clan and the illegitimate lineage, have built castles and residents and have posted jito (manager and lord of manor) of the clan in hamlets of Ishikawa-no-sho (village of Ishikawa).</e>
<cmt>「尊卑文脈」は「尊卑分脈」の誤りと思われますので、訂正して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Sonpi Bunmyaku (Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble), in the period of the generations from Arimitsu to the fourth head of the clan (the early Kamakura period), Mutsu Ishikawa clan seems to have promoted separation of the clan and the illegitimate lineage, have built castles and residents and have posted jito (manager and lord of manor) of the clan in hamlets of Ishikawa-no-sho (village of Ishikawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Lineage Sects of Noble and Humble, during the period of the generations from Arimitsu to the fourth head of the clan (the early Kamakura period), the Mutsu Ishikawa clan seemed to have promoted separation of the clan and the illegitimate lineage, have built castles and residents and have posted managers and lords of the manors of the clan in hamlets in the Ishikawa village.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Horlicks(id:62133), Rinseidou(id:220318), ５１６(id:45205), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>