<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>養和の飢饉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famine of Yowa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famine of Yowa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famine of Yowa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>養和の飢饉（ようわのききん）とは、1181年に発生した大飢饉。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famine of Yowa was a devastating famine that occurred in 1181.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The famine of Yowa was a devastating famine that occurred in 1181.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famine of Yowa was a devastating famine that occurred in 1181.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>源氏・平氏による争乱期（治承・寿永の乱）の最中に発生した飢饉であり、源平盛衰記や方丈記など当時の状況を詳細に記す史料も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The famine occurred during the period of conflict (Jisho-Juei War), and there remain many historical documents to describe the situation at that time in detail such as the Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans) and the Hojoki (An Account of My Hut).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The famine occurred during a period of conflict (Jisho-Juei War), and there remain many historical documents whicho describe the situation in detail such as the Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans) and the Hojoki (An Account of My Hut).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The famine occurred during a period of conflict (Jisho-Juei War), and there remain many historical documents which describe the situation in detail such as the Genpei Seisuiki (The Rise and Decline of the Minamoto and Taira clans) and the Hojoki (An Account of My Hut).</e>
<cmt>whicho→which</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>前年の1180年が極端に降水量が少ない年であり、干魃により農産物の収穫量が激減、翌年には京都を含め西日本一帯が飢饉に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rainfall in 1180 of the previous year was well below normal, and because of drought, the crop yields decreased significantly and the entire western Japan including Kyoto was plagued by famine in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rainfall in 1180 was well below normal, and crop yields decreased significantly due to drought, and the entire western Japan including Kyoto was plagued by famine the following year.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rainfall in 1180 was well below normal, and crop yields decreased significantly due to drought, and the entire western Japan including Kyoto was plagued by famine the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大量の餓死者は発生もちろんのこと、土地を捨てて逃亡する農民が多数発生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only did many people starve to death, but also a large number of farmers fled from their homes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only did many people starve to death, but also a large number of farmers fled from their homes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only did many people starve to death, but also a large number of farmers fled from their homes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>地域社会が崩壊し、混乱は全国的に波及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local communities collapsed and chaos spread across the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local communities collapsed and chaos spread across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local communities collapsed and chaos spread across the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>京都市中</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Within Kyoto City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within Kyoto City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>方丈記では、京都市中の死者を4万2300人とし、市中に遺体があふれていたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hojoki, it is described that 42,300 people died in Kyoto City, and that the city was filled with corpses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hojoki, it is written that 42,300 people died in Kyoto City, and that the city was filled with corpses.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hojoki, it is written that 42,300 people died in Kyoto City, and that the city was filled with corpses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>あまりの多さに供養が追いつかず、仁和寺の僧が死者の額に「阿」の字を記して回ったとも伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that because there were too many dead people to hold a memorial service for each of them, monks at the Ninna-ji Temple went around the city to mark the Sanskrit character &apos;a&apos; (,the first letter in the Sanskrit characters, 阿 in kanji) on the foreheads of the dead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that because there were so many dead people, it was impossible to hold a memorial service for each of them, monks at the Ninna-ji Temple went around the city to mark the Sanskrit character &apos;a&apos; (,the first letter in the Sanskrit characters, 阿 in kanji) on the foreheads of the dead.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that because there were so many dead people, it was impossible to hold a memorial service for each of them, monks at the Ninna-ji Temple went around the city to mark the Sanskrit character &apos;a&apos; (,the first letter in the Sanskrit characters, 阿 in kanji) on the foreheads of the dead.</e>
<cmt>本文にはない「阿」の説明がされていますが、残しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>こうした市中の混乱が、源義仲の活動（1180年挙兵、1183年上洛）を容易にする遠因となっていたことも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This chaos is believed to have been a remote cause of making MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s operations (raising of an army in 1180 and advancement to Kyoto in 1183) easier to carry out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This chaos is believed to have been a factor in making MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s operations (raising of an army in 1180 and advancement to Kyoto in 1183) easier to carry out.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This chaos is believed to have been a factor in making MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s operations (raising of an army in 1180 and advancement to Kyoto in 1183) easier to carry out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 かずー(id:174476), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>