<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>城米</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>城米（じょうまい）とは、本来は江戸幕府直轄地（いわゆる「天領」）からの年貢米を指すが、後に兵糧米のために幕府・譜代大名藩などに備蓄された米のことを指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomai originally means the annual rice tax from Edo bakufu directly controlled land (so-called &quot;tenryo&quot;), but later, it means the rice stocked by bakufu or fudai daimyo domain (a domain of a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) as a provisions of rice for the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomai originally means the annual rice tax from Edo bakufu directly controlled land (so-called &apos;tenryo&apos;), but later, it means the rice stocked by the bakufu or fudai daimyo domain (a domain of a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) as provisions of rice for the army.</e>
<cmt>指示書に従い、ダブルクォーテーションをシングルクォーテションに変更しました。Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。Provisionsの前のaを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomai originally means the annual rice tax from Edo bakufu directly controlled land (so-called &apos;tenryo&apos;), but later, it means the rice stocked by the bakufu or fudai daimyo domain (a domain of a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) as provisions of rice for the army.</e>
<cmt>‘ ’→ &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御城米（おしろまい）・城付米（しろつけまい）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called oshiromai or shirotsukemai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called oshiromai or shirotsukemai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called oshiromai or shirotsukemai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>享保15年（1730年）には、幕府直轄領の年貢米である城米と区別するために御用米（ごようまい）と改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By 1730, it was renamed as goyomai to distinguish it from jomai which means the annual rice tax of dominion under direct control of bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By 1730, it was renamed as goyomai to distinguish it from jomai which means the annual rice tax of dominion under direct control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By 1730, it was renamed as goyomai to distinguish it from jomai which means the annual rice tax of dominion under direct control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>原型は豊臣政権時代に存在し、城米奉行（じょうまいぶぎょう）が置かれて福島正則・毛利高政らが任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A prototype existed in the Toyotomi government era, and there was jomai bugyo (a magistrate of administering the annual rice tax), and Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Takamasa MOURI were appointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A prototype existed in the Toyotomi government era, where a position of jomai bugyo (a magistrate of administering the annual rice tax) was created and Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Takamasa MOURI were appointed.</e>
<cmt>3つの文章をすべてandでつなぐのは不自然なため、左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A prototype existed in the Toyotomi government era, where a position of jomai bugyo (a magistrate of administering the annual rice tax) was created and Masanori FUKUSHIMA and Takamasa MOURI were appointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸幕府でもその方針が継承されて直轄地からの年貢米の余剰を江戸城などに備蓄して有事の際には兵糧米とすることとなっていたが、寛永年間に入ると、その一層の充実が求められ、寛永10年（1633年）に譜代諸藩に対して幕府年貢米あるいは御用金を供給して米の備蓄・管理を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo bakufu succeeded this policy, and rice surpluses from the directly controlled land were stockpiled as provisions of rice for the army in case of emergency, and when Kanei era started, people wanted to make the system more perfect, so in 1633, fudai shohan (domains of hereditary vassals) were provided with the annual rice tax or goyokin (the money the Edo bakufu charged temporarily on farmers and merchants) and ordered to stockpile and administer the rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu succeeded this policy, stockpiling rice surpluses from the directly controlled land as provisions of rice for the army in case of emergency, and further expansion of the system was needed when Kanei era started, so fudai shohan (domains of hereditary vassals) were provided with the annual rice tax or goyokin (the money the Edo bakufu charged temporarily on farmers and merchants) and ordered to stockpile and administer the rice in 1633.</e>
<cmt>文の連結をスムーズにするために、二つ目の文章を変更しました。Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。寛永年間に入ると、その一層の充実が求められの部分をより自然な表現になるように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu succeeded this policy, stockpiling rice surpluses from the directly controlled land as provisions of rice for the army in case of emergency, and further expansion of the system was needed when Kanei era started, so fudai shohan (domains of hereditary vassals) were provided with the annual rice tax or goyokin (the money the Edo bakufu charged temporarily on farmers and merchants) and ordered to stockpile and administer the rice in 1633.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>3年後には江戸の浅草御蔵にも専用の施設が置かれて城米奉行が任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three years later, an exclusive institutuion was established in Asakusa okura in Edo, and jomai bugyo was appointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three years later, an exclusive institution was established in Asakusa okura in Edo, and jomai bugyo was appointed.</e>
<cmt>institutuionのミススペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three years later, an exclusive institution was established in Asakusa okura in Edo, and jomai bugyo was appointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幕府は城米奉行・譜代諸藩に対して、毎年城米の中身を入れ替えて有事に備えることを命じ、譜代藩の転封の際には引継ぎの一環として、法規通りの城米備蓄の有無と備蓄の方針の確認が求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu ordered jomai bugyo and fudai shohan to change the jomai every year and prepare for emergency, and when fudai domains changed the territory, they were required to check whether there is jomai stock based on regulations and the policy of the stock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu ordered jomai bugyo and fudai shohan to change the jomai every year and prepare for emergency, and when fudai domains changed the territory, they were required to check whether there is jomai stock based on regulations and the policy of the stock.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu ordered jomai bugyo and fudai shohan to change the jomai every year and prepare for emergency, and when fudai domains changed the territory, they were required to check whether there is jomai stock based on regulations and the policy of the stock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>以後、寛文元年（1661年）・貞享2年（1685年）にも城米備蓄の増加が命じられ、東海道の宿場町に対しても同様の措置を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, in 1661 and 1685, bakufu ordered to increase the jomai stock, and it also adopted the same measure to shukuba-machi (post station) in Tokaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, in 1661 and 1685, the bakufu ordered to increase the jomai stock, and it also adopted the same measure to shukuba-machi (post station) in Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, in 1661 and 1685, the bakufu ordered to increase the jomai stock, and it also adopted the same measure to shukuba-machi (post station) in Tokaido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>貞享2年の制によれば、全国に44.2万石の城米が備蓄され、江戸城・大坂城・二条城・駿府城と言った幕府直轄の城や譜代諸藩の城、東海道宿駅などの計68ヶ所に分散して備蓄されることになっており、また、延宝元年（1673年）には、幕府が民間の廻船を雇船して城米を指定の備蓄地へ輸送するための専用船（城米積船）とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the system of 1685, 442,000 koku (approximately 79.6 million liters of crop yield) of jomai was stocked all over Japan, and it was dispersively stocked in totally 68 places such as directly-controlled castles by bakufu (Edo-jo Castle, Osaka-jo Castle, Nijo-jo Castle, Sunpu-jo Castle) or shukueki (post town), and also, by 1673, bakufu hired private cargo-vessels and used them as dedicated vessels (jomai sekisen) to carry jomai to specified places where jomai was stocked.</e>
<cmt>「江戸城・大坂城・二条城・駿府城と言った幕府直轄の城」は一文で上手く訳せなかったので、「江戸城・大坂城・二条城・駿府城」を（）に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the system of 1685, 442,000 koku (approximately 79.6 million liters of crop yield) of jomai was stocked all over Japan, and it was dispersively stocked in totally 68 places such as castles in the bakufu directly-controlled lands or in fudai domains (the Edo-jo Castle, Osaka-jo Castle, Nijo-jo Castle, Sunpu-jo Castle) or shukueki (post town), and also, in 1673, the bakufu hired private cargo-vessels and used them as dedicated vessels (jomai sekisen) to carry jomai to specified places where jomai was stocked.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuとcastleの前にtheを入れました。譜代諸藩の城が抜けていたので入れました。By 1673をinに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the system of 1685, 442,000 koku (approximately 79.6 million liters of crop yield) of jomai was stocked all over Japan, and it was dispersively stocked in totally 68 places such as castles in the bakufu directly-controlled lands or in fudai domains (the Edo-jo Castle, Osaka-jo Castle, Nijo-jo Castle, Sunpu-jo Castle) or shukueki (post town), and also, in 1673, the bakufu hired private cargo-vessels and used them as dedicated vessels (jomai sekisen) to carry jomai to specified places where jomai was stocked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>城米積船は高額で雇船される代わりに幕府の厳重な管理下に置かれて城米以外の一切の物資の搬送を禁じられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomai sekisen were paid a large amount of money, but instead, they were strictly controlled by bakufu and they were prohibited from carrying things other than jomai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomai sekisen were paid a large amount of money, but instead, they were strictly controlled by the bakufu and they were prohibited from carrying goods other than jomai.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。Thingsをgoodsに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomai sekisen were paid a large amount of money, but instead, they were strictly controlled by the bakufu and they were prohibited from carrying goods other than jomai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>条件が厳格であったために次第に成り手に事欠くようになったために、寛保3年（1743年）には許可制ながらも空船時の一般貨物の搬送も許されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu&apos;s requirement was so strict that the number of jomai sekisen decreased, and then in 1743, bakufu allowed jomai sekisen to carry general cargo under its license system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakufu&apos;s requirement was so strict that the number of jomai sekisen decreased, and then in 1743, the bakufu allowed jomai sekisen to carry general cargo under its license system.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu&apos;s requirement was so strict that the number of jomai sekisen decreased, and then in 1743, the bakufu allowed jomai sekisen to carry general cargo under its license system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>当初、軍事目的のための備蓄米であった城米も長い間の平和のために次第に飢饉などの災害の救済や臨時の出費の際の財源に流用されるようになり、ついに元禄2年（1689年）には、幕府財政の赤字穴埋めのために備蓄量を寛文以前に戻し、その余剰を売却させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, because of the long-lasting peace, jomai which was stockpiled for the purpose of the military was gradually being used as a redress for the disaster such as famine, or diverted to the resources of extraordinary expenses, and finally, in 1689, bakufu put the criteria of stock back before Kanbun era to cover the deficit of its financial affairs, and sold the surplus rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, because of the long-lasting peace, jomai which was originally stockpiled for the purpose of the military was gradually being used as a redress for the disaster such as famine, or diverted to the resources of extraordinary expenses, and finally, in 1689, the bakufu put the criteria of stock back before Kanbun era to cover the deficit of its financial affairs and sold the surplus rice.</e>
<cmt>originallyをstockpiledの前に入れました。Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, because of the long-lasting peace, jomai which was originally stockpiled for the purpose of the military was gradually being used as a redress for the disaster such as famine, or diverted to the resources of extraordinary expenses, and finally, in 1689, the bakufu put the criteria of stock back before Kanbun era to cover the deficit of its financial affairs and sold the surplus rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>享保15年に城米が「御用米」と改められた背景には、実際には災害救済や財政調整のために用いられて軍事色が払拭されていた現状に応じたものであるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the background that jomai was changed to &quot;goyomai&quot; in 1730 is that practically, it was used for disaster relief or adjustment to finance and lose the meaning of military use, and thus, the meaning of the real situation was adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the background that led to the change of jomai to &apos;goyomai&apos; in 1730 was closely related to the actual situation of the time where the stock was used for disaster relief or financial adjustment and military significance was faded.</e>
<cmt>自然な表現にするために左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the background that led to the change of jomai to &apos;goyomai&apos; in 1730 was closely related to the actual situation of the time where the stock was used for disaster relief or financial adjustment and military significance was faded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後、享保の大飢饉や天明の大飢饉の救済のためにも御用米が活用されたが、松平定信の寛政の改革では、囲米を導入して御用米の役目を代行させ、御用米を当初の軍事専用に復帰させようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later on, goyomai was used to relieve the Great Famine of Kyoho or the Tenmei Famine, but in Kansei reform by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, kakoimai (it refers to the system where rice was stored by bakufu, clans and towns and villages in case of emergency) was introduced as a substitute for goyomai and bakufu tried to revive original goyomai again for military use only, but it was still being used as a purpose of disaster relief or finance because the situation of bakufu&apos;s finance was getting worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later on, goyomai was used to relieve the Great Famine of Kyoho or the Tenmei Famine, but in Kansei reform by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, kakoimai (it refers to the system where rice was stored by the bakufu, clans and towns and villages in case of emergency) was introduced as a substitute for goyomai and the bakufu tried to revive original goyomai used for military purpose only.</e>
<cmt>Bakufuの前にtheを入れました。一文が長くなりすぎて、不自然なひょうげんになっているので、二文に分けました。一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later on, goyomai was used to relieve the Great Famine of Kyoho or the Tenmei Famine, but in Kansei reform by Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, kakoimai (it refers to the system where rice was stored by the bakufu, clans and towns and villages in case of emergency) was introduced as a substitute for goyomai and the bakufu tried to revive original goyomai used for military purpose only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、幕府財政の悪化などによって依然として、災害や財政目的での利用が続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was still being used as a purpose of disaster relief or finance because the situation of the bakufu&apos;s finance was getting worse.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was still being used as a purpose of disaster relief or finance because the situation of the bakufu&apos;s finance was getting worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>