<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>享禄・天文の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>享禄・天文の乱（きょうろく・てんぶんのらん）は、戦国時代_(日本)初期の浄土真宗本願寺宗門における教団改革を巡る内紛と、これに触発されて発生した対外戦争の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion is a general term of both the internal conflict within the Hongan-ji Temple sect of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) over the sectarian reform in the early Sengoku Period and the external war provoked by the conflict.</e>
<cmt>Wikiの方には「_(日本)」の記述はないので翻訳していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion is the general term for the internal conflict within the Hongan-ji Temple sect of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) over the sectarian reform in the early Sengoku Period and the external war provoked by the conflict.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion is the general term for the internal conflict within the Hongan-ji Temple sect of Jodo Shinshu (the True Pure Land Sect of Buddhism) over the sectarian reform in the early Sengoku Period and the external war provoked by the conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>享禄4年（1531年）の享禄の錯乱（きょうろくのさくらん）または大小一揆（だいしょういっき）と呼ばれる内紛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An internal conflict called the Kyoroku War or Daisho Ikki (the Big League-Little League War) that occurred in 1531</e>
<cmt>・Wikipediaでは、箇条書きになっているので、名詞句にしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An internal conflict called the Kyoroku War or Daisho Ikki (the Big League-Little League War) in 1531</e>
<cmt>不要な訳は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An internal conflict called the Kyoroku War or Daisho Ikki (the Big League-Little League War) in 1531</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>天文_(元号)元年（1532年）から同4年（1535年）の細川氏・畠山氏などとの戦いである天文の錯乱（てんぶんのさくらん）または天文の乱（てんぶんのらん）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A war against the Hosokawa and Hatakeyama clans called the Tenbun War or the Tenbun Rebellion that occurred from 1532 to 1535</e>
<cmt>・Wikipediaでは、箇条書きになっているので、名詞句にしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A war against the Hosokawa and Hatakeyama clans called the Tenbun War or the Tenbun Rebellion from 1532 to 1535</e>
<cmt>不要な訳とスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A war against the Hosokawa and Hatakeyama clans called the Tenbun War or the Tenbun Rebellion from 1532 to 1535</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>上記2つからなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion refers to these two events mentioned above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion refers to these two events mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kyoroku-Tenbun Rebellion refers to these two events mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>この2つの戦いを一括りにすることの是非については、議論の余地があるものの、両者とも本願寺10世証如と、その後見人蓮淳（8世蓮如の6男で証如の外祖父であり大叔父でもある）による法主の権限強化を図った政策方針の末に生じた出来事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is disputable to treat these two wars as one historical event, but both wars happened as a result of the policy by which Shonyo, 10th chief priest of Honganji-Temple, and his guardian Renjun (the 6th son of Rennyo, the 8th chief priest, and also both a maternal grandfather and a grand-uncle of Shonyo) tried to strengthen the authority of hoshu (a head of a Buddhist sect).</e>
<cmt>・括弧内の文章が句点で分かれていたので、11行目の文章とつなげて、一文に変更しました。・序数、年齢、年号、大きい数字には算用数字を使っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is disputable to treat these two wars as one historical event, but both wars happened as a result of the policy by which Shonyo, the 10th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, and his guardian Renjun (the 6th son of Rennyo, the 8th chief priest, and also both a maternal grandfather and a grand-uncle of Shonyo) tried to strengthen the authority of hoshu (a head of a Buddhist sect).</e>
<cmt>本願寺の書き方を修正しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is disputable to treat these two wars as one historical event, but both wars happened as a result of the policy by which Shonyo, the 10th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, and his guardian Renjun (the 6th son of Rennyo, the 8th chief priest, and also both a maternal grandfather and a grand-uncle of Shonyo) tried to strengthen the authority of hoshu (a head of a Buddhist sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、後者は日蓮宗における「法華一揆」と重複している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the Tenbun Rebellion overlaps &apos;the Hokke uprising&apos; by the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, the Tenbun Rebellion overlaps with &apos;the Hokke uprising&apos; by the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, the Tenbun Rebellion overlaps with &apos;the Hokke uprising&apos; by the Nichiren sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>蓮如の一門政策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sectarian policy of Rennyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sectarian policy of Rennyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sectarian policy of Rennyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>文中の（　）の年はユリウス暦、月日は西暦部分を除き全て和暦、宣明暦の長暦による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bracketed years in the sentences are based on the Julian calendar and the dates are all on one of the Japanese calendars, the long calendar of the Senmyo calendar except the ones on the western calendar.</e>
<cmt>・英文では西暦しか使わないと思うので、不要な英文かと思いますが、一応翻訳しておきます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bracketed years in the sentences are based on the Julian calendar and the dates are all on one of the Japanese calendars, the long calendar of the Senmyo calendar except the ones on the western calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bracketed years in the sentences are based on the Julian calendar and the dates are all on one of the Japanese calendars, the long calendar of the Senmyo calendar except the ones on the western calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>8世蓮如は北陸地方や畿内において国人・農民を信者として取り込み、本願寺を独立した教団としての地位を確立させたものの、同時にそれは周辺の守護大名・荘園領主や既存の宗派・寺院との摩擦を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Rennyo, 8th chief priest of Honganji-Temple, brought local lords and peasants living in Hokuriku Region and Kinai Region (the provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) as devotees of his sect to establish the position of Hongan-ji Temple as an independent religious community, it caused discord between him and the shugo daimyo (provincial military governors) and lords of manors around him and also between him and the sects and temples that had already existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Rennyo, the 8th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, won local lords and peasants in Hokuriku Region and Kinai Region (the provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) over to his sect as believers and established the position of Hongan-ji Temple as an independent religious community, it caused discord between him and the neighboring shugo daimyo (provincial military governors) and lords of manors and also between him and the existing sects and temples.</e>
<cmt>本願寺の書き方を修正しました。文法を修正しました。信者はdevoteeでは熱狂的なというニュアンスがありますのでbelieversとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Rennyo, the 8th chief priest of Hongan-ji Temple, won local lords and peasants in Hokuriku Region and Kinai Region (the provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) over to his sect as believers and established the position of Hongan-ji Temple as an independent religious community, it caused discord between him and the neighboring shugo daimyo (provincial military governors) and lords of manors and also between him and the existing sects and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その結果、平和主義や一揆の禁止などを説きながらも、教団を守るために一向一揆を組織し、更には守護などの世俗権力との連携をするという難しい選択に迫られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, on one hand he preached pacifism and the prohibition of uprisings, but on the other hand he had to make a hard decision that he would organize the Ikko-Ikki army to protect the religious community and furthermore that he would receive the cooperation from the worldly powers such as provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>日本語では「一揆」や「一向一揆」がuprisingという出来事ではなく、人を指す言葉として使っているので、armyとしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, on one hand he preached pacifism and the prohibition of uprisings, but on the other hand he had to make a hard decision to organize the Ikko-Ikki army to protect the religious community and furthermore to receive the cooperation from the secular powers such as provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>世俗はsecularが一般的かと思いますので修正しました。言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, on one hand he preached pacifism and the prohibition of uprisings, but on the other hand he had to make a hard decision to organize the Ikko-Ikki army to protect the religious community and furthermore to receive the cooperation from the secular powers such as provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に加賀国においては教団への保護の約束を信じて蓮如自身が一揆とともに守護富樫氏の内紛に加担（文明_(日本)5年の「多屋衆決議文」）し、その後教団の力を恐れた富樫氏が弾圧を加えたため門徒らが激しく抵抗し、結果的に富樫氏を倒して一国を領有する事態となってしまっていた（加賀一向一揆）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in Kaga Province, Rennyo himself participated in the internal conflict of the Togashi clan, a provincial military governor, along with the Ikki army, believing Togashi&apos;s protection for his religious community (&apos;Taya-shu ketsugi bun&apos; [Resolution of Taya Group] in 1473), but after that, the Togashi clan, who feared the power of the religious community, oppressed them, and then the followers fiercely resisted his oppression, and as a result the followers overthrew the Togashi clan and owned a province (Kaga Ikko-Ikki Revolt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in Kaga Province, Rennyo himself participated in the internal conflict of the Togashi clan, a provincial military governor, along with the Ikki army, believing Togashi&apos;s protection for his religious community (&apos;Taya-shu ketsugi bun&apos; [Resolution of Taya Group] in 1473), but after that, the Togashi clan who feared the power of the religious community oppressed them which the followers fiercely resisted to the extent that they overthrew the Togashi clan and owned the province (Kaga Ikko-Ikki Revolt).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in Kaga Province, Rennyo himself participated in the internal conflict of the Togashi clan, a provincial military governor, along with the Ikki army, believing Togashi&apos;s protection for his religious community (&apos;Taya-shu ketsugi bun&apos; [Resolution of Taya Group] in 1473), but after that, the Togashi clan who feared the power of the religious community oppressed them which the followers fiercely resisted to the extent that they overthrew the Togashi clan and owned the province (Kaga Ikko-Ikki Revolt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは蓮如が一番危惧していた本願寺宗門の「反体制」視につながりかねない出来事であり、事実室町幕府征夷大将軍である足利義尚は本願寺を討伐することも検討したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an incident which could lead to the &apos;antiestablishment&apos; movement against the Hongan-ji sect, which was what Rennyo feared most, and in fact Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdued the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) is said to have considered subduing Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an incident which could lead to the &apos;antiestablishment&apos; movement against the Hongan-ji sect, which was what Rennyo feared most, and in fact Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdued the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) is said to have considered subduing Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an incident which could lead to the &apos;antiestablishment&apos; movement against the Hongan-ji sect, which was what Rennyo feared most, and in fact Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdued the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) is said to have considered subduing Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、管領細川政元はこれに強く反対し、間もなく義尚自身も病死したために本願寺討伐の件は中止されて幕府から要求されていた加賀門徒の破門も有耶無耶とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA objected to it and also Yoshihisa died from a disease, subduing Hongan-ji Temple was canceled, and the excommunication of the Kaga-monto (Kaga-sect) went up in the air.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA objected to it and also Yoshihisa died from a disease, subjugation Hongan-ji Temple was canceled, and the excommunication of the Kaga-monto (Kaga-sect) was left up in the air.</e>
<cmt>慣用句を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Shogunal Deputy Masamoto HOSOKAWA objected to it and also Yoshihisa died from a disease, subjugation Hongan-ji Temple was canceled, and the excommunication of the Kaga-monto (Kaga-sect) was left up in the air.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>間もなく蓮如は、長男順如の死後後継者に定めていた五男実如に山科本願寺法主の地位を譲って摂津国石山御坊に退いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon, Rennyo abdicated from the hoshu of Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple in favor of his fifth son Jitsunyo, who had been chosen as a successor of the first son Junnyo after his death, and Rennyo secluded himself into Ishiyama Gobo (Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple) in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon, Rennyo abdicated from the hoshu of Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple in favor of his fifth son Jitsunyo, who had been chosen as the successor after the death of the first son Junnyo, and Rennyo secluded himself into Ishiyama Gobo (Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple) in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon, Rennyo abdicated from the hoshu of Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple in favor of his fifth son Jitsunyo, who had been chosen as the successor after the death of the first son Junnyo, and Rennyo secluded himself into Ishiyama Gobo (Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple) in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>後を継いだ実如にとっては門徒を見捨てて加賀国を放棄することは、すなわち延暦寺への従属を余儀なくされ、親鸞の教義を説くことの禁止を強要されていた蓮如以前の本願寺に戻ることであり浄土真宗の教えそのものを放棄するに等しい行為であったために受け入れられるものではなかった｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the successor Jitsunyo, abandoning his followers and discarding Kaga Province meant subordinating himself to Enryaku-ji Temple, returning to what Hongan-ji Temple was before Rennyo, where they were prohibited from preaching Shinran&apos;s creed, and almost giving up the doctrine of Jodo Shinshu itself, so he could not accept it.</e>
<cmt>2文入っていたので、後列に1行挿入し、そちらに2文目を移しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the successor Jitsunyo, abandoning his followers and discarding Kaga Province meant subordinating himself to Enryaku-ji Temple, returning to what Hongan-ji Temple was before Rennyo, where they were prohibited from preaching Shinran&apos;s creed, and almost giving up the doctrine of Jodo Shinshu itself, so he could not accept it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the successor Jitsunyo, abandoning his followers and discarding Kaga Province meant subordinating himself to Enryaku-ji Temple, returning to what Hongan-ji Temple was before Rennyo, where they were prohibited from preaching Shinran&apos;s creed, and almost giving up the doctrine of Jodo Shinshu itself, so he could not accept it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そのため実如は、全ての既存勢力が本願寺を警戒する中において唯一本願寺擁護の立場を取っていた政元との協調路線を模索するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Jitsunyo tried to seek a cooperative policy with Masamoto, who was solely taking a supportive position of Hongan-ji Temple while all the present powers were cautious of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Jitsunyo tried to seek a cooperative policy with Masamoto who was solely taking a supportive position for Hongan-ji Temple, while all the present powers were cautious of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Jitsunyo tried to seek a cooperative policy with Masamoto who was solely taking a supportive position for Hongan-ji Temple, while all the present powers were cautious of Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『本願寺作法之次第』という本願寺に伝わる書籍には政元の山科本願寺参詣のためだけに蓮如の指示で精進料理ではなく戒律的に問題のある魚料理に献立を変更したいきさつが載せられている程である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A book handed down in Hongan-ji Temple, &quot;Hongan-ji saho no shidai&quot; (The Orders of Manners in Hongan-ji Temple), writes about the situation where the menu was changed from a vegetarian dish to a fish dish which was problematic in terms of the doctrine, under Rennyo&apos;s instruction only for Masamoto&apos;s visit to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A book handed down in Hongan-ji Temple, &quot;Hongan-ji saho no shidai&quot; (The Orders of Manners in Hongan-ji Temple), writes about the situation where the menu was changed from a vegetarian dish to a fish dish which was problematic in terms of the doctrine, under Rennyo&apos;s instruction only for Masamoto&apos;s visit to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A book handed down in Hongan-ji Temple, &quot;Hongan-ji saho no shidai&quot; (The Orders of Manners in Hongan-ji Temple), writes about the situation where the menu was changed from a vegetarian dish to a fish dish which was problematic in terms of the doctrine, under Rennyo&apos;s instruction only for Masamoto&apos;s visit to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>一方、政元も明応の政変によって将軍足利義稙を京都から追放して管領主導の政権を樹立したために諸国の守護大名達の反感を買っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Masamoto banished Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA from Kyoto by the Coup of Meio and established an administration lead by Kanrei (shogunal deputy), and there fore provincial military governors had ill feelings against him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Masamoto banished Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA from Kyoto by the Coup of Meio and established an administration led by Kanrei (shogunal deputy) which caused provincial military governors to hold ill feelings against him.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Masamoto banished Shogun Yoshitane ASHIKAGA from Kyoto by the Coup of Meio and established an administration led by Kanrei (shogunal deputy) which caused provincial military governors to hold ill feelings against him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>政元にとってはこうした守旧派の守護達よりも新しく台頭した一揆勢力の方が信頼が置ける存在と考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto thought that he could believe rather the newly emerging Ikko followers than the old-guard provincial military governors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto thought that he could believe rather the newly emerging Ikko followers than the old-guard provincial military governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto thought that he could believe rather the newly emerging Ikko followers than the old-guard provincial military governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>本願寺と細川政元――既存勢力から睨まれた両者が歩み寄るのは当然の成り行きであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was natural that Hongan-ji Temple and Masamoto HOSOKAWA--the two that were given a hostile look from the present powers--cooperated with each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was natural that Hongan-ji Temple and Masamoto HOSOKAWA--the two given a hostile look from the present powers--cooperated.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was natural that Hongan-ji Temple and Masamoto HOSOKAWA--the two given a hostile look from the present powers--cooperated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>明応8年（1499年）、蓮如が危篤に陥ると遺言が彼の子供達に示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1499, when Rennyo fell into critical condition, his will was shown to his children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1499, when Rennyo fell into critical condition, his will was shown to his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1499, when Rennyo fell into critical condition, his will was shown to his children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>蓮如は親鸞直系の末裔である一族の団結を求め、法主を継承した実如を中心に各地の住持となった子供達がその藩屏として教団を守ってゆくことを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rennyo wanted the solidarity among his families which were the direct descendants of Shinran and also wanted his children who became chief priests at various places, especially Jitsunyo who succeeded to hoshu, to protect the religious community as playing an act of guarding walls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rennyo wanted the solidarity among his families which were the direct descendants of Shinran and also wanted his children who became chief priests at various places, especially Jitsunyo who succeeded to hoshu, to protect the religious community as the guarding walls.</e>
<cmt>不要な訳を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rennyo wanted the solidarity among his families which were the direct descendants of Shinran and also wanted his children who became chief priests at various places, especially Jitsunyo who succeeded to hoshu, to protect the religious community as the guarding walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に加賀においては3男蓮綱の松岡寺・4男蓮誓の光教寺・7男蓮悟の本泉寺（初代住持は次男蓮乗）の「賀州三ヶ寺（加賀三山）」を法主の現地における代行として頂点に置き国内の寺院・門徒を統率することが求められていた（この体制を特に事実上の最高執行機関となった松岡寺と本泉寺の両寺院より「両御山」体制も呼ぶ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in Kaga Province, Shoko-ji Temple of the 3rd son Renko, Kokyo-ji Temple of the 4th son Rensei, and Honsen-ji Temple of the 7th son Rengo (the first chief priest was the second son Renjo)--&apos;Gashu Sanka-ji Temples, or Kaga Sanzan&apos; (Three Temples in Kaga Province)--were placed at the top as local representatives of hoshu and asked to direct the temples and followers in the province (this system was especially called the &apos;ryogozan&apos; (two temples) system after the two virtually highest executive temples, Shoko-ji Temple and Honsen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>「三ヶ寺」の読みが確認できませんでした。「さんかじ」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in Kaga Province, Shoko-ji Temple of the 3rd son Renko, Kokyo-ji Temple of the 4th son Rensei, and Honsen-ji Temple of the 7th son Rengo (the first chief priest was the second son Renjo)--&apos;Gashu Sanka-ji Temples (Kaga Sanzan) [Three Temples in Kaga Province]&apos;--were placed at the top as local representatives of hoshu and required to direct the temples and followers in the province (this system was especially called the &apos;ryogozan&apos; (two temples) system because of the two virtually highest executive temples, Shoko-ji Temple and Honsen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>「三ヶ寺」の読み不明記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in Kaga Province, Shoko-ji Temple of the 3rd son Renko, Kokyo-ji Temple of the 4th son Rensei, and Honsen-ji Temple of the 7th son Rengo (the first chief priest was the second son Renjo)--&apos;Gashu Sanka-ji Temples (Kaga Sanzan) [Three Temples in Kaga Province]&apos;--were placed at the top as local representatives of hoshu and required to direct the temples and followers in the province (this system was especially called the &apos;ryogozan&apos; (two temples) system because of the two virtually highest executive temples, Shoko-ji Temple and Honsen-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その支配体制は富樫氏滅亡以前である文明年間末期の段階において室町幕府が守護に対して下す奉行人奉書などの命令書が富樫政親ではなく直接蓮綱・蓮悟あてに送付されていることからでも分かる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ruling system can be noticed when we see the fact that the orders such as bugyonin hosho (magistrate orders) given from the Muromachi bakufu to provincial governors in the late Bunmei Era, when the Togashi clan still existed, were not sent to Masachika TOGASHI but directly to Renko and Rengo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ruling system can be seen in the fact that the orders such as bugyonin hosho (magistrate orders) given from the Muromachi bakufu to provincial governors in the late Bunmei Era when the Togashi clan still existed, were not sent to Masachika TOGASHI but sent directly to Renko and Rengo.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ruling system can be seen in the fact that the orders such as bugyonin hosho (magistrate orders) given from the Muromachi bakufu to provincial governors in the late Bunmei Era when the Togashi clan still existed, were not sent to Masachika TOGASHI but sent directly to Renko and Rengo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>河内国錯乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawachi Province disturbance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawachi Province disturbance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawachi Province disturbance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>だが、生涯に4人の妻と死別して5人の妻を娶り、13男14女を儲けた蓮如の死後、一族間に不協和音が見られるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Rennyo, who had been bereaved of four wives, married the fifth wife, and begot thirteen sons and fourteen daughters, a discord started in his family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Rennyo who married five wives among whom four died and begot thirteen sons and fourteen daughters in his lifetime, discord erupted between his family.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。原文により忠実な訳にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Rennyo who married five wives among whom four died and begot thirteen sons and fourteen daughters in his lifetime, discord erupted between his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>永正2年（1505年）、細川政元に対抗するため畠山氏をはじめ朝倉氏などの有力守護大名が一斉に軍事作戦を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1505, dominant shugo guardian feudal lords such as the Hatakeyama and Asakura clans began a military action in concert.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1505, dominant shugo guardian feudal lords such as the Hatakeyama and Asakura clans began a military action in concert to counter Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>「細川政元に対抗するため」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1505, dominant shugo guardian feudal lords such as the Hatakeyama and Asakura clans began a military action in concert to counter Masamoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>本願寺にとって朝倉氏の領国である越前国は加賀の南隣であるだけでなく蓮如のかつての拠点吉崎御坊をはじめとして多くの寺院・門徒がおり、畠山氏の領国である能登国・越中国も加賀の北隣であるだけでなく越中の砺波郡は賀州三ヶ寺の事実上支配下にあり、かねてから畠山氏はその奪還を狙っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Hongan-ji Temple, Echizen Province, the territory of the Asakura clan, was not only located to the direct south of Kaga, but there were many temples and followers over there including Yoshizaki Gobo, where was once Rennyo&apos;s foothold, and moreover Noto Province and Ecchu Province, the territory of the Hatakeyama clan was not only located to the direct north of Kaga, but Gashu Sanka-ji Temples virtually ruled Tonami County in Ecchu, where the Hatakeyama clan had been trying to recapture since before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Hongan-ji Temple, Echizen Province, the territory of the Asakura clan, was not only located to the direct south of Kaga, but there were many temples and followers including Yoshizaki Gobo which was once Rennyo&apos;s foothold, and Noto Province and Ecchu Province, the territory of the Hatakeyama clan was not only located to the direct north of Kaga, but Gashu Sanka-ji Temples virtually ruled Tonami County in Ecchu where the Hatakeyama clan was always trying to recapture.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Hongan-ji Temple, Echizen Province, the territory of the Asakura clan, was not only located to the direct south of Kaga, but there were many temples and followers including Yoshizaki Gobo which was once Rennyo&apos;s foothold, and Noto Province and Ecchu Province, the territory of the Hatakeyama clan was not only located to the direct north of Kaga, but Gashu Sanka-ji Temples virtually ruled Tonami County in Ecchu where the Hatakeyama clan was always trying to recapture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>そこで政元直々の訪問による協力依頼を受けた実如は北陸・畿内の信徒を総動員して北陸門徒は周辺3国へ、畿内門徒は畠山氏の根拠地である河内国への侵攻を命令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After receiving a cooperation request from Masamoto by his direct visit, Jitsunyo mobilized all his followers in Hokuriku and Kinai and ordered the ones in Hokuriku to attack the nearby three provinces and the ones in Kinai Kawachi Province, the Hatakeyama clan&apos;s base ground.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After receiving a cooperation request from Masamoto by his direct visit, Jitsunyo mobilized all his followers in Hokuriku and Kinai and ordered the ones in Hokuriku to attack the nearby three provinces and the ones in Kinai to attack Kawachi Province, the Hatakeyama clan&apos;s base ground.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After receiving a cooperation request from Masamoto by his direct visit, Jitsunyo mobilized all his followers in Hokuriku and Kinai and ordered the ones in Hokuriku to attack the nearby three provinces and the ones in Kinai to attack Kawachi Province, the Hatakeyama clan&apos;s base ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>ところが蓮如の最後の妻でその死後も石山御坊に在住していた蓮能は畠山氏出身で、また摂津・河内の門徒達もその関係により長年畠山氏と友好的な関係を維持してきたためにこの決定に不満を抱き、蓮能の長子で石山御坊の住持であった蓮如の9男で17歳の実賢を擁立して法主交替を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Renno, the last wife of Rennyo, who kept living in Ishiyama Gobo after Rennyo&apos;s death, was from the Hatakeyama clan and also since the followers in Settsu and Kawachi had long kept a friendly relationship with the Hatakeyama clan for that reason, they were dissatisfied with the decision and asked to change hoshu by backing up Jitsugen at 17, who was the 1st son of Renno, the 9th son of Rennyo and a chief priest of Ishiyama Gobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Renno, the last wife of Rennyo, who kept living in Ishiyama Gobo after Rennyo&apos;s death, was from the Hatakeyama clan and also since the followers in Settsu and Kawachi had long kept a friendly relationship with the Hatakeyama clan for that reason, they were dissatisfied with the decision and asked to change hoshu by backing up Jitsugen at 17, who was the 1st son of Renno, the 9th son of Rennyo and a chief priest of Ishiyama Gobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Renno, the last wife of Rennyo, who kept living in Ishiyama Gobo after Rennyo&apos;s death, was from the Hatakeyama clan and also since the followers in Settsu and Kawachi had long kept a friendly relationship with the Hatakeyama clan for that reason, they were dissatisfied with the decision and asked to change hoshu by backing up Jitsugen at 17, who was the 1st son of Renno, the 9th son of Rennyo and a chief priest of Ishiyama Gobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>実如はこれに対して永正3年（1506年）1月、下間頼慶を派遣して蓮能・実賢・実順（11男）・実従（13男）を逮捕・追放して、加賀でも本泉寺蓮悟の養子となっていた実悟（10男）が事実上廃嫡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1506, Jitsunyo sent Raikei SHIMOTSUMA to deal with it and arrested or banished Renno, Jitsugen, Jitsujun (11th son), and Jitsuju (13th son); and in Kaga Jitsugo (10th son), who had been adopted by Rengo in Honsen-ji Temple, was virtually disinherited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1506, Jitsunyo sent Raikei SHIMOTSUMA to deal with it and either arrested or banished Renno, Jitsugen, Jitsujun (11th son), and Jitsuju (13th son), and in Kaga, Jitsugo (10th son) who had been adopted by Rengo of Honsen-ji Temple was virtually disinherited.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1506, Jitsunyo sent Raikei SHIMOTSUMA to deal with it and either arrested or banished Renno, Jitsugen, Jitsujun (11th son), and Jitsuju (13th son), and in Kaga, Jitsugo (10th son) who had been adopted by Rengo of Honsen-ji Temple was virtually disinherited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これを「大坂一乱」または「河内国錯乱」と呼ぶ（石山御坊（大坂）は摂津国だが、実賢支持者に河内出身者が多くいたためである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; (A Disturbance in Osaka) or &apos;Kawachikoku sakuran&apos; (Kawachi Province Disturbance) (this is because Ishiyama Gobo [Osaka] was located in Settsu Province, but many supporters of Jitsugen were from Kawachi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; (A Disturbance in Osaka) or &apos;Kawachikoku sakuran&apos; (Kawachi Province Disturbance) (this is because many supporters of Jitsugen were from Kawachi while Ishiyama Gobo [Osaka] was located in Settsu Province).</e>
<cmt>語順を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is called &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; (A Disturbance in Osaka) or &apos;Kawachikoku sakuran&apos; (Kawachi Province Disturbance) (this is because many supporters of Jitsugen were from Kawachi while Ishiyama Gobo [Osaka] was located in Settsu Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>だが、朝倉氏との戦いは九頭竜川の戦いで敗れて逆に朝倉氏によって吉崎御坊は破壊された上に本願寺門徒への禁宗令が出され、蓮如以前からある数少ない末寺である超勝寺・本覚寺 (小松市)などは信者を連れて加賀に逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Jitsunyo lost against the Asakura clan in the Battle of Kuzuryugawa, and the Asakura clan destroyed Yoshizaki Gobo and prohibited believing in the Ikko sect, so a few branch temples that had been existed before Rennyo such as Chosho-ji Temple, Hongaku-ji Temple (in Komatsu City), and so on, escaped to Kaga with their followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Jitsunyo lost against the Asakura clan in the Battle of Kuzuryugawa, and the Asakura clan destroyed Yoshizaki Gobo in return and prohibited believing in the Ikko sect, so some of the few branch temples that had existed before Rennyo such as Chosho-ji Temple, Hongaku-ji Temple (in Komatsu City) escaped to Kaga with their followers.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Jitsunyo lost against the Asakura clan in the Battle of Kuzuryugawa, and the Asakura clan destroyed Yoshizaki Gobo in return and prohibited believing in the Ikko sect, so some of the few branch temples that had existed before Rennyo such as Chosho-ji Temple, Hongaku-ji Temple (in Komatsu City) escaped to Kaga with their followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>一方畠山氏との戦いでも般若野の戦い (戦国時代)で援軍に来た越後国の長尾能景（上杉氏守護代）を討ち取っただけに留まり成果はあげられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the battle against the Hatakeyama clan too, Rennyo only subjugated Yoshikage NAGAO (Shugodai [deputy military governor] of the Uesugi clan) in Echigo Province, who came as reinforcements in the Battle of Hannya-no (of the Sengoku Period), and gained short results.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the battle against the Hatakeyama clan too, Rennyo only subjugated Yoshikage NAGAO (Shugodai [deputy military governor] of the Uesugi clan) of Echigo Province, who came as reinforcements to the Battle of Hannya-no (Sengoku Period).</e>
<cmt>不要な訳を削除しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the battle against the Hatakeyama clan too, Rennyo only subjugated Yoshikage NAGAO (Shugodai [deputy military governor] of the Uesugi clan) of Echigo Province, who came as reinforcements to the Battle of Hannya-no (Sengoku Period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>そして、永正4年6月23日 (旧暦)（1507年8月1日））、細川政元は養子・細川澄之の支持者によって暗殺され、更にもう一人の養子である細川澄元との戦いを開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1507, Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated by the supporters of his adopted son Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, who started a battle against another adopted son Sumimoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1507, Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated by the supporters of his adopted son Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, who started a battle against another adopted son Sumimoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, 1507, Masamoto HOSOKAWA was assassinated by the supporters of his adopted son Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA, who started a battle against another adopted son Sumimoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これを知った実如は後難を恐れて翌日には近江国堅田本福寺の明顕・明宗_(僧)親子を頼って逃走した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo, who heard of this, ran away, in fear of future problems, to Myoken and his child Myoshu at Honpuku-ji Temple in Katata, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo, who heard of this, escaped the very next day in fear for the consequences to Myoken and his child Myoshu at Honpuku-ji Temple in Katata, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>語彙の選択を修正しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo, who heard of this, escaped the very next day in fear for the consequences to Myoken and his child Myoshu at Honpuku-ji Temple in Katata, Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その後混乱は続き、まずは細川澄之が、続いて細川澄元が討たれて、最終的に政権を奪ったのは本願寺に対して一番の強硬派であった細川高国であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disturbance continued after that, and first Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA was killed, and then Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was slew, and finally the one who took the administration was Takakuni HOSOKAWA, who was the toughest hard-liner against Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disturbance continued in which Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA was killed first and then Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was slew, and the one who finally took the administration was Takakuni HOSOKAWA, the toughest hard-liner against Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように、言い回しを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disturbance continued in which Sumiyuki HOSOKAWA was killed first and then Sumimoto HOSOKAWA was slew, and the one who finally took the administration was Takakuni HOSOKAWA, the toughest hard-liner against Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>かくして実如は、永正6年3月22日 (旧暦)に山科本願寺に復帰するまでの2年間を近江堅田で生活することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, Jitsunyo was forced to live in Omi Katata for two years until he went back to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple on April 21, 1509.</e>
<cmt>西暦はWikipediaで確認しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, Jitsunyo was forced to live in Omi Katata for two years until he went back to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple on April 21, 1509.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, Jitsunyo was forced to live in Omi Katata for two years until he went back to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple on April 21, 1509.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>実如の教団改革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsunyo&apos;s reform of the religious community</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsunyo&apos;s reform of the religious community</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsunyo&apos;s reform of the religious community</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>細川政元の死とその後の2年間の亡命生活は実如にとっては大きな打撃であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death of Masamoto HOSOKAWA and the following two years of his exile caused big damage to Jitsunyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death of Masamoto HOSOKAWA and the following two years of exile caused big damage to Jitsunyo.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death of Masamoto HOSOKAWA and the following two years of exile caused big damage to Jitsunyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>同時に教団を維持するための守りの姿勢を固める重要性も出てきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, at the same time, he felt the necessity to take a defensive action for the protection of the religious community.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he felt the necessity to take a defensive action to protect the religious community.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he felt the necessity to take a defensive action to protect the religious community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>そこで実如は寺の実務を次男で後継者となっていた円如と自分の同母弟で蓮如の6男にして円如の舅でもあった近江顕証寺･伊勢国願証寺両寺の住持を兼ねていた蓮淳に教団運営を任せることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Jitsunyo decided to entrust the management of the religious community to Ennyo, who was his 2nd son and his successor, and Renjun, who was the 6th son of Rennyo, his younger maternal half-brother, a father-in-law of Ennyo, and a chief priest of both Omi Kensho-ji Temple and Gansho-ji Temple in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Jitsunyo decided to entrust the management of the religious community to Ennyo, his 2nd son and successor and Renjun, his younger maternal half-brother, the 6th son of Rennyo, a father-in-law of Ennyo, and the chief priest of both Omi Kensho-ji Temple and Gansho-ji Temple in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。分かりやすいように語順を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Jitsunyo decided to entrust the management of the religious community to Ennyo, his 2nd son and successor and Renjun, his younger maternal half-brother, the 6th son of Rennyo, a father-in-law of Ennyo, and the chief priest of both Omi Kensho-ji Temple and Gansho-ji Temple in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>以後、円如と蓮淳は実如の意向を受けて教団の改革に乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Ennyo and Renjun started to reform the religious community under Jitsunyo&apos;s instruction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Ennyo and Renjun started to reform the religious community under Jitsunyo&apos;s instruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Ennyo and Renjun started to reform the religious community under Jitsunyo&apos;s instruction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>まず蓮如の著した「御文」と呼ばれる文書の中から80通を選んで5帖に編集し宗門信条の基本とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First of all, they selected 80 letters from the documents written by Rennyo, called &apos;Ofumi,&apos; edited them into five quires, and determined the basic doctrine of the sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First of all, they selected 80 letters from the documents written by Rennyo, called &apos;Ofumi,&apos; edited them into five quires to determine the basic doctrine of the sect.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First of all, they selected 80 letters from the documents written by Rennyo, called &apos;Ofumi,&apos; edited them into five quires to determine the basic doctrine of the sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="42">
<j>続いて、永正15年（1518年）、新たな3法令を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, in 1518, they established three new laws.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, in 1518, they established three new laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, in 1518, they established three new laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="43">
<j>一つ目は俗に「三法令」と呼ばれているもので、以下の3つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first law was vulgarly called &apos;Sanhourei&apos; (Three Laws) which are:</e>
<cmt>「三法令」の読みが「さんぽうれい」か「さんほうれい」か確認できません。「さんほうれい」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first law was vulgarly called &apos;Sanhourei&apos; (Three Laws) which are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first law was vulgarly called &apos;Sanhourei&apos; (Three Laws) which are:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>武装・合戦の禁止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prohibition of armament and battles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prohibition of armament and battles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prohibition of armament and battles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>派閥・徒党の禁止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prohibition of sect and fact forming</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prohibition of sect and faction</e>
<cmt>徒党はfactionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prohibition of sect and faction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>年貢不払いの禁止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prohibition of nonpayment of land tax</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prohibition of nonpayment of land tax</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prohibition of nonpayment of land tax</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>北陸各地の門徒達から偶々病気治療のために上洛する蓮誓に誓約書を託させて提出させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They made the followers at various places in Hokuriku write covenants and hand them over Rensei, who had a chance to come to Kyoto for the treatment of his disease, to turn them in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They made the followers in various places in Hokuriku write covenants and hand them over to Rensei, who had a chance to come to Kyoto for the treatment of his disease, to turn them in.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They made the followers in various places in Hokuriku write covenants and hand them over to Rensei, who had a chance to come to Kyoto for the treatment of his disease, to turn them in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="48">
<j>二つ目は新しい坊（寺）の建設禁止と既存の坊の整理統合を命じたもので、同時に寺号付与の権利を本山である本願寺法主のみが保持することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second law prohibited building new temples and ordered reorganization of the temples that had existed, and at the same time it was decided that the hoshu of the head temple Hongan-ji Temple only had the right to decide temples&apos; names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second law prohibited building new temples and ordered reorganization of the existing temples, and at the same time it was decided that the hoshu of the head temple Hongan-ji Temple only had the right to decide temples&apos; names.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second law prohibited building new temples and ordered reorganization of the existing temples, and at the same time it was decided that the hoshu of the head temple Hongan-ji Temple only had the right to decide temples&apos; names.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これにより寺の設置廃止の全てを本願寺の統制下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made all the rights to establish and abolish temples under Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This brought all the rights to establish and abolish temples under Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This brought all the rights to establish and abolish temples under Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>最後に翌16年に定めた「一門一家制」の制定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lastly, &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System (the system that divided the Hongan-ji families into Ichimonshu [clansman, for a legitimate son] and Ikkeshu [the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple, for a second son and younger]) was established in 1519.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lastly, &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System (the system that divided the Hongan-ji families into Ichimonshu [clansman, for a legitimate son] and Ikkeshu [the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple, for a second son and younger]) was established in 1519.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lastly, &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System (the system that divided the Hongan-ji families into Ichimonshu [clansman, for a legitimate son] and Ikkeshu [the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple, for a second son and younger]) was established in 1519.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>これは従来「一家衆」と呼ばれていた本願寺の一族寺院の間に家格を定めたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This created family ranks among temples belonging to the Hongan-ji Temple family which were called &apos;ikkeshu&apos; (the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This created family ranks among temples belonging to the Hongan-ji Temple family which were called &apos;ikkeshu&apos; (the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This created family ranks among temples belonging to the Hongan-ji Temple family which were called &apos;ikkeshu&apos; (the same lineage people as the Hongan-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>即ち、次の3つになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ranks consisted of the next three:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ranks consisted of the next three:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ranks consisted of the next three:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="53">
<j>連枝…法主の子供・兄弟。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renshi: The children and brothers of a hoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renshi: The children and brothers of a hoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renshi: The children and brothers of a hoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="54">
<j>一門…連枝の嫡男（第二世代）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichimon: A legitimate son of renshi (the second generation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichimon: A legitimate son of renshi (the second generation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichimon: A legitimate son of renshi (the second generation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="55">
<j>一家…連枝の次男以下と蓮如以前に分かれた一族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikke: A second son and younger of renshi, and the family branches before Rennyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikke: The second and younger sons of renshi and the families branched before Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikke: The second and younger sons of renshi and the families branched before Rennyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>「末の一家衆」とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called &apos;Sue no ikkeshu&apos; (youngest ikkeshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called &apos;Sue no ikkeshu&apos; (youngest ikkeshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called &apos;Sue no ikkeshu&apos; (youngest ikkeshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="57">
<j>これにより｢親鸞の御血の道｣と呼ばれた直系が継承する法主に権限を集約し、その藩屏たる連枝・一門の優位が定められたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These laws concentrated the power to hoshu which was succeeded by the direct lineage called &apos;Shinran no michi no michi&apos; (literally, the way of Shinran&apos;s blood) and established the superiority of renshi and ichimon to act as guarding walls.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These laws concentrated the power to hoshu which was succeeded by the direct lineage called &apos;Shinran no michi no michi&apos; (literally, the way of Shinran&apos;s blood) and established the superiority of renshi and ichimon which acted as guarding walls.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These laws concentrated the power to hoshu which was succeeded by the direct lineage called &apos;Shinran no michi no michi&apos; (literally, the way of Shinran&apos;s blood) and established the superiority of renshi and ichimon which acted as guarding walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="58">
<j>こうした一連の改革は一向一揆の活動を抑制し、幕府や各地の大名、他宗派との共存を目的とするものでこれまでの政策の大転換ともいえるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These series of reforms controlled the activity for the Ikko-Ikki army, with a view to coexisting with the bakufu, daimyo (feudal lords) at various places, and other religious schools, and it can be said to have been a drastic change of its policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These series of reforms curbed activities of the Ikko-Ikki army and can be said to have drastically changed its policy with a view to coexisting with the bakufu, local daimyo (feudal lords) in various places, and other religious schools.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。語彙の選択と語順も変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These series of reforms curbed activities of the Ikko-Ikki army and can be said to have drastically changed its policy with a view to coexisting with the bakufu, local daimyo (feudal lords) in various places, and other religious schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="59">
<j>当然一連の改革に対する末寺・門徒の一部の反発もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of course, there came resistance from part of branch temples and followers against the series of reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of course, there came resistance from part of branch temples and followers against the series of reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of course, there came resistance from part of branch temples and followers against the series of reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>永正15年、朝倉氏によって越前を追放されて加賀に逃れていた本覚寺蓮恵が「三法令」の戦争の禁止によって越前への帰還が困難になると本泉寺蓮悟に苦情を申し立てて相論となったところ、蓮悟の上申で破門処分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1518, Rene at Hongaku-ji Temple, who had been banished from Echizen by the Asakura clan and had stayed in Kaga, had difficulty in coming back to Echizen due to the prohibition of wars stipulated in &apos;Sanhourei,&apos; appealed to Rengo at Honsen-ji Temple and disputed over it, and after Rengo&apos;s report Rene was excommunicated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1518, Rene of Hongaku-ji Temple, who had been banished from Echizen by the Asakura clan and sheltered in Kaga appealed to Rengo of Honsen-ji Temple that he would have difficulty in coming back to Echizen due to the prohibition of wars stipulated in &apos;Sanhourei&apos; and disputed with him, as a result of which Rengo reported it to hoshu and Rene was excommunicated.</e>
<cmt>上申した先が法主であることを明記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1518, Rene of Hongaku-ji Temple, who had been banished from Echizen by the Asakura clan and sheltered in Kaga appealed to Rengo of Honsen-ji Temple that he would have difficulty in coming back to Echizen due to the prohibition of wars stipulated in &apos;Sanhourei&apos; and disputed with him, as a result of which Rengo reported it to hoshu and Rene was excommunicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>続いて顕証寺蓮淳が先に実如が退避した堅田本福寺の明宗に不正ありと上申して破門処分となった（ただし蓮淳の場合には、別の意図により起こしたもので実際には本福寺は冤罪であったとされている（詳細は後述））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Renjun at Kensho-ji Temple reported that Meiso at Katata Honpuku-ji Temple, where Jitsunyo had withdrawn into, was doing wrong, and Meiso was excommunicated (although Renjun did it for another purpose and Honpuku-ji Temple is said to have suffered a false charge; the details are mentioned later).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Renjun of Kensho-ji Temple reported to hoshu that Meiso of Katata Honpuku-ji Temple, where Jitsunyo evacuated, was doing wrong and Meiso was excommunicated (Renjun did it for another purpose and Honpuku-ji Temple is said to have suffered a false charge; the details are mentioned later).</e>
<cmt>上申した先が法主であることを明記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Renjun of Kensho-ji Temple reported to hoshu that Meiso of Katata Honpuku-ji Temple, where Jitsunyo evacuated, was doing wrong and Meiso was excommunicated (Renjun did it for another purpose and Honpuku-ji Temple is said to have suffered a false charge; the details are mentioned later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>両寺院ともすぐに許されたものの、本福寺の先代明顕は先の実如の件のみならず、蓮如が延暦寺によって京都を追われた際にもこれを匿い、本覚寺の先代蓮光はその蓮如のために吉崎御坊を建立してこれを迎え入れた人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both temples were forgiven soon after, but the previous chief priest of Honpuku-ji Temple, Myoken, had offered shelter not only to Jitsunyo, as mentioned before, but also to Rennyo when he was banished from Kyoto by Enryaku-ji Temple, and the previous chief priest of Hongaku-ji Temple, Renko, had welcomed Rennyo by building up Yoshizaki Gobo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both temples were forgiven soon after, but the previous chief priest of Honpuku-ji Temple Myoken had offered shelter not only to Jitsunyo as mentioned before, but also to Rennyo when he was banished from Kyoto by Enryaku-ji Temple and the previous chief priest of Hongaku-ji Temple Renko had welcomed Rennyo by building up Yoshizaki Gobo.</e>
<cmt>不要なカンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both temples were forgiven soon after, but the previous chief priest of Honpuku-ji Temple Myoken had offered shelter not only to Jitsunyo as mentioned before, but also to Rennyo when he was banished from Kyoto by Enryaku-ji Temple and the previous chief priest of Hongaku-ji Temple Renko had welcomed Rennyo by building up Yoshizaki Gobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>この二人の功績なくして今日の本願寺は存在し得なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present Hongan-ji Temple could not exist without the cooperation of these two priests.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present Hongan-ji Temple could not exist without the cooperation of these two priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present Hongan-ji Temple could not exist without the cooperation of these two priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>その息子達でさえも容赦なく破門した法主・連枝の権力に信徒は震え上がったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the hoshu and renshi excommunicated even their sons without mercy, and the followers were frightened with their power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the hoshu and renshi excommunicated even their sons without mercy, and the followers were frightened with their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the hoshu and renshi excommunicated even their sons without mercy, and the followers were frightened with their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="65">
<j>だが、永正18年（1521年）に円如が死去、4年後の大永5年（1525年）には実如も死去してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1521, Ennyo died, and four years later, in 1525, Jitsunyo also died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1521, Ennyo died and four years later in 1525, Jitsunyo also died.</e>
<cmt>不要なカンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1521, Ennyo died and four years later in 1525, Jitsunyo also died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>遺された円如の遺児証如（永正13年（1516年）生まれ、実如死去時10歳）の将来を危惧した実如は蓮淳･蓮悟･実円（三河国本宗寺、実如の4男で現存していた唯一の男子）・蓮慶（蓮綱の嫡子）・顕誓（蓮誉の嫡子）の5人に証如への忠誠と親鸞以来の教義の擁護、既存の政治・宗教勢力との共存を遺言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Worrying about the future of a bereaved child of Ennyo, Shonyo (born in 1516, at 10 when Jitsunyo died), Jitsunyo left the will that instructed five priests of Renjun, Rengo, Jitsuen (at Honso-ji Temple in Mikawa Province; the 4th son of Jitsunyo and the only male child), Renkei (Renko&apos;s legitimate child), and Kensei (Renyo&apos;s legitimate child) to practice loyalty to Shonyo, to protect the doctrine that had been kept since Sinran, and to coexist with the present political and religious powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Worried about the future of Shonyo, a bereaved child of Ennyo (born in 1516, he was 10 when Jitsunyo died), Jitsunyo left the will to instruct five priests, Renjun, Rengo, Jitsuen (at Honso-ji Temple in Mikawa Province; the 4th son of Jitsunyo and the only male child alive), Renkei (Renko&apos;s legitimate child), and Kensei (Renyo&apos;s legitimate child) to practice loyalty to Shonyo, to protect the doctrine that had been kept since Sinran, and to coexist with the present political and religious powers.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Worried about the future of Shonyo, a bereaved child of Ennyo (born in 1516, he was 10 when Jitsunyo died), Jitsunyo left the will to instruct five priests, Renjun, Rengo, Jitsuen (at Honso-ji Temple in Mikawa Province; the 4th son of Jitsunyo and the only male child alive), Renkei (Renko&apos;s legitimate child), and Kensei (Renyo&apos;s legitimate child) to practice loyalty to Shonyo, to protect the doctrine that had been kept since Sinran, and to coexist with the present political and religious powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>そして、特に証如の外祖父であり、5人中唯一の畿内在住であった蓮淳にはその後見と養護を託した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially to Renjun, who was a maternal grandfather of Shonyo and only the priest who lived in the Kinai region, Jitsunyo entrusted Shonyo and asked him to be his guardian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially to Renjun, who was the maternal grandfather of Shonyo and the only priest who lived in the Kinai region, Jitsunyo entrusted Shonyo and asked him to be his guardian.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially to Renjun, who was the maternal grandfather of Shonyo and the only priest who lived in the Kinai region, Jitsunyo entrusted Shonyo and asked him to be his guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>享禄の錯乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoroku War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoroku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoroku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>さて蓮如には生前に5人の妻を娶り、13人の男子があったが、最後の妻蓮能の子供達は先の「大坂一乱」で排斥され、4番目の妻の子蓮芸は摂津国富田 (高槻市)に教行寺を建てた後に実如に先立って死去、3番目の妻には男子がいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Rennyo had five wives in his lifetime and left thirteen sons, the children of the last wife Renno were expelled by &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; mentioned above, and the children of the 4th wife Rengei died before Rennyo after he built Kyogo-ji Temple at Tomita, Settsu Province, and the 3rd wife did not have a son.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処・蓮芸は「れんげい」のようです。（http://www.yamadera.info/seiten/c2/kikigakiF.htm）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Rennyo had five wives in his lifetime and left thirteen sons, the children of the last wife Renno were expelled by &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; mentioned above, and Rengei, the child of the 4th wife died before Rennyo after he built Kyogo-ji Temple in Tomita, Settsu Province, and the 3rd wife did not have a son.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Rennyo had five wives in his lifetime and left thirteen sons, the children of the last wife Renno were expelled by &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; mentioned above, and Rengei, the child of the 4th wife died before Rennyo after he built Kyogo-ji Temple in Tomita, Settsu Province, and the 3rd wife did not have a son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その中で、自然と最初の妻である如了とその実妹で実如を生んだ2番目の妻蓮祐の遺した7人の男子の存在は宗門の間で崇敬の対象となっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a situation, the seven sons, who were the bereaved children of both the first wife Nyoryo, and her real younger sister and the second wife of Rennyo, Rensuke, who bore Jitsunyo, naturally became objects of followers&apos; respect.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処・如了は「にょりょう」と読むようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a situation, the seven sons, the bereaved children of the first wife Nyoryo and her real younger sister Rensuke, the second wife who bore Jitsunyo, naturally became objects of followers&apos; respect.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。助長な訳は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a situation, the seven sons, the bereaved children of the first wife Nyoryo and her real younger sister Rensuke, the second wife who bore Jitsunyo, naturally became objects of followers&apos; respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>ところが、後継者とされた順如（父に先立ち死去）・実如はともかく、他の5人の男子のうち4人が北陸に派遣されて共同で加賀とその周辺の事実上の国主としての地位を得たのにも関わらず、6男の蓮淳だけは順如が遺した顕証寺の住持に補されて畿内に留められ、教団内において大きな仕事を与えられてこなかったことに不満を抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, aside from Jyunnyo (who died before his father) and Jitsunyo assigned as successors, four of the other five sons were dispatched to Hokuriku and virtually gained the positions of kokushu (landed daimyo) ruling Kaga and the surrounded provinces, but the sixth son Renjun was appointed to a chief priest of Kensho-ji Temple which Jyunnyo left, and forced to remain in Kinai and therefore he had felt discontented with not being given an important mission in the religious community.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though Jyunnyo (who died before his father) and Jitsunyo were treated as successor and the four of the other five sons were dispatched to Hokuriku and virtually gained the positions of kokushu (landed daimyo) in Kaga and the surrounded provinces, the sixth son Renjun was appointed to the chief priest of Kensho-ji Temple which Jyunnyo left and forced to remain in Kinai, which made him discontent about not being given an important mission in the religious community.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。文脈が不自然にならないように、言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though Jyunnyo (who died before his father) and Jitsunyo were treated as successor and the four of the other five sons were dispatched to Hokuriku and virtually gained the positions of kokushu (landed daimyo) in Kaga and the surrounded provinces, the sixth son Renjun was appointed to the chief priest of Kensho-ji Temple which Jyunnyo left and forced to remain in Kinai, which made him discontent about not being given an important mission in the religious community.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>だが、ここで新法主の保護者・後見人の地位が与えられたことで一躍北陸の兄弟を上回る権力を持つ事となった蓮淳は孫である法主・証如の権力拡大に乗り出すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Renjun, who was given the position of protector and guardian of a new hoshu at this moment and gained the power exceeding that of his brothers in Hokuriku, began to expand the authority of the hoshu Shonyo, who was a grandson of Renjun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But given the position of protector and guardian of the new hoshu, Renjun now gained the power exceeding that of his brothers in Hokuriku and began to expand the authority of the hoshu Shonyo, grandson of Renjun.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。文脈が不自然にならないように、言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But given the position of protector and guardian of the new hoshu, Renjun now gained the power exceeding that of his brothers in Hokuriku and began to expand the authority of the hoshu Shonyo, grandson of Renjun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これは裏を返せば後見人である蓮淳自身の権力拡大が目的であったが、形式上は「法主を頂点とした権力機構の確立」という実如以来の方針に忠実に従ったものであったから、この大義名分を前に異論を挿める者は存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was actually for the expansion of Renjun&apos;s authority as a guardian, but formally he was following the policy that had been kept since Jitsunyo, &apos;the establishment of the power structure with hoshu at the top,&apos; and therefore for this legitimate reason no one could raise an objection against him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This actually aimed to expand the guardian Renjun&apos;s authority, but formally he was following the policy that had been kept since Jitsunyo, &apos;the establishment of the power structure with hoshu at the top,&apos; and for this legitimate reason, no one could raise an objection against him.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。文脈が不自然にならないように、言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This actually aimed to expand the guardian Renjun&apos;s authority, but formally he was following the policy that had been kept since Jitsunyo, &apos;the establishment of the power structure with hoshu at the top,&apos; and for this legitimate reason, no one could raise an objection against him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>堅田本福寺破門事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katata Honpuku-ji Temple excommunication incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katata Honpuku-ji Temple excommunication incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katata Honpuku-ji Temple excommunication incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>その最初の標的となったのは先述の堅田本福寺である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first target was Katata Honpuku-ji Temple as mentioned before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first target was Katata Honpuku-ji Temple as mentioned before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first target was Katata Honpuku-ji Temple as mentioned before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>同寺は末寺の中でも歴史が長く信徒も大勢いたこと、堅田が琵琶湖水運の拠点として栄えていた事から、本願寺に勝るとも劣らない裕福な寺院であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This temple had many followers because it had the longest history among branch temples, and Katata was prospering as a base of the water transport of Lake Biwa, and therefore the temple was as rich as Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This temple had many followers because it had the longest history among the branch temples and Katata prospered as a base of the water transport of Lake Biwa, which made it as rich as Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This temple had many followers because it had the longest history among the branch temples and Katata prospered as a base of the water transport of Lake Biwa, which made it as rich as Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>そのため、表向きはこうした大規模な末寺の権力を抑圧して本願寺に権力を集めることとされたが、実際には大津市にあった蓮淳の顕証寺と地域が重複するために門徒・布施の取り合いとなり、常に新興の顕証寺が不利に立ってしまうことに対しての腹いせであったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So the formal reason was to concentrate the power on Hongan-ji Temple by suppressing the power of large-scale branch temples, but the real reason was seemingly to revenge the permanent disadvantage of newly-built Kensho-ji Temple in a struggle for followers and donations against Renjun&apos;s Kensho-ji Temple in their shared parish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the formal reason was to concentrate the power on Hongan-ji Temple by suppressing the power of large-scale branch temples, the real reason was seemingly to revenge the permanent disadvantage of Renjun&apos;s newly-built Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu city in a scramble for followers and donations between Hongan-ji Temple whose parish overlapped with that of Kensho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>原文のニュアンスが出るように、訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the formal reason was to concentrate the power on Hongan-ji Temple by suppressing the power of large-scale branch temples, the real reason was seemingly to revenge the permanent disadvantage of Renjun&apos;s newly-built Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu city in a scramble for followers and donations between Hongan-ji Temple whose parish overlapped with that of Kensho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="76">
<j>既に実如在世中にも同寺は一度破門を受けているが、その際蓮淳は本福寺の門徒を圧迫して捏造した証拠を真実と認めさせる署名まで行わせたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though this temple had once been excommunicated while Jitsunyo was still alive, it is said that at that time Renjun compelled the followers of Honpuku-ji Temple to sign to approve forged evidence as true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this temple was once excommunicated during Jitsunyo&apos;s lifetime, Renjun allegedly compelled the followers of Honpuku-ji Temple to sign to approve forged evidence as true.</e>
<cmt>助長な訳は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this temple was once excommunicated during Jitsunyo&apos;s lifetime, Renjun allegedly compelled the followers of Honpuku-ji Temple to sign to approve forged evidence as true.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その事情が発覚したために実如によって破門はすぐに取り消されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since this fact was revealed, Jitsunyo nullified the excommunication at once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as it was revealed, Jitsunyo nullified the excommunication.</e>
<cmt>時制に関する訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as it was revealed, Jitsunyo nullified the excommunication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>その後、本福寺が用意した蓮如・実如が退避していた御坊は「大坂一乱」で対立法主に立てられて追放された実賢が復帰を許された際に与えられて一門寺院の一つとして独立して称徳寺と改称した（後年に慈敬寺と再び改名する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Gobo, where had been prepared by Honpuku-ji Temple and used as a refuge of Rennyo and Jitsunyo, was given to Jitsugen, who had been selected as an opposing hoshu during &apos;Osaka ichiran&apos; and banished, when he was allowed to return, and it became independent as one of the family temples and renamed Shotoku-ji Temple (later renamed Jikei-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the gobo prepared by Honpuku-ji Temple as an evacuation of Rennyo and Jitsunyo was given to Jitsugen, who had been banished for being selected as the opposing hoshu during &apos;Osaka ichiran,&apos; when he was allowed to return, and it became independent as one of the family temples and renamed Shotoku-ji Temple (later renamed Jikei-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the gobo prepared by Honpuku-ji Temple as an evacuation of Rennyo and Jitsunyo was given to Jitsugen, who had been banished for being selected as the opposing hoshu during &apos;Osaka ichiran,&apos; when he was allowed to return, and it became independent as one of the family temples and renamed Shotoku-ji Temple (later renamed Jikei-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>実賢の死後、同寺の後見もしていた蓮淳は大永7年（1527年）称徳寺が本福寺の門徒を引き抜こうとして一家寺院の本福寺がそれを阻止しようとしたのは「一門一家制」、ひいては本願寺そのものへの反逆であるとして本福寺は再度破門された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Jitsugen&apos;s death, Renjun, who had been a guardian of this temple, excommunicated Honpuku-ji Temple again in 1527 under the pretext that the blockage by Honpuku-ji Temple, an Ikke temple, against Honpuku-ji Temple&apos;s headhunting of followers was a treachery to &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System,&apos; and eventually to Hongan-ji itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Jitsugen&apos;s death, Renjun who served as the guardian of this temple excommunicated Honpuku-ji Temple again in 1527 under the pretext that Honpuku-ji Temple, an Ikke temple, attempted to block Shotoku-ji Temple from headhunting followers, which meant treachery to &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System&apos; and eventually to Hongan-ji itself.</e>
<cmt>称徳寺とすべきところが本福寺となっていました。助長な訳は言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Jitsugen&apos;s death, Renjun who served as the guardian of this temple excommunicated Honpuku-ji Temple again in 1527 under the pretext that Honpuku-ji Temple, an Ikke temple, attempted to block Shotoku-ji Temple from headhunting followers, which meant treachery to &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System&apos; and eventually to Hongan-ji itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>これによって本福寺は代々の財産も門徒も悉く失ってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, Honpuku-ji Temple lost all the property and all the followers inherited for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, Honpuku-ji Temple lost all the property and all the followers inherited for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, Honpuku-ji Temple lost all the property and all the followers inherited for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="81">
<j>更に天文元年（1532年）に3度目の破門を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in 1532, the temple was excommunicated for the third time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in 1532, the temple was excommunicated for the third time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in 1532, the temple was excommunicated for the third time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>これは後述の山科本願寺と顕証寺が焼き討ちにされた際に本福寺が救援を出さなかったことを理由にしたものであるが、これは2度の破門で本福寺が完全に荒廃して救援を出せるだけの門徒もいなかったこと、そして後述のように当の蓮淳が真っ先に逃亡している事から見れば明らかに本末転倒であり、逆恨みでしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because Honpuku-ji Temple did not send a rescue when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple and Kensho-ji Temple suffered a fire attack, but if it was considered that Honpuku-ji Temple had not had followers enough to send a rescue due to the complete destruction caused by the two excommunications and also that Renjun was the first person who escaped, this accusation was totally wrong and quite a false charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because Honpuku-ji Temple did not send a rescue when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple and Kensho-ji Temple suffered a fire attack, but Honpuku-ji Temple did not have enough followers to form a rescue due to the complete destruction caused by the last two excommunications and, seen from the fact that Renjun was the first person who escaped, this accusation was totally wrong and quite a false charge.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because Honpuku-ji Temple did not send a rescue when Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple and Kensho-ji Temple suffered a fire attack, but Honpuku-ji Temple did not have enough followers to form a rescue due to the complete destruction caused by the last two excommunications and, seen from the fact that Renjun was the first person who escaped, this accusation was totally wrong and quite a false charge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>天文9年6月2日_(旧暦)に本福寺明宗が迫害の果てに72歳で餓死すると、蓮淳は破門解除の条件として称徳寺（慈敬寺）の末寺になるという条件を付けものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 19, 1540, after Meiso at Honpuku-ji Temple starved to death at 72 as a result of being oppressed, Renjun released Honpuku-ji Temple from excommunication with the condition that it became a branch temple of Shotoku-ji Temple (Jikei-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 19, 1540, after Meiso at Honpuku-ji Temple starved to death at 72 as a result of the oppression, Renjun released Honpuku-ji Temple from excommunication with the condition that it became a branch temple of Shotoku-ji Temple (Jikei-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 19, 1540, after Meiso at Honpuku-ji Temple starved to death at 72 as a result of the oppression, Renjun released Honpuku-ji Temple from excommunication with the condition that it became a branch temple of Shotoku-ji Temple (Jikei-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>これによって本福寺は見せしめのために廃絶寸前にまで追い込まれたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This drove Honpuku-ji Temple to practical extinction as a lesson to other temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This drove Honpuku-ji Temple to practical extinction as a lesson to other temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This drove Honpuku-ji Temple to practical extinction as a lesson to other temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>大小一揆と賀州三ヶ寺粛清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisho ikki and Gashu Sanka-ji Temples purge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisho ikki and Gashu Sanka-ji Temples purge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisho ikki and Gashu Sanka-ji Temples purge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>本福寺との争いに勝利した蓮淳は再び中央政界に目を向けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun, who gained a victory against Honpuku-ji Temple, started to look toward the center of the politics again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun, who gained a victory against Honpuku-ji Temple, started to look toward the center of the politics again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun, who gained a victory against Honpuku-ji Temple, started to look toward the center of the politics again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>大永7年（1527年）反本願寺の細川高国に対して三好元長が擁立する細川晴元（澄元の子）が挙兵した際に側近の下間頼秀・下間頼盛兄弟を晴元側に派遣して支援をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1527, when Harumoto HOSOKAWA (Sumimoto&apos;s child), who were supported by Motonaga MIYOSHI, raised an army against anti-Hongan-ji Temple Takakuni HOSOKAWA, Renjun sent Raishu and Raisei of the SHIMOTSUMA brothers to the side of Harumoto to support him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1527 when Harumoto HOSOKAWA (Sumimoto&apos;s child) supported by Motonaga MIYOSHI raised an army against anti-Hongan-ji Temple Takakuni HOSOKAWA, Renjun sent his aides Raishu and Raisei of the SHIMOTSUMA brothers to support Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>助長な訳は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1527 when Harumoto HOSOKAWA (Sumimoto&apos;s child) supported by Motonaga MIYOSHI raised an army against anti-Hongan-ji Temple Takakuni HOSOKAWA, Renjun sent his aides Raishu and Raisei of the SHIMOTSUMA brothers to support Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>これに対して晴元は北陸にある高国派荘園の占拠を要望し、蓮淳はこの処理に自分の娘婿である超勝寺実顕と下間頼秀を任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In return, Harumoto requested the occupation of a manor owned by the Takakuni sect, and Renjun assigned his adopted son-in-law Jikken at Chosho-ji Temple and Raishu SHIMOTSUMA to deal with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In return, Harumoto requested the occupation of a manor owned by the Takakuni sect, and Renjun assigned his adopted son-in-law Jikken at Chosho-ji Temple and Raishu SHIMOTSUMA to deal with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In return, Harumoto requested the occupation of a manor owned by the Takakuni sect, and Renjun assigned his adopted son-in-law Jikken at Chosho-ji Temple and Raishu SHIMOTSUMA to deal with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>超勝寺は先の本覚寺蓮恵の一件以来、本覚寺と並んで賀州三ヶ寺から圧迫を受けていたが元々は蓮如以前からの由緒のある末寺であり、北陸全域に門徒を抱えており、｢北の超勝寺・南の本覚寺｣と呼ばれてきた状況は加賀一向一揆後も変わりがなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chosho-ji Temple had been oppressed in the same way as Hongaku-ji Temple by Gashu Sanka-ji Temples since the incident caused by Rene at Hongaku-ji Temple as mentioned before, but it was originally a historic branch temple that had existed before Rennyo and had followers all around Hokuriku, and its fame as called &apos;Chosho-ji Temple in the north, Hongaku-ji Temple in the south&apos; was invariable after the uprising of the Ikko sect followers in Kaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chosho-ji Temple had been oppressed in the same way as Hongaku-ji Temple by Gashu Sanka-ji Temples since the incident caused by Rene at Hongaku-ji Temple as mentioned before, but it was originally a historic branch temple that had existed before Rennyo and had followers all around Hokuriku, and its fame described as &apos;Chosho-ji Temple in the north, Hongaku-ji Temple in the south&apos; was invariable even after the uprising of the Ikko sect followers in Kaga.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chosho-ji Temple had been oppressed in the same way as Hongaku-ji Temple by Gashu Sanka-ji Temples since the incident caused by Rene at Hongaku-ji Temple as mentioned before, but it was originally a historic branch temple that had existed before Rennyo and had followers all around Hokuriku, and its fame described as &apos;Chosho-ji Temple in the north, Hongaku-ji Temple in the south&apos; was invariable even after the uprising of the Ikko sect followers in Kaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>実顕は法主証如名義で出された舅蓮淳の命令をたてに賀州三ヶ寺に相談もなくこれらの荘園代官を自己の門徒に交代させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jitsugen replaced the local governors of the manor into his own followers without any consultations with Gashu Sanka-ji Temples on the strength of the command of Renjun, a father-in-law of Shonyo, given under the name of hoshu Shonyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jitsugen replaced the local governors of the manor with his own followers without any consultations to Gashu Sanka-ji Temples on the strength of the command of Renjun, a father-in-law of Shonyo, issued under the name of hoshu Shonyo.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jitsugen replaced the local governors of the manor with his own followers without any consultations to Gashu Sanka-ji Temples on the strength of the command of Renjun, a father-in-law of Shonyo, issued under the name of hoshu Shonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>これに対して、賀州三ヶ寺側の蓮悟･蓮綱（蓮慶）父子・顕誓・実悟は本願寺に抗議するとともに実顕と下間頼秀を糾弾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reaction to this, Gashu Sanka-ji Temple&apos;s side--Rengo, Renko and his child Renkei, Kensei, and Jitsugo--protested to Hongan-ji Temple and denounced Jitsugen and Raishu SHIMOTSUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reaction to this, Gashu Sanka-ji Temple side--Rengo, Renko and his child Renkei, Kensei, and Jitsugo--protested to Hongan-ji Temple and denounced Jitsugen and Raishu SHIMOTSUMA.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reaction to this, Gashu Sanka-ji Temple side--Rengo, Renko and his child Renkei, Kensei, and Jitsugo--protested to Hongan-ji Temple and denounced Jitsugen and Raishu SHIMOTSUMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>そして享禄4年（1531年）5月9日_(旧暦)、賀州三ヶ寺は「三法令」・「一門一家制」違反などを理由に超勝寺討伐の命令を下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 9 (the old calendar), 1531, Gashu Sanka-ji Temples gave orders to subdue Chosho-ji Temple on the grounds that it violated &apos;Sanhorei&apos; and &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 25, 1531, Gashu Sanka-ji Temples gave orders to subdue Chosho-ji Temple on the grounds that it violated &apos;Sanhorei&apos; and &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System.&apos;</e>
<cmt>旧暦はユリウス暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 25, 1531, Gashu Sanka-ji Temples gave orders to subdue Chosho-ji Temple on the grounds that it violated &apos;Sanhorei&apos; and &apos;Ichimon-Ikke System.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>ところが、超勝寺は先の一件に恨みを抱く本覚寺蓮恵の救援を受けた上、更に北陸各地にいる両寺の門徒を蜂起させたために賀州三ヶ寺は思わぬ苦戦を強いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Chosho-ji Temple was reinforced by Rene at Hongaku-ji Temple, who had a grudge about the matter mentioned above, and made the followers of both temples at various place in Hokuriku rise up in revolt, and this suffered Gashu Sanka-ji Temples against their expectations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Chosho-ji Temple was reinforced by Rene of Hongaku-ji Temple, who held grudge since the above matter, and made the followers of the two temple all over Hokuriku rise up in revolt, which made Gashu Sanka-ji Temples suffer beyond their expectations.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Chosho-ji Temple was reinforced by Rene of Hongaku-ji Temple, who held grudge since the above matter, and made the followers of the two temple all over Hokuriku rise up in revolt, which made Gashu Sanka-ji Temples suffer beyond their expectations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>更に急遽山科本願寺に戻った下間頼秀の報告を受けた蓮淳は超勝寺実顕の行為はあくまでも法主の命令に従ったものであり、その命に逆らうものは法主への反逆であるとして超勝寺と全国の門徒に対して賀州三ヶ寺の討伐命令を証如の名で発したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Rennyo, who had received the report from Raishu SHIMOTSUMA who had rushed back to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, asserted that the act of Jitsugen at Chosho-ji Temple just followed the order from hoshu and that those who opposed the order were the traitors to hoshu, and gave orders under the name of Shonyo to Chosho-ji Temple and the followers throughout the country that Gashu Sanka-ji Temples be subjugated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, receiving the report from Raishu SHIMOTSUMA who rushed back to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, Rennyo asserted that Jitsugen of Chosho-ji Temple just followed the order from hoshu and that those who opposed the order were the traitors to hoshu, and gave orders under the name of Shonyo to Chosho-ji Temple and the followers throughout the country that Gashu Sanka-ji Temples be subjugated.</e>
<cmt>語順を入れ替えました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, receiving the report from Raishu SHIMOTSUMA who rushed back to Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, Rennyo asserted that Jitsugen of Chosho-ji Temple just followed the order from hoshu and that those who opposed the order were the traitors to hoshu, and gave orders under the name of Shonyo to Chosho-ji Temple and the followers throughout the country that Gashu Sanka-ji Temples be subjugated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>6月には東海地方・畿内の門徒が山科に結集して、実如の子である実円と下間頼盛に率いられて出陣し、門徒として知られていた飛騨国の内ヶ島氏の支援を受けて飛騨山中から加賀に侵入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, the followers from the Tokai region and Kinai were massed in Yamashina, left for the front under the command of Jitsunyo&apos;s child Jitsuen and Raisei SHIMOTSUMA, and invaded Kaga from the mountains in Hida with the support of the Uchigashima clan in Hida Province, who had been known as one of the followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, the followers from the Tokai region and Kinai massed in Yamashina, left for the front under the command of Jitsunyo&apos;s child Jitsuen and Raisei SHIMOTSUMA, and invaded Kaga from the Hida mountains with the support of the Uchigashima clan in Hida Province, who had been known as one of the followers.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, the followers from the Tokai region and Kinai massed in Yamashina, left for the front under the command of Jitsunyo&apos;s child Jitsuen and Raisei SHIMOTSUMA, and invaded Kaga from the Hida mountains with the support of the Uchigashima clan in Hida Province, who had been known as one of the followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>これを見た賀州三ヶ寺側の門徒の動揺は激しく、｢仏敵｣になることを恐れた寝返りが相次いだため、松岡寺と本泉寺はたちまち超勝寺と援軍を主力とする本願寺軍の手に奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking at this, the followers of Gashu Sanka-ji Temples became greatly upset, and one betrayal happened after another in fear of being &apos;Enemies of Buddhists,&apos; so Shoko-ji Temple and Honsen-ji Temple were immediately taken by Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s army organized from the followers of Chosho-ji Temple and the reinforcements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking at this, the followers of Gashu Sanka-ji Temples became greatly upset and one betrayal happened after another in fear of being &apos;Enemies of Buddhists&apos; so that Shoko-ji Temple and Honsen-ji Temple were immediately taken by Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s army organized by the followers of Chosho-ji Temple and the reinforcements.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking at this, the followers of Gashu Sanka-ji Temples became greatly upset and one betrayal happened after another in fear of being &apos;Enemies of Buddhists&apos; so that Shoko-ji Temple and Honsen-ji Temple were immediately taken by Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s army organized by the followers of Chosho-ji Temple and the reinforcements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>これに対して本願寺に打撃を与える機会を狙っていた越前の朝倉孝景 (10代当主)が賀州三ヶ寺の支援のために加賀へ出兵。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA (10th family head) in Echizen, who had been seeking a chance to give a blow to Hongan-ji Temple, dispatched troops to support Gashu Sanka-ji Temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakage ASAKURA (10th family head) in Echizen, who were seeking a chance to give a blow to Hongan-ji Temple, dispatched troops to support Gashu Sanka-ji Temples.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakage ASAKURA (10th family head) in Echizen, who were seeking a chance to give a blow to Hongan-ji Temple, dispatched troops to support Gashu Sanka-ji Temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>続いて能登畠山氏の一族で蓮能の実兄・畠山家俊も甥である実悟救援を理由に主君畠山義総の許しを得て加賀へ出兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, a family member of the Hatakeyama clan and Renno&apos;s real brother, Ietoshi HATAKEYAMA, sent troops to Kaga on the ground of assisting his nephew Jitsugo after he got permission from the lord Yoshifusa HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Ietoshi HATAKEYAMA, a family member of the Hatakeyama clan in Noto and Renno&apos;s real brother sent troops to Kaga on the ground of assisting his nephew Jitsugo after he got permission from the lord Yoshifusa HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>語順を入れ替えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Ietoshi HATAKEYAMA, a family member of the Hatakeyama clan in Noto and Renno&apos;s real brother sent troops to Kaga on the ground of assisting his nephew Jitsugo after he got permission from the lord Yoshifusa HATAKEYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>9月26日_(旧暦)、加賀国手取川において朝倉教景（宗滴）・賀州三ヶ寺連合軍が本願寺軍を一旦は破るものの、11月の津幡の戦いでは逆に本願寺側の反撃によって畠山家俊らが討ち死にして潰滅し、賀州三ヶ寺最後の光教寺も陥落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 26 (the older calendar), around the Tedori River in Kaga Province, the allied troops of Norikage (Soteki) ASAKURA and Gashu Sanka-ji Temples once defeated the troops of Hongan-ji Temple, but in the Battle of Tsubata in November the counterattack by Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s side killed Ietoshi HATAKEYAMA and others, annihilated the enemy, and captured Kokyo-ji Temple, the last temple of Gashu Sanka-ji Temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 5, around the Tedori River in Kaga Province, the allied troops of Norikage (Soteki) ASAKURA and Gashu Sanka-ji Temples once defeated the troops of Hongan-ji Temple, but in the Battle of Tsubata in November the counterattack by Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s side killed Ietoshi HATAKEYAMA and annihilated his troops and Kokyo-ji Temple, the last temple of Gashu Sanka-ji Temples was captured.</e>
<cmt>旧暦はユリウス暦に修正しました。不要な訳は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 5, around the Tedori River in Kaga Province, the allied troops of Norikage (Soteki) ASAKURA and Gashu Sanka-ji Temples once defeated the troops of Hongan-ji Temple, but in the Battle of Tsubata in November the counterattack by Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s side killed Ietoshi HATAKEYAMA and annihilated his troops and Kokyo-ji Temple, the last temple of Gashu Sanka-ji Temples was captured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>この戦いで蓮綱は幽閉されて間もなく死去、蓮慶は処刑され、蓮悟・顕誓・実悟は加賀を脱出して全国の末寺・門徒に対して引き続き追討命令が下され、6年後の旧賀州三ヶ寺門徒の本覚寺襲撃計画を理由に正式に破門された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this battle, Renko was placed into confinement and died soon after, Renkei was executed, Rengo, Kensei, and Jitsugo fled from Kaga, and they were hunted down by branch temples and followers all through the country under orders, and six years later they were officially excommunicated for the Hongaku-ji Temple assault plan executed by the old Gashu Sanka-ji Temples&apos; followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Renko was confined and died soon, Renkei was executed, Rengo, Kensei, and Jitsugo fled from Kaga and became the subject of orders to hunt them down issued to branch temples and followers all through the country, and six years later they were officially excommunicated for the Hongaku-ji Temple assault plan executed by the old Gashu Sanka-ji Temples followers.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Renko was confined and died soon, Renkei was executed, Rengo, Kensei, and Jitsugo fled from Kaga and became the subject of orders to hunt them down issued to branch temples and followers all through the country, and six years later they were officially excommunicated for the Hongaku-ji Temple assault plan executed by the old Gashu Sanka-ji Temples followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>これによって本願寺法主を頂点とする支配体制が完成し、同時に主だった一族を悉く粛清した外祖父蓮淳が法主・証如を擁して絶対的な地位を築き上げることになる（さすがの蓮淳も兄弟や甥を殺害したり追放したことを後には後悔したらしく、乱から19年後の死の間際になって証如に要望して顕誓・実悟ら生き残りの復帰が認められている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This perfected the ruling system placing Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s hoshu at the top, and at the same time a maternal grand father Renjun, who had purged the major family members, started to build an absolute position under the name of hoshu Shonyo (even Renjun may have later repented killing or banishing his brothers and his nephew since, nineteen years after the battle, just before he died, he asked Shonyo to permit reassociation of the survivors, Kensei, Jitsugo, and others).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This perfected the ruling system with Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s hoshu at the top, and at the same time the maternal grandfather Renjun, who had purged the major family members, started to build an absolute position under the name of hoshu Shonyo (Renjun seems to have later repented killing or banishing his brothers and his nephew because, nineteen years after the battle, just before he died, he asked Shonyo to permit reassociation of the survivors, Kensei, Jitsugo, and others).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This perfected the ruling system with Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s hoshu at the top, and at the same time the maternal grandfather Renjun, who had purged the major family members, started to build an absolute position under the name of hoshu Shonyo (Renjun seems to have later repented killing or banishing his brothers and his nephew because, nineteen years after the battle, just before he died, he asked Shonyo to permit reassociation of the survivors, Kensei, Jitsugo, and others).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>この内紛は一向一揆同士の戦いに発展した事から、本願寺法主の命令を奉じた超勝寺・本覚寺側を「大一揆」、加賀の国主権限を認められながら反逆者として粛清された賀州三ヶ寺側を「小一揆」と呼ぶ事からこれを「大小一揆」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This internal conflict developed into the battle between the Ikko sects, and the Chosho-ji Temple and Hongan-ji Temple side which were given orders from Hongan-ji hoshu was called &apos;Dai-Ikki&apos; (Big League), and the Gashu Sanka-ji Temples side which was purged as traitors despite the fact that they were authorized as governors of the Kaga Domain was called &apos;Sho-Ikki&apos; (Little League), and that is why this battle was called &apos;Daisho Ikki.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This internal conflict developed into the battle between the Ikko sects in which the Chosho-ji Temple and Hongan-ji Temple side which confined to orders from Hongan-ji hoshu was called &apos;Dai-Ikki&apos; (Big League) and the Gashu Sanka-ji Temples side which was purged as traitors despite they were authorized as governors of the Kaga Domain was called &apos;Sho-Ikki&apos; (Little League), which is why this battle is also called &apos;Daisho Ikki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>接続詞を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This internal conflict developed into the battle between the Ikko sects in which the Chosho-ji Temple and Hongan-ji Temple side which confined to orders from Hongan-ji hoshu was called &apos;Dai-Ikki&apos; (Big League) and the Gashu Sanka-ji Temples side which was purged as traitors despite they were authorized as governors of the Kaga Domain was called &apos;Sho-Ikki&apos; (Little League), which is why this battle is also called &apos;Daisho Ikki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="102">
<j>これによって加賀を初めとする北陸地方の門徒は本願寺派遣の代官による直接支配下に置かれることとなり、天文15年(1546年)にその象徴として金沢市に尾山御坊が建立されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this battle, the followers in the Hokuriku region including Kaga were under the direct dominance of the magistrates belonging to the Hongan-ji School, and in 1546 Oyama Gobo was built in Kanazawa City as its symbol.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this battle, the followers in the Hokuriku region including Kaga fell under the direct dominance of the magistrates dispatched by the Hongan-ji Temple, and in 1546 Oyama Gobo was built in Kanazawa City as its symbol.</e>
<cmt>「本願寺派遣の」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this battle, the followers in the Hokuriku region including Kaga fell under the direct dominance of the magistrates dispatched by the Hongan-ji Temple, and in 1546 Oyama Gobo was built in Kanazawa City as its symbol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>天文の錯乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenbun War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenbun War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenbun War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>畠山・三好討伐</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjugation of Hatakeyama and Miyoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subjugation of Hatakeyama and Miyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subjugation of Hatakeyama and Miyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>詳細については飯盛山城飯盛城の戦いを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to the Battle of Imoriyama Castle for the details.</e>
<cmt>「飯盛山城」と「飯盛城」の2つ書いてありますが、「飯盛山城」で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to the Battle of Imoriyama Castle for the details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to the Battle of Imoriyama Castle for the details.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="104">
<j>享禄の錯乱の最中であった6月、大物崩れの勝者として細川高国を自害させ、声望を高めた細川晴元であったが、その晴元支持派だった蓮淳の名声も更に高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, in the middle of the Kyoroku War, Harumoto HOSOKAWA enhanced his fame as a victor of the Battle of Daimotsu and as the one who made Takakuni HOSOKAWA commit suicide, and it also increased the reputation of Renjun who supported Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, in the middle of the Kyoroku War, Harumoto HOSOKAWA enhanced his fame by winning the Battle of Daimotsu and making Takakuni HOSOKAWA commit suicide, which also enhanced the reputation of Renjun who supported Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>自然な文章になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, in the middle of the Kyoroku War, Harumoto HOSOKAWA enhanced his fame by winning the Battle of Daimotsu and making Takakuni HOSOKAWA commit suicide, which also enhanced the reputation of Renjun who supported Harumoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>その頃、主家である河内守護 畠山義堯から離反して晴元への転属を画策する木沢長政から、晴元への内応の仲介依頼を受けた蓮淳であったが、間もなくこの事を義宣に知られてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Renjun was asked by Nagamasa KIZAWA, who had tried to leave his master, Yoshitake (Yoshinobu) HATAKEYAMA, governor of Kawachi Province, and also had tried to belong to Harumoto, to intervene for his betrayal, but soon it was known by Yoshinobu.</e>
<cmt>「義宣」は「畠山義堯」の別名のようですが、いきなりでてくると分からないので、括弧で入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Renjun was asked by Nagamasa KIZAWA, who was trying to leave his master Yoshitake (Yoshinobu) HATAKEYAMA, the governor of Kawachi Province, to belong to Harumoto, to intervene for his betrayal, but it soon came to Yoshinobu&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>時制と言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Renjun was asked by Nagamasa KIZAWA, who was trying to leave his master Yoshitake (Yoshinobu) HATAKEYAMA, the governor of Kawachi Province, to belong to Harumoto, to intervene for his betrayal, but it soon came to Yoshinobu&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="106">
<j>同年8月、木沢討伐に乗り出した義宣には三好元長まで加担した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1531, Yoshinobu started to suppress KIZAWA and there even Motonaga MIYOSHI participated in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, 1531, Yoshinobu started to suppress KIZAWA, which was joined even by Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 1531, Yoshinobu started to suppress KIZAWA, which was joined even by Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>一方、長政からの救援要請を受けた晴元は、対応に苦慮。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harumoto, who was requested for support by Nagamasa, did not know how to deal with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harumoto did not know how to deal with Nagamasa&apos;s request for support.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harumoto did not know how to deal with Nagamasa&apos;s request for support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>自分に度々意見する元長の存在を疎ましく思っていたとはいえ、劣勢の長政への肩入れも得策ではなかったためか、両軍への撤兵要請で事を収めようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although he had felt annoying about Motonaga, who often criticized him, it was not advantageous to help almost losing Nagamasa, and therefore he attempted to put this battle to an end by calling on withdrawal to both sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although he was annoyed about Motonaga who often criticized him, it was not advantageous to help almost losing Nagamasa, and therefore he attempted to put this battle to an end by calling on withdrawal to both sides.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although he was annoyed about Motonaga who often criticized him, it was not advantageous to help almost losing Nagamasa, and therefore he attempted to put this battle to an end by calling on withdrawal to both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="109">
<j>だが翌享禄5年（1532年）5月、畠山・三好連合は、木沢長政を再攻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in May, 1532, the allied troops of Hatakeyama and Miyoshi attacked Nagamasa KIZAWA again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in May, 1532, the allied troops of Hatakeyama and Miyoshi attacked Nagamasa KIZAWA again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in May, 1532, the allied troops of Hatakeyama and Miyoshi attacked Nagamasa KIZAWA again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>そこで晴元は、木沢の一件の発端を作った蓮淳に対して、義堯と元長の討伐への協力を依頼した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Harumoto requested Renjun, who was the cause of the incident about KIZAWA, to cooperate in putting down Yoshitaka and Motonaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So Harumoto requested Renjun, who caused the KIZAWA incident, to cooperate in putting down Yoshitaka and Motonaga.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So Harumoto requested Renjun, who caused the KIZAWA incident, to cooperate in putting down Yoshitaka and Motonaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>『単なる武家の騒乱でありながら宗門が参戦する』事態を、蓮淳は了承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun accepted the situation under which &quot;a religious community participated in a war between samurai families.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun accepted the situation where &quot;a religious community participated in a mere war between samurai families.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「単なる」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun accepted the situation where &quot;a religious community participated in a mere war between samurai families.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="112">
<j>畿内における宗門の責任者であった蓮淳は、熱心な法華宗徒であった元長に対し深い恨みを抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Renjun, who was responsible for the religious community in Kinai, had strong resentment against Motonaga, who was a pious follower of the Hokke sect (Nichiren sect).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Renjun, who was responsible for the religious community in Kinai, had strong resentment against Motonaga, who was a pious follower of the Hokke sect (Nichiren sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Renjun, who was responsible for the religious community in Kinai, had strong resentment against Motonaga, who was a pious follower of the Hokke sect (Nichiren sect).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>以前、本願寺門徒による和泉や山城の法華宗徒への圧迫の一件を聞きつけた三好元長によって、本願寺側は弾圧を加えられた事があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, Motonaga MIYOSHI, who had heard the Hongan-ji Temple followers persecute the Hokke sect followers in Izumi and Yamashiro, oppressed the Hongan-ji Temples side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, Motonaga MIYOSHI, who had heard the Hongan-ji Temple followers persecute the Hokke sect followers in Izumi and Yamashiro, oppressed the Hongan-ji Temples side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, Motonaga MIYOSHI, who had heard the Hongan-ji Temple followers persecute the Hokke sect followers in Izumi and Yamashiro, oppressed the Hongan-ji Temples side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>そのため蓮淳は、17歳になった証如に勧めて法主である証如自らに出陣させ、畿内における『浄土真宗と法華宗の最終決戦』と位置づけることで全畿内の門徒結集を促して、この戦いを大きく盛り上げたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is why Renjun recommended Shonyo, who turned 17, to go for a battle for himself as hoshu, and put this battle as &quot;the ultimate battle between Jodo Shinshu and the Hokke sect&quot; in Kinai, to encourage all the followers in Kinai to participate in this battle and to make this battle a big campaign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is why Renjun recommended Shonyo, the hoshu himself who turned 17, to go for a battle, and positioned this battle as &quot;the ultimate battle between Jodo Shinshu and the Hokke sect&quot; in Kinai to encourage all the followers in Kinai to participate in this battle, in order to make this battle a big campaign.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is why Renjun recommended Shonyo, the hoshu himself who turned 17, to go for a battle, and positioned this battle as &quot;the ultimate battle between Jodo Shinshu and the Hokke sect&quot; in Kinai to encourage all the followers in Kinai to participate in this battle, in order to make this battle a big campaign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="115">
<j>同年6月15日 (旧暦)（7月17日）、10万（一説には20万）と言われた本願寺門徒の参戦で戦況は一変。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 15 (the old calendar) (July 17), 1532, the battle situation drastically changed by the participation of 100 thousand (200 thousand in a theory) of the Hongan-ji Temple followers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 17, 1532, the battle situation drastically changed by the participation of 100,000 (200,000 in a theory) Hongan-ji Temple followers.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は削除しました。数字の書き方を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 17, 1532, the battle situation drastically changed by the participation of 100,000 (200,000 in a theory) Hongan-ji Temple followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>逃げ切れなかった畠山義堯を自害させた上に、同月6月20日 (旧暦)（7月22日）には包囲した堺市の顕本寺 (堺市)で三好元長を自害に追い込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA, who could not successfully run away, killed himself, and further on June 20 (the old calendar) (July 22) Motonaga MIYOSHI was forced to take his own life at besieged Kenpon-ji Temple (of Sakai City) in Sakai City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA failed to run away and killed himself as well as Motonaga MIYOSHI who was forced to take his own life at besieged Kenpon-ji Temple in Sakai City on July 22.</e>
<cmt>重複していた堺市は削除しました。助長な表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitaka HATAKEYAMA failed to run away and killed himself as well as Motonaga MIYOSHI who was forced to take his own life at besieged Kenpon-ji Temple in Sakai City on July 22.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>その上、堺に鎮座していた足利義維の四国追放も重なって堺公方も消滅させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, who had dwelled in Sakai City, was banished to Shikoku, and consequently Sakaikubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City) perished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, who had dwelled in Sakai City, was banished to Shikoku, and consequently Sakaikubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City) perished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Yoshitsuna ASHIKAGA, who had dwelled in Sakai City, was banished to Shikoku, and consequently Sakaikubo (the municipal government based in Sakai City) perished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="118">
<j>ところが、一向一揆にとって法華宗の象徴ともいうべき仏敵 三好元長との戦いが終わっても一揆軍の蜂起は収まらず、法華宗以外の仏教宗派を追放すべきだとする門徒の声が、証如や蓮淳による静止命令をも振り払った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the uprising of the Ikki army did not calm down after the battle against the enemy of Buddhists and a symbol of the Hokke sect for the Ikko sect, Motonaga MIYOSHI, and the voice of followers saying that other Buddhist schools than the Hokke sect should be driven away overwhelmed the withholding orders by Shonyo and Renjun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the uprising of the Ikki army did not calm down even after the battle against Motonaga MIYOSHI, the enemy of Buddhists and a symbol of the Hokke sect, and the voice of followers to drive away other Buddhist schools than the Hokke sect overwhelmed the withholding orders by Shonyo and Renjun.</e>
<cmt>「法華宗以外」とありますが、その逆だと思われます。もしくは「法華宗以外の仏教宗派も」ではないでしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the uprising of the Ikki army did not calm down even after the battle against Motonaga MIYOSHI, the enemy of Buddhists and a symbol of the Hokke sect, and the voice of followers to drive away other Buddhist schools than the Hokke sect overwhelmed the withholding orders by Shonyo and Renjun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="119">
<j>大和国では守護である興福寺と同国内で戦国大名化しつつあった筒井順興・越智利基を攻め滅ぼすべく一揆軍が奈良に突入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Yamato Province, the Ikki army charged into Nara to destroy a provincial governorate Kofuku-ji Temple, and Junko TSUTSUI and Toshimoto OCHI, who were growing into the figures like daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period in the province.</e>
<cmt>「越智利基」の読みが確認できませんでした。「おちとしもと」と読んでいます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Yamato Province, the Ikki army charged into Nara to destroy the provincial governorate Kofuku-ji Temple and Junko TSUTSUI and Toshimoto OCHI, who were growing like daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period in the province.</e>
<cmt>助長な表現は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Yamato Province, the Ikki army charged into Nara to destroy the provincial governorate Kofuku-ji Temple and Junko TSUTSUI and Toshimoto OCHI, who were growing like daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>一揆は本願寺にとってもゆかりがある大乗院（蓮如幼少時修行の場所）を始めとして興福寺の全ての塔頭を焼き払い、猿沢池のコイや春日社のシカも悉く食い尽くされたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ikki army burned down all the sub-temples of Kofuku-ji Temple including Daijo-in Temple (the practice spot of Rennyo in his childhood), where had some connection with Hongan-ji Temple, and it is said that all the carp in Sarusawa-ike Pond and all the deer in Kasuga-sha Shrine were eaten up by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ikki army burned down all the sub-temples of Kofuku-ji Temple including Daijo-in Temple (the practice spot of Rennyo in his childhood) which had some connection with Hongan-ji Temple, and it is said that all the carp in Sarusawa-ike Pond and all the deer in Kasuga-sha Shrine were eaten up by them.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ikki army burned down all the sub-temples of Kofuku-ji Temple including Daijo-in Temple (the practice spot of Rennyo in his childhood) which had some connection with Hongan-ji Temple, and it is said that all the carp in Sarusawa-ike Pond and all the deer in Kasuga-sha Shrine were eaten up by them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>最終的には筒井氏・越智氏の援軍によって一向一揆は奈良から追われたものの、本願寺は面目を失墜して奈良の永代禁制を受け入れざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, the Ikko-Ikki army was expelled from Nara by the reinforcements of the Tsutsui and Ochi clans, but Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s fame was ravaged and could not avoid accepting the permanent prohibition of entering Nara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the Ikko-Ikki army was expelled from Nara by the reinforcements of the Tsutsui and Ochi clans, but Hongan-ji Temple lost its prestige and could not avoid accepting the permanent prohibition of entering Nara.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the Ikko-Ikki army was expelled from Nara by the reinforcements of the Tsutsui and Ochi clans, but Hongan-ji Temple lost its prestige and could not avoid accepting the permanent prohibition of entering Nara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>山科本願寺焼討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fire attack on Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fire attack on Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fire attack on Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="122">
<j>詳細については山科本願寺山科本願寺の戦いを参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the details, refer to the Battle of Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>「山科本願寺」がニ回書かれているので、一回で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the details, refer to the Battle of Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the details, refer to the Battle of Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>これに驚いた細川晴元は室町幕府管領の立場から、本願寺との決別と一向一揆鎮圧を決意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surprised at this, Harumoto HOSOKAWA decided to separate from Hongan-ji Temple and suppress the Ikko-Ikki army from the position of Muromachi bakufu kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprised at this, Harumoto HOSOKAWA decided to separate from Hongan-ji Temple and suppress the Ikko-Ikki army from the position of Muromachi bakufu kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprised at this, Harumoto HOSOKAWA decided to separate from Hongan-ji Temple and suppress the Ikko-Ikki army from the position of Muromachi bakufu kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Muromachi bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>これを知った蓮淳は一向一揆の行動を事実上追認して細川晴元攻撃を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Knowing it, Renjun virtually affirmed the action of the Ikko-Ikki army and ordered to attack Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Knowing it, Renjun virtually affirmed the action of the Ikko-Ikki army and ordered to attack Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Knowing it, Renjun virtually affirmed the action of the Ikko-Ikki army and ordered to attack Harumoto HOSOKAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>ところが晴元の命令にまず木沢長政が従い、更に本願寺を嫌う近江守護六角定頼と一向一揆に対抗する形で京都と山城国の法華宗徒が編成した法華一揆が呼応した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, first, Nagamasa KIZAWA obeyed Harumoto&apos;s order, and then responded Omi shugo (the governor of Omi Province) Sadayori ROKKAKU, who abhorred Hongan-ji Temple, and the Hokke-Ikki army mobilized by the Hokke sect followers in Kyoto and Yamashiro Province to confront the Ikko-Ikki army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nagamasa KIZAWA first responded to Harumoto&apos;s order, followed by Omi shugo (the governor of Omi Province) Sadayori ROKKAKU who abhorred Hongan-ji Temple, and the Hokke-Ikki army mobilized by the Hokke sect followers in Kyoto and Yamashiro Province to confront the Ikko-Ikki army.</e>
<cmt>接続詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nagamasa KIZAWA first responded to Harumoto&apos;s order, followed by Omi shugo (the governor of Omi Province) Sadayori ROKKAKU who abhorred Hongan-ji Temple, and the Hokke-Ikki army mobilized by the Hokke sect followers in Kyoto and Yamashiro Province to confront the Ikko-Ikki army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="126">
<j>天文に改元後の同年8月7日_(旧暦)、京都に集結した法華一揆は京都にある本願寺教団の寺院を次々に攻撃、8月12日_(旧暦)には六角氏と連合して蓮淳のいる大津の顕証寺を攻め落とし、続いて8月23日_(旧暦)には、証如のいる山科本願寺を3万の大軍が包囲して、8月24日_(旧暦)には同寺も炎上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 7 (the old calendar), 1532, after the era was changed to Tenbun, the Hokke-Ikki army which assembled in Kyoto attacked temples after temples belonging to the Hongan-ji Temple community, and on August 12 (the old calendar) they associated with the Rokkaku clan and captured Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu, where Renjun stayed, and on August 23 (the old calendar) they besieged Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, where Shonyo stayed, with a large force of 30 thousand men, and on August 24 (the old calendar) Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple went up in flames.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 6, 1532, after the era changed to Tenbun, the Hokke-Ikki army assembled in Kyoto and attacked temples after temples belonging to the Hongan-ji Temple community, and on September 11 they associated with the Rokkaku clan and captured Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu where Renjun stayed, and on September 23 they besieged Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple where Shonyo stayed, with a large force of 30,000 men, and on August 22 (the old calendar) Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple went up in flames.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。旧暦はユリウス暦に修正しました。数字の書き方を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 6, 1532, after the era changed to Tenbun, the Hokke-Ikki army assembled in Kyoto and attacked temples after temples belonging to the Hongan-ji Temple community, and on September 11 they associated with the Rokkaku clan and captured Kensho-ji Temple in Otsu where Renjun stayed, and on September 23 they besieged Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple where Shonyo stayed, with a large force of 30,000 men, and on August 22 (the old calendar) Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple went up in flames.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>ところが肝腎の蓮淳は顕証寺陥落の際にもう一つの拠点であった伊勢長島願証寺へと逃走して息子実恵 (浄土真宗)の元に潜伏した（ちなみに前述の本福寺の3度目の破門が行われたのはこの最中であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Kensho-ji Temple fell down, however, the most important figure Renjun ran away to another foothold Ise-Nagashima Gansho-ji Temple, and hid himself in his son&apos;s, Jitsue&apos;s (Jodo Shishu) (by the way, the third excommunication of Honpuku-ji Temple, mentioned above, was done in the course of this event).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Kensho-ji Temple fell down, however, the most important figure Renjun ran away to another foothold Ise-Nagashima Gansho-ji Temple, and hid himself in his son Jitsue&apos;s place (Jodo Shishu) (by the way, the third excommunication of Honpuku-ji Temple, mentioned above, was done in the course of this event).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Kensho-ji Temple fell down, however, the most important figure Renjun ran away to another foothold Ise-Nagashima Gansho-ji Temple, and hid himself in his son Jitsue&apos;s place (Jodo Shishu) (by the way, the third excommunication of Honpuku-ji Temple, mentioned above, was done in the course of this event).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>孤立した証如は山科本願寺に退避していた蓮如の末子・実従が発見して辛うじて石山御坊に連れ出したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isolated Shonyo was found by Renyo&apos;s youngest son Jitsuju, who had retreated into Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, and was narrowly carried away to Ishiyama Gobo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isolated Shonyo was found by Renyo&apos;s youngest son Jitsuju, who had retreated into Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, and was narrowly carried away to Ishiyama Gobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isolated Shonyo was found by Renyo&apos;s youngest son Jitsuju, who had retreated into Yamashina Hongan-ji Temple, and was narrowly carried away to Ishiyama Gobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>石山本願寺への移転と和議成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transfer to Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple and the reconciliation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transfer to Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple and the reconciliation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transfer to Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple and the reconciliation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="129">
<j>証如は石山御坊を「石山本願寺」と改めて、新たな根拠地として蓮淳に代わって門徒達を指揮していた下間頼秀・頼盛兄弟に防戦を命じたが、続いて富田教行寺が攻め落とされて石山本願寺もまた細川・六角・法華一揆連合軍に包囲された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonyo renamed Ishiyama Gobo &apos;Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple&apos; and put it as a new foothold, and ordered Raishu SHIMOTSUMA and his brother Raisei SHIMOTSUMA, who was taking command in place of Renjun, to defend the temple, but Tomita Kyogyo-ji Temple was captured, and Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple was surrounded by the allied army of Hosokawa, Rokkaku, and the Hokke-Ikki army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonyo renamed Ishiyama Gobo &apos;Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple&apos; and made it his new foothold, and ordered Raishu and Raisei SHIMOTSUMA who were taking command in place of Renjun, to defend the temple, but Tomita Kyogyo-ji Temple was captured and Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple was surrounded by the allied army of Hosokawa, Rokkaku, and the Hokke-Ikki army.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonyo renamed Ishiyama Gobo &apos;Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple&apos; and made it his new foothold, and ordered Raishu and Raisei SHIMOTSUMA who were taking command in place of Renjun, to defend the temple, but Tomita Kyogyo-ji Temple was captured and Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple was surrounded by the allied army of Hosokawa, Rokkaku, and the Hokke-Ikki army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>ところが翌天文2年（1533年）に入ると、細川高国の弟・細川晴国や三好元長派であった波多野稙通ら晴元に恨みを抱く勢力と連携して晴元を攻撃して一時包囲を解くことに成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the year of 1533 started, however, they could temporarily broke the besiegement by attacking Harumoto in association with the forces having hard feelings against Harumoto such as Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s brother Harukuni HOSOKAWA and Tanemichi HATANO belonging to the sect of Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, after turning into 1533, they temporarily broke the besiegement by attacking Harumoto in association with the forces having hard feelings against Harumoto such as Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s brother Harukuni HOSOKAWA and Tanemichi HATANO belonging to the sect of Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, after turning into 1533, they temporarily broke the besiegement by attacking Harumoto in association with the forces having hard feelings against Harumoto such as Takakuni HOSOKAWA&apos;s brother Harukuni HOSOKAWA and Tanemichi HATANO belonging to the sect of Motonaga MIYOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>だが、それは逆に将軍足利義晴から晴元へ下された本願寺討伐令という大義名分を与えるだけに終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This adversely resulted in Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA&apos;s order to suppress Hongan-ji Temple, giving a legitimate reason to Harumoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This adversely ended up in giving a legitimate reason to Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA&apos;s order to Harumoto to suppress Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>語順を入れ替えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This adversely ended up in giving a legitimate reason to Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA&apos;s order to Harumoto to suppress Hongan-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>その後戦況は一進一退を続けたが、天文4年（1536年）6月には細川軍の総攻撃が始まると、当時の後奈良天皇の日記にも「本願寺滅亡」と記されたほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the situation of the war got better and worse, but in June, 1536, the Hosokawa army launched an all-out attack, and the Hongan-ji Temple side was as ruined as written as &apos;Hongan-ji Temple destroyed&apos; in the diary of Emperor Gonara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the situation of the war got better and worse, but in June, 1536, the Hosokawa army launched an all-out attack and the Hongan-ji Temple side was as ruined as written as &apos;Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed&apos; in the diary of Emperor Gonara.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the situation of the war got better and worse, but in June, 1536, the Hosokawa army launched an all-out attack and the Hongan-ji Temple side was as ruined as written as &apos;Hongan-ji Temple was destroyed&apos; in the diary of Emperor Gonara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="133">
<j>これを機に証如も4月に長島から呼び戻した蓮淳とともに和議を図り、下間兄弟を今回の一揆の扇動者としてその責任を転嫁することで証如・蓮淳の責任を不問とし、彼らや近江などの畿内門徒の総破門を行うことを条件にこの年の11月に幕府・細川・六角との和議が成立したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this timing, Shonyo began peace negotiations with Renjun, who had been called back from Nagashima in April, and with the conditions that Shonyo and Renjun were discharged by imputing the responsibility of having instigated this Ikki uprising to Shimotsuma brothers and that they and all the followers in Kinai were excommunicated, the reconciliation with the bakufu, Hosokawa, and Rokkaku was achieved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this timing, Shonyo began peace negotiations with Renjun who was called back from Nagashima in April, and Shonyo and Renjun were discharged by imputing the responsibility of having instigated this Ikki uprising to Shimotsuma brothers and, with the condition that they and all the followers in Kinai be excommunicated, the reconciliation between the bakufu, Hosokawa, and Rokkaku was achieved in November.</e>
<cmt>11月の訳を補いました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this timing, Shonyo began peace negotiations with Renjun who was called back from Nagashima in April, and Shonyo and Renjun were discharged by imputing the responsibility of having instigated this Ikki uprising to Shimotsuma brothers and, with the condition that they and all the followers in Kinai be excommunicated, the reconciliation between the bakufu, Hosokawa, and Rokkaku was achieved in November.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>和議終了後も蓮淳は証如の求めに応じて石山本願寺に留って成人した証如の補佐役として従来の立場を事実上回復し、天文19年（1550年）に同寺で没するまで蓮淳は証如の名において本願寺の事実上の最高指導者としての地位を保持し続けることになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the reconciliation, Renjun continued to stay in Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple at Shonyo&apos;s request and practically recovered the position as he used to be in, as the assistant of Shonyo, who came of age, and until he died at this temple in 1550 Renjun kept the position as the virtual supreme leader of Hongan-ji Temple under the name of Shonyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the reconciliation, Renjun continued to stay in Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple at Shonyo&apos;s request and practically recovered the position as he used to be in, as the assistant of Shonyo, who came of age, and until he died at this temple in 1550 Renjun kept the position as the virtual supreme leader of Hongan-ji Temple under the name of Shonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the reconciliation, Renjun continued to stay in Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple at Shonyo&apos;s request and practically recovered the position as he used to be in, as the assistant of Shonyo, who came of age, and until he died at this temple in 1550 Renjun kept the position as the virtual supreme leader of Hongan-ji Temple under the name of Shonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 赤井彗星(id:18381), 与左衛門(id:159462), ZassouTori(id:136771), Sarusaru(id:52747), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 経済準学士(id:22656), 水野白楓(id:22811), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Point136(id:211299), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Comyu(id:58135), Toki-ho(id:10691), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>