<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大津城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Otsu-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Otsu-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Otsu-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大津城の戦い（おおつじょうのたたかい）とは、（慶長5年9月7日 (旧暦)（1600年10月13日）） - 慶長5年9月15日 (旧暦)（1600年10月21日））まで行なわれた戦い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Otsu-jo Castle took place from October 13, 1600 to October 21, 1600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Otsu-jo Castle took place from October 13, 1600 to October 21, 1600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Otsu-jo Castle took place from October 13, 1600 to October 21, 1600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>豊臣秀吉の死後、天下人の座を狙う徳川家康と、豊臣氏擁護の立場から家康と対立する石田三成ら反家康派の対立は、慶長5年の会津攻めを契機として表面化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died, the opposition between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who set out to rule the world, and Mitsunari ISHIDA as a defender of the Toyotomi clan with anti-Ieyasu group came to the fore in the wake of the attack on Aizu in 1600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died, the opposition between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who set out to rule the world, Mitsunari ISHIDA, a defender of the Toyotomi clan and member of the anti-Ieyasu group, came to the forefront in the wake of the attack on Aizu in 1600.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI died, the opposition between Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who set out to rule the world, Mitsunari ISHIDA, a defender of the Toyotomi clan and member of the anti-Ieyasu group, came to the forefront in the wake of the attack on Aizu in 1600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>石田三成は家康が会津攻めに赴いたことを好機として、大谷吉継や毛利輝元ら反家康派の諸大名を糾合して挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking the opportunity of Ieyasu&apos;s going off to attack Aizu, Mitsunari ISHIDA rallied anti-Ieyasu daimyos (feudal lords) such as Yoshitsugu OTANI and Terumoto MORI and took up arms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking the opportunity presented by Ieyasu leaving to attack Aizu, Mitsunari ISHIDA rallied anti-Ieyasu daimyos (feudal lords) such as Yoshitsugu OTANI and Terumoto MORI and took up arms.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking the opportunity presented by Ieyasu leaving to attack Aizu, Mitsunari ISHIDA rallied anti-Ieyasu daimyos (feudal lords) such as Yoshitsugu OTANI and Terumoto MORI and took up arms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そして、家康が畿内を留守にしている隙をついて伏見城を落とし、次いで北陸地方や伊勢国伊勢方面の平定に乗り出していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then he captured the Fushiki-jo Castle exploiting Ieyasu&apos;s absence from Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), and after that he set out to suppress Hokuriku region and Ise area in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then captured the Fushiki-jo Castle exploiting Ieyasu&apos;s absence from the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), and after that he set out to suppress the Hokuriku region and Ise area in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then captured the Fushiki-jo Castle exploiting Ieyasu&apos;s absence from the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), and after that he set out to suppress the Hokuriku region and Ise area in Ise Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>北陸方面の平定には、越前国敦賀の大名である大谷吉継が担当することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsugu OTANI, who was a daimyo in Tsuruga, Echizen Province, came to handle the suppression of Hokuriku area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsugu OTANI, who was a daimyo in Tsuruga, Echizen Province, assisted with the suppression of the Hokuriku area.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsugu OTANI, who was a daimyo in Tsuruga, Echizen Province, assisted with the suppression of the Hokuriku area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして、この北陸方面軍の一員として、近江国大津城の城主・京極高次が加わっていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as a member of Hokuriku area force Takatsugu KYOGOKU, the lord of Otsu-jo Castle in Omi Province, was in Yoshitsugu army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And as a member of the Hokuriku area force Takatsugu KYOGOKU, the lord of Otsu-jo Castle in Omi Province, was part of the Yoshitsugu army.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And as a member of the Hokuriku area force Takatsugu KYOGOKU, the lord of Otsu-jo Castle in Omi Province, was part of the Yoshitsugu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが高次は吉継が北陸から美濃国へと転進する最中に突如東軍に寝返り、手勢3000名を率いて大津城に籠城し防備を固め始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, while Yoshitsugu was changing his course from Hokuriku area to Mino Province, Takatsugu suddenly switched to the East side, led his 3000 soldiers to Otsu-jo Castle and fortified the defense in there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, while Yoshitsugu was changing his course from the Hokuriku area to Mino Province, Takatsugu suddenly switched to the East side, led his 3,000 soldiers to Otsu-jo Castle and fortified the defenses there.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, while Yoshitsugu was changing his course from the Hokuriku area to Mino Province, Takatsugu suddenly switched to the East side, led his 3,000 soldiers to Otsu-jo Castle and fortified the defenses there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この出来事に大坂城の淀殿は驚き、高次夫人に使者を遣わして（淀殿の妹である初（常高院）は高次の正室として城中にあった）、停戦・降伏を求めるが大津側は断固として拒否。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo; Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s concubine and the mother of Hideyori, the heir to the Toyotomi clan) was surprised to hear the treachery and dispatched an envoy to Takatsugu&apos;s wife (Yodo-dono&apos;s younger sister Hatsu/Joko-in was in Otsu-jo Castle as she was the Takatsugu&apos;s lawful wife) to call for truce and surrender but Otsu side never accepted it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo; Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s concubine and the mother of Hideyori, the heir to the Toyotomi clan) was surprised to hear of this treachery and dispatched an envoy to Takatsugu&apos;s wife (Yodo-dono&apos;s younger sister Hatsu/Joko-in was at Otsu-jo Castle as she was Takatsugu&apos;s lawful wife) to call for a truce and surrender, but the Otsu side never accepted it.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yodo-dono (Lady Yodo; Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s concubine and the mother of Hideyori, the heir to the Toyotomi clan) was surprised to hear of this treachery and dispatched an envoy to Takatsugu&apos;s wife (Yodo-dono&apos;s younger sister Hatsu/Joko-in was at Otsu-jo Castle as she was Takatsugu&apos;s lawful wife) to call for a truce and surrender, but the Otsu side never accepted it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>これに対して西軍側は高次の裏切りに対する報復として、毛利元康を大将とし、それに立花宗茂、毛利秀包、筑紫広門ら九州方面の諸大名の軍勢を中心とした総勢1万5000人の軍勢をもって、慶長5年9月7日より大津城に対して包囲攻撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response the West squad started to besiege Otsu-jo Castle on October 13, 1600 with 15000-strong force mainly organized with daimyos in Kyushu areas such as Muneshige TACHIBANA, Hidekane MORI and Hirokado TSUKUSHI and led by Motoyasu MORI in retribution for Takatsugu&apos;s treachery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, the West squad started to besiege Otsu-jo Castle on October 13, 1600 with a force of 15,000 strong mainly organized by daimyos in the Kyushu areas such as Muneshige TACHIBANA, Hidekane MORI and Hirokado TSUKUSHI and led by Motoyasu MORI in retribution for Takatsugu&apos;s treachery.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, the West squad started to besiege Otsu-jo Castle on October 13, 1600 with a force of 15,000 strong mainly organized by daimyos in the Kyushu areas such as Muneshige TACHIBANA, Hidekane MORI and Hirokado TSUKUSHI and led by Motoyasu MORI in retribution for Takatsugu&apos;s treachery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし高次は城を死守し、容易に城攻めは捗らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Takatsugu defended the castle to the last and the siege didn&apos;t make good progress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Takatsugu defended the castle to the last and the siege made poor progress.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Takatsugu defended the castle to the last and the siege made poor progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中でも赤尾伊豆・山田大炊の活躍はめざましく、精兵500を率いて城外の大軍へ討って出、存分に暴れ回ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially well done performers were AKAO Izu no kami and Oi YAMADA, who are said to have sallied forth from the castle with 500 elite warriors and stormed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who took an especially active role included AKAO Izu no kami and Oi YAMADA, who are said to have sallied forth from the castle with 500 elite warriors and stormed their enemy.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who took an especially active role included Akao Izu no kami and Oi YAMADA, who are said to have sallied forth from the castle with 500 elite warriors and stormed their enemy.</e>
<cmt>AKAO→Akao「赤尾伊豆」は赤尾伊豆守のことですが、赤尾伊豆と名乗っていたそうなので、Akao Izu で良いのではと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>攻めあぐねた寄せ手は、十三日には大砲を城内に撃ち込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The offensive force were at a loss how to continue and fired shots from cannons at the castle on October 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The offensive force were at a loss on how to continue, and fired cannons at the castle on October 19.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The offensive force were at a loss on how to continue, and fired cannons at the castle on October 19.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>砲弾は天守にも命中、城内は大混乱となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The artillery shells hit the main tower of a castle and caused havoc inside the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The artillery shells hit the main tower of the castle and caused havoc inside.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The artillery shells hit the main tower of the castle and caused havoc inside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>高次も必死に防戦するが、ここに立花勢の先鋒大将・立花吉右衛門が一隊を率いて城壁に取り付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatsugu defended hard but a spearhead convoy led by Kichiemon TACHIBANA from the Tachibana force reached castellated wall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatsugu defended fiercely, but a spearhead convoy led by Kichiemon TACHIBANA from the Tachibana force reached the castle walls.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatsugu defended fiercely, but a spearhead convoy led by Kichiemon TACHIBANA from the Tachibana force reached the castle walls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>高次をはじめとする京極勢は奮戦したが遂に力尽き、9月15日に降伏して大津城を開城する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatsugu and other Kyogoku forces fought up but ran out of steam in the end and surrendered the castle on October 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatsugu and other Kyogoku forces fought to the last, but eventually became exhausted and surrendered the castle on October 21st.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatsugu and other Kyogoku forces fought to the last, but eventually became exhausted and surrendered the castle on October 21st.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>高次は一命を助けられ、高野山に上って出家することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatsugu had his life spared and entered into priesthood in the Koyasan (Mt. Koya) temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatsugu&apos;s life was spared and he entered into priesthood at the Koyasan (Mt. Koya) temple.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatsugu&apos;s life was spared and he entered into priesthood at the Koyasan (Mt. Koya) temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">clout</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effect</e>
<cmt>Reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>この大津城攻防戦は、戦術的には西軍が勝利したが、戦略的には西軍の敗北であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The West squad won tactically at this siege of Otsu-jo Castle but was defeated strategically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The West squad won tactically at this siege of Otsu-jo Castle but was defeated strategically.</e>
<cmt>Extra space.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The West squad won tactically at this siege of Otsu-jo Castle but was defeated strategically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>なぜならば、高次が大津城を開城した9月15日は、関ヶ原の戦いが繰り広げられた当日だったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because October 21, 1600 when Takatsugu surrendered Otsu-jo Castle was the very day when the Battle of Sekigahara took place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because October 21, 1600, when Takatsugu surrendered Otsu-jo Castle, was the very day that the Battle of Sekigahara took place.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because October 21, 1600, when Takatsugu surrendered Otsu-jo Castle, was the very day that the Battle of Sekigahara took place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>つまり、西軍は本来なら関ヶ原にあったはずの1万5000人の兵力を欠いたまま東軍と戦うという不利な状況に追い込まれていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It means that the West squad was forced under such disadvantages as to fight against the East squad without 15000 warriors that should have been deployed to Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Which means that the West squad was forced to fight with the disadvantage of fighting against the East squad without the 15,000 warriors that should have been deployed to Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Which means that the West squad was forced to fight with the disadvantage of fighting against the East squad without the 15,000 warriors that should have been deployed to Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>特に、家康がその武勇を恐れていた立花宗茂が関ヶ原の本戦に参加できなかったということは、家康にとっては幸運であり、西軍にとっては不運でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially nonappearance of Muneshige TACHIBANA at Skigahara was lucky for Ieyasu and unlucky for the West squad because Ieyasu feared Muneshige&apos;s gallantry in action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lack of participation by Muneshige TACHIBANA at Sekigahara was especially lucky for Ieyasu and unlucky for the West squad because Ieyasu feared Muneshige&apos;s gallantry in action.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lack of participation by Muneshige TACHIBANA at Sekigahara was especially lucky for Ieyasu and unlucky for the West squad because Ieyasu feared Muneshige&apos;s gallantry in action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>もし、宗茂が1万を超える大軍を率いて本戦に参加できていたなら、東西両軍の勝敗は変わっていた可能さえ指摘されているのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even such a possibility is point out that if Muneshige had joined the Battle of Sekigahara with more than 10000 force, the tide of the battle might have been different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is the possibility that if Muneshige had joined the Battle of Sekigahara with a force of more than 10,000, the outcome of the battle may have been different.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is the possibility that if Muneshige had joined the Battle of Sekigahara with a force of more than 10,000, the outcome of the battle may have been different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ちなみに、宗茂は9月15日に大津城を開城させた後、軍勢を率いて草津市にまで進出していたが、そこで西軍の壊滅を知って大坂城に退却することを余儀なくされ、戦後に改易されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, after Muneshige had made Takatsugu surrender Otsu-jo Castle on October 21, he and his troops advanced to Kusatsu city, where he knew the rout of the West squad and was forced to retreat to Osaka-jo Castle, and after the battle he forfeited the rank of Samurai and properties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, after Muneshige had made Takatsugu surrender Otsu-jo Castle on October 21, he and his troops advanced to Kusatsu city, where he knew of the defeat of the West squad and was forced to retreat to Osaka-jo Castle; because of this, after the battle he forfeited the rank of Samurai and his properties.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, after Muneshige had made Takatsugu surrender Otsu-jo Castle on October 21, he and his troops advanced to Kusatsu city, where he knew of the defeat of the West squad and was forced to retreat to Osaka-jo Castle; because of this, after the battle he forfeited the rank of Samurai and his properties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、敗軍の将である京極高次に対して、家康はあの立花宗茂をよく押さえてくれたということから、関ヶ原後に高次の弟・京極高知を使者として高野山に派遣し、大名としての復帰を許しただけではなく、若狭国一国小浜城9万2000石 (単位)の所領を与えるなど、宗茂を大津城に引き付けたことを大いに賞賛したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Ieyasu praised Takatsugu KYOGOKU very much for attracting Muneshige TACHIBANA to Otsu-jo Castle and containing him, so after the Battle of Sekigahara he sent Takatomo KYOGOKU, Takatsugu&apos;s younger brother, to Koyasan and not only allowed him to return as a daimyo but also gave him territories of Obama-jo Castle 92000 koku (unit) in Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Takatsugu KYOGOKU received great praise from Ieyasu for attracting Muneshige TACHIBANA to Otsu-jo Castle and containing him there, so much so that after the Battle of Sekigahara he sent Takatomo KYOGOKU, Takatsugu&apos;s younger brother, to Koyasan and not only allowed him to return as a daimyo but also gave him the territories of Obama-jo Castle, comprised of 92,000 koku (unit), in Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Takatsugu KYOGOKU received great praise from Ieyasu for attracting Muneshige TACHIBANA to Otsu-jo Castle and containing him there, so much so that after the Battle of Sekigahara he sent Takatomo KYOGOKU, Takatsugu&apos;s younger brother, to Koyasan and not only allowed him to return as a daimyo but also gave him the territories of Obama-jo Castle, comprised of 92,000 koku (unit), in Wakasa Province.</e>
<cmt>「なお」が「also」となっていましたが、宗茂は「改易」されたのに高次は「賞賛」されたので、「on the other hand」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Nevylax(id:38464), シェーラ(id:17988), Shostakist(id:54214), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>