<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二卿事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikyo Jiken (The Incidents triggered by two court nobles)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikyo Jiken (Dual incidents triggered by two court nobles)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikyo Jiken (Dual incidents triggered by two court nobles)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二卿事件（にきょうじけん）は、明治4年(1871年)、攘夷派の公卿、愛宕通旭と外山光輔が明治政府の転覆を謀ったクーデター未遂事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nikyo Jiken was abortive coup d&apos;etat in which Michiteru OTAGI and Mitsusuke TOYAMA, nobles in joi-ha (supporters of expulsion of the foreigners), attempted an overthrow of the Meiji Government in 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nikyo Jiken was an abortive coup d&apos;etat in which Michiteru OTAGI and Mitsusuke TOYAMA, nobles in joi-ha (supporters of expulsion of the foreigners), attempted to overthrow the Meiji Government in 1871.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nikyo Jiken was an abortive coup d&apos;etat in which Michiteru OTAGI and Mitsusuke TOYAMA, nobles in joi-ha (supporters of expulsion of the foreigners), attempted to overthrow the Meiji Government in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>尊皇攘夷の中心的な役割を果たしてきた薩摩藩・長州藩両藩を中心とした明治政府が成立したことにより、攘夷が断行されると信じていた全国の攘夷派は明治政府が戊辰戦争が終わると直ちに「開国和親」を国是とする方針を打ち出したことに強い失意と憤慨を抱いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The joi-ha all over the nation believed that foreigners would be expelled by the establishment of the Meiji Government whose main members were from Satsuma and Choshu clans that played important roles in the expulsion of the foreigners, but they were deeply disappointed and outraged by the Meiji Government issuing a policy of &quot;Kaikoku Washin (opening the country to the world with peace and amity)&quot; immediately after the end of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The joi-ha all over the nation believed that foreigners would be expelled by the establishment of the Meiji Government whose main members were from Satsuma and Choshu clans that played important roles in the expulsion of the foreigners, but they were deeply disappointed and outraged by the Meiji Government&apos;s issuance of the &quot;Kaikoku Washin policy (opening the country to the world with peace and amity)&quot; immediately after the end of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The joi-ha all over the nation believed that foreigners would be expelled by the establishment of the Meiji Government whose main members were from Satsuma and Choshu clans that played important roles in the expulsion of the foreigners, but they were deeply disappointed and outraged by the Meiji Government&apos;s issuance of the &apos;Kaikoku Washin (opening the country to the world with peace and amity)&apos; policy immediately after the end of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;開国和親の説明をその直後に置くために、policy の場所を移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これは倒幕に参加していた薩長土肥の志士や公家の一部にも及んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such emotion spread into the royalists from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa, Hizen, that participated in overthrowing the Shogunate, and a part of court nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This outrage spread to the royalists from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa, Hizen, that participated in overthrowing the Shogunate, and some of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This outrage spread to the royalists from Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa, Hizen, that participated in overthrowing the Shogunate, and some of the court nobles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>彼らは明治政府を倒して新しい政府を作り直して攘夷を行って外国と戦うべきであると唱えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They insisted on overthrowing the Meiji Government, establishing a new government, expelling the foreigners, and fighting against foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They insisted on overthrowing the Meiji Government, establishing a new government, expelling the foreigners, and fighting against foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They insisted on overthrowing the Meiji Government, establishing a new government, expelling the foreigners, and fighting against foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その先駆けとなったのが、明治2年12月1日（1870年1月2日）に長州藩で発生した大楽源太郎に率いられた奇兵隊などによる「脱隊騒動」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The spearhead of the movement was &quot;Dattai Sodo (a riot of dropouts from armies)&quot; caused by Kiheitai Army led by Gentaro DAIRAKU and others in the domain of Choshu on January 2, 1870.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The spearhead of the movement was &quot;Dattai Sodo (a riot of dropouts from armies)&quot; which originated in the Kiheitai Army led by Gentaro DAIRAKU and others in the domain of Choshu on January 2, 1870.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The spearhead of the movement was &apos;Dattai Sodo (a riot of dropouts from armies)&apos; which originated in the Kiheitai Army led by Gentaro DAIRAKU and others in the domain of Choshu on January 2, 1870.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この反乱は木戸孝允らによって間もなく鎮圧されたものの、大楽は九州に逃亡して攘夷派が藩政を掌握していた久留米藩や熊本藩の河上彦斎らの支援を受けて再起を伺った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the riot was soon suppressed by Takayoshi KIDO and others, Dairaku escaped to Kyushu and waited for an opportunity to make a comeback supported by Gensai KAWAKAMI and others from the clans of Kurume and Kumamoto, where the joi-ha took control of domain duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the riot was soon suppressed by Takayoshi KIDO and others, Dairaku escaped to Kyushu and waited for an opportunity to make a comeback supported by Gensai KAWAKAMI and others from the clans of Kurume and Kumamoto, where the joi-ha took control of domain duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the riot was soon suppressed by Takayoshi KIDO and others, Dairaku escaped to Kyushu and waited for an opportunity to make a comeback supported by Gensai KAWAKAMI and others from the clans of Kurume and Kumamoto, where the joi-ha took control of domain duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、大楽の救援に駆けつけていた土佐藩の堀内誠之進は京都に逃れて同地の攘夷派志士の糾合を画策した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Seinoshin HORIUCHI from Tosa clan, who had come up to help Dairaku, escaped to Kyoto and planned to rally the patriots of the joi-ha there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Seinoshin HORIUCHI from Tosa clan, who had come up to help Dairaku, escaped to Kyoto and planned to rally the patriots of the joi-ha there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Seinoshin HORIUCHI from Tosa clan, who had come up to help Dairaku, escaped to Kyoto and planned to rally the patriots of the joi-ha there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>計画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その頃、明治政府の参与を免ぜられて京都に引籠もっていた愛宕通旭はかつて廷臣八十八卿列参事件にも加わった事があり、「天皇の藩屏」たる公卿が薩長の下級武士によって政治の中枢から切り離されていくことに苛立ちを感じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Michiteru OTAGI, retired from the position of the councilor of Meiji Government and secluded in Kyoto, felt irritated that the court nobles once having participated in the Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court and being &quot;the guarding wall of the emperor&quot; were taken away from the center of the politics by lower-ranking samurai of Satsuma and Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Michiteru OTAGI, retired from the position of the councilor of Meiji Government and secluded in Kyoto, felt irritated that the court nobles who had once participated in the Demo of eighty-eight retainers of Imperial Court and being &quot;the guarding wall of the emperor&quot; were taken away from the center of the politics by lower-ranking samurai of Satsuma and Choshu.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Michiteru OTAGI, who had been dismissed from the position of councilor to the Meiji Government and retired to Kyoto, felt irritated that, despite having participated in the demonstration held by 88 retainers of the Imperial Court and been part of &apos;the protective wall for the emperor&apos;, he had now been cut off from the center of politics by lower-ranking samurai from Satsuma and Choshu.</e>
<cmt>retired→dismissed （「免ぜられ」のため）&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;全体的に内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これに対して家臣の比喜多源二・安木劉太郎らは同情して、明治政府を倒して明治天皇を京都へ連れ帰って攘夷を断行するべきであると進言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His vassals including Genji HIKITA and Ryutaro YASUKI sympathized with him, and offered that they should bring the Emperor Meiji back to Kyoto and force through the expulsion of the foreigners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His vassals including Genji HIKITA and Ryutaro YASUKI, sympathized with him, and offered to bring the Emperor Meiji back to Kyoto and force the expulsion of the foreigners.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His vassals including Genji HIKITA and Ryutaro YASUKI, sympathized with him, and offered to overthrow the Meiji government, bring the Emperor Meiji back to Kyoto and force the expulsion of the foreigners.</e>
<cmt>「明治政府を倒し」を追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>更に比喜多は弾正台で横井小楠暗殺事件の捜査を担当しながら逆に横井を糾弾しようとしたことで知られる古賀十郎とその友人である秋田藩の中村恕助を招き入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikita further invited Juro KOGA, known by trying to accuse Shonan YOKOI while investigating the assassination case of Yokoi in danjodai (Board of Censors), and his friend, Josuke NAKAMURA from Akita clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikita further invited Juro KOGA, known accusing Shonan YOKOI during an investigation in to assassination of Yokoi in danjodai (Board of Censors), and his friend, Josuke NAKAMURA from the Akita clan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikita further invited Juro KOGA, known accusing Shonan YOKOI during an investigation into assassination of Yokoi in danjodai (Board of Censors), and his friend, Josuke NAKAMURA from the Akita clan.</e>
<cmt>in to→into</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>古賀と中村は天皇と主だった公卿が東京にいる以上、まず東京で事を起こさなければ意味がないと説き、これに同意した愛宕は明治4年1月28日（1871年3月18日）に比喜多・安木らを連れて京都を出て2月4日（3月24日）に東京に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga and Nakamura asserted that nothing would change without causing a trouble in Tokyo as long as the emperor and important court nobles stayed in Tokyo, and Otagi, who agreed their assertion, left Kyoto with Hikita, Yasuki, and others on March 18, 1871, and entered Tokyo on March 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga and Nakamura asserted that nothing would change without trouble was caused in Tokyo as long as the emperor and important court nobles stayed in Tokyo, and Otagi, who agreed with this assertion, left Kyoto with Hikita, Yasuki, and others on March 18, 1871, and entered Tokyo on March 24.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga and Nakamura asserted that nothing would change unless trouble was caused in Tokyo as long as the emperor and important court nobles stayed in Tokyo, and Otagi, who agreed with this assertion, left Kyoto with Hikita, Yasuki, and others on March 18, 1871, and entered Tokyo on March 24.</e>
<cmt>without→unless</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>東京に入った愛宕主従は古賀・中村に誘われた秋田・久留米藩士や前述の堀内誠之進らと謀議を重ね、秋田藩内の同志に呼びかけて日光を占領し、更に東京に火を放って天皇を京都に連れ出す作戦を練った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otagi and his men that arrived in Tokyo repeatedly plotted together with Seinoshin HORIUCHI and retainers of Akita and Kurume clans called for by Koga and Nakamura, and made a plan to take the emperor to Kyoto by calling for the members in Akita clan, occupying Nikko with them, and further setting Tokyo on fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Called by Koga and Nakamura, Otagi and his men arrived in Tokyo, and repeatedly plotted together with Seinoshin HORIUCHI and retainers of the Akita and Kurume clans to occupy Nikko with help from the members from the Akita clan, setting fire to Tokiyo and taking the emperor to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otagi and his men arrived in Tokyo, and repeatedly plotted together with Seinoshin HORIUCHI and retainers of the Akita and Kurume clans, who were called by Koga and Nakamura, to occupy Nikko with help from the members from the Akita clan, setting fire to Tokiyo and taking the emperor to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>NCの文では「古賀・中村に誘われた」のが愛宕主従になってしまうので、訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>一方、同じ頃同じく京都に滞在していた外山光輔も家臣の高田修とともに同じような計画を結んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Mitsusuke TOYAMA, who was staying in Kyoto at the same time, was also making a similar plan with his vassal, Osamu TAKADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Mitsusuke TOYAMA, who was staying in Kyoto at the same time, was also making a similar plan with his vassal, Osamu TAKADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Mitsusuke TOYAMA, who was staying in Kyoto at the same time, was also making a similar plan with his vassal, Osamu TAKADA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>高田は青蓮院門跡家臣三宅瓦全や菊亭家家臣矢田期穏清斎父子、美作国庄屋立石公久らと密談を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takada had a secret meeting with Gazen MIYAKE who was the vassal of Shoren-in Monzeki Temple, Toshiyasu and Seisai YATA who were father and son and the vassals of the Kikutei family, Kimihisa TATEISHI who was the village headman of Mimasaka Province, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takada had a secret meeting with Gazen MIYAKE who was the vassal of Shoren-in Monzeki Temple, Toshiyasu and Seisai YATA who were father and son and the vassals of the Kikutei family, Kimihisa TATEISHI who was the village headman of Mimasaka Province, and others.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takada had a secret meeting with Gazen MIYAKE who was the vassal of Shoren-in Monzeki Temple, Toshiyasu and Seisai YATA who were father and son and the vassals of the Kikutei family, Kimihisa TATEISHI who was the village headman of Mimasaka Province, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>特に立石は久留米藩領内に匿われている大楽とも連絡を取っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, Tateishi was in contact with Dairaku given shelter in the domain of Kurume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, Tateishi was in contact with Dairaku who were being given shelter in the domain of Kurume.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, Tateishi was in contact with Dairaku who was being given shelter in the domain of Kurume.</e>
<cmt>were→was</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>更に東京で愛宕が同じような計画を立てていることを知った外山は使者を送って協力を結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyama, who learned that Otagi was making a similar plan in Tokyo, further sent a messenger and joined hands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyama, who learned that Otagi was making a similar plan in Tokyo, sent a messenger and joined hands with Otagi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyama, who learned that Otagi was making a similar plan in Tokyo, sent a messenger and joined hands with Otagi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>愛宕の計画に加わっていた久留米藩士達も当然、本国の同志や彼らの庇護下にあった大楽と連絡を取り合っていたことから、愛宕・外山・久留米藩及び大楽による三角同盟が形成されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Kurume retainers taking part in Otagi&apos;s plan were naturally in contact with the members in their domain and Dairaku under their shelter, a triangle alliance among Otagi, Toyama, Kurume clan, and Dairaku was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Kurume retainers taking part in Otagi&apos;s plan were naturally in contact with the members in their domain and Dairaku under their shelter, a triangle alliance among Otagi, Toyama, Kurume clan, and Dairaku was formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Kurume retainers taking part in Otagi&apos;s plan were naturally in contact with the members in their domain and Dairaku under their shelter, a triangle alliance among Otagi, Toyama, Kurume clan, and Dairaku was formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>発覚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exposure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exposure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exposure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ところが、中川宮を取り込もうとしたところで折りしも発生した広沢真臣暗殺事件の捜査中であった政府側に情報が漏れ、山縣有朋を中心に摘発に乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, trying to count Nakagawa no miya in, information was leaked to the government side that was investigating for the assassination case of Saneomi HIROSAWA that occurred in a bad timing, and Aritomo YAMAGATA and others started revelation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, trying to count Nakagawa no miya in, information was leaked to the government that was investigating the assassination of Saneomi HIROSAWA, Aritomo YAMAGATA and others started to realize what was happenening.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, trying to count Nakagawa no miya in, information was leaked to the government that was investigating the assassination of Saneomi HIROSAWA, Aritomo YAMAGATA and others started to investigate what was happenening.</e>
<cmt>realize→investigate</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>まず、3月7日（4月26日）に外山光輔が捕縛され、10日に東京の久留米藩藩邸が政府に押収されて藩知事有馬頼咸が幽閉された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, Mitsusuke TOYAMA was captured on April 26, the residence of Kurume domain in Tokyo was confiscated by the government on April 29, and Yorishige ARIMA, governor of domain, was incarcerated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, Mitsusuke TOYAMA was captured on April 26, while a residence of the Kurume domain in Tokyo was confiscated by the government on April 29, and Yorishige ARIMA, governor of domain, was incarcerated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, Mitsusuke TOYAMA was captured on April 26, while a residence of the Kurume domain in Tokyo was confiscated by the government on April 29, and Yorishige ARIMA, governor of domain, was incarcerated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>13日（5月2日）には政府の命令を受けた熊本藩兵が久留米城を接収して藩幹部を拘束（大楽は直前に逃亡）し、14日には愛宕通旭が捕縛された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 2, samurai of Kumamoto clan took over Kurume Castle and arrested top officials of the clan (Dairaku escaped in the last minute) under an order from the government, and Michiteru OTAGI was arrested on May 3.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 2, samurai of Kumamoto clan took over Kurume Castle and arrested top officials of the clan (Dairaku escaped in the last minute) under orders from the government, and Michiteru OTAGI was arrested on May 3.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 2, samurai of Kumamoto clan took over Kurume Castle and arrested top officials of the clan (Dairaku escaped in the last minute) under orders from the government, and Michiteru OTAGI was arrested on May 3.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>最終的には339名が逮捕されることとなり「安政の大獄以来の大獄」となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As many as 339 people were arrested at last, this was &quot;the largest suppression after Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As many as 339 people were arrested at last, this was &quot;the largest suppression after Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate).&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As many as 339 people were arrested at last, this was &apos;the largest suppression after Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="25">
<j>首謀者の二人は明治4年12月3日（1872年1月12日）、切腹させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two of the masterminds were forced to commit seppuku on January 12, 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two masterminds were forced to commit seppuku on January 12, 1872.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two masterminds were forced to commit seppuku on January 12, 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 下総大納言(id:43461), KASAGI(id:24405), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>