<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>味舌藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mashita Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mashita Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mashita Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>味舌藩（ましたはん）は摂津国嶋下郡味舌（現在の大阪府摂津市三島）にあった藩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mashita Domain was located in Mashita, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province (present Mishima, Settsu City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mashita Domain was located in Mashita, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province (present Mishima, Settsu City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mashita Domain was located in Mashita, Shimashimo County, Settsu Province (present Mishima, Settsu City, Osaka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藩庁は味舌陣屋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government building was called Mashita jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government building was called Mashita Jinya.</e>
<cmt>「陣屋」→地方の役所を意味することもあるが、城を持たない小大名の屋敷を呼ぶのにも使われる。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E9%99%A3%E5%B1%8B）ここでは固有名詞として&quot;Mashita Jinya&quot;で良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government building was called Mashita Jinya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>豊臣秀吉の臣として大坂城にいた織田信長の弟織田長益（有楽斎）は、摂津国嶋下郡に2千石を知行していたが、慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いの後、大和国山辺郡に新たに恩賞として2万7千石を加増された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasu (Yurakusai) ODA, the younger brother of Nobunaga ODA, who lived in Osaka-jo Castle as a vassal of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, was granted 27,000 Goku crop yields in Yamabe County, Yamato Province as a reward for his contribution to the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 in addition to the 2,000 Goku crop yields which he had already been enfeoffed in Shimashimo County, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasu (Urakusai) ODA, who was the younger brother of Nobunaga ODA and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in Osaka-jo Castle, was granted the territory of 27,000 koku in Yamabe County, Yamato Province as a reward for his contribution to the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, in addition to the territory of 2,000 koku which he had already been enfeoffed in Shimashimo County, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>「有楽斎」は「うらくさい」。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E7%B9%94%E7%94%B0%E6%9C%89%E6%A5%BD%E6%96%8E）大阪城に住んでいたわけではないと思うので、&quot;lived in&quot;を修正しました。「石」は翻訳仕様指示書に従って&quot;koku&quot;と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasu (Urakusai) ODA, who was the younger brother of Nobunaga ODA and served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in Osaka-jo Castle, was granted the territory of 27,000 koku in Yamabe County, Yamato Province as a reward for his contribution to the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, in addition to the territory of 2,000 koku which he had already been enfeoffed in Shimashimo County, Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これにより都合3万石を領し、大名に列することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, he came to possess a total of 30,000 Goku crop yields to rank with daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, he came to possess a total of 30,000 koku territory to rank with daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>「石」は翻訳仕様指示書に従って&quot;koku&quot;と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, he came to possess a total of 30,000 koku territory to rank with daimyo (Japanese feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>やがて、元和 (日本)元年（1615年）、大和国式上郡・山辺郡・摂津国嶋下郡のうちから1万石を四男織田長政 (大名)（戒重藩）に、同年、式上・山辺2郡の内から1万石を五男織田尚長（柳本藩）にそれぞれ分与し、残余の1万石は自分の養老領とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he gave 10,000 Goku crop yields from Shikijo County and Yamabe County of Yamato Province and Shimashimo County of Settsu Province away to his fourth son Nagamasa ODA (daimyo) (Kaiju Domain) and another 10,000 Goku crop yields from Shikijo and Yamabe County to his fifth son Naonaga ODA (Yanagimoto Domain) in the same year, saving the remaining 10,000 Goku crop yields as an asylum land for his old age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he gave the territory of 10,000 koku in Shikijo County and Yamabe County of Yamato Province and Shimashimo County of Settsu Province away to his fourth son Nagamasa ODA (daimyo) (Kaiju Domain) and another 10,000 koku territory in Shikijo and Yamabe County to his fifth son Naonaga ODA (Yanagimoto Domain) in the same year, saving the remaining 10,000 koku terriotory for his old age.</e>
<cmt>「石」は翻訳仕様指示書に従って&quot;koku&quot;と修正。「養老領」→&quot;asylum&quot;は「保護施設、養老院」ですが、ここでは単に老後のための領地、の意味だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he gave the territory of 10,000 koku in Shikijo County and Yamabe County of Yamato Province and Shimashimo County of Settsu Province away to his fourth son Nagamasa ODA (daimyo) (Kaiju Domain) and another 10,000 koku territory in Shikijo and Yamabe County to his fifth son Naonaga ODA (Yanagimoto Domain) in the same year, saving the remaining 10,000 koku terriotory for his old age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>元和7年（1621年）長益が死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasu died in 1621.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasu died in 1621.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasu died in 1621.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>長男織田長孝は、関ヶ原の戦いの軍功により美濃国大野郡 (美濃国)に1万石を賜っていたが（野村藩）、既に慶長11年（1606年）死去しており、その子織田長則（～寛永8年）に嗣子がなく、家が絶えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since his eldest son Nagataka ODA, who received 10,000 Goku crop yields in Ono District, Mino Province (Mino Province) in return for his distinguished military service during the Battle of Sekigahara, had already died in 1606, and Nagataka&apos;s son Naganori ODA (died in 1631) had no heir, Nagamasu&apos;s death put an end to the Oda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His eldest son Nagataka ODA received the territory of 10,000 koku (Nomura Domain) in Ono County, Mino Province in return for his distinguished military service during the Battle of Sekigahara, but died in 1606, and his son Naganori ODA died without heir (in 1631), which put an end to the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>「石」は翻訳仕様指示書に従って&quot;koku&quot;と修正。同様に「郡」は&quot;County&quot;に修正。(美濃国)は繰り返しになるため削除しました。（野村藩）→訳抜け。織田家が絶えたのは長益ではなく長則の死によってです。（長益が亡くなったとき、長則はまだ存命中）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His eldest son Nagataka ODA received the territory of 10,000 koku (Nomura Domain) in Ono County, Mino Province in return for his distinguished military service during the Battle of Sekigahara, but died in 1606, and his son Naganori ODA died without heir (in 1631), which put an end to the Oda family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>長益の養老領1万石は除封となり、また長則の弟長政の子孫は加賀藩の家臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasu&apos;s 10,000-Goku-crop-yields asylum land was deprived and the descendants of Nagamasa, younger brother of Naganori, became vassals of the Kaga Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasu&apos;s territory of 10,000 koku was deprived of, and the descendants of Nagamasa, younger brother of Naganori, became vassals of the Kaga Domain.</e>
<cmt>「石」は翻訳仕様指示書に従って&quot;koku&quot;と修正。&quot;deprived&quot;→&quot;deprived of&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasu&apos;s territory of 10,000 koku was deprived of, and the descendants of Nagamasa, younger brother of Naganori, became vassals of the Kaga Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kansai explorer(id:48975), Straysheep(id:42448), Roga246(id:53246), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>