<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>五箇条の御誓文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter Oath of Five Articles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter Oath of Five Articles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter Oath of Five Articles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>五箇条の御誓文（ごかじょうのごせいもん）とは、明治元年3月14日 (旧暦)（1868年4月6日）に明治天皇（当時15歳）が公卿や諸侯などに示した明治政府の基本方針。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter Oath of Five Articles was basic policy of the Meiji government represented to Kugyo (court nobles) and lords by the Emperor Meiji (15 years old at that time) on April 6, 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter Oath of Five Articles was basic policy of the Meiji government represented to Kugyo (court nobles) and lords by the Emperor Meiji (15 years old at that time) on April 6, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter Oath of Five Articles was basic policy of the Meiji government represented to Kugyo (court nobles) and lords by the Emperor Meiji (15 years old at that time) on April 6, 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正式名称は御誓文であり、以下では御誓文と表記する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hereinafter it is written the formal name Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hereinafter referred to as Charter Oath, proper name of Charter Oath of Five Articles.</e>
<cmt>より多く使われている表現に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hereinafter referred to as Charter Oath, proper name of Charter Oath of Five Articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>起草の過程</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Drafting proces</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Drafting process</e>
<cmt>スペルミスproces→process</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Drafting process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>明治新政府は発足当初から公議を標榜し、その具体的方策としての国是を模索していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the beginning of inauguration, the New Meiji Government advocated fair discussion and sought national policy as the concrete measure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning of inauguration, the New Meiji Government advocated fair discussion and sought national policy as the concrete measure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning of inauguration, the New Meiji Government advocated fair discussion and sought national policy as the concrete measure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治元年正月、福井藩出身の参与由利公正が、坂本龍馬の船中八策と似ている部分が多い議事之体大意五箇条を起案し、参与東久世通禧を通じて議定兼副総裁の岩倉具視に提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New Year in 1868, Sanyo, Kosei YURI from Fukui Domain made up Gijinoteitaii Five Articles which was similar much to Senchu hassaku (the basic outline of the new regime drawn up by Ryoma Sakamoto) of Ryoma SAKAMOTO and submitted to gijo (official post) and vice-president, Tomomi IWAKURA through Sanyo (councillor), Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New Year in 1868, Sanyo (councilor), Kosei YURI from Fukui Domain made up Gijinoteitaii Five Articles which was partially similar to Senchu hassaku (the basic outline of the new regime drawn up by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) and submitted to gijo (official post) and vice-president, Tomomi IWAKURA through Sanyo, Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE.</e>
<cmt>参与（Sanyo)が初出時に説明されていないため、訂正。Similar much to →　particially similar toに変更。()内にby Ryoma Sakamotoと明記されているため、of Ryoma SAKAMOTOを削除。（）Sakamoto→SAKAMOTOのに変更。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New Year in 1868, Sanyo (councilor), Kosei YURI from Fukui Domain made up Gijinoteitaii Five Articles which was partially similar to Senchu hassaku (the basic outline of the new regime drawn up by Ryoma SAKAMOTO) and submitted to gijo (official post) and vice-president, Tomomi IWAKURA through Sanyo, Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>制度取調参与の福岡孝弟は、この由利五箇条に対して第一条冒頭に「列侯会議を興し」の字句を入れるなどして封建的な方向へ後退させ、表題も会盟に改めたため、列侯会盟の色彩が非常に強くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Seido torishirabe Sanyo (Councilor in charge of examining regulations) Takachika FUKUOKA added words &apos;setting up a council by feudal lords&apos; at the beginning of the first article of Yuri gokajo (Five Articles designed by Yuri), it stepped back to feudalistic direction and also because of the change of title to kaimei the mood of pledge of feudal lords deepened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Seido torishirabe Sanyo (Councilor in charge of examining regulations) Takachika FUKUOKA added words &apos;setting up a council by feudal lords&apos; at the beginning of the first article of the Yuri gokajo (Five Articles designed by Yuri) and the title was changed to &quot;kaimei&quot; (pledge of feudal lords), it stepped back to feudalistic direction and the mood of pledge of feudal lords deepened.</e>
<cmt>※Yuri gokajoは既出のGijinoteitaii Five Articlesのことであるため、Yuri gokajoの前にthe を挿入しました。※Kaimei（会盟）の説明がありません。用語集を参照し補いました。※全体的に文章の流れを変更しました。以下、全角で‘’となっている部分はすべて半角に変更しました。(変更箇所が非常に多いため、変更箇所全部に変更理由を記載することはできませんでしたが、これが理由で変更を行った場合のみ（他の変更理由がない場合のみ）コメントにその旨を記載しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Seido torishirabe Sanyo (Councilor in charge of examining regulations) Takachika FUKUOKA added words &apos;setting up a council by feudal lords&apos; at the beginning of the first article of the Yuri gokajo (Five Articles designed by Yuri) and the title was changed to &quot;kaimei&quot; (pledge of feudal lords), it stepped back to feudalistic direction and the mood of pledge of feudal lords deepened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>さらに福岡は発表の形式として天皇と諸侯が共に会盟を約する形を提案した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuoka also proposed to commitment to kaimei of the emperor and lords as an announcement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuoka also requested the Emperor&apos;s and lords&apos;s commitment to kaimei as an announcement.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。(用語統一リスト参照） of the emperor and lords→ the Emperor&apos;s and loards&apos;sに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuoka also requested the Emperor&apos;s and lords&apos;s commitment to kaimei as an announcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、この「会盟」形式は、天皇と諸侯とを対等に扱うものであり王政復古 (日本)の理念に反するという批判にさらされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However this &apos;kaimei&apos; which treated equally the emperor and lords was criticized that it was against the principle of Restoration of Imperial Rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However this &apos;kaimei&apos; which treated equally the Emperor and lords was criticized that it was against the principle of Restoration of Imperial Rule.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However this &apos;kaimei&apos; which treated equally the Emperor and lords was criticized that it was against the principle of Restoration of Imperial Rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで、総裁局顧問の木戸孝允が、天皇が天神地祗（てんじんちぎ。分かり易く言えば神）を祀り、神前で公卿・諸侯を率いている状態で共に誓いかつ全員が署名するという形式を提案し、採用されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore general bureau adviser Takayoshi KIDO proposed that the emperor enshrined tenjinchigi (the gods of heaven and earth) and pledged and singed together with Kugyo (court noble) and lords in front of the alter and it was adopted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore general bureau adviser Takayoshi KIDO proposed another form that the emperor pray to tenjinchigi (the gods of heaven and earth) as leader of Kugyo and lords, then pledge and sign together with them, and the proposal was adopted.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。全体的に変更しました。特に「祀り」の部分はenshrine（安置する）ではなく祈願する(pray to)に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore general bureau adviser Takayoshi KIDO proposed another form that the emperor pray to tenjinchigi (the gods of heaven and earth) as leader of Kugyo and lords, then pledge and sign together with them, and the proposal was adopted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その際、木戸孝允は、福岡案第一条の「列侯会議を興し」を「広ク会議ヲ興シ」に改め、「徴士」の任用期間を制限していた福岡案第五条を削除して木戸最終案第四条を新たに組み込み、五箇条の順序を体裁良く整え直すなどして大幅に変更を加え、より普遍的な内容にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Takayoshi KIDO revised &apos;setting up a council by feudal lords&apos; in the first article of Fukuoka&apos;s draft to &apos;setting up a council widely&apos; and deleted the article 5 which restricted the term of &apos;chosi&apos; (official) and added newly the article 4 of Kido&apos;s final draft and put the order of the article 5 in proper order and the contents became more universal by those big changes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Takayoshi KIDO changed &apos;setting up a council by feudal lords&apos; in the first article of Fukuoka&apos;s draft to &apos;setting up deliberative assemblies widely&apos; and deleted the article 5 which restricted the term of &apos;choshi&apos; (official) and added newly the article 4 of Kido&apos;s final draft and put the order of the whole five articles in proper order and the contents became more universal by those big changes.</e>
<cmt>revised→changedに変更しました。‘setting up a council widely’→‘setting up deliberative assmblies widely’に変更しました。五箇条と第五条の違いがわかりにくいため、五箇条はwhole five Articlesに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Takayoshi KIDO changed &apos;setting up a council by feudal lords&apos; in the first article of Fukuoka&apos;s draft to &apos;setting up deliberative assemblies widely&apos; and deleted the article 5 which restricted the term of &apos;choshi&apos; (official) and added newly the article 4 of Kido&apos;s final draft and put the order of the whole five articles in proper order and the contents became more universal by those big changes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、議定兼副総裁の三条実美も福岡案表題の「会盟」を「誓」に修正したため、木戸による五箇条が「誓文」「御誓文」「五箇条誓文」「五箇条の御誓文」と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also gijo (official post) and a vice-president Sanetomi SANJO revised &apos;kaimei&apos; of the title of Fukuoka&apos;s draft to &apos;oath&apos;, therefore Five Articles of Kito was called &apos;Seimon&apos; &apos;Goseimon&apos; (oath), &apos;Gokajo Seimon&apos; &apos;Gokajo no Goseimon&apos; (Charter Oath of Five Articles).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also gijo (official post) and a vice-president Sanetomi SANJO changed &apos;kaimei&apos; of the title of Fukuoka&apos;s draft to &apos;oath,&apos; therefore Five Articles by Kido was called &apos;Seimon,&apos; &apos;Goseimon,&apos; &apos;Gokajo Seimon,&apos; or &apos;Gokajo no Goseimon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>revised→changedに変更しました。of Kito→by Kidoに変更しました。ここで五箇条の呼び方を紹介しているので、それぞれ（）内の意味は省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also gijo (official post) and a vice-president Sanetomi SANJO changed &apos;kaimei&apos; of the title of Fukuoka&apos;s draft to &apos;oath,&apos; therefore Five Articles by Kido was called &apos;Seimon,&apos; &apos;Goseimon,&apos; &apos;Gokajo Seimon,&apos; or &apos;Gokajo no Goseimon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この木戸五箇条が天下に布告すべき日本の国是として明治天皇の裁可を受け、1868年（慶応4年）3月14日、朝廷の規模の大きさを天下に確定させんとする木戸の狙い通り、誓約された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Kido gokajo (Five Articles designed by Kido) was approved by the Emperor Meiji as Japanese national policy to be declared in the worlds and was pledged on March 14, 1868 just as Kido targeted to ensure the large scale of Imperial court to the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Kido gokajo (Five Articles designed by Kido) was approved by the Emperor Meiji as Japanese national policy to be declared to the world and was pledged on March 14, 1868 just as Kido targeted to ensure the large scale of Imperial court to the world.</e>
<cmt>in the worlds→to the world,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Kido gokajo (Five Articles designed by Kido) was approved by the Emperor Meiji as Japanese national policy to be declared to the world and was pledged on March 14, 1868 just as Kido targeted to ensure the large scale of Imperial court to the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>木戸は後日、「天下の侯伯と誓い、億兆の向ふ所を知らしめ、藩主をして其責に任ぜんと欲し」たと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kito stated later &apos;it pledged with kohaku (nobles), showed the direction for gazillion of people and gave the lords of domains responsibilities&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kido stated later that he aimed &apos;to pledge with kohaku (nobles), show the direction for people and give the lords of domains responsibilities.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Kito→Kidoに変更しました。億兆には「人民・万民」の意味があるため、gazillion of people → peopleに変更しました。　（参考：デジタル大辞泉（小学館））「と欲し」は「を意図した」と解釈し、訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kido stated later that he aimed &apos;to pledge with kohaku (nobles), show the direction for people and give the lords of domains responsibilities.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>儀式と布告</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceremony and declaration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceremony and declaration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceremony and declaration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>御誓文は明治天皇の勅命によって、3月13日 (旧暦)に天皇の書道指南役であった有栖川宮幟仁親王の手で正本が揮毫され、翌3月14日 (旧暦)、京都御所の正殿である京都御所紫宸殿で行われた天神地祇御誓祭という儀式によって示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original of Charter Oath was written by Prince Arisugawa Takahito on royal command of the Emperor Meiji on March 13 and showed in the ceremony, Tenjinchigigoseisai (the gods of heaven and earth pledge festival) held at the main building, Kyoto Imperial Palace Shishinden hall on March 14.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original of Charter Oath was written by Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Takahito who gave the Emperor instructions in calligraphy on royal command of the Emperor Meiji on March 13 (old lunar calendar) and shown in the ceremony, Tenjinchigigoseisai (the gods of heaven and earth festival for oath) held at the main building, Kyoto Imperial Palace Shishinden hall on March 14 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>1.用語統一リストに基づき変更しました。：有栖川宮幟仁親王→Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Takahito2.書道指南役追記しました。3.(旧暦）が明示されていなかったため、（）付けで追記。（年号がないため、新暦の日付が割り出せません。）4.showed→shownに変更しました。5.御誓祭→用語集の登録を参考に（）内変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original of Charter Oath was written by Arisugawanomiya Imperial Prince Takahito who gave the Emperor instructions in calligraphy on royal command of the Emperor Meiji on March 13 (old lunar calendar) and shown in the ceremony, Tenjinchigigoseisai (the gods of heaven and earth festival for oath) held at the main building, Kyoto Imperial Palace Shishinden hall on March 14 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>天神地祇御誓祭の前には、天皇の書簡である御宸翰が披瀝されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Tenjinchigigoseisai, a letter of the emperor Shinkan was presented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Tenjinchigigoseisai, Shinkan (a letter in the Emperor&apos;s own hand) was presented.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。Shinkanは用語集を変更に（）内で説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Tenjinchigigoseisai, Shinkan (a letter in the Emperor&apos;s own hand) was presented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>同日正午、在京の公卿・諸侯・徴士ら群臣が着座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At noon on the same day, a crowd or large number of the retainers such as Kugyo, lords and choshi (men of eminent virtue) in Kyoto were seated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At noon on the same day, Kugyo, lords and choshi in Kyoto were seated.</e>
<cmt>群臣、ここでは特に訳出する必要がないと考えましたので省きました。(men of eminent virtue)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At noon on the same day, Kugyo, lords and choshi in Kyoto were seated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>神祇官が塩水行事、散米行事、神おろし神歌、献供の儀式を行った後、天皇が出御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Jingikan (Department of Divinities) performed ceremonies of salt water, sanmai (throwing rice), kamioroshi kami uta (God&apos;s song of seance) and offering, the emperor arrived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Jingikan (officer of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) performed ceremonies of salt water, sanmai (throwing rice), kamioroshi kami uta (God&apos;s song of seance) and offering, the Emperor arrived.</e>
<cmt>神祇官の（）説明は用語集を参照し変更しました。emperor→Emperorにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Jingikan (officer of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) performed ceremonies of salt water, sanmai (throwing rice), kamioroshi kami uta (God&apos;s song of seance) and offering, the Emperor arrived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>議定兼副総裁の三条実美が天皇に代わって神前で御祭文を奉読。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gijo and vice-president Sanetomi SANJO read the saimon (address to the gods) before the altar in place of the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In place of the Emperor, gijo and vice-president Sanetomi SANJO read the saimon (address to the gods) in front of the altar.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。In place of the Emperorの位置変更しました。(文頭）before→in front of に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In place of the Emperor, gijo and vice-president Sanetomi SANJO read the saimon (address to the gods) in front of the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天皇みずから幣帛の玉串を捧げて神拝して再び着座。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor prayed to God offering heihaku tamagushi and took a seat again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor prayed to God offering tamagushi (branch of a sacred tree) as heihaku (general term for offering to God) and took a seat again.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。幣帛・玉串の説明がないため補いました。（幣帛の玉串は「幣帛として玉串を捧げた」と解釈しました。）幣帛：神社で、神前に奉献するものの総称。玉串：幣帛の一。サカキなど常緑樹の小枝に紙の幣あるいは木綿をつけ神前に供えるもの。 （デジタル大辞泉（小学館））</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor prayed to God offering tamagushi (branch of a sacred tree) as heihaku (general term for offering to God) and took a seat again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>三条が再び神前で御誓文を奉読し、続いて勅語を読み上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanjo read Charter Oath before the altar again and read Ordinance subsequently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanjo read Charter Oath in front of the altar again and read Ordinance subsequently.</e>
<cmt>before→in front of に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanjo read Charter Oath in front of the altar again and read Ordinance subsequently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、公卿・諸侯が一人ずつ神位と玉座に拝礼し、奉答書に署名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that one each of Kugo and lord prayed to shini (deity) and the Emperor&apos;s seat and signed on hotosho (document to reply to the throne).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that Kugo and lord prayed to shini (deity) and the Emperor&apos;s seat and signed on hotosho (document to reply to the throne) one by one.</e>
<cmt>一人ずつ→one by one と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that Kugo and lord prayed to shini (deity) and the Emperor&apos;s seat and signed on hotosho (document to reply to the throne) one by one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その途中で天皇は退出。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the middle the emperor left there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the ceremony the Emperor left there.</e>
<cmt>emperor→Emperorにしました。In the middle→During the ceremonyに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the ceremony the Emperor left there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>最後に神祇事務局が神あげ神歌の儀式を行い群臣が退出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last Jingi Jimukyoku (Shintō Worship Bureau) held a ceremony of kamiage kami uta (a kind of God&apos;s song) and the retainers left there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At last Jingi Jimukyoku (Shinto Worship Bureau) held a ceremony of kamiage kami uta (a kind of God&apos;s song) and the retainers left there.</e>
<cmt>Shintō→Shintoに変更しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last Jingi Jimukyoku (Shinto Worship Bureau) held a ceremony of kamiage kami uta (a kind of God&apos;s song) and the retainers left there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>御誓文は太政官日誌をもって一般に布告された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter Oath was declared by Daijokan (the Great Council of State) to the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter Oath was declared by Daijokan nittshi (official publication of the Great Council of State) to the public.</e>
<cmt>太政官日誌が訳出されていません。（太政官となっている）。Daijokan nittshi (official publication of the Great Council of State)に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter Oath was declared by Daijokan nittshi (official publication of the Great Council of State) to the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>太政官日誌には「御誓文之御写」が勅語と奉答書とともに掲載されたほか、その前後には天神地祇御誓祭の式次第と御祭文や御宸翰が掲載された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Daijokan diary &apos;the copy of Charter Oath&apos; was published with Ordinance and response paper, and also before and after that program of Tenjinchigigoseisai, saimon and shinkan were published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The copy of Charter Oath&apos; was in the Daijokan nittshi with Ordinance and response paper, and also the program of Tenjinchigigoseisai, saimon and shinkan were put on before and after the article.</e>
<cmt>※全体的に変更しました。記事に「一般に布告」されたとあること、またWebで検索したところ、太政官日誌は機関紙であるとの記述がみられたため、「太政官日誌」記述を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The copy of Charter Oath&apos; was in the Daijokan nittshi with Ordinance and response paper, and also the program of Tenjinchigigoseisai, saimon and shinkan were put on before and after the article.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当時の太政官日誌は都市の書店で一般に発売されていたが、各農村にまで配布されておらず、一般国民に対しては、キリスト教の禁止など幕府の旧来の政策を踏襲する五榜の掲示が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daijokan diary of the day was sold commonly in urban book stores, but not distributed in the rural areas yet and to the general public Gobo no keiji (five edict boards) taking over traditional policies of bakufu such as a ban of Christianity was posted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time Daijokan nittshi was available at urban book stores, but not distributed in the rural areas yet and to the general public Gobo no keiji (five edict boards) taking over traditional policies of bakufu such as a ban of Christianity was posted.</e>
<cmt>※前半部分的に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time Daijokan nittshi was available at urban book stores, but not distributed in the rural areas yet and to the general public Gobo no keiji (five edict boards) taking over traditional policies of bakufu such as a ban of Christianity was posted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>政体書体制での御誓文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter Oath in the system of the Constitution of 1868</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter Oath in the system of the Constitution of 1868</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter Oath in the system of the Constitution of 1868</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>明治元年閏4月に明治新政府の政治体制を定めた政体書は、劈頭で「大いに斯国是を定め制度規律を建てるは御誓文を以て目的とす」と掲げ、続いて御誓文の五箇条全文を引用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1868, the Constitution of the New Meiji Government regime declared &apos;to aim Charter Oath deciding new national policy and establishing systems&apos; and consequently quoted the whole text of Five Articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1868, the Constitution of the New Meiji Government regime declared &apos;to define Charter Oath as the objectives, establish new national policy, systems and regulations&apos; and consequently quoted whole texts of Five Articles.</e>
<cmt>※全体的に変更しました。「御誓文を以て目的とす」「御誓文を目標として」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1868, the Constitution of the New Meiji Government regime declared &apos;to define Charter Oath as the objectives, establish new national policy, systems and regulations&apos; and consequently quoted whole texts of Five Articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>政体書は、アメリカ憲法の影響を受けたものであり、三権分立や官職の互選、藩代表議会の設置などが定められ、また、地方行政は「御誓文を体すべし」とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Constitution of 1868 was affected by the American Constitution setting out separation of powers (of administration, legislation, and judicature),gosen (mutual election) of government post, the introduction of domain parliament and local administration was considered &apos;to follow Charter Oath&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Constitution of 1868 was affected by the American Constitution, separation of powers (of administration, legislation, and judicature), gosen (mutual election) of government posts, and the introduction of domain parliament were stated and local administration was considered &apos;shall abide by Charter Oath.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全体的に変更しました。(文の流れ、接続を変更）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Constitution of 1868 was affected by the American Constitution, separation of powers (of administration, legislation, and judicature), gosen (mutual election) of government posts, and the introduction of domain parliament were stated and local administration was considered &apos;shall abide by Charter Oath.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>このほか、同年4月12日の布告では、諸藩に対して御誓文の趣旨に沿って人材抜擢などの改革を進めることを命じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than those, on the declaration of April 12 in the same year it ordered domains to proceed with reform such as sellection for talented people following the purpose of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than those, on the declaration of April 12 in the same year it ordered domains to proceed with reform such as selection for talented people based on the purpose of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>following→based onに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than those, on the declaration of April 12 in the same year it ordered domains to proceed with reform such as selection for talented people based on the purpose of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、各地の人民に対して出された告諭書にも御誓文を部分的に引用する例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in kokuyusho (document of official notice) to people in various places, Charter Oath was quoted in some cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in kokuyusho (document of official notice) to people in various places, Charter Oath was quoted in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in kokuyusho (document of official notice) to people in various places, Charter Oath was quoted in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>例えば、明治元年8月の「奥羽士民に対する告諭」は御誓文の第一条を元に「広く会議を興し万機公論に決するは素より天下の事一人の私する所にあらざればなり」と述べ、同年10月の「京都府下人民告諭大意」は第三条を元に「上下心を一にし、末々に至るまで各其志を遂げさせ」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in August 1868, &apos;official notice to shimin (warrior and ordinary people) of Ou region&apos; stated &apos;All affairs of State shall be referred to public opinion through general conferences because &apos; based on the first article of Charter Oath</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in August 1868, &apos;official notice to shimin (warrior and ordinary people) of Ou region stated &apos;All affairs of State shall be referred to public opinion through general conferences because affairs of state shall not belong to a single person&apos; based on the first article of Charter Oath, in October of the same year, &apos;an outline of official notice to residents in Kyoto Prefecture stated &apos;The government and the people shall act in harmony to accomplish one&apos;s aspiration&apos; based on the third article of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>※全体的に変更しました。訳が不足しています。（特に「京都府下～」は全く訳出されていません。）「上下心を一にし、末々に至るまで各其志を遂げさせ」は「官民が心をひとつにしてそれぞれ（各個人の）目標を達成できるようにする」と解釈しました。また、「広く会議を興し万機公論に決する」は五箇条の御誓文本文の訳と区別するため異なる訳をあてています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in August 1868, &apos;official notice to shimin (warrior and ordinary people) of Ou region stated &apos;All affairs of State shall be referred to public opinion through general conferences because affairs of state shall not belong to a single person&apos; based on the first article of Charter Oath, in October of the same year, &apos;an outline of official notice to residents in Kyoto Prefecture stated &apos;The government and the people shall act in harmony to accomplish one&apos;s aspiration&apos; based on the third article of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>御誓文の復活</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Resurgence of Charter Oath</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Restoration of Charter Oath</e>
<cmt>Resurgence→Restorationに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Restoration of Charter Oath</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>その後、政体書体制がなし崩しになり、さらには明治4年（1871年）の廃藩置県により中央集権が確立するに至り、御誓文の存在意義が薄れかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Constitution of 1868 was undermined and moreover in 1871 centralization was established by Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) and the importance of Charter Oath began to fade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system based on the Constitution of 1868 was undermined and moreover in 1871 centralization was established by Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) and the importance of Charter Oath began to fade.</e>
<cmt>政体書体制The system based on the Constitution～に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system based on the Constitution of 1868 was undermined and moreover in 1871 centralization was established by Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) and the importance of Charter Oath began to fade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>明治5年（1872年）4月1日、岩倉使節団がワシントン滞在中、御誓文の話題になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 1, 1872, when Iwakura Mission was staying in Washington, Charter Oath came to an issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 1, 1872, when Iwakura Mission was staying in Washington, Charter Oath came to an issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 1, 1872, when Iwakura Mission was staying in Washington, Charter Oath came to an issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>木戸孝允は「なるほど左様なことがあった。その御誓文を今覚えておるか」と言い、その存在を忘れていた模様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi KIDO said &apos;that&apos;s right. That happened. Do you still remember the Charter Oath?&apos; and seemed to have forgotten the existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi KIDO said &apos;That&apos;s right. That happened. Do you still remember the Charter Oath?&apos; and seemed to have forgotten the existence.</e>
<cmt>that&apos;right 最初のｔを大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi KIDO said &apos;That&apos;s right. That happened. Do you still remember the Charter Oath?&apos; and seemed to have forgotten the existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この時、御誓文の写しを貰った木戸孝允は翌日には「かの御誓文は昨夜反復熟読したが、実によくできておる。この御主意は決して改変してはならぬ。自分の目の黒い間は死を賭しても支持する」と語った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi KIDO was given a copy of Charter Oath at that time and on the next day he said &apos;I read that Charter Oath carefully more than once and found it remarkable. The main idea shouldn&apos;t be changed. I support it with my life as long as I&apos;m alive.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi KIDO was given a copy of Charter Oath at that time and on the next day he said &apos;I read that Charter Oath carefully more than once and found it remarkable. The main idea shouldn&apos;t be changed. I support it with my life as long as I&apos;m alive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi KIDO was given a copy of Charter Oath at that time and on the next day he said &apos;I read that Charter Oath carefully more than once and found it remarkable. The main idea shouldn&apos;t be changed. I support it with my life as long as I&apos;m alive.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1875年（明治8年）、木戸孝允の主導により出された立憲政体の詔書で「誓文の意を拡充して...漸次に国家立憲の政体を立て」と宣言。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1875, it was declared in Shosho of the constitutional system of government issued on the initiative of Takayoshi KIDO &apos;expand the main idea of Charter Oath…establish constitutional state&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1875, it was declared in Rikkenseitai no Shosho (An imperial edict for the establishment of the constitutional system of government) issued on the initiative of Takayoshi KIDO, &apos;expand the main idea of Charter Oath…gradually establish constitutional state.&apos;</e>
<cmt>立憲政体の詔書：登録用語をもとに変更しました。…establish の前にgradually 「漸次に」を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1875, it was declared in Rikkenseitai no Shosho (An imperial edict for the establishment of the constitutional system of government) issued on the initiative of Takayoshi KIDO, &apos;expand the main idea of Charter Oath…gradually establish constitutional state.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>立憲政治の実現に向けての出発点として御誓文を位置付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter Oath was positioned as the starting point to realize constitutional government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter Oath was positioned as the starting point to realize constitutional government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter Oath was positioned as the starting point to realize constitutional government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>自由民権運動と御誓文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and Charter Oath</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and Charter Oath</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and Charter Oath</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>自由民権運動が高まる中、御誓文は立憲政治の実現を公約したものとして一般に受け止められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement was growing, Charter Oath was accepted generally as a pledge of realization of constitutional government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement was growing, Charter Oath was accepted generally as a pledge of realization of constitutional government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement was growing, Charter Oath was accepted generally as a pledge of realization of constitutional government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>特に第一条「広く会議を興し万機公論に決すべし」は、当初は民選議会を意図したものではなかったが、後に民選議会を開設すべき根拠とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially the first article &apos;All affairs of State shall be referred to public opinion through general conferences&apos; was not intended popularly-elected parliament at the beginning, but later it was considered as a basis of introduction of popularly-elected parliament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially the first article &apos;Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion&apos; was not intended for popularly-elected parliament at the beginning, but later it was considered as a basis of introduction of popularly-elected parliament.</e>
<cmt>intended の後にforを追加しました。「広く会議を興し万機公論に決すべし」は下記に五箇条の御誓文本文について解説されている部分の訳をあてました。（本文書全体で統一されていなかったため。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially the first article &apos;Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion&apos; was not intended for popularly-elected parliament at the beginning, but later it was considered as a basis of introduction of popularly-elected parliament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>例えば、1880年（明治13年）4月に植木枝盛が起草し片岡健吉・河野広中らが提出した「国会を開設するの允可を上願する書」が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, &apos;petition to establish the Diet&apos; drawn up by Emori UEKI in April 1880 and submitted by Kenkichi KATAOKA and Hironaka KONO is well-known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, &apos;petition to establish the Diet&apos; drawn up by Emori UEKI in April 1880 and submitted by Kenkichi KATAOKA and Hironaka KONO is well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, &apos;petition to establish the Diet&apos; drawn up by Emori UEKI in April 1880 and submitted by Kenkichi KATAOKA and Hironaka KONO is well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>明治憲法制定により帝国議会が開設されるまでの間、自由民権派は御誓文の実現を求めて政府に対する批判を繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until Imperial Diet was introduced based on Meiji Constitution, the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights group criticized the government repeatedly demanding realization of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until Imperial Diet was introduced based on Meiji Constitution, the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights group criticized the government repeatedly demanding realization of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until Imperial Diet was introduced based on Meiji Constitution, the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights group criticized the government repeatedly demanding realization of Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>戦後の御誓文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Charter Oath after the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Charter Oath after the World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt>以下の内容から第二次世界大戦と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Charter Oath after the World War Ⅱ</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>戦後、1946年（昭和21年）1月1日の昭和天皇の人間宣言で、御誓文の条文が引用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, provision of Charter Oath was quoted in Humanity declaration of the Emperor Showa on January 1, 1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, provisions of Charter Oath was quoted in Humanity declaration of the Emperor Showa on January 1, 1946.</e>
<cmt>provision→provisionsに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, provisions of Charter Oath was quoted in Humanity declaration of the Emperor Showa on January 1, 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>昭和天皇は幣原喜重郎首相が連合国軍最高司令官総司令部に主導されて作成した草案を初めて見た際に、「これで結構だが、これまでも皇室が決して独裁的なものでなかったことを示すために、明治天皇の五箇条の御誓文を加えることはできないだろうか」と述べ、急遽GHQの許可を得て加えられることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Emperor Showa saw the draft of prime minister Kijuro SHIDEHARA led by General Headquarters Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers for the first time, he said &apos;it is fine, but to show that the Imperial Family has never been dictatorial, it that possible to add Charter Oath of Five Articles of the Emperor Meiji?&apos; and it was decided in haste to be added under permission from GHQ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Emperor Showa saw the draft of prime minister Kijuro SHIDEHARA led by the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) for the first time, the Emperor said &apos;it is fine, but to show that the Imperial Family has never been dictatorial, it that possible to add Charter Oath of Five Articles of the Emperor Meiji?&apos; and it was added in haste under permission from GHQ.</e>
<cmt>用語集を参照し連合国軍最高司令官総司令部はthe General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ)と訳出しました。He→the Emperorに変更しました。it was decided in haste to be added→it was added in haste に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Emperor Showa saw the draft of prime minister Kijuro SHIDEHARA led by the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) for the first time, the Emperor said &apos;it is fine, but to show that the Imperial Family has never been dictatorial, it that possible to add Charter Oath of Five Articles of the Emperor Meiji?&apos; and it was added in haste under permission from GHQ.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>天皇は後に、「それが実は、あの詔書の一番の目的であって、神格とかそういうことは二の問題でした。（中略）民主主義を採用したのは明治大帝の思召しである。しかも神に誓われた。そうして五箇条御誓文を発して、それが基となって明治憲法ができたんで、民主主義というものは決して輸入物ではないということを示す必要が大いにあったと思います。」と語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor said later &apos;actually it was the purpose of the edict, so the divinity or other things came next. (snip) it was the emperor Meiji that adopted democracy. He also swore to God and issued Charter Oath of Five Articles, by which Meiji Constitution was made, so I think it was very necessary to show that democracy was not imported.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor said later &apos;actually it was the purpose of the edict, so the divinity or other things came next. (snip) it was the emperor Meiji who adopted democracy. He also swore to God and issued Charter Oath of Five Articles, by which Meiji Constitution was made, so I think it was necessary to show that democracy was not imported.&apos;</e>
<cmt>that→whoに変更しました。Very削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor said later &apos;actually it was the purpose of the edict, so the divinity or other things came next. (snip) it was the emperor Meiji who adopted democracy. He also swore to God and issued Charter Oath of Five Articles, by which Meiji Constitution was made, so I think it was necessary to show that democracy was not imported.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="44">
<j>1946年（昭和21年）6月25日、衆議院本会議における日本国憲法案の審議の初め、当時の吉田茂首相は御誓文に言及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 25, 1946, at the beginning of consideration of the Constitution of Japan in the Lower House, then Prime Minister Shigeru YOSHIDA referred to Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 25, 1946, at the beginning of consideration of the Constitution of Japan in the Lower House, Prime Minister Shigeru YOSHIDA referred to Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>then削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 25, 1946, at the beginning of consideration of the Constitution of Japan in the Lower House, Prime Minister Shigeru YOSHIDA referred to Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>「日本の憲法は御承知のごとく五箇条の御誓文から出発したものと云ってもよいのでありますが、いわゆる五箇条の御誓文なるものは、日本の歴史、日本の国情をただ文字に現わしただけの話でありまして、御誓文の精神、それが日本国の国体であります。日本国そのものであったのであります。この御誓文を見ましても、日本国は民主主義であり、デモクラシーそのものであり、あえて君権政治とか、あるいは圧制政治の国体でなかったことは明瞭であります」と答弁した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He answered &apos;As you know, it can be said that the Constitution of Japan started from Charter Oath. So-called Charter Oath of Five Articles was just written expressing the history and the state of affairs of Japan. The spirit of Charter Oath itself is the national policy of Japan and what Japan is. Seeing Charter Oath, Japan is a democratic country and democracy itself. It is obvious that the national policy was not monarchy or repressive government.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He answered &apos;As you know, it can be said that the Constitution of Japan started from Charter Oath. So-called Charter Oath of Five Articles was just written expressing the history and the state of affairs of Japan. The spirit of Charter Oath itself is the national policy of Japan and what Japan is. Seeing Charter Oath, Japan is a democratic country and democracy itself. It is obvious that the national policy was not monarchy or repressive government.&apos;</e>
<cmt>句読点が全角になっていたため修正を試みましたが、trans2にコピー＆ペーストまたは直接入力を行ってもセルに色が付いてしまいます。ご対応お願いします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He answered &apos;As you know, it can be said that the Constitution of Japan started from Charter Oath. So-called Charter Oath of Five Articles was just written expressing the history and the state of affairs of Japan. The spirit of Charter Oath itself is the national policy of Japan and what Japan is. Seeing Charter Oath, Japan is a democratic country and democracy itself. It is obvious that the national policy was not monarchy or repressive government.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このように敗戦後の初期には支配層は五箇条の御誓文は民主主義の原理であると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This way, in early times after defeat in the war, the ruling classes claimed that Charter Oath of Five Articles was the principle of democracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the example above, shortly after the war, the ruling class claimed that Charter Oath of Five Articles was the principle of democracy.</e>
<cmt>this way→as the example aboveに変更しました。after defeat in the war → shortly after the warに変更しました。classes→classに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the example above, shortly after the war, the ruling class claimed that Charter Oath of Five Articles was the principle of democracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>正式な表題は、法令全書によると、「御誓文」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formal title was &apos;Charter Oath&apos; according to Horei Zensho (Compendium of laws and regulations).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formal title is &apos;Charter Oath&apos; according to Horei Zensho (Compendium of laws and regulations).</e>
<cmt>was→isに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formal title is &apos;Charter Oath&apos; according to Horei Zensho (Compendium of laws and regulations).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>明治天皇自身がこれを呼ぶときは単に「誓文」という（例えば1875年の立憲政体の詔書）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji called that just &apos;seimon&apos; (Charter Oath), (for example in Shosho of the constitutional system of government in 1875).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Meiji called that just &apos;seimon&apos; (Charter Oath), (for example in Rikkenseitai no Shosho in 1875).</e>
<cmt>Shosho of the constitutional system of government→Rikkenseitai no Shoshoに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji called that just &apos;seimon&apos; (Charter Oath), (for example in Rikkenseitai no Shosho in 1875).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>よく使われる「五箇条の御誓文」などの呼称は、後の時代の通称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names like &apos;Gokajo no goseimon&apos; (Charter Oath of Five Articles) which were often called were common names in later days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names like &apos;Gokajo no goseimon&apos; which were often called were common names in later period.</e>
<cmt>()内の説明は省略しました。In later days→later periodeに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names like &apos;Gokajo no goseimon&apos; which were often called were common names in later period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>御誓文の本体は、明治天皇が天神地祇に誓った五つの条文からなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The body of Charter Oath consisted of 5 provisions which the Emperor Meiji swore to the gods of heaven and earth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The body of Charter Oath consisted of 5 provisions which the Emperor Meiji swore to the gods of heaven and earth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The body of Charter Oath consisted of 5 provisions which the Emperor Meiji swore to the gods of heaven and earth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この他、御誓文には勅語と奉答書が付属している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Charter Oath has Ordinance and hotosho (document to reply to the throne).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Charter Oath has Ordinance and hotosho.</e>
<cmt>hotosho既出のため()内削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Charter Oath has Ordinance and hotosho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>御誓文の各条および勅語・奉答書について解説すると次の通り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each provision of Charter Oath and Ordinance and hotosho are explained as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each provision of Charter Oath and Ordinance and hotosho are explained as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each provision of Charter Oath and Ordinance and hotosho are explained as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>一 広ク会議ヲ興シ万機公論ニ決スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">広ク会議ヲ興シ万機公論ニ決スヘシ (Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1. 広ク会議ヲ興シ万機公論ニ決スヘシ (Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion.)</e>
<cmt>数字を追加しました。(trans1の表記方法（第二条以下）に従いました。）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1. 広ク会議ヲ興シ万機公論ニ決スヘシ (Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>（現代表記）広く会議を興し、万機公論に決すべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 広く会議を興し、万機公論に決すべし。(Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 広く会議を興し、万機公論に決すべし。(Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion.)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 広く会議を興し、万機公論に決すべし。(Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established and all matters decided by open discussion.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>（由利案第五条）万機公論に決し私に論ずるなかれ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The fifth article of Yuri draft) 万機公論に決し私に論ずるなかれ (All affairs of the state shall be widely discussed and all matters decided not by private discussion.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The fifth article of Yuri draft) 万機公論に決し私に論ずるなかれ。 (All affairs of the state shall be widely discussed and all matters shall not be decided by private discussion.)</e>
<cmt>decided not by→shall not be decided byに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The fifth article of Yuri draft) 万機公論に決し私に論ずるなかれ。 (All affairs of the state shall be widely discussed and all matters shall not be decided by private discussion.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>（福岡案第一条）列侯会議を興し万機公論に決すべし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The first article of Fukuoka draft) 列侯会議を興し万機公論に決すべし (Council by feudal lords shall be established and all matters decided by open discussion)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The first article of Fukuoka draft) 列侯会議を興し万機公論に決すべし (Council by feudal lords shall be established and all matters decided by open discussion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The first article of Fukuoka draft) 列侯会議を興し万機公論に決すべし (Council by feudal lords shall be established and all matters decided by open discussion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>この条文は、由利案では第五条であったが、福岡によって第一条に移された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article was the fifth in the Yuri draft, but it was changed to the first by Fukuoka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article was the fifth in the Yuri draft, but it was changed to the first by Fukuoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This article was the fifth in the Yuri draft, but it was changed to the first by Fukuoka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その理由は「諸侯会議を以て第一着の事業と考え」たためと福岡自身が回顧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuoka himself looked back that it was because &apos;he thought loads conference as the most important work&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuoka himself looked back that it was because he thought &apos;establishment of lords conference is the first work to be done.&apos;</e>
<cmt>loads→lordsに変更しました。一着「仕事などで最初に着手すること。」デジタル大辞泉（小学館）を参考にthe most important work→the first work to be done</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuoka himself looked back that it was because he thought &apos;establishment of lords conference is the first work to be done.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>（福岡孝弟『五箇条御誓文と政体書の由来に就いて』1919年に依る。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Base on &quot;The origin of Charter Oath of Five Articles and the Constitution of 1868&quot; written by Takachika FUKUOKA in 1919)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Base on &quot;The origin of Charter Oath of Five Articles and the Constitution of 1868&quot; written by Takachika FUKUOKA in 1919)</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Base on &quot;The origin of Charter Oath of Five Articles and the Constitution of 1868&quot; written by Takachika FUKUOKA in 1919)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>(以下、福岡の回顧は特に断らない限りこれに依る。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Hereinafter Fukuoka&apos;s memoir is based on this unless otherwise stated.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Hereinafter Fukuoka&apos;s retrospect is based on this unless otherwise stated.)</e>
<cmt>memoir→metrospectに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Hereinafter Fukuoka&apos;s retrospect is based on this unless otherwise stated.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="60">
<j>前段の「広く会議を興し」については、由利案には「会議」に相当する語はなく、福岡の修正案で「列侯会議」の語があらわれ、これが最終段階で「広く会議」と修正された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the first part &apos;Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established&apos;, in the Yuri draft there was no word equivalent to &apos;assembly&apos; and in the revised draft of Fukuoka &apos;Council by feudal lords appeared and at the final stage it was revised to &apos;widely established deliberative assemblies&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the first part &apos;Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established,&apos; in the Yuri draft there was no word equivalent to &apos;assembly&apos; and in the revised draft of Fukuoka &apos;Council by feudal lords&apos; appeared and at the final stage it was revised to &apos;widely established deliberative assemblies.&apos;</e>
<cmt>句読点を追加・位置変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the first part &apos;Deliberative assemblies shall be widely established,&apos; in the Yuri draft there was no word equivalent to &apos;assembly&apos; and in the revised draft of Fukuoka &apos;Council by feudal lords&apos; appeared and at the final stage it was revised to &apos;widely established deliberative assemblies.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>福岡は後年「この時平民までも此議会に与らしめる御つもりであったか」と問われ、「それは後から考えればそうも解釈されるが、御恥ずかしい話ですが当時私はまだその考えはなかったです」「広くとは人々の意見を広く集めて会議するというのではなく府藩県にわたりて広く何処にも会議を興すという義です」と答えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuoka was asked in later years &apos;Are you also going to get common people engaged in this assemblies at that time?&apos; and he answered &apos;It can be interpreted so in retrospect, but I&apos;m ashamed to say, I was not thinking about that yet at that time&apos; &apos;Widely didn&apos;t mean holding assemblies by gathering people&apos;s opinions widely, but holding assemblies widely all through the prefectures.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuoka was asked in later years &apos;Were you also going to get common people engaged in this assemblies at that time?&apos; and he answered &apos;It can be interpreted so in retrospect, but I&apos;m ashamed to say, I was not thinking about that at that time&apos; &apos;Widely didn&apos;t mean holding assemblies by gathering people&apos;s opinions widely, but holding assemblies widely through all prefectures.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Are you→Were youに変更しました。Yet 削除しました。All through the prefectures→through all prefecturesに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuoka was asked in later years &apos;Were you also going to get common people engaged in this assemblies at that time?&apos; and he answered &apos;It can be interpreted so in retrospect, but I&apos;m ashamed to say, I was not thinking about that at that time&apos; &apos;Widely didn&apos;t mean holding assemblies by gathering people&apos;s opinions widely, but holding assemblies widely through all prefectures.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかしながら、ここを「列侯会議」に限定せずに漠然と「広く会議」に改めたことは、後に起草者たちの意図を離れ、民権論者によって民選議会を開設すべき根拠として拡張解釈されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the vague revision to &apos;widely established deliberative assemblies&apos; not restricting &apos;councils by feudal lords&apos; was extended later by Civil rights advocates as the authority to establish popularly-elected parliament, being far from the original intentions of drafters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the vague revision to &apos;widely established deliberative assemblies&apos; not restricting &apos;councils by feudal lords&apos; was extended later by civil rights advocates as the authority to establish popularly-elected parliament, being far from the original intentions of drafters.</e>
<cmt>Civil→civilに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the vague revision to &apos;widely established deliberative assemblies&apos; not restricting &apos;councils by feudal lords&apos; was extended later by civil rights advocates as the authority to establish popularly-elected parliament, being far from the original intentions of drafters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また明治政府自身もそのように解釈するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also the Meiji government itself interpreted it like that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also the Meiji government itself interpreted it like that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also the Meiji government itself interpreted it like that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="64">
<j>後段の「万機」は「あらゆる重要事項」の意味。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;All affairs of the state&apos; in the latter part meant &apos;every important affairs&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;万機&apos; in the latter part meant &apos;every important affairs.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ここは「万機」という単語の解釈であるため、英訳と比較するのはおかしく思えます。よって漢字表記に改めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;万機&apos; in the latter part meant &apos;every important affairs.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>「公論」は公議と同義、または公議輿論の略語であり、「みんなの意見」または「公開された議論」といったような意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;公論&apos; (open discussion) is a synonym or abbreviation of public opinion which means &apos;everyone&apos;s opinion&apos; or &apos;open discussion&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">公論&apos; (open discussion) is a synonym or abbreviation of &apos;公議輿論&apos; which means &apos;everyone&apos;s opinion&apos; or &apos;open discussion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>上記と同様の理由で、適宜漢字表記を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">公論&apos; (open discussion) is a synonym or abbreviation of &apos;公議輿論&apos; which means &apos;everyone&apos;s opinion&apos; or &apos;open discussion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>「万機公論に決すべし」の語句は、由利と親交のあった坂本竜馬の船中八策（慶応三年六月）に「万機宜しく公議に決すへし」とあり、ここから採られたものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the phrase &apos;all matters decided by open discussion&apos; was adopted from &apos;万機公論に決すべし&apos; (all matters decided by open discussion) of Senchu hassaku (the basic outline of the new regime) (in 1867) drawn up by Ryoma Sakamoto who was a friend of Yuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the phrase &apos;万機公論に決すべし(all matters decided by open discussion)&apos; was adopted from &apos;万機宜しく公議に決すへし (all matters decided by open discussion)&apos; of Senchu hassaku (the basic outline of the new regime) (in 1867) drawn up by Ryoma SAKAMOTO who was a friend of Yuri.</e>
<cmt>上記と同様の理由で、適宜漢字表記を追加しました。※船中八策から引用されたはずの文章が、五箇条のご誓文の文章と入れ替わっています。（訂正済み）※Sakamoto→SAKAMOTOに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the phrase &apos;万機公論に決すべし(all matters decided by open discussion)&apos; was adopted from &apos;万機宜しく公議に決すへし (all matters decided by open discussion)&apos; of Senchu hassaku (the basic outline of the new regime) (in 1867) drawn up by Ryoma SAKAMOTO who was a friend of Yuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>由利の草稿では、初めは「万機公議」と書き、後で「万機公論」と改めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the draft of Yuri it was written first &apos;banki kogi&apos; (deliberative assemblies shall be widely established for all affairs of the state) and later revised to &apos;banki koron&apos; (all affairs of the state shall be widely discussed).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the draft of Yuri it was written first &apos;banki kogi&apos; (万機公議) and later revised to &apos;banki koron&apos; (万機公論).</e>
<cmt>比較の対象がよくわからなくなっています。よって、前例と同じく、適宜漢字表記を追加して、比較対象を整理しました。公議：公衆の是認する議論。世上一般の議論。公論。（第五版広辞苑（岩波書店））</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the draft of Yuri it was written first &apos;banki kogi&apos; (万機公議) and later revised to &apos;banki koron&apos; (万機公論).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>一 上下心ヲ一ニシテ盛ニ経綸ヲ行フヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2. 上下心ヲ一ニシテ盛ニ経綸ヲ行フヘシ(All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2. 上下心ヲ一ニシテ盛ニ経綸ヲ行フヘシ(All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2. 上下心ヲ一ニシテ盛ニ経綸ヲ行フヘシ(All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>（現代表記）上下心を一にして、さかんに経綸を行うべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 上下心を一にして、さかんに経綸を行うべし。(All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 上下心を一にして、さかんに経綸を行うべし。(All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 上下心を一にして、さかんに経綸を行うべし。(All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>（由利案第二条）士民心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふを要す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The second article of Yuri draft) 士民心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふを要す (All classes, shimin (warrior and ordinary people) shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The second article of Yuri draft) 士民心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふを要す (All classes, shimin (warrior and ordinary people) shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The second article of Yuri draft) 士民心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふを要す (All classes, shimin (warrior and ordinary people) shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="70">
<j>（福岡案第三条）上下心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふべし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The third article of Fukuoka draft) 上下心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふべし (All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The third article of Fukuoka draft) 上下心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふべし (All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The third article of Fukuoka draft) 上下心を一にし盛に経綸を行ふべし (All classes, high and low, shall be united in vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="71">
<j>冒頭の「上下」は、由利案では「士民」だったが、福岡の回顧によれば「一層意味を広くするために士民を上下に改めた」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;High and low&apos; at the beginning was &apos;shimin&apos; in the Yuri draft, however according to the memoir of Fukuoka &apos;shimin was changed to high and low to broaden the meaning more&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">High and low&apos; at the beginning was &apos;shimin&apos; in the Yuri draft, however according to retrospect of Fukuoka &apos;shimin was changed to high and low to broaden the meaning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>memoir→metrospectに変更しました。句読点の位置変更しました。More削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">High and low&apos; at the beginning was &apos;shimin&apos; in the Yuri draft, however according to retrospect of Fukuoka &apos;shimin was changed to high and low to broaden the meaning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>「心を一にして」は日本国民の団結を表現する当時の決まり文句であり、江戸期の水戸学者の著作から後の教育勅語に至るまで広く使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Shall be united&apos; was cliche expressing the unity of Japanese people at the time and was used widely form literary works of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) academics in the Edo period to the Imperial Rescript on Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">心を一にして (Shall be united) &apos; was cliche expressing the unity of Japanese people at the time and was used widely from literary works of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) academics in the Edo period to the Imperial Rescript on Education.</e>
<cmt>前例と同じく、適宜漢字表記を追加して、比較対象を整理しました。Form→ｆromに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">心を一にして (Shall be united) &apos; was cliche expressing the unity of Japanese people at the time and was used widely from literary works of Mitogaku (the scholarship and academic traditions that arose in the Mito Domain) academics in the Edo period to the Imperial Rescript on Education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="73">
<j>後段の「経綸」の語の解釈には注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be carefully interpreted &apos;the administration of affairs of state&apos; in the latter part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;経綸(the administration of affairs of state)&apos; in the latter part should be carefully interpreted.</e>
<cmt>前例と同じく、適宜漢字表記を追加して、比較対象を整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;経綸(the administration of affairs of state)&apos; in the latter part should be carefully interpreted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>由利の出身藩である越前藩のために横井小楠が著した「国是三論」において「一国上の経綸」という章があり、そこでは主に財政経済について論じられていることから、その影響を受けた由利は経綸の語を専ら経済の意味で用いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kokuze Sanron (the Three Major Discussion of State Policy) written by Shonan YOKOI for Echizen Domain where Yuri came, there is a chapter &apos;the administration of affairs of state&apos; in which finance and economy were discussed mainly, therefore Yuri who was affected by that, always used the phrase as economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kokuze Sanron (the Three Major Discussion of State Policy) written by Shonan YOKOI for Echizen Domain where Yuri came from, there is a chapter &apos;一国上の経綸 (the administration of affairs of state) &apos; in which finance and economy were mainly discussed, because Yuri who was affected by that, always used the word &apos;経綸&apos; as economy.</e>
<cmt>全体的に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kokuze Sanron (the Three Major Discussion of State Policy) written by Shonan YOKOI for Echizen Domain where Yuri came from, there is a chapter &apos;一国上の経綸 (the administration of affairs of state) &apos; in which finance and economy were mainly discussed, because Yuri who was affected by that, always used the word &apos;経綸&apos; as economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>したがって、この条文のいう「盛に経綸を行う」とは由利にとっては「経済を振興する」という意味であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore &apos;vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state&apos; in this article probably meant &apos;encouraging economy&apos; for Yuri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore &apos;盛に経綸を行う (vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state) &apos; in this article probably meant &apos;encouraging economy&apos; for Yuri.</e>
<cmt>前例と同じく、適宜漢字表記を追加して、比較対象を整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore &apos;盛に経綸を行う (vigorously carrying out the administration of affairs of state) &apos; in this article probably meant &apos;encouraging economy&apos; for Yuri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>もっとも、当時、経綸の語は一般に馴染みのある語ではなく、江戸版の太政官日誌では経綸を経論と誤記しケイロンとルビを振っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at that time the phrase 経綸 (the administration of affairs of state) was not familiar to common people and in Daijokan diary of Edo version it was written wrongly as 経論 having kana to indicate the pronunciation, keiron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at that time the phrase 経綸 (the administration of affairs of state) was not familiar to common people, in Daijokan nittshi of Edo version it was written wrongly as 経論 with wrong pronunciation &apos;keiron(&apos;keirin&apos;is right pronunciation of the word).&apos;</e>
<cmt>太政官日誌の表記、前例に基づき変更しました。誤記の部分についても適宜変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at that time the phrase 経綸 (the administration of affairs of state) was not familiar to common people, in Daijokan nittshi of Edo version it was written wrongly as 経論 with wrong pronunciation &apos;keiron(&apos;keirin&apos;is right pronunciation of the word).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>福岡は後に回顧して「由利が盛に経綸経綸という文句を口癖のごとく振りまわしていた所であったからそのままにして置いたのである。経綸という字の意味は元は経済とか財政とかを意味していたようであるが、これは説く人々の解釈に任してよいのである」と述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Fukuoka looked back that later, he said &apos;Yuri kept saying the word, keiron at that time, so I just left it. Keiron seemed to mean originally economy and finance, but it can be interpreted by each preacher.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Fukuoka looked back that later, he said &apos;Yuri kept saying the word, keirin at that time, so I just left it. Keirin seemed to mean originally economy and finance, but it can be interpreted by each preacher.&apos;</e>
<cmt>経綸の発音はけいりんです。(該当部分変更済み）（第五版広辞苑（岩波書店））</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Fukuoka looked back that later, he said &apos;Yuri kept saying the word, keirin at that time, so I just left it. Keirin seemed to mean originally economy and finance, but it can be interpreted by each preacher.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>一般的には、経綸の語は、経済政策に限らず国家の政策全般を意味するものとして理解されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally the word, keiron is understood as a word referring not only economic policy but also genera national policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally the word, keirin is understood as a word referring not only economic policy but also general national policy.</e>
<cmt>経綸の発音はけいりんです。(該当部分変更済み）（第五版広辞苑（岩波書店））genera→generalに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally the word, keirin is understood as a word referring not only economic policy but also general national policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>一 官武一途庶民ニ至ル迄各其志ヲ遂ケ人心ヲシテ倦マサラシメン事ヲ要ス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3. 官武一途庶民ニ至ル迄各其志ヲ遂ケ人心ヲシテ倦マサラシメン事ヲ要ス(The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3. 官武一途庶民ニ至ル迄各其志ヲ遂ケ人心ヲシテ倦マサラシメン事ヲ要ス(The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3. 官武一途庶民ニ至ル迄各其志ヲ遂ケ人心ヲシテ倦マサラシメン事ヲ要ス(The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="79">
<j>（現代表記）官武一途庶民にいたるまで、おのおのその志を遂げ、人心をして倦まざらしめんことを要す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 官武一途庶民にいたるまで、おのおのその志を遂げ、人心をして倦まざらしめんことを要す。(The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 官武一途庶民にいたるまで、おのおのその志を遂げ、人心をして倦まざらしめんことを要す。(The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 官武一途庶民にいたるまで、おのおのその志を遂げ、人心をして倦まざらしめんことを要す。(The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>（由利案第一条）庶民志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを欲す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The first article of Yuri draft) 庶民志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを欲す (The common people shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The first article of Yuri draft) 庶民志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを欲す (The common people shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The first article of Yuri draft) 庶民志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを欲す (The common people shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="81">
<j>（福岡案第二条）官武一途庶民に至る迄各其志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを要す</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The second article of Fukuoka draft)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The second article of Fukuoka draft) 官武一途庶民に至る迄各其志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを要す。 (The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>訳文が抜けています。五箇条の御誓文と同義の文と考え、御誓文の該当部分の訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The second article of Fukuoka draft) 官武一途庶民に至る迄各其志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむるを要す。 (The common people, no less than the civil and military officials, shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="82">
<j>由利案ではこの条文は第一条に置かれ最重視されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yuri draft it was the first article being emphasized most.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Yuri draft it was the first article and was most emphasized.</e>
<cmt>全体に的に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Yuri draft it was the first article and was most emphasized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>由利は後の著書「英雄観」で「庶民をして各志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむべしとは、治国の要道であって、古今東西の善由利は後の著書「英雄観」で「庶民をして各志を遂げ人心をして倦まざらしむべしとは、治国の要道であって、古今東西の善政は悉くこの一言に帰着するのである。みよ、立憲政じゃというても、あるいは名君の仁政じゃといっても、要はこれに他ならぬのである。」と述べている。政は悉くこの一言に帰着するのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuri wrote later in his book &apos;Heroism&apos;, &apos;The common people shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent means a important way to lead a nation. Good government of all ages and countries comes back to this. Look, constitutional government as well as benevolent rule of wise ruler are neither more nor less than this.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuri wrote later in his book &apos;Heroism,&apos; &apos;The common people shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent means a important way to lead a nation, and Good government of all ages and countries comes back to this. Look, constitutional government as well as benevolent rule of wise ruler are neither more nor less than this.&apos; and all politics lead to this after all.</e>
<cmt>「政は悉くこの一言に帰着するのである。」→all politics lead to this after all.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuri wrote later in his book &apos;Heroism,&apos; &apos;The common people shall all be allowed to pursue their own calling so that there may be no discontent means a important way to lead a nation, and Good government of all ages and countries comes back to this. Look, constitutional government as well as benevolent rule of wise ruler are neither more nor less than this.&apos; and all politics lead to this after all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="84">
<j>冒頭の「官武一途」は語は福岡孝弟の修正案で追加されたものであり、「官」とは太政官すなわち中央政府、「武」とは武家すなわち地方の諸侯、「一途」は一体を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;No less than the civil and military officials&apos; at the beginning was added in the revised draft of Takachika FUKUOKA and &apos;the civil officials&apos; means Daijokan (the Great Council of State) or central government, &apos;the military officials&apos; means military families or regional lords, &apos;no less than&apos; means united.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;官武一途 (no less than the civil and military officials)&apos; at the beginning was added in the revised draft of Takachika FUKUOKA and &apos;官 (the civil officials) &apos; means Daijokan (the Great Council of State) and central government, &apos;武 (the military officials) &apos; means military families and regional lords, &apos;一途 (no less than) &apos; means united.</e>
<cmt>前例と同じく、適宜漢字表記を追加して、比較対象を整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;官武一途 (no less than the civil and military officials)&apos; at the beginning was added in the revised draft of Takachika FUKUOKA and &apos;官 (the civil officials) &apos; means Daijokan (the Great Council of State) and central government, &apos;武 (the military officials) &apos; means military families and regional lords, &apos;一途 (no less than) &apos; means united.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これは福岡の回顧では「官武一途即ち朝廷と諸侯が一体となって天下の政治を行う」意味としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the momoir of Fukuoka &apos;No less than the civil and military officials means government of the country in which Imperial court and lords are engaged together&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the retrospect of Fukuoka &apos;No less than the civil and military officials means government of the country in which Imperial court and lords are engaged together.&apos;</e>
<cmt>memoir→metrospectに変更しました。句読点の位置変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the retrospect of Fukuoka &apos;No less than the civil and military officials means government of the country in which Imperial court and lords are engaged together.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この条文は、もともとの由利の意図では庶民の社会生活の充足をうたったものであったが、福岡が政治の意味を込めて「官武一途」の語を挿入したため、条文の主旨が不明瞭になったことが指摘されている（稲田正次）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provision declared social life of the common people originally based on the intention of Yuri, however, because Fukuoka added &apos;No less than the civil and military officials&apos; meaning politics, it is pointed out that the point of the provision became unclear (Masatsugu INADA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provision declared fulfilling social life of the common people originally based on the intention of Yuri, however, because Fukuoka added &apos;No less than the civil and military officials&apos; meaning politics, it is pointed out that the point of the provision became unclear (Masatsugu INADA).</e>
<cmt>fulfillingをsocial lifeの前に挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provision declared fulfilling social life of the common people originally based on the intention of Yuri, however, because Fukuoka added &apos;No less than the civil and military officials&apos; meaning politics, it is pointed out that the point of the provision became unclear (Masatsugu INADA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>一 旧来ノ陋習ヲ破リ天地ノ公道ニ基クヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4.旧来ノ陋習ヲ破リ天地ノ公道ニ基クヘシ(Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon the just laws of Nature.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4. 旧来ノ陋習ヲ破リ天地ノ公道ニ基クヘシ(Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon the just laws of Nature.)</e>
<cmt>4.の後に半角スペースを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4. 旧来ノ陋習ヲ破リ天地ノ公道ニ基クヘシ(Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon the just laws of Nature.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>（現代表記）旧来の陋習を破り、天地の公道に基づくべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 旧来の陋習を破り、天地の公道に基づくべし。(Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon the just laws of Nature.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 旧来の陋習を破り、天地の公道に基づくべし。(Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon the just laws of Nature.)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 旧来の陋習を破り、天地の公道に基づくべし。(Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon the just laws of Nature.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>（木戸当初案）旧来の陋習を破り宇内の通義に従ふへし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The first draft of Kito) 旧来の陋習を破り宇内の通義に従ふへし (Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon accepted meaning of the whole world.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The first draft of Kido) 旧来の陋習を破り宇内の通義に従ふへし (Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon accepted orders of the whole world.)</e>
<cmt>Kito→Kidoに変更しました。Meaning→orders</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The first draft of Kido) 旧来の陋習を破り宇内の通義に従ふへし (Evil customs of the past shall be broken off and everything based upon accepted orders of the whole world.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="89">
<j>この条文は由利案や福岡案では存在せず、木戸の修正により登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provision was not in the drafts of Yuri and Fukuoka and appeared by the revision of Kiso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provision was not in the drafts of Yuri and Fukuoka and appeared by the revision of Kido.</e>
<cmt>Kiso→Kidoに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provision was not in the drafts of Yuri and Fukuoka and appeared by the revision of Kido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>木戸当初案の「宇内（うだい）」は「天下」「世界」の別表現である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Udai&apos; (the whole world) of the first draft of Kido was another expression of &apos;tenka&apos; &apos;sekai&apos; (world).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Udai&apos; (the whole world) of the first draft of Kido was another expression of &apos;tenka&apos; &apos;sekai&apos; (world).</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Udai&apos; (the whole world) of the first draft of Kido was another expression of &apos;tenka&apos; &apos;sekai&apos; (world).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>「通義（つうぎ）」は「広く一般に通用する道理」という意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Tsugi&apos; (Accepted meaning) means &apos;order accepted by common people widely&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsugi&apos; (Accepted orders) means &apos;orders accepted by common people widely.&apos;</e>
<cmt>meaning→ordersに変更しました。Order→ordersに変更しました。句読点の位置変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsugi&apos; (Accepted orders) means &apos;orders accepted by common people widely.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>（いずれも三省堂『大辞林』第三版）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(All from the 3rd edision of &quot;Daijirin Japanese Dictionary&quot; of Sanseido)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(All from the 3rd edition of &quot;Daijirin Japanese Dictionary&quot; of Sanseido)</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(All from the 3rd edition of &quot;Daijirin Japanese Dictionary&quot; of Sanseido)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="93">
<j>この条文を、戦前の研究者尾佐竹猛は、「旧来の陋習」は鎖国攘夷を指し、「天地の公道」は万国公法すなわち国際法の意味であり、この条文は開国の方針を規定したものとして狭く解釈していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding this provision, a researcher before the war Takeki OSATAKE interpreted narrowly that &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; referred to national isolation as well as expulsion of foreigners and &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; meant international public law or international law and this provision defined a policy of opening of the country to the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding this provision, a researcher before the war Takeki OSATAKE interpreted narrowly that &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; referred to national isolation as well as expulsion of foreigners and &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; meant international public law or international law, and he concluded this provision defined a policy of opening of the country to the world.</e>
<cmt>he concluded追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding this provision, a researcher before the war Takeki OSATAKE interpreted narrowly that &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; referred to national isolation as well as expulsion of foreigners and &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; meant international public law or international law, and he concluded this provision defined a policy of opening of the country to the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="94">
<j>しかし、これに対し、稲田正次・松尾正人・佐々木克たちは、「天地の公道」は開国の方針や国際法を示すことだけではなかったと明確に説明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in contrast, Masatsugu INADA, Masahito MATSUO, Suguru SASAKI explained clearly that &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; didn&apos;t only refer to a policy of opening of the country to the world and international law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in contrast, Masatsugu INADA, Masahito MATSUO, Suguru SASAKI explained clearly that &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; didn&apos;t only refer to a policy of opening of the country to the world and international law.</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in contrast, Masatsugu INADA, Masahito MATSUO, Suguru SASAKI explained clearly that &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; didn&apos;t only refer to a policy of opening of the country to the world and international law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>その理由として、御誓文と同時に出された宸翰に出てくる「旧来の陋習」の語がそもそも鎖国攘夷の意味に限定されていないこと、また木戸孝允自身が「打破すべき封建性」「打破すべき閉鎖性」の意味で「旧習」「旧来の陋習」「陋習」という言葉を広く使用していること、また、大久保利通でさえ木戸の「旧来の陋習」と同じ意味のことを「因循の腐臭」とより痛烈に批判していること、つまり、薩長いずれも密留学をさせ倒幕に立ち上がった開明的雄藩であったにもかかわらず長州の木戸より薩摩の大久保のほうが藩主父子・出身藩の内部事情などのためにより批判的にならざるを得ない危険な封建性・閉鎖性をより自覚していたということ（寺田屋事件～西南戦争）、更に、岩倉具視も他の文書で「天地の公道」という全く同じ言葉を万国公法とはおよそ次元の異なる「天然自然の条理というような意味」で用いていることなどが挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the reason, they explained that the word &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; in shinkan (Imperial letter) issued at the same time as Charter Oath was not restricted to national isolation as well as expulsion of foreigners and Takayoshi KIDO himself used the words &apos;old customs&apos; &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; &apos;conventions&apos; widely as meaning of &apos;feudalism to be conquered&apos; &apos;closed nature to be conquered&apos; and even Toshimichi OKUBO severely criticized the same thing as &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; of Kido for &apos;corrupt smell of indecision&apos;, in other word, though both Satsuma and Choshu provided overseas education secretly and were liberal domains overthrowing the Shogunate, Okubo from Satsuma recognized more about dangerous feudalism as well as closed nature than Kido from Choshu, which he had to criticize because of father and son of the lords of the domain and internal circumstances of his domain (The Teradaya Incident - Seinan War), moreover Tomomi IWAKURA also used just the same words &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; as &apos;meaning of reason of nature&apos; in other document, which meant totally different from international public law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the reason, they explained that the word &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; in shinkan (Imperial letter) issued at the same time as Charter Oath was not restricted to national isolation as well as expulsion of foreigners, and Takayoshi KIDO himself used the words &apos;old customs&apos;, &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; and &apos;conventions&apos; widely as meaning of &apos;feudalism to be conquered&apos; or &apos;closed nature to be conquered&apos;, and even Toshimichi OKUBO severely criticized the same thing as &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; mentioned by Kido for &apos;corrupt smell of old customes&apos;, in other word, though both Satsuma and Choshu provided overseas education secretly and were liberal domains led the movement of overthrowing the Shogunate, Okubo from Satsuma recognized more about dangerous feudalism as well as closed nature than Kido from Choshu, Okubo had to criticize more extreme because of internal affair regarding father and son of the lords of his domain and internal circumstances of his domain (The Teradaya Incident - Seinan War), moreover Tomomi IWAKURA also used just the same words &apos;the laws of Nature&apos; as &apos;reason of nature&apos; in other document, which meant totally different from international public law.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the reason, they explained that the word &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; in shinkan (Imperial letter) issued at the same time as Charter Oath was not restricted to national isolation as well as expulsion of foreigners, and Takayoshi KIDO himself used the words &apos;old customs&apos;, &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; and &apos;conventions&apos; widely as meaning of &apos;feudalism to be conquered&apos; or &apos;closed nature to be conquered&apos;, and even Toshimichi OKUBO severely criticized the same thing as &apos;evil customs of the past&apos; mentioned by Kido for &apos;corrupt smell of old customes&apos;, in other word, though both Satsuma and Choshu provided overseas education secretly and were liberal domains led the movement of overthrowing the Shogunate, Okubo from Satsuma recognized more about dangerous feudalism as well as closed nature than Kido from Choshu, Okubo had to criticize more extreme because of internal affair regarding father and son of the lords of his domain and internal circumstances of his domain (The Teradaya Incident - Seinan War), moreover Tomomi IWAKURA also used just the same words &apos;the laws of Nature&apos; as &apos;reason of nature&apos; in other document, which meant totally different from international public law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>総じて、「天地の公道」（木戸当初案では「宇内の通義」）とは、普遍的な宇宙の摂理に基づく人の道を指しているものと解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general &apos;the just laws of Nature&apos; (Udai no Tsugi in the first draft of Kido) is interpreted as a way of human based on the workings of the universe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general &apos;天地の公道 (the just laws of Nature) &apos; (宇内の通義 (Udai no Tsugi) &apos; in the first draft of Kido is interpreted as a way of human based on the workings of the universe.</e>
<cmt>前例と同じく、適宜漢字表記を追加して、比較対象を整理しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general &apos;天地の公道 (the just laws of Nature) &apos; (宇内の通義 (Udai no Tsugi) &apos; in the first draft of Kido is interpreted as a way of human based on the workings of the universe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>一 智識ヲ世界ニ求メ大ニ皇基ヲ振起スヘシ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">一 智識ヲ世界ニ求メ大ニ皇基ヲ振起スヘシ(5. Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5. 智識ヲ世界ニ求メ大ニ皇基ヲ振起スヘシ(Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>数字表記は既出の五箇条の御誓文部分に準拠しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5. 智識ヲ世界ニ求メ大ニ皇基ヲ振起スヘシ(Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>（現代表記）智識を世界に求め、大いに皇基を振起すべし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 智識を世界に求め、大いに皇基を振起すべし。(Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 智識を世界に求め、大いに皇基を振起すべし。(Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 智識を世界に求め、大いに皇基を振起すべし。(Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>（由利案第三条）智識を世界に求め広く皇基を振起すへし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The 3rd article of Yuri draft) 智識を世界に求め広く皇基を振起すへし (Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The 3rd article of Yuri draft) 智識を世界に求め広く皇基を振起すへし (Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>3rdの表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The 3rd article of Yuri draft) 智識を世界に求め広く皇基を振起すへし (Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>（福岡案第四条）智識を世界に求め大に皇基を振起すべし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The 4th article of Fukuoka draft) 智識を世界に求め大に皇基を振起すべし (Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The 4th article of Fukuoka draft) 智識を世界に求め大に皇基を振起すべし (Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>4thの表記を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The 4th article of Fukuoka draft) 智識を世界に求め大に皇基を振起すべし (Knowledge shall be sought throughout the world so as to strengthen the foundation of imperial rule.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="100">
<j>前段の「智識を世界に求め」については、前述の横井小楠「国是三論」に「智識を世界万国に取て」とあり、ここから採られたものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding &apos;knowledge shall be sought throughout the world&apos; in the first part, it seemed to be adopted from &apos;knowledge shall be taken from the world&apos; above mentioned Kokuze Sanron (the Three Major Discussion of State Policy) by Shonan YOKOI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding &apos;knowledge shall be sought throughout the world&apos; in the first part, it seemed to have been adopted from &apos;knowledge shall be taken from the world&apos; from above mentioned Kokuze Sanron by Shonan YOKOI</e>
<cmt>国是三論は既出であるため、（）内の説明は省略しました。Seemed to be adopted → eemed to have been adopted に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding &apos;knowledge shall be sought throughout the world&apos; in the first part, it seemed to have been adopted from &apos;knowledge shall be taken from the world&apos; from above mentioned Kokuze Sanron by Shonan YOKOI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>後段の「皇基」とは「天皇が国を治める基礎」というような意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;The foundation of imperial rule&apos; in the latter part means &apos;the foundation for the emperor to rule the nation&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foundation of imperial rule&apos; in the latter part means &apos;the foundation for the Emperor to rule the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>the emperor→the Emperorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foundation of imperial rule&apos; in the latter part means &apos;the foundation for the Emperor to rule the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="102">
<j>福岡はこの条文を「従来の鎖国的陋習を打破して広く世界の長を採り之を集めて大成するの趣旨である」と回顧している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukuoka looked back this provision as &apos;the aim is to break down evil customs from the past like national isolation and to take and accomplish advantages from the world&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukuoka looked back this provision as &apos;the aim is to break down evil customs from the past like national isolation and to take and accomplish advantages from the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukuoka looked back this provision as &apos;the aim is to break down evil customs from the past like national isolation and to take and accomplish advantages from the world.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>勅語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordinance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>（現代表記）我が国未曾有の変革を為んとし、朕、躬を以って衆に先んじ天地神明に誓い、大にこの国是を定め、万民保全の道を立んとす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 我が国未曾有の変革を為んとし、朕、躬を以って衆に先んじ天地神明に誓い、大にこの国是を定め、万民保全の道を立んとす。</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 我が国未曾有の変革を為んとし、朕、躬を以って衆に先んじ天地神明に誓い、大にこの国是を定め、万民保全の道を立んとす。</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 我が国未曾有の変革を為んとし、朕、躬を以って衆に先んじ天地神明に誓い、大にこの国是を定め、万民保全の道を立んとす。</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>衆またこの趣旨に基き協心努力せよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 衆またこの趣旨に基き協心努力せよ。</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 衆またこの趣旨に基き協心努力せよ。</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 衆またこの趣旨に基き協心努力せよ。</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>年号月日 御諱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 年号月日 御諱</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 年号月日 御諱 (onimina ［real name］)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。「御諱」に説明を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 年号月日 御諱 (onimina ［real name］)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="106">
<j>（意味）我が国は未曾有の変革を為そうとし、わたくし天皇が自ら皆に率先して天地神明に誓い、大いにこの国是を定め、万民を保全する道を立てようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Meaning) our country is making unprecedented transformation and I the emperor take initiative to swear to God of the world, establish this national policy and preserve all the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Meaning) our country is making unprecedented transformation and I, the Emperor take initiative to swear to God, establish this national policy and preserve all the people.</e>
<cmt>the emperor→the Emperorに変更しました。Of the worldを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Meaning) our country is making unprecedented transformation and I, the Emperor take initiative to swear to God, establish this national policy and preserve all the people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>皆もまたこの趣旨に基づき心を合わせて努力せよ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Meaning) everybody, make your own effort supporting each other based of the aim.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Meaning) everybody, make your own effort supporting each other based of the aim.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Meaning) everybody, make your own effort supporting each other based of the aim.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="108">
<j>この勅語は、明治天皇が神前で五箇条を誓った後、群臣に向けて下した言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This ordinance was announced by the Emperor Meiji to a crowd of his subjects after having swore Five Articles before the altar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This ordinance was announced by the Emperor Meiji to a crowd of his subjects after having swore Five Articles before the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This ordinance was announced by the Emperor Meiji to a crowd of his subjects after having swore Five Articles before the altar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>なお、明治天皇の言葉といっても、天皇自身が声に出した言葉ではなく、実際には三条実美が読み上げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not so that the Emperor Meiji said it out loud, but Sanetomi SANJO read it out actually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Meiji didn&apos;t actually read out these sentences but Sanetomi SANJO read out in behalf of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>全体的に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji didn&apos;t actually read out these sentences but Sanetomi SANJO read out in behalf of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="110">
<j>勅語中「年号月日」とある箇所は、実際の日付が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the part of &apos;年号月日&apos; (year, month, date) in the ordinance, actual date was written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the part of &apos;年号月日&apos; (year, month, date) in the ordinance, actual date was written.</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the part of &apos;年号月日&apos; (year, month, date) in the ordinance, actual date was written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>「御諱」とは実名のことであり、ここには明治天皇の実名の睦仁が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;御諱&apos; means real name and the real name of the Emperor Meiji, Mutsuhito was written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">御諱&apos; means real name and the real name of the Emperor Meiji, Mutsuhito was written.</e>
<cmt>全角記号を半角に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">御諱&apos; means real name and the real name of the Emperor Meiji, Mutsuhito was written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>奉答書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotosho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotosho</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>（現代表記）勅意宏遠、誠に以って感銘に堪えず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 勅意宏遠、誠に以って感銘に堪えず。</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 勅意宏遠、誠に以って感銘に堪えず。</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 勅意宏遠、誠に以って感銘に堪えず。</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>今日の急務、永世の基礎、この他に出べからず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 今日の急務、永世の基礎、この他に出べからず</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 今日の急務、永世の基礎、この他に出べからず</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 今日の急務、永世の基礎、この他に出べからず</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>臣等謹んで叡旨を奉載し死を誓い、黽勉従事、冀くは以って宸襟を安じ奉らん。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 臣等謹んで叡旨を奉載し死を誓い、黽勉従事、冀くは以って宸襟を安じ奉らん。</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 臣等謹んで叡旨を奉載し死を誓い、黽勉従事、冀くは以って宸襟を安じ奉らん。</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では2件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 臣等謹んで叡旨を奉載し死を誓い、黽勉従事、冀くは以って宸襟を安じ奉らん。</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>慶応四年戊辰三月 総裁名印 公卿諸侯各名印</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(modern written system) 慶応四年戊辰三月 総裁名印 公卿諸侯各名印</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(modern written Japanese) 慶応四年戊辰三月 総裁名印 公卿諸侯各名印 (on March 1868, signatures of president, Kugyo and lords.)</e>
<cmt>Web調査を行ったところ&quot;modern written system&quot;では3件しかヒットしなかったため、&quot;modern written Japanese&quot;に変更しました。日本語による説明文がないため、（）で補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(modern written Japanese) 慶応四年戊辰三月 総裁名印 公卿諸侯各名印 (on March 1868, signatures of president, Kugyo and lords.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="116">
<j>（意味）天皇の意志は遠大であり、誠に感銘に堪えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Meaning) the wish of the emperor is lofty which make us strongly impressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Meaning) the wish of the emperor is lofty which make us strongly impressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Meaning) the wish of the emperor is lofty which make us strongly impressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>今日の急務と永世の基礎は、これに他ならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Meaning) this is exactly our urgent business of today and permanent base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Meaning) this is exactly our urgent business of today and permanent base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Meaning) this is exactly our urgent business of today and permanent base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>我ら臣下は謹んで天皇の意向を承り、死を誓い、勤勉に従事し、願わくは天皇を安心させよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">We subjects will gracefully accept the wish of the emperor, pledge our lives, engage diligently and make the emperor feel at ease, hopefully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We subjects will gracefully accept the wish of the Emperor, pledge our lives, engage diligently and make the Emperor feel at ease, hopefully.</e>
<cmt>the emperor→the Emperorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">We subjects will gracefully accept the wish of the Emperor, pledge our lives, engage diligently and make the Emperor feel at ease, hopefully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="119">
<j>奉答書は、群臣が天皇の意志に従うことを表明した文書であり、総裁以下の群臣の署名がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hotosho was a document that his subjects expressed their intention to follow the emperor, which had the signature of the president and the other subjets&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hotosho was a document that his subjects expressed their intention to follow the Emperor, which had the signature of the president and the other subjects.</e>
<cmt>the emperor→the Emperorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hotosho was a document that his subjects expressed their intention to follow the Emperor, which had the signature of the president and the other subjects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>3月14日 (旧暦)当日には411名の公卿と諸侯が署名し、残りの者は後日署名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 14, 411 Kugyo and lords signed on it and the others did it later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 14, 411 Kugyo and lords signed on it and the others did it later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 14, 411 Kugyo and lords signed on it and the others did it later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>署名者には公卿と諸侯のほか、同年5月に天皇に直属する朝臣となった旧幕府旗本のうち千石以上の領地を持つ者も加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than Kugyo (court noble) and lords, people from Edo hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) holding more than 1,000 koku teritory, who became direct Ason (second highest of the eight hereditary titles) of the emperor in May of the same year joined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Kugyo and lords, former hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) holding more than 1,000 koku territory, who became direct retainers of the Emperor in May of the same year joined.</e>
<cmt>公卿の（）説明は既出であるため省略しました。the emperor→the Emperorに変更しました。※trans1では「朝臣」が「あそん」として解釈されていますが、ここでは広く「朝臣（ちょうしん）」(朝廷の臣下・廷臣の意）、つまり天皇率いる新政府の構成員と考える方が適当かと思われます。Trans2ではこの解釈に従い、訳出しました。People from Edo hatamoto→former hatamoto</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than Kugyo and lords, former hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) holding more than 1,000 koku territory, who became direct retainers of the Emperor in May of the same year joined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>最終的には、公卿と諸侯は総計544名、その他288名が署名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, 544 Kugyo and lords as well as 288 the other people singed on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, 544 Kugyo and lords as well as 288 the other people signed on it.</e>
<cmt>the emperor→the Emperorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, 544 Kugyo and lords as well as 288 the other people signed on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>なお、木戸孝允ら藩士出身の新政府実力者たちの署名はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are no signatures of kingmakers of the new government including Takayoshi KIDO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are no signatures of kingmakers of the new government including Takayoshi KIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are no signatures of kingmakers of the new government including Takayoshi KIDO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="124">
<j>奉答書の日付が「慶応四年」となっているが、後の一世一元の詔により慶応四年は1月1日 (旧暦)に遡って明治元年に改められた（大正以降の改元とは異なるので要注意）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The date of hotosho was written the 4th year of Keio era, but by the edict of the practice of assigning one era name to the reign of eachi emperor it was changed to the first year of Meiji era, back in January 1. (different from changing the name of an era after Taisho)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The date of hotosho was written as the 4th year of Keio era, but by the edict of the practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor, it was changed to the first year of Meiji era, back in January 1 (different from changing the name of an era after Taisho).</e>
<cmt>eachi→eachに変更しました。asを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The date of hotosho was written as the 4th year of Keio era, but by the edict of the practice of assigning one era name to the reign of each emperor, it was changed to the first year of Meiji era, back in January 1 (different from changing the name of an era after Taisho).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>このため、ここの「慶応四年」は「明治元年」に読みかえるのが正式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is official that &apos;the 4th year of Keio era&apos; is to be read &apos;the first year of Meiji era&apos; here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is official that &apos;the 4th year of Keio era&apos; is to be read as &apos;the first year of Meiji era&apos; here.</e>
<cmt>asを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is official that &apos;the 4th year of Keio era&apos; is to be read as &apos;the first year of Meiji era&apos; here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="126">
<j>天神地祇御誓祭で三条実美が御誓文を読み上げる光景を日本画家の乾南陽が描き、昭和3年に旧土佐藩主の山内家が明治神宮に奉納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style painter Nanyo INUI painted the picture that Sanetomi SANJO was reading out Charter Oath in the festival of the gods of heaven and earth and the lord of Tosa domain, the Yamauchi family devoted it to the Meiji-jingu Shrine in 1828.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style painter Nanyo INUI painted a picture that Sanetomi SANJO was reading out Charter Oath at the festival of the gods of heaven and earth and the lord of Tosa domain, the Yamauchi family devoted it to the Meiji-jingu Shrine in 1928.</e>
<cmt>the picture→a pictureに変更しました。In the festival → at the festivalに変更しました。昭和3年→正しくは1928年です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style painter Nanyo INUI painted a picture that Sanetomi SANJO was reading out Charter Oath at the festival of the gods of heaven and earth and the lord of Tosa domain, the Yamauchi family devoted it to the Meiji-jingu Shrine in 1928.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>『五箇條御誓文』と題して明治神宮外苑聖徳記念絵画館で展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is on display as the title &quot;Charter Oath of Five Articles&quot; in Seitoku Kinen Kaigakan in the outer garden of the Meiji-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is on display as the title &quot;Charter Oath of Five Articles&quot; in Seitoku Kinen Kaigakan (Meiji Memorial Picture Gallery) in the outer garden of the Meiji-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>()内で聖徳記念絵画館の説明を追加しました。（用語集を参照）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is on display as the title &quot;Charter Oath of Five Articles&quot; in Seitoku Kinen Kaigakan (Meiji Memorial Picture Gallery) in the outer garden of the Meiji-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>教科書や歴史書にもよく載っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also often appears in school text books and history books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also often appears in school text books and history books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also often appears in school text books and history books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="129">
<j>小泉純一郎は首相在任当時、御誓文を元にした決まり文句「万機公論に決すべし」をよく使っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Junichiro KOIZUMI was the Prime Minister, he often used the phrase &apos; all matters decided by open discussion&apos; from Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Junichiro KOIZUMI was the Prime Minister, he often used the phrase &apos;all matters decided by open discussion&apos; from Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>allの前の半角スペースを詰めました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Junichiro KOIZUMI was the Prime Minister, he often used the phrase &apos;all matters decided by open discussion&apos; from Charter Oath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>2001年に小泉首相の所信表明演説が書籍として出版された際のタイトルは「万機公論に決すべし」であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2001 the policy speech of Prime Minister Koizumi was published having the title &apos;all matters decided by open discussion&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2001 the policy speech of Prime Minister Koizumi was published as a book with the title &apos;万機公論に決すべし (all matters decided by open discussion).&apos;</e>
<cmt>as a book withを追加しました。Havingを削除しました。万機公論に決すべし（タイトル）を追加しました。句読点の位置を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2001 the policy speech of Prime Minister Koizumi was published as a book with the title &apos;万機公論に決すべし (all matters decided by open discussion).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="131">
<j>2005年7月7日、由利公正が作成し福岡孝弟の加筆訂正のある草稿が競売にかけられる旨の報道があり、5日後に福井県が2388万8000円で落札したと発表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 7, 2005, there was news report that the draft made by Kosei YURI and improved by Takachika FUKUOKA was auctioned and 5 days later Fukui Prefecture announced successful bid for 23,888,000 yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 7, 2005, there was news report that the draft made by Kosei YURI and improved by Takachika FUKUOKA was auctioned and 5 days later Fukui Prefecture announced successful bid for 23,888,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 7, 2005, there was news report that the draft made by Kosei YURI and improved by Takachika FUKUOKA was auctioned and 5 days later Fukui Prefecture announced successful bid for 23,888,000 yen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>福井県立図書館（福井市）・福井県立若狭図書学習センター（小浜市）で公開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was shown in Fukui library in Fukui City and Fukui Prefectural Wakasa Library &amp; Life-Long Learning Center in Obama City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was shown in Fukui library in Fukui City and Fukui Prefectural Wakasa Library &amp; Life-Long Learning Center in Obama City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was shown in Fukui library in Fukui City and Fukui Prefectural Wakasa Library &amp; Life-Long Learning Center in Obama City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="133">
<j>国税庁と在日朝鮮人商工連合会の間で取り交わされたとされる以下の五項目の合意も五箇条の御誓文と呼ばれることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The agreement including 5 items made between the National Tax Administration Agency and Federation of Chamber of Commerce and Industry of Korean resident in Japan is also called Charter Oath of Five Articles sometimes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The agreement including 5 items made between the National Tax Administration Agency and Federation of Chamber of Commerce and Industry of Korean resident in Japan is also called Charter Oath of Five Articles sometimes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The agreement including 5 items made between the National Tax Administration Agency and Federation of Chamber of Commerce and Industry of Korean resident in Japan is also called Charter Oath of Five Articles sometimes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>国税庁は合意の存在を認めていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The National Tax Administration Agency do not admit the existence of the agreement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The National Tax Administration Agency do not admit the existence of the agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The National Tax Administration Agency do not admit the existence of the agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Πrate(id:11329), Aotake(id:34929), FREEZA(id:68069), TuvicBot(id:64131), Reggaeman(id:6214), ダブルで(id:158102), にごう(id:23317), 無言雀師(id:13124), Kurz(id:1601), 竜馬(id:14477), Michey.M(id:906), A6M4(id:14155), Boa(id:20845), Shin-改(id:9914), Dokutou(id:14850), IwaimBot(id:190695), Loveless(id:129239), Point136(id:211299), あやみ(id:165659), Tinecici(id:192914), Volfgang(id:98768), Poe(id:16973), DCyokohama(id:26779), Izayohi(id:13095), Carbuncle(id:346), Cozy(id:132), 水野白楓(id:22811), Race(id:131322), かげろん(id:202674), 俊平太郎(id:34056), Memosa(id:131221), YukkeBot(id:251107), Sgrwar(id:56407), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), WingsRadar(id:213443), Kafuka1964(id:105407), SeraphGood(id:144616), シャさん(id:43303), ひろくん(id:79638), 岡部碩道(id:182846), Super Hatsukari(id:46966), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>