<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>椀飯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oban</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>椀飯（おうばん・埦飯・垸飯）とは、他人を饗応する際の献立の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oban was a type of menu for entertaining guests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oban was a type of menu for entertaining guests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oban was a type of menu for entertaining guests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後には饗応を趣旨とする儀式・行事自体をも指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also later used to indicate the ceremony and event of entertaining guests with food itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it later indicated the ceremony and event of entertaining guests with food.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it later indicated the ceremony and event of entertaining guests with food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代においては、節会や節供などの恒例・臨時の宮中行事の際に、椀（埦）に高く盛った姫飯を中心に酒肴や菓子などの副食物を添えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Heian period, scheduled and temporary court events such as Sechie and Sechiku (seasonal festivals) had Himeii (cooked rice) piled high in a bowl as the centerpiece with side dishes such as dishes for drinking and snacks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Heian period, scheduled and temporary court events such as Sechie and Sechiku (seasonal festivals) had Himeii (cooked rice) piled high in a bowl as the centerpiece with side dishes such as dishes for drinking and snacks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period, scheduled and temporary court events such as Sechie and Sechiku (seasonal festivals) had Himeii (cooked rice) piled high in a bowl as the centerpiece with side dishes such as dishes for drinking and snacks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>椀飯には「殿上の椀飯」と「所々の椀飯」があり、必要な場合にその都度所管の殿上人数名に分担して調達させていたが、あくまでも公式な行事部分とは一線を画した弁当・軽食の類であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oban was classified into &quot;Tenjo no oban&quot; and &quot;Shosho no oba&quot; and this was gathered by the several designated tenjobito (high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) when necessary, but these were bento (packed meals)/light snacks that were considered separate from the official ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oban was classified into &quot;Tenjo no oban&quot; and &quot;Shosho no oba&quot; and this was gathered by the several designated tenjobito (high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) when necessary, but these were bento (packed meals)/light snacks that were considered separate from the official ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oban was classified into &apos;Tenjo no oban&apos; and &apos;Shosho no oba&apos; and this was gathered by the several designated tenjobito (high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) when necessary, but these were bento (packed meals)/light snacks that were considered separate from the official ceremony.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>殿上人が食する「殿上の椀飯」は折敷に据えた飯器・汁器・盤(佐良)・窪器・箸を載せ、折櫃の中に笥に盛った菜、外居（行器）に入れた菓子、小折敷の上に載せた瓶子と杯を配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tenjo no oban&quot; eaten by the tenjobito had a rice bowl, soup bowl, plate, small dish and chopsticks on a Oshiki (tray with folded edges) with Sai (side dishes) in Ke(dishes) inside a Oribitsu, Kashi(sweets) in a Hokai (wooden lidded container) and Heishi (sake serving cup) and hai (drinking cup) were placed on a small Oshiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tenjo no oban&quot; eaten by the tenjobito had a rice bowl, soup bowl, plate, small dish and chopsticks on a Oshiki (tray with folded edges) with Sai (side dishes) in Ke(dishes) inside a Oribitsu, Kashi (sweets) in a Hokai (wooden lidded container) and Heishi (sake serving cup) and hai (drinking cup) were placed on a small Oshiki.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenjo no oban&apos; eaten by the tenjobito had a rice bowl, soup bowl, plate, small dish and chopsticks on a Oshiki (tray with folded edges) with Sai (side dishes) in Ke(dishes) inside a Oribitsu, Kashi (sweets) in a Hokai (wooden lidded container) and Heishi (sake serving cup) and hai (drinking cup) were placed on a small Oshiki.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>台盤所・滝口・武者所などの官人に対して振舞われる「所々の椀飯」はこれより簡略であり、台盤に飯器と箸を載せ、折櫃の中に笥に盛った菜、外居（行器）に入れた菓子は「殿上の椀飯」と同様とするが、その他の内容についてはその時々に応じた差異があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shosho no oban&quot; were served to officials at the Daibadokoro, Takiguchi, Mushasdokoro and was simpler than the above, with a rice bowl and chopsticks on a tray, Sai in Ke inside a Oribitsu bamboo and Kashi in a Hokai were the same as &quot;Tenjo no oban&quot;, but other contents differed according to the situation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shosho no oban&quot; were served to officials at the Daibadokoro, Takiguchi, Mushasdokoro and was simpler than the above, with a rice bowl and chopsticks on a tray, Sai in Ke inside a Oribitsu bamboo and Kashi in a Hokai were the same as &quot;Tenjo no oban,&quot; but other contents differed according to the situation</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosho no oban&apos; were served to officials at the Daibandokoro, Takiguchi, Mushadokoro and was simpler than the above, with a rice bowl and chopsticks on a tray, Sai in Ke inside a Oribitsu bamboo and Kashi in a Hokai were the same as &apos;Tenjo no oban,&apos; but other contents differed according to the situation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。DaibadokoroをDaibandokoroに変更しました(用語統一）。MushasdokoroをMushadokoroに変更しました。文末にピリオドを打ちました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>院政期以後、鎌倉時代にかけて次第に儀式的な要素を帯びるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the cloistered government phase, oban started to hold a more ceremonial aspect during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the cloistered government phase, oban started to hold a more ceremonial aspect during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the cloistered government period, oban started to hold a more ceremonial aspect during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>phaseをperiodに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>例えば、国司の赴任の際に在庁官人らが椀飯を奉って歓迎の饗宴を行う慣例が行われるようになり、在庁官人から武士に椀飯の慣習が広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, local officials served oban as a welcome banquet for the newly appointed Kokushi and this custom of oban spread from local officials to the bushi (samurai) class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, local officials served oban as a welcome banquet for the newly appointed Kokushi and this custom of oban spread from local officials to the bushi (samurai) class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, local officials served oban as a welcome banquet for the newly appointed Kokushi and this custom of oban spread from local officials to the bushi (samurai) class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>源頼朝による鎌倉幕府の成立以後、元服や移徙などの重要な儀礼の際には椀飯が行われ、とりわけ年始に行われる「歳首の椀飯」は武家政権の最も重要な儀式の1つとして行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Kamakura bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, oban was served at important ceremonies such as Genpuku (coming of age) and Ito(moving), and the &quot;Saishu no oban&quot; that was served in the beginning of the year became one of the most important ceremonies of the buke (military) government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Kamakura bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, oban was served at important ceremonies such as Genpuku (coming of age) and Ito (moving), and the &quot;Saishu no oban&quot; that was served in the beginning of the year became one of the most important ceremonies of the buke (military) government.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was established by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, oban was served at important ceremonies such as Genpuku (coming of age) and Ito (moving), and the &apos;Saishu no oban&apos; that was served in the beginning of the year became one of the most important ceremonies of the buke (military) government.</e>
<cmt>bakufu (Japanese のかっこの前にスペースを挿入しました。&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉幕府では元日より数日にわたり、北条氏をはじめとする有力な御家人が征夷大将軍に対して太刀・名馬・弓矢とともに椀飯を奉った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Kamakura bakufu, for a few days from the first day of the year, the Hokujo clan and other prominent gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) presented the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) with oban together with swords, good horses and bows and arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Kamakura bakufu, for a few days from the first day of the year, the Hokujo clan and other prominent gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) presented the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) with oban together with swords, good horses, and bows and arrows.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Kamakura bakufu, for a few days from the first day of the year, the Hojo clan and other prominent gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) presented the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) with oban together with swords, good horses, and bows and arrows.</e>
<cmt>HokujoをHojoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>室町幕府においては、有力守護大名家の家督（棟梁）が将軍に椀飯を奉って会食を行う儀式となり、大名家ごとに将軍の元に出向いて椀飯を奉る日付が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Muromachi bakufu, there was a ceremony where prominent Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) family heads (toryo) served oban to the shogun and ate together, and the date to serve oban at the shogun&apos;s place was chosen for each Daimyo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Muromachi bakufu, there was a ceremony where prominent Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) family heads (toryo) served oban to the shogun and ate together, and the date to serve oban at the shogun&apos;s place was chosen for each Daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Muromachi bakufu, there was a ceremony where prominent Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) family heads (toryo) served oban to the shogun and ate together, and the date to serve oban at the shogun&apos;s place was chosen for each Daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>すなわち、元日は時の管領が、2日は土岐氏、3日は佐々木氏、7日は赤松氏、15日は山名氏が行うこととされた（なお、佐々木氏が京極氏と六角氏に分裂すると、両氏が毎年交代で椀飯を奉ることとなった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, Oban was to be served on New Year&apos;s day by the kanrei (shogunal deputy) of that time, Toki clan on the second, Sasaki clan on the third, Akamatsu clan on the seventh, and Yamanaka clan on the fifteenth (However, when the Sasaki clan split into Kyogoku clan and Rokkaku clan, the two clans took turns in serving oban).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, Oban was to be served on New Year&apos;s day by the kanrei (shogunal deputy) of that time, Toki clan on the second, Sasaki clan on the third, Akamatsu clan on the seventh, and Yamanaka clan on the fifteenth (However, when the Sasaki clan split into the Kyogoku and Rokkaku clans, the two clans took turns serving oban).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, Oban was to be served on New Year&apos;s day by the kanrei (shogunal deputy) of that time, Toki clan on the second, Sasaki clan on the third, Akamatsu clan on the seventh, and Yamanaka clan on the fifteenth (However, when the Sasaki clan split into the Kyogoku and Rokkaku clans, the two clans took turns serving oban).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>当時の献立は椀飯と打鮑・海月・梅干の3品に酢と塩を添えて折敷に載せて出すものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The menu at that time was rice in a bowl with the three dishes, abalone, jellyfish and pickled plum, with vinegar and salt on a Oshiki (tray).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The menu at that time was rice in a bowl with the three dishes, abalone, jellyfish, and pickled plum, with vinegar and salt on an Oshiki (tray).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The menu at that time was rice in a bowl with the three dishes, abalone, jellyfish, and pickled plum, with vinegar and salt on an Oshiki (tray).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、「庖丁」と称して将軍の御前で生きた魚を料理人に調理させて献じる趣向なども行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, an event called Hosho, where live fish was prepared by a chef in front of the shogun was also conducted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, an event called Hosho, where live fish was prepared by a chef in front of the shogun was also conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, an event called &apos;Hosho&apos;, where live fish was prepared by a chef in front of the shogun was also conducted.</e>
<cmt>&apos;を挿入しました。庖丁の読みが不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>応仁の乱後、幕府における椀飯は行われなくなり、その一方で一般の武家社会においては家臣が主君を接待する儀式から、年始や節供などに主君が家臣を接待する儀式へと変質を遂げていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Onin Resistance, oban at the bakufu was not conducted any more, but within the ordinary buke society, it transformed from a ceremony where vassals entertained their lord into a ceremony where the lord entertained his vassals in the beginning of the year and Sechi (seasonal) times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Onin Resistance, oban at the bakufu was not conducted any more, but within the ordinary buke society, it transformed from a ceremony where vassals entertained their lord into a ceremony where the lord entertained his vassals in the beginning of the year and Sechi (seasonal) times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Onin War, oban was not conducted at the bakufu any more, but within the ordinary buke society, it transformed from a ceremony where vassals entertained their lord into a ceremony where the lord entertained his vassals in the beginning of the year and Sechi (seasonal) times.</e>
<cmt>ResistanceをWarに変更しました。一部、翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸幕府においては、年始に江戸在府の御三家が老中以下の幕閣や有力旗本を饗応し、同じく町奉行が役宅で与力らを饗応することを椀飯と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo bakufu, the Gosanke(the three privileged branches of theTokugawa family) in Edo would entertain the roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) and other prominent council members and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), and in a similar way, the Machibugyo(town magistrate) would entertain yoriki (police sergeant) and others at the official residence and these were considered oban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo bakufu, the Gosanke (the three privileged branches of theTokugawa family) in Edo would entertain the roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) and other prominent council members and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), and in a similar way, the Machibugyo (town magistrate) would entertain yoriki (police sergeant) and others at the official residence and these were considered oban.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo bakufu, the Gosanke (the three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) in Edo would entertain the roju (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders) and other prominent council members and hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), and in a similar way, the Machibugyo (town magistrate) would entertain yoriki (police sergeant) and others at the official residence and these were considered oban.</e>
<cmt>theとTokugawaの間にスペースを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>こうした風習は民間にも広まり、年始に親類縁者や友人知人を招いて馳走することを「椀飯振舞」「節振舞」と呼び、これが転じて「大盤振舞」という言葉の語源となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such customs spread to the public and the act of inviting relatives and friends at the beginning of the year was called &quot;Oban burumai&quot;, &quot;&quot;Sechi burumai, and this is said to be the origin of &quot;Oban burumai (being generous)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such customs spread to the public and the act of inviting relatives and friends at the beginning of the year was called &quot;Oban burumai,&quot; Sechi burumai, and this is said to be the origin of &quot;Oban burumai (being generous)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such customs spread to the public and the act of inviting relatives and friends at the beginning of the year was called &apos;Oban burumai,&apos; &apos;Sechi burumai,&apos; and this is said to be the origin of &apos;Oban burumai (being generous).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>