<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>神戸事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>神戸事件（こうべじけん）とは慶応4年1月11日 (旧暦)（1868年2月4日）、神戸（現・神戸市）三宮神社前において備前藩（現・岡山県）兵が隊列を横切ったフランス人水兵らを負傷させたうえ、居留地（現・旧居留地）予定地を検分中の欧米諸国公使らに水平射撃を加えた事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Incident was an incident occurred in February 4, 1868, in front of Kobe (current Kobe City) Sannomiya-jinja Shrine, the troops of the domain of Bizen (current Okayama Prefecture) injured the French sailors who crossed the rank, and shot horizontally to the Ministers from Western countries who were inspecting the settlement site (current former settlement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Incident was an incident that occurred on February 4, 1868, in which in front of Sannomiya-jinja Shrine of Kobe (present-day Kobe City), a troop of the domain of Bizen (present-day Okayama Prefecture) injured French sailors who had crossed the array of the troop, and shot horizontally to the Minister-Counselors from Western countries who were inspecting the place which was supposed to be the settlement site (present-day Former Foreign Settlement).</e>
<cmt>occurは「起こる」の意の自動詞ですので、過去分詞として名詞を修飾するのは不自然です。日付につく前置詞はinではなくonです（以下同様）。適切な関係詞を補わなければ文が成立しません。「隊列」は「列」であることを明確にするためarrayと訳します。Ministerには他の意味もあるので「公使」はminister-counselorと訳します（以下同様）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Incident was an incident that occurred on February 4, 1868, in which in front of Sannomiya-jinja Shrine of Kobe (present-day Kobe City), a troop of the domain of Bizen (present-day Okayama Prefecture) injured French sailors who had crossed the array of the troop, and shot horizontally to the Minister-Counselors from Western countries who were inspecting the place which was supposed to be the settlement site (present-day Former Foreign Settlement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治政府初の外交問題となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That incident became the first diplomatic problem for the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That incident became the first diplomatic problem for the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That incident became the first diplomatic problem for the Meiji government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>この事件により、一時、外国軍が神戸中心部を占拠するに至るなどの動きにまで発展したが、その際に問題を起こした隊の責任者であった滝善三郎が切腹する事で一応の解決を見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident expanded to the occupation of the center of Kobe by the foreign military temporarily, but the person in charge of the rank that caused the incident Zenzaburo TAKI committed suicide by disembowelment led to the solution for the present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident expanded to the temporal occupation of the center of Kobe by the foreign military, but the person in charge of the troop that caused the incident, Zenzaburo TAKI, committed suicide by disembowelment, which led to a tentative solution.</e>
<cmt>「占領」を名詞で表しているので「一時」はそれを修飾する形容詞にするのが自然です。適切な関係詞を補わなければ文の後半が成立しません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident expanded to the temporal occupation of the center of Kobe by the foreign military, but the person in charge of the troop that caused the incident, Zenzaburo TAKI, committed suicide by disembowelment, which led to a tentative solution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>相前後して堺事件が発生し、共に外国人に切腹を深く印象付けることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai Incident occurred right after the incident, so Seppku (to commit suicide by disembowelment) gave a strong impression to the foreigners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai Incident occurred right after this incident, so through these two incidents Seppuku (to commit suicide by disembowelment) gave a strong impression to foreigners.</e>
<cmt>「共に」を訳出します。「切腹」のローマ字表記のミスを修正します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai Incident occurred right after this incident, so through these two incidents Seppuku (to commit suicide by disembowelment) gave a strong impression to foreigners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事件の発端</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outset of the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outset of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The outset of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>慶応4年1月3日 (旧暦)（1868年1月27日）、戊辰戦争が開戦、間も無く、徳川方の尼崎藩（現・兵庫県）を牽制するため、明治新政府は備前藩に摂津国西宮（現・西宮市）の警備を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 27, 1868, soon after the outbreak of Boshin War, new Meiji government ordered domain of Bizen the security of Settsu Province, Nishinomiya (current Nishinomiya City) in order to contain Tokugawa-side domain of Amagasaki (current Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after the outbreak of Boshin War on January 27, 1868, the new Meiji government ordered the domain of Bizen to guard Settsu Province, Nishinomiya (present-day Nishinomiya City) in order to contain the domain of Amagasaki (present-day Hyogo Prefecture), which was on the side of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>1868年1月27日は「警護を命じた」日ではなく戊辰戦争の開戦日ですから、そのように訳さなければなりません。名詞domainは冠詞を要します（以下同様）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after the outbreak of Boshin War on January 27, 1868, the new Meiji government ordered the domain of Bizen to guard Settsu Province, Nishinomiya (present-day Nishinomiya City) in order to contain the domain of Amagasaki (present-day Hyogo Prefecture), which was on the side of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>備前藩では1月5日 (旧暦)（1月29日）までに2,000人の兵を出立させ、このうち家老・日置帯刀（へきたてわき）率いる500人（800人説もある）は大砲を伴って陸路を進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Domain of Bizen sent 2000 of troops by January 29, 500 troops (800 troops in another theory) out of them led by Karo (chief retainer) Tatewaki HEKI advanced on the ground with a cannon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain of Bizen sent 2,000 soldiers before January 29, and of all the soldiers, 500 (some theory insists that it was 800) led by Karo (chief retainer) Tatewaki HEKI advanced on the ground with a cannon.</e>
<cmt>適切な接続詞を補わなければ文が成立しません。「…説もある」の訳が分かりにくいので言い換えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain of Bizen sent 2,000 soldiers before January 29, and of all the soldiers, 500 (some theory insists that it was 800) led by Karo (chief retainer) Tatewaki HEKI advanced on the ground with a cannon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この際、慶応3年12月7日 (旧暦)（1868年1月1日）の兵庫開港（現・神戸港）に伴い、大名行列と外国人の衝突を避けるために徳川幕府によって作られた「徳川道」を通らず、西国街道を進んだことが事件の引き金の一つとなってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the opening of Hyogo port (current Kobe port) in January 1, 1868, in order to avoid a conflict with Daimyo-gyoretsu (feudal lord&apos;s costumed procession) and foreigners they walked Nishioka Kaido Road rather than &apos;TOKUGAWA Road&apos; made by TOKUGAWA bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and this act became one of the triggers of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These soldiers chose to walk on the Saigoku-kaido Road instead of the &apos;TOKUGAWA Road,&apos; built by the bakufu in order to prevent foreigners from bumping into Daimyo-gyoretsu (feudal lord&apos;s costumed procession), due to the opening of Hyogo port (present-day Kobe port) on January 1, 1868, and this choice partly triggered the Incident.</e>
<cmt>日本語の文意が英語に適切に反映されていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These soldiers chose to walk on the Saigoku-kaido Road instead of the &apos;TOKUGAWA Road,&apos; built by the bakufu in order to prevent foreigners from bumping into Daimyo-gyoretsu (feudal lord&apos;s costumed procession), due to the opening of Hyogo port (present-day Kobe port) on January 1, 1868, and this choice partly triggered the Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>1月11日（2月4日）13時過ぎ、備前藩兵の隊列が神戸三宮神社近くに差しかかった時、付近の建物から出てきたフランス人水兵2人が列を横切ろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 4, at 1 pm or later, when a rank of the troops of domain of Bizen came by Kobe Sannomiya-jinja Shrine, two French sailors came out from a building nearby were going to cross the rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A little past 13:00 on February 4, when the troops of the domain of Bizen approached Kobe Sannomiya-jinja Shrine, two French sailors came out of a nearby building and tried to cross the array.</e>
<cmt>「…過ぎ」はa little past…です。「差しかかる」come byは自動詞句ですから目的語をとりません。「…から出てくる」はcome out ofの方が一般的です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A little past 13:00 on February 4, when the troops of the domain of Bizen approached Kobe Sannomiya-jinja Shrine, two French sailors came out of a nearby building and tried to cross the array.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これは日本側から見ると武家諸法度に定められた「供割」（ともわり）と呼ばれる非常に無礼な行為で、これを見た第3砲兵隊長・滝善三郎正信が槍を持って制止に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the point of Japan, this was a very rude act called &apos;Tomowari&apos; provided in Bukeshohatto (Acts for the Military Houses), so that a chief of the third battery Zenzaburo Masanobu TAKI stopped them holding a spear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the viewpoint of Japan, this was a very rude act called &apos;Tomowari,&apos; which was provided in Bukeshohatto (Acts for the Military Houses), so that a chief of the third battery Zenzaburo Masanobu TAKI stopped them, holding a spear.</e>
<cmt>「日本側の観点から」ですから「観点」viewpointを用います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the viewpoint of Japan, this was a very rude act called &apos;Tomowari,&apos; which was provided in Bukeshohatto (Acts for the Military Houses), so that a chief of the third battery Zenzaburo Masanobu TAKI stopped them, holding a spear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、言葉が通じず、強引に隊列を横切ろうとする水兵に対し、滝が槍で突きかかり軽傷を負わせてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the sailors could not understand his words and muscled to cross the troop, TAKI slightly injured them by riding atilt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the sailors could not understand his words and muscled to cross the array, TAKI slightly injured them by tilting with the spear.</e>
<cmt>「槍で突きかかり」は動詞tilt「突く」を用いて表します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the sailors could not understand his words and muscled to cross the array, TAKI slightly injured them by tilting with the spear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>これに対していったん民家に退いた水兵数人が拳銃を取り出し、それを見た滝が「鉄砲、鉄砲」と叫んだのを発砲命令と受け取った藩兵が発砲、銃撃戦に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The several sailors who once left to the private house came back holding the pistols, TAKI looked at it and shouted &apos;Pistols, pistols&apos;, so that the troops misunderstood that was the order to fire, it developed to the gunfight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, several sailors once retreated into a private house and took out their pistols, and TAKI, seeing their pistols, shouted&apos;Pistols, pistols,&apos;so that his men mistakenly took his shout for an order to fire and a gunfight was started.</e>
<cmt>「拳銃を取り出し」の部分が「拳銃を持って戻って来た」という訳になっています。Misunderstandはthat節を目的語にとりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, several sailors once retreated into a private house and took out their pistols, and TAKI, seeing their pistols, shouted&apos;Pistols, pistols,&apos;so that his men mistakenly took his shout for an order to fire and a gunfight was started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この西国街道沿いにおける小競り合いが、隣接する居留地予定地を実況検分していた欧米諸国公使たちに銃口を向け、数度一斉射撃を加えることに発展する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was a skirmish on the Saigoku kaido Road, some pistols were pointed to the ministers from western countries who were inspecting the site of the settlement and fusilladed them several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was started as a skirmish on the Saigoku kaido Road, some pistols were pointed to the minister-counselors from western countries who were inspecting the settlement site nearby and fusilladed them several times.</e>
<cmt>自然な英文にするため「（小競り合い）として始まった」という語句を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was started as a skirmish on the Saigoku kaido Road, some pistols were pointed to the minister-counselors from western countries who were inspecting the settlement site nearby and fusilladed them several times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>弾はほとんどあたらず頭上を飛び越して、居留地の反対側にある旧幕府の兵庫運上所（神戸税関）の屋上に翻る列国の国旗を穴だらけにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the bullets passed over their heads and shot and made holes the international flags on the rooftop of Hyogo Unjo- sho (Kobe custom office) of the former bakufu standing on the other side of the settlement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the bullets passed over their heads instead of hitting them and made holes in foreign flags flying on the rooftop of Hyogo Unjo- sho (Kobe custom office) of the former bakufu located on the other side of the settlement.</e>
<cmt>「当たらず」を訳出します。「…に穴をあける」はmake a hole in…です。「列国の国旗」は「外国の国旗」と言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the bullets passed over their heads instead of hitting them and made holes in foreign flags flying on the rooftop of Hyogo Unjo- sho (Kobe custom office) of the former bakufu located on the other side of the settlement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>威嚇射撃であったのか、殺意はあったが訓練不足により命中しなかったのかに関して欧米人の証言も一致していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether that was menace shooting or missing of the target due to a lack of practice, the testimonies of the Westerners differ.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Westerners&apos; testimonies differed as to whether this was intended as warning shots or the soldiers intended to kill but failed due to a lack of practice.</e>
<cmt>文が成立していません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Westerners&apos; testimonies differed as to whether this was intended as warning shots or the soldiers intended to kill but failed due to a lack of practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>事件の推移</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition of the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transition of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transition of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>自らも現場に居合わせたイギリス公使ハリー・パークスは激怒し、折しも兵庫開港を祝って集結していた各国艦船に緊急事態を通達、アメリカ海兵隊、イギリスの警備隊、フランスの水兵が備前藩兵を居留地外に追撃し、生田川の河原で撃ち合いとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">English minister Harry Parks who was at the site got furious, announced the emergency to the warships of each country that were gathered to celebrate the opening of Hyogo port, then Marine forces of the United States, the British guards, and French sailors chased the troops of domain of Bizen out of the settlement and exchanged gunfire at the side of Ikutagawa-River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">English minister-counselor Harry PARKS, who happened to be at the site himself, got furious, announced the emergency to the foreign warships that were gathered to celebrate the opening of Hyogo port, then the U.S. Marine force, British guards, and French sailors chased the troops of the domain of Bizen out of the settlement and exchanged gunfire at the side of Ikutagawa-River.</e>
<cmt>人名の姓は大文字で表記します（以下同様）。「現場に居合わせなかった」ハリー・パークスが存在するわけではありませんのでここは非制限用法の関係詞にしなければなりません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">English minister-counselor Harry PARKS, who happened to be at the site himself, got furious, announced the emergency to the foreign warships that were gathered to celebrate the opening of Hyogo port, then the U.S. Marine force, British guards, and French sailors chased the troops of the domain of Bizen out of the settlement and exchanged gunfire at the side of Ikutagawa-River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>備前側では、家老日置が藩兵隊に射撃中止・撤退を命令、お互いに死者も無く負傷者もほとんど無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo (Chief retainer) HEKI of Bizen side ordered to stop firing and withdraw, so that no one died and very few people injured in both sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HEKI, Karo of Bizen, ordered the troops to stop firing and withdraw, so that no one died and very few people were injured in both sides.</e>
<cmt>「藩兵隊に」を訳出します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HEKI, Karo of Bizen, ordered the troops to stop firing and withdraw, so that no one died and very few people were injured in both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>神戸に領事館を持つ列強諸国は、同日中に、居留地（外国人居留地）防衛の名目をもって神戸中心部を軍事占拠し、兵庫港に停泊する日本船舶を拿捕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The powerful countries which had consulates in Kobe executed military occupation at the center of Kobe on that day in the name of the guard of the settlement (foreign settlement), and seized the Japanese ships anchoring at Hyogo port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The powerful countries which had consulates in Kobe executed military occupation at the center of Kobe on that day in the name of the guard of the settlement (foreign settlement), and seized the Japanese ships anchoring at Hyogo port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The powerful countries which had consulates in Kobe executed military occupation at the center of Kobe on that day in the name of the guard of the settlement (foreign settlement), and seized the Japanese ships anchoring at Hyogo port.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この時点では、朝廷は諸外国に対して徳川幕府から明治政府への政権移譲を宣言しておらず、伊藤俊輔（後の伊藤博文）が折衝に当たるも決裂するに至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time the Imperial Court had not declared to the foreign countries about the handover of political power from TOKUGAWA bakufu to the Meiji Government, Shunsuke ITO (later Hirobumi ITO) held talks with them, but it broke down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time the Imperial Court had not declared to the foreign countries the handover of political power from the TOKUGAWA bakufu to the Meiji Government, and Shunsuke ITO (later Hirobumi ITO) held talks with them but the negotiation broke down.</e>
<cmt>「政権移譲」はdeclaredの目的語として訳出します。It broke downのitが何を受けるのか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time the Imperial Court had not declared to the foreign countries the handover of political power from the TOKUGAWA bakufu to the Meiji Government, and Shunsuke ITO (later Hirobumi ITO) held talks with them but the negotiation broke down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>1月15日 (旧暦)（2月8日）、急遽、開国和親を朝廷より宣言した上で明治新政府への政権移譲を表明、東久世通禧（ひがしくぜみちとみ）を代表として交渉を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 8, Imperial Court was rushed into declaration of opening of a country to the world and amity, and announced the handover of the political power to the Meiji Government, then resumed the negotiation by Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE as a representative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 8, the Imperial Court was rushed into declaring the opening of a country to the world and amity, and announcing the handover of the political power to the Meiji Government, and then resumed the negotiation with Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE as its representative.</e>
<cmt>前出時Imperial Courtにtheがついていますので、ここでも統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 8, the Imperial Court was rushed into declaring the opening of a country to the world and amity, and announcing the handover of the political power to the Meiji Government, and then resumed the negotiation with Michitomi HIGASHIKUZE as its representative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>諸外国側の要求は日本在留外国人の身柄の安全保証と当該事件の日本側責任者の厳重処罰、すなわち滝の処刑というものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The requirements from the foreign countries were the guarantee of safety of the foreigners living in Japan and the severe punishment of the Japanese who was in charge of the incident, which meant the execution of TAKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The requirements from the foreign countries were the guarantee of safety of the foreigners living in Japan and the severe punishment of the Japanese who was in charge of the incident, which meant the execution of TAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The requirements from the foreign countries were the guarantee of safety of the foreigners living in Japan and the severe punishment of the Japanese who was in charge of the incident, which meant the execution of TAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この事件における外国人側被害に対して処罰が重すぎるのではないかとの声もあり、また、日本側としては滝の行為は、少なくとも「供割」への対処は武士として当然のものでもあったが、列強の強い要求の前に抗うことが出来ず、伊藤や五代才助（後の五代友厚）を通じた伊達宗城の期限ギリギリまでの助命嘆願もフランスのレオン・ロッシュをはじめとする公使投票の前に否決される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were some opinions that the punishment against the injury of the foreigners was too severe, or the act of TAKI was not surprising as the reaction to &apos;Tomowari&apos; as a samurai, but they could not deny the strong demand of the powerful countries, the plea for sparing a life given by Munenari DATE through ITO and Saisuke GODAI (later Tomoatsu GODAI) to the last minute of the deadline was failed by the voting of Leon Roches of France and other ministers&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some opinions that the punishment for injuring foreigners was too severe, and from the Japanese viewpoint the act of TAKI was quite natural for a samurai, at least as a reaction to &apos;Tomowari,&apos;but it was difficult to resist the strong demand of the powerful countries and the plea for saving TAKI made by Munenari DATE through ITO and Saisuke GODAI (later Tomoatsu GODAI) to the last minute of the deadline was rejected by the voting of Leon ROCHES of France and other minister-counselors&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「日本側としては」「少なくとも…への対応は」を訳出します。They could not deny…のtheyが何を指すのか不明確ですので構文を変更します。「助命」を直訳しても説明不足ですので表現を補います。Make a plea forという組み合わせですのでgivenではなくmadeにします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some opinions that the punishment for injuring foreigners was too severe, and from the Japanese viewpoint the act of TAKI was quite natural for a samurai, at least as a reaction to &apos;Tomowari,&apos;but it was difficult to resist the strong demand of the powerful countries and the plea for saving TAKI made by Munenari DATE through ITO and Saisuke GODAI (later Tomoatsu GODAI) to the last minute of the deadline was rejected by the voting of Leon ROCHES of France and other minister-counselors&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>結局、2月2日 (旧暦)（2月24日）、備前藩は諸外国側の要求を受け入れ、2月9日 (旧暦)（3月2日）、永福寺において列強外交官列席のもとで滝を切腹させるのと同時に備前藩部隊を率いた日置について謹慎を課すということで、一応の決着を見たのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At last on February 24, domain of Bizen accepted the requirement of the foreign countries, on March 2, TAKI committed suicide by disembowelment in the presence of the diplomats of powerful countries at Eifukuji Temple, and at the same time, HEKI, who was a chief of domain of Bizen troops, was ordered the house arrest, then the incident was settled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At last on February 24, the domain of Bizen accepted the demand of the foreign countries, and on March 2 it made TAKI commit suicide by disembowelment in the presence of the diplomats of the powerful countries at Eifukuji Temple and at the same tiime put HEKI, who was a chief of the troops of the domain of Bizen, under house arrest, which tentatively settled the Incident.</e>
<cmt>「切腹させる」「謹慎を課す」という日本文に合わせて「備前藩」を主語にした文に統一します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At last on February 24, the domain of Bizen accepted the demand of the foreign countries, and on March 2 it made TAKI commit suicide by disembowelment in the presence of the diplomats of the powerful countries at Eifukuji Temple and at the same tiime put HEKI, who was a chief of the troops of the domain of Bizen, under house arrest, which tentatively settled the Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>事件の意味</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meaning of the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>神戸事件は大政奉還を経て明治新政府政権となって初めての外交事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobe Incident was the first diplomat incident since the Meiji government was established through Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobe Incident was the first diplomat incident since the Meiji government was established through Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobe Incident was the first diplomat incident since the Meiji government was established through Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>結果として諸国列強に押し切られる形で滝善三郎という1人の命を代償として問題を解決する形にはなったが、これ以降、明治政府が対外政策に当たる正当な政府であるということを諸外国に示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently the matter was solved with a compensation of one man&apos;s life, Zenzaburo TAKI, under the pressure by the powerful countries, but afterwards, the Meiji government appealed them that it was the legitimate government that practiced the diplomatic policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently the matter was solved by sacrificing the life of a man, Zenzaburo TAKI, under the pressure by the powerful countries, but the Meiji government appealed to them its legitimacy as a government in charge of the diplomatic policy after that.</e>
<cmt>「代価、報酬」compensationではやや不自然ですので「犠牲」に言い換えます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently the matter was solved by sacrificing the life of a man, Zenzaburo TAKI, under the pressure by the powerful countries, but the Meiji government appealed to them its legitimacy as a government in charge of the diplomatic policy after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、朝廷がこのときまで唱えていた「攘夷」（外国を討ち払う）政策を「開国和親」へと一気に方針転換させた事件でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it was the incident that the Imperial Court was forced to change its policy drastically from &apos;Joi&apos; (expulsion of foreigners) to &apos;Opening of a country to the world and amity&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also it was the incident that forced the Imperial Court to change its policy drastically from &apos;Joi&apos; (expulsion of foreigners) to &apos;Opening of a country to the world and amity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>it wasとthatを取り除いても文として成立しないので、強調構文が成立していません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also it was the incident that forced the Imperial Court to change its policy drastically from &apos;Joi&apos; (expulsion of foreigners) to &apos;Opening of a country to the world and amity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただし、この「開国和親」表明は外交団に対するものであり、新政府内にも未だ攘夷を支持する者もいることから、国内に対してはその事実を明確にはしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the expression of &apos;opening of a country to the world and amity&apos; was for the foreign diplomats, and still there were some supporters of Joi in the new government, so that the fact was not cleared domestically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the announcement of &apos;opening of a country to the world and amity&apos; was made only to the foreign diplomats, and still there were some supporters of Joi within the new government, so that the fact was not disclosed domestically.</e>
<cmt>この「表明」は「発表」と訳すのが自然です。「明確にする」は「開示する」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the announcement of &apos;opening of a country to the world and amity&apos; was made only to the foreign diplomats, and still there were some supporters of Joi within the new government, so that the fact was not disclosed domestically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>国内に対する正式な表明は翌年5月28日 (旧暦)（1869年7月7日）に行われた新政府の上局会議における決定によるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formal expression in Japan was a decision bade at the conference of a law-making body in the new government taken place in July 7, 1869.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formal domestic announcement was a decision made at the conference of a law-making body in the new government on July 7, 1869.</e>
<cmt>bid a decisionという言い方はしませんので、このbadeはmadeのミススペリングと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formal domestic announcement was a decision made at the conference of a law-making body in the new government on July 7, 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>この問題の行方によっては薩英戦争同様の事態に進展する可能性もあり、さらに神戸が香港や上海市の様に理不尽な占領下に置かれる事態も起こり得たことから、滝善三郎の犠牲によって危機回避がなされたことは日本史の流れにおいても重大な出来事であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a possibility that this incident would have developed to the same level of Anglo-Satsuma War depending on the conclusion, and Kobe might have been under the unreasonable occupation like Hong Kong or Shanghai City, they could avoid the risk at the sacrifice of Zenzaburo TAKI, and that was the important incident in the stream of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Depending on the conclusion, this incident would possibly have developed into as serious a situation as Anglo-Satsuma War, and Kobe might have been put under the unreasonable occupation like Hong Kong or Shanghai City, so it is also important in the context of the Japanese history that the national crisis could be avoided at the sacrifice of Zenzaburo TAKI.</e>
<cmt>日本語の文意が英語に適切に反映されていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Depending on the conclusion, this incident would possibly have developed into as serious a situation as Anglo-Satsuma War, and Kobe might have been put under the unreasonable occupation like Hong Kong or Shanghai City, so it is also important in the context of the Japanese history that the national crisis could be avoided at the sacrifice of Zenzaburo TAKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>エピソード</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Episode</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>シーパワー論の提唱者として後年名を知られることになるアルフレッド・セイヤー・マハン少佐は、神戸事件の最中、兵庫港に停泊する米国艦イロコイ号の副長を務めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major Alfred Thayer Mahan, who would become a famous person as an advocator of the theory of sea power, was the vice chief of the US warship Ikoroi which was anchoring at Hyogo port during the Kobe Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Alfred Thayer MAHAN, who later became famous as an advocator of the theory of sea power, was the vice chief of the U.S. warship Ikoroi, which was anchoring at Hyogo port during the Kobe Incident.</e>
<cmt>become a famous personは冗漫な表現ですのでbecome famousとします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Alfred Thayer MAHAN, who later became famous as an advocator of the theory of sea power, was the vice chief of the U.S. warship Ikoroi, which was anchoring at Hyogo port during the Kobe Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), 水野白楓(id:22811), Public(id:100693), Nonomura(id:72557), Udon-ya(id:48431), たとゥ(id:25557), TAMA(id:25299), BAKU(id:55205), 7O(id:276328), 柴崎力栄(id:306719), サニードレッシング(id:15736), Nnn(id:26535), 下総大納言(id:43461), IwaimBot(id:190695), おきた(id:18906), Ete(id:28565), Eine Herbstschlange Expeditions Partei(id:143885), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>