<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>任官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointment (Ninkan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointment (Ninkan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointment (Ninkan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>任官（にんかん）とは、官職に任用されることをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninkan means being appointed to a government post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninkan means being appointed to a government post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninkan means being appointed to a government post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>古くは奈良時代の律令制導入の際より日本の官制において用いられた用語であり、今日の政府や国家機関等においても使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninkan is a term which was formerly used in the Japanese government-regulated organisations since the implementation of the Ritsuryo system in the Nara era and is still used today in the government and state institutions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninkan is a term which was formerly used in the Japanese government-regulated organisations since the implementation of the Ritsuryo system in the Nara era and is still used today in the government and state institutions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninkan is a term which was formerly used in the Japanese government-regulated organisations since the implementation of the Ritsuryo system in the Nara era and is still used today in the government and state institutions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>今日では国家公務員の職、特に裁判官、検察官、自衛官（即応予備自衛官、予備自衛官を含む）、警察官、海上保安官などに任ぜられる場合に用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays ninkan is used when appointing government officials, especially judges, Self-Defense force officials (including rapid-reaction reserve officials and reserve officials),police officers and Maritime Safety officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays ninkan is used when appointing government officials, especially judges, public prosecutors, Self-Defense force officials (including rapid-reaction reserve officials and reserve officials), police officers and Maritime Safety officials.</e>
<cmt>「検察官」訳抜けに対応しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays ninkan is used when appointing government officials, especially judges, public prosecutors, Self-Defense force officials (including rapid-reaction reserve officials and reserve officials), police officers and Maritime Safety officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>対義語は免官、退官。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The antonym of ninkan is menkan (dismissal) and taikan (retirement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The antonym of ninkan is menkan (dismissal) and taikan (retirement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The antonym of ninkan is menkan (dismissal) and taikan (retirement).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、関連用語として、任官拒否という用語もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A related term is ninkankyohi, which means refusal of appointment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A related term is ninkankyohi, which means refusal of appointment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A related term is ninkankyohi, which means refusal of appointment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>用法としては、司法試験合格者のうち、裁判官等への任官を拒否するために用いられ、その他には防衛大学校卒業者が自衛官への任官を拒否する場合にも用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a rule ninkankyohi is used in the case when somebody who passed the bar examination refuses to be appointed as a judge or when somebody graduates from the National Defense Academy refuses to get appointed as a Self-Defense force official.</e>
<cmt>http://www.nda.ac.jp/index-j.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a rule, ninkankyohi is used in the case when somebody who passed the bar examination refuses to be appointed as a judge or when somebody graduates from the National Defense Academy refuses to get appointed as a Self-Defense force official.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a rule, ninkankyohi is used in the case when somebody who passed the bar examination refuses to be appointed as a judge or when somebody graduates from the National Defense Academy refuses to get appointed as a Self-Defense force official.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、国家公務員が異なる官庁・職種に転じる場合、転官ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When government officials transfer to a different government office or workplace the term tenkan is used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When government officials transfer to a different government office or workplace, the term tenkan is used.</e>
<cmt>カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When government officials transfer to a different government office or workplace, the term tenkan is used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>律令制下の任官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appointment under the Ritsuryo system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appointment under the Ritsuryo system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appointment under the Ritsuryo system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>律令制下における官職の序列は位階に基づいて定められ、ともに不可分の関係にあり官位と称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system, the rank of government posts were decided upon court ranks, which were nondivisible and called</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Ritsuryo system the rank of government posts (kanshoku) were decided upon court ranks (ikai), which were nondivisable and called kan-i (official court ranks).</e>
<cmt>後半訳抜けに対応しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Ritsuryo system the rank of government posts (kanshoku) were decided upon court ranks (ikai), which were nondivisable and called kan-i (official court ranks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>即ち、位階に相当する官職に任ずる官位相当制を基本とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based upon the kanisoto sei (the ranks of the bureaucracy system) one was appointed to a government post according to his court rank. At the appointment ceremony &quot;jimoku&quot;, held by personnel of the Imperial court, court ranks and posts were often given at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, one was appointed to a government post according to his court rank, which was called kanisoto sei (the ranks of the bureaucracy system).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処訳文が2 文になっていたので分割し、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, one was appointed to a government post according to his court rank, which was called kanisoto sei (the ranks of the bureaucracy system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>朝廷の人事である除目では叙位任官は同時になされることも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the appointment ceremony &quot;jimoku&quot;, held by personnel of the Imperial court, court ranks and posts were often given at the same time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the appointment ceremony &quot;jimoku&quot;, held by personnel of the Imperial court, court ranks and posts were often given at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>鎌倉幕府と自由任官の禁止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu and the prohibition of free appointments (Jiyuninkan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura bakufu and the prohibition of direct appointments (Jiyuninkan)</e>
<cmt>「自由任官」は「幕府を介さず朝廷から直接任官」の意なので、&quot;direct apointments&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu and the prohibition of direct appointments (Jiyuninkan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>鎌倉時代以降、鎌倉幕府の御家人たる武士の叙位任官は鎌倉殿を通じて朝廷に具申することを原則として、御家人が直接的に朝廷から叙位任官を受けることを厳禁とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Kamakura period, as a general rule, the samurai who became shogunal retainers reported via the lord of Kamakura about the conferment of a court rank and appointment to an office to the Imperial Court. For the shogunal retainers it was strictly prohibited to receive a rank and office directly from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Kamakura period, as a general rule, the conferments of a court rank and appointment to an office of samurai who were shogunal retainers were reported to the Imperial Court via the lord of Kamakura, and it was strictly prohibited for the shogunal retainers to receive a rank and office directly from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>一文にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Kamakura period, as a general rule, the conferments of a court rank and appointment to an office of samurai who were shogunal retainers were reported to the Imperial Court via the lord of Kamakura, and it was strictly prohibited for the shogunal retainers to receive a rank and office directly from the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは、御家人の主人はあくまで幕府主宰者たる鎌倉殿であり、御家人が直接的に朝廷と関わりを持つことは、御家人の離反や自立などの事態を招く危険もあり、これを予防する意味があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was intended to prevent shogunal retainers to have direct relation with the Imperial Court because the master of shogunal retainers were the lord of kamakura, who held the bakufu, and the bakufu feared that direct relation between shogunal retainers and the Imperial Court might lead to estrangement or independence of shogunal retainers.</e>
<cmt>訳抜けです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was intended to prevent shogunal retainers from having a direct relation with the Imperial Court because the master of shogunal retainers was the lord of Kamakura, who held the bakufu, and the bakufu feared that a direct relation between shogunal retainers and the Imperial Court might lead to estrangement or independence of shogunal retainers.</e>
<cmt>prevent shogunal retainers to have→prevent shogunal retainers from having a</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この禁を破り、御家人が鎌倉幕府を介せず、または許しを得ることなく、叙位任官することを自由任官という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When this prohibition was violated and a shogunal retainer received a rank or post without involving the Kamakura shogunate and without permission, that is called Jiyuninkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this prohibition was violated and a shogunal retainer received a rank or post directly (not via the Kamakura shogunate) or without permission, that was called Jiyuninkan.</e>
<cmt>時制など。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this prohibition was violated and a shogunal retainer received a rank or post directly (not via the Kamakura shogunate) or without permission, that was called Jiyuninkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>幕府では御家人の任官を将軍による統制下に置くため幕府内に官途奉行を置き、武家の任官の申請窓口とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to put appointments of posts (ninkan) under the control of the shogun a commissioner was set up in the shogunate, who acted as a contact for samurai families (buke), who applied for ninkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to put appointments of posts (ninkan) under the control of the shogun, Kanto-bugyo (a commissioner of the appointment to an office) was set up in the shogunate, who acted as a contact for samurai families (buke), who applied for ninkan.</e>
<cmt>「官途奉行」抜け。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to put appointments of posts (ninkan) under the control of the shogun, Kanto-bugyo (a commissioner of the appointment to an office) was set up in the shogunate, who acted as a contact for samurai families (buke), who applied for ninkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>実際には、頼朝の時代に源義経をはじめ、24人の東国御家人が自由任官をし、墨俣以東に入ることを禁ぜられた事例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually there were cases: starting with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune in the time of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, 24 shogunal retainers of the eastern provinces (Togoku) were appointed freely and were forbidden to go east of Sunamoto (Gifu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually there were a case in which 24 shogunal retainers of the eastern provinces (Togoku) inclulding MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune in the time of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, were appointed directly and were forbidden to go east of Sunamoto (Gifu).</e>
<cmt>「をはじめ」の訳など。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually there were a case in which 24 shogunal retainers of the eastern provinces (Togoku) inclulding MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune in the time of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, were appointed directly and were forbidden to go east of Sunamoto (Gifu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Jozai senjo(id:239008), Kumatora(id:16941), Huugo(id:61491), PrimeN(id:102297), のり230(id:125870), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>