<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>口宣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzen (transcription of emperor&apos;s verbal edict)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzen (transcription of emperor&apos;s verbal edict)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzen</e>
<cmt>説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>口宣（くぜん）とは、平安時代中期から用いられるようになった非公式な公文書書式で、天皇の勅旨を口頭で受けた蔵人所職事（職事蔵人・蔵人頭もしくは五位蔵人）がその内容を文書化して太政官上卿に伝える目的のために使われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzen was an informal form of an official document that came into use from the mid Heian period -- which was used by shikiji (administrative assistant) at kurodo dokoro (the Office of Imperial Household Logistics) (shikiji kurodo, kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) or goi no kurodo (Chamberlain of the Fifth Rank)) in transcribing the verbally received emperor&apos;s edict for conveying it to shokei (high-ranking court noble) at Daijokan (Grand Council of State.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzen was an informal form of official document that came into use from the mid Heian period -- which was used by shikiji (administrative assistant) at kurodo dokoro (the Office of Imperial Household Logistics) (shikiji kurodo, kurodo no to - Head Chamberlain) or goi no kurodo (Chamberlain of the Fifth Rank) in transcribing the verbally received emperor&apos;s edict for conveying it to shokei (high-ranking court noble) at Daijokan (Grand Council of State.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation, word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzen was an informal form of official document that came into use from the mid Heian period -- which was used by shikiji (administrative assistant) at kurodo dokoro (the Office of Imperial Household Logistics) (shikiji kurodo, kurodo no to - Head Chamberlain) or goi no kurodo (Chamberlain of the Fifth Rank) in transcribing the verbally received emperor&apos;s edict for conveying it to shokei (high-ranking court noble) at Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>宣旨と共通する部分が多いがその書式に異なる部分がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had many parts in common with senji except for its form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had many parts in common with senji except for its form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had many parts in common with senji except for its form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>弘仁元年（810年）の薬子の変をきっかけに蔵人所が設置されると、従来は後宮の内侍司を通して伝えられていた天皇の勅旨の太政官への伝達が、次第に蔵人所の職事によって行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the kurodo dokoro was founded after the Kusuko Incident in 810, the shikiji at the kurodo dokoro gradually assumed the role of conveying the imperial edict to the Daijokan -- the order had conventionally been conveyed by naishishi (also referred to as naishi no tsukasa; messengers from the palace attendants) at kokyu (the women&apos;s quarters of the Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the kurodo dokoro was founded after the Kusuko Incident in 810, the shikiji at the kurodo dokoro gradually assumed the role of conveying the imperial edict to the Daijokan -- the order had conventionally been conveyed by naishishi (also referred to as naishi no tsukasa; messengers from the palace attendants) at kokyu (the women&apos;s quarters of the Imperial Palace.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the kurodo dokoro was founded after the Kusuko Incident in 810, the shikiji at the kurodo dokoro gradually assumed the role of conveying the imperial edict to the Daijokan -- the order had conventionally been conveyed by naishishi (also referred to as naishi no tsukasa; messengers from the palace attendants) at kokyu (the women&apos;s quarters of the Imperial Palace).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>天皇の勅旨を奉じた職事蔵人は太政官の陣定に赴いて上卿に対してその内容を口頭で伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the shikiji kurodo received the imperial edict, he took it to the jin no sadame (Council of State deliberation) and verbally conveyed it to the shokei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the shikiji kurodo received the imperial edict, he took it to the jin no sadame (Council of State deliberation) and verbally conveyed it to the shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the shikiji kurodo received the imperial edict, he took it to the jin no sadame (Council of State deliberation) and verbally conveyed it to the shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これを職事の仰詞と称したが、勅旨の内容を口で伝える（宣べる）ことから、「口宣」もしくは「宣旨」とも称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was referred to as Oosekotoba (the words of His Majesty) given through the shikiji, also referred to as &apos;kuzen&apos; (literally means stated through a mouth) or &apos;senji&apos; (literally means to state to that effect) because the order was verbally conveyed (verbally stated.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was referred to as Oosekotoba (the words of His Majesty) given through the shikiji, also referred to as &apos;kuzen&apos; (literally means stated by mouth) or &apos;senji&apos; (literally means to state to that effect) because the order was verbally conveyed (verbally stated.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was referred to as Oosekotoba (the words of His Majesty) given through the shikiji, also referred to as &apos;kuzen&apos; (literally means stated by mouth) or &apos;senji&apos; (literally means to state to that effect) because the order was verbally conveyed (verbally stated).</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、上卿が常に太政官にいるとは限らず、天皇の側が臨時の勅旨を発する事もあり得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the shokei was not always present at the Daijokan, which was why the emperor&apos;s side could have issued an extraordinary edict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the shokei was not always present at the Daijokan, which was why the emperor&apos;s side could have issued an extraordinary edict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the shokei was not always present at the Daijokan, which was why the emperor&apos;s side could have issued an extraordinary edict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのため、命令を伝える間に蔵人の誤りその他により天皇の出した命令と上卿が実際に受けた命令が食い違う可能性もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was why an error made by the kurodo or something happened in the process of conveying the edict might have resulted in a discrepancy between the order issued by the emperor and the order practically received by the shokei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was why an error made by the kurodo or something happened in the process of conveying the edict might have resulted in a discrepancy between the order issued by the emperor and the order practically received by the shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was why an error made by the kurodo or something happened in the process of conveying the edict might have resulted in a discrepancy between the order issued by the emperor and the order practically received by the shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、あらかじめ天皇の勅旨を紙に書いてそれを上卿に渡すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, the custom was established to put the imperial edict on a sheet of paper in advance to be handed to the shokei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For that reason, the custom was established to prepare the imperial edict on a sheet of paper in advance to be handed to the shokei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For that reason, the custom was established to prepare the imperial edict on a sheet of paper in advance to be handed to the shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これが「口宣」もしくは「宣旨」へと発展する事になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was shaped up into &apos;kuzen&apos; or &apos;senji&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was shaped up into &apos;kuzen&apos; or &apos;senji&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was shaped up into &apos;kuzen&apos; or &apos;senji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ピリオド位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>口宣は最初の行に出された年月日を書いてからその下に一字分を開けて「宣旨」という2文字を書き入れ、次の行以後にその内容を記し、最後の行には勅旨の奉者（受けた者）の位署（蔵人所における官職・その他の兼官職・氏名）の後にその下に小さく「奉」の1文字を据える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the form of kuzen: Put the date of issue in the first line; then two Chinese characters &apos;宣旨&apos; (senji) in the second line from the date line; below the line of the two Chinese letters, the contents of the senji; and isho (the government post at kurodo dokoro, an additional post, and name) of hosha (the personnel who received) of the imperial edict, with a Chinese character &apos;奉&apos; added in a size smaller than that of the other letters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the form of kuzen: Put the date of issue in the first line; then two Chinese characters &apos;宣旨&apos; (senji) on the second line from the date line; below the line of the two Chinese letters, the contents of the senji; and isho (the government post at kurodo dokoro, an additional post, and name) of hosha (the personnel who receive it) of the imperial edict, with a Chinese character &apos;奉&apos; added in a size smaller than that of the other letters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the form of kuzen: Put the date of issue in the first line; then two Chinese characters &apos;宣旨&apos; (senji) on the second line from the date line; below the line of the two Chinese letters, the contents of the senji; and isho (the government post at kurodo dokoro, an additional post, and name) of hosha (the personnel who receive it) of the imperial edict, with a Chinese character &apos;奉&apos; added in a size smaller than that of the other letters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>この形式は11世紀に完成されたもので、口宣が行われた初期（10世紀前半）には、宣旨との書式の区別が確立しておらず、年月日が最後の行の位署の上に記載されたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form was established in the 11th century -- When the kuzen began to be practiced (the first half of 10th century), the form of kuzen had not been distinguished from the form of senji yet, such that the date was put above the isho in the last line in some cases of kuzen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The form was established in the eleventh century -- When the kuzen began to be practiced (in the first half of tenth century), the form of kuzen had not been distinguished from the form of senji yet, and the date was put above the isho in the last line in some cases for kuzen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form was established in the eleventh century -- When the kuzen began to be practiced (in the first half of tenth century), the form of kuzen had not been distinguished from the form of senji yet, and the date was put above the isho in the last line in some cases for kuzen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、用紙は職事蔵人がいつ勅旨を受けても対応できるように、またあくまでも勅旨伝達は口頭であり口宣は覚書（メモ）として作成されるという性格により、製造が簡便である中古紙を再生した宿紙を用いるのが例とされ、後に書式の一環として定着するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to make the shikiji kurodo always prepared for the imperial order and because the imperial edict was entirely conveyed verbally and the kuzen was made just as a memorandum (memo), the custom was established to use sheets of shukushi (also referred to as sukushi), which was simply made by recycling used paper -- That choice of paper formed a part of the document standards later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to make the shikiji, kurodo always prepared for the imperial order and because the imperial edict was entirely conveyed verbally and the kuzen was made just as a memorandum (memo), the custom was established using sheets of shukushi (also referred to as sukushi), which was simply made by recycling used paper -- That choice of paper formed a part of the document standards later on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to make the shikiji, kurodo always prepared for the imperial order and because the imperial edict was entirely conveyed verbally and the kuzen was made just as a memorandum (memo), the custom was established using sheets of shukushi (also referred to as sukushi), which was simply made by recycling used paper -- That choice of paper formed a part of the document standards later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、後には院政を行う太上天皇・太上法皇（いわゆる「治天の君」）が太政官に対して命令を発する時も口宣が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, a Retired Emperor or a Priestly Retired Emperor (so-called &apos;Chiten no kimi&apos;) who pulled the strings behind the scenes also used the kuzen for issuing an order to the Daijokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, a Retired Emperor or a Priestly Retired Emperor (so-called &apos;Chiten no kimi&apos;) who pulled the strings behind the scenes also used the kuzen for issuing an order to the Daijokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, a Retired Emperor or a Cloistered Retired Emperor (so-called &apos;Chiten no kimi&apos;) who pulled the strings behind the scenes also used the kuzen for issuing an order to the Daijokan.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは律令に定められた正統な統治機関は天皇及び太政官であり、法的な根拠を持たない治天の君が命令を行う場合には、こうした非公式な公文書形式を採用せざるを得なかったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the legitimate government organs established by the Ritsuryo codes were the Emperor and the Daijokan, Chiten no kimi who has no legal basis could not but use such an informal form of official document to issue an order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since legitimate government organs established by the Ritsuryo codes were the Emperor and the Daijokan, Chiten no kimi who had no legal basis had to use such an informal form of official document to issue an order.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since legitimate government organs established by the Ritsuryo codes were the Emperor and the Daijokan, Chiten no kimi who had no legal basis had to use such an informal form of official document to issue an order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>口宣案</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzen-an (draft of kuzen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzen-an (draft of kuzen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzen-an</e>
<cmt>説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>口宣案（くぜんあん）とは、元来は口宣の案文であり、覚書（メモ）の下書き程度の意味合いでしかなかったが、後には太政官を経由せずに直接実務担当者に勅旨の内容を伝えるために用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuzen-an&apos; was originally a draft proposal of kuzen, meaning no more than an incomplete version of a memorandum (memo); but later, it came into use as a means of directly conveying the imperial order to the working-level officials, bypassing the Daijokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuzen-an&apos; was originally a draft proposal of kuzen, meaning no more than an incomplete version of a memorandum (memo); but later, it came into use as a means of directly conveying the imperial order to working-level officials, bypassing the Daijokan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuzen-an&apos; was originally a draft proposal of kuzen, meaning no more than an incomplete version of a memorandum (memo); but later, it came into use as a means of directly conveying the imperial order to working-level officials, bypassing the Daijokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>鎌倉時代までに様々な正規のルートを通さない命令を発するための公文書が作成されたが、人事に関する命令は詔書・太政官符・位記などの正規の公文書の発給手続が守られてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various official documents for orders issued off the regular route were created up to the Kamakura period, but exceptionally the documents for orders regarding the personnel matters were created by sticking to the steps of issuing such regular official documents as the Imperial Rescript, the documents issued by the Daijokan, and the diploma of court rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various official documents for orders issued off the regular route were created until the Kamakura period, but exceptionally the documents for orders regarding personnel matters were created by sticking to the steps of issuing such regular official documents as an Imperial Rescript, the documents issued by the Daijokan, and the diploma of court rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various official documents for orders issued off the regular route were created until the Kamakura period, but exceptionally the documents for orders regarding personnel matters were created by sticking to the steps of issuing such regular official documents as an Imperial Rescript, the documents issued by the Daijokan, and the diploma of court rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは治天の君が人事権を行使する場合でも同じであり、天皇の命令という体裁を取り、更に太政官に伝えられてそこから実務担当者に命令が届くという複雑な手続を要した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was the same in the case where Chiten no kimi exercised his right of personnel management such that it was required to follow complicated procedures of putting on the appearance of the imperial order, conveyed to the Daijokan and further to the working-level officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was the same in the case where Chiten no kimi exercised his right of personnel management such that it was required to follow complicated procedures of putting on the appearance of an imperial order, conveyed to the Daijokan and further to the working-level officials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was the same in the case where Chiten no kimi exercised his right of personnel management such that it was required to follow complicated procedures of putting on the appearance of an imperial order, conveyed to the Daijokan and further to the working-level officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これに対して後嵯峨天皇の頃から実際の人事権者である治天の君の人事決定を迅速に人事担当者に伝える必要性から、治天の君（天皇親政の場合は天皇）の命令を受けた職事蔵人が、口宣を上卿に渡す前にあらかじめ下書きを名目としてもう1通案文を口宣と全く同じ様に作成して、この案文に口宣を出した治天の君の院宣（あるいは天皇の綸旨）を添えて実務担当者に渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But from the tenure of Emperor Gosaga, in order to meet the requirement of conveying the personnel change made by the Chiten no kimi -- who had the virtual right of personnel management -- to the official responsible for the personnel matters as soon as possible, the shikiji kurodo who received the order issued by the Chiten no kimi (or the Emperor if under the personal rule of the Emperor) drew up a copy of the draft proposal of kuzen on the pretext of making an incomplete version of the kuzen and handed the copy of the draft proposal with inzen (document transcribed a retired emperor&apos;s order) of the Chiten no kimi who issued the kuzen (or a document transcribed of the Emperor&apos;s order) to the working-level officials, before submitting the kuzen to the shokei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But from the tenure of Emperor Gosaga, in order to meet the requirement of conveying personnel change made by the Chiten no kimi -- who had the virtual right of personnel management -- to the official responsible for personnel matters as soon as possible, the shikiji kurodo who received the order issued by the Chiten no kimi (or the Emperor if under the personal rule of the Emperor) drew up a copy of the draft proposal of kuzen on the pretext of making an incomplete version of the kuzen and handed the copy of the draft proposal with inzen (document transcribed a retired emperor&apos;s order) of the Chiten no kimi who issued the kuzen (or a document transcribed of the Emperor&apos;s order) to the working-level officials, before submitting the kuzen to the shokei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But from the tenure of Emperor Gosaga, in order to meet the requirement of conveying personnel change made by the Chiten no kimi -- who had the virtual right of personnel management -- to the official responsible for personnel matters as soon as possible, the shikiji kurodo who received the order issued by the Chiten no kimi (or the Emperor if under the personal rule of the Emperor) drew up a copy of the draft proposal of kuzen on the pretext of making an incomplete version of the kuzen and handed the copy of the draft proposal with inzen (document transcribed a retired emperor&apos;s order) of the Chiten no kimi who issued the kuzen (or a document transcribed of the Emperor&apos;s order) to the working-level officials, before submitting the kuzen to the shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>これは、口宣正文と区別するために端裏に「口宣案」の3文字と最初の行の右上に「銘」と呼ばれる口宣を渡した上卿の氏名を付記した上で渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For distinguishing the copy from the script (original) of the kuzen, the three Chinese characters &apos;口宣案&apos; (kuzen-an; draft of kuzen) were put on the reverse edge and the so-called &apos;mei&apos;, the name of the shokei to whom the kuzen was submitted, was added at the upper right to the first line of the copy before being handed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For distinguishing the copy from the script (original) of the kuzen, the three Chinese characters &apos;口宣案&apos; (kuzen-an; draft of kuzen) were written on the reverse edge and the so-called &apos;mei,&apos; the name of the shokei to whom the kuzen was submitted, was added on the upper right of the first line of the copy before being handed over.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For distinguishing the copy from the script (original) of the kuzen, the three Chinese characters &apos;口宣案&apos; (kuzen-an; draft of kuzen) were written on the reverse edge and the so-called &apos;mei,&apos; the name of the shokei to whom the kuzen was submitted, was added on the upper right of the first line of the copy before being handed over.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>本来は口宣案が担当者に渡された後に、全く同じ内容の命令が太政官から担当者に宣下される手筈となっていたが、後には太政官での宣下手続が省略されて、口宣案をもって正式な命令証書とみなされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, it was arranged that the kuzen-an was handed to the working-level officials and then order of same content was issued by the Daijokan to the working-level officials -- Later, the step of issuing the order at the Daijokan was omitted, and the kuzen-an was considered to be the formal rescript.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it was arranged so that the kuzen-an was handed to the working-level officials and then the same order was issued by the Daijokan to the working-level officials -- Later, the step of issuing the order at the Daijokan was omitted, and the kuzen-an was considered to be the formal rescript.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was arranged so that the kuzen-an was handed to the working-level officials and then the same order was issued by the Daijokan to the working-level officials -- Later, the step of issuing the order at the Daijokan was omitted, and the kuzen-an was considered to be the formal rescript.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 春秋君(id:174988), Blue-comet(id:192801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>