<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平忠常の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revolt of TAIRA no Tadatsune</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revolt of TAIRA no Tadatsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revolt of TAIRA no Tadatsune</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平忠常の乱（たいらのただつねのらん）は平安時代に房総半島（上総国、下総国、安房国）で起きた反乱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revolt of TAIRA no Tadatsune occurred in the Boso peninsula (Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province, Awa Province) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The revolt of TAIRA no Tadatsune occurred in the Boso peninsula (Kazusa, Shimousa, Awa Provinces) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The revolt of TAIRA no Tadatsune occurred in the Boso peninsula (Kazusa, Shimousa, Awa Provinces) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平将門の乱以来平穏だった平安時代の関東地方では久しい大規模な反乱であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a rebellion that happened in Kanto Region in the Heian period where it had been quiet for a long time since Taira no Masakado Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a massive rebellion that happened in Kanto Region which had been peaceful for a long time since Taira no Masakado Rebellion, in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>大規模なの訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a massive rebellion that happened in Kanto Region which had been peaceful for a long time since Taira no Masakado Rebellion, in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>平将門の子孫に当たる平忠常が乱を起こし、朝廷は討伐軍を派遣するが3年にわたって鎮圧できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsune, who was a descendant of TAIRA no Masakado raised a revolt and the Imperial Court dispatched a punitive force, but they could not suppress it for over three years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Tadatsune who was a descendant of TAIRA no Masakado raised a revolt and the Imperial Court dispatched a punitive force, but they could not suppress it for over three years.</e>
<cmt>カンマを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Tadatsune who was a descendant of TAIRA no Masakado raised a revolt and the Imperial Court dispatched a punitive force, but they could not suppress it for over three years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>有力武士の源頼信が起用されるに及び忠常は降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a dominant Samurai, MINAMOTO no Yorinobu was appointed, Tadatsune surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a dominant Samurai, MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, was appointed, Tadatsune was surrendered.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a dominant Samurai, MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, was appointed, Tadatsune was surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この乱により房総三カ国は大いに荒廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this revolt, three provinces of Boso were ruined badly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this revolt, the three Boso provinces were ruined badly.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this revolt, the three Boso provinces were ruined badly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>長元の乱ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Chogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called Chogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called Chogen Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>平良文は下総国相馬郡 (下総国)を本拠に村岡五郎と称し、子の平忠頼、孫の忠常の三代に渡り関東で勢力を伸ばした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshifumi was called Goro MURAOKA and based in the Soma country, Shimousa Province and extended power over three generation of his son TAIRA no Tadayori and grandson Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoshifumi was called Goro MURAOKA and was based in the Soma country, Shimousa Province and extended power with his son TAIRA no Tadayori and grandson Tadatsune over three generations.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoshifumi was called Goro MURAOKA and was based in the Soma country, Shimousa Province and extended power with his son TAIRA no Tadayori and grandson Tadatsune over three generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>忠常は上総国、下総国、常陸国に父祖以来の広大な所領を有し、傍若無人に振る舞い、国司の命に服さず納税の義務も果たさなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune owned large territory over Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Hitachi Province, behaved outrageously and did not fulfill obligation to pay taxes without obeying orders of Kokushi (provincial governor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune owned a large territory in Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Hitachi Province, behaved outrageously and did not obey orders of the Kokushi (provincial governor) nor fulfill his obligations to pay taxes.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune owned a large territory in Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Hitachi Province, behaved outrageously and did not obey orders of the Kokushi (provincial governor) nor fulfill his obligations to pay taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>長元元年（1028年）6月、忠常は安房守平惟忠を焼き殺す事件を起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, 1028, an incident occurred in which Tadatsune burned TAIRA no Koretada, Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province) to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, 1028, an incident occurred in which Tadatsune burned TAIRA no Koretada, Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province), to death.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, 1028, an incident occurred in which Tadatsune burned TAIRA no Koretada, Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province), to death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>原因は不明だが、受領と在地領主である忠常との対立が高じたものらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cause is not clear, but it seems that this was because of the deepened confrontation between Zuryo (provincial governor) and Tadatsune, the resident land holder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its cause is not clear, but it seems that this was because of the deepened confrontation between Zuryo (provincial governor) and Tadatsune, the resident land holder.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its cause is not clear, but it seems that this was because of the deepened confrontation between Zuryo (provincial governor) and Tadatsune, the resident land holder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>続いて忠常は上総国の国衙を占領してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune subsequently occupied the kokuga (provincial government office compounds).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune subsequently occupied the kokuga (provincial government office compounds) in the Kazusa province.</e>
<cmt>抜けた部分を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune subsequently occupied the kokuga (provincial government office compounds) in the Kazusa province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>上総介縣犬養為政の妻子が京へ逃れ、これを見た上総国の国人たちは忠常に加担して反乱は房総三カ国（上総国、下総国、安房国）に広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wife and children of Tamemasa INUKAI, Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) escaped to Kyoto and the kokujins (provincial warriors) in Kazusa Province who saw this cooperated Tadatsune and the rebel extended to the three provinces of Boso (Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Awa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wife and children of Tamemasa INUKAI, Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province), escaped to Kyoto and the kokujins (provincial warriors) in Kazusa Province who saw this cooperated with Tadatsune and the rebellion extended to the three Boso provinces (Kazusa, Shimousa and Awa).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wife and children of Tamemasa INUKAI, Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province), escaped to Kyoto and the kokujins (provincial warriors) in Kazusa Province who saw this cooperated with Tadatsune and the rebellion extended to the three Boso provinces (Kazusa, Shimousa and Awa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>当時、在地豪族（地方軍事貴族）はたびたび国衙に反抗的な行動をとっていたが、中央の有力貴族との私的な関係を通じて不問になることが多く、実際に追討宣旨が下されることは稀だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, local powerful clans (local military aristocracies) often behaved disaffectedly to kokuga, but it was overlooked due to the private relationship with central dominant nobilities, so it was rare that an imperial decree to hunt down and kill Tadatsune was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, local powerful clans (local military aristocracies) often behaved disaffectedly to the kokuga (provincial government office), but it was overlooked due to the private relationship with central dominant nobilities, so an imperial decree to hunt down and kill Tadatsune was rarely issued.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, local powerful clans (local military aristocracies) often behaved disaffectedly to the kokuga (provincial government office), but it was overlooked due to the private relationship with central dominant nobilities, so an imperial decree to hunt down and kill Tadatsune was rarely issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>事件の報は朝廷に伝えられ追討使として源頼信・平正輔・平直方・中原成通が候補にあがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident was reported to the Imperial Court and MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, TAIRA no Masasuke, TAIRA no Naokata and NAKAHARA no Narimichi were nominated as tsuitoshi, envoy to search and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident was reported to the Imperial Court, and MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, TAIRA no Masasuke, TAIRA no Naokata and NAKAHARA no Narimichi were nominated as tsuitoshi, envoys to search and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident was reported to the Imperial Court, and MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, TAIRA no Masasuke, TAIRA no Naokata and NAKAHARA no Narimichi were nominated as tsuitoshi, envoys to search and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>右大臣・藤原実資は陣定において、頼信を推薦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, Minister of the Right, recommended Yorinobi at Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, Minister of the Right, recommended Yorinobi at the Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Sanesuke, Minister of the Right, recommended Yorinobi at the Jin no sadame (ancient cabinet council).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>頼信は常陸介在任中に忠常を臣従させており、事態の穏便な解決のためには最適と考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune served Yorinobu when he was appointed as Hitachi no suke and Yorinobu thought that he was best suited to settle the situation peacefully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune served Yorinobu when he was appointed as Hitachi no suke and Yorinobu thought that he was best suited to settling the situation peacefully.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune served Yorinobu when he was appointed as Hitachi no suke and Yorinobu thought that he was best suited to settling the situation peacefully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>他の公卿も同調するが、後一条天皇の裁可により検非違使右衛門少尉・平直方と検非違使左衛門少志・中原成道が追討使に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other Kugyos (high court nobles) agreed with him, but TAIRA no Naokata, Uemon no shojo, kebiishi (official with judicial and police powers) and NAKAHARA no Narimichi, Zaemon no shochi (junior assistant lieutenant), kebiishi were appointed as tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Kugyos (high court nobles) agreed with him, but TAIRA no Naokata, Uemon no shojo, kebiishi (official with judicial and police powers), and NAKAHARA no Narimichi, Zaemon no shochi (junior assistant lieutenant), kebiishi, were appointed as tsuitoshi with the approval of Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>「後一条天皇の裁可により」の訳が抜けていましたので、追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Kugyos (high court nobles) agreed with him, but TAIRA no Naokata, Uemon no shojo, kebiishi (official with judicial and police powers), and NAKAHARA no Narimichi, Zaemon no shochi (junior assistant lieutenant), kebiishi, were appointed as tsuitoshi with the approval of Emperor Goichijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>直方を追討使に抜擢したのは、関白・藤原頼通だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, chief adviser to the Emperor, who appointed Naokata as tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, chief adviser to the Emperor, who appointed Naokata as tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, chief adviser to the Emperor, who appointed Naokata as tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>直方は平貞盛流の嫡流ともいえる立場であり、同じ貞盛流の常陸平氏と連携していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naokata was in the position of a direct descendant of Taira no Sadamori line and had cooperated with the Hitachi-Heishi (Taira clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naokata was in the position of a direct descendant of Taira no Sadamori and had cooperated with Hitachi-Heishi (Taira clan) which were also descendants of Taira no Sadamori.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naokata was in the position of a direct descendant of Taira no Sadamori and had cooperated with Hitachi-Heishi (Taira clan) which were also descendants of Taira no Sadamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>常陸平氏は、武蔵・下総を勢力基盤とする良文流平氏とは長年の敵対関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hitachi-Heishi had had adversarial relationship with the Yoshifumi-line Taira clan who bases in Musashi and Shimousa for many years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hitachi-Heishi had an adversarial relationship with the Taira clan of Yoshifumi line, based in Musashi and Shimousa for many years.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hitachi-Heishi had an adversarial relationship with the Taira clan of Yoshifumi line, based in Musashi and Shimousa for many years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>直方は頼通の家人であり、頼通に働きかけることで追討使に任命されたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naokata was the Kenin (retainer) of Yorimichi and it is assumed that he approached Yorimichi to be assigned to Tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naokata was a Kenin (retainer) of Yorimichi and it is assumed that he asked Yorimichi to assign him to Tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naokata was a Kenin (retainer) of Yorimichi and it is assumed that he asked Yorimichi to assign him to Tsuitoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>直方は国家の公認のもとに、平忠常ら良文流平氏を排除する立場を得ることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the official recognition of the sate, Naokata succeeded in obtaining the position to exclude the Yoshifumi line Taira clan including TAIRA no Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the official recognition of the state, Naokata succeeded in obtaining the position to exclude the Taira clan of Yoshifumi line, including TAIRA no Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>誤記を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the official recognition of the state, Naokata succeeded in obtaining the position to exclude the Taira clan of Yoshifumi line, including TAIRA no Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>8月、京都に潜入した忠常の郎党が捕らえられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, the roto (retainer) of Tadatsune who infiltrated Kyoto was captured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, the roto (retainer) of Tadatsune who infiltrated Kyoto was captured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, the roto (retainer) of Tadatsune who infiltrated Kyoto was captured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>郎党は内大臣藤原教通（忠常の「私君」にあたる人物）宛ての書状を持っており、追討令の不当を訴える内容だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The roto had a letter addressed to FUJIWARA no Norimichi (??? the private master ??? of Tadatsune), minister of the center, reporting the unconscionability of the order to track down and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>私君の意味が不明です。private master としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The roto had a letter addressed to FUJIWARA no Norimichi (the private master of Tadatsune), minister of the center, reporting the injustice of the order to track down and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The roto had a letter addressed to FUJIWARA no Norimichi (the private master of Tadatsune), minister of the center, reporting the injustice of the order to track down and kill Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>平直方と中原成道は吉日を選び任命から40余日も後の8月5日亥の刻（午後10時）に兵200を率いて京を出立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Naokata and NAKAHARA no Narimichi selected &quot;Kitsujitsu&quot; (lucky day) and at 10 p.m. on August 5, about 40 days after their appointment, they left Kyoto with their 200 soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Naokata and NAKAHARA no Narimichi selected a &quot;Kitsujitsu&quot; (lucky day) and they left Kyoto with their 200 soldiers at 10 p.m. on August 5, about 40 days after their appointment.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Naokata and NAKAHARA no Narimichi selected a &quot;Kitsujitsu&quot; (lucky day) and they left Kyoto with their 200 soldiers at 10 p.m. on August 5, about 40 days after their appointment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>夜中にもかかわらず、見物人が集まり見送ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of midnight, many spectators gathered to see them off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of midnight, many spectators gathered to see them off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of midnight, many spectators gathered to see them off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>翌年には、直方の父・平維時が上総介に任命され追討も本格化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, TAIRA no Koretoki, the father of Naokata was appointed as Kazusa no suke and the punitive force were well underway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, TAIRA no Koretoki, the father of Naokata, was appointed as Kazusa no suke and the punitive force got into full swing.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, TAIRA no Koretoki, the father of Naokata, was appointed as Kazusa no suke and the punitive force got into full swing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>国家から謀叛人扱いされた忠常は、徹底抗戦を余儀なくされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune, regarded as a rebel by the state, was forced to resistance to the bitter end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune, regarded as a rebel by the state, was forced to resist to the bitter end.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune, regarded as a rebel by the state, was forced to resist to the bitter end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>追討使の中原成道は消極的で、関東へ向かう途上、母親の病を理由に美濃国で滞陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tsuitoshi, NAKAHARA no Narimichi was inactive and on the way to Kanto, his army stayed in Mino Province because his mother was sick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tsuitoshi, NAKAHARA no Narimichi was inactive and his army stayed in Mino Province on the way to Kanto because his mother was sick.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tsuitoshi, NAKAHARA no Narimichi was inactive and his army stayed in Mino Province on the way to Kanto because his mother was sick.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>合戦の詳細は不明だが消極派の成道と積極派の直方は仲たがいしたため討伐軍は苦戦し、乱は一向に鎮圧できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The details of the battle is unknown, but the relationship between passive Narimichi and active Naokata was worsen, the punitive force struggled and could not suppress the rebel at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The details of the battle are unknown, but the relationship between passive Narimichi and active Naokata worsened, the punitive force made a poor fight and could not suppress the rebellion at all.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The details of the battle are unknown, but the relationship between passive Narimichi and active Naokata worsened, the punitive force made a poor fight and could not suppress the rebellion at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>長元2年（1029年）2月、朝廷は東海道、東山道、北陸道の諸国へ忠常追討の官符を下して討伐軍を補強させるが鎮定はすすまなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1029, the Imperial Court issued kanpu (official document from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) to strengthen the punitive force, but the suppression did not made progress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, 1029, the Imperial Court issued a kanpu (official document from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) to strengthen the punitive force, but the suppression did not made progress.</e>
<cmt>不定冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 1029, the Imperial Court issued a kanpu (official document from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) to strengthen the punitive force, but the suppression did not made progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>同年12月には都への報告を怠ったという理由で成道は解任されてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narimichi was removed his post for the reason that he failed to report to the government in December of the year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narimichi was removed from his post for the reason that he failed to report to the imperial court in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt>fromとsameを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narimichi was removed from his post for the reason that he failed to report to the imperial court in December of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>長元3年（1030年）3月、忠常は安房国の国衙を襲撃して、安房守藤原光業を放逐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1030, Tadatsune attacked kokuga and ejected FUJIWARA no Mitsunari, Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1030, Tadatsune attacked the kokuga and ejected FUJIWARA no Mitsunari, Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province).</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1030, Tadatsune attacked the kokuga and ejected FUJIWARA no Mitsunari, Awa no kami (Governor of Awa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>朝廷は後任の安房守に平正輔を任じるが、平正輔は伊勢国で同族の平致経と抗争を繰り返している最中で任国へ向かうどころではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court appointed TAIRA no Masasuke to the substitute Awa no kami, but he was in the middle of the repeated fighting with the same clan TAIRA no Munetsune and TAIRA no Munetsune could not leave for the appointed province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court appointed TAIRA no Masasuke to the substitute Awa no kami, but he could not leave for the appointed province because he was in the middle of repeated fighting with TAIRA no Munetsune of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。誤記を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court appointed TAIRA no Masasuke to the substitute Awa no kami, but he could not leave for the appointed province because he was in the middle of repeated fighting with TAIRA no Munetsune of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>忠常は上総国夷隅郡伊志みの要害に立て篭もって抵抗を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune holed up in the military fortress in Ishimi, Isumi County, Kazusa Province continued resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune holed up in a military fortress in Ishimi, Isumi County, Kazusa Province and continued resistance.</e>
<cmt>andを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune holed up in a military fortress in Ishimi, Isumi County, Kazusa Province and continued resistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>乱は長期戦となり、戦場となった上総国、下総国、安房国の疲弊ははなはだしかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The revolt was prolonged and attrition was tremendous in the battlefield, Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The revolt prolonged and Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Awa Province where battles were fought were exhausted..</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The revolt prolonged and Kazusa Province, Shimousa Province and Awa Province where battles were fought were exhausted..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>下総守藤原為頼は飢餓にせまられ、その妻子は憂死したと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that FUJIWARA no Tameyori, the Shimousa no kami, was subject to famine and his wife and children were dead.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that FUJIWARA no Tameyori, the Shimousa no kami, was subject to famine and his wife and children died.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that FUJIWARA no Tameyori, the Shimousa no kami, was subject to famine and his wife and children died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>同年9月、業を煮やした朝廷は平直方を召還し、代わって甲斐国守源頼信を追討使に任じて忠常討伐を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September of the year, the frustrated imperial court recalled TAIRA no Naokata and appointed MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, Kai no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Kai) as tsuitoshi and ordered suppression of Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September of the same year, the frustrated imperial court recalled TAIRA no Naokata and appointed MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, Kai no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Kai) as tsuitoshi and ordered suppression of Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>sameを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September of the same year, the frustrated imperial court recalled TAIRA no Naokata and appointed MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, Kai no kuni no Kami (officer in charge of regional administration in Kai) as tsuitoshi and ordered suppression of Tadatsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>頼信は直ぐには出立せず、準備を整えた上で忠常の子の一法師をともなって甲斐国へ下向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorinobu did not depart soon, but after making good preparations, he left down for Kai Province with his son, Ipposhi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorinobu did not depart soon, but after making good preparations, he left down for Kai Province with his son, Ipposhi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorinobu did not depart soon, but after making good preparations, he left down for Kai Province with his son, Ipposhi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>長期に及ぶ戦いで忠常の軍は疲弊していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of long battle, the army of Tadatsune was war-worn.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of long battle, the army of Tadatsune was war-worn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of long battle, the army of Tadatsune was war-worn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>頼信が上総国へ出立しようとした長元4年（1031年）春に忠常は出家して子と従者をしたがえて頼信に降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the spring of 1031, when Yorinobu was to leave for Kazusa Province, Tadatsune entered into priesthood and surrendered with his children and followers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the spring of 1031, when Yorinobu was to leave for Kazusa Province, Tadatsune entered into priesthood and surrendered with his children and followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the spring of 1031, when Yorinobu was to leave for Kazusa Province, Tadatsune entered into priesthood and surrendered with his children and followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>頼信は忠常を連れて帰還の途につくが、同年6月、美濃国野上で忠常は病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori headed back to home with Tadatsune, but in June of the year, Tadatsune died of illness in Nogami, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori headed back to home with Tadatsune, but in June of the same year, Tadatsune died of illness in Nogami, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori headed back to home with Tadatsune, but in June of the same year, Tadatsune died of illness in Nogami, Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>頼信は忠常の首をはねて帰京した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori beheaded Tadatsune and returned Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori beheaded Tadatsune and returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori beheaded Tadatsune and returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>忠常の首はいったん梟首とされたが、降人の首をさらすべきではないとして従者へ返され、また忠常の子の平常将と平常近も罪を許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatsune&apos;s head was exposed, but it was returned to his followers since the head of Koin (person of surrender) should not be exposed and sins of Tadatsune&apos;s children TAIRA no Tsunemasa and TAIRA no Tsunechika were forgiven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatsune&apos;s head was exposed, but it was returned to his followers since the head of Koin (person of surrender) should not be exposed and the sins of Tadatsune&apos;s children TAIRA no Tsunemasa and TAIRA no Tsunechika were forgiven.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatsune&apos;s head was exposed, but it was returned to his followers since the head of Koin (person of surrender) should not be exposed and the sins of Tadatsune&apos;s children TAIRA no Tsunemasa and TAIRA no Tsunechika were forgiven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>長元5年（1032年）功により頼信は美濃守に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1032, Yorinobu was appointed Mino no kami due to his achievement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1032, Yorinobu was appointed Mino no kami due to his achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1032, Yorinobu was appointed Mino no kami due to his achievement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="46">
<j>平直方の征伐にも屈しなかった忠常が、頼信の出陣によりあっけなく降伏したのは、忠常が頼信の家人であった（『今昔物語集』）ためであるともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the reason for Tadatsune, who did not yield to the conquest of TAIRA no Naokata, simply surrendered due to the participation of Yorinobu was because Tadatsune was a kenin (retainer) of Yorinobu (&quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu)&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Tadatsune, who did not yield to the conquest of TAIRA no Naokata, simply surrendered when Yorinobu participated because Tadatsune was a kenin (retainer) of Yorinobu (&quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu)&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past)).</e>
<cmt>表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Tadatsune, who did not yield to the conquest of TAIRA no Naokata, simply surrendered when Yorinobu participated because Tadatsune was a kenin (retainer) of Yorinobu (&quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu)&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="47">
<j>この乱の主戦場になった房総三カ国（下総国、上総国、安房国）は大きな被害を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three provinces in Boso (Shimousa Province, Kazusa Province and Awa Province), the major battle fields of the rebel, were badly suffered.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three provinces in Boso (Shimousa Province, Kazusa Province and Awa Province), the major battle fields of the rebel, were badly suffered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three provinces in Boso (Shimousa Province, Kazusa Province and Awa Province), the major battle fields of the rebel, were badly suffered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>上総守藤原辰重の報告によると本来、上総国の作田は2万2千町あったが、僅かに18町に減ってしまったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the report of Tatsushige FUJIWARA, Kazusa no kami, the field in Kazusa Province was used to be 22,000-cho but reduced to 18-cho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the report of Tatsushige FUJIWARA, Kazusa no kami, the area of rice fields in Kazusa Province was used to be 22,000-cho, but reduced to 18-cho.</e>
<cmt>表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the report of Tatsushige FUJIWARA, Kazusa no kami, the area of rice fields in Kazusa Province was used to be 22,000-cho, but reduced to 18-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>だが、同時にその原因は追討使であった平直方や諸国兵士、すなわち朝廷軍による収奪であったと明言している（『左経記』長元7年10月24日条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, at the same time, the cause is obviously said to be grab by TAIRA no Naokata, tsuitoshi, and country soldiers, that is, imperial court army &quot;Sakeiki&quot; (A Diary of MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori, the section of October 24, 1034)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, at the same time, it is clearly stated that it was caused by plundering by the tsuitoshi TAIRA no Naokata and country soldiers who formed the imperial court army (&quot;Sakeiki&quot; (A Diary of MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori, the section of October 24, 1034)).</e>
<cmt>表現を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, at the same time, it is clearly stated that it was caused by plundering by the tsuitoshi TAIRA no Naokata and country soldiers who formed the imperial court army (&quot;Sakeiki&quot; (A Diary of MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori, the section of October 24, 1034)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="50">
<j>この乱を平定することにより坂東平氏の多くが頼信の配下に入り、清和源氏が東国で勢力を広げる契機となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the stabilization of this revolt, many of the Bando-Heishi clan went under control of Yorinobu and it was a key factor that Seiwa-Genji extended their power in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the stabilization of this revolt, many of the Bando-Heishi clan went under control of Yorinobu and it was a key factor that Seiwa-Genji extended their power in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the stabilization of this revolt, many of the Bando-Heishi clan went under control of Yorinobu and it was a key factor that Seiwa-Genji extended their power in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Libertas(id:40611), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 味っ子(id:17086), Yanahan(id:2437), Hkato(id:78953), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>