<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo (chief retainer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo (chief retainer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo (chief retainer)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>家老（かろう）とは、武家の家臣団のうち最高の地位にあった役職で、複数人おり合議によって政治・経済を補佐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo indicated the highest post available for the retainers of a samurai family, and more than one person occupied the post to assist the master about political and economical affairs through consultation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo was the highest post available for the retainers of a samurai family, and more than one person occupied the post to consult with and assist the master with political and economical affairs.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo was the highest post available for the retainers of a samurai family, and more than one person occupied the post to consult with and assist the master with political and economical affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>武家社会の勃興した鎌倉時代よりみられるが、室町時代までは年寄（としより、おとな）・宿老（しゅくろう）・執事（しつじ）などと呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a post already existed in the Kamakura period when the samurai-based society started, and was called Toshiyori (or Otona), Shukuro or Shitusji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a post already existed in the Kamakura period, the start of samurai-based society, and was called Toshiyori (or Otona), Shukuro or Shitusji.</e>
<cmt>when...started&gt;the start of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a post already existed in the Kamakura period, the start of samurai-based society, and was called Toshiyori (or Otona), Shukuro or Shitsuji.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>通常、家臣団の中でも重臣と呼ばれる有力な家臣が任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ordinarily, powerful retainers called senior vassals were appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ordinarily, powerful retainers called senior vassals were appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ordinarily, powerful retainers called senior vassals were appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また主家の譜代家臣が任ぜられるのが通常で、主家の分家などの一門の者が、家老職に就くことは原則的にはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was customary that persons whose families had been a retainer of the master&apos;s family for generations were appointed to the post, and the persons who belonged to a branch family of the master&apos;s family were basically not appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was customary that people whose family had been retainers of the master&apos;s family for generations were appointed to the post, and people who belonged to a branch family of the master&apos;s family were not appointed in principle.</e>
<cmt>persons&gt;people. basically&gt;in principle</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was customary that people whose family had been retainers of the master&apos;s family for generations were appointed to the post, and people who belonged to a branch family of the master&apos;s family were not appointed in principle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし次第にこの原則は崩れ、財政難などから、藩主の庶子は、養子縁組先がないと、家老はおろか給人級の家臣として分家させられることも珍しくなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, over time, this rule could not become kept, and due to financial or other reasons, it became not rare that when an illegitimate child of a lord was not adopted by a family, the child was appointed to Karo or was forced to leave the master&apos;s family, generating a branch family with a territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, over time this rule came to be broken and for financial or other reasons, it was not rare for an illegitimate child of a lord not adopted by a family to be appointed as a Karo or forced to leave the master&apos;s family, generating a branch family with territory.</e>
<cmt>could not become kept&gt;came to be broken. become not&gt;was not.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, over time this rule came to be broken and for financial or other reasons, it was not rare for an illegitimate child of a lord not adopted by a family to be appointed as a Karo or forced to leave the master&apos;s family, generating a branch family with territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>分家筋で家老職をはじめ家臣の役職に就くことは、主家の親戚から家臣になったことを意味し、主家断絶時の相続権が無くなったと見なされることが通例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a person from a branch family assumed the Karo or other post for a retainer of the master&apos;s family, it meant that the person became a retainer of the master&apos;s family from its relative, and it was customary that the person lost the heirship when no heir became available for the master&apos;s family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a person from a branch family assumed the role of Karo or other retainer post, it meant that the person changed from a relative to a retainer of the master&apos;s family, and when there were succession disputes they were not considered to have any claim to heirship.</e>
<cmt>became&gt;changed. no heir became available&gt;succession disputes. lost the heirship&gt;were not considered to have any claim to heirship.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a person from a branch family assumed the role of Karo or other retainer post, it meant that the person changed from a relative to a retainer of the master&apos;s family, and when there were succession disputes they were not considered to have any claim to heirship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代になると、江戸幕府の置かれた江戸には、各藩・将軍家の旗本屋敷（江戸屋敷）が置かれ、ここに在勤した家老を江戸家老・江戸詰家老などと呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entering the Edo period, residences of domains and of Hatamoto (retainers) of the shogun family were placed in Edo where the Edo bakufu was located, and the Karo officers who worked in these residences were called Edo-garo or Edozume-garo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period began, residences of domains and of Hatamoto (retainers) of the shogun family were placed in Edo where the Edo bakufu was located, and the Karo officers who worked in these residences were called Edo-garo or Edozume-garo.</e>
<cmt>Entering&gt;after...began</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period began, residences of domains and of Hatamoto (retainers) of the shogun family were placed in Edo where the Edo bakufu was located, and the Karo officers who worked in these residences were called Edo-garo or Edozume-garo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>一方、知行地に在勤した家老を国家老・在所家老と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Karo officer who worked in chigyo-chi (the lord&apos;s territory) was Kuni-garo or Zaisho-garo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Karo officers who worked in chigyo-chi (the lord&apos;s territory) were called Kuni-garo or Zaisho-garo.</e>
<cmt>officer&gt;officers. was&gt;were called</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Karo officers who worked in chigyo-chi (the lord&apos;s territory) were called Kuni-garo or Zaisho-garo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>主君が城主以上のときは城代家老も置かれたが、主君が城主大名や、陣屋のときは、城代家老は、当然に設置されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a lord had a castle but did not reside there, Jodai-garo, Karo in charge of the castle, was placed, but when a lord resided in a castle or in jinya (his regional government office), jodai-garo was not placed naturally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a lord had a castle but did not reside there, a Jodai-garo (Karo in charge of the castle) was installed, but when a lord resided in a castle or jinya (his regional government office), naturally jodai-garo were not installed.</e>
<cmt>placed&gt;installed. was not placed naturally&gt; naturally were not installed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a lord had a castle but did not reside there, a Jodai-garo (Karo in charge of the castle) was installed, but when a lord resided in a castle or jinya (his regional government office), naturally jodai-garo were not installed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>城代家老と、国家老の両方が設置されているときは、城代家老のほうが格上なのが通例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When both Kuni-garo and Jodai-garo were placed, it was customary that Jodai-garo was placed above Kuni-garo in the rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When both Kuni-garo and Jodai-garo were appointed, it was customary for the Jodai-garo to be placed in a higher rank to Kuni-garo.</e>
<cmt>bothの繰り返しを直しました。placed&gt;appointed, was placed above in the rank&gt;to be placed in a higher rank</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When both Kuni-garo and Jodai-garo were appointed, it was customary for the Jodai-garo to be placed in a higher rank than Kuni-garo.</e>
<cmt>to→than</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>複数人いた家老のうち最も地位の高いものは筆頭家老・家老首座・一番家老など呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the Karo officers was called Hitto-garo, Karo-shuza, or Ichiban-garo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the Karo officers was called Hitto-garo, Karo-shuza, or Ichiban-garo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the Karo officers was called Hitto-garo, Karo-shuza, or Ichiban-garo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>政治・経済の中心となって差配する家老を藩によっては、仕置家老と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Karo officers who were centrally in charge of political and economical affairs were called Shioki-garo in some domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo officers who were mainly in charge of political and economical affairs were called Shioki-garo in some domains.</e>
<cmt>centrally&gt;mainly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo officers who were mainly in charge of political and economical affairs were called Shioki-garo in some domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>城代家老と仕置家老が併置された藩にあっては、どちらが格上かは、一義的に断定できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Jodai-garo and Shioki-garo were placed at the same time in a domain, it cannot definitely say either of which was placed higher in the rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When both Jodai-garo and Shioki-garo were appointed at the same time in a domain, there was no conclusive definition of which held higher rank.</e>
<cmt>placed&gt;appointed. cannot definitely say&gt;the was no conclusive definition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When both Jodai-garo and Shioki-garo were appointed at the same time in a domain, there was no conclusive definition of which held higher rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>家老は、徳川御三家の御附家老や、御三卿付きの家老を除き、徳川将軍家の陪臣であるから、将軍に謁見の資格がないのが大原則である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except Otsuke-garo (the Karo assigned directly by the shogun) of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family) and Karo for gosankyo (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family), Karo officers were not a direct retainer of the Tokugawa shogun family, and it was a basic rule that the ordinary Karo officers were not entitled to have an audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Except for the Otsuke-garo (the Karo assigned directly by the shogun) and the Karo for gosankyo (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family), there was a fundamental rule that ordinary Karo officers were not entitled to have an audience with the shogun as they were direct retainers of the Tokugawa shogun family.</e>
<cmt>「陪臣であるから」が本文の意味ですから、&quot;As they were direct retainers&quot;のように解釈しましたが、trans1にある&quot;Were not direct retainers&quot;の方が合理的なので、orginalに間違えがあるのではないかと思っております。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Except for the Otsuke-garo (the Karo assigned directly by the shogun) and the Karo for gosankyo (three privileged branch families of the Tokugawa family), there was a fundamental rule that ordinary Karo officers were not entitled to have an audience with the shogun as they were not direct retainers of the Tokugawa shogun family.</e>
<cmt>「陪臣」は、臣下の臣、「又家来」という意味なので、trans１の解釈で良いと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、例外もあり親藩や、譜代大名の家老連綿の家系の多くには、幕府から、将軍家の旗本の格式を与えられ、将軍に謁見の資格を持ち、関所で下馬することを免除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were also exceptions: The Karo officers of Shinpan (whose lords were in the male linage of the Tokugwa shogun family) or the Karo officers whose families occupied the Karo post of Fudai daimyo (a daimyo who was a retainer of the Tokugawa family from before the Battle of Sekigahara) for generations were given the status of Hatamoto of the shogun family, being entitled to have an audience with the shogun and being permitted not to alight from the horse at checking stations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were also exceptions: Karo officers of Shinpan (whose lords were in the male lineage of the Tokugawa shogun family) and Karo officers whose families were Karo to Fudai daimyo (daimyo who were retainers of the Tokugawa family from before the Battle of Sekigahara) were given the status of Hatamoto of the shogun family for generations, being entitled to have an audience with the shogun and to not alight from their horse at checking stations.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were also exceptions: Karo officers of Shinpan (whose lords were in the male lineage of the Tokugawa shogun family) and Karo officers whose families were Karo to Fudai daimyo (daimyo who were retainers of the Tokugawa family from before the Battle of Sekigahara) were given the status of Hatamoto of the shogun family for generations, being entitled to have an audience with the shogun and to not alight from their horse at checking stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>徳川四天王の家老の中には、旗本の格式だけでなく幕府からも併せて家禄を受ける場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the Karo officers of the families of Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals having served Tokugawa Ieyasu) were given by the bakufu Karoku (hereditary stipend) in addition to the Hatamoto status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the Karo officers of the families of Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals who served Tokugawa Ieyasu) were also given Karoku (hereditary stipend) by the bakufu in addition to Hatamoto status.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the Karo officers of the families of Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals who served Tokugawa Ieyasu) were also given Karoku (hereditary stipend) by the bakufu in addition to Hatamoto status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>一方、外様大名の家老連綿の家系の場合は、将軍に謁見の資格を与えられるのは、万石以上や特別な由緒を持つ者に限られた極めて稀な例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, of the families who had produced a Karo officer of Tozama-daimyo (the daimyo who became to belong the Tokugawa side after the Battle of Sekigawara) for generations, only those with a 10,000 koku (approx. 180 liters/koku) or more of rice crop or with a special origin, the number of both of which was quite limited, were entitled to have an audience with shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the case of families who had been Karo to a Tozama-daimyo for generations, only those with a 10,000 koku (approx. 180 litres) or more of rice crop or those of special lineage (of whom there were very few) were entitled to have an audience with shogun.</e>
<cmt>the number of both was quite limited&gt;of whom there were very few</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the case of families who had been Karo to a Tozama-daimyo (the daimyo who became to belong the Tokugawa side after the Battle of Sekigawara) for generations, only those with a 10,000 koku (approx. 180 litres/koku) or more of rice crop or those of special lineage (of whom there were very few) were entitled to have an audience with shogun.</e>
<cmt>外様大名の英訳を追加原文の内容に合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸時代初期までは、家老と年寄が未分化であった藩も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the early Edo period, the Karo post and the Toshiyori post were not clearly differentiated yet in many domains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the early Edo period, the posts of Karo and Toshiyori were still not clearly differentiated in many domains.</e>
<cmt>the...post and the...post&gt;the posts of... yet&gt;still</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the early Edo period, the posts of Karo and Toshiyori were still not clearly differentiated in many domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかしながら、次第に年寄の上層部が家老として、分化するようになり、年寄と呼称される役職は、家老そのものではなく、家老に次ぐ役職である場合が一般化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, over time, the upper class officers in the Toshiyori post became to be differentiated as Karo officers, and the Toshiyori post generally became not Karo itself but the post next to Karo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, over time, the upper class officers in Toshiyori posts came to be distinguished as Karo officers, and generally, most Toshiyori did not become Karo itself but the next post down.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, over time, the upper class officers in Toshiyori posts came to be distinguished as Karo officers, and generally, most Toshiyori did not become Karo itself but the next post down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>年寄職と、中老職が同義として、使用される藩もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some domains, the Toshiyori post and the post called Churo were used for indicating the same meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some domains, the Toshiyori and Churo posts were used to mean the same thing.</e>
<cmt>indication the same meaning&gt;mean the same thing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some domains, the Toshiyori and Churo posts were used to mean the same thing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>小藩の場合は、家老に次ぐ年寄は、置かれないことがほとんどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most of small domains, the Toshiyori post next to the Karo post was not placed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most small domains, there was no Toshiyori post following Karo.</e>
<cmt>was not placed&gt;there was not</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most small domains, there was no Toshiyori post following Karo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="22">
<j>大藩の家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo in big domains</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo in large domains</e>
<cmt>big&gt;large</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo in large domains</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大藩の家老は大名並みに1万石以上の石高を有し、自身の知行地に城や陣屋を持つものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Karo officers in big domains were provided with a 10,000 koku or more of rice crop and possessed a castle or jinya in their own territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Karo officers in large domains were provided with 10,000 koku or more of rice crop and possessed a castle or jinya in their own territories.</e>
<cmt>big&gt;large</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Karo officers in large domains were provided with 10,000 koku or more of rice crop and possessed a castle or jinya in their own territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>1万石以上の知行地を持つ家臣を大名分と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retainers with a territory of a 10,000 koku or more of rice crop were called Daimyo-bun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retainers with a territory of 10,000 koku or more of rice crop were called Daimyo-bun.</e>
<cmt>aを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retainers with a territory of 10,000 koku or more of rice crop were called Daimyo-bun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="25">
<j>江戸時代の家老として最も高禄であった家系は、加賀藩100万石の本多家5万石である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family line that earned the highest hereditary stipend as a Karo officer was the 50,000-koku Honda family in the 1million-koku Kaga domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family that earned the highest hereditary stipend as Karo officers in the Edo Period was the 50,000-koku Honda family in the 1million-koku Kaga domain.</e>
<cmt>in the Edo Periodを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family that earned the highest hereditary stipend as Karo officers in the Edo Period was the 50,000-koku Honda family in the 1million-koku Kaga domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>上杉景勝（120万石）の家老、直江兼続（直轄6万石　寄騎領24万石　計30万石）の養子となった本多政重（5,000石）が、関ヶ原の戦い後に大減封を受けた上杉家を退去して、加賀藩前田氏に仕官して、本多姓に復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige HONDA (with a 5,000 koku of rice drop), who became an adopted son of Kanetsugu NAOE, a Karo officer of Kagekatsu UESUGI (with 1.2 million koku), left the Uesugi family after his salary was cut greatly after the Battle of Sekigahara, and became to work for the Maeda family in the Kaga domain, restoring his original family name.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige HONDA (with a 5,000 koku rice crop), who became an adopted son of Kanetsugu NAOE, a Karo officer of Kagekatsu UESUGI with 1.2 million koku, left the Uesugi family when his salary was drastically cut after the Battle of Sekigahara, and began to work for the Maeda family in the Kaga domain, restoring his original family name.</e>
<cmt>greatly&gt;drastically</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige HONDA (with a 5,000 koku rice crop), who became an adopted son of Kanetsugu NAOE with 300,000 koku, a Karo officer of Kagekatsu UESUGI with 1.2 million koku, left the Uesugi family when his salary was drastically cut after the Battle of Sekigahara, and began to work for the Maeda family in the Kaga domain, restoring his original family name.</e>
<cmt>計30万石の訳を追加しました。直轄、寄騎領の訳は不明（一原文一訳文の例外対処）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これがのが加賀藩前田氏の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the origin of the Honda family in the Kaga domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the origin of the Honda family in the Kaga domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the origin of the Honda family in the Kaga domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「加賀藩の領地の一部（越前国）を幕府に返還せよ」との命令を撤回させた交渉の勲功で、大加増を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made the order of &quot;Part of the Kaga domain territory (Echizen Province) should be returned to the bakufu&quot; retracted, and with this distinguished contribution to the domain, he had his stipend raised considerably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After forcing a retraction of the order: &quot;Part of the Kaga domain territory (Echizen Province) should be returned to the bakufu,&quot; he had his stipend raised considerably for this distinguished contribution to the domain,</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After forcing a retraction of the order: &quot;Part of the Kaga domain territory (Echizen Province) should be returned to the bakufu,&quot; he had his stipend raised considerably for this distinguished contribution to the domain,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="29">
<j>小藩及び、幕府旗本の家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo in small-sized domains and Karo in the Hatamoto of the bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo in small domains and Karo in the Hatamoto of the bakufu</e>
<cmt>small-sized&gt;small</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo in small domains and Karo in the Hatamoto of the bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>小藩（1万石）の家老は、家老連綿の家格の出身者の場合で、おおむね300石前後の蔵米取りの者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In small-sized (10,000-koku) domains, most of the Karo officers whose families had occupied the Karo post for generations earned an around 300 koku of kuramai (rice crop given as salary).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In small (10,000-koku) domains, most of the Karo officers whose families had occupied the Karo post for generations earned around 300 koku of kuramai (rice crop given as salary).</e>
<cmt>small-sized&gt;small. anを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In small (10,000-koku) domains, most of the Karo officers whose families had occupied the Karo post for generations earned around 300 koku of kuramai (rice crop given as salary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>もっとも田畑を給人地として与える割合の大きい藩では、家禄はさらに低く抑える例もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some domains where more farm land was given as Kyujin-chi (see below), the hereditary stipend was less than that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some domains where more farm land was given as Kyujin-chi (see below), the hereditary stipend was less than that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some domains where more farm land was given as Kyujin-chi (see below), the hereditary stipend was less than that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="32">
<j>ここでいう給人地とは、地方知行制で云う給人地（＝領地）を指すのではなく、家格に応じて支給される田畑のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, Kyujin-chi does not indicate the Kyujin-chi (territory) in the Chiho-chigyo system (in which land control right was given to Hatamoto or others), but the farm land was supplied depending the social status of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, Kyujin-chi differs from that of the Chiho-chigyo system (in which the right to land control was given to Hatamoto or others), in that farm land was supplied depending the social status of the family.</e>
<cmt>does not indicate&gt;Differs</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, Kyujin-chi differs from that of the Chiho-chigyo system (in which the right to land control was given to Hatamoto or others), in that farm land was supplied depending the social status of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="33">
<j>この制度を導入していた小藩では、家老などの上級層は、家老であっても小身な者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the small-sized domain employed this system, most of the persons in the upper class, including even the Karo officers, earned a little.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the small domains involved in this system, most of the upper class, including even the Karo officers, earned only a humble stipend.</e>
<cmt>a little&gt;only a humble stipend</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the small domains involved in this system, most of the upper class, including even the Karo officers, earned only a humble stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そのため、江戸時代後期となり、商品経済が浸透して物価高となると、その家臣（つまり陪臣）に農作業をさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when, entering the latter half of the Edo period, the commodity economy increasingly more expanded and prices of goods became higher, they made their retainers (called Baishin as well) engaged in farming.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when the commodity economy continued to expand and prices of goods became higher in the latter half of the Edo period, they engaged their retainers (called Baishin) in farming.</e>
<cmt>順番を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when the commodity economy continued to expand and prices of goods became higher in the latter half of the Edo period, they engaged their retainers (called Baishin) in farming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>中級層以下の藩士は、自ら家族と共にこれに当たり、半ば農民化していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the feudal retainers of domain in the middle or lower classes, together with their family members, were engaged in farming, making them farmers virtually.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the middle or lower class feudal domain retainers were engaged in farming together with their family members, making them virtually farmers.</e>
<cmt>簡潔にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the middle or lower class feudal domain retainers were engaged in farming together with their family members, making them virtually farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="36">
<j>幕府旗本の場合は、3,000石以上の大身旗本、及び家禄が約400石ながら、交代寄合であった徳川将軍家の本家筋に当たる松平郷松平家の家系など特別な場合を除き、家老は置かれないのが通例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the Hatamoto of the bakufu, no Karo post was placed customarily, except big Hatamoto with a 3,000 or more koku of rice crop and the lineage of the Matsudaira family, with the kotaiyoriai status, in the Matsudaira-go (area), which was the master family of the Tokugawa shogun family,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the Hatamoto of the bakufu, it was custom for no Karo to be appointed, except for large Hatamoto with 3,000 or more koku of rice crop, special cases such as lineage to the Matsudaira family, masters of the Tokugawa shogun family, who although only possessing roughly 400 koku of rice crop, had kotaiyoriai status,</e>
<cmt>交代寄合の意味は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the Hatamoto of the bakufu, it was custom for no Karo to be appointed, except for large Hatamoto with 3,000 or more koku of rice crop, special cases such as lineage to the Matsudaira family, masters of the Tokugawa shogun family, who although only possessing roughly 400 koku of rice crop, had kotaiyoriai status,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>おおむね500石以上、3,000石未満の旗本の場合は、家臣の最高位の職名は、用人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the Hatamoto with a rice crop of 500 koku or more and less than 3,000 koku, the highest post available for their retainers was the post called Yonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Hatamoto with a rice crop of between 500 and 3,000 koku, the highest post available for their retainers was called Yonin.</e>
<cmt>簡潔にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Hatamoto with a rice crop of between 500 and 3,000 koku, the highest post available for their retainers was called Yonin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>家老を設置した将軍家の旗本は、およそ250家（2％未満）であり、その家老は80石から、多くても100石強程度であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the Hatamoto families of the shogun families where Karo was placed was roughly 250 (less than 2% of all the Hatamoto families), and the earning of these Karo officers was 80 koku to 100 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Hatamoto families who appointed Karo was roughly 250 (less than 2%), and the earnings of these Karo officers was from 80 to 100 koku.</e>
<cmt>was placed&gt;appointed. earning&gt;earnings.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Hatamoto families who appointed Karo was roughly 250 (less than 2%), and the earnings of these Karo officers was from 80 to 100 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="39">
<j>付家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuke-garo (see below)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuke-garo (see below)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuke-garo (see below)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また、分家した家に本家より監視・監督する役割を担って配された家老を御附家老と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Karo officer who was sent from the main family to its branched family to watch and supervise the state of the branched family was called a Tsuke-garo officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo officers sent from a main family to its branched family to inspect and supervise was called a Tsuke-garo officer.</e>
<cmt>the karo officer&gt;複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo officers sent from a main family to its branched family to inspect and supervise was called a Tsuke-garo officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>付家老は、本藩（本家）と支藩（分家）の両方から、家禄を受けている場合と、出仕先の支藩からのみ家禄を受けて、支藩に次第に取り込まれていく場合とがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Tsuke-garo officers earned their stipend from both the main domain (family) and the branch domain (family), and some other Tsuke-garo officers earned their stipend only from the branch family where they were sent, being gradually taken into the branch domain side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Tsuke-garo officers earned their stipend from both the main domain (honke) and the branch domain (bunke), whilst others earned theirs only from the branch family where they were sent, being gradually taken into the branch domain side.</e>
<cmt>(family)&gt;(honke),(bunke)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Tsuke-garo officers earned their stipend from both the main domain (honke=main family) and the branch domain (bunke=branch family), whilst others earned theirs only from the branch family where they were sent, being gradually taken into the branch domain side.</e>
<cmt>英訳を補いました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="42">
<j>将軍家から、徳川御三家に遣わされていた付家老は、幕府と藩の双方から家禄を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tsuke-garo officers who were sent to the Tokugawa gosanke families earned their hereditary stipend from both the bakufu and the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tsuke-garo officers who were sent to the Tokugawa gosanke families earned their hereditary stipend from both the bakufu and the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tsuke-garo officers who were sent to the Tokugawa gosanke families earned their hereditary stipend from both the bakufu and the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>尾張藩成瀬氏や、紀伊藩水野氏及び、安藤氏のように城主となり、官位、官職を受けていた付家老もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Tsuke-garo officers, for example, the Naruse family in the Owari domain and the Mizuno family and the Ando family in the Kii domain, became the lord of a castle, with a governmental rank and post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Tsuke-garo officers, for example, the Naruse family in Owari domain and the Mizuno and Ando families in the Kii domain, became castle lords with a governmental rank and post.</e>
<cmt>簡潔にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Tsuke-garo officers, for example, the Naruse family in the Owari domain and the Mizuno and Ando families in the Kii domain, became castle lords with a governmental rank and post.</e>
<cmt>冠詞をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これらは、家老と言えど大名と同等の格式を与えられ、主家の参勤交代随伴時においても、大名並みの格式と威光を放ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that these Karo officers were given a status equivalent to that of daimyo: For example, even in accompanying the travel for Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) of the families where they served, they showed the status and prestige equivalent to those of daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that these Karo officers were given a status equivalent to that of daimyo: for example, even in when travelling with the family they served for Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) they were granterd the status and prestige equivalent a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>簡潔にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that these Karo officers were given a status equivalent to that of daimyo: for example, even in when travelling with the family they served for Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) they were granterd the status and prestige equivalent a daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="45">
<j>御三卿付きの家老は、御三卿が将軍家の家族という扱いであったため、江戸城留守居と並ぶ、将軍家旗本の最高の役職とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Karo for gosankyo, together with Edo-jo-rusui (the post for the officer in charge of the Edo castle while shogun was absent from the castle), was said the highest post available for the Hatamoto of the shogun family, because, gosankyo was dealt with as members of the shogun family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Karo for the gosankyo, together with Edo-jo-rusui (the officer in charge of the Edo castle while shogun was absent), were said to be the highest posts available for Hatamoto of the shogun family, because gosankyo were treated as members of the family itself.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Karo for the gosankyo, together with Edo-jo-rusui (the officer in charge of the Edo castle while shogun was absent), were said to be the highest posts available for Hatamoto of the shogun family, because gosankyo were treated as members of the shogun family.</e>
<cmt>用語修正しました。（一原文一訳文の例外対処）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかしながら、3,000石級以下の旗本で、有能な者が任じられることも珍しくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was not rare that competent Hatamoto persons with an earning of 3,000 koku or less were appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was not rare that competent Hatamoto with an earning of 3,000 koku or less were appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt>personsを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was not rare that competent Hatamoto with an earning of 3,000 koku or less were appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="47">
<j>家老格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo-kaku (see below)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo-kaku (see below)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo-kaku (see below)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>江戸時代において家老職は譜代重鎮の家臣による世襲、もしくは有力な譜代の家臣（家老職を出せる家格の家臣）による交代制となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Karo post was inherited by the families of prominent Fudai retainers, or was occupied alternately by powerful Fudai retainers (the retainers with the status enabled to produce a Karo officer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the Karo post was inherited by the families of prominent Fudai retainers, or was occupied alternately by powerful Fudai retainers themselves (who had the status to appoint Karo officers).</e>
<cmt>themselvesを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the Karo post was inherited by the families of prominent Fudai retainers, or was occupied alternately by powerful Fudai retainers themselves (who had the status to appoint Karo officers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし、譜代の家臣ではなくとも家中（かちゅう）で実力を認められて家老に準ずる地位に登用されるものもおり、彼らを家老格・家老並・家老列などと呼ぶこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some persons who were not Fudai retainers were sometimes appointed to a post equivalent to Karo due to their abilities, and they were sometimes called Karo-kaku, Karo-nami, or Karo-retsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even people who were not Fudai retainers were sometimes appointed to a post equivalent to Karo due to their abilities, and were called Karo-kaku, Karo-nami, or Karo-retsu.</e>
<cmt>some persons&gt;even people</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even people who were not Fudai retainers were sometimes appointed to a post equivalent to Karo due to their abilities, and were called Karo-kaku, Karo-nami, or Karo-retsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="50">
<j>また自分の家が連綿としてきた家格以上の役職である家老に抜擢された者を、「一代家老」と呼ぶこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who was selected to Karo, a post above those that were available for its family status for generations, was called &quot;Ichida-garo&quot; (one-generation Karo) as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, people who were selected as Karo despite their family status having been lower for generations, were called &quot;Ichidai-garo&quot; (first-generation Karo).</e>
<cmt>ichida-garo&gt;ichidai-garo. person.people. a post above&gt;despite their family status having been lower</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, people who were selected as Karo despite their family status having been lower for generations, were called &quot;Ichidai-garo&quot; (first-generation Karo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="51">
<j>家老格という呼称には、家老職を出せる家格（家老級の家柄）という意味と、一代家老という意味で使用される場合の2通りに使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of Karo-kaku is used for indicating either the family status enabled to produce a Karo officer (the family line for the Karo class) or Ichidai-garo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Karo-kaku is used to indicate either the family status able to produce a Karo officer (the family line for the Karo class) or Ichidai-garo.</e>
<cmt>for indicating&gt;to indicate. enabled to.able to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Karo-kaku is used to indicate either the family status able to produce a Karo officer (the family line for the Karo class) or Ichidai-garo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>加賀藩前田家のような大藩になると家老職を出せる家格（家老級の家柄）は、70家にも及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a big domain, for example, the Maeda family in the Kaga domain, the number of the families with the status enabled to produce a Karo officer reached up to 70.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a large domain, for example, the Maeda family in the Kaga domain, the number of the families with status high enough to produce Karo officer reached up to 70.</e>
<cmt>big&gt;large</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a large domain, for example, the Maeda family in the Kaga domain, the number of the families with status high enough to produce Karo officer reached up to 70.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="53">
<j>一代家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichidai-garo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichidai-garo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichidai-garo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>江戸時代も年代が経つにつれて、一代家老が登用される例が微増して行き一代家老に対して、家老連綿の家柄である門閥出身の家老を、永代家老と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over time in the Edo period, the number of examples where an Ichidai-garo officer was appointed increased little by little, and for these Ichidai-garo officers, the Karo officers from the families that had produced a Karo officer for generations were called Eidai-garo (permanent Karo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over the years in the Edo period, the examples of an Ichidai-garo officer being appointed increased little by little, and in contrast to these Ichidai-garo officers, the Karo officers from families that had produced a Karo officer for generations were called Eidai-garo (permanent Karo).</e>
<cmt>time&gt;the years. number of examples&gt;example. for&gt;in contrast to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over the years in the Edo period, the examples of an Ichidai-garo officer being appointed increased little by little, and in contrast to these Ichidai-garo officers, the Karo officers from families that had produced a Karo officer for generations were called Eidai-garo (permanent Karo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="55">
<j>家老の異称として執政、参政を使うこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shissei or Sansei were also used for indicating Karo sometimes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shissei or Sansei were also used sometimes to indicate Karo.</e>
<cmt>for indicating&gt;to indicate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shissei or Sansei were also used sometimes to indicate Karo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="56">
<j>有能な者が実力によって、一代家老（家老格）に登用された代表例として、幕末に活躍した越後長岡藩の河井継之助、薩摩藩の調所広郷、長州藩の村田清風、そして、古くは元禄期の元禄赤穂事件の討ち入りで、有名になった赤穂藩の大野知房などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following were typical examples of Ichidai-garo officers who were appointed to the post due to their abilities: Tsugunosuke KAWAI in the Echigo-Nagaoka domain, Hirosato ZUSHO in the Satsuma domain, and Seifu MURATA all of whom played an active part towards the end of the bakufu system, and as an older example, Tomofusa ONO in the Ako domain who became famous for the raid in the Ako incident in the Genroku era (1688 - 1704).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following were typical examples of Ichidai-garo officers who were appointed to the post due to their abilities: Tsugunosuke KAWAI of Echigo-Nagaoka domain, Hirosato ZUSHO of Satsuma domain, and Seifu MURATA of Choshu domain, all of whom played an active part in the abolition of the bakufu system, and as an older example, Tomofusa ONO of Ako domain who became famous for launching a raid during the Ako incident in the Genroku era (1688 - 1704).</e>
<cmt>the...domain&gt;...domain. the raid&gt;launching a raid</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following were typical examples of Ichidai-garo officers who were appointed to the post due to their abilities: Tsugunosuke KAWAI of the Echigo-Nagaoka domain, Hirosato ZUSHO of the Satsuma domain, and Seifu MURATA of the Choshu domain, all of whom played an active part in the abolition of the bakufu system, and as an older example, Tomofusa ONO of the Ako domain who became famous for launching a raid during the Ako Incident in the Genroku era (1688 - 1704).</e>
<cmt>藩名はtheをつけることで統一しました。(用語統一リスト41による）incident→Incident</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>家老制の弊害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bad effects of the Karo system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Malpractice in the Karo system</e>
<cmt>bad effects&gt;malpractice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Malpractice in the Karo system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>家老は、特別な大藩を除き2人から数人程度、置かれたが、政治改革や世継ぎ問題に絡んで派閥抗争が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With two to several Karo officers placed, except in especially big domains, factional strife occurred in relation to political reforms or heir-related matters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though with two or more Karo officers were installed, except in especially large domains, factional strife still occurred in relation to political reforms and succession issues.</e>
<cmt>to several&gt;or more. placed&gt;installed. big&gt;large. heir-related matters&gt;succession issues.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though with two or more Karo officers were installed, except in especially large domains, factional strife still occurred in relation to political reforms and succession issues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>このような抗争が「お家騒動」の元凶となり、最悪の場合、改易にまで至ることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such strife caused &quot;a family feud,&quot; leading in the worst case to the abolishment of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such strife caused &quot;family feuds,&quot; leading in the worst cases to the abolishment of the family.</e>
<cmt>a family feud&gt;複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such strife caused &quot;family feuds,&quot; leading in the worst cases to the abolishment of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="59">
<j>また家老は、主君のための責任要員的な性格があったとの指摘もあり、主君の身代わりとして責任を取ることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also pointed out that the Karo post was provided with the feature of bearing responsibility instead of their master, and actually, some Karo officers took responsibility instead of their masters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has also been pointed out that the Karo post was had the feature of taking responsibility instead of one&apos;s master, and actually, some Karo officers took blows in place of their masters.</e>
<cmt>responsibilty&gt;blows. instead&gt;inplace of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has also been pointed out that the Karo post was had the feature of taking responsibility instead of one&apos;s master, and actually, some Karo officers took the blame in place of their masters.</e>
<cmt>blow→blame　の方がよいと思います</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>最悪の場合は、切腹や斬首を受ける形で、その責めを全うすることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the worst case, some Karo officers completed their duties through Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) or through decapitation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the worst cases, some Karo officers completed their duties as far as Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) or decapitation.</e>
<cmt>case&gt;cases. through&gt;as far as</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the worst cases, some Karo officers completed their duties as far as Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) or decapitation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>徳川家における家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karo in the Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karo in the Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karo in the Tokugawa family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>徳川氏ではこれに当たる役職を老中と呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tokugawa clan, the post corresponding to Karo was called Roju.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tokugawa clan, the post corresponding to Karo was called Roju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tokugawa clan, the post corresponding to Karo was called Roju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>江戸幕府開府後も、幕閣最高位の役職としてこの名を踏襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the Edo bakufu was established, this title name continued being used for the highest post available for the cabinet officials of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the Edo bakufu was established, this title continued to be used for the highest post available to cabinet officials of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>title name&gt;title. being&gt; to be</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the Edo bakufu was established, this title continued to be used for the highest post available to cabinet officials of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また、臨時の役職として老中の上に大老が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tairo post above Roju was placed temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A post called Tairo was also placed temporarily above Roju.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A post called Tairo was also placed temporarily above Roju.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ちなみに徳川氏がまだ三河国の一地方大名であった時代は、酒井家が家老（老中）連綿の家柄であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, when the Tokugawa family was a local daimyo in Mikawa Province, the Sakai family took the post of Karo (Roju) for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, when Tokugawa was still a local daimyo in Mikawa Province, the Sakai family took the post of Karo (Roju) for generations.</e>
<cmt>By the wayは話し言葉なので、Incidentally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, when Tokugawa was still a local daimyo in Mikawa Province, the Sakai family took the post of Karo (Roju) for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>また石川数正が家康の信任を得て、この職に昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting trust of Ieyasu, Kazumasa ISHIKAWA was promoted to this post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having gained Ieyasu&apos;s trust, Kazumasa ISHIKAWA was promoted to this post.</e>
<cmt>getting trust&gt;having gained trust</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having gained Ieyasu&apos;s trust, Kazumasa ISHIKAWA was promoted to this post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>陪臣の叙爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial court ranks for baishin (retainers of shogun&apos;s retainers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial court ranks for baishin (retainers of shogun&apos;s retainers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial court ranks for baishin (retainers of shogun&apos;s retainers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>尾張家・紀伊家・水戸家の御三家並びに加賀前田家の家老はそれぞれ決められた定数内で従五位下諸大夫へ叙爵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A specified number of Karo officers of the gosanke families of the Owari family, Kii family and Mito family, and of the Kaga-Maeda family were awarded Shodaibu at Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A specified number of Karo officers of the gosanke families of the Owari family, Kii family and Mito family, and of the Kaga-Maeda family were awarded Shodaibu at Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A specified number of Karo officers of the gosanke families of the Owari family, Kii family and Mito family, and of the Kaga-Maeda family were awarded Shodaibu at Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>前任者が死没・隠居し、欠員が発生した後に、主家より幕府へ推挙された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a Karo officer with a rank died or retired form the post, generating a vacancy for the rank post, a Karo officer was recommended for the rank post from the family to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a Karo officer with rank died or retired from the post, generating a vacancy, a Karo officer was recommended for the rank post from the family to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>a rank&gt;rank. form&gt;from.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a Karo officer with rank died or retired from the post, generating a vacancy, a Karo officer was recommended for the rank post from the family to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>叙爵した者は死没・隠居するまでその官位を保持していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When awarded the rank post, the Karo officer retained the rank until he died or retired from the post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When awarded the rank, the Karo officer retained it until he died or retired from the post.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When awarded the rank, the Karo officer retained it until he died or retired from the post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>通常の諸大夫成の場合、幕府より朝廷への年賀使として高家が上京する際に口宣頂戴奉書をまとめて持参し、その高家が口宣案をまとめて江戸へ持ち帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of gaining the ordinary shodaibusei rank, the officer from koke (a privileged family under Tokugawa Shogunate), who went to the Imperial court for New Year&apos;s greetings, put together Guzenchodaihosho (a document to solicit an order from the emperor) and brought it to the court, and brought back the Guzen-an (Imperial order for the solicitation) to Edo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処口宣頂戴奉書：　定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of gaining ordinary shodaibusei rank, an officer from a koke (a privileged family under the Tokugawa Shogunate), who went to the Imperial court for New Year&apos;s greetings, put together a Guzenchodaihosho (a document to solicit an order from the emperor) and brought it to the court, bringing back a Guzen-an (Imperial order for solicitation) to Edo.</e>
<cmt>Rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of gaining ordinary shodaibusei rank, an officer from a koke (a privileged family under the Tokugawa Shogunate), who went to the Imperial court for New Year&apos;s greetings, put together a Guzenchodaihosho (a document to solicit an order from the emperor) and brought it to the court, bringing back a Guzen-an (Imperial order for solicitation) to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかしながら、四品以上に叙爵される場合同様、幕府の許可後、各主家で独自に使者を派遣し、叙爵の手続きをとっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as in the case in which an imperial court rank of Shihon or higher was to be awarded, the master family sent the Imperial court a messenger to have the rank awarded, after getting approval from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処四品以上に昇進する大名家一覧以上に叙爵される場合同様、：　ウェッブ上の表現　”四品以上に叙爵される場合同様、”に変更した上で、訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in cases for instance where an imperial court rank of Shihon or higher was to be awarded, the master family sent the Imperial court a messenger to have the rank awarded, after getting approval from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>as in the case in which&gt;in cases for instance where</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the same way as in cases for instance where an imperial court rank of Shihon or higher was to be awarded, the master family sent the Imperial court a messenger to have the rank awarded, after getting approval from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>｢同様」を訳出する必要があります（一原文一訳文の例外対処）</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>尾張家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Owari family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Owari family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Owari family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>- 6名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Six Karo officers (the Takegoshi family and the Naruse family, both Otsuke-garo officers, were treated preferentially, with the Shodaibu rank permitted ordinarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Six Karo officers (the Takegoshi family and the Naruse family, both Otsuke-garo officers, were treated preferentially, with the usual Shodaibu rank permitted.</e>
<cmt>ordinarily&gt;the usual</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six Karo officers</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理()内の括弧を[]にしました。記号については削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>（御附家老竹腰氏・成瀬氏を優遇し、常時の諸大夫を許される。その他渡辺氏などが叙任）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Watanabe family was also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Watanabe family was also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Takegoshi family and the Naruse family, both Otsuke-garo officers, were treated preferentially, with the usual Shodaibu rank permitted. In addition, the Watanabe family was also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>紀伊家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kii family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kii family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kii family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>- 6名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Six Karo officers (the Ando family and the Mizuno family, both Otsuke-garo officers, were treated preferentially, with the Shodaibu rank permitted ordinarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Six Karo officers (the Ando family and the Mizuno family, both Otsuke-garo officers, were treated preferentially, with the usual Shodaibu rank permitted.</e>
<cmt>ordinarily&gt;the usual</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six Karo officers</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理　()内の括弧を[]にしました。記号については削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>（御附家老安藤氏・水野氏を優遇し、常時の諸大夫を許される。その他安房正木氏・岡野氏などが叙任）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, each of the Awamasaki family and the Okano family were also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, each of the Awamasaki family and the Okano family were also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Ando family and the Mizuno family, both Otsuke-garo officers, were treated preferentially, with the usual Shodaibu rank permitted. In addition, each of the Awamasaki family and the Okano family were also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="77">
<j>水戸家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mito family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Mito family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Mito family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>- 5名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Five Karo officers (the Nakayama family, the Otsuke-garo officer, was treated preferentially, with the Shodaibu rank permitted ordinarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Five Karo officers (the Nakayama family, the Otsuke-garo officer, were treated preferentially, with the usual Shodaibu rank permitted.</e>
<cmt>was&gt;were. ordinarily&gt;the usual</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five Karo officers</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理　()内の括弧を[]にしました。記号については削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>（御附家老中山氏を優遇し、常時の諸大夫を許される。その他雑賀氏・山野辺氏などが叙任）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, each of the Saiga family and the Yamanobe family were also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, each of the Saiga family and the Yamanobe family were also awarded a rank.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Nakayama family, the Otsuke-garo officer, were treated preferentially, with the usual Shodaibu rank permitted. In addition, each of the Saiga family and the Yamanobe family were also awarded a rank).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>前田家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Maeda family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Maeda family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Maeda family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>- 4名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">- Four Karo officers (the Honda family and the Maeda Tosa no Kami family, both retainers of the Maeda family, were treated preferentially, with the Shodaibu rank permitted ordinarily for each of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">- Four Karo officers (the Honda family and the Maeda Tosa no Kami family, both retainers of the Maeda family, were treated preferentially, with the Shodaibu rank permitted ordinarily for each of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four Karo officers</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理　()内の括弧を[]にしました。記号については削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>（加賀藩家臣より本多氏・前田土佐守家を優遇し、常時の諸大夫を許される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The Honda family and the Maeda Tosa no Kami family, both retainers of the Maeda family, were treated preferentially, with the Shodaibu rank permitted ordinarily for each of them.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>その他、駿河徳川家・甲府徳川家・館林徳川家・越前松平家・福井藩の陪臣叙爵があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, ranks were also given to baishin (retainers) of the Suruga-Tokugawa family, of the Kofu-Tokugawa family, of Tatebayashi-Tokugawa family, of the Echizen-Matsudaira family or of the Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, ranks were also given to baishin (retainers) of the Suruga-Tokugawa family, of the Kofu-Tokugawa family, of Tatebayashi-Tokugawa family, of the Echizen-Matsudaira family and of the Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt>or&gt;and</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, ranks were also given to baishin (retainers) of the Suruga-Tokugawa family, of the Kofu-Tokugawa family, of Tatebayashi-Tokugawa family, of the Echizen-Matsudaira family and of the Fukui domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>著名な家老</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Famous Karo officers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Famous Karo officers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Famous Karo officers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>直江兼続（米沢藩上杉家家老。戦国時代の上杉家の武将）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetsugu NAOE (a Karo officer of the Uesugi family in the Yonezawa domain. A busho (Japanese military commander) of the Uesugi family in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetsugu NAOE (a Karo officer of the Uesugi family in the Yonezawa domain. A busho (Japanese military commander) of the Uesugi family in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetsugu NAOE (a Karo officer of the Uesugi family in the Yonezawa domain. A busho [Japanese military commander] of the Uesugi family in the Sengoku period [Period of Warring States].)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="85">
<j>大石良雄（赤穂藩浅野家首席家老。元禄赤穂事件で名をあげ、忠臣蔵の主人公となった）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI (the chief Karo officer of the Asano family in the Ako domain. He became famous due to the Ako incident in the Genroku era, becoming the main character in the Chushingura story (a story of loyal retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshio OISHI (the chief Karo officer of the Asano family in the Ako domain. He became famous due to the Ako incident in the Genroku era, becoming the main character in the Chushingura story (a story of loyal retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshio OISHI (the chief Karo officer of the Asano family in the Ako domain. He became famous due to the Ako Incident in the Genroku era, becoming the main character in the Chushingura story [a story of loyal retainers].)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="86">
<j>多胡真蔭（津和野藩亀井氏家老。吉良上野介のイジメから藩主を守ったと伝わる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanekake TAKO (A Karo officer of the Kamei family in the Tsuwano domain. It is said that he protected the lord of his domain from bullying by Kira Kozuke no Suke.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanekake TAKO (A Karo officer of the Kamei family in the Tsuwano domain. It is said that he protected the lord of his domain from being bullied by Kira Kozuke no Suke.)</e>
<cmt>bullying&gt;being bullied</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanekake TAKO (A Karo officer of the Kamei family in the Tsuwano domain. It is said that he protected the lord of his domain from being bullied by Kira Kozuke no Suke.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="87">
<j>原田宗輔（仙台藩家老。伊達騒動の中心人物）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munesuke HARADA (A Karo officer of the Sendai domain. The central person in Date Sodo (the Date family disturbance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munesuke HARADA (A Karo officer of the Sendai domain. The central figure in Date Sodo (the Date family disturbance).</e>
<cmt>person&gt;figure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munesuke HARADA (A Karo officer of the Sendai domain. The central figure in Date Sodo [the Date family disturbance].)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="88">
<j>栗山利章（福岡藩家老。黒田騒動の中心人物）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiakira KURIYAMA (A Karo officer of the Fukuoka domain. The central person in Kuroda Sodo (the Kuroda family disturbance).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiakira KURIYAMA (A Karo officer of the Fukuoka domain. The central figure in Kuroda Sodo (the Kuroda family disturbance).</e>
<cmt>person&gt;figure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiakira KURIYAMA (A Karo officer of the Fukuoka domain. The central figure in Kuroda Sodo [the Kuroda family disturbance].)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="89">
<j>小栗正矩（越後国高田藩松平家首席家老。越後騒動の中心人物）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masanori OGURI (The chief Karo officer of the Matsudaira family in the Takada domain, Echigo Province. The central person in Echigo Sodo (a disturbance in Echigo)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masanori OGURI (The chief Karo officer of the Matsudaira family in the Takada domain, Echigo Province. The central figure in Echigo Sodo (a disturbance in Echigo)).</e>
<cmt>person&gt;figure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masanori OGURI (The chief Karo officer of the Matsudaira family in the Takada domain, Echigo Province. The central figure in Echigo Sodo [a disturbance in Echigo].)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="90">
<j>恩田民親（松代藩家老。藩財政再建に尽力）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamichika ONDA (A Karo Officer of the Matsushiro domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamichika ONDA (A Karo Officer of the Matsushiro domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamichika ONDA (A Karo Officer of the Matsushiro domain. He made efforts to rebuild domain finance.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="91">
<j>河合道臣（姫路藩酒井家家老。姫路藩政を改革し、負債完済に成功）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroomi KAWAI (A Karo officer of the Sakai family in the Himeji domain. He reformed the administration of the Himeji domain government, successfully completing the payment of all domain debts.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroomi KAWAI (A Karo officer of the Sakai family in the Himeji domain. He reformed the administration of the Himeji domain government, successfully completing payment of all domain debts.)</e>
<cmt>theを省略</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroomi KAWAI (A Karo officer of the Sakai family in the Himeji domain. He reformed the administration of the Himeji domain government, successfully completing payment of all domain debts.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="92">
<j>渡辺崋山（田原藩三宅氏家老。天保期の藩政改革で幕府より唯一表彰に預かる。蘭学者として有名）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE (A Karo officer of the Miyake family in the Tahara domain. Only he received an official commendation from the bakufu in the movements to reform domain government administration in the Tenpo era (1830 - 1844). He is famous as a Rangakusha scholar (a person who studied Western sciences thorough the Dutch language) as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan WATANABE (A Karo officer of the Miyake family in the Tahara domain. He was the only one to receive an official commendation from the bakufu in the movements to reform domain government administration in the Tenpo era (1830 - 1844). He is famous as a Rangakusha scholar (a person who studied Western sciences thorough the Dutch language) as well.</e>
<cmt>only he&gt;he was the only one</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE (A Karo officer of the Miyake family in the Tahara domain. He was the only one to receive an official commendation from the bakufu in the movements to reform domain government administration in the Tenpo era [1830 - 1844]. He is famous as a Rangakusha scholar [a person who studied Western sciences thorough the Dutch language] as well.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="93">
<j>調所広郷（薩摩藩家老。薩摩藩政の改革をおこなう）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirosato ZUSHO (A Karo officer in the Satsuma domain. He reformed the administration of the Satsuma domain government.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirosato ZUSHO (A Karo officer in the Satsuma domain. He reformed the administration of the Satsuma domain government.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirosato ZUSHO (A Karo officer in the Satsuma domain. He reformed the administration of the Satsuma domain government.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="94">
<j>安島帯刀（水戸藩家老。安政の大獄の際に井伊直弼に切腹させられた。のち勅命により名誉回復）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatewaki AJIMA (A Karo officer in the Mito domain. He was forced by Naosuke II to commit ritual suicide by disembowelment in Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate in the Ansei era (1854 - 1860). Later, his reputation was restored by an Imperial order).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatewaki AJIMA (A Karo officer in the Mito domain. He was forced by Naosuke II to commit ritual suicide by disembowelment in Ansei no Taigoku (suppression of extremists by the Shogunate in the Ansei era (1854 - 1860). Later, his reputation was restored by an Imperial order).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatewaki AJIMA (A Karo officer in the Mito domain. He was forced by Naosuke II to commit ritual suicide by disembowelment in Ansei no Taigoku [suppression of extremists by the Shogunate in the Ansei era (1854 - 1860)]. Later, his reputation was restored by an Imperial order.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="95">
<j>小松清廉（薩摩藩家老。明治維新の功労者の一人）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyokado KOMATSU (A Karo officer in the Satsuma domain. He was a person who rendered distinguished services in Meiji Restoration.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyokado KOMATSU (A Karo officer in the Satsuma domain. He was a person who rendered distinguished services in Meiji Restoration.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyokado KOMATSU (A Karo officer in the Satsuma domain. He was a person who rendered distinguished services in Meiji Restoration.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="96">
<j>西郷頼母（会津藩家老。戊辰戦争の際の会津藩首脳）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanomo SAIGO (A Karo officer in the Aizu domain. In Boshin Civil War, he was one of the main persons in the Aizu domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanomo SAIGO (A Karo officer in the Aizu domain. In Boshin Civil War, he was one of the main figures from the Aizu domain.</e>
<cmt>people&gt;figures</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanomo SAIGO (A Karo officer in the Aizu domain. In Boshin Civil War, he was one of the main figures from the Aizu domain.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が短いので、後列もこちらにまとめました。()内の括弧を[]にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Bakkai(id:7233), Reggaeman(id:6214), Tetsusaburou(id:58913), HI(id:72996), 牧野幕府(id:119716), 味っ子(id:17086), 高円寺藩(id:302968), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), NPD(id:58640), 海衛士(id:19229), 怪蘇(id:45514), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), こぶまき(id:38278), Yas(id:739), けんち(id:5147), Enter456(id:247777), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>