<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中富川の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of Nakatomigawa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle of Nakatomigawa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River</e>
<cmt>battleの頭文字を大文字に変更、Nakatomigawa→the Nakatomi-gawa Riverとしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中富川の戦い（なかとみがわのたたかい）は、1582年（天正10年）、四国統一を目指す土佐国の長宗我部元親と阿波国の十河存保との間で起きた一戦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River, in 1582, was a war between Motochika CHOSOKABE, a lord of Tosa Province, who intended to integrate Shikoku region, and Masayasu SOGO, a lord of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River, in 1582, was a battle between Motochika CHOSOKABE, a lord of Tosa Province, who intended to integrate the Shikoku region, and Masayasu SOGO, a lord of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River, in 1582, was a battle between Motochika CHOSOKABE, a lord of Tosa Province, who intended to integrate the Shikoku region, and Masayasu SOGO, a lord of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>battleの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>四国の川中島の戦いとも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called the battle of Kawanakajima in Shikoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called the battle of Kawanakajima in Shikoku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the Battle of Kawanakajima in Shikoku.</e>
<cmt>battleの頭文字を大文字に変更、was→isとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>戦いまでの経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the circumstances</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The circumstances</e>
<cmt>Capitalization</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circumstances</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>長宗我部元親は当初織田信長による四国征伐の備えで兵を休めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motochika CHOSOKABE had his troops stand by to prepare against the expediton to Shikoku by Nobunaga ODA</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motochika CHOSOKABE had his troops stand by to prepare against the expedition to Shikoku by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motochika CHOSOKABE had his troops stand by to prepare against the expedition to Shikoku by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし明智光秀による本能寺の変により信長が死んだ事により、三好康長は畿内に帰り危機は去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the crisis passed away when Nobunaga ODA was killed by Mitsuhide AKECHI in the Honoji incident and Yasunaga MIYOSHI left for Kinai Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the crisis passed away when Nobunaga ODA was killed by Mitsuhide AKECHI in the Honoji incident and Yasunaga MIYOSHI left for Kinai Province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the crisis passed away when Nobunaga ODA was killed by Mitsuhide AKECHI in the Honno-ji Incident and Yasunaga MIYOSHI left for Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>the Honoji incident→the Honno-ji Incident、Kinai Province→Kinai regionに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そこで元親の弟、香宗我部親泰や元親の嫡男、長宗我部信親は一気に勝瑞城を攻め落とそうと兵を進め一宮城 (阿波国)、夷山城を落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikayasu KOSOKABE, a younger brother of Motochika and Nobuchika CHOSOKABE, a legitimate child of Motochika put their troops forward to capture Shozui-jo Castle after seizing Ichinomiya-jo Castle (Awa Province) and Ebisuyama-jo Catsle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikayasu KOSOKABE, a younger brother of Motochika and Nobuchika CHOSOKABE, a legitimate child of Motochika put their troops forward to capture Shozui-jo Castle after seizing Ichinomiya-jo Castle (Awa Province) and Ebisuyama-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikayasu KOSOKABE, a younger brother of Motochika and Nobuchika CHOSOKABE, a legitimate child of Motochika put their troops forward to capture Shozui-jo Castle after seizing Ichinomiya-jo Castle (Awa Province) and Ebisuyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後岡豊城で一領具足を交えて軍議を開き、その結果阿波の完全制圧を目指す事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, having concil of war including ichiryo gusoku, the self-made rural samurai, they aimed to take complete control of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, having a council of war including ichiryo gusoku, the self-made rural samurai, they aimed to take complete control of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, having a council of war including ichiryo gusoku, the self-made rural samurai, they aimed to take complete control of Awa Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>元親は兵力増強の為、十五歳以上から六十歳までの領民の中で戦に参戦できる者を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motochika collected people age from 15 to 60, who could participate in the war to raise its troop strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motochika collected people aged from 15 to 60, who could participate in the war to raise his troop strength.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motochika collected people aged from 15 to 60, who could participate in the war to raise his troop strength.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中富川の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of the Nakatomi-gawa River</e>
<cmt>battleの頭文字を大文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>8月28日に中富川にて決戦の火蓋が切られた（兵力は長宗我部23000、十河6000）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 28, they opened fire at the Nakatomi-gawa River. (Chosokabe force 23000, Sogo force 6000)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 28, they opened fire at the Nakatomi-gawa River. (Chosokabe force 23000, Sogo force 6000)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 24, they opened fire at the Nakatomi-gawa River (Chosokabe force 23000, Sogo force 6000).</e>
<cmt>新暦に修正(年号は前出の1582年（天正10年）と判断)、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大方の予想では、十河側は勝瑞城に籠城すると見られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most people expected Sogo force would have confined themselves in the Shozui-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most people expected the Sogo force to have confined themselves in the Shozui-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most people expected the Sogo force to have confined themselves in the Shozui-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし十河側は野戦を選んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Sogo force chose field battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Sogo force chose field battle.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Sogo force chose field battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>十河側の先鋒が川を渡り始めるや長宗我部勢はあらかじめ上流の川をせき止めておいた堰を切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as the van of the Tokachi force crossed the river, Chosokabe force broke the dam, which they already had built to stop the flow at its upstream.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as the van of the Tokachi force crossed the river, the Chosokabe force broke the dam, which they already had built to stop the flow upstream.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as the van of the Sogo force crossed the river, the Chosokabe force broke the dam, which they already had built to stop the flow upstream.</e>
<cmt>Tokachi force→Sogo forceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>水を一気に流した為、十河兵は流される者が多数出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The flash flood swept away many Sogo soldiers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The flash flood swept away many Sogo soldiers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The flash flood swept away many Sogo soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後十河勢は総崩れとなり、勝瑞城へ退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Sogo force was routed and retreated into the Shozui-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Sogo force was routed and retreated into Shozui-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Sogo force was routed and retreated into Shozui-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 219.106の者(id:151047), 蚯蚓(id:254651), 河川一等兵(id:41231), 明鳳寺清松(id:220607), 睡眠学習(id:154363), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>