<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>沙沙貴山君</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasakiyama gimi or Sasakiyama no kimi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasakiyama gimi, or Sasakiyama no kimi</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasakiyama gimi</e>
<cmt>or Sasakiyama no kimi 削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>沙沙貴山君(ささきやまぎみ,ささきやまのきみ)は古代豪族の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sasakiyama gimi or Sasakiyama no kimi (沙沙貴山君) is one of the powerful families in the ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sasakiyama gimi, or Sasakiyama no kimi (沙沙貴山君), was one of the powerful families in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sasakiyama gimi, or Sasakiyama no kimi (沙沙貴山君), was one of the powerful families in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>狭々城山君とも書かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also written 狭々城山君.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also written as 狭々城山君.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also written as 狭々城山君.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>孝元天皇の皇子である大彦命を始祖とする阿倍臣一族とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered as the Abe clan founded by a prince of the Emperor Kogen, Obiko no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered as the Abe clan, which was founded by a prince of the Emperor Kogen, Obiko no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered as the Abe clan, which was founded by a prince of the Emperor Kogen, Obiko no Mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>蒲生・神崎両郡の大領として近江（現在の滋賀県）に勢力を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had power as the lord of Gamo-gun and Kanzaki-gun in Omi (presently Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had power as the lord of Gamo-gun and Kanzaki-gun in Omi (the present-day Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had power as the lord of Gamo County and Kanzaki County in Omi (the present-day Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>gun→County</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>祖先は陵戸(みささぎのへ)で沙沙貴(ささき)の名前も陵戸が変化した物と言う説があるが、日本書紀には「狭々城山君韓袋宿裲」（ささきやまぎみからふくろのすくね）が雄略天皇による押磐皇子謀殺に荷担したために罰せられ、死刑とする代わりに身分を落とし賤民である陵戸とされ全ての官籍を剥奪の上で山部連の下に置かれたが、同族の「置目老嫗」（おきめのおみな）が押磐皇子の遺骨の所在を知らせた功により置目老嫗の兄である「倭袋宿裲」が韓袋宿裲に代わり狭々城山君の姓を賜ったとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that the name Sasaki was changed from the ancestor&apos;s name Misasagi no He, however, in Nihonshoki it was written that &apos;Sasakiyama gimi Karafukuro no Sukune&apos; helped the Emperor Yuryaku to murder the prince Oshiha and therefore he was demoted to humble rank Ryoko instead of death penalty and transferred under Yamabe no muraji after deprived any title, but because &apos;Okime no Omina&apos; from his family told where the remains of the prince Oshiha were placed, &apos;Yamato Fukuro no Sukune&apos; was ginven the name Sasaki in place of Karafukuro no Sukune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that the name Sasaki was changed from the ancestor&apos;s name, Misasagi no He, but in Nihonshoki it was written that &apos;Sasakiyama gimi Karafukuro no Sukune&apos; helped the Emperor Yuryaku to murder Prince Oshiha and was therefore demoted to the humble rank of Ryoko instead of receiving the death penalty and was transferred under Yamabe no muraji after being deprived of any title; however, because &apos;Okime no Omina&apos; from his family confessed to where the remains of the prince Oshiha were placed, &apos;Yamato Fukuro no Sukune&apos; was given the name Sasaki in place of Karafukuro no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that the name Sasaki was changed from the ancestor&apos;s name, Misasagi no He, but in Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) it was written that &apos;Sasakiyama gimi Karafukuro no Sukune&apos; helped the Emperor Yuryaku to murder Prince Oshiha and was therefore demoted to the humble rank of Ryoko instead of receiving the death penalty and was transferred under Yamabe no muraji after being deprived of any title; however, because &apos;Okime no Omina&apos; from his family confessed to where the remains of the Prince Oshiha were placed, &apos;Yamato Fukuro no Sukune&apos;, who was the brother of Okime no Omina, was given the name Sasakiyama gimi in place of Karafukuro no Sukune.</e>
<cmt>日本書紀の定訳’→&apos;prince→PrinceSasaki→Sasakiyama gimi「置目老嫗の兄である」訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このことから、狭々城山君の姓は陵戸とは無関係に存在していたと考えられ、実際には仁徳天皇の名代である雀部(ささきべ／ささべ)を祖先とする一族だと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of that, it is thought that the family name of Sasakiyama gimi would be nothing to do with Misasagi no He and it would be a family descended from Sasakibe (or Sasabe) owned by the Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, it is thought that the family name of Sasakiyama gimi would have nothing to do with Misasagi no He but would instead be a family descended from Sasakibe (or Sasabe) owned by Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, it is thought that the family name of Sasakiyama gimi would have nothing to do with Misasagi no He but would instead be a family descended from Sasakibe (or Sasabe) owned by Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>owned　</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>沙沙貴山君一族は、平安時代までその勢力を保っており、いわゆる宇多源氏の佐々木氏の、少なくとも一部を構成したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the family Sasakiyama gimi which kept the power until the Heian period, was, at least, a part of the Sasaki clan from the Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the family Sasakiyama gimi, which maintained power until the Heian period, was at least a part of the Sasaki clan from the Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the family Sasakiyama gimi, which maintained power until the Heian period, was at least a part of the Sasaki clan from the Uda-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 伏儀(id:142093), 氷村(id:188228), Championship2006(id:38664), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>