<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>小柴垣草紙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koshibagaki Soshi&quot; (The Tale of the Brushwood Fence)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshibagaki Soshi</e>
<cmt>omit translation of title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshibagaki Zoshi</e>
<cmt>SoshiをZoshiに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>小柴垣草紙（こしばがきぞうし）は、絵巻物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koshibagaki Soshi&quot; (The Tale of the Brushwood Fence) is a picture scroll.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshibagaki Soshi (The Tale of the Brushwood Fence) is a picture scroll.</e>
<cmt>remove double quotes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshibagaki Zoshi (The Tale of the Brushwood Fence) is a picture scroll.</e>
<cmt>SoshiをZoshiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>小柴垣草子とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;Soshi&quot; can be represented in two ways by Chinese character, &quot;草紙&quot; and &quot;草子.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshibagaki Soshi, usually written as 小柴垣草紙 in kanji, can also be written as 小柴垣草子.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshibagaki Zoshi, usually written as 小柴垣草紙 in kanji, can also be written as 小柴垣草子.</e>
<cmt>SoshiをZoshiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>花山天皇朝寛和斎宮済子女王と野々宮における公役滝口平致光との密通の噂が流れ、ついには済子の伊勢行きが取りやめになったという、『十訓抄』にある物語に基づく秘戯図である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koshibagaki Soshi&quot; is drawings of a secret affair based on a story of &quot;Jikkinsho&quot; (Miscellany of Ten Maxims,) which says that a rumor went around about adultery between Princess Nariko, the vestal virgin princess serving at Ise Shrine during the reign of Emperor Kazan in Kanna era, and TAIRA no Munemitsu, a warrior of &quot;takiguchi&quot; (a special guard unit attached to the Chamberlain&apos;s Office,) and, because of the rumor, Princess Nariko&apos;s serving at Ise Shrine was cancelled at last.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshibagaki Soshi are drawings of a secret affair based on a story of Jikkinsho (Miscellany of Ten Maxims), which says that during the reign of Emperor Kazan in Kanna era, a rumor went around about adultery between Princess Nariko, the vestal virgin princess, and Taira no Munemitsu, a warrior of &quot;Takiguchi&quot; (a special guard unit attached to the Chamberlain&apos;s Office), which led to the cancellation of Princess Nariko&apos;s service at the Ise Shrine.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshibagaki Zoshi are drawings of a secret affair based on a story of &quot;Jikkinsho&quot; (Miscellany of Ten Maxims), which says that during the reign of Emperor Kazan in Kanna era, a rumor went around about adultery between Princess Nariko, the vestal virgin princess, and Taira no Munemitsu, a warrior of &quot;Takiguchi&quot; (a special guard unit attached to the Chamberlain&apos;s Office), which led to the cancellation of Princess Nariko&apos;s service at the Ise Shrine.</e>
<cmt>SoshiをZoshiに変更しました。原文の『』の部分に&quot; &quot;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>春画とも目される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The picture scroll is also regarded as &quot;shunga&quot; (pornographic painting.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The picture scroll is also regarded as a &quot;shunga&quot; (pornographic painting).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The picture scroll is also regarded as a &quot;shunga&quot; (pornographic painting).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>伝写本が少なくなく、さまざまな異本がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because quite a few copies of &quot;Koshibagaki Soshi&quot; were transcribed by hand, various versions of the picture scroll exist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because quite a few copies of the &quot;Koshibagaki Soshi&quot; were transcribed by hand, various versions of the picture scroll exist.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because quite a few copies of the &quot;Koshibagaki Zoshi&quot; were transcribed by hand, various versions of the picture scrolls exist.</e>
<cmt>SoshiをZoshiに変更しました。scrollをscrollsに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>画は藤原信実筆、詞は藤原為家筆とも、画は住吉慶恩筆、詞は久我通具筆ともいい、ほかに豊後法橋画というもの、土佐光則画というものなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The drawings and the texts of some versions were drawn by FUJIWARA no Nobuzane and written by FUJIWARA no Tameie, and those of other versions were drawn by Keion SUMIYOSHI and written by Michitomo KOGA, and some other versions were drawn by Bungo-hokkyo or Mitsunori TOSA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some versions had drawings drawn by Fujiwara no Nobuzane and text written by Fujiwara no Tameie, while some had drawings drawn by Keion Sumiyoshi and text written by Michitomo Koga, while others had drawings drawn by Bungo-hokkyo or Mitsunori Tosa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some versions had drawings drawn by Fujiwara no Nobuzane and text written by Fujiwara no Tameie, while some had drawings drawn by Keion Sumiyoshi and text written by Michitomo Koga, while others had drawings drawn by Bungo-hokkyo or Mitsunori Tosa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鎌倉時代末期の作であろうとも南北朝時代 (日本)末期の作であろうともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the original picture scroll was made at the end of Kamakura period or at the end of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the original picture scroll was made at the end of Kamakura period or towards the end of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the original picture scroll was made at the end of Kamakura period or towards the end of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Masyu(id:31065), Blizzardbreaker(id:248394), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>