<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>氷上川継の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu&apos;s Coup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu&apos;s War (a political event in Nara period)</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu&apos;s War (a political event in Nara period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>氷上川継の乱（ひかみのかわつぐのらん）は奈良時代の政治事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu&apos;s Coup was a political event in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu&apos;s War was a political event in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu&apos;s War was a political event in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天武天皇の曾孫の氷上川継が謀反を企てるが露見して失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu, the great-grandchild of Emperor Tenmu, planned the rebellion; however, the plan was exposed and failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu, the great-grandchild of Emperor Tenmu, planned the rebellion, however, the plan was exposed and failed.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu, the great-grandchild of Emperor Tenmu, planned the rebellion, however, the plan was exposed and failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>宝亀元年（770年）称徳天皇が崩御して、天智天皇の孫の白壁王が即位した（光仁天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 770 AD, Shirakabe no okimi, the grandchild of Emperor Tenchi, was enthroned (as Emperor Konin) after Emperor Shotoku died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 770, Shirakabe no okimi (Prince Shirakabe), the grandchild of Emperor Tenchi, was enthroned (as Emperor Konin) after Emperor Shotoku died.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 770, Shirakabe no okimi (Prince Shirakabe), the grandchild of Emperor Tenchi, was enthroned (as Emperor Konin) after Emperor Shotoku died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>壬申の乱以来、天武天皇の子孫が皇位を世襲してきたが、奈良期に打ち続いた政変で天武系の皇族の多くが殺されるか刑を受けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A descendant of Emperor Tenmu inherited the imperial throne after Jinshin Coup; however, many imperial family members from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu were either killed or punished due to continuous political changes during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A descendant of Emperor Tenmu inherited the imperial throne after Jinshin War, however, many Imperial Family members from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu were either killed or punished due to continuous political changes during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A descendant of Emperor Tenmu inherited the imperial throne after Jinshin War, however, many Imperial Family members from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu were either killed or punished due to continuous political changes during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため称徳天皇の死によって天武系の主流が断絶して、天智系の天皇が復活することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, mainstream factions of the Imperial line from Emperor Tenmu died out after the death of Emperor Shotoku, leading to the revival of the Imperial of Tenji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, mainstream factions of the Imperial line from Emperor Tenmu died out after the death of Emperor Shotoku, leading to the revival of the Imperial of Tenji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, mainstream factions of the Imperial line from Emperor Tenmu died out after the death of Emperor Shotoku, leading to the revival of the Imperial of Tenji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>氷上川継は塩焼王（氷上塩焼）と不破内親王（聖武天皇の皇女）の子で天武天皇の曾孫になるが、塩焼王が藤原仲麻呂の乱に与して処刑されたこともあり、皇嗣からは外されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu was the child of Prince Shioyaki (HIKAMI no Shioyaki) and Imperial Princess Fuwa (the Imperial princess of Emperor Shomu) and was also the great-grandchild of Emperor Tenmu; however, HIKAMI was disenthroned due to the execution of Prince Shioyaki from his involvemnt in FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s Coup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu was the child of Shioyaki no okimi (Prince Shioyaki or HIKAMI no Shioyaki) and Imperial Princess Fuwa (the Imperial princess of Emperor Shomu) and was also the great-grandchild of Emperor Tenmu, however, Hikami was dethroned due to the execution of Shioyaki no okimi from his involvement in FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HIKAMI no Kawatsugu was the child of Shioyaki no okimi (Prince Shioyaki or HIKAMI no Shioyaki) and Imperial Princess Fuwa (the Imperial princess of Emperor Shomu) and was also the great-grandchild of Emperor Tenmu, however, Hikami was dethroned due to the execution of Shioyaki no okimi from his involvement in FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>両親とも天武天皇の系統の川継こそが正統の皇位継承者であると考える者も少なくなかったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many believed that Kawatsugu, whose parents were both from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu, should be the legitimate succession to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many believed that Kawatsugu, whose parents were both from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu, should be the legitimate succession to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many believed that Kawatsugu, whose parents were both from the Imperial line of Emperor Tenmu, should be the legitimate succession to the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>天応 (日本)元年（781年）光仁天皇は皇太子の山部親王へ譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 781 AD, Emperor Konin enthroned Imperial Prince Yamabe, the Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 781, Emperor Konin enthroned Imperial Prince Yamabe, the Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 781, Emperor Konin enthroned Imperial Prince Yamabe, the Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>桓武天皇である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the enthronement of Emperor Kanmu was accomplished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the enthronement of Emperor Kanmu was accomplished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the enthronement of Emperor Kanmu was accomplished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>即位の翌年の延暦元年（782年）閏正月、川継の資人の大和乙人が武器を帯びて宮中に闖入して捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Intercalary January of 782 AD, the following year of enthronment, YAMATO no Otohito, a shijin (a lower rank officer of the Imperial or noble families, used as a guard or miscellaneous serviceman) of Kawatsugu, was captured after he entered the palace wearing weapons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, 782, the following year of the enthronement, YAMATO no Otohito, a shijin (a lower rank officer of the Imperial or noble families, used as a guard or miscellaneous serviceman) of Kawatsugu, was captured after he entered the palace wearing weapons.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、スペル修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, 782, the following year of the enthronement, YAMATO no Otohito, a shijin (a lower rank officer of the Imperial or noble families, used as a guard or miscellaneous serviceman) of Kawatsugu, was captured after he entered the palace wearing weapons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>訊問を受けた乙人は主人の川継の謀反を白状する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the hearing, Otohito confessed about the rebellion planned by Kawatsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the hearing, Otohito confessed about the rebellion planned by Kawatsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the hearing, Otohito confessed about the rebellion planned by Kawatsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その証言は同月10日夜に川継が一味を集めて北門から宮中に押し入り、朝廷を倒そうと云うものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His confession revealed Kawatsugu&apos;s plan to gather a group of people to break into the palace from Hokumon (the North gate), and overthrow the Imperial Court in the evening of the 10th of the same month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His confession revealed Kawatsugu&apos;s plan to gather a group of people to break into the palace from Hokumon (the North gate), and overthrow the Imperial Court in the evening of March 2.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His confession revealed Kawatsugu&apos;s plan to gather a group of people to break into the palace from Hokumon (the North gate), and overthrow the Imperial Court in the evening of March 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>直ちに川継を捕らえるため勅使が派遣されるが、川継はいち早く逃亡してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the confession, the Imperial envoy was sent to capture Kawatsugu: however, Kawatsugu was already gone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the confession, the Imperial envoy was sent to capture Kawatsugu, however, Kawatsugu was already gone.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the confession, the Imperial envoy was sent to capture Kawatsugu, however, Kawatsugu was already gone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>間もなく、同月14日に川継は大和国葛上郡に潜伏しているところを捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 14th of the same month, Kawatsugu was captured while he was hiding in Katsuragi no Kamikoori, Yamato no Kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 14, the same month, Kawatsugu was captured while he was hiding in Katsujo County, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 14, the same month, Kawatsugu was captured while he was hiding in Katsujo County, Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>川継の罪は極刑に値するところ、死一等を減じられて伊豆国へ流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though the crime that Kawatsugu committed was deserving of the punishment of death, he instead received a lower punishment and was exiled to Izu no kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though the crime that Kawatsugu committed was deserving of the punishment of death, he instead received a lower punishment and was exiled to Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though the crime that Kawatsugu committed was deserving of the punishment of death, he instead received a lower punishment and was exiled to Izu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>母の不破内親王と川継の姉妹は淡路国へ流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His mother, Imperial Princess Fuwa, and his sisters were exiled to Awaji no kuni.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His mother, Imperial Princess Fuwa, and his sisters were exiled to Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His mother, Imperial Princess Fuwa, and his sisters were exiled to Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この事件に連座して川継の舅である参議・藤原浜成（藤原京家）は大宰員外帥に左遷され、京家は二代目にして早くも没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of being implicated in the incident, Sangi (a councilor) FUJIWARA no Hamanari (the FUJIWARA Kyoke; the Western House of the Fujiwara clan), his father-in-law, was demoted to the Dazai no ingai no sochii and the Kyoke collapsed at only the second generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of being implicated in the incident, Sangi (a councilor) FUJIWARA no Hamanari (the Capital House of the Fujiwara clan), his father-in-law, was demoted to the Dazai no ingai no sochi (an outer official of the Dazaifu) and the Capital House collapsed at only the second generation.</e>
<cmt>用語補足し、統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of being implicated in the incident, Sangi (a councilor) FUJIWARA no Hamanari (the Capital House of the Fujiwara clan), his father-in-law, was demoted to the Dazai no ingai no sochi (an outer official of the Dazaifu) and the Capital House collapsed at only the second generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また山上船主、三方王、参議・大伴家持、右衛士督・坂上苅田麻呂らも処罰を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, YAMANOUE no Funanushi, Mikata, Sangi OTOMO no Yakamochi, Ueji no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) SAKANOUE no Karitamaro were also punished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, YAMANOUE no Funanushi, Mikata no okimi, Sangi OTOMO no Yakamochi, Ueji no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) SAKANOUE no Karitamaro were also punished.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, YAMANOUE no Funanushi, Mikata no okimi, Sangi OTOMO no Yakamochi, Ueji no kami (Captain of the Right Division of Outer Palace Guards) SAKANOUE no Karitamaro were also punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>（家持、苅田麻呂は嫌疑がはれてもとの地位に復している）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Yakamochi and Karitamaro cleared their suspicions and regained to their ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Yakamochi and Karitamaro cleared their suspicions and regained to their ranks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Yakamochi and Karitamaro cleared their suspicions and regained to their ranks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>同年5月、右大臣藤原魚名が罷免されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May of the same year, Udaijin FUJIWARA no Uona was discharged from his office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, Udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Uona was discharged from his office.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year, Udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Uona was discharged from his office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>『続日本紀』には罪状についての記録はないが、川継の事件に連座したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no record about Uona&apos;s crime in &quot;Shlunihongi&quot;; however, it is thought that he was implicated in Kawatsugu&apos;s incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no record about Uona&apos;s crime in &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; however, it is thought that he was implicated in Kawatsugu&apos;s incident.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no record about Uona&apos;s crime in &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; however, it is thought that he was implicated in Kawatsugu&apos;s incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>この事件によって天武系の皇族は完全に皇位継承から排除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, the Imperial family from Emperor Tenmu line was completely removed from the succession of the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, the Imperial family from Emperor Tenmu line was completely removed from the succession of the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, the Imperial family from Emperor Tenmu line was completely removed from the succession of the Imperial Throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>桓武天皇の崩御後の大同 (日本)元年（806年）川継は罪を許されて従五位下に復している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 806, after the death of Emperor Kenmu, the crime of Kawatsugu was forgiven and he returned to Jugoi no ge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 806, after the death of Emperor Kenmu, the crime of Kawatsugu was forgiven and he returned to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 806, after the death of Emperor Kenmu, the crime of Kawatsugu was forgiven and he returned to Jugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Masyu(id:31065), 味っ子(id:17086), Novo(id:87875), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>