<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>番役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banyaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banyaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banyaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>番役（ばんやく）とは、日本史上において順番に交替勤務にあたること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Banyaku refers to working different shifts by rotation in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Banyaku refers to working different shifts by rotation in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Banyaku refers to working different shifts by rotation in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>律令制における衛士上番や平安時代中期以後における大番（天皇・上皇の御所や摂関家の邸宅警備）などの朝廷関係機関を警備する番役が古くから存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From old times, there existed Banyaku in charge of guarding institutions related to the Imperial Court such as Eji-joban (serving in Eji (guard) by coming up to Kyoto from a province) in the Ritsuryo system, Oban (guard for the imperial palace of the emperor and retired emperor, and residence of Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) in and after the mid Heian period, and so on.</e>
<cmt>衛士上番→Eji-joban (serving in Eji (guard) by coming up to Kyoto from a province)[衛士上番とは、地方から京にのぼって、衛士の任務につくこと（Yahoo!辞書ーじょうばん【上番】より）なので、英訳を変更し、また「衛士」は職名を表す固有名詞なので、大文字にて表記しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From old times, there existed Banyaku in charge of guarding institutions related to the Imperial Court such as Eji-joban (serving in Eji [guard] by coming up to Kyoto from a province) in the Ritsuryo system, Oban (guard for the imperial palace of the emperor and retired emperor, and residence of Sekkan-ke [the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor]) in and after the mid Heian period, and so on.</e>
<cmt>・カッコ内カッコを訂正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From old times, there existed Banyaku in charge of guarding institutions related to the Imperial Court such as Eji-joban (serving in Eji [guard] by coming up to Kyoto from a province) in the Ritsuryo system, Oban (guard for the imperial palace of the emperor and retired emperor, and residence of Sekkan-ke [the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor]) in and after the mid Heian period, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉幕府は全国の御家人に御家人役と呼ばれる軍役の一環として各種の番役をかけるとともに、朝廷に対する番役負担の一部を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) imposed various kinds of Banyaku on Gokenin (shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu) across the country as part of military service called Gokeninyaku, and succeeded to part of load of Banyaku to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) imposed various kinds of Banyaku on Gokenin (shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu) across the country as part of military service called Gokeninyaku, and succeeded to part of load of Banyaku to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) imposed various kinds of Banyaku on Gokenin (shogunal retainers of the Kamakura bakufu) across the country as part of military service called Gokeninyaku, and succeeded to part of load of Banyaku to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>最大のものは大番役と呼ばれるもので、京都の大番を継承した「京都大番役」と同様に鎌倉にあった将軍御所や幕府機関を警備する「鎌倉大番役」が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The biggest one was called Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto), and as well as &apos;Kyoto Obanyaku&apos; inheriting Oban in Kyoto, there existed &apos;Kamakura Obanyaku&apos; which guarded a Shogun&apos;s palace and governmental institutions in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The biggest one was called Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto), and as well as &apos;Kyoto Obanyaku&apos; inheriting Oban in Kyoto, there existed &apos;Kamakura Obanyaku&apos; which guarded a Shogun&apos;s palace and governmental institutions in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The biggest one was called Obanyaku (a job to guard Kyoto), and as well as &apos;Kyoto Obanyaku&apos; inheriting Oban in Kyoto, there existed &apos;Kamakura Obanyaku&apos; which guarded a Shogun&apos;s palace and governmental institutions in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>令制国の守護は国内の御家人を大番役に従事させるために必要な権限が与えられており（「大番催促」）、大犯三箇条のうちの1つに数えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo (provincial constable) in ryoseikoku (province) was granted authority necessary to cause Gokenin in the province to engage in Obanyaku (&apos;Oban-saisoku (Shugo&apos;s authority to command Gokenin, lower ranked vassals to guard Kyoto), and such authority was regarded as one of Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo (provincial constable) in ryoseikoku (province) was granted authority necessary to cause Gokenin in the province to engage in Obanyaku (&apos;Oban-saisoku (Shugo&apos;s authority to command Gokenin, lower ranked vassals to guard Kyoto), and such authority was regarded as one of Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo (provincial constable) in ryoseikoku (province) was granted authority necessary to cause Gokenin in the province to engage in Obanyaku (&apos;Oban-saisoku (Shugo&apos;s authority to command Gokenin, lower ranked vassals to guard Kyoto), and such authority was regarded as one of Taibon Sankajo (three major tasks of peacekeeping).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>元寇を機に異国警固番役が追加された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of Mongol invasion attempts against Japan, Ikokukeigobanyaku (military service imposed on Gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) in the Kyushu area by bakufu in order to provide against the invasion of Yuan dynasty) was added.</e>
<cmt>異国警固番役→Ikokukeigobanyaku (military service imposed on Gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) in the Kyushu area by bakufu in order to provide against the invasion of Yuan dynasty)[対訳・定訳では、Ikokukeigobanyaku (military service imposed to gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) in the Kyushu area by bakufu in order to provide against the invasion of Yuan dynasty)と表記されておりますが、「人に課す場合は、&quot;impose something on someone&quot;なので、&quot;to&quot;を&quot;on&quot;に変更し、また、「御家人」は上記において大文字にて表記しているので、これに合わせました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of Mongol invasion attempts against Japan, Ikokukeigobanyaku (military service imposed on Gokenin [immediate vassals of the shogunate] in the Kyushu area by bakufu in order to provide against the invasion of Yuan dynasty) was added.</e>
<cmt>・カッコ内カッコを訂正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the occasion of Mongol invasion attempts against Japan, Ikokukeigobanyaku (military service imposed on Gokenin [immediate vassals of the shogunate] in the Kyushu area by bakufu in order to provide against the invasion of Yuan dynasty) was added.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>