<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>座頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>座頭（ざとう）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zato</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zato</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸期における盲人の階級の一。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zato is one of the social classes of the blind people during the Edo peroid in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zato is one of the social classes of the blind during the Edo period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>peopleを削除しました。 Peroidのミススペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zato is one of the social classes of the blind during the Edo period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>またこれより転じて按摩、鍼灸、琵琶法師などへの呼びかけとしても用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word had also come to be used to refer to masseurs, acupuncturists, and biwa-playing minstrels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word had also come to be used to refer to masseurs, acupuncturists, and biwa-playing minstrels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word had also come to be used to refer to masseurs, acupuncturists, and biwa-playing minstrels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>由来 - 当道座</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of this word is Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of this word is Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of this word is Todo-za (the traditional guild for the blind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>元々は平曲を演奏する琵琶法師の称号として呼ばれた「検校（けんぎょう）」、「別当（べっとう）」、「勾当（こうとう）」、「座頭（ざとう）」に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word was orignally one of the titles for a biwa-playing minstrel who played Heikyoku (a narrative which features the Tale of the Heike playing Biwa music): kengyo (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za), betto (superintendent), Koto (the third title of the official ranks within the Todo-za), and zato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word was originally one of the titles for biwa-playing minstrels who played Heikyoku (a narrative which features the Tale of the Heike playing Biwa music): &apos;Kengyo&apos; (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za), &apos;Betto&apos; (superintendent), &apos;Koto&apos; (the third title of the official ranks within the Todo-za), and &apos;Zato.&apos;</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word was originally one of the titles for biwa-playing minstrels who played Heikyoku (a narrative which features the Tale of the Heike playing Biwa music): &apos;Kengyo&apos; (the highest title of the official ranks within the Todo-za), &apos;Betto&apos; (superintendent), &apos;Koto&apos; (the third title of the official ranks within the Todo-za), and &apos;Zato.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>古来、琵琶法師には盲目の人々が多かったが、『平家物語』を語る職業人として鎌倉時代頃から「当道座」と言われる団体を形作るようになり、それは権威としても互助組織としても、彼らの座（組合）として機能した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Biwa-playing ministrels, who were often blind from ancient times, began forming a group called &apos;Todo-za,&apos; a group of professionals who narrated the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heiki), from around the Kamakura period, and this association (za) functioned as the authority and an organization that provided mutual aid for the members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Biwa-playing minstrels, who were often blind from ancient times, began forming a group called &apos;Todo-za,&apos; a group of professionals who narrated the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike), from around the Kamakura period, and this association (za) functioned as the authority and an organization that provided mutual aid for the members.</e>
<cmt>Heikiのミススペルを修正しました。Ministrelsのミススペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Biwa-playing minstrels, who were often blind from ancient times, began forming a group called &apos;Todo-za,&apos; a group of professionals who narrated the &quot;Heike Monogatari&quot; (Tale of the Heike), from around the Kamakura period, and this association (za) functioned as the authority and an organization that provided mutual aid for the members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その中で定められていた集団規則によれば、彼らは検校、別当、勾当、座頭の四つの位階に、細かくは73の段階に分けられていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to their group regulations of their associations, they had four main social classes: kengyo, betto, koto, and zato, however, the total number of all the social classes of the biwa-playing ministrels was 73.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to group regulations of the association, they were divided into four official court ranks: Kengyo, Betto, Koto, and Zato, and further divided into 73 ranks.</e>
<cmt>groupの前のtheirを削除しました。social classesをofficial ranksに変更しました。原文により忠実になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to group regulations of the association, they were divided into four official court ranks: Kengyo, Betto, Koto, and Zato, and further divided into 73 ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これらの官位段階は、当道座に属し職分に励んで、申請して認められれば、一定の年月をおいて順次得ることができたが、大変に年月がかかり、一生かかっても検校まで進めないほどだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was possible to make a request and get higher official court ranks as long as they belonged to Todo-za and fulfilled their responsibilities of their job, however, it took so much time to gain a higher position that they could not even promote to kengyo in their whole life.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was possible to make a request and get higher official court ranks as long as they belonged to Todo-za and fulfilled their responsibilities of their job, however, it took so much time to gain a higher position that they could not even promote to kengyo in their whole life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was possible to make a request and get higher official court ranks as long as they belonged to Todo-za and fulfilled their responsibilities of their job, however, it took so much time to gain a higher position that they could not even promote to kengyo in their whole life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため金銀によって早期に官位を取得することも出来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was allowed to get a higher official position faster by exchanging it with money.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was allowed to get a higher official position faster by exchanging it with money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was allowed to get a higher official position faster by exchanging it with money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代に入ると当道座は盲人団体として幕府の公認と保護を受けるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period, Todo-za received the official permission and protection as the group of blind people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, Todo-za received the official permission and protection as the group of the blind.</e>
<cmt>AfterをInに変更しました。Blind peopleをthe blindに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, Todo-za received the official permission and protection as the group of the blind.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この頃には平曲は次第に下火になり、それに加え地歌三味線、箏曲、胡弓等の演奏家、作曲家としてや、鍼灸、按摩が当道座の主要な職分となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, Heikyoku became gradually unpopular and the main jobs of Todo-za became the players or composers of juta shamisen (traditional Japanese shamisen music), sokyoku (koto music), kokyu (Chinese fiddle), acupunctures, and masseurs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Heikyoku became gradually unpopular and the main jobs of Todo-za became the players or composers of jiuta shamisen (traditional Japanese shamisen music), sokyoku (koto music), kokyu (Chinese fiddle), acupunctures, and masseurs.</e>
<cmt>jutaのミススペルを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Heikyoku became gradually unpopular and the main jobs of Todo-za became the players or composers of jiuta shamisen (traditional Japanese shamisen music), sokyoku (koto music), kokyu (Chinese fiddle), acupunctures, and masseurs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>結果としてこのような盲人保護政策が、江戸時代の音楽や鍼灸医学の発展の重要な要素になったと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, these protection policies of the blind became a major cause for the development of music during the Edo period and acupuncture technology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, these protection policies of the blind became a major cause for the development of music during the Edo period and acupuncture technology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, these protection policies of the blind became a major cause for the development of music during the Edo period and acupuncture technology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また座頭相撲など見せ物に就く者たちもいたり、元禄頃から官位昇格費用の取得を容易にするために高利の金貸しが公認されたので、悪辣な金融業者となる者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, some blind people worked in the show business such as zato sumo or unscrupulous moneylenders, because high interst money lending business to help the blind to spend it as the payment used to request for the promotion of official court ranks was permitted from around the Genroku era, which started in 1688.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, some blind people worked in the show business such as zato sumo or became unscrupulous moneylenders because high interest money lending business was officially approved around the Genroku era to help the blind to get money for the promotion of the official court rank.</e>
<cmt>意味が明瞭になるように左記のように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, some blind people worked in the show business such as zato sumo or became unscrupulous moneylenders because high interest money lending business was officially approved around the Genroku era to help the blind to get money for the promotion of the official court rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>当道に対する保護は、明治元年（1868年）に廃止されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, It is said that the protection for the blind was abolished in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that the protection for the blind was abolished in 1868.</e>
<cmt>ItのIを小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that the protection for the blind was abolished in 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Cprobot(id:97843), Wapp(id:87866), Eekus(id:87677), Neeeee(id:86826), Mixtures(id:29234), Macss(id:87864), Point136(id:211299), NIKE(id:16342), Hermes(id:21387), Fwng3431(id:31854), 詠狸庵(id:41048), Gombe(id:27), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>