<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>集外三十六歌仙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugai Sanjurokkasen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugai Sanjurokkasen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugai Sanjurokkasen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>集外三十六歌仙（しゅうがいさんじゅうろっかせん）は、室町時代から江戸時代初頭にかけての歌人を三十六歌仙に倣って取り上げたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugai Sanjurokkasen is a collection of poems by 36 poets from Muromachi period to early Edo period following the example of Sanjurokkasen (36 Master Poets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugai Sanjurokkasen is a collection of poems by 36 poets from the Muromachi Period to the early Edo Period following the example of Sanjurokkasen (36 Master Poets).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugai Sanjurokkasen is a collection of poems by 36 poets from the Muromachi period to the early Edo period following the example of Sanjurokkasen (36 Master Poets).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「集外」は二十一代集に載せられなかったとの意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shugai&quot; means that they were not included in Nijuichidai-shu (the twenty-one collections of waka poems compiled by imperial command).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shugai&quot; means that they were not included in Nijuichidai-shu (the twenty-one collections of waka poems compiled by imperial command).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugai&apos; means that they were not included in Nijuichidai-shu (the 21 collections of waka poems compiled by imperial command).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション等を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後水尾天皇の勅撰と伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said to be personally selected by Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said to have been personally selected by Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said to have been personally selected by Emperor Gomizunoo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>公家歌人が撰ばれず、武将歌人や連歌師が多いのが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The collection is characterized by the fact that many of the poets included are not court noble poets, but they are warrior-poets and renga-shi (linked verse poets).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The collection is characterized by the fact that many of the poets included are not court noble poets, but warrior-poets and renga-shi (linked verse poets).</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The collection is characterized by the fact that many of the poets included are not court noble poets, but warrior-poets and renga-shi (linked verse poets).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>姫路市立美術館に酒井抱一が描いた集外三十六歌仙の画帖が収蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himeji City Museum of Art houses an album by Hoitsu SAKAI depicting the scenes from Shugai Sanjurokkasen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Himeji City Museum of Art houses an album by Hoitsu SAKAI depicting scenes from Shugai Sanjurokkasen.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Himeji City Museum of Art houses an album by Hoitsu SAKAI depicting scenes from Shugai Sanjurokkasen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 桂鷺淵(id:151322), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>