<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>閑院流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanin-ryu (one of the Fujiwara clique)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanin-ryu (a linage of court noble of a branch one of the Fujiwara clique)</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanin-ryu (a linage of court noble of a branch one of the Fujiwara clique)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>閑院流（かんいんりゅう）とは、三条家・西園寺家・徳大寺家をはじめとする藤原北家支流の公家の一門。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanin-ryu is a kuge or court noble&apos;s family of a branch of FUJIWARA Hokke (one of the four FUJIWARA family lines) including the Sanjo Family, the Saionji Family, or the Tokudaiji family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanin-ryu was a linage of kuge (court noble) of a branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan including the Sanjo Family, the Saionji Family, or the Tokudaiji family.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanin-ryu was a linage of kuge (court noble) of a branch of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan including the Sanjo Family, the Saionji Family, or the Tokudaiji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>院政期に外戚の立場を得たことで大きな勢力を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family came into power by gaining maternal relatives in the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family came into power by gaining maternal relatives in the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired emperor).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family came into power by gaining maternal relatives in the insei period (during the period of the government by the retired emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>藤原道長の叔父・閑院大臣藤原公季に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanin-ryu was originated from FUJIWARA no Kinsue, Kanin minister, an uncle of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanin-ryu was originated from FUJIWARA no Kinsue, Kanin minister, an uncle of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanin-ryu was originated from FUJIWARA no Kinsue, Kanin minister, an uncle of FUJIWARA no Michinaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>閑院はもともと北家繁栄の基礎を築いた藤原冬嗣の邸宅で、公季がこれを伝領し住み、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代初期にかけては里内裏としても使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kainin was originally the residence of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu who formed the basis of Hokke&apos;s prosperity and Kinsue inherited it and lived there, and the residence was also used as a satodairi (a temporary palace) from the end of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanin was originally the residence of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu who formed the basis of the Northern House&apos;s prosperity, before it was inherited and lived by Kinsue, then it was also used as a satodairi (a temporary palace) from the end of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>スペル、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanin was originally the residence of FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu who formed the basis of the Northern House&apos;s prosperity, before it was inherited and lived by Kinsue, then it was also used as a satodairi (a temporary palace) from the end of the Heian period to the early Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>公季は、入内させた娘に皇子女はできなかったものの、道長の執政下において長く内大臣の任にあって道長政権を支え、右大臣を経て晩年には太政大臣に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though his daughter whom he made judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) had no Imperial princes and princesses, Kinsue held the post of Minister of the Palace for a long time under the administration of Michinaga and supported Michinaga&apos;s government and was promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) in his last days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although his daughter whom he made judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) had no Imperial princes and princesses, Kinsue held the post of Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace) for a long time under the administration of Michinaga to support the Michinaga&apos;s government then he was promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) in his last days after appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。訳漏れ。「右大臣を経て」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although his daughter whom he made judai (an Imperial Consort&apos;s bridal entry into court) had no Imperial princes and princesses, Kinsue held the post of Naidaijin (Minister of the Palace) for a long time under the administration of Michinaga to support the Michinaga&apos;s government then he was promoted to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state) in his last days after appointed to Udaijin (Minister of the Right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>3代目の藤原公成の娘藤原茂子が藤原能信の養女として後三条天皇に入内し白河天皇を生んだ頃から代々の天皇の外戚として権勢を振るうようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He started to dominate the power as a maternal relative of the emperor for generations from around when FUJIWARA no Moshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinnari, the third, became an adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu and married Emperor Gosanjo and had the child, the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He started to dominate the power as a maternal relative of the emperor for generations from around when FUJIWARA no Moshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinnari, the third, became an adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu and married Emperor Gosanjo to have the child, the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He started to dominate the power as a maternal relative of the emperor for generations from around when FUJIWARA no Moshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinnari, the third, became an adopted daughter of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu and married Emperor Gosanjo to have the child, the Emperor Shirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>すなわち、4代藤原実季の娘藤原苡子は鳥羽天皇の生母、5代藤原公実の娘藤原璋子は崇徳天皇・後白河天皇の生母となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, FUJIWARA no Ishi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Sanesue, the fourth, became the real mother of Emperor Toba and FUJIWARA no Shoshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinzane, the fifth, became the real mother of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, FUJIWARA no Ishi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Sanesue, the fourth, became the biological mother of Emperor Toba and FUJIWARA no Shoshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinzane, the fifth, became the biological mother of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, FUJIWARA no Ishi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Sanesue, the fourth, became the biological mother of Emperor Toba and FUJIWARA no Shoshi, the daughter of FUJIWARA no Kinzane, the fifth, became the biological mother of Emperor Sutoku and Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鳥羽即位時、公実は摂関家の若年の当主藤原忠実を侮り、幼帝の外舅の地位にある自分こそ摂政に就任すべしと主張したが、「四代もの間、諸大夫として仕えた者が今摂関を望むとは」と白河院別当の源俊明に一蹴された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Toba ascended the throne, Kinzane took lightly FUJIWARA no Tadazane, young family head of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) and argued that he himself who had been at the position of maternal father of young emperor should have assumed the post of Sekkan (regent to the emperor), but he was scoffed at by MINAMOTO no Toshiaki, Chief of the Office of the Retired Emperor Shirakawa, reproving that the man who had served for four emperors as Shodaibu still tried to seek the post of Sekkan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Toba ascended the throne, Kinzane took lightly FUJIWARA no Tadazane, young family head of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) and argued that he himself who had been at the position of maternal father of the young Emperor should have assumed the post of Sessho (regent to the emperor), but he was scoffed at by MINAMOTO no Toshiaki, Chief of the Office of the Retired Emperor Shirakawa, reproving that &apos;the man who had served for four emperors as Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than court nobles) still tried to seek the post of Sekkan (regent and adviser).&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Toba ascended the throne, Kinzane took lightly FUJIWARA no Tadazane, young family head of Sekkan-ke (line of regents and advisers) and argued that he himself who had been at the position of maternal father of the young Emperor should have assumed the post of Sessho (regent to the emperor), but he was scoffed at by MINAMOTO no Toshiaki, Chief of the Office of the Retired Emperor Shirakawa, reproving that &apos;the man who had served for four emperors as Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than court nobles) still tried to seek the post of Sekkan (regent and adviser).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この公実の子の代に至り、三条・西園寺・徳大寺の主要三家に分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinzane&apos;s children generation, the family split into three families of Sanjo, Saionji, and Tokudaiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the generation of Kinzane&apos;s children, the family split into three major families of Sanjo, Saionji, and Tokudaiji.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the generation of Kinzane&apos;s children, the family split into three major families of Sanjo, Saionji, and Tokudaiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>閑院流藤原氏は、三条・西園寺・徳大寺家および西園寺家庶流の菊亭家が摂家に次ぐ家格の清華家、三条家庶流の正親町三条家および三条西家がそれに次ぐ大臣家となって公家中に重きをなし、他にも羽林家として19家があって一門繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanin-ryu FUJIWARA family included Sanjo, Saionji, Tokudaiji families, and the Kikutei family, a branch family of the Saionji family, that became the Seiga family, the next Kakaku (family status) rank after Sekke, and the Ogimachisanjo family and the Sanjonishi family, branch families of the Sanjo family, that became the next rank of house of minister, and they had influence among court nobles, and there were 16 other families as the Urin family and the entire family was blessed with prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Fujiwara clan of the Kanin-ryu, four families as Sanjo, Saionji, Tokudaiji, and Kikutei, a branch family of the Saionji family, becoming the Seiga family, the next Kakaku (family status) rank after Sekke, and two families as Ogimachisanjo and Sanjonishi, both were branch of the Sanjo family, becoming the Daijin family (the house of minister), the rank after the Seiga family, had influence among court nobles, and they were blessed with prosperity along with 19 other families such as the Urin family.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Fujiwara clan of the Kanin-ryu, four families as Sanjo, Saionji, Tokudaiji, and Kikutei, a branch family of the Saionji family, becoming the Seiga family, the next Kakaku (family status) rank after Sekke, and two families as Ogimachisanjo and Sanjonishi, both were branch of the Sanjo family, becoming the Daijin family (the house of minister), the rank after the Seiga family, had influence among court nobles, and they were blessed with prosperity along with 19 other families such as the Urin family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>一門諸家の当主について、一部を除いて代々「公」と「実」を交互に名前の一字とするのを例としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the family&apos;s custom to use alternately Chinese characters, &quot;公&quot; and &quot;実&quot;, in the names of family heads of each clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some exception but it was the family&apos;s custom to alternately use the Chinese characters &apos;公&apos; and &apos;実&apos; in the names of the head of the families.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some exception but it was the family&apos;s custom to alternately use the Chinese characters &apos;公&apos; and &apos;実&apos; in the names of the head of the families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また「季」も通字として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;季&quot; was also used as tsuji (distinctive character used in the names of all people belonging to a single clan or lineage).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">季&apos; was also used as tsuji (distinctive character used in the names of all people belonging to a single clan or lineage).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">季&apos; was also used as tsuji (distinctive character used in the names of all people belonging to a single clan or lineage).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 エルシード(id:122427), Andee(id:20421), Richknight(id:141069), Blueroses5327(id:97718), 伊集院聖(id:53199), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>