<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豊臣政権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Toyotomi Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toyotomi Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toyotomi Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豊臣政権（とよとみせいけん）は、天正18年（1590年）、（ただし、実質的には天正13年（1585年））から、慶長8年（1603年）まで成立していた豊臣氏による日本国の政権。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Toyotomi government was a Japanese government ruling the country from 1590 (in fact, 1585) to 1603.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toyotomi government was a Japanese government that ruled the country from 1590 (in fact, 1585) to 1603.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toyotomi government was a Japanese government that ruled the country from 1590 (in fact, 1585) to 1603.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>豊臣氏政権（とよとみしせいけん）とも言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called the Toyotomi-clan government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the Toyotomi-clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the Toyotomi-clan government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief Personal History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>政権確立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of the government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>天正10年（1582年）6月2日 (旧暦)、織田信長が明智光秀によって討たれた（本能寺の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 2, 1582, Nobunaga ODA was killed by Mitsuhide AKECHI (the Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 2, 1582, Nobunaga ODA was killed by Mitsuhide AKECHI (the Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 2, 1582, Nobunaga ODA was killed by Mitsuhide AKECHI (the Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このとき、中国方面総司令官として備中にあった信長の家臣豊臣秀吉は、直ちに毛利輝元と講和して軍を東に返して、明智光秀を討った（山崎の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who was a vassal of Nobunaga&apos;s, and in Bicchu (the western part of Okayama Prefecture) as a commander in chief of the force coming from around Chugoku region, imediately made a peace treaty with Terumoto MORI, lead his army back to east and killed Mitsuhide AKECHI (the Battle of Yamazaki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, a vassal of Nobunaga&apos;s, who was in Bicchu (the western part of Okayama Prefecture) as a commander in chief of the forces coming from around the Chugoku region, immediately made a peace treaty with Terumoto MORI, lead his army back east and killed Mitsuhide AKECHI (the Battle of Yamazaki).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, a vassal of Nobunaga&apos;s, who was in Bicchu (the western part of Okayama Prefecture) as a commander in chief of the forces coming from around the Chugoku region, immediately made a peace treaty with Terumoto MORI, lead his army back east and killed Mitsuhide AKECHI (the Battle of Yamazaki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>光秀を討った功績により、秀吉の発言力は他の織田家臣を圧倒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That great achievement made Hideyoshi&apos;s forcefulness of speech overpower Nobunaga&apos;s other vassals.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this great achievement Hideyoshi&apos;s forcefulness of speech overpowered Nobunaga&apos;s other vassals.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this great achievement, Hideyoshi&apos;s forcefulness of speech overpowered Nobunaga&apos;s other vassals.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>清洲会議において柴田勝家が推薦する織田信孝（信長の三男）を抑えて、信長の嫡孫である織田秀信（織田信忠の嫡男）を信長の後継者として擁立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Kiyosu conference, Hideyoshi decided to elect Hidenobu ODA (the eldest son of Nobutada ODA) as the successor to Nobunaga, over Nobutaka ODA (Nobunaga&apos;s third son) recommended by Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Kiyosu conference, Hideyoshi decided to elect Hidenobu ODA (the eldest son of Nobutada ODA) as the successor to Nobunaga, over Nobutaka ODA (Nobunaga&apos;s third son) who was recommended by Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Kiyosu conference, Hideyoshi decided to elect Hidenobu ODA (the eldest legitimate son of Nobutada ODA) as the successor to Nobunaga, over Nobutaka ODA (Nobunaga&apos;s third son) who was recommended by Katsuie SHIBATA.</e>
<cmt>eldest → eldest legitimate</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>翌年には、反秀吉の急先鋒であった柴田勝家と織田信孝を賤ヶ岳の戦いにおいて滅ぼし、滝川一益を降した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, Hideyoshi killed Katsuie SHIBATA and Nobutaka ODA, the banguards of anti-Hideyoshi group in the Battle of Shizugatake and made Kazumasu TAKIGAWA surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, Hideyoshi killed Katsuie SHIBATA and Nobutaka ODA, the vanguards of the anti-Hideyoshi group at the Battle of Shizugatake and made Kazumasu TAKIGAWA surrender.</e>
<cmt>reword. Spelling.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, Hideyoshi killed Katsuie SHIBATA and Nobutaka ODA, the vanguards of the anti-Hideyoshi group at the Battle of Shizugatake and made Kazumasu TAKIGAWA surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そして前田利家や金森長近ら旧織田家臣を自分の配下として組み込んだ秀吉は、信長の事実上の後継者としての地位を確立するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After having old vassals of the Oda clan, including Toshiie MAEDA and Nagachika KANAMORI work under him, Hideyoshi made himself the actual successor to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After having old vassals of the Oda clan, including Toshiie MAEDA and Nagachika KANAMORI work under him, Hideyoshi made himself the actual successor to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After having old vassals of the Oda clan, including Toshiie MAEDA and Nagachika KANAMORI work under him, Hideyoshi made himself the actual successor to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>これに不満を持った織田信雄（信長の次男）が、天正12年（1584年）に信長の盟友であった徳川家康と結んで、反秀吉の兵を挙げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobukatsu ODA, Nobunaga&apos;s second son, who was discontent with that, raised an anti-Hideyoshi army in 1584 with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had been an ally of Nobunaga&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobukatsu ODA, Nobunaga&apos;s second son, who was discontent with this, raised an anti-Hideyoshi army in 1584 with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had been an ally of Nobunaga&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobukatsu ODA, Nobunaga&apos;s second son, who was discontent with this, raised an anti-Hideyoshi army in 1584 with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who had been an ally of Nobunaga&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>兵力的には秀吉軍が圧倒的に優勢であったが、家康の巧みな戦術の前に秀吉軍は小牧・長久手の戦いで局地的に敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hideoyoshi&apos;s force of arms overpowerd Ieyasu&apos;s, Hideyoshi was defeated locally, at Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, since Ieyasu was a superb tactician.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hideoyoshi&apos;s military force overpowered Ieyasu&apos;s, Hideyoshi was defeated locally, at the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, because Ieyasu was a superb tactician.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hideoyoshi&apos;s military force overpowered Ieyasu&apos;s, Hideyoshi was defeated locally, at the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, because Ieyasu was a superb tactician.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかしその後、織田信雄は秀吉の強大な兵力に圧迫され、家康に相談なく秀吉と単独講和する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, however, Hideyoshi&apos;s tremendous force bore upon Nobuo, who made a peace treaty all by himself without a counsel with Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, however, Hideyoshi&apos;s tremendous force bore upon Nobuo, who made a peace treaty all by himself without counsel from Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, however, Hideyoshi&apos;s tremendous force bore upon Nobukatsu, who made a peace treaty all by himself without counsel from Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>Nobuo→Nobukatsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>信雄と秀吉の講和により、家康も秀吉と戦うための大義名分を失いひとまず和議に応じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the treaty, Ieyasu no longer had any legitimate reason to fight against Hideyoshi and accepted a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this treaty, Ieyasu no longer had any legitimate reason to fight against Hideyoshi and accepted a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this treaty, Ieyasu no longer had any legitimate reason to fight against Hideyoshi and accepted a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>天正13年（1585年）、秀吉は前年・前々年の戦いで常に自らの背後を脅かした紀伊国の諸勢力（紀州攻め）、四国の長宗我部元親（四国平定）を相次いで攻略した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1585, Hideyoshi attacked and captured several forces in Kii Province(attack on Kishu) and Motochika CHOSOKABE in Shikoku region(subjugation of Shikoku); they had threatened Hideyoshi from behind during the former two years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1585, Hideyoshi attacked and captured several forces in Kii Province (attack on Kishu) and Motochika CHOSOKABE in the Shikoku region (subjugation of Shikoku); they had threatened Hideyoshi behind his back over the last two years.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1585, Hideyoshi attacked and captured several forces in Kii Province (attack on Kishu) and Motochika CHOSOKABE in the Shikoku region (subjugation of Shikoku); they had threatened Hideyoshi behind his back over the last two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>またこの年7月、関白相論を経て正親町天皇より関白に任じられ、翌年には豊臣姓も下賜された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July that year, Hideyoshi was nominated as to be Kanpaku(chief adviser to the Emperor) after &apos;kanpaku soron&apos; (disagreement over Kanpaku position) and in the following year, the family name, &apos;the Toyotomi clan&apos; was given to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July that year, Hideyoshi was nominated to be the Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) after &apos;kanpaku soron&apos; (disagreement over Kanpaku position) and in the following year, the family name, &apos;the Toyotomi clan&apos; was given to him.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July that year, Hideyoshi was nominated to be the Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) after &apos;kanpaku soron&apos; (disagreement over Kanpaku position) and in the following year, the family name, &apos;the Toyotomi clan&apos; was given to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは、秀吉が朝廷から天下の実力者として認められ、朝廷から政治を委任されたことを意味している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It meant that the imperial court admitted that Hideyoshi was the most powerful person in Japan and that the court delegated him the authority to rule Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This meant that the imperial court admitted that Hideyoshi was the most powerful person in Japan and that the court delegated him the authority to rule Japan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This meant that the imperial court admitted that Hideyoshi was the most powerful person in Japan and that the court delegated him the authority to rule Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>つまりこの時点で、事実上の豊臣政権が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, the Toyotomi government was literally established at that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, the Toyotomi government was in fact established at that point.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, the Toyotomi government was in fact established at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>全国統一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The unification of the whole country</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The unification of the whole country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The unification of the whole country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>天正14年（1586年）、秀吉は生母の大政所を人質として家康のもとへ送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1586, Hideyoshi sent his real mother, Omandokoro (the mother of a Kanpaku), to Ieyasu as a hostage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1586, Hideyoshi sent his real mother, Omandokoro (the mother of a Kanpaku), to Ieyasu as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1586, Hideyoshi sent his real mother, Omandokoro (the mother of a Kanpaku), to Ieyasu as a hostage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>こうして遂に家康も秀吉に臣従せざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That finally made Ieyasu serve Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This finally made Ieyasu serve Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This finally made Ieyasu serve Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、この頃には越後国の上杉景勝、安芸国の毛利輝元らも、秀吉に臣従することを誓っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Kagekatsu UESUGI in Echigo Province, Terumoto MORI in Aki Province and others pleadged alliance to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Kagekatsu UESUGI in Echigo Province, Terumoto MORI in Aki Province and others pledged allegiance to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Kagekatsu UESUGI in Echigo Province, Terumoto MORI in Aki Province and others pledged allegiance to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして天正15年（1587年）には九州を席捲しつつあった薩摩国の島津義久を惣無事令に違反したとして討ち秀吉の前に遂に屈服させ（九州平定）、西国は完全に豊臣氏の支配下に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, Hideyoshi attacked and captured Yoshihisa SHIMAZU, who was going to control Kyushu, by condemning him for having broken &apos;Ou Sobujirei (peace edict for Ou region)&apos; (the subjugation of Kyushu), which meant the western part of Japan was completely under Hideyoshi&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, Hideyoshi attacked and captured Yoshihisa SHIMAZU, who was going to control Kyushu, by condemning him for having broken &apos;Ou Sobujirei&apos; (peace edict for Ou region) (the subjugation of Kyushu), which meant the western part of Japan was completely under Hideyoshi&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>moved apostrophe</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, Hideyoshi attacked and captured Yoshihisa SHIMAZU, who was going to control Kyushu, by condemning him for having broken &apos;Ou Sobujirei&apos; (peace edict for Ou region) (the subjugation of Kyushu), which meant the western part of Japan was completely under Hideyoshi&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>惣無事令に違反した北条氏政・北条氏直親子を、天正18年（1590年）、23万人の大兵力を動員して攻略（小田原攻め）、さらに東北の伊達政宗や最上義光らも秀吉に臣従することを誓い（奥州仕置）、ここに豊臣政権のもとに天下統一は成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1590, Hideyoshi, with his tremendous military force of 230.000 soldiers, attacked and captured Ujimasa HOJO and his son, Ujinao, who had broken &apos;Ou Sobujirei&apos;(Attack of Odawara), and Masamune DATE, Yoshiaki MOGAMI and others in Tohoku (the northeast) region pledged alliance to Hideyoshi (Oshu Shioki (approach to punish the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power); the whold country was unified under the Toyotomi goverment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1590, Hideyoshi, with his tremendous military force of 230,000 soldiers, attacked and captured Ujimasa HOJO and his son, Ujinao, who had broken &apos;Ou Sobujirei&apos; (Attack of Odawara), and Masamune DATE, Yoshiaki MOGAMI and others in Tohoku (the northeast) region pledged allegiance to Hideyoshi (Oshu Shioki (approach to punish the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power)); and by this the whole country was unified under the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1590, Hideyoshi, with his tremendous military force of 230,000 soldiers, attacked and captured Ujimasa HOJO and his son, Ujinao, who had broken &apos;Ou Sobujirei&apos; (Attack of Odawara), and Masamune DATE, Yoshiaki MOGAMI and others in Tohoku (the northeast) region pledged allegiance to Hideyoshi (Oshu Shioki (approach to punish the powerful warriors in the area of Oshu, to prevent them from strengthening their power)); and by this the whole country was unified under the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この時点で、豊臣政権は日本全国に威令が及ぶ日本の統一政権として成立したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the Toyotomi government was established as the only government that could give orders to any place in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the Toyotomi government was established as the only government that could give orders to any place in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the Toyotomi government was established as the only government that could give orders to any place in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>天下統一が如実に表れているのが、天正19年（1591年）に起こった九戸政実の乱であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kunohe-masazane-no-ran (the Rebellion of Masazane KUNOHE), which occurred in 1591, proved Hideyoshi&apos;s unification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kunohe-masazane-no-ran (the Rebellion of Masazane KUNOHE), which occurred in 1591, proved Hideyoshi&apos;s unification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kunohe-masazane-no-ran (the Rebellion of Masazane KUNOHE), which occurred in 1591, proved Hideyoshi&apos;s unification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>南部氏は自力での討伐をできず、秀吉は蒲生氏郷・石田三成らを大将に6万人の軍勢を奥州の僻地に派遣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Nanbu clan could not subdue Masazane, Hideyoshi sent the military force of 60,000 soldiers, with Ujisato GAMO and Mitsunari ISHIDA and others as their leaders, to the remote rural areas in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Nanbu clan could not subdue Masazane, Hideyoshi sent a military force of 60,000 soldiers, with Ujisato GAMO and Mitsunari ISHIDA and others as their leaders, to the remote rural areas in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing the Mutsu and Dewa provinces).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Nanbu clan could not subdue Masazane, Hideyoshi sent a military force of 60,000 soldiers, with Ujisato GAMO and Mitsunari ISHIDA and others as their leaders, to the remote rural areas in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing the Mutsu and Dewa provinces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>室町幕府第8代将軍・足利義政以来の室町幕府にはできなかったことであり、ここに豊臣秀吉の天下一統が成ったと見てよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi Bakufu of the post-eighth shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA could not have attained such a thing, which meant Hideyoshi&apos;s unification of Japan was established at that point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi Bakufu of the post-eighth shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, could not have attained such a thing, which indicated that Hideyoshi&apos;s unification of Japan was fully established at that point.</e>
<cmt>Reword. Unsure why &quot;Muromachi&quot; is red.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi Bakufu of the post-eighth shogun, Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA, could not have attained such a thing, which indicated that Hideyoshi&apos;s unification of Japan was fully established at that point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>文禄の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bunroku War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bunroku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bunroku War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>全国統一を達成した秀吉は、文禄元年（1592年）、明の征服を目指して、全国諸大名に李氏朝鮮への出兵を命じた（文禄の役）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1592 (the first year in the Bunroku era), Hideyoshi, who had unified the nation, ordered &apos;daimyo(feudal lords&apos; all over the country to dispatch troops to Joseon Dynasty (Korea) in order to conquer Ming (the Bunroku War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1592 (the first year in the Bunroku era), Hideyoshi, who had unified the nation, ordered &apos;daimyo&apos; (feudal lords) all over the country to dispatch troops to the Joseon Dynasty (Korea) in order to conquer Ming (the Bunroku War).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1592 (the first year in the Bunroku era), Hideyoshi, who had unified the nation, ordered &apos;daimyo&apos; (feudal lords) all over the country to dispatch troops to the Joseon Dynasty (Korea) in order to conquer Ming (the Bunroku War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>倭寇や女真族との紛争以外本格的な戦争経験がない朝鮮正規軍を、戦国時代 (日本)を経て大量の鉄砲を装備した日本軍が圧倒し連戦連勝を重ねた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean regular force, which had never experienced a full-scale war except troubles with &apos;wako(Japanese pirates)&apos; or the Joshin tribe, was overwhelmed and always defeated by the Japanese military force, which were equipped with a large amount of guns after the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean regular force, which had never experienced a full-scale war except troubles with &apos;wako&apos; (Japanese pirates) or the Joshin tribe, was overwhelmed and completely defeated by the Japanese military force, which were equipped with a large amount of guns after the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean regular force, which had never experienced a full-scale war except troubles with &apos;wako&apos; (Japanese pirates) or the Joshin tribe, was overwhelmed and completely defeated by the Japanese military force, which was equipped with a large amount of guns after the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>were　→ was</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また朝鮮民衆の協力もあり、王都ソウル特別市や平壌を次々と占領するなど朝鮮領土の大部分を占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the cooperation of Korean people, the Japanese force conquered most parts of Korea by conquering the capital, Seoul Special City, and Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the cooperation of the Korean people, the Japanese forces conquered most parts of Korea by conquering the capital, Seoul Special City, and Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>I believe the &quot;special&quot; could be removed from &quot;Seoul Special City&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the cooperation of the Korean people, the Japanese forces conquered most parts of Korea by conquering the capital, Seoul Special City, and Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>これに対し、李氏朝鮮の特権階級であった両班は各地で民衆を組織化し義兵軍を編成して反抗を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yangban&apos;,traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynast, organized Korean people at various places, formed a volunteer army and started fighting against the Japanese force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yangban&apos;, traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty, organized Korean people at various places, formed a volunteer army and started fighting against the Japanese forces.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yangban&apos;, traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty, organized Korean people at various places, formed a volunteer army and started fighting against the Japanese forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>海上では李舜臣率いる朝鮮水軍に敗北した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At sea, the Japanese force was defeated by the Korean Navy led by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At sea, the Japanese force was defeated by the Korean Navy led by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At sea, the Japanese force was defeated by the Korean Navy led by Yi Sun-sin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このため戦線を縮小し防御体制を取って翌年に備えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, the Japanese force decided to prepare for the next year by drawing dawn its battle line and digging in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, the Japanese force decided to prepare for the next year by drawing down its battle line and digging in.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, the Japanese force decided to prepare for the next year by drawing down its battle line and digging in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）になると、朝鮮に明軍が本格的に来援し攻勢に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1593, Ming helped Korea in a full-scale way and went on an offensive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1593, Ming gave its full support to Korea and went on the offensive.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1593, Ming gave its full support to Korea and went on the offensive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>明・朝鮮軍は平壌を抜き漢城に迫ったが、日本軍は碧蹄館の戦いでこれを撃破する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ming-Korean army occupied Pyongyang and came close to Hanseong, but the Japanese force defeated them at the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming-Korean army occupied Pyongyang and came close to Hanseong, but the Japanese forces defeated them at the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming-Korean army occupied Pyongyang and came close to Hanseong, but the Japanese forces defeated them at the Battle of Hekitenkai (ByeogJe Gwan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>以後戦線は膠着し、日本軍は兵糧不足に陥り、明軍は数万匹の馬が餓死するなど、双方が兵站に苦しむこととなると、講和交渉が開始され休戦に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, the battle line was in a stalemate and both suffered from logistic problems; the Japanese force ran out of provisions while the Ming lost hundreds of thousands of horsesforce because of starvation, which led to the discussion of a peace treaty and then to the agreement to truce.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, the battle drew to a stalemate as both sides suffered from logistical problems; the Japanese forces ran out of provisions while the Ming lost hundreds of thousands of horses due to starvation, which led to the discussion of a peace treaty and then to a truce agreement.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, the battle drew to a stalemate as both sides suffered from logistical problems; the Japanese forces ran out of provisions while the Ming lost hundreds of thousands of horses due to starvation, which led to the discussion of a peace treaty and then to a truce agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>秀次事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>文禄2年（1593年）に、秀吉に実子の豊臣秀頼が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1593, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, Hideyoshi&apos;s biological child was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1593, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, Hideyoshi&apos;s biological child was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1593, Hideyori TOYOTOMI, Hideyoshi&apos;s biological child was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>秀吉はすでに実子の誕生をあきらめて、養子の豊臣秀次（秀吉の甥）を後継者に指名していたが、文禄4年（1595年）に謀反の容疑で秀次およびその一族を全て処刑した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi, who had given up having his biological child and designated his adopted son, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI (Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew) to be as his successor, executed Hidetsugu and his family on suspicion of a rebellion in 1595.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi, who had given up having his own biological child become his successor, designated his adopted son, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI (Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew) to be his successor, and executed Hidetsugu and his family on suspicion of a rebellion in 1595.</e>
<cmt>reword.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi, who had given up having his own biological child become his successor, designated his adopted son, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI (Hideyoshi&apos;s nephew) to be his successor, and executed Hidetsugu and his family on suspicion of a rebellion in 1595.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これは秀吉が秀頼を後継者にするためだったともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu is said to have been executed so that Hideyoshi could make Hideyori his successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu is said to have been executed so that Hideyoshi could make Hideyori his successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu is said to have been executed so that Hideyoshi could make Hideyori his successor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>慶長の役と秀吉の死</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keicho Campaign and Hideyoshi&apos;s death</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keicho Campaign and Hideyoshi&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keicho Campaign and Hideyoshi&apos;s death</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>石田三成、小西行長らによって進められていた明との講和は決裂し、慶長2年（1597年）には再び、朝鮮出兵が行なわれた（文禄・慶長の役慶長の役）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The peace treaty with Ming, which Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI and others promoted, broke down, and in 1597 (the second year of the Keicho era), the second dispatch of troops to Korea was conducted (the Bunroku-Keicho War/ Keicho War).</e>
<cmt>（文禄・慶長の役慶長の役）は（文禄・慶長の役・慶長の役）と考えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peace treaty with Ming, which Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI and others promoted, broke down, and in 1597 (the second year of the Keicho era), the second dispatch of troops to Korea was conducted (the Bunroku-Keicho War/ Keicho War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peace treaty with Ming, which Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI and others promoted, broke down, and in 1597 (the second year of the Keicho era), the second dispatch of troops to Korea was conducted (the Bunroku-Keicho War/ Keicho War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>『浅野家文書』によると、この再出兵の目的は赤国（全羅道）を残らず成敗し、余力をもって青国（忠清道）その他を討つこととされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Asanoke monjo (the document of the Asano family), the purpose of the second dispatch was to punish the red country (Jeolla Province) completely, and then conquer the blue country (Chungcheong Province) and other areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Asanoke monjo (the records of the Asano family), the purpose of the second dispatch was to punish the red country (Jeolla Province) completely, and then conquer the blue country (Chungcheong Province) and other areas.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Asanoke monjo (the records of the Asano family), the purpose of the second dispatch was to punish the red country (Jeolla Province) completely, and then conquer the blue country (Chungcheong Province) and other areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>日本軍は、漆川梁海戦で朝鮮水軍を壊滅させると進撃を開始し、たちまち全羅道の道都全州を占領、忠清道の稷山で明軍と交戦（稷山の戦い：双方とも自軍の勝利と記録）した後、京畿道 (朝鮮八道)の安城市・竹山まで進撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having wiped out the Korean navy at The naval Battle of Chilcheollyang, the Japanese force made an attack, conquered cities of Chonju of Jeolla Province, fought against the Ming force at Shokusan (the Battle of Shokusan: both forces recorded they had won.), and made an attack to Chikusan, Anjo-city of Gyeonggi Province (Eight Provinces of Korea).</e>
<cmt>「道都全州」の定訳が分かりませんでした。「安城市・竹山」の読み方・定訳が分かりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having wiped out the Korean navy at The naval Battle of Chilcheollyang, the Japanese forces attacked and conquered the cities of Chonju of Jeolla Province, fought against the Ming force at Shokusan (the Battle of Shokusan: both forces recorded they had won.), and also attacked Chikusan, Anjo-city of Gyeonggi Province (Eight Provinces of Korea).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having wiped out the Korean navy at The naval Battle of Chilcheollyang, the Japanese forces attacked and conquered the cities of Chonju of Jeolla Province, fought against the Ming force at Shokusan (the Battle of Shokusan: both forces recorded they had won.), and also attacked Chikusan, Anjo-city of Gyeonggi Province (Eight Provinces of Korea).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>日本軍は約２ヶ月で全羅道、忠清道を席巻し、京畿道への進出を果たすと、冬を前に朝鮮半島南岸に撤収し、各地に新たな城（倭城）の築城を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having conquered Jeolla Province, Chungcheong Province and advanced into Gyeonggi Province within about two months, the japanese force returned to the southern shore of Korean Peninsula before winter and started the establishment of new castles (Japanese castles) in various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having conquered Jeolla Province, Chungcheong Province and advanced into Gyeonggi Province within about two months, the Japanese forces returned to the southern shore of the Korean Peninsula before winter and started the establishment of new castles (Japanese castles) in various places.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having conquered Jeolla Province, Chungcheong Province and advanced into Gyeonggi Province within about two months, the Japanese forces returned to the southern shore of the Korean Peninsula before winter and started the establishment of new castles (Japanese castles) in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その中で最も東端に位置する蔚山城が未完成のまま、年末から翌慶長3年（1598年）初めにかけて明・朝鮮軍の攻撃を受けるが撃退に成功する（第一次蔚山城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Urusan-jo Castle, at the eastmost edge, was under the construction, the Japanese force was attacked by the Ming-Korean force from the end of 1597 to the beginning of 1599, the Japanese fought the enemy off (the first Battle of Ulsan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Urusan-jo Castle, at the east most edge of Korea, was under construction, the Japanese forces were attacked by the Ming-Korean forces from the end of 1597 to the beginning of 1599; the Japanese fought the enemy off (the first Battle of Ulsan).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Urusan-jo Castle, at the east most edge of Korea, was under construction, the Japanese forces were attacked by the Ming-Korean forces from the end of 1597 to the beginning of 1598; the Japanese fought the enemy off (the first Battle of Ulsan).</e>
<cmt>和暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="43">
<j>9月末から10月初めにかけて明・朝鮮軍は総力を挙げた攻勢をかけ、日本軍の順天城、泗川城、蔚山城を攻撃したがすべて撃退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Ming-Korean force waged all-out war and attacked Junten-jo, Shisen-jo and Urusan-jo Castles, which had been established by the Japanese force, from the end of September to the beginning of October in 1599, the Japanese force fought them off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite the Ming-Korean forces waging all-out war and attacking Junten-jo, Shisen-jo and Urusan-jo Castles, which had been established by the Japanese forces, from the end of September to the beginning of October in 1599, the Japanese forces fought them off.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite the Ming-Korean forces waging all-out war and attacking Junten-jo, Shisen-jo and Urusan-jo Castles, which had been established by the Japanese forces, from the beginning of October to the end of October in 1598, the Japanese forces fought them off.</e>
<cmt>和暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>特に泗川城では島津義弘が明・朝鮮軍を大破した（泗川の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU smashed up the Ming-Korean force at Shisen-jo Castle (the Battle of Sacheon).</e>
<cmt>「泗川城」と「泗川」における「泗川」の英訳が用語集で異なっています。用語集のままにしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU devastated the Ming-Korean force at Shisen-jo Castle (the Battle of Sacheon).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU devastated the Ming-Korean force at Shisen-jo Castle (the Battle of Sacheon).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>明・朝鮮軍の総力を挙げた攻勢を撃退した日本軍であったが、既に8月18日に秀吉は死去していた（享年62）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Japanese force fought off the all-out attack from the Ming-Korean force, Hideyoshi had already died on August 18 (died at 62).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Japanese forces fought off the all-out attack from the Ming-Korean forces, Hideyoshi had already died on August 18th (died at the age of 62).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Japanese forces fought off the all-out attack from the Ming-Korean forces, Hideyoshi had already died on September 18th (died at the age of 62).</e>
<cmt>和暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このため10月になって朝鮮からの帰国命令が発せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The order to return to Japan was issued in October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The order to return to Japan was issued in October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The order to return to Japan was issued in November.</e>
<cmt>和暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>帰国段階で明・朝鮮水軍の妨害を受け、露梁海戦を戦うことになるが、11月末までに全軍帰国を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although on their way back to Japan, the Japanese force was hindered by the Ming-Korean navy and fought the Battle of Noryang, all returned to Japan by the end of November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On their way back to Japan, despite the Japanese forces being hindered by the Ming-Korean navy at the Battle of Noryang, all returned to Japan by the end of November.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On their way back to Japan, despite the Japanese forces being hindered by the Ming-Korean navy at the Battle of Noryang, all returned to Japan by the end of December.</e>
<cmt>和暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>政権崩壊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collapse of the Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collapse of the Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collapse of the Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>秀吉の死後、豊臣氏は秀吉の嫡男である秀頼が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, Hideyori, his first son, succeeded to the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, Hideyori, his first son, succeeded the position of head of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi&apos;s death, Hideyori, his first son, succeeded the position of head of the Toyotomi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし、秀頼はわずか6歳の幼主であったため、豊臣氏内部で秀吉の晩年からすでに発芽していた加藤清正、福島正則ら武断派と石田三成、小西行長らによる文治派の対立が表面化し、豊臣家臣団は分裂する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Hideyori was only six years old, the conflict between Budan-ha (a political faction that is willing to resort to military means to achieve its aims) consisting of Kiyomasa KATO, Masanori FUKUSHIMA and others and Bunchi-ha(a civilian party) consisting of Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI, and others, which had started during Hideyoshi&apos;s last years, became obvious and the TOYOTOMI vassals were split off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Hideyori was only six years old, the conflict between the Budan-ha (a political faction willing to resort to military means to achieve its aims) consisting of Kiyomasa KATO, Masanori FUKUSHIMA and others, and the Bunchi-ha (a civilian party) consisting of Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI, and others, which had started during Hideyoshi&apos;s last years, came to a head and the TOYOTOMI vassals were split off.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Hideyori was only six years old, the conflict between the Budan-ha (a political faction willing to resort to military means to achieve its aims) consisting of Kiyomasa KATO, Masanori FUKUSHIMA and others, and the Bunchi-ha (a civilian party) consisting of Mitsunari ISHIDA, Yukinaga KONISHI, and others, which had started during Hideyoshi&apos;s last years, came to a head and the TOYOTOMI vassals were split off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>さらに徳川家康も天下人を目指して、伊達政宗らと無断婚姻を行なうなど、豊臣政権は次第に衰退の兆しを見せてゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA aimed to be &apos;tenkabito&apos; (a person becoming the ruler of the country) and had an unauthorized marriage with Munemasa DATE; thus, the TOYOTOMI government showed signs of decline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA aimed to be &apos;tenkabito&apos; (a person becoming the ruler of the country) and entered an unauthorized marriage with Munemasa DATE; thus, showing signs of the TOYOTOMI government&apos;s decline.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA aimed to be &apos;tenkabito&apos; (a person becoming the ruler of the country) and entered an unauthorized marriage with Masamune DATE; thus, showing signs of the TOYOTOMI government&apos;s decline.</e>
<cmt>Munemasa → Masamune</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>慶長4年（1599年）には、秀頼の後見人として豊臣政権を何とか支えていた前田利家が死去する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1599, Toshie MAEDA, who managed to support the government as Hideyori&apos;s guardian, passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1599, Toshie MAEDA, who managed to support the government as Hideyori&apos;s guardian, passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1599, Toshiie MAEDA, who managed to support the government as Hideyori&apos;s guardian, passed away.</e>
<cmt>Toshie → Toshiie</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このため、家康の勢力が諸大名の中でも特に抜きん出ることとなり、家康は次第に天下の権を掌握するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That made Ieyasu gain prominence among other feudal lords, and Ieyasu gradually came to grasp the power to control the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This allowed Ieyasu to gain prominence among other feudal lords, and Ieyasu gradually came to hold the power to control the nation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This allowed Ieyasu to gain prominence among other feudal lords, and Ieyasu gradually came to hold the power to control the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>一方、豊臣政権擁護の立場から、石田三成は上杉景勝や毛利輝元、宇喜多秀家らと共に家康との対立を試みる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Mitsunari ISHIDA, together with Kagekatsu UESUGI, Terumoto MORI, Hideie UKITA and others, tried to fight against Ieyasu in order to protect the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Mitsunari ISHIDA, together with Kagekatsu UESUGI, Terumoto MORI, Hideie UKITA and others, tried to fight against Ieyasu in order to protect the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Mitsunari ISHIDA, together with Kagekatsu UESUGI, Terumoto MORI, Hideie UKITA and others, tried to fight against Ieyasu in order to protect the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>が、慶長5年（1600年）9月の関ヶ原の戦いにおいて、三成ら豊臣方（西軍）は敗れ、三成ら主だった者はことごとく処刑、改易された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Battle of Sekigahara in September, 1600, the Toyotomi-side (the western army) including Mitsunari was defeated, and the main leaders including Mitsunari were executed or punished by being deprived of their domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at the Battle of Sekigahara in September, in 1600, the Toyotomi-side (the western army) including Mitsunari was defeated, and the main leaders including Mitsunari were executed or punished by being deprived of their domain.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at the Battle of Sekigahara in September, in 1600, the Toyotomi-side (the western army) including Mitsunari was defeated, and the main leaders including Mitsunari were executed or punished by being deprived of their domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>そして関ヶ原の戦後処理により、豊臣氏は摂津国・河内国・和泉国の3カ国、65万石を支配する一大名へと転落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The post-war treatment degraded the Toyotomi clan into one feudal lord who owned three Provinces, Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi provinces, with 650,000 koku (approximately 117 million liters of crop yield). (That meant Hideyoshi&apos;s policy of having placed &apos;kurairechi (the land directly controlled by the Toyotomi clan)&apos; in various places worked negatively.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The post-war reorganization degraded the Toyotomi clan down to one feudal lord who owned three Provinces, the Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi provinces, with 650,000 koku (approximately 117 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The post-war reorganization degraded the Toyotomi clan down to one feudal lord who owned three Provinces, the Settsu, Kawachi and Izumi provinces, with 650,000 koku (approximately 117 million liters of crop yield).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>（これは秀吉による全国各地に豊臣家の蔵入地を設定した政策が、裏目に出たのである。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Which meant Hideyoshi&apos;s policy of &apos;kurairechi&apos; (land directly controlled by the Toyotomi clan) was unsuccessful in various ways.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Which meant Hideyoshi&apos;s policy of &apos;kurairechi&apos; (land directly controlled by the Toyotomi clan) was unsuccessful in various ways.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>関ヶ原の戦後処理で諸大名の領地替えを行った際に、自動的にこれら蔵入地が消滅してしまったのである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ieyasu changed various feaudal lords&apos; domains in the post-war treatment, those &apos;kurairechi&apos; automatically disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ieyasu changed various feudal lords&apos; domains in the post-war reorganization, those &apos;kurairechi&apos; automatically disappeared.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ieyasu changed various feudal lords&apos; domains in the post-war reorganization, those &apos;kurairechi&apos; automatically disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>そして慶長8年（1603年）に徳川家康が征夷大将軍として江戸幕府を開いたことにより、豊臣政権は終焉したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s opening Edo Bakufu (Edo shogunate) as Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) in 1603 put the Toyotomi government into an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s establishing the Edo Bakufu (Edo shogunate) as Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) in 1603 put an end to the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu Tokugawa&apos;s establishing the Edo Bakufu (Edo shogunate) as Seiitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) in 1603 put an end to the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>Seitaishogun → Seiitaishogun</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>その後、豊臣氏はあくまで徳川氏に従わず、独立を維持しようとしたため、慶長19年（1614年）からの大坂の陣において、家康により滅ぼされたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, since the Toyotomi clan would not obey the Tokugawa clan but tried to be independent, they were defeated by Ieyasu in Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka), which started in 1614.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, as the Toyotomi clan would not obey the Tokugawa clan and attempted to be independent, they were defeated by Ieyasu in Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka), which started in 1614.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, as the Toyotomi clan would not obey the Tokugawa clan and attempted to be independent, they were defeated by Ieyasu in Osaka no Jin (The Siege of Osaka), which started in 1614.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>豊臣政権の性格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristics of the Toyotomi government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of the Toyotomi government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of the Toyotomi government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>豊臣政権は、前政権の織田政権と同じく、君主である秀吉に権力が集中する形態を取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like the former government, the Oda government, the Toyotomi government had a form that Hideyoshi, the monarch grasped the powe all by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the former government, the Oda government, the Toyotomi government was organized so that Hideyoshi, the monarch, held all of the power by himself.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like the former government, the Oda government, the Toyotomi government was organized so that Hideyoshi, the monarch, held all of the power by himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>秀吉の治世としては太閤検地や刀狩令など日本全国の土地や民衆のすべてを管理する中央集権となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the reign of Hideyoshi, he established centralized administrative framework that controlled lands and people all over the country by conducting Taiko kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey) and giving command to collect swords, and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the reign of Hideyoshi, he established a centralized administrative framework that controlled lands and people all over the country by conducting Taiko kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey), giving commands to collect swords, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the reign of Hideyoshi, he established a centralized administrative framework that controlled lands and people all over the country by conducting Taiko kenchi (Hideyoshi Toyotomi&apos;s nationwide land survey), giving commands to collect swords, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>毛利氏、島津氏、伊達氏、徳川氏、上杉氏ら100万石にならんとする大大名がいるが、秀吉生存中は彼らに執政権を与えず、石田氏や大谷氏ら自身の子飼い大名に近畿周辺の小禄に封じて政治をさせている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were several &apos;Daidaimyo&apos; (a feudal lord having a greater stipend) including the Mori, the Shimazu, the Date, the Tokugawa, and the Uesugi clans, who owned almost one million-koku provinces, Hideyoshi, while he was alive, didn&apos;t give them any authority to control the administration but had the feudal lords who were reared from an early age, such as the Ishida and the Otani clans, govern the country by making them live around Kinki region and giving them small stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were several &apos;Daidaimyo&apos; (a feudal lord given a greater stipend) including the Mori, the Shimazu, the Date, the Tokugawa, and the Uesugi clans, who owned provinces almost one million-koku in size, Hideyoshi, while he was alive, didn&apos;t give them any authority to control the administration but instead had the feudal lords who were reared from an early age, such as the Ishida and the Otani clans, govern the country by making them live around the Kinki region and giving them a small stipend.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were several &apos;Daidaimyo&apos; (a feudal lord given a greater stipend) including the Mori, the Shimazu, the Date, the Tokugawa, and the Uesugi clans, who owned provinces almost one million-koku in size, Hideyoshi, while he was alive, didn&apos;t give them any authority to control the administration but instead had the feudal lords who were reared from an early age, such as the Ishida and the Otani clans, govern the country by making them live around the Kinki region and giving them a small stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>また各地に蔵入地（政府直轄地）を設定して遠隔支配するような仕組みを整えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi also established &apos;kurairechi (the land directly controlled by the goverment) in various places and formed the remotely-controling system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi also established &apos;kurairechi&apos; (the land directly controlled by the government) in various places and formed a system of remote control.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi also established &apos;kurairechi&apos; (the land directly controlled by the government) in various places and formed a system of remote control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>バテレン追放令をだすなどキリスト教を禁ずる一方でヨーロッパとの交易は盛んに推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While he forbid Christianity, which was symbolized by &apos;Bateren Tsuihorei&apos; (an edict expelling the European missionaries), he earnestly promoted commerce with Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he forbid Christianity, which was symbolized by &apos;Bateren Tsuihorei&apos; (an edict expelling the European missionaries), he earnestly promoted commerce with Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he forbid Christianity, which was symbolized by &apos;Bateren Tsuihorei&apos; (an edict expelling the European missionaries), he earnestly promoted commerce with Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="65">
<j>また、秀吉は当初は征夷大将軍への就任に意欲を示したとも言われているが実現せず、代わって偶発的事情から得た関白の地位を武家である豊臣氏による世襲制度（公家である藤原氏の五摂家を排除）に変更して、幕府制度に代わる武家関白制（ぶけかんぱくせい）とも言うべき体制を導入しようとしたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that after the failure to accomplish Hideyoshi&apos;s desire to become &apos;Seii Taishogun&apos;, he introduced a new system, &apos;the Kanpaku system by the samurai family&apos; instead of &apos;Bakufu&apos; system; the status of &apos;Kanpaku&apos; was given to him through accidental events, and he tried to change the status into the Toyotomi-clan hereditary system (by excluding five Fujiwara Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that after Hideyoshi&apos;s failure to accomplish his desire to become &apos;Seii Taishogun&apos;, he introduced a new system, &apos;the Kanpaku system by the samurai family&apos; instead of the &apos;Bakufu&apos; system; the status of &apos;Kanpaku&apos; was given to him through accidental events, and he tried to change the status to the Toyotomi-clan hereditary system (by excluding five Fujiwara Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku)).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that after Hideyoshi&apos;s failure to accomplish his desire to become &apos;Seii Taishogun&apos;, he introduced a new system, &apos;the Kanpaku system by the samurai family&apos; instead of the &apos;Bakufu&apos; system; the status of &apos;Kanpaku&apos; was given to him through accidental events, and he tried to change the status to the Toyotomi-clan hereditary system (by excluding five Fujiwara Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho and Kanpaku)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>豊臣秀次への関白位譲渡も引退を目的としたものではなく、関白位の豊臣氏世襲を宣言するものであり実権は依然として秀吉が保持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The transfer of &apos;Kanpaku&apos; to Hidetsugu Toyotomi did not mean Hideyoshi&apos;s retirement but the declaration of the Toyotomi-clan&apos;s heredity of that position, and Hideyoshi maintained the real power. (Ironically, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA transferred the position of &apos;Seii taishogun&apos; to his son, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and was in charge of politics as &apos;Ogosho (a leading figure)&apos; in order to show that the Tokugawa clan would inherit the position of &apos;Seii taishogun&apos; and he would not return the political administration to Hideyori, Hideyoshi&apos;s bereaved son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The transfer of &apos;Kanpaku&apos; to Hidetsugu Toyotomi did not mean Hideyoshi&apos;s retirement but the declaration of the Toyotomi-clan&apos;s heritage of that position, and Hideyoshi maintained the real power.</e>
<cmt>reword一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The transfer of &apos;Kanpaku&apos; to Hidetsugu Toyotomi did not mean Hideyoshi&apos;s retirement but the declaration of the Toyotomi-clan&apos;s heritage of that position, and Hideyoshi maintained the real power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>（皮肉にも徳川家康も征夷大将軍位の徳川氏世襲と秀吉の遺児・秀頼への政権返上の意思が無い事を示すために息子徳川秀忠に将軍を継がせて自らは大御所として政権を運営している。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Ironically, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA transferred the position of &apos;Seii taishogun&apos; to his son, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and was in charge of politics as &apos;Ogosho&apos; (a leading figure) in order to show that the Tokugawa clan would inherit the position of &apos;Seii taishogun&apos; and he would not return the political administration to Hideyori, Hideyoshi&apos;s bereaved son.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Ironically, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA transferred the position of &apos;Seii taishogun&apos; to his son, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and was in charge of politics as &apos;Ogosho&apos; (a leading figure) in order to show that the Tokugawa clan would inherit the position of &apos;Seii taishogun&apos; and he would not return the political administration to Hideyori, Hideyoshi&apos;s bereaved son.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="68">
<j>対外政策としては明に替わり日本がその中心になる華夷思想を打ち出し、ルソン・琉球国・高山国（当時、台湾に存在すると考えられていた国）・李氏朝鮮などに服属と朝貢を求める武威を背景にした強硬政策を推進している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding a diplomatic policy, Hideyoshi insisted &apos;Sinocentrism&apos; in which Japan would be the center instead of Ming and based on military force, applied a hard-line policy that required Luzon, Ryukyukoku, Takasagun (the country believed to exist in Taiwan in those days), Joseon Dynasty and others to yield allegiance and bring tributes to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In regards to diplomatic policy, Hideyoshi insisted &apos;Sinocentrism&apos; in which Japan would be the center instead of Ming and based on military force, applied a hard-line policy that required Luzon, Ryukyukoku, Takasagun (the country believed to exist in Taiwan in those days), Joseon Dynasty and others to yield allegiance and bring tributes to Japan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In regards to diplomatic policy, Hideyoshi insisted &apos;Sinocentrism&apos; in which Japan would be the center instead of Ming and based on military force, applied a hard-line policy that required Luzon, Ryukyukoku, Takasagun (the country believed to exist in Taiwan in those days), Joseon Dynasty and others to yield allegiance and bring tributes to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>特に朝鮮に対しては「服属」を強く求めると共に「征明の先導」（征明嚮導）を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Joseon Dynasty that Hideyoshi strongly required &apos;submission&apos; and &apos;the guide for conquest of the Ming (Seimin kyodo).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the Joseon Dynasty that Hideyoshi strongly required &apos;submission&apos; from and &apos;the guide for conquest of the Ming&apos; (Seimin kyodo).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the Joseon Dynasty that Hideyoshi strongly required &apos;submission&apos; from and &apos;the guide for conquest of the Ming&apos; (Seimin kyodo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし朝鮮の立場は建国以来、明の属国であり、その外交方針をここで変える意思はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Joseon Dynasty had been a tributary nation to Ming since its establishment, and it would not change its diplomatic policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Joseon Dynasty had been a tributary nation to Ming since its establishment, and it would not change its diplomatic policies.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Joseon Dynasty had been a tributary nation to Ming since its establishment, and it would not change its diplomatic policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>交渉に当たった対馬の宗氏は、これを何とか穏便に済まそうとして、秀吉が求める「朝貢使」の派遣を秀吉の全国統一の「祝賀使」の派遣に置き換えて要請した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The So clan in Tsushima, who negotiated between Hideyoshi and Joseon Dynasty, trying to settle peacefully, required Joseon Dynasty to send &apos;celebratory delegates&apos; for the unification of Japan, instead of &apos;tributary delegates,&apos; which Hideyoshi had required.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The So clan in Tsushima, who negotiated between Hideyoshi and the Joseon Dynasty, pursuing a peaceful settlement, required the Joseon Dynasty to send &apos;celebratory delegates&apos; for the unification of Japan, instead of &apos;tributary delegates,&apos; which Hideyoshi had required.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The So clan in Tsushima, who negotiated between Hideyoshi and the Joseon Dynasty, pursuing a peaceful settlement, required the Joseon Dynasty to send &apos;celebratory delegates&apos; for the unification of Japan, instead of &apos;tributary delegates,&apos; which Hideyoshi had required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>すると、朝鮮としても日本側の状況を探りたい事情もあり使者を派遣した（賊探使）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joseon Dynasty sent their delegates partly because they wanted to find out what was going on in Japan. (searching delegates)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「賊探使」の定訳は見つけられませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Joseon Dynasty sent their delegates partly because they wanted to find out what was going on in Japan (searching delegates).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Joseon Dynasty sent their delegates partly because they wanted to find out what was going on in Japan (searching delegates).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>もっとも朝鮮側にしてみれば使者は表向きが「祝賀使」であり実態は「賊探使」に過ぎず、秀吉に対して「朝貢」したつもりも「服属」したつもりも無かった訳であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Joseon Dynasty officially sent &apos;celebratory delegates, their real intention was to find out Japanese situation, so they did not mean to pay &apos;tributes&apos; or yield allegiance to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Joseon Dynasty officially sent &apos;celebratory delegates,&apos; their real intention was to learn about Japan&apos;s current situation, and they did not intend to pay &apos;tributes&apos; or yield allegiance to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Joseon Dynasty officially sent &apos;celebratory delegates,&apos; their real intention was to learn about Japan&apos;s current situation, and they did not intend to pay &apos;tributes&apos; or yield allegiance to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>が、この朝鮮使を宗氏は「朝貢使」と称して秀吉に謁見させると、秀吉からしてみると、要求に応じ「朝貢使」を派遣し「服属」してきた朝鮮に、以前からの要求通り征明の先導（征明嚮導）を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the So clan introduced these Korean delegates as &apos;tributary delegates&apos; to Hideyoshi, he believed that Joseon Dynasty sent &apos;tributary delegates&apos; and yield allegiance to him as he had demanded, and ordered them again to be the guide for conquest of the Ming (Seimin kyodo).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the So clan introduced these Korean delegates as &apos;tributary delegates&apos; to Hideyoshi, he believed that the Joseon Dynasty had sent &apos;tributary delegates&apos; to yield allegiance to him as he had demanded, and ordered them again to be the guide for conquest of the Ming (Seimin kyodo).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the So clan introduced these Korean delegates as &apos;tributary delegates&apos; to Hideyoshi, he believed that the Joseon Dynasty had sent &apos;tributary delegates&apos; to yield allegiance to him as he had demanded, and ordered them again to be the guide for conquest of the Ming (Seimin kyodo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>しかし、明に服属する朝鮮に要求に応じる気配はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Joseon Dynasty, which had been a tributary nation to Ming, would not follow his order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Joseon Dynasty, which had been a tributary nation to Ming, would not follow his order.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Joseon Dynasty, which had been a tributary nation to Ming, would not follow his order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これは秀吉にしてみれば朝鮮が「服属」の誓約違反を犯したことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi cosidered it as Korean&apos;s breaking the pledge of &apos;submission&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi considered this as the Korean&apos;s breaking the pledge of &apos;submission&apos;.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi considered this as the Korean&apos;s breaking the pledge of &apos;submission&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>このためまず朝鮮を攻めることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Hideyoshi decided to attack Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Hideyoshi decided to attack Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, Hideyoshi decided to attack Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>この大陸侵攻・朝鮮出兵は戦争途中で秀吉の死によって終結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The invasion of the Asian continent and the dispatch of troops to Korea finished at Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The invasion of the Asian continent and the dispatch of troops to Korea finished upon Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The invasion of the Asian continent and the dispatch of troops to Korea finished upon Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>ただでさえ少なかった秀吉の縁者である豊臣秀長・豊臣鶴松・大政所・朝日姫らが、天正末期に次々と死去したことは、豊臣政権に大打撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi originally had a few relatives, and Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, Omandokoro, Asahihime (Hideyoshi&apos;s younger sister and Ieyasu&apos;s lawful wife) and others passed away one after another, which caused heavy damage to the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi originally had few relatives, and as Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, Omandokoro, Asahihime (Hideyoshi&apos;s younger sister and Ieyasu&apos;s lawful wife) and others passed away one after another, it caused heavy damage to the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi originally had few relatives, and as Hidenaga TOYOTOMI, Tsurumatsu TOYOTOMI, Omandokoro, Asahihime (Hideyoshi&apos;s younger sister and Ieyasu&apos;s lawful wife) and others passed away one after another, it caused heavy damage to the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>にも関わらず、文禄年間に秀吉が行なった豊臣秀次とその一族に対する粛清は、豊臣一族の衰退を決定的なものとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of such damage, Hideyoshi purged Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and his family during the Bunroku period, which made the decline of the Toyotomi clan conclusive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite this, Hideyoshi purged Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and his family during the Bunroku period, which made the decline of the Toyotomi clan conclusive.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite this, Hideyoshi purged Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI and his family during the Bunroku period, which made the decline of the Toyotomi clan conclusive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="81">
<j>また、秀吉は子飼いの家臣団を、武断派と文治派で分離してそれぞれ登用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi also devided his vassals trained from their boyhood into Budan-ha and Bunchi-ha, and had them work hard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi also divided his vassals trained from their boyhood into Budan-ha and Bunchi-ha, and had them work hard.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi also divided his vassals trained from their boyhood into Budan-ha and Bunchi-ha, and had them work hard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>人材を効率よく使おうという秀吉らしいやり方と言えるのだが、それは秀吉没後に加藤清正ら武断派と、石田三成ら文治派の抗争へと発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it can be said that it was typical of Hideyoshi&apos;s way of using people effectively, it resulted in the conflict between Budan-ha including Kiyomasa KATO and Bunchi-ha including Mitsunari ISHIDA after Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it can be said that it was typical of Hideyoshi&apos;s way of using people effectively, it resulted in the conflict between Budan-ha including Kiyomasa KATO and Bunchi-ha including Mitsunari ISHIDA after Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it can be said that it was typical of Hideyoshi&apos;s way of using people effectively, it resulted in the conflict between Budan-ha including Kiyomasa KATO and Bunchi-ha including Mitsunari ISHIDA after Hideyoshi&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>さらに秀吉は晩年、後継者の秀頼における豊臣政権を磐石なものとするために、諸大名に無断で婚姻を結ぶことを禁止している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his late years, Hideyoshi forbade feudal lords to make marital relationships with each other without his permission in order to stabilize the Toyotomi government, to which his son, Hideyori, would succeed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his later years, Hideyoshi forbade feudal lords to make marital relationships with each other without his permission in order to stabilize the Toyotomi government, to which his son, Hideyori, would succeed.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his later years, Hideyoshi forbade feudal lords to make marital relationships with each other without his permission in order to stabilize the Toyotomi government, to which his son, Hideyori, would succeed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>さらに徳川家康・前田利家・毛利輝元・宇喜多秀家・小早川隆景（慶長2年の隆景没後は、上杉景勝）ら、有力大名を五大老に任じて豊臣政権の最高機関とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Hideyoshi established the supreme organ of the Toyotomi government by appointing the following influential feudal lords to be as &apos;Gotairo&apos; (Council of Five Elders): Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Toshiie MAEDA, Terumoto MORI, Hideie UKITA, and Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (Kagekatsu UESUGI after Takakage&apos;s death in 1597).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Hideyoshi established the supreme organization of the Toyotomi government by appointing the following influential feudal lords as &apos;Gotairo&apos; (Council of Five Elders): Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Toshiie MAEDA, Terumoto MORI, Hideie UKITA, and Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (Kagekatsu UESUGI after Takakage&apos;s death in 1597).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Hideyoshi established the supreme organization of the Toyotomi government by appointing the following influential feudal lords as &apos;Gotairo&apos; (Council of Five Elders): Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Toshiie MAEDA, Terumoto MORI, Hideie UKITA, and Takakage KOBAYAKAWA (Kagekatsu UESUGI after Takakage&apos;s death in 1597).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これはいわゆる内閣制度であり、この五大老の合議によって天下の諸事が決定されるというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was a so-called cabinet system and various matters should be decided by the agreement of &apos;Gotairo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a so-called cabinet system and various matters were decided by the agreement of the &apos;Gotairo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a so-called cabinet system and various matters were decided by the agreement of the &apos;Gotairo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また、検地などの事務的な処理に関しては、秀吉子飼いの家臣である石田三成・浅野長政・前田玄以・増田長盛・長束正家らいわゆる五奉行によって執行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clerical work, such as land survey, was conducted by so-called Gobugyo (five major magistrates), Hideyoshi&apos;s vassals trained from their boyhood: Mitsunari ISHIDA, Nagamasa ASANO, Geni MAEDA, Nagamori MASHITA and Masaie NAGATSUKA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clerical work, such as land survey, was conducted by so-called Gobugyo (five major magistrates), Hideyoshi&apos;s vassals trained from their boyhood: Mitsunari ISHIDA, Nagamasa ASANO, Geni MAEDA, Nagamori MASHITA and Masaie NAGATSUKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clerical work, such as land survey, was conducted by so-called Gobugyo (five major magistrates), Hideyoshi&apos;s vassals trained from their boyhood: Mitsunari ISHIDA, Nagamasa ASANO, Geni MAEDA, Nagamori MASHITA and Masaie NAGATSUKA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>そして、この五大老と五奉行の調整・監視役として堀尾吉晴・中村一氏・生駒親正らが三中老を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA and Chikamasa IKOMA worked as &apos;Sanchuro (arbitration office)&apos; in order to control and supervise &apos;Gotairo&apos; and &apos;Gobugyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA and Chikamasa IKOMA worked as &apos;Sanchuro&apos; (arbitration office) in order to control and supervise &apos;Gotairo&apos; and &apos;Gobugyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiharu HORIO, Kazuuji NAKAMURA and Chikamasa IKOMA worked as &apos;Sanchuro&apos; (arbitration office) in order to control and supervise &apos;Gotairo&apos; and &apos;Gobugyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="88">
<j>しかし、これら五大老・三中老・五奉行の制度はいずれも、政治機構としては未熟だったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, those systems, Gotairo, Sanchuro and Gobugyo, are said not to have developed enough as a political structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, those systems, Gotairo, Sanchuro and Gobugyo, are said to have not developed enough as political structures.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, those systems, Gotairo, Sanchuro and Gobugyo, are said to have not developed enough as political structures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>事実、秀吉の没後に五大老の中でも特にその勢力が抜きん出ていた徳川家康は、豊臣氏に無断で諸大名と婚姻関係を結んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, Ieyasu Tokugawa, who became outstandingly influential after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, made marital relationships with several lords without the Toyotomi clan&apos;s permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, Ieyasu Tokugawa, who became outstandingly influential after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, made marital relationships with several lords without the Toyotomi clan&apos;s permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, Ieyasu Tokugawa, who became outstandingly influential after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, made marital relationships with several lords without the Toyotomi clan&apos;s permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>秀吉がこの政治機構を定めたのは、家康に対する牽制の意味もあったと言われているが、結果的にみてそれは失敗に終わったと言えるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Hideyoshi established that political structure partly because he wanted to contain Ieyasu, Hideyoshi&apos;s intention seemed to result in failure. (However, the Toyotomi clan could control the Tokugawa clan while Toshiie Maeda was alive, because Toshiie could compete with Ieyasu: if Toshiie had not passed away only eight months after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, Ieyasu might have had difficulty in gaining reins of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While it is said that Hideyoshi established that political structure partly because he wanted to contain Ieyasu, Hideyoshi&apos;s intentions seemed to have resulted in failure.</e>
<cmt>reword一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While it is said that Hideyoshi established that political structure partly because he wanted to contain Ieyasu, Hideyoshi&apos;s intentions seemed to have resulted in failure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>（ただし、家康と対抗可能な勢力を誇っていた前田利家が存命中は、徳川家が豊臣家を上回る権威を持つことは阻止できており、利家が秀吉の死から僅か8ヵ月後に病死しなければ家康の政権獲得は困難だったとも考えられる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, the Toyotomi clan could control the Tokugawa clan while Toshiie Maeda was alive, because Toshiie could compete with Ieyasu: if Toshiie had not passed away only eight months after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, Ieyasu might have had difficulty in gaining control of the government.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, the Toyotomi clan could control the Tokugawa clan while Toshiie Maeda was alive, because Toshiie could compete with Ieyasu: if Toshiie had not passed away only eight months after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, Ieyasu might have had difficulty in gaining control of the government.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="92">
<j>豊臣氏の所領（蔵入地）も、全国合わせて222万石と、家康が関東で支配していた250万石に及ばない石高であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Toyotomi clan&apos;s territory (directly-controlled land) was 2,220,000 koku in total and it was less than Ieyasu&apos;s territory in Kanto region, which was 2,500,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toyotomi clan&apos;s territory (directly-controlled land) was 2,220,000 koku in total and was less than Ieyasu&apos;s territory in the Kanto region, which was 2,500,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toyotomi clan&apos;s territory (directly-controlled land) was 2,220,000 koku in total and was less than Ieyasu&apos;s territory in the Kanto region, which was 2,500,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>ただし、全国の主要金山・銀山を支配していたため、財政的には豊臣氏が徳川氏を圧倒していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since the Toyotomi clan owned major gold and silver mines, they financially overpowered the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the Toyotomi clan owned the major gold and silver mines, they financially overpowered the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the Toyotomi clan owned the major gold and silver mines, they financially overpowered the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>また秀吉の222万石というのは多くの直臣に所領を分け与えた残りであり、一方の家康の250万石は直臣に分け与えた所領もあわせての数字であり、家康自身の蔵入地は約100万石であるので秀吉の方が大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Hideyoshi, after having giving some of his territory to his great vassal, literally owned 2,220,000 koku-land, Ieyasu&apos;s 2,500,000 koku-territory included the lands given to his vassal, and Ieyasu&apos;s directly-controlled land was one million koku-territory; Hideyoshi&apos;s territory was in fact much bigger than Ieyasu&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Hideyoshi, after having given some of his territory to his greatest vassal, directly owned 2,220,000 koku-land, Ieyasu&apos;s 2,500,000 koku-territory included the lands given to his vassal, and Ieyasu&apos;s directly-controlled land was one million koku-territory; therefore, Hideyoshi&apos;s territory was in fact much bigger than Ieyasu&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Hideyoshi, after having given some of his territory to his greatest vassal, directly owned 2,220,000 koku-land, Ieyasu&apos;s 2,500,000 koku-territory included the lands given to his vassal, and Ieyasu&apos;s directly-controlled land was one million koku-territory; therefore, Hideyoshi&apos;s territory was in fact much bigger than Ieyasu&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>ただ、家康が豊臣政権下でかなりの勢力を持っていた事は事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet, it was a fact that Ieyasu was really influential even in the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet, the fact remained that Ieyasu continued to be very influential even in the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, the fact remained that Ieyasu continued to be very influential even in the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>そして、家康には及ばずとも他にも大勢力を持つ大名は多数存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some feudal lords were also influential even though they were less influential than Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some feudal lords were also influential even though they were less influential than Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some feudal lords were also influential even though they were less influential than Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>このように、豊臣政権の政権基盤は秀吉という強大な一独裁者のもとで、大勢力を持つ諸大名の上に乗っかり、危ういバランスによって何とか機能していた一代政権に過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned above, the Toyotomi government functioned, keeping a fragile balance, only when it depended upon influential feudal lords under the control of Hideyoshi, a very powerful dictator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, the Toyotomi government functioned, keeping a fragile balance, only when it depended upon influential feudal lords under the control of Hideyoshi, a very powerful dictator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, the Toyotomi government functioned, keeping a fragile balance, only when it depended upon influential feudal lords under the control of Hideyoshi, a very powerful dictator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>このため、秀吉没後に豊臣政権の矛盾、及び弱体が表面化し、わずか数年の後に徳川氏によって取って代わられることとなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, the Toyotomi government&apos;s inconsistencies and weak points came to the surface and it was taken over by the Tokugawa clan within a few years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, the Toyotomi government&apos;s inconsistencies and weak points came to the surface and it was taken over by the Tokugawa clan within a few years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, after Hideyoshi&apos;s death, the Toyotomi government&apos;s inconsistencies and weak points came to the surface and it was taken over by the Tokugawa clan within a few years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>豊臣政権の組織</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Organization of the Toyotomi Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Organization of the Toyotomi Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Organization of the Toyotomi Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="99">
<j>豊臣政権では、国政の執行官僚としての奉行は当初から存在していたが、体制を定めた体系的な法令は政権末期まで存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although theToyotomi Government had &apos;bugho&apos;, magistrates as government bureaucrats who were in charge of national politics from its beginning, they didn&apos;t have any systematic laws until the end of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Toyotomi Government had &apos;bugho&apos;, magistrates as government bureaucrats who were in charge of national politics from its beginning, they didn&apos;t have any systematic laws until the end of the government.</e>
<cmt>Added space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Toyotomi Government had &apos;bugho&apos;, magistrates as government bureaucrats who were in charge of national politics from its beginning, they didn&apos;t have any systematic laws until the end of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）に豊臣秀吉は豊臣秀次を謀反を企てたとの理由で切腹させ秀次の部下も粛正した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI accused Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI of raising a rebellion and made Hidetsugu suicide by disembowelment and punished Hidetsugu&apos;s vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI accused Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI of raising a rebellion and made Hidetsugu commit suicide by disembowelment and punished Hidetsugu&apos;s vassals.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI accused Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI of raising a rebellion and made Hidetsugu commit suicide by disembowelment and punished Hidetsugu&apos;s vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>この権力の空白と幼君の豊臣秀頼補佐のために後の五大老の連署を受けて同年「御掟」五箇条と「御掟追加」九箇条を公布し政権機能を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, due to the power vacuum and the assistant for Hideyori TOYOTOMI, the very young lord, &apos;On Okite (five rules and regulations)&apos; and &apos;On OkiteTsuika (the nine supplement of the rules and regulations)&apos; were issued under the &apos;rensho (assistant to regents)&apos; of &apos;Gotairo&apos; and the political function of the government was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, due to the power vacuum and for the assistant of Hideyori TOYOTOMI, a very young lord, &apos;On Okite&apos; (five rules and regulations) and &apos;On Okite Tsuika&apos; (nine supplements to the rules and regulations) were issued under the &apos;rensho&apos; (assistant to regents) of &apos;Gotairo&apos; and the political function of the government was established.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, due to the power vacuum and for the assistant of Hideyori TOYOTOMI, a very young lord, &apos;On Okite&apos; (five rules and regulations) and &apos;On Okite Tsuika&apos; (nine supplements to the rules and regulations) were issued under the &apos;rensho&apos; (assistant to regents) of &apos;Gotairo&apos; and the political function of the government was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>五大老・三中老が置かれ、行政、司法、財政、土木、宗教の担当官として五奉行を設置、また訴訟の受理・聴取を担当する十人衆が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotairo&apos; and &apos;Sanchuro&apos; were established and &apos;Gobugyo&apos;, who were in charge of public administration, justice, financial administration, civil engineering work and religion, and &apos;Juhinshu (Ten influential families),&apos; who were in charge of acceptance of lawsuit and hearing of opinions, were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotairo&apos; and &apos;Sanchuro&apos; were established as well as &apos;Gobugyo&apos;, who were in charge of public administration, justice, financial administration, civil engineering work and religion, and &apos;Juhinshu&apos; (Ten influential families), who were in charge of the acceptance of lawsuits and hearing of opinions, were established.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotairo&apos; and &apos;Sanchuro&apos; were established as well as &apos;Gobugyo&apos;, who were in charge of public administration, justice, financial administration, civil engineering work and religion, and &apos;Juhinshu&apos; (Ten influential families), who were in charge of the acceptance of lawsuits and hearing of opinions, were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>豊臣秀吉が慶長3年（1598年）に死去するとこれらの体制で政権を維持することとなったが、必ずしも法令が機能したとは言えない結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMi passed away in 1598, those systems were to support the Toyotomi government; however, the laws did not always function.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI passed away in 1598, those systems were to support the Toyotomi government; however, the laws did not always function.</e>
<cmt>Capitalized TOYOTOMI</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI passed away in 1598, those systems were to support the Toyotomi government; however, the laws did not always function.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>なお「御掟」「御掟追加」の条文は後に江戸幕府の「武家諸法度」に大幅に取り入れられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the provisions written in &apos;On Okite&apos; and &apos;On OkiteTsuika&apos; were adopted into &apos;Buke shohatto (Laws for the Military Houses)&apos; issued by &apos;Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the provisions written in &apos;On Okite&apos; and &apos;On Okite Tsuika&apos; were adopted into &apos;Buke shohatto&apos; (Laws for the Military Houses) issued by the &apos;Edo bakufu&apos; (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the provisions written in &apos;On Okite&apos; and &apos;On Okite Tsuika&apos; were adopted into &apos;Buke shohatto&apos; (Laws for the Military Houses) issued by the &apos;Edo bakufu&apos; (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="105">
<j>地方においては、朱印状を発行して大名の統治権を改めて認めるという大名知行制を敷いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In local regions, the Toyotomi government established &apos;Daimyo chigyo system (enfeoffment system to a Daimyo)&apos;; the government admitted each feudal lord&apos;s sovereignity by issuing &apos;shuinjo (a vermillion seal letter).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In local regions, the Toyotomi government established a &apos;Daimyo chigyo system&apos; (system of giving fiefs to a Daimyo); the government admitted each feudal lord&apos;s sovereignty by issuing &apos;shuinjo&apos; (a vermillion seal letter).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In local regions, the Toyotomi government established a &apos;Daimyo chigyo system&apos; (system of giving fiefs to a Daimyo); the government admitted each feudal lord&apos;s sovereignty by issuing &apos;shuinjo&apos; (a vermillion seal letter).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>室町時代の守護大名は国ごとあるいは郡ごとの一円支配だったのに対し、秀吉は太閤蔵入地を設定して大名の支配を郷村単位の支配としたことに意義がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While &apos;shugo daimyo&apos; (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) in Muromachi period reigned one whole region or province, Hideyoshi established the land directly controlled of the Taiko Hideyoshi and made the unit that each feudal lord could reign &apos;goson (a self-governing village).&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While &apos;shugo daimyo&apos; (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) during the Muromachi period reigned over a whole region or province, Hideyoshi established the land directly controlled by Taiko Hideyoshi and made the area that each feudal lord could reign &apos;goson&apos; (a self-governing village).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While &apos;shugo daimyo&apos; (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) during the Muromachi period reigned over a whole region or province, Hideyoshi established the land directly controlled by Taiko Hideyoshi and made the area that each feudal lord could reign &apos;goson&apos; (a self-governing village).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>各大名は近くにあった太閤蔵入地の米などの納入の義務があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each feudal lord had several duties including the payment of rice in Hideyoshi&apos;s directly-controlled land near their territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each feudal lord had several duties including the payment of rice to Hideyoshi&apos;s directly-controlled land near their territory.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each feudal lord had several duties including the payment of rice to Hideyoshi&apos;s directly-controlled land near their territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>また、中央政権は太閤蔵入地を通じてその地の財政・内政に関与することができるなど、豊臣政権は地方に発言力があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The central administration was able to take part in the rural area&apos;s financial and domestic administrations through Hideyoshi&apos;s directly-controlled land, which indicated the local regions carried a lot of weight.</e>
<cmt>中央政権が地方に介入できるのに、何故地方に発言力があったのか、日本文の意味がわかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The central administration was able to take part in the rural area&apos;s financial and domestic administrations through Hideyoshi&apos;s directly-controlled land, which indicated the local regions carried a lot of weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The central administration was able to take part in the rural area&apos;s financial and domestic administrations through Hideyoshi&apos;s directly-controlled land, which indicated the local regions carried a lot of weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>大名配置についても、大坂の周辺に譜代の大名を置き、徳川家康を関東に移すなど外様は辺境に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi placed &apos;fudai daimyo&apos; (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Toyotomi clan) near Osaka and &apos;tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord)&apos; in remote region, just like placing Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi placed &apos;fudai daimyo&apos; (a daimyo in hereditary vassalage to the Toyotomi clan) near Osaka and &apos;tozama daimyo&apos; (nonhereditary feudal lord) in remote regions, similar to placing Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi placed &apos;fudai daimyo&apos; (a daimyo in hereditary vassalage to the Toyotomi clan) near Osaka, while placing &apos;tozama daimyo&apos; (nonhereditary feudal lord) in remote regions such as shifting Ieyasu TOKUGAWA to the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>後半、文意を反映して若干修正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>そして石田三成など政務を執る奉行衆は20万石前後とし、外様には政権参与を原則的に許してないなど、政務者と軍事力の分離が図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi tried to prevent those in charge of government practices from having military force; for example, Hideyoshi gave 200,000 koku to &apos;bugyoshu (group of magistrates)&apos;, including Mitsunari ISHIDA, and didn&apos;t allow &apos;tozama&apos; to participate in reins of government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi tried to prevent those in charge of government practices from having military forces; for example, Hideyoshi gave 200,000 koku to the &apos;bugyoshu&apos; (group of magistrates), including Mitsunari ISHIDA, and didn&apos;t allow &apos;tozama&apos; to participate in government affairs.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi tried to prevent those in charge of government practices from having military forces; for example, Hideyoshi gave 200,000 koku to the &apos;bugyoshu&apos; (group of magistrates), including Mitsunari ISHIDA, and didn&apos;t allow &apos;tozama&apos; to participate in government affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="111">
<j>豊臣政権の財政基盤は、以下の三つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following three were the financial bases of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following three things were the financial basis of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following three things were the financial basis of the Toyotomi government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>第一に、上記に掲げた太閤蔵入地約200万石、第二に、直轄領とした金山・銀山（佐渡国佐渡金山、石見国石見銀山、但馬国生野銀山）から上がる金銀の収益（金銀の収益を背景に、平安時代に発行された皇朝十二銭以来となる国内発行の貨幣（天正大判・天正通宝）を発行）、第三に、商業が発達した都市（大坂、堺、京都、伏見、長崎）を直轄地とすることから上がる収益であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, by gaining approximately two million koku from the land directly controlled of the Taiko Hideyoshi; second, by gaining profits of gold and silver from gold and silver mines, which were Hideyoshi&apos;s direct control territory (Sado Gold Mine of Sado Province and Iwami Silver Mine of Iwami Province and Ikuno Silver Mine of Tajima Privince) (Hideyoshi issued the new coins, &apos;Tensho-Oban&apos; and &apos;Tensho Tsuho&apos; after a long interval since &apos;Kocho-Junisen (twelve coins casted in Japan)&apos; had been issued in the Heian period; third, gaining profits by directly controlling cities where commerce had developed (Osaka, Sakai, Kyoto, Fushimi and Nagasaki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, by gaining approximately two million koku from the land directly controlled by Taiko Hideyoshi; second, by gaining profits of gold and silver from gold and silver mines, which were part of Hideyoshi&apos;s directly controlled territories (Sado Gold Mine of Sado Province and Iwami Silver Mine of Iwami Province and Ikuno Silver Mine of Tajima Province) (Hideyoshi issued the new coins, &apos;Tensho-Oban&apos; and &apos;Tensho Tsuho&apos; after a long interval since &apos;Kocho-Junisen&apos; (twelve coins casted in Japan) had been issued in the Heian period; third, gaining profits by directly controlling cities where commerce had developed (Osaka, Sakai, Kyoto, Fushimi and Nagasaki).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, by gaining approximately two million koku from the land directly controlled by Taiko Hideyoshi; second, by gaining profits of gold and silver from gold and silver mines, which were part of Hideyoshi&apos;s directly controlled territories (Sado Gold Mine of Sado Province and Iwami Silver Mine of Iwami Province and Ikuno Silver Mine of Tajima Province) (Hideyoshi issued the new coins, &apos;Tensho-Oban&apos; and &apos;Tensho Tsuho&apos; after a long interval since &apos;Kocho-Junisen&apos; (twelve coins casted in Japan) had been issued in the Heian period; third, gaining profits by directly controlling cities where commerce had developed (Osaka, Sakai, Kyoto, Fushimi and Nagasaki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 初瀬(id:74855), ドルチェット(id:46458), Yasumi(id:44933), 経済準学士(id:22656), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), HI(id:72996), Yanahan(id:2437), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Ytp.rs(id:202698), Shinkansen(id:13703), Kokada jnet(id:84730), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Miya(id:1881), 総督(id:124846), KSKS(id:97637), たなしん(id:162581), Arawodas(id:213174), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 越中掾(id:149423), シェーラ(id:17988), Tokugawa(id:61656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>