<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>電車焼き討ち事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Train Arson Attack</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train Arson Attack</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train Arson Attack</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>電車焼き討ち事件（でんしゃやきうちじけん）は、電車やその施設を放火すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Densha Yakiuchi Jiken (lit. Train Arson Attack) is to attack and fire trains and other facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Densha Yakiuchi Jiken (literally Train Arson Attack) was to cause arson to trains and other facilities.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Densha Yakiuchi Jiken (literally Train Arson Attack) was to cause arson to trains and other facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>主な電車焼き討ち事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major examples of Train Arson Attack</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major examples of Train Arson Attack</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major examples of Train Arson Attack</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>東京の市内電車（後の東京都電）における焼き討ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fire attack for trains in Tokyo City (later known as Tokyo Metropolitan Train).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Train arsons in Tokyo city (later known as Tokyo Metropolitan Train).</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Train arsons in Tokyo city (later known as Tokyo Metropolitan Train).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>1906年（明治39年）、当時東京市内に路面電車を運行していた東京電車鉄道、東京市街鉄道、東京電気鉄道の三社が合併して東京鉄道とすることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1906 it was decided that three railroad companies which ran trams within Tokyo City, Tokyo Densha Tetsudo, Tokyo Shigai Tetsudo and Tokyo Denki Tetsudo were merged under the new name of Tokyo Tetsudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was decided in 1906 that three railroad companies called Tokyo Densha Tetsudo (Tokyo Train Railway), Tokyo Shigai Tetsudo (Tokyo City Railway) and Tokyo Denki Tetsudo (Tokyo Electric Railway) that ran streetcars within Tokyo City in those days merged under the new name of Tokyo Tetsudo.</e>
<cmt>文法を編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was decided in 1906 that three railroad companies called Tokyo Densha Tetsudo (Tokyo Train Railway), Tokyo Shigai Tetsudo (Tokyo City Railway) and Tokyo Denki Tetsudo (Tokyo Electric Railway) that ran streetcars within Tokyo City in those days merged under the new name of Tokyo Tetsudo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>当時各社3銭、他社線に乗り換えるとさらに3銭の運賃体系となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time when users changed to the line of other companies, they were charged extra 3 sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each company costed three sen (hundredth of a yen), and extra three yen was charged for changing to the train line of another company.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each company costed three sen (hundredth of a yen), and extra three yen was charged for changing to the train line of another company.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当時の利用客からは全社共通運賃を望む声が多く、また全社日露戦争によって課せられた通行税によって経営を圧迫していたため、三社合併と同時に運賃を4銭均一制とすることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As much of the users of those days demanded a standardized fare and all the three companies suffered from the new tax on transportation which begun with the Japanese-Russo War, they decided to merge and fix the fare to 4 sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As much of the commuters of those days demanded a standardized fare and all companies suffered from the new transportation tax due to the Russo-Japanese War, they decided to merge and fix the fare to four sen.</e>
<cmt>Run-on sentenceでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As much of the commuters of those days demanded a standardized fare and all companies suffered from the new transportation tax due to the Russo-Japanese War, they decided to merge and fix the fare to four sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>ところが市民は運賃値上げに強く反対し、実施日が近付くにつれ「電車運賃値上げ反対市民大会」を開催した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, people strongly objected the raise of the fare, and as the date came, they started to hold a public gathering for objection to it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, citizens strongly opposed to the raise of the fare and held the &apos;Public Gathering of Citizens Opposing to the Increase of Train Fare&apos; as the day came close.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。「」内の文章が翻訳されてませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, citizens strongly opposed to the raise of the fare and held the &apos;Public Gathering of Citizens Opposing to the Increase of Train Fare&apos; as the day came close.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして暴徒化した市民らは電車に投石、放火等の破壊行為を繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then they became violent and repeated violence like throwing stones or firing trains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Citizens who became violent performed violent acts such as threw stones at trains causing arson repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Citizens who became violent performed violent acts such as threw stones at trains causing arson repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このときに破壊された電車は54両に上り、100名以上の検挙者を出す事件に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of the trains destructed amounted to 54, and more than 100 were arrested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of the trains destructed during this incident amounted to 54, and more than 100 people were arrested.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of the trains destructed during this incident amounted to 54, and more than 100 people were arrested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>またこの事件をきっかけに電車の公営化を望む声が強まり、1911年（明治44年）の東京市による買収へとつながっていくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These incidents also left the growing demand for the public operation of railroad companies, and resulted in the acquisition by Tokyo City in 1911.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These incidents also left the growing demand for the public operation of railroad companies, and resulted in the acquisition by Tokyo City in 1911.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These incidents also left the growing demand for the public operation of railroad companies, and resulted in the acquisition by Tokyo City in 1911.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>名古屋電気鉄道（名古屋市電の前身）における焼き討ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fire attack for trains of Nagoya Denki Tetsudo (later known as Nagoya Shiden).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Arson at Nagoya Denki Tetsudo (former name of Nagoya Shiden) (Nagoya City Train).</e>
<cmt>Fire attacksよりarsonの方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Arson at Nagoya Denki Tetsudo (former name of Nagoya Shiden) (Nagoya City Train).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>1914年（大正3年）、名古屋市において路面電車を運営していた名古屋電気鉄道（名電）に対し、不況下（当時はまだ、第一次世界大戦が勃発した直後）のもと市民は運賃の高さに不満を持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1914, Nagoyo Denki Testudo ran trams within Nagoua City but people under the economy depression (it was just soon after the first World Wide War occurred) were frustrated with the high price of the fare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1914, people under the economy depression (it was just soon after the First World War occurred) were frustrated with the high price of the fare of Nagoyo Denki Testudo ran streetcars in Nagoya city.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1914, people under the economy depression (it was just soon after the First World War occurred) were frustrated with the high price of the fare of Nagoyo Denki Testudo ran streetcars in Nagoya city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>名電の運賃値上げを機にその不満が噴出し、市内路線の事業独占を糾弾すべくデモクラシー運動を展開する団体が鶴舞公園で主催した「電車賃値下問題市民大会」に多数が集まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The frustration became more apparent when Nagoya Denki Tetsudo raised the fare, and to accuse their monopoly supply of the railroad service within the city, one democracy organization held &quot;Public Meeting Concerning The Drop Of The Train Fare&quot; at the Tsurumai park and many people gathered there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The frustration became more apparent when Nagoya Denki Tetsudo raised the fare, and one democracy organization held &quot;Public Meeting Concerning The Drop Of The Train Fare&quot; at the Tsurumai park and many people gathered there to accuse their monopoly supply of the railroad service within the city.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The frustration became more apparent when Nagoya Denki Tetsudo raised the fare, and one democracy organization held &apos;Public Meeting Concerning The Drop Of The Train Fare&apos; at the Tsurumai park and many people gathered there to accuse their monopoly supply of the railroad service within the city.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot; → &apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>会終了後に高揚した一部の参加者が暴徒と化し、偶々近くを走行していた市内電車や、郡部線（郊外路線）のターミナル駅であった柳橋駅、隣接の名電本社へ破壊・放火するなどの事態に発展し、本社建屋・柳橋駅舎と電車23両などが被災（焼失・破壊）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the end of the meeting, part of the participants became so violent that they destructed and fire the city train that was running around them, the Yanagibashi station that was a terminal port for the suburbs lines, the main shrine of Nagoya Denki Tetsudo. As a result, the building of the company, the facilities of the Yanagibashi station and 23 trains were destructed by fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some participants resulted to violence at the end of the meeting, and the situation developed into the destruction and arson of city train running across every parts of the city, facilities of the Yanagibashi station that was a terminal port for the suburban line, headquarter of Nagoya Denki Tetsudo adjacent to it, and 23 trains.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some participants resulted to violence at the end of the meeting, and the situation developed into the destruction and arson of city train running across every parts of the city, facilities of the Yanagibashi station that was a terminal port for the suburban line, headquarter of Nagoya Denki Tetsudo adjacent to it, and 23 trains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これによって、名古屋市当局は市内路線の市有化を強力に求めるべきとの考えを強め、事態収拾のため25年後までの市有化（市内全路線の譲渡）を名電に約束させ、1922年（大正11年）に名古屋電気鉄道の名古屋鉄道と名古屋市電への分割・事業譲渡として結実した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this incident, the authorities of Nagoya city came to realize the necessity of promoting the municipalization of railroad lines in the city, and to settle the situation let Nagoya Denki Tetsudo make an promise they would cede the right of the all lines to the Nagoya city within the next 25 years, and in 1922, the business of Nagoya Denki Tetsudo was spilt and succeed by Nagoya Tetsudo and Nagoya Shiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authorities of Nagoya city came to realize the necessity of promoting the municipalization of railways in the city due to this incident, and to settle the situation let Nagoya Denki Tetsudo make an promise they would pass the right to all lines to the Nagoya city within the next 25 years, and Nagoya Denki Tetsudo was spilt into Nagoya Tetsudo (Nagoya Railway Co., Ltd.) and Nagoya Shiden (Nagoya City Railway) in 1922.</e>
<cmt>Run-on sentenceでした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authorities of Nagoya city came to realize the necessity of promoting the municipalization of railways in the city due to this incident, and to settle the situation let Nagoya Denki Tetsudo make an promise they would pass the right to all lines to the Nagoya city within the next 25 years, and Nagoya Denki Tetsudo was spilt into Nagoya Tetsudo (Nagoya Railway Co., Ltd.) and Nagoya Shiden (Nagoya City Railway) in 1922.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kone(id:377), 名古屋市16(id:74281), Rusk(id:9895), 継之助(id:39352), 経済準学士(id:22656), Lemmingdead(id:16179), Shinkansen(id:13703), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>