<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>豪族</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozoku (local ruling family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozoku (local ruling family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozoku (local ruling family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>豪族（ごうぞく）とは、国家や諸侯などの広域政権の領域の内部に存在し、ある地方において多くの土地や財産や私兵を持ち一定の地域的支配権を持つ一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gozoku refers to a family who existed within a large government of the nation, lords and so on, had many lands, properties and private soldiers in a region, and had a certain level of regional sovereignty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gozoku refers to a family who existed within a broader-based political power of a nation, lords and so on, had many lands, properties and private soldiers in a region, and had a certain level of regional sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>the→a,large government→broader-based political power と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gozoku refers to a family who existed within a broader-based political power of a nation, lords and so on, had many lands, properties and private soldiers in a region, and had a certain level of regional sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>地域的支配権の源泉は自分自身の所有する財産や武力であり、広域政権の権威を権力の本質的な源泉とする地方官は豪族とは呼ばれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The source of regional sovereignty was own properties and military force, and Chihokan (a local official) whose power substantially derived from the authority in the large government was not called Gozoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The source of regional sovereignty was its own properties and military force, and the Chihokan (a local official) whose power substantially derived from the authority in a broader-based political power was not called Gozoku.</e>
<cmt>its, the を補いました。the→a,large government→broader-based political power と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The source of regional sovereignty was its own properties and military force, and the Chihokan (a local official) whose power substantially derived from the authority in a broader-based political power was not called Gozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ただし地方官と豪族は排他的なカテゴリーではなく、同一人が双方を兼ねたり、カテゴリー間を移行したりするケースは多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, each category of Chihokan and Gozoku was not exclusive, and in many cases, the same person was categorized as both Chihokan and Gozoku or moved between the categories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, each category of Chihokan and Gozoku was not exclusive, and in many cases, the same person was categorized as both Chihokan and Gozoku or moved between the two categories.</e>
<cmt>two を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, each category of Chihokan and Gozoku was not exclusive, and in many cases, the same person was categorized as both Chihokan and Gozoku or moved between the two categories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>広域政権側が政権安定のために豪族層の政権内への取り込みを行ったり、逆に広域政権の支配力が弱まると地方官が豪族化することがあるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the large government incorporated a class of Gozoku into the government in order to stabilize the government, or adversely Chihokan became Gozoku when the ruling power of large government weakened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the broader-based political power incorporated a class of Gozoku into their administration in order to stabilize the political power, or adversely Chihokan became Gozoku when the ruling power of the broader-based political administration weakened.</e>
<cmt>large government→broader-based political power,the government→their administration, government→political power,文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the broader-based political power incorporated a class of Gozoku into their administration in order to stabilize the political power, or adversely Chihokan became Gozoku when the ruling power of the broader-based political administration weakened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本史においては、歴史的用語として、古墳時代・大和時代ごろまでの地方の首長層、在地勢力を豪族と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Japanese history, as a historical term, a local chief class and local power clan until the Kofun period (tumulus period) and Yamato period were called Gozoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Japanese history, as a historical term, a local chief class and local power clan until the Kofun period (tumulus period) and the Yamato period were called Gozoku.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Japanese history, as a historical term, a local chief class and local power clan until the Kofun period (tumulus period) and the Yamato period were called Gozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>例えば物部氏、蘇我氏、巨勢氏、平群氏その他。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples are the Mononobe clan, Soga clan, Kose clan, Heguri clan and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples are the Mononobe clan, the Soga clan, the Kose clan, the Heguri clan and others.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples are the Mononobe clan, the Soga clan, the Kose clan, the Heguri clan and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>館・集落や祭礼施設など堀に囲まれた豪族居館跡が発掘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of Gozoku&apos;s residence surrounded a moat such as residence, community, facilities for rites and festivals and so on were excavated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sites of Gozoku residences surrounded by moats, including residences, communities, facilities for rites and festivals and so on were excavated.</e>
<cmt>remains→sites,a moat→by moats,カンマを補いました。文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sites of Gozoku residences surrounded by moats, including residences, communities, facilities for rites and festivals and so on were excavated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大和朝廷は大王（おおきみ）を推戴する豪族、特に大和の中央豪族たちによる連合政権というべきものであり、大王位の継承を巡る争いは豪族たちの軍事力によって行われ、豪族たちの向背が帰趨を制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamato Dynasty was actually a coalition government by Gozoku being presided over by Okimi (great king), especially Gozoku living in Yamato, and since any dispute over succession of post of Okimi was conducted by the Gozoku&apos;s military power, a consequence depended on the decision of attitude of more than one Gozoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamato Dynasty was actually a coalition government by Gozoku being presided over by an Okimi (great king), especially Gozoku living in Yamato, and since any dispute over succession to the post of Okimi was conducted by the Gozoku&apos;s military power, a consequence depended on the stances of more than one Gozoku.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamato Dynasty was actually a coalition government by Gozoku being presided over by an Okimi (great king), especially Gozoku living in Yamato, and since any dispute over succession to the post of Okimi was conducted by the Gozoku&apos;s military power, a consequence depended on the stances of more than one Gozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後律令制度の導入により朝廷の任命する官僚による地方統治と中央豪族の宮廷貴族化が計られるとともに、豪族のある者は政権の中枢を担う貴族となり、またある者は中央の官衙機構を担う中・下級の実務系の官人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, by reason of introducing the ritsuryo system (the system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), it was planned to govern a region by bureaucrats who were appointed by the imperial court and to transform Gozoku who lived in the capital into court nobles, and at the same time, some of Gozoku became nobles in charge of nucleus of the government, and some became intermediate and low-ranking officials for practical works in charge of governmental bureaucratic structure of the central government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, due to the introduction of the ritsuryo system (the system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), governing regions by bureaucrats who were appointed by the imperial court and to transform Gozoku who lived in the capital into court nobles were planed, and at the same time, some of Gozoku became nobles in charge of the nucleus of the government, and some became middle and low-ranking officials for practical works in charge of governmental bureaucratic structure of the central government.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, due to the introduction of the ritsuryo system (the system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), governing regions by bureaucrats who were appointed by the imperial court and to transform Gozoku who lived in the capital into court nobles were planed, and at the same time, some of Gozoku became nobles in charge of the nucleus of the government, and some became middle and low-ranking officials for practical works in charge of governmental bureaucratic structure of the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また地方の首長層であった豪族たちの多くは郡司層に姿を変えてゆき、中央から派遣される官僚である国司の監督下で地方統治を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of Gozoku who were included in the local chief class were transformed into a class of Gunji (local magistrates), and reigned over regions under the supervision of Kokushi (provincial governor) who was dispatched from the central government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of Gozoku who were belonging to the local chief class were transformed into the class of Gunji (local magistrates), and reigned over regions under the supervision of Kokushi (provincial governor) who was dispatched from the central government.</e>
<cmt>included in→belonging to, a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of Gozoku who were belonging to the local chief class were transformed into the class of Gunji (local magistrates), and reigned over regions under the supervision of Kokushi (provincial governor) who was dispatched from the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>こうして歴史的用語としての豪族の語は歴史記述の表舞台からは姿を消す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how the term &apos;Gozoku&apos; as a historical term disappeared from a front stage of historical description.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how the word &apos;Gozoku&apos; as a historical term disappeared from the front stage of historical description.</e>
<cmt>term→word,a→the と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how the word &apos;Gozoku&apos; as a historical term disappeared from the front stage of historical description.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>律令制下における国司による地方統治は、民衆に対して古来の首長権の権威をもって望む郡司層との協力関係に依存するものであったが、しだいにこの権威は平安時代初期の律令制のほころびとともに低下していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local governance by Kokushi under the ritsuryo system relied on a cooperative relationship with the class of Gunji who took an attitude toward people with authority of ancient chieftainship, but this authority declined gradually along with fraying of the ritsuryo system in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local governance by Kokushi under the ritsuryo system relied on a cooperative relationship with the class of Gunji, who ruled with the authority of ancient chieftainship over people, but this authority declined gradually along with fraying of the ritsuryo system in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>文の中ほどを文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local governance by Kokushi under the ritsuryo system relied on a cooperative relationship with the class of Gunji, who ruled with the authority of ancient chieftainship over people, but this authority declined gradually along with fraying of the ritsuryo system in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>代わって在地社会の民衆を直接把握して支配下に置いたのは、元郡司層や土着国司子弟などから成長し、田堵や負名の資格で大規模な農地経営を行うようになっていった富豪の輩、有力百姓階層であり、彼らを現地赴任国司の筆頭者たる受領が支配するようになっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who directly took hold and control of people in the local society instead were those in a rich class and powerful farmer class who were grown-up children of class of former Gunji and native Kokushi, and came to conduct a large-scale farmland management in the capacity of Tato (a field manager) or Fumyo (a local tax manager), and they came to be controlled by Zuryo who was a head of Kokushi transferred to a locale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who directly took hold and control of people in the local society instead, were those in the wealthy class and the powerful farmer class who grew from the younger people of class of former Gunji and native Kokushi and so on, and came to conduct a large-scale farmland management in the qualifications of Tato (a field manager) or Fumyo (a local tax manager), and they came to be controlled by Zuryo who was a head of Kokushi transferred to the locale.</e>
<cmt>the, カンマを補いました。a rich→the wealthy,capacity→qualifications,文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who directly took hold and control of people in the local society instead, were those in the wealthy class and the powerful farmer class who grew from the younger people of class of former Gunji and native Kokushi and so on, and came to conduct a large-scale farmland management in the qualifications of Tato (a field manager) or Fumyo (a local tax manager), and they came to be controlled by Zuryo who was a head of Kokushi transferred to the locale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この地方統治構造の変化と共に登場した武士は、その初期の一部において、例えば平将門などのように豪族的な性格を持つものであるが、古代史と同様な意味合いでの豪族しては扱われない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai appearing along with this change in the structure of local governance had a character of Gozoku like TAIRA no Masakado in part of the initial stages, but was not treated as Gozoku in the sense similar to that in the ancient history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai appeared along with this change in the structure of local governance, and some had a character of Gozoku like TAIRA no Masakado, in part of the initial stages, but were not treated as Gozoku in the meaning same as that in the ancient history.</e>
<cmt>appearing→appeared,was→were,sense→meaning,similar to→same as と修正しました。カンマ, and some を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai appeared along with this change in the structure of local governance, and some had a character of Gozoku like TAIRA no Masakado, in part of the initial stages, but were not treated as Gozoku in the meaning same as that in the ancient history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、豪族を、「勢力のある一族」「有力な一族」という意味での一般的な使用（例えば「南北朝時代の○○国△△郡の豪族」というような使用）では、豪族という形容は、その後の時代の地頭や悪党、国人出自などの領主クラスの大名分の武家に対してしばしば使用され、戦国時代・安土桃山時代まで豪族という形容をすることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the general use of Gozoku as the meaning of &apos;a potent clan&apos; or &apos;powerful clan&apos; (for example the use like &apos;Gozoku in △△-gun, OO Province in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts), the term &quot;Gozoku&quot; was often used to describe Jito (manager and lord of manor), Akuto (a villain in the medieval times), and samurai family at the same level as daimyo in the feudal lord class from Kokujin (local samurai) in subsequent periods, and they were sometimes described as Gozoku until the Sengoku period (period of warring states) and Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the general use of Gozoku as the meaning of &apos;a potent clan&apos; or &apos;powerful clan&apos; (for example the use like &apos;Gozoku in △△ District, OO Province&apos; in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts), the term &quot;Gozoku&quot; was often used to describe Jito (manager and lord of manor), Akuto (a villain in the medieval times), and samurai families at the same level as daimyo in the feudal lord class from Kokujin (local samurai) in the subsequent periods, and they were sometimes described as Gozoku until the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) and the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>-gun→District,family→families,クォートを修正しました。the を補いました。「戦国時代」を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the general use of Gozoku as the meaning of &apos;a potent clan&apos; or &apos;powerful clan&apos; (for example the use like &apos;Gozoku in △△ District, OO Province&apos; in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts), the term &quot;Gozoku&quot; was often used to describe Jito (manager and lord of manor), Akuto (a villain in the medieval times), and samurai families at the same level as daimyo in the feudal lord class from Kokujin (local samurai) in the subsequent periods, and they were sometimes described as Gozoku until the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) and the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Race(id:131322), 海衛士(id:19229), ラスト番長(id:188377), Juyukichi(id:16958), Loveless(id:129239), Extrahitz(id:26245), Morio(id:35464), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), BAKU(id:55205), Ete(id:28565), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>