<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>漢学紀源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakukigen</e>
<cmt>書名の訳は、「紀源」の意味を確定できなかったので記載しませんでした。しかし、書物の内容と漢字「紀」の意味から類推すると、&quot;The origin of the Study of the Chinese classics&quot;で問題ないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakukigen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakukigen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>漢学紀源（かんがくきげん）は、江戸時代後期に薩摩藩伊地知季安によって書かれた漢学史書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kangakukigen is a history book of the study of the Chinese classics written by Sueyasu IJICHI of Satsuma domain in the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>「伊地知季安」は、「いじちすえよし」、「いじちすえなが」と読む説もあるが (Wikipedia上でのみ確認)、『日本人名大辞典』 （講談社）と『國史大辞典』 （吉川弘文館） に基づいて読み方を決定しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kangakukigen is a history book of the study of the Chinese classics written by Sueyasu IJICHI of Satsuma domain in the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kangakukigen is a history book of the study of the Chinese classics written by Sueyasu IJICHI of Satsuma domain in the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全5巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>著者が近思録崩れに連座して遠島とされた後に本土に移されて幽閉された文化 (日本)9年（1812年）から天保12年（1841年）の時期に書かれたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems that the book was written in the period between 1812 and 1841 when he was moved back to the main land and confined after he was implicated in the Kinshiroku-kuzure affair (the family feud in Satsuma domain in 1808) and exiled to a remote island.</e>
<cmt>前後関係を分かりやすくする為に、「近思録崩れ」の解説に西暦を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems that the book was written in the period between 1812 and 1841 when he was moved back to the main land and confined after he was implicated in the Kinshiroku-kuzure affair (the family feud in Satsuma domain in 1808) and exiled to a remote island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems that the book was written in the period between 1812 and 1841 when he was moved back to the main land and confined after he was implicated in the Kinshiroku-kuzure affair (the family feud in Satsuma domain in 1808) and exiled to a remote island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>巻1では、日本に儒教が伝来したと当時考えられていた神功皇后期から、徐福・王仁・聖徳太子・粟田真人・吉備真備・菅原道真・義堂周信ら、古代から室町時代における五山文化興隆期を扱い、巻2では、五山文化から薩摩国の儒教文化を興隆させた桂庵玄樹の登場までを扱い、巻3では薩南学派の発展に尽した島津忠良や南浦文之の活躍や江戸時代初期の儒学を扱い、巻4では薩南学派の総本山とされた正龍寺 (指宿市)の歴史や元禄・享保以後の薩摩藩の儒教史を扱っているが未完である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 1 deals with the history of Confucianism in Japan from the ancient times to the prosperity stage of Gozan Bunka (culture of the Five Official Temples between the end of the Kamakura Period and the Muromachi Period) such as the age of Empress Jingu which was thought in the author&apos;s day to be the time when Confucianism was introduced to Japan, then Jofuku, Prince Shotoku, AWATA no Mahito, KIBI no Makibi, SUGAWARA no Michizane and Shushin Gido, Volume 2 deals with the period from Gozan Bunka to the appearance of Genju KEIAN who brought prosperity to the culture of Confucianism in Satsuma domain, Volume 3 deals with the activity of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU and Bunshi NANPO who tried to develop Satsunangaku school (school of Neo-Confucianism in Satsuma), Volume 4 deals with the history of Shoryu-ji Temple (in now Ibusuki City) which was the center of Satsunangaku school and the history of Confucianism in Satsuma domain after the Genroku and the Kyoho Era, however, this volume is unfinished.</e>
<cmt>※理解を助ける為に原文に無い語句を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 1 deals with the history of Confucianism in Japan from the ancient times to the prosperity stage of Gozan Bunka (culture of the Five Official Temples between the end of the Kamakura Period and the Muromachi Period) such as the age of Empress Jingu which was thought in the author&apos;s day to be the time when Confucianism was introduced to Japan, then Jofuku, Wani (Wang In), Prince Shotoku, AWATA no Mahito, KIBI no Makibi, SUGAWARA no Michizane and Shushin Gido, Volume 2 deals with the period from Gozan Bunka to the appearance of Genju KEIAN who brought prosperity to the culture of Confucianism in Satsuma domain, Volume 3 deals with the activity of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU and Bunshi NANPO who tried to develop Satsunangaku school (school of Neo-Confucianism in Satsuma) and Confucianism in early Edo period, and Volume 4 deals with the history of Shoryu-ji Temple (in current Ibusuki City) which was the center of Satsunangaku school and the history of Confucianism in Satsuma domain after the Genroku and the Kyoho Era, but this volume is unfinished.</e>
<cmt>「王仁」、「江戸時代初期の儒学」訳抜けを補いました。however→but に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 1 deals with the history of Confucianism in Japan from the ancient times to the prosperity stage of Gozan Bunka (culture of the Five Official Temples between the end of the Kamakura Period and the Muromachi Period) such as the age of Empress Jingu which was thought in the author&apos;s day to be the time when Confucianism was introduced to Japan, then Jofuku, Wani (Wang In), Prince Shotoku, AWATA no Mahito, KIBI no Makibi, SUGAWARA no Michizane and Shushin Gido, Volume 2 deals with the period from Gozan Bunka to the appearance of Genju KEIAN who brought prosperity to the culture of Confucianism in Satsuma domain, Volume 3 deals with the activity of Tadayoshi SHIMAZU and Bunshi NANPO who tried to develop Satsunangaku school (school of Neo-Confucianism in Satsuma) and Confucianism in early Edo period, and Volume 4 deals with the history of Shoryu-ji Temple (in current Ibusuki City) which was the center of Satsunangaku school and the history of Confucianism in Satsuma domain after the Genroku and the Kyoho Era, but this volume is unfinished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>巻5は付録で佐藤一斎との書簡など季安自身の儒教史を扱っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 5 is the supplement, and it deals with his own Confucianism history such as the letters between Issai SATO.</e>
<cmt>原文からは、「巻5が付録」なのか「巻5の付録」なのかが曖昧ですが、巻4が未完であり、巻5に関する内容の解説が無いことから、前者の解釈を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 5 is the supplement, and it deals with his own Confucianism history such as the letters between Issai SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 5 is the supplement, and it deals with his own Confucianism history such as the letters between Issai SATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Ohura(id:5986), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>