<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>西宮記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saikyuki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saikyuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saikyuki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>西宮記（さいきゅうき/さいぐうき）は、平安時代に源高明によって撰述された有職故実・儀式書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saikyuki (it ca be pronounced &quot;Saiguki&quot;) was a book on Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and rites, which was compiled by MINAMOTO no Takaakira in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saikyuki (it ca be pronounced &quot;Saiguki&quot;) was a book on Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and rites, which was compiled by MINAMOTO no Takaakira during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saikyuki (Saiguki) was a book on Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules of ceremony and etiquette) and rites, which was compiled by MINAMOTO no Takaakira during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Saikyuki (Saiguki) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>高明は醍醐天皇の皇子として生まれ、臣籍降下の後に左大臣に昇りながら、安和の変で大宰府に左遷されたことで知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaakira was born as a prince of Emperor Daigo and is known for having been promoted to Sadaijin (Minister of the left) after demotion from nobility to subject.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaakira was born as a prince of Emperor Daigo and is known for having been promoted to Sadaijin (Minister of the left) after demotion from nobility to subject.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaakira was born as a prince of Emperor Daigo and is known for having been demoted to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) in the Anna Incident after being promoted to Sadaijin (minister of the left) after demotion from nobility to subject.</e>
<cmt>安和の変　以降を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、『源氏物語』の光源氏のモデルの1人とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is also said to have been one of the models of Genji HIKARU in &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He is also said to have been one of the models of Genji HIKARU in &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He is also said to have been one of the models of Hikaru Genji in &quot;The Tale of Genji.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Hikaru Genji, The Tale of Genji としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>高明邸が当時では珍しく西宮（右京）側にあったことから、「西宮左大臣」の異名で呼ばれ、書名の由来となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Takaakira&apos;s house was on the side of Saikyu (west part of capital), which was unusual at the time, he was also known as &apos;Saikyu Sadaijin,&apos; from which the book title was derived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Takaakira&apos;s house was on the side of Saikyu (west part of capital), which was unusual at the time, he was also known as &apos;Saikyu Sadaijin,&apos; from which the book title was derived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Takaakira&apos;s house was on the side of Saikyu (west part of capital), which was unusual at the time, he was also known as &apos;Saikyu Sadaijin,&apos; from which the book title was derived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>本書の執筆年代は不明であるが、動機の1つとして安和の変の際にともに大宰府に送られた息子源俊賢に有職故実を伝授するために執筆されたとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not known when the book was written, but some people say that it was written in order to initiate Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules for ceremony and etiquette) to his son MINAMOTO no Toshitaka who had been sent to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) with him during the Anwa Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not known when the book was written, but some people say that it was written in order to initiate Yusoku kojitsu (court and samurai rules for ceremony and etiquette) to his son MINAMOTO no Toshitaka who had been sent to Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) with him during the Anwa Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not known when the book was written, but some people say that one of the motivations to write it was to initiate Yusoku kojitsu to his son MINAMOTO no Toshikata who had been sent to Dazai-fu with him during the Anwa Incident.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。Toshikata に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>何度か増補・校訂が行われたらしく、初稿本・再稿本などが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book appears to have been enlarged and revised several times, and the first manuscript and the revised manuscripts exist.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book appears to have been enlarged and revised several times, and the first and the revised manuscripts exist.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book appears to have been enlarged and revised several times, and the first and the revised manuscripts exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>更に高明没後にも後一条天皇の時代に整理・加筆された（源経頼説がある）部分があり、内容・構成が違う3種類以上の系統の本があったとみられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there are parts that were improved (by MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori, according to a theory) after the death of Takaakira, and it is considered that there were more than three lines of books with different contents and organizations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there are parts that were improved (by MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori, according to a theory) after the death of Takaakira, and it is considered that there were more than three lines of books with different contents and organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there are parts that were improved (by MINAMOTO no Tsuneyori, according to a theory) after the death of Takaakira during the reign of the Emperor Goichijo, and it is considered that there were more than three lines of books with different contents and organizations.</e>
<cmt>後一条天皇　追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>更に書写の途中で他の書の内容の混入や重複した記述も行われたと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also considered that some contents of other books were mixed in while copying and that there are overlapping descriptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also considered that some contents of other books were mixed in while copying and that there are overlapping descriptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also considered that some contents of other books were mixed in while copying and that there are overlapping descriptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため、巻数が様々で記録では4巻・10巻・15巻・16巻などと伝えられているが、現存本には17巻・18巻本なども存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, there are different theories about how many volumes the book came in, but among the existing books, there is a book in seventeen volumes and one in eighteen volumes, though the record indicates various numbers including four, ten, fifteen and sixteen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, there are different theories about how many volumes the book came in, but among the existing books, there is a book in seventeen volumes and one in eighteen volumes, though the record indicates various numbers including four, ten, fifteen, and sixteen.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, there are different theories about how many volumes the book came in, but among the existing books, there is a book in 17 volumes and one in 18 volumes, although the record indicates various numbers including 4, 10, 15, and 16.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、15巻本が高明による原撰本と考えられているが現存せず、本文を整理して代わりに勘物などを充実させた10巻本が流布本として広く知られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the book in fifteen volumes was the original version by Takaakira, but it does not exist, and the book in ten volumes was widely known as the rufu-bon (widely circulated edition), which had been sorted out and added kanmotsu (annotation of a book) instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the book in fifteen volumes was the original version by Takaakira, but it does not exist, and the book in ten volumes was widely known as the rufu-bon (widely circulated edition), which had been sorted out and added kanmotsu (annotation of a book) instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the book in 15 volumes was the original version by Takaakira, but it does not exist, and the book in 10 volumes was widely known as the rufu-bon (widely circulated edition), which had been sorted out and added kanmotsu (annotation of a book) instead.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>基本的な構造としては、毎年の恒例行事を1月から12月まで月ごとに配列した「恒例」と臨時に発生する行事について記した「臨時」に分けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, the structure is divided into two parts: &apos;Annual&apos; where annual events per month were lined up from January to December and &apos;Temporary&apos; where descriptions are given about the events that took place on a temporary basis.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, the structure is divided into two parts: &apos;Annual&apos; where annual events per month were lined up from January to December and &apos;Temporary&apos; where descriptions are given about the events that took place on a temporary basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, the structure is divided into two parts: &apos;Annual&apos; where annual events per month were lined up from January to December and &apos;Temporary&apos; where descriptions are given about the events that took place on a temporary basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>個々の記述は割注を含めた「本文」と多くの文献の引用などによって出典を示した多数の頭書・傍書・裏書などからなる「勘物」から構成されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each description consists of the &apos;text&apos; including notes inserted between the lines, and kanmotsu (annotation of a book) comprised of many Tosho (superscription), 傍書, and book-end notes showing the sources of quotations from many books.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each description consists of the &apos;text&apos; including notes inserted between the lines, and kanmotsu (annotation of a book) comprised of many Tosho (superscription), 傍書, and book-end notes showing the sources of quotations from many books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each description consists of the &apos;text&apos; including notes inserted between the lines, and &apos;kanmotsu&apos; comprised of many Tosho (superscription), bosho (傍書) (additions or supplements written by the side of the main texts), and book-end notes showing the sources of quotations from many books.</e>
<cmt>傍書→bosho (additions or supplements written by the side of the main texts) としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>10世紀の宮中儀式の内容とその由来ついて詳細に知るための根本史料として重要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is an important historical material that provides the details about the contents of the ceremonial rites of imperial court and the origins of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is an important historical material that provides the details about the contents of the ceremonial rites of imperial court and the origins of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is an important historical material that provides in detail the contents and origins about the ceremonial rites of Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>現在知られている古写本としては、尊経閣文庫蔵書の巻子本18巻（恒例7巻・臨時10巻・目録1巻、ただし恒例1巻・臨時4巻は重複）、東山御文庫蔵書の巻子本3巻（恒例1月分1巻、臨時2巻）、宮内庁書陵部蔵書の巻子本17巻（恒例8巻・臨時9巻、ただし恒例・臨時のうちそれぞれ2巻は江戸時代の写本）などが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eighteen volumes of Kansubon (book in scroll style) possessed by Sonkenkaku bunko (seven volumes of Annual, ten volumes of Temporary, and one volume of catalogue, though one of the volumes of Annual and four volumes of Temporary overlap) and seventeen volumes of Kansubon in the collection of Imperial Household Archives (eight volumes of Annual, nine volumes of Temporary, though two volumes of each overlap) are among the known old manuscripts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eighteen volumes of Kansubon (book in scroll style) possessed by Sonkenkaku bunko (seven volumes of Annual, ten volumes of Temporary, and one volume of catalogue, though one of the volumes of Annual and four volumes of Temporary overlap) and seventeen volumes of Kansubon in the collection of Imperial Household Archives (eight volumes of Annual, nine volumes of Temporary, though two volumes of each overlap) are among the known old manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">18 volumes of Kansubon (book in scroll style) possessed by Sonkeikaku-bunko Library (7 volumes of Annual, 10 volumes of Temporary, and 1 volume of catalogue, although one of the volumes of Annual and 4 volumes of Temporary overlap), 3 volumes of Kansubon possessed by Higashiyama Go-bunko collection (1 volume of the section on January of Annual and 2 volumes of Temporary), and 17 volumes of Kansubon in the collection of Imperial Household Archives (8 volumes of Annual, 9 volumes of Temporary, although 2 volumes of each were manuscripts from the Edo period) are among the known old manuscripts.</e>
<cmt>一部アラビア数字にしました。翻訳を追加しました。固有名詞の読みを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>