<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>軍部大臣現役武官制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule (Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule)</e>
<cmt>語順を仕様指示書に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>軍部大臣現役武官制（ぐんぶだいじんげんえきぶかんせい）とは、軍部大臣（陸軍大臣、海軍大臣）の補任資格を現役の武官（軍人）に限る制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; (Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei) is a regulation to limit the appointing authority of military ministers (Minister of Army and navy) to only active military officers.</e>
<cmt>補人資格: appointing authority</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule) is a regulation to limit the appointing authority of Military Ministers (Minister of War and the Navy) to only active military officers.</e>
<cmt>語順を仕様指示書に合わせました(上記に同じ)。&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; (Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei) &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule) military ministers &gt; Military MinistersMinister of Army and navy &gt; Minister of War and the Navy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule) is a regulation to limit the appointing authority of Military Ministers (Minister of War and the Navy) to only active military officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現役武官に限るため、文官はもちろん予備役・後備役・退役の武官には、補任資格がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the fact that the authority is limited to only active military officers, military officers including Yobieki (reserve duty), Kobieki (one of military service that came after Geneki and Yobieki), and Taieki (retired) do not have appointing authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the fact that the authority is limited to only active military officers, military officers including Yobieki (reserve duty), Kobieki (one of military service that came after Geneki and Yobieki), and Taieki (retired) do not have appointing authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the fact that the authority is limited to only active military officers, military officers including Yobieki (reserve duty), Kobieki (one of military service that came after Geneki and Yobieki), and Taieki (retired) do not have appointing authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>文民統制の対義語として用いられることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Rule is the antithesis of civil regulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rule is the antithesis of civil regulation.</e>
<cmt>Rule &gt; rule</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rule is the antithesis of civil regulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>軍部大臣現役武官制は、軍部大臣の補任資格を現役武官の大将・中将に限る制度であり、軍部大臣の補任資格を武官の大将・中将に限る「軍部大臣武官制」より資格者の範囲をさらに狭めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; is a regulation to limit military ministers&apos; appointing authority to only active Taisho (general) and Chusho (lieutenant general), and limit this authority to military officers such as Taisho and Chusho in accordance with &apos;Military Ministers to be Officers&apos; to narrow down the cadidates.</e>
<cmt>Original text is confusing; repeating the same thing twice.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei is a regulation to limit Military Ministers&apos; appointing authority to only active Taisho (general) and Chusho (lieutenant general), and limit this authority to military officers such as Taisho and Chusho in accordance with &apos;Gunbu Daijin Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers)&apos; to narrow down the candidates.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seimilitary ministers &gt; Military MinistersMilitary Ministers to be Officers &gt; Gunbu Daijin Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers) cadidates &gt; candidates</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei is a regulation to limit Military Ministers&apos; appointing authority to only active Taisho (general) and Chusho (lieutenant general), and limit this authority to military officers such as Taisho and Chusho in accordance with &apos;Gunbu Daijin Bukan sei (Military Ministers to be Officers)&apos; to narrow down the candidates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>現役とは平時軍務に従事する常備兵役を指し、現役武官の人事は、内閣 (日本)の関与が不可能な天皇の統帥権に関わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geneki (active officer) refers to an individual in regular military service engaged in normal military affairs, and their administration is under the supreme command of the emperor that the Cabinet cannot affect.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t think the （日本） part was necessary.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geneki (active officer) refers to an individual in regular military service engaged in normal military affairs, and their administration is under the supreme command of the Emperor that the Cabinet cannot affect.</e>
<cmt>the emperor &gt; the Emperor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geneki (active officer) refers to an individual in regular military service engaged in normal military affairs, and their administration is under the supreme command of the Emperor that the Cabinet cannot affect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このため、軍部大臣現役武官制の採用によって組閣に軍部の合意が事実上必要となり、軍部によるその意向にそわない組閣の阻止が可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, by employing &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule,&quot; it was, in fact, necessary for the formation of a Cabinet to obtain the consent of the military and through the employment of this regulation, the military was able to prevent the formation of any Cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, by employing Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei, it was, in fact, necessary for the formation of a Cabinet to obtain the consent of the military and through the employment of this regulation the military was able to prevent the formation of any Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seiカンマを削除しました。regulation, &gt; regulation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, by employing Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei, it was, in fact, necessary for the formation of a Cabinet to obtain the consent of the military and through the employment of this regulation the military was able to prevent the formation of any Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、たとえ一度組閣されても、内閣が軍部と対立した場合、軍が軍部大臣を辞職させて後任を指定しないことにより内閣を総辞職に追い込み、合法的な倒閣を行うことができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if a Cabinet was formed and a conflict between the Cabinet and the military occured, the military legally owned the power to dissolve any Cabinet by forcing a minister to resign and not designating a replacement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if a Cabinet was formed, in case that a conflict between the Cabinet and the military occurred, the military legally owned the power to dissolve any Cabinet by forcing a Military Minister to resign and not designating a replacement.</e>
<cmt>原文の文脈に合うよう変更しました。a Cabinet was formed and a conflict &gt; a Cabinet was formed, in case that a conflictoccured &gt; occurredminister &gt; Military Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if a Cabinet was formed, in case that a conflict between the Cabinet and the military occurred, the military legally owned the power to dissolve any Cabinet by forcing a Military Minister to resign and not designating a replacement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このようにして、軍部の政治介入が可能となり、軍部の政治的優位が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how the political intervention of the military became possible and defined the military&apos;s political superiority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how the political intervention of the military became possible and defined the military&apos;s political superiority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how the political intervention of the military became possible and defined the military&apos;s political superiority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本では、明治時代の初め、当時の軍部大臣に当たる兵部卿の補任資格を「少将以上」の者に限っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, candidates for the appointing authority of Hyobukyo (Minister for Military Affairs), which was the military minister at that time, were limited only to ranks higher than &apos;Shosho&apos; (Major general).</e>
<cmt>I think 「日本では」 is unnecessary in this context; it is obvious that this passage is refering to the Japanese military. I omitted that part.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Meiji period, candidates for the appointing authority of Hyobukyo (Minister for Military Affairs), which was the Military Minister at that time, were limited only to ranks &apos;higher than Shosho (major general)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>higher than &apos;Shosho&apos; (Major general). &gt; &apos;higher than Shosho (major general)&apos;.military minister &gt; Military Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, candidates for the appointing authority of Hyobukyo (Minister for Military Affairs), which was the Military Minister at that time, were limited only to ranks &apos;higher than Shosho (major general)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その後、同様の規定は中断したり復活したりしていたが、1900年（明治33年）に、山縣有朋首相の主導で、軍部大臣現役武官制を明確に規定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, the same restriction was repeatedly aborted and revived; however, &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; was redefined by prime minister Aritomo YAMAGATA in 1900.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, the same restriction was repeatedly aborted and revived; however, Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was redefined by Prime Minister Aritomo YAMAGATA in 1900.</e>
<cmt>Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seiprime minister Aritomo YAMAGATA &gt; Prime Minister Aritomo YAMAGATA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, the same restriction was repeatedly aborted and revived; however, Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was redefined by Prime Minister Aritomo YAMAGATA in 1900.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは、当時勢力を伸張していた政党に対して、軍部を権力の淵源としていた藩閥が、影響力を維持するために執った措置とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered a measure that the domain cliques, whose autority was derived from the military, took to retain their influence over the political parties that were expanding their power at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Domain clique&quot; sounds funny, but I couldn&apos;t come up with something better.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considered a measure that the domain cliques, whose authority was derived from the military, took to retain their influence over the political parties that were expanding their power at that time.</e>
<cmt>autority &gt; authority無駄なスペースを削除しました。military, took &gt; military, took</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is considered a measure that the domain cliques, whose authority was derived from the military, took to retain their influence over the political parties that were expanding their power at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、日露戦争後の国際状況の安定と政党政治の成熟により藩閥と軍部の影響力は衰え、1913年（大正2年）には軍部大臣の補任資格を「現役」に限る制度が改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the global stablization and maturity of the party government after the Russo-Japanese War, the domain cliques and the military lost their influence and the system was revised to regulate the military minister&apos;s appointing autority to only &apos;active role&apos; in 1913.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the global stabilization and maturity of the party government after the Russo-Japanese War, the domain cliques and the military lost their influence and the system was revised to regulate the military minister&apos;s appointing authority to only &apos;active-duty&apos; in 1913.</e>
<cmt>stablization &gt; stabilizationautority &gt; authority active role &gt; active-duty</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the global stabilization and maturity of the party government after the Russo-Japanese War, the domain cliques and the military lost their influence and the system was revised to regulate the military minister&apos;s appointing authority to only &apos;active-duty&apos; in 1913.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>再び軍部の影響力が強まった1936年（昭和11年）に軍部大臣現役武官制は復活し、1945年（昭和20年）の終戦後、軍部大臣が消滅するまで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the military influence came back in full force in 1936, the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; was revived and continued until the military minister&apos;s role became extinct after the end of the World War II in 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the military influence came back in full force in 1936, Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was revived and continued until the Military Minister&apos;s role became extinct after the end of the World War II in 1945.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seimilitary minister&apos;s &gt; Military Minister&apos;s</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the military influence came back in full force in 1936, Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was revived and continued until the Military Minister&apos;s role became extinct after the end of the World War II in 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>一方、日本以外の国、特に西欧諸国においては、第二次世界大戦以前においても軍部大臣に文官を任用する例も多く、政治の軍事に対する優位を原則とするシビリアン・コントロールの理念が確立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the oher hand, in many countries other than Japan especially in Western Europe, there were examples of civil officers who were appointed to the position of military minister even after the World War II, and the Civilian Control philosophy which claims the superiority of military afairs over politics was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in many countries other than Japan especially in Western Europe, there were examples of civil officers who were appointed to the position of Military Minister even after the World War II, and the Civilian Control philosophy which claims the superiority of military affairs over politics was established.</e>
<cmt>oher &gt; othermilitary minister &gt; Military Ministerafairs &gt; affairs</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in many countries other than Japan especially in Western Europe, there were examples of civil officers who were appointed to the position of Military Minister even after the World War II, and the Civilian Control philosophy which claims the superiority of military affairs over politics was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prehistory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prehistory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prehistory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>軍部大臣現役武官制は、1871年（明治4年）7月、兵部省職員令に「卿一人　本官少将以上」として、兵部卿には少将以上の者をあてると定めたことが起源とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; was originated from the Hyobusho&apos;s Shikinryo (law which stipulates duties of this ministries) in July, 1871: &apos;one minister with a rank higher than Shosho,&apos; defined the eligibility of Hyobusho as having to be higher than the Shoho rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was originated from the Hyobusho&apos;s Shikinryo (law which stipulates duties of the Ministry of Military) in July, 1871: &apos;one minister with a rank higher than Shosho,&apos; defined the eligibility of Hyobukyo as having to be higher than the Shosho rank.</e>
<cmt>Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seithis ministries &gt; the Ministry of Militarythe eligibility of Hyobusho &gt; the eligibility of HyobukyoShoho &gt; Shosho</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was originated from the Hyobusho&apos;s Shikinryo (law which stipulates duties of the Ministry of Military) in July, 1871: &apos;one minister with a rank higher than Shosho,&apos; defined the eligibility of Hyobukyo as having to be higher than the Shosho rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、1886年（明治19年）2月27日に公布された各省官制（明治19年勅令第2号）では、次官以下の「陸軍省職員」、「海軍省職員」については、「武官ヲ以テ之ニ補ス」として、原則的に武官を任用すると定めたものの（陸軍2条、海軍2条、通則25条）、大臣については特に定めを置かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to each ministry regulation (imperial edict Vol.2, 1886), publically announced in February 27, 1886, with regards to officers in the &apos;Ministry of the Army&apos; and the &apos;Ministry of the Navy&apos; that were lower than the Suke (vice minister) rank and defined as &apos;with military officer rank, eligible to appoint,&apos; it was determined that the military officer will be installed in principal; however, there were no rules about the ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, according to each ministry regulation (imperial edict Vol.2, 1886), publically announced in February 27, 1886, with regards to &apos;officers in the Department of War and the Department of the Navy&apos; lower than the Suke (vice minister) rank, &apos;military officers are eligible to be appointed this position&apos; and it was determined that military officers would be installed in principal (Army regulations, article 2; Navy regulations, article 2; General regulations, article 25); however, there were no rules about the ministers.</e>
<cmt>「その後」の訳が抜けていたので追加しました。原文の文脈に合うよう「with regards to」に続く文面を修正しました。the Ministry of the Army &gt; the Department of Warthe Ministry of the Navy &gt; the Department of the Navy「（陸軍2条、海軍2条、通則25条）」の訳が抜けているので追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, according to each ministry regulation (imperial edict Vol.2, 1886), publically announced in February 27, 1886, with regards to &apos;officers in the Department of War and the Department of the Navy&apos; lower than the Suke (vice minister) rank, &apos;military officers are eligible to be appointed this position&apos; and it was determined that military officers would be installed in principal (Army regulations, article 2; Navy regulations, article 2; General regulations, article 25); however, there were no rules about the ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>1890年（明治23年）3月27日には、陸軍官制および海軍官制を改正し、「職員」に武官を任用するとの原則規定を削除した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 27, 1890, the Army and the Navy regulations were revised and the rule to install military officers as &apos;personnel&apos; in principal was crossed off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 27, 1890, the Army and the Navy regulations were revised and the rule to install military officers as &apos;personnel&apos; in principal was crossed off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 27, 1890, the Army and the Navy regulations were revised and the rule to install military officers as &apos;personnel&apos; in principal was crossed off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ただ、陸軍省官制では大臣に「将官」をあてると定め（別表）、海軍省官制では特に定めを置かなかった（別表参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was ruled that the &apos;general&apos; (shokan) will be placed as a minister (appendix) according to the Army regulations, however, there was no specification in the Navy regulations (see appendix).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was ruled that &apos;Shokan&apos; will be placed as a minister (appendix) according to the Department of War regulations, however, there was no specification in the Department of the Navy regulations (see appendix).</e>
<cmt>the &apos;general&apos; (shokan) &gt; &apos;Shokan&apos;the Army regulations &gt; the Department of War regulationsthe Navy regulations &gt; the Department of the Navy regulations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was ruled that &apos;Shokan&apos; will be placed as a minister (appendix) according to the Department of War regulations, however, there was no specification in the Department of the Navy regulations (see appendix).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>翌1891年（明治24年）7月27日には、陸軍省官制を改正して、大臣および次官に「将官」をあてるとの定めを削除した（別表参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 2, 1891, the Ministry of the Army regulation was revised: the rule that a minister and Suke will be installed as a &apos;general&apos; was crossed off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 2, 1891, the Department of War regulation was revised: the rule that a minister and Suke will be installed as &apos;Shokan&apos; was crossed off.</e>
<cmt>a &apos;general&apos; &gt; &apos;Shokan&apos;the Ministry of the Army &gt; the Department of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 2, 1891, the Department of War regulation was revised: the rule that a minister and Suke will be installed as &apos;Shokan&apos; was crossed off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これにより、陸海軍省ともに、大臣を武官に限るとの定めをなくした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This also removed the rule for both the Ministry of the Army and the Navy that only a military officer could be installed as a minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This also removed the rule for both the Department of War and the Navy that only a military officer could be installed as a minister.</e>
<cmt>the Ministry of the Army and the Navy&gt; the Department of War and the Navy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This also removed the rule for both the Department of War and the Navy that only a military officer could be installed as a minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、この時期においても現役将官以外が軍部大臣となった例はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, even in this era, there is no evidence that anyone but active generals became military ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, even in this era, there is no evidence that anyone but active generals became Military Ministers.</e>
<cmt>military ministers &gt; Military Ministers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even in this era, there is no evidence that anyone but active generals became Military Ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>創設</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Foundation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Foundation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Foundation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>1900年（明治33年）、第2次山縣内閣は、陸軍省官制および海軍省官制を改正し、「大臣（大中将）」、「陸軍大臣及総務長官ニ任セラルルモノハ現役将官ヲ以テス」と定めた（附表、別表）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, the second Yamagata Cabinet revised the Ministry of the Army regulation and the Ministry of the Navy regulation, and determined that a &apos;minister (lieutenant general)&apos; and &apos;a candidate that the Army minister and the secretary appoint shall be an active general&apos; (appended table, appendix).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1900, the second Yamagata Cabinet revised the Department of War regulation and the Department of the Navy regulation, and determined that a &apos;minister (lieutenant general)&apos; and &apos;a candidate appointed as War Minister and the Secretary shall be an active general&apos; (appended table, appendix).</e>
<cmt>a candidateの文を修正しました。the Army regulation &gt; the Department of War regulationthe Navy regulation &gt; the Department of the Navy regulationthe Army minister and the secretary &gt; War Minister and the Secretary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900, the second Yamagata Cabinet revised the Department of War regulation and the Department of the Navy regulation, and determined that a &apos;minister (lieutenant general)&apos; and &apos;a candidate appointed as War Minister and the Secretary shall be an active general&apos; (appended table, appendix).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これは、軍部を権力の淵源としていた藩閥勢力が、当時力を付けて来た議会・政党勢力の軍事費削減攻勢に対する処置として執ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This action was taken by the domain cliques whose authority originated in the military, to go against the cut-back of military expenditures of the assembly and the political party which then had power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This action was taken by the domain cliques whose authority originated in the military, to go against the cut-back of military expenditures of the assembly and the political party which then had power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This action was taken by the domain cliques whose authority originated in the military, to go against the cut-back of military expenditures of the assembly and the political party which then had power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これ以後、大命降下があっても、軍部が現役武官の中から大臣候補を挙げなければ組閣できず、辞職して代わりの候補を出さなければ内閣を維持することもできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, even if an imperial command was given, the military would only elect a ministerial candidate from active military officers in order to form a Cabinet and they could not retain a Cabinet unless a Cabinet minister resigned and elected another candidate.</e>
<cmt>The meaning of original text is confusing.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, even if an imperial command was given, the military would only elect a ministerial candidate from active military officers in order to form a Cabinet and they could not retain a Cabinet unless electing another candidate after a Military Minister resigned.</e>
<cmt>訳1では「内閣が辞職する」となっていたのですが、「軍部大臣が辞職する」と解釈して修正しました。unless a Cabinet minister resigned and elected another candidate &gt; unless electing another candidatea after a Military Minister resigned</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, even if an imperial command was given, the military would only elect a ministerial candidate from active military officers in order to form a Cabinet and they could not retain a Cabinet unless electing another candidate after a Military Minister resigned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この規定によって、軍部の意向を抜きに組閣し、内閣を維持することは難しくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Retaining a Cabinet without the military&apos;s consent became difficult with this regulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Retaining a Cabinet without the military&apos;s consent became difficult with this regulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Retaining a Cabinet without the military&apos;s consent became difficult with this regulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>第二次西園寺公望内閣のとき、緊縮財政による国家財政再建や行政整理を理由に、西園寺公望首相が、陸軍による「二個師団増設」の要求を拒否した（二個師団増設問題）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the second Kinmochi SAIONJI Cabinet, because of the national financial reconstruction and the administraion by reduced budget, prime minister Kinomochi SAIONJI refused the Army&apos;s &apos;two division expansion&apos; demand (two divisions expansion issue).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the second Kinmochi SAIONJI Cabinet, because of the national financial reconstruction and the administration by reduced budget, Prime Minister Kinomochi SAIONJI refused the Army&apos;s &apos;two division expansion&apos; demand (two divisions&apos; expansion issue).</e>
<cmt>administraion &gt; administrationprime minister &gt; Prime Ministerdivisions &gt; divisions&apos;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the second Kinmochi SAIONJI Cabinet, because of the national financial reconstruction and the administration by reduced budget, Prime Minister Kinomochi SAIONJI refused the Army&apos;s &apos;two division expansion&apos; demand (two divisions&apos; expansion issue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これに対して、上原勇作陸軍大臣が、単独で帷幄上奏して辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To which minister of the Army, Yusaku UEHARA, acted as iaku-joso (to make comments on military affairs to the Emperor with full responsibility of the results) and resigned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To which War Minister Yusaku UEHARA acted as iaku-joso (to make comments on military affairs to the Emperor with full responsibility of the results) and resigned.</e>
<cmt>minister of the Army, Yusaku UEHARA, &gt; War Minister Yusaku UEHARA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, War Minister Yusaku UEHARA acted as iaku-joso (to make comments on military affairs to the Emperor with full responsibility of the results) and resigned.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>陸軍は後任の候補を出さず、軍部大臣現役武官制のために、第二次西園寺内閣は陸軍大臣を欠き、内閣は総辞職せざるを得なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Army did not elect a replacement in accordance with the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot;; therefore, the second Kinomochi SAIONJI lacked a minister of the Army and the Cabinet as a whole was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Army did not elect a replacement, and in accordance with the Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei; therefore, the second Kinomochi SAIONJI lacked the Minister of War and the Cabinet as a whole was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>a replacement in accordance &gt; a replacement, and in accordanceMilitary Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seithe Minister of the Army &gt; the Minister of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Army did not elect a replacement, and in accordance with the Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei; therefore, the second Kinomochi SAIONJI lacked the Minister of War and the Cabinet as a whole was dissolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>結果的に軍部による合法的な倒閣が実現される恰好となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, termination of a Cabinet by the military was legally granted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, termination of a Cabinet by the military was legally granted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, termination of a Cabinet by the military was legally granted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>この政変は「陸軍のストライキ」と言われ、以降、国政において軍部大臣現役武官制が注目される契機となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This political change was called &apos;the Strike of the Army&apos; and then triggered the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; to attract attention in national politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This political change was called &apos;the Strike of the Army&apos; and then triggered the Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei to attract attention in national politics.</e>
<cmt>Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This political change was called &apos;the Strike of the Army&apos; and then triggered the Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei to attract attention in national politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>廃止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abolition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abolition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abolition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>1913年（大正2年）6月13日、第1次山本内閣において、陸軍省官制および海軍省官制を改正して、軍部大臣の補任資格を現役将官に限るとの規定を削除した（附表、別表）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 13, 1913, with the first Yamamoto Cabinet, the Ministry of the Army and the Ministry of the Navy were revised; the rule to limit the military minister&apos;s appointing authority to only active officers was crossed off (appended table, appendix).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 13, 1913, with the first Yamamoto Cabinet, the Department of War and the Department of the Navy were revised; the rule to limit the Military Ministers&apos; appointing authority to only active officers was crossed off (appended table, appendix).</e>
<cmt>the military minister&apos;s appointing authority &gt; the Military Ministers&apos; appointing authoritythe Ministry of the Army &gt; the Department of Warthe Ministry of the Navy &gt; the Department of the Navy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 13, 1913, with the first Yamamoto Cabinet, the Department of War and the Department of the Navy were revised; the rule to limit the Military Ministers&apos; appointing authority to only active officers was crossed off (appended table, appendix).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この改正により、軍部大臣武官制は存続したものの、軍部大臣現役武官制は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This amendment abolished the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rules&quot; although the &quot;Military Minsters to be Officers Rules&quot; remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This amendment abolished Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei although Gunbu Daijin Bukan sei remained.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seiMilitary Ministers to be Officers &gt; Gunbu Daijin Bukan sei</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This amendment abolished Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei although Gunbu Daijin Bukan sei remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これは、当時、一大国民運動となっていた護憲運動の影響を受けて、山縣有朋・桂太郎らを中心とする軍部と藩閥の反対を押し切り、山本権兵衛内閣総理大臣と木越安綱陸軍大臣が断行したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This, at the time, was influenced by a major civic movement, the Constitution Protection Movement, when prime minister Gombei YAMAMOTO and the Army minister Yasutsuna KIGOSHI pushed through the disagreements among the military and the doman clique including Arimoto YAMADATA and Taro KATSURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This, at the time, was influenced by a major civic movement, the Constitution Protection Movement, when Prime Minister Gombei YAMAMOTO and War Minister Yasutsuna KIGOSHI pushed through the disagreements among the military and the domain clique including Arimoto YAMADATA and Taro KATSURA.</e>
<cmt>Doman &gt; domainprime minister &gt; Prime MinisterArmy Minister &gt; War Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This, at the time, was influenced by a major civic movement, the Constitution Protection Movement, when Prime Minister Gombei YAMAMOTO and War Minister Yasutsuna KIGOSHI pushed through the disagreements among the military and the domain clique including Arimoto YAMADATA and Taro KATSURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この結果、日清戦争と日露戦争の軍歴により国民的人気の高かった木越は、中将のまま定年前に予備役に編入させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, KIGOSHI who earned his high reputation though Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War from the public, was transferred to reserve duty retaining the title of Chujo (lieutenant general) before his retirement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Kigoshi who earned his high reputation through Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War from the public was transferred to reserve duty retaining the title of Chujo (lieutenant general) before his retirement.</e>
<cmt>KIGOSHI &gt; Kigoshithough &gt; throughpublic, &gt; public</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Kigoshi who earned his high reputation through Sino-Japanese War and Russo-Japanese War from the public was transferred to reserve duty retaining the title of Chujo (lieutenant general) before his retirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>なお、実際の運用では、予備役・後備役・退役の将官などから軍部大臣を任命した例はなく、一旦現役に復帰してから大臣に任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an actuality, there was no example of a military minister being elected from Shokan (general) from Yobieki (reserve duty), Kobieki (one of military service that came after Geneki and Yobieki), and Taieki (retired); a cadidate once returned to active duty and was elected as a minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an actuality, there was no example of a Military Minister being elected from Shokan from Yobieki, Kobieki, and Taieki; a candidate once returned to active duty and was elected as a minister.</e>
<cmt>military minister &gt; Military MinisterShokan (general) from Yobieki (reserve duty), Kobieki (one of military service that came after Geneki and Yobieki), and Taieki (retired) &gt; Shokan from Yobieki, Kobieki, and Taieki;cadidate &gt; candidate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an actuality, there was no example of a Military Minister being elected from Shokan from Yobieki, Kobieki, and Taieki; a candidate once returned to active duty and was elected as a minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし、補任資格が予備役・後備役・退役の将官まで広がったことで、大臣候補の範囲も広がり、以後組閣時の苦労が激減した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the fact that the range of the appointing authority was expanded to Yobieki, Kobieki, and Taieki, the range of ministerial cadidates was automatically expanded as well; this alleviated possible issues during the formation of a Cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the fact that the range of the appointing authority was expanded to Yobieki, Kobieki, and Taieki, the range of ministerial candidates was automatically expanded as well; this alleviated possible issues during the formation of a Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>cadidate &gt; candidate</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the fact that the range of the appointing authority was expanded to Yobieki, Kobieki, and Taieki, the range of ministerial candidates was automatically expanded as well; this alleviated possible issues during the formation of a Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>もっとも、第1次山本内閣の後を受けて大命降下した清浦奎吾は、海軍拡張（八八艦隊の建造費用）について海軍と合意できず、海軍大臣候補が得られなかったため、組閣を断念している（鰻香内閣）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Keigo KIYOURA, however, who was given an imperial command after taking over the first Yamamoto Cabinet, it proved impossible to gain consensus in regards to the Navy expansion (construction costs for fleet 88) and to obtain the Navy&apos;s ministerial candidates; therefore, he gave up on forming a Cabinet (Manko Cabinet).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Keigo KIYOURA, however, who was given an imperial command after taking over the first Yamamoto Cabinet, it proved impossible to gain consensus in regards to the Navy expansion (construction costs for fleet 88) and to obtain the Navy&apos;s ministerial candidates; therefore, he gave up on forming a Cabinet (Manko Cabinet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Keigo KIYOURA, however, who was given an imperial command after taking over the first Yamamoto Cabinet, it proved impossible to gain consensus in regards to the Navy expansion (construction costs for fleet 88) and to obtain the Navy&apos;s ministerial candidates; therefore, he gave up on forming a Cabinet (Manko Cabinet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>伊藤正徳 (軍事評論家)によると、制度としては予備役でもよいとなっていても、実際問題として誰が適任で誰が空いているか、清浦には全く見当がつかなかった上に相談相手も得られなかったので組閣断念に至ったという（また、清浦が軍部大臣現役武官制の擁護者であった山縣有朋の側近であったことも大きい）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Shotoku ITO (military critic), even if Yobieki was accepted by the system, KIYOURA probably would not have known who might be appropriate or available, and besides he did not have any consultants to discuss with; therefore, he gave up on forming a Cabinet (moreover, the fact that KIYOURA was a close adviser of Arimoto YAMAGATA, who was an advocate for the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule,&quot; played a part).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Shotoku ITO (military critic), even if Yobieki was accepted by the system, Kiyoura probably would not have known who might be appropriate or available, and besides he did not have any consultants to discuss with; therefore, he gave up on forming a Cabinet (moreover, the fact that Kiyoura was a close adviser of Arimoto YAMAGATA, who was an advocate for Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei, played a part).</e>
<cmt>KIYOURA &gt; Kiyoura&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Shotoku ITO (military critic), even if Yobieki was accepted by the system, Kiyoura probably would not have known who might be appropriate or available, and besides he did not have any consultants to discuss with; therefore, he gave up on forming a Cabinet (moreover, the fact that Kiyoura was a close adviser of Arimoto YAMAGATA, who was an advocate for Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei, played a part).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>復活</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revival</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revival</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="39">
<j>1936年（昭和11年）、広田内閣のとき、陸軍省官制及び海軍省官制に「大臣及次官ニ任セラルル者ハ現役将官トス」との規定を設けて（附表、別表）、軍部大臣現役武官制を復活させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1936, during the Hirota Cabinet, the regulation &apos;a candidate that a minister and a Suke (vice minister) appoint shall be an active general&apos; was implemented (appended table, appendix) and the &quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; was revived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1936, during the Hirota Cabinet, the regulation &apos;a candidate that a minister and a Suke (vice minister) appoint shall be an active general&apos; was implemented as the Department of War and the Navy regulation (appended table, appendix) and Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was revived.</e>
<cmt>「陸軍省官制及び海軍省官制に」の訳が抜けているので追加しました。&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1936, during the Hirota Cabinet, the regulation &apos;a candidate that a minister and a Suke (vice minister) appoint shall be an active general&apos; was implemented as the Department of War and the Navy regulation (appended table, appendix) and Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei was revived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この制度復活の口実には、「二・二六事件への関与が疑われた予備役武官（事件への関与が疑われた荒木貞夫や真崎甚三郎が、事件後に予備役に編入されていた）を、軍部大臣に就かせない」ということが挙げられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason behind this system was &apos;not to replace the suspected Yobieki military officers of the involvement in the Feburary 26th Incident (suspects for the incident&apos;s involvement, Sadao ARAKI and Jinzaburo MAZAKI, were then transferred to Yobieki after the incident) to the military minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason behind this system&apos;s revival was &apos;not to replace the suspected Yobieki military officers of the involvement in the Feburary 26th Incident (suspects for the incident&apos;s involvement, Sadao ARAKI and Jinzaburo MAZAKI, were then transferred to Yobieki after the incident) to the military minister.</e>
<cmt>「復活」の訳が抜けていたので追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason behind this system&apos;s revival was &apos;not to replace the suspected Yobieki military officers of the involvement in the Feburary 26th Incident (suspects for the incident&apos;s involvement, Sadao ARAKI and Jinzaburo MAZAKI, were then transferred to Yobieki after the incident) to the military minister.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この制度を復活させた広田内閣は、腹切り問答によって自らが制定した軍部大臣現役武官制による陸軍大臣と揉めて、議会を解散する要求を拒絶する代わりに総辞職に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hirota Cabinet, who revived this system, had a conflict due to the Harakiri Mondo (the Harakiri questionaires) with the Minister of the Army over the Military &quot;Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; which he formulated himself, and was driven to resign instead of commanding the assembly to dismiss.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hirota Cabinet, which revived this system, had a conflict due to the Harakiri Mondo (the Harakiri questionaires) with the Minister of War over Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei which he formulated himself, and was driven to resign instead of commanding the assembly to dismiss.</e>
<cmt>who &gt; which&quot;Military Ministers to be Officers on Active-duty Rule&quot; &gt; Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan seithe Minister of the Army &gt; the Minister of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hirota Cabinet, which revived this system, had a conflict due to the Harakiri Mondo (the Harakiri questionaires) with the Minister of War over Gunbu Daijin Geneki Bukan sei which he formulated himself, and was driven to resign instead of commanding the assembly to dismiss.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>その後、1937年（昭和12年）に宇垣一成（予備役陸軍大将）に対して天皇から首相候補に指名されて組閣命令が下った際、陸軍から陸軍大臣の候補者が得られずに組閣を断念せざるを得ない状態へ追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterwards, when Kazushige UGAKI (yobieki army general) was named by the emperor to be a candidate for prime minister, he could not obtain a candidate for the Minister of the Army from within the Army and driven into a situation in which he had to give up forming the Cabinet in 1937.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, when Kazushige UGAKI (Yobieki Army General) was named by the Emperor to be a candidate for Prime Minister, he could not obtain a candidate for the Minister of War from within the Army and driven into a situation in which he had to give up forming the Cabinet in 1937.</e>
<cmt>yobieki army general &gt; Yobieki Army Generalthe emperor &gt; the Emperorprime minister &gt; Prime Ministerthe Minister of the Army &gt; the Minister of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, when Kazushige UGAKI (Yobieki Army General) was named by the Emperor to be a candidate for Prime Minister, he could not obtain a candidate for the Minister of War from within the Army and driven into a situation in which he had to give up forming the Cabinet in 1937.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1940年には米内内閣が畑俊六陸相の単独辞職により崩壊するなど、日本の軍国主義の深刻化に拍車をかけることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The resignation of a single minister of the Army, Shunroku HATA, in 1940 caused the Yonai Cabinet to fail and spurred Japanese militarism to further intensify.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The single resignation of War Minister Shunroku HATA in 1940 caused the Yonai Cabinet to fail and spurred Japanese militarism to further intensify.</e>
<cmt>The resignation of a single minister of the Army, Shunroku HATA &gt; The single resignation of War Minister Shunroku HATA</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The single resignation of War Minister Shunroku HATA in 1940 caused the Yonai Cabinet to fail and spurred Japanese militarism to further intensify.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>なお、大命降下された宇垣から入閣交渉を受けた小磯国昭（当時朝鮮軍 (日本軍)司令官）は「引き受けたとしても、東京に来る途中で「予備役編入」の電報が陸軍上層部から届いて、それで終わりですよ」と答えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, it is said that Kuniaki KOISO (commander of Korean Army (Japanese Army) at that time) who was given an offer to join the Cabinet by UGAKI who held an imperial command, answered, &apos;Even if I accept it, I will probably receive a telegram addressed &apos;Yobieki Transfer&apos; from the upper stratum of the Army, and that&apos;s it.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, it is said that Kuniaki KOISO (commander of Korean Army (Japanese Army) at that time) who was given an offer to join the Cabinet by Ugaki who held an imperial command, answered, &apos;Even if I accept it, I will probably receive a telegram addressed &apos;Yobieki Transfer&apos; from the upper stratum of the Army, and that&apos;s it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>UGAKI &gt; Ugaki</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, it is said that Kuniaki KOISO (commander of Korean Army (Japanese Army) at that time) who was given an offer to join the Cabinet by Ugaki who held an imperial command, answered, &apos;Even if I accept it, I will probably receive a telegram addressed &apos;Yobieki Transfer&apos; from the upper stratum of the Army, and that&apos;s it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>このように現役武官制と言っても現役武官の誰でも陸相に出来るというわけではなく、「軍の総意」にかなわない人事は不可能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, not every active officer was eligible to be a minister of the Army even though it was called the active military officer system; it was impossible for cadidates who did not meet &apos;the military consensus.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, not every active officer was eligible to be a Minister of War even though it was called the active military officer system; it was impossible for candidates who did not meet &apos;the military consensus.&apos;</e>
<cmt>cadidates &gt; candidatesa minister of the Army &gt; a Minister of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, not every active officer was eligible to be a Minister of War even though it was called the active military officer system; it was impossible for candidates who did not meet &apos;the military consensus.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>陸軍の場合は陸軍三長官会議（陸相・参謀総長・教育総監）の合意によって新陸相を推挙することとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of the Army, a new minister of the Army was only recommended with the agreement of the Army&apos;s three Kami (three director generals) (minister of the Army, the Chief of the General Staff, and the Educational Commissioner).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of the Army, a new War Minister was only recommended with the agreement of the Army&apos;s three Kami (three director generals) (War Minister, the Chief of the General Staff, and the Educational Commissioner).</e>
<cmt>minister of the Army &gt; War Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of the Army, a new War Minister was only recommended with the agreement of the Army&apos;s three Kami (three director generals) (War Minister, the Chief of the General Staff, and the Educational Commissioner).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>この「天皇の軍隊の最高幹部がなんら倫理的葛藤なしに天皇の指名した首相を拒否・打倒する」事態については、山本七平・小室直樹・堺屋太一などが社会評論の題材として分析している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Shichihei YAMAMOTO, Naoki KOMURO, and Taichi SAKAIYA analysed the matter that &apos;the top Army executive of the emperor refuses or dismisses a prime minister who the emperor designates&apos; as a subject of social criticism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichihei YAMAMOTO, Naoki KOMURO, and Taichi SAKAIYA analyzed the matter that &apos;the top Army executives of the emperor refuses or dismisses a prime minister who the Emperor designates&apos; as a subject of social criticism.</e>
<cmt>「It is believed that」は原文に無い為、削除しました。Analysed &gt; analyzedArmy executive　&gt; Army executivesthe emperor &gt; the Emperor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichihei YAMAMOTO, Naoki KOMURO, and Taichi SAKAIYA analyzed the matter that &apos;the top Army executives of the emperor refuses or dismisses a prime minister who the Emperor designates&apos; as a subject of social criticism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）、東條内閣が総辞職した際に、東條英機が後継の小磯内閣の陸軍大臣として居残るという動きがあった（東條は首相兼陸相であった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1944, when the TOJO Cabinet dissolved, there was a move by Hideki TOJO to remain as the minister of the Army for the replacement KOISO Cabinet (TOJO was the prime minister and the minister of the Army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1944, when the Tojo Cabinet dissolved, there was a move by Hideki TOJO to remain as the Minister of War for the replacement Koiso Cabinet (Tojo was the Prime Minister and the War Minister).</e>
<cmt>the TOJO Cabinet&gt; the Tojo CabinetKOISO &gt; KoisoTOJO &gt; Tojothe minister of the Army &gt; the Minister of Warthe prime minister and the minister of the Army &gt; the Prime Minister and the War Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1944, when the Tojo Cabinet dissolved, there was a move by Hideki TOJO to remain as the Minister of War for the replacement Koiso Cabinet (Tojo was the Prime Minister and the War Minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この時、当時重臣になっていた広田が小磯に対して「僕と寺内君（現役武官制復活当時の寺内寿一陸相）の合意で、陸相人事は三長官の合意に関係なく新首相が自由に指名していいということになっているから」と告げて、小磯はこれを一つの根拠として東條の陸相留任を阻止したという逸話がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, HIROTA who was then Jushin (chief retainer) told KOISO, &apos;An agreement has been made between Mr. Terauchi (Hisaichi TERAUCHI who was the minister of the Army during revival of the Active Military Officer System) and me, as for the personnel affairs, we&apos;ve accepted to designate a new prime minister regardless of the consent of three Kami (three director generals)&apos; and it is said that this incident was one of the reasons for KOISO preventing TOJO from remaining as the minister of the Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Hirota who was then Jushin (chief retainer) told Koiso, &apos;An agreement has been made between Mr. Terauchi (Hisaichi TERAUCHI who was the Minister of War during revival of Geneki Bukan sei) and me, as for the personnel affairs, we&apos;ve accepted to designate a new Prime Minister regardless of the consent of three Kami&apos; and it is said that this incident was one of the reasons for Koiso preventing Tojo from remaining as the Minister of War.</e>
<cmt>HIROTA &gt; HirotaKOISO &gt; Koisothe Active Military Officer System &gt; Geneki Bukan seiKami (three director generals) &gt; Kamiprime minister &gt; Prime Ministerthe minister of the Army &gt; the Minister of War</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Hirota who was then Jushin (chief retainer) told Koiso, &apos;An agreement has been made between Mr. Terauchi (Hisaichi TERAUCHI who was the Minister of War during revival of Geneki Bukan sei) and me, as for the personnel affairs, we&apos;ve accepted to designate a new Prime Minister regardless of the consent of three Kami&apos; and it is said that this incident was one of the reasons for Koiso preventing Tojo from remaining as the Minister of War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>ただし、この時以外の実際の運用はまったく広田が言うようにはなっておらず、もう一方の当事者寺内はこの時南方軍司令官で海外出征中であり、小磯にしても「話が違う」と思っても指摘するわけがないので真偽不明の話ともいえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the authenticity of this story is doubtful for two reasons: the first, except this time the actual operation totally contradicted HIROTA&apos;s remarks, the second was that the other party, TERAUCHI, was a Southern troop commander in the field abroad at that time and KOISO would not point out &apos;the story is wrong&apos; even if he thought so.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the authenticity of this story is doubtful for two reasons: the first, except this time the actual operation totally contradicted Hirota&apos;s remarks, the second was that the other party, Terauchi, was a Southern troop commander in the field abroad at that time and Koiso would not point out &apos;the story is wrong&apos; even if he thought so.</e>
<cmt>HIROTA &gt; HirotaKOISO &gt; KoisoTERAUCHI &gt; Terauchi</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the authenticity of this story is doubtful for two reasons: the first, except this time the actual operation totally contradicted Hirota&apos;s remarks, the second was that the other party, Terauchi, was a Southern troop commander in the field abroad at that time and Koiso would not point out &apos;the story is wrong&apos; even if he thought so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>なお、昭和期には海軍大臣人事が問題となって内閣の死命が制せられた例はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides this, there was no example of a Cabinet being held up by issues of the navy minister&apos;s personnel affairs during the Showa era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides this, there was no example of a Cabinet being held up by issues of the Navy Minister&apos;s personnel affairs during the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>navy minister&apos;s &gt; Navy Minister&apos;sthe Showa era &gt; the Showa period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides this, there was no example of a Cabinet being held up by issues of the Navy Minister&apos;s personnel affairs during the Showa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>ただ、東條内閣が成立する時に海軍が海相候補として出した豊田副武を東條英機が拒否し、海軍次官の沢本頼雄が「東條じゃどうせ戦争になるから代わりを出さない（ことによって東條内閣を潰す）ことにしましょう」と進言したことがあるが、及川古志郎海相らの判断で嶋田繁太郎を出すことになり、東條内閣は無事成立に至ったという例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were a couple of matters when the TOJO Cabinet was formed; the first, Hideki TOJO refused Soemu TOYODA whom the navy selected as a candidate for the minister of the Navy; the second, deputy minister of the Navy, Yorio SAWAMOTO proceeded with the plan that &apos;it&apos;s going to be a war with TOJO so we shall not select a candidate (to crash the TOJO Cabinet by not selecting),&apos; however, as Shigetaro SHIMADA was selected with the judgement of Koshiro OIKAWA and other ministers of the Navy, the TOJO Cabinet was finally formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were a couple of matters when the Tojo Cabinet was formed; the first, Hideki TOJO refused Soemu TOYODA whom the navy selected as a candidate for the Minister of the Navy; the second, deputy minister of the Navy, Yorio SAWAMOTO proceeded with the plan that &apos;it&apos;s going to be a war with Tojo so we shall not select a candidate (to crash the Tojo Cabinet by not selecting),&apos; however, as Shigetaro SHIMADA was selected with the judgment of Navy Minister Koshiro OIKAWA and others, the Tojo Cabinet was finally formed.</e>
<cmt>the TOJO Cabinet &gt; the Tojo Cabinet with TOJO &gt; with Tojothe minister of the Navy &gt; the Minister of the Navyjudgement &gt; judgmentKoshiro OIKAWA and other ministers of the Navy, &gt; Navy Minister Koshiro OIKAWA and others,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were a couple of matters when the Tojo Cabinet was formed; the first, Hideki TOJO refused Soemu TOYODA whom the navy selected as a candidate for the Minister of the Navy; the second, deputy minister of the Navy, Yorio SAWAMOTO proceeded with the plan that &apos;it&apos;s going to be a war with Tojo so we shall not select a candidate (to crash the Tojo Cabinet by not selecting),&apos; however, as Shigetaro SHIMADA was selected with the judgment of Navy Minister Koshiro OIKAWA and others, the Tojo Cabinet was finally formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>消滅とその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disappearance and After</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disappearance and After</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disappearance and After</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>1945年（昭和20年）8月、ポツダム宣言を受諾したことによって日本軍は武装を解除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the Potsdam Declaration in August, 1945, the Japanese army was disassembled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the Potsdam Declaration in August, 1945, the Japanese army was disassembled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the Potsdam Declaration in August, 1945, the Japanese army was disassembled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>同年12月、陸軍省は廃止されて第一復員省へ、海軍省は廃止されて第二復員省へ、それぞれ改組されて軍部大臣は消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December of the same year, the ministry of the Army was abolished and became the first to demobilize, the ministry of the Navy was abolished and became the second to demobilize; the military ministery was reorganized and dismantled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December of the same year, the Department of War was abolished and became the Department of Veterans Affairs Ⅰ, the Department of the Navy was abolished and became the Department of Veterans Affairs Ⅱ; the Military Ministers was reorganized and dismantled.</e>
<cmt>the ministry of the Army &gt; the Department of Warthe ministry of the Navy &gt; the Department of the Navythe first to demobilize &gt; the Department of Veterans Affairs Ⅰ（定訳不明です）the second to demobilize &gt; the Department of Veterans Affairs Ⅱ （定訳不明です）military ministery &gt; Military Ministers</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December of the same year, the Department of War was abolished and became the Department of Veterans Affairs I, the Department of the Navy was abolished and became the Department of Veterans Affairs II; the Military Ministers was reorganized and dismantled.</e>
<cmt>スペース調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>1947年（昭和22年）に施行された日本国憲法では、以下のように定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Constitution of Japan, implemented in 1947, stipulated the following:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Constitution of Japan, implemented in 1947, stipulated the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Constitution of Japan, implemented in 1947, stipulated the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>「陸海空軍その他の戦力は、これを保持しない。」（日本国憲法第9条）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land, sea, and air forces, as well as other war potential, will never be maintained (Japanese Constitution, article 9).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Army-Navy-Air Force, as well as other war potential, will never be maintained. (Japanese Constitution, article 9)</e>
<cmt>Land, sea, and air forces &gt; Army-Navy-Air Forceピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Army-Navy-Air Force, as well as other war potential, will never be maintained.&apos; (Japanese Constitution, article 9)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>「内閣総理大臣その他の国務大臣は、文民でなければならない。」（日本国憲法第66条）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Prime Minister and other Ministers of State must be civilians (Japanese Constitution, article 66).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Prime Minister and other Ministers of State must be civilians. (Japanese Constitution, article 66)</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Prime Minister and other Ministers of State must be civilians.&apos; (Japanese Constitution, article 66)</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これにより、軍隊がないために武官も軍部大臣も存在せず、仮に武官がいたとしても国務大臣には就けないこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because there was no military, there was no military officer nor military minister; even if a military officer exsisted, he could not gain a position as a Minister of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because there was no military, there was no military officer nor Military Minister; even if a military officer existed, he could not gain a position as a Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>exsisted &gt; existedmilitary minister &gt; Military Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because there was no military, there was no military officer nor Military Minister; even if a military officer existed, he could not gain a position as a Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>しかし、その後の国際情勢の変転に伴い、1950年（昭和25年）には、軍隊に匹敵する装備を持つ警察予備隊が創設され、この事務を掌理するため警察予備隊本部が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the change in international situations, the National Police Reserve, which had equal equipment as the Army, was formed and the National Police Army head-quarters was created to manage its administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the change in international situations, the National Police Reserve, which had equal equipment as the Army, was formed and the National Police Army Head Quarters was created to manage its administration.</e>
<cmt>head-quarters &gt; Head Quarters</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the change in international situations, the National Police Reserve, which had equal equipment as the Army, was formed and the National Police Army Head Quarters was created to manage its administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>この警察予備隊本部の長官は国務大臣ではなく、警察予備隊担当の国務大臣が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chief of this National Police Reserve head-quarters was not a Minister of State but a Minister of State who managed the National Police Reserve was created instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief of this National Police Reserve Head Quarters was not a Minister of State but a Minister of State who managed the National Police Reserve was created instead.</e>
<cmt>head-quarters &gt; Head QuartersChief &gt; The chief</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief of this National Police Reserve Head Quarters was not a Minister of State but a Minister of State who managed the National Police Reserve was created instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>警察予備隊は、保安隊を経て、1954年（昭和29年）に自衛隊となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan Self-Defense Forces grew out of the National Police Reserve in 1954 after it was recognized as a Peace Preservation Corps.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan Self-Defense Forces grew out of the National Police Reserve in 1954 after it was reorganized as a Peace Preservation Corps.</e>
<cmt>recognized &gt; reorganized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japan Self-Defense Forces grew out of the National Police Reserve in 1954 after it was reorganized as a Peace Preservation Corps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>自衛隊の事務は、防衛庁（後に防衛省）が掌理し、防衛庁長官（後に防衛大臣）には国務大臣があてられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The administraion of the Japan Self-Defense Forces was managed by the Defence Agency (Ministry of Defence) and of the Chief Defence Agency (current Secretary of State for Defence) was managed by the Minister of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The administration of the Japan Self-Defense Forces was managed by the Defense Agency (later Ministry of Defense) and of the Chief Defense Agency (later Secretary of State for Defense) was managed by the Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>administraion &gt; administrationDefence &gt; Defense「後に」の訳が抜けているので追加しました。current &gt; later</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The administration of the Japan Self-Defense Forces was managed by the Defense Agency (later Ministry of Defense) and of the Chief Defense Agency (later Secretary of State for Defense) was managed by the Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>国際的には、事実上、防衛庁長官（防衛大臣）は軍部大臣、自衛隊は軍隊、自衛官は武官と目されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Internationally, the Chief Defence Agency (Secretary of State for Defence) was recognized as a military minister and the Japan Self-Defense Forces were recognized as a military, and a Self-Defence Official was recognized as a military officer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Internationally, the Chief Defense Agency (Minister of Defense) was recognized as a Military Minister and the Japan Self-Defense Forces were recognized as a military, and a Self-Defense Official was recognized as a military officer.</e>
<cmt>Defence &gt; Defensemilitary minister &gt; Military Minister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Internationally, the Chief Defense Agency (Minister of Defense) was recognized as a Military Minister and the Japan Self-Defense Forces were recognized as a military, and a Self-Defense Official was recognized as a military officer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし、現役の自衛官が防衛大臣を兼ねることはともかく、かつて職業軍人であった者や自衛官であった者が、防衛大臣に就任すること自体は憲法違反にあたらないと解されている（例えば、旧海軍経理学校出身の中曽根康弘（中佐）、松野頼三（少佐）、山下元利（中尉）らや陸上自衛隊自衛官（二等陸尉）であった中谷元が防衛庁長官に就任している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, weather or not an active Self-Defense Official concorrently serves as a Secretary of State for Defence, it is understood that appointment of a trade military man or a Self-Defence official to a Secretary of State for Defence itself is not illegal (For instance, Yasuhiro NAKASONE (lieutenant colonel) who graduated from the Naval Paymasters&apos; School, Raizo MATSUNO (major), Ganri YAMASHITA (lieutenant), and Gen NAKATANI who was in the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (First Lieutenant) were appointed to Chief Secretary of State for Defence).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, whether or not an active Self-Defense Official concurrently serves as a Secretary of State for Defense, it is understood that appointment of a career military man or a Self-Defense official to a Secretary of State for Defense itself is not illegal (For instance, Yasuhiro NAKASONE (lieutenant colonel) who graduated from the Naval Paymasters&apos; School, Raizo MATSUNO (major), Ganri YAMASHITA (lieutenant), and Gen NAKATANI who was in the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (First Lieutenant) were appointed to Chief Secretary of State for Defense).</e>
<cmt>weather &gt; whetherconcorrently &gt; concurrentlyDefence &gt; Defensetrade military man &gt; career military man</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, whether or not an active Self-Defense Official concurrently serves as a Secretary of State for Defense, it is understood that appointment of a career military man or a Self-Defense official to a Secretary of State for Defense itself is not illegal (For instance, Yasuhiro NAKASONE (lieutenant colonel) who graduated from the Naval Paymasters&apos; School, Raizo MATSUNO (major), Ganri YAMASHITA (lieutenant), and Gen NAKATANI who was in the Japanese Self-Defense Forces (First Lieutenant) were appointed to Chief Secretary of State for Defense).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>だが、海軍大将だった野村吉三郎は1950年代に防衛庁長官に就任させる構想が存在したが、文民統制の観点から断念となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a conspiracy to appoint Kichisaburo NOMURA, who was the Navy General at that time, to a Chief Secretary of State for Defence; however, it was ceased due to a civilian regulation point of view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a conspiracy to appoint Kichisaburo NOMURA, who was the Navy General at that time, to a Chief Secretary of State for Defense; however, it was ceased due to a civilian regulation point of view.</e>
<cmt>Defence &gt; Defense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a conspiracy to appoint Kichisaburo NOMURA, who was the Navy General at that time, to a Chief Secretary of State for Defense; however, it was ceased due to a civilian regulation point of view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="66">
<j>なお、武官にあたる自衛官（いわゆる制服組）のみならず、文民（文官）にあたる内部部局の防衛参事官、書記官等（いわゆる背広組）であっても、防衛大臣その他の国務大臣を兼ねることは禁じられていると解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, even if a candidate was a Self-Defence Official (the so-called uniform team), a civilian (civil officer), the internel Defense Counseller, or secretary (the so-called sebiro (business suit) team), it is understood that it is prohibited to be appointed concurrently as the Secretary of State for Defence and any other Minister of State.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, even if a candidate was a Self-Defense Official (the so-called uniform team), a civilian (civil officer), the internal Defense Counselor, or secretary (the so-called sebiro (business suit) team), it is understood that it is prohibited to be appointed concurrently as the Secretary of State for Defense and any other Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>Defence &gt; Defenseinternel &gt; internalCounseller &gt; Counselor</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, even if a candidate was a Self-Defense Official (the so-called uniform team), a civilian (civil officer), the internal Defense Counselor, or secretary (the so-called sebiro (business suit) team), it is understood that it is prohibited to be appointed concurrently as the Secretary of State for Defense and any other Minister of State.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>なぜなら、防衛省の職員は、制服組はもちろん背広組も自衛隊の隊員とされ（自衛隊法2条5項）、隊員は政治的行為が制限されているからである（同法61条、同施行令86条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because personnel of the Ministry of Defence, including the uniform team and the sebiro team, are considered as a part of Self-Defence Forces (Self-Defense Forces Act Chapter 2, Article 5), and the Self-Defence Forces are restricted by the political acts (in the same Act; Chapter 61, the same implementation orders; Article 86).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because personnel of the Ministry of Defense, including the uniform team and the sebiro team, are considered as a part of Self-Defense Forces (Self-Defense Forces Act Chapter 2, Article 5), and the Self-Defense Forces are restricted by the political acts (in the same Act; Chapter 61, the same implementation orders; Article 86).</e>
<cmt>Defence &gt; Defense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because personnel of the Ministry of Defense, including the uniform team and the sebiro team, are considered as a part of Self-Defense Forces (Self-Defense Forces Act Chapter 2, Article 5), and the Self-Defense Forces are restricted by the political acts (in the same Act; Chapter 61, the same implementation orders; Article 86).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sizuru(id:52926), Central.jcg(id:29852), Kzy(id:9253), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), MIsogi(id:20599), 経済準学士(id:22656), Rambler(id:59491), 水野白楓(id:22811), Reedo(id:155043), Hatsune(id:26654), Kurz(id:1601), 玄史生(id:43670), PrimeN(id:102297), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Worldtraveler(id:197286), U1p(id:48290), Oraoraora(id:112602), 唐棣色(id:64681), Bokka7568(id:275377), Aryarya(id:35365), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>