<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東勝寺合戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東勝寺合戦（とうしょうじがっせん）は、鎌倉時代末期の1333年（元弘3年、正慶2年）に相模国鎌倉（現在の鎌倉市）で行われた戦い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tosho-ji War was the battle fought in Kamakura (the present Kamakura City), Sagami Province in 1333, when the Kamakura period came near to its end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tosho-ji War was a battle fought in Kamakura (the present Kamakura City), Sagami Province in 1333, when the Kamakura period was near to its end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tosho-ji War was a battle fought in Kamakura (the present Kamakura City), Sagami Province in 1333, at the end of Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表現を他のトピックとあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1331年（元弘元年、元徳3年）から開始された後醍醐天皇の倒幕運動である元弘の乱の最後の戦いで、鎌倉幕府は滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war was the last phase of the Genko War which was started by Emperor Godaigo as the anti-shogunate movement in 1331, and the Tosho-ji War put an end to the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war was the last phase of the Genko War which was started by Emperor Godaigo as the anti-shogunate movement in 1331, and the Tosho-ji War put an end to the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war was the last phase of the Genko War which was started by Emperor Godaigo as the anti-shogunate movement in 1331, and the Tosho-ji War put an end to the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>「幕府」の訳を他のトピックとあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>東勝寺は、北条泰時が退耕行勇（たいこうぎょうゆう）を開山として葛西ヶ谷（鎌倉市小町）に創建した北条氏の菩提寺である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosho-ji Temple was constructed by Yasutoki HOJO as the family temple of the Hojo clan, and he put Gyoyu TAIKO as its first chief priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosho-ji Temple was constructed by Yasutoki HOJO as the family temple of the Hojo clan, and he sinstalled Gyoyu TAIKO as its first chief priest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosho-ji Temple was constructed by Yasutoki HOJO as the family temple of the Hojo clan, and he installed Gyoyu TAIKO as its first chief priest.</e>
<cmt>文法的な修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>表現を他とあわせました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>1331年（元弘元年、元徳3年）8月、後醍醐天皇が笠置山 (京都府)で挙兵、これに応じて楠木正成も河内で挙兵して、元弘の乱が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1331 (by the lunar calendar), Emperor Godaigo raised an army on Mt. Kasagi (in the present Kyoto Prefecture), and Masashige KUSUNOKI collaterally raised his army in Kawachi Province, which was the start of the Genko War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1331 (by the lunar calendar), Emperor Godaigo raised an army on Mt. Kasagi (in the present Kyoto Prefecture), and Masashige KUSUNOKI collaterally raised his army in Kawachi Province, which was the start of the Genko War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1331, Emperor Godaigo raised an army on Mt. Kasagi (in the present Kyoto Prefecture), and Masashige KUSUNOKI collaterally raised his army in Kawachi Province, which was the start of the Genko War.</e>
<cmt>「 (by the lunar calendar),」を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幕府では鎮圧の兵を上らせ、上野国の御家人新田義貞も加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So the Kamakura shogunate sent the army to suppress them, and Yoshisada NITTA, who was &quot;gokenin&quot; (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) in Kozuke Province, joined the shogun&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, the Kamakura shogunate sent the army to suppress them, and Yoshisada NITTA, who was &quot;gokenin&quot; (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) in Kozuke Province, joined the shogun&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura bakufu sent the army to suppress them, and Yoshisada NITTA, who was gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) in Kozuke Province, joined the bakufu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をし、ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>9月には笠置山が陥落し、後醍醐天皇は捕らえられて隠岐へ配流とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September (by the lunar calendar), the army on Mt. Kasagi surrendered, and Emperor Godaigo was captured and was banished to one of Oki islands.</e>
<cmt>※「隠岐島」は、正確にはそのような名称の島があるわけでなく、幾つかの群島の集まりですのでそれに応じた表現にしています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September (by the lunar calendar), the army on Mt. Kasagi surrendered, and Emperor Godaigo was captured and was banished to one of the Oki islands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, the army on Mt. Kasagi surrendered, and Emperor Godaigo was captured and was banished to one of the Oki islands.</e>
<cmt>「 (by the lunar calendar),」を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1333年（元弘3年、正慶2年）、楠木勢は千早城で再挙し、幕府の大軍を相手に奮戦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333, Masashige KUSUNOKI raised his army once again in Chihaya-jo Castle, and he fought hard against the shogunate large army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333, Masashige KUSUNOKI raised his army once again in Chihaya-jo Castle, and fought hard against the large shogunate army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1333, forces of Kusunoki raised the army once again in Chihaya-jo Castle, and fought hard against the large bakufu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに触発されて播磨では赤松則村（円心）が蜂起し、伊予でも反乱が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Encouraged by Masashige, Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) rose in rebellion in Harima Province and a similar rebellion occurred in Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Encouraged by Masashige, Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) rose in rebellion in Harima Province and a similar rebellion occurred in Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encouraged by this, Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) rose in rebellion in Harima Province and a similar rebellion occurred in Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府はさらに北条一族名越高家と下野国の有力御家人、足利高氏（足利尊氏）に大軍を率いさせて西国に派遣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And so, the Kamakura shogunate dispatched Takaie NAGOE, the member of the Hojo clan, &amp; Takauji ASHIKAGA, the influential gokenin in Shimotsuke Province, as the commanders of the large army to the western provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And so, the Kamakura shogunate dispatched Takaie NAGOE, a member of the Hojo clan, &amp; Takauji ASHIKAGA, the influential gokenin in Shimotsuke Province, as the commanders of the large army to the western provinces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And so, the Kamakura bakufu dispatched Takaie NAGOE, a member of the Hojo clan, and Takauji ASHIKAGA, the influential gokenin in Shimotsuke Province, as the commanders of the large army to the western provinces.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>閏2月には後醍醐天皇が隠岐島を脱出して船上山に拠り、4月には足利高氏が篠村八幡において鎌倉に反旗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the intercalary second month, Emperor Godaigo escaped from the island and put a strategic foothold on Mt. Senjo, and in April (by the lunar calendar), Takauji ASHIKAGA rebelled against the Kamakura shogunate at Shinomura-Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the intercalary second month, Emperor Godaigo escaped from the island and established a strategic foothold on Mt. Senjo, and in April (by the lunar calendar), Takauji ASHIKAGA rebelled against the Kamakura shogunate at Shinomura-Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the intercalary February, Emperor Godaigo escaped from Oki and established a strategic foothold on Mt. Senjo, and in April, Takauji ASHIKAGA rebelled against the Kamakura bakufu at Shinomura-Hachimangu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>足利勢らは京都の六波羅探題を滅ぼし、都を制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forces of Ashikaga destroyed &quot;Rokuhara Tandai&quot; (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) and brought Kyoto under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The forces of Ashikaga destroyed &quot;Rokuhara Tandai&quot; (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) and brought Kyoto under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The forces of Ashikaga destroyed Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) and brought Kyoto under control.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>5月、上野へ帰った新田義貞は生品神社において挙兵し、東山道を西進して鎌倉進撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May (by the lunar calendar), Yoshisada NITTA, who had already returned to Kozuke Province, raised his army in Ikushina-jinja Shrine, and his forces started to advance for Kamakura heading westward on Tosan-do Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May (by the lunar calendar), Yoshisada NITTA, who had already returned to Kozuke Province, raised his army in Ikushina-jinja Shrine, and his forces started to advance on Kamakura heading westward on Tosan-do Road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, Yoshisada NITTA, who had already returned to Kozuke Province, raised his army in Ikushina-jinja Shrine, and his forces started to advance on Kamakura heading westward on Tosan-do Road.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>新田軍は一族や周辺豪族を集めて兵を増やしつつ、利根川を越えて武蔵国へ進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Increasing the number of soldiers by absorbing &quot;gozoku&quot; (local ruling families) around the area &amp; Yoshisada&apos;s own relatives, his forces advanced for Musashi Province crossing over Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increasing the number of soldiers by absorbing &quot;gozoku&quot; (local ruling families) around the area &amp; Yoshisada&apos;s own relatives, his forces advanced for Musashi Province crossing over the Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increasing the number of soldiers by absorbing gozoku (local ruling families) around the area and Yoshisada&apos;s own relatives, his forces advanced for Musashi Province crossing over the Tone-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>鎌倉を脱出した高氏の嫡子である千寿王（足利義詮）と合流、鎌倉街道を進む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joining up with the forces of Takauji&apos;s heir Senjuo (later, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), Yoshisada&apos;s forces advanced on Kamakura-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joining up with the forces of Takauji&apos;s heir Senjuo (later, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), Yoshisada&apos;s forces advanced on the Kamakura-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joining up with the forces of Takauji&apos;s heir Senjuo (later, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), Yoshisada&apos;s forces advanced on the Kamakura-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>幕府側では北条泰家らを迎撃のために向かわせるが、入間川 (多摩川水系)と久米川（東京都東村山市）での合戦で敗退し、分倍河原の戦い (鎌倉時代)（東京都府中市 (東京都)）でも敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuie HOJO and others were sent to intercept the rebel forces, but they were defeated in the fights at Iruma-gawa River (the Tama-gawa River system) &amp; Kume-gawa River (in the present Higashimurayama City, Tokyo) and they were also beated at the Bubaigawara War (fought in the present Fuchu City, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuie HOJO and others were sent to intercept the rebel forces, but they were defeated in the battles at Iruma-gawa River (the Tama-gawa River system) &amp; Kume-gawa River (in the present Higashimurayama City, Tokyo) and they were also beated in the Bubaigawara War (fought in the present day Fuchu City, Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuie HOJO and others were sent to intercept the rebel forces, but they were defeated in the battles at Iruma-gawa River (the Tama-gawa River system) and Kume-gawa River (in the present Higashimurayama City, Tokyo Prefecture) and they were also beat in the battle of Bubaigawara (fought in the present day Fuchu City, Tokyo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>＆をandとし、住所表記などを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>新田軍は鎌倉へと迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The forces of Nitta drew near to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The forces of Nitta drew near Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The forces of Nitta drew near Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development of the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development of the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Development of the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>各地で敗走した鎌倉勢は、鎌倉の七切通しを封鎖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura forces were routed in many places, so they blockaded seven roads (slopes) which had been cut through mountainous terrain of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura forces were routed in many places, so they blockaded seven roads (slopes) which had been cut through mountainous terrain of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura forces were routed in many places, so they blockaded seven roads (slopes) which had been cut through mountainous terrain of Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>新田勢は関口を本拠に、小袋坂（巨福呂、こぶくろざか）、化粧坂（けわいざか）、極楽寺坂の三方から攻撃し、義貞はそれぞれ将を一族で固めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Filling his army captains with his own relatives, Yoshisada put his army base at Sekiguchi and attacked the Kamakura forces from three directions : Kobukuro-zaka Slope, Kewai-zaka Slope and Gokuraku-zaka Slope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Filling his army captains with his own relatives, Yoshisada put his army base at Sekiguchi and attacked the Kamakura forces from three directions: Kobukuro-zaka, Kewai-zaka, and Gokuraku-zaka Slopes.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Filling his army captains with his own relatives, Yoshisada put his army base at Sekiguchi and attacked the Kamakura forces from three directions: Kobukuro-zaka, Kewai-zaka, and Gokurakuji-zaka Slopes.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>小袋坂は山側で鎌倉勢の赤橋守時が守るのに対し新田勢の堀口貞満らが攻め、中央の化粧坂には北条貞将に対し新田義貞、脇屋義助が率いる主力が攻める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Kobukuro-zaka Slope, situated on a mountain, Sadamitsu HORIGUCHI on the side of Yoshisada forces made an attack against Moritoki AKAHASHI on the side of the Kamakura shogunate, and at Kewai-zaka Slope, situated at the center of Kamakura, the main forces led by Yoshisada NITTA &amp; Yoshisuke WAKIYA made an attack against Sadayuki HOJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Kobukuro-zaka Slope, situated on a mountain, Sadamitsu HORIGUCHI, on the side of Yoshisada forces, attacked Moritoki AKAHASHI, on the side of the Kamakura shogunate, and on Kewai-zaka Slope, situated in the center of Kamakura, the main forces led by Yoshisada NITTA &amp; Yoshisuke WAKIYA attacked Sadayuki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Kobukuro-zaka Slope, situated on a mountain, Sadamitsu HORIGUCHI, on the side of Yoshisada forces, attacked Moritoki AKAHASHI, on the side of the Kamakura bakufu, and on Kewai-zaka Slope, situated in the center of Kamakura, the main forces led by Yoshisada NITTA and Yoshisuke WAKIYA attacked Sadayuki HOJO.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>七里ヶ浜に面する海側の極楽寺坂は大仏貞直が守り、大舘宗氏らが攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Gokuraku-ji-zaka Slope, situated on Shichiri-ga-hama Seacoast, Muneuji ODATE attacked Sadanao OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On Gokuraku-ji-zaka Slope, situated on the Shichiri-ga-hama Seacoast, Muneuji ODATE attacked Sadanao OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Gokurakuji-zaka Slope, situated on the Shichiri-ga-hama Seacoast, Muneuji ODATE attacked Sadanao OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt>表記修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>戦いは膠着し、特に極楽寺坂では大舘宗氏が戦死するほど苦戦する（大舘氏参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These fights came to a deadlock, and especially at Gokuraku-ji-zaka Slope, Yoshisada&apos;s forces had a hard fight, symbolized by the death of Muneuji ODATE (cf. the article of &quot;The Odate clan&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These battles came to a deadlock, and especially on the Gokuraku-ji-zaka Slope, Yoshisada&apos;s forces had a hard fight, symbolized by the death of Muneuji ODATE (cf. the article of &quot;The Odate clan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>vocabulary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These battles came to a deadlock, and especially on Gokurakuji-zaka Slope, Yoshisada&apos;s forces had a hard fight, symbolized by the death of Muneuji ODATE (cf. the article of &quot;The Odate clan&quot;).</e>
<cmt>文法的な修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>義貞は切通しの突破を諦めて稲村ヶ崎からの鎌倉入りを試みる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So Yoshisada gave up breaking through seven slopes, and he tried to enter Kamakura by sea at Inamura-ga-saki Cape instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So Yoshisada gave up trying to break through the seven slopes, and, instead, tried to enter Kamakura by sea via Inamura-ga-saki Cape.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So Yoshisada gave up trying to break through the seven slopes, and, instead, tried to enter Kamakura by sea via Inamura-ga-saki Cape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>室町時代に成立した軍記物語『太平記』によれば、義貞が海神に祈願すると潮が引き、新田勢は鎌倉に進入したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war chronicle &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) written in the Muromachi period says the forces of Nitta could enter Kamakura since the tide went out on Yoshisada&apos;s prayer to the sea-god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war chronicle &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) written in the Muromachi period says the forces of Nitta successfully entered Kamakura because the tide went out, in answer to Yoshisada&apos;s prayer to the sea-god.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war chronicle &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace) written in the Muromachi period said the forces of Nitta successfully entered Kamakura because the tide went out, in answer to Yoshisada&apos;s prayer to the sea-god.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>背後を突かれた幕府軍は総崩れとなり鎌倉や切通しなどで大仏貞直、大仏宣政、本間泰宣、金沢貞将などは戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Attacked from behind, the Kamakura shogunate forces suffered a total defeat, so Sadanao OSARAGI, Nobumasa OSARAGI, Yasunobu HONMA, Sadayuki KANESAWA were killed in the war at Kamakura or some slope.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attacked from behind, the Kamakura shogunate forces suffered a total defeat, so Sadanao OSARAGI, Nobumasa OSARAGI, Yasunobu HONMA, Sadayuki KANESAWA were killed in the war at Kamakura on some slope there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attacked from behind, the Kamakura bakufu forces suffered a total defeat, so Sadanao OSARAGI, Nobumasa OSARAGI, Yasunobu HONMA, Sadayuki KANESAWA were killed in the war at Kamakura on some slope there.</e>
<cmt>前出の修正をしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>北条高時らは東勝寺において自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatoki HOJO and his vassals committed suicide in Tosho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatoki HOJO and his vassals committed suicide at Tosho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatoki HOJO and his vassals committed suicide at Tosho-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>東勝寺に篭った北条一族と家臣は、『太平記』によれば、長崎高重、摂津道準から順にそれぞれ腹を切り、最後に北条高時、安達時顕と自害したという。（他に北条基時、長崎高資、北条貞顕など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiheiki says the whole members of the Hojo clan &amp; their vassals shut themselves up in Tosho-ji Temple and committed harakiri in turn, from Takashige NAGASAKI &amp; Dojun SETTSU, and in the end, Takatoki HOJO &amp; Tokiaki ADACHI; besides, Mototoki HOJO, Takasuke NAGASAKI, Sadaaki HOJO also committed suicide on this occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiheiki says all members of the Hojo clan &amp; their vassals shut themselves up in Tosho-ji Temple and committed harakiri in turn, from Takashige NAGASAKI &amp; Dojun SETTSU, and in the end, Takatoki HOJO &amp; Tokiaki ADACHI; also, Mototoki HOJO, Takasuke NAGASAKI, Sadaaki HOJO committed suicide on this occasion.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiheiki said all members of the Hojo clan and their vassals shut themselves up in Tosho-ji Temple and committed suicide by disembowelment (harakiri) in turn, from Takashige NAGASAKI and Dojun SETTSU, and in the end, Takatoki HOJO and Tokiaki ADACHI; also, Mototoki HOJO, Takasuke NAGASAKI, Sadaaki HOJO committed suicide on this occasion.</e>
<cmt>切腹の表現を他とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『太平記』には、自害した人々は283人の北条一族と家臣の870人とあるが、文学的誇張もあると考慮される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Taiheiki, the number of samurai who committed suicide was 283 about the Hojo clan, and that about their vassals was 870, but this could be an exaggeration for highlighting their tragedy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Taiheiki, the number of samurai that committed suicide was 283 in the Hojo clan, and their vassals numbered 870, but this could be an exaggeration to highlight their tragedy.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Taiheiki, the number of samurai that committed suicide by disembowelment was 283 in the Hojo clan, and their vassals numbered 870, but this could be an exaggeration to highlight their tragedy.</e>
<cmt>切腹の表現を他とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>東勝寺合戦をめぐる伝承</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folklore about the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folklore about the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folklore about the Tosho-ji War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>現在の東勝寺の旧跡の北方には｢腹切りやぐら｣と呼ばれるやぐらが存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, in the north of the remains of Tosho-ji Temple, there exist &quot;Harakiri Yagura&quot; (Harakiri Caves).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present, in the north amongst the remains of Tosho-ji Temple, there exist &quot;Harakiri Yagura&quot; (Harakiri Caves).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present, in the north among the remains of Tosho-ji Temple, there exist &quot;Harakiri Yagura&quot; (Caves of committing suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>切腹の表現を他とあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>東勝寺旧跡での発掘調査では三つ鱗の入った瓦などが見つかるものの遺骨の発見はなく、新田勢や時宗の僧らによって遺体が処理されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the research excavation of the Tosho-ji Temple&apos;s remains was done, tiles inscribed with &quot;Mitsu uroko&quot; (crest of the Hojo clan, three scales in a circle) and other cultual assets were found while the ashes of the war dead were not, so the dead bodies are deemed to have been transferred to another place by the forces of Nitta, Buddhist priests of Ji sect, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the research excavation of the Tosho-ji Temple&apos;s remains was conducted, tiles inscribed with &quot;Mitsu uroko&quot; (crest of the Hojo clan, three scales in a circle) and other cultual assets were found while the ashes of the war dead were not, so the dead bodies are deemed to have been transferred to another place by the forces of Nitta, Buddhist priests of Ji sect, and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Tosho-ji Temple site was excavated, Mitsu uroko (tiles inscribed with three scales in a circle, the crest of the Hojo clan), and other cultural artifacts were discovered; no cremated ashes of the war dead were ever found, and it is assumed their remains were taken to another place, possibly by Buddhist priests of the Ji sect, Nitta forces or others.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>腹切りやぐらは、その名称から東勝寺での戦死者と何らかの関係があるとされていて、今でも供養会では卒塔婆が立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of Harakiri Yagura is deemed to have some relation to the war dead at Tosho-ji Temple, so even today at &quot;Kuyo-e&quot; (a memorial service), &quot;sotoba&quot; (a tall and narrow wooden tablet for the dead, usually set up behind a grave) is stood there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Harakiri Yagura is deemed to have some relationship to the war dead at Tosho-ji Temple, so even today at &quot;Kuyo-e&quot; (a memorial service), &quot;sotoba&quot; (a tall and narrow wooden tablet for the dead, usually set up behind a grave) is still standing there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Harakiri Yagura is associated with the war dead at Tosho-ji Temple, and even today when Kuyo-e (memorial services) are held, a sotoba (a tall, narrow wooden tablet for the dead, usually raised behind a grave) is still erected there.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>ただ高時の首塚を伝えるやぐらは、各所に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the cave that is said &quot;Kubi-zuka&quot; (a burial mound for a head) of Takatoki HOJO exists in various places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, caves that are said to be &quot;Kubi-zuka&quot; (a burial mound for a head) for Takatoki HOJO exists in various places.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, caves that are said to be Kubi-zuka (a burial mound for a head) for Takatoki HOJO exists in various places.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="32">
<j>鎌倉でのこの戦闘の後、この地で死んだ北条一族を弔うため、足利尊氏によって宝戒寺が建てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this war in Kamakura, Takauji ASHIKAGA built Hokai-ji Temple to pray for the Hojo clan killed here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this war in Kamakura, Takauji ASHIKAGA built Hokai-ji Temple to pray for the Hojo clan that was killed here.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this war in Kamakura, Takauji ASHIKAGA built Hokai-ji Temple to pray for the Hojo clan that was killed here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>宝戒寺の地は、もとの北条執権邸の地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokai-ji Temple exists at the former residece of Hojo &quot;Shikken&quot; (the regent of the Kamakura shogunate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokai-ji Temple exists at the former residence of Hojo &quot;Shikken&quot; (the regent of the Kamakura shogunate).</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokai-ji Temple exists at the former residence of Hojo Shikken (the regent of the Kamakura bakufu).</e>
<cmt>「幕府」の訳を他のトピックとあわせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="34">
<j>鎌倉市浄明寺の釈迦堂谷奥山頂部には釈迦堂奥やぐら群と称する多数のやぐら群が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the mountaintop (the back of the valley) where Shaka-do Hall of Jomyo-ji Temple stands (in the present Kamakura City), there were many groups of caves, called &quot;Shaka-do oku Yagura-gun,&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the mountaintop (the back of the valley) where Shaka-do Hall of Jomyo-ji Temple stands (in present day Kamakura City), there were many groups of caves, called &quot;Shaka-do oku Yagura-gun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the mountaintop (the back of the valley) where Shaka-do Hall of Jomyo-ji Temple stands (in present day Kamakura City), there were many groups of caves, called Shaka-do oku Yagura-gun.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その中心には「宝戒寺二世普川国師入定窟」と伝わる巨大なやぐらがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And at their center existed the giant cave that was said &quot;the cave in which Fusen, the second chief priest of Hokai-ji Temple, did his calm contemplation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And at their center existed a giant cave that was said to be &quot;the cave in which Fusen, the second chief priest of Hokai-ji Temple, practiced his calm contemplation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And at their center existed a giant cave that was said to be &quot;the cave in which Fusen, the second chief priest of Hokai-ji Temple, practiced his calm contemplation.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>やぐら群には多量の生焼けの人骨があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the groups of caves, there seem to have existed many dead bodies not cremated perfectly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the groups of caves, there seem to have been many dead bodies not completely cremated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the groups of caves, there seem to have been many dead bodies not completely cremated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>昔から東勝寺での戦死者の遺体をこのやぐら群に葬ったとの伝承があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From many years ago, there has been a folklore that the bodies of the war dead at Tosho-ji Temple were transferred and buried here.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From many years ago, there has been a folklore that the bodies of the war dead at Tosho-ji Temple were transferred and buried here.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The folklore of the region maintains the war dead of Tosho-ji Temple were removed and buried here.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>昭和40年代の宅地開発の際にやぐらが破壊され、「元弘三年五月廿八日」の銘のある五輪塔の一部が発見された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When housing lots were developed during the decade from 1965, the caves were destroyed and a part of &quot;gorinto&quot; (a gravestone composed of five pieces piled up one upon another) was found, in which the date &quot;July 18, 1333&quot; was inscribed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When housing lots were developed during the decade from 1965, the caves were destroyed and a part of a &quot;gorinto&quot; (a gravestone composed of five pieces piled up one upon another) was found, in which the date &quot;July 18, 1333&quot; was inscribed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When housing lots were developed during the decade from 1965, the caves were destroyed and a part of a gorinto (a gravestone composed of five pieces piled up one upon another) was found, in which the date &quot;July 18, 1333&quot; was inscribed.</e>
<cmt>一部ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>まさに東勝寺合戦の初七日の供養をしめすものであり、伝承が事実であったことがわかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This exactly shows that the memorial service was held on the sixth date after their death, so the folklore turned out to be true.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows exactly that the memorial service was held on the sixth date after their death, so the folklore turned out to be true.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows exactly that the memorial service was held on the sixth date after their death at Tosho-ji War, so the folklore turned out to be true.</e>
<cmt>「東勝寺合戦」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>やぐら群は昭和40年頃に宅地造成によって主要部が破壊されたが、一部は現存しているという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major part of the group caves were destroyed for housing lots development around 1965, but some caves are said to exist even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major part of the group caves were destroyed for housing lots development around 1965, but some caves are said to exist even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major part of the group caves were destroyed for housing lots development around 1965, but some caves are said to exist even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), 玄史生(id:43670), 与左衛門(id:159462), Masanori88(id:20692), 水野白楓(id:22811), S. Ohdachi(id:303729), Lupinoid(id:68), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Kuma83(id:31177), お掃除大好き(id:99320), Cave cattum(id:41235), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>