<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高梨氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takanashi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takanashi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanashi clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>高梨氏（たかなしし）は、信濃国北部（高井郡・水内郡）に割拠した武家の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takanashi clan is a samurai family which dominated the north of Shinano Province (Takai County and Minochi County)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takanashi clan was a samurai family that dominated the north of Shinano Province (Takai and Minochi counties).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanashi clan was a samurai family that dominated the north of Shinano Province (Takai and Minochi counties).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全盛期の本拠地は、現在の長野県中野市。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan&apos;s base in its prime was present-day Nakano city, Nagano prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan&apos;s base, in its prime, was the area of what is now Nakano City, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan&apos;s base, in its prime, was the area of what is now Nakano City, Nagano Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>平安末期から源平合戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late Heian period to the Genpei War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late Heian period to the Genpei War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late Heian period to the Genpei War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>高梨氏は、同じ北信濃の名族清和源氏井上氏を名乗り、源家季の息子高梨盛光の末裔であると称している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takanashi clan announces its name as Inoue of the prominent Seiwa Genji in northern Shinano and claims they are descendants of TAKANASHI Morimitsu, a son of MINAMOTO no Iesue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takanashi clan announces its name as Inoue of the prominent Seiwa Genji in northern Shinano, and claims descendency from TAKANASHI Morimitsu, a son of MINAMOTO no Iesue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanashi clan announces its name as Inoue of the prominent Seiwa Genji (Minamoto clan) in northern Shinano, and claims descendency from Morimitsu TAKANASHI, a son of MINAMOTO no Iesue.</e>
<cmt>Minamoto clan 追記TAKANASHI Morimitsu→Morimitsu TAKANASHIa son の前のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし系図には疑うべき余地も多く、実際には源平合戦の際は井上一族では無く北安曇の仁科氏らと行動を共にしていたので、当時の慣習から見て別の一族であった可能性がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as its genealogy has some doubtful parts and the Takanashi clan fought in the Genpei War along with the Nishina clan of northern Azumi, not the Inoue clan, the Takanashi clan probably does not belong to the Inoue clan in view of the custom of the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because there are uncertain aspects of its genealogy and the Takanashi clan fought in the Genpei War along with the Nishina clan of northern Azumi, not the Inoue clan, the Takanashi clan probably doesn&apos;t belong to the Inoue clan, considering the custom of the time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because there are uncertain aspects of its genealogy and the Takanashi clan fought in the Genpei War along with the Nishina clan of northern Azumi, not the Inoue clan, the Takanashi clan probably doesn&apos;t belong to the Inoue clan, considering the custom of the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、高梨氏は仁科氏と同じく中原兼遠の婿になっていたので、この婚姻関係によって執るべき軍事行動が変化（男系親族井上氏に従わず、外戚中原氏へ加担）したということも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a member of the Takanashi clan as well as one of the Nishina clan was a son-in-law of NAKAHARA Kaneto, so that the relation by marriage may have made the Takanashi clan join the army of the Nakahara clan, a consort clan, not that of the Inoue clan, the paternal relative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a member of the Takanashi clan (as well as one from the Nishina clan) was a son-in-law of NAKAHARA Kaneto, so that the relation by marriage may have made the Takanashi clan join the army of the Nakahara clan, a consort clan, instead of the Inoue clan, the paternal relative.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a member of the Takanashi clan (as well as one from the Nishina clan) was a son-in-law of Kaneto NAKAHARA, so that the relation by marriage may have made the Takanashi clan join the army of the Nakahara clan, a consort clan, instead of the Inoue clan, the paternal relative.</e>
<cmt>NAKAHARA Kaneto→Kaneto NAKAHARA</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>高梨高信・高梨忠直らは源義仲傘下として越後から南下した城資茂率いる平家方を破り、その後も源義仲に最後まで従ったと思われ、高梨忠直は京都の六条河原で刑死した記録が残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKANASHI Takanobu and TAKANASHI Tadanao who were affiliated with MINAMOTO Yoshinaka won the Heike led by JO no Sukemochi who had moved south from Echigo, and then seem to have accompanied Minamoto Yoshinaka to his end because it is recorded that TAKANASHI Tadanao was executed at Rokujo Kawara in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKANASHI Takanobu and TAKANASHI Tadanao, who were affiliated with MINAMOTO Yoshinaka, won the Heike led by JO no Sukemochi, who had moved south from Echigo, and then seem to have accompanied Minamoto Yoshinaka to his end, because it is recorded that TAKANASHI Tadanao was executed at Rokujo Kawara, in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takanobu TAKANASHI and Tadanao TAKANASHI, who were affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, won the Heike led by JO no Sukemochi, who had moved south from Echigo, and then seem to have accompanied Minamoto no Yoshinaka to his end, because it is recorded that Tadanao TAKANASHI was executed at the Rokujo-gawara riverbed, in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正源義仲は no を追記六条河原を用語集の訳に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、建久元年(1190年)頼朝が上洛した際の御家人の中に高梨次郎の名が見え、鎌倉時代も御家人として存続していた事が伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoritomo moved to Kyoto with his gokenin in 1190, TAKANASHI Jiro was included among the gokenin, so that the Takanashi clan is considered to have remained a gokenin during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoritomo moved to Kyoto with his gokenin in 1190, TAKANASHI Jiro was included among the gokenin, so that the Takanashi clan is considered to have remained a gokenin during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoritomo moved to Kyoto with his gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods)in 1190, Jiro TAKANASHI was included among the gokenin, so that the Takanashi clan is considered to have retained its position as gokenin during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正御家人の説明補足原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後は保科氏らと婚姻関係を結びつつ北方へ領土を拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the clan expanded the territory to north having marriage connection with the Hoshina clan and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the clan expanded its territory northward, having marriage connections with the Hoshina clan and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the clan expanded its territory northward, having marriage connections with the Hoshina clan and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>南北朝時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Nanboku-cho period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nanboku-cho period</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>続く南北朝時代 (日本)には埴科郡に割拠する有力豪族村上氏と共に北朝 (日本)方に属し、正平 (日本)6年/観応2年(1351年)6月に高梨経頼は小笠原為経・小笠原光宗らと足利直義の諏訪直頼の代官祢津宗貞と野辺原（須坂市野辺）で戦い、8月には富部河原、善光寺、米子城（須坂市米子）で戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Nanboku-cho period, along with the powerful Murakami clan that was active in Hanishina County, the Takashina clan was on the Hoku-cho side, and TAKANASHI Tsuneyori along with OGASAWARA Tametsune and OGASAWARA Mitsumune fought NETSU Munesada, local governor for SUWA Naoyori, on the ASHIKAGA Naoyoshi side at Nobehara (Nobe, Suzaka city) in June, 1351 with and at Tobe Gawara, Zenko Temple, Yonako Castle (Yonako, Suzaka city) in August.</e>
<cmt>（日本）は訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nanboku-cho period, along with the powerful Murakami clan, which was active in Hanishina County, the Takashina clan was on the Hoku-cho side, and TAKANASHI Tsuneyori (along with OGASAWARA Tametsune and OGASAWARA Mitsumune) fought NETSU Munesada, the local governor for SUWA Naoyori, on the ASHIKAGA Naoyoshi side at Nobehara (Nobe, Suzaka City) in June of 1351 with and at Tobe Gawara, Zenko Temple, Yonako Castle (Yonako, Suzaka City) in August.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, the Takashina clan and the powerful Murakami clan, which was active in Hanishina County, were on the Northern Court side, and Tsuneyori TAKANASHI (along with Tametsune OGASAWARA and Mitsumune OGASAWARA) fought Munesada NETSU, the local governor for Naoyori SUWA, on the side of Naoyoshi ASHIKAGA, at Nobehara (Nobe, Suzaka City) in July of 1351 at Tobe Gawara, Zenko-ji Temple, Yonago-jo Castle (Yonago, Suzaka City) in September.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の定訳姓名の順番を訂正Zenko→Zenko-jiYonako→Yonago-joYonako→Yonago旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また守護の斯波義種に反抗して元中4年/嘉慶 (日本)元年（1387年）善光寺に村上頼国、小笠原清順、長沼太郎らと挙兵し5月に平柴（長野市安茂里）の守護所を攻めて漆田原（長野市中御所）で戦い、8月には守護代の二宮氏泰が篭城する横山城を攻め落とし、続いて生仁城（千曲市雨宮）も攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takanashi clan resisted the governor SHIBA Yoshitane, rose in arms at Zenko Temple along with MURAKAMI Yorikuni, OGASAWARA Seijun and NAGANUMA Taro in 1387, attacked the prefectural office in Hirashiba (Amori, Nagano city) in May, fought at Urushidahara (Nakagosho, Nagano city), captured Yokoyama Castle in which NINOMIYA Ujiyasu took refuge in August and attacked Namani Castle (Amamiya, Chikuma city).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takanashi clan resisted the governor SHIBA Yoshitane, rose in arms at Zenko Temple along with MURAKAMI Yorikuni, OGASAWARA Seijun and NAGANUMA Taro in 1387, attacked the prefectural office in Hirashiba (Amori, Nagano City) in May, fought at Urushidahara (Nakagosho, Nagano City), captured Yokoyama Castle (in which NINOMIYA Ujiyasu had taken refuge) in August, and attacked Namani Castle (Amamiya, Chikuma City).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanashi clan resisted the governor Yoshitane SHIBA, rose in arms at Zenko-ji Temple along with Yorikuni MURAKAMI, Seijun OGASAWARA and Taro NAGANUMA in 1387, attacked the prefectural office in Hirashiba (Amori, Nagano City) in May, fought at Urushidahara (Nakagosho, Nagano City), captured Yokoyama-jo Castle (in which Ujiyasu NINOMIYA, Shugodai [deputy of Shugo, provincial constable] had taken refuge) in September, and attacked Namani-jo Castle (Amamiya, Chikuma City).</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正Zenko→Zenko-jiYokoyama→Yokoyama-joNamani→Namani-jo旧暦→グレゴリオ暦「守護代の」訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>北信濃の南朝方香坂心覚（根津氏一族と思われる香坂氏6代目）との抗争にも高梨五郎・高梨時綱らの名前が出てくる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is recorded that TAKANASHI Goro and TAKANASHI Tokitsuna fought KOSAKA Shinkaku (the sixth head of the Kosaka clan that seems to have been the Nezu clan) in northern Shinano on the Nancho side</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded that TAKANASHI Goro and TAKANASHI Tokitsuna fought KOSAKA Shinkaku (the sixth head of the Kosaka clan, which seems to have been the Nezu clan) in northern Shinano on the Nancho side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded that Goro TAKANASHI and Tokitsuna TAKANASHI fought Shinkaku KOSAKA (the sixth head of the Kosaka clan, which seems to have been the Nezu clan) in northern Shinano on the Southern Court side.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正Nancho→Southern Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>室町時代中期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mid Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mid-Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mid-Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>更に応永7年（1400年）に信濃守護職小笠原長秀との間で行われた大塔合戦では、高梨氏や井上一族など北信濃衆は500騎を動員しており、この数は信濃国人衆の筆頭（信濃惣大将）である村上氏と同数で、東信濃の名族海野氏の300騎を上回る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Oto War between OGASAWARA Nagahide, Shinano governor, and local lords in 1400, northern Shinano lords such as the Takanashi clan and the Inoue family gathered five hundred warriors while the Murakami clan gathered five hundred warriors and the prominent Unno clan of eastern Shinano gathered only three hundred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Oto War between OGASAWARA Nagahide, the Shinano governor, and local lords in 1400, northern Shinano lords such as the Takanashi clan and the Inoue family gathered 500 warriors, while the Murakami clan gathered 500 warriors and the prominent Unno clan of eastern Shinano gathered only 300.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Oto War between Nagahide OGASAWARA, the Shinano governor, and local lords in 1400, northern Shinano lords such as the Takanashi clan and the Inoue family gathered 500 warriors, while the Murakami clan gathered 500 warriors and the prominent Unno clan of eastern Shinano gathered only 300.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正「信濃国人衆の筆頭（信濃惣大将）である」　訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>c（1403年）に細川慈忠が守護代として入国した際には村上氏や大井氏、井上氏らが従わず段の原や生仁城で戦ったものの敗走し、翌年12月には高梨朝秀とも合戦となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When HOSOKAWA Shigetada entered the province as a local governor in 1403, the Murakami clan, the Oi clan and the Inoue clan did not obey him, so that Shigetada fought them at Dannohara or Namani Castle, but took flight, and then fought TAKANASHI Tomohide in December next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When HOSOKAWA Shigetada entered the province as a local governor in 1403, the Murakami clan, the Oi clan and the Inoue clan did not obey him, so that Shigetada fought them at Dannohara or Namani Castle but ultimately took flight, and then fought TAKANASHI Tomohide in December of the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shigetada HOSOKAWA entered the province as a local governor in 1403, the Murakami clan, the Oi clan and the Inoue clan did not obey him, so that Shigetada fought them at Dannohara or Namani-jo Castle but ultimately took flight, and then fought Tomohide TAKANASHI in January, 1405.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正Namani→Namani-joDecember of the following year→January, 1405 ご確認願います。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このように南北朝時代に善光寺平北部地域一帯から越後の一部にまで及ぶ勢力拡大に成功した様子が伺われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The TAKANASHI clan dominated the northern parts of Zenkojidaira and a part of Echigo successfully during the Nanboku-cho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The TAKANASHI clan was successful in dominating the northern parts of Zenkojidaira and a part of Echigo during the Nanboku-cho period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanashi clan was successful in dominating the northern parts of Zenkojidaira and a part of Echigo during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>TAKANASHI→Takanashi南北朝時代の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>室町時代には、高梨惣領家と山田高梨・中村高梨・江部高梨を併せて高梨四家と呼ばれていたと記されている（「上高井歴史」より）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the head family of the Takanashi clan, Yamada Takanashi, Nakamura Takanashi and Ebe Takanashi are called the four families of Takanashi (from &quot;the history of Kamitakai&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, the head families of the Takanashi clan--Yamada Takanashi, Nakamura Takanashi and Ebe Takanashi--were called the four families of Takanashi (from &quot;the history of Kamitakai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the head family of the Takanashi, Yamada Takanashi, Nakamura Takanashi and Ebe Takanashi were called the four families of Takanashi (from &apos;the history of Kamitakai&apos;).</e>
<cmt>the head families of the Takanashi clan--→オリジナル訳に近い形に戻しました。&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>地理的に近い越後国にも所領があったことから越後の勢力の影響を高梨氏も受けるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geologically, the Takanashi clan came to be influenced by the force of Echigo Province where they had their property as it was close geographically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geographically, the Takanashi clan came to be influenced by the force of nearby Echigo Province, where it had property.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geographically, the Takanashi clan came to be influenced by the force of nearby Echigo Province, where it had property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>寛正4年(1463年)12月に、信濃守護職を得た越後守護上杉房定の一族上杉右馬頭が高井郡高橋（中野市西条）に攻め入った際には、高梨政高がこれを討取ってしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAKANASHI Masataka defeated UESUGI Umanokami who was appointed Shinano governor, a member of UESUGI Fusasada, Echigo governor when Umanokami invaded Takahashi, Takai County (Saijo, Nakano City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKANASHI Masataka defeated UESUGI Umanokami, who was the appointed Shinano governor, a member of UESUGI Fusasada, Echigo governor when Umanokami invaded Takahashi, Takai County (Saijo, Nakano City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masataka TAKANASHI defeated Uesugi Umanokami (Captain of the Right Division of Bureau of Horses), who was the appointed Shinano governor, a member of Fusasada UESUGI, Echigo governor when Umanokami invaded Takahashi, Takai County (Saijo, Nakano City).</e>
<cmt>右馬守の説明補足UESUGI→Uesugi姓名の順番を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>高梨氏は信濃村上氏と共に、北信濃の一大勢力として認識されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Takahashi clan as well as the Murakami clan in Shinano came to be recognized as a big force of northern Shinano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takahashi clan, as well as the Murakami clan in Shinano, came to be recognized as major force in northern Shinano.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takahashi clan, as well as the Murakami clan in Shinano, came to be recognized as major force in northern Shinano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>戦国時代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the warring states period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Warring States period</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Warring States period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>高梨政盛の代に、越後守護代の長尾氏と関係を強めるため、長尾能景に娘（政盛と能景は同年代であるため、政高の娘である可能性が高い）を嫁がせるが、その娘が産んだ長尾為景（上杉謙信の父）が越後守護代となり、室町末期には越後で守護上杉氏と長尾家の争いが起きると、高梨氏もそれに巻き込まれることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In TAKANASHI Masamori&apos;s time, to strengthen connection between the Tkanashi and the Nagao clans, local governor of Echigo, Masamori made his daughter marry NAGAO Yoshikage (as Masamori and Yoshikage were at the same age, she was probably a daughter of Masataka) and the daughter bore NAGAO Tamekage (the father of UESUGI Kenshin) who grew into a local governor of Echigo, so that the Takanashi clan was involved in the conflict between the Uesugi clan, governor of Echigo, and the Nagao clan in Echigo in the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In TAKANASHI Masamori&apos;s time, to strengthen the connection between the Takanashi and Nagao clans, the local governor of Echigo, Masamori, had his daughter marry NAGAO Yoshikage (since Masamori and Yoshikage were at the same age, she was probably a daughter of Masataka) and the daughter bore NAGAO Tamekage (the father of UESUGI Kenshin), who ultimately became a local governor of Echigo, so that the Takanashi clan was involved in the conflict between the Uesugi clan, the governor of Echigo, and the Nagao clan in Echigo during the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Masamori TAKANASHI&apos;s time, to strengthen the connection between the Takanashi and Nagao clans, the deputy governor of Echigo, Masamori, had his daughter marry Yoshikage NAGAO (since Masamori and Yoshikage were at the same age, she was probably a daughter of Masataka) and the daughter bore Tamekage NAGAO (the father of Kenshin UESUGI), who ultimately became a deputy governor of Echigo, so that the Takanashi clan was involved in the conflict between the Uesugi clan, the governor of Echigo, and the Nagao clan in Echigo during the late Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正local→deputy</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>永正4年（1507年）、為景が越後守護上杉房能を殺害する際に支援している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tkanashi clan helped Tamekage to kill UESUGI Fusayoshi, governor of Echigo, in 1507.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takanashi clan helped Tamekage assassinate UESUGI Fusayoshi, the governor of Echigo, in 1507.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takanashi clan helped Tamekage assassinate Fusayoshi UESUGI, the governor of Echigo, in 1507.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また房能の兄で関東管領上杉顕定が為景を一旦は放逐するが、永正7年（1510年）の長森原の戦いに為景方の援軍として出陣して顕定を敗死させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">UESUGI Akisada of Kanto kanrei, a brohter of Fusayoshi, ejected Tamekage, but went to fight in the Nagamorihara battle in 1510 for the Tamekage side and died in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">UESUGI Akisada of Kanto kanrei, a brother of Fusayoshi, ejected Tamekage, but went to fight in the Battle of Nagamorihara in 1510 for the Tamekage side, whereupon he died.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akisada UESUGI of Kanto kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), a brother of Fusayoshi, ejected Tamekage, but went to fight in the Battle of Nagamorihara in 1510 for the Tamekage side, whereupon he died.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正関東管領の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>政盛は永正10年（1513年）頃までに善光寺平北部の中野郷を奪取して本拠地と定め、高梨氏の全盛期を築いたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori deprived Nakano in the northern parts of Zenkojidaira, made it the base around 1513, and led to the heyday of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori deprived Nakano in the northern parts of Zenkojidaira and made it a base around 1513, which led to the heyday of the clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori deprived Nakano in the northern parts of Zenkojidaira and made it a base around 1513, which led to the heyday of the clan.</e>
<cmt>of の後のスペース短縮</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかしその年のうちに政盛が死去、越後では為景と新守護上杉定実の争いが起き、近隣の井上一族を始め北信濃の国人衆が上杉方に付き、唯一の長尾方として孤立していく事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Masamori died within the year, the conflict between Tamekage and UESUGI Sadazane, a new governor, took place in Echigo, local lords in northern Shinano including neighboring Inoue family sided with the Uesugi and the Takanashi clan was isolated as the Nagao side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Masamori died within the year, the conflict between Tamekage and UESUGI Sadazane, a new governor, took place in Echigo, local lords in northern Shinano (including the neighboring Inoue family) sided with the Uesugi, and the Takanashi clan was isolated as the Nagao side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Masamori died within the year, the conflict between Tamekage and Sadazane UESUGI, a new governor, took place in Echigo, local lords in northern Shinano (including the neighboring Inoue family) sided with the Uesugi, and the Takanashi clan was isolated as the Nagao side.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>更に善光寺平を手中に収めようとする村上氏との対立もあり、以後高梨氏は弱体化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict with the Murakami clan that intended to take possession of Zenkojidaira took place, and then the Takanashi clan was destabilized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict with the Murakami clan, which intended to take possession of Zenkojidaira, took place, and the Takanashi clan was thus destabilized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict with the Murakami clan, which intended to take possession of Zenkojidaira, took place, and the Takanashi clan was thus destabilized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>それでも政盛の孫の高梨政頼の頃まで独立性を保ってきたが、村上氏を撃破した甲斐国の武田信玄の侵攻を受け、弘治 (日本)年間（1555 - 1558）に本拠地中野郷から信越国境に近い飯山郷まで後退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the time of TAKANASHI Masayori, a grandson of Masamori, the Takanashi clan remained independent, but TAKEDA Shingen of Kai Province who had destroyed the Murakami clan invaded the land of the Takanashi clan and they retreated to Iiyama area close to the boundary of Shinano and Echigo from Nakano, the base, between1555 and 1558.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the time of TAKANASHI Masayori, a grandson of Masamori, the Takanashi clan remained independent, but TAKEDA Shingen, of Kai Province, who had destroyed the Murakami clan, invaded the land of the Takanashi clan and they retreated to the Iiyama area close to the boundary of Shinano and Echigo from Nakano, the base, between1555 and 1558.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the time of Masayori TAKANASHI, a grandson of Masamori, the Takanashi clan remained independent, but Shingen TAKEDA, of Kai Province, who had destroyed the Murakami clan, invaded the land of the Takanashi clan and they retreated to the Iiyama area close to the boundary of Shinano and Echigo from Nakano, the base, between 1555 and 1558.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正1555 の前にスペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>その後、上杉謙信の支援を受けて一時的に所領を取り返したが、その後武田と長尾（上杉）の対立（川中島の戦い）の中で他の北信濃国人衆と共に上杉家の家臣化が進んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, UESUGI Kenshin helped the Takanashi clan to get the manor back, but the Takanashi clan as well as other local lords in northern Shinano became retainers of the Uesugi family during the confliction between Takeda and Nagao (Uesugi) (Kawanakajima War).</e>
<cmt>（上杉謙信）は重複しているので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, UESUGI Kenshin helped the Takanashi clan to get the manor back, but the Takanashi clan as well as other local lords in northern Shinano became retainers of the Uesugi family during the conflict between Takeda and Nagao (Uesugi) (Kawanakajima War).</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Kenshin UESUGI helped the Takanashi clan to get the manor back, but the Takanashi clan as well as other local lords in northern Shinano became retainers of the Uesugi family during the conflict between Takeda and Nagao (Uesugi) (Kawanakajima War).</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="30">
<j>武田氏の滅亡後、北信濃を任された森長可が本能寺の変により撤退、代わって上杉景勝が進出するのに伴って高梨氏は旧領に復帰することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the downfall of the Takeda clan, MORI Nagayoshi who had been left to be in charge of northern Shinano beaten a retreat by the incident at Honno-ji and the Takanashi clan retrieved the old manor when UESUGI Kagekatsu gained ground,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the downfall of the Takeda clan, MORI Nagayoshi, who had been placed in charge of northern Shinano, retreated due to the incident at Honno-ji, and the Takanashi clan retrieved the old manor once UESUGI Kagekatsu gained ground.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the downfall of the Takeda clan, Nagayoshi MORI, who had been placed in charge of northern Shinano, retreated due to the incident at Honno-ji, and the Takanashi clan retrieved the old manor once Kagekatsu UESUGI gained ground.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その後上杉家は、会津・米沢藩と転封を重ねるが、政頼の子・高梨頼親もこれに従っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the Uesugi family forced to change their domains, from Aizu Domain to Yonezawa Domain, and TAKANASHI Yorichika, a child of Masayori, followed the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uesugi family was then forced to change its domain from Aizu Domain to Yonezawa Domain, and TAKANASHI Yorichika, a child of Masayori, followed the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uesugi family was then forced to change its domain from Aizu Domain to Yonezawa Domain, and Yorichika TAKANASHI, a child of Masayori, followed the Uesugi family.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>彼の子孫は米沢藩士として江戸時代に代々続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His descendants survived the Edo period as a member of the Yonezawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His descendants survived the Edo period as members of the Yonezawa clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His descendants survived the Edo period as members of the Yonezawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>この系統の他に、尾張国や丹後国または相模国などに移住した高梨氏もあったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other lines of the Takanashi clan are saod to have moved to Owari Province, Tango Province or Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other lines of the Takanashi clan are said to have moved to Owari Province, Tango Province or Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other lines of the Takanashi clan are said to have moved to Owari Province, Tango Province or Sagami Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>現在の高梨家の末裔として認知されている一族は尾張高梨家出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The authorized descendant of the Takanashi clan today is from the Owari Takanashi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The authorized descendant of the Takanashi clan today is from the Owari Takanashi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The authorized descendant of the Takanashi clan today is from the Owari Takanashi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Chiew(id:39745), 左近衛少将(id:124441), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), カイの迷宮(id:72682), 常陸介(id:176100), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>