<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>橘奈良麻呂の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Revolt of TACHIBANA no Naramaro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rebellion of TACHIBANA no Naramaro</e>
<cmt>Rebellion として統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rebellion of TACHIBANA no Naramaro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>橘奈良麻呂の乱（たちばなのならまろのらん）は奈良時代のクーデターである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Revolt of TACHIBANA no Naramaro was a coup that occurred during the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Rebellion of TACHIBANA no Naramaro was a coup that occurred during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>Rebellion として統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rebellion of TACHIBANA no Naramaro was a coup that occurred during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>橘奈良麻呂が藤原仲麻呂を滅ぼして、天皇の廃立を企てたが、密告により露見して未遂に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Naramaro planned to overpower FUJIWARA no Nakamaro and to enthrone and dethrone the emperor; however, the coup did not succeed due to its exposure by a force of betrayal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TACHIBANA no Naramaro planned to overpower FUJIWARA no Nakamaro and to enthrone and dethrone the emperor; however, the coup did not succeed due to its exposure by a force of betrayal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TACHIBANA no Naramaro planned to overpower FUJIWARA no Nakamaro and to enthrone and dethrone the emperor; however, the coup did not succeed due to its exposure by a force of betrayal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>事件前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History prior to the revolt</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History prior to the rebellion</e>
<cmt>Rebellion として統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History prior to the rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>橘奈良麻呂の父の左大臣橘諸兄は、聖武天皇の治世に政権を担当していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Father of TACHIBANA no Naramaro, Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) TACHIBANA no Moroe, was in charge of a political affair during the period of the Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Father of TACHIBANA no Naramaro, Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) TACHIBANA no Moroe, was in charge of a political affair during the period of the Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Father of TACHIBANA no Naramaro, Sadaijin (Minister of the Left) TACHIBANA no Moroe, was in charge of a political affair during the period of the Emperor Shomu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>天平15年(743年)、難波行幸中の聖武天皇が病に倒れた時、奈良麻呂は佐伯全成に対し小野東人らと謀り次期天皇に黄文王を擁立する旨の計画を漏らす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 743 AD, Naramaro leaked his conspiracy, which was planned with ONO no Azumahit, of enthroning Prince Kibume as the next emperor to Saeki no Matanari after Emperor Shomu became ill during the Namuba-gyoko (an imperial visit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 743, Naramaro leaked his conspiracy, which was planned with ONO no Azumahito, of enthroning Prince Kibumi as the next emperor to SAEKI no Matanari after Emperor Shomu became ill during the imperial visit to Namba.</e>
<cmt>名字を大文字にしました。難波行幸→imperial visit to Namba としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 743, Naramaro leaked his conspiracy, which was planned with ONO no Azumahito, of enthroning Prince Kibumi as the next emperor to SAEKI no Matanari after Emperor Shomu became ill during the imperial visit to Nanba.</e>
<cmt>Namba→Nanbaとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>天平勝宝元年（749年）、聖武天皇が譲位して皇女の阿倍内親王（孝謙天皇）が即位すると、天皇の母の光明皇后に信任されていた藤原仲麻呂が皇太后のために新設された紫微中台の長官（紫微令）に任命される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 749 AD, Fujiwara no Nakamaro who was trusted by Empress Komyo, the emperor&apos;s mother, was appointed to be Kami (a director) of Shibi Chudai (the office that handled the principal empress Komyo&apos;s affairs) which was estabishled for Empress&apos;s dowager after Emperor Shomu abdicated her throne to Imperial Princess Abe (Emperor Koken).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 749, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro who was trusted by Empress Komyo, the emperor&apos;s mother, was appointed to be Kami (a director) of Shibi Chudai (the office that handled the Empress Komyo&apos;s affairs) which was established for Empress&apos;s dowager after Emperor Shomu abdicated his throne to Imperial Princess Abe (Empress Koken).</e>
<cmt>聖武天皇は男性であるため、his throne としました。孝謙天皇は女性であるため、Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 749, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro who was trusted by Empress Komyo, the emperor&apos;s mother, was appointed to be Kami (a director) of Shibi Chudai (the office that handled the Empress Komyo&apos;s affairs) which was established for Empress&apos;s dowager after Emperor Shomu abdicated his throne to Imperial Princess Abe (Empress Koken).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>仲麻呂は孝謙天皇からも寵愛深く、急速に台頭してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakamaro was strongly favored by Emperor Koken and rapidly gained power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakamaro was strongly favored by Empress Koken and rapidly gained power.</e>
<cmt>孝謙天皇は女性であるため、Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakamaro was strongly favored by Empress Koken and rapidly gained power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一方、阿倍内親王の皇位継承に批判的と見られていた橘諸兄親子の勢力は次第に衰退することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the power of TACHIBANA no Moroe and his father, who were considered to be critical to the succession of Imperial Princess Abe to the Emperor, declined gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the power of TACHIBANA no Moroe and his father, who were considered to be critical to the succession of Imperial Princess Abe to the Emperor, declined gradually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the power of TACHIBANA no Moroe and his father, who were considered to be critical to the succession of Imperial Princess Abe to the Emperor, declined gradually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>藤原氏の台頭に危機感を抱いた奈良麻呂は11月の孝謙天皇即位大嘗祭の時佐伯全成に再び謀反の計画を謀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naramaro, who felt threatened by the empowerment of the FUJIWARA clan, talked to Saeki no Mtanari again about his plan of rebellion during the Daijo-sai festival (a festival that celebrated the succession of an emperor) to enthrone Emperor Koken in November.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naramaro, who felt threatened by the empowerment of the Fujiwara clan, talked to SAEKI no Matanari again about his plan of rebellion during the Daijo-sai festival (a festival that celebrated the succession of an emperor) to enthrone Empress Koken in December.</e>
<cmt>人名を修正しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naramaro, who felt threatened by the empowerment of the Fujiwara clan, talked to SAEKI no Matanari again about his plan of rebellion during the Daijo-sai festival (a festival that celebrated the succession of an emperor) to enthrone Empress Koken in December.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし全成が謀反への参加を拒絶したため謀反を実行することが出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Naramaro could not excecute the rebellion because Matanari refused to join his rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Naramaro could not execute the rebellion because Matanari refused to join his rebellion.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Naramaro could not execute the rebellion because Matanari refused to join his rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>天平勝宝7歳（755年）、諸兄の従者佐味宮守から、諸兄が酒宴の席で朝廷を誹謗したとの密告があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 755 AD, SAMI no Miyamori, a servant of Moroe, leaked information from Moroe, which he revealed during a party, regarding his intended abuse towards the imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 755, SAMI no Miyamori, a servant of Moroe, leaked information that Moroe had slandered against the Imperial Court during a party.</e>
<cmt>誹謗したのは諸兄であったと思われるので、左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 755, SAMI no Miyamori, a servant of Moroe, leaked information that Moroe had slandered against the Imperial Court during a party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>聖武太上天皇はこれを問題としなかったが、翌天平勝宝8歳(756年)2月、これを恥じた諸兄は辞職した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomu Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor) was not concerned with this information; however, Moroe, ashamed of his actions, resigned from his position in Feburary, 756.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Retired Emperor Shomu was not concerned with this information; however, Moroe, ashamed of his actions, resigned from his position in March, 756.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Retired Emperor Shomu was not concerned with this information; however, Moroe, ashamed of his actions, resigned from his position in March, 756.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>(2年後諸兄は失意のうちに75歳で死去)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Moroe died with disappointment two years later at the age of 74.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Moroe died with disappointment two years later at the age of 75.)</e>
<cmt>75 に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Moroe died with disappointment two years later at the age of 75.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>同年4月、聖武上皇不豫の際黄金を携えて陸奥より上京した佐伯全成に対して三度謀反の計画を謀った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of 756, Naramaro talked to SAEKI, who was visiting the capital from the Mutsu Province with a monetary gold during Emperor Shomu&apos;s sickness, about the rebellion for the third time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May of 756, Naramaro talked to SAEKI no Matanari, who was visiting the capital from the Mutsu Province with a monetary gold during Emperor Shomu&apos;s sickness, about the rebellion for the third time.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May of 756, Naramaro talked to SAEKI no Matanari, who was visiting the capital from the Mutsu Province with a monetary gold during Emperor Shomu&apos;s sickness, about the rebellion for the third time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このとき奈良麻呂は大伴古麻呂を誘い、大伴佐伯両氏族をもって黄文王擁立を告げるが佐伯大伴両氏はともにこれを拒絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naramaro asked OTOMO no Komara to enthrone Prince Kibumi together with the SAEKI clan; however, both SAEKI and OTOMO refused the proposal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naramaro asked OTOMO no Komaro to enthrone Prince Kibumi together with the Saeki clan; however, both SAEKI and OTOMO refused the proposal.</e>
<cmt>Saeki clan としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naramaro asked OTOMO no Komaro to enthrone Prince Kibumi together with the Saeki clan; however, both SAEKI and OTOMO refused the proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>同年5月2日、聖武太上天皇が崩御する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 2, 756 AD, Shomu Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor) died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 8, 756, the Retired Emperor Shomu died.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor Shomu としました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 8, 756, the Retired Emperor Shomu died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>太上天皇の遺言により道祖王が立太子された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Daijo Tenno&apos;s will, Funado no Okimi became Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to his will, Funado no Okimi (Prince Funado) became the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>Prince Funado を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to his will, Funado no Okimi (Prince Funado) became the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>翌天平宝字元年（757年）4月、道祖王が孝謙天皇の不興を受けて廃され、代わって仲麻呂が推す淳仁天皇が立太子される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April of 757 AD, Funado no Okimi was dethroned due to Emperor Koken&apos;s displeasure and, instead, Emperor Junnin who was recommended by Nakamaro became Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April of 757, Funado no Okimi was dethroned due to Empress Koken&apos;s displeasure and, instead, Emperor Junnin who was recommended by Nakamaro became Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt>孝謙天皇は女性であるため、Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April of 757, Funado no Okimi was dethroned due to Empress Koken&apos;s displeasure and, instead, Emperor Junnin who was recommended by Nakamaro became Crowned Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>陰謀の計画と発覚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Scheme and disclosure of the conspiracy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Scheme and disclosure of the conspiracy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Scheme and disclosure of the conspiracy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>仲麻呂の専横に不満を持ったのが、諸兄の子の奈良麻呂である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naramara, the son of Moroe, felt dissatisfaction towards Nakamaro&apos;s arbitrary behavior.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naramaro, the son of Moroe, felt dissatisfaction towards Nakamaro&apos;s arbitrary behavior.</e>
<cmt>人名のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naramaro, the son of Moroe, felt dissatisfaction towards Nakamaro&apos;s arbitrary behavior.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>奈良麻呂は不満を持つ者たちを集めて仲麻呂を除こうと画策する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naramaro schemed to gather people who felt similarly and eliminate Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naramaro schemed to gather people who felt similarly in order to eliminate Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>in order to eliminate としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naramaro schemed to gather people who felt similarly in order to eliminate Nakamaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>同年6月28日 (旧暦)（7月22日）、山背王が孝謙天皇に「奈良麻呂が兵をもって仲麻呂の邸を包囲しようと計画している」と密告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 22, 757 AD, Yamashiro-O (Prince Yamashiro) informed Emperor Koken about the scheme that Naramaro was planning to surround Nakamaro&apos;s residence with soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 22, 757, Yamashiro-O (Prince Yamashiro) informed Empress Koken of the scheme that Naramaro was planning to surround Nakamaro&apos;s residence with soldiers.</e>
<cmt>AD を削除しました。Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 22, 757, Yamashiro-O (Prince Yamashiro) informed Empress Koken of the scheme that Naramaro was planning to surround Nakamaro&apos;s residence with soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>7月2日 (旧暦)（7月26日）、孝謙天皇と光明皇太后が、諸臣に対して「謀反の噂があるが、皆が逆心を抱くのをやめ、朝廷に従うように」との詔勅を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 26, both Emperor Koken and Empress Dowager Komyo informed their director to not act with treachery and obey the Imperial Court regardless of any rumors of the conspiracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 26, both Empress Koken and Empress Dowager Komyo informed their retainers that they should not act with treachery and obey the Imperial Court regardless of any rumors of the conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 26, both Empress Koken and Empress Dowager Komyo informed their retainers that they should not act with treachery and obey the Imperial Court regardless of any rumors of the conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、その日の夜、中衛府の舎人上道斐太都から、前備前国国司小野東人に謀反への参加を呼びかけられたと仲麻呂へ密告があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on the same evening, Nakamaro was informed by KAMITSUMICHI no Hitatsu, a toneri (a palace servant) of Chuefu (guard), that ONO no Azumahito, an ex-Kokushi (a provincial governer) of Bizen Province, asked him to join the rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on the same evening, Nakamaro was informed by KAMITSUMICHI no Hitatsu, a toneri (a palace servant) of Chuefu (guard), that ONO no Azumahito, an ex-Kokushi (a provincial governor) of Bizen Province, asked him to join the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on the same evening, Nakamaro was informed by KAMITSUMICHI no Hitatsu, a toneri (a palace servant) of Chuefu (guard), that ONO no Azumahito, an ex-Kokushi (a provincial governor) of Bizen Province, asked him to join the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>仲麻呂はただちに孝謙天皇に報告して、中衛府の兵を動かして前皇太子道祖王の邸を包囲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakamaro immediately informed Emperor Koken and sent soldiers from Chuefu to surround the residence of ex-crown Prince Funado no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakamaro immediately informed Empress Koken and sent soldiers from Chuefu to surround the residence of ex-Crown Prince Funado no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakamaro immediately informed Empress Koken and sent soldiers from Chuefu to surround the residence of ex-Crown Prince Funado no Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>小野東人らを捕らえて左衛士府の獄に下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People, including ONO no Azumahito, were arrested and put into the jail in Saejifu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People, including ONO no Azumahito, were arrested and put into the jail in Saejifu (Left Division of Guards).</e>
<cmt>左衛士府　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People, including ONO no Azumahito, were arrested and put into the jail in Saejifu (Left Division of Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>翌7月3日 (旧暦)（7月27日）、右大臣・藤原豊成、中納言・藤原永手らが小野東人を訊問。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following day, July 27, Udaijin (the minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Toyonari, Chunagon (a vive-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Nagate, and others visited ONO no Azumahito and had a hearing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the following day, July 27, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Toyonari, Chunagon (a vive-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Nagate, and others visited ONO no Azumahito and had a hearing.</e>
<cmt>Minister of the Right を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the following day, July 27, Udaijin (Minister of the Right) FUJIWARA no Toyonari, Chunagon (a vive-councilor of state) FUJIWARA no Nagate, and others visited ONO no Azumahito and had a hearing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>東人は無実を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azumahito insisted his innocence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azumahito insisted his innocence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azumahito insisted his innocence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その報告を受けて、孝謙天皇は仲麻呂を傍らに置いて、塩焼王、安宿王、黄文王、橘奈良麻呂、大伴古麻呂を前に「謀反の企てがあるとの報告があるが自分は信じない」との宣命を読み上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After receiving the report from the hearing, Emperor Koken, with Nakamaro beside him, read an imperial edict in front of Princes Shioyaki, Atsukabe, and Kibumi and TACHIBANA no Naramaro, and OTOMO no Komaro that established his disbelief in the conspiracy even though there was a report that confirmed the ensuing rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After receiving the report from the hearing, Empress Koken, with Nakamaro beside him, read an imperial edict in front of Prince Shioyaki, Prince Asukabe, Prince Kibumi, TACHIBANA no Naramaro and OTOMO no Komaro that established her disbelief in the conspiracy even though there was a report that confirmed the ensuing rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Empress Koken としました。 his →her としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After receiving the report from the hearing, Empress Koken, with Nakamaro beside him, read an imperial edict in front of Prince Shioyaki, Prince Asukabe, Prince Kibumi, TACHIBANA no Naramaro and OTOMO no Komaro that established her disbelief in the conspiracy even though there was a report that confirmed the ensuing rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>ところが同日事態は急変する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the situation suddenly changed on the same day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the situation suddenly changed on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the situation suddenly changed on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>右大臣豊成が訊問から外され、再度、永手らを左衛士府に派遣し小野東人、答本忠節（たほのちゅうせつ）らを拷問にかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Udaijin Toyonari was removed from the hearing and Nagate and others were re-sent to Saejifu to torture people including ONO no Azumahito and TAHO no Chusetsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Udaijin Toyonari was removed from the hearing and Nagate and others were re-sent to Saejifu to torture people including ONO no Azumahito and TAHO no Chusetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Udaijin Toyonari was removed from the hearing and Nagate and others were re-sent to Saejifu to torture people including ONO no Azumahito and TAHO no Chusetsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>東人らは一転して謀反を自白した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azumahito and others changed their attitude and confessed about the rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azumahito and others changed their attitude and confessed about the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azumahito and others changed their attitude and confessed about the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>その内容は、橘奈良麻呂、大伴古麻呂、安宿王、黄文王らが一味して兵を発して、仲麻呂の邸を襲って殺し巣ことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The content of the plot revealed that TACHIBANA no Naramaro, OTOMO no Komaro, Prince Asukabe, Prince Kibumito, and others planned to gather troops and attack Nakamaro&apos;s residence and assassinate him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The content of the plot revealed that TACHIBANA no Naramaro, OTOMO no Komaro, Prince Asukabe, Prince Kibumi, and others planned to gather troops and attack Nakamaro&apos;s residence and assassinate him.</e>
<cmt>Kibumito →Kibumi としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The content of the plot revealed that TACHIBANA no Naramaro, OTOMO no Komaro, Prince Asukabe, Prince Kibumi, and others planned to gather troops and attack Nakamaro&apos;s residence and assassinate him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>更に、皇太子を退け、次いで皇太后の宮を包囲して駅鈴と玉璽を奪うこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, they planned to remove Crowned Prince, then surround Empress Dowager&apos;s palace to steal Ekirei (a bell needed for the exercise of Imperial power) and the Imperial Seal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, they planned to remove Crown Prince, then surround Empress Dowager&apos;s palace to steal Ekirei (a bell needed for the exercise of Imperial power) and the Imperial Seal.</e>
<cmt>Crown Prince としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, they planned to remove Crown Prince, then surround Empress Dowager&apos;s palace to steal Ekirei (a bell needed for the exercise of Imperial power) and the Imperial Seal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そして、右大臣豊成を奉じて天下に号令し、その後天皇を廃し、塩焼王、道祖王、安宿王、黄文王の中から天皇を推戴するというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the plan involved Udaijin Toyonari to present an announcement to the society, to discontinue the Go-Emperor system, and to chose one of Prince Shioyaki, Funado no Okimi, Prince Asukabe, and the Prince Kibumi as the emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the plan involved Udaijin Toyonari to present an announcement to the society, then to dethrone the Emperor, and to chose one of Prince Shioyaki, Funado no Okimi, Prince Asukabe, and the Prince Kibumi as the emperor.</e>
<cmt>その後天皇を廃し→then to dethrone the Emperor としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the plan involved Udaijin Toyonari to present an announcement to the society, then to dethrone the Emperor, and to chose one of Prince Shioyaki, Funado no Okimi, Prince Asukabe, and the Prince Kibumi as the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>過酷な処分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Severe punishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Severe punishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Severe punishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>東人の供述により、7月4日 (旧暦)（7月28日）に奈良麻呂をはじめ、道祖王、黄文王、大伴古麻呂、多冶比犢養(たじひのこうしかい)、賀茂角足(かものつのたり)ら、一味に名を挙げられた人々は直ちに逮捕され、永手らの訊問を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Azumahito&apos;s confession, people, including Naramaro, Prince Funado, Prince Kibumi, OTOMO no Komaro, TAJHI no Koshikai, and KAMO no Tsunotari, who were considered to be members of the rebellion were immediately arrested and tortured by Nagate and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Azumahito&apos;s confession, people, including Naramaro, Funado no Okimi, Prince Kibumi, OTOMO no Komaro, TAJIHI no Koshikai, and KAMO no Tsunotari, who were considered to be members of the rebellion were immediately arrested and tortured by Nagate and others.</e>
<cmt>人名を一部修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Azumahito&apos;s confession, people, including Naramaro, Funado no Okimi, Prince Kibumi, OTOMO no Komaro, TAJIHI no Koshikai, and KAMO no Tsunotari, who were considered to be members of the rebellion were immediately arrested and tortured by Nagate and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>訊問が進むにつれ、全員が謀反を白状した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the torturing progressed, all of them confessed about the rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the torturing progressed, all of them confessed about the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the torturing progressed, all of them confessed about the rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>奈良麻呂は永手の聴取に対して「東大寺などを造営し人民が辛苦している。政治が無道だから反乱を企てた。」と打ち明けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naramaro confessed that he planned the rebellion because the government had no mercy and its people were suffering from hardship caused by the construction of the Todaiji Temple and other factors.</e>
<cmt>55,56,57をひとつの文にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naramaro confessed that he planned the rebellion because the government had no mercy and its people were suffering from hardship caused by the construction of the Todai-ji Temple and other factors.</e>
<cmt>Todai-ji Temple としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naramaro confessed that he planned the rebellion because the government had no mercy and its people were suffering from hardship caused by the construction of the Todai-ji Temple and other factors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>この後すぐに獄に移され、永手、百済王敬福、船王らの監督下、杖で全身を何度も打つ拷問が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after the confession, he was transferred to a jail and tortured by repeated beating with a stick under the supervision of Nagate, Kyofuku KUDARANOKONIKISHI, Prince Fune, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after the confession, he was transferred to a jail and tortured by repeated beating with a stick under the supervision of Nagate, Kyofuku KUDARANOKONIKISHI, Prince Fune, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after the confession, he was transferred to a jail and tortured by repeated beating with a stick under the supervision of Nagate, Kyofuku KUDARANOKONIKISHI, Prince Fune, and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>道祖王（麻度比と改名）、黄文王（久奈多夫礼と改名）、古麻呂、東人、犢養、角足（乃呂志と改名）は同日、過酷な拷問に耐えかねて次々と絶命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Funado no Okimi (changed his name to Madohi), Prince Kibumi (changed his name to Kunatabure), Komaro, Azumahito, Koshikai, Tsunotari (changed his name to Noroshi) died one after another because of the severe torture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Funado no Okimi (changed his name to Madohi), Prince Kibumi (changed his name to Kunatabure), Komaro, Azumahito, Koshikai, Tsunotari (changed his name to Noroshi) died one after another on the same day because of the severe torture.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Funado no Okimi (changed his name to Madohi), Prince Kibumi (changed his name to Kunatabure), Komaro, Azumahito, Koshikai, Tsunotari (changed his name to Noroshi) died one after another on the same day because of the severe torture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また首謀者である奈良麻呂の名が続日本紀に残されていないが、同じく拷問死したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, even though Naramaro&apos;s name did not appear in &quot;Shokunihongi&quot; (Continuation Japanese Period), he was considered to be dead in jail like other members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, even though Naramaro&apos;s name did not appear in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), he was considered to be dead in jail like other members.</e>
<cmt>続日本紀　表記を他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, even though Naramaro&apos;s name did not appear in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued), he was considered to be dead in jail like other members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="40">
<j>安宿王は佐渡島、大伴古慈悲（藤原不比等の娘婿）は土佐国に配流された（両者ともその後赦免)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Asukabe was sent to Sadoga-shima Island and OTOMO no Kojihi (a husband of FUJIWARA no Fuhito&apos;s daughter) was sent to Tosa Province even though they were remitted later.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Asukabe was sent to Sadoga-shima Island and OTOMO no Kojihi (a husband of FUJIWARA no Fuhito&apos;s daughter) was sent to Tosa Province (they were remitted later).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Asukabe was sent to Sadoga-shima Island and OTOMO no Kojihi (a husband of FUJIWARA no Fuhito&apos;s daughter) was sent to Tosa Province (they were remitted later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>塩焼王は直接関与した証拠がなかったために臣籍降下（「氷上塩焼」と改名）することで不問とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Shioyaki was not punished because there was no evidence indicating his direct involvment in the rebellion; however, his position as a member of the Imperial family was revoked (changed his name to &quot;HIKAMI no Shioyaki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shioyaki was not punished because there was no evidence indicating his direct involvement in the rebellion; however, his position as a member of the Imperial family was revoked, demoting him from nobility to a subject (changed his name to &apos;HIKAMI no Shioyaki&apos;).</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shioyaki was not punished because there was no evidence indicating his direct involvement in the rebellion; however, his position as a member of the Imperial family was revoked, demoting him from nobility to a subject (changed his name to &apos;HIKAMI no Shioyaki&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>反乱計画に直接関与していなかったものの全成は捕縛され奈良麻呂から謀反をもちかけられた顛末を自白した上で自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Matanari was not directly involved in the planning of the rebellion, he was arrested and confessed, revealing the plans for the rebellion established by Naramaro; he later committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Matanari was not directly involved in the planning of the rebellion, he was arrested and confessed, revealing the plans for the rebellion established by Naramaro; he later committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Matanari was not directly involved in the planning of the rebellion, he was arrested and confessed, revealing the plans for the rebellion established by Naramaro; he later committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>他にもこの事件に連座して流罪、徒罪、没官などの処罰を受けた役人は443人にのぼる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">443 people were implicated in the plot and were punished by deportation, imprisonment, and were revoked of their status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">443 people were implicated in the plot and were punished by deportation, imprisonment, and were revoked of their status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">443 people were implicated in the plot and were punished by deportation, imprisonment, and were revoked of their status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また、右大臣・藤原豊成が息子藤原乙縄とともに事件に関係したとして大宰員外帥に左遷された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toyonari was considered to be involved in the plot with his son, FUJIWARA no Ototada, and was demoted to Dazainoingenosochi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toyonari was considered to be involved in the plot with his son, FUJIWARA no Ototada, and was demoted to Dazainoingenosochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices, which was a position for demotion)</e>
<cmt>大宰員外帥→大宰権帥　と同じポストであるようですが、左遷された貴族に対して使われる表現のようですので、左記のように補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Udaijin FUJIWARA no Toyonari was considered to be involved in the plot with his son, FUJIWARA no Ototada, and was demoted to Dazainoingenosochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices, which was a position for demotion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また、中納言・藤原永手も、その後仲麻呂派で固められた朝廷内で政治的に孤立し逼塞を余儀なくされたと言う説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover,there is a theory that Chunagon (a middle counselor) FUJIWARA no Nagate was politically isolated in the imperial Court, where the Nakamaro clan was empowered, and forced to fall into obscurity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there is a theory that Chunagon FUJIWARA no Nagate was politically isolated in the Imperial Court, where the Nakamaro faction was empowered, and forced to fall into obscurity.</e>
<cmt>中納言　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there is a theory that Chunagon FUJIWARA no Nagate was politically isolated in the Imperial Court, where the Nakamaro faction was empowered, and forced to fall into obscurity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>皮肉にも豊成・永手らは反仲麻呂派であると同時に奈良麻呂らの標的とされた孝謙天皇の側近であった人々であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ironically, people such as Toyonari and Nagate were members of the anti-Nakamaro party as well as close advisors to Emperor Koken, a target of Naramaro.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ironically, people such as Toyonari and Nagate were members of the anti-Nakamaro party as well as close advisors to Empress Koken, a target of Naramaro.</e>
<cmt>Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ironically, people such as Toyonari and Nagate were members of the anti-Nakamaro party as well as close advisors to Empress Koken, a target of Naramaro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>彼らは、天皇廃立を企てた奈良麻呂らに対して過酷な尋問や拷問を行った人々でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were the people who performed the intense interrogation and torture against Nakamaro and others who planned the enthronement and dethronement of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the people who performed the intense interrogation and torture against Nakamaro and others who planned the enthronement and dethronement of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the people who performed the intense interrogation and torture against Nakamaro and others who planned the enthronement and dethronement of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>仲麻呂はこの事件により、自分に不満を持つ政敵を一掃することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nakamaro succeeded to clean away all political enemies who held dissatisfaction towards him as a result of this event.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakamaro succeeded to clean away all political enemies who held dissatisfaction towards him as a result of this event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakamaro succeeded to clean away all political enemies who held dissatisfaction towards him as a result of this event.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>天平宝字2年（758年）、大炊王が即位し（淳仁天皇）、仲麻呂は太保（右大臣）に任ぜられ、恵美押勝の名を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 758 AD, Prince Oi was enthroned (Emperor Junnin) and Nakamaro was appointed Taiho (Udaijin) gaining the name of EMI no Oshikatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 758, Prince Oi was enthroned (Emperor Junnin) and Nakamaro was appointed Taiho (Udaijin) gaining the name of EMI no Oshikatsu.</e>
<cmt>ADを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 758, Prince Oi was enthroned (Emperor Junnin) and Nakamaro was appointed Taiho (Udaijin) gaining the name of EMI no Oshikatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そして、天平宝字4年（760年）には太師（太政大臣）にまで登りつめ栄耀栄華を極めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in 760 AD, Nakamaro became the Taishi (Daijyo-daijin the Grand Minister) and lived luxuriously and prosperously.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in 760, Nakamaro became the Taishi (Daijo-daijin [Grand Minister of State]) and lived luxuriously and prosperously.</e>
<cmt>ADを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in 760, Nakamaro became the Taishi (Daijo-daijin [Grand Minister of State]) and lived luxuriously and prosperously.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>だが、その没落も早く、孝謙天皇の寵愛は道鏡に移った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his fall came quickly after Emperor Koken&apos;s love moved to Dokyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his fall came quickly after Empress Koken&apos;s love moved to Dokyo.</e>
<cmt>Empress Koken としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his fall came quickly after Empress Koken&apos;s love moved to Dokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>天平宝字8年（764年）、仲麻呂は乱を起こして敗れ、その一族は滅んだ（藤原仲麻呂の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 764 AD, Nakamaro lost a coup (a coup of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) that he started and his clan perished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 764, Nakamaro lost a coup (the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) that he started and his clan perished.</e>
<cmt>ADを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 764, Nakamaro lost a coup (the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) that he started and his clan perished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yanahan(id:2437), 味っ子(id:17086), Giniro(id:39859), 水野白楓(id:22811), Kamitani(id:30757), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>