<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>敵討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katakiuchi (Revenge)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katakiuchi (Revenge)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katakiuchi (Revenge)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>敵討（かたきうち）とは、直接の尊属を殺害した者に対して私刑として復讐を行う制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Katakiuchi&quot; is the practice of taking out one&apos;s revenge, by taking the law into his own hands, against someone who killed a direct ancestor of the revenging party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Katakiuchi&quot; is the practice of taking out one&apos;s revenge, by taking the law into his own hands, against someone who has killed a direct ancestor of the avenging party.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katakiuchi is the practice of taking out one&apos;s revenge, by taking the law into his own hands, against someone who has killed a direct ancestor of the avenging party.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では中世頃からこの慣行があり、江戸時代になって法制化され、仇討ち（あだうち）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This practice existed in Japan from around the medieval period; it was legislated in the Edo Period and was called &quot;Adauchi&quot; (revenge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This practice existed in Japan from around the medieval period; it was legislated in the Edo period and was called &quot;Adauchi (revenge&quot;).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This practice existed in Japan from around the medieval period; it was legislated in the Edo period and was called Adauchi (revenge).</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>敵討の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Katakiuchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The History of Katakiuchi</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The History of Katakiuchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』巻十四雄略紀には、456年（安康天皇3年）に起きた『眉輪王の変』の記事があり、これが史料に残る最古の敵討事件とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Vol. 14, &quot;Yuryakuki&quot; (period of Emperor Yuryaku), contains an article on the &quot;Conspiracy of Prince Mayowa&quot; which occurred in 456, and this is regarded as the oldest case of Katakiuchi remaining in historical materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Vol. 14, &quot;Yuryakuki&quot; (period of Emperor Yuryaku), contains an article on the &quot;Conspiracy of Prince Mayowa,&quot; which occurred in 456, and this is regarded as the oldest case of Katakiuchi remaining in historical materials.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), Vol. 14, &quot;Yuryakuki&quot; (period of Emperor Yuryaku), contains an article on the &quot;Conspiracy of Prince Mayowa,&quot; which occurred in 456, and this is regarded as the oldest case of Katakiuchi remaining in historical materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>眉輪王の義理の父にあたる安康天皇はかつて眉輪王の父である大草香皇子を殺し、母である中磯皇女を自らの妃とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a time in the past, Emperor Anko, who was the father-in-law of Prince Mayowa, killed Prince Mayowa&apos;s father, Imperial Prince Okusaka, and married Prince Mayowa&apos;s mother, Imperial Princess Nakashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time in the past, Emperor Anko, who was the father-in-law of Prince Mayowa, killed Prince Mayowa&apos;s father, Imperial Prince Okusaka, and married Prince Mayowa&apos;s mother, Imperial Princess Nakashi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time in the past, Emperor Anko, who was the father-in-law of Prince Mayowa, killed Prince Mayowa&apos;s father, Imperial Prince Okusaka, and married Prince Mayowa&apos;s mother, Imperial Princess Nakashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>安康天皇はある日ふとその事を漏らし、それを聞いた眉輪王は安康天皇が熟睡しているところを刺し殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day Emperor Anko inadvertently mentioned this fact; Prince Mayowa, who heard it, stabbed Emperor Anko to death while he was in a deep sleep.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day Emperor Anko inadvertently mentioned this fact, and consequently Prince Mayowa, who overheard it, stabbed Emperor Anko to death while he was in a deep sleep.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day Emperor Anko inadvertently mentioned this fact, and consequently Prince Mayowa, who overheard it, stabbed Emperor Anko to death while he was in a deep sleep.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>事件後、その動機を追究された眉輪王は「臣元不求天位、唯報父仇而已」（私は皇位を狙ったのではない、ただ父の仇に報いただけだ）と答えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Prince Mayowa was pressed for his motive after the affair, he replied: &quot;I was not seeking the Imperial Throne, I was only avenging my father&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Prince Mayowa was pressed for his motive after the affair, he replied: &quot;I wasn&apos;t seeking the Imperial Throne, I was only avenging my father.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Prince Mayowa was pressed for his motive after the affair, he replied: &apos;I wasn&apos;t seeking the Imperial Throne, I was only avenging my father.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>その後仇討ちは武士階級の台頭以来広く見られるようになるが、江戸幕府によって法制化されるに至ってその形式が完成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Katakiuchi became prevalent along with the rise of the samurai hierarchy, and when the practice was legislated by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), it took a complete form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Katakiuchi became prevalent along with the rise of the samurai hierarchy, and when the practice was legislated by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), it took a complete form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Katakiuchi became prevalent along with the rise of the samurai hierarchy, and when the practice was legislated by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), it took a complete form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>範囲は父母や兄等尊属の親族が殺害された場合に限られ、卑属（妻子や弟・妹を含む）に対するものは基本的に認められない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its extent was limited to the case of having one&apos;s direct family member such as his parent or older sibling being killed, and was not basically allowed when it was intended for a descendent (including his wife, child, and younger sibling).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its extent was limited to the case of having one&apos;s direct family member (such as a parent or older sibling) killed, so basically it wasn&apos;t allowed when it was intended for a descendent (including one&apos;s wife, child or younger sibling).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its extent was limited to the case of having one&apos;s direct family member (such as a parent or older sibling) killed, so basically it wasn&apos;t allowed when it was intended for a descendent (including one&apos;s wife, child or younger sibling).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>又中世の血族意識から起こった風俗であるので、主君のように血縁関係のない者について行われることは少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, since this custom arose out of the sense of blood tie in the medieval period, it was rarely conducted for someone who had no blood relationship such as one&apos;s lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, since this custom arose out of the sense of blood ties in the medieval period, it was rarely carried out against someone who had no blood relationship, such as one&apos;s lord.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, since this custom arose out of the sense of blood ties in the medieval period, it was rarely carried out against someone who had no blood relationship, such as one&apos;s lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>武士身分の場合は主君の免状を受け、他国へわたる場合には奉行所への届出が必要で、町奉行所の敵討帳に記載され、謄本を受け取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the revenging party was of samurai status, he received a permit from his lord; if he were to travel to another province, he needed to report it to a magistrate&apos;s office to have the information recorded on the Katakiuchi List at the town magistrate&apos;s office, and received a copy of the original.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the avenging party was of samurai status, he received a permit from his lord; if he was to travel to another province, he needed to report it to a magistrate&apos;s office in order to have the information recorded on the Katakiuchi List at the town magistrate&apos;s office, whereupon he received a copy of the original.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the avenging party was of samurai status, he received a permit from his lord; if he was to travel to another province, he needed to report it to a magistrate&apos;s office in order to have the information recorded on the Katakiuchi List at the town magistrate&apos;s office, whereupon he received a copy of the original.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>無許可の敵討の例もあったが、現地の役人が調査し、敵討であると認められなければ殺人として罪せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were unauthorized cases of Katakiuchi as well, but if local officers investigated the case and did not acknowledge it as Katakiuchi, the revenging party was punished as a murderer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were unauthorized cases of Katakiuchi as well, but if local officers investigated such a case and did not acknowledge it as Katakiuchi, the avenging party would be punished as a murderer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were unauthorized cases of Katakiuchi as well, but if local officers investigated such a case and did not acknowledge it as Katakiuchi, the avenging party would be punished as a murderer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、敵討をした相手に対して復讐をする重敵討は禁止されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Ju-Katakiuchi (double Katakiuchi), or an act of taking revenge on the originally revenging party was prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Ju-Katakiuchi (double Katakiuchi), or the act of taking revenge on the originally avenging party, was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Ju-Katakiuchi (double Katakiuchi), or the act of taking revenge on the originally avenging party, was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>敵討の許可が行われたのは基本的に武士階級についてのみであったが、それ以外の身分の者でも敵討を行う者はまま見られ、上記のような手続きを踏まなかった武士階級の敵討同様、孝子の所業として大目に見られ、場合によっては賞賛されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, Katakiuchi was permitted only to those of the samurai hierarchy althogh it was occasionally performed by those of other social standings; such cases were overlooked as deeds by dutiful children as with the Katakiuchi by those of the samurai hierarchy who did not go through the above-described procedures; in some cases, such deeds were often praised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, Katakiuchi was permitted only to those of the samurai hierarchy, although it was occasionally performed by those of other social standings; such cases were overlooked as deeds by dutiful children, as with the Katakiuchi by those of the samurai hierarchy who did not go through the above-described procedures; and in some cases these deeds were praised.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, Katakiuchi was permitted only to those of the samurai hierarchy, although it was occasionally performed by those of other social standings; such cases were overlooked as deeds by dutiful children, as with the Katakiuchi by those of the samurai hierarchy who did not go through the above-described procedures; and in some cases these deeds were praised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>又武家の当主が殺害された場合、その嫡子が相手を敵討ちしなければ、家名の継承が許されないとする慣習も広く見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the custom, in which if the head of a samurai family was killed, his legitimate child had to get his revenge or otherwise he was not allowed to succeed the family name, was widely found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the custom in which, if the head of a samurai family was killed, his legitimate child had to get his revenge or wouldn&apos;t be allowed to succeed the family name, was widespread.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the custom in which, if the head of a samurai family was killed, his legitimate child had to get his revenge or wouldn&apos;t be allowed to succeed the family name, was widespread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、敵討は決闘であるため、敵とされる側にもこれを迎え撃つ正当防衛が認められており、殺害した場合は「返り討ち」と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Katakiuchi was a duel, it was allowed for the target of the revenge, or the opponent, to act in self-defense by a counterattack; if the opponent killed the revenging party, this was called &quot;Kaeriuchi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Katakiuchi was a duel, it was allowed for the target of the revenge, or the opponent, to act in self-defense by a counterattack; if the opponent killed the avenging party, this was called &quot;Kaeriuchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Katakiuchi was a duel, it was allowed for the target of the revenge, or the opponent, to act in self-defense by a counterattack; if the opponent killed the avenging party, this was called &apos;Kaeriuchi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>近親者を殺されてその復讐をする例は、南イタリアを始めとして、世界各地で見られるが、江戸時代の敵討は、喧嘩両成敗を補完する方法として法制化されていたことと、主眼は復讐ではなく武士の意地・面目であるとされていた点に特徴がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cases of having one&apos;s close relative killed and taking his revenge are found in various parts of the world including southern Italy; however, Katakiuchi of the Edo Period are characterized in that it was legitimated as a method to supplement Kenka Ryoseibai (in a quarrel both parties are to blame) and that the aim was not the revenge but pride / honor of a samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cases of revenge after the killing of a close relative are found in various parts of the world, including southern Italy; however, the characteristic of Katakiuchi in the Edo period is that it was legitimized as a method to supplement Kenka Ryoseibai (in a quarrel both parties are to blame) and that the aim was not the revenge but the pride or honor of a samurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cases of revenge after the killing of a close relative are found in various parts of the world, including southern Italy; however, the characteristic of Katakiuchi in the Edo period is that it was legitimized as a method to supplement Kenka Ryoseibai (in a quarrel both parties are to blame) and that the aim was not the revenge but the pride or honor of a samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>特に江戸時代には、敵討の中でも曾我兄弟の仇討ち(1193年、『曽我物語』)、鍵屋の辻の決闘(1634年)、元禄赤穂事件(1702年、『忠臣蔵』)は「三大仇討ち」と呼ばれ、多くの作品で人々に親しまれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the Edo Period, of the cases of Katakiuchi, the Adauchi cases by Soga brothers were called the &quot;Three Major Adauchi Cases&quot; and became known to people in many works (&quot;Story of the Soga Family&quot; in 1193; the duel at Kagiya no Tsuji in 1634; and Genroku Ako Incident, or &quot;Chushingura&quot;, in 1702).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly in the Edo period, of the cases of Katakiuchi, the Adauchi cases by the Soga brothers were known as the &quot;Three Major Adauchi Cases&quot; and became known to people in many works (&quot;Story of the Soga Family&quot; in 1193; the duel at Kagiya no Tsuji in 1634; and the Genroku Ako Incident, or &quot;Chushingura,&quot; in 1702).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly in the Edo period, of the cases of Katakiuchi, the Adauchi cases by the Soga brothers were known as the &apos;Three Major Adauchi Cases&apos; and became known to people in many works (&quot;Story of the Soga Family&quot; in 1193; the duel at Kagiya no Tsuji in 1634; and the Genroku Ako Incident, or &quot;Chushingura,&quot; in 1702).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>明治になると司法卿の江藤新平らによる司法制度の整備が行われ、1873年（明治6）2月7日、明治政府は第37号布告で『敵討禁止令』を発布し、禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the time Meiji Period rolled around, a judicial system was developed by Shihokyo (administrator of Ministry of Justice) such as Shinpei ETO, and Katakiuchi was banned by the Meiji Government by the issuance of &quot;Katakiuchi kinshirei&quot; (ban of revenge) in Decree No. 37 on February 7, 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the arrival of the Meiji period, a judicial system was developed by Shihokyo (administrator of Ministry of Justice) such as Shinpei ETO, and on February 7, 1873, Katakiuchi was banned by the Meiji Government through the issuance of &quot;Katakiuchi kinshirei (ban on revenge)&quot; in Decree No. 37.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the arrival of the Meiji period, a judicial system was developed by Shihokyo (administrator of Ministry of Justice) such as Shinpei ETO, and on February 7, 1873, Katakiuchi was banned by the Meiji Government through the issuance of &quot;Katakiuchi kinshirei (ban on revenge)&quot; in Decree No. 37.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>御成敗式目と敵討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goseibai-shikimoku (code of conduct for samurai) and Katakiuchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goseibai-shikimoku (Samurai Code of Conduct) and Katakiuchi</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goseibai-shikimoku (Samurai Code of Conduct) and Katakiuchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>御成敗式目（貞永式目）第十条には、殺人や傷害、役職目的の殺人や強盗殺人の規定があるが、このなかに敵討の禁止を定める規定がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Article 10 of Goseibai-shikimoku, or Joei-shikimoku (another term for Goseibai-shikimoku, later named after the Joei Period during which Goseibai-shikimoku was established), contains provisions on murder, injury, murder targeted at a post, and murder-robbery; ban of Katakiuchi is stipulated therein.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 10 of Goseibai-shikimoku, or Joei-shikimoku (another term for Goseibai-shikimoku, later named after the Joei period during which Goseibai-shikimoku was established), contains provisions on murder, injury, murder targeted at a post, and murder-robbery; the prohibition of Katakiuchi is stipulated therein.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 10 of Goseibai-shikimoku, or Joei-shikimoku (another term for Goseibai-shikimoku, later named after the Joei period during which Goseibai-shikimoku was established), contains provisions on murder, injury, murder targeted at a post, and murder-robbery; the prohibition of Katakiuchi is stipulated therein.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>現代訳：（大意）子や孫が父祖の仇を殺した場合、（殺人をおかした犯人の）父や祖父がそのことを知らなくても同じ罪（死刑か流罪･財産没収）を課せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Japanese translation: (Synopsis) If a son or grandson kills the foe of his father or grandfather, the father or grandfather (of the perpetrator of the killing) will be punished for the same crime (death penalty or transportation, or asset forfeiture) regardless of such person being aware of the crime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Japanese translation (synopsis): If a son or a grandson kills the foe of his father or grandfather, the father or grandfather (of the perpetrator of the killing) will be punished for the same crime (death penalty, deportation or asset forfeiture) regardless of whether such person was aware of the crime.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Japanese translation (synopsis): If a son or a grandson kills the foe of his father or grandfather, the father or grandfather (of the perpetrator of the killing) will be punished for the same crime (death penalty, deportation or asset forfeiture) regardless of whether such person was aware of the crime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>父祖の憤りを充たすために宿願を遂げたのであるから。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because the killing was done to satisfy the cherished desire of the father or grandfather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because the killing was committed in order to satisfy the cherished desire of the father or grandfather.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because the killing was committed in order to satisfy the cherished desire of the father or grandfather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>父祖が死亡している場合はもとより無関係であるが、父祖が存命中に子孫が父祖のために敵討をすれば、父祖も連座で罰せられるとの規定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It goes without saying that this would be irrelevant if the father or grandfather were already dead; however, this provision stipulates that if the son or grandson revenged for his father or grandfather while his father or grandfather was still alive, his father or grandfather would be punished as well for being guilty by association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It goes without saying that this would be irrelevant if the father or grandfather were already dead; however, this provision stipulates that if the son or grandson avenged his father or grandfather while his father or grandfather was still alive, his father or grandfather would also be punished for being guilty by association.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It goes without saying that this would be irrelevant if the father or grandfather were already dead; however, this provision stipulates that if the son or grandson avenged his father or grandfather while his father or grandfather was still alive, his father or grandfather would also be punished for being guilty by association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>御成敗式目では父祖のための敵討は処罰の対象とされており、江戸時代に見られる敵討の文脈とは異なるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Goseibai-shikimoku, Katakiuchi for the father or grandfather was the subject of punishment; this is different from the context of Katakiuchi seen in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Goseibai-shikimoku, Katakiuchi for the father or grandfather was the subject of punishment; this is different from the context of Katakiuchi seen in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Goseibai-shikimoku, Katakiuchi for the father or grandfather was the subject of punishment; this is different from the context of Katakiuchi seen in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>曾我兄弟の仇討ちでは敵討後に捕えられた弟五郎時致は斬首されており、頼朝の代の先例に準じる御成敗式目の規定はこの処置に沿っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Adauchi by Soga brothers, the younger brother Goro Tokimune SOGA, who was captured after Katakiuchi, was beheaded, and the provisions of Goseibai-shikimoku which conform to the precedents during the reign of Yoritomo (MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a shogun) reflect this disposition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Adauchi by the Soga brothers, the younger brother, Goro Tokimune SOGA, who was captured after Katakiuchi, was beheaded; and the provisions of Goseibai-shikimoku, which conform to the precedents during the reign of Yoritomo (MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a shogun), reflect this disposition.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Adauchi by the Soga brothers, the younger brother, Goro Tokimune SOGA, who was captured after Katakiuchi, was beheaded; and the provisions of Goseibai-shikimoku, which conform to the precedents during the reign of Yoritomo (MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a shogun), reflect this disposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>女敵討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Megatakiuchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Megatakiuchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Megatakiuchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>妻が姦通した際に姦通相手と妻を殺害することを女敵討（めがたきうち）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Megatakiuchi&quot; referred to the killing of one&apos;s wife in adultery along with the man with whom she committed the adultery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Megatakiuchi&quot; referred to the killing of one&apos;s wife in adultery along with the man with whom she had committed the adultery.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Megatakiuchi referred to the killing of one&apos;s wife in adultery along with the man with whom she had committed the adultery.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』がないので&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>姦通が表沙汰になった際の女敵討は武士にとっては義務であったが、たとえ達成しても名誉にはならないため、表沙汰にせずに内々で示談にするケースも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Megatakiuchi was the duty of a samurai once the adultery came to light, but since it did no one any great credit even when Megatakiuchi was achieved, such case was often settled in private without being made public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Megatakiuchi was the duty of a samurai once the adultery came to light, but since it did no one any great credit even when Megatakiuchi was achieved, such cases were often settled in private without being made public.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Megatakiuchi was the duty of a samurai once the adultery came to light, but since it did no one any great credit even when Megatakiuchi was achieved, such cases were often settled in private without being made public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>代表的な仇討事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major cases of Adauchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major Cases of Adauchi</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major Cases of Adauchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>正月の初夢に見ると縁起が良い夢をあげて「一富士、二鷹、三なすび」（いちふじ、にたか、さんなすび）という伝統的な表現がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the traditional expression of &quot;Mount Fuji for first, hawk for second, and eggplant for third&quot; as the lucky items to dream about in the first dream of the new year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is the traditional expression &quot;Mount Fuji for first, hawk for second and eggplant for third&quot; as the lucky items to dream about in the first dream of the new year.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is the traditional expression &apos;Mount Fuji for first, hawk for second and eggplant for third&apos; as the lucky items to dream about in the first dream of the new year.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これは一説には江戸時代の中頃から「三大仇討ち」として喧伝されてきた「曾我兄弟の仇討ち」（曾我兄弟は富士山の裾野市で巻狩りが行なわれた際にこれに乗じて仇討ちを行なった）、「赤穂浪士の討ち入り」（播磨国赤穂藩浅野家の家紋が「丸に違い鷹の羽」だったことから）、「伊賀越えの仇討ち」（伊賀国はなすびの産地として知られていたことから）のことを言ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, this expression referred to the Adauchi cases which were widely known from the middle of the Edo Period as the &quot;Three Major Adauchi Cases&quot;: &quot;Adauchi by Soga brothers&quot; (Soga brothers performed Adauchi by taking advantage of the makigari (a form of hunting by surrounding the target from various directions) which took place in Susono City at the foot of Mount Fuji); &quot;Ako Roshi no Uchiiri&quot; (since the seal of the Asano family of the Ako clan in Harima Province was a &quot;hawk&apos;s feather and not a circle&quot;); and &quot;Igagoe no Adauchi&quot; (since Iga Province was known as the production area of eggplants).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, this expression referred to the Adauchi cases that were widely known from the middle of the Edo period as the &quot;Three Major Adauchi Cases&quot;: &quot;Adauchi by the Soga brothers&quot; (the Soga brothers performed Adauchi by taking advantage of the makigari (a form of hunting by surrounding the target from various directions) which took place in Susono City at the foot of Mount Fuji); &quot;Ako Roshi no Uchiiri&quot; (since the seal of the Asano family of the Ako clan, in Harima Province, was a &quot;hawk&apos;s feather without a circle&quot;); and &quot;Igagoe no Adauchi&quot; (since Iga Province was known as an area for the production of eggplant).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, this expression referred to the Adauchi cases that were widely known from the middle of the Edo period as the &apos;Three Major Adauchi Cases&apos;: &apos;Adauchi by the Soga brothers&apos; (the Soga brothers performed Adauchi by taking advantage of the makigari (a form of hunting by surrounding the target from various directions) which took place in Susono City at the foot of Mount Fuji); &apos;Ako Roshi no Uchiiri&apos; (since the seal of the Asano family of the Ako clan, in Harima Province, was a &apos;hawk&apos;s feather without a circle&apos;); and &apos;Igagoe no Adauchi&apos; (since Iga Province was known as an area for the production of eggplant).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>以下は代表的な仇討ち事件：</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major cases of Adauchi are as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major cases of Adauchi are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major cases of Adauchi are as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>曾我兄弟の仇討ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adauchi by Soga brothers;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adauchi by the Soga brothers;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adauchi by the Soga brothers;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>源実朝落命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>天下茶屋の仇討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adauchi at Tenkachaya / Tengajaya;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adauchi at Tenkachaya (Tengajaya);</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adauchi at Tengachaya;</e>
<cmt>天下茶屋→Tengachaya</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>鍵屋の辻の決闘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duel at Kagiya no Tsuji;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The duel at Kagiya no Tsuji;</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duel at Kagiya no Tsuji;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>浄瑠璃坂の仇討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adauchi at Joruri Zaka;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adauchi at Joruri Zaka;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adauchi at Joruri Zaka;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>亀山の仇討ち</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adauchi at Kameyama;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adauchi at Kameyama;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adauchi at Kameyama;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>高田馬場の決闘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duel at Takadanobaba; and</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The duel at Takadanobaba; and</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duel at Takadanobaba; and</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>元禄赤穂事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Genroku Ako Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>フィクションにおける敵討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Adauchi in fictions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adauchi in fiction</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adauchi in fiction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>歌舞伎や浄瑠璃の一ジャンルとして「仇討狂言」という物が存在するほど、敵討を主題とした作品は広く支持されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Works on the subject of Katakiuchi have been widely supported, so much so that there is a genre called &quot;Adauchi kyogen&quot; (comic drama on Adauchi) in Kabuki and Joruri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Works on the subject of Katakiuchi have been widely supported, so much so that there is a genre called &quot;Adauchi kyogen&quot; (comic drama on Adauchi) in Kabuki and Joruri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Works on the subject of Katakiuchi have been widely supported, so much so that there is a genre called &quot;Adauchi kyogen&quot; (comic drama on Adauchi) in Kabuki and Joruri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>現代でも時代劇で物語の中によく取り取り入れられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even today, Katakiuchi is often portrayed in stories of samurai dramas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even today, Katakiuchi is often portrayed in the stories of samurai dramas.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even today, Katakiuchi is often portrayed in the stories of samurai dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>漫画や小説、映画などでも、主要人物の行動原理としてしばしば採用される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katakiuchi is also frequently adapted as the behavioral principle of the main character in comic books, novels, and movies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katakiuchi is also frequently adapted as the behavioral principle of the main character in comic books, novels and movies.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katakiuchi is also frequently adapted as the behavioral principle of the main character in comic books, novels and movies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>特にサスペンスや推理小説といったフィクションでは犯人の犯行動機として設定されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in fictions such as suspense stories and mysteries, Katakiuchi is often made the setting for the motive of crime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in works of fiction, such as suspense stories and mysteries, Katakiuchi is often made the setting for the motive of crime.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in works of fiction, such as suspense stories and mysteries, Katakiuchi is often made the setting for the motive of crime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>現実の刑事事件でも復讐を目的として犯行に至った例は見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even real criminal cases include those in which the crime developed with the aim of revenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even real criminal cases include those in which the crime developed with the aim of revenge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even real criminal cases include those in which the crime developed with the aim of revenge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 模様砂漠(id:254067), Izayohi(id:13095), 経済準学士(id:22656), Mikcun(id:46906), Sloop25(id:35005), RekishiEJ(id:43355), Mercurius(id:57130), Baf(id:31737), 白拍子花子(id:244805), EULE(id:74209), PeachLover(id:56909), Shin-改(id:9914), おきた(id:18906), Shimoxx(id:9332), Point136(id:211299), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>