<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>家臣団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kashindan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashindan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashindan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>家臣団（かしんだん）とは、征夷大将軍や大名など武家に仕える家臣層・家臣の集団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Kashindan means the group of vassals serving for samurai families, such as the family of seii taishogun (literally, a general who subsides barbarians) or daimyo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Kashindan refers to the group of vassals serving samurai families, such as the family of the Seii Taishogun (literally, a general who subsides barbarians) or a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar; I know &quot;Seii Taishogun&quot; is not capitalized in the word list, but it just looks better to me this way, so I changed it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Kashindan refers to the group of vassals serving samurai families, such as the family of the Seii Taishogun (literally, a general who subsides barbarians) or a daimyo (Japanese territorial lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中世以前の主従関係</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relation of master and vassals until the medieval period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between master and vassal until the medieval period</e>
<cmt>added &quot;The&quot; at the beginning; changed &quot;relation&quot; to &quot;relationship&quot;; changed &quot;of&quot; to &quot;between&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between master and vassal until the medieval period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>中世以前の武士の主従関係において武門の棟梁に従属する武士を家人と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the relation of master and vassals until the medieval period, samurai who were subordinated to bumon no toryo (leader of samurai families) were called kenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the medieval period, samurai within a master and vassal relationship who were subordinate to a Bumon no toryo (leader of samurai families) were called Kenin.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the medieval period, samurai within a master and vassal relationship who were subordinate to a Bumon no toryo (leader of samurai families) were called Kenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>こうした家人の多くは平安時代の郡司・土豪の系譜をひき、国府の在庁官人として国府行政の一端を担っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of kenin were the descendants of gunji (local magistrate)/dogo (local powerful clan) in the Heian period and were engaged in the administration jobs at kokufu (provincial government office) as local officials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most Kenin during the Heian period were descendants of a Gunji (local magistrate) or Dogo (local powerful clan) and were engaged in the administration of the Kokufu (provincial government office) as local officials.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar; capitalized &quot;Kokufu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Kenin during the Heian period were descendants of a Gunji (local magistrate) or Dogo (local powerful clan) and were engaged in the administration of the Kokufu (provincial government office) as local officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>一方で院宮王臣家や有力な寺社に荘園を寄進して国府の重税から逃れることで財政負担と朝廷からの干渉・介入を防いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, they evaded heavy tax imposed by kokufu and prevented Imperial Court&apos;s intervention/interference by donating shoen (manor) to engu oshinke (a general term for Imperial families and nobilities) and influential temples/shrines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, they evaded heavy taxes imposed by the Kokufu and prevented intervention by the Imperial Court by donating shoen (manor) to Engu oshinke (a general term for Imperial families and nobilities) and influential temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;On the other hand&quot; to &quot;Meanwhile&quot;; eliminated &quot;interference&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, they evaded heavy taxes imposed by the Kokufu and prevented intervention by the Imperial Court by donating shoen (manor) to Ingu oshinke (a general term for Imperial families and nobilities) and influential temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>Engu oshinke→Ingu oshinkeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同時に対外的な武力侵攻に対しては貴い血筋と武名、朝廷や権門との親密さを背景に地方に強固な勢力を持つ武門の棟梁に臣従して本領安堵を請い、その保護下に入ることで難を逃れたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, they rendered homage and service to bumon no toryo, who had strong power in provinces thanks to their noble bloodline and close relationship with the Imperial Court and powerful nobilities, in return for honryo-ando (acknowledgement of inherited territories) so that they could get out of trouble under the protection of bumon no toryo in the event of military attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, they rendered homage and service to a Bumon no toryo, who held great provincial power due to their noble bloodline and close relationship with the Imperial Court and powerful nobilities. They did so in return for honryo-ando (acknowledgement of inherited territories) so that they could get out of trouble under the protection of the Bumon no toryo in the event of military attack.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences since this was uncomfortably long as one; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, they rendered homage and service to a Bumon no toryo, who held great provincial power due to their noble bloodline and close relationship with the Imperial Court and powerful nobilities; they did so in return for honryo-ando (acknowledgement of inherited territories) so that they could get out of trouble under the protection of the Bumon no toryo in the event of military attack.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドで二文にわかれていますが、セミコロンで一文になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>即ち、地方武士の多くは自己保存のために利害を共有できる権威・権力者と複数の主従関係を持つことで、独立と自己保存、そして勢力拡大の機会を獲得していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, many of local samurai managed to secure their independence, their survival and the opportunity to expand their territory by establishing multiple relations with powerful/influential persons who shared a mutual interest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, many local samurai managed to secure independence, survival and opportunities to expand their territory by establishing multiple relationships with powerful and influential individuals who shared mutual interests.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, many local samurai managed to secure independence, survival and opportunities to expand their territory by establishing multiple relationships with powerful and influential individuals who shared mutual interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>特に武士間の主従関係においては利害が如実であり、不利な戦況にある武門の棟梁の下から去り、敵対勢力への鞍替えをしたり、背く場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the relation of master and vassals among samurai was highly dependant on interests, vassals sometimes abandoned bumon no toryo if and when he was in the unfavorable war situation and veered around to the opponent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the relationship between master and vassal among samurai was highly dependent on interests, at times vassals would abandon a Bumon no toryo, if and when they came under an unfavorable situation due to a war and changed loyalty to the opponent.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;veered around to the opponent&quot; to &quot;changed loyalty to the opponent&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the relationship between master and vassal among samurai was highly dependent on interests, at times vassals would abandon a Bumon no toryo, if and when they came under an unfavorable situation due to a war and changed loyalty to the opponent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>武士の主従関係とはけして絶対的なものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relation of master and vassals among samurai was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As such, the relationship between master and vassal among samurai was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;As such&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As such, the relationship between master and vassal among samurai was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>初の武家政権となる鎌倉幕府が成立して以降も同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kamakura bakufu was established as the first military government, such situation didn&apos;t chage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation did not change even after the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as the first military government.</e>
<cmt>rearraranged sentence and fixed grammar; added description of bakufu to follow the word list</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation did not change even after the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as the first military government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>室町時代に至ると、武家の主従関係はそれ以前よりは強固とな関係となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, the relation of master and vassals among samurai became stronger compared to former times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it became the Muromachi period, the relationship between master and vassal among samurai became comparably stronger to earlier times.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became the Muromachi period, the relationship between master and vassal among samurai became comparably stronger to earlier times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉時代の守護の系譜をひく武家は室町幕府においても多くが守護として任ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of samurai who were descended from shugo (military governor) in the Kamakura period were appointed shugo also by Muromachi bakufu and they obtained the authority to impose taxes on shoen based on the new system like hanzei (the system under which shugo were allowed to collect half of the taxes from shoen) and shugouke (the contract system under which shoen&apos;s owner entrusted shugo to manage his shoen and pay the customs).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many samurai descendants of a Shugo (military governor) during the Kamakura period were appointed to the position again by the Muromachi bakufu. They obtained the authority to impose taxes on shoen based on new systems like hanzei (a system under which Shugo were allowed to collect half of the taxes from shoen) and shugouke (the contract system under which the owner of a shoen entrusted a Shugo to manage their shoen and pay customs).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many samurai descendants of a Shugo (military governor) during the Kamakura period were appointed to the position again by the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それまでにない半済や守護請の権限を獲得し荘園への収税権をかけることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They obtained the authority to impose taxes on shoen based on new systems like hanzei (a system under which Shugo were allowed to collect half of the taxes from shoen) and shugouke (the contract system under which the owner of a shoen entrusted a Shugo to manage their shoen and pay customs).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同時に、任国の旧地頭層の系譜をひく国人領主を被官として従属させ、院宮王臣家や寺社の荘園にも守護請など一定の収税権を獲得するなど、強い勢力基盤を形成するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, they made kokujin ryoshu (local samurai), who were descended from jito (military land steward), their subprdinates, acquired the authority of collecting taxes from shoen owned by engu oshinke and temples/shrines and strengthened their power base.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, they made the descendents of a Jito (military land steward) called Kokujin ryoshu (local samurai) their subordinates, acquired the authority to collect taxes from shoen owned by Engu oshinke, temples and shrines, and strengthened their power base.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Kokujin&quot; &quot;Jito&quot; and &quot;Engu&quot;; subprdinates→subordinates; rearranged sentence to read more naturally; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, they made the descendents of a Jito (military land steward) called Kokujin ryoshu (local samurai) their subordinates, acquired the authority to collect taxes from shoen owned by Ingu oshinke, temples and shrines, and strengthened their power base.</e>
<cmt>Engu oshinke→Ingu oshinkeに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>国人領主も幕府の奉公衆の地位を得て守護の干渉を防いだり逆に牽制することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of kokujin ryoshu protected themselves from shugo&apos;s intervention or checked the movement of shugo by obtaining the status of bakufu&apos; hokoshu (military post of bakufu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A number of Kokujin ryoshu protected themselves from intervention by a Shugo or checked the movements of Shugo by obtaining the status of bakufu hokoshu (a military post of the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;some&quot; to &quot;a number&quot;; capitalized &quot;Kokujin&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A number of Kokujin ryoshu protected themselves from intervention by a Shugo or checked the movements of Shugo by obtaining the status of bakufu hokoshu (a military post of the bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>逆に守護の被官として貢献度を高め守護代の地位を勝ち得たり、幕府や守護を通じて官位を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They obtained the position of shugodai (deputy of shugo) or other official positions by serving for shugo or through shugo or bakufu and protected themselves from outside enemy or justified their ruling authority based on such positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conversely, some obtained the position of Shugodai (deputy of Shugo), or other official positions by serving the Shugo, through the Shugo or the bakufu. In this case, they protected themselves from outside enemies or justified their ruling authority based on their positions.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Shugodai&quot;; split sentence into two for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more naturally; capitalized &quot;Shugo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conversely, some obtained the position of Shugodai (deputy of Shugo), or other official positions by serving the Shugo, through the Shugo or the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その威光を背景に対外勢力の侵略を防いだり、自らの支配権の正当化が図られたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, they protected themselves from outside enemies or justified their ruling authority based on their positions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>一方でそれら守護や国人の支配権は無条件に強固になったわけではなく、被官が他の守護に寝返ったり、他の国人と一揆を結んで守護の干渉を防ぐこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, strengthening of ruling power of shugo or kokujin was not necessarily achieved smoothly since their vassals often went over to other shugo or rebelled against shugo in alliance with other kokujin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, strengthening the ruling power of a Shugo or Kokujin was not necessarily accomplished smoothly, due to vassals often changing loyalty to other Shugo or rebelled against a Shugo in an alliance with another Kokujin.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;However&quot; to &quot;On the other hand&quot;; capitalized &quot;Kokujin&quot; and &quot;Shugo&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, strengthening the ruling power of a Shugo or Kokujin was not necessarily accomplished smoothly, due to vassals often changing loyalty to other Shugo or rebelled against a Shugo in an alliance with another Kokujin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>荘園に対する収税についても守護使不入を勝ち得た荘園には介入の余地がなく、非合法で横領する他はこれらを支配下に組み入れることは困難であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning tax collection, they couldn&apos;t collect tax from shoen which obtained the right of shugoshi funyu (right to reject shugo&apos;s entrance) and they had no way to collect other than embezzling illegally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of tax collection as well, taxes could not be collected from Shoen after they obtained the right of Shugoshi funyu (a right to reject the entrance of a Shugo) and they had no way to collect money without embezzling illegally.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of tax collection as well, taxes could not be collected from Shoen after they obtained the right of Shugoshi funyu (a right to reject the entrance of a Shugo) and they had no way to collect money without embezzling illegally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>国人領主も同様であり一門や庶家、配下の土豪層とは主君と家来というよりは緩やかな同盟関係に近く、国人領主の存在は主君というより盟主に近かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of kokujin ryoshu, their relation with sept, branch families or dogo under their rule was similar to an alliance, rather than the relation of master and vassals, and kokujin ryoshu were similar to leaders, rather than masters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Kokujin ryoshu, their relationship with clan members, branch families and Dogo under their rule was similar to an alliance, rather than a relationship of master and vassal. In this sense, Kokujin ryoshu were more akin to leaders rather than masters.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;sept&quot; to &quot;clan members&quot; since it is not a word, so far as I know (I noticed it is the first word that shows up on eijiro…); fixed grammar; split into two sentences for easier reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Kokujin ryoshu, their relationship with clan members, branch families and Dogo under their rule was similar to an alliance, rather than a relationship of master and vassal; in this sense, Kokujin ryoshu were more akin to leaders rather than masters.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドで二文に分かれていますが、セミコロンでつなぎました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>故に国人が配下の庶家や土豪の意向を無視することはできなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, kokujin couldn&apos;t neglect the intention of their branch families or dogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokujin were therefore unable to neglect the intentions of their branch families and Dogo.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokujin were therefore unable to neglect the intentions of their branch families and Dogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ややもすれば、国人の配下が幕府や守護に願い出て国人として自立を図ることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, subordinates of kokujin became independent as kokujin by appealing bakufu or shugo and when conflict of interests occurred, some branch families rebelled against kokujin in public and fought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, subordinates of Kokujin became independent Kokujin by appealing to the bakufu or the Shugo. When conflict of interests occurred, some branch families went so far as to publicly rebel against the Kokujin and engage in battle.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; capitalized &quot;Kokujin&quot; and &quot;Shugo&quot;; changed translation a bit at the end to encompass the strong meaning of &quot;ことすらあった&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, subordinates of Kokujin became independent Kokujin by appealing to the bakufu or the Shugo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、利害をたがえた場合、庶家が国人に公然と反逆し合戦に及ぶことすらあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When conflict of interests occurred, some branch families went so far as to publicly rebel against the Kokujin and engage in battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>即ち、中世以前の武家の主従関係は利害を共有することにより成立し、けして絶対的なものではなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As explained above, the relation of master and vassals among samurai until the medieval period was only based on the common interests and was not absolute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown above, the relationship of master and vassal among samurai until the medieval period was based only on the common interests of both parties and was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown above, the relationship of master and vassal among samurai until the medieval period was based only on the common interests of both parties and was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>戦国大名と家臣団</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengoku daimyo (warring lords) and Kashindan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)) and Kashindan</e>
<cmt>fixed Sengoku daimyo description to match the word list; added description for Sengoku Period;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period (period of Warring States)) and Kashindan</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>戦国時代以降も、主従関係において利害の共有が重要であることに違いはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The importance of common interests for the relation of master and vassals didn&apos;t change in the period of Warring States.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The importance of common interests in a relationship of master and vassal did not change in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;period of Warring States&quot; to &quot;Sengoku Period&quot; since a description is provided above; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The importance of common interests in a relationship of master and vassal did not change in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>むしろ、下克上やより利害を違えた場合、鞍替えすることが当然視されるに及んでより顕著となったといってよい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rather, it became more apparent since gekokujo (the revolt of vassals against their lords) or changing a master in the event of serious interests conflict came to be seen as a matter of course.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather, it was even more apparent when vassals began changing masters in the event of a serious conflict of interest and Gekokujo (a revolt of vassals against their lords) became a matter of course.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Gekokujo&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather, it was even more apparent when vassals began changing masters in the event of a serious conflict of interest and Gekokujo (a revolt of vassals against their lords) became a matter of course.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>但し、室町時代以前の守護大名や守護代、国人領主と戦国大名の大きな違いは強固な家臣団を形成し得たかどうかにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the big difference between shugo daimyo (military governor), shugodai or kokujin ryoshu in the Muromachi Period and sengoku daimyo lied in whether or not they could organize strong Kashindan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The big difference between the Sengoku daimyo and the Shugo daimyo (military governors), Shugodai and Kokujin ryoshu from the Muromachi period, however, was in whether or not they could organize strong Kashindan.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The big difference between the Sengoku daimyo and the Shugo daimyo (military governors), Shugodai and Kokujin ryoshu from the Muromachi period, however, was in whether or not they could organize strong Kashindan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>大名の家臣団にとって、中世以前と大きく異なるのが、有能な家臣の登用である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike shugo daimyo etc. in the medieval period, sengoku daimyo actively appointed capable vassals to important positions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike their counterparts in the medieval period, Sengoku daimyo actively appointed capable vassals to important positions.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;shugo daimyo etc&quot; to &quot;counterparts&quot;; capitalized &quot;Sengoku&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike their counterparts in the medieval period, Sengoku daimyo actively appointed capable vassals to important positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>一門や庶家、縁戚、或いは有力国人や土豪を系譜に持つ有力家臣が大名家の内政を左右することは珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, sept, branch families, relatives, powerful kokujin and/or vassals who were descended from dogo generally presided over the politics of daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally presiding over the politics of a daimyo family were clan members, branch families, relatives, powerful Kokujin and vassals who were descendants of the Dogo (local clan).</e>
<cmt>added description for &quot;dogo&quot;; rearranged sentence to read more naturally; changed &quot;sept&quot; to &quot;clan members&quot; since &quot;sept&quot; is not a word, so far as I know</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally presiding over the politics of a daimyo family were clan members, branch families, relatives, powerful Kokujin and vassals who were descendants of the Dogo.</e>
<cmt>Dogo→既出のため補足削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>尾張国の戦国大名織田信長が、農民の子から足軽になった羽柴秀吉（豊臣秀吉）を家臣に登用したように、実力次第では出世が可能になるのも、戦国大名の家臣団において見られたひとつの傾向であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, one of characteristics of sengoku daimyo&apos;s Kashindan was a promotion based on person&apos;s ability as seen in the case of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), who was born to peasant&apos;s family, became ashigaru (common foot soldier) and was promoted to a vassal by Nobunaga ODA, sengoku daimyo in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the Kashindan under a Sengoku daimyo, however, there was a trend to give promotions based on abilities. This was seen in the case of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) who had been born from a peasant family, became an ashigaru (common foot soldier) and was promoted to a vassal by Nobunaga ODA, a Sengoku daimyo in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the Kashindan under a Sengoku daimyo, however, there was a trend to give promotions based on abilities; this was seen in the case of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) who had been born from a peasant family, became an ashigaru (common foot soldier) and was promoted to a vassal by Nobunaga ODA, a Sengoku daimyo in Owari Province.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドで二文に分かれていますが、セミコロンでつなぎました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>一方で血縁と伝統的な主従関係の下に成立した譜代の家臣と実力を買われ登用された新参の軋轢も生まれることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, conflicts were also seen between hereditary vassals who were based on bloodline or traditional master-vassals relation and persons who were newly appointed thanks to their ability.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there were also conflicts between hereditary vassals, who held their status based on bloodline or traditional master-vassal relationships, and individuals who were newly appointed due to their abilities.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there were also conflicts between hereditary vassals, who held their status based on bloodline or traditional master-vassal relationships, and individuals who were newly appointed due to their abilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>また、戦国時代も後期に至ると、有力な大名はそれまでの半独立的な地位と状況によっては命令を拒むことができた被官層を完全に従属させ家臣とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Warring States period, powerful sengoku daimyo brought their vassals, who had been independent to a certain degree and were able to refuse orders depending on circumstances up to then, into complete subordination.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Sengoku Period, powerful Sengoku daimyo brought their vassals into complete subordination, whereas before they had been independent to a certain degree and were able to refuse orders depending on the circumstances.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Warring States period&quot; to &quot;Sengoku Period&quot; to match the word list; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Sengoku period, powerful Sengoku daimyo brought their vassals into complete subordination, whereas before they had been independent to a certain degree and were able to refuse orders depending on the circumstances.</e>
<cmt>Periodの頭文字を小文字に変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そして、城下町を形成して屋敷を与え、家臣または家臣とその妻子を住まわせることで背信を防いだり、次第に武士の土着化を防ぐようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, they constructed castle towns, gave residences and got vassals and their family to reside there so that they could prevent vassals&apos; revolt and indigenization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengoku daimyo constructed castle towns, giving residences to their vassals and families inside the towns in order to prevent revolts and indigenization.</e>
<cmt>I&apos;m not sure &quot;indigenization&quot; is a word, but since it works so well here, I can understand it and can&apos;t find a better word to use, I left it alone; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengoku daimyo constructed castle towns, giving residences to their vassals and families inside the towns in order to prevent revolts and indigenization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>豊臣秀吉が関白となって以降は兵農分離が進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI became kanpaku (A chief adviser to the Emperor), heinobunri (separation of warrior class from the soil of its territory) policy was implemented and as a result, vassals who had been engaged in agriculture in their territories in times of peace became full-time bureaucrats or warriors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI became a Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), a policy called heinobunri (separation of warrior class from the soil of its territory) was implemented. As a result of the policy, vassals who had been engaged in agriculture in their territories in times of peace became full-time bureaucrats or warriors.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Kanpaku&quot;; split into two sentences for easier reading and fixed grammar accordingly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI became a Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), a policy called heinobunri (separation of warrior class from the soil of its territory) was implemented.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>その結果、平時は知行地で農業にも携わった家臣を完全なる文吏または武人として専業化させるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the policy, vassals who had been engaged in agriculture in their territories in times of peace became full-time bureaucrats or warriors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>大名と家臣の関係も必要に応じ登城し務めを果たす関係から常に登城し務めを果たす専従の関係へと発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the relation between daimyo and vassals developed into the one under which vassals, who had come to castle and worked only when necessary, were required to come to castle and work everyday.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This caused a change in the relationship between vassals and daimyo. Whereas vassals formerly went to the castle to work when necessary, under the new policy they were required to work in the castle every day.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences and fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This caused a change in the relationship between vassals and daimyo; whereas vassals formerly went to the castle to work when necessary, under the new policy they were required to work in the castle every day.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドで二文に分かれていますが、セミコロンでつなぎました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>江戸時代以降となると、将軍の絶対的な権力の下で直臣たる近世大名と陪臣である家臣団の関係はより絶対的な主従関係となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period when shogun held absolute authority, the relation between kinsei (early modern) daimyo, who were jikishin (great vassal), and their Kashindan, who were baishin (indirect vassal), became much more absolute.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period when the Shogun held absolute authority, relations between Kinsei daimyo (early modern lords), who were Jikishin (great vassals), and their Kashindan, who were Baishin (indirect vassals), became a categorical master-subordinate relationship.</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Shogun&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally; used &quot;master-subordinate relationship for &quot;主従関係&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period when the Shogun held absolute authority, relations between Kinsei daimyo (early modern lords), who were Jikishin (great vassals), and their Kashindan, who were Baishin (indirect vassals), became a categorical master-subordinate relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>家臣に領地を与え、または本領安堵をし土地支配権を認める知行制に替えて、武士の給与を俸禄制とし、大名の土地支配権を大名が一括して担う傾向が強くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo adopted horoku (salary) system in place of chigyo system (the system under which vassals were give the land or entitled to the right to rule the land) and monopolized the right to rule the land.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo adopted a horoku (salary) system in place of the chigyo system (a system under which vassals were entitled and given the right to rule the land) and monopolized the right to rule the land.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo adopted a horoku (salary) system in place of the chigyo system (a system under which vassals were entitled and given the right to rule the land) and monopolized the right to rule the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その中で次第に家臣団が支配下の領主群から、大名家の奉公集団への性格を強めることになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the nature of Kashindan changed from a group of ryoshu to a group of employees serving for daimyo family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under these circumstances, the nature of Kashindan changed from a group of ryoshu (feudal lords) to a group of employees serving a daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;such&quot; to &quot;these&quot;; added explanation for &quot;ryoshu&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under these circumstances, the nature of Kashindan changed from a group of ryoshu (feudal lords) to a group of employees serving a daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>平穏な時代の訪れとともに武断的な家臣よりは文治的な家臣が重用されるようになったことに加え、安土桃山時代になされた兵農分離に加え江戸時代に俸禄制が主流になったことで武士の吏僚化が益々進んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the arrival of peaceful time, samurai increasingly became buraucratic not only because of the fact that vassals excelled in governance were given important positions instead of those excelled in military affairs but also because of heinobunri policy implemented in the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the adoption of horoku system in the Edo period</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it became a peaceful period, samurai became increasingly bureaucratic, not only due to vassals being given important positions when they excelled in governance instead of in military affairs, but because of the heinobunri policy implemented in the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the adoption of the horoku system in the Edo period as well.</e>
<cmt>buraucratic→bureaucratic; changed &quot;With the arrival of peaceful time&quot; to &quot;As it became a peaceful period&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became a peaceful period, samurai became increasingly bureaucratic, not only due to vassals being given important positions when they excelled in governance instead of in military affairs, but because of the heinobunri policy implemented in the Azuchi-Momoyama period and the adoption of the horoku system in the Edo period as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その結果、領主としての武士は官僚・役人としての武士としての性格を強めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the nature of samurai changed from ryoshu to bureaucrats/officials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted in the nature of samurai changing from ryoshu to bureaucrats and officials.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted in the nature of samurai changing from ryoshu to bureaucrats and officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fryed-peach(id:63402), Mobnoboka(id:35218), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>