<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正保郷帳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoho-gocho</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoho-gocho (Statistical Book of the Shoho Era)</e>
<cmt>指示通りタイトルに補足説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoho-gocho (Statistical Book of the Shoho Era)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正保郷帳（しょうほうごうちょう）は、日本の江戸幕府が諸大名に命じて令制国単位で作らせた郷帳で、村の名と村高（村の生産力）をまとめた統計書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoho-gocho is gocho which the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) ordered daimyo (feudal lords) to prepare per ryoseikoku (province), and statistics which put together the names and muradaka (total yields) of villages.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoho-gocho is a statistical book which the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) ordered daimyo (feudal lords) to prepare by ryoseikoku (province), putting together the names and muradaka (total yields) of villages.</e>
<cmt>・gochoでは意味が通じないため修正しました。・～単位はperではなくbyが適切と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoho-gocho is a statistical book which the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) ordered daimyo (feudal lords) to prepare by ryoseikoku (province), putting together the names and muradaka (total yields) of villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1644年に作成が命じられ、それから数年がかりで国ごとに提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu ordered preparation of gocho in 1644, and it took several years for daimyo to submit gocho for each province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu ordered preparation of gocho in 1644, and it took several years for daimyo to submit gocho for each province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu ordered preparation of gocho in 1644, and it took several years for daimyo to submit gocho for each province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>このときには国絵図（正保国絵図）、城絵図（正保城絵図）、城模型、街道の帳簿もあわせて作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time domain maps (Shoho-kuniezu), pictorial maps of the castle (Shoho-shiroezu), a model of the castle and an account book of kaido (roads) were prepared along with gocho.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, domain maps (Shoho-kuniezu), pictorial maps of the castle (Shoho-shiroezu), a model of the castle and an account book of kaido (roads) were prepared along with gocho.</e>
<cmt>文頭の句の後には一般的にコンマを入れた方が読みやすいので入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, domain maps (Shoho-kuniezu), pictorial maps of the castle (Shoho-shiroezu), a model of the castle and an account book of kaido (roads) were prepared along with gocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>作成の過程と目的</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process and purpose of preparation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Process and purpose of preparation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Process and purpose of preparation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>正保元年（1644年）12月2日に、征夷大将軍徳川家光が郷帳の作成と提出を大名に命じるよう大目付井上政重と宮城和甫に指示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 2, 1644, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Iemitsu TOKUGAWA instructed Ometsuke Masashige INOUE and Masayoshi MIYAGI to order daimyo to prepare and submit gocho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 30, 1644, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Iemitsu TOKUGAWA instructed Ometsuke Masashige INOUE and Masayoshi MIYAGI to order daimyo to prepare and submit gocho.</e>
<cmt>・旧暦のままでしたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 30, 1644, Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Iemitsu TOKUGAWA instructed Ometsuke Masashige INOUE and Masayoshi MIYAGI to order daimyo to prepare and submit gocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>16日から井上と宮城が諸大名の留守居を呼び出して来年中の提出を命じ、また幕府の代官にも同様の指示を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 16 INOUE and MIYAGI started to summon rusui (caretaker or keeper (official post in the Edo era)) of daimyo and order them to submit gocho within that year, in addition to giving the same instructions to daikan (local governor) of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 13, 1645, Inoue and Miyagi started to summon rusui (caretaker or keeper [official post in the Edo era]) of daimyo and order them to submit gocho within that year and gave the same instructions to daikan (local governor) of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>・旧暦のままでしたので修正しました。・井上と宮城は名字だけですので頭文字だけ大文字の表記にしました。・丸括弧の中の括弧は統一事項どおり[]に変えました。・in addition toはここでは不明瞭なので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 13, 1645, Inoue and Miyagi started to summon rusui (caretaker or keeper [official post in the Edo era]) of daimyo and order them to submit gocho within that year and gave the same instructions to daikan (local governor) of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このとき提出を命じられたのは、郷帳のほかに、国絵図、城絵図、海陸の道筋と古城を書いた道之帳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time submission of domain maps, pictorial maps of the castle and michi-no-cho in which land and sea routes and old castles were illustrated, as well as of gocho, was required.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, the documents required to be submitted were domain maps, pictorial maps of the castle and michi-no-cho, in which land and sea routes and old castles were illustrated, as well as gocho.</e>
<cmt>・「このとき」は統一用語のon this occasionが適切と思われます。・主語と動詞が離れすぎているので、表現を変えました。・michi-no-choの後は補足説明であり、非制限用法が適切なためコンマを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, the documents required to be submitted were domain maps, pictorial maps of the castle and michi-no-cho, in which land and sea routes and old castles were illustrated, as well as gocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>東海道筋の城持ち大名は、さらに城の木製模型を作って提出するよう求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo who had a castle along Tokaido were ordered to submit a wooden model of their castle as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo who had a castle along Tokai-do Road were ordered to submit a wooden model of their castle as well.</e>
<cmt>Tokaidoだけでは何のことかわからないため、Roadの付いた訳語に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo who had a castle along Tokai-do Road were ordered to submit a wooden model of their castle as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>多くの国では提出まで数年かかり、正保年間（1644年 - 1648年）より後にずれこむものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It took several years for many provinces to submit gocho, and some gocho were submitted as late as during the Shoho era (1644 to 1648).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It took several years for many provinces to submit gocho, and some gocho were submitted as late as during the Shoho era (1644 to 1648) or later.</e>
<cmt>「～より後」とあるので、or laterを付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It took several years for many provinces to submit gocho, and some gocho were submitted as late as during the Shoho era (1644 to 1648) or later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>郷帳は村単位の高を記すものだが、正保郷帳作成にあたり幕府は総計を各大名の表高に一致させるよう指示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gocho generally recorded total yields of each village, but the bakufu instructed to make the total sum equal to omote-daka (face value of kokudaka assessed by the feudal government) of each daimyo in preparing Shoho-gocho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gocho generally recorded total yields of each village, but the bakufu instructed to make the total sum equal to omote-daka of each daimyo in preparing Shoho-gocho.</e>
<cmt>表高は直後に説明文があるので、ここでの説明は省きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gocho generally recorded total yields of each village, but the bakufu instructed to make the total sum equal to omote-daka of each daimyo in preparing Shoho-gocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>表高は大名が領地を与えられたときに記された石高で、実際の石高とは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omote-daka was kokudaka (crop yield) specified at the time of grant of territory, and it was different from actual crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omote-daka was kokudaka (crop yield) specified at the time of grant of territory, and it was different from actual crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omote-daka was kokudaka (crop yield) specified at the time of grant of territory, and it was different from actual crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>大名の実際の生産力を把握することよりも、表高で測られる大名の序列や格式の変更を嫌ったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu tried to avoid changes in the rank order and social status of daimyo represented by kokudaka, rather than comprehending the actual state of production of daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu tried to avoid changes in the rank order and social status of daimyo represented by kokudaka, rather than to comprehend the actual state of production of daimyo.</e>
<cmt>rather than以降がto avoidと並列関係になっていないため、to comprehendとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu tried to avoid changes in the rank order and social status of daimyo represented by kokudaka, rather than to comprehend the actual state of production of daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>作成単位は原則として国だが、蝦夷地、琉球、小豆島がそれぞれ一単位となり、陸奥国は7つに分割された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle gocho were prepared per province, but they were prepared for each of Ezochi (inhabited area of Ainu), Ryukyu and Shodo-shima Islands, and Mutsu Province was divided into seven parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, gocho were prepared per province, but Ezochi (inhabited area of Ainu), Ryukyu and Shodo-shima Island were each treated as one province, and Mutsu Province was divided into seven parts.</e>
<cmt>・文頭の前置詞句の後には一般的にコンマが使われるため挿入しました。・小豆島は慣例的に1つの島として扱われるのでIslandとしました。・「蝦夷地～一単位となり」の部分は意味がずれていますので、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, gocho were prepared per province, but Ezochi (inhabited area of Ainu), Ryukyu and Shodo-shima Island were each treated as one province, and Mutsu Province was divided into seven parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>複数の大名がある国では、有力大名がとりまとめ役にされたり、複数大名が分担協同したりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In provinces governed by several daimyo, the leading daimyo was ordered to orchestrate preparation or several daimyo shared the task.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In provinces governed by several daimyo, the leading daimyo was ordered to orchestrate preparation, or several daimyo shared the task.</e>
<cmt>2つの主文が並んでいますのでコンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In provinces governed by several daimyo, the leading daimyo was ordered to orchestrate preparation, or several daimyo shared the task.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>現在の資料状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present situation of materials</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The present situation of materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The present situation of materials</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>幕府が保管していたものは大半失われたが、作成にあたった大名家に残ったものが国単位で残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the gocho stored by the bakufu were lost, but gocho which were left in the house of daimyo who had prepared them remain in some provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the gocho stored by the bakufu were lost, but gocho which were left in the house of daimyo who had prepared them remain in some provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the gocho stored by the bakufu were lost, but gocho which were left in the house of daimyo who had prepared them remain in some provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>各地方で県史、市町村史が資料として採録したり、図書館や研究団体が資料として出版しているので、地元の分だけを閲覧するのは比較的容易である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gocho which remain locally are relatively easy to see, because they are contained in the history book of the prefecture or of the municipalities, or published as materials by libraries and research groups in various areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gocho which remain locally are relatively easy to see, because they are contained in the history book of the prefecture or of the municipalities, or published as materials by libraries and research groups in various areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gocho which remain locally are relatively easy to see, because they are contained in the history book of the prefecture or of the municipalities, or published as materials by libraries and research groups in various areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BitBucket(id:30999), Kinori(id:443), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>