<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>両統迭立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto Tetsuritsu</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>両統迭立（りょうとうてつりつ）とは、一国の君主の家系が2つに分裂し、それぞれの家系から交互に国王を即位させている状態をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryototetsuritsu&quot; refers to the situation where the family line of a country&apos;s monarchy is split into two and the monarch is alternately selected from these two family lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryototetsuritsu&quot; refers to the situation where the family line of a country&apos;s monarchy is split into two and the monarch is alternately selected from these two family lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryoto tetsuritsu&quot; refers to the situation where the family line of a country&apos;s monarchy is split into two and the monarch is alternately selected from these two family lines.</e>
<cmt>“を&quot;に訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では、鎌倉時代に天皇家（当時の呼称では「王家」）が2つの家系に分裂し、治天と天皇の継承が両統迭立の状態にあったことが最も著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Royal Family (at that time called &quot;Oke&quot;) during the Kamakura Period was split into two family lines and was best known to be in the state of Ryototetsuritsu regarding the succession of Chiten (retired emperor who runs the cloistered government) and Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Royal Family (at that time called &quot;Oke&quot;) during the Kamakura Period was split into two family lines and was best known to be in the state of Ryototetsuritsu regarding the succession of Chiten (retired emperor who runs the cloistered government) and Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial family (at that time called &apos;Oke&apos;) during the Kamakura period was split into two family lines and was best known to be in the state of Ryoto tetsuritsu regarding the succession of Chiten (retired emperor who runs the cloistered government) and Emperor.</e>
<cmt>“を&apos;に訂正しました。Royal Family→Imperial family に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>鎌倉時代の両統迭立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu during the Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu during the Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu during the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>スペース補足period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この時代の両統迭立は、後嵯峨天皇の第3皇子後深草天皇の子孫である持明院統と、第4皇子亀山天皇の子孫である大覚寺統とのあいだで行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ryototetsuritsu in this ｐeriod was between the Jimyo-in line, descendants of Emperor Go-Saga&apos;s third son, Emperor Go-Fukasa, and the Daikaku-ji line, descendants of fourth son Emperor Kameyama</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ryototetsuritsu in this ｐeriod was between the Jimyo-in line, descendants of Emperor Go-Saga&apos;s third son, Emperor Go-Fukasa, and the Daikaku-ji line, descendants of fourth son Emperor Kameyama</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ryoto tetsuritsu in this period was between the Jimyoin line, descendants of Emperor Gosaga&apos;s third son, Emperor Gofukakusa, and the Daikakuji line, descendants of fourth son Emperor Kameyama.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足period半角にしました。ハイフン削除。名前の表記訂正。ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>端緒</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>仁治3年（1242年）に即位した後嵯峨は、寛元4年（1246年）に皇太子久仁（後深草、4歳）に譲位して院政を開始したあと、後深草に皇子が生まれるのを待たず、正嘉2年（1258年）に後深草（16歳）の同母弟恒仁（亀山、10歳）を皇太子とし、さらに翌正元 (日本)元年（1259年）には後深草から恒仁に譲位させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1242, Go-Saga became Emperor, abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Hisahito (Go-Fukasa, aged 4) and started a cloister government in 1246, and then in 1258, without waiting for Go-Fukasa to have a prince, installed Go-Fukasa (aged 16)&apos;s younger half brother, Tsunehito (Kameyama, aged 10), as Crown Prince and in 1259, he made Go-Fukasa abdicate so Tsunehito could become Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1242, Go-Saga became Emperor, abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Hisahito (Go-Fukasa, aged 4) and started a cloister government in 1246, and then in 1258, without waiting for Go-Fukasa to have a prince, installed Go-Fukasa (aged 16)&apos;s younger half brother, Tsunehito (Kameyama, aged 10), as Crown Prince and in 1259, he made Go-Fukasa abdicate so Tsunehito could become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1242, Gosaga became Emperor, abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Hisahito (Gofukakusa, aged 4) and started a cloister government in 1246, and then in 1258, without waiting for Gofukakusa to have a prince, installed Gofukakusa (aged 16)&apos;s younger half brother, Tsunehito (Kameyama, aged 10), as Crown Prince and in 1259, he made Gofukakusa abdicate so Tsunehito could become Emperor.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後深草にはその後皇子が生まれたが、文永5年（1268年）、後嵯峨は、後深草の嫡男（第2皇子）煕仁（4歳）をさしおいて亀山の嫡男（第2皇子）世仁（2歳）を皇太子とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Fukasa later had sons, and in 1268, Go-Saga installed Kameyama&apos;s heir (second prince) Yohito (aged 2) as Crown Prince instead of Go-Fukasa&apos;s heir (second son) Hirohito (aged 4).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Fukasa later had sons, and in 1268, Go-Saga installed Kameyama&apos;s heir (second prince) Yohito (aged 2) as Crown Prince instead of Go-Fukasa&apos;s heir (second son) Hirohito (aged 4).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gofukakusa later had sons, and in 1268, Gosaga installed Kameyama&apos;s heir (second prince) Yohito (aged 2) as Crown Prince instead of Gofukakusa&apos;s heir (second son) Hirohito (aged 4).</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>この一連の措置から、後嵯峨が亀山を自らの後継者としその子孫に皇統を伝える意図を持っていたことは容易に推測できるが、後嵯峨はその意図を明確にせずに文永9年（1272年）に死去した（53歳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this string of actions, it is easy to presume that Go-Saga wanted Kameyama and his descendants as his successors, but Go-Saga died in 1272 without clarifying his wishes (aged 53).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this string of actions, it is easy to presume that Go-Saga wanted Kameyama and his descendants as his successors, but Go-Saga died in 1272 without clarifying his wishes (aged 53).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this string of actions, it is easy to presume that Gosaga wanted Kameyama and his descendants as his successors, but Gosaga died in 1272 without clarifying his wishes (aged 53).</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>遺言状も財産の分与をこまごまと定めるのみで後継者を指名する文言はなく、ただ次代の治天の指名は鎌倉幕府の意向に従うようにという遺志だけが示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His will only specified the division of property without naming a successor, only indicating his wish that the naming the next Chiten should follow the wishes of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His will only specified the division of property without naming a successor, only indicating his wish that the naming the next Chiten should follow the wishes of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His will only specified the division of property without naming a successor, only indicating his wish that the naming the next Chiten should follow the wishes of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後深草と亀山はそれぞれ次代の治天となることを望んで争い、裁定は幕府に持ち込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since both Go-Fukasa and Kameyama wanted to be the next Chiten and a fight broke out, the bakufu was asked to make a ruling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since both Go-Fukasa and Kameyama wanted to be the next Chiten and a fight broke out, the bakufu was asked to make a ruling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since both Gofukakusa and Kameyama wanted to be the next Chiten and a fight broke out, the bakufu was asked to make a ruling.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕府は、後嵯峨の正妻であり後深草と亀山の生母でもある大宮院に故人の真意がどちらにあったかを照会し、大宮院が亀山の名を挙げたことから亀山を治天に指名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu asked Omiya-in, who was the first wife and biological mother of Go-Fukasa and Kameyama, which of the sons was the deceased choice and Omiya-in gave Kameyama&apos;s name, who was subsequently named as Chiten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu asked Omiya-in, who was the first wife and biological mother of Go-Fukasa and Kameyama, which of the sons was the deceased choice and Omiya-in gave Kameyama&apos;s name, who was subsequently named as Chiten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu asked Omiyain, who was the first wife and biological mother of Gofukakusa and Kameyama, which of the sons was the deceased choice and Omiyain gave Kameyama&apos;s name, who was subsequently named as Chiten.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後嵯峨がこのような曖昧な態度をとったのは、自身が幕府の介入によって傍系から予想外の即位をした経験を踏まえ、後継者を指名しても幕府の意にかなわなければ簡単に覆されてしまうことをよく知っていたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why Go-saga took such an unclear stance was based on his own experience as being unexpectedly selected from a collateral family line to ascend to Emperor due to the bakufu&apos;s intervention, and knew well that if he named a successor that was not to the bakufu&apos;s liking, it would easily have been changed by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason why Go-saga took such an unclear stance was based on his own experience as being unexpectedly selected from a collateral family line to ascend to Emperor due to the bakufu&apos;s intervention, and knew well that if he named a successor that was not to the bakufu&apos;s liking, it would easily have been changed by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason why Gosaga took such an unclear stance was based on his own experience as being unexpectedly selected from a collateral family line to ascend to Emperor due to the bakufu&apos;s intervention, and knew well that if he named a successor that was not to the bakufu&apos;s liking, it would easily have been changed by the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>亀山はしばらく在位のまま政務を執り、文永11年（1274年）には皇太子世仁（8歳、後宇多天皇）に譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameyama attended to government affairs for a short period as Emperor and then abdicated the throne in 1274 to Crown Prince Yohito (aged 8, Emperor Go-Uta).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameyama attended to government affairs for a short period as Emperor and then abdicated the throne in 1274 to Crown Prince Yohito (aged 8, Emperor Go-Uta).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameyama attended to government affairs for a short period as Emperor and then abdicated the throne in 1274 to Crown Prince Yohito (aged 8, Emperor Gouda).</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>一方、兄でありながら治天の地位を逃した後深草は不満を募らせ、後宇多が即位すると抗議のため太上天皇の待遇を辞退して出家しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Go-Fukasa, who lost the position of Chiten even though he was the older brother, became frustrated and when Go-Uta became Emperor, he declined the position of Daijo-Tenno and tried to become a priest as a sign of protest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Go-Fukasa, who lost the position of Chiten, even though he was the older brother, became frustrated and when Go-Uta became Emperor, he declined the position of Daijo-Tenno and tried to become a priest as a sign of protest.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Gofukakusa, who lost the position of Chiten, even though he was the older brother, became frustrated and when Gouda became Emperor, he declined the position of Daijo Tenno (the retired emperor) and tried to become a priest as a sign of protest.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。Daijo Tenno (the retired emperor)に訂正補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>後嵯峨は、膨大な王家領荘園群のうち、全国100ヶ所以上の荘園から構成される大荘園群長講堂領を後深草が相続できるようとりはからっていたが、それだけでは後深草の不満は収まらなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amongst the extensive royal private estates, Go-Saga had planned so that Go-Fukasa could inherit the large Chokodo private estates group consisting of over 100 estates around the country, but Go-Fukasa was not satisfied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amongst the extensive royal private estates, Go-Saga had planned so that Go-Fukasa could inherit the large Chokodo group of private estates consisting of over 100 estates around the country, but Go-Fukasa was not satisfied.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst the extensive Imperial private estates, Gosaga had planned so that Gofukakusa could inherit the large Chokodo group of private estates consisting of over 100 estates around the country, but Gofukakusa was not satisfied.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>のちに長講堂領は持明院統の重要な財政基盤となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later the Chokodo estates became an important financial foundation for the Jimyo-in line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later the Chokodo estates became an important financial foundation for the Jimyo-in line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later the Chokodo estates became an important financial foundation for the Jimyoin line.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>亀山も対抗措置としてやはり200ヶ所にのぼる大荘園群八条院領をのちに手に入れ、こちらは大覚寺統の主要な財政基盤となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameyama also inherited the large Hachijo-in private estate group consisting of over 200 estates and this became the main financial foundation for the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameyama also inherited the large Hachijo-in private estate group consisting of over 200 estates and this became the main financial foundation for the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameyama also inherited the large Hachijoin private estate group consisting of over 200 estates and this became the main financial foundation for the Daikakuji line.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>2つの皇統は、こののち、治天・天皇・皇太子の地位だけでなく、女院などの皇族たちが分散して管理する王家領荘園群の熾烈な争奪戦も演じることになり、王家は政治的にだけではなく経済的にも分裂状況に陥ることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two royal lines fought fiercely over not only the positions of Chiten, Emperor and Crown Prince, but also the royal private estates separately managed by nyoin (title given to some high-ranking female royal family member who have been Empress, etc.) and other royal family members, leading to a division within the Royal Family, both financially as well as politically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two royal lines fought fiercely over not only the positions of Chiten, Emperor, and Crown Prince, but also the royal private estates separately managed by nyoin (title given to some high-ranking female royal family member who have been Empress, etc.) and other royal family members, leading to a division within the Royal Family, both financially as well as politically.</e>
<cmt>comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two Imperial lines fought fiercely over not only the positions of Chiten, Emperor, and Crown Prince, but also the Imperial private estates separately managed by nyoin (title given to some high-ranking female Imperial family member who have been Empress, etc.) and other Imperial family members, leading to a division within the Imperial family, both financially as well as politically.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後深草の不満を受けて幕府が介入し、建治元年（1275年）に煕仁（11歳）を皇太子に指名、将来、後深草が治天となることを保証した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to Go-Fukasa&apos;s dissatisfaction, the bakufu intervened and in 1275, named Hirohito (aged 11) as Crown Prince and guaranteed Go-Fukasa would be Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to Go-Fukasa&apos;s dissatisfaction, the bakufu intervened and in 1275, named Hirohito (aged 11) as Crown Prince and guaranteed Go-Fukasa would be Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to Gofukakusa&apos;s dissatisfaction, the bakufu intervened and in 1275, named Hirohito (aged 11) as Crown Prince and guaranteed Gofukakusa would be Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この介入は、執権北条時宗が後深草の立場に同情したためという説明が当時からなされている（『増鏡』）ほか、得宗と治天の交渉を仲介する立場にある関東申次西園寺実兼が亀山父子よりも後深草父子と親しかったため、後深草にとって有利な解決をはかったことも指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the explanation for this intervention that has been given since it happened that the Regent Tokumune HOKUJO sympathized with Go-Fukasa&apos;s situation (&quot;Masukagami&quot;), it has been pointed out that the Kanto Moshitsugi, Sanekane SAIIONJI, who was in the position to mediate between Tokumune and the Chiten, was more intimate with the Go-Fukasa father and son than the Kameyama father and son and could have worked for a more advantageous solution for Go-Fukasa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the explanation for this intervention that has been given since it happened that the Regent Tokumune HOKUJO sympathized with Go-Fukasa&apos;s situation (&quot;Masukagami&quot;), it has been pointed out that the Kanto Moshitsugi, Sanekane SAIIONJI, who was in the position to mediate between Tokumune and the Chiten, was more intimate with the Go-Fukasa father and son than the Kameyama father and son and could have worked for a more advantageous solution for Go-Fukasa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the explanation for this intervention that has been given since it happened that the Regent Tokimune HOJO sympathized with Gofukakusa&apos;s situation (&quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror)), it has been pointed out that the Kanto Moshitsugi, Sanekane SAIONJI, who was in the position to mediate between Tokimune and the Chiten, was more intimate with the Gofukakusa father and son than the Kameyama father and son and could have worked for a more advantageous solution for Gofukakusa.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。Tokimune HOJOに訂正しました。&quot;Masukagami&quot; (The Clear Mirror)に訂正しました。SAIONJIに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この時点ですでに幕府は摂関家が分裂したのと同様に王家をも分裂させる意図を持っていたとも言われる（本郷和人）が、史料がなく真相は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, the regent family had already split within the bakufu, and it is said that there were intentions to split the royal family in the same way (Kazuto HONGO), but there are no historical documents to prove this and the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the regent family had already split within the bakufu, and it is said that there were intentions to split the royal family in the same way (Kazuto HONGO), but there are no historical documents to prove this and the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the regent family had already split within the bakufu, and it is said that there were intentions to split the Imperial family in the same way (Kazuto HONGO), but there are no historical documents to prove this and the truth is unknown.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>鎌倉時代には、公家社会一般で分家を次々に創出させる傾向が見られたことにも留意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also necessary to note that in the Kamakura Period, the Imperial court society in general had a tendency to produce branch families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also necessary to note that in the Kamakura Period, the Imperial court society in general had a tendency to produce branch families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also necessary to note that in the Kamakura period, the Imperial court society in general had a tendency to produce branch families.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>いずれにしても、建治元年の幕府の介入によって、後深草と亀山の両人が等しく皇位を子孫に伝え自らは治天となる資格を有することが確定し、これが以後200年に及ぶ王家分裂の端緒となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, due to the intervention of the bakufu in 1275, it was determined that both Go-Fukasa and Kameyama had equal right to have their descendants as Emperor and both had eligibility to become Chiten themselves, and this was the beginning of the division of the royal family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, due to the intervention of the bakufu in 1275, it was determined that both Go-Fukasa and Kameyama had equal right to have their descendants as Emperor and both had eligibility to become Chiten themselves, and this was the beginning of the division of the royal family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, due to the intervention of the bakufu in 1275, it was determined that both Gofukakusa and Kameyama had equal right to have their descendants as Emperor and both had eligibility to become Chiten themselves, and this was the beginning of the division of the Imperial family which lasted for two hundred years.</e>
<cmt>名前の表記訂正。royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>定着</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>亀山は、朝廷の訴訟処理機構の整備を進め、また公家社会の身分秩序を律する「弘安礼節（弘安書札礼）」を制定するなど、意欲的に政務に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameyama worked extensively to arrange a court management system within the Imperial court, and established &quot;Koanreisetsu (Koan Shosatsurei)&quot; to maintain class order within the Imperial Court society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameyama worked extensively to arrange a court management system within the Imperial court, and established &quot;Koanreisetsu (Koan Shosatsurei)&quot; to maintain class order within the Imperial Court society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameyama worked extensively to arrange a court management system within the Imperial court, and established &quot;Koanreisetsu&quot; (Koan Shosatsurei) to maintain class order within the Imperial Court society.</e>
<cmt>“を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この時期を「弘安の徳政」とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period is called the &quot;Virtuous Government of Koan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This period is called the &quot;Virtuous Government of Koan&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This period is called the &apos;Koan no tokusei&apos; (political reforms in Koan era).</e>
<cmt>“を&apos;に訂正しました。Koan no tokusei (political reforms in Koan era)に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>同じころ幕府でも安達泰盛が主導する徳政が行われており、亀山と泰盛とのあいだには文化交流など個人的なつながりもあることから、公武両徳政には密接な連関があるものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the bakufu had a virtuous government led by Yasumori ADACHI, it is thought that there was a close relationship between virtuous governments in both Imperial and Military courts due to the fact that there were cultural exchange at the individual level between Kameyama and Yasumori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the bakufu had a virtuous government led by Yasumori ADACHI, it is thought that there was a close relationship between virtuous governments in both Imperial and Military courts due to the fact that there were cultural exchanges at the individual level between Kameyama and Yasumori.</e>
<cmt>plural &quot;s&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the bakufu had political reforms led by Yasumori ADACHI, it is thought that there was a close relationship between virtuous governments in both Imperial and Military courts due to the fact that there were cultural exchanges at the individual level between Kameyama and Yasumori.</e>
<cmt>a virtuous government→political reformsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし、弘安8年（1285年）に泰盛とその与党が平頼綱らのクーデタ（霜月騒動）により殺害・追放されて幕府の政策が転換すると、その影響が朝廷にも及び、亀山院政は動揺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1285, Yasumori and his group members were killed/exiled in a coup d&apos;etat by TAIRANO-no-Yoritsuna (Shimotsuki Incident) leading to a change in direction of bakufu measures that affected the Imperial Court, stunning the Kameyama Cloister Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1285, Yasumori and his group members were killed/exiled in a coup d&apos;etat by TAIRANO-no-Yoritsuna (Shimotsuki Incident) leading to a change in direction of bakufu measures that affected the Imperial Court, stunning the Kameyama Cloistered Government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added to Cloister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1285, Yasumori and his group members were killed and exiled in a coup d&apos;etat by TAIRA no Yoritsuna (Shimotsuki Incident) leading to a change in direction of bakufu measures that affected the Imperial Court, stunning the Kameyama Cloistered Government.</e>
<cmt>/をandに訂正しました。TAIRA no Yoritsunaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>このころ後深草も後嵯峨は亀山を後継者に指名してはいない旨を幕府に申し入れるなどの工作を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, Go-Fukusa schemed, lodging a complaint to the bakufu that Go-Saga did not name Kameyama as his heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Go-Fukusa schemed, lodging a complaint to the bakufu that Go-Saga did not name Kameyama as his heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Gofukakusa schemed, lodging a complaint to the bakufu that Gosaga did not name Kameyama as his heir.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>亀山が倒幕を考えている、という噂が立つなどの政情不安のなか、結局、弘安10年（1287年）になって幕府は治天・天皇の交替を要求し、皇太子煕仁（23歳、伏見天皇）が践祚して後深草による院政が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the midst of political unrest, when Kameyama was rumored to be thinking of overthrowing the the Shogunate, the bakufu ordered a change in Chiten and Emperor in 1287, with the Crown Prince Hirohito (aged 23, Emperor Fushimi) ascending the throne and Go-Fukakusa starting a cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the midst of political unrest, when Kameyama was rumored to be thinking of overthrowing the the Shogunate, the bakufu ordered a change in Chiten and Emperor in 1287, with the Crown Prince Hirohito (aged 23, Emperor Fushimi) ascending the throne and Go-Fukakusa starting a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added to Cloister</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the midst of political unrest, when Kameyama was rumored to be thinking of overthrowing the Shogunate, the bakufu ordered a change in Chiten and Emperor in 1287, with the Crown Prince Hirohito (aged 23, Emperor Fushimi) ascending the throne and Gofukakusa starting a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。theの繰り返し削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>正応2年（1289年）にはこれも幕府の指名により伏見の第1皇子胤仁（2歳）が皇太子に立てられ、さらに同年後深草の皇子久明親王が鎌倉殿として幕府に迎えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1289, also by designation of the bakufu, Fushimi&apos;s first son, Tanehito (aged 2) was installed as Crown Prince and during the same year, Go-Fukasa&apos;s son Hisaaki Shinno was greeted as the head of the Kamakura Sogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1289, also by designation of the bakufu, Fushimi&apos;s first son, Tanehito (aged 2) was installed as Crown Prince and during the same year, Go-Fukasa&apos;s son Hisaaki Shinno was greeted as the head of the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>spelling &quot;Shogunate&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1289, also by designation of the bakufu, Fushimi&apos;s first son, Tanehito (aged 2) was installed as Crown Prince and during the same year, Gofukakusa&apos;s son Imperial Prince Hisaaki was greeted as the head of the Kamakura Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>後深草はこれを見届けると正応3年（1290年）に出家（48歳）し、治天の政務も伏見に譲って引退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After witnessing this, Go-Fukasa retired and became a priest in 1290 (aged 48), also yielding the job of Chiten to Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After witnessing this, Go-Fukasa retired and became a priest in 1290 (aged 48), also yielding the job of Chiten to Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After witnessing this, Gofukakusa retired and became a priest in 1290 (aged 48), also yielding the job of Chiten to Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>この時点では、まだ両統迭立が完全には定着しておらず、貴族たちもいずれか一方の皇統にのみ仕えて派閥を形成するということはなかったため、それまで大覚寺統の治天に仕えていた貴族たちはそのまま持明院統の治天に仕えることになり、大覚寺統は一気に勢力を失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, Ryototetsuritsu had not yet completely embedded itself, and the aristocracy did not yet create factions so the aristocrats who served the Daikaku-ji line Chiten worked for the subsequent Jimyo-iin line Chinten, leading to the sudden decline of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, Ryototetsuritsu had not yet completely embedded itself, and the aristocracy did not yet create factions so the aristocrats who served the Daikaku-ji line Chiten worked for the subsequent Jimyo-iin line Chiten, leading to the sudden decline of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt>Spelling &quot;Chinten&quot; changed to &quot;Chiten&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, Ryoto tetsuritsu had not yet completely embedded itself, and the aristocracy did not yet create factions so the aristocrats who served the Daikakuji line Chiten worked for the subsequent Jimyoin line Chiten, leading to the sudden decline of the Daikakuji line.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。ハイフン削除。スペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>亀山は失意のうちに正応2年に出家（41歳）し、翌正応3年に霜月騒動で所領を失った武士浅原為頼らが内裏に乱入し伏見を殺害しようとする事件が起きると関与を疑われ、起請文を幕府に提出して身の潔白を主張しなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kameyama was disappointed and became a priest in 1289 (aged 41), and was accused of being involved in a incident where bushi Tameyori ASAHARA and others who lost their territory during the Shimotsuki Incident, invaded the Royal Palace and tried to assassinate Fushimi, and had to submit an appeal to the bakufu to clear his name in 1290.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kameyama was disappointed and became a priest in 1289 (aged 41), and was accused of being involved in an incident where bushi Tameyori ASAHARA and others who lost their territory during the Shimotsuki Incident, invaded the Royal Palace and tried to assassinate Fushimi, and had to submit an appeal to the bakufu to clear his name in 1290.</e>
<cmt>grammar,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kameyama was disappointed and became a priest in 1289 (aged 41), and was accused of being involved in an incident where bushi Tameyori ASAHARA and others who lost their territory during the Shimotsuki Incident, invaded the Imperial Palace and tried to assassinate Fushimi, and had to submit an appeal to the bakufu to clear his name in 1290.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>治天となった伏見は、亀山の時代に整備された訴訟処理機構をさらに拡充し、家柄にとらわれない人材登用を積極的にめざすなど、政務の振興に努力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Fushimi became Chiten, he worked diligently for advancement and continued to expand the court management system and actively recruited without bias towards family lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Fushimi became Chiten, he worked diligently for advancement and continued to expand the court management system and actively recruited without bias towards family lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Fushimi became Chiten, he worked diligently for advancement and continued to expand the court management system and actively recruited without bias towards family lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>伏見が抜擢した人物としてもっとも著名なのは京極為兼である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous person that Fushimi recruited was Tamekane KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous person that Fushimi recruited was Tamekane KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous person that Fushimi recruited was Tamekane KYOGOKU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>為兼は伏見の信任を背景に二条派と並ぶ歌壇の一方の指導者となっただけでなく、政務にも深く関与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamekane was trusted by Fushimi and was the leader of the leading tanka (short poem) circle other than the Nijo school, and was also heavily involved in government affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamekane was trusted by Fushimi and was the leader of the leading tanka (short poem) circle other than the Nijo school, and was also heavily involved in government affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamekane was trusted by Fushimi and was the leader of the leading tanka (short poem) circle other than the Nijo school, and was also heavily involved in government affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>ただ、為兼の強烈な個性は多くの敵をつくり、伏見の積極的な政治姿勢とも相まって、西園寺実兼との対立や幕府の警戒を呼ぶ結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tamekane&apos;s individualistic character made many enemies and together with Fushimi&apos;s progressive governing stance, it led to confrontation with Sanekane SAIONJI and called attention from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tamekane&apos;s individualistic character made many enemies and together with Fushimi&apos;s progressive governing stance, it led to confrontation with Sanekane SAIONJI and called attention from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tamekane&apos;s individualistic character made many enemies and together with Fushimi&apos;s progressive governing stance, it led to confrontation with Sanekane SAIONJI and called attention from the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>伏見は永仁6年（1298年）に皇太子胤仁（10歳、後伏見天皇）に譲位したが、次の皇太子の人選をめぐって大覚寺統の巻き返しが起こり、実兼もこれに加担した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1298, Fushimi abdicated in favor of the Crown Prince Tanehito (aged 10, Emperor Go-Fushimi), but a comeback by the Daikaku-ji line that Sanekane also participated in was staged regarding the nomination of the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1298, Fushimi abdicated in favor of the Crown Prince Tanehito (aged 10, Emperor Go-Fushimi), but a comeback by the Daikaku-ji line that Sanekane also participated in was staged regarding the nomination of the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1298, Fushimi abdicated in favor of the Crown Prince Tanehito (aged 10, Emperor Gofushimi), but a comeback by the Daikakuji line that Sanekane also participated in was staged regarding the nomination of the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>結局、皇太子には後宇多の第1皇子邦治（14歳）が指名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Go-Uta&apos;s first son, Kuniharu (aged 1) was named as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Go-Uta&apos;s first son, Kuniharu (aged 1) was named as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Gouda&apos;s first son, Kuniharu (aged 14) was named as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。14に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>伏見は引き続き政務を執ったが政権は安定せず、正安3年（1301年）、幕府は治天・天皇の交替を要求し、皇太子邦治（17歳、後二条天皇）が践祚して後宇多による院政が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi continued to attend to government affairs, but the government did not stabilize and the bakufu ordered a change in Chiten and Emperor in 1287, with the Crown Prince Kuniharu (aged 17, Emperor Go-Nijo) ascending the throne and Go-Uta starting a cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi continued to attend to government affairs, but the government did not stabilize and the bakufu ordered a change in Chiten and Emperor in 1287, with the Crown Prince Kuniharu (aged 17, Emperor Go-Nijo) ascending the throne and Go-Uta starting a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added to &quot;Cloister&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi continued to attend to government affairs, but the government did not stabilize and the bakufu ordered a change in Chiten and Emperor in 1301, with the Crown Prince Kuniharu (aged 17, Emperor Gonijo) ascending the throne and Gouda starting a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>1301に訂正しました。名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="42">
<j>両統迭立が鎌倉幕府（最高権力者は得宗北条貞時）の公式な方針として表明されたのは、この交替のときが最初である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This change is the first time when Ryototetsuritsu was announced as being the official policy of the Kamakura Shogunate (when its supreme leader was Tokumune HOKUJO Sadatoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This change is the first time when Ryototetsuritsu was announced as being the official policy of the Kamakura Shogunate (when its supreme leader was Tokumune HOKUJO Sadatoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This change is the first time when Ryoto tetsuritsu was announced as being the official policy of the Kamakura Shogunate (when its supreme leader was Tokuso Sadatoki HOJO).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。)補足。名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>以後滅亡まで幕府はこの方針を堅持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu continued this policy until it fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu continued this policy until it fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu continued this policy until it fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>王家の分裂を固定化する意図によるものとする説と、皇位継承を王家の自律に任せ直接的な関与を避ける意図によるものとする説とが対立している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two opposing theories, one that this was done to establish a division in the Royal Family, and the other is that it was done to avoid direct intervention and leave the Imperial succession to the autonomy of the Royal Family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two opposing theories, one that this was done to establish a division in the Royal Family, and the other is that it was done to avoid direct intervention and leave the Imperial succession to the autonomy of the Royal Family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two opposing theories, one that this was done to establish a division in the Imperial family, and the other is that it was done to avoid direct intervention and leave the Imperial succession to the autonomy of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>両統迭立の定着にともない、一方の皇統に専属的に仕える貴族が出現しはじめ、また治天の側も貴族たちにそれを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Ryototetsuritsu became established, aristocrats that served only one of the royal lines started to appear, and the Chiten side also asked that of its aristocrats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Ryototetsuritsu became established, aristocrats that served only one of the royal lines started to appear, and the Chiten side also asked that of its aristocrats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Ryoto tetsuritsu became established, aristocrats that served only one of the Imperial lines started to appear, and the Chiten side also asked that of its aristocrats.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>王家の分裂が公家社会全体の分裂へと発展してゆくことになった一方、貴族たちの治天への従属は深まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the division of the Royal Family led to the division of Imperial Court society in general, the subordination of the aristocrats to the Chiten side also progressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the division of the Royal Family led to the division of Imperial Court society in general, the subordination of the aristocrats to the Chiten side also progressed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the division of the Imperial family led to the division of Imperial Court society in general, the subordination of the aristocrats to the Chiten side also progressed.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、政務の交替とともに朝廷の高官・要職が一斉に入れ換えられ、一方の皇統の治天が下した訴訟の判決が他方の皇統の治天によって安易に覆されるなどの混乱も生じ、朝廷の権威の低下を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the high officials and important positions were all changed when the heads were changes, confusion such as the judgment of a court cases during a Chiten in one line being easily upturned by the other line&apos;s Chiten occurred and this led to a decline in the Imperial Court&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the high officials and important positions were all changed when the heads were changed, confusion such as the judgment of a court cases during a Chiten in one line being easily upturned by the other line&apos;s Chiten occurred and this led to a decline in the Imperial Court&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>&quot;s&quot; replaces &quot;d&quot; in &quot;changes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the high officials and important positions were all changed when the heads were changed, confusion such as the judgment of a court cases during a Chiten in one line being easily upturned by the other line&apos;s Chiten occurred and this led to a decline in the Imperial Court&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="48">
<j>両統迭立の方針に基づき、次の皇太子は持明院統から出すこととされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the policy of Ryototetsuritsu, the next Crown Prince was to come from the Jimyo-in line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the policy of Ryototetsuritsu, the next Crown Prince was to come from the Jimyo-in line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the policy of Ryoto tetsuritsu, the next Crown Prince was to come from the Jimyoin line.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>13歳の後伏見にはまだ皇子がなく、伏見の第4皇子富仁（5歳）が皇太子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The thirteen year old Go-Fushimi had no princes and therefore Fushimi&apos;s fourth son, Tomihito (aged 5) became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The thirteen year old Go-Fushimi had no princes and therefore Fushimi&apos;s fourth son, Tomihito (aged 5) became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 13 year old Gofushimi had no princes and therefore Fushimi&apos;s fourth son, Tomihito (aged 5) became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>2つに分裂した王家がさらに分裂する可能性が生じ、伏見は持明院統の分裂を防止するため富仁を後伏見の猶子とする措置をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The possibility of further division threatened and Fushimi took measures to make Tomihito as Go-Fushimi&apos;s adopted heir.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The possibility of further division threatened and Fushimi took measures to make Tomihito as Go-Fushimi&apos;s adopted heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The possibility of further division threatened and Fushimi took measures to make Tomihito as Gofushimi&apos;s adopted heir.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>大覚寺統では、すでに後二条には正安2年（1300年）に第1皇子邦良親王が生まれて将来の皇位継承が予定されていたにもかかわらず、亀山が乾元 (日本)2年（1303年）に生まれた自分の皇子恒明親王を偏愛するあまり、邦良に代えて恒明を皇位につけることを後宇多と伏見に約束させて、さらなる皇統分裂の種を蒔いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Daikaku-ji line already had its future heir apparent for the throne because Go-Nijo&apos;s first son, Kuniyoshi Shinno was born in 1300, Kameyama was partial to his son Tsuneaki Shinno who was born in 1303, and had made Go-Uta and Fushimi promise to place Tsuneaki instead of Kuniyoshi on the throne, which led to further seeds of Imperial lineage division.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Daikaku-ji line already had its future heir apparent for the throne because Go-Nijo&apos;s first son, Kuniyoshi Shinno was born in 1300, Kameyama was partial to his son Tsuneaki Shinno who was born in 1303, and had made Go-Uta and Fushimi promise to place Tsuneaki instead of Kuniyoshi on the throne, which led to further seeds of Imperial lineage division.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Daikakuji line already had its future heir apparent for the throne because Gonijo&apos;s first son, Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi was born in 1300, Kameyama was partial to his son Imperial Prince Tsuneaki who was born in 1303, and had made Gouda and Fushimi promise to place Tsuneaki instead of Kuniyoshi on the throne, which led to further seeds of Imperial lineage division.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="52">
<j>嘉元2年（1304年）に後深草が62歳で死去、翌嘉元3年（1305年）には亀山が57歳で死去し、両統迭立は第2世代の時代に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1304, Go-Fukasa died at 62, and in 1305, Kameyama died at 57, and Ryototetsuritsu entered its second generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1304, Go-Fukasa died at 62, and in 1305, Kameyama died at 57, and Ryototetsuritsu entered its second generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1304, Gofukakusa died at 62, and in 1305, Kameyama died at 57, and Ryoto tetsuritsu entered its second generation.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>後宇多もやはり政務に精励することで自己の皇統の正統性を補強しようと努力している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Uta also attended to government affairs diligently to strengthen the claims of his royal line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Uta also attended to government affairs diligently to strengthen the claims of his royal line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gouda also attended to government affairs diligently to strengthen the claims of his Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>また、真言密教に傾倒して、徳治2年（1307年）には出家している（41歳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also a devout follower of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism and became a monk in 1307 (aged 41).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also a devout follower of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism and became a monk in 1307 (aged 41).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also a devout follower of Shingon Esoteric Buddhism and became a monk in 1307 (aged 41).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>これも個人的な信仰だけでなく、宗教的権威により皇統の正統性を強化する意図を含むものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was not only meant as a personal religion, but intended to strengthen the legitimacy of the royal line by religious authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was not only meant as a personal religion, but intended to strengthen the legitimacy of the royal line by religious authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was not only meant as a personal religion, but intended to strengthen the legitimacy of the royal line by religious authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>しかし、徳治3年（1308年）に後二条（24歳）が急死して皇太子富仁（12歳、花園天皇）が践祚し、伏見による院政が再開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1308, Go-Nijo (aged 24) died suddenly and the Crown Prince Tomihito (aged 12, Emperor Hanazono) ascended the throne and Fushimi started a cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1308, Go-Nijo (aged 24) died suddenly and the Crown Prince Tomihito (aged 12, Emperor Hanazono) ascended the throne and Fushimi started a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>changed to &quot;cloistered&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1308, Gonijo (aged 24) died suddenly and the Crown Prince Tomihito (aged 12, Emperor Hanazono) ascended the throne and Fushimi started a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>大覚寺統から皇太子が選ばれることになったが、後宇多は、皇太子として嫡孫邦良（9歳）ではなく第2皇子尊治（21歳）を選んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Crown Prince was to come from the Daikaku-ji line, but Go-Uta chose not his direct grandson Kuniyoshi, but his second Prince Takaharu (aged 21).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Crown Prince was to come from the Daikaku-ji line, but Go-Uta chose not his direct grandson Kuniyoshi, but his second Prince Takaharu (aged 21).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Crown Prince was to come from the Daikakuji line, but Gouda chose not his direct grandson Kuniyoshi (aged 9), but his second Prince Takaharu (aged 21).</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。(aged 9)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>邦良の幼少と病弱を考慮し、また恒明を皇太子とすることを要求する勢力を抑えるための措置だったが、結局これも問題をさらに複雑なものにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This choice took into account the youth and poor health of Kuniyoshi and was a measure to suppress the force that was demanding Tsuneaki as Crown Prince, but in conclusion this only led to make the problem even more complex.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This choice took into account the youth and poor health of Kuniyoshi and was a measure to suppress the force that was demanding Tsuneaki as Crown Prince, but in conclusion this only led to make the problem even more complex.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This choice took into account the youth and poor health of Kuniyoshi and was a measure to suppress the force that was demanding Tsuneaki as Crown Prince, but in conclusion this only led to make the problem even more complex.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>なお、伏見も正和2年（1313年）に出家し、治天の政務を後伏見に譲っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1313, Fushimi became a priest and yielded the government affairs as Chiten to Go-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1313, Fushimi became a priest and yielded the government affairs as Chiten to Go-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1313, Fushimi became a priest and yielded the government affairs as Chiten to Gofushimi.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="60">
<j>両統迭立の定着により、両統とも時期を待てばいずれ政務を執ることができるようになると、今度は両統ともその時期をなるべく早めようとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Ryototetsuritsu became established and both lines were able to govern as long as they could wait, the next thing that happened was that they tried to move that event forward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Ryototetsuritsu became established and both lines were able to govern as long as they could wait, the next thing that happened was that they tried to move that event forward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Ryoto tetsuritsu became established and both lines were able to govern as long as they could wait, the next thing that happened was that they tried to move that event forward.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>それは、具体的にはもっぱら鎌倉幕府へ特使を派遣して現在の天皇を譲位させるように請願するかたちで行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was specifically accomplished by sending special envoys to the Kamakura Shogunate and appeal for the abdication of the current Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was specifically accomplished by sending special envoys to the Kamakura Shogunate to appeal for the abdication of the current Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was specifically accomplished by sending special envoys to the Kamakura Shogunate to appeal for the abdication of the current Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>特にこのころ、伏見は第1次の院政期から引き続いて幕府から警戒されており、かつての亀山のように倒幕を考えているという噂も立つほどで、正和5年（1316年）には、伏見は幕府に告文を提出して潔白を訴えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially around this time, Fushimi was held in suspicion from the bakufu continuing on from his first cloister government, and there were even rumors that he was thinking of going against the bakufu and he submitted a official document appealing to the bakufu about his innocence in 1316.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially around this time, Fushimi was held in suspicion from the bakufu continuing on from his first cloistered government, and there were even rumors that he was thinking of going against the bakufu and he submitted a official document appealing to the bakufu about his innocence in 1316.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially around this time, Fushimi was held in suspicion from the bakufu continuing on from his first cloistered government, and there were even rumors that he was thinking of going against the bakufu and he submitted a official document appealing to the bakufu about his innocence in 1316.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>当然、治天・天皇の交替を求める大覚寺統からの圧力は増大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As expected, the pressure exerted by the Daikaku-ji line demanding a change in Chiten/Emperor grew.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As expected, the pressure exerted by the Daikaku-ji line demanding a change in Chiten/Emperor grew.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As expected, the pressure exerted by the Daikakuji line demanding a change in Chiten/Emperor grew.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>対応に苦しんだ幕府は、文保元年（1317年）、次回の皇位継承については両統の協議により決定し、特使の派遣はやめるように指示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu struggled to handle the issue and in 1317, it indicated that the next succession was to be decided by discussion between the two lines and prohibited the sending of special envoys.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu struggled to handle the issue and in 1317, it indicated that the next succession was to be decided by discussion between the two lines and prohibited the sending of special envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu struggled to handle the issue and in 1317, it indicated that the next succession was to be decided by discussion between the two lines and prohibited the sending of special envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>協議の場で後宇多は花園が皇太子尊治に譲位すること、次の皇太子には邦良を立てることを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the discussion, Go-Utada demanded that Hanazono abdicate in favor of the Crown Prince Takaharu, and place Kuniyoshi as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the discussion, Go-Utada demanded that Hanazono abdicate in favor of the Crown Prince Takaharu, and place Kuniyoshi as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the discussion, Gouda demanded that Hanazono abdicate in favor of the Crown Prince Takaharu, and place Kuniyoshi as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>伏見は花園の譲位は受け入れたが、皇太子には後伏見の第1皇子量仁（5歳）を立てることを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimi accepted the abdication of Hanazono, but wanted Go-Fushimi&apos;s first son Kazuhito (aged 5) as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimi accepted the abdication of Hanazono, but wanted Go-Fushimi&apos;s first son Kazuhito (aged 5) as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimi accepted the abdication of Hanazono, but wanted Gofushimi&apos;s first son Kazuhito (aged 5) as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>協議はいったん決裂したが、同年伏見が53歳で死去すると両統の力関係が変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The discussions broke up, but the power balance between the two lines changed when Fushimi died at 53 in the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The discussions broke up, but the power balance between the two lines changed when Fushimi died at 53 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The discussions broke up, but the power balance between the two lines changed when Fushimi died at 53 in the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>後宇多は再び花園の譲位を要求し、後伏見はこれを拒むことができず、翌文保2年（1318年）には尊治（31歳、後醍醐天皇）が践祚し、邦良（19歳）が皇太子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Utada demanded Hanazono&apos;s abdication again, and Go-Fushimi could not go against this, so in 1318, the Takaharu (aged 31, Emperor Go-Daigo) ascended the throne and Kuniyoshi (aged 19) became the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Utada demanded Hanazono&apos;s abdication again, and Go-Fushimi could not go against this, so in 1318, the Takaharu (aged 31, Emperor Go-Daigo) ascended the throne and Kuniyoshi (aged 19) became the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gouda demanded Hanazono&apos;s abdication again, and Gofushimi could not go against this, so in 1318, the Takaharu (aged 31, Emperor Godaigo) ascended the throne and Kuniyoshi (aged 19) became the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>交換条件として、後宇多は邦良の次の皇太子には量仁を立てることを後伏見に約束している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an exchange condition, Go-Uta promised Go-Fushimi that Kazuhito would become the next Crown Prince after Kuniyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an exchange condition, Go-Uta promised Go-Fushimi that Kazuhito would become the next Crown Prince after Kuniyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an exchange condition, Gouda promised Gofushimi that Kazuhito would become the next Crown Prince after Kuniyoshi.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>両統迭立は、すでに当然のこととして定着していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu was now established as a given.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu was now established as a given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu was now established as a given.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>後醍醐の践祚とともに後宇多の院政が再開されたが、後宇多は大覚寺門跡を創設して自ら門主となるなど密教への傾倒をさらに深め、また年齢とともに体調を崩してしだいに政務に倦み、元亨元年（1321年）には治天の政務を後醍醐に譲り、元亨4年（1324年）には58歳で死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Go-Daigo&apos;s accession, Go-Uta&apos;s cloister government was reinstated, but Go-Uta himself became further devout in esoteric Buddhism and became the chief priest himself by establishing Daikaku-ji Temple Monseki and he started to let the reins go with government affairs as his health declined along the years, relinquishing the duties as Chiten to Go-Daigo in 1321 and he died at the age of 58 in 1324.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Go-Daigo&apos;s accession, Go-Uta&apos;s cloistered government was reinstated, but Go-Uta himself became further devout in esoteric Buddhism and became the chief priest himself by establishing Daikaku-ji Temple Monseki and he started to let the reins go with government affairs as his health declined along the years, relinquishing the duties as Chiten to Go-Daigo in 1321 and he died at the age of 58 in 1324.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Godaigo&apos;s accession, Gouda&apos;s cloistered government was reinstated, but Gouda himself became further devout in esoteric Buddhism and became the chief priest himself by establishing Daikakuji Temple Monseki and he started to let the reins go with government affairs as his health declined along the years, relinquishing the duties as Chiten to Godaigo in 1321 and he died at the age of 58 in 1324.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>両統迭立は第3世代の時代を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu entered into its third generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu entered into its third generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu entered into its third generation.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="73">
<j>解消</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">End</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">End</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">End</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>後宇多は、あくまでも邦良を自分の正統な後継者と考えており、後醍醐の即位は邦良が成人するまでの“中継ぎ”でしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Uta considered Kuniyoshi as his genuine successor and the accession of Go-Daigo was only an &quot;interim&quot; measure until Kuniyoshi came to age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Uta considered Kuniyoshi as his genuine successor and the accession of Go-Daigo was only an &quot;interim&quot; measure until Kuniyoshi came to age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gouda considered Kuniyoshi as his genuine successor and the accession of Godaigo was only an &quot;interim&quot; measure until Kuniyoshi came to age.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>後宇多が記した大覚寺統の所領処分目録には、後醍醐の子孫は皇位継承権を持たないこと、後醍醐は邦良を自分の実子と思って待遇することなどが記され、そのことは関係者にも周知された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the property allocation list for the Daikaku-ji line written by Go-Uta wrote that Go-Daigo&apos;s descendants had no right to succession and Go-Daigo should consider Kuniyoshi as his own son and this was also known to those concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the property allocation list for the Daikaku-ji line written by Go-Uta, he wrote that Go-Daigo&apos;s descendants had no right to succession and Go-Daigo should consider Kuniyoshi as his own son and this was also known to those concerned.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the property allocation list for the Daikakuji line written by Gouda, he wrote that Godaigo&apos;s descendants had no right to succession and Godaigo should consider Kuniyoshi as his own son and this was also known to those concerned.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>当時の持明院統の関係者が残したメモには、後醍醐の地位が「一代主」と表現されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a memorandum left by a person associated with the Jimyo-in line at that time expresses Go-Daigo&apos;s position as an&quot;One-generation head&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a memorandum left by a person associated with the Jimyo-in line at that time expresses Go-Daigo&apos;s position as a &quot;One-generation head&quot;.</e>
<cmt>&quot;an&quot; changed to &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a memorandum left by a person associated with the Jimyoin line at that time expresses Godaigo&apos;s position as a &apos;One-generation head.&apos;</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。”を&apos;に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>後醍醐は、天皇としての権威を十全に主張できない立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Daigo was in a position where he could not express all of the authority given to him as Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Daigo was in a position where he could not express all of the authority given to him as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo was in a position where he could not express all of the authority given to him as Emperor.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>持明院統における花園も同様に“中継ぎ”の立場にあったが、伏見の意向で、花園は兄後伏見の猶子として持明院統の「嫡嗣」と呼ばれ、さらに後伏見の子息量仁が花園の猶子とされて、花園を持明院統の嫡流に組み込む、いわば“顔を立てる”配慮がなされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanazono of the Jimyo-in line was also in a similar &quot;interim&quot; position, but through the wishes of Fushimi, Hanazono was considered as his older brother Go-Fushimi&apos;s son and called the &quot;heir&quot; of Jimyo-in line and Go-Fushimi&apos;s son Kazuhito was made Hanazono&apos;s son, and Hanazono was fitted into the direct descendant line to save face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanazono of the Jimyo-in line was also in a similar &quot;interim&quot; position, but through the wishes of Fushimi, Hanazono was considered as his older brother Go-Fushimi&apos;s son and called the &quot;heir&quot; of the Jimyo-in line and Go-Fushimi&apos;s son Kazuhito was made Hanazono&apos;s son, and Hanazono was fitted into the direct descendant line to save face.</e>
<cmt>:&quot;the&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanazono of the Jimyoin line was also in a similar &quot;interim&quot; position, but through the wishes of Fushimi, Hanazono was considered as his older brother Gofushimi&apos;s son and called the &apos;heir&apos; of the Jimyoin line and Gofushimi&apos;s son Kazuhito was made Hanazono&apos;s son, and Hanazono was fitted into the direct descendant line to save face.</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。”を&apos;に訂正しました。名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>その温厚な人柄もあって、花園は自らの置かれた立場を従順に受け入れ、むしろ量仁の養育に力を注いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since he also had a mild personality, Hanazono accepted his position and actually spent much of his energy in nurturing Kazuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since he also had a mild personality, Hanazono accepted his position and actually spent much of his energy in nurturing Kazuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since he also had a mild personality, Hanazono accepted his position and in fact spent much of his energy in nurturing Kazuhito.</e>
<cmt>actually -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>しかし、後醍醐は自らの立場に強い不満をいだき、激しく反発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Go-Daigo was very unsatisfied with his position and became rebellious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Go-Daigo was very dissatisfied with his position and became rebellious.</e>
<cmt>changed to &quot;dissatisfied&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Godaigo was very dissatisfied with his position and became rebellious.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>元亨元年に後宇多が後醍醐に治天の政務を譲ったのは、後醍醐の強要によるものではないかと推測する研究者（網野善彦、森茂暁）もいるほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are even some researchers (Yoshihiko AMINO, Shigeaki MORI) who think that Go-Utada relinquished his government affair duties as Chiten to Go-Daigo in 1321 because of strong pressure from Go-Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are even some researchers (Yoshihiko AMINO, Shigeaki MORI) who think that Go-Utada relinquished his government affair duties as Chiten to Go-Daigo in 1321 because of strong pressure from Go-Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are even some researchers (Yoshihiko AMINO and Shigeaki MORI) who think that Gouda relinquished his government affair duties as Chiten to Godaigo in 1321 because of strong pressure from Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="82">
<j>このような後醍醐の感情は、政務を掌握してからのきわめて精力的な政策展開にも表現されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such feelings of Go-Daigo are expressed on how extensively he developed his policies after starting to take government affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such feelings of Go-Daigo are expressed on how extensively he developed his policies after starting to take up governmental affairs.</e>
<cmt>&quot;up&quot; inserted, changed to &quot;governmental&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such feelings of Godaigo are expressed on how extensively he developed his policies after starting to take up governmental affairs.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これまで歴代の治天が進めてきた訴訟処理機構の整備や迅速な訴訟処理、有為な人材の登用などは当然であるが、後醍醐は、沽酒法（米価・酒価公定令）、洛中への地口銭賦課などの経済政策にも取り組み、さらには洛中酒鑪役賦課令、神人公事停止令、関所停止令などを発して、それまで治天の権限の及ばなかった領域へも積極的に手を伸ばして朝廷自体の権力基盤の拡大をも目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, Go-Daigo worked on the court management system, speedy court case processing and recruitment of useful human resources that past Chiten had worked on, but he also worked on financial measures such as Koshu-ho(Law defining the price of rice and sake), Jiguchisen-ka to Rakuchu (extra tax on houses and fields in central Kyoto) but he also tried to enlarge the power base of the Imperial Court itself by actively working on areas that the authority of past Chiten did not reach and issued RakuchuShuroyakuFuka-rei, ShinjinKojiTeishi-rei, Sekishoteishi-rei, etc.</e>
<cmt>洛中酒鑪役賦課令、神人公事停止令、関所停止令-&gt;RakuchuShuroyakuFuka-rei, ShinjinKojiTeishi-rei, Sekishoteishi-rei としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, Go-Daigo worked on the court management system, speedy court case processing and recruitment of useful human resources that past Chiten had worked on, but he also worked on financial measures such as Koshu-ho (Law defining the price of rice and sake), Jiguchisen-ka to Rakuchu (extra tax on houses and fields in central Kyoto) but he also tried to enlarge the power base of the Imperial Court itself by actively working on areas that the authority of past Chiten did not reach and issued RakuchuShuroyakuFuka-rei, ShinjinKojiTeishi-rei, Sekishoteishi-rei, etc.</e>
<cmt>&quot;space&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, Godaigo worked on the court management system, speedy court case processing and recruitment of useful human resources that past Chiten had worked on, but he also worked on financial measures such as Koshu-ho (Law defining the price of rice and sake), Jiguchisen-ka to Rakuchu (extra tax on houses and fields in central Kyoto) but he also tried to enlarge the power base of the Imperial Court itself by actively working on areas that the authority of past Chiten did not reach and issued Rakuchu Shuroyaku Fuka-rei, Shinjin Koji Teishi-rei, Sekishoteishi-rei, etc.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="84">
<j>しかし、このような新政策は、当然、既得権を侵害される貴族・大寺社の抵抗や全国統一政権としての性格を強めつつあった幕府の規制を受けて充分な成果を挙げることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such new measures naturally did not attain sufficient results because of resistance from aristocrats, large temples and shrines that had their privileges infringed upon and the restrictions imposed by the bakufu, which was strengthening its character as an united national government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such new measures naturally did not attain sufficient results because of resistance from aristocrats, large temples and shrines that had their privileges infringed upon and the restrictions imposed by the bakufu, which was strengthening its character as a united national government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;an&quot; changed to &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, such new measures naturally did not attain sufficient results because of resistance from aristocrats, large temples and shrines that had their privileges infringed upon and the restrictions imposed by the bakufu, which was strengthening its character as a united national government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>また、後醍醐は朝廷内部で孤立しており、手足となって働く人材が不足していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Go-Daigo was isolated within the Imperial Court and there were insufficient human resources to work as his hands and feet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Go-Daigo was isolated within the Imperial Court and there were insufficient human resources to work as his hands and feet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Godaigo was isolated within the Imperial Court and there were insufficient human resources to work as his hands and feet.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>後嵯峨院政以来整備されてきた朝廷の訴訟処理機構で伝奏や奉行などの役職に就き実務を担う家柄（名家の家柄）を確立させてきた貴族たちは、すでにいずれかの皇統に組織されてそれぞれ主従関係を結んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aristocrats that have established the lineage (lineage of reputable families) of who becomes Tenso, Bugyo and other practical positions in the court management system of the Imperial Court that had been worked on since the cloister government of G-Saga, had already tied master-subordinate relationships with one of the Royal lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aristocrats that have established the lineage (lineage of reputable families) of who becomes Tenso, Bugyo, and other practical positions in the court management system of the Imperial Court that had been worked on since the cloistered government of G-Saga, had already tied master-subordinate relationships with one of the Royal lines.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aristocrats that have established the lineage (lineage of reputable families) of who becomes Tenso, Bugyo, and other practical positions in the court management system of the Imperial Court that had been worked on since the cloistered government of Gosaga, had already tied master-subordinate relationships with one of the Imperial lines.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>持明院統に仕える貴族たちが後醍醐に協力しなかったのはもちろん、大覚寺統に仕える貴族たちも多くは「一代主」でしかない後醍醐よりも嫡流の邦良に仕えることを選んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aristocrats subordinate to the Jimyo-in line naturally did not cooperate with Go-Daigo, but many of the aristocrats subordinate to Daikaku-ji line preferred the direct descendent Kuniyoshi to the &quot;One-generation-head&quot; Go-Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aristocrats subordinate to the Jimyo-in line naturally did not cooperate with Go-Daigo, but many of the aristocrats subordinate to Daikaku-ji line preferred the direct descendent Kuniyoshi to the &quot;One-generation-head&quot; Go-Daigo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aristocrats subordinate to the Jimyoin line naturally did not cooperate with Godaigo, but many of the aristocrats subordinate to Daikakuji line preferred the direct descendent Kuniyoshi to the &apos;One-generation-head&apos; Godaigo.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>後醍醐に仕えたのは、学問や芸能、信仰などを通じて後醍醐と個人的なつながりのあった者や、新たに名家の家柄への上昇を目指す低い家格の家系の出身者が中心だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who worked for Go-Daigo were people who had a personal relationship with him through study, arts, religion, etc., and were mainly people who were descended from lower class families who wanted their family lines tobecome premier lineages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who worked for Go-Daigo were people who had a personal relationship with him through study, arts, religion, etc., and were mainly people who were descended from lower class families who wanted their family lines to become premier lineages.</e>
<cmt>space added before &quot;family&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who worked for Godaigo were people who had a personal relationship with him through study, arts, religion, etc., and were mainly people who were descended from lower class families who wanted their family lines to become premier lineages.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="89">
<j>「一代主」の立場を甘受することもできず、自らが理想とする政策を充分に実現することもできなかった後醍醐は、唯一の突破口として武力により既存の政治秩序を根こそぎ破壊する道を選ぶことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not being able to accept that he was in the position of &quot;One- generation-head&quot;and not being to sufficiently implement his idealized measures, he selected the path of destroying the existing political order by force as a way of breaking out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not being able to accept that he was in the position of a &quot;One- generation-head&quot;and not being to sufficiently implement his idealized measures, he selected the path of destroying the existing political order by force as a way of breaking out.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot; added,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not being able to accept that he was in the position of a &apos;One-generation-head&apos; and not being to sufficiently implement his idealized measures, he selected the path of destroying the existing political order by force as a way of breaking out.</e>
<cmt>”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>当時、相続に関して父母の遺言は絶対的な効力を持っており、幕府や朝廷の法廷でも容易にそれを覆すことはできなかったほどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those times, the will of parents regarding inheritance had absolute effectiveness and even the court at the bakufu or Imperial court could not easily upturn that decision.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those times, the will of parents regarding inheritance had absolute effectiveness and even the court at the bakufu or Imperial court could not easily upturn that decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those times, the will of parents regarding inheritance had absolute effectiveness and even the court at the bakufu or Imperial court could not easily upturn that decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>後宇多の定めた皇位継承プランを尋常の手段で変更することは難しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was difficult to change the succession plan for the Imperial Throne that was determined by Go-Uta using normal measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was difficult to change the succession plan for the Imperial Throne that was determined by Go-Uta using normal measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was difficult to change the succession plan for the Imperial Throne that was determined by Gouda using normal measures.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>まして、両統迭立が幕府の方針として明確にされている以上、後醍醐の攻撃対象に幕府も含まれることになるのは必然的だったと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Ryototetsuritsu was a bakufu policy, it was natural that the bakufu was included as Go-Daigo&apos;s offensive target</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Ryototetsuritsu was a bakufu policy, it was natural that the bakufu was included as Go-Daigo&apos;s offensive target</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Ryoto tetsuritsu was a bakufu policy, it was natural that the bakufu was included as Godaigo&apos;s offensive target</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="93">
<j>後醍醐の第1次の武力倒幕計画が発覚したのは、元亨4年9月のことだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was September 1324 when Go-Daigo&apos;s first armed bakufu overthrow plan was uncovered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was September 1324 when Go-Daigo&apos;s first armed bakufu overthrow plan was uncovered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was September, 1324 when Godaigo&apos;s first armed bakufu overthrow plan was uncovered.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。,補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>後宇多の死去が同年6月であるから、まるで父の死を待っていたかのようなタイミングである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The death of Go-Uta was in June 1324, so the timing was as if he had waited for his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The death of Go-Uta was in June 1324, so the timing was as if he had waited for his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The death of Gouda was in June 1324, so the timing was as if he had waited for his father&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この年は12月に正中 (日本)と改元されたので、これを正中の変と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since in December of that year the name of the year was changed to Seichu, so this is called the &quot;Seichu Incident&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since in December of that year the name of the year was changed to Seichu, so this is called the &quot;Seichu Incident&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since in December of that year the name of the year was changed to Seichu, so this is called the &quot;Seichu Incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>計画は事前に幕府に漏れ、参画した者はある者は殺害され、ある者は逮捕されたが、結局、朝廷関係者では、後醍醐の側近日野資朝が佐渡に配流されただけで後醍醐は罪を問われなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plan was leaked to the bakufu and some participating members were killed, while some were arrested, but in the end, only Go-Daigo&apos;s aide, Suketomo HINO was exiled to Sado among the Imperial court relations and Go-Daigo was not accused of any crimes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan was leaked to the bakufu and some participating members were killed, while some were arrested, but in the end, only Go-Daigo&apos;s aide, Suketomo HINO was exiled to Sado among the Imperial court relations and Go-Daigo was not accused of any crimes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan was leaked to the bakufu and some participating members were killed, while some were arrested, but in the end, only Godaigo&apos;s aide, Suketomo HINO was exiled to Sado among the Imperial Court relations and Godaigo was not accused of any crimes.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Court大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="97">
<j>後醍醐と不和になっていた邦良は、正中の変以後、後醍醐を早期に譲位させるようたびたび幕府に請願していたが、正中4年（1326年）に急死してしまう（27歳）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyoshi was not on friendly terms with Go-Daigo and since the Seichu Incident, he had appealed to the bakufu to have Go-Daigo abdicate as soon as possible, but he died suddenly in 1326.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyoshi was not on friendly terms with Go-Daigo and since the Seichu Incident, he had appealed to the bakufu to have Go-Daigo abdicate as soon as possible, but he died suddenly in 1326.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyoshi was not on friendly terms with Godaigo and since the Seichu Incident, he had appealed to the bakufu to have Godaigo abdicate as soon as possible, but he died suddenly in 1326 (at age 27).</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。年齢を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>持明院統の嫡子量仁のほか、後二条の死後に立太子の機会を逸した恒明、邦良の同母弟邦省親王、後醍醐の第1皇子尊良親王らが次の皇太子の座を争い、最終的には幕府の裁定で量仁（14歳）が皇太子に指名された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position of Crown Prince was fought over by Kazuhito, the direct heir of Jimyo-in line, Kunimi, who was the younger brother with the same mother of Tsuneaki and Kuniyoshi Shinno who lost their chances to become Crown Prince after Go-Nijo died, and Go-Daigo&apos;s first son, Takayoshi Shinno, and in the end, Kazuhito (aged 14) was designated Crown Prince by the bakufu&apos;s ruling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of Crown Prince was fought over by Kazuhito, the direct heir of the Jimyo-in line, Kunimi, who was the younger brother with the same mother of Tsuneaki and Kuniyoshi Shinno who lost their chances to become Crown Prince after Go-Nijo died, and Go-Daigo&apos;s first son, Takayoshi Shinno, and in the end, Kazuhito (aged 14) was designated Crown Prince by the bakufu&apos;s ruling.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of Crown Prince was fought over by Kazuhito, the direct heir of the Jimyoin line, Kunimi, who was the younger brother with the same mother of Tsuneaki and Kuniyoshi Shinno who lost their chances to become Crown Prince after Gonijo died, and Godaigo&apos;s first son, Imperial Prince Takayoshi, and in the end, Kazuhito (aged 14) was designated Crown Prince by the bakufu&apos;s ruling.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。名前の訂正しました。Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>邦良も幼い男子を遺しており、彼らも将来は後醍醐の強力なライバルとなり得る立場にあって、後醍醐の「一代主」としての立場は幕府の権威のもとでますます明確となり、彼の倒幕志向もますます強まることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuniyoshi also left a young son, and he was also in a position to be a strong rival of Go-Daigo in the future, and the position of Go-Daigo as a &quot;One-generation-head&quot; was becoming even clearer under the authority of the bakufu and his tendency towards overthrowing the bakufu became stronger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuniyoshi also left a young son, and he was also in a position to be a strong rival of Go-Daigo in the future, and the position of Go-Daigo as a &quot;One-generation-head&quot; was becoming even clearer under the authority of the bakufu and his tendency towards overthrowing the bakufu became stronger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuniyoshi also left a young son, and he was also in a position to be a strong rival of Godaigo in the future, and the position of Godaigo as a &apos;One-generation-head&apos; was becoming even clearer under the authority of the bakufu and his tendency towards overthrowing the bakufu became stronger.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="100">
<j>第2次の武力倒幕計画も元徳3年（1331年）に事前に発覚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second armed bakufu overthrow plan was also discovered beforehand in 1331.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second armed bakufu overthrow plan was also discovered beforehand in 1331.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second armed bakufu overthrow plan was also discovered beforehand in 1331.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>今回は幕府の対応は強硬だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This time the bakufu took strong measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This time the bakufu took strong measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion the bakufu took strong measures.</e>
<cmt>&quot;This time&quot; -&gt; &quot;On this occasion&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>後醍醐は予定を早めて武装蜂起（元弘の変）に踏み切ったが、幕府は関係者の逮捕に着手するとともに、大軍を動員して鎮圧に乗り出し、後醍醐も逮捕されることを避けて京都を脱出し自ら叛乱軍に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Go-Daigo decided to lead an military uprising earlier than planned (Genko Incident), the bakufu started to arrest related people and moved large forces to suppress the revolt, so Go-Daigo eluded arrest by escaping Kyoto and joined his rebel army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Go-Daigo decided to lead a military uprising earlier than planned (Genko Incident), the bakufu started to arrest related people and moved large forces to suppress the revolt, so Go-Daigo eluded arrest by escaping Kyoto and joined his rebel army.</e>
<cmt>&quot;an&quot; changed to &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Godaigo decided to lead a military uprising earlier than planned (Genko Incident), the bakufu started to arrest related people and moved large forces to suppress the revolt, so Godaigo eluded arrest by escaping Kyoto and joined his rebel army.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>京都を制圧した幕府は、本人不在のまますぐに後醍醐を廃位し、皇太子量仁（19歳、光厳天皇）を践祚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu controlled Kyoto and immediately deposed Godaigo in absentia and Crown Prince Kazuhito (aged 19, Emperor Kogon) ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu controlled Kyoto and immediately deposed Godaigo in absentia and Crown Prince Kazuhito (aged 19, Emperor Kogon) ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu controlled Kyoto and immediately deposed Godaigo in absentia and Crown Prince Kazuhito (aged 19, Emperor Kogon) ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>この年8月、京都脱出の直前に後醍醐は元弘と改元しているが、幕府はこの改元も認めず、もとの元徳の元号をそのまま使用させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Daigo changed the name of the era to &quot;Genko&quot; in August just before his escape from Kyoto, but the bakufu did not recognize this change and continued to use the previous name, &quot;Gentoku&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Daigo changed the name of the era to &quot;Genko&quot; in August just before his escape from Kyoto, but the bakufu did not recognize this change and continued to use the previous name, &quot;Gentoku&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo changed the name of the era to &quot;Genko&quot; in August just before his escape from Kyoto, but the bakufu did not recognize this change and continued to use the previous name, &quot;Gentoku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>まもなく後醍醐は捕虜となり、承久の乱の先例に従って謀反人として隠岐に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shortly, Go-Daigo was captured and exiled to Oki as a traitor, following the example of Jyoku no Ran.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly, Go-Daigo was captured and exiled to Oki as a traitor, following the example of Jyoku no Ran.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly, Godaigo was captured and exiled to Oki as a traitor, following the example of Jokyu Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Jokyu Disturbanceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>計画に参画した皇子たちや貴族たちも死刑を含む厳罰に処された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Participating princes and aristocrats were also severely punished with punishment including execution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Participating princes and aristocrats were also severely punished with punishment including execution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Participating princes and aristocrats were also severely punished with punishment including execution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="107">
<j>光厳の践祚とともに後伏見の院政が再開された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the ascension of Kogon, Go-Fushimi started a cloister government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the ascension of Kogon, Go-Fushimi started a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the ascension of Kogon, Gofushimi started a cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>後伏見がまず着手したのは次の皇太子の人選である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first thing that Go-Fushimi started was the selection of the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first thing that Go-Fushimi started was the selection of the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first thing that Gofushimi started was the selection of the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>大覚寺統は邦良の早世と後醍醐の謀反とで壊滅状態にあり、持明院統が皇位を独占することも不可能ではなかったが、後伏見は幕府の意向もあって両統迭立の原則にあくまで忠実だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it was not impossible for the Jimyo-in line to monopolize the throne since the Daikaku-ji line was in a devastated state with Kuniyoshi&apos;s early death and Go-Daigo&apos;s rebellion, Go-Fushimi was true to the principle of Ryototetsuritsu in accord with the bakufu&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was not impossible for the Jimyo-in line to monopolize the throne since the Daikaku-ji line was in a devastated state with Kuniyoshi&apos;s early death and Go-Daigo&apos;s rebellion, Go-Fushimi was true to the principle of Ryototetsuritsu in accord with the bakufu&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was not impossible for the Jimyoin line to monopolize the throne since the Daikakuji line was in a devastated state with Kuniyoshi&apos;s early death and Godaigo&apos;s rebellion, Gofushimi was true to the principle of Ryoto tetsuritsu in accord with the bakufu&apos;s wishes.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。名前の訂正しました。スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>邦良の未亡人である禖子（後宇多の皇女）を大覚寺統の家長に擬して、彼女に次期皇太子の推薦を要請したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He asked the widow of Kuniyoshi, Baishi (princess of Go-Uta) to recommend the next Crown Prince as the acting head of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He asked the widow of Kuniyoshi, Baishi (princess of Go-Uta) to recommend the next Crown Prince as the acting head of the Daikaku-ji line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He asked the widow of Kuniyoshi, Baishi (princess of Gouda) to recommend the next Crown Prince as the acting head of the Daikakuji line.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>禖子は、後醍醐の冷遇のもとで12歳になるまで元服もできず、正式な命名もされていなかった邦良の第1王子を推薦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baishi recommended Kuniyoshi&apos;s first prince, who was treated coldly by Go-Daigo, not allowed to have the coming-of -age ceremony until 12 and not yet officially named.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baishi recommended Kuniyoshi&apos;s first prince, who was treated coldly by Go-Daigo, not allowed to have the coming-of -age ceremony until 12 and not yet officially named.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baishi recommended Kuniyoshi&apos;s first prince, who was treated coldly by Godaigo, not allowed to have the coming-of -age ceremony until 12 and not yet officially named.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>王子は持明院統により康仁親王と命名され、同時に親王とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prince was named Yasuhito Shinno by the Jimyo-in line and was also made Shinno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prince was named Yasuhito Shinno by the Jimyo-in line and was also made Shinno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prince was named Imperial Prince Yasuhito by the Jimyoin line and was also made Imperial Prince.</e>
<cmt>Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>禖子も大覚寺統の家長にふさわしく女院（崇明門院）の地位を与えられて上皇に准じる立場に就けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baishi was given the position Nyoin (Sumeimon-in) befitting her rank as the family head of the Daikaku-ji line, giving her the rank similar to ex-Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baishi was given the position Nyoin (Sumeimon-in) befitting her rank as the family head of the Daikaku-ji line, giving her a rank similar to ex-Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; changed to &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baishi was given the position Nyoin (Sumeimonin) befitting her rank as the family head of the Daikakuji line, giving her a rank similar to Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。&quot;ex-Emperor&quot; -&gt; &quot;Retired Emperor&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>崇明門院の後見のもと、康仁が皇太子となり、持明院統の支援で大覚寺統は再建されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the regency of Sumeimon-in, Yasuhito became Crown Prince and the Daikaku-ji line was reestablished with the support of the Jimei-in line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the regency of Sumeimon-in, Yasuhito became Crown Prince and the Daikaku-ji line was reestablished with the support of the Jimei-in line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the regency of Sumeimonin, Yasuhito became Crown Prince and the Daikakuji line was reestablished with the support of the Jimyoin line.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。Jimyoinに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="115">
<j>元弘の変が失敗に終わったあとも、幕府の追及を逃れた後醍醐の皇子護良親王、楠木正成らのゲリラ的抵抗運動は続き、規模的にも地域的にも次第に純然たる叛乱へと拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Genko Incident ended in failure, guerilla like resistance continued under Go-Daigo&apos;s son, Moriyoshi Shinno and Masashige KUSUNOKI, and gradually the size and region increased until it was a true insurrection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Genko Incident ended in failure, guerilla like resistance continued under Go-Daigo&apos;s son, Moriyoshi Shinno and Masashige KUSUNOKI, and gradually the size and region increased until it was a true insurrection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Genko Incident ended in failure, guerilla like resistance continued under Godaigo&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Moriyoshi and Masashige KUSUNOKI, and gradually the size and region increased until it was a true insurrection.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>正慶2年（1333年）には後醍醐が隠岐を脱出して伯耆に滞在し、自ら叛乱に参加する態度を示すとともに、広く各地の武士団に叛乱への参加を呼びかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1333, Go-Daigo escaped Oki and stayed at Hoki, indicating his wishes to directly participation the insurrection and widely made a call for participation among the armed groups around the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1333, Go-Daigo escaped Oki and stayed at Hoki, indicating his wishes to directly participation the insurrection and widely made a call for participation among the armed groups around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1333, Godaigo escaped Oki and stayed at Hoki, indicating his wishes to directly participation the insurrection and widely made a call for participation among the armed groups around the country.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>幕府は名越高家と足利尊氏を総大将とする大軍を動員して近畿地方に増派し、叛乱の鎮圧をはかったが、高家は京都に着いてまもなく緒戦で戦死し、尊氏は後醍醐の呼びかけに応じて叛乱軍に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu moved a large force lead by Takaie NAKOSHI and Takauji ASHIKAGA, adding more soldiers in the Kinki region to contain the insurrection, but Takaie died in battle shortly after arriving in Kyoto and Takauji answered Go-Daigo&apos;s call to join the insurrection force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu moved a large force lead by Takaie NAKOSHI and Takauji ASHIKAGA, adding more soldiers in the Kinki region to contain the insurrection, but Takaie died in battle shortly after arriving in Kyoto and Takauji answered Go-Daigo&apos;s call to join the insurrection force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu moved a large force lead by Takaie NAGOE and Takauji ASHIKAGA, adding more soldiers in the Kinki region to contain the insurrection, but Takaie died in battle shortly after arriving in Kyoto and Takauji answered Godaigo&apos;s call to join the insurrection force.</e>
<cmt>Takaie NAGOEに訂正しました。名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>北条氏に次ぐ家格と勢力を誇る有力御家人である足利氏が幕府から離反した影響は甚大で、叛乱は瞬く間に全国に波及、鎌倉幕府は短時日でもろくも崩壊してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The effect that the Ashikaga clan, who were a prominent vassal of the Shogun after the Hokujyo clan in lineage and power, defected from the bakufu was very large and the insurrection rapidly engulfed the whole nation, with the Kamakura bakufu quickly reduced to disintegration..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The effect that the Ashikaga clan, who were a prominent vassal of the Shogun after the Hokujyo clan in lineage and power, defected from the bakufu was very large and the insurrection rapidly engulfed the whole nation, with the Kamakura bakufu quickly reduced to disintegration..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The effect that the Ashikaga clan, who were a prominent vassal of the Shogun after the Hojo clan in lineage and power, defected from the bakufu was very large and the insurrection rapidly engulfed the whole nation, with the Kamakura bakufu quickly reduced to disintegration.</e>
<cmt>Hojoに訂正しました。余分なピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="119">
<j>権力の空白を埋めたのは、まだ伯耆にいた後醍醐である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who filled the gap in power was Go-Daigo, who was still in Hoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who filled the gap in power was Go-Daigo, who was still in Hoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person who filled the gap in power was Godaigo, who was still in Hoki.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>後醍醐は、京都に帰還するよりも早く命令を発して、元弘の変以後の朝廷の政治的行為をすべて取り消した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Daigo issued orders before his return to Kyoto and erased all political actions by the Imperial Court after the Seigen Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Daigo issued orders before his return to Kyoto and erased all political actions by the Imperial Court after the Seigen Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo issued orders before his return to Kyoto and erased all political actions by the Imperial Court after the Genko Incident.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Genko Incidentに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>後伏見の政務が停止され、光厳が廃位されたのは当然であるが、後醍醐はそもそも元徳3年に自分が廃位された事実自体を認めず、隠岐に流されていた間も自分はずっと天皇に在位していたという立場をとり、従って光厳の即位と在位も“なかったこと”にされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was natural that government affairs by Go-Fushimi were terminated and Kogon was deposed, but Go-Daigo did not even recognize that he was deposed in 1331, and took the stance that he was ruling during the whole time he was exiled in Oki, so therefore there was &quot;no accession nor rule&quot; of Kogon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was natural that government affairs by Go-Fushimi were terminated and Kogon was deposed, but Go-Daigo did not even recognize that he was deposed in 1331, and took the stance that he was ruling during the whole time he was exiled in Oki, so therefore there was &quot;no accession nor rule&quot; of Kogon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was natural that government affairs by Gofushimi were terminated and Kogon was deposed, but Godaigo did not even recognize that he was deposed in 1331, and took the stance that he was ruling during the whole time he was exiled in Oki, so therefore there was &quot;no accession nor rule&quot; of Kogon.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>後宇多の遺言はなお有効であり、いったん自らの退位を認めてしてしまえば、治天として政務を執る資格も子孫に皇位を伝える資格も失われかねないことを後醍醐はよく承知していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Daigo knew well that Go-Uta&apos;s will was still in effect and if he recognized that he had abdicated, he might lose eligibility to rule as Chiten or pass the throne on to his descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Daigo knew well that Go-Uta&apos;s will was still in effect and if he recognized that he had abdicated, he might lose eligibility to rule as Chiten or pass the throne on to his descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo knew well that Gouda&apos;s will was still in effect and if he recognized that he had abdicated, he might lose eligibility to rule as Chiten or pass the throne on to his descendants.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>光厳にはいちおう上皇の称号と待遇が与えられたが、それは通例の前天皇に対する優遇措置ではなく、あくまでも皇太子の地位を辞退したことに対する褒賞であることが明示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was clearly indicated that Kogen was given the title and privileges of Joko but not as preferential treatment for being the former Emperor but as a prize for refraining the position of Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was clearly indicated that Kogen was given the title and privileges of Joko but not as preferential treatment for being the former Emperor, but as a prize for refraining the position of Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>comma inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was clearly indicated that Kogon was given the title and privileges of the retired emperor but not as preferential treatment for being the former Emperor, but as a prize for refraining the position of Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>上皇→the Retired Emperorに訂正しました。名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>光厳から将来治天として政務を執る資格を奪う措置であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a measure to prevent Kogen from ruling as Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a measure to prevent Kogen from ruling as Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a measure to prevent Kogon from ruling as Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>後伏見は前途を悲観して出家している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Fushimi abandoned hope for the future and became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Fushimi abandoned hope for the future and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gofushimi abandoned hope for the future and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>康仁も皇太子を廃され、親王の称号までも奪われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasuhito was deposed as Crown Prince and even the title of Shinno was taken away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasuhito was deposed as Crown Prince and even the title of Shinno was taken away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasuhito was deposed as Crown Prince and even the title of Imperial Prince was taken away.</e>
<cmt>Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>正慶2年の年号も元弘3年と改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the era was changed and &quot;Seikei 2&quot; became &quot;Genko 3&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the era was changed and &quot;Seikei 2&quot; became &quot;Genko 3&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the era was changed and &quot;the second year of Seikei&quot; became &quot;the third year of Genko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。元号の表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>翌元弘4年（1334年）には後醍醐の皇子恒良親王（12歳）が皇太子に立てられ、持明院統の皇統としての地位は完全に否定され、3世代、50年以上にわたった両統迭立はここに終焉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, 1334, saw Go-Daigo&apos;s son Tsuneyoshi Shinno (aged 12) as Crown Prince and the position of the Jimyo-in line as a Emperor&apos;s line was completely negated, and here the Ryototetsuritsu that spanned three generations and continued over 50 years came to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, 1334, saw Go-Daigo&apos;s son Tsuneyoshi Shinno (aged 12) as Crown Prince and the position of the Jimyo-in line as a Emperor&apos;s line was completely negated, and here the Ryototetsuritsu that spanned three generations and continued over 50 years came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, 1334, saw Godaigo&apos;s son Imperial Prince Tsuneyoshi (aged 12) as Crown Prince and the position of the Jimyoin line as a Emperor&apos;s line was completely negated, and here the Ryoto tetsuritsu that spanned three generations and continued over 50 years came to an end.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。ハイフン削除。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="129">
<j>後日談</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sequel</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sequel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sequel</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>両統迭立は終わっても、その理念は、なおしばらく残存した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though Ryototetsuritsu ended, the concept still remained for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though Ryototetsuritsu ended, the concept still remained for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though Ryoto tetsuritsu ended, the concept still remained for a while.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>後醍醐の新政権が足利尊氏の離反により建武 (日本)3年（1336年）に崩壊すると、尊氏の奏請により光厳の院政が開始され（後伏見はこの年49歳で死去している）、光厳の同母弟豊仁（16歳、光明天皇）が践祚したが、皇太子に立てられたのは、廃太子康仁でも、光厳の第1皇子興仁（3歳）でもなく、後醍醐の皇子成良親王（12歳）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new Go-Daigo government collapsed in 1336 due to Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s defection and the cloister government by Kogon was initiated by Takauji&apos;s request (Go-Fushimi died in the same year at 49), and Kogon&apos;s brother Toyohito (aged 16, Emperor Komei) ascended the throne and the Crown Prince was not the deposed prince Yasuhito or Kogon&apos;s first son Prince Okihito (aged 3), but Go-Daigo&apos;s son Nariyoshi Shinno (aged 12).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new Go-Daigo government collapsed in 1336 due to Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s defection and the cloistered government by Kogon was initiated by Takauji&apos;s request (Go-Fushimi died in the same year at 49), and Kogon&apos;s brother Toyohito (aged 16, Emperor Komei) ascended the throne and the Crown Prince was not the deposed prince Yasuhito or Kogon&apos;s first son Prince Okihito (aged 3), but Go-Daigo&apos;s son Nariyoshi Shinno (aged 12).</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new Godaigo government collapsed in 1336 due to Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s defection and the cloistered government by Kogon was initiated by Takauji&apos;s request (Gofushimi died in the same year at 49), and Kogon&apos;s brother Toyohito (aged 16, Emperor Komei) ascended the throne and the Crown Prince was not the deposed prince Yasuhito or Kogon&apos;s first son Prince Okihito (aged 3), but Godaigo&apos;s son Imperial Prince Nariyoshi (aged 12).</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>後醍醐には正式な前天皇としての上皇の称号と待遇が与えられ、これで後醍醐には将来治天として政務を執る可能性が生じることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Daigo was officially given the title and privileges of Joko as the previous Emperor and Go-Daigo had the possibility of ruling as Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Daigo was officially given the title and privileges of Joko as the previous Emperor and Go-Daigo had the possibility of ruling as Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo was officially given the title and privileges of the retired emperor as the previous Emperor and Godaigo had the possibility of ruling as Chiten in the future.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。上皇→the Retired Emperorに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>このような措置は、後醍醐から譲歩を引き出し、自らの新政権に協力させたい尊氏の意向によるものであったが、後醍醐はいっさいの妥協を拒み、すぐに京都を脱出して吉野に自らの朝廷を樹立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These measures were taken under the wishes of Takauji, who wanted to extract concessions from Go-Daigo and have him cooperate with Takauji&apos;s new government, but Go-Daigo refused any compromises and immediately escaped Kyoto to establish his own imperial court in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These measures were taken under the wishes of Takauji, who wanted to extract concessions from Go-Daigo and have him cooperate with Takauji&apos;s new government, but Go-Daigo refused any compromises and immediately escaped Kyoto to establish his own imperial court in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These measures were taken under the wishes of Takauji, who wanted to extract concessions from Godaigo and have him cooperate with Takauji&apos;s new government, but Godaigo refused any compromises and immediately escaped Kyoto to establish his own imperial court in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>王家は両統迭立の時代から南北朝並立の時代へはっきりと転換したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Royal Family made a clear transition from Ryototetsuritsu era to Northern and Southern Dynasties era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Royal Family made a clear transition from the Ryototetsuritsu era to the Northern and Southern Dynasties era.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial family made a clear transition from the Ryoto tetsuritsu era to the Northern and Southern Dynasties era.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>利用価値のなくなった成良はまもなく皇太子を廃され、建武5年（1338年）には興仁（5歳、のちの崇光天皇）が皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nariyoshi had no value and was deposed as Crown Prince and in 1338, Okihito (aged 5, later Emperor Suko) was made Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nariyoshi had no value and was deposed as Crown Prince and in 1338, Okihito (aged 5, later Emperor Suko) was made Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nariyoshi had no value and was deposed as Crown Prince and in 1338, Okihito (aged 5, later Emperor Suko) was made Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="136">
<j>明徳3年（1392年）に足利義満がまとめた南北朝合一に際しても、両統迭立の理念が再度持ち出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concept of Ryototetsuritsu was again brought up upon the union of Northern and Southern Dynasties that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA concluded in 1392.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concept of Ryototetsuritsu was again brought up upon the union of Northern and Southern Dynasties that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA concluded in 1392.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concept of Ryoto tetsuritsu was again brought up upon the union of Northern and Southern Dynasties that Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA concluded in 1392.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>合一後は、北朝の後小松天皇の子孫と南朝の後亀山天皇の子孫とのあいだで両統迭立を行うことが、合一の条件に盛り込まれたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu after unification between the descendants of Emperor Go-Komatsu of the Northern Dynasty and Go-Kameyama of the Southern Dynasty was included as one of the unification conditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu, after unification between the descendants of Emperor Go-Komatsu of the Northern Dynasty and Go-Kameyama of the Southern Dynasty, was included as one of the unification conditions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;commas&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu, after unification between the descendants of Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Dynasty and Gokameyama of the Southern Dynasty, was included as one of the unification conditions.</e>
<cmt>名前の訂正しました。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="138">
<j>もっとも、当時の南北両朝の力関係から言って、北朝側はもちろん、南朝側も、この条件が遵守されるとは考えていなかったはずであり、実際にも遵守されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, judging from the power balance of both Southern and Northern Dynasties at that time, not only the Northern Dynasty but also the Southern Dynasty probably did not think this condition would be followed and in reality, it was not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, judging from the power balance of both Southern and Northern Dynasties at that time, not only the Northern Dynasty but also the Southern Dynasty probably did not think this condition would be followed and in reality, it was not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, judging from the power balance of both Southern and Northern Dynasties at that time, not only the Northern Dynasty but also the Southern Dynasty probably did not think this condition would be followed and in reality, it was not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>しかし、この条件を口実として、旧南朝の皇族の子孫や旧南朝にゆかりのある人々による室町幕府に対する抵抗や叛乱がその後も100年にわたって相次いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this condition served as a reason for former Southern Dynasty royal family descendants and related people to continue on with resistance and insurrections against the Muromachi bakufu for around 100 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this condition served as a reason for former Southern Dynasty royal family descendants and related people to continue on with resistance and insurrections against the Muromachi bakufu for around 100 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this condition served as a reason for former Southern Dynasty Imperial family descendants and related people to continue on with resistance and insurrections against the Muromachi bakufu for around 100 years.</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>これらの運動を後南朝という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This activity is called the post-Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This activity is called the post-Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This activity is called the second Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>後南朝→the second Southern Dynasty</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="141">
<j>平安時代の両統迭立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu during the Heian Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu during the Heian Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu during the Heian period</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。periodl小文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>平安時代にも、両統迭立の状況が2度にわたって発生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu occurred twice during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu occurred twice during the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu occurred twice during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。periodl小文字にしました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="143">
<j>嵯峨流と淳和流の迭立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuritsu between Saga-ryu and Junna-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuritsu between Saga-ryu and Junna-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuritsu between Saga line and Junna line</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。ryu→line</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>平安京を建設した桓武天皇には、多数の妻妾と多数の皇子女があったが、なかでも皇位継承についてもっとも有利な立場にあるとみなされていたのは、安殿、神野、大伴の3人の皇子であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu, who established Heian-kyo, had many wives, concubines, and princes and princesses, but the three princes that were thought to be in an advantageous position for Imperial succession were Ate, Kamino, and Otomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Kanmu, who established Heian-kyo, had many wives, concubines, and princes, and princesses, but the three princes that were thought to be in an advantageous position for Imperial succession were Ate, Kamino, and Otomo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Kanmu, who established Heian-kyo, had many wives, concubines, and princes, and princesses, but the three princes that were thought to be in an advantageous position for Imperial succession were Ate, Kamino, and Otomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>彼らはいずれも皇后もしくはそれに準じる待遇を受けた藤原氏藤原式家出身の女性を母とし、さらに桓武の意向で異母姉妹にあたる内親王を妻としていた（安殿は朝原内親王と大宅内親王の2人、神野は高津内親王、大伴は高志内親王）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their mothers were all from the Fujiwara clan or related family who were empress or received similar treatment, and due to the wishes of Kanmu, they all had wives that were Naishinno and their half-sisters with a different mother (Ate had two wives, Asahara Naishinno and Oyake Naishinno, Kamino had Takatsu Naishinno, and Oyaka had Takashi Naishinno).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their mothers were all from the Fujiwara clan or related family who were empress or received similar treatment, and due to the wishes of Kanmu, they all had wives that were Naishinno and their half-sisters with a different mother (Ate had two wives, Asahara Naishinno and Oyake Naishinno, Kamino had Takatsu Naishinno, and Oyaka had Takashi Naishinno).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their mothers were all from the Fujiwara clan or related family who were empress or received similar treatment, and due to the wishes of Kanmu, they all had wives that were Imperial Princesses and their half-sisters with a different mother (Ate had two wives, Imperial Princess Asahara and Imperial Princess Oyake, Kamino had Imperial Princess Takatsu, and Otomo had Imperial Princess Koshi).</e>
<cmt>Naishinno削除、Imperial Princessesに訂正しました。Otomoに訂正しました。高志→Koshi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>3人の皇子をあえて並び立たせ、将来複雑な皇位継承争いを引き起こしかねない措置をとった桓武の真意は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What the true wishes of Kanmu were by taking such measures that might lead to a complex competition for the Imperial succession by intentionally lining the three princes is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What the true wishes of Kanmu were by taking such measures that might lead to a complex competition for the Imperial succession by intentionally lining the three princes is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What the true wishes of Kanmu were by taking such measures that might lead to a complex competition for the Imperial succession by intentionally lining the three princes is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>まず、第1皇子である安殿が延暦4年（785年）に皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, the first prince Ate was instated as Crown Prince in 785.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, the first prince Ate was instated as Crown Prince in 785.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, the first prince Ate was instated as Crown Prince in 785.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>彼は桓武の死を受けて延暦25年（806年）に即位（平城天皇）し、皇太子には同母弟の神野を立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He ascended the throne upon Kanmu&apos;s death in 806 as Emperor Heijyo, and placed his brother Kamino, who shared the same mother, as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He ascended the throne upon Kanmu&apos;s death in 806 as Emperor Heijyo, and placed his brother Kamino, who shared the same mother, as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He ascended the throne upon Kanmu&apos;s death in 806 as Emperor Heizei, and placed his brother Kamino, who shared the same mother, as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>平城は朝原と大宅の2人との間に子はなく、ほかの皇子たちはいずれも母の身分が低く、神野と大伴の隠然たる権威と存在感を無視することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heijyo was not able to ignore the authority and existence that Kamino and Otomo had, because Asahara and Oyake did not have any children and all the other princes had lowly-born mothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heijyo was not able to ignore the authority and existence that Kamino and Otomo had, because Asahara and Oyake did not have any children and all the other princes had lowly-born mothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizei was not able to ignore the authority and existence that Kamino and Otomo had, because Asahara and Oyake did not have any children and all the other princes had lowly-born mothers.</e>
<cmt>平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="150">
<j>長期間皇太子で過ごした平城には、それなりに自らの施政に対する抱負があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heijyo had spent a long time as Crown Prince and had a certain degree of ideas about how to govern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heijyo had spent a long time as Crown Prince and had a certain degree of ideas about how to govern.</e>
<cmt>&quot;s&quot; removed</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizei had spent a long time as Crown Prince and had a certain degree of ideas about how to govern.</e>
<cmt>平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>新天皇が先帝死去の翌年になるのを待って改元する先例に反して即位後ただちに大同 (日本)と改元し、桓武がさかんに行った蝦夷侵略の軍事行動や遷都にともなう土木工事のために弛緩した財政の引き締め、機能していない官司の整理、参議を廃止して太政官が地方政治を直接監督する観察使を置くなど積極的に政治改革に取り組んだが、若いころから病身だった彼はやがて体調を崩し、早くも大同4年（809年）には皇太子神野（嵯峨天皇）に譲位することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rather than wait until the year after the preceding Emperor died to change the name of the era which was the custom, the new Emperor changed the era name into Dodai and tightened the budget that had loosened while Kanmu had made frequent military activity against the Siberian invasion and moved the capital, and actively worked on organizing redundant court positions, placing of a Kansatsushi, where Daijokan directly watches over regional government and abolishing Sangi, but he was sickly from a young age and abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Kamino (Emperor Saga) in 809.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather than wait until the year after the preceding Emperor died to change the name of the era which was the custom, the new Emperor changed the era name into Dodai and tightened the budget that had loosened while Kanmu had conducted frequent military activity against the Siberian invasion and moved the capital, and actively worked on organizing redundant court positions, placing of a Kansatsushi, where Daijokan directly watches over regional government and abolishing Sangi, but he was sickly from a young age and abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Kamino (Emperor Saga) in 809.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather than wait until the year after the preceding Emperor died to change the name of the era which was the custom, the new Emperor changed the era name into Dodai and tightened the budget that had loosened while Kanmu had conducted frequent military activity against the Siberian invasion and moved the capital, and actively worked on organizing redundant court positions, placing of a Kansatsushi, where Daijokan directly watches over regional government and abolishing Sangi, but he was sickly from a young age and abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Kamino (Emperor Saga) in 809.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>嵯峨にはすでに高津との間に生まれた皇子業良親王がいたが、業良は先天的に心身に重篤な障碍を負っており、皇位継承は不可能とみなされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga already had a son with Takatsu called Nariyoshi Shinno, but Nariyoshi had a severe physical and mental congenital disability and was considered to have no possibility of attaining the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga already had a son with Takatsu called Nariyoshi Shinno, but Nariyoshi had a severe physical and mental congenital disability and was considered to have no possibility of attaining the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga already had a son with Takatsu called Imperial Prince Nariyoshi, but Nariyoshi had a severe physical and mental congenital disability and was considered to have no possibility of attaining the throne.</e>
<cmt>Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>大伴にも高志との間に恒世親王が生まれていたが、平城は大伴父子の存在を無視してあえて自分の皇子高岳親王を皇太子に立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomo had a son with Takashi called Tsuneyo Shinno, but Heijyo ignored the existence of the Otomo father and son and explicitly placed his son, Takaoka Shinno as Crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otomo had a son with Takashi called Tsuneyo Shinno, but Heijyo ignored the existence of the Otomo father and son and explicitly placed his son, Takaoka Shinno as Crown prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otomo had a son with Koshi called Imperial Prince Tsuneyo, but Heizei ignored the existence of the Otomo father and son and explicitly placed his son, Imperial Prince Takaoka as Crown prince.</e>
<cmt>Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="154">
<j>退位して太上天皇となった平城は、生まれ故郷である平城京に移り住み、体調がやや回復すると再度政務に意欲を示し、独自に天皇としての権限を行使しはじめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After abdicating and becoming an ex-Emperor (Daijotenno), Heijyo returned to his birthplace, Heijyo-kyo, and when his health recovered slightly, he returned to ruling and started to use the rights of an emperor on his own accord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After abdicating and becoming an ex-Emperor (Daijotenno), Heijyo returned to his birthplace, Heijyo-kyo, and when his health recovered slightly, he returned to ruling and started to use the rights of an emperor on his own accord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After abdicating and becoming the Retired Empreor, Heizei returned to his birthplace, Heijo-kyo, and when his health recovered slightly, he returned to ruling and started to use the rights of an emperor on his own accord.</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired Empreor平城→HeizeiHeijoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>もともと太上天皇は天皇と同格かつ同等の権限を有するものとされ、最初の太上天皇である持統天皇と文武天皇以来、太上天皇と天皇が共同で執政することは当然のこととされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, a Daijotenno was considered to hold the same and equivalent authority as an emperor, so it was considered natural that the ex-emperor and emperor rule together since the first ex-Emperor Emperor Jito and Emperor Bunmu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, a Daijotenno was considered to hold the same and equivalent authority as an emperor, so it was considered natural that the ex-emperor and emperor rule together since the first ex-Emperor Emperor Jito and Emperor Bunmu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, a retired empreor was considered to hold the same and equivalent authority as an emperor, so it was considered natural that the retired emperor and emperor rule together since the first Retired Emperor Jito and Emperor Monmu.</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired EmpreorMonmuに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>しかし、これは太上天皇が天皇の直系尊属ないしそれに準じた立場を有する場合にこそ円滑に機能するものであり、同母兄弟である平城と嵯峨の間ではむしろ政治の混乱と両者の対立抗争の原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this only functions smoothly when the ex-emperor is a direct ancestor or equivalent to the emperor, but it only led to political confusion and conflict between Heijyo and Sage because they were half brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this only functions smoothly when the ex-emperor is a direct ancestor or equivalent to the emperor, but it only led to political confusion and conflict between Heijyo and Sage because they were half brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this only functions smoothly when the retired emperor is a direct ancestor or equivalent to the emperor, but it only led to political confusion and conflict between Heizei and Saga because they were half brothers.</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired Empreor平城→HeizeiHeizei and Sagaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>翌弘仁元年（810年）、平城が平城京への遷都を嵯峨に命令すると、嵯峨は一気にクーデタに踏み切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When in the next year, 810, Heijyo commanded Saga to relocate the capital to Heijyo, Saga decided to raise a coup d&apos;etat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When in the next year, 810, Heijyo commanded Saga to relocate the capital to Heijyo, Saga decided to raise a coup d&apos;etat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When in the next year, 810, Heizei commanded Saga to relocate the capital to Heijo-kyo, Saga decided to raise a coup d&apos;etat.</e>
<cmt>平城→HeizeiHeijo-kyoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>平城は予想外の事態に驚き、東国へ逃れて再起しようとしたが、嵯峨の派遣した軍隊に進路を遮られて挫折、すべての権力を放棄して出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heijyo was surprised at the turn of events and tried to make a comeback by escaping to the East Country, but was blocked by armed forces sent by Saga and defeated, he then relinquished all authority and became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heijyo was surprised at the turn of events and tried to make a comeback by escaping to the East Country, but was blocked by armed forces sent by Saga and defeated, he then relinquished all authority and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizei was surprised at the turn of events and tried to make a comeback by escaping to the East Country, but was blocked by armed forces sent by Saga and defeated, he then relinquished all authority and became a priest.</e>
<cmt>平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>高岳も皇太子の地位を追われ、同じく出家している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takaoka was stripped of his position as Crown Prince and also became a priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takaoka was stripped of his position as Crown Prince and also became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takaoka was stripped of his position as Crown Prince and also became a priest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="160">
<j>嵯峨が高岳に代えて皇太子に立てたのは大伴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga installed Otomo instead of Takaoka as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga installed Otomo instead of Takaoka as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga installed Otomo instead of Takaoka as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>嵯峨に皇太子とすべき皇子がいないこともあったが、やはり大伴の権威と存在感を尊重したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Saga did not have any sons to select as Crown Prince anyway, it was a measure to respect the authority and existence of Otomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Saga did not have any sons to select as Crown Prince anyway, it was a measure to respect the authority and existence of Otomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Saga did not have any sons to select as Crown Prince anyway, it was a measure to respect the authority and existence of Otomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>平城との争いで大伴が嵯峨を支持した事情もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was also the circumstance that Otomo supported Saga in the conflict with Heijyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was also the circumstance that Otomo supported Saga in the conflict with Heijyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was also the circumstance that Otomo supported Saga in the conflict with Heizei.</e>
<cmt>平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>嵯峨は平城と対立し武力衝突にまで至った轍を踏まないよう、兄弟の融和に細心の注意を払い、大伴の立場を最大限尊重することに努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saga paid great care in reconciling between brothers and tried to respect Otomo&apos;s position as much as possible so as not to repeat the conflict with Heijo that ended in armed confrontation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saga paid great care in reconciling between brothers and tried to respect Otomo&apos;s position as much as possible so as not to repeat the conflict with Heijo that ended in armed confrontation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saga paid great care in reconciling between brothers and tried to respect Otomo&apos;s position as much as possible so as not to repeat the conflict with Heizei that ended in armed confrontation.</e>
<cmt>平城→Heizei</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>皇女正子内親王を大伴に嫁がせたこともそうであるが、その最大のものは、弘仁14年（824年）に大伴に譲位するに際して、もともと天皇が譲位とともに自動的にその地位につくものとされていた太上天皇の地位を辞退したことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One sign was to wed his princess Masako Naishinno to Otomo, but the most significant was when he abdicated the throne to Otomo in 824, he declined the position of ex-Emperor even if it was a position automatically assumed to be taken up by the abdicating emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One sign was to wed his princess Masako Naishinno to Otomo, but the most significant was when he abdicated the throne to Otomo in 824, he declined the position of ex-Emperor even if it was a position automatically assumed to be taken up by the abdicating emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One sign was to wed his princess, Imperial Princess Masako to Otomo, but the most significant was when he abdicated the throne to Otomo in 824, he declined the position of Retired Emperor even if it was a position automatically assumed to be taken up by the abdicating emperor.</e>
<cmt>Naishinno削除、Imperial Princessに訂正しました。ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired Empreor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>退位後は一皇族の地位に降り、後任の天皇となる大伴（淳和天皇）に全権力を委ねることを表明したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his abdication, he returned to his status as one of the royal family members, and publicly announced that he left all power to the coming emperor Otomo (Emperor Junna).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his abdication, he returned to his status as one of the royal family members, and publicly announced that he left all power to the coming emperor Otomo (Emperor Junna).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his abdication, he returned to his status as one of the Imperial family members, and publicly announced that he left all power to the coming Emperor Otomo (Emperor Junna).</e>
<cmt>royal→Imperialに訂正しました。Emperor大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>譲位を受けた淳和はもちろんこれを受け入れず、両者の間で押し問答があったが、結局、嵯峨がいったん太上天皇を辞退したうえで、あらためて淳和が嵯峨に太上天皇の称号と待遇を贈ることで決着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of course Junna who accepted the abdication did not accept this, and after serious discussions between the two, it was decided in the end that Saga was to decline the position of ex-emperor and then Junna was to present the title and privileges of ex-emperor to Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of course Junna who accepted the abdication did not accept this, and after serious discussions between the two, it was decided in the end that Saga was to decline the position of ex-emperor and then Junna was to present the title and privileges of ex-emperor to Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of course Junna who accepted the abdication did not accept this, and after serious discussions between the two, it was decided in the end that Saga was to decline the position of retired emperor and then Junna was to present the title and privileges of retired emperor to Saga.</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired Empreor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>このことで、太上天皇の地位は後任の天皇から与えられることに根拠を持つものに変質し、在位の天皇の優位性が確立して、二頭政治・二重権力の弊害は解消されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to a change in the position of ex-emperor as a position to be given by the coming emperor, and established the superiority of the residing emperor, relieving the harmful effects of diarchy/dual power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to a change in the position of ex-emperor as a position to be given by the coming emperor, and established the superiority of the residing emperor, relieving the harmful effects of diarchy/dual power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to a change in the position of retired emperor as a position to be given by the coming emperor, and established the superiority of the residing emperor, relieving the harmful effects of diarchy/dual power.</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired Empreor</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="168">
<j>嵯峨と淳和の融和と互譲はその後も続けられ、ことあるごとに強調された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reconciliation and mutual concession continued on, and was emphasized at every occasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reconciliation and mutual concession continued on, and was emphasized at every occasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reconciliation and mutual concession continued on, and was emphasized at every occasion.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>淳和の即位に際しては嵯峨と皇后橘嘉智子との間に生まれた皇子正良が皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the ascension of Junna, the prince Masara, who was born between Saga and Empress TACHIBANA-no-Kachiko, became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the ascension of Junna, the prince Masara, who was born between Saga and Empress TACHIBANA-no-Kachiko, became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the ascension of Junna, the prince Masara, who was born between Saga and Empress TACHIBANA no Kachiko, became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>天長10年（833年）に淳和が皇太子正良（仁明天皇）に譲位すると、ここでも淳和の太上天皇辞退・皇后正子の皇太后辞退と新天皇仁明による拒絶が繰り返され、皇太子には淳和と正子との間に生まれた皇子恒貞親王が立てられた（高志・恒世はともにすでに早世していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 833, Junna abdicated the throne to the Crow Prince Masara (Emperor Ninmyo) and here the declination of ex-emperor by Junna and ex-empress by Empress Masako and the refusal by the new Emperor Ninmyo was repeated, and the Crown Prince was decided to be the prince born between Junwa and Masako, Tsunesada Shinno (Takashi and Tsuneyo had already died young).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 833, Junna abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Masara (Emperor Ninmyo) and here the declination of ex-emperor by Junna and ex-empress by Empress Masako and the refusal by the new Emperor Ninmyo was repeated, and the Crown Prince was decided to be the prince born between Junwa and Masako, Tsunesada Shinno (Takashi and Tsuneyo had already died young).</e>
<cmt>Spelling,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 833, Junna abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Masara (Emperor Ninmyo) and here the declination of retired emperor by Junna and empress dowager by Empress Masako and the refusal by the new Emperor Ninmyo was repeated, and the Crown Prince was decided to be the prince born between Junna and Masako, Imperial Prince Tsunesada (Koshi and Tsuneyo had already died young).</e>
<cmt>ex-Emperor (Daijotenno)→the Retired Empreorex-empress→Empress DowagerJunnaに訂正ました。高志→KoshiShinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="171">
<j>しかし、このような嵯峨と淳和の関係は、あくまでも2人の個人的な信頼関係にとどまり、貴族たちの広く受け入れるところとはならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such relationship between Saga and Junna was only a personal relationship of trust and was not accepted widely among the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such relationship between Saga and Junna was only a personal relationship of trust and was not accepted widely among the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, such relationship between Saga and Junna was only a personal relationship of trust and was not accepted widely among the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>むしろ、貴族たちが嵯峨派と淳和派に分裂する傾向さえ見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rather, the aristocracy even showed a tendency to break apart into Saga-ha and Junna-ha.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather, the aristocracy even showed a tendency to break apart into Saga-ha and Junna-ha.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather, the aristocracy even showed a tendency to break apart into Saga group and Junna group.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。ha→groupに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>承和 (日本)7年（840年）に淳和が死去し、承和9年（842年）に嵯峨が危篤に陥ると、この分裂はたちまち表面化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Junna died in 840and Saga fell into critical condition, this break up became apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Junna died in 840 and Saga fell into critical condition, this break up became apparent.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Junna died in 840 and Saga fell into critical condition in 842, this break up became apparent.</e>
<cmt>年号を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>まず、春宮坊帯刀伴健岑と但馬権守橘逸勢の2人が、平城の皇子阿保親王のもとを訪れ、東国に赴いて叛乱を起こすことを勧めたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, it is said that Shungubo-Tachihaki, TOMO-no-Kowamine and the Governor of Tajima, TACHIBANA-no-Hayanari visited Heijyo&apos;s son, Abo Shinno and tried to convince him to go to the East and lead an insurrection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, it is said that Shungubo-Tachihaki, TOMO-no-Kowamine and the Governor of Tajima, TACHIBANA-no-Hayanari visited Heijyo&apos;s son, Abo Shinno and tried to convince him to go to the East and lead an insurrection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, it is said that Togu-bo Tachihaki, TOMO no Kowamine and Tajima no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Tajima Province), TACHIBANA no Hayanari visited Heizei&apos;s son, Imperial Prince Abo and tried to convince him to go to the East and lead an insurrection.</e>
<cmt>春宮坊帯刀→Togu-bo Tachihaki に訂正しました。名前のハイフン削除。但馬権守→Tajima no Gon no kami (Provisional Governor of Tajima Province) に訂正しました。平城→HeizeiShinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>阿保は、父の失脚のときに大宰権帥に左遷されて九州に移された苦い経験を持っていたので、このような話には乗らず、すぐに当時は太皇太后になっていた嘉智子に報告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abo had a bitter experience when his father was deposed and sent to Kyushu as Dazai-no-gonnosochi, did not follow their advice and immediately reported this to Kachiko, who was ex-empress at that time</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abo had a bitter experience when his father was deposed and sent to Kyushu as Dazai-no-gonnosochi, did not follow their advice and immediately reported this to Kachiko, who was ex-empress at that time</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abo had a bitter experience when his father was deposed and sent to Kyushu as Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices), did not follow their advice and immediately reported this to Kachiko, who was the Grand Empress Dowager at that time.</e>
<cmt>大宰権帥→Dazai gon no sochi (Provisional Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices)太皇太后→Grand Empress Dowagerピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>この間に嵯峨は死去している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Saga passed away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Saga passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Saga passed away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>嘉智子は中納言藤原良房を通じてこれを仁明に伝え、関係者の逮捕と処罰が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachiko informed Ninmyo via Chunagon, Yoshifusa FUJIWARA and the arrest and punishment of associated people began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kachiko informed Ninmyo via Chunagon, Yoshifusa FUJIWARA and the arrest and punishment of associated people began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kachiko informed Ninmyo via Chunagon (vice-councilor of state), FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and the arrest and punishment of associated people began.</e>
<cmt>(vice-councilor of state)補足。FUJIWARA no Yoshifusaに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>健岑と逸勢は容疑を否認したが結局流罪とされ、淳和に近い立場にいた貴族たちが解任され、ついには恒貞も連坐して皇太子の地位を追われ、かつての高岳と同じように出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kowamine and Hayanari both denied the charges but were exiled and aristocrats close to Junna were dismissed from office, and finally, Tsunesada was deposed as Crown Prince to take joint responsibility and he became a priest as Takaoka did in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kowamine and Hayanari both denied the charges but were exiled and aristocrats close to Junna were dismissed from office, and finally, Tsunesada was deposed as Crown Prince to take joint responsibility and he became a priest as Takaoka did in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kowamine and Hayanari both denied the charges but were exiled and aristocrats close to Junna were dismissed from office, and finally, Tsunesada was deposed as Crown Prince to take joint responsibility and he became a priest as Takaoka did in the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>この事件を承和の変と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident is the &quot;Jowa Incident&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident is the &quot;Jowa Incident&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident is the &quot;Jowa Incident.&quot;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>首謀者である健岑と逸勢の地位が、このような謀反を計画するにはあまりにも低く（また、家系的にも傍流出身で「藤原氏による他氏排斥」の対象にもなり得ない）、また計画に関与したとしたとして処罰された人々も叛乱に荷担する動機が見当たらないことから、事件自体をでっちあげとみなす説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the positions of the chief plotters, Kowamine and Hayanari, were so low (and also from branch lines of lineages that would not even be a target for &quot;elimination of other clans by the Fujiwara clan&quot;) for planning such an insurrection and the people who were punished for being associated with the plan had no motives, there is a theory that proposes that the whole incident was made up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the positions of the chief plotters, Kowamine and Hayanari, were so low (and also from branch lines of lineages that would not even be a target for &quot;elimination of other clans by the Fujiwara clan&quot;) for planning such an insurrection and the people who were punished for being associated with the plan had no motives, there is a theory that proposes that the whole incident was made up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the positions of the chief plotters, Kowamine and Hayanari, were so low (and also from branch lines of lineages that would not even be a target for &apos;elimination of other clans by the Fujiwara clan&apos;) for planning such an insurrection and the people who were punished for being associated with the plan had no motives, there is a theory that proposes that the whole incident was made up.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて”を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>いずれにせよ、次の皇太子には仁明の第1皇子道康（のちの文徳天皇）が立てられ、皇統は嵯峨の子孫に一本化されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, the next Crown Prince was Ninmyo&apos;s first son, Michiyasu (later Emperor Buntoku), and the Imperial line was united to the descendants of Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, the next Crown Prince was Ninmyo&apos;s first son, Michiyasu (later Emperor Buntoku), and the Imperial line was united to the descendants of Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, the next Crown Prince was Ninmyo&apos;s first son, Michiyasu (later Emperor Montoku), and the Imperial line was united to the descendants of Saga.</e>
<cmt>文徳天皇→Emperor Montoku に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>道康の母藤原順子の兄である良房の権力掌握のきっかけとなった事件でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was also the opportunity for Michiyasu&apos;s mother, Junshi FUJIWARA&apos;s older brother Yoshifusa to grab hold of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident was also the opportunity for Michiyasu&apos;s mother, Junshi FUJIWARA&apos;s older brother Yoshifusa to grab hold of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident was also the opportunity for Michiyasu&apos;s mother, FUJIWARA no Junshi&apos;s older brother Yoshifusa to grab hold of power.</e>
<cmt>藤原順子→FUJIWARA no Junshi に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="183">
<j>冷泉流と円融流の迭立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tetsuritsu of Reizei-ryu and Enyu-ryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tetsuritsu of Reizei-ryu and Enyu-ryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tetsuritsu of Reizei line and Enyu line</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。ryu→line</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>天慶9年（946年）に即位した村上天皇は、天暦4年（950年）に第2皇子憲平が生まれるとすぐに皇太子に立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As soon as Emperor Murakami ascended in 946, he placed a Crown Prince as soon as his second son Norihira was born in 950.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As soon as Emperor Murakami ascended in 946, he placed a Crown Prince as soon as his second son Norihira was born in 950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As soon as Emperor Murakami ascended in 946, he placed a Crown Prince as soon as his second son Norihira was born in 950.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>同年に生まれた第1皇子広平親王が中納言藤原元方の娘藤原祐姫を母としていたのに対し、憲平は右大臣藤原師輔の娘藤原安子を母としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whereas the first son Hirohira Shinno was born in the same year to Chunagon FUJIWARA-no-Motokata&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Sukehime, Norihira&apos;s mother was Udaijin FUJIWARA-no-Morosuke&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Anshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas the first son Hirohira Shinno was born in the same year to Chunagon FUJIWARA-no-Motokata&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Sukehime, Norihira&apos;s mother was Udaijin FUJIWARA-no-Morosuke&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Anshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas the first son Imperial Prince Hirohira was born in the same year to Chunagon FUJIWARA no Motokata&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Sukehime, Norihira&apos;s mother was Udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Morosuke&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Anshi.</e>
<cmt>Shinno削除、Imperial Prince補足しました。ハイフン削除。(minister of the right)説明補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>村上は、次期天皇の外戚としてあえて師輔を選んだことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Murakami selected Morosuke as the maternal relative for the next Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Murakami selected Morosuke as the maternal relative for the next Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Murakami selected Morosuke as the maternal relative for the next Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>安子は皇太子の母であることにより天徳 (日本)2年（958年）に皇后に立てられ、村上の寵愛も篤かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 985, Anshi became Empress because she was the Crown Prince&apos;s mother and also was Murakami&apos;s favorite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 985, Anshi became Empress because she was the Crown Prince&apos;s mother and also was Murakami&apos;s favorite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 958, Anshi became Empress because she was the Crown Prince&apos;s mother and also was Murakami&apos;s favorite.</e>
<cmt>958に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>憲平は、村上の先代朱雀天皇のひとり娘である昌子内親王と結婚し、その立場はさらに強化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Norihira married Shoshi Naishinno, the only daughter of Emperor Suzaku, who was the emperor before Murakami, and strengthen his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Norihira married Shoshi Naishinno, the only daughter of Emperor Suzaku, who was the emperor before Murakami, and strengthened his position.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Norihira married Imperial Princess Shoshi, the only daughter of Emperor Suzaku, who was the emperor before Murakami, and strengthened his position.</e>
<cmt>Naishinno削除、Imperial Princessに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>しかし、成長するにつれて憲平の精神はしだいに変調をきたし、狂気の兆候をあらわすようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as he grew up, the mental state of Norihira was altered and he started to show signs of madness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as he grew up, the mental state of Norihira was altered and he started to show signs of madness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as he grew up, the mental state of Norihira was altered and he started to show signs of madness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>それでも、皇后の長男であり、先帝の女婿であり、有力な外戚に支えられた憲平を廃嫡する決断は村上には結局できなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since he was the first son of the Empress and the son-in-law of the previous Emperor, with support from influential maternal relatives, Murakami could not make the decision to disinherit Norihira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since he was the first son of the Empress and the son-in-law of the previous Emperor, with support from influential maternal relatives, Murakami could not make the decision to disinherit Norihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since he was the first son of the Empress and the son-in-law of the previous Emperor, with support from influential maternal relatives, Murakami could not make the decision to disinherit Norihira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>村上は康保4年（967年）に死去し、18歳の憲平が践祚した（冷泉天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murakami died in 967, and Norihira ascended the throne at 18 (Emperor Reizen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murakami died in 967, and Norihira ascended the throne at 18 (Emperor Reizen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murakami died in 967, and Norihira ascended the throne at 18 (Emperor Reizei).</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="192">
<j>冷泉の狂気はすでに誰の目にもあきらかな状態に至っており、その在位は短期間であることが当初から予測されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reizen&apos;s madness was already apparent to everyone and it was predicted from the beginning that his rule would be short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reizen&apos;s madness was already apparent to everyone and it was predicted from the beginning that his rule would be short.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reizei&apos;s madness was already apparent to everyone and it was predicted from the beginning that his rule would be short.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>冷泉には皇后となった昌子のほか、藤原伊尹（師輔の長男）の娘藤原懐子ら複数の妻がいたがまだ皇子がなく、皇太子の人選が急がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than Shoshi who became Empress, Reizen had various wives such as FUJIWARA-no-Koretada (FUJIWARA-no-Motokata&apos;s first son) &apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Kaishi, but there were no sons yet and the selection of a Crown Prince was of immediate concern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Shoshi who became Empress, Reizen had various wives such as FUJIWARA-no-Koretada (FUJIWARA-no-Motokata&apos;s first son) &apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Kaishi, but there were no sons yet and the selection of a Crown Prince was of immediate concern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than Shoshi who became Empress, Reizei had various wives such as FUJIWARA no Koretada (FUJIWARA no Motokata&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kaishi, but there were no sons yet and the selection of a Crown Prince was of immediate concern.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>このような場合にまず候補となるのは冷泉の同母弟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, the candidates are Reizen&apos;s half-brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, the candidates are Reizen&apos;s half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, the candidates are Reizei&apos;s half-brothers.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>候補者には、2歳年下の為平と9歳年下の守平の2人がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two candidates, Tamehira, who was 2 years younger, and Morihira, who was 9 years younger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two candidates, Tamehira, who was 2 years younger, and Morihira, who was 9 years younger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two candidates, Tamehira, who was 2 years younger, and Morihira, who was 9 years younger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>結局、康保4年（967年）に守平が皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, Morihira was named Crown Prince in 967.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Morihira was named Crown Prince in 967.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Morihira was named Crown Prince in 967.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>為平が源高明の女婿であることから、藤原氏の貴族たちに忌避されたとするのが通説であるが、冷泉と年齢の近い為平を皇太子とした場合、冷泉の在位が短期間になりすぎることに配慮したものとする説（保立道久）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The usual theory is that the Fujiwara clan aristocrats did not want Tamehira since he was MINAMOTO-no-Takaaki&apos;s son-in-law, but there is also the theory that it was taken into consideration that if Tamehira, who is close in age with Reizen was selected as Crown Prince, the rule of Reizen may be too short (Michihisa HODACHI).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The usual theory is that the Fujiwara clan aristocrats did not want Tamehira since he was MINAMOTO-no-Takaaki&apos;s son-in-law, but there is also the theory that it was taken into consideration that if Tamehira, who is close in age with Reizen was selected as Crown Prince, the rule of Reizen may be too short (Michihisa HODACHI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The usual theory is that the Fujiwara clan aristocrats did not want Tamehira since he was MINAMOTO no Takaaki&apos;s son-in-law, but there is also the theory that it was taken into consideration that if Tamehira, who is close in age with Reizei was selected as Crown Prince, the rule of Reizei may be too short (Michihisa HODACHI).</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="198">
<j>安和元年（968年）、懐子が冷泉の第1皇子師貞を出産した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 968, Kaishi gave birth to Reizen&apos;s first prince, Morosada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 968, Kaishi gave birth to Reizen&apos;s first prince, Morosada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 968, Kaishi gave birth to Reizei&apos;s first prince, Morosada.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>このことは、かえって冷泉の譲位を早めることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This actually shortened the period until the abdication of Reizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This actually shortened the period until the abdication of Reizen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This in fact shortened the period until the abdication of Reizei.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>冷泉が譲位しても、引き続き冷泉の子孫が皇統を維持する見通しが立ったからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because now there was a chance for Reizen&apos;s descendants to continue the Imperial line even after Reizen&apos;s abdication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because now there was a chance for Reizen&apos;s descendants to continue the Imperial line even after Reizen&apos;s abdication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because now there was a chance for Reizei&apos;s descendants to continue the Imperial line even after Reizei&apos;s abdication.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>安和2年（969年）、冷泉は皇太子守平（円融天皇）に譲位し、次の皇太子には師貞が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 969, Reizen abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Morihira (Emperor Enyu) and Morosada became the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 969, Reizen abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Morihira (Emperor Enyu) and Morosada became the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 969, Reizei abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Morihira (Emperor Enyu) and Morosada became the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>円融は、のちの鎌倉時代の花園や後醍醐と同様の“中継ぎ”の天皇とされたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enyu was an &quot;interim&quot; Emperor, similar to Hanazono and Go-Daigo in the later Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enyu was an &quot;interim&quot; Emperor, similar to Hanazono and Go-Daigo in the later Kamakura Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enyu was an &quot;interim&quot; Emperor, similar to Hanazono and Godaigo in the later Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。名前表記の訂正しました。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="203">
<j>しかし、花園や後醍醐のケースと異なり、冷泉と円融のケースでは、父村上、母安子、外祖父師輔がいずれもすでに死去しており、皇位継承をコントロールする親権者が存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Reizen and Enyu&apos;s case, different from Hanazono and Go-Daigo, father Murakami, mother Anshi, male relative Morosuke were all dead and there was no guardian to control the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in Reizen and Enyu&apos;s case, different from Hanazono and Go-Daigo, father Murakami, mother Anshi, male relative Morosuke were all dead and there was no guardian to control the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in Reizei and Enyu&apos;s case, different from Hanazono and Godaigo, father Murakami, mother Anshi, male relative Morosuke were all dead and there was no guardian to control the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>冷泉天皇→Emperor Reizei に訂正しました。名前表記の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>さらにこの時期、師輔の弟藤原師尹、兄藤原実頼、長男伊尹が相次いで死去し、次代の外戚の地位をめぐって実頼・師輔・師尹の子どもたちの世代の貴族たちが相争う状況が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this time, Morosuke&apos;s younger bother Morotada, older brother, FUJIWARA-no-Michiyori, first son Koretada, had died consecutively and a situation were the aristocrats in the generation of children of Michiyori, Morosuke, Morotada fought amongst themselves to obtain the position as the next maternal relative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time, Morosuke&apos;s younger bother Morotada, older brother, FUJIWARA-no-Michiyori, first son Koretada, had died consecutively and a situation were the aristocrats in the generation of children of Michiyori, Morosuke, Morotada fought amongst themselves to obtain the position as the next maternal relative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time, Morosuke&apos;s younger bother Morotada, older brother, FUJIWARA no Saneyori, first son Koretada, had died consecutively and a situation were the aristocrats in the generation of children of Saneyori, Morosuke, Morotada fought amongst themselves to obtain the position as the next maternal relative.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。藤原実頼→FUJIWARA no Saneyori に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>円融もこのような権力の空白状況のなかで、新皇統を確立する可能性のある候補者として注目され、藤原兼通（師輔の次男）の娘藤原こう子、藤原頼忠（実頼の長男）の娘藤原遵子、藤原兼家（師輔の三男）の娘東三条院ら、皇后となり皇太子を産むにふさわしい身分の妻と有力な外戚の後ろ盾を得ることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this situation where there was a power vacuum, Enyu attracted attention as a candidate to establish a new Imperial lineage and was able to obtain wives with high lineage who could become empress and give birth to a crown prince, such as FUJIWARA-no-Kanemichi(Morosuke&apos;s second son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Koshi,FUJIWARA-no-Yoritada (Mitsuyori&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Junshi, FUJIWARA-no-Kaneie (Morosute&apos;s third son)&apos;s daughter, Higashisanjyo-in and also the support of influential maternal relatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this situation where there was a power vacuum, Enyu attracted attention as a candidate to establish a new Imperial lineage and was able to obtain wives with high lineage who could become empress and give birth to a crown prince, such as FUJIWARA-no-Kanemichi(Morosuke&apos;s second son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Koshi,FUJIWARA-no-Yoritada (Mitsuyori&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Junshi, FUJIWARA-no-Kaneie (Morosute&apos;s third son)&apos;s daughter, Higashisanjyo-in and also the support of influential maternal relatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this situation where there was a power vacuum, Enyu attracted attention as a candidate to establish a new Imperial lineage and was able to obtain wives with high lineage who could become empress and give birth to a crown prince, such as FUJIWARA no Kanemichi (Morosuke&apos;s second son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Koshi,FUJIWARA no Yoritada (Saneyori&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Junshi, FUJIWARA no Kaneie (Morosute&apos;s third son)&apos;s daughter, Higashisanjyoin and also the support of influential maternal relatives.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。スペース補足。藤原実頼→FUJIWARA no Saneyori に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>円融も独自の皇統を創始する意欲を強く持っており、また、最初に皇后とした媓子の死後、皇子懐仁を産んだ詮子をさしおいて、皇子のいない遵子を皇后に立てるなど、貴族たちを手玉に取るような行動にも出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enyu also wanted to establish his own imperial line and after the death of the first Empress Koshi, skipping Senshi who was the mother of the prince Yasuhito, he made the childless Junko Empress and acted as if he was leading the aristocrats around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enyu also wanted to establish his own imperial line and after the death of the first Empress Koshi, skipping Senshi who was the mother of the prince Yasuhito, he made the childless Junko Empress and acted as if he was leading the aristocrats around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enyu also wanted to establish his own imperial line and after the death of the first Empress Koshi, skipping Senshi who was the mother of the prince Yasuhito, he made the childless Junshi Empress and acted as if he was leading the aristocrats around.</e>
<cmt>遵子→Junshi に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="207">
<j>この行動は、兼家・詮子父子の憤激を招き、詮子の内裏退出と兼家一家の政務ボイコットという事態に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This behavior made father Kaneie and daugther Senshi angry, leading to Senshi leaving the Imperial Palace and Kaneie&apos;s family boycotting administration duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This behavior made father Kaneie and daugther Senshi angry, leading to Senshi leaving the Imperial Palace and Kaneie&apos;s family boycotting administration duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This behavior made father Kaneie and daughter Senshi angry, leading to Senshi leaving the Imperial Palace and Kaneie&apos;s family boycotting administration duties.</e>
<cmt>daughterスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>円融と兼家は対立の末にひとつの妥協点を見出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the confrontation, Enyu and Kaneie reached a compromise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the confrontation, Enyu and Kaneie reached a compromise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the confrontation, Enyu and Kaneie reached a compromise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>円融が譲位する代わりに、懐仁を皇太子に立てるというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was for Enyu to abdicate and place Yasuhito as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was for Enyu to abdicate and place Yasuhito as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was for Enyu to abdicate and place Yasuhito as Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>円融は子息の皇位継承を確実なものにして“中継ぎ”の立場を脱することに成功し、兼家は外孫を皇太子にすることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enyu was able to escape the position of &quot;interim&quot; by establishing his descendants as successors to the Imperial title and Kaneie was able to become the maternal grandfather to a crown prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enyu was able to escape the position of &quot;interim&quot; by establishing his descendants as successors to the Imperial title and Kaneie was able to become the maternal grandfather to a crown prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enyu was able to escape the position of &quot;interim&quot; by establishing his descendants as successors to the Imperial title and Kaneie was able to become the maternal grandfather to a crown prince.</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>両者にとって大きなメリットのある妥協であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a compromise that had large benefits to both sides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a compromise that had large benefits to both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a compromise that had large benefits to both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="212">
<j>こうして永観2年（984年）、円融は皇太子師貞に譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hence in 984, Enyu abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Morosada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence in 984, Enyu abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Morosada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence in 984, Enyu abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Morosada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>次の皇太子には懐仁が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next Crown Prince was Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next Crown Prince was Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next Crown Prince was Yasuhito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>即位した師貞（花山天皇）は、外祖父伊尹がすでに死去し、外戚関係にない頼忠が関白の地位にあることを踏まえ、伊尹の長男藤原義懐と乳母子の藤原惟成を相談役として、関白に政務を委任することなく積極的に親政を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morosada (Emperor Kazan)&apos;s maternal grandfather Koretada had already died and Yoritada who had no maternal relative relations was Kanpaku (chancellor), he actively ruled without delegation to the Kanpaku with Koretada&apos;s first son, FUJIWARA-no-Yoshichika&apos;s and FUJIWARA-no-Korenari, son of his nurse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morosada (Emperor Kazan)&apos;s maternal grandfather Koretada had already died and Yoritada who had no maternal relative relations was Kanpaku (chancellor), he actively ruled without delegation to the Kanpaku with Koretada&apos;s first son, FUJIWARA-no-Yoshichika&apos;s and FUJIWARA-no-Korenari, son of his nurse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morosada (Emperor Kazan)&apos;s maternal grandfather Koretada had already died and Yoritada who had no maternal relative relations was Kanpaku (chancellor), he actively ruled without delegation to the Kanpaku with Koretada&apos;s first son, FUJIWARA no Yoshichika and son of his nurse, FUJIWARA no Korenari.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。&apos;s削除。語順訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>新立荘園の停止、貨幣流通の促進、物価の公定などの新政策が次々に打ち出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New political measures such as the termination of creating new private estates, promotion of circulation of coinage, public determination of selling prices, etc. was announced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New political measures such as the termination of creating new private estates, promotion of circulation of coinage, public determination of selling prices, etc. were announced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New political measures such as the termination of creating new private estates, promotion of circulation of coinage, public determination of selling prices, etc. were announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="216">
<j>しかし、花山は父の血を受け継いだのか、性格に異常なところがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, perhaps Kazan inherited his father&apos;s blood, but he had an abnormal personality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, perhaps Kazan inherited his father&apos;s blood, but he had an abnormal personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, perhaps Kazan inherited his father&apos;s blood, but he had an abnormal personality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>それは特に女性関係に現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was especially apparent with his relationship with women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was especially apparent with his relationship with women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was especially apparent with his relationship with women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>特定の女性に執着して異常に深く寵愛しながら、やがて飽きて別の女性に寵愛を移す、ということが繰り返された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became extremely and abnormally attached to a certain woman, eventually getting sick of her and then he would be attracted to a different woman, and this cycle went on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became extremely and abnormally attached to a certain woman, eventually getting sick of her and then he would be attracted to a different woman, and this cycle went on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became extremely and abnormally attached to a certain woman, eventually getting sick of her and then he would be attracted to a different woman, and this cycle went on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>寛和2年（986年）、当時花山の寵愛をほしいままにしていた女御藤原し子（藤原為光の娘）が病死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 986, Nyogo FUJIWARA-no-Shishi (daughter of FUJIWARA-no-Tamemitsu), who had all of Kazan&apos;s attention at that time, died of disease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 986, Nyogo FUJIWARA-no-Shishi (daughter of FUJIWARA-no-Tamemitsu), who had all of Kazan&apos;s attention at that time, died of disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 986, Nyogo (a consort of an emperor) FUJIWARA no Shishi (daughter of FUJIWARA no Tamemitsu), who had all of Kazan&apos;s attention at that time, died of disease.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。(a consort of an emperor)説明補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>忯子は妊娠中であったが、出産準備のため実家に戻ろうとしたのを花山が無理に引き止めたため体調を崩して死に至ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Shishi was pregnant and wanted to go back to her parent&apos;s home to have the baby, but Kazan forcefully kept her in court, which led to her getting ill and eventually dying.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Shishi was pregnant and wanted to go back to her parent&apos;s home to have the baby, but Kazan forcefully kept her in court, which led to her getting ill and eventually dying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Shishi was pregnant and wanted to go back to her parent&apos;s home to have the baby, but Kazan forcefully kept her in court, which led to her getting ill and eventually dying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>花山の悲しみは尋常ではなく、出家遁世を考えるほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sadness of Kazan was abnormal and he even thought about becoming a priest and retiring from the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sadness of Kazan was abnormal and he even thought about becoming a priest and retiring from the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sadness of Kazan was abnormal and he even thought about becoming a priest and retiring from the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>花山の幼なじみであった藤原道兼（兼家の三男）の教唆もあって花山はついに出家を決意、夜陰に乗じて内裏を抜け出し、道兼に付き添われて山科の元慶寺（花山寺）に赴き剃髪した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the solicitation of Kazan&apos;s childhood friend FUJIWARA-no-Michikane (Kaneie&apos;s third son), Kazan finally decided on becoming a priest, escaping the court in the cover of darkness and went to Gankei-ji Temple (Kazan-ji Temple) in Yamashina, Kyoto together with Michikane to have his hair shaved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the solicitation of Kazan&apos;s childhood friend FUJIWARA-no-Michikane (Kaneie&apos;s third son), Kazan finally decided on becoming a priest, escaping the court in the cover of darkness and went to Gankei-ji Temple (Kazan-ji Temple) in Yamashina, Kyoto together with Michikane to have his head shaved.</e>
<cmt>&quot;hair&quot; changed to &quot;head&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the solicitation of Kazan&apos;s childhood friend FUJIWARA no Michikane (Kaneie&apos;s third son), Kazan finally decided on becoming a priest, escaping the court in the cover of darkness and went to Gankei-ji Temple (Kazan-ji Temple) in Yamashina, Kyoto together with Michikane to have his head shaved.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>出家により花山は自動的に退位したことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By becoming a priest, Kazan was automatically considered to have abdicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By becoming a priest, Kazan was automatically considered to have abdicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By becoming a priest, Kazan was automatically considered to have abdicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>道兼の行動はもちろん父兼家と示し合わせてのものであり、花山が元慶寺へ向かう道筋は兼家が派遣した武士たちにより警備されており、道兼が花山とともに出家させられそうになったときは武士たちが実力で救出する手はずになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michikane&apos;s activity was obviously planned together with his father Kaneie, and the path to Gankei-ji temple was guarded by bushi sent by Kaneie, and if Michikane was about to be made a priest with Kazan, the bushi were supposed to rescue him by force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michikane&apos;s activity was obviously planned together with his father Kaneie, and the path to Gankei-ji temple was guarded by bushi sent by Kaneie, and if Michikane was about to be made a priest with Kazan, the bushi were supposed to rescue him by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michikane&apos;s activity was obviously planned together with his father Kaneie, and the path to Gankei-ji Temple was guarded by bushi sent by Kaneie, and if Michikane was about to be made a priest with Kazan, the bushi were supposed to rescue him by force.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>兼家自身は天皇不在の内裏に深夜参入し、大急ぎで譲位の手続きを進めて翌朝には皇太子懐仁（一条天皇）を践祚させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie himself arrived in the middle of the night at the Imperial Palace without its emperor to quickly do the administrative work necessary for abdication and the next morning, he had the Crown Prince Yasuhito (Emperor Ichijo) ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie himself arrived in the middle of the night at the Imperial Palace without its emperor to quickly do the administrative work necessary for abdication and the next morning, he had the Crown Prince Yasuhito (Emperor Ichijo) ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie himself arrived in the middle of the night at the Imperial Palace without its emperor to quickly do the administrative work necessary for abdication and the next morning, he had the Crown Prince Yasuhito (Emperor Ichijo) ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>兼家は新天皇の外祖父として頼忠に代わって摂政となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie was the new Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather and became regent instead of Yoritada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie was the new Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather and became regent instead of Yoritada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie was the new Emperor&apos;s maternal grandfather and became regent instead of Yoritada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="227">
<j>まだ7歳の一条に当然皇子はなく、また一条は円融の唯一の皇子であったから、皇太子は冷泉の皇子から選ぶほかなく、兼家の娘藤原超子が産んだ冷泉の第2皇子居貞が皇太子となり、ここに両統迭立の状況が出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ichijo was 7 years old and obviously did not have a son, and since Ichijo was Enyu&apos;s only son, the Crown Prince had to be selected from among Reizen&apos;s sons, and because Reizen&apos;s second son, Okisada, whose mother was Kaneie&apos;s daughter FUJIWARA-no- Choshi, a Ryototetsuritsu situation arose.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ichijo was 7 years old and obviously did not have a son, and since Ichijo was Enyu&apos;s only son, the Crown Prince had to be selected from among Reizen&apos;s sons, and because Reizen&apos;s second son, Okisada, whose mother was Kaneie&apos;s daughter FUJIWARA-no- Choshi, a Ryototetsuritsu situation arose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ichijo was 7 years old and obviously did not have a son, and since Ichijo was Enyu&apos;s only son, the Crown Prince had to be selected from among Reizei&apos;s sons, and because Reizei&apos;s second son, Okisada, whose mother was Kaneie&apos;s daughter FUJIWARA no Choshi, a Ryoto tetsuritsu situation arose.</e>
<cmt>Reizen→Reizei に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>居貞は一条より4歳年上であり「老東宮」などと揶揄された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okisada was 4 years older than Ichijo and was ridiculed as &quot;Ro-togu&quot;(elderly crown prince&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okisada was 4 years older than Ichijo and was ridiculed as &quot;Ro-togu&quot;(elderly crown prince&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okisada was 4 years older than Ichijo and was ridiculed as &apos;Ro-togu&apos; (elderly crown prince).</e>
<cmt>”を&apos;に訂正しました。)補足。”削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>兼家は天皇と皇太子の外祖父を一身に兼ね、絶大な権力を掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie was both the Emperor and Crown Prince&apos;s maternal grandfather and had obtained absolute power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie was both the Emperor and Crown Prince&apos;s maternal grandfather and had obtained absolute power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie was both the Emperor and Crown Prince&apos;s maternal grandfather and had obtained absolute power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>円融も幼帝の父として一定の政治的影響力を獲得し“院政”的な状況を生み出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enyu also obtained a certain degree of political clout by being the young emperor&apos;s father, leading to a &quot;cloister government&quot;-like situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enyu also obtained a certain degree of political clout by being the young emperor&apos;s father, leading to a &quot;cloistered government&quot;-like situation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;ed&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enyu also obtained a certain degree of political clout by being the young emperor&apos;s father, leading to a &quot;cloistered government&quot;-like situation.</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="231">
<j>永祚 (日本)2年（989年）に兼家が、翌正暦2年（990年）に円融が相次いで死去し、円融即位直後の“親権者不在”の状況が再現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie in 989, Enyu in 990 died consecutively and there was a situation of &quot;no guardian&quot; similar to that immediately after Enyu&apos;s ascension to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie in 989, Enyu in 990 died consecutively and there was a situation of &quot;no guardian&quot; similar to that immediately after Enyu&apos;s ascension to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie in 989, Enyu in 990 died consecutively and there was a situation of &quot;no guardian&quot; similar to that immediately after Enyu&apos;s ascension to the throne.</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>違ったのは、一条の母詮子がなお健在だったことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The circumstance was different in that Ichijo&apos;s mother Senshi was still healthy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The circumstance was different in that Ichijo&apos;s mother Senshi was still healthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The circumstance was different in that Ichijo&apos;s mother Senshi was still healthy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>兼家の跡は長男藤原道隆が継ぎ、娘藤原定子を后位に空席がないにもかかわらず強引に皇后に立てるなど、一時は強力な権力を振るったが、長徳元年（995年）に病死、跡を継いだ道兼も道隆に1ヶ月ほど遅れて病死し、道隆の嫡男藤原伊周と兼家の四男藤原道長が跡目を争った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaneie&apos;s first son FUJIWARA-no-Michitaka took Kaneie&apos;s place and even though for a while he acted with absolute authority such as there being no opening as empress but forcibly making his daughter FUJIWARA-no-Teishi as Empress, he died in 995, and his heir Michikane died about one month after Michitaka, leaving Michitaka&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA-no-Korechika and Kaneie&apos;s fourth son FUJIWARA-no-Michinaga to fight over the position of family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaneie&apos;s first son FUJIWARA-no-Michitaka took Kaneie&apos;s place and even though for a while he acted with absolute authority such as there being no opening as empress but forcibly making his daughter FUJIWARA-no-Teishi as Empress, he died in 995, and his heir Michikane died about one month after Michitaka, leaving Michitaka&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA-no-Korechika and Kaneie&apos;s fourth son FUJIWARA-no-Michinaga to fight over the position of family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaneie&apos;s first son FUJIWARA no Michitaka took Kaneie&apos;s place and even though for a while he acted with absolute authority such as there being no opening as empress but forcibly making his daughter FUJIWARA no Teishi as Empress, he died in 995, and his heir Michikane died about one month after Michitaka, leaving Michitaka&apos;s heir, FUJIWARA no Korechika and Kaneie&apos;s fourth son FUJIWARA no Michinaga to fight over the position of family head.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>結局、詮子の支持を受けた道長が最終的な勝利を手にし、内覧の地位に就いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, Michinaga, who had Senshi&apos;s support, gained the position and became Nairan (position allowing first glance of any documents to be sent to the emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Michinaga, who had Senshi&apos;s support, gained the position and became Nairan (position allowing first glance of any documents to be sent to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Michinaga, who had Senshi&apos;s support, gained the position and became Nairan (position allowing first glance of any documents to be sent to the emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="235">
<j>道長はその後、伊周の起こした不祥事に乗じて伊周を大宰権帥に左遷し、娘上東門院を一条の皇后として、権力を磐石のものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga later sent Korechika away as Dazai-no-gonnosochi seizing the opportunity of Korechika&apos;s misconduct and had his daughter Jotomon-in (Shoshi) become Ichijo&apos;s Empress, consolidating his power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga later sent Korechika away as Dazai-no-gonnosochi seizing the opportunity of Korechika&apos;s misconduct and had his daughter Jotomon-in (Shoshi) become Ichijo&apos;s Empress, consolidating his power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga later sent Korechika away as Dazai gon no sochi seizing the opportunity of Korechika&apos;s misconduct and had his daughter Jotomonin (Shoshi) become Ichijo&apos;s Empress, consolidating his power.</e>
<cmt>大宰権帥→Dazai gon no sochi 前出に合わせて訂正しました。ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="236">
<j>政局がもっぱら一条を中心として展開してゆくなかで、皇太子居貞は孤立しており、皇統としての冷泉流の劣勢はあきらかだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the political scene was centered with Ichijo, Crown Prince Okisada was isolated and it was clear that Reizen-ryu was the inferior Imperial line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the political scene was centered with Ichijo, Crown Prince Okisada was isolated and it was clear that Reizen-ryu was the inferior Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the political scene was centered with Ichijo, Crown Prince Okisada was isolated and it was clear that Reizei line was the inferior Imperial line.</e>
<cmt>Reizen→Reizei に訂正しました。ハイフン削除。ryu→line</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="237">
<j>狂気の父冷泉はもちろん、政治に関心を失い、信仰にのめりこむ一方で、遊興と漁色にふけることも忘れない兄花山もまったく頼りにならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neither his father Reizen, who was mad, nor his older brother Kazan, who had lost interest in politics and dabbled in religion, but also enjoyed taking pleasures and philandering, were able to offer any support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neither his father Reizen, who was mad, nor his older brother Kazan, who had lost interest in politics and dabbled in religion, but also enjoyed taking pleasures and philandering, were able to offer any support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neither his father Reizei, who was mad, nor his older brother Kazan, who had lost interest in politics and dabbled in religion, but also enjoyed taking pleasures and philandering, were able to offer any support.</e>
<cmt>Reizen→Reizei に訂正しました。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>居貞は藤原済時（師尹の長男）の娘藤原せい子と道隆の娘藤原原子を妻としていたが、済時と道隆は長徳元年に揃って死去してしまい、居貞は有力な外戚の後ろ盾を得ることもできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okisada had FUJIWARA-no-Naritoki (Morotada&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Seishi and Michitaka&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Genshi as wives, but Naritoki and Michitaka both died in 995, and Okisada had no influential maternal relative for support.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okisada had FUJIWARA-no-Naritoki (Morotada&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Seishi and Michitaka&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Genshi as wives, but Naritoki and Michitaka both died in 995, and Okisada had no influential maternal relative for support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okisada had FUJIWARA no Naritoki (Morotada&apos;s first son)&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Seishi and Michitaka&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Genshi as wives, but Naritoki and Michitaka both died in 995, and Okisada had no influential maternal relative for support.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>しかも原子は長保4年（1002年）に子どもを遺さずに死去してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Genshi died in 1002 without any children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Genshi died in 1002 without any children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Genshi died in 1002 without any children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>また、一条がわずか11歳で入内した彰子が皇子を産むのを待ち続けた結果、居貞は皇太子のまま25年も即位を待たされることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okisada had to wait for 25 years before accession because Ichijo waited for Shoshi, who entered the court when she was 11, to have a prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okisada had to wait for 25 years before accession because Ichijo waited for Shoshi, who entered the court when she was 11, to have a prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okisada had to wait for 25 years before accession because Ichijo waited for Shoshi, who entered the court when she was 11, to have a prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="241">
<j>寛弘8年（1011年）、一条は死に臨んでようやく皇太子居貞（三条天皇）に譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1011, Ichijo was nearing death and finally abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Okisada (Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1011, Ichijo was nearing death and finally abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Okisada (Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1011, Ichijo was nearing death and finally abdicated the throne to the Crown Prince Okisada (Emperor Sanjo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>次の皇太子には、彰子が産んだ一条の第2皇子敦成が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next Crown Prince was Shoshi&apos;s second prince Atsunari.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next Crown Prince was Shoshi&apos;s second prince Atsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next Crown Prince was Shoshi&apos;s second prince Atsunari.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>次代の天皇の外祖父の地位を確保した道長は三条の早期の譲位を望み、両者の折り合いは悪かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michinaga had obtained the position of maternal grandfather of the next emperor and wished for the early abdication of Sanjo, hence the relationship between the two was rocky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michinaga had obtained the position of maternal grandfather of the next emperor and wished for the early abdication of Sanjo, hence the relationship between the two was rocky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michinaga had obtained the position of maternal grandfather of the next emperor and wished for the early abdication of Sanjo, hence the relationship between the two was rocky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>一方で、道長は娘藤原妍子を三条の皇后にしようとして、長年連れ添った娍子を尊重する三条とさらに軋轢を生じさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Michinaga tried to have his daughter FUJIWARA-no-Kenshi as Sanjo&apos;s Empress and this did not improve their relationship because Sanjo respected FUJIWARA-no-Seshi, who he had been together for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Michinaga tried to have his daughter FUJIWARA-no-Kenshi as Sanjo&apos;s Empress and this did not improve their relationship because Sanjo respected FUJIWARA-no-Seshi, who he had been together for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Michinaga tried to have his daughter FUJIWARA no Kenshi as Sanjo&apos;s Empress and this did not improve their relationship because Sanjo respected FUJIWARA no Seishi, who he had been together for a long time.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。娍子→Seishi に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>結局、定子と彰子の2人を同時に皇后としていた一条の先例にならい、娍子と妍子を揃って皇后とすることになったが、道長の強大な勢威と三条の権力基盤の弱さを反映して、まず妍子を立后させ、その後に娍子を立后させることになっただけでなく、妍子の立后の儀式には多くの貴族たちが積極的に協力したのに対し、娍子の立后の儀式には道長の妨害もあって貴族たちのサボタージュが続出し、三条やその側近たちを憤激させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, taking the past case where Ichijo had both Teishi and Shoshi as Empress, Seshi and Kenshi were both to become Empress, but reflecting the all mighty authority of Michinaga and the weak power base of Sanjo, not only was Kenshi was first to become Empress and then Seshi, but although many aristocrats cooperated actively for the ceremony for the making of Kenshi as Empress, Seshi&apos;s ceremony was met with sabotage by Michinaga and not attended by many aristocrats, angering Sanjo and his aides.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, taking the past case where Ichijo had both Teishi and Shoshi as Empress, Seshi and Kenshi were both to become Empress, but reflecting the all mighty authority of Michinaga and the weak power base of Sanjo, not only was Kenshi was first to become Empress and then Seshi, but although many aristocrats cooperated actively for the ceremony for the making of Kenshi as Empress, Seshi&apos;s ceremony was met with sabotage by Michinaga and not attended by many aristocrats, angering Sanjo and his aides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, taking the past case where Ichijo had both Teishi and Shoshi as Empress, Seishi and Kenshi were both to become Empress, but reflecting the all mighty authority of Michinaga and the weak power base of Sanjo, not only was Kenshi was first to become Empress and then Seishi, but although many aristocrats cooperated actively for the ceremony for the making of Kenshi as Empress, Seishi&apos;s ceremony was met with sabotage by Michinaga and not attended by many aristocrats, angering Sanjo and his aides.</e>
<cmt>娍子→Seishi に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="246">
<j>やがて三条が眼病を患うと、道長ははっきりと三条に譲位を勧めるようになり、視力の低下で政務や日常生活にも支障をきたすようになった三条は、長和5年（1016年）には皇太子敦成（後一条天皇）に譲位せざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, Sanjo suffered from an eye disease and Michinaga started to clearly suggest abdication to Sanjo, and in 1016, Sanjo reluctantly abdicated to the Crown Prince Atsunari (Emperor Go-Ichijo) because his decrease in eyesight started to infringe upon governing duties and daily life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, Sanjo suffered from an eye disease and Michinaga started to clearly suggest abdication to Sanjo, and in 1016, Sanjo reluctantly abdicated to the Crown Prince Atsunari (Emperor Go-Ichijo) because his decrease in eyesight started to infringe upon governing duties and daily life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, Sanjo suffered from an eye disease and Michinaga started to clearly suggest abdication to Sanjo, and in 1016, Sanjo reluctantly abdicated to the Crown Prince Atsunari (Emperor Goichijo) because his decrease in eyesight started to infringe upon governing duties and daily life.</e>
<cmt>名前表記の訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>三条の強い意向により、皇太子には娍子を母とする三条の第1皇子小一条院が立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the strong wishes of Sanjo, the Crown Prince was Sanjo and Seishi&apos;s first son, Sho-Ichijyo-in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the strong wishes of Sanjo, the Crown Prince was Sanjo and Seishi&apos;s first son, Sho-Ichijyo-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the strong wishes of Sanjo, the Crown Prince was Sanjo and Seishi&apos;s first son, Koichijoin.</e>
<cmt>小一条院→Koichijoin に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="248">
<j>敦明は皇太子にはなったものの、やはり父同様に道長からの圧迫と政界での孤立に悩むことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsuaki became Crown Prince, but as with his father he suffered from pressure from Michinaga and isolation within the political field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuaki became Crown Prince, but as with his father he suffered from pressure from Michinaga and isolation within the political field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuaki became Crown Prince, but as with his father he suffered from pressure from Michinaga and isolation within the political field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>寛仁元年（1017年）に三条が死去すると、敦明はついに皇太子の辞退を決意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1017, when Sanjo died, Atsuaki decided to refrain from being the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1017, when Sanjo died, Atsuaki decided to refrain from being the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1017, when Sanjo died, Atsuaki decided to refrain from being the Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>これは単なる逃避行動ではなく、政治的取引であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was not an act of escapism but a political trade-off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was not an act of escapism but a political trade-off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was not an act of escapism but a political trade-off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>敦明は、皇太子の地位と引き換えに、太上天皇に准じた待遇を得て、さらに道長の娘婿となることを交換条件として提示し、道長に承諾させたうえで皇太子を退いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Atsuaki indicated the exchange conditions to obtain treatment equivalent to that of an ex-emperor and also becoming Michinaga&apos;s son-in-law in exchange for the position of Crown Prince, and got Michinaga to agree before leaving the position of Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Atsuaki indicated the exchange conditions to obtain treatment equivalent to that of an ex-emperor and also becoming Michinaga&apos;s son-in-law in exchange for the position of Crown Prince, and got Michinaga to agree before leaving the position of Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Atsuaki indicated the exchange conditions to obtain treatment equivalent to that of the Retired Emperor and also becoming Michinaga&apos;s son-in-law in exchange for the position of Crown Prince, and got Michinaga to agree before leaving the position of Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>太上天皇→Daijo Tenno (the Retired Emperor)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>この約束は遵守され、敦明には上皇に准じて「小一条院」の院号と年官年爵などが与えられ、上皇同様に院庁も設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This promise was kept and Atsuaki was given the title &quot;Sho-Ichijyo-in&quot; equivalent to a Joko, received Nenkan, Nensyaku and had a In-cho (office) similar to a Joko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This promise was kept and Atsuaki was given the title &quot;Sho-Ichijyo-in&quot; equivalent to a Joko, received Nenkan, Nensyaku and had a In-cho (office) similar to a Joko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This promise was kept and Atsuaki was given the title &apos;Koichijoin&apos; equivalent to the Retired Emperor, received Nenkan, Nensyaku and had a In-cho (office) similar to the Retired Emperor.</e>
<cmt>小一条院→Koichijoin に訂正しました。”を&apos;に訂正しました。Joko→the Retired Emperor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>また道長の娘藤原寛子が小一条の女御となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Kanshi became Sho-Ichijyo&apos;s Nyogo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA-no-Kanshi became Sho-Ichijyo&apos;s Nyogo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Michinaga&apos;s daughter, FUJIWARA no Kanshi became Koichijoin&apos;s Nyogo.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。小一条院→Koichijoin に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>代わって皇太子に立てられたのは、後一条の同母弟（彰子の息子）であり、やはり道長の外孫である敦良（のちの後朱雀天皇）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, Go-Ichijyo&apos;s younger half-brother (Shoshi&apos;s son), Atsuyoshi (later Emperor Go-Suzaku), who was also one of Michinaga&apos;s grandchildren became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, Go-Ichijyo&apos;s younger half-brother (Shoshi&apos;s son), Atsuyoshi (later Emperor Go-Suzaku), who was also one of Michinaga&apos;s grandchildren, became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, Goichijo&apos;s younger half-brother (Shoshi&apos;s son), Atsunaga (later Emperor Gosuzaku), who was also one of Michinaga&apos;s grandchildren, became Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。名前表記の訂正しました。敦良→Atsunaga に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>こうして、道長の権威と権力が朝廷を圧するなかで両統迭立は終焉し、皇統は円融の子孫に一本化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how Ryototetsuritsu ended with Michinaga&apos;s authority and power putting pressure on the Imperial Court and the Imperial Line was united with Enyu&apos;s descendants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how Ryototetsuritsu ended with Michinaga&apos;s authority and power putting pressure on the Imperial Court and the Imperial Line was united with Enyu&apos;s descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how Ryoto tetsuritsu ended with Michinaga&apos;s authority and power putting pressure on the Imperial Court and the Imperial line was united with Enyu&apos;s descendants.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。line小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="256">
<j>冷泉流皇統から天皇が即位することはなくなったが、その血統は女系を通じて後年に影響を残した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were no further Emperors made from the Reizen-ryu Imperial line, but the blood line continued through the maternal side of the family and affected the family in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were no further Emperors made from the Reizen-ryu Imperial line, but the blood line continued through the maternal side of the family and affected the family in later years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were no further Emperors made from the Reizei&apos;s Imperial line, but the blood line continued through the maternal side of the family and affected the family in later years.</e>
<cmt>Reizeiに訂正しました。-ryu削除、&apos;s補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>三条と妍子の間に生まれた陽明門院が皇太子敦良の妻となり、第2王子尊仁を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komyomon-in born between Sanjo and Kenshi became Crown Prince Atsuyoshi&apos;s wife and she gave birth to the second prince Takahito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komyomon-in born between Sanjo and Kenshi became Crown Prince Atsuyoshi&apos;s wife and she gave birth to the second prince Takahito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komyomonin born between Sanjo and Kenshi became Crown Prince Atsunaga&apos;s wife and she gave birth to the second prince Takahito.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。敦良→Atsunaga に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>尊仁は父後朱雀の死後、異母兄の後冷泉天皇の皇太子に立てられ、後冷泉が皇子を遺さずに死去すると、跡を継いで天皇（後三条天皇）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takahito after his father Go-Suzaku&apos;s death was made Crown Prince for his older half brother Emperor Go-Reizen, and when Go-Reizen died without a son, he became Emperor (Emperor Go-Sanjyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takahito after his father Go-Suzaku&apos;s death was made Crown Prince for his older half brother Emperor Go-Reizen, and when Go-Reizen died without a son, he became Emperor (Emperor Go-Sanjyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takahito after his father Gosuzaku&apos;s death was made Crown Prince for his older half brother Emperor Goreizei, and when Goreizei died without a son, he became Emperor (Emperor Gosanjo).</e>
<cmt>名前表記の訂正しました。Reizeiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>彼の追号「後三条」は、彼が外祖父三条の後継者であることを意味しており、生前自ら定めたものだという説もある（『栄花物語』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This title after death &quot;Go-Sanjyo&quot; is said to have been chosen by himself while he was alive to mean that he was the heir of his maternal grandfather, Sanjo (&quot;A Tale of Flowering Fortunes&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This title after death &quot;Go-Sanjyo&quot; is said to have been chosen by himself while he was alive to mean that he was the heir of his maternal grandfather, Sanjo (&quot;A Tale of Flowering Fortunes&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This title after death &apos;Gosanjo&apos; is said to have been chosen by himself while he was alive to mean that he was the heir of his maternal grandfather, Sanjo (&quot;A Tale of Flowering Fortunes&quot;).</e>
<cmt>名前表記の訂正しました。”を&apos;に訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>また、後三条の妻のひとりに小一条の息子源基平の娘源基子がおり、第2皇子実仁親王 (平安時代)と第3皇子輔仁親王を産んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, one of Go-Sanjyo&apos;s wives was Sho-Ichijyo&apos;s son, MINAMOTO-no-Motohira&apos;s daughter, MINAMOTO-no-Kishi, and she gave birth to his second prince Mitsuhito Shinno (Heian Period) and third son Sukehito Shinno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, one of Go-Sanjyo&apos;s wives was Sho-Ichijyo&apos;s son, MINAMOTO-no-Motohira&apos;s daughter, MINAMOTO-no-Kishi, and she gave birth to his second prince Mitsuhito Shinno (Heian Period) and third son Sukehito Shinno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, one of Gosanjo&apos;s wives was Koichijo&apos;s son, MINAMOTO no Motohira&apos;s daughter, MINAMOTO no Kishi, and she gave birth to his second prince, Imperial Prince Sanehito (Heian period) and third prince, Imperial Prince Sukehito.</e>
<cmt>名前表記の訂正しました。ハイフン削除。小一条院→Koichijoin に訂正しました。実仁親王→Imperial Prince Sanehito、Shinno削除。period小文字にしました。son→prince に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>実仁は、異母兄白河天皇の即位にあたり皇太子に立てられたが即位の機会を得ずに早世した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuhito became Crown Prince upon the accession of his half brother Emperor Shirakawa, but died early without a chance to ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuhito became Crown Prince upon the accession of his half brother Emperor Shirakawa, but died early without a chance to ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanehito became Crown Prince upon the accession of his half brother Emperor Shirakawa, but died early without a chance to ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt>実仁→Sanehito</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>同母弟として実仁の身代わりとみなされた輔仁は、皇太子にはなれなかったものの、長寿を保った祖母禎子（陽明門院）の庇護の下、白河とその子息堀河天皇の皇位継承上のライバルとして一時は政界に大きな勢力を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukehito was considered a replacement for his half brother Mitsuhito did not become Crown Prince, but under the protection of his long-lived grandmother Teishi (Komyomon-in), at one time he was influential in the political field as a rival candidate for Emperor against Shirakawa and his son Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukehito was considered a replacement for his half brother Mitsuhito did not become Crown Prince, but under the protection of his long-lived grandmother Teishi (Komyomon-in), at one time he was influential in the political field as a rival candidate for Emperor against Shirakawa and his son Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukehito was considered a replacement for his half brother Sanehito did not become Crown Prince, but under the protection of his long-lived grandmother Teishi (Komyomonin), at one time he was influential in the political field as a rival candidate for Emperor against Shirakawa and his son Emperor Horikawa.</e>
<cmt>実仁→Sanehitoハイフン削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="263">
<j>日本以外の国の両統迭立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryototetsuritsu in countries other than Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryototetsuritsu in countries other than Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoto tetsuritsu in countries other than Japan</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>ペルシア湾の最深部に位置する小国クウェートは、サバーハ家が首長（アミール）の称号を名乗り統治している君主国である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuwait, a small country located at the far end of the Persian Gulf is a monarchy with the House of Al-Sabah ruling as chief (Emir).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuwait, a small country located at the far end of the Persian Gulf is a monarchy with the House of Al-Sabah ruling as chief (Emir).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuwait, a small country located at the far end of the Persian Gulf is a monarchy with the House of Al-Sabah ruling as chief (Emir).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>現在の地に建国され初代サバーハが首長に選出されたのは1756年である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Sabah selected as Emir since the country was built at its present location was 1756.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first Sabah selected as Emir since the country was built at its present location was 1756.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first Sabah selected as Emir since the country was built at its present location was 1756.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>もとはオスマン帝国の宗主権の下にあったが、1899年、第7代首長ムバラクがイギリスの保護国となることでオスマン帝国の支配を脱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally under the suzerainty of the Ottoman Empire, in 1899, the seventh Emir Mubarak decided to escape the control of the Ottoman Empire by becoming a protectorate of the British Empire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally under the suzerainty of the Ottoman Empire, in 1899, the seventh Emir Mubarak decided to escape the control of the Ottoman Empire by becoming a protectorate of the British Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally under the suzerainty of the Ottoman Empire, in 1899, the seventh Emir Mubarak decided to escape the control of the Ottoman Empire by becoming a protectorate of the British Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>ムバラクはサバーハ家中興の英主とされ「大首長」と尊称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mubarak is considered to be a wise lord for leading the restoration of the House of Al-Sabah and is respectfully called &quot;Paramount Chief&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mubarak is considered to be a wise lord for leading the restoration of the House of Al-Sabah and is respectfully called &quot;Paramount Chief&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mubarak is considered to be a wise lord for leading the restoration of the House of Al-Sabah and is respectfully called &quot;Paramount Chief.&quot;</e>
<cmt>”を&quot;に訂正しました。ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>その後1961年にはイギリスの保護下から離れ独立国となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later in 1961, it escaped the protection of the United Kingdom and became an independent country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in 1961, it escaped the protection of the United Kingdom and became an independent country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later in 1961, it escaped the protection of the United Kingdom and became an independent country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="269">
<j>ムバラクのあと、長男ジャービルが第8代、次男サリームが第9代の首長となり、さらにジャービルの息子アハマドが第10代を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Mubarak, his first son Jabir became the eighth, his second son Salim became the ninth and Jabir&apos;s son, Ahmad became the tenth chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Mubarak, his first son Jabir became the eighth, his second son Salim became the ninth and Jabir&apos;s son, Ahmad became the tenth chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Mubarak, his first son Jabir became the eighth, his second son Salim became the ninth and Jabir&apos;s son, Ahmad became the tenth chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>その後、ジャービルの子孫とサリームの子孫がほぼ交互に首長の位につくことが慣行となってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it became tradition to alternate the post of Emir between the descendants of Jabir and the descendants of Salim.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it became tradition to alternate the post of Emir between the descendants of Jabir and the descendants of Salim.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it became tradition to alternate the post of Emir between the descendants of Jabir and the descendants of Salim.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>歴代の首長の出身家系は次のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage of the past Emirs are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lineage of the past Emirs are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lineage of the past Emirs are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="272">
<j>第10代　アハマド … ジャービル系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenth chief Ahmad...Jabir line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenth chief Ahmad...Jabir line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenth chief Ahmad: Jabir line</e>
<cmt>The補足しました。コロンで区切った表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>第11代　アブドゥッラー … サリーム系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eleventh chief Abdullah///Salim line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eleventh chief Abdullah///Salim line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eleventh chief Abdullah: Salim line</e>
<cmt>The補足しました。コロンで区切った表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>第12代　サバーハ … サリーム系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Twelfth chief Sabah...Salim line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twelfth chief Sabah...Salim line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelfth chief Sabah: Salim line</e>
<cmt>The補足しました。コロンで区切った表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>第13代　ジャービル … ジャービル系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirteenth chief Jabir...Jabir line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirteenth chief Jabir...Jabir line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The thirteenth chief Jabir: Jabir line</e>
<cmt>The補足しました。コロンで区切った表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>第14代　サアド … サリーム系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fourteenth chief Saad... Salim line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fourteenth chief Saad... Salim line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourteenth chief Saad: Salim line</e>
<cmt>The補足しました。コロンで区切った表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>第15代　サバーハ（現首長）… ジャービル系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fifteenth chief Sabah (current Emir)...Jabir line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fifteenth chief Sabah (current Emir)...Jabir line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fifteenth chief Sabah (current Emir): Jabir line</e>
<cmt>The補足しました。コロンで区切った表記に統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="278">
<j>2006年に首長ジャービルが長い闘病の末に死去、皇太子サアドがただちに首長位を継承したものの、サアドもすでに高齢かつ病身で、首長としての公務に耐えられる状態ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2006, the Chief Jabir died after a long period of battling disease, and although the Crown Prince Saad became chief, he was also elderly and sick and was not in any condition to conduct the duties as chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2006, the Chief Jabir died after a long period of battling disease, and although the Crown Prince Saad became chief, he was also elderly and sick and was not in any condition to conduct the duties as chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2006, the Chief Jabir died after a long period of battling disease, and although the Crown Prince Saad became chief, he was also elderly and sick and was not in any condition to conduct the duties as chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>もともと近年クウェート政界ではサリーム系王族よりもジャービル系王族の方が優位に立ちつつあったが、サアドの即位にあたって、ジャービル系王族を中心に、執務不可能を理由にサアドに退位を求める声があがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent years, in the Kuwait political field, Jabir line royal family members had superiority over Salim line members, and upon Saad&apos;s ascension, there was a voice mainly from the Jabir line royal family members for Saad to abdicate because of his not being able to execute his duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, in the Kuwait political field, Jabir line royal family members had superiority over Salim line members, and upon Saad&apos;s ascension, there was a voice mainly from the Jabir line royal family members for Saad to abdicate because of his not being able to execute his duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, in the Kuwait political field, Jabir line royal family members had superiority over Salim line members, and upon Saad&apos;s ascension, there was a voice mainly from the Jabir line royal family members for Saad to abdicate because of his not being able to execute his duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="280">
<j>代わって首長に推されたのは、首相として、病身で執務できない首長ジャービルと皇太子サアドに代わって国政の実権を握っていたジャービル系王族のサバーハであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, Sabah, a royal member of the Jabir line who had the actual power of national government working in place of the sick Chief Jabir and Crown Prince Saad as Prime Minister, was nominated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, Sabah, a royal member of the Jabir line who had the actual power of national government working in place of the sick Chief Jabir and Crown Prince Saad as Prime Minister, was nominated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, Sabah, a royal member of the Jabir line who had the actual power of national government working in place of the sick Chief Jabir and Crown Prince Saad as Prime Minister, was nominated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>クウェートでは、首相であることは次期皇太子の最有力候補であることを意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kuwait, the Prime Minister is considered the most likely candidate as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kuwait, the Prime Minister is considered the most likely candidate as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kuwait, the Prime Minister is considered the most likely candidate as the next Crown Prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>サリーム系王族は当然これに抵抗し、両派のあいだで妥協の道も探られたが、結局決裂に終わり、ジャービル系が掌握する政府は、首長解任権を持つ議会に首長サアドを解任する議案を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Salim line royal members naturally were against this, and there were efforts to reach a compromise between the two lines, but the talks ended in breaking up and the government run by the Jabir line submitted a bill to dismiss the chief to the congress, which has the right to dismiss the chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Salim line royal members naturally were against this, and there were efforts to reach a compromise between the two lines, but the talks ended in breaking up and the government run by the Jabir line submitted a bill to dismiss the chief to the congress, which has the right to dismiss the chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Salim line royal members naturally were against this, and there were efforts to reach a compromise between the two lines, but the talks ended in breaking up and the government run by the Jabir line submitted a bill to dismiss the chief to the congress, which has the right to dismiss the chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>議会は満場一致で首長解任を決議し、新首長にサバーハを指名した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The congress unianimously decided on dismissing the Chief and named Sabah as the new Chief.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The congress unianimously decided on dismissing the Chief and named Sabah as the new Chief.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The congress unanimously decided on dismissing the Chief and named Sabah as the new Chief.</e>
<cmt>unanimouslyスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>サアドは廃位される不名誉を避けようと、自発的に退位する旨の文書を議会に届けたが、採決に間に合わなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In an attempt to deflect the dishonor of being dethroned, Saad submitted a document regarding voluntary abdication to the congress but this was not voted on in time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In an attempt to deflect the dishonor of being dethroned, Saad submitted a document regarding voluntary abdication to the congress, but this was not voted on in time.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In an attempt to deflect the dishonor of being dethroned, Saad submitted a document regarding voluntary abdication to the congress, but this was not voted on in time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>サアドの首長在位はわずか10日間であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saad&apos;s tenure as Chief was only 10 days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saad&apos;s tenure as Chief was only 10 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saad&apos;s tenure as Chief was only 10 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="286">
<j>首長となったサバーハは、異母弟ナワーフを皇太子に、甥ナーセルを首相に任命し、要職をジャービル系で独占した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Sabah became Chief, he named his younger half brother Nawaf, who has the same father, as Crown Prince and his nephew Nasser as Prime Minister, and major positions are taken up by the Jabir line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Sabah became Chief, he named his younger half brother Nawaf, who has the same father, as Crown Prince and his nephew Nasser as Prime Minister, and major positions are taken up by the Jabir line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Sabah became Chief, he named his younger half brother Nawaf, who has the same father, as Crown Prince and his nephew Nasser as Prime Minister, and major positions are taken up by the Jabir line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>今後、クウェートの首長位はジャービル系が独占し、サリーム系は凋落の道をたどるであろうと予測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the future, the post of Chief is expected to be monopolized by the Jabir line and it is predicted that the Salim line will decline.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the future, the post of Chief is expected to be monopolized by the Jabir line and it is predicted that the Salim line will decline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the future, the post of Chief is expected to be monopolized by the Jabir line and it is predicted that the Salim line will decline.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), ロリ(id:613), Nidarin(id:6420), 経済準学士(id:22656), MIsogi(id:20599), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), PATMAN(id:145791), VoidAimai(id:212464), 難民(id:4644), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Shimoxx(id:9332), Komatta(id:52309), 伏儀(id:142093), 呆庵入道(id:74721), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>