<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>土曜会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Doyokai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Doyokai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Doyokai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>土曜会（どようかい）とは、明治時代・大正時代に存在した貴族院_(日本)の院内会派（1901年12月7日－1919年11月15日）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Doyokai (literally &quot;the Saturday Group&quot;) was an internal faction within the House of Peers in Japan&apos;s National Diet; the Doyokai lasted from the Meiji period into the Taisho period (from December 7, 1901 to November 15, 1919).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Doyokai (literally &quot;the Saturday Group&quot;) was an internal faction within the House of Peers in Japan&apos;s National Diet; the Doyokai lasted from the Meiji period into the Taisho period (from December 7, 1901 to November 15, 1919).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Doyokai (literally &quot;the Saturday Group&quot;) was an internal faction within the House of Peers in Japan&apos;s National Diet; the Doyokai lasted from the Meiji period into the Taisho period (from December 7, 1901 to November 15, 1919).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>最大会派研究会_(貴族院)の台頭に憂慮を抱いていた朝日倶楽部と庚子会（懇話会の後身）が合同して53名（公爵2名・伯爵3名・子爵7名・男爵5名・勅撰議員17名・多額納税議員19名）にて結成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Doyokai was formed when the Asahi Club and the Koshikai (which was the successor to the Konwakai), fearing the emergence of maximally factional study groups (in the House of Peers), joined forces to reach 53 members (two Dukes, three Counts, seven Viscounts, five Barons, seventeen members by imperial decree, and nineteen large-scale taxpayers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Doyokai was formed when the Asahi Club and the Koshikai (which was the successor to the Konwakai), fearing the emergence of maximally factional study groups (in the House of Peers), joined forces to reach 53 members (two Dukes, three Counts, seven Viscounts, five Barons, seventeen members by imperial decree, and nineteen large-scale taxpayers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Doyokai was formed when the Asahi Club and the Koshikai (which was the successor to the Konwakai), fearing the emergence of a maximal faction, Kenkyukai (in the House of Peers), joined forces to reach 53 members (two Dukes, three Counts, seven Viscounts, five Barons, 17 members by imperial decree, and 19 high taxpayers).</e>
<cmt>研究会は固有名詞ですので、そのまま音訳しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>初代幹事長に二条基弘が選出されたが、実際には曾我祐準・小沢武雄・谷干城らが中心として運営されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motohiro NIJO was elected the first chief secretary of the Doyokai, but in reality the Doyokai was run by others, chief among them Sukenori SOGA, Takeo OZAWA, and Tateki TANI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motohiro NIJO was elected the first chief secretary of the Doyokai, but in reality the Doyokai was run by others, chief among them Sukenori SOGA, Takeo OZAWA, and Tateki TANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motohiro NIJO was elected the first chief secretary of the Doyokai, but in reality the Doyokai was run by others, chief among them Sukenori SOGA, Takeo OZAWA, and Tateki TANI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>一時、56名まで増加するも、後に離脱者が相次ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At one time the Doyokai swelled to reach 56 members, but thereafter many members began leaving the group one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At one time the Doyokai swelled to reach 56 members, but thereafter many members began leaving the group one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At one time the Doyokai swelled to reach 56 members, but thereafter many members began leaving the group one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特に1919年の男爵議員による公正会結成に伴う同議員の大量離脱に伴って院内交渉団体としての資格を失ったのを機に解散して第1次無所属との合同を行うことを決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group continued losing members, particularly after the 1919 formation of the Koseikai (Fairness Group) by the Barons in the House of Peers, at which point, having lost the majority of its members, the Doyokai had effectively lost the ability to conduct internal House of Peers negotiations, and it was therefore decided to merge the group with the first Mushozoku (Unaffiliated Group).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group continued losing members, particularly after the 1919 formation of the Koseikai (Fairness Group) by the Barons in the House of Peers, at which point, having lost the majority of its members, the Doyokai had effectively lost the ability to conduct internal House of Peers negotiations, and it was therefore decided to merge the group with the first Mushozoku (Unaffiliated Group).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group continued losing members, particularly after the 1919 formation of the Koseikai (Fairness Group) by the Barons in the House of Peers, at which point, having lost the majority of its members, the Doyokai had lost the qualification as a internal negotiation faction of the House of Peers, and it was therefore decided to merge the group with the first Mushozoku (Unaffiliated Group).</e>
<cmt>「院内交渉団体としての資格」の訳を代えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>結果的に有爵議員はこれに従わず、会の多数を占める勅撰議員と多額納税議員のみが合同に参加して同成会を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in fact, those group members who held a peerage (a rank in the nobility) refused to honor this arrangement, and so it was only those who were in the House of Peers by imperial decree and the large-scale taxpayers--who in fact comprised the majority of the Doyokai--that participated in the merger and thereby formed the Doseikai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in fact, those group members who held a peerage (a rank in the nobility) refused to honor this arrangement, and so it was only those who were in the House of Peers by imperial decree and the large-scale taxpayers--who in fact comprised the majority of the Doyokai--that participated in the merger and thereby formed the Doseikai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in fact, those group members who held a peerage (a rank in the nobility) refused to honor this arrangement, and so it was only those who were in the House of Peers by imperial decree and the high taxpayers, who in fact comprised the majority of the Doyokai, that participated in the merger and thereby formed the Doseikai.</e>
<cmt>--を,にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>