<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陪臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baishin (indirect vassal)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baishin (indirect vassal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baishin (indirect vassal)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>陪臣（ばいしん）とは、武家の主従関係において家臣の家臣を指した呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baishin refers to a name indicating a vassal of vassal in the samurai&apos;s relationship between lord and vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baishin refers to a name indicating a vassal of vassal in the samurai&apos;s relationship between lord and vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baishin refers to a name indicating a vassal of vassal in the samurai&apos;s relationship between lord and vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「またもの」、「また家来」とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called &apos;Matamono&apos; or &apos;Matakerai&apos; (indirect retainer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called &apos;Matamono&apos; or &apos;Matakerai&apos; (indirect retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called &apos;Matamono&apos; or &apos;Matakerai&apos; (indirect retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>今日の近代官僚機構、会社組織であれば、ある職員は「課長の部下」であると同時に「課長を部下として使う部長の部下」でもあるので、部長が課長を介さず、職員に職務を依頼したり、逆に報告を行うことはあまり珍しくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking a present-day modern bureaucratic organization or corporate organization for instance, since some staff member is a &apos;subordinate to a section chief&apos; and also a &apos;subordinate to a department director using such section chief as subordinate,&apos; it is not very rare that the department director requests such staff member to perform duties not through the section chief, or that such staff member gives a report to the department director directly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking a present-day modern bureaucratic organization or corporate organization for instance, since some staff member is a &apos;subordinate to a section chief&apos; and also a &apos;subordinate to a department director using such section chief as subordinate,&apos; it is not very rare that the department director requests such staff member to perform duties not through the section chief, or that such staff member gives a report to the department director directly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking a present-day modern bureaucratic organization or corporate organization for instance, since some staff member is a &apos;subordinate to a section chief&apos; and also a &apos;subordinate to a department director using such section chief as subordinate,&apos; it is not very rare that the department director requests such staff member to perform duties not through the section chief, or that such staff member gives a report to the department director directly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、武士団や、それを基盤にした江戸時代の幕府や各藩の官僚機構は、あくまでも個別の家相互の主従関係のネットワークで構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, bushidan (samurai group), and a bureaucratic organization based on it in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) or each domain in the Edo period was only formed by a network of mutual relationship between lord and vassal in an individual clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, bushidan (samurai group), and a bureaucratic organization based on it in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) or each domain in the Edo period was only formed by a network of mutual relationship between lord and vassal in an individual clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, bushidan (samurai group), and a bureaucratic organization based on it in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) or each domain in the Edo period was only formed by a network of mutual relationship between lord and vassal in an individual clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、例えば忠臣蔵で有名な大石家は赤穂浅野家の家臣であるが、大石家の家臣は浅野家とは直接の主従関係を持たなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, for example, the Oishi family which was famous for Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers) was a vassal of the Asano family of Ako Domain, but vassals of Oishi family did not have a direct master-servant relationship with the Asano family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, for example, the Oishi family which was famous for Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers) was a vassal of the Asano family of Ako Domain, but vassals of the Oishi family did not have a direct master-servant relationship with the Asano family.</e>
<cmt>Oishi familyには定冠詞が必要なため追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, for example, the Oishi family which was famous for Chushingura (The Treasury of Loyal Retainers) was a vassal of the Asano family of Ako Domain, but vassals of the Oishi family did not have a direct master-servant relationship with the Asano family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この場合、大石家の家臣は浅野家の陪臣であり、浅野家は大石家の家臣に直接の命令権を持たなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, vassals of Oishi family were baishin (indirect vassal) of Asano family, and the Asano family did not have the right to directly give orders to vassals of Oishi family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, vassals of the Oishi family were baishin (indirect vassal) of the Asano family, and the Asano family did not have the right to directly give orders to vassals of the Oishi family.</e>
<cmt>Oishi familyおよびAsano familyには定冠詞が必要なため追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, vassals of the Oishi family were baishin (indirect vassal) of the Asano family, and the Asano family did not have the right to directly give orders to vassals of the Oishi family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸幕府の職制においては、徳川将軍家の直接の家臣を直参と呼んだのに対し、将軍家は、大名や旗本の家臣を「陪臣」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the office organization of Edo bakufu, direct vassals of the Tokugawa Shogun family were called jikisan (immediate retainer), while the Shogun family called vassals of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) &apos;baishin.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the office organization of the Edo bakufu, direct vassals of the Tokugawa Shogun family were called jikisan (immediate retainer), while the Shogun family called vassals of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) &apos;baishin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・Edo bakufuには定冠詞が必要なため追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the office organization of the Edo bakufu, direct vassals of the Tokugawa Shogun family were called jikisan (immediate retainer), while the Shogun family called vassals of daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and hatamoto (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) &apos;baishin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>だから上記の大石家も、浅野家の家臣だが、徳川将軍家から見れば陪臣になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why the aforementioned Oishi family was a vassal of Asano family, but was baishin for the Tokugawa Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why the aforementioned Oishi family was a vassal of the Asano family, but was baishin for the Tokugawa Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>Asano familyには定冠詞が必要なため追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why the aforementioned Oishi family was a vassal of the Asano family, but was baishin for the Tokugawa Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>彼らは大名、旗本にとっては直参であり、徳川将軍家からは陪臣となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were jikisan (immediate retainer) for daimyo and hatamoto, and were baishin for the Tokugawa Shogun family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were jikisan (immediate retainer) for daimyo and hatamoto, and were baishin for the Tokugawa Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were jikisan (immediate retainer) for daimyo and hatamoto, and were baishin for the Tokugawa Shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また彼らの家臣は大名・旗本にとっての陪臣であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, their vassals were baishin for daimyo and hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, their vassals were baishin for daimyo and hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, their vassals were baishin for daimyo and hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>上下関係の確立した江戸時代に於いては、直参は将軍への拝謁が許されていたのに対し、陪臣はたとえ藩で1万石以上と大名並みの石高を有する家老でも拝謁は許されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period when the superior-inferior relationships were established, jikisan was permitted to have an audience with the shogun, but baishin was not permitted to have an audience with the shogun even if such baishin was Karo (chief retainer) whose clan had a daimyo-level yield of not less than 100,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period when the superior-inferior relationships were established, jikisan was permitted to have an audience with the shogun, but baishin was not permitted to have an audience with the shogun even if such baishin was Karo (chief retainer) whose clan had a daimyo-level yield of not less than 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>・指示に従って、石高の石はkokuとしました。・1万石の数値が1桁違います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period when the superior-inferior relationships were established, jikisan was permitted to have an audience with the shogun, but baishin was not permitted to have an audience with the shogun even if such baishin was Karo (chief retainer) whose clan had a daimyo-level yield of not less than 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>彼らは将軍との主従関係を持たず、拝謁の資格を有しなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They did not have a master-servant relationship with a shogun, and were not entitled to have an audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They did not have a master-servant relationship with a shogun, and were not entitled to have an audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They did not have a master-servant relationship with a shogun, and were not entitled to have an audience with the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>同様に陪臣が他家の主君に直接面会をすることも出来なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Baishin could not directly meet with lords of other clans, either.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Baishin could not directly meet with lords of other clans, either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Baishin could not directly meet with lords of other clans, either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>主君が不在であったり病気等の理由で江戸城に登城できない場合、陪臣が登城し用件を老中・若年寄など幕閣に伝える場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a lord was absent or could not come to the Edo-jo Castle by reasons of sickness or others, baishin sometimes came to castle and transmitted a message to the cabinet officials of the Shogunate such as roju (senior councillor of the Tokugawa shogunate), wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a lord was absent or could not come to the Edo-jo Castle by reasons of sickness or others, baishin sometimes came to castle and transmitted a message to the cabinet officials of the Shogunate such as roju (senior councilor of the Tokugawa shogunate) and wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt>such asに「など」の意味があるため、and so onは削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a lord was absent or could not come to the Edo-jo Castle by reasons of sickness or others, baishin sometimes came to castle and transmitted a message to the cabinet officials of the Shogunate such as roju (senior councilor of the Tokugawa shogunate) and wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この際も幕閣は他家主君であるので、「御用取次」を介して用件が伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the message was transmitted through &apos;goyotoritsugi&apos; (an attendant to Shogun to announce a visitor and convey the message) because the cabinet officials of the Shogunate were also lords of other clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the message was transmitted through &apos;goyotoritsugi&apos; (an attendant to Shogun to announce a visitor and convey the message) because the cabinet officials of the Shogunate were also lords of other clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the message was transmitted through &apos;goyotoritsugi&apos; (an attendant to Shogun to announce a visitor and convey the message) because the cabinet officials of the Shogunate were also lords of other clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>天下の三陪臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Great three baishin in the country</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Great three baishin in the country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Great three baishin in the country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>『名将言行録』に天下の三陪臣が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Meisho Genkoroku&quot; (the collections of anecdotes of great commanders in Japanese history) named great three baishin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Meisho Genkoroku&quot; (the collections of anecdotes of great commanders in Japanese history) named great three baishin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Meisho Genkoroku&quot; (the collections of anecdotes of great commanders in Japanese history) named great three baishin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>「陪臣にして、直江山城、小早川左衛門、堀監物杯は天下の仕置をするとも仕兼間敷（しかねまじき）ものなり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;In spite of being baishin, Naoe Yamashiro (referring to Kanetsugu NAOE), Kobayakawa Saemon (referring to Takakage KOBAYAKAWA) and Hori Kenmotsuhai (referring to Naomasa HORI) were people who conducted shikanemajiki&apos; of maintaining good order of the country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>直江山城→Noe Yamashiro (referring to Kanetsugu NAOE)[下の文にて『直江兼続』の名前が出てくるので、同一人物であることを示すために、説明を付しました。以下、「小早川左衛門」「堀監物杯」も同様に対応しました]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of being baishin, Naoe Yamashiro (referring to Kanetsugu NAOE), Kobayakawa Saemon (referring to Takakage KOBAYAKAWA) and Hori Kenmotsuhai (referring to Naomasa HORI) were people were shikanemajiki although they maintained good order of the country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・「仕置をするとも～」は、「天下の仕置をしたが、仕兼間敷者でもあった」という意味に解釈されます。現状では、仕兼間敷と仕置が同格になっています。「仕兼間敷」の定訳が不明ですが、続く文から判断して、陪臣であることを指していると思われます。・仕兼間敷→shikanemajiki [定訳不明です]</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of being baishin, Naoe Yamashiro (referring to Kanetsugu NAOE), Kobayakawa Saemon (referring to Takakage KOBAYAKAWA) and Hori Kenmotsuhai (referring to Naomasa HORI) were people were shikanemajiki although they maintained good order of the country.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>豊臣秀吉が主君で、その直臣である、上杉景勝の家臣直江兼続、毛利輝元の家臣小早川隆景、堀秀政の家臣堀直政はそれぞれ陪臣にあたり、陪臣であるが天下の仕置も務まると評価したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanetsugu NAOE, Takakage KOBAYAKAWA and Naomasa HORI were respectively a vassal of Kagekatsu UESUGI, Terumoto MORI and Hidemasa HORI whose lord was Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and who were his direct retainers, which means that such three vassals were respectively equivalent to baishin of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and therefore, the above evaluation was given that they could play a role even in maintaining good order of the country although they were baishin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanetsugu NAOE, Takakage KOBAYAKAWA and Naomasa HORI were respectively a vassal of Kagekatsu UESUGI, Terumoto MORI and Hidemasa HORI whose lord was Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and who were his direct retainers, which means that such three vassals were respectively equivalent to baishin of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and therefore, the above evaluation was given to indicate that they could play a role even in maintaining good order of the country although they were baishin.</e>
<cmt>・was given thatは不完全なため、was given to indicate thatとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanetsugu NAOE, Takakage KOBAYAKAWA and Naomasa HORI were respectively a vassal of Kagekatsu UESUGI, Terumoto MORI and Hidemasa HORI whose lord was Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and who were his direct retainers, which means that such three vassals were respectively equivalent to baishin of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and therefore, the above evaluation was given to indicate that they could play a role even in maintaining good order of the country although they were baishin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Junger(id:10282), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), 堀五郎右衛門(id:84263), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>