<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>惣掟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So-okite</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So-okite</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So-okite</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>惣掟（そうおきて）は、中世日本において、百姓らが自主的に定めた惣村内部の法令。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So-okite is a statute that peasants defined independently within a soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association) in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So-okite is a statute defined independently by peasants within a soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association) in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;that peasants defined independently&quot; to &quot;defined independantly by peasants&quot; to read a bit more easily.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So-okite was a statute defined independently by peasants within a soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association) in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>村掟（むらおきて）、地下掟（じげおきて）ということもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as muraokite (village rules) and jige okite (lower class nobles&apos; rules).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as muraokite (village rules) and jige okite (lower class nobles&apos; rules).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as muraokite (village rules) and jige okite (lower class nobles&apos; rules).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>惣掟は、惣村の全構成員による寄合で決議されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So-okite was usually resolved in an assembly of all members of a soson.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So-okite was usually resolved in an assembly with all members of a soson.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Of&quot;-&quot;with&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So-okite was usually resolved in an assembly with all members of a soson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、惣村構成員に対する惣掟の効力は非常に強く作用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, so-okite was effective to them very strongly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, so-okite was strongly effective.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;effective to them very strongly&quot; to &quot;strongly effective&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, so-okite was strongly effective to the members of soson.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>特に、共同体秩序を崩壊させるような行為（窃盗、放火、殺人など）に対する罰則は、ほとんどの場合で死刑とされており、大変厳しいものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The penal regulations were very severe; especially the crimes that disturb the order of community (such as theft, arson and homicide) resulted in a death penalty in almost all cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The penal regulations were very severe; in particular the crimes that disturbed the order of community (such as theft, arson and homicide) resulted in the death penalty in almost all cases.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Especially&quot;-&quot;in particular&quot;. &quot;Disturb&quot;-&quot;disturbed&quot;. &quot;A death penalty&quot;-&quot;the death penalty&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The penal regulations were very severe; in particular the crimes that disturbed the order of community (such as theft, arson and homicide) resulted in the death penalty in almost all cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>その反面、その他の規定に対する違反については、惣村からの追放や財産の没収という罰則を伴っていたが、一定年限（数ヶ月～数年）が経過した後は、惣村の衆議によって解除されるケースがほとんどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, although penal regulations for other violations were banishment from a soson or confiscation of property, they were usually pardoned after a fixed period (several months to several years) by the public discussion of the soson.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, although penal regulations for other violations were banishment from a soson or confiscation of property, they were usually pardoned after a fixed period (several months to several years) by the public discussion of the soson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, although penal regulations for other violations were banishment from a soson or confiscation of property, they were usually pardoned after a fixed period (several months to several years) by the public discussion of the soson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中世前期（平安時代～鎌倉時代）までは、民衆（百姓など）を規制する法令は、律令・公家法・本所法・武家法など支配者により定められたものしか存在していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before early medieval (from Heian period to Kamakura period), general public (peasant etc.) was regulated only by the laws established by rulers, such as the Ritsuryo codes, court noble law, honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) law, and samurai law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the early medieval period (from the Heian to Kamakura periods), the general public (peasants etc.) were regulated only by the laws established by rulers, such as the Ritsuryo codes, court noble law, honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) law, and samurai law.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot; and &quot;period&quot; to &quot;medieval&quot;. Added &quot;the&quot; to &quot;general public&quot;. &quot;Was regulated&quot;-&quot;were regulated&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the early medieval period (from the Heian to Kamakura periods), the general public (peasants etc.) were regulated only by the laws established by rulers, such as the Ritsuryo codes, court noble law, honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) law, and samurai law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>それに伴い、民衆に対する司法権・警察権の行使（検断沙汰）も支配者である荘園・国衙領領主や地頭武士に限られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, only the rulers, such as the lord of a manor and Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) and the lord-of-a-manor samurai, might exercise the jurisdiction and police powers (criminal cases) to the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, only the rulers, such as the lord of a manor and Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) and the lord-of-a-manor samurai, could exercise the jurisdiction and police powers (criminal cases) to the general public.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Might&quot;-&quot;could&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, only the rulers, such as the lord of a manor and Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) and the lord-of-a-manor samurai, could exercise the jurisdiction and police powers (criminal cases) to the general public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、鎌倉後期ごろから室町前期にかけて、名（みょう）システムによる支配体型が崩壊していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the ruling structure based on myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) system was being collapsed from the late of Kamakura period to early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the ruling structure based on the myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) system deteriorated from the late Kamakura period to the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Being collapsed&quot;-&quot;deteriorated&quot;. Cut &quot;of&quot;. Added &quot;the&quot; to &quot;…period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the ruling structure based on the myo (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) system deteriorated from the late Kamakura period to the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>リンク文字列が含まれていたため、原文・訳文共に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それまで分散して居住し特に連帯してこなかった百姓らが、新たに集住して村落をつくり、強い自治意識と連帯意識に支えられた惣村を形成するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The peasants who had lived individually, started to live in a new village and form a soson community with strong autonomous concerns and sense of common bonds.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peasants who had lived individually, started to live in a new village and form a soson community with strong autonomous concerns and sense of common bonds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peasants who had lived individually, started to live in a new village and form a soson community with strong autonomous concerns and sense of common bonds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>惣村は、原則としては荘園・公領領主や地頭・守護などによって支配される建前であったが、これら支配者の規制を唯々諾々として受け入れていた訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although soson was technically governed by the lord of a manor and Imperial estate or shugo and jito (military governor and estate steward), the people of soson had not necessarily accepted the control of these rulers obediently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although soson was technically governed by the lord of a manor and Imperial estate or shugo and jito (military governor and estate steward), the people of soson had not necessarily accepted the control of these rulers obediently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although soson was technically governed by the lord of a manor and Imperial estate or shugo and jito (military governor and estate steward), the people of soson had not necessarily accepted the control of these rulers obediently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>一つの権利主体として、支配者に対し権利の要求を行うことがしばしば見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a one group, they often demanded their right.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They often demanded their rights as one group.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;as one group&quot; to the end.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They often demanded their rights from rulers as one group.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こうした要求活動を通じて惣村の自治権が強化されていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The autonomy of the soson had been increased through such demanding actions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The autonomy of the soson was increased through such demanding actions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Had been&quot;-&quot;was&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The autonomy of the soson was increased through such demanding actions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>反対に支配者側も惣村の了解が得られない限り、勝手に惣村への法令・規制を発布できない状況も生まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, rulers could no longer issue a statute and regulation for a soson without consent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, rulers could no longer issue a statute and regulation for a soson without consent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, rulers could no longer issue a statute and regulation for a soson without consent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>このように、惣村は支配者側との交渉を通じて各種権利を獲得していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the soson acquires various rights through negotiation with rulers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the soson acquired various rights through negotiation with their rulers.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Acquire&quot;-&quot;acquired&quot;. Added &quot;their&quot; to &quot;rulers&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the soson acquired various rights through negotiation with their rulers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その権利を明文化して惣内部の法令とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These rights were stipulated and became regulation within the soson.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These rights were stipulated and became regulation within the soson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These rights were stipulated and became regulation within the soson.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これが惣掟である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the so-okite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the so-okite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the so-okite.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、支配者からの一定の検断権を排除（拒否）する代わりに、惣村独自の検断権を行使する必要も生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in order to refuse a certain right to judge criminal cases of the rulers, people of the soson need to exercise their own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in order to refuse a certain right to judge criminal cases of the rulers, people of the soson needed to exercise their own.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Need&quot;-&quot;needed&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in order to refuse a certain right to judge criminal cases of the rulers, people of the soson needed to exercise their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そこで、惣村構成員が遵守すべき項目についても、内部法令として明文化されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, provisions that a soson member should follow were also often stipulated as a domestic statute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, provisions that a soson member should follow were also often stipulated as a domestic statute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, provisions that a soson member should follow were also often stipulated as a domestic statute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これも惣掟の起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is also the origin of so-okite.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is also the origin of so-okite.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was also the origin of so-okite.</e>
<cmt>過去形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>当時先進地域だった畿内において、惣掟の事例数・その内容が最も発展していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), where was an advanced region at that time, so-okite was most developed quantitatively as well as qualitatively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), which was an advanced region at that time, so-okite was most developed quantitatively as well as qualitatively.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Where&quot;-&quot;which&quot;. &quot;The Kinai region&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara), which was an advanced region at that time, so-okite was most developed quantitatively as well as qualitatively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>惣掟は、室町中期ごろが最も盛んで、戦国時代　（日本）にまで継続する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The so-okite had reached its peak in the middle of Muromachi period and lasted until the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The so-okite had reached its peak in the middle of Muromachi period and lasted until the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The so-okite had reached its peak in the middle of Muromachi period and lasted until the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、戦国大名による一円支配が伸展するにつれて、惣村の自治権も剥奪されていき、惣掟も消滅するか、自治色を薄めた内容へと変質していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period started to rule the entire region, the autonomy of the soson was divested, and the so-okite was disappeared or thinned its autonomy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period started to rule the entire region, the autonomy of the soson was divested, and the autonomy of the so-okite thinned out or disappeared.</e>
<cmt>Changed &quot;the so-okite was disappeared or thinned its autonomy&quot; to &quot;and the autonomy of the so-okite thinned out or disappeared&quot;to read more naturally.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) started to rule the entire region, the autonomy of the soson was divested, and the autonomy of the so-okite thinned out or disappeared.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>惣掟の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The examples of so-okite</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of so-okite</e>
<cmt>Cut &quot;the&quot;.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of so-okite</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Shimoxx(id:9332), Singing(id:134656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>