<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>遥任</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonin (a term concerning provincial governors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonin (a term concerning provincial governors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonin</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>遥任（ようにん、旧字体で遙任と表記することもある）とは、日本の奈良時代・平安時代などに、国司が任国へ赴任しなかったことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">遥任 (yonin) (the expression of 遙任 was also used sometimes) indicates that the person who was appointed to a kokushi (governor) of a province did not live in the province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">遥任 (yonin) (the expression of 遙任 was also used sometimes) indicates that the person who was appointed to a kokushi (governor) of a province did not live in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">遥任 (yonin) (the expression of 遙任 was also used sometimes) indicates that the person who was appointed to a kokushi (governor) of a province did not live in the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>遥授（ようじゅ、遙授）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called yoju (遥授 or 遙授 in Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called yoju (遥授 or 遙授 in Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called yoju (遥授 or 遙授 in Chinese characters).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>遥任国司は、目代と呼ばれる代理人を現地へ派遣するなどして、俸禄・租税などの収入を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonin kokushi gained his incomes of salary and taxes from his deputy called mokudai who was sent to the province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonin kokushi recieved his income, salary, and taxes from his deputy called mokudai who was sent to the province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonin kokushi received his income, salary, and taxes from his deputy called mokudai who was sent to the province.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>遥任は奈良期の頃から行われていたが、ごく稀であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yonin practice existed from around the Nara period, but was used only rarely at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The yonin practice existed from around the Nara period, but was used only rarely at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yonin practice existed from around the Nara period, but was used only rarely at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>奈良期はまだ、律令制による統治が有効に機能しており、律令制に基づく支配を地方まで貫徹するため、国司が任地へ赴き、現地支配を行う必要があったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because, in the Nara period, control based on the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) functioned effectively and, to extend the control based on the Ritsuryo system over every part of the country, it was necessary that kokushi moved to the assigned province to control it directly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because,during the Nara period, control based upon the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) functioned effectively and, to extend the control based on the Ritsuryo system over every part of the country, it was necessary for the kokushi to move to the assigned province to maintain direct control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because, during the Nara period, control based upon the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) functioned effectively and, to extend the control based on the Ritsuryo system over every part of the country, it was necessary for the kokushi to move to the assigned province to maintain direct control.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、平安時代に入ると、弘仁年間には議政官にも関わらず職封（封戸）が低かった参議に対して国守との兼務・遥任を認める例が慣例として現れた（参議兼国制）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, entering the Heian period, the following custom began to be employed: When there was a Sangi (councilor) who, though being a legislator, was awarded with a small number of shikifu (or fuko) (the families that the Sangi could control), he was appointed to a kokushi as well, with his yonin approved, (called sangikenkokusei (literally, the system in which a Sangi was allowed to assume a kokushi as well)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, entering the Heian period, the following custom began to be employed: When there was a Sangi (councilor) while being a legislator, was awarded with a small number of shikifu (or fuko) (families that the Sangi could control), he was appointed to kokushi as well, with his yonin approved, (called sangikenkokusei - literally, the system in which a Sangi was allowed to assume a kokushi as well).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, entering the Heian period, the following custom began to be employed: When there was a Sangi (councilor) while being a legislator, was awarded with a small number of shikifu (or fuko) (families that the Sangi could control), he was appointed to kokushi as well, with his yonin approved, (called sangikenkokusei - literally, the system in which a Sangi was allowed to assume a kokushi as well).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天長年間に上総国、常陸国、上野国が親王任国に定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tencho period (824 -834), the Kazusa province, Hitachi province and Kozuke province were assigned to shinnou-ninkoku (see below).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tencho period (824 -834), Kazusa province, Hitachi province and Kozuke province were assigned to shinnou-ninkoku (see below).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tencho period (824 -834), Kazusa Province, Hitachi Province and Kozuke Province were assigned to shinno-ninkoku (see below).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>親王任国とは、増加した親王に官職をあてがうため、特定の国の長官（国守）に親王を当てることとしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shinnou-ninkoku indicates a province where, to assign a governmental position to each of the shinno (princes) whose number had increased, the post of the provincial government head (kokushi) was allocated to a shinno.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A shinnou-ninkoku indicates a province where, to assign a governmental position to each of the shinno (princes) whose number had increased, the post of the provincial government head (kokushi) was allocated to a shinno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A shinno-ninkoku indicates a province where, to assign a governmental position to each of the shinno (princes) whose number had increased, the post of the provincial government head (kokushi) was allocated to a shinno.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>親王が現地へ赴任することはまずあり得ず、いわば遥任を朝廷公認で制度化したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it never happened that a shinno moved to the province to whose kokushu he was appointed, it can be said that the Imperial court approved the yonin system publicly</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it never happened that a shinno moved to the province to whose kokushu he was appointed, it can be said that the Imperial court publicly approved the yonin system</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it never happened that a shinno moved to the province to whose kokushu he was appointed, it can be said that the Imperial court publicly approved the yonin system.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>9世紀・10世紀頃になると、各地で富豪と呼ばれる有力農民が登場・成長していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ninth or tenth century, powerful farmers called fugo appeared and continued increasing their strength in various areas of the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the ninth or tenth century, powerful farmers called fugo appeared and continued to increase their strength in various areas of the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the ninth or tenth century, powerful farmers called fugo appeared and continued to increase their strength in various areas of the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>古代の戸籍制度・班田収授法などによる律令制的な人別支配の維持が困難となっていた当時、国司は公田を名田という単位へ再編するとともに、有力農民層（田堵という）へ名田の経営と名田からの租税徴収を請け負わせていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, it became difficult to maintain the control of each person like in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), based on a family registration system and Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of rice land), and therefore, kokushi (provincial governors) reorganized Koden (fields administered directly by a ruler) into myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) and became to entrust the work of managing myoden and collecting taxes from there to powerful farmers (called tato).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, it became difficult to maintain control over each person like in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), based on a family registration system and Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of rice land), and therefore, kokushi (provincial governors) reorganized Koden (fields administered directly by a ruler) into myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) and came to entrust the work of managing myoden and collecting taxes from there to powerful farmers (called tato).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, it became difficult to maintain control over each person like in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), based on a family registration system and Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of rice land), and therefore, kokushi (provincial governors) reorganized Koden (fields administered directly by a ruler) into myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder) and came to entrust the work of managing myoden and collecting taxes from there to powerful farmers (called tato).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>こうした支配体制を名体制（みょうたいせい）または王朝体制（おうちょうたいせい）などというが、これにより、国司は一定の租税収入を確保することができるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a control system was called myotaisei or ochotaisei, and with this system, kokushi became to able to secure a certain amount of tax income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a control system was called myotaisei or ochotaisei, and with this system, kokushi able to secure a certain amount of tax income.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a control system was called myotaisei or ochotaisei, and with this system, kokushi able to secure a certain amount of tax income.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>一定の租税額が確保できたことを背景として、朝廷は国司へ徴税・軍事などを委任していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With such a situation as a background, the Imperial court started entrusting tax collection and military affairs to kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against this background, the Imperial court started entrusting tax collection and military affairs to kokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against this background, the Imperial court started entrusting tax collection and military affairs to kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この体制を国司請負制ということがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is sometimes called Kokushi ukeoi sei (literally, a system entrusted to kokushi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is sometimes called Kokushi ukeoi sei (literally, a system entrusted to kokushi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is sometimes called Kokushi ukeoi sei (literally, a system entrusted to kokushi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>広範な権限を与えられた国司は、現地の有力者を登用したり、代理人（目代という）を派遣したりして、現地支配を行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given a wide-ranging right, kokushi became to control his assigned province through the local powerful persons he employed or his deputy (called mokudai) he sent to the province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given wide-ranging rights, kokushi came to control his assigned province through the local powerful persons he employed or his deputy (called mokudai) that he sent to the province</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given wide-ranging rights, kokushi came to control his assigned province through the local powerful persons he employed or his deputy (called mokudai) that he sent to the province.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そうなると、国司が任国へ赴任する必要が薄れて、実際に任国へ赴任しない国司が次々と現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the necessity of his moving to the assigned province became weak, and there appeared many kokushi, one after another, who did not move to their assigned provinces actually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the necessity of his moving to the assigned province became weak, and there appeared many kokushi, one after another, who did not actually move to their assigned provinces actually.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the necessity of his moving to the assigned province became weak, and there appeared many kokushi, one after another, who did not actually move to their assigned provinces actually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これが平安期の遥任であり、時期を追うごとに遥任国司は増加していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the yonin in the Heian period, and the number of yonin-kokushi increased with the times..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the yonin during the Heian period, and the number of yonin-kokushi increased with the times..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the yonin during the Heian period, and the number of yonin-kokushi increased with the times.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>こうした状況に対し、913年（延喜13年）、醍醐天皇が遥任国司を取り締まる法令を発したが、効果はあまりなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such a situation, Emperor Daigo issued in 913 a law to control yonin-kokushi, but could not gain any substantial results.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such a situation, Emperor Daigo issued in 913 a law to control yonin-kokushi, but could not gain any substantial results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such a situation, Emperor Daigo issued in 913 a law to control yonin-kokushi, but could not gain any substantial results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>平安中期ごろには、遥任は一般的に見られるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the middle era of the Heian period, yonin had become a usual practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the middle era of the Heian period, yonin had become a usual practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the middle era of the Heian period, yonin had become a usual practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして、実際に任国へ赴任した国司のうち、最高責任者を受領と呼ぶようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the head of kokushi who actually moved to their assigned province became called zuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the head of kokushi who actually moved to their assigned province became called zuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the head of kokushi who actually moved to their assigned province became called zuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>本来、国司の最高職は国守だったが、遥任により現地に在住しなかった場合は、介・掾・目のうちから受領が出ていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the highest position of kokushi was kokushu, but when kokushu did not live in his assigned province, a person at the rank of suke, jo or sakan (these ranks were in this order, with suke the highest) was appointed to zuryo.</e>
<cmt>(国司)|目：　原文にないので、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the highest position of kokushi was kokushu, but when kokushu did not live in his assigned province, a person at the rank of suke, jo or sakan (these ranks were in this order, with suke the highest) was appointed to zuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the highest position of kokushi was kokushu, but when kokushu did not live in his assigned province, a person at the rank of suke, jo or sakan (these ranks were in this order, with suke the highest) was appointed to zuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>その後、国司が実質的に消滅する室町時代まで、国司の遥任が収まることはなく、常態化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, until the Muromachi period when kokushi was extinct virtually, the yonin practice of kokushi did not stop and became ordinary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, until the Muromachi period when kokushi was virtually extinct, the yonin of kokushi did not stop and became ordinary practice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, until the Muromachi period when kokushi was virtually extinct, the yonin of kokushi did not stop and became ordinary practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 春野秋葉(id:36725), Shimoxx(id:9332), 梟(id:117930), Aloha-vodka(id:22493), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>