<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>健児</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kondei (Regular Soldiers Guarding Kokubu (Ancient Provincial Offices) or Sekisho (Checking station))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kondei (regular soldiers guarding the Kokubu (ancient provincial offices) or Sekisho (checking station))</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kondei (regular soldiers guarding the Kokubu (ancient provincial offices) or Sekisho (checking station))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>健児（こんでい）は、奈良時代から平安時代における地方軍事力として整備された軍団。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kondei&quot; means well-equipped cohorts which were organized as local military forces from Nara Period through Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kondei&quot; means well-equipped cohorts, which were organized as local military forces from the Nara period through the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kondei&quot; means well-equipped cohorts, which were organized as local military forces from the Nara period through the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>8世紀初頭に本格運用され始めた律令制においては、国家の軍事組織として全国各地に軍団 (古代日本)を置くこととしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cohorts (of ancient Japan) were deployed throughout the nation as the nation&apos;s military organization under the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on ritsuryo codes) which began to take full effect in the beginning of eighth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cohorts (of ancient Japan) were deployed throughout the nation as the nation&apos;s military organization under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on ritsuryo codes), which began to take full effect at the beginning of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cohorts were deployed throughout the country as the national military organization under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo codes), which began to take full effect at the beginning of the eighth century.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>軍団は3～4郡ごとに設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A cohort was allocated in every three or four counties.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A cohort was allocated to every three or four counties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A cohort was allocated to every three or four counties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>正丁（成年男子）3人に1人が兵士として徴発される規定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to its provisions, a cohort could commandeer one soldier out of three adult men.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to its provisions, a cohort could commandeer one out of three adult men to serve as a soldier.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to its provisions, a cohort could commandeer one out of three adult men as a soldier.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>天平6年4月23日（734年）に出された勅（天皇の命令）には、「健児・儲士・選士の租と雑徭を半分免除する」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the imperial decree issued on April 23, 734, it was described that kondei, choshi (non-regular soldiers) and senshi (soldiers guarding Kyushu region) were exempted from half of so (rice tax) and zoyo (irregular corvee.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the imperial decree issued on April 23, 734, it was described that kondei, choshi (non-regular soldiers) and senshi (soldiers guarding the Kyushu region) were exempted from half the so (rice tax) and zoyo (irregular corvee).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial decree issued on May 30, 734, said that kondei, choshi (non-regular soldiers) and senshi (soldiers guarding the Kyushu region) were exempted from a half amount of both so (rice tax) and zoyo (irregular corvee).</e>
<cmt>FB指示に従って修正の上、旧暦を西暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>健児は元々、軍団兵士の一区分だったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, kondei is believed to have been originally just one segment of a cohort.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it&apos;s believed that a kondei was originally one segment of a cohort.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it&apos;s believed that the term &quot;kondei&quot; originally referred to a status or a position of a cohort soldier.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天平10年（738年）には、北陸道と南海道を除く諸道で健児を停止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the year of 738, operation of kondei was totally suspended except on Hokuriku-do road and Nankai-do road.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the year 738, the operation of kondei was totally suspended except on the Hokuriku-do and Nankai-do roads.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 738, the operation of kondei was totally suspended in all regions except for the Hokuriku-do and the Nankai-do Regions.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これにより健児は一旦、ほぼ廃止することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this suspension, almost all kondei became abolished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this suspension, nearly all kondei were abolished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this suspension, nearly all kondei were temporarily abolished.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、天平宝字6年（762年）になって、健児が一部復活した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But later in 762, kondei system became partly revived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later in 762, the kondei system was partially revived.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the kondei system was partially revived in 762.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>伊勢国・近江国・美濃国・越前国の4か国において郡司の子弟と百姓の中から、20歳以上40歳以下で弓馬の訓練を受けた者を選んで健児とすることとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In four provinces of Ise, Omi, Mino and Echizen, kondei were formed with younger people selected from gunji (local magistrates) families and peasants, who were aged between 20 and 40 years old and trained in kyuba (archery and equestrianism.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the four provinces of Ise, Omi, Mino and Echizen, kondei were formed with younger people selected from the gunji (local magistrate) families and peasants of 20 to 40 years of age, and were trained in kyuba (archery and equestrianism).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the four provinces of Ise, Omi, Mino and Echizen, kondei were formed with people who were between 20 years old and 40 years old and were trained in archery and horseback riding, and they were selected from young members of gunji (local magistrate) families and peasants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>健児の置かれた4か国はいずれも畿内と東国の間に位置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those four provinces, where kondei were revived, are all located in between Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those four provinces, where kondei were revived, are all located between the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those four provinces, where kondei were revived, are all located between the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>当時最大の権力者だった恵美押勝（藤原仲麻呂）により、対東国防備の強化のため、健児を復活したのだとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that these kondei were restored by then greatest mogul EMI no Oshikatsu (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro) who intended to reinforce defences against Togoku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that these kondei were restored by the greatest mogul of that time, EMI no Oshikatsu (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro), who intended to reinforce the defenses against Togoku.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an opinion that these kondei were restored by the greatest mogul of that time, EMI no Oshikatsu (FUJIWARA no Nakamaro), who intended to reinforce the defenses against Togoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>8世紀末の桓武天皇は、現状との乖離が大きくなりつつあった律令制を再建するため、大規模な行政改革に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of eighth century, Emperor Kanmu started a large-scale administrative reform to reconstruct the ritsuryo system which was widening its difference from the real conditions..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the eighth century, Emperor Kanmu started a large-scale administrative reform in order to reconstruct the Ritsuryo system, which was becoming increasingly distant from the actual conditions.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the eighth century, Emperor Kanmu started a large-scale administrative reform in order to reconstruct the Ritsuryo system, which was becoming increasingly distant from the actual conditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その一環として、延暦11年6月（792年）、陸奥国・出羽国・佐渡国・西海道諸国を除く諸国の軍団・兵士を廃止し、代わって健児の制を布いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a part of this reform, in June of 792, he abolished cohorts and soldiers deployed in various provinces except such provinces as Mutsu, Dewa and Sado and other provinces along Saikaido Road, and then replaced them with kondei system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As part of that reform, in June 792 he abolished the use of cohorts and soldiers deployed in various provinces except for Mutsu, Dewa and Sado and other provinces along the Saikaido Road, and replaced them with the kondei system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As part of that reform, in June 792, he discharged cohorts and soldiers deployed in all provinces except for Mutsu Province, Dewa Province, Sado Province, and provinces in the Saikai-do Region, and established the kondei system instead.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この時の健児は天平宝字6年と同様、郡司の子弟と百姓のうち弓馬に秀でた者を選抜することとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Just like the case in 762, the restoration of kondei system this time was proceeded by recruiting young manpower preeminent in archery and equestrianism, selected from families of Gunji (local magistrates) and peasants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As was the case in 762, this restoration of the kondei system was preceded by the recruitment of young manpower with emphasis on archery and equestrianism; such men were selected from the families of the Gunji (local magistrates) and peasantry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This kondei system was established in the same way as the system of the year of 762, and consequently, people who were skilled in archery and horseback riding were selected from young members of gunji (local magistrate) families and peasants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>従前からの健児制を全国に拡大したものといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seen in this light, this time movement may be regarded just as an expansion of conventional kondei system throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considered in that light, this movement may be regarded as an expansion of the conventional kondei system throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that this system was the nationwide version of the older kondei system.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これにより、百姓らの兵役の負担はほぼ解消されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through this movement, peasants were mostly relieved of the burden of military services,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this movement, peasants were generally relieved of the burden of military service.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this movement, peasants were relieved of most part of their burden of military service.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、軍団・兵士が廃止されなかった地域、すなわち、佐渡・西海道では海外諸国の潜在的な脅威が存在していたし、陸奥・出羽では対蝦夷戦争が継続していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, those regions where conventional cohorts and soldiers were not abolished were either still facing potential threats from abroad, like Sado and other provinces along Saikaido road, or still continuing wars against Ezo (northerners), like Mutsu and Dewa provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, those regions in which conventional cohorts and soldiers were not abolished either continued to face potential threats from abroad, like Sado and other provinces along the Saikaido Road, or the continuing wars against the Ezo (northerners), such as Mutsu and Dewa provinces.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, as for those regions in which conventional cohorts and soldiers were not abolished, Sado Province and the Saika-do Region still faced potential threats from abroad, and Mutsu and Dewa Provinces continued fighting against Ezo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これらの地域では従前の軍制を維持する必要があったため、軍制の軽量化といえる健児制は導入されなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These regions were required to keep conventional military system, and for this reason they did not introduce kondei system which meant cutting down of the scale of current military system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These regions were required to maintain conventional military systems, and for that reason they didn&apos;t introduce the kondei system, which would have meant reducing the scale of their systems.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since these regions required the maintenance of the conventional military system, they didn&apos;t introduce the kondei system, which would have meant a scaled down military force to them.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、軍団が復活すると、健児は軍団の兵士として位置づけられ、10世紀ごろには、健児維持に用するための健児田が設定されたり、全国定員が約3600人（陸奥・出羽・佐渡にも置かれるようになったが、西海道には置かれなかった）とされていたことなどが判っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now, we have learnt that subsequently cohorts revived, and conventional kondei were taken into the cohort system to become their soldiers, that in around tenth century kondeiden (tax exempted rice fields for kondei) were laid down, and that number of members of all kondei throughout the nation was set to 3,600 including those of Mutsu, Dewa and Sado provinces where kondei were later additionally deployed (though no kondei was deployed in the provinces along Saikaido road.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">We have thus learned that the cohorts were subsequently revived, and that conventional kondei were taken into the cohort system to become soldiers; that in or around the tenth century, kondeiden (tax exempted rice fields for kondei) were laid down; and that the number of members of all kondei throughout the nation was set at 3,600, including those of Mutsu, Dewa and Sado provinces, where kondei were later additionally deployed (though kondei were not deployed in the provinces along the Saikaido Road).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been discovered that kondei soldiers were later included in the cohort system once the cohorts were revived, and subsequently, a special tax exemption system called kondei-den was established in order to maintain kondei, and approximately 3,600 kondei soldiers were deployed throughout the country (kondei were deployed in Mutsu, Dewa, and Sado Provinces as well, but not deployed in the Saikai-do Region) as a general rule in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>（延喜式などによる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Reference is made to the Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers.))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Reference is made to the Engishiki (an ancient book of codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Reference is made to the Engishiki (an ancient book of codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Shimoxx(id:9332), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), NDR(id:5500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>