<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>部民制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bemin sei (the system of Yamato Dynasty)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bemin System (the system of Yamato sovereignty)</e>
<cmt>system の方が分かりやすいと判断し、左記のようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bemin System (the system of Yamato sovereignty)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>部民制（べみんせい）とは、ヤマト王権の制度であり、王権への従属・奉仕の体制、朝廷の仕事分掌の体制をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bemin sei is the system of the Yamato sovereignty, and is the system of subordination and service to the sovereignty and the system of the division of duties of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bemin system is a system during the Yamato sovereignty, which refers to the system of subordination and service to the sovereignty and the system of the division of duties at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>bemin system と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bemin system is a system during the Yamato sovereignty, which refers to the system of subordination and service to the sovereignty and the system of the division of duties at the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その種類は極めて多く、大きく二つのグループに分けることが出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were extremely many types of bemin sei, and it is possible to separate these into two big groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were quite a few types of bemin system, which can roughly be divided into two groups.</e>
<cmt>bemin system と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were quite a few types of bemin system, which can roughly be divided into two groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一つは何らかの仕事にかかわる一団で、もう一つは王宮や豪族に所属する一団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is a group which was involved in some kind of duty, and the other is a group which belonged with the royal palace or a powerful family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is a group which was involved in some kind of duties, and the other is a group which belonged to the royal palace or a powerful family.</e>
<cmt>belonged to としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is a group which was involved in some kind of duties, and the other is a group which belonged to the royal palace or a powerful family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>前者には語部・馬飼部、後者には蘇我氏・大伴氏などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the former, kataribe (reciter) and umakaibe (horse caretakers), and for the latter, the Soga clan and the Otomo clan are examples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples for the former group include kataribe (reciter) and umakaibe (horse caretakers), and those for the latter group include the Soga clan and the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples for the former group include kataribe (reciter) and umakaibe (horse caretakers), and those for the latter group include the Soga clan and the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>語部は、伴造（とものみやつこ）である語造（かたりべのみやつこ）氏に率いられ、朝廷の儀式の場で詞章（かたりごと）を奏することをその職掌とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kataribe&apos;s job was to recite verses for the ceremonies of the Imperial Court led by Kataribenomiyako, who was a Tomonomiyatsuko (chief of various departments at the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kataribe&apos;s job was to recite verses for the ceremonies of the Imperial Court led by Kataribenomiyatsuko clan, who was a Tomonomiyatsuko (chief of various departments at the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kataribe&apos;s job was to recite verses for the ceremonies of the Imperial Court led by Kataribenomiyatsuko clan, who was a Tomonomiyatsuko (chief of various departments at the Imperial Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>蘇我氏や大伴氏が蘇我部や大伴部を所有しえたのも、彼らが王権を支える臣・連として、朝廷組織のなかにその位置を占めていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Soga clan and the Otomo Clan were able to own most of the Sogabe and Otomobe also because, as subjects who supported the sovereignty, they held much of these positions in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Soga clan and the Otomo clan were able to own the Sogabe (group of people owned by the Soga clan) and Otomobe (group of people owned by the Otomo clan) also because, as the clans with Omi and Muraji (both are one of the hereditary titles) who supported the sovereignty, they held many positions in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>蘇我部→group of people who owned by the Soga clan　としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Soga clan and the Otomo clan were able to own the Sogabe (group of people owned by the Soga clan) and Otomobe (group of people owned by the Otomo clan) also because, as the clans with Omi and Muraji (both are one of the hereditary titles) who supported the sovereignty, they held many positions in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>律令制の実施に伴って廃止されていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bemin sei started to abolish with the enforcement of the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bemin system began to be abolished with the enforcement of the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>bemin system と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bemin system began to be abolished with the enforcement of the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>律令制の実施後の部称は、たんに父系の血縁を表示するだけの称号であるにすぎず、所属する集団との関係を示すものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of be after the enforcement of the ritsuryo system were merely titles which just indicated a blood relationship with the paternal line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names of the be (division) after the enforcement of the ritsuryo system were merely titles which just showed a blood relationship with the paternal line, and did not indicate the relationship to the group to which one belonged.</e>
<cmt>be (division）と補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names of the be (division) after the enforcement of the ritsuryo system were merely titles which just showed a blood relationship with the paternal line, and did not indicate the relationship to the group to which one belonged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>670年（天智9）の古代の戸籍制度庚午（こうご）の年籍（こうごのねんじゃく）以後、すべての人民が戸籍に登録されるようになると、部称は個人の姓として残され、以後は代々父系によって継承されることになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the ancient family registration system, Kogo no Nenjyaku, in 670 and every citizen registered their name on the family register, the name of the be was left as an individual&apos;s surname and afterwards it was succeeded for generations by the paternal side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the enforcement of Koko no Nenjaku, which was the ancient family registration system in 670, every citizen registered their name on the family register, and the name of the be was left as an individual&apos;s surname and afterwards it was succeeded for generations by the paternal line.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the enforcement of Koko no Nenjaku, which was the ancient family registration system in 670, every citizen registered their name on the family register, and the name of the be was left as an individual&apos;s surname and afterwards it was succeeded for generations by the paternal line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>部民制の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment of the bemin sei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The establishment of the bemin system</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。bemin system と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The establishment of the bemin system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>5世紀頃には、畿内の及びその周辺の中小豪族をトノモリ（殿守）・モヒトリ（水取）・カニモリ（掃守）・カドモリ（門守）など、宮廷の各種の職務を世襲的に分掌する「トモ」として、大王 (ヤマト王権)のもとに組織する体制が成立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the 5th century, as a &quot;Tomo&quot; which divided the the small and medium local ruling families in the Kinai region (in and around the capital) and areas around it into various duties of the Imperial Court hereditarily, such as Tonomori, Mohitori, Kanimori, and Kadomori, an organization was established under the great king (Yamato sovereignty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the fifth century, a &apos;Tomo&apos; system was already established under the great king (Yamato sovereignty), in which small and medium local ruling families in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and areas around it were divided into various duties of the Imperial Court hereditarily, such as Tonomori, Mohitori, Kanimori, and Kadomori.</e>
<cmt>語順を変更しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the fifth century, a &apos;Tomo&apos; system was already established under the great king (Yamato sovereignty), in which small and medium local ruling families in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) and areas around it were divided into various duties of the Imperial Court hereditarily, such as Tonomori, Mohitori, Kanimori, and Kadomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのようなトモ制の拡大・発展の結果、5世紀後半には、さらにトモノミヤツコ（伴造）がトモ（伴）を率いるという体制も整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of the development and expansion of this kind of Tomo system, by the later half of the 5th century, a system in which the Tomonomiyatsuko (chief of various departments at the Imperial Court) leads the Tomo was prepared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of the development and expansion of such Tomo system, by the latter half of the fifth century, a system was organized in which the Tomonomiyatsuko led the Tomo.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of the development and expansion of such Tomo system, by the latter half of the fifth century, a system was organized in which the Tomonomiyatsuko led the Tomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>氏姓制度（うじかばねせいど）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of clans and hereditary titles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of clans and hereditary titles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system of clans and hereditary titles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>ヤマト政権の豪族層は、氏と呼ばれる組織を形成していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The powerful family class of the Yamato regime formed an organization called &quot;uji.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The powerful family class of the Yamato regime formed an organization called uji (clan).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークを削除しました。氏→uji (clan) と補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The powerful family class of the Yamato regime formed an organization called uji (clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>蘇我氏・紀氏・大伴氏・物部氏・秦氏・漢氏・忌部氏・史氏等をはじめ大小幾多のウジがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many uji, large and small, starting with uji such as the Soga clan, the Ki clan, the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan, the Hata clan, the Kan clan, the Inbe clan, and the Shi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many uji, large and small, such as the Soga clan, the Ki clan, the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan, the Hata clan, the Kan clan, the Inbe clan, and the Shi clan.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many uji, large and small, such as the Soga clan, the Ki clan, the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan, the Hata clan, the Kan clan, the Inbe clan, and the Shi clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>古代のウジは、血縁関係ないし血縁意識によって結ばれた多くの家よりなる同族集団で、有力家族の長が氏上（うじのかみ、うじがみ）となり、族長的な地位に立っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient uji were peer groups of many families joined by blood relationships or blood consciousness, and the head of a powerful family became the head of the uji and occupied a position similar to the head of a clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient uji were peer groups of many families joined by blood relationships or blood consciousness, and the head of a powerful family became the head of the uji and occupied a position similar to the head of a clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient uji were peer groups of many families joined by blood relationships or blood consciousness, and the head of a powerful family became the head of the uji and occupied a position similar to the head of a clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その直系・傍系の血縁者や非血縁者の家族を氏人（うじびと）といい、これに隷属し統率されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family of the blood relatives or unrelated members who were in direct or a collateral line to the head uji were called ujibito and were under the rule of the head uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family of the blood relatives or unrelated members who were in a direct or a collateral line to the head uji were called ujibito and were under the rule of the head uji.</e>
<cmt>a direct としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family of the blood relatives or unrelated members who were in a direct or a collateral line to the head uji were called ujibito and were under the rule of the head uji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>ウジは、ヤマト政権の政治組織という性格をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The uji had a characteristic of being a political organization of the Yamato regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uji had a characteristic of being a political organization of the Yamato regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uji had a characteristic of being a political organization of the Yamato regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ウジはたんに自然発生的に形成された血縁的集団ではなく、大王に臣従を誓い、奉仕することを義務づけられた血縁的集団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The uji were not just a group of blood relatives who formed by a natural occurrence, but were a group of blood relatives who swore vassalage to the great king, and were obliged to serve the great king.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uji were not just a group of blood relatives who were formed by a natural occurrence, but were a group of blood relatives who swore vassalage to and were obliged to serve the great king.</e>
<cmt>the great king を一箇所削除しました。Who were formed としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uji were not just a group of blood relatives who were formed by a natural occurrence, but were a group of blood relatives who swore vassalage to and were obliged to serve the great king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>中央・地方のウジは、大王との間に隷属・奉仕の関係を結び、それを前提にして氏上は朝廷における一定の政治的地位や官職・職務に就く資格と、それを世襲する権利を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The uji in the capital and provinces established a relationship with the great king of subordinate and server, and on this premise, they were given the license to take up fixed political standings and government posts/duties along with the right to make these hereditary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uji in the capital and local provinces established a relationship with the great king of vassalage and service, and on this premise, they were given the license to take up fixed political standings and government posts/duties along with the right to make them hereditary.</e>
<cmt>隷属・奉仕→vassalage and service　としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uji in the capital and local provinces established a relationship with the great king of vassalage and service, and on this premise, they were given the license to take up fixed political standings and government posts/duties along with the right to make them hereditary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、その出自（しゅつじ）や政治的地位・官職の高下・職務内容の違いに応じて、カバネを賜与され、部民（べみん）などの隷属民を領有することを認められたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the uji were given kabane (hereditary titles) according to differences in their status by birth and political status/rank of government post/content of duty, and it was permitted for them to own subordinates such as the bemin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the uji were given kabane (hereditary titles) according to differences in their status by birth and political status/rank of government post/content of duty, and it was permitted for them to own subordinates such as the bemin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the uji were given kabane (hereditary titles) according to differences in their status by birth and political status/rank of government post/content of duty, and it was permitted for them to own subordinates such as the bemin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="22">
<j>一般に氏姓（うじかばね）制といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally this is called the ujikabane system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Generally this is called the ujikabane system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Generally this is called the ujikabane system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>カバネには臣（おみ）・連（むらじ）・伴造（とものみやつこ）・国造（くにのみやつこ）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabane includes Omi, Muraji, Tomonomiyatsuko (chief of various departments at the Imperial Court), and Kuninomiyatsuko (heads of local governments).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabane includes Omi, Muraji, Tomonomiyatsuko and Kuninomiyatsuko (heads of local governments).</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabane includes Omi, Muraji, Tomonomiyatsuko and Kuninomiyatsuko (heads of local governments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="24">
<j>ウジの組織は、5世紀末以降、史料から確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The organization of uji can be confirmed by historical materials after the end of the fifth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The organization of uji can be confirmed by historical materials after the end of the fifth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The organization of uji can be confirmed by historical materials after the end of the fifth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>広範に整備されるのは6世紀のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is in the sixth century, when the uji developed extensively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is in the sixth century, when the uji developed extensively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is in the sixth century, when the uji developed extensively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>臣（おみ）と連（むらじ）は、基本的な違いが存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There existed a fundamental difference between the Omi and Muraji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There existed a fundamental difference between Omi and Muraji.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There existed a fundamental difference between Omi and Muraji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>それは、臣と称する豪族は、蘇我氏・吉備氏など、一般に地名をウジの名とし、それぞれの地域を基盤とする首長であったのに対して、連と称した豪族は、大伴氏・物部氏など、トモとしての職掌を名にもつ伴造のウジとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to the powerful family who called themselves Omi, who generally used place names for their uji names, such as the Soga clan and Kibi clan and were chiefs who used their area as base, the powerful family who called themselves Muraji made the Tomonomiyatsuko (chief of various departments at the Imperial Court) who held the names of their official duties as a Tomo, such as the Otomo clan and Mononobe clan, the uji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to the powerful clans who called themselves Omi, who generally used place names for their uji names, such as the Soga clan and Kibi clan and were chiefs who used their area as a base, those who called themselves Muraji had the uji name after the Tomonomiyatsuko who had the names of their official duties as a Tomo, such as the Otomo clan and Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。2箇所目のThe powerful family →those に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to the powerful clans who called themselves Omi, who generally used place names for their uji names, such as the Soga clan and Kibi clan and were chiefs who used their area as a base, those who called themselves Muraji had the uji name after the Tomonomiyatsuko who had the names of their official duties as a Tomo, such as the Otomo clan and Mononobe clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>つまり、臣は王権に対して相対的な独自性を有するが、連は大王への臣従をその本質としたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the Omi were relatively independent towards the regime, but the Muraji made vassalage to the great king their essential.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, Omi were relatively independent towards the regime, while Muraji regarded vassalage to the great king their essential.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, Omi were relatively independent towards the regime, while Muraji regarded vassalage to the great king their essential.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="29">
<j>伴造氏族の成立は、雄略天皇朝において認められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The establishment of the Tomonomiyatsuko clan was approved by Emperor Yuryaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The establishment of the Tomonomiyatsuko clan can be confirmed during the era of Emperor Yuryaku.</e>
<cmt>認められる→can be confirmed に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The establishment of the Tomonomiyatsuko clan can be confirmed during the era of Emperor Yuryaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>金錯銘鉄剣にみえるヲワケは、杖刀人集団（トモ）を率いる伴造であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owake, which is seen on an iron sword with gold inscription, was the Tomonomiyatsuko who led a group of jyotonin (Tomo).</e>
<cmt>杖刀人の適訳がみつからなかったので、そのままローマ字にしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Owake, which is seen on an iron sword with gold inscription, was the Tomonomiyatsuko who led a group of jotojin (guardsmen) (Tomo).</e>
<cmt>杖刀人→jotojin (guardsmen)　としました。（杖刀人は近衛兵のような役割をしていたため）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Owake, which is seen on an iron sword with gold inscription, was the Tomonomiyatsuko who led a group of jotojin (guardsmen) (Tomo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="31">
<j>品部、部曲・民部、子代・名代・御名代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe (technicians in offices), kakibe, koshiro/nashiro/minashiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe (technicians in offices), kakibe, koshiro/nashiro/minashiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe (technicians in offices), kakibe, koshiro/nashiro/minashiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>今日の一般的な理解は次のようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The present general view of these are in the following paragraphs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today&apos;s general view of these are in the following paragraphs.</e>
<cmt>today&apos;s としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today&apos;s general view of these are in the following paragraphs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="33">
<j>品部（しなべ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe (technicians in offices)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>海部（あまべ）、飼部（かいべ（犬・鳥・馬など））などのように具体的な仕事名を帯びる部のことで、それぞれ伴造に統率され、朝廷に所属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amabe was a division which took on specific work names such as kaibe (dogs, birds, horses), and each of these were led by the tomonomiyatsuko, and belonged to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A division which took on specific work names such as amabe and kaibe (dogs, birds, horses), each of which was led by the tomonomiyatsuko, and belonged to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A division which took on specific work names such as amabe and kaibe (dogs, birds, horses), each of which was led by the tomonomiyatsuko, and belonged to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="35">
<j>子代（こしろ）・御名代（みなしろ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshiro/Minashiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshiro/Minashiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshiro/Minashiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>刑部（おさかべ）・額田部（ぬかたべ）など、王（宮）名のついた部のことで、伴造に統括される一種の品部であるが、特に王家・王族の所有である点が特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshiro/Minashiro were divisions named after names of kings (imperial), such as osakabe and nukatabe, and were a kind of shinabe unified by the tomonomiyatsuko, and it&apos;s characteristic was that they particularly belonged to the royal family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Divisions named after names of kings (princes), such as osakabe and nukatabe, which were a kind of shinabe controlled by the tomonomiyatsuko, with a characteristic that they particularly belonged to the royal families.</e>
<cmt>宮→prince としました。一文につなげました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Divisions named after names of kings (princes), such as osakabe and nukatabe, which were a kind of shinabe controlled by the tomonomiyatsuko, with a characteristic that they particularly belonged to the royal families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>品部は、舎人（とねり）・靫負（ゆげい）・膳夫（かしわで）などとして奉仕する</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinabe served as a toneri (palace servant), yugei (gate guard), kashiwade (cook), and such.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinabe served as a toneri (palace servant), yugei (gate guard), kashiwade (cook), and such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinabe served as a toneri (palace servant), yugei (gate guard), kashiwade (cook), and such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="38">
<j>部曲（かきべ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakibe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakibe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakibe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>諸豪族の所有民で、蘇我部・大伴部など、豪族の名を帯びる部である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakibe were divisions of people owned by many powerful families, which carried the names of the powerful family, such as Sogabe and Otomobe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A division of people owned by many powerful clans, which carried their names such as Sogabe and Otomobe.</e>
<cmt>表現を他と統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A division of people owned by many powerful clans, which carried their names such as Sogabe and Otomobe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="40">
<j>部とその所有者との関係を軸とした説明であるが、異論も多いようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a description centered around the relationship of be and their owners, but there also looks to be much objection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Above is a description centered around the relationship between the divisions and their owners, but there also seems to be many objections.</e>
<cmt>many objections としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Above is a description centered around the relationship between the divisions and their owners, but there also seems to be many objections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>（ここは、鎌田元一や前之園亮一の部民制を主に参考にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The bemin sei of Motokazu KAMADA and Ryoichi MAENOSONO were mainly referenced here).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The bemin system studied by Motokazu KAMADA and Ryoichi MAENOSONO were mainly referenced here.)</e>
<cmt>studied by を追加しました。Bemin system としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The bemin system studied by Motokazu KAMADA and Ryoichi MAENOSONO were mainly referenced here.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Mikeneko(id:18205), Non-stop24(id:10471), Ceridwen(id:36889), Kinori(id:443), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shikire(id:1623), Shimoxx(id:9332), Woodport(id:26192), 竹麦魚(id:11012), BAKU(id:55205), 彩華1226(id:64711), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>