<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>家領</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keryo (family holdings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keryo (family holdings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keryo</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>家領（けりょう）とは中世の権門が代々伝領してきた所領・荘園などのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keryo was such holdings as shoryo (individual estate) and shoen (landed estate) inherited by kenmon (ruling elite) for generations in the Medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keryo were such holdings as shoryo (individual estates) and shoen (landed estates) inherited by kenmon (ruling elite) for generations in Medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keryo were such holdings as shoryo (individual estates) and shoen (manor in medieval Japan) inherited by kenmon (an influential family) for generations in Medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>奈良時代末期から平安時代初期に皇親・貴族が所有して家牒・家符・家印などを用いた命令文書で家司などに命じて経営させた初期荘園を「○○家領」「××家田」などと呼称したのが最初と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered that the first example of keryo was the early shoen which was owned by koshin (imperial family) or court nobles who ordered ie no tsukasa (house steward) or the like via order documents using kacho (tag), kafu (code), iejirushi (house mark showing ownership of the family) to operate the holding from the end of the Nara period to the early Heian period -- They were called &apos;XX keryo&apos; (XX family&apos;s holding) or &apos;XX kaden&apos; (XX family&apos;s paddy field.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered that the first example of keryo was of the early shoen which were owned by koshin (the Imperial family) or court nobles who ordered ie no tsukasa (house stewards) and the like via order documents using a kacho (tag), kafu (code), and iejirushi (house mark showing ownership by the family) to operate the holding from the end of the Nara Period to the early Heian Period; they were called &apos;XX keryo&apos; (XX family&apos;s holding) or &apos;XX kaden&apos; (XX family&apos;s paddy field).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered that the first example of keryo was of the early shoen which were owned by koshin (the Imperial family) or court nobles who ordered Ie no tsukasa (house stewards) and the like via order documents using a kacho (tag), kafu (code), and iejirushi (house mark showing ownership by the family) to operate the holding from the end of the Nara period to the early Heian period; they were called &apos;XX keryo&apos; (XX family&apos;s holding) or &apos;XX kaden&apos; (XX family&apos;s paddy field).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中期以後、藤原北家などの藤原氏一族が更に細分化され、九条流・小野宮流・閑院流などが成立し、やがて九条流から派生した御堂流が摂家としての地位を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the mid Heian period, the Fujiwara clan including the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan was subdivided into the Kujo line, Ononomiya line, Kanin line and the like, and the Mido line which derived from the Kujo line established the status of sekke (the line of regents.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the mid Heian Period, the Fujiwara clan including the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, was subdivided into the Kujo line, Ononomiya line, Kanin line and the like, and the Mido line which derived from the Kujo line established the status of sekke (the line of regents).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the mid Heian period, the Fujiwara clan including the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan, was subdivided into the Kujo line, Ononomiya line, Kanin line and the like, and the Mido line which derived from the Kujo line established the status of Sekke (line of regents and advisers).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その過程でそれぞれの氏や家に附属する所領や荘園、持仏堂などの施設が一族内部を統制する機能を持ち、氏長者や家長などの本主によって管理されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that process, shoryo and shoen which belonged to each clan and each house as well as facility such as jibutsudo (Buddhist sanctuary) had assumed functions to control the clan; then, the main family such as Uji no Choja (chieftain) or kacho (family head) began to manage them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that process, shoryo and shoen which belonged to each clan and each house, as well as facilities such as jibutsudo (Buddhist sanctuaries) had assumed functions to control the clan; at that time, the main family such as Uji no Choja (chieftain) or kacho (family head) began to manage them.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that process, shoryo and shoen which belonged to each clan and each house, as well as facilities such as jibutsudo (Buddhist sanctuaries) had assumed functions to control the clan; at that time, the main family such as Uji no Choja (chieftain) or kacho (family head) began to manage them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そうした所領や荘園をそれぞれの本主の官職・位階に基づいて区別され、本主の政所によって統括され、家司を預所に補任して荘務を行わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those shoryo and shoen were classified according to kanshoku (official position) and ikai (court rank) of respective main family, controlled over by mandokoro (administrative office) of the main family, and ie no tsukasa was appointed to carry out the duty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those shoryo and shoen were classified according to the kanshoku (official position) and ikai (court rank) of the respective main family, controlled over by the mandokoro (administrative office) of the main family, and the ie no tsukasa was appointed to carry out the role.</e>
<cmt>Word choice, grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those shoryo and shoen were classified according to the kanshoku (official position) and ikai (court rank) of the respective main family, controlled over by the mandokoro (administrative office) of the main family, and the Ie no tsukasa was appointed to carry out the role.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>家領の権利書である公験は家記などとともに代々嫡男などの後継者に継承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kugen (a standard deed acknowledging a holder&apos;s ownership), which was deed of keryo, was inherited for generations by heir such as a legitimate son along with kaki (records inherited within the family.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kugen (a standard deed acknowledging a holder&apos;s ownership), which was a deed of the keryo, was inherited for generations by an heir such as a legitimate son, along with the kaki (records inherited within the family.)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kugen (a standard deed acknowledging a holder&apos;s ownership), which was a deed of the keryo, was inherited for generations by an heir such as a legitimate son, along with the kaki (records inherited within the family).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>権門の中でも最大の家領を有していたのは、御堂流摂関家であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the kenmon, Mido line sekkanke owned the biggest karyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the kenmon, the Mido line sekkanke owned the biggest karyo.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the kenmon, the Mido line Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) owned the biggest karyo.</e>
<cmt>用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元は藤氏長者としての所領を中核としていたが、後には氏院である勧学院や同流ゆかりの寺院である法成寺や平等院などの寺院領が摂関家の家領として扱われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the shoryo the family owned as the chieftain of the Fujiwara clan mainly accounted for the family&apos;s holdings; but later, kangakuin (school founded in Heian-kyo) which was Uji no In (cerebrated villa), jiinryo (holdings of temple) such as Hosei-ji Temple or Byodo-in Temple which were temples closely related with the line of the house, became to be treated as keryo of the sekkanke (the Fujiwara regent&apos;s line.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the shoryo the family owned as the chieftain of the Fujiwara clan mainly accounted for the family&apos;s holdings; but later, the kangakuin (a school founded in Heian-kyo) which was Uji no In (celebrated villa), jiinryo (the holdings of a temple) such as of Hosei-ji Temple or Byodo-in Temple which were temples closely related with the line of the house, became treated as keryo of the sekkanke (the Fujiwara regent&apos;s line).</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the shoryo the family owned as the chieftain of the Fujiwara clan mainly accounted for the family&apos;s holdings; but later, the kangakuin (a school founded in Heian-kyo [the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto]) which was Uji no In (celebrated villa), jiinryo (the holdings of a temple) such as of Hosei-ji Temple or Byodo-in Temple which were temples closely related with the line of the house, became treated as keryo of the Sekkan-ke (the Fujiwara regent&apos;s line).</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、摂関家の分立に伴ってこうした家領は渡領（殿下渡領）として摂関・藤氏長者の地位とともに移動し、院政期以後に摂関家の財産となった所領・荘園は近衛家・九条家などに分割され、後に5つに分立したそれぞれの摂関家固有の家領として確立されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, as the sekkanke branched, the aforementioned keryo were transferred as watariryo (land transferred from lord to lord) (or, denka watariryo) with the rank of sekkan and the chieftain of the Fujiwara clan; the shoryo and shoen which were added to the estate of the sekkanke after the insei (rule by cloistered emperor) period was divided among the Konoe family, the Kujo family, and the like; and later, they were established as the keryo inherent to respective five branched sekkanke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, as the sekkanke were divided, the aforementioned keryo were transferred as watariryo (land transferred from lord to lord), or denka watariryo, with the rank of sekkan and the chieftain of the Fujiwara clan; the shoryo and shoen which were added to the estate of the sekkanke after the insei (period of rule by a cloistered emperor) was divided among the Konoe family, the Kujo family, and the like; and later, they were established as the keryo inherent to respective five branched sekkanke.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, as the Sekkan-ke were divided, the aforementioned keryo were transferred as watariryo (land transferred from lord to lord) (also known as denka watariryo), with the rank of sekkan and the chieftain of the Fujiwara clan; the shoryo and shoen which were added to the estate of the Sekkan-ke after the insei (period of rule by a cloistered emperor) was divided among the Konoe family, the Kujo family, and the like; and later, they were established as the keryo inherent to respective five branched Sekkan-ke.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>