<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>下克上</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekokujo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekokujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekokujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>下剋上 / 下克上 （げこくじょう）とは、日本史において下位の者が上位の者を政治的、軍事的に打倒して身分秩序を侵す行為をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gekokujo (&quot;the low overturn the high,&quot; a term used to describe retainers overthrowing their lords) describes situations when a person of lower rank overthrows a superior either politically or militarily, and then supplants the superior&apos;s position in society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gekokujo (&quot;the low overturning the high,&quot; a term used to describe retainers overthrowing their lords) describes situations that occur when a person of lower rank overthrows a superior either politically or militarily, and then supplants the superior&apos;s position in society.</e>
<cmt>&quot;overturn&quot; changed to overturning, &quot;situations when&quot; changed to &quot;situations that occur when&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gekokujo (&quot;the low overturning the high,&quot; a term used to describe retainers overthrowing their lords) describes situations in Japanese history that occur when a person of lower rank overthrows a superior either politically or militarily, and then supplants the superior&apos;s position in society.</e>
<cmt>意味不明瞭。文中順番を変更するかたちで修正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>Summaryに修正</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>用語としては鎌倉時代から南北朝時代 (日本)より見られ、鎌倉時代後期から出現した自らの既得権益を守るために権力と戦う悪党や、南北朝時代の社会的風潮であった「ばさら」も下剋上の一種とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a term, gekokujo was in use from the Kamakura period through to the Nanbokucho period; examples of gekokujo include the scoundrels that started to appear near the end of the Kamakura period and fought against the authorities in order to protect their own vested interests, as well as the anti-authoritarian social movement known as &quot;basara&quot; (&quot;vajra&quot; in Sanskrit) that occurred during the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a term, gekokujo was in use from the Kamakura period through to the Nanbokucho period; examples of gekokujo include the scoundrels that started to appear near the end of the Kamakura period who fought against the authorities in order to protect their own vested interests, as well as the anti-authoritarian social movement known as &quot;basara&quot; (&quot;vajra&quot; in Sanskrit) that occurred during the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot; changed to &quot;who&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a term, gekokujo was in use from the Kamakura period through to the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan); examples of gekokujo include the scoundrels that started to appear near the end of the Kamakura period who fought against the authorities in order to protect their own vested interests, as well as the anti-authoritarian social movement known as &quot;basara&quot; (&quot;vajra&quot; in Sanskrit) that occurred during the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Nanbokucho period&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>足利尊氏は1336年に制定した幕府の基本法典である「建武式目」にてばさらを禁止している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basara activities were banned in the Kemmu Code, the fundamental code of laws for the shogunate established by Takauji ASHIKAGA in 1336.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basara activities were banned in the Kemmu Code, which was the fundamental code of laws for the shogunate established by Takauji ASHIKAGA in 1336.</e>
<cmt>&quot;which was&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basara activities were banned in the Kenmu Code, which was the fundamental code of laws for the shogunate established by Takauji ASHIKAGA in 1336.</e>
<cmt>Kemmu→kenmu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>「下剋上する成出者」と二条河原の落書に唄われ戦国時代 (日本)の社会的風潮を象徴する言葉ともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term also appeared in the phrase &quot;Those who establish themselves by gekokujo (overthrowing their lords)&quot; in the book &quot;Scrawlings from the Nijo gawara,&quot; coming to be used as a symbol of the social tendencies of the Warring States period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term also appeared in the phrase &quot;Those who establish themselves by gekokujo (overthrowing their lords)&quot; in the book &quot;Scrawlings from the Nijo gawara,&quot; coming to be used as a symbol of the social tendencies of the Warring States period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term also appeared in the phrase &quot;Those who establish themselves by gekokujo (overthrowing their lords)&quot; in the book &quot;Scrawlings from the Nijo gawara,&quot; coming to be used as a symbol of the social tendencies of the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Warring States period→the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>公家は武家に、将軍は管領に、守護は守護代にと下位の者に実権を奪われ、こうした状況を下剋上と理解するのが、当時のほぼ一般的な観念だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When we look back on historic situations where a lower-ranked group usurped the authority of their superiors, as when the aristocracy was overthrown by the military class, the Shogun by the Kanrei, and the Protectors (essentially provincial governors) by their deputy Protectors, we label it &quot;gekokujo,&quot; but for people actually in the Warring States period, such situations were more or less par for the course.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When we look back on historic situations where a lower-ranked group usurped the authority of their superiors, as when the aristocracy was overthrown by the samurai class, the Shogun by the Kanrei, and the Protectors (essentially provincial governors) by their deputy Protectors, we label it &quot;gekokujo,&quot; but for people actually in the Warring States period, such situations were more or less par for the course.</e>
<cmt>&quot;military&quot; replaced with &quot;samurai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When we look back on historic situations where a lower-ranked group usurped the authority of their superiors, as when the aristocracy was overthrown by the samurai class, the Shogun by the Kanrei (shogunal deputy), and the Protectors (essentially provincial governors) by their deputy Protectors, we label it &quot;gekokujo,&quot; but for people in fact in the Sengoku Period, such situations were more or less par for the course.</e>
<cmt>(shogunal deputy)補足Warring States period→the Sengoku Period&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、一族衆が宗家の地位を奪って戦国大名化する例は枚挙にいとまがないほどであり、例えば、島津忠良・南部晴政・里見義堯らの事例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, cases where members of a given family usurped the position of head of the family and made themselves daimyo (warlords) are too numerous to count; examples include Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, Harumasa NANBU, and Yoshitaka SATOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, cases where members of a given family usurped the position of head of the family and made themselves daimyo (warlords) are too numerous to count; examples include Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, Harumasa NANBU, and Yoshitaka SATOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, cases where members of a given family usurped the position of head of the family and made themselves daimyo (territorial lords) are too numerous to count; examples include Tadayoshi SHIMAZU, Harumasa NANBU, and Yoshitaka SATOMI.</e>
<cmt>warlords→territorial lords</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>下剋上を鎌倉期から武家社会に見られた主君押込め慣行として理解する見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One point of view holds that the custom of shukun oshikome (shutting away/neutralizing one&apos;s lord) often seen among warrior society in the Kamakura period is another type of gekokujo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One point of view holds that the custom of shukun oshikome (shutting away/neutralizing one&apos;s lord) often seen among the warrior society in the Kamakura period is another type of gekokujo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;warrior&quot; changed to &quot;the warrior&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One point of view holds that the custom of shukun oshikome (shutting away/neutralizing one&apos;s lord) often seen among the warrior society in the Kamakura period is another type of gekokujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>中世の武家社会において、主君は家臣にとって必ずしも絶対的な存在ではなく、主君と家臣団は相互に依存・協力しあう運命共同体であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the warrior society of the medieval period, the existence and position of a lord was not necessarily guaranteed or absolute to his retainers; instead, lords and their group of retainers had a shared fate, and were in a relationship of mutual cooperation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the samurai society of the medieval period, the existence and position of a lord was not necessarily guaranteed or absolute to his retainers; instead, lords and their group of retainers had a shared fate, and their relationship was one of mutual cooperation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;warrior&quot; replaced with &quot;samurai,&quot; last sentence after comma, sentence construction changed for clarity and ease of reading</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the samurai society of the medieval period, the existence and position of a lord was not necessarily guaranteed or absolute to his retainers; instead, lords and their group of retainers had a shared fate, and their relationship was one of mutual cooperation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、家臣団の意向を無視する主君は、しばしば家臣団の衆議によって廃立され、時には家臣団の有力者が衆議に基づいて新たな主君となることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, those lords who ignored the desires and ideas of their retainers were often driven from power and replaced by someone else via a meeting of the retainers, and occasionally a powerful retainer would install himself as the new lord with the support of the group of retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, those lords who ignored the desires and ideas of their retainers were often driven from power and replaced by someone else via a meeting of the retainers, and occasionally a powerful retainer would install himself as the new lord with the support of the group of retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, those lords who ignored the desires and ideas of their retainers were often driven from power and replaced by someone else via a meeting of the retainers, and occasionally a powerful retainer would install himself as the new lord with the support of the group of retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>こうした傾向は室町期に顕著となり、赤松氏による将軍足利義教の殺害（嘉吉の乱）、細川政元による将軍足利義材の廃立（明応の政変）、松永久秀による将軍足利義輝の殺害は、いずれも将軍家に対する主君押込めとして理解することが可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This sort of tendency is a striking feature of the Muromachi period; Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA being assassinated by the Akamatsu clan (in the Kakitsu Revolt), Shogun Yoshiki ASHIKAGA being driven from power by Masamoto HOSOKAWA and replaced (in the Meio Coup), and Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA&apos;s assassination by Hisahide MATSUNAGA can all be understood as examples of shukun oshikome (shutting away/ neutralizing their lords) against the Shogunal family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This sort of tendency is a striking feature of the Muromachi period; Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA being assassinated by the Akamatsu clan (in the Kakitsu Revolt), Shogun Yoshiki ASHIKAGA being driven from power by Masamoto HOSOKAWA and replaced (in the Meio Coup), and Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA&apos;s assassination by Hisahide MATSUNAGA can all be understood as examples of shukun oshikome (shutting away/ neutralizing their lords) against the Shogunal family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This sort of tendency is a striking feature of the Muromachi period; Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA being assassinated by the Akamatsu clan (in the Kakitsu Revolt), Shogun Yoshiki ASHIKAGA being driven from power by Masamoto HOSOKAWA and replaced (in the Meio Coup), and Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA&apos;s assassination by Hisahide MATSUNAGA can all be understood as examples of shukun oshikome (shutting away/ neutralizing their lords) against the Shogunal family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>またその他、河内守護家畠山氏や管領家細川氏では守護代による主君廃立がたびたび行われ、陶晴賢による大内義隆の追放・討滅、武田信玄による父武田信虎の追放なども主君押込めの一例とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to these examples, there were frequently cases, like with the Protector family of Kawachi province and the Hosokawa clan, who held the position of Kanrei, where deputy Protectors (shugo) drove their lords from power and replaced them; other cases of shukun oshikome include when Harukata SUE engineered the banishment and annihilation of Yoshitaka OUCHI, and when Shingen TAKEDA brought about the exile of his own father, Nobutora TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to these examples, there were frequently cases, like with the Protector family of Kawachi province and the Hosokawa clan, who held the position of Kanrei, where deputy Protectors (shugo) drove their lords from power and replaced them; other cases of shukun oshikome include when Harukata SUE engineered the banishment and annihilation of Yoshitaka OUCHI, and when Shingen TAKEDA brought about the exile of his own father, Nobutora TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to these examples, there were frequently cases, such as the Protector family of Kawachi Province and the Hosokawa clan, who held the position of Kanrei, where deputy Protectors (shugo) drove their lords from power and replaced them; other cases of shukun oshikome include when Harukata SUE engineered the banishment and annihilation of Yoshitaka OUCHI, and when Shingen TAKEDA brought about the exile of his own father, Nobutora TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>like with” =&gt; “ such as”province→Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>このように、戦国期の流動的な権力状況の中心原理を、下剋上ではなく、主君押込めによって捉え直す考えが次第に主流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the mainstream view on the central principle underlying the unstable political situation in the Warring States period gradually shifted from thinking it was gekokujo to people simply taking power for themselves via shukun oshikome.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, the mainstream view on the central principle underlying the unstable political situation during the Warring States period gradually shifted from thinking it was gekokujo to people simply taking power for themselves via shukun oshikome.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot; changed to &quot;during&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the mainstream view on the central principle underlying the unstable political situation during the Sengoku Period gradually shifted from thinking it was gekokujo to people simply taking power for themselves via shukun oshikome.</e>
<cmt>Warring States period→the Sengoku Period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>戦国大名による領国支配は決して専制的なものではなく、家臣団の衆議・意向を汲み取っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The control the daimyo in the Warring States period extended over their territories was definitely not autocratic; instead, it was premised on the approval and inclinations of their group of retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The control that the daimyo in the Warring States period extended over their territories was definitely not autocratic; instead, it was premised on the approval and inclinations of their group of retainers.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The control the daimyo&quot; changed to &quot;The control that the daimyo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The control that the daimyo in the Sengoku Period extended over their territories was definitely not autocratic; instead, it was premised on the approval and inclinations of their group of retainers.</e>
<cmt>Warring States period→the Sengoku Period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その観点からすると、戦国期の大名領国制は戦国大名と家臣団の協同連帯によって成立したと見ることもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When looked at from this viewpoint, it is possible to see the system by which daimyo in the Warring States period ruled their domains as having come into existence via cooperation and solidarity between the daimyo and their groups of retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When looked at from this viewpoint, it is possible to see the system by which daimyo in the Warring States period ruled their domains as having come into existence via cooperation and solidarity between the daimyo and their groups of retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When looked at from this viewpoint, it is possible to see the system by which daimyo in the Sengoku Period ruled their domains as having come into existence via cooperation and solidarity between the daimyo and their groups of retainers.</e>
<cmt>Warring States period→the Sengoku Period</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>家臣団の衆議・意向を無視あるいは軽視した主君は、廃立の憂き目に遭い、世間から下剋上と評されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lords who ignored--or worse yet, despised--the will and inclination of their group of retainers were sure to experience the misery of being deposed and replaced, and judged a fitting target for gekokujo by society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lords who ignored--or worse yet, despised--the will and inclination of their group of retainers were sure to experience the misery of being deposed and replaced, and judged a fitting target for gekokujo by society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lords who ignored--or worse yet, despised--the will and inclination of their group of retainers were likely to experience the misery of being deposed and replaced, and judged a fitting target for gekokujo by society.</e>
<cmt>“sure to” =&gt; “ likely to” もしくは “certain to”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、豊臣秀吉政権の確立以降、こうした主君押込めは沈静化し、少なくとも徳川将軍家では見られなくなったが、各大名では比較的頻繁に行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet starting from the establishement of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s government, situations of shukun oshikome dwindled into tranquility, or at any rate weren&apos;t seen inside the Tokugawa family itself (which held the shogunate), but remained comparatively frequent among the various daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet, starting from the establishment of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s government, situations of shukun oshikome calmed down, and were not seen inside the Tokugawa family itself (which held the shogunate), but shukun oshikome remained comparatively frequent among the various daimyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;dwindled into tranquility&quot; changed to &quot;camed down,&quot; comma added after &quot;yet&quot; &quot;or at any rate&quot; changed to &quot;and&quot; &quot;weren&apos;t&quot; changed to &quot;were not&quot; &quot;shukun oshikome&quot; added after &quot;but&quot; for clarity and readability.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, starting from the establishment of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s government, situations of shukun oshikome calmed down, and were not seen inside the Tokugawa family itself (which held the shogunate), but shukun oshikome remained comparatively frequent among the various daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>下剋上の一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A list of famous examples of gekokujo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A list of famous examples of gekokujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A list of famous examples of gekokujo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>1441年(嘉吉1)には6代将軍の足利義教が家臣の赤松満祐親子により暗殺される嘉吉の乱が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1441 (the first year of the Kakitsu era), the sixth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshinori, was assassinated by Mitsusuke AKAMATSU and his son in the Kakitsu Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1441 (the first year of the Kakitsu era), the sixth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshinori, was assassinated by Mitsusuke AKAMATSU and his son during the Kakitsu Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot; replaced with &quot;during&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1441, the sixth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshinori, was assassinated by Mitsusuke AKAMATSU and his son during the Kakitsu Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>(the first year of the Kakitsu era)特に年号が問題になっている箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>1493年(明応3)には細川政元らにより10代将軍足利義稙を廃立する明応の政変で11代将軍足利義澄を擁立し、自身が幕政を主導する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493 (the third year of the Meio era), the tenth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshitane, was deposed by Masamoto HOSOKAWA and allies and replaced by the eleventh Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshizumi, while Masamoto himself assumed de facto leadership of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1493 (the third year of the Meio era), the tenth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshitane, was deposed by Masamoto HOSOKAWA and allies and replaced by the eleventh Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshizumi, while Masamoto himself assumed de facto leadership of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, the tenth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshitane, was deposed by Masamoto HOSOKAWA and allies and replaced by the eleventh Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshizumi, while Masamoto himself assumed de facto leadership of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>(the third year of the Meio era)特に年号が問題になっている箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>1551年(天文 (元号)20)、斎藤道三が守護の土岐頼芸を追放して美濃国の主となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1551 (the 20th year of the Tenmon era), Dosan SAITO drove his lord the Protector Yorinari TOKI into exile and himself became lord of Mino province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1551 (the 20th year of the Tenmon era), Dosan SAITO drove his lord the Protector Yorinari TOKI into exile and he himself became lord of Mino province.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;he&quot; to &quot;himself&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1551, Dosan SAITO drove his lord the Protector Yorinari TOKI into exile and he himself became lord of Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>(the 20th year of the Tenmon era)特に年号が問題になっている箇所ではないので、削除province→Province</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>1565年には松永久秀らにより13代将軍の足利義輝が暗殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1565, the thirteenth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshiteru, was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and his allies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1565, the thirteenth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshiteru, was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and his allies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1565, the thirteenth Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshiteru, was assassinated by Hisahide MATSUNAGA and his allies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="21">
<j>1573年には織田信長と対立した15代将軍の足利義昭が京都より追放される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1573, the fifteenth (and last) Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshiaki, was exiled from Kyoto after losing his confrontation with Nobunada ODA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1573, the fifteenth (and last) Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshiaki, was exiled from Kyoto after losing in a confrontation with Nobunada ODA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;losing his confrontation&quot; changed to &quot;losing in a confrontation&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1573, the fifteenth (and last) Ashikaga Shogun, Yoshiaki, was exiled from Kyoto after losing in a confrontation with Nobunada ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="22">
<j>1582年（天正10）本能寺の変。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582, there was the Incident at Honnoji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582, there was an Incident at Honnoji temple</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; changed to &quot;an&quot; this sentence seems to continue to the next cell so, I removed the period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582, there was an Incident at Honnoji temple.</e>
<cmt>一文として扱う。ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>織田信長に対する明智光秀の謀反。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In it, Nobunaga ODA was the victim of an insurrection by his vassal Mitsuhide Akechi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">during which, Nobunaga ODA was the victim of an insurrection by his vassal Mitsuhide Akechi.</e>
<cmt>It seems this sentence should be a continuation of the previous sentence above. The period should be eliminated and the capital &quot;D&quot; should be lower case &quot;d&quot; comma after &quot;which&quot; should be eliminated.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the incident, Nobunaga ODA was the victim of an insurrection by his vassal Mitsuhide Akechi.</e>
<cmt>during which→During the incident</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>1582年(天正10)、織田家重臣が尾張国清洲城に集まり、本能寺の変で死去した織田信長の後継者を決定すべく、会議を開く（清洲会議）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So in 1582 (the tenth year of the Tenssho era), the vassals of the Oda clan gathered at Kiyosu castle in Owari province (modern-day Aichi Pref.), and began their meeting (the Kiyosu meeting) to determine the rightful successor to the slain Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, in 1582 (the tenth year of the Tenssho era), the vassals of the Oda clan gathered at Kiyosu castle in Owari province (modern-day Aichi Pref.), and began their meeting (the Kiyosu meeting) to determine the rightful successor to the slain Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>comma added after &quot;So&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, in 1582, the vassals of the Oda family gathered at Kiyosu castle in Owari Province (modern-day Aichi Pref.), and began their meeting (the Kiyosu meeting) to determine the rightful successor to the slain Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>(the tenth year of the Tenssho era)特に年号が問題になっている箇所ではないので、削除province→Provinceより原文に忠実にするためODA補足&quot;Oda clan&quot;→&quot;Oda family&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>本能寺の変の首謀者である明智光秀の討伐において最大の功績を上げた豊臣秀吉は、信長の嫡孫にあたる三法師（織田秀信）を傀儡の後継者として指名し、信長の実質的後継を奪う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had the greatest record of achievements after hunting down and killing Mitsuhide AKECHI--the ringleader of the Incident at Honnoji temple--nominated Hidenobu ODA, the grandson of Nobunaga, as a puppet ruler (Hidenobu was only two at the time), thereby usurping the lion&apos;s share of successional power for himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had the greatest record of achievements after hunting down and killing Mitsuhide AKECHI--the ringleader of the Incident at Honnoji temple--nominated Hidenobu ODA, the grandson of Nobunaga, as a puppet ruler (Hidenobu was only two at the time), thereby usurping the lion&apos;s share of successional power for himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who had the greatest record of achievements after hunting down and killing Mitsuhide AKECHI--the ringleader of the Incident at Honnoji temple--nominated Hidenobu ODA, the grandson of Nobunaga, as a puppet ruler (Hidenobu was only two at the time), thereby usurping the lion&apos;s share of successional power for himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 空機(id:90384), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), Doskoi 8(id:1070), 味っ子(id:17086), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 松平定治(id:146386), Kamitani(id:30757), Goodpro(id:11362), でここ(id:9565), Yukichin(id:725), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Tietew(id:4054), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 秀の介(id:490), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), Shimoxx(id:9332), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), いぬだ・わん(id:36792), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>