<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>十津川郷士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sammurai from Totsugawa area in Nara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totsukawa Goshi (Samurai from Totsukawa area in Nara)</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。Totsugawa Goshi の読みも追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totsukawa Goshi (Samurai from Totsukawa area in Nara)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>十津川郷士（とつかわごうし）は、南大和（奈良県）の十津川郷に在住していた郷士集団。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totsukawa Goshi is a group of samurai who lived in Totsukawago, Minami Yamato (Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totsukawa Goshi is a group of samurai who lived in Totsukawa-go, Minami Yamato (Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Totsukawa-go としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totsukawa Goshi is a group of samurai who lived in Totsukawa-go, Minami Yamato (Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>十津川村は南大和の村で、神武天皇東征のとき道案内に立った八咫烏（ヤタガラス）をトーテムトーテミズム（英：Totemism）とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totsukawa-mura is a village located in Minami-Yamato and this village makes yatagarasu (the sacred crow), who guided Emperor when the Emperor went to the East, the totem of the village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totsukawa-mura is a village located in Minami-Yamato, which makes yatagarasu (the sacred crow), who was a guide for the Emperor Jinmu when he went to the East, the totem of the village.</e>
<cmt>神武天皇　を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totsukawa-mura is a village located in Minami-Yamato, which makes yatagarasu (the sacred crow), who was a guide for the Emperor Jinmu when he went to the East, the totem of the village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幕末に御所警備の際、日の丸に「菱十（菱の中に十字）」の旗を頂き、それ以前の「丸十（丸に十字）」から、以後菱十紋を旗印とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period when the people in the village served as the Imperial guard, they received a national flag with the emblem in which the character ju is placed inside a lozenge; before receiving this flag, the emblem at the village was the character ju placed inside a circle; after receiving the flag with the character ju inside a lozenge, Totsukawa-mura changed their emblem to the character ju placed inside a lozenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period when the people in the village served as the Imperial guard, they received a national flag with the emblem in which the character ju was placed inside a lozenge; after receiving this flag, Totsukawa-mura changed their emblem of their flag to the character ju placed inside a lozenge from the previous one, which was the character ju placed inside a circle.</e>
<cmt>一部重複していると思われる表現を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period when the people in the village served as the Imperial guard, they received a national flag with the emblem in which the character ju was placed inside a lozenge; after receiving this flag, Totsukawa-mura changed their emblem of their flag to the character ju placed inside a lozenge from the previous one, which was the character ju placed inside a circle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>今日、十津川村および北海道の新十津川町のマークも同紋である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present the mark of Totsukawa-mura and that of Shintotsukakawa-cho share the same design.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At present the mark of Totsukawa-mura and that of Shintotsukawa-cho in Hokkaido share the same design.</e>
<cmt>北海道　を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At present the mark of Totsukawa-mura and that of Shintotsukawa-cho in Hokkaido share the same design.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後述するような、むしろ特異とも言える独立独歩の精神からか、現在の十津川村も平成の大合併に際しても、最初から近隣のどの自治体とも合併する気などなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">we will describe later, Totsukawa-mura has a strong sense of self-reliance which can be said unique; and it might come from this strong sense of self-reliance, it is said that the present Totsukawa-mura did not have the intention to merge from the very beginning when big merges were very popular among the regional communities as the era moved to Heisei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It might be due to the strong, or even peculiar sense of their self-reliance, which will be described later, that the present Totsukawa-mura is said to have had no intention of being merged with other municipalities from the beginning even upon the great merger of the Heisei period.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It might be due to the strong, or even peculiar sense of their self-reliance, which will be described later, that the present Totsukawa-mura is said to have had no intention of being merged with other municipalities from the beginning even upon the great merger of the Heisei period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その背景として独特の地理的歴史的環境から十津川は文化や言語の面でも特色が強いことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the background of the sense of strong self-reliance, we can cite the unique geographic and historical environment; because of this environment, in culture and language, Totsukawa has its own characteristics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the background of the sense of strong self-reliance, we can cite that Totsukawa has a strong characteristics in its culture and language due to the unique geographic and historical environment.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the background of the sense of strong self-reliance, we can cite that Totsukawa has a strong characteristics in its culture and language due to the unique geographic and historical environment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>民俗学者の柳田國男も近畿圏にありながら標準語的なアクセントであるその特色について注目している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folklorist Kunio YANAGIDA also has an interest in the fact that people in Totsukawa speak with an accent which is similar to Japan&apos;s standard accent even though the village is located in Kinki area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folklorist Kunio YANAGIDA also has an interest in the fact that people in Totsukawa speak with an accent which is similar to Japan&apos;s standard accent even though the village is located in Kinki area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folklorist Kunio YANAGIDA also has an interest in the fact that people in Totsukawa speak with an accent which is similar to Japan&apos;s standard accent even though the village is located in Kinki area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>古代～江戸時代後期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient times to the late Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient times to the late Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient times to the late Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>古くから地域の住民は朝廷に仕えており、壬申の乱の折にも村から出兵、また平治の乱にも出兵している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local residents have been serving the Imperial Court from a long time ago; when the Jinshin War occurred, the village dispatched troops; for the Heiji War, the village also dispatched troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local residents served the Imperial Court from a long time ago; the village dispatched troops to the Jinshin War, and also later to the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local residents served the Imperial Court from a long time ago; the village dispatched troops to the Jinshin War, and also later to the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらの戦功によりたびたび税減免措置を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to these services, Totsukawa have received reduction or exemption measures on taxes quite often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to these services, Totsukawa received tax reduction or exemption measures quite often.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to these services, Totsukawa received tax reduction or exemption measures quite often.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これは明治期の地租改正まで続き、全国でもおよそ最も長い減免措置であろうと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such reduction or exemption in tax continued up to the Media Period in which the land tax reform was executed; it is said Totsukawa might have received reduction or exemption measures for the longest time in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such reduction or exemption from tax continued up to the land-tax reform in the Meiji period; it is said Totsukawa might have received reduction or exemption measures for the longest time in Japan.</e>
<cmt>exemption from としました。スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such reduction or exemption from tax continued up to the land-tax reform in the Meiji period; it is said Totsukawa might have received reduction or exemption measures for the longest time in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)時も吉野の吉野朝廷につくしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Totsukawa also devoted their service to the Imperial Court of Yoshino in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Totsukawa also devoted their service to the Imperial Court of Yoshino in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>at →　during としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Totsukawa also devoted their service to the Imperial Court of Yoshino in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>米のほとんどとれない山中ということもあり、室町時代になっても守護の支配下に入らなかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totsukawa is located in the steep mountainous region and rice production is almost nil; therefore, it is said that Totsukawa was not controlled by the provincial military governor when times changed from the Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totsukawa is located in the steep mountainous region and rice production is almost nil; therefore, it is said that Totsukawa was not controlled by the provincial military governor when times changed from the Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totsukawa is located in the steep mountainous region and rice production is almost nil; therefore, it is said that Totsukawa was not controlled by the provincial military governor when times changed from the Heian period to the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>太閤検地時にも年貢が赦免された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land tax was pardoned at the time of a land survey conducted by Toyotomi HIDEYOSHIi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land tax was pardoned at the time of a land survey conducted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>人名の表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land tax was pardoned at the time of a land survey conducted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大坂の陣の際は十津川郷士千人が徳川方となり、近隣の豊臣派の一揆を鎮圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Osaka no Jinn (The Siege of Osaka)1000 samurai from Totsukawa area supported the Tokugawa side and suppressed uprisings in neighboring provinces of Toyotomi faction in neighborhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Siege of Osaka, 1000 samurai from Totsukawa area supported the Tokugawa side and suppressed uprisings in neighboring provinces of Toyotomi faction.</e>
<cmt>Siege of Osaka　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Siege of Osaka, 1000 samurai from Totsukawa area supported the Tokugawa side and suppressed uprisings in neighboring provinces of Toyotomi faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この功も合わせて、江戸時代に入っても大和の五條代官所の下で天領となり免租され、住民は郷士と名乗ることを許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This achievement at the time of the Siege of Osaka was also taken into consideration; when times changed from the Muromachi period to the Edo period, Totsukawa became the Shogun&apos;s demesne land tax is exempted under the Gojo Magistrate office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This achievement at the time of the Siege of Osaka was also taken into consideration; when times changed to the Edo period, Totsukawa became the Shogun&apos;s demesne where land tax was exempted under the Gojo magistrate office in Yamato Province, and people were allowed to call themselves goshi (country samurai).</e>
<cmt>室町時代から　の表現を削除しました。文末の翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This achievement at the time of the Siege of Osaka was also taken into consideration; when times changed to the Edo period, Totsukawa became the Shogun&apos;s demesne where land tax was exempted under the Gojo magistrate office in Yamato Province, and people were allowed to call themselves goshi (country samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>以上のような経緯があり、十津川郷士は純粋な勤皇であり、討幕運動の意識は薄かったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totsukawa has the historical background as described above; it is said that Totsukawa Goshi was a pure pro-Imperial and they did not think about anti-shogunate movement much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totsukawa has the historical background as described above; it is said that Totsukawa goshi was pure pro-Imperial and they did not think about anti-shogunate movement much.</e>
<cmt>a pure のaを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totsukawa has the historical background as described above; it is said that Totsukawa goshi was pure pro-Imperial and they did not think about anti-shogunate movement much.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>険しい山に守られた稀有な歴史があり、古来より先述の南朝をはじめとして源義経など、貴種の流人、時勢の逃走者、表舞台への再起を志す者が多く辿り着く場所であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Totsukawa has its uncommon history protected by the steep mountains; from ancient times Totsukawa was the place for exiles of noble birth including people in the Southern Court, MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, for runaway people from the times, for people who aim to return to the front stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Totsukawa has its uncommon history protected by the steep mountains; from ancient times Totsukawa was the place for exiles of noble birth including people in the Southern Court such as MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, for runaway people from the times, and for people who aimed to return to the front stage.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Totsukawa has its uncommon history protected by the steep mountains; from ancient times Totsukawa was the place for exiles of noble birth including people in the Southern Court such as MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune, for runaway people from the times, and for people who aimed to return to the front stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>幕末</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>幕末になると、上平主税などを筆頭に勤皇の志士となるものも多く、また千名を超える兵動員力を期待され、過激派公家の思惑などから薩摩藩、長州藩、土佐藩等と並んで宮廷警護を命ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, including Chikara UEHIRA many local people became pro-Imperial patriots; Totsukawa was expected to dispatch more than 1,000 soldiers; with the expectations of radical nobles, Totsukawa was ordered to go to the Court to guard the Palace with Satuma Domain, Choshu Domain, and Tosa Domain side by side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, many local people including Chikara UEHIRA became pro-Imperial patriots, and Totsukawa was expected to dispatch more than 1,000 soldiers; with the expectations of radical nobles, Totsukawa was ordered to go to the Court to guard the Palace along with Satuma Domain, Choshu Domain, and Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, many local people including Chikara UEHIRA became pro-Imperial patriots, and Totsukawa was expected to dispatch more than 1,000 soldiers; with the expectations of radical nobles, Totsukawa was ordered to go to the Court to guard the Palace along with Satuma Domain, Choshu Domain, and Tosa Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>天誅組の変の際には多くの郷士が参加していが、装備の古さや天誅組側の戦略の無さなどから劣勢であり、朝廷より「天誅組は朝廷軍ではない」との正式判断が出されたため離脱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tenchu-gumi incident occurred many samurai in Totsukawa joined Tenchu-gumi (Heavenly Avenging Force); however, for several reasons ultimately the participants broke away; some of the reasons included the antiquity of the equipment, numerical inferiority, and official judgment that &quot;Tenchu-gumi was not Imperial army,&quot; and the lack of strategic skills in the Tenchu-gumi side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tenchu-gumi Incident occurred, many samurai in Totsukawa joined Tenchu-gumi (Heavenly Avenging Force); however, they eventually left the force due to the antiquity of the equipment, lack of strategies held by the Tenchu-gumi, and the official judgment by the Imperial Court that &apos;Tenchu-gumi was not an Imperial army.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tenchu-gumi Incident occurred, many samurai in Totsukawa joined Tenchu-gumi (Heavenly Avenging Force); however, they eventually left the force due to the antiquity of the equipment, lack of strategies held by the Tenchu-gumi, and the official judgment by the Imperial Court that &apos;Tenchu-gumi was not an Imperial army.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、大総督官直属の朝廷御親兵として越後国から会津藩の倒幕戦争に赴き帰還。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward under the direct control of the governor-general, as the Imperial Court army to convoy the Emperor, from the Echigo Province proceeded to the war to overthrow the Shogunate of Aizu Domain and returned to Totsukawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward they headed to the Aizu Province from the Echigo Province as the Imperial Court army to convoy the Emperor under the direct control of the governor-general to join the war to overthrow the Shogunate, and returned to Totsukawa.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward they headed to the Aizu Province from the Echigo Province as the Imperial Court army to convoy the Emperor under the direct control of the governor-general to join the war to overthrow the Shogunate, and returned to Totsukawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>維新後は全員士族となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, all the members became samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, all the members became samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, all the members became samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>だが、前述の上平など一部過激派は新政府の近代化政策に反発して横井小楠暗殺事件などを起こしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the radicals repelled the modernization policy of the new government, and including the above-mentioned UEHIRA some radical faction caused the Shonan Yokoi assassination incident to occur.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the radicals including the above UEHIRA repelled the modernization policy of the new government, which led to the assassination of Shonan YOKOI.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the radicals including the above UEHIRA repelled the modernization policy of the new government, which led to the assassination of Shonan YOKOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>逸話</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anecdotes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>山中の寒村のため近代化装備にこそ乗り遅れたが、古来よりの武道には長けていた者が多かったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Shogoro NAKAI, one of Totsukawa Goshi, was walking the path along the Shijo-kawa River in Kyoto with his friend who left Tosa Domain; they were drunk and outran a sword by force of liquor, and they began a confused fight with strangers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People in Totsukawa failed to keep up with the modern equipment as it was a cold village in the mountains, but it is said that there were quite a few people who were excellent at ancient martial arts.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People in Totsukawa failed to keep up with the modern equipment as it was a cold village in the mountains, but it is said that there were quite a few people who were excellent at ancient martial arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>例として、十津川郷士の一人中井庄五郎が友人の土佐脱藩士と、京の四条の川畔を酔って歩いてた際、酒の勢いで刀を抜いて乱闘になったことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Shogoro NAKAI, one of Totsukawa Goshi, was walking the path along the Shijo-kawa River in Kyoto with his friend who left Tosa Domain; they were drunk and outran a sword by force of liquor, and they began a confused fight with strangers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Shogoro NAKAI, one of Totsukawa goshi, was walking the path along a river in Shijo of Kyoto with his friend who had left Tosa Domain; they were drunk and outran a sword by force of liquor, and began a confused fight with strangers.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Shogoro NAKAI, one of Totsukawa goshi, was walking the path along a river in Shijo of Kyoto with his friend who had left Tosa Domain; they were drunk and outran a sword by force of liquor, and began a confused fight with strangers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その斬り合った相手がよりにもよって新選組の永倉新八、沖田総司、斎藤一の歴々であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other men with whom he fought happend to be members of Shinsengumi, Shinpachi NAGAKURA, Soji OKITA, Hajime SAITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those with whom he fought happened to be the members of Shinsen-gumi (an Edo shogunate police force located in Kyoto); Shinpachi NAGAKURA, Soji OKITA and Hajime SAITO.</e>
<cmt>一部表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those with whom he fought happened to be the members of Shinsen-gumi (an Edo shogunate police force located in Kyoto); Shinpachi NAGAKURA, Soji OKITA and Hajime SAITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>双方酔っていた上、中井は重傷を負った土佐脱藩士を担いで戦線離脱しているのだが、十津川郷士の個々の戦力と胆力、普段からの武道研磨の度合いがわかる話である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both sides were intoxicated and NAKAI needed to stop the fight to carry his friends, who bore a serious wound, on his shoulder; however, this episode reveals us individual Totsukawa Goshi&apos;s fighting power, courage, and the level of the technique in martial arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both sides were intoxicated and NAKAI needed to stop the fight to carry his friends, who bore a serious wound, on his shoulder; however, this episode reveals us individual Totsukawa goshi&apos;s fighting power, courage, and the level of the technique in martial arts.</e>
<cmt>goshi としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both sides were intoxicated and NAKAI needed to stop the fight to carry his friends, who bore a serious wound, on his shoulder; however, this episode reveals us individual Totsukawa goshi&apos;s fighting power, courage, and the level of the technique in martial arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>新政府要人である横井小楠暗殺事件で島流し（島流し刑の最後の例）となった上平主税が、伊豆新島への終身流刑（約十年後特赦）となった際、流刑船内で同じく島流しとなる新選組最後の局長・相馬主計と出会った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both sides were intoxicated and NAKAI needed to stop the fight to carry his friends, who bore a serious wound, on his shoulder; however, this episode reveals us individual Totsukawa Goshi&apos;s fighting power, courage, and the level of the technique in martial arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikara UEHIRA, who was exiled to Nii-jima Island of Izu (the last case of banishment) because of his involvement in the assassination of Shonan YOKOI, a key figure in the new government (he was later given a special pardon after ten years), met Kazue SOMA, who was the last head of Shinsen-gumi and was also banished to the island, on an exile ship.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikara UEHIRA, who was exiled to Nii-jima Island of Izu (the last case of banishment) because of his involvement in the assassination of Shonan YOKOI, a key figure in the new government (he was later given a special pardon after ten years), met Kazue SOMA, who was the last head of Shinsen-gumi and was also banished to the island, on an exile ship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>上平と相馬は、相馬が先に赦免されるまでの二年間、親しく交際していたと伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that UEHIRA and SOMA kept the friendly relationship for two years before Soma pardoned first</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that UEHIRA and SOMA kept a friendly relationship for two years before SOMA pardoned first.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that UEHIRA and SOMA kept a friendly relationship for two years before SOMA pardoned first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Travis88000(id:54662), Parachutes(id:139813), カテゴリ整理専用(id:146185), 寒(id:53831), 宗純(id:232846), Reggaeman(id:6214), Zorac(id:28001), ぎぼうし(id:139427), こぶまき(id:38278), 味っ子(id:17086), 三圭(id:54383), Pakkached(id:257261), Jade0416(id:104181), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>