<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>織田政権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oda government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oda government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oda government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>織田政権（おだせいけん）とは、天正元年（1573年）（実質的には永禄11年（1568年））から天正10年（1582年）まで成立した日本の武家政権。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oda government is a samurai government in Japan existed from 1573 (virtually 1568) to 1582.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda government is a samurai government which existed in Japan from 1573 (virtually 1568) to 1582.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda government is a samurai government which existed in Japan from 1573 (virtually 1568) to 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>略史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>政権確立の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details on the establishment of the Oda government.</e>
<cmt>Missing Translation. Added my own rough translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details on the establishment of the Oda government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>永禄3年（1560年）に織田信長は今川義元を桶狭間の戦いで破ると、その勢いをもって美濃国を制覇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA beat Yoshimoto IMAGAWA in the Battle of Okehazama in 1560, and with the momentum, he conquered Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga ODA beat Yoshimoto IMAGAWA in the Battle of Okehazama in 1560, and with that momentum, he conquered Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA beat Yoshimoto IMAGAWA in the Battle of Okehazama in 1560, and with that momentum, he conquered Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>永禄11年（1568年）には前将軍・足利義輝の弟・足利義昭を奉じて上洛し、それまで京都にて政権を確立していた三好・松永政権を追放・屈服させることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, brother of the former shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA as his lord, Nobunaga successfully banished and subdued Miyoshi and Matsunaga administration which had been in power in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, brother of the former shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA as his lord, Nobunaga successfully banished and subdued Miyoshi and Matsunaga and their administration which had been in power in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1568, with Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, brother of the former shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA as his lord, Nobunaga successfully banished and subdued Miyoshi and Matsunaga and their administration which had been in power in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「永禄11年（1568年）には」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これにより、信長は足利義昭を室町幕府の第15代将軍に擁立し、自らはその後見人として政権を確立したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This enabled Nobunaga to put forward Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as the 15th shogun of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government) and he, as a guardian of him, established the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This enabled Nobunaga to put forward Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as the 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government) and he, as his guardian, established the government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This enabled Nobunaga to put forward Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA as the 15th shogun of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and he, as his guardian, established the government.</e>
<cmt>幕府の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>その後、信長は伊勢国の北畠具教、河内国の三好義継、大和国の松永久秀ら、畿内における諸大名をことごとく支配下に置き、畿内に一大勢力圏を築くに至ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Nobunaga subjugated all daimyos (Japanese feudal lord) in Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) such as Tomonori KITABATAKE of Ise Province, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI of Kawachi Province and Hisahide MATSUNAGA of Yamato Province, and gained control over the large part of Kinai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Nobunaga subjugated all daimyos (Japanese feudal lord) in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) such as Tomonori KITABATAKE of Ise Province, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI of Kawachi Province and Hisahide MATSUNAGA of Yamato Province, and gained control over the majority of the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Nobunaga subjugated all daimyos (Japanese feudal lord) in the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto) such as Tomonori KITABATAKE of Ise Province, Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI of Kawachi Province and Hisahide MATSUNAGA of Yamato Province, and gained control over the majority of the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>政権の危機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crisis of the government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Crisis within the government</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Crisis within the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、信長の傀儡でしかなかった義昭は、やがてその立場に不満を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshiaki soon became dissatisfied with his position as Nobunaga&apos;s puppet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshiaki soon became dissatisfied with his position as Nobunaga&apos;s puppet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshiaki soon became dissatisfied with his position as Nobunaga&apos;s puppet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして、信長が義昭の行動を制限する「殿中御掟」を成立させると、両者の対立は決定的なものとなった。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nobunaga set up &apos;Denchu on okite (regulations for the shogunal residence) to hold back Yoshiaki, the antagonism between the two became conclusive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nobunaga set up &apos;Denchu on okite&apos; (regulations for the shogunal residence) to hold back Yoshiaki, the antagonism between the two solidified.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nobunaga set up &apos;Denchu on okite&apos; (regulations for the shogunal residence) to hold back Yoshiaki, the antagonism between the two solidified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>義昭は甲斐国の武田信玄や安芸国の毛利輝元、近江国の浅井長政や越前国の朝倉義景、摂津国の石山本願寺などに信長追討令を下し、信長包囲網を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki commanded Shingen TAKEDA of Kai Province, Terumoto MORI of Aki Province, Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province, Yoshikage ASAKURA of Echizen Province, Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple in Settsu Province and others to hunt down and kill Nobunaga and organized an anti-Nobunaga network.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki commanded Shingen TAKEDA of Kai Province, Terumoto MORI of Aki Province, Nagamasa ASAI of Omi Province, Yoshikage ASAKURA of Echizen Province, Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple in Settsu Province and others to hunt down and kill Nobunaga and organized an anti-Nobunaga network.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki commanded Shingen TAKEDA of Kai Province, Terumoto MORI of Aki Province, Nagamasa AZAI of Omi Province, Yoshikage ASAKURA of Echizen Province, Ishiyama Hongan-ji Temple in Settsu Province and others to hunt down and kill Nobunaga and organized an anti-Nobunaga network.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これに対して信長は、姉川の戦いや延暦寺の比叡山焼き討ち (1571年)など、敵対勢力をことごとく破ったが、強敵・武田信玄の前に三方ヶ原の戦いで同盟軍たる徳川軍が大敗すると、さすがの信長も危機に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, Nobunaga defeated enemy forces in the Battle of Anegawa, the fire attack against Enryaku-ji Temple in Mt. Hiei (in 1571) and other battles, but his allied force of Tokugawa was soundly defeated by Shingen TAKEDA, a powerful enemy, in the Battle of Mikatagahara, which brought Nobunaga to a crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, Nobunaga defeated enemy forces in the Battle of Anegawa, set fire to the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei (in 1571) and won other battles, but Tokugawa&apos;s allied forces were soundly defeated by Shingen TAKEDA, a powerful enemy, in the Battle of Mikatagahara, which brought Nobunaga to a crisis.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Nobunaga defeated enemy forces in the Battle of Anegawa, set fire to the Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei (in 1571) and won other battles, but Tokugawa&apos;s allied forces were soundly defeated by Shingen TAKEDA, a powerful enemy, in the Battle of Mikatagahara, which brought Nobunaga to a crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし幸運にも元亀4年（1573年）4月、上洛半ばにして武田信玄は病死し、武田軍は甲斐に引き揚げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fortunately, though, Shingen TAKEDA died from a disease on his way to Kyoto in April, 1573 and his army returned to Kai Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fortunately, though, Shingen TAKEDA died from a disease on his way to Kyoto in April, 1573 and his army returned to the Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fortunately, though, Shingen TAKEDA died from a disease on his way to Kyoto in May, 1573 and his army returned to the Kai Province.</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>信長はこの好機を見逃さず、直ちに軍勢を率いて上洛し、将軍・義昭を河内に追放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga took advantage of this opportunity and immediately went to Kyoto with his army and banished the Shogun Yoshiaki to Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga took advantage of this opportunity and immediately went to Kyoto with his army and banished the Shogun Yoshiaki to Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga took advantage of this opportunity and immediately went to Kyoto with his army and banished the Shogun Yoshiaki to Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これにより、室町幕府は事実上崩壊し、畿内に織田政権が確立したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was virtually the end of the Muromachi bakufu and the Oda government was established in Kinai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was virtually the end of the Muromachi bakufu and the Oda government was established in Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was virtually the end of the Muromachi bakufu and the Oda government was established in Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その後、信長は勢いに乗って浅井長政、朝倉義景、三好義継ら敵対勢力をことごとく滅ぼし、畿内周辺を完全に勢力圏に収めたのであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Nobunaga took the momentum and destroyed enemy forces such as Nagamasa ASAI, Yoshikage ASAKURA and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI to take full control of Kinai and its surrounding area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Nobunaga continued with this momentum and destroyed his enemy forces such as Nagamasa ASAI, Yoshikage ASAKURA and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI to take full control of Kinai and its surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Nobunaga continued with this momentum and destroyed his enemy forces such as Nagamasa AZAI, Yoshikage ASAKURA and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI to take full control of Kinai and its surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>ASAI→AZAI</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>勢力拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expansion of the sphere of influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expansion of the sphere of influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expansion of the sphere of influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>天正2年（1574年）に伊勢の長島一向一揆を鎮圧した信長は、翌年には長篠の戦いにおいて信玄の後継者である武田勝頼率いる武田軍を巧みな火縄銃戦術でもって討ち滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga subdued Ise Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko Buddhist sect followers in Nagashima, Ise Province) in 1574, and the next year, he defeated the TAKEDA army led by Katsuyori TAKEDA, the successor of Shingen TAKEDA, in the Battle of Nagashino with ingenious use of matchlock guns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga subdued Ise Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko Buddhist sect followers in Nagashima, Ise Province) in 1574, and the next year, he defeated the TAKEDA army led by Katsuyori TAKEDA, the successor of Shingen TAKEDA, at the Battle of Nagashino with an ingenious use of matchlock guns.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga subdued Ise Nagashima Ikko Ikki (an uprising of Ikko Buddhist sect followers in Nagashima, Ise Province) in 1574, and the next year, he defeated the Takeda army led by Katsuyori TAKEDA, the successor of Shingen TAKEDA, at the Battle of Nagashino with an ingenious use of matchlock guns.</e>
<cmt>TAKEDA army→Takeda army</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>さらに同年、越前・加賀国で信長に反逆した一向宗徒を根絶やしにし、同地を支配下に置くに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Nobunaga also eradicated the Ikko sect followers who rebeled against him in Echizen and Kaga Provinces to take control of the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Nobunaga also eradicated the Ikko sect followers who rebelled against him in the Echizen and Kaga Provinces to take control of the area.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, Nobunaga also eradicated the Ikko sect followers who rebelled against him in the Echizen and Kaga Provinces to take control of the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし信玄没後、信長にとって最大の強敵となっていた上杉謙信が天正4年（1576年）に石山本願寺と講和して信長との同盟を破棄し、翌年には柴田勝家率いる織田軍を手取川の戦いで粉砕するなどした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kenshin UESUGI, the biggest enemy of Nobunaga after Shingen&apos;s death, conciliated with Ishiyamahongan-ji Temple in 1576 and broke the alliance with Nobunaga, and in the next year, he crushed the ODA army led by Katsuie SHIBATA in the Battle at Tetori River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kenshin UESUGI, the biggest enemy of Nobunaga after Shingen&apos;s death, conciliated with Ishiyamahongan-ji Temple in 1576 and broke their alliance with Nobunaga, and in the next year, he crushed the ODA army led by Katsuie SHIBATA in the Battle at Tetori River.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kenshin UESUGI, the biggest enemy of Nobunaga after Shingen&apos;s death, conciliated with Ishiyamahongan-ji Temple in 1576 and broke their alliance with Nobunaga, and in the next year, he crushed the Oda army led by Katsuie SHIBATA in the Battle at Tetori River.</e>
<cmt>ODA→Oda</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これに乗じて大和の松永久秀、石山本願寺、安芸の毛利輝元、甲斐の武田勝頼らが一斉に反信長として動き出したため、再び信長は包囲網に取り囲まれることとなり、危機に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisahide MATSUNAGA of Yamato Province, Ishiyamahongan-ji Temple, Terumoto MORI, Katsuyori TAKEDA and others took this opportunity and simultaneously took actions against Nobunaga, and as a result, Nobunaga, besieged by the enemies, faced a crisis again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisahide MATSUNAGA of Yamato Province, Ishiyamahongan-ji Temple, Terumoto MORI, Katsuyori TAKEDA and others took this opportunity and simultaneously took action against Nobunaga, and as a result, Nobunaga, besieged by his enemies, faced a crisis once more.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisahide MATSUNAGA of Yamato Province, Ishiyamahongan-ji Temple, Terumoto MORI of Aki Province, Katsuyori TAKEDA of Kai Province and others took this opportunity and simultaneously took action against Nobunaga, and as a result, Nobunaga, besieged by his enemies, faced a crisis once more.</e>
<cmt>「安芸の」「甲斐の」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、その謙信が天正6年（1578年）3月に急死すると、信長はまたもそれに乗じて、反信長勢力をことごとく打ち破ってゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when Kenshin died suddenly in May 1578, Nobunaga again seized the occasion and defeated all the anti-Nobunaga forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Kenshin died suddenly in May 1578, Nobunaga again seized the occasion and defeated all the anti-Nobunaga forces.</e>
<cmt>Extra space.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Kenshin died suddenly in May 1578, Nobunaga again seized the occasion and defeated all the anti-Nobunaga forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、上杉氏も謙信没後は養子の上杉景勝が継いだが、景勝は信長の敵ではなく、また御館の乱という御家騒動から勢力が減退したため、謙信死去により、信長の天下布武はさらに前進したといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kenshin&apos;s death, UESUGI Clan was headed by his adopted son, Kagekatsu UESUGI, who was no threat to Nobunaga, and their power declined due to a family trouble called Otate War, therefore it can be said that the death of Kenshin facilitated Nobunaga&apos;s Tenka-fubu (a slogan meaning that the samurai rules the whole world).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kenshin&apos;s death, the UESUGI Clan was headed by his adopted son, Kagekatsu UESUGI, who was no threat to Nobunaga, and their power declined due to family trouble called the Otate War, therefore it can be said that the death of Kenshin facilitated Nobunaga&apos;s Tenka-fubu (a slogan meaning that the samurai rules the whole world).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kenshin&apos;s death, the Uesugi Clan was headed by his adopted son, Kagekatsu UESUGI, who was no threat to Nobunaga, and their power declined due to family trouble called the Otate War, therefore it can be said that the death of Kenshin facilitated Nobunaga&apos;s Tenka-fubu (a slogan meaning that the samurai rules the whole world).</e>
<cmt>UESUGI→Uesugi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>政権崩壊へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Collapse of the government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Collapse of the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Collapse of the government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>天正10年（1582年）3月に武田氏を滅ぼしたことで、織田氏の勢力は畿内（紀伊国を除く）から、東は中部地方（越後国を除く）にかけて、西は中国東部、四国の一部にかけてという強大な勢力に伸張していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By defeating TAKEDA Clan in May 1582, the power of ODA Clan became huge with its territory ranging from Kinai region (except Kii Province) through Chubu region (except Echigo Province) in the east and the eastrern part of Chugoku region and a part of Shikoku in the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By defeating the TAKEDA Clan in May 1582, the power of the ODA Clan became huge with its territory ranging from the Kinai region (except Kii Province) through the Chubu region (except Echigo Province) to the east and the eastern part of the Chugoku region and a part of Shikoku in the east.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By defeating the Takeda Clan in May 1582, the power of the Oda Clan became huge with its territory ranging from the Kinai region (except Kii Province) through the Chubu region (except Echigo Province) to the east and the eastern part of the Chugoku region and a part of Shikoku in the west.</e>
<cmt>TAKEDA→TakedaODA→Oda最後のeast→west</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この頃が、まさに織田政権の絶頂期と言えるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oda government was at its peak around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda government was at its peak around that time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda government was at its peak around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、九州の大友氏、関東の後北条氏、東北の伊達氏などは信長に恭順する姿勢を見せており、このまま順調にいけば、織田政権による天下統一はほぼ達成されるとみられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otomo clan in Kyushu, Gohojo clan in Kanto region, and Date clan also signaled their alligience, so the Oda Government was expected to unify the whole country if things went well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Otomo clan in Kyushu, the Gohojo clan in Kanto region, and the Date clan also signaled their allegiance, so the Oda Government was expected to unify the whole country if things went well.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Otomo clan in Kyushu, the Gohojo clan in Kanto, and the Date clan in Tohoku also signaled their allegiance, so the Oda Government was expected to unify the whole country if things went well.</e>
<cmt>「東北の」 訳漏れ対応しました。Ｒegion 削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、同年6月2日、信長が家臣の明智光秀の謀反により、本能寺にて自害（本能寺の変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on June 2 of the same year, Nobunaga killed himself at Honno-ji Temple in the rebellion raised by his vassal, Mitsuhide AKECHI (Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on June 2nd of the same year, Nobunaga killed himself at Honno-ji Temple during the rebellion raised by his vassal, Mitsuhide AKECHI (Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on July 1st of the same year, Nobunaga killed himself at Honno-ji Temple during the rebellion raised by his vassal, Mitsuhide AKECHI (Honnoji Incident).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>このとき、嫡男の織田信忠も二条城にて自害してしまったため、織田氏には政権を運営できる人物が消えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga&apos;s legitimate son, Nobutada ODA also killed himself at Nijo-jo Castle then, therefore there was no one left in The Oda clan who could run the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga&apos;s legitimate son, Nobutada ODA also killed himself at the Nijo-jo Castle, thus there was no one left in the Oda clan who could run the government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga&apos;s legitimate son, Nobutada ODA also killed himself at the Nijo-jo Castle, thus there was no one left in the Oda clan who could run the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>つまりこの時点で、織田政権は完全に崩壊したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, at this point in time, the Oda government collapsed completely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ultimately, at this point in time, the Oda government collapsed completely.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ultimately, at this point in time, the Oda government collapsed completely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="26">
<j>その後、織田氏の家督は信長の嫡孫・織田秀信が継いだが、秀信は豊臣秀吉の傀儡にすぎず、また清洲会議により、信長の旧領はことごとく織田家臣団によって分割相続されたため、織田政権、というより織田氏自体が、政権から単なる一大名に転落してしまったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Hidenobu ODA, legitimate grandson of Nobunaga, took over as head of the family, but he was just a puppet of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and due to the results of the Kiyosu conference, Nobunaga&apos;s former territories were all divided and succeeded by his vassals, so the Oda clan itself fell from the power and was reduced to an ordinary daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After which, Hidenobu ODA, the legitimate grandson of Nobunaga, took over as head of the family, but he was just a puppet of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and due to the results of the Kiyosu conference, Nobunaga&apos;s former territories were all divided and succeeded by his vassals, so the Oda clan itself fell from power and was reduced to the status of an ordinary daimyo.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After which, Hidenobu ODA, the legitimate grandson of Nobunaga, took over as head of the family, but he was just a puppet of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, and due to the results of the Kiyosu conference, Nobunaga&apos;s former territories were all divided and succeeded by his vassals, so the Oda clan itself fell from power and was reduced to the status of an ordinary daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>政権機構</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Governmental system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governmental system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Governmental system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>織田政権は、京都に上洛して政権を確立してから、信長が死去する10数年間という短期間に勢力を拡大できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oda government extended its power in such a short period of ten years beginning with his going to Kyoto and establishment of the government and ending with his death.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda government extended its power in such a short period of just ten years, beginning with his going to Kyoto and the establishment of the Oda government and ending with his death.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda government extended its power in such a short period of just 10 years, beginning with his going to Kyoto and the establishment of the Oda government and ending with his death.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その要因のひとつとして、その政権内部が強固に確立されていたからだと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is partly because the inside of the government was firmly established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is partly because the foundation for the government was firmly established.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is partly because the foundation for the government was firmly established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>楽市楽座等の経済政策により、金銭で多くの軍役従事者を雇用することができたため、農繁期・農閑期を問わず、京など政略的・戦略的要地に、長期的に大軍を派遣することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The economic policy, Rakuichi-rakuza (Free markets and open guilds) made it possible to hire many pursuers of military service, therefore, the long-term dispatch of a large army was doable even in busy farming season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The economic policy, Rakuichi-rakuza (Free markets and open guilds) made it possible to hire many pursuers of military service, therefore, the long-term dispatch of a large army was doable even during the busy farming season.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The economic policy, Rakuichi-rakuza (Free markets and open guilds) made it possible to hire many pursuers of military service, therefore, the long-term dispatch of a large army was doable even during the busy farming season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そのため既存の勢力（武田氏・上杉氏等）のように、その軍団を構成する多数の国人・地侍の意向に配慮する必要もなく、独裁的に政治・軍事を展開することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, unlike existing powers (Takeda clan, Uesugi clan etc.), they were able to take political or military actions autocratically with no need to consider wishes of many local or provincial samurai who formed the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, unlike existing powers (Takeda clan, Uesugi clan etc.), they were able to take political or military actions autocratically with no need to consider the wishes of the many local or provincial samurai who formed the army.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, unlike existing powers (Takeda clan, Uesugi clan etc.), they were able to take political or military actions autocratically with no need to consider the wishes of the many local or provincial samurai who formed the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>またそのような常備軍を中核にすることによって、その行動は常に迅速であり、他を圧倒した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With such a standing army at its core, their actions were always swift and overwhelming.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With such a standing army at its core, their actions were always swift and overwhelming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With such a standing army at its core, their actions were always swift and overwhelming.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>ただし、近年の研究では他の戦国大名も独自にこれらの政策に取り組んでいたことが明らかになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, recent studies have revealed that other daimyo in the Warring State period also adopted these policies independently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, recent studies have revealed that other daimyo in the Warring State period also adopted these policies independently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, recent studies have revealed that other Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) also adopted these policies independently.</e>
<cmt>戦国大名の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>信長は最も早くこれを大規模に成し遂げることができた。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga successfully carried out these policies in a large scale earlier than the others.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga successfully carried out these policies in large scale earlier than the others.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga successfully carried out these policies in large scale earlier than the others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>生産力の高い濃尾平野を早い時期に統一的に支配できたことが大きな要因である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main factor for this is that he succeeded in bringing the productive Nobi Plain under unified rule.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main factor for this is that he succeeded in bringing the productive Nobi Plain under a unified rule.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main factor for this is that he succeeded in bringing the productive Nobi Plain under a unified rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="35">
<j>鎌倉中期から徐々に発展してきた貨幣経済や商業・流通経済を政策に取り込んだ体制の維持の成功は、豊臣秀吉や蒲生氏郷など多くの模倣者や追随者を生んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He succeeded in maintaining the system by adopting money economy and commodity markets which gradually developed after mid-Kamakura period, and the success gave rise to many imitators and followers such as Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ujisato GAMO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He succeeded in maintaining this system by adopting a monetary economy and commodity markets which gradually developed after the mid-Kamakura period; this success also gave rise to many imitators and followers such as Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ujisato GAMO.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He succeeded in maintaining this system by adopting a monetary economy and commodity markets which gradually developed after the mid-Kamakura period; this success also gave rise to many imitators and followers such as Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ujisato GAMO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>信長は同時多方面軍を採用し、大規模に活用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga adopted the army system which enable to respond at multiuple regions simultaneously and operated it in a large scale.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga adopted an army system which enabled him to react in multiple regions simultaneously and operated it in a large scale.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga adopted an army system which enabled him to react in multiple regions simultaneously and operated it in a large scale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>北陸方面：柴田勝家を方面軍総司令官として、与力に前田利家や佐々成政らを配属。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokuriku region: Katsuie SHIBATA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Toshiie MAEDA and Narimasa SASSA was assigned as yoriki (mounted warrior belonged to a general in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokuriku region: Katsuie SHIBATA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Toshiie MAEDA and Narimasa SASSA were assigned as yoriki (mounted warrior belonging to a general in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokuriku region: Katsuie SHIBATA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Toshiie MAEDA and Narimasa SASSA were assigned as yoriki (mounted warrior belonging to a general in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>中国方面：羽柴秀吉を方面軍総司令官として、与力に黒田孝高や蜂須賀正勝らを配属。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chugoku region: Hideyoshi HASHIBA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Yoshikata KURODA and Masakatsu HACHISUKA was assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chugoku region: Hideyoshi HASHIBA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Yoshikata KURODA and Masakatsu HACHISUKA were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chugoku region: Hideyoshi HASHIBA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Yoshikata KURODA and Masakatsu HACHISUKA were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="39">
<j>畿内方面：明智光秀を方面軍総司令官として、与力に細川藤孝・細川忠興父子や筒井順慶を配属。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinai region: Mitsuhide AKECHI was appointed as commander in chief on the region, and Fujitaka HOSOKAWA and his son, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and Junkei TSUTSUI were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinai region: Mitsuhide AKECHI was appointed as commander in chief on the region, and Fujitaka HOSOKAWA and his son, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and Junkei TSUTSUI were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinai region: Mitsuhide AKECHI was appointed as commander in chief on the region, and Fujitaka HOSOKAWA and his son, Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, and Junkei TSUTSUI were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="40">
<j>関東方面：滝川一益を方面軍総司令官として、与力に森長可や川尻秀隆を配属。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto region: Kazumasu TAKIGAWA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Nagayoshi MORI and Hidetaka KAWAJIRI were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto region: Kazumasu TAKIGAWA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Nagayoshi MORI and Hidetaka KAWAJIRI were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto region: Kazumasu TAKIGAWA was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Nagayoshi MORI and Hidetaka KAWAJIRI were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>四国方面：信長の三男・織田信孝を方面軍総司令官として、与力に丹羽長秀や蜂屋頼隆らを配属。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shikoku region: Nobutaka ODA, the third son of Nobunaga, was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Nagahide NIWA and Yoritaka HACHIYA were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shikoku region: Nobutaka ODA, the third son of Nobunaga, was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Nagahide NIWA and Yoritaka HACHIYA were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shikoku region: Nobutaka ODA, the third son of Nobunaga, was appointed as commander in chief of the region, and Nagahide NIWA and Yoritaka HACHIYA were assigned as yoriki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>信長存命中は、この方面軍による機能がうまく作用して、各地で連戦連勝を重ねて、織田政権は短期間で領土を拡大することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Nobunaga was alive, these regional armies worked well and won battle after battle in various places and contributed to the Oda government successfully extending their territory in a short period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Nobunaga was alive, these regional armies worked well and won battle after battle in various places and contributed to the Oda government successfully extending their territory over a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Nobunaga was alive, these regional armies worked well and won battle after battle in various places and contributed to the Oda government successfully extending their territory over a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ただし、柴田勝家や羽柴秀吉、明智光秀など、その方面軍司令官たちが擁する兵力は、上杉や毛利など、一大名の兵力をはるかに凌ぐ大兵力であり、つまり総司令官が謀反を起こして織田政権から独立しようと企てれば、簡単にできたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the military capability of such commanders as Shibata Katsuie, Hideyoshi HASHIBA and Mitsuhide AKECHI was much larger than that of an ordinary daimyo, and therefore, if a commander in chief plotted a rebellion, it was easy to carry out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the military capability of such commanders as Shibata Katsuie, Hideyoshi HASHIBA and Mitsuhide AKECHI was much larger than that of an ordinary daimyo, and therefore, if a commander in chief plotted a rebellion, it was easy to carry out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the military capability of such commanders as Katsuie SHIBATA, Hideyoshi HASHIBA and Mitsuhide AKECHI was much larger than that of an ordinary daimyo, and therefore, if a commander in chief plotted a rebellion, it was easy to carry out.</e>
<cmt>Shibata Katsuie→Katsuie SHIBATA</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>信長が明智光秀に本能寺で襲われたのが、それを如実に示しているように、信長は配下の家臣に兵力を与えすぎていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As cleary shown by the fact that Nobunaga was raided by Mitsuhide AKECHI at Honno-ji Temple, Nobunaga gave too much force to his vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As clearly shown by the fact that Nobunaga was raided by Mitsuhide AKECHI at Honno-ji Temple, Nobunaga gave too much military force to his vassals.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As clearly shown by the fact that Nobunaga was raided by Mitsuhide AKECHI at Honno-ji Temple, Nobunaga gave too much military force to his vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>以上から、信長の方面軍制度は、急激な勢力拡大を可能にしたが、同時に自分の首を絞めることとなったため、失敗したとも言えるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is safe to say that Nobunaga&apos;s regional army system was a failure, because it enabled him to extend his power but dug his own grave as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is safe to say that Nobunaga&apos;s regional army system was a failure, because it enabled him to extend his power but dug his own grave as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is safe to say that Nobunaga&apos;s regional army system was a failure, because it enabled him to extend his power but dug his own grave as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="46">
<j>その一方、織田政権崩壊の原因は、政権の構造的な問題より、むしろ織田信忠の死が大きいとする意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, according to a different view, the collapse of the Oda government wa mainly caused by the death of Nobutada ODA, not by the structural problem of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, according to a different view, the collapse of the Oda government was mainly caused by the death of Nobutada ODA, not by a structural problem within the government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, according to a different view, the collapse of the Oda government was mainly caused by the death of Nobutada ODA, not by a structural problem within the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>すなわち、信長は本能寺の変以前に、大名としての織田家の家督は信忠に譲っており、自らは、織田・柴田・明智・羽柴・神戸（信孝）・北畠（信雄）などの「大名（信長の取立による大名）」の上に君臨する存在となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say, Nobukatsu already handed over the headship of the family to Nobutada before the Honno-ji Incident, and reined over such &apos;daimyo (selected by Nobunaga)&apos; as Oda, Shibata, Akechi, Hashiba, (Nobutaka) KANBE, and (Nobuo) KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is to say, Nobukatsu had already handed over the headship of the family to Nobutada before the Honno-ji Incident, and he reined over such &apos;daimyo (selected by Nobunaga)&apos; as Oda, Shibata, Akechi, Hashiba, (Nobutaka) KANBE, and (Nobuo) KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is to say, Nobukatsu had already handed over the headship of the family to Nobutada before the Honno-ji Incident, and he reined over such &apos;daimyo (selected by Nobunaga)&apos; as Oda, Shibata, Akechi, Hashiba, (Nobutaka) KANBE, and (Nobuo) KITABATAKE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そのため、配下の柴田や明智などの大名が、毛利や上杉などの信長に臣従していない大名より大きな兵力をもっていても組織としては問題がなく、むしろ合理的であったと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is of no problem for the organization and is actually rational that his vassals such as SHIBATA and AKECHI had larger military force than that of such dimyo as MORI and UESUGI who did not serve to Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there was no problem with the organization and it was actually rational that his vassals, such as SHIBATA and AKECHI, had larger military forces than that of such daimyo as MORI and UESUGI who did not serve under Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there was no problem with the organization and it was actually rational that his vassals, such as Shibata and Akechi, had larger military forces than that of such daimyo as Mori and Uesugi who did not serve under Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>大文字のみの名前を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>つまり織田家はすでに信長の直接指揮から外れているため、信長自らが巨大な兵力をもつことは組織としての弊害が大きいといえる（信忠が大兵力をもつのであれば問題ない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, Oda clan was already not under Nobunaga&apos;s direct control, therefore, if Nobunaga himself had a huge military force, it would have had a harmful influence on the organization. (It was OK that Nobutada had a large military force).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the Oda clan was already not under Nobunaga&apos;s direct control, therefore, if Nobunaga himself had a huge military force, it would have had a harmful influence on the organization. (It was acceptable that Nobutada had a large military force).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the Oda clan was already not under Nobunaga&apos;s direct control, therefore, if Nobunaga himself had a huge military force, it would have had a harmful influence on the organization (It was acceptable that Nobutada had a large military force).</e>
<cmt>文末のピリオドを括弧内へ移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そのため、仮に信長配下の大名の謀反により信長が倒されても、信長傘下でもっとも大勢力をもつ織田家の当主が生き残っていれば、政権が維持できる構造になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the system, Oda clan was supposed to be able to stay in power if the head of Oda clan having the largest military force survived even in case Nobunaga was killed in a rebellion raised by his vassals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the system, the Oda clan was supposed to be able to stay in power as long as the head of Oda clan having the largest military force survived, even if Nobunaga was killed in a rebellion raised by his vassals</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the system, the Oda clan was supposed to be able to stay in power as long as the head of Oda clan having the largest military force survived, even if Nobunaga was killed in a rebellion raised by his vassals.</e>
<cmt>文末にピリオド</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>従って政権崩壊の主要因は後継者の死亡との説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the main reason for the fall of the government is the death of successor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the main reason for the fall of the government was the death of the successor.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, therefore, the main reason for the fall of the government was the death of the successor.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="52">
<j>他にも、織田政権が崩壊した理由には、極端な能力主義を採ったために、信長死後の羽柴秀吉による織田家の簒奪を許したことが主要因との意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In another opinion, Oda government collapsed because he adopted radical meritocracy, which allowed HIdeyoshi HASHIBA to seize Oda&apos;s position after Nobunaga&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another opinion states that, the Oda government collapsed because he adopted radical meritocracy, which allowed Hideyoshi HASHIBA to seize Oda&apos;s position after Nobunaga&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory suggests that the Oda government collapsed because Nobunaga adopted a system of radical meritocracy, which allowed Hideyoshi HASHIBA to usurp the position of the Oda clan after Nobunaga&apos;s death.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そのために、徳川幕府は、能力よりも忠誠心や家柄、譜代家臣を重視する旧来の封建体制を復活させ、体制維持に努めたとの意見もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order not to make the same mistake, Tokugawa bakufu restored the old feudal system under which loyalty, family line and fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals) were more important than ability to maintain the regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order not to make the same mistake, the Tokugawa bakufu restored the old feudal system under which loyalty, family lineage and fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals) were more important than the ability to maintain the regime.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some believe that, in order to avoid making the same mistake, the Tokugawa shogunate restored the old feudal system under which loyalty, family lineage and fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals) were more important than the ability to maintain the regime.</e>
<cmt>bakufu→shogunate原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="54">
<j>信長は京都支配を重要視し、村井貞勝を京都所司代として、朝廷に対する交渉や監視を任せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga placed importance on the rule of Kyoto, and appointed Sadakatsu MURAI as Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy) for negotiation and surveillance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga placed importance on the rule of Kyoto, and appointed Sadakatsu MURAI as the Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy) for negotiation and surveillance.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga placed importance on the rule of Kyoto, and appointed Sadakatsu MURAI as the Kyoto shoshidai (The Kyoto deputy) for negotiation and surveillance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>貞勝は信長の期待にこたえて、信長存命中は大過なく京都を統治している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadakatsu, living up to Nobunaga&apos;s expectation, governed Kyoto without a big mistake while Nobunaga was alive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadakatsu, living up to Nobunaga&apos;s expectation, governed Kyoto without any serious mistakes while Nobunaga was alive.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadakatsu, living up to Nobunaga&apos;s expectation, governed Kyoto without any serious mistakes while Nobunaga was alive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 初瀬(id:74855), 経済準学士(id:22656), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), BitBucket(id:30999), Yanahan(id:2437), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Ytp.rs(id:202698), Anton21(id:158479), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 今井哲郎(id:127766), 総督(id:124846), Shimoxx(id:9332), Muhammad jp(id:89111), Fuji 3(id:52650), シェーラ(id:17988), Orihakat(id:99279), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>