<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>延喜・天暦の治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engi, Tenryaku no chi (reign of Emperor Daigo and Murakami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engi, Tenryaku no chi (the reigns of Emperor Daigo and Murakami)</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engi, Tenryaku no chi</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>延喜・天暦の治（えんぎ・てんりゃくのち）とは、平安時代中期（10世紀）の醍醐天皇・村上天皇両天皇の治世を聖代視した呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engi, Tenryaku no chi is a magnificent imperial reign name of the reigns of Emperor Daigo and Emperor Murakami in the mid-Heian period (the 10 the century).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engi, Tenryaku no chi is the magnificent imperial reign name for the reigns of Emperor Daigo and Emperor Murakami in the mid Heian Period (the 10th century).</e>
<cmt>Capitalized, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engi, Tenryaku no chi is the magnificent imperial reign name for the reigns of Emperor Daigo and Emperor Murakami in the mid Heian Period (the 10th century).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>延喜は醍醐の、天暦は村上の元号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engi is the era name of Emperor Daigo, and Tenryaku, Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engi is the era name of Emperor Daigo, and Tenryaku of Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engi is the era name of Emperor Daigo, and Tenryaku of Emperor Murakami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>延喜の治および天暦の治も参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See also Engi no chi and Tenryaku no chi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See also Engi no chi and Tenryaku no chi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See also Engi no chi and Tenryaku no chi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>両治世は天皇親政が行われ、王朝政治・王朝文化の最盛期となった理想の時代として後世の人々に観念された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both reigns were directly ruled by emperors and were considered by succeeding generations as the ideal period when governments and cultures of their dynasty ages enjoyed the height of prosperity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In both reigns the emperor ruled directly and this era has been considered by succeeding generations as the golden age of government and culture under the dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In both reigns the emperor ruled directly and this era has been considered by succeeding generations as the golden age of government and culture under the dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>両治世を聖代視する考えは、早くも10世紀後半には現れており、11世紀前葉～中葉ごろの貴族社会に広く浸透した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opinion to see both reigns as a magnificent and ideal period was recognized as early as the 10th century and it became prevalent in all noble societies in around the first half and the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This elevated view became apparent as early as the 10th century and it became prevalent in all parts of noble society in around the first half to the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This elevated view became apparent as early as the late 10th century and it became prevalent in all parts of noble society in around the first half to the middle of the 11th century.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当時は摂関家が政治の上層を独占する摂関政治が展開し、中流・下流貴族は特定の官職を世襲してそれ以上の昇進が望めない、といった家職の固定化が進んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the regency government that &quot;Sekkan-ke,&quot; the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, monopolized the highest level of political power was developed and the forming social standing and fixing family business and trade were undergoing so the nobility in the middle lower class only inherited a specific government post and could not ask any more promotion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the regency government that &quot;Sekkan-ke,&quot; the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, monopolized the highest level of political power was developed and the forming social standing and fixing family business and trade were undergoing so the nobility in the middle lower class only inherited a specific government post and could not ask any more promotion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the regency government that Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor) monopolized the highest level of political power was developed and the forming social standing and fixing family business and trade were undergoing so the nobility in the middle lower class only inherited a specific government post and could not ask any more promotion.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そうした中で、中流貴族も上層へある程度昇進していた延喜・天暦期を理想の治世とする考えが中下流貴族の間に広まったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these situation, the idea that viewed the Engi and Tenryaku periods as ideal reigns when even the middle class of noblemen could be promoted to higher level to some extent became popular among the middle lower class noblemen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these situation, the idea that viewed the Engi and Tenryaku periods as ideal reigns when even the middle class of noblemen could be promoted to higher level to some extent became popular among the middle lower class noblemen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these situation, the idea that viewed the Engi and Tenryaku eras as ideal reigns when even the middle class of noblemen could be promoted to higher level to some extent became popular among the middle lower class noblemen.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>実際には、延喜・天暦期は律令制体制から王朝国家体制へ移行する過渡期に当たっており、様々な改革が展開した時期であり、それらの改革は天皇親政というよりも、徐々に形成しつつあった摂関政治によって支えられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually, the period of Engi and Tenryaku fell upon the transitional period to the dynasty state from the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and the period when various reforms were carried out and these reforms were supported by not the direct rule by emperors but Sekkan governments which had been gradually formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually, the period of Engi and Tenryaku fell upon the transitional period to the dynasty state from the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and the period when various reforms were carried out and these reforms were supported by not the direct rule by emperors but Sekkan governments which had been gradually formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually, the eras of Engi and Tenryaku fell upon the transitional period to the dynasty state from the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and the period when various reforms were carried out and these reforms were supported by not the direct rule by emperors but Sekkan governments which had been gradually formed.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、後世の人々によって、延喜・天暦期の聖代視は意識的に喧伝されていき、平安後期には理想の政治像として定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Engi and Tenryaku periods were consciously trumpeted by people of succeeding generations and they were firmly fixed as an ideal politic symbol in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Engi and Tenryaku periods were consciously trumpeted by people of succeeding generations and they were firmly fixed as an ideal politic symbol in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Engi and Tenryaku eras were consciously trumpeted by people of succeeding generations and they were firmly fixed as an ideal politic symbol in the latter half of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>後醍醐天皇も延喜・天暦期を天皇親政が行われた理想の時代と認識し、武家政治を排して建武の新政を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo also acknowledged the Engi and Tenryaku periods as the ideal reigns when the direct rule by emperors was carried out and he rejected a samurai government and conducted the Kemmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo also acknowledged the Engi and Tenryaku periods as the ideal reigns when the direct rule by emperors was carried out and he rejected a samurai government and conducted the Kemmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo also acknowledged the Engi and Tenryaku eras as the ideal reigns when the direct rule by emperors was carried out and he rejected a samurai government and conducted the Kenmu Restoration.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸末期にも延喜・天暦の治を理想視する思想が明治維新の原動力の一つとなり、そうした考えは明治以降の皇国史観にも引き継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in the end of the Edo period, the thought to idealize the Engi and Tenryaku periods became one of the locomotives for the Meiji Restoration and this thought was carried over also to Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto) after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also toward the end of the Edo Period, the idealization of the Engi and Tenryaku periods became one of the drivers for the Meiji Restoration and this thought carried over into Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto) after the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>Capitalization, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also toward the end of the Edo period, the idealization of the Engi and Tenryaku eras became one of the drivers for the Meiji Restoration and this thought carried over into Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto) after the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>第二次世界大戦後に研究が進むと、潜在的に不満を抱いていた中下流の文人貴族層による過大な評価であることが明らかとなり、またその時期の実際の政策も宇多天皇期及びその後の宇多上皇による事実上の院政下で行われたものの延長でしかないことが明らかになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As further research was done after World War II, it became apparent that the periods were overrated by people in the literary nobility of the middle class who were frustrated at the system and the actual policies in that time were only an extension of the ones in the Emperor Uda period and virtually under the politics by Insei (ruled by the retired Emperor) and the subsequent retired Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As further research was done after World War II, it became apparent that the periods were overrated by people in the literary nobility in the middle and lower classes who were frustrated at the system of rule at the time, and the actual policies of that time were merely an extension of the ones of the Emperor Uda period, and the politics of the period were those of Insei (rule by the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As further research was done after World War II, it became apparent that the eras were overrated by people in the literary nobility in the middle and lower classes who were potentially frustrated at the system of rule at the time, and the actual policies of that time were merely an extension of the ones by the Emperor Uda era and under Insei (rule by the retired emperor) of consecutive reign by Retired Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、摂関政治の前提である摂政・関白自体が延喜・天暦期には臨時の職に過ぎなかったことも明らかにされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also revealed that, the presumption of the regency government, Sessho Kampaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor) itself was only a temporary post in the Engi and Tenryaku periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also revealed that, the assumption of a regency government, Sessho Kampaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor), was only a temporary post in the Engi and Tenryaku periods.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also revealed that, the assumption of a regency government, Sessho Kanpaku (regent and chief adviser to the Emperor), was only a temporary post in the Engi and Tenryaku eras.</e>
<cmt>スペルなど修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これによって、延喜・天暦期を特別に重視することなく、9世紀から11世紀までの期間を律令国家期から王朝国家期への移行期としてとらえる見解が通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this, the view that the period from the 9th century to the 11th century was the transition period from the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes to the system of the dynasty state was commonly accepted, without focusing on the Engi and Tenryaku periods too much.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following this reappraisal, the view that the period from the 9th century to the 11th century was a transition period from the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes to a dynastic state system became commonly accepted, without focusing on the Engi and Tenryaku periods too much.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, grammar, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this reappraisal, the view that the period from the 9th century to the 11th century was a transition period from the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes to a dynastic state system became commonly accepted, without focusing on the Engi and Tenryaku eras too much.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>