<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>学問源流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gakumongenryu (The Origin of Learning)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gakumongenryu (The Origin of Learning)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gakumongenryu (The Origin of Learning)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>『学問源流』（がくもんげんりゅう）は、江戸時代中期に那波師曾（魯堂）によって書かれた漢学史書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gakumongenryu&quot; is a history book of the study of Chinese classics written by Shiso NABA (Rodo NABA, NABA is also pronounced NAWA) in the middle of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>「師曾」の読み方が確定できなかったので、そのまま音読みにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gakumongenryu&quot; is a history book of the study of Chinese classics written by Shiso NABA (Rodo NABA, NABA is also pronounced NAWA) in the middle of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gakumongenryu&quot; is a history book of the study of Chinese classics written by Shiso NABA (Rodo NABA, NABA is also pronounced NAWA) in the middle of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全1巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a one-volume book.</e>
<cmt>原文は単語のみですが、句点があるので省略部分のある文であると判断し、文の形になるように補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a one-volume book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a one-volume book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>寛政元年（1789年）、自分の余命を悟った師曾が門人に口述筆記させ、その死後に遺品を整理していた実弟の奥田元継（奥田尚斎）がこれを発見し、師曾の嫡子と相談の上で同6年（1794年）に刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1789, Shiso, who realized his days were numbered, made his pupil write at his dictation, after his death, his own younger brother Mototsugu OKUDA (Shosai OKUDA) found the manuscript while he was arranging the articles left by Shiso, and talked with the heir of Shiso, then published it in 1794.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1789, Shiso, who realized his days were numbered, made his pupil write at his dictation, after his death, his own younger brother Mototsugu OKUDA (Shosai OKUDA) found the manuscript while he was arranging the articles left by Shiso, and talked with the heir of Shiso, then published it in 1794.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1789, Shiso, who realized his days were numbered, made his pupil write at his dictation, after his death, his own younger brother Mototsugu OKUDA (Shosai OKUDA) found the manuscript while he was arranging the articles left by Shiso, and talked with the heir of Shiso, then published it in 1794.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>全体として朱子学を擁護して、朱子学至上主義の史観が貫かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the whole, the book defends Shushigaku (Sogaku: Neo- Confucianism founded on the doctrines of ZHU Xi) and sticks to the view of history to consider Shushigaku to be supreme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the whole, the book defends Shushigaku (Sogaku: Neo- Confucianism founded on the doctrines of ZHU Xi) and sticks to the view of history to consider Shushigaku to be supreme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the whole, the book defends Shushigaku (Sogaku: Neo- Confucianism founded on the doctrines of ZHU Xi) and sticks to the view of history to consider Shushigaku to be supreme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>延喜・天暦以来、儒教が仏教に圧倒されて儒教が禅僧の学問と化したこと、藤原惺窩が日本における宋学の端緒を付けたこと、その後伊藤仁斎・伊藤東涯父子や山崎闇斎・中江藤樹・荻生徂徠らが、名利をもって陽明学や古文辞学などの異説を掲げて朱子学の排撃を試みたこと、だが朱子学こそが名利を捨てて学問として成就された正統な儒学であることを論じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He writes that Confucianism had been overwhelmed by Bhuddism since the Engi and Tenryaku Period and it changed into the learning of Zen monks, that Seika FUJIWARA began the serious study of Shushigaku, and that later Jinsai ITO and his son Togai ITO, Ansai YAMAZAKI, Toju NAKAE, and Sorai OGYU tried to criticize Shushigaku for meiri (fame and profit), insisting on different theories from Shushigaku such as Yomeigaku (Neo-Confucianism based on teaching of WANG Yangming) and Kobunjigaku (study of ancient rhetoric school), and finally he stresses that Shushigaku is the right and completed Confucianism from which meiri was eliminated.</e>
<cmt>(1)「端緒を付けた」：　宋学は藤原惺窩以前に入っているので、「端緒を付けた」のは本格的な研究についてであると解釈し、&quot;began the serious study of Shushigaku&quot;としました。(2)「名利をもって」：　「名利」はどの儒学の学派でも避けるべきものだそうです。そのため、「名利をもって」を「名利を論拠、あるいは理論的な手段として」と解釈することは出来ません。そこで、著者はこの本の中で他の学派の矛盾を突いているとの記述(吉川弘文館『國史大辞典』）を基にして、私の推測で訳を作成しました。つまり、著者は『他の学派は本来儒家が避けるべき名利（功名心や世俗の利益）を求めて朱子学を攻撃しているのだ』と主張していると解釈し、&quot;for meiri (fame and profit)&quot;と訳しました。しかし、これはあくまでも私の解釈です。可能であるなら、原文の著者にこの部分について確認をとるか、『学問源流』の研究者、あるいは原典そのものに当たるのが最も確実だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He writes that Confucianism had been overwhelmed by Buddhism since the Engi and Tenryaku Period and it changed into the learning of Zen monks, that Seika FUJIWARA began the serious study of Shushigaku, and that later Jinsai ITO and his son Togai ITO, Ansai YAMAZAKI, Toju NAKAE, and Sorai OGYU tried to criticize Shushigaku for meiri (fame and profit), insisting on different theories from Shushigaku such as Yomeigaku (Neo-Confucianism based on teaching of WANG Yangming) and Kobunjigaku (study of ancient rhetoric school), and finally he stresses that Shushigaku is the right and completed Confucianism from which meiri was eliminated.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。Bhuddism→Buddhism</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He writes that Confucianism had been overwhelmed by Buddhism since the Engi and Tenryaku Period and it changed into the learning of Zen monks, that Seika FUJIWARA began the serious study of Shushigaku, and that later Jinsai ITO and his son Togai ITO, Ansai YAMAZAKI, Toju NAKAE, and Sorai OGYU tried to criticize Shushigaku for meiri (fame and profit), insisting on different theories from Shushigaku such as Yomeigaku (Neo-Confucianism based on teaching of WANG Yangming) and Kobunjigaku (study of ancient rhetoric school), and finally he stresses that Shushigaku is the right and completed Confucianism from which meiri was eliminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>更に中国における詩文の歴史についても論じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also deals with the history of prose and poetry in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also deals with the history of prose and poetry in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also deals with the history of prose and poetry in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>朱子学擁護という当時の時代の要請とその分かりやすい文章から、江戸時代を通じて何回か刊行され、明治以後も博文館より活字本として刊行されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was published several times through the Edo Period because of the demand to defend Shushigaku at that time and its clear writing, after the Meiji Period, it was also published with movable type system by Hakubunkan (a publisher).</e>
<cmt>「活字本として」について：　江戸時代には活版印刷は一般的ではなく、普及したのは明治時代からです。&quot;with movable type system&quot;とすることでその部分を強調しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was published several times through the Edo Period because of the demand to defend Shushigaku at that time and its clear writing, after the Meiji Period, it was also published with movable type system by Hakubunkan (a publisher).</e>
<cmt>「clear　writing,」間の全角ｽﾍﾟｰｽを半角ｽﾍﾟｰｽに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was published several times through the Edo Period because of the demand to defend Shushigaku at that time and its clear writing, after the Meiji Period, it was also published with movable type system by Hakubunkan (a publisher).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Mooko(id:36162), Ohura(id:5986), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>