<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>代銭納</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisenno</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisenno</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisenno</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>代銭納（だいせんのう）とは、中世日本の荘園・国衙領・武家領などにおいて、公事や年貢、地子などの納入を現物に代わって貨幣で納入する制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Daisenno means the system to pay kuji (public service), nengu (tribute) and/or jishi (land tax) in cash, instead of in kind, that was introduced in medieval Japan at shoen (manor), kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office) and/or bukeryo (territories of samurai family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Daisenno means the system of paying kuji (public service), nengu (tribute), and/or jishi (land tax) in cash, instead of in kind, that was introduced in medieval Japan at the shoen (manor), kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office), and/or bukeryo (territories of samurai family).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Daisenno means the system of paying kuji (public service), nengu (tribute), and/or jishi (land tax) in cash, instead of in kind, that was introduced in medieval Japan at the shoen (manor), kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office), and/or bukeryo (territories of samurai family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>農業生産の高まりと宋銭の流入によって商工業が全国的に発展した鎌倉時代中期以後から見られるようになり、南北朝時代_(日本)には全国的に普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system began to be used in mid-Kamakura period when commerce and industries developed nationwide thanks to boosting agricultural production and the circulation of Sung currency and spread throughout the nation in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system started in the mid-Kamakura period when commerce and industries developed nationwide thanks to boosting agricultural production and the circulation of Sung currency and spread throughout the nation in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system started in the mid-Kamakura period when commerce and industries developed nationwide thanks to boosting agricultural production and the circulation of Sung currency and spread throughout the nation in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>