<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>門葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monyo (blood line, lineage, connected by blood)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monyo (blood line, lineage, connected by blood)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monyo (blood line, lineage, connected by blood)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>門葉（もんよう）とは、一般的に血縁関係がある一族を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monyo generally refers to the families that are connected by blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;monyo&quot; generally referred to families that were related by blood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;monyo&quot; generally referred to families that were related by blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後に、擬似的な血縁関係で編成された家臣団での格式を指す名称としても使用されることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it was also used for the rank name to refer to a social status in vassals who were related by similar blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it was also used for the rank name in reference to a social status among vassals who were related by similar blood.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it was also used for the rank name in reference to a social status among vassals who were related by similar blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>御門葉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gomonyo (a family with a honorary status)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gomonyo (a family with honorary status)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gomonyo (a family with honorary status)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>御門葉とは清和源氏の一門のうち鎌倉幕府において鎌倉殿の一門としての処遇を受けた者をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gomonyo refers to those who, among the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), were treated as a family of Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura) in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;gomonyo&quot; referred to those who, among the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), were treated as a family of Kamakura-dono (Lord of Kamakura) in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;gomonyo&quot; referred to those who, among the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), were treated as a family of Kamakura-dono (Lord of Kamakura) in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>源頼朝から源実朝までの三代の源氏将軍の時代、鎌倉殿と同族の源氏一門は狭義には河内源氏、広義には清和源氏に広く存在したが、鎌倉殿への忠勤の姿勢を重んじ、同族に対す甘えを許さず、すべての源氏一門が鎌倉殿の親族として処遇されたわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of three generations of Genji shogunate family from MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, the Genji clans that belonged to the same clan of Kamakura-dono existed in the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) in a restricted sense and in Seiwa-Genji in a broad sense, but all Genji clans were not always treated as the family of Kamakura-dono, because the loyalty to Kamakura-dono were much highly valued and dependence on the family was not permitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of three generations of the Genji shogunate family, from MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, the Genji clans that belonged to the same clan of Kamakura-dono existed in the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) in a restricted sense and in Seiwa-Genji in a broad sense, but not all Genji clans were always treated as the family of Kamakura-dono because the loyalty to Kamakura-dono was very highly valued and dependence on the family was not permitted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of three generations of the Genji shogunate family, from MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, the Genji clans that belonged to the same clan of Kamakura-dono existed in the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) in a restricted sense and in Seiwa-Genji in a broad sense, but not all Genji clans were always treated as the family of Kamakura-dono because the loyalty to Kamakura-dono was highly valued and dependence on the family was not permitted.</e>
<cmt>veryを除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>多くの源氏一門は叙位任官を除き、特に無碍に鎌倉殿と同様に源姓を称することを禁じられ、あくまで家人として遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Genji clans, except for the conferment of a court rank and appointment to an office, were forbidden to profusely share common Minamoto Family name in the same way as the Kamakura-dono, and were treated as just Kenin (retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Genji clans, except for the conferment of a court rank and appointment to an office, were forbidden to broadly share a common Minamoto family name in the same way as the Kamakura-dono, and were treated simply as Kenin (retainers).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Genji clans, except for the conferment of a court rank and appointment to an office, were forbidden to broadly share a common Minamoto family name in the same way as the Kamakura-dono, and were treated simply as Kenin (retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>源頼朝が鎌倉に武家政権を打ち立てると、頼朝は清和源氏一族内で、特に功績を認めた者だけに源姓を名乗ることを許可し、他の源氏一族が公式の場で源姓を名乗ることを禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo established the military government in Kamakura, Yoritomo gave those who got credit for their distinguished services among the Seiwa-Genji a permission to use the Minamoto Family name and prohibited other Genji clans to use the name in formal occasions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo established the military government in Kamakura, Yoritomo allowed those who had been credited for their distinguished services among the Seiwa-Genji the permission to use the Minamoto family name, but he prohibited other Genji clans from using the name at formal occasions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo established the military government in Kamakura, Yoritomo allowed those who had been credited for their distinguished services among the Seiwa-Genji the permission to use the Minamoto family name, but he prohibited other Genji clans from using the name at formal occasions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文治元年（1185年）8月16日（旧暦）の除目で国司に任ぜられた6名が始まり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monyo originated from six people who were appointed Kokushi (provincial governor) at Jimoku (ceremony for appointing officials) on August 16, 1185.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monyo originated from six people who were appointed as Kokushi (provincial governors) at Jimoku (ceremony for the appointment of officials) on August 16, 1185.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monyo originated from six people who were appointed as Kokushi (provincial governors) at Jimoku (ceremony for the appointment of officials) on August 16, 1185 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>(old lunar calendar)を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これを認められた家は御門葉と呼ばれ、格式では将軍家に次ぐ扱いを受け、他の御家人と一線を画した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families that were acknowledged as monyo were called gomonyo and treated second to the Shogun family in the social status and drew the line at other gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families that were acknowledged as monyo were called gomonyo and treated second to the shogun family in social status; this drew the line at other gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families that were acknowledged as monyo were called gomonyo and treated second to the shogun family in social status; this drew the line at other gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その為、御門葉と認められることは大変な名誉と見なされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, to be acknowledged as a gomonyo was considered as a great honor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was considered a great honor to be acknowledged as a gomonyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was considered a great honor to be acknowledged as a gomonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>ちなみに、最初に認められた6人は、頼朝と源義経の仲が険悪化する以前に推挙されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, the first six people had been recommended before Yoritomo got onto bad terms with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, the first six people had been recommended before Yoritomo got onto bad terms with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, the first six people had been recommended before Yoritomo got onto bad terms with MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そして、除目が発表された時には頼朝と義経の仲は険悪化しており、義経は事実上御門葉とは認めなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, when Jimoku was made public, the relationship between Yoritomo and Yoshitsune had been strained, so Yoshitsune was not factually acknowledged as a gomonyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the relationship between Yoritomo and Yoshitsune was strained at the point that Jimoku was made public, so Yoshitsune wasn&apos;t factually acknowledged as a gomonyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the relationship between Yoritomo and Yoshitsune was strained at the point that Jimoku was made public, so Yoshitsune wasn&apos;t factually acknowledged as a gomonyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この門葉の顔ぶれを見る限り、門葉たる地位を付与されるためには、血筋上の嫡流庶流や頼朝の血筋との近接性はあまり問題ではなく、あくまで忠勤の目覚ましい清和源氏であることがその要件であったということができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given how members of these monyo were selected, in order to be given the status of monyo, what mattered was not the main or branch of the family blood or how close to Yoritomo&apos;s blood but being the faithful Seiwa-Genji, which was the only requirements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given the manner in which the members of these monyo were selected, in order to be given the status of monyo, what mattered wasn&apos;t the main line or branch of the family blood nor how close one was to Yoritomo&apos;s blood but was instead being the faithful Seiwa-Genji, which was the only requirement.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given the manner in which the members of these monyo were selected, in order to be given the status of monyo, what mattered wasn&apos;t the main line or branch of the family blood nor how close one was to Yoritomo&apos;s blood but was instead being the faithful Seiwa-Genji, which was the only requirement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>実弟である源範頼、阿野全成そして義経らはこれに含まれず、頼朝と比較的血筋の近い河内源氏のうちでも新田氏の庶子　山名義範や足利義兼に限られ、逆に、頼朝の4代前の祖先　源義家の弟　源義光を祖先とする甲斐源氏の加賀美遠光、安田義資、また6代前の祖先 河内源氏の祖　源頼信の兄　源頼光を祖先とする摂津源氏の源有綱など限りなく遠縁の者が門葉に列していることが確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritomo&apos;s own younger brothers, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, Zenjo ANO, and Yoshitsune were not included in these monyo, while those included were limited to Yoshinori YAMANA, a child born out of wedlock of the Nitta Clan, among the Kawachi-Genji that had a relatively close blood tie with Yoritomo, and Yoshikane ASHIKAGA, but on the other hand, those distantly-related were also included such as Tomitsu KAGAMI of the Kai-Genji that descended from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, young brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the ancestor of four generations before Yoritomo, and Yoshisuke YASUDA, and MINAMOTO no Aritsuna of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan) that descended from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, elder brother of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, the originator of the Kawachi-Genji, the ancestor of six generations before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritomo&apos;s own younger brothers, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, Zenjo ANO and Yoshitsune, weren&apos;t included in these monyo, while those included were limited to Yoshinori YAMANA, a child born out of wedlock of the Nitta clan, among the Kawachi-Genji that had relatively close blood ties with Yoritomo, and Yoshikane ASHIKAGA; however, those who were distantly related were also included, such as Tomitsu KAGAMI of the Kai-Genji that had descended from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the ancestor of four generations before Yoritomo, and Yoshisuke YASUDA; and MINAMOTO no Aritsuna of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), which was descended from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, the elder brother of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, the originator of the Kawachi-Genji, the ancestor of six generations before.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritomo&apos;s own younger brothers, MINAMOTO no Noriyori, Zenjo ANO and Yoshitsune, weren&apos;t included in these monyo, while those included were limited to Yoshinori YAMANA, a child born out of wedlock of the Nitta clan, among the Kawachi-Genji that had relatively close blood ties with Yoritomo, and Yoshikane ASHIKAGA; however, those who were distantly related were also included, such as Tomitsu KAGAMI of the Kai-Genji that had descended from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, the younger brother of MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, the ancestor of four generations before Yoritomo, and Yoshisuke YASUDA; and MINAMOTO no Aritsuna of the Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), which was descended from MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, the elder brother of MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, the originator of the Kawachi-Genji, the ancestor of six generations before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海衛士(id:19229), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>