<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朱器台盤</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuki-daiban (vermilion-lacquered mounted bowl)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuki-daiban (vermilion-lacquered household goods that were the Fujiwara clan&apos;s treasures)</e>
<cmt>説明の&quot;mounted bowl&quot;は用語集に登録してある訳ですが、「くくりつけのボウル/流し」の意味なので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuki-daiban (vermilion-lacquered household goods that were the Fujiwara clan&apos;s treasures)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朱器台盤（しゅきだいばん）とは、藤原氏の家宝として歴代藤氏長者に継承されてきた朱塗りの什器のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuki-daiban is vermilion-lacquered household goods succeeded as the Fujiwara clan&apos;s family treasure by successive Toshi choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>「朱塗り」は「red lacquer」で登録されていますが、「朱器台盤」が「vermilion-lacquered mounted bowl」で登録されていますので、「vermilion-lacquered」を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuki-daiban are vermilion-lacquered household goods succeeded as the Fujiwara clan&apos;s treasures by successive Toshi choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Fujiwara clan&apos;s family treasure&quot;→clanとfamilyが重複するので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuki-daiban are vermilion-lacquered household goods succeeded as the Fujiwara clan&apos;s treasures by successive Toshi choja (head of the Fujiwara clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>正月の大臣大饗の際に用いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were used at Shogatsu daijin daikyo (minister&apos;s New Year banquet).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were used at New Year&apos;s banquet held by ministers (the Fujiwara clan in this case).</e>
<cmt>「正月の大臣大饗」→ローマ字表記する必要はないと思います。ここでの「大臣」は藤原氏のことなので、説明を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were used at New Year&apos;s banquet held by ministers (the Fujiwara clan in this case).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>諸記録によれば、大饗の際に用いた朱器（朱塗りの食器・酒器）が長櫃4台に納められ、また朱器を置くための台盤が大きな物が5つありそれを含めて27個存在したとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is noted from several records that shuki (vermilion-lacquered dishes and drinking vessels) for grand banquets were stored in four nagahitsu (long wooden box with a lid) and there were 27 daiban (a Heian-period long, low, rectangular table on which food was served in the emperor&apos;s residential compound of the imperial palace) to place shuki, including five large daiban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is noted from several records that shuki (vermilion-lacquered dishes and drinking vessels) for grand banquets were stored in four nagabitsu (long wooden box with a lid) and there were 27 daiban (low and rectangular table on which food was served, used by nobles in the Heian period) to place shuki, including five large daiban.</e>
<cmt>「長櫃」→正確には「ながびつ」のようです。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E9%95%B7%E6%AB%83）「台盤」→（）内の説明ですが、皇居で使われるものとは限りません。ここでは藤原氏が使うものです。また、&quot;a Heian-period long&quot;という表現に違和感があります。「平安時代の、長い」という意味だと思いますが、&quot;rectangular&quot;（長方形）と言っているので、longはいらないと思います。実際それほど細長いものでもありません。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%8F%B0%E7%9B%A4）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is noted from several records that shuki (vermilion-lacquered dishes and drinking vessels) for grand banquets were stored in four nagabitsu (long wooden box with a lid) and there were 27 daiban (low and rectangular table on which food was served, used by nobles in the Heian period) to place shuki, including five large daiban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>伝承によれば、藤原冬嗣が勧学院に納めた物とされ、以後代々勧学院の別当を兼務した藤氏長者が所持していたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the tradition, they were contributed to Kangakuin (educational institution) by FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu and have been in successive Toshi choja who doubled as betto (chief officer) of Kangakuin for generations.</e>
<cmt>勧学院の登録訳がinstitutionsと複数になっていますが、単数が正しいと思いますので、institutionとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the tradition, they were contributed to Kangakuin (educational institution) by FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu and possessed by successive Toshi choja who doubled as betto (chief officer) of Kangakuin for generations.</e>
<cmt>「所持していた」→過去形に修正。朱器は現存していないので、現在完了は使えません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the tradition, they were contributed to Kangakuin (educational institution) by FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu and possessed by successive Toshi choja who doubled as betto (chief officer) of Kangakuin for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、記録上実際に確認できるのは藤原兼家以後のこととされ、朱器台盤の授受（「朱器渡りの儀」）が藤氏長者交替の際に東三条殿において行われたのは藤原師実以後とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But their first confirmed appearance in written records is not until FUJIWARA no Kaneie and the first transfer of Shuki-daiban (&apos;Shuki watari no gi&apos; [Ceremony for the transfer of Shuki]) to be held on the occasion of the change of Toshi choja at Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace did not take place until FUJIWARA no Morosane.</e>
<cmt>「朱器渡りの儀」定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But their first confirmed appearance in written records is after the time of FUJIWARA no Kaneie and the first transfer of Shuki-daiban (&apos;Shuki watari no gi&apos; [Ceremony for the transfer of Shuki]) to be held on the occasion of the change of Toshi choja at Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace did not take place until the time of FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt>「藤原師実」→正確には「もろざね」のようです。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%97%A4%E5%8E%9F%E5%B8%AB%E5%AE%9F）他、文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But their first confirmed appearance in written records is after the time of FUJIWARA no Kaneie and the first transfer of Shuki-daiban (&apos;Shuki watari no gi&apos; [Ceremony for the transfer of Shuki]) to be held on the occasion of the change of Toshi choja at Higashi Sanjo-dono Palace did not take place until the time of FUJIWARA no Morozane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>久安6年（1150年）、藤原忠実が長男の関白藤原忠通を義絶して次男の藤原頼長を藤氏長者とした際に武士達に命じて強引に朱器台盤を頼長のもとに移した故事は良く知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a well-known historical event that, when FUJIWARA no Tadazane disowned his eldest son FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, who was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) in 1150 and designated his second son FUJIWARA no Yorinaga as Toshi choja, Tadazane ordered samurai to transfer Shuki-daiban to Yorinaga by force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a well-known historical event that, when FUJIWARA no Tadazane disowned his eldest son FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, who was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) in 1150 and designated his second son FUJIWARA no Yorinaga as Toshi choja, Tadazane ordered samurai to transfer Shuki-daiban to Yorinaga by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a well-known historical event that, when FUJIWARA no Tadazane disowned his eldest son FUJIWARA no Tadamichi, who was Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) in 1150 and designated his second son FUJIWARA no Yorinaga as Toshi choja, Tadazane ordered samurai to transfer Shuki-daiban to Yorinaga by force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが、宮中行事などの衰退によって大饗が開かれることがなくなった上、相次ぐ戦乱や五摂家の成立による短期間での藤氏長者の交替などによって朱器台盤は散逸してしまったらしく、延文6年（康安元年/1361年）に近衛道嗣が藤氏長者に就任した際には「朱器渡りの儀」が行われていないために、その以前の段階で朱器台盤は既に存在していなかったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, because grand banquets ceased to be held due to the decline of court functions and because Shuki-daiban were scattered and lost in successive conflicts and changes of Toshi choja within a short period of time caused by the formation of Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho [regent] and Kanpaku), &apos;Shuki watari no gi&apos; no longer took place when Michitsugu KONOE assumed the post of Toshi choja in 1361, which suggests that Shuki-daiban had already been lost before that time.</e>
<cmt>登録されている「相次ぐ戦乱」の「in the area」はこの文の場合は不要と思われますので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But grand banquets ceased to be held due to the decline of court functions, and in addition, Shuki-daiban seem to have been scattered and lost due to successive conflicts and changes of Toshi choja within a short period of time caused by the formation of Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho [regent] and Kanpaku), and when Michitsugu KONOE assumed the post of Toshi choja in 1361, &apos;Shuki watari no gi&apos; no longer took place, which suggests that Shuki-daiban had already been lost before that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;because&quot;を使わず、「朱器渡りの儀」が行われなくなるまでの経緯として訳した方が分かりやすいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But grand banquets ceased to be held due to the decline of court functions, and in addition, Shuki-daiban seem to have been scattered and lost due to successive conflicts and changes of Toshi choja within a short period of time caused by the formation of Gosekke (five top Fujiwara families whose members were eligible for the positions of Sessho [regent] and Kanpaku), and when Michitsugu KONOE assumed the post of Toshi choja in 1361, &apos;Shuki watari no gi&apos; no longer took place, which suggests that Shuki-daiban had already been lost before that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), ５１６(id:45205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>