<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>会見県設置運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movement to create Aimi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>※会見県設置運動　定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movement to create Aimi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement to create Aimi Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>会見県設置運動（あいみけんせっちうんどう）は明治23年（1890年）から翌24年（1891年）にかけて鳥取県米子市を中心に起きた新県設置運動のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movement to create Aimi Prefecture was a movement that people requested to create new prefecture, the movement was centered in Yonago City, Tottori Prefecture from 1890 to 1891.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movement to create Aimi Prefecture was a movement that people requested to create a new prefecture, and the movement was centered in Yonago City, Tottori Prefecture from 1890 to 1891.</e>
<cmt>a, and を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement to create Aimi Prefecture was a movement that people requested to create a new prefecture, and the movement was centered in Yonago City, Tottori Prefecture from 1890 to 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>鳥取県の西部、旧伯耆国のなかでも「西伯耆」と呼ばれた地方は古くから出雲国との密接な交流が存在し、現在でも同一の雲伯方言を話している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The west part of Tottori Prefecture, especially the district called &apos;Nishi Hoki&apos; in Hoki Province (old provincial name) had close relationship with Izumo Province and people there speak the same dialect so called Unpaku dialect today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The west part of Tottori Prefecture, especially the district called &apos;Nishi Hoki&apos; in Hoki Province (old provincial name) had close relationship with Izumo Province and people there speak the same dialect so called Unpaku dialect today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The west part of Tottori Prefecture, especially the district called &apos;Nishi Hoki&apos; in Hoki Province (old provincial name) had close relationship with Izumo Province and people there speak the same dialect so called Unpaku dialect today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治14年（1881年）、鳥取市の士族などによる「鳥取県再置運動」により因・伯2国を以って鳥取県が再置されたが、依然として島根とのつながりを重視する米子地方の人々は島根県への編入を求めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1881, the &apos;request to reconfigure the territory of Tottori prefecture&apos; movement occurred which was supported including shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) in Tottori city, as the result Tottori Prefecture was reconfigured with Inaba Province and Houki Province, however people lived in Yonago district wished incorporation into Shimane Prefecture because they considered the relationship with people in Shimane Prefecture was important.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1881, by &apos;the movement to request to reconfigure the territory of Tottori prefecture&apos; supported by shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) in Tottori city, Tottori Prefecture was reconfigured with Inaba Province and Houki Province, however people lived in Yonago district wished incorporation of the district into Shimane Prefecture because they considered the relationship with people in Shimane Prefecture was important.</e>
<cmt>語順および表現を変更しました。目的語(district) を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1881, by &apos;the movement to request to reconfigure the territory of Tottori prefecture&apos; supported by shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors) in Tottori city, Tottori Prefecture was reconfigured with Inaba Province and Houki Province, however people lived in Yonago district wished incorporation of the district into Shimane Prefecture because they considered the relationship with people in Shimane Prefecture was important.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのような中での府県制の公布と帝国議会開設による「請願権」の獲得は新県設置に向けた運動を高まらせる要因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that period, because prefectural system and &apos;the right of petition&apos; was introduced, the movement to create a new prefecture was activated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that period, because the prefectural system was issued and &apos;the right of petition&apos; was introduced through the establishment of the Imperial Diet, the movement to create a new prefecture was growing.</e>
<cmt>帝国議会開設による：訳もれです。activated ⇒ growing に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that period, because the prefectural system was issued and &apos;the right of petition&apos; was introduced through the establishment of the Imperial Diet, the movement to create a new prefecture was growing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>会見県設置に向けた取り組みと結果</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Approach and result of the movement to create Aimi Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approach to and result of the movement to create Aimi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>approach to に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approach to and result of the movement to create Aimi Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>以前からくすぶっていた新県構想は請願権の獲得によって一気に高まり、明治23年（1890年）の夏頃には「会見郡・汗入郡・日野郡3郡の島根県編入案」と「鳥取・島根両県を合併させ、会見県を新設する案」の2つが示された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Previously existed conception of creating a new prefecture was activated rapidly after the right of petition was obtained, In summer of 1890, 2 ideas such as &apos;idea to incorporate Aimi, Aseri and Hino-gung into Shimane Prefecture&apos; and &apos;idea to incorporate Tottori and Shimane Prefecture and create Aimi Prefecture&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The previously-existing conception of creating a new prefecture grew rapidly after the right of petition was obtained, and in the summer of 1890, 2 ideas such as &apos;incorporating Aimi, Aseri and Hino counties into Shimane Prefecture&apos; and &apos;incorporating Tottori and Shimane Prefecture and create Aimi Prefecture&apos; were presented.</e>
<cmt>The previously-existing に訂正しました。 was activated ⇒　grew に変更しました。In ⇒ and in the に訂正しました。idea to incorporate　⇒ incorporating に訂正しました。-gung ⇒ counties に訂正しました。が示された：訳もれです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The previously-existing conception of creating a new prefecture grew rapidly after the right of petition was obtained, and in the summer of 1890, 2 ideas such as &apos;incorporating Aimi, Aseri and Hino counties into Shimane Prefecture&apos; and &apos;incorporating Tottori and Shimane Prefecture and create Aimi Prefecture&apos; were presented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>特に後者の案は島根県の石見国を広島県に編入させ、会見郡米子町に県庁を設置するものであり、同時期に石見地方から広島県への編入を求める請願がなされたこともあり、議会や内閣に対して盛んに請願が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, because the second idea included incorporation of former Iwami Province into Hiroshima Prefecture and at the same time, a request was made by residents to incorporate Iwami district into Hiroshima Prefecture, a lot of petitions were made to the parliament and cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, because the latter idea was to incorporate Iwami Province in Shimane Prefecture into Hiroshima Prefecture and establish the Prefectural Office in Yonago town, Aimi County, and at the same time, a request was made by residents in Iwami district to incorporate the district into Hiroshima Prefecture, a lot of petitions were made to the parliament and cabinet.</e>
<cmt>後者：latterに訂正しました。included incorporation of former ⇒ was to incorporate に訂正しました。in Shimane Prefecture を追加しました。会見郡米子町に県庁を設置するものであり：訳もれです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, because the latter idea was to incorporate Iwami Province in Shimane Prefecture into Hiroshima Prefecture and establish the Prefectural Office in Yonago town, Aimi County, and at the same time, a request was made by residents in Iwami district to incorporate the district into Hiroshima Prefecture, a lot of petitions were made to the parliament and cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>これらを主導していた人物は元・鳥取藩家老で元・米子城主の荒尾成勲、坂口平兵衛 (初代)、遠藤春彦、小西清太、野坂茂三郎、小倉直人、門脇重雄などの米子地方を代表する名士達であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The leaders of the movement were former chief retainers of Tottori Domain and castellan of Yonago-jo castle, 荒尾成勲, Heibei SAKAGUCHI (founder), Haruhiko ENDO, 清太 KONISHI, Mosaburo NOSAKA, 小倉直人 and Shigeo KADOWAKI, prominent figures in Yonago district.</e>
<cmt>※荒尾成勲・(小西）清太・小倉直人：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The leaders of the movement were former chief retainers of Tottori Domain and a castellan of Yonago-jo castle, 荒尾成勲, Heibei SAKAGUCHI (founder), Haruhiko ENDO, 清太 KONISHI, Mosaburo NOSAKA, 小倉直人 and Shigeo KADOWAKI, and they were prominent figures in Yonago district.</e>
<cmt>and they were を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The leaders of the movement were former chief retainers of Tottori Domain and a castellan of Yonago-jo castle, 荒尾成勲, Heibei SAKAGUCHI (founder), Haruhiko ENDO, 清太 KONISHI, Mosaburo NOSAKA, 小倉直人 and Shigeo KADOWAKI, and they were prominent figures in Yonago district.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>翌24年2月1日には有志146名が集まって協議会が開かれ、議長に遠藤春彦を選出、会見・汗入両郡の各戸より1銭ずつ出してもらって集めた400円の活動資金をもとに本格的に活動を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1, 1891, a council meeting was held by 146 of voluntary members, then Haruhiko ENDO was elected as a chairman and they started actual activities using a fund of 400 yen which was supplied by 1sen(hundredth of a yen) from each family in Aimi and Aseri-gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 1, 1891, a council meeting was held by 146 of voluntary members, then Haruhiko ENDO was elected as a chairman and they hit the ground running using 400 yen funded by donations of 1sen(hundredth of a yen) by each family in Aimi and Aseri counties.</e>
<cmt>In ⇒ On に訂正しました。started actual activities ⇒ hit the ground running に訂正しました。a fund of 400 yen which was supplied by 1sen(hundredth of a yen) from each family　⇒ 400 yen funded by donations of 1sen(hundredth of a yen) by each family に訂正しました。-gun ⇒ counties に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 1, 1891, a council meeting was held by 146 of voluntary members, then Haruhiko ENDO was elected as a chairman and they hit the ground running using 400 yen funded by donations of 1sen(hundredth of a yen) by each family in Aimi and Aseri counties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>この他、新県設置による利点として3～4万円の地方税負担の減少（当時の鳥取県は島根県と比較して、地租と一戸あたりの負担が地租で8銭、一戸あたりで48銭の差が存在していた）が挙げられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a benefit of creating new prefecture, reduction up to 30,000 to 40,000 yen of local tax was expected (at that time, the amount of land tax in Shimane Prefecture was cheaper than Tottori Prefecture, for example, 地租と一戸あたりの負担が地租で8銭、一戸あたりで48銭の差が存在していた)が挙げられていた。</e>
<cmt>※地租と一戸あたりの負担が地租で8銭、一戸あたりで48銭の差が存在していた）が挙げられていた。原文意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a benefit of creating a new prefecture, reduction of local tax by 30,000 to 40,000 yen was expected (at that time, the amount of land tax and load per household in Shimane Prefecture were cheaper than those in Tottori Prefecture, for example, the difference was 8 sen for land tax, and 48 sen for load per household).</e>
<cmt>creating a new prefecture に訂正しました。reduction of local tax by 30,000 to 40,000 yen に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a benefit of creating a new prefecture, reduction of local tax by 30,000 to 40,000 yen was expected (at that time, the amount of land tax and load per household in Shimane Prefecture were cheaper than those in Tottori Prefecture, for example, the difference was 8 sen for land tax, and 48 sen for load per household).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治24年10月には再び請願が行われたが、運動が米子地方に限られたものであり、他の鳥取・倉吉地方は総じて冷淡な反応を示し、県下全域に広がるものではなかったため、結局実現には至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1891, a petition was made again but the movement was activated only in Yonago district and other district such as Tottori and Kurayoshi didn&apos;t show much interest, because the movement didn&apos;t grow in all district in prefecture, the petition was not realized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1891, a petition was made again but the movement was held only in Yonago district and other districts such as Tottori and Kurayoshi didn&apos;t show much interest, and the petition was not accepted because the movement didn&apos;t grow in all districts in the prefecture,.</e>
<cmt>activated ⇒ held に変更しました。other districts：複数形に訂正しました。all districts：複数形に訂正しました。realized ⇒ accepted に訂正しました。in the prefecture に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1891, a petition was made again but the movement was held only in Yonago district and other districts such as Tottori and Kurayoshi didn&apos;t show much interest, and the petition was not accepted because the movement didn&apos;t grow in all districts in the prefecture,.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>その後の情勢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later situations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later situations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later situations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その後も完全に新県構想が絶えた訳ではなく、大正時代には県議会に両県の合併案が提出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the conception of creating a new prefecture was not abolished, a proposal requesting incorporation of two prefectures was submitted to the prefectural assembly in Taisho Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the conception of creating a new prefecture was not abolished, and a proposal requesting incorporation of two prefectures was submitted to the prefectural assembly in Taisho Period.</e>
<cmt>and を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the conception of creating a new prefecture was not abolished, and a proposal requesting incorporation of two prefectures was submitted to the prefectural assembly in Taisho Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>現在、道州制導入に際して米子市・境港市・松江市などを合併して「中海市｣を誕生させる動きがあるが、それもこの「会見県」構想に端を発するものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, regarding introduction of regional system, there is a movement to incorporate Yonago City, Sakaiminato City and Matsue City and create new city called Nakaumi City, It would appear that this movement came from the conception of &apos;Aimi Prefecture&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, there is a movement to incorporate Yonago City, Sakaiminato City and Matsue City to create a new city called Nakaumi City at the introduction of a regional system, and it would appear that this movement came from the conception of &apos;Aimi Prefecture&apos;.</e>
<cmt>a を追加しました。and ⇒ to に変更しました。It ⇒ and it に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, there is a movement to incorporate Yonago City, Sakaiminato City and Matsue City to create a new city called Nakaumi City at the introduction of a regional system, and it would appear that this movement came from the conception of &apos;Aimi Prefecture&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>