<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>霜月騒動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shimotsuki Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shimotsuki Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimotsuki Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>霜月騒動（しもつきそうどう）とは、鎌倉時代後期の弘安8年（1285年）11月17日 (旧暦)に鎌倉で起こった鎌倉幕府の政変。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Simotsuki Incident was a political change in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) that occurred in Kamakura in the latter half of the Kamakura period on December 21, 1285.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Simotsuki Incident was a political change in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) that occurred in Kamakura in the latter half of the Kamakura period on December 21, 1285.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Simotsuki Incident was a political change in the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) that occurred in Kamakura in the latter half of the Kamakura period on December 21, 1285.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>8代執権北条時宗の死後、有力御家人の安達泰盛と、内管領の平頼綱が対立し、頼綱方の先制攻撃を受けた泰盛とその一族・与党が滅ぼされた事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an incident that occurred after the eighth regent Tokimune HOJO died and the senior vassal, Yasumori ADACHI, Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family) and TAIRA no Yoritsune were in opposition to each other and then Yasumori, his family and the ruling party were destroyed by the Yoritsuna party&apos;s pre-emptive attacks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of the eighth regent Tokimune HOJO, the senior vassal Yasumori ADACHI and TAIRA no Yoritsune, Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family [the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan]) opposed each other and Yasumori, his family, and his party were destroyed in this incident in which Yoritsuna&apos;s party made the preemptive attack.</e>
<cmt>構文が分かりにくくなっていたので全面的に修正しました。与党は政党ではなく、仲間という意味でつかわれていますのでpartyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of the eighth regent Tokimune HOJO, the senior vassal Yasumori ADACHI and TAIRA no Yoritsune, Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family [the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan]) opposed each other and Yasumori, his family, and his party were destroyed in this incident in which Yoritsuna&apos;s party made the preemptive attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>弘安合戦、安達泰盛の乱、秋田城介（あきたじょうのすけ）の乱ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was also called the Battle of Koan, the Yasumori ADACHI war or the Jonosuke AKITA war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident is also called the Battle of Koan, the Yasumori ADACHI war or the Jonosuke AKITA war.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident is also called the Battle of Koan, the Yasumori ADACHI war or the Jonosuke AKITA war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>安達泰盛は幕府創設以来の有力御家人安達氏の一族で、北条氏得宗家の外戚として執権北条時宗を支え、越訴、御恩奉行などの重職を歴任した幕政の中心人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumori ADACHI was a member of the Adachi clan, senior vassals since the Kamakura government was established and supported the regent Tokimune HOJO as a maternal relative of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, and were key figures experienced in important positions like a Osso (legal institutions of Kamakura bakufu, which filled the role of hearing cases such as retrials and direct appeals to a senior official) and Goon bugyo (御恩奉行) (commissioner of the grant of honors/distribution of rewards).</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumori ADACHI was a member of the Adachi clan, the senior vassals since the Kamakura government was established, and he supported the regent Tokimune HOJO as a maternal relative of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, and was a key figure experienced in important positions like an Ossobugyo (temporary position in charge of retrials and accepting appeals in Kamakura bakufu) and Goon bugyo (commissioner in charge of issuing the deed of rewards.)</e>
<cmt>「越訴、御恩奉行」は「越訴奉行と御恩奉行」ですので、単語リストの御恩奉行の訳をあてはめました。不要な感じは削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumori ADACHI was a member of the Adachi clan, the senior vassals since the Kamakura government was established, and he supported the regent Tokimune HOJO as a maternal relative of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, and was a key figure experienced in important positions like an Ossobugyo (temporary position in charge of retrials and accepting appeals in Kamakura bakufu) and Goon bugyo (commissioner in charge of issuing the deed of rewards.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平頼綱は時宗の乳母父で北条氏得宗家の執事内管領であり、得宗権力を具現する立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoritsuna was a male nurse of tokimune and an under secretary of the head of Tokuso family and he was in a position to embody the authority of Tokuso.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoritsuna was a male nurse of Tokimune and the under secretary of the head of Tokuso family and he was in a position to embody the authority of Tokuso.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。名前を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoritsuna was a male nurse of Tokimune and the under secretary of the head of Tokuso family and he was in a position to embody the authority of Tokuso.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>幕府では外様御家人を支持勢力とする泰盛と、頼綱を筆頭とする得宗被官勢力が拮抗していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kamakura bakufu, Yasumori who was supported by tozama gokenin (nonhereditary lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura period) competed against Tokuso&apos;s vassal party lead by Yoritsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kamakura bakufu, Yasumori who was supported by tozama gokenin (nonhereditary lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura period) competed against Tokuso&apos;s vassal party led by Yoritsuna.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamakura bakufu, Yasumori who was supported by tozama gokenin (nonhereditary lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura period) competed against Tokuso&apos;s vassal party led by Yoritsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>弘安7年（1284年）に両者の調停役となっていた執権時宗が死去し、14歳の嫡子北条貞時が9代執権となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1284, Tokimune the regent to the shogunate died. He had played a coordinating role between both parties, and 14 years old legitimate child, Tokisada HOJO became the ninth regent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1284, Tokimune, the regent to the shogunate who had played a coordinating role between both parties, died and his 14-year-old legitimate child Sadatoki HOJO became the ninth regent.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。時宗の読みを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1284, Tokimune, the regent to the shogunate who had played a coordinating role between both parties, died and his 14-year-old legitimate child Sadatoki HOJO became the ninth regent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>元寇以来、内外に諸問題が噴出する中で幕政運営を巡って両者の対立は激化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confrontation and rivalry became intense over government administration with internal and external issues appearing one after another since the Mongol invasion attempts on Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confrontation and rivalry became intense over government administration amid internal and external issues erupting one after another since the Mongol invasion attempts on Japan.</e>
<cmt>単語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confrontation and rivalry became intense over government administration amid internal and external issues erupting one after another since the Mongol invasion attempts on Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>貞時の外祖父として幕政を主導する立場となった泰盛は弘安徳政と呼ばれる幕政改革に着手し、新たな法令を大量に発布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yasumori got a position to lead the government administration as the maternal grandfather of Tokisada, he launched a political reform called &quot;Koan tokusei&quot; and promulgated a large number of laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yasumori got a position to lead the government administration as the maternal grandfather of Sadatoki, he launched a political reform called &apos;Koan tokusei&apos; and promulgated a large number of laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。時宗の読みを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yasumori got a position to lead the government administration as the maternal grandfather of Sadatoki, he launched a political reform called &apos;Koan tokusei&apos; and promulgated a large number of laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>征夷大将軍を戴く御家人制度の立て直しを図る泰盛の改革は御家人層を拡大し、将軍権威の発揚して得宗権力と御内人の幕政への介入を抑制するもので、得宗被官である頼綱らに利害が及ぶものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumori&apos;s reforms aimed to reorganize the Gokenin system (immediate vassals of the shogunate in the Kamakura period) overseen by Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) in order to expand the Gokenin class and enhance the shogun&apos;s authority to prevent any increase in Tokuso&apos;s power and Gokenin&apos;s intervention into politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumori&apos;s reforms aimed to reorganize the Gokenin system (immediate vassals of the shogunate in the Kamakura period) overseen by Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) in order to expand the Gokenin class and enhance the shogun&apos;s authority to prevent any increase in Tokuso&apos;s power and Gokenin&apos;s intervention into politics, which would influence the position of Yoritsuna and other Tokuso&apos;s vassals.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。「得宗被官である頼綱らに利害が及ぶものであった。」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumori&apos;s reforms aimed to reorganize the Gokenin system (immediate vassals of the shogunate in the Kamakura period) overseen by Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) in order to expand the Gokenin class and enhance the shogun&apos;s authority to prevent any increase in Tokuso&apos;s power and Gokenin&apos;s intervention into politics, which would influence the position of Yoritsuna and other Tokuso&apos;s vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>弘安8年（1285年）11月4日と14日に頼綱は日光山別当源恵に依頼し、泰盛伐の祈祷を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoritsuna requested Genkei (源恵), betto (the head secretary of a temple) in Nikko-zan mountain to give an invocation to subdue Yasumori on December 8 and 18, 1285.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoritsuna requested Genkei, the betto (the head secretary of a temple) in Nikko-zan mountain to give an invocation to subdue Yasumori on December 8 and 18, 1285.</e>
<cmt>不要な漢字は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoritsuna requested Genkei, the betto (the head secretary of a temple) in Nikko-zan mountain to give an invocation to subdue Yasumori on December 8 and 18, 1285.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>合戦の状況を語る唯一の一次史料である霜月騒動覚聞書によると、11月17日の午前中、松谷の別荘に居た泰盛は、世間が騒がしくなった事に気付き、昼の12時頃塔ノ辻にある出仕用の屋形に出かけ、貞時邸に出仕したところを頼綱の手勢の襲撃を受けて殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the shimotsuki Incident note (霜月騒動覚聞書), the only primary archive describing the incident, when Yasumori was in a second house in Matsutani on December 21, he noticed a restlessness in the world and went back to his residence to prepare to attend court, but he was attacked and killed by Yoritsuna&apos;s soldiers when he arrived at Sadatoki&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Shimotsuki Incident note, the only primary archive describing the incident, when Yasumori was in his second house in Matsutani in the morning of December 21, he noticed a restlessness in the world and went back to his residence in Tonotsuji around midday to prepare to attend court, but he was attacked and killed by Yoritsuna&apos;s soldiers when he arrived at Sadatoki&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>「昼の12時頃塔ノ辻にある」の訳を補いました。Shimotsukeは大文字にしました。不要な漢字は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Shimotsuki Incident note, the only primary archive describing the incident, when Yasumori was in his second house in Matsutani in the morning of December 21, he noticed a restlessness in the world and went back to his residence in Tonotsuji around midday to prepare to attend court, but he was attacked and killed by Yoritsuna&apos;s soldiers when he arrived at Sadatoki&apos;s residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>死者30名、負傷者10名に及び、これをきっかけに大きな衝突が起こり、将軍御所が延焼、午後4時頃に合戦は安達方の敗北となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This attack saw 30 dead and 10 injured people triggering a big conflict in resulting fire spreading to the shogun&apos;s palace and the Adachi&apos;s party was defeated by 4 pm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This attack left 30 people dead and 10 people injured triggering a big conflict which resulted in fire to spread to the shogun&apos;s palace and the Adachi&apos;s party was defeated by 4 pm.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This attack left 30 people dead and 10 people injured triggering a big conflict which resulted in fire to spread to the shogun&apos;s palace and the Adachi&apos;s party was defeated by 4 pm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>安達時景は飯山に逃亡したが殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokikage ADACHI escaped to Iiyama, but he was killed later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokikage ADACHI escaped to Iiyama, but he was killed there.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokikage ADACHI escaped to Iiyama, but he was killed there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>泰盛の一族500名余りが自害し、騒動は全国に波及して各地で泰盛派が追撃を受け、自害に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 500 members of Yasumori&apos;s party committed suicide and the incident extended across the nation and Yasumori&apos;s party in various places were pursued and forced to committed suicide,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 500 members of Yasumori&apos;s family committed suicide and the incident extended across country and Yasumori&apos;s party in various places were pursued and forced to commit suicide,</e>
<cmt>一族はfamilyにしました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 500 members of Yasumori&apos;s family committed suicide and the incident extended across country and Yasumori&apos;s party in various places were pursued and forced to commit suicide,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>安達氏の基盤である上野国・武蔵国の御家人の被害は多く、武蔵では武藤少卿左衛門、遠江国では安達宗顕、常陸国では安達重景、信濃国では伴野彦二郎らが自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of suicides in the Gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate in the Kamakura period)in Kozuke Province and Musashi Province, the Adachi clan&apos;s base, was huge, Shokyozaemon Muto (武藤少卿左衛門) in Musashi, Muneaki ADACHI (安達宗顕) in Totomo province, Shigekage ADACHI in Hitachi province and Hikojiro BANNO in Shinano province committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The damage to the Gokenin in Kozuke Province and Musashi Province, the Adachi clan&apos;s bases, was huge, for example, Shokyozaemon Muto (武藤少卿左衛門) in Musashi, Muneaki ADACHI (安達宗顕) in Totomo province, Shigekage ADACHI in Hitachi province and Hikojiro BANNO in Shinano province committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>「被害」は必ずしも自害とは限らないのでdamageとしました。不要な説明、スペースは削除しました。人名の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The damage to the Gokenin in Kozuke Province and Musashi Province, the Adachi clan&apos;s bases, was huge, for example, Shokyozaemon Muto (武藤少卿左衛門) in Musashi, Muneaki ADACHI (安達宗顕) in Totomo province, Shigekage ADACHI in Hitachi province and Hikojiro BANNO in Shinano province committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>九州では泰盛の子安達盛宗が岩門合戦で敗死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyushu region, Morimune ADACHI, son of Yasumori died during the battle of Iwato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyushu region, Morimune ADACHI, son of Yasumori died during the battle of Iwato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyushu region, Morimune ADACHI, son of Yasumori died during the battle of Iwato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これだけの人数が一気に討ち死に、自害に追い込まれたのは用意周到な計画の元で時間を定めて一斉に襲撃したためと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is supposed that such a large number of people died in the battle and were forced to committed suicide because this attack started at a specific time based on a religious plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is supposed that such a large number of people died in the battle or were forced to commit suicide because this attack was carried out simultaneously based on a well-prepared plan.</e>
<cmt>文脈と文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is supposed that such a large number of people died in the battle or were forced to commit suicide because this attack was carried out simultaneously based on a well-prepared plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>泰盛与党として罹災したのは泰盛一族の他、小笠原氏、足利氏、伴野氏、伊東氏、武藤氏（少弐氏）、その他は藤原相範、吉良満氏、殖田又太郎（大江泰広）、小早川三郎左衛門、三科蔵人、天野景村、伊賀景家、二階堂行景、（大井）美作三郎左衛門、綱島二郎入道、池上藤内左衛門の尉、行方少二郎、南部孫二郎（政連？）、有坂三郎、鎌田弥藤二左衛門尉、秋山人々など、幕府創設以来の有力御家人層の多くが見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families who were suffered from this battle as members of Yasumori&apos;s ruling party other than the Yasumori family were the Ogasawara clan, the Ashikaga clan, the Tomono clan, the Ito clan, the Muto clan (Shoni clan) and many powerful gokenin since the foundation of Kamakura bakufu were suffered like Ainori FUJIWARA (藤原相範), Mitsuruuji KIRA, Matataro UETA (Yasuhiro Oe), Saburozaemon KOBAYAKAWA, Kurodo SANKA, Kagemura AMANO, Kageie IGA, Yukiie NIKAIDO, Mimasakasaburozaemon (OI) (美作三郎左衛門), Jironyudo TSUNASHIMA (綱島二郎入道), a lord of Tonaizaemon IKEGAMI (池上藤内左衛門), Shojiro YUKIKATA (行方少二郎), Magojiro (Masatsura?) NANBU, Saburo ARISAKA, Yatonisaemoni KAMATA (鎌田弥藤二左衛門尉), Hitobito AKIYAMA (秋山人々).</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Victims of this battle among the members of Yasumori&apos;s party other than the Yasumori family were the Ogasawara clan, the Ashikaga clan, the Tomono clan, the Ito clan, and the Muto clan (Shoni clan) and many powerful gokenin since the foundation of Kamakura bakufu also suffered, such as Ainori FUJIWARA (藤原相範), Mitsuruuji KIRA, Matataro UETA (Yasuhiro Oe), Saburozaemon KOBAYAKAWA, Kurodo SANKA, Kagemura AMANO, Kageie IGA, Yukiie NIKAIDO, Mimasakasaburozaemon (OI) (美作三郎左衛門), Jironyudo TSUNASHIMA (綱島二郎入道), a lord of Tonaizaemon IKEGAMI (池上藤内左衛門), Shojiro YUKIKATA (行方少二郎), Magojiro (Masatsura?) NANBU, Saburo ARISAKA, Yatonisaemoni KAMATA (鎌田弥藤二左衛門尉), and Hitobito AKIYAMA (秋山人々).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。人名の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Victims of this battle among the members of Yasumori&apos;s party other than the Yasumori family were the Ogasawara clan, the Ashikaga clan, the Tomono clan, the Ito clan, and the Muto clan (Shoni clan) and many powerful gokenin since the foundation of Kamakura bakufu also suffered, such as Ainori FUJIWARA (藤原相範), Mitsuruuji KIRA, Matataro UETA (Yasuhiro Oe), Saburozaemon KOBAYAKAWA, Kurodo SANKA, Kagemura AMANO, Kageie IGA, Yukiie NIKAIDO, Mimasakasaburozaemon (OI) (美作三郎左衛門), Jironyudo TSUNASHIMA (綱島二郎入道), a lord of Tonaizaemon IKEGAMI (池上藤内左衛門), Shojiro YUKIKATA (行方少二郎), Magojiro (Masatsura?) NANBU, Saburo ARISAKA, Yatonisaemoni KAMATA (鎌田弥藤二左衛門尉), and Hitobito AKIYAMA (秋山人々).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>一方頼綱方の討手として得宗被官化した御家人の佐々木氏、今川氏、千葉氏なども加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Sasaki clan, the Imagawa clan and the Chiba clan joined this attack as pursuer of Tokuso&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Sasaki clan, the Imagawa clan and the Chiba clan joined this attack as pursuer of Tokuso&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Sasaki clan, the Imagawa clan and the Chiba clan joined this attack as pursuer of Tokuso&apos;s vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このように同族内でも頼綱方と泰盛方に分かれるなど、幕府を大きく二分した争乱であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As one family was broken down into two, Yoritsuna party and Yasumori party, this conflict split bakufu into large two groups.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This conflict split the bakufu into two large groups, even a family was broken down into two; Yoritsuna party and Yasumori party,</e>
<cmt>語順を入れ替えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This conflict split the bakufu into two large groups, even a family was broken down into two; Yoritsuna party and Yasumori party,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>泰盛と縁戚関係のあった金沢貞顕は下総国に蟄居の身となり、宇都宮景綱、長井宗秀らが失脚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadaaki KANESAWA, Yasumori&apos;s relative, was confined in Shimousa Province and Kagetuna UTSUNOMIYA and Munehide NAGAI fell from power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadaaki KANESAWA, Yasumori&apos;s relative, was confined in Shimousa Province and Kagetuna UTSUNOMIYA and Munehide NAGAI fell from power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadaaki KANESAWA, Yasumori&apos;s relative, was confined in Shimousa Province and Kagetuna UTSUNOMIYA and Munehide NAGAI fell from power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>霜月騒動後の鎌倉幕府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu after the shimotsuki incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura bakufu after the Shimotsuki incident</e>
<cmt>Shimotsukiは大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu after the Shimotsuki incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="23">
<j>実権を握った平頼綱は泰盛の弘安改革を否定し、幕府の人事は得宗を頂点に北条氏 (大仏流)、北条氏 (名越流)を中心に北条一族の支配となり、足利氏ら旧来の御家人の姿は無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoritsuna held a real power and rejected Yasumori&apos;s Koan reform, most of positions in bakufu were occupied by the Hojo family topped by Tokuso centered mainly around the Osaragi line of the Hojo clan and the Nagoe line of the Hojo clan, and no important positions were given to old gokenin like the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoritsuna held a real power and rejected Yasumori&apos;s Koan reform, and the most of the positions in the bakufu were occupied by the Hojo family, with Tokuso at the top and the Osaragi line of the Hojo clan and the Nagoe line of the Hojo clan at the center, and no important positions were given to old gokenin like the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoritsuna held a real power and rejected Yasumori&apos;s Koan reform, and the most of the positions in the bakufu were occupied by the Hojo family, with Tokuso at the top and the Osaragi line of the Hojo clan and the Nagoe line of the Hojo clan at the center, and no important positions were given to old gokenin like the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>京都では泰盛と協調して弘安徳政を行っていたと見られる亀山上皇の院政停止（持明院統伏見天皇即位）が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, the retired Emperor Kameyama, who was alleged to carry out Koan tokusei with Yasumori was forced to terminate his Insei (government by a retired emperor) (Jimyoin line Emperor Fushimi ascended the throne).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, the retired Emperor Kameyama, who is said to have carried out Koan tokusei (political reforms in the Koan era) with Yasumori was forced to terminate his Insei (government by a retired emperor) (Jimyoin line Emperor Fushimi ascended the throne.)</e>
<cmt>弘安徳政の説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, the retired Emperor Kameyama, who is said to have carried out Koan tokusei (political reforms in the Koan era) with Yasumori was forced to terminate his Insei (government by a retired emperor) (Jimyoin line Emperor Fushimi ascended the throne.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>将軍問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun issue</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun issue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun issue</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>『保暦間記』によると、頼綱は泰盛の子安達宗景が源頼朝の落胤であると称して源氏に改姓し、謀反を起こして将軍になろうとしている、と貞時に讒言したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Horyakukanki&quot; (A History Book of the 14 century in Japan), Yoritsuna gave a slanderous account to Sadatoki that Mumekage Adachi, a son of Yasumori, called himself an illegitimate child of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and changed his family name to the Minamoto clan to become shogun by raising a rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Horyakukanki&quot; (A History Book of the 14 century in Japan), Yoritsuna gave Sadatoki a slanderous account of Mumekage Adachi, a son of Yasumori, saying that he was claiming himself as an illegitimate child of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and changed his family name to the Minamoto clan to become shogun by raising a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Horyakukanki&quot; (A History Book of the 14 century in Japan), Yoritsuna gave Sadatoki a slanderous account of Mumekage Adachi, a son of Yasumori, saying that he was claiming himself as an illegitimate child of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo and changed his family name to the Minamoto clan to become shogun by raising a rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>泰盛は源氏将軍に伝えられる「髭切」を京都のある霊社から探し出して法華堂の御逗子に納めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasumori found &quot;Higekiri&quot; (celebrated sword) handed down in Genji shogun in some reisha shrine in Kyoto and dedicated it to Hokkedo hall in Zushi (御逗子).</e>
<cmt>読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasumori found &apos;Higekiri&apos; (celebrated sword) handed down in Genji shogun in some reisha shrine in Kyoto and dedicated it to the Buddhist altar in the Hokkedo hall.</e>
<cmt>御逗子は地名ではなく厨子のことです。定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasumori found &apos;Higekiri&apos; (celebrated sword) handed down in Genji shogun in some reisha shrine in Kyoto and dedicated it to the Buddhist altar in the Hokkedo hall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>髭切りの太刀は霜月騒動で行方不明になったのち、12月5日に探し出され、貞時によって「赤字の錦袋」（平氏を称する北条氏は赤旗）に包まれて再び法華堂に奉納された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Higekiri sword was lost during the shimotsuki incident, it was discovered on January 8, and Sadatoki indicated it was wrapped by &quot;Red brocade&quot; (Flag color of the Hojo clan, refer themselves as the Taira clan, was red).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Higekiri sword was lost during the Shimotsuki incident, it was discovered on January 8, and Sadatoki indicated it was wrapped by &quot;Red brocade&quot; (Red was the flag color of the Hojo clan who refered themselves as the Taira clan.)</e>
<cmt>Shimotsukiは大文字にしました。自然な訳になるように語順を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Higekiri sword was lost during the Shimotsuki incident, it was discovered on January 8, and Sadatoki indicated it was wrapped by &quot;Red brocade&quot; (Red was the flag color of the Hojo clan who refered themselves as the Taira clan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>本来鎌倉殿と御家人の主従関係で成り立っていた幕府内部において、総領制が行き詰まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the Kamakura bakufu was established based on master-servant relationship between the Kamakura-don (lord of Kamakura) and the Gokenin, however the Soryo system (the eldest son system for the succession of the head of the family) was getting bogged down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the Kamakura bakufu was established based on master-servant relationship between the Kamakura-don (lord of Kamakura) and the Gokenin, however the Soryo system (the eldest son system for the succession of the head of the family) was getting bogged down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the Kamakura bakufu was established based on master-servant relationship between the Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura) and the Gokenin, however the Soryo system (the eldest son system for the succession of the head of the family) was getting bogged down.</e>
<cmt>Kamakura-don →Kamakura-donoに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>これにより零細化した御家人が得宗被官の御内人として取り込まれ、得宗と御内人の主従関係を築くようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokenin faced financial issues and they were employed by Tokuso&apos;s vassals as a Miuchibito (private vassals of the tokuso) and a master-servant relationship was established between Tokuso and Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>一原文一翻訳の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokenin faced financial issues and they were employed by Tokuso&apos;s vassals as a Miuchibito (private vassals of the tokuso) and a master-servant relationship was established between Tokuso and Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースは削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokenin faced financial issues and they were employed by Tokuso&apos;s vassals as a Miuchibito (private vassals of the tokuso) and a master-servant relationship was established between Tokuso and Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>泰盛の改革で救済対象であった零細御家人は、御内人として得宗方の討手に回ったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Petty gokenins who were subject to relief in Yasumori&apos;s reform became pursuers of Tokuso party as Gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Petty gokenins who had been the subject of relief in Yasumori&apos;s reform became pursuers of Tokuso party as Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Petty gokenins who had been the subject of relief in Yasumori&apos;s reform became pursuers of Tokuso party as Miuchibito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>一方、幕府創設以来の御家人達にとって、一段身分が低く、あくまでも北条家の家臣に過ぎない内管領・御内人が権勢を振るう事への反発は強く、それら外様御家人層の多くが泰盛方に加わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Gokenins since the foundation of Kamakura bakufu were offended by Uchi-Kanrei (head of Tokuso Family) and Miuchibito since Uchi-kanreia and Miuchibito had the reins of power eventhough they were of lower rank than Gokenins, as a result, most of tozama gokenin (nonhereditary lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura period) joined Yasumori&apos;s party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Gokenins since the foundation of Kamakura bakufu were offended by Uchi-Kanrei and Miuchibito since Uchi-kanreia holding the reins of power despite they were of lower ranks than Gokenin and, as a result, most of tozama gokenin (nonhereditary lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura period) joined Yasumori&apos;s party.</e>
<cmt>重複する説明を削除しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Gokenins since the foundation of Kamakura bakufu were offended by Uchi-Kanrei and Miuchibito since Uchi-kanreia holding the reins of power despite they were of lower ranks than Gokenin and, as a result, most of tozama gokenin (nonhereditary lower-ranking vassal in the Kamakura period) joined Yasumori&apos;s party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>将軍問題は得宗が幕府の頂点にありながらも、その出自の低さ故に自ら将軍になる事の出来ない北条氏が最後まで乗り越える事の出来ない壁となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan couldn&apos;t get over Shogun issue in the end as Tokuso couldn&apos;t become Shogun due to his low status by birth eventhough he was the most powerful lord of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan couldn&apos;t get over Shogun issue in the end as Tokuso couldn&apos;t become Shogun due to his low status by birth eventhough he was the most powerful lord of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan couldn&apos;t get over Shogun issue in the end as Tokuso couldn&apos;t become Shogun due to his low status by birth eventhough he was the most powerful lord of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 水野白楓(id:22811), ちちぶ(id:184715), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Kichyou(id:19769), Junger(id:10282), SieBot(id:126695), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>