<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寛平の治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpyo no chi (Glorious rule in Kanpyo era)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpyo no chi (Glorious rule in Kanpyo era)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpyo no chi (Glorious rule in Kanpyo era)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寛平の治（かんぴょうのち）は、平安時代中期（9世紀後期）の宇多天皇の治世を理想視した呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpyo no chi is a name of the rule by Emperor Uda in the mid-Heian Period (late 9th century) regarded as an ideal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpyo no chi is the name of the rule by Emperor Uda in the mid-Heian Period (late 9th century) which was largely regarded as ideal.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpyo no chi is the name of the rule by Emperor Uda in the mid-Heian Period (late 9th century) which was largely regarded as ideal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>寛平は宇多天皇の治世の元号である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpyo is an name of the era ruled by Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpyo is the name of the era ruled by Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpyo is the name of the era ruled by Emperor Uda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>宇多天皇は、891年（寛平3年）の関白藤原基経の死後摂関を置かず、源能有を事実上の首班として藤原時平と菅原道真、平季長等の近臣を重用し各種政治改革を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Uda did not appoint Sekkan (regents and advisers) after the death of Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Mototsune in 891, and carried out various political reforms using MINAMOTO no Yoshiari as a virtual leader and promoting trusted vassals such as FUJIWARA no Tokihira, SUGAWARA no Michizane, and TAIRA no Suenaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Uda did not appoint Sekkan (regents and advisers) after the death of Kanpaku FUJIWARA no Mototsune in 891, and carried out various political reforms using MINAMOTO no Yoshiari as a virtual leader, promoting trusted vassals such as FUJIWARA no Tokihira, SUGAWARA no Michizane, and TAIRA no Suenaga.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Uda did not appoint Sekkan (regents and advisers) after the death of Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) FUJIWARA no Mototsune in 891, and carried out various political reforms using MINAMOTO no Yoshiari as a virtual leader, promoting trusted vassals such as FUJIWARA no Tokihira, SUGAWARA no Michizane, and TAIRA no Suenaga.</e>
<cmt>関白の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>近年の研究では、従来から言われていた894年（寛平6年）の遣唐使廃止や896年（寛平8年）の造籍、私営田抑制、滝口の武士の設置等に加え、国司に一国内の租税納入を請け負わせる国司請負や、位田等からの俸給給付等を民部省を通さずに各国で行う等、国司の権限を強化する改革を次々と行ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to recent studies, in addition to the abolition of Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China) in 894, register of population, restriction of the private land, and deployment of Takiguchi no Bushi (the guards of the Imperial Palace who was in charge of near waterfall in the palace) in 896, he seems to have continuously carried out reforms to strengthen the power of kokushi (provincial governors), such as kokushi ukeoi to make kokushi collect all local taxes in their provinces, and making each province to pay the salary directly from iden (fields given based on ikai, the court rank) without going through.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to recent studies, in addition to the abolition of Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China) in 894, register of population, restriction of the private land, and deployment of Takiguchi no Bushi (the guards of the Imperial Palace who were in charge near the palace waterfall) in 896, he seems to have continuously carried out reforms to strengthen the power of kokushi (provincial governors), such as kokushi ukeoi to make kokushi collect all local taxes in their provinces, and making each province pay the salary directly from iden (fields given based on ikai, the court rank) without going through the minbusho (ministry of taxation).</e>
<cmt>Missing translation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to recent studies, in addition to the abolition of Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China) in 894, register of population, restriction of the private land, and deployment of Takiguchi no Bushi (the guards of the Imperial Palace who were in charge near the palace waterfall) in 896, he seems to have continuously carried out reforms to strengthen the power of kokushi (provincial governors), such as kokushi ukeoi to make kokushi collect all local taxes in their provinces, and making each province pay the salary directly from iden (fields given based on ikai, the court rank) without going through the minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>民部省の定訳追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、天皇親政が行われた治世と評価されたが、摂関不設置は阿衡事件に懲りた宇多天皇が皇族を母とする藤原氏腹でない天皇であったことと、藤原氏藤氏長者時平がまだ若かったことが原因とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This era was highly evaluated due to the direct rule by the emperor, and the sekkan were not appointed because Emperor Uda disgusted with the Ako Incident was not born from a mother from the Fujiwara family having an imperial mother, and because Tokihira, the head of the Fujiwara family, was still young.</e>
<cmt>「藤原氏藤氏長者時平」とありますが、「藤原氏長者時平」の誤りと思われますので、そのように訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This era was highly regarded due to the direct rule by the emperor, and sekkan were not appointed because Emperor Uda was disgusted with the Ako Incident and was not born from a mother from the Fujiwara family having an imperial mother, and because Tokihira, the head of the Fujiwara family, was still young.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This era was highly regarded due to the direct rule by the emperor, and sekkan were not appointed because Emperor Uda was disgusted with the Ako Incident and was not born from a mother from the Fujiwara family having an imperial mother, and because Tokihira, the head of the Fujiwara family, was still young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>897年（寛平9年）、宇多天皇は皇太子敦仁親王（醍醐天皇）に譲位し、その2年後に自ら造立した仁和寺で出家し法皇と称したが、病気がちの醍醐天皇に代わって、実際の政務を執っていたいう説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 897, Emperor Uda abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Atsugimi (Emperor Daigo), and became a priest in Ninna-ji Temple built by himself and called himself Cloistered Emperor two years later, but there is an assumption that he actually managed political affairs in place of often-ailing Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 897, Emperor Uda abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Atsugimi (Emperor Daigo), and became a priest in Ninna-ji Temple which he built himself and called himself Cloistered Emperor two years later, but there is an assumption that he actually managed political affairs in place of the oft-ailing Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 897, Emperor Uda abdicated the throne to Crown Prince Atsugimi (Emperor Daigo), and became a priest in Ninna-ji Temple which he built himself and called himself Cloistered Emperor two years later, but there is an assumption that he in fact managed political affairs in place of the oft-ailing Emperor Daigo.</e>
<cmt>actually -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>「延喜天暦の治」と賞せられる醍醐天皇（延喜の治）・村上天皇（天暦の治）の「善政」とされるものの多くは寛平の治の政策の延長上に過ぎず、従来延喜年間のこととされている奴婢制度廃止令も寛平年中に出された形跡があるとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of what are called &quot;good politics&quot; in the eras of Emperor Daigo (Engi no chi) and Emperor Murakami (Tenryaku no chi) highly evaluated as &quot;Engi-Tenryaku-no-chi&quot; were only extensions of the political measures taken in Kanpyo no chi, and a theory tells there is an evidence that the abolition of slavery was issued in Kanpyo era, which is generally believed to have been issued in Enki era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of what was called &quot;good politics&quot; in the era of Emperor Daigo (Engi no chi) and Emperor Murakami (Tenryaku no chi) and which were highly evaluated as &quot;Engi-Tenryaku-no-chi&quot; were only extensions of the political measures taken in Kanpyo no chi, and one theory holds that there is evidence that the abolition of slavery was issued in Kanpyo era, which is generally believed to have been issued in the Enki era.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of what was called &apos;good politics&apos; in the era of Emperor Daigo (Engi no chi) and Emperor Murakami (Tenryaku no chi) and which were highly evaluated as &apos;Engi-Tenryaku-no-ch&apos; were only extensions of the political measures taken in Kanpyo no chi, and one theory holds that there is evidence that the abolition of slavery was issued in the Kanpyo era, which is generally believed to have been issued in the Enkgi era.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Kanpyo era→the Kanpyo eraEnki era→Engi era</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>寛平の治は、王臣家が諸国富豪と直接結びつくことを規制することで権門（有力貴族・寺社）を抑制し、小農民を保護するという律令制への回帰を強く志向したものであり、併せて蔵人所の充実や検非違使庁の権限拡充等天皇直属機関の強化を行うものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpyo no chi was strongly intended for a return to the Ritsuryo system that protected tenant farmers and suppressed influential families (noble families, temples and shrines with power) by restricting direct bondage between oshinke (nobles in the capital) and rich class in the provinces, and at the same time, also intended for a reinforcement of organizations ruled by the emperor, including an enhancement of the kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) and an increase of authority of Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpyo no chi was intended as a return to the Ritsuryo system that protected tenant farmers and suppressed influential families (noble families, temples and shrines with power) by restricting direct bondage between oshinke (nobles in the capital) and the rich classes in the provinces, while at the same time, it was also intended to reinforce organizations ruled by the emperor, including enhancing the kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) and an increase of authority by the Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpyo no chi was intended as a return to the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) that protected tenant farmers and suppressed influential families (noble families, temples and shrines with power) by restricting direct bondage between oshinke (nobles in the capital) and the rich classes in the provinces, while at the same time, it was also intended to reinforce organizations ruled by the emperor, including enhancing the kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) and an increase of authority by the Kebiishicho (Office of Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>律令制の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、後の延喜の治とともに現実の社会制度の変革に適合せず必ずしも成功したとは言えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, like later Enki no chi, these measures did not fit the change of the real social system, and were hardly successful.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, like later Enki no chi, these measures did not fit the change of the real social system, and were hardly successful.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, like later Engi no chi, these measures did not fit the change of the real social system, and were hardly successful.</e>
<cmt>Enki→Engi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし近年、道真主導による王朝国家体制への転換準備期であったが、時平により道真の政治の記録が抹殺されたため詳細が不明となっていたにすぎないとする意見が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, however, there is an opinion that it was a preliminary period to convert into the system of the dynasty state lead by Michizane, and that details were not known because Tokihira destroyed records of the politics by Michizane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, however, there is an opinion that it was a preliminary period to convert it into the system of the dynasty state lead by Michizane, and that details were not known because Tokihira destroyed the political records by Michizane.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, however, there is an opinion that it was a preliminary period to convert it into the system of the dynasty state lead by Michizane, and that details were not known because Tokihira destroyed the political records by Michizane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>