<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>キリシタン大名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christian daimyo (Christian feudal lord)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christian daimyo</e>
<cmt>Adding &quot;feudal lord&quot; is both unnecessary and unsightly in the title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christian daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大村純忠と有馬晴信とともに天正遣欧少年使節をローマに送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tensho Keno Shonen Shisetsu (the Tensho Boy Mission to Europe) was sent to Rome together with Sumitada OMURA and Harunobu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tensho Boy Mission to Europe (known as the Tensho Keno Shonen Shisetsu in Japanese) was sent to Rome together with Sumitada OMURA and Harunobu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>Beginning the sentence with such a long Japanese term is sounds clumsy; better to begin with English and put the Japanese in the parentheses.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tensho Boy Mission to Europe (known as the Tensho Keno Shonen Shisetsu in Japanese) was sent to Rome together with Sumitada OMURA and Harunobu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>キリシタン大名（キリシタンだいみょう、吉利支丹大名）はキリスト教を信仰した大名のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Christian daimyo was a feudal lord who believed in Christianity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Christian daimyo&quot; refers to those daimyo (feudal lords) who professed faith in Christianity.</e>
<cmt>Minor structure, phrasing problems</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Christian daimyo&quot; refers to those daimyo (feudal lords) who professed faith in Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Warring States Period</e>
<cmt>Japanese unnecessary here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Warring States Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>フランシスコ・ザビエルは戦国時代 (日本)の日本をよく理解し、まず各地の戦国大名たちに領内での布教の許可を求め、さらに布教を円滑に進めるために大名自身に対する布教も行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Francis Xavier knew Japan in the Sengoku period well, asked warlords in various places to give him permission of propagation, and moreover even taught daimyo Christianity in order to run things smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Francis Xavier understood society in Warring States-era Japan extremely well; first he sought permission to proselytize from daimyo all over Japan, and then, in order to ensure his missionary work would go smoothly, even began proselytizing to the daimyo themselves.</e>
<cmt>&quot;society&quot; seems necessary here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Francis Xavier understood society in the Warring States period extremely well; first he sought permission to proselytize from daimyo all over Japan, and then, in order to ensure his missionary work would go smoothly, even began proselytizing to the daimyo themselves.</e>
<cmt>用語集の表記に従い、Warring States-era Japan を the Warring States period に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後から来日した宣教師たちも同様に各地の大名に謁見し、領内布教の許可や大名自身への布教を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Missionaries who came to Japan after him also visited daimyo in various places, got permission to spread the religion in the domain, and also proselytized daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Missionaries who came to Japan after Xavier&apos;s time also went to see daimyo in various places throughout Japan, and just as Xavier had, they obtained permission to spread Christianity in the domains of those daimyo, and also proselytized to the daimyo themselves.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Missionaries who came to Japan after Xavier&apos;s time also went to see daimyo in various places throughout Japan, and just as Xavier had, they obtained permission to spread Christianity in the domains of those daimyo, and also proselytized to the daimyo themselves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その際、大名たちの歓心を得るために、布教の見返りに南蛮貿易や武器の援助などを提示した者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to get in favor with daimyo, some missionaries supported Japan&apos;s trade with Spain and Portugal and gave them weapons in return for permission of propagation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to win favor with these daimyo, and in return for permission to proselytize, some missionaries agreed both to support Japan&apos;s trade with Spain and Portugal and to provide them with weapons.</e>
<cmt>Structure, phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to win favor with these daimyo, and in return for permission to proselytize, some missionaries agreed both to support Japan&apos;s trade with Spain and Portugal and to provide them with weapons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>大名側もこうした宣教師から得られる利益をより多く得ようと、入信して歓心を買った者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, some daimyo came to believe in Christianity and won missionaries&apos; favor, trying to get more benefits from them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the daimyo, there were some who professed their faith in Christianity in order to curry favor with the missionaries, hoping to get more such benefits from them.</e>
<cmt>Structure, phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the daimyo, there were some who professed their faith in Christianity in order to curry favor with the missionaries, hoping to get more such benefits from them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>入信した大名の領地では、特に顕著にキリスト教が広がることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the domain of daimyo who became a Christian, Christianity came to spread remarkably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Christianity began spreading remarkably fast, especially in those domains whose daimyo had professed their faith.</e>
<cmt>Structure</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Christianity began spreading remarkably fast, especially in those domains whose daimyo had professed their faith.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかしキリスト教が広まると、キリスト教の教義や、キリシタン大名の人徳や活躍ぶり（特に高山右近）に感化され、自ら入信する大名が現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Christianity spread, daimyo who were influenced by a doctrine of Christianity, daimyo&apos;s virtues, and their energetic activity (especially Ukon TAKAYAMA), came to believe in the religion for themselves.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Christianity continued to spread, some daimyo (notably Ukon TAKAYAMA) found themselves impressed with Christianity&apos;s doctrines as well as with the virtue and vigor of Christian daimyo, and chose to believe in the religion on their own initiative.</e>
<cmt>Structure, phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Christianity continued to spread, some daimyo (notably Ukon TAKAYAMA) found themselves impressed with Christianity&apos;s doctrines as well as with the virtue and vigor of Christian daimyo, and chose to believe in the religion on their own initiative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>南蛮貿易に関係のない内陸部などでもキリシタン大名は増えていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the inland areas which did not have anything to do with a trade with Spain and Portugal, the number of Christian daimyo increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of Christian daimyo continued to increase, even in landlocked regions and other areas unconnected the trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>Structure, phrasing, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of Christian daimyo continued to increase, even in landlocked regions and other areas unconnected the trade with Spain and Portugal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>キリスト教に入信した大名とその配下達の中には、宣教師たちの意見を聞き入れ領地内の寺院や神社を破壊したり焼き払うなどの行動を取った者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the daimyo and his retainers who became Christians, some broke and burnt up temples and shrines in their territory, following missionaries&apos; opinion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those who became Christians, some daimyo and their retainers took heed of the missionaries&apos; views and chose to burn or knock down temples and shrines in their territory.</e>
<cmt>Structure, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those who became Christians, some daimyo and their retainers took heed of the missionaries&apos; views and chose to burn or knock down temples and shrines in their territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>仏教や神道を奉ずる大名の中にも、僧侶たちの意見を聞き入れ外来の宗教であるキリスト教を『邪教』として弾圧する者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting Buddhist priests&apos; opinion, some daimyo who believed in Buddhism or Shinto considered Christianity, a foreign religion, as &quot;heresy,&quot; and oppressed it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among those daimyo who professed faith in Buddhism or Shinto, some took heed of the monks&apos; or priests&apos; views and branded Christianity, a foreign religion, a type of &quot;heresy,&quot; oppressing its followers.</e>
<cmt>Structure, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among those daimyo who professed faith in Buddhism or Shinto, some took heed of the monks&apos; or priests&apos; views and branded Christianity, a foreign religion, a type of &quot;heresy,&quot; oppressing its followers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そしてキリスト教徒と日本の旧来の宗教の信者達との間に憎悪と対立を深めていくことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then hatred and opposition came to develop between the believers of Christianity and Japanese religion from old times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, hatred and opposition sprang up between those who believed in Christianity and those who professed faith in the older Japanese religions.</e>
<cmt>Structure, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, hatred and opposition sprang up between those who believed in Christianity and those who professed faith in the older Japanese religions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、豊臣秀吉によりバテレン追放令（伴天連追放令）が出され、キリシタン大名に対する政治的な圧力が強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI issued Bateren Tsuihorei (an edict expelling the European missionaries), and Christian daimyo were put under political pressure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along these lines, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI issued the Bateren Tsuihorei (an edict expelling the Jesuit missionaries), putting Christian daimyo under intensified political pressure.</e>
<cmt>Word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along these lines, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI issued the Bateren Tsuihorei (an edict expelling the Jesuit missionaries), putting Christian daimyo under intensified political pressure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>多くの大名が改易、もしくは仏教か神道への改宗を余儀なくされ（強制改宗）、キリスト教の禁教と迫害の時代に入っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many daimyo were forced to be deprive of samurai status and forfeited the family territories, or be converted into Buddhist or Shintoist (compulsive conversion), and the period of anti-Christian edicts and persecution for Christianity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many daimyo were forced to relinquish their samurai status and forfeit their hereditary territories, or were compelled to profess faith in Buddhism or Shinto (compulsory conversion), ushering in a period of anti-Christian edicts and persecution of Christianity.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many daimyo were forced to relinquish their samurai status and forfeit their hereditary territories, or were compelled to profess faith in Buddhism or Shinto (compulsory conversion), ushering in a period of anti-Christian edicts and persecution of Christianity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸時代に入り、1613年（慶長18年）には禁教令も出されたため、最後まで棄教を拒んだ高山右近はマニラに追放され、有馬晴信は刑死し、以後キリシタン大名は存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Edo period came and the Ban on Christianity was issued in 1613, Ukon TAKAYAMA, who refused to lapse from Christianity, was expelled to Manila, and Harunobu ARIMA was executed, so there has been no Christian daimyo since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period began the Ban on Christianity was issued in 1613, as a consequence of which Ukon TAKAYAMA, who refused to the very last to recant his Christian faith, was banished to Manila, and Harunobu ARIMA was executed; from that point onward there were no more Christian daimyo.</e>
<cmt>Structure, word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period began the Ban on Christianity was issued in 1613, as a consequence of which Ukon TAKAYAMA, who refused to the very last to recant his Christian faith, was banished to Manila, and Harunobu ARIMA was executed; from that point onward there were no more Christian daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>彼らの領内にいた多数のキリシタンは、仏教に改宗するか、隠れキリシタンとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Christian in their territories were converted into Buddhist, or became a crypto-Christian.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the Christians in their territories converted to Buddhism or became crypto-Christians.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the Christians in their territories converted to Buddhism or became crypto-Christians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、劇的な例では旧有馬晴信領で起こった島原の乱という大規模な一揆の際に殺害され、表から消えていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were also some Christina who were dramatically killed and disappeared from the center stage in the Shimabara War, a large-scale uprising which occurred in the old territory of Harunobu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet many Christians were to suffer a far more dramatic end, vanishing from the scene after being slaughtered during the Shimabara Rebellion, a large-scale uprising which occurred in the former territory of Harunobu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, structure, phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet many Christians were to suffer a far more dramatic end, vanishing from the scene after being slaughtered during the Shimabara Rebellion, a large-scale uprising which occurred in the former territory of Harunobu ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 TT(id:46431), Straysheep(id:42448), Sheynhertz-Unbayg(id:15456), Sapphire123(id:147732), Harupri(id:133581), Kamakura(id:472), YODAFON(id:161109), Lucas0123(id:130266), Johncapistrano(id:969), 前田左衛門佐(id:194701), Tietew(id:4054), Gakuinryou(id:9665), Pulpo(id:249039), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Blowback(id:173308), R28Bot(id:177951), Chiew(id:39745), Point136(id:211299), KASAGI(id:24405), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>