<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>遣隋使</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenzuishi (Japanese Envoy to Sui Dynasty China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenzuishi (Japanese Envoy to Sui Dynasty China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenzuishi (Japanese Envoy to Sui Dynasty China)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>遣隋使（けんずいし）とは、推古天皇朝の俀國（倭国）が隋に派遣した朝貢使のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Kenzuishi&quot; refers to a Japanese tributary envoy dispatched to Sui during the reign of Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Kenzuishi&quot; refers to Japanese tributary envoys dispatched to the Sui rulers in China during the reign of Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Kenzuishi&quot; refers to Japanese tributary envoys dispatched to the Sui rulers in China during the reign of Empress Suiko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>600年（推古8年）～618年（推古26年）の18年間に5回以上派遣されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenzuishi were dispatched more than five times for 18 years, between 600 and 618.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenzuishi were dispatched over five times in the 18 years between 600 and 618.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenzuishi were dispatched over five times in the 18 years between 600 and 618.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>なお日本という名称は遣唐使のときから使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They started to use the name &quot;Nihon&quot; (Japan) in the period of kentoshi (Japanese envoys to Tang Dynasty China).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Use of the name &quot;Nihon&quot; (Japan) began in the kentoshi period (Japanese envoys to Tang Dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Use of the name &quot;Nihon&quot; (Japan) began in the kentoshi period (Japanese envoys to Tang Dynasty China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>大阪の住吉大社近くの住吉津から出発し、住吉の細江（現・細江川。細井川駅）から大阪湾に出、難波津を経て瀬戸内海を九州へ向かい、そこから玄界灘に出る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kenzuishi and his staff departed from the Suminoetsu Port near the Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine in Osaka, heading to the Osaka Bay via Hosoe of Sumiyoshi (present-day the Hosoe River, the Hosoigawa Station), and then they left the Naniwa no Tsu (Naniwa Port) and went across the Seto Inland Sea to go to the Genkai-nada Sea in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kenzuishi and his staff would depart from Suminoetsu Port near Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine in Osaka, heading to Osaka Bay via Sumiyoshi-no-Hosoe (present-day Hosoe River and Hosoigawa Station), and then leave Naniwa-no-Tsu (Naniwa Port) and go across the Seto Inland Sea to the Genkai-nada Sea in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kenzuishi and his staff would depart from Suminoetsu Port near Sumiyoshi-taisha Shrine in Osaka, heading to Osaka Bay via Sumiyoshi-no-Hosoe (present-day Hosoe River and Hosoigawa Station), and then leave Naniwa-no-Tsu (Naniwa Port) and go across the Seto Inland Sea to the Genkai-nada Sea in the Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>倭の五王による南朝への奉献以来約1世紀を経て再開された遣隋使の目的は、東アジアの中心国・先進国である隋の文化の摂取が主であるが、朝鮮半島での影響力維持の意図もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispatch of envoys to China was resumed one century after tributary envoys to the Southern Dynasty dispatched by the five kings of Wa (Japan), and its most important purpose was to learn the culture of Sui, a key and leading country in East Asia, but they also intended to maintain their influence over the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dispatch of envoys to China was resumed one century after the tributary envoys to the Southern Dynasty sent by the five kings of Wa (Japan), with the primary purpose of learning about Sui culture, as they were a key and leading country in East Asia, but also with the intention of maintaining Japanese influence over the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dispatch of envoys to China was resumed one century after the tributary envoys to the Southern Dynasty sent by the five kings of Wa (Japan), with the primary purpose of learning about Sui culture, as they were a key and leading country in East Asia, but also with the intention of maintaining Japanese influence over the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この外交方針は次の遣唐使の派遣にも引き継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People still kept these diplomatic policies when they began the next envoy system called kentoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These diplomatic policies remained in place when the next envoy system, called kentoshi, began.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These diplomatic policies remained in place when the next envoy system, called kentoshi, began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>第一回（600年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first dispatch (600)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first dispatch (600)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first dispatch (600)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この派遣第一回 開皇20年（600年）は、『日本書紀』に記載はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) does not mention this first kenzuishi dispatched in 600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) does not mention this first kenzuishi dispatched in 600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki (Chronicles of Japan) does not mention this first kenzuishi dispatched in 600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>『隋書』「東夷傳俀國傳」は高祖楊堅の問いに遣使が答えた様子を載せている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The section called &apos;the Record of Eastern Barbarians, the Record of Wakoku (Japan)&apos; in &quot;Suishu&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty) includes a scene between Emperor Wen, who was the founder of the dynasty, and an envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section called &apos;the Record of Eastern Barbarians, the Record of Wakoku (Japan)&apos; in &quot;Suishu&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty) includes a scene between Emperor Wen, who was the founder of the dynasty, and an envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section called &apos;the Record of Eastern Barbarians, the Record of Wakoku (Japan)&apos; in &quot;Suishu&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty) includes a scene between Emperor Wen, who was the founder of the dynasty, and an envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>「開皇二十年 俀王姓阿毎 字多利思北孤 號阿輩雞彌 遣使詣闕 上令所司訪其風俗 使者言俀王以天爲兄 以日爲弟 天未明時出聽政 跏趺坐 日出便停理務 云委我弟 高祖曰 此太無義理 於是訓令改之」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>以後の文章がこの原文の書き下し文になっているため、この文章の翻訳は致しません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There came a king of Wa whose last name was Ame, azana (nickname) was Tarashihiko, and go (pseudonym) was Okimi in 600. He sent an envoy to the Imperial palace. The emperor asked the envoy about the culture of Wa through his servant. The envoy said that the king of Wa regarded the heaven as his elder brother and the sun as his younger brother. He got up before daybreak and attended to government affairs, sitting with his legs crossed on the floor. Once the sun came high, he stopped his work and told his younger brother to take over him. The emperor said that it totally lacked justice. The emperor tried to dissuade the king from doing this.&apos;</e>
<cmt>同訳を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>開皇二十年、俀王、姓は阿毎、字は多利思北孤、阿輩&amp;ampx96de弥と号（な）づく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There came a king of Wa whose last name was Ame, azana (nickname) was Tarashihiko, and go (pseudonym) was Okimi in 600.</e>
<cmt>原文で文字化けしている個所はウェブで確認し、「阿輩雞弥」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 600, there was a king of Wa whose last name was Ame, azana (nickname) was Tarashihiko, and go (pseudonym) was Okimi.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 600, there was a king of Wa whose last name was Ame, azana (nickname) was Tarashihiko, and go (pseudonym) was Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>使いを遣わして闕（けつ）に詣（いた）る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He sent an envoy to the Imperial palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He sent an envoy to the Imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He sent an envoy to the Imperial palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>上、所司（しょし）をしてその風俗を問わしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor asked the envoy about the culture of Wa through his servant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through his servant, the emperor asked the envoy about the culture of Wa.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through his servant, the emperor asked the envoy about the culture of Wa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>使者言う、俀王は天を以て兄と為し、日を以て弟と為す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The envoy said that the king of Wa regarded the heaven as his elder brother and the sun as his younger brother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The envoy said that the king of Wa regarded the heavens as his elder brother and the sun as his younger brother.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The envoy said that the king of Wa regarded the heavens as his elder brother and the sun as his younger brother.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天未（いま）だ明けざる時、出でて政（まつりごと）を聴く跏趺（かふ）して座す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He got up before daybreak and attended to government affairs, sitting with his legs crossed on the floor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He got up before daybreak and attended to government affairs, sitting with his legs crossed on the floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He got up before daybreak and attended to government affairs, sitting with his legs crossed on the floor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>日出ずれば、すなわち理務を停（とど）めて云う、我が弟に委（ゆだ）ぬと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the sun came high, he stopped his work and told his younger brother to take over him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the sun had risen high, he stopped his work and told his younger brother to take over for him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the sun had risen high, he stopped his work and told his younger brother to take over for him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>高祖曰く、此れ大いに義理なし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor said that it totally lacked justice.</e>
<cmt>「高祖」とは創設者のことですが、ここではわかりやすいように皇帝として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor said that this totally lacked justice.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Not sure about this translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor said that this totally lacked justice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>是に於て訓（おし）えて之を改めしむ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor tried to dissuade the king from doing this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor tried to dissuade the king from doing this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor tried to dissuade the king from doing this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>俀王（通説では俀は倭の誤りとする）姓の阿毎はアメ、多利思北孤（通説では北は比の誤り多利思比孤とする）はタラシヒコ、つまりアメタラシヒコで、天より垂下した彦（天に出自をもつ尊い男）の意とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the king of Wa (written as 俀 in Japanese, but it is generally said that the Chinese character of 俀 should be 倭 correctly) whose last name was Ame was Tarashihiko (written as 多利思北孤 in Japanese, but it is generally believed that the character 北 had been originally 比 and his name should be written as 多利思比孤), and it is thought that his full name Ametarashibiko meant a noble man who was originally from the heaven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the king of Wa (written as 俀 in Japanese, but it is generally said that the Chinese character of 俀 should actually be 倭), whose last name was Ame, was Tarashihiko (written as 多利思北孤 in Japanese, but it is generally thought that the character 北 had been originally 比 and his name should be written as 多利思比孤), and it is thought that his full name, Ametarashibiko, meant a noble man who was originally from heaven.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the king of Wa (written as 俀 in Japanese, but it is generally said that the Chinese character of 俀 should actually be 倭), whose last name was Ame, was Tarashihiko (written as 多利思北孤 in Japanese, but it is generally thought that the character 北 had been originally 比 and his name should be written as 多利思比孤), and it is thought that his full name, Ametarashibiko, meant a noble man who was originally from heaven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>阿輩&amp;ampx96de弥はオホキミで、大王 (ヤマト王権)とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okimi, written as 阿輩雞弥 in Japanese, is said to mean a great king.</e>
<cmt>原文で文字化けしている個所はウェブで確認し、「阿輩雞弥」として訳出いたしました。原文に大王（ヤマト王権）とありますが、リンク先の用語と混ざっているようです。ウェブを確認し「大王」として訳出いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okimi, written as 阿輩雞弥 in Japanese, is said to mean a great king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okimi, written as 阿輩雞弥 in Japanese, is said to mean a great king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>開皇20年は、推古天皇8年にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The year of 600 is equivalent to Suikotenno (which is a Japanese era name) 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The year 600 is equivalent to Suikotenno (Japanese era name) 8.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The year 600 is equivalent to Suikotenno (Japanese era name) 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>この時派遣された使者に対し、高祖は所司を通じて俀國の風俗を尋ねさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor asked the envoy dispatched in that year about customs of Wakoku through his servant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor asked the envoy dispatched that year about the customs of Wakoku through his servant.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor asked the envoy dispatched that year about the customs of Wakoku through his servant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>使者は俀王を「姓阿毎 字多利思北孤」号を「阿輩雞彌」と云うと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The envoy said that the last name of the king of Wa was Ame, his azana was Tarashihiko, and his go was Okimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The envoy said that the last name of the king of Wa was Ame, his azana was Tarashihiko, and his go was Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The envoy said that the last name of the king of Wa was Ame, his azana was Tarashihiko, and his go was Okimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>ところが、高祖からみると、俀國の政治のあり方が納得できず、道理に反したものに思えたのであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the emperor did not accept the political system of Wakoku due to his sense of value, and moreover, it seemed unreasonable to him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the emperor did not accept the political system of Wakoku due to his personal values, and moreover, it seemed unreasonable to him.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the emperor did not accept the political system of Wakoku due to his personal values, and moreover, it seemed unreasonable to him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そこで改めるよう訓令したというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was why the emperor told the king to change their political system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That was why the emperor told the king to change their political system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That was why the emperor told the king to change their political system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>第二回（607年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second dispatch (607)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second dispatch (607)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second dispatch (607)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>第二回目は、『日本書紀』に記載されており、607年（推古15年）に小野妹子が大唐国に国書を持って派遣されたと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nohonshoki mentions the second dispatch, and it says ONO no Imoko was sent to Great Tang with the sovereign&apos;s message in 607.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nohonshoki mentions the second dispatch, and it says ONO no Imoko was sent to Great Tang with the sovereign&apos;s message in 607.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nohonshoki mentions the second dispatch, and it says ONO no Imoko was sent to Great Tang with the sovereign&apos;s message in 607.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>倭王から隋皇帝煬帝（ようだい）に宛てた国書が、『隋書』「東夷傳俀國傳」に以下のように書き出されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the section of &apos;the Record of Eastern Barbarians, the Record of Wakoku (Japan)&apos; in &quot;Suishu&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty), the beginning of the official message of the king of Wa written to Yang Guang, the emperor of Sui, was as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the section of &apos;the Record of Eastern Barbarians, the Record of Wakoku (Japan)&apos; in &quot;Suishu&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty), the beginning of the official message of the king of Wa written to Yang Guang, the emperor of Sui, was as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the section of &apos;the Record of Eastern Barbarians, the Record of Wakoku (Japan)&apos; in &quot;Suishu&quot; (the Book of the Sui Dynasty), the beginning of the official message of the king of Wa written to Yang Guang, the emperor of Sui, was as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>「日出處天子致書日沒處天子無恙云云」（日出ずる処の天子、書を日没する処の天子に致す。恙無しや、云々）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperor of the Land of the Rising Sun is writing to the emperor of the Land of the Setting Sun, and I hope you are doing well.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperor of the Land of the Rising Sun is writing to the emperor of the Land of the Setting Sun, and I hope you are doing well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperor of the Land of the Rising Sun is writing to the emperor of the Land of the Setting Sun, and I hope you are doing well.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これを見た煬帝は立腹し、外交担当官である鴻臚卿（こうろけい）に「蕃夷の書に無礼あらば、また以て聞するなかれ」と命じたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This message made Yang Guang angry, and it is said that he told a foreign service officer whose position was called korokei (the chief of the office which was in charge of the entertainment of foreign envoys or ambassadors) not to talk about this country because the message was rude.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This message made Yang Guang angry, and it is said that he told a foreign service officer whose position was called korokei (the chief of the office which was in charge of the entertainment of foreign envoys or ambassadors) not to talk about this country because the message was rude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This message made Yang Guang angry, and it is said that he told a foreign service officer whose position was called korokei (the chief of the office which was in charge of the entertainment of foreign envoys or ambassadors) not to talk about this country because the message was rude.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>無礼な蕃夷の書は、今後自分に見せるな、というのである（「帝覽之不悅 謂鴻臚卿曰 蠻夷書有無禮者 勿復以聞」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, he told the officer never to show such rude letters from barbarians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, he told the officer never to present him again with such rude letters from barbarians.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, he told the officer never to present him again with such rude letters from barbarians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="32">
<j>なお、煬帝が立腹したのは俀王が「天子」を名乗ったことについてであり、「日出處」「日沒處」との記述にではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yang Guang became angry because the king of Wa called himself &apos;the emperor,&apos; and he was not angry at the terms &apos;the Land of the Rising Sun&apos; and &apos;the Land of the Setting Sun.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yang Guang became angry because the king of Wa called himself &apos;the emperor,&apos; not because of the use of the terms &apos;the Land of the Rising Sun&apos; and &apos;the Land of the Setting Sun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yang Guang became angry because the king of Wa called himself &apos;the emperor,&apos; not because of the use of the terms &apos;the Land of the Rising Sun&apos; and &apos;the Land of the Setting Sun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>「日出處」「日沒處」は『摩訶般若波羅蜜多経』の注釈書『大智度論』に日出処是東方 日没処是西方　とあるなど、単に東西の方角を表す仏教用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The terms &apos;the Land of the Rising Sun&apos; and &apos;the Land of the Setting Sun&apos; are just Buddhist terms which refer to the east and the west, as &quot;Daichidoron&quot; (Commentary on the Great Wisdom Sutra), an annotated edition of &quot;Makahannyaramitashingyo&quot; (The Great Treatise on Perfection of Wisdom), says that the land of the rising sun is east, and the land of the setting sun is west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The terms &apos;the Land of the Rising Sun&apos; and &apos;the Land of the Setting Sun&apos; are simply Buddhist terms which refer to the east and the west, as &quot;Daichidoron&quot; (Commentary on the Great Wisdom Sutra), an annotated edition of &quot;Makahannyaramitashingyo&quot; (The Great Treatise on Perfection of Wisdom), says that the land of the rising sun is the east, and the land of the setting sun is the west.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The terms &apos;the Land of the Rising Sun&apos; and &apos;the Land of the Setting Sun&apos; are simply Buddhist terms which refer to the east and the west, as &quot;Daichidoron&quot; (Commentary on the Great Wisdom Sutra), an annotated edition of &quot;Makahannyaharamitashingyo&quot; (The Great Treatise on Perfection of Wisdom), says that the land of the rising sun is the east, and the land of the setting sun is the west.</e>
<cmt>Makahannyaramitashingyo→Makahannyaharamitashingyo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>ただし、仏教用語を用いたことで中華的冊封体制からの離脱を表明する表現であったとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, it is also thought that they used the Buddhist terms to announce their secession from Chinese tributary system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, it is also thought that they used the Buddhist terms to announce their secession from the Chinese tributary system.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, it is also thought that they used the Buddhist terms to announce their secession from the Chinese tributary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="35">
<j>小野妹子は、その後返書を持たされて返されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward ONO no Imoko left for Japan with a reply from Yang Guang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, ONO no Imoko left for Japan with a reply from Yang Guang.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterwards, ONO no Imoko left for Japan with a reply from Yang Guang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>煬帝の家臣である裴世清を連れて帰国した妹子は、返書を百済に盗まれて無くしてしまったと言明している（「臣參還之時 唐帝以書授臣 然經過百濟國之日 百濟人探以掠取 是以不得上」『日本書紀』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; Imoko said he did not have the reply because a person from Baekje stole it, when he returned to Japan with Hai Seisei, a vassel of Yang Guang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; Imoko said he did not have the reply because a person from Baekje stole it, when he returned to Japan with Hai Seisei, a vassel of Yang Guang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; Imoko said he did not have the reply because a person from Baekje stole it, when he returned to Japan with Hai Seisei, a vassal of Yang Guang.</e>
<cmt>vassel→vassal</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この事は、煬帝からの返書は倭国を臣下扱いする物だったのでこれを見せて怒りを買う事を恐れた妹子が返書を破棄してしまったのではないかと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that Imoko destroyed the reply from Yang Guang because Yang Guang regarded Wakoku as a dependency of Sui, and he was afraid that the letter might make the king angry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Imoko destroyed the reply from Yang Guang because Yang Guang regarded Wakoku to be a subject of the Sui, and he was afraid that the letter might make the king angry.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Imoko destroyed the reply from Yang Guang because Yang Guang regarded Wakoku to be a subject of the Sui, and he was afraid that the letter might make the king angry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="38">
<j>斐世清が持ってきたとされる書が『日本書紀』にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki mentions a letter that is said to have been brought by Hai Seisei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonshoki mentions a letter that is said to have been brought by Hai Seisei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonshoki mentions a letter that is said to have been brought by Hai Seisei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="39">
<j>「皇帝、倭王に問う。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I want to ask the king of Wa about the following.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文頭はシングルクオーテーションを二重につけてあります（一つだと表示されないため）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I want to ask the king of Wa about the following.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I want to ask the king of Wa about the following.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>「朕は、天命を受けて、天下を統治し、みずからの徳をひろめて、すべてのものに及ぼしたいと思っている。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I want to obey Heaven&apos;s will, reign over the whole country, and spread my power to command love and respect to have a good effect on all people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文頭はシングルクオーテーションを二重につけてあります（一つだと表示されないため）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I want to obey Heaven&apos;s will, reign over the whole country, and spread my power to command love and respect to have a good effect on all people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I want to obey Heaven&apos;s will, reign over the whole country, and spread my power to command love and respect to have a good effect on all people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>「人びとを愛育したというこころに、遠い近いの区別はない。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The distance between us does not affect a mind to love and develop people.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文頭はシングルクオーテーションを二重につけてあります（一つだと表示されないため）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The distance between us does not affect the desire to raise people lovingly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The distance between us does not affect the desire to raise people lovingly.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>「倭王は海のかなたにいて、よく人民を治め、国内は安楽で、風俗はおだやかだということを知った。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I realize that the king of Wa rules people appropriately beyond the sea, and additionally, people live in ease and comfort and their customs and manners are moderate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文頭はシングルクオーテーションを二重につけてあります（一つだと表示されないため）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I realize that the king of Wa rules people appropriately beyond the sea, and additionally, that his people live in ease and comfort and their customs and manners are moderate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I realize that the king of Wa rules people appropriately beyond the sea, and additionally, that his people live in ease and comfort and their customs and manners are moderate.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>「こころばえを至誠に、遠く朝献してきたねんごろなこころを、朕はうれしく思う。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">I am pleased at your coming over here with utmost sincerity and I&apos;m glad with such warm heart.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文頭はシングルクオーテーションを二重につけてあります（一つだと表示されないため）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">I am pleased that you came here with kind-heartedness and utmost sincerity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">I am pleased that you came here with kind-heartedness and utmost sincerity.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="44">
<j>（「皇帝問倭皇 使人長吏大禮 蘇因高等至具懷 朕欽承寶命 臨養區宇 思弘德化 覃被含靈 愛育之情 無隔遐邇 知皇介居海表 撫寧民庶 境內安樂 風俗融合 深氣至誠 遠脩朝貢 丹款之美 朕有嘉焉 稍暄 比如常也 故遣鴻臚寺掌客裴世清等 旨宣往意 并送物如別」『日本書紀』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈困難なため訳出できず。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="45">
<j>これは倭皇となっており、倭王として臣下扱いする物ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this description, the king of Wa is referred to as the emperor of Wa, and he does not regard him as his vassal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this description, the king of Wa is referred to as the emperor of Wa, and he does not regard him as his vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this description, the king of Wa is referred to as the emperor of Wa, and he does not regard him as his vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>『日本書紀』によるこれに対する返書の書き出しも東の天皇が敬いて西の皇帝に白す（「東天皇敬白西皇帝」『日本書紀』）とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; the reply to this letter starts with the phrase &apos;東天皇敬白西皇帝&apos; (the emperor of the east respectfully writes to the emperor of the west).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; the reply to this letter starts with the phrase &apos;東天皇敬白西皇帝&apos; (the emperor of the east respectfully writes to the emperor of the west).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; the reply to this letter starts with the phrase &apos;東天皇敬白西皇帝&apos; (the emperor of the east respectfully writes to the emperor of the west).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これを持って天皇号の始まりとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people believe people began to use the title of Tenno (Emperor) at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some believe that people began to use the title of Tenno (Emperor) at that time.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some believe that people began to use the title of Tenno (Emperor) at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="48">
<j>遣使の派遣状況</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispatches of Tributary Envoys</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispatches of Tributary Envoys</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispatches of Tributary Envoys</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>遣隋使の派遣を年表風に整理すると次のようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is a chronological-like table of dispatches of kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is a chronological table of kenzuishi dispatches.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a chronological table of kenzuishi dispatches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="50">
<j>600年（推古8年）第1回遣隋使派遣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">600: The first kenzuishi dispatch</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">600: The first kenzuishi dispatch</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">600: The first kenzuishi dispatch</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>この頃まだ俀國は、外交儀礼に疎く、国書も持たず遣使した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Wakoku was not familiar with diplomatic etiquette, and the envoy went to Sui without the sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Wakoku was not familiar with diplomatic etiquette, and the envoy went to Sui without the sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Wakoku was not familiar with diplomatic etiquette, and the envoy went to Sui without the sovereign&apos;s message.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>（『隋書』俀國伝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="53">
<j>607年（推古15年） - 608年（推古16年）第2回遣隋使、小野妹子（おののいもこ）らを遣わす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">607-608: ONO no Imoko was sent as the second kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">607-608: ONO no Imoko was sent as the second kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">607-608: ONO no Imoko was sent as the second kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>「日出処の天子......」の国書を持参した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He brought the sovereign&apos;s message of the Emperor of the Rising Sun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He brought the sovereign&apos;s message as &quot;the Emperor of the Rising Sun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He brought the sovereign&apos;s message as &quot;the Emperor of the Rising Sun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>小野妹子、裴世清らとともに住吉津に着き、帰国する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ONO no Imoko returned to Japan arriving at Suminoetsu Port with Hai Seisei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ONO no Imoko returned to Japan, arriving at Suminoetsu Port with Hai Seisei.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ONO no Imoko returned to Japan, arriving at Suminoetsu Port with Hai Seisei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>（『日本書紀』、『隋書』俀國伝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="57">
<j>608年（推古16年） - ? （『隋書』煬帝紀）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">608 - unknown (&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Yang Guang)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">608 - unknown (&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Yang Guang)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">608 - unknown (&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Yang Guang)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>608年（推古16年） - 609年（推古17年）第3回遣隋使、小野妹子・吉士雄成など隋に遣わされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">608 - 609: ONO no Imoko and KISHI no Onari were sent as the third kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">608 - 609: ONO no Imoko and KISHI no Onari were sent as the third kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">608 - 609: ONO no Imoko and KISHI no Onari were sent as the third kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>この時、学生として倭漢直福因（やまとのあやのあたいふくいん）・奈羅訳語恵明（ならのおさえみょう）高向玄理（たかむくのあやひとくろまろ）・新漢人大圀（いまきのあやひとだいこく）・学問僧として新漢人日文（にちもん、後の僧旻）・南淵請安ら8人、隋へ留学する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eight people wert to Sui for study including students such as YAMATOAYA no Ataifukuin, NARA no Osaemyo, TAKAMUKU no Ayahitokuromaro, IMAKI no Ayahitodaikoku and learning priests such as IMAKI no Ayahito Nichimon (later became Somin) and MINABUCHI no Shoan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eight people wert to Sui for study, including students such as YAMATOAYA no Ataifukuin, NARA no Osaemyo, TAKAMUKU no Ayahitokuromaro, IMAKI no Ayahitodaikoku and priests-in-training such as IMAKI no Ayahito Nichimon (who later became Somin) and MINABUCHI no Shoan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eight people went to Sui for study, including students such as YAMATOAYA no Ataifukuin, NARA no Osaemyo, TAKAMUKU no Ayahitokuromaro, IMAKI no Ayahitodaikoku and priests-in-training such as IMAKI no Ayahito Nichimon (who later became Somin) and MINABUCHI no Shoan.</e>
<cmt>wert→went</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>隋使裴世清帰国する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hai Seisei, an envoy from Sui, returned to his country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hai Seisei, an envoy from Sui, returned to his country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hai Seisei, an envoy from Sui, returned to his country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>（『日本書紀』、『隋書』俀國伝）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Wakoku)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="62">
<j>610年（推古18年） - ?　第4回遣隋使を派遣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">610 - unknown: The fourth kenzuishi was dispatched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">610 - unknown: The fourth kenzuishi was dispatched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">610 - unknown: The fourth kenzuishi was dispatched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>（『隋書』煬帝紀）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Yang Guang)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Yang Guang)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Suishu&quot; the Record of Yang Guang)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="64">
<j>614年（推古22年） - 615年（推古23年）第5回遣隋使、犬上御田鍬（いぬかみのみたすき）・矢田部造らを隋に遣わす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">614 - 615: INUKAMI no Mitasuki and YATABE no Miyatsuko were sent as the fifth kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">614 - 615: INUKAMI no Mitasuki and YATABE no Miyatsuko were sent as the fifth kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">614 - 615: INUKAMI no Mitasuki and YATABE no Miyatsuko were sent as the fifth kenzuishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>百済使、犬上御田鍬に従って来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An envoy from Baekje came to Japan with INUGAMI no Mitasuki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An envoy from Baekje came to Japan with INUGAMI no Mitasuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An envoy from Baekje came to Japan with INUGAMI no Mitasuki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>（『日本書紀』）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&quot;Nihonshoki&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="67">
<j>618年（推古26年）隋滅ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">618: Sui went to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">618: the Sui Dynasty fell.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">618: the Sui Dynasty fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="68">
<j>遣使の『日本書紀』と『隋書』の主な違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major differences of envoys between &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The major differences of the envoy descriptions in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; are as follows.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The major differences of the envoy descriptions in the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and &quot;Suishu&quot; are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>第一回遣隋使は『日本書紀』に記載がなく『隋書』にあるのみ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonshoki does not have a description about the first kenzuishi, although &quot;Suishu&quot; does.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; does not have a description about the first kenzuishi, although &quot;Suishu&quot; does.</e>
<cmt>Added quotation marks for consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; does not have a description about the first kenzuishi, although &quot;Suishu&quot; does.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="70">
<j>ここでは中国史に合わせて遣隋使として紹介しているが、『日本書紀』では「隋」ではなく「大唐國」に遣使を派遣したとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this article, the first envoy is described as the first kenzuishi in accordance with Chinese history, but &quot;Nishonshoki&quot; says the envoy was dispatched to &apos;Great Tang&apos; instead of Sui.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this article, the first envoy is described as the first kenzuishi in accordance with Chinese history, but &quot;Nishonshoki&quot; says the envoy was dispatched to &apos;Great Tang&apos; instead of Sui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this article, the first envoy is described as the first kenzuishi in accordance with Chinese history, but &quot;Nishonshoki&quot; says the envoy was dispatched to &apos;Great Tang&apos; instead of Sui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="71">
<j>『日本書紀』では裴世清、『隋書』では編纂された時期が唐太宗 (唐)の時期であったので、太宗の諱・世民を避諱して裴清となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Hai Seisei appears in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; he is referred to as Hai Sei in &quot;Suishu&quot; because this book was compiled in the reign of Tang Tai Zong and the book avoids his imina (real name) Seimin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Hai Seisei appears in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; he is referred to as Hai Sei in &quot;Suishu&quot; because this book was compiled in the reign of Tang Tai Zong and the book avoids his imina (real name), Seimin.</e>
<cmt>Added a comma. This is a bit unclear.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Hai Seisei appears in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; he is referred to as Hai Sei in &quot;Suishu&quot; because this book was compiled in the reign of Tang Tai Zong and the book avoids his imina (real name), Seimin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="72">
<j>小野妹子の返書紛失事件は『日本書紀』にはあるが『隋書』にはない（『隋書』には小野妹子の名前自体が出てこない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishonshoki mentions the story that ONO no Imoko lost the sovereign&apos;s reply, but &quot;Suishu&quot; does not (&quot;Suishu&quot; does not even mention ONO no Imoko).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishonshoki mentions the story that ONO no Imoko lost the sovereign&apos;s reply, but &quot;Suishu&quot; does not (&quot;Suishu&quot; does not even mention ONO no Imoko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishonshoki mentions the story that ONO no Imoko lost the sovereign&apos;s reply, but &quot;Suishu&quot; does not (&quot;Suishu&quot; does not even mention ONO no Imoko).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="73">
<j>『隋書』では竹斯國と秦王國の国名が出てくるが大和の国に当たる国名は記されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suishu mentions the country names of Tsukushi and Shino, but no country name referring to Yamato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suishu mentions the country names of Tsukushi and Shino, but no country name referring to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suishu mentions the country names of Tsukushi and Shino, but no country name referring to Yamato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>しかし、「都於邪靡堆」とあることから、都は「邪靡堆」にあったと推察される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is thought that its capital was &apos;Yamato,&apos; written as 邪靡堆, from the description &apos;都於邪靡堆.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is thought that its capital was &apos;Yamato,&apos; written as 邪靡堆, from the description &apos;都於邪靡堆.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is thought that its capital was &apos;Yamato,&apos; written as 邪靡堆, from the description &apos;都於邪靡堆.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 デーモン博士(id:99293), ロリ(id:613), Izayohi(id:13095), Straysheep(id:42448), 万華鏡(id:24615), 松茸(id:27535), Law soma(id:45202), Sat.K(id:3751), 阿修羅(id:29454), Extrahitz(id:26245), Seibuabina(id:37532), Rai koku(id:1661), Fx(id:485), Clarin(id:60278), Greenland4(id:114494), Hokuto7(id:18100), Shinkansen(id:13703), 彩華1226(id:64711), Kamitani(id:30757), Gombe(id:27), Tanuki Z(id:612), らりた(id:1327), Bandalgom(id:31841), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Shimoxx(id:9332), 水平芳(id:203583), Dnssgh(id:118255), Yosemite(id:5808), Junger(id:10282), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>