<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>川勝氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawakatsu clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawakatsu clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawakatsu Clan</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>川勝氏（かわかつし、かわかつうじ）は、日本の氏族のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kawakatsu clan (Kawakatsu-shi or Kawakatsu-uji) was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kawakatsu clan (Kawakatsu-shi or Kawakatsu-uji) was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kawakatsu clan (Kawakatsu-shi or Kawakatsu-uji) was a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本姓は秦氏。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their original family name was Hata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their original family name was Hata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their original family name was Hata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>秦河勝の後裔と伝えられるが、その系譜は必ずしも明確ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had been considered the descendants of Kawakatsu HATA (Hirotaka HATA), although clear genealogy doesn&apos;t remain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are said to be the descendents of Kawakatsu HATA (Hirotaka HATA), although the genealogy is unclear.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are said to be the descendents of Kawakatsu HATA (also known as Hirotaka HATA), although the genealogy is unclear.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>分家も少なくないが、江戸幕府の幕臣川勝氏がよく知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among their many branches, the vassals Kawakatsu clan who had served the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) is well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among their many branches, the Kawakatsu clan vassals who served the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) are well known.</e>
<cmt>Moved &quot;vassals&quot;Deleted &quot;had&quot;is &gt; are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among their many branches, the Kawakatsu clan vassals who served the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun) are well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>家紋は、桐に鳳凰、釘抜、五七桐、五三桐など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kamon (crest) of the Kawakatsu clan (the vassals of the Edo bakufu) was Kiri ni Hoo (paulownia with an imaginary bird of ancient China), Kuginuki (nail puller in the shape of a diamond), Go-shichi no Kiri (seventeen paulownia flowers divided into three groups as 5＋7＋5), Go-san no Kiri (eleven paulownia flowers divided into three groups as 3＋5＋3) and so on.</e>
<cmt>*鳳凰ほうおうhoo (fenghuang) a miraculous bird</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kamon (crests) of the Kawakatsu clan (the vassals of the Edo bakufu) included the Kiri ni Hoo (paulownia flowers with a mythical fenghuang bird), Kuginuki (nail puller in the shape of a diamond), Go-shichi no Kiri (seventeen paulownia flowers divided into three groups as 5＋7＋5), Go-san no Kiri (eleven paulownia flowers divided into three groups as 3＋5＋3).</e>
<cmt>crest &gt; crestswas &gt; includedAdded &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;flowers&quot;an imaginary bird of ancient China &gt; a mythical fenghuang birdDeleted &quot;and so on&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kamon (crests) of the Kawakatsu clan (the vassals of the Edo bakufu) included the Kiri ni Hoo (paulownia flowers with a mythical fenghuang bird), Kuginuki (nail puller in the shape of a diamond), Go-shichi no Kiri (seventeen paulownia flowers divided into three groups as 5＋7＋5), Go-san no Kiri (eleven paulownia flowers divided into three groups as 3＋5＋3).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>通し字は、それぞれ「広」、「隆」、「氏」（家紋、通し字とも幕臣川勝氏）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The toshiji (common kanji character which the male members shared in given names) of the Kawakatsu clan (the vassals of the Edo bakufu) was &apos;広&apos;, &apos;隆&apos; and &apos;氏&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The toshiji (common kanji characters which the male members shared in given names) of the Kawakatsu clan (the vassals of the Edo bakufu) were &apos;広&apos;, &apos;隆&apos; and &apos;氏&apos;.</e>
<cmt>character &gt; characterswas &gt; were</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The toshiji (common kanji characters which the male members shared in given names) of the Kawakatsu clan (the vassals of the Edo bakufu) were &apos;広,&apos; &apos;隆&apos; and &apos;氏.&apos;</e>
<cmt>位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Overview</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Overview</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Career</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)、丹波国桑田郡下田の国人領主(美作守)であった下田広氏の嫡男、川勝広継（光照）のとき川勝を称したのが始まりだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan) Hirotsugu KAWAKATSU (Mitsuteru KAWAKATSU), the son and heir of Mimasaka no kami Hirouji SHIMODA, called himself Kawakatsu first (Hirouji had been a governor of Shimoda in Kuwata County in Tanba Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan originated during the Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan) when Hirotsugu KAWAKATSU (Mitsuteru KAWAKATSU), the son and heir of Mimasaka no kami Hirouji SHIMODA, called himself Kawakatsu first (Hirouji had been a governor of Shimoda in Kuwata County in Tanba Province).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to reflect source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan originated during the Sengoku period (period of warring states in Japan) when Hirotsugu KAWAKATSU (Mitsuteru KAWAKATSU), the son and heir of Mimasaka no kami Hirouji SHIMODA, called himself Kawakatsu first (Hirouji had been a governor of Shimoda in Kuwata County in Tanba Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>家伝によれば、下田美作守広氏は秦河勝（広隆）の嫡流とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family had said that Hirouji SHIMODA had been a descendant of the legitimate line of Kawakatsu HATA (Hirotaka HATA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to family tradition, Hirouji SHIMODA was a descendent of Kawakatsu HATA (Hirotaka HATA).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten to reflect source text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to family tradition, Hirouji SHIMODA was a descendent of Kawakatsu HATA (also known as Hirotaka HATA).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>川勝氏（下田氏）は桑田郡・船井郡内を知行し、室町幕府に仕えてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kawakatsu clan (the Shimoda clan) had governed Kuwata County and Funai County, and had served the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kawakatsu clan (the Shimoda clan) had governed Kuwata County and Funai County, and had served the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kawakatsu clan (the Shimoda clan) had governed Kuwata County and Funai County, and had served the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>先の応仁の乱では、幕府の管領を務めた細川勝元に従って、他の国人衆とともに合戦に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Onin War, the members of the clan had served Kanrei (Shogunal deputy) Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and fought battles as well as other governors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Onin War, members of the clan had served Kanrei (Shogunal deputy) Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and fought battles as was the case for other governors.</e>
<cmt>In &gt; DuringDeleted &quot;the&quot;as well as&gt; as was the case for</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Onin War, members of the clan had served Kanrei (Shogunal deputy) Katsumoto HOSOKAWA and fought battles as was the case for other governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>川勝広継は12代将軍足利義晴、13代将軍足利義輝に仕え、北桑田郡美山町静原の島城を本城とし、八木の守護代内藤氏、京北の宇津氏、篠山の波多野氏など、丹波の武将と対峙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirotsugu KAWAKATSU served the 12th Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA and the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, setting the family&apos;s base at Shima-jo Castle in Miyamacho-sizuhara (Kita-kuwata County) to counter the other strong commanders of Tanba Province such as the Naito clan who had been Shugodai (Deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Yagi, the Uzu clan of Keihoku, and the Hatano clan of Sasayama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirotsugu KAWAKATSU served the 12th Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA and the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, setting the family&apos;s base at Shima-jo Castle in Miyamacho-sizuhara (Kita-kuwata County) to counter the other strong commanders of Tanba Province such as the Naito clan who had been Shugodai (Deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Yagi, the Uzu clan of Keihoku, and the Hatano clan of Sasayama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirotsugu KAWAKATSU served the 12th Shogun Yoshiharu ASHIKAGA and the 13th Shogun Yoshiteru ASHIKAGA, setting the family&apos;s base at Shima-jo Castle in Miyamacho-shizuhara (Kita-kuwata County) to counter the other strong commanders of Tanba Province such as the Naito clan who had been Shugodai (Deputy of Shugo, provincial constable) of Yagi, the Uzu clan of Keihoku, and the Hatano clan of Sasayama.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>広継の嫡男川勝継氏は織田信長に従い、天正元年（1573年）、信長の命を受けた細川幽斎に従って、山城国の淀古城攻め（淀古城第二次淀古城の戦い）に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The son and heir of Hirotsugu, Tsuguuji KAWAKATSU served Nobunaga ODA, and in 1573, fought the Attack against Yodo-kojo Castle in Yamashiro Province (the second battle at Yodo-kojo Castle) under his superior Yusai HOSOKAWA who had been ordered by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The son and heir of Hirotsugu, Tsuguuji KAWAKATSU served Nobunaga ODA, and in 1573, fought in the attack against Yodo-kojo Castle in Yamashiro Province (the second battle at Yodo-kojo Castle) under his superior Yusai HOSOKAWA who had been ordered by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>the Attack &gt; in the attack</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son and heir of Hirotsugu, Tsuguuji KAWAKATSU served Nobunaga ODA, and in 1573, fought in the attack against Yodo-kojo Castle in Yamashiro Province (the second battle at Yodo-kojo Castle) under his superior Yusai HOSOKAWA who had been ordered by Nobunaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、天正4年（1576年）からの明智光秀の丹波攻略には与力となって協力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Capture of Tanba (started in 1576), he cooperated with Mitsuhide AKECHI as Yoriki (a police sergeant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the capture of Tanba (started in 1576), he cooperated with Mitsuhide AKECHI as a Yoriki (a police sergeant).</e>
<cmt>In &gt; DuringCapture &gt; captureAdded &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the capture of Tanba (started in 1576), he cooperated with Mitsuhide AKECHI as a Yoriki (a police sergeant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>継氏の嫡男川勝秀氏は豊臣秀吉に仕え、秀吉の馬廻を務めて、天正10年（1582年）、丹波国何鹿郡内に3,535石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The son and heir of Tsuguuji, Hideuji KAWAKATSU served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as Umamawari (a bodyguard), and in 1582 he was given 3,535 koku (637.68 cubic meters) of Ikaruga County in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The son and heir of Tsuguuji, Hideuji KAWAKATSU served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as an Umamawari (a bodyguard), and in 1582 he was given 3,535 koku (637.68 cubic meters) of Ikaruga County in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;an&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The son and heir of Tsuguuji, Hideuji KAWAKATSU served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as an Umamawari (a bodyguard), and in 1582 he was given 3,535 koku (637.68 cubic meters) of Ikaruga County in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、文禄元年（1592年）からの文禄・慶長の役では、肥前国名護屋城に在陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Bunroku Keicho Campaign (started in 1592), he set his camp at Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Bunroku Keicho Campaign (started in 1592), he set up his camp at Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;up&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Bunroku Keicho Campaign (started in 1592), he set up his camp at Nagoya-jo Castle in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>慶長5年（1600年）の関ヶ原の戦いでは、嫡男川勝広綱とともに西軍に与して丹後国田辺城 (丹後国)攻撃（田辺城の戦い）に参加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara (1600), he threw himself and his heir Hirotsuna KAWAKATSU into the West Army, and fought in the Attack against Tanabe-jo Castle in Tango Province (the Battle at Tanabe-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the Battle of Sekigahara (1600), he and his heir Hirotsuna KAWAKATSU joined the West Army, and fought in the attack against Tanabe-jo Castle in Tango Province (the Battle at Tanabe-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the Battle of Sekigahara (1600), he and his heir Hirotsuna KAWAKATSU joined the West Army, and fought in the attack against Tanabe-jo Castle in Tango Province (the Battle at Tanabe-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、秀氏父子は徳川家康に赦されて、改易を免れることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the West Army lost, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the top of the East Army) forgave Hideuji and Hirotsuna, and didn&apos;t give them punishment of kaieki (forfeiture of status and possession).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the West Army lost, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the leader of the East Army) forgave Hideuji and Hirotsuna, and they avoided the punishment of kaieki (forfeiture of status and possession).</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the West Army lost, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the leader of the East Army) forgave Hideuji and Hirotsuna, and they avoided the punishment of kaieki (forfeiture of status and possession).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>慶長6年（1601年）、室町時代以来の丹波の旧族、細川忠興の推挙により召し出され、秀氏は旗本家を興した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601 Hideuji was allow to serve the Tokugawa family by recommendation of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, a member of a time-honored clan in Tanba (since Muromachi period), and given the house status of Hatamoto (a direct retainer of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>*serve the Tokugawa family…at that time the Edo bakufu hadn&apos;t been established yet</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601 Hideuji was allowed to serve the Tokugawa family by the recommendation of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, a member of a time-honored clan in Tanba (since the Muromachi period), and given the house status of Hatamoto (a direct retainer of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>allow &gt; allowedAdded &quot;the&quot; (x2)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601 Hideuji was allowed to serve the Tokugawa family by the recommendation of Tadaoki HOSOKAWA, a member of a time-honored clan in Tanba (since the Muromachi period), and given the house status of Hatamoto (a direct retainer of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>慶長12年（1607年）、広綱は父秀氏の家督を継いだ（知行は丹波内3,570石余）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1607 Hirotsuna became the head of the clan and was given chigyo (enfeoffment) of more than 3,570 koku (644 cubic meters) in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1607 Hirotsuna became the head of the clan and was given a chigyo (enfeoffment) of more than 3,570 koku (644 cubic meters) in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;a&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1607 Hirotsuna became the head of the clan and was given a chigyo (enfeoffment) of more than 3,570 koku (644 cubic meters) in Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>江戸時代には、秀氏・広綱に始まる旗本の川勝家（本家）の他に、広継の嫡男の川勝継氏の系統からは3家の旗本家が出ている（系譜1）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, except for the head family to which Hideuji and Hirotsuna belonged, three families of the Tsuguuji KAWAKATSU (the oldest son of Hirotsugu) line were given the house status of Hatamoto (genealogy 1).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exception of the head family to which Hideuji and Hirotsuna belonged, three families of the Tsuguuji KAWAKATSU (the oldest son of Hirotsugu) line were given the house status of Hatamoto (genealogy 1) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of the head family to which Hideuji and Hirotsuna belonged, three families of the Tsuguuji KAWAKATSU (the oldest son of Hirotsugu) line were given the house status of Hatamoto (genealogy 1) during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、広継の二男の川勝知氏の系統からも4家の旗本家が出ている（系譜2）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four families of the Tomouji KAWAKATSU (the second son of Hirotsugu) line were also given the house status of Hatamoto (genealogy 2).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four families of the Tomouji KAWAKATSU (the second son of Hirotsugu) line were also given the house status of Hatamoto (genealogy 2).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four families of the Tomouji KAWAKATSU (the second son of Hirotsugu) line were also given the house status of Hatamoto (genealogy 2).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これら旗本家は、若年寄、大目付、勘定奉行、外国奉行、外国（事務）副総裁、開成所総奉行などを務めた幕臣を、主に幕末に輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate, the members of those families of Hatamoto were appointed to important posts such as Wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in Edo bakufu), Ometsuke (Chief inspector of the Edo bakufu), Kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), Vice President of the administrators of Gaikoku bugyo (magistrate of foreign affairs), Chief of Kaiseijo (magistrate for examination of foreign books).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate, the members of those families of Hatamoto were appointed to important posts such as Wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu), Ometsuke (Chief inspector of the Edo bakufu), Kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), Vice President of the administrators of Gaikoku bugyo (magistrate of foreign affairs), and Chief of Kaiseijo (magistrate for examination of foreign books).</e>
<cmt>Added &quot;the&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Tokugawa Shogunate, the members of those families of Hatamoto were appointed to important posts such as Wakadoshiyori (a managerial position in the Edo bakufu), Ometsuke (Chief inspector of the Edo bakufu), Kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), Vice President of the administrators of Gaikoku bugyo (magistrate of foreign affairs), and Chief of Kaiseijo (magistrate for examination of foreign books).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>明治元年（1868年）の江戸開城に際して、川勝広運は同年正月23日より若年寄を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately before the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle (April 1868), on January 23 Hirokazu KAWAKATSU was appointed to Wakadoshiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately before the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle (1868) on January 23, Hirokazu KAWAKATSU was appointed to Wakadoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>Deleted &quot;April&quot;Moved comma</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately before the Surrender of Edo-jo Castle (1868) on January 23, Hirokazu KAWAKATSU was appointed to Wakadoshiyori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、外国奉行であった川勝広道は同年2月6日、外国（事務）総裁山口直毅のもとで外国（事務）副総裁となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 6 February 1868, Gaikoku bugyo Hiromichi KAWAKATSU was appointed to the Vice President of the administrators, his superior was Naoki YAMAGUCHI (President of the administrators of Gaikoku bugyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 6, 1868, Gaikoku bugyo Hiromichi KAWAKATSU was appointed Vice President of the administrators, and his superior was Naoki YAMAGUCHI (President of the administrators of Gaikoku bugyo).</e>
<cmt>6 February 1868 &gt; February 6, 1868Deleted &quot;to the&quot;Added &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 6, 1868, Gaikoku bugyo Hiromichi KAWAKATSU was appointed Vice President of the administrators, and his superior was Naoki YAMAGUCHI (President of the administrators of Gaikoku bugyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>幕臣以外にも、八戸藩、棚倉藩、八幡藩そして忍藩などに、川勝氏が存した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Except for the vassals of the Edo bakufu, there were other Kawakatsu clans in Hachinohe Domain, Tanafura Domain, Hachiman Domain, Oshi Domain and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the vassals of the Edo bakufu, there were other Kawakatsu clans in areas such as Hachinohe Domain, Tanafura Domain, Hachiman Domain, and Oshi Domain.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten for fluency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the vassals of the Edo bakufu, there were other Kawakatsu clans in areas such as Hachinohe Domain, Tanakura Domain, Hachiman Domain, and Oshi Domain.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>各々の藩において、川勝氏は家老等の要職を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members of those Kawakatsu clans served governments of domains in important positions such as Karo (Chief retainer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members of those Kawakatsu clans served governments of domains in important positions such as Karo (Chief retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members of those Kawakatsu clans served governments of domains in important positions such as Karo (Chief retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Chatamabot(id:304037), DRKAWA(id:248054), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>