<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寺田</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiden fields (a term concerning rice fields)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiden fields (a term concerning rice fields)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiden fields</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寺田（じでん、てらだ）とは、日本において、仏教寺院の運営経費にあてる田をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiden (also called terada) fields indicate, in Japan, rice fields whose output was used for operating Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiden (also called terada) fields indicate, in Japan, rice fields whereby output was used for operating Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiden (also called terada) fields indicate, in Japan, rice fields whereby output was used for operating Buddhist temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本に仏教が伝来したのは、6世紀中期の欽明天皇のときとされているが、本格的に寺院が建立され、仏教が興隆し始めたのは、6世紀末～7世紀前期の推古天皇の頃であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Buddhism was brought to Japan in the era of Emperor Kinmei, or in the middle era of the sixth century, and it is in the era of Empress Suiko, or in the era from around the end of the sixth century to the first half of the seventh century, that temples were built in earnest and Buddhism started flourishing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Buddhism was brought to Japan in the era of Emperor Kinmei, or in the middle era of the sixth century, and it is in the era of Empress Suiko, or the era from around the end of the sixth century to the first half of the seventh century, that temples were built in earnest and Buddhism started flourishing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Buddhism was brought to Japan in the era of Emperor Kinmei, or in the middle era of the sixth century, and it is in the era of Empress Suiko, or the era from around the end of the sixth century to the first half of the seventh century, that temples were built in earnest and Buddhism started flourishing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>仏教寺院の運営には当然経費を要するため、寺院の収入源として寺田が設定されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cost was naturally necessary for operating a temple, and jiden fields became set as a source of the incomes of temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cost was naturally necessary for operating a temple, and jiden fields became set as a source of the incomes for the temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cost was naturally necessary for operating a temple, and jiden fields became set as a source of the incomes for the temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>7世紀後半に律令制が整備され、田地は口分田などの班田収授法の体系に組み込まれていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the latter half of the seventh century when the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was established, farmland became integrated into the system of Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of farmland), such as kubunden (the farmland given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the latter half of the seventh century when the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based upon the ritsuryo code) was established, farmland became integrated into the system of Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of farmland), such as kubunden (farmland given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the latter half of the seventh century when the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based upon the ritsuryo code) was established, farmland became integrated into the system of Handen Shuju ho (the law of periodic reallocations of farmland), such as kubunden (farmland given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしながら、寺田（および神社の運営にあてる神田）のみは、班田の対象外とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, jinden fields (as well as shinden (also called kamita or kanda) fields whose output was used for operating shrines) alone were excluded from handen fields (the allotted farmland).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, jinden fields (as well as shinden - also called kamita or kanda) fields where the output was used for operating shrines) alone were excluded from handen fields (allotted farmland).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, jinden fields (as well as shinden - also called kamita or kanda) fields where the output was used for operating shrines) alone were excluded from handen fields (allotted farmland).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは、寺田および神田が、寺院や神社の所有物ではなく、神仏に帰属するものと認識されていたことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because it was recognized that jiden fields or shinden fields were not owned by temples or shrines but belonged to Buddha or gods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because it was recognized that jiden fields or shinden fields were not owned by temples or shrines but belonged to Buddha or gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because it was recognized that jiden fields or shinden fields were not owned by temples or shrines but belonged to Buddha or gods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そのため、神仏に帰属する寺田・神田の売買は禁止されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was prohibited to buy or sell the jiden fields and shinden fields belonging to temples and shrines, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was prohibited to buy or sell the jiden fields and shinden fields that belonged to temples and shrines, respectively.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was prohibited to buy or sell the jiden fields and shinden fields that belonged to temples and shrines, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>8世紀に成立した大宝律令・養老律令では、僧尼令・田令などに寺田に関する規定が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiho Code and Yoro Code established in the eighth century, regulations concerning jiden fields were specified in Soni ryo (regulations for monks and nuns) and Denryo (regulations for farmland).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiho Code and Yoro Code established in the eighth century, regulations concerning jiden fields that were specified in Soni ryo (regulations for monks and nuns) and Denryo (regulations for farmland).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiho Code and Yoro Code established in the eighth century, regulations concerning jiden fields that were specified in Soni ryo (regulations for monks and nuns) and Denryo (regulations for farmland).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>令文には、寺田を6年1班の班田収授の対象から除外する、すなわち不輸租田（租税を免除した田地）とすることが規定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these regulations, it was stipulated that jiden fields were excluded from the farmland for which allocation was made every six years, or were specified for Fuyusoden (the farmland for which tax was exempted).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these regulations, it was stipulated that jiden fields were excluded from farmland for which allocation was made every six years, or were specified for Fuyusoden (the farmland for which tax was exempted).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these regulations, it was stipulated that jiden fields were excluded from farmland for which allocation was made every six years, or were specified for Fuyusoden (the farmland for which tax was exempted).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その反面、個人から寺院へ田地を施入（寄付）することは禁止されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it was prohibited to donate farmland to temples personally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it was prohibited to donate farmland to temples personally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it was prohibited to donate farmland to temples personally.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、8世紀中期に墾田永年私財法が施行されると、有力な大寺社は積極的に墾田を進めて、荘園を確保していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the middle era of the eight century when Konden einen shizai Law (a law allowing farmers who developed new arable land to own it permanently) was enforced, dominant temples and shrines developed arable land actively, acquiring shoen (manors) in this way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during the middle era of the eighth century when Konden einen shizai Law (aw allowing farmers who developed new arable land to own it permanently) was enforced, dominant temples and shrines actively developed arable land, acquiring shoen (manors) this way.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during the middle era of the eighth century when Konden einen shizai Law (law allowing farmers who developed new arable land to own it permanently) was enforced, dominant temples and shrines actively developed arable land, acquiring shoen (manors) this way.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この墾田開発は、半ば、仏教興隆を目的とする律令政府が主導したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such development of arable land was promoted by the Ritsuryo code-based government to make Buddhism more prosperous.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such development of arable land was promoted by the Ritsuryo code-based government to make Buddhism more prosperous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such development of arable land was promoted by the Ritsuryo code-based government to make Buddhism more prosperous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>例えば地方国司による東大寺の荘園開発を示す史料などが多数発見されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, many historical documents indicating that local kokushi (provincial governors) developed manors for Todai-ji Temple have been found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, many historical documents indicating that local kokushi (provincial governors) developed manors for Todai-ji Temple have been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, many historical documents indicating that local kokushi (provincial governors) developed manors for Todai-ji Temple have been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>こうして開発した荘園について、寺院は寺田であると主張し、政府から不輸の権 (日本)（租税免除の権利）を獲得していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples insisted that the manors developed in this way constituted jiden fields, acquiring Fuyu no ken (in Japan) (the right of tax exemption).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temples insisted that the manors developed in this way constituted jiden fields, acquiring Fuyu no ken (in Japan) (the right of tax exemption).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temples insisted that the manors developed in this way constituted jiden fields, acquiring Fuyu no ken (in Japan) (the right of tax exemption).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>9世紀～10世紀に律令制が崩壊した後も、寺田には不輸の権が認められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the collapse of the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in the ninth century to tenth century, Fuyu no ken continued being applied to jiden fields.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the collapse of the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in the ninth century to tenth century, Fuyu no ken continued being applied to jiden fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the collapse of the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in the ninth century to tenth century, Fuyu no ken continued being applied to jiden fields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>そのため、墾田や買収などで付近の田地を集積していた田堵（有力農民）＝開発領主は、自分の経営する田地を有力寺院（または有力神社）へ寄進することで、不輸の権を獲得しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Tato (powerful farmers), or the owners of newly developed arable land, who acquired large arable land through development or buying land donated their farmland to dominant temples (or dominant shrines) to obtain Fuyu no ken.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Tato (powerful farmers), or the owners of newly developed arable land, who acquired large tracts arable land through development or buying land, donated their farmland to dominant temples (or dominant shrines) to obtain Fuyu no ken.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Tato (powerful farmers), or the owners of newly developed arable land, who acquired large tracts arable land through development or buying land, donated their farmland to dominant temples (or dominant shrines) to obtain Fuyu no ken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため、有力寺社には荘園の寄進が集中した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, dominant temples or shrines had many manors donated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, dominant temples or shrines had many manors donated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, dominant temples or shrines had many manors donated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、11世紀～13世紀ごろに荘園公領制が成立すると、荘園や国衙領の除田（じょでん、免税田を意味する）の一つとして寺田が位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around the eleventh century to the thirteenth century when shoen koryo sei (the system of public land and private estates) was established, jiden fields were dealt with in the same way as that for joden fields (fields for which tax was exempted) of manors or Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the eleventh to the thirteenth century when shoen koryo sei (the system of public land and private estates) was established, jiden fields were dealt with in the same way as that for joden fields (fields for which tax was exempted) of manors or Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the eleventh to the thirteenth century when shoen koryo sei (the system of public land and private estates) was established, jiden fields were dealt with in the same way as that for joden fields (fields for which tax was exempted) of manors or Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>寺田にかかる年貢・公事は、領主の収入とはならず、寺院運営の経費にあてられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nengu (land tax) and kuji (public duties) levied on jiden fields did not become incomes of the territory lord but were used for operating the temples concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nengu (land tax) and kuji (public duties) levied on jiden fields did not become incomes of the territorial lord, but were used for operating the temples concerned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nengu (land tax) and kuji (public duties) levied on jiden fields did not become incomes of the territorial lord, but were used for operating the temples concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>地名・名字</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geographical names and family names</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geographical names and family names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geographical names and family names</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>日本の地名としての寺田は、上記の寺田に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jiden or Terada remaining as geographical names in Japan originates in the jiden or terada described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jiden or Terada remaining as geographical names in Japan originated in the jiden or terada described above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jiden or Terada remaining as geographical names in Japan originated in the jiden or terada described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>寺田は日本各地に存在したため、地名としての寺田も日本全国に分布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because jiden fields existed throughout Japan, Jiden or Terada as geographical names remain throughout Japan as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because jiden fields existed throughout Japan, Jiden or Terada as geographical names remain throughout Japan as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because jiden fields existed throughout Japan, Jiden or Terada as geographical names remain throughout Japan as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>また、日本の名字（姓）の寺田も、上記の寺田に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Jiden or Terada as a family name also originates in the jiden or terad described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Jiden or Terada as a family name also originated in jiden or terada described above.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Jiden or Terada as a family name also originated in jiden or terada described above.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), NDR(id:5500), Nopira(id:29335), Greenland4(id:114494), 10cm(id:147838), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>