<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正倉院文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin monjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正倉院文書（しょうそういんもんじょ）は、東大寺正倉院に保管されてきた文書群で、主に東大寺写経所が作成した文書群のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin monjo refers to document collections kept in the Todai-ji Temple Shosoin, which are mainly created by the Sutra copying office at the Todai-ji Temple (in its narrow sense, shosoin monjo refers to documents created by the Sutra copying office located in chuso [middle section] of the Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin monjo refers to document collections kept in Todai-ji Temple Shosoin, which are mainly created by the Sutra copying office at Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（続く括弧内が2文になり、2番目の文だけ外に出されていました。よって、まず括弧内の文章をこの本文と切り離し、さらにそれらを一文ずつ括弧でとじました。）Todai-ji Temple 前の the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin monjo refers to document collections kept in Todai-ji Temple Shosoin, which are mainly created by the Sutra copying office at Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>（狭義には中倉の写経所文書を正倉院文書と呼ぶ。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In its narrow sense, shosoin monjo refers to documents created by the Sutra copying office located in Chuso [the middle section] of Todai-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（続く括弧内が2文になり、2番目の文だけ外に出されていました。よって、括弧内の文章を前の本文と切り離し、さらに一文ずつ括弧でとじました。）chuso を Chuso に修正しました。middle section の前に the を追記しました。Todai-ji Temple 前の the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In its narrow sense, shosoin monjo refers to documents created by the Sutra copying office located in Chuso [the middle section] of Todai-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>（この他、北倉文書がある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides this, there is hokuso monjo (documents kept in the north section of the Todai-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Besides this, there are hokuso monjo (documents kept in the north section of Todai-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内が2文になり、2番目のこの文だけ外に出されていました。よって、括弧内の文章を前の本文と切り離し、さらに一文ずつ括弧でとじました。句点は括弧内に入れました。There is を there are に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Besides this, there are hokuso monjo (documents kept in the north section of Todai-ji Temple.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>奈良時代に関する豊富な情報を含む史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin monjo is a historical material including a wealth information on the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin monjo are historical materials including a wealth of information on the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>is を are に、material を複数形に、a wealth of の of を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin monjo are historical materials including a wealth of information on the Nara Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>律令制下で官庁が作成した文書や諸国からの報告書のほとんどは短期間（戸籍の保存期間は比較的長く30年）で廃棄されていたが、東大寺写経所では廃棄文書の裏面を帳簿として再利用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although most of the monjo created by the authority or the reports collected from the various districts under the ritsuryo system (the historical law system based on the philosophies of Confucianism and Chinese Legalism in Japan) were disposed of after a short period (however, koseki [Japanese family registry] was kept longer, almost for 30 years), the back side of the disposed monjo was reused for an account book in the Sutra copying office at the Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the monjo which were created by authorities and reports collected from various provinces under ritsuryo system (the historical law system based on the philosophies of Confucianism and Chinese Legalism in Japan) were disposed of after a short period (except koseki [Japanese family registry] - these were kept a little longer, for about 30 years), but the Sutra copying office at Todai-ji Temple used the back sides of the waste monjo as ledger paper.</e>
<cmt>全文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the monjo which were created by authorities and reports collected from various provinces under ritsuryo system (the historical law system based on the philosophies of Confucianism and Chinese Legalism in Japan) were disposed of after a short period (except koseki [Japanese family registry] - these were kept a little longer, for about 30 years), but the Sutra copying office at Todai-ji Temple used the back sides of the waste monjo as ledger paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>8世紀（神亀～宝亀年間の約50年）の写経所文書が正倉院に納められ、保存されてきたため、奈良時代の戸籍・正税帳などの貴重な史料が今日まで残ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the monjo created by the Sutra copying office during the eighth century (approximately 50 years from the Jinki to Hoki period) were placed and kept in the Shosoin, the important historical materials including kosei and shozeicho (an account book prepared by kokushi [officials] for the Daijo-kan [the Department of State in Japan] created in the Nara period are still remaining today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the monjo created by the Sutra copying office during the 8th century (for about 50 years from the Jinki to Hoki era, [724 - 781]) were placed and have been preserved in Shosoin, valuable historical materials including koseki and shozeicho (balance sheets of tax rice) created in the Nara Period still remain today.</e>
<cmt>全文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the monjo created by the Sutra copying office during the 8th century (for about 50 years from the Jinki to Hoki era, [724 - 781]) were placed and have been preserved in Shosoin, valuable historical materials including koseki and shozeicho (balance sheets of tax rice) created in the Nara Period still remain today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代後期、穂井田忠友（平田篤胤に学んだ国学者）によって写経所文書の紙背にある史料が注目され、1833年-1836年（天保4-7年）、元の戸籍・正税帳などの状態を復元すべく一部の文書が抜出されて、45巻（正集）にまとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Edo period, the historical materials written on the back side of monjo created by the Sutra copying office were noticed by Tadatomo HOIDA (a scholar of Japanese classical literature taught by Atsutane HIRATA), and between 1833 and 1836, some monjo were selected in order to restore those kosei and shozeicho to their original forms and compiled into 45 volumes (primary book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Edo Period, Tadatomo HOIDA (a scholar of Japanese classical literature taught by Atsutane HIRATA) took notice of the historical materials which were written on the back side of monjo from the Sutra copying office; some monjo were picked out in order to restore those kosei and shozeicho to their original states, and these were then compiled into 45 volumes (master document) from 1833 to 1836.</e>
<cmt>全文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Edo Period, Tadatomo HOIDA (a scholar of Japanese classical literature taught by Atsutane HIRATA) took notice of the historical materials which were written on the back side of monjo from the Sutra copying office; some monjo were picked out in order to restore those kosei and shozeicho to their original states, and these were then compiled into 45 volumes (master document) from 1833 to 1836.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治時代以降は内務省、宮内省により整理が続けられ、667巻5冊の形態になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji period, those documents were sorted out by the Ministry of Home Affairs and the Ministry of the Imperial Household, resulting in 667 volumes and 5 books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji period, those documents continued to be organised by the Ministry of Home Affairs and the Ministry of the Imperial Household, resulting in 667 volumes and 5 books.</e>
<cmt>sorted out を continued to be organised に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, those documents continued to be organised by the Ministry of Home Affairs and the Ministry of the Imperial Household, resulting in 667 volumes and 5 books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これにより文書の研究は大きく進んだが、一方で写経所文書は断片化されてしまい、かつての形態とは異なってしまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the study on monjo has advanced dramatically; however, the monjo created by the Sutra copying office has been broken into pieces and has turned into something different from its original form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although this led to a dramatic advance in the study of monjo, the monjo created by the Sutra copying office has been broken into pieces and has turned into something different from its original form.</e>
<cmt>前半を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although this led to a dramatic advance in the study of monjo, the monjo created by the Sutra copying office has been broken into pieces and has turned into something different from its original form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>建築史家・福山敏男は写経所文書に含まれていた石山寺関係史料の復元考察を行い、石山寺の造営過程（761年-）を浮かび上がらせた（「奈良時代に於ける石山寺の造営」1933年、『日本建築史の研究』所収）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshio FUKUYAMA, an architectural historian, restored and observed historical materials related to the Ishiyama-dera Temple included in monjo created by the Sutra copying office, and clearly showed the construction procedures for the Ishiyama-dera Temple (in 761 -) (&apos;Construction of the Ishiyama-dera Temple in the Nara period&apos; 1933, included in &quot;Nihon kenchiku shi no kenkyu [Complete Works of History of Japanese Architecture]&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshio FUKUYAMA, an architectural historian, restored and studied historical materials related to Ishiyama-dera Temple, which were included in monjo created by the Sutra copying office and clearly showed the construction procedures for Ishiyama-dera Temple (constructed from 761) (&apos;Construction of Ishiyama-dera Temple in the Nara Period,&apos; 1933, included in &quot;Nihon kenchiku shi no kenkyu&quot; [Complete Works of the History of Japanese Architecture]).</e>
<cmt>Ishiyama-dera Temple の前の the を削除しました。which were を追記しました。Period の 語頭を大文字に修正しました。History の前に the を付記しました。併記された意味を &quot; &quot;外に出しました。他、数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshio FUKUYAMA, an architectural historian, restored and studied historical materials related to Ishiyama-dera Temple, which were included in monjo created by the Sutra copying office and clearly showed the construction procedures for Ishiyama-dera Temple (constructed from 761) (&apos;Construction of Ishiyama-dera Temple in the Nara Period,&apos; 1933, included in &quot;Nihon kenchiku shi no kenkyu&quot; [Complete Works of the History of Japanese Architecture]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>福山の研究以降、写経所文書の研究も進められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his research, the research on monjo created by the Sutra copying office has been advanced as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his research, more research on monjo created by the Sutra copying office has been done.</e>
<cmt>the を削除し more を追記しました。advanced as well を done に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his research, more research on monjo created by the Sutra copying office has been done.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>正倉院文書は『大日本古文書』（編年文書、25冊、1901-1940年）に活字化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin monjo was published as &quot;Dai nihon komonjo (Old documents of Japan)&quot; (chronology monjo, 25 books, 1901-1940).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin monjo was published as &quot;Dai Nihon Komonjo&quot; (Old Documents of Japan) (chronology monjo, 25 books, 1901-1940).</e>
<cmt>題名中の単語の語頭を大文字に修正しました。併記された意味を &quot; &quot;外に出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin monjo was published as &quot;Dai Nihon Komonjo&quot; (Old Documents of Japan) (chronology monjo, 25 books, 1901-1940).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>原本は非公開で、正倉院の曝涼にあわせて、毎年秋の正倉院展（奈良国立博物館）において数点が公開される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the original documents remain unpublicized, some of them will be publicized in fall at the Annual Exhibition of Shosoin Treasures (held at the Nara National Museum) during the bakuryo (airing) at the Shosoin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the original documents remain unpublicized, some of them are publicized at the Annual Exhibition of Shosoin Treasures in fall (held at Nara National Museum) while they are being aired at Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>will be を are に修正しました。Nara National Museum の前の the を削除しました。during the bakuryo (airing) at the Shosoin を while they are being aired at Shosoin に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the original documents remain unpublicized, some of them are publicized at the Annual Exhibition of Shosoin Treasures in fall (held at Nara National Museum) while they are being aired at Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 翰林硯士(id:99377), Sapphire123(id:147732), Lobbyonce(id:195963), 水野白楓(id:22811), KurmUmy(id:202680), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>