<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大和永享の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Eikyo War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Eikyo War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Eikyo War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>大和永享の乱（やまとえいきょうのらん）は、室町時代の正長2年（1429年）に大和国で発生した戦乱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Eikyo War occurred in Yamato Province in 1429, Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Eikyo War occurred in Yamato Province in 1429, in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Eikyo War occurred in Yamato Province in 1429, in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>興福寺大乗院衆徒の豊田氏と興福寺一乗院衆徒の井戸氏の対立に端を発し、大和一国に広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originated from the hostility between the Toyota clan, monk-soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple Daijo-in, and the Ido clan, monk-soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple Ichijo-in, and spread to the whole Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated from the hostility between the Toyota clan, monk-soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple Daijo-in, and the Ido clan, monk-soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple Ichijo-in, and spread to the whole Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated from the hostility between the Toyota clan, monk-soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple Daijo-in, and the Ido clan, monk-soldiers of Kofuku-ji Temple Ichijo-in, and spread to the whole Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>乱の経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evolution of War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evolution of the War</e>
<cmt>特定の乱を指すので、&quot;the&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evolution of the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>大和国国人は、興福寺の二大門跡である大乗院・一乗院の衆徒、あるいは春日社の神人（国民）として組織されていたが、南北朝時代 (日本)には、南朝 (日本)方であった国民の越智氏と北朝 (日本)方であった一乗院衆徒の筒井氏を中心とし激しく争っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local lords of Yamato Province were organized as either monk-soldiers of Daijo-in or Ichijo-in, the two biggest monzeki (temple formerly led by founder of sect, temple in which resided a member of nobility or imperial family) of Kofuku-ji Temple, or jinin (Kokumin) (associates of Shinto shrines) of Kasuga-sha Shrine but, in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they fought each other divided into the Southern Court (Japan) side led by the Ochi clan of Kokumin and the Northern Court (Japan) side led by the Tsutsui clan of Ichijo-in monk-soldier.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local lords of Yamato Province were either monk-soldiers of Daijo-in or Ichijo-in, the two biggest monzeki (temple formerly led by founder of sect, temple in which resided a member of nobility or imperial family) of Kofuku-ji Temple, or kokumin who were jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Kasuga-sha Shrine, but in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they fought each other divided into the Southern Court (Japan) side led by the Ochi clan of kokumin and the Northern Court (Japan) side led by the Tsutsui clan of Ichijo-in monk-soldier.</e>
<cmt>「国民」→神人一般ではなく、特に春日社の神人を指す。（http://www2.harimaya.com/sengoku/html/oti_k.html）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local lords of Yamato Province were either monk-soldiers of Daijo-in or Ichijo-in, the two biggest monzeki (temple formerly led by founder of sect, temple in which resided a member of nobility or imperial family) of Kofuku-ji Temple, or kokumin who were jinin (associates of Shinto shrines) of Kasuga-sha Shrine, but in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they fought each other divided into the Southern Court (Japan) side led by the Ochi clan of kokumin and the Northern Court (Japan) side led by the Tsutsui clan of Ichijo-in monk-soldier.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>北朝方の勝利の下室町幕府が安定して以後も、幕府の支持を得た筒井氏に対し、越智氏も大和国南部を中心として勢力を維持し紛争は継続していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the triumph of the Northern Court side stabilized the Muromachi shogunate, the conflict lasted between the Tsutsui clan, who won the support from the shogunate, and the Ochi clan, who continued to maintain power especially in the southern part of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the triumph of the Northern Court side stabilized the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the conflict lasted between the Tsutsui clan, who won the support from the shogunate, and the Ochi clan, who continued to maintain power especially in the southern part of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>「室町幕府」→用語統一リストに従って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the triumph of the Northern Court side stabilized the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), the conflict lasted between the Tsutsui clan, who won the support from the shogunate, and the Ochi clan, who continued to maintain power especially in the southern part of Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>応永21年（1414年）には興福寺の訴えにより幕府が仲裁に乗り出し、国人衆が幕府に直属し私闘をしない旨の誓約をしたが、争乱の火はくすぶり続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the shogunate arbitrated the conflict in 1414 upon receiving an appeal from the Kofuku-ji Temple and made Kokujin-shu (local samurais) promise to report to the shogunate and never to have a duel, the fire of conflict continued to simmer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the shogunate arbitrated the conflict in 1414 upon receiving an appeal from the Kofuku-ji Temple and made Kokujin-shu (local samurai) promise to report to the shogunate and never to have a duel, the fire of conflict continued to simmer.</e>
<cmt>&quot;samurai&quot;には複数形のsはつけないと思います。スペースを半角に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the shogunate arbitrated the conflict in 1414 upon receiving an appeal from the Kofuku-ji Temple and made Kokujin-shu (local samurai) promise to report to the shogunate and never to have a duel, the fire of conflict continued to simmer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>一進一退の攻防</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seesaw Battle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seesaw Battle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seesaw Battle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>正長2年（1429年）7月、豊田中坊と井戸某の間に争いが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1429, Toyota 中坊 and a certain Ido started a duel.</e>
<cmt>豊田中坊の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1429, Toyota 中坊 and a certain Ido started a duel.</e>
<cmt>正長2年（1429年）7月→西暦では8月「豊田中坊」→読み方不明です。訳もそのままにしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1429, Toyota 中坊 and a certain Ido started a duel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>興福寺と幕府は停戦勧告をしたが一向に争いはやまず、豊田方についた越智氏、箸尾氏らは井戸方に加勢した筒井氏、十市氏を攻めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple and shogunate recommend cease-fire in vain and the Ochi clan and the Hashio clan, who took sides with Toyota, attacked the Tsutsui clan and the Tochi clan, who took sides with Ido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofuku-ji Temple and the shogunate recommended cease-fire in vain and the Ochi clan and the Hashio clan, who took sides with Toyota, attacked the Tsutsui clan and the Tochi clan, who took sides with Ido.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofuku-ji Temple and the shogunate recommended cease-fire in vain and the Ochi clan and the Hashio clan, who took sides with Toyota, attacked the Tsutsui clan and the Tochi clan, who took sides with Ido.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>翌永享2年（1430年）2月には井戸氏と同族の筒井氏を支持する幕府より、興福寺に対し豊田討伐の指示が出、更に翌永享3年（1431年）8月には筒井氏と箸尾氏が互いに相手方の居城を攻めるなど戦乱は拡大。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in February 1430, the shogunate ordered Kofuku-ji Temple to subdue Toyota in support of the Ido clan and its related Tsutsui clan but the maelstrom of war expanded, so that the Tsutsui clan and the Hashio clan attacked the castle of each other&apos;s daimyo (feudal lord) in August 1431.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, in March 1430, the shogunate ordered Kofuku-ji Temple to subdue Toyota in support of the Ido clan and its related Tsutsui clan but the maelstrom of war expanded, so that the Tsutsui clan and the Hashio clan both attacked the other&apos;s castle in September 1431.</e>
<cmt>永享2年（1430年）2月→新暦では3月。永享3年（1431年）8月→新暦では9月。「相手方の居城」→&quot;castle of each other&apos;s daimyo&quot;だと、それぞれの主君の城、の意味に取れます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, in March 1430, the shogunate ordered Kofuku-ji Temple to subdue Toyota in support of the Ido clan and its related Tsutsui clan but the maelstrom of war expanded, so that the Tsutsui clan and the Hashio clan both attacked the other&apos;s castle in September 1431.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>将軍足利義教は箸尾氏に対し撤兵勧告をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA advised the Hashio clan to withdraw their troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA advised the Hashio clan to withdraw their troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA advised the Hashio clan to withdraw their troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>翌永享4年（1432年）9月には越智・箸尾両氏に筒井氏が大敗し、井戸方の形勢不利になっていたが、筒井光宣が幕府に訴えたことで戦局に変化が生じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in September 1432, the Ochi and Hashio clan suffered a crushing defeat to the Tsutsui clan which turned the course of the war against Ido side but the situation changed after Mitsunobu TSUTSUI appealed to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>「筒井光宣」読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, in October 1432, the Tsutsui clan suffered a crushing defeat to the Ochi and Hashio clan, which turned the course of the war against Ido side, but the situation changed after Mitsunobu TSUTSUI appealed to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>永享4年（1432年）9月→新暦だと10月。負けたのは越智・箸尾両氏ではなく、筒井氏の方。&quot;which&quot;は前の文全体を先行詞としているため、非制限用法で、前にコンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, in October 1432, the Tsutsui clan suffered a crushing defeat to the Ochi and Hashio clan, which turned the course of the war against Ido side, but the situation changed after Mitsunobu TSUTSUI appealed to the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕府はそれまでの不介入方針を変更し越智氏討伐を決め、越智氏は大和南部に没落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate reversed its nonintervention policy and decided to subdue the Ochi clan, which led the Ochi clan to fall and escape to the sothern Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate reversed its nonintervention policy and decided to subdue the Ochi clan, which led the Ochi clan to fall and escape to the southern Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;southern&quot;のスペルミス。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate reversed its nonintervention policy and decided to subdue the Ochi clan, which led the Ochi clan to fall and escape to the southern Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかしその後、河内国守護の畠山満家が越智維通を支援、筒井氏も細川持之を頼ったが、永享6年（1434年）に入ると越智氏は勢いを盛り返し、筒井氏は再度大敗を喫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, after that, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, shugo (provincial constable) of Kawachi Province, provided support to Koremichi OCHI and, although the Tsutsui clan sought help from Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA, the Ochi clan regained momentum in 1434 and badly defeated the Tsutsui clan again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, after that, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, shugo (provincial constable) of Kawachi Province, provided support to Koremichi OCHI and, although the Tsutsui clan sought help from Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA, the Ochi clan regained momentum in 1434 and badly defeated the Tsutsui clan again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, after that, Mitsuie HATAKEYAMA, shugo (provincial constable) of Kawachi Province, provided support to Koremichi OCHI and, although the Tsutsui clan sought help from Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA, the Ochi clan regained momentum in 1434 and badly defeated the Tsutsui clan again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>翌永享7年（1435年）義教は光宣の訴えにより越智維通らの再度の討伐を決め、幕府軍を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1435, Yoshinori once again made up his mind to subdue Koremichi OCHI and his allies by the request from Mitsunobu and dispatched the army of bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1435, Yoshinori once again made up his mind to subdue Koremichi OCHI and his allies by the request from Mitsunobu and dispatched the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>「幕府」は修正により既出なので、ここで（）内の説明は不要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1435, Yoshinori once again made up his mind to subdue Koremichi OCHI and his allies by the request from Mitsunobu and dispatched the army of bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>越智氏は多武峰に籠もり敗れたものの以後も抗戦を続け、斯波持有率いる幕府軍は永享9年5月22日 (旧暦)（1437年6月25日）に大合戦に及んだが決着がつかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ochi clan barricaded itself in Tonomine and continued to resist even after it was defeated so much that the army of bakufu led by Mochiari SHIBA was unable to settle the battle even when it went all the way to fight a great battle in June 25, 1437.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ochi clan barricaded itself in Tonomine, and though having been defeated, continued to resist so much that the army of bakufu led by Mochiari SHIBA was unable to settle the battle even when it went all the way to fight a great battle on June 25, 1437.</e>
<cmt>「敗れたものの」→位置を変えた方が分かりやすいと思います。&quot;in June 25&quot;→&quot;on June 25&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ochi clan barricaded itself in Tonomine, and though having been defeated, continued to resist so much that the army of bakufu led by Mochiari SHIBA was unable to settle the battle even when it went all the way to fight a great battle on June 25, 1437.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>綸旨発給</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issuance of Rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issuance of Rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issuance of Rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>長引く南朝遺臣の討伐に加え同年7月11日 (旧暦)（8月12日）、義教と不仲であった弟の義昭の出奔をみた幕府首脳は、大覚寺が南朝ゆかりであること、玉川宮、護聖院宮らの南朝皇族も共に逃亡したことなどから、後南朝・義昭に加え、当時幕府派の関東管領上杉憲実と対立していた鎌倉公方足利持氏の連携を疑った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 12, 1437 when the shogunate was trying to subdue the surviving retainers of the Southern Court, Yoshiaki, who was at odds with his older brother Yoshinori ran away, so the leaders of the shogunate doubted the involvement of not only Yoshiaki of Gonancho (Second Southern Court) but also Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) who was in conflict with Norizane UESUGI, kanrei of Kanto (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region) because Daikaku-ji Temple was associated with the Southern Court and because the Imperial family of the Southern Court who lived in Tamagawanomiya Palace and Shogoinnomiya Palace ran away, too.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処玉川宮と護聖院宮は、「宮」を表すPalaceをつけました。南朝は本ファイルの他の箇所でSouthern Courtとしていますので、南朝皇族もnanchoとはしませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 12, 1437 when the shogunate was trying to subdue the surviving retainers of the Southern Court, Yoshiaki, who was at odds with his older brother Yoshinori ran away, so the leaders of the shogunate suspected the involvement of not only Yoshiaki of Gonancho (Second Southern Court) but also Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) who was in conflict with Norizane UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), because Daikaku-ji Temple (from where Yoshiaki ran away) was associated with the Southern Court and also imperial princes of the Southern Court, Tamagawa no miya and Goshoin no miya ran away, too.</e>
<cmt>&quot;doubt&quot;は「不確かだと思う」否定的な疑念を表すので、ここでは&quot;suspect&quot;の方が良いと思います。「関東管領」は役職名なので、そのまま&quot;kanto kanrei&quot;の方が良いと思います。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E8%B6%B3%E5%88%A9%E7%BE%A9%E6%98%AD）「大覚寺」→義昭が出奔した寺であることを説明した方が良いと思います。「玉川宮」「護聖院宮」→宮殿ではなく、人名です。また、読みは「ごしょういんのみや」です。（http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=jA-0i5qTjyYC&amp;pg=PA101&amp;lpg=PA101&amp;dq=%E8%AD%B7%E8%81%96%E9%99%A2%E5%AE%AE%E3%80%80%E7%8E%89%E5%B7%9D%E5%AE%AE&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=C2py9xCjIU&amp;sig=cD7ZOAfpcY35NDkZqj5nxdehuLM&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=nix6TP3vL8vRcd6V9P0F&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=4&amp;ved=0CCMQ6AEwAw#v=onepage&amp;q=%E8%AD%B7%E8%81%96%E9%99%A2%E5%AE%AE%E3%80%80%E7%8E%89%E5%B7%9D%E5%AE%AE&amp;f=false）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 12, 1437 when the shogunate was trying to subdue the surviving retainers of the Southern Court, Yoshiaki, who was at odds with his older brother Yoshinori ran away, so the leaders of the shogunate suspected the involvement of not only Yoshiaki of Gonancho (Second Southern Court) but also Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region) who was in conflict with Norizane UESUGI, Kanto Kanrei (a shogunal deputy for the Kanto region), because Daikaku-ji Temple (from where Yoshiaki ran away) was associated with the Southern Court and also imperial princes of the Southern Court, Tamagawa no miya and Goshoin no miya ran away, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>翌永享10年8月28日 (旧暦)（1438年9月17日）に多武峰を対象とした治罰綸旨を後花園天皇に極秘に発給してもらい総攻撃を開始し、翌永享11年（1439年）3月に至り越智維通が討たれ、11年に及ぶ戦乱は一旦終結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, in September 17, 1438, they requested Emperor Gohanazono in strict secrecy to issue Jibatsu Rinji (imperial order to punish enemies) targeted at Tonomine in order to start an all-out assault, which finally ended the decade-long war with the death of Koremichi OCHI in March 1439.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 17, 1438, they requested the Emperor Gohanazono in strict secrecy to issue Jibatsu Rinji (imperial order to punish enemies) targeting at Tonomine in order to start an all-out assault, which finally ended the war that had lasted for 11 years with the death of Koremichi OCHI in April 1439.</e>
<cmt>文頭の&quot;So&quot;は口語的なので削除しました。「11年に及ぶ戦乱」→decadeは10年なので、原文通り11年と修正。永享11年（1439年）3月→新暦では4月。他、文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 17, 1438, they requested the Emperor Gohanazono in strict secrecy to issue Jibatsu Rinji (imperial order to punish enemies) targeting at Tonomine in order to start an all-out assault, which finally ended the war that had lasted for 11 years with the death of Koremichi OCHI in April 1439.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしながら、越智氏の乱と持氏、義昭との連携については確たる証拠がなく疑問であるという論者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But some people advocates that there are no clear evidence of linkage between the Ochi clan war and Mochiuji and Yoshiaki and that it must be left as an open question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But some people advocate that there is no clear evidence of linkage between the Ochi clan war and Mochiuji and Yoshiaki, and therefore it must be left as an open question.</e>
<cmt>文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But some people advocate that there is no clear evidence of linkage between the Ochi clan war and Mochiuji and Yoshiaki, and therefore it must be left as an open question.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>今谷明は朝敵とは到底いえない持氏を対象とした治罰綸旨発給をしてもらうために南朝方であることから朝敵であることが確実な越智氏との連携を主張したものと推察している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akira IMATANI infers that the reason why the shogunate claimed the cooperation between Mochiuji and the Ochi clan, who was on the Southern Court side and evidently an Emperor&apos;s enemy, was to get the Jibatsu Rinji against Mochiuji because Mochiuji was far from being called as Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akira IMATANI infers that the reason why the shogunate claimed the cooperation between Mochiuji and the Ochi clan, who was on the Southern Court side and evidently an Emperor&apos;s enemy, was to get the Jibatsu Rinji against Mochiuji because Mochiuji was far from being called as Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akira IMATANI infers that the reason why the shogunate claimed the cooperation between Mochiuji and the Ochi clan, who was on the Southern Court side and evidently an Emperor&apos;s enemy, was to get the Jibatsu Rinji against Mochiuji because Mochiuji was far from being called as Emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、義昭の合流についても、義昭出奔を粛正を恐れた単なる逃亡と見る説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory which regards the running way of Yoshiaki as just an escape in fear of tightening discipline, leading him to join in the Southern Court side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, concerning the participation of Yoshiaki, there is a theory that regards the running away of Yoshiaki as a mere escape in fear of purge.</e>
<cmt>「義昭の合流についても」→実際に義昭が南朝側と合流したわけではなく、「義昭の合流についても疑問があり、単なる逃亡と見る説がある」という意味だと思います。「粛正」→&quot;tightening discipline&quot;は「規則を厳しくすること」なので、&quot;purge&quot;の方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, concerning the participation of Yoshiaki, there is a theory that regards the running away of Yoshiaki as a mere escape in fear of purge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>この乱により興福寺の権威は揺らぎ義教の支配が強まったが、永享12年（1440年）には早くも、結城合戦と関連した動きを見せた越智氏討伐のため幕府軍が出陣している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This war undermined the authority of Kofuku-ji Temple and strengthened the rule of Yoshinori but, as early as in 1440, the army of bakufu was forced to go back into battle to subdue the Ochi clan who made a move connected with Yuki War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This war undermined the authority of Kofuku-ji Temple and strengthened the rule of Yoshinori but, as early as in 1440, the army of bakufu was forced to go back into battle to subdue the Ochi clan who made a move connected with Yuki War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This war undermined the authority of Kofuku-ji Temple and strengthened the rule of Yoshinori but, as early as in 1440, the army of bakufu was forced to go back into battle to subdue the Ochi clan who made a move connected with Yuki War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>嘉吉の乱で義教が暗殺されると大和国内は再び混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshinori was murdered in Kakitsu War, Yamato Province again fell into chaos.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshinori was murdered in Kakitsu War, Yamato Province again fell into chaos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshinori was murdered in Kakitsu War, Yamato Province again fell into chaos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>筒井氏内部の家督争いに畠山氏、越智氏らが介入し、更には当の畠山氏の家督争いと続き、応仁の乱を経て大和国は戦国時代へと突入していくこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the Hatakeyama clan and the Ochi clan intervened into the succession dispute of the Tsutsui clan which further developed into the succession dispute of the Hatakeyama clan, followed by Onin war, and then, Yamato Province entered the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Hatakeyama clan and the Ochi clan intervened into the succession dispute of the Tsutsui clan, which further developed into the succession dispute of the Hatakeyama clan, followed by the Onin war, and then, Yamato Province entered the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>&quot;which&quot;は前の文全体を先行詞としているため、非制限用法で、前にコンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Hatakeyama clan and the Ochi clan intervened into the succession dispute of the Tsutsui clan, which further developed into the succession dispute of the Hatakeyama clan, followed by the Onin war, and then, Yamato Province entered the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nate(id:165259), Law soma(id:45202), 白鉢巻(id:250052), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>