<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平禅門の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heizenmon Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heizenmon Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizenmon Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平禅門の乱（へいぜんもんのらん）は、鎌倉時代の1293年（永仁元年）に鎌倉で起こった政変である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heizenmon Incident refers to the coup which took place in Kamakura in 1293 during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heizenmon Incident refers to the coup which took place in Kamakura in 1293 during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>The Heizenmon Incidentとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heizenmon Incident refers to the coup which took place in Kamakura in 1293 during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>北条得宗家執事の平頼綱は、鎌倉幕府鎌倉幕府の執権一覧北条時宗が死去し、その子北条貞時が9代執権となった翌1285年（弘安8年）、政治路線で対立していた有力御家人安達泰盛や泰盛派の御家人を霜月騒動で討伐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoritsuna, who was the steward of the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan, avenged a senior vassal Yasumori ADACHI and other vassals of Yasumori&apos;s faction, with whom he had conflicts in political lines, in the Shimotsuki Incident in 1285, which is a year after Tokimune HOJO, who was one of the regents of the Kamakura Shogunate, died and Tokimune&apos;s son Sadatoki HOJO became the ninth regent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Yoritsuna, who was the steward of the Hojo Tokuso family (main branch of the Hojo family), avenged a senior vassal Yasumori ADACHI and other vassals of Yasumori&apos;s faction, with whom he had conflicts in political lines, in the Shimotsuki Incident in 1285, which was a year after Tokimune HOJO, who was one of the regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), died and Tokimune&apos;s son Sadatoki HOJO became the ninth regent.</e>
<cmt>「北条得宗家」→the Hojo Tokuso familyとし補足追加、is→was、the Kamakura Shogunate→the Kamakura bakufuに修正、bakufuの補足追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Yoritsuna, who was the steward of the Hojo Tokuso family (main branch of the Hojo family), avenged a senior vassal Yasumori ADACHI and other vassals of Yasumori&apos;s faction, with whom he had conflicts in political lines, in the Shimotsuki Incident in 1285, which was a year after Tokimune HOJO, who was one of the regents of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), died and Tokimune&apos;s son Sadatoki HOJO became the ninth regent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後暫くは、頼綱は追加法を頻繁に出すなど手続きを重視した政治運営を行っていたが、1287年（弘安10年）に、征夷大将軍源惟康が立親王して惟康親王となった時期に政治姿勢を一変させ、恐怖政治へと邁進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For a while afterwards, Yoritsuna carried out politics focusing on procedures, for example, frequent submission of additional laws, but in 1287, at the time when Shogun (Generalissimo) MINAMOTO no Koreyasu was given the title of Prince and became Prince Koreyasu, Yoritsuna changed his attitude toward politics suddenly and worked toward a reign of terror.</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍はshogunと短く訳し、（　）に補足した。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a while afterwards, Yoritsuna carried out politics focusing on procedures, for example, frequent submission of additional laws, but in 1287, at the time when Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) MINAMOTO no Koreyasu was given the title of Imperial Prince and became Imperial Prince Koreyasu, Yoritsuna changed his attitude toward politics suddenly and worked toward a reign of terror.</e>
<cmt>Shogun→Seii Taishogunとし補足修正、titile of Prince→title of Imperial Prince、Prince Koreyasu→Imperial Prince Koreyasuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a while afterwards, Yoritsuna carried out politics focusing on procedures, for example, frequent submission of additional laws, but in 1287, at the time when Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) MINAMOTO no Koreyasu was given the title of Imperial Prince and became Imperial Prince Koreyasu, Yoritsuna changed his attitude toward politics suddenly and worked toward a reign of terror.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>貞時は、頼綱に支えられて自らを頂点とする得宗専制体制を敷いたが、頼綱の権勢に不安を抱くようになり、ついに1293年（永仁元年）、鎌倉大地震の混乱に乗じて鎌倉・経師ヶ谷の頼綱邸を攻撃し、頼綱を自刃させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Yoritsuna&apos;s support, Sadatoki established the tyranny of the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan in which Sadatoki himself was the leader, but he came to be disturbed by Yoritsuna&apos;s reins of power and, finally in 1293, taking advantage of the turmoil caused by the Kamakura Earthquake, Sadatoki invaded Yoritsuna&apos;s house in Gyojigayatsu in Kamakura and made him commit suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Yoritsuna&apos;s support, Sadatoki established the tyranny of the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan in which Sadatoki himself was the leader, but he came to be disturbed by Yoritsuna&apos;s reins of power and, finally in 1293, taking advantage of the turmoil caused by the Kamakura Earthquake, Sadatoki invaded Yoritsuna&apos;s house in Gyojigayatsu in Kamakura and made him commit suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Yoritsuna&apos;s support, Sadatoki established the tyranny of the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan in which Sadatoki himself was the leader, but he came to be disturbed by Yoritsuna&apos;s reins of power and, finally in 1293, taking advantage of the turmoil caused by the Kamakura Earthquake, Sadatoki invaded Yoritsuna&apos;s house in Gyojigayatsu in Kamakura and made him commit suicide with his sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>頼綱と不和だった嫡男平宗綱の讒訴によるものという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that this incident was caused by slander made by a legitimate son TAIRA no Munetsuna, who hadn&apos;t got along with Yoritsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been said that this incident was caused by slander made by a legitimate son TAIRA no Munetsuna, who had not got along with Yoritsuna.</e>
<cmt>hadn&apos;t→had notとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been said that this incident was caused by slander made by a legitimate son TAIRA no Munetsuna, who had not got along with Yoritsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>以後、頼綱一族ら御内人の勢力は一時後退して、貞時の専制政治が始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the momentum of miuchibito (private vassals of the tokuso) including the family of Yoritsuna was diminished at one point, and Sadatoki started his tyranny.</e>
<cmt>御内人に（　）を補足した。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the momentum of miuchibito (private vassals of the Tokuso) including the family of Yoritsuna was diminished at one point, and Sadatoki started his tyranny.</e>
<cmt>the Tokusoとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the momentum of miuchibito (private vassals of the Tokuso) including the family of Yoritsuna was diminished at one point, and Sadatoki started his tyranny.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>北条顕時や安達氏など霜月騒動で没落を余儀なくされた勢力も徐々に幕府中枢に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vigorous vassals such as Akitoki HOJO and ADACHI who were forced to give in in the Shimotsuki Incident gradually came back to the center of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vigorous vassals such as Akitoki HOJO and the Adachi clan who were forced to give in the Shimotsuki Incident gradually came back to the center of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>ADACHI→the Adachi clan、in in→in、the Bakufu→the bakufuに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vigorous vassals such as Akitoki HOJO and the Adachi clan who were forced to give in the Shimotsuki Incident gradually came back to the center of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 悪源太義平(id:26422), Mnd(id:15140), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Junger(id:10282), Kawai(id:5634), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>