<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>集治監</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shujikan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shujikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shujikan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>集治監（しゅうじかん）とは明治に作られた現代の刑務所の前身。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shujikan was the predecessor of modern-day prison and was created in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shujikan were the predecessor of modern-day prisons created in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>省略可能部を省きました。後の文脈より、複数形にした方が</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shujikan were the predecessor of modern-day prisons created in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>所長は典獄と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chief of Shujikan was called Tengoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chief of Shujikan was called Tengoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chief of Shujikan was called Tengoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1879年に内務省 (日本)直轄の集治監が小菅（現在の東京拘置所の敷地にあった）と宮城（宮城刑務所の前身）を皮切りに全国各地に作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting in Kosuge (which was located on the site of today&apos;s Tokyo Detention House) and Miyagi (the predecessor of Miyagi Prison), Shujikan was built under the direct control of the Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan) across the country in 1879.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting in Kosuge (which was located on the site of today&apos;s Tokyo Detention House) and Miyagi (the predecessor of Miyagi Prison) in 1879, Shujikan were built across the country under the direct control of the Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt>不要な半角スペースを除きました。文脈からすると複数として訳した方が良いように思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting in Kosuge (which was located on the site of today&apos;s Tokyo Detention House) and Miyagi (the predecessor of Miyagi Prison) in 1879, Shujikan were built across the country under the direct control of the Ministry of Home Affairs (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>収容者に強制労働を強いたことに批判が集まったこと、1894年頃から徐々に強制労働的な受刑者の使役を廃止、1903年以降は監獄と名を改め発展的に消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to a lot of criticism of forcing prisoners to work, forced labor was gradually abolished since around 1894, and Shujikan was dissolved in order that a better prison may be formed after being renamed as Kangoku after 1903.</e>
<cmt>&quot;批判が集まったこと&quot;を”批判があつまったので”と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to mounting criticism of forcing hard labor on prisoners, forced labor was gradually abolished since around 1894, and Shujikan were renamed Kangoku and dissolved to form new facilities after 1903.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to mounting criticism of forcing hard labor on prisoners, forced labor was gradually abolished since around 1894, and Shujikan were renamed Kangoku and dissolved to form new facilities after 1903.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>北海道の集治監</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shujikan in Hokkaido</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shujikan in Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shujikan in Hokkaido</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>北海道では、ロシアの南下政策に対抗するため開拓が急務とされており、人口比で他の地域以上の施設が作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hokkaido, more facilities were established per capita than in other areas because the reclamation of Hokkaido was urgent need to counter Russia&apos;s southward expansion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hokkaido, more facilities were established per capita than in other areas because the reclamation of Hokkaido was an urgent need to counter Russia&apos;s southward expansion.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hokkaido, more facilities were established per capita than in other areas because the reclamation of Hokkaido was an urgent need to counter Russia&apos;s southward expansion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>樺戸（月形町）、空知（三笠市）、釧路（標茶町、網走は釧路の分監）など、北海道内の要所要所に作られ、受刑者は開拓のための労働に従事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shujikan was built at key places within Hokkaido, including Kabato (Tsukigata-cho), Sorachi (Mikasa City), and Kushiro (Shibecha, Abashiri prison was a branch of Kushiro Shujikan), and prisoners were engaged in labor for reclamation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shujikan was built at key places within Hokkaido, including Kabato (Tsukigata-cho Town), Sorachi (Mikasa City), and Kushiro (Shibecha-cho Town [the Abashiri prison was a branch of Kushiro Shujikan]), and prisoners were engaged in labor for reclamation.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため[]とtownを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shujikan was built at key places within Hokkaido, including Kabato (Tsukigata-cho Town), Sorachi (Mikasa City), and Kushiro (Shibecha-cho Town [the Abashiri prison was a branch of Kushiro Shujikan]), and prisoners were engaged in labor for reclamation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>樺戸や網走では道路建設が、空知や釧路では炭鉱、硫黄鉱山（アトサヌプリなど）の労働などに動員された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prisoners were mobilized for road building in Kabato and Abashiri, and for the labor in coal mine and sulfur mine (in Mt. Atosanupuri and so on) in Sorachi and Kushiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prisoners were mobilized for road building in Kabato and Abashiri, and for the labor in coal or sulfur mines (in Mt. Atosanupuri and so on) in Sorachi and Kushiro.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prisoners were mobilized for road building in Kabato and Abashiri, and for the labor in coal or sulfur mines (in Mt. Atosanupuri and so on) in Sorachi and Kushiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>樺戸集治監及び空知集治監の受刑者による上川道路（現在の国道12号）建設が名高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamikawa Road (present National Route 12) is renowned as the road which was constructed by the prisoners in Kabato Shujikan and Sorachi Shujikan.</e>
<cmt>”受刑者により建設された道路として名高い”と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikawa Road (present National Route 12) is renowned as the road which was constructed by the prisoners in Kabato Shujikan and Sorachi Shujikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikawa Road (present National Route 12) is renowned as the road which was constructed by the prisoners in Kabato Shujikan and Sorachi Shujikan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>当初の受刑者には、西南戦争などで捕縛された不平士族、後年には加波山事件や秩父事件などに参画して逮捕された者など、思想犯的な傾向を持つ収容者も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many inmates placed in Shujikan had a tendency toward ideological offenders; for example, in early times there were fuhei shizoku (former samurai with gripes) captured during the Seinan War, and in late times there were people who were arrested due to participation in Kabasan Incident, Chichibu Incident and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many inmates of Shujikan had a tendency toward ideological offenses: they included first fuhei shizoku (former samurai with gripes) captured during the Seinan War, and later those who were arrested due to participation in Kabasan Incident, Chichibu Incident and so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the first inmates at the Shujikan tended to have been imprisoned for ideological offenses; these inmates included fuhei shizoku (discontented former samurai) who had been captured during the Seinan War, and in later years, those who had been arrested due to their participation in the Kabasan Incident, the Chichibu Incident, and so on.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>北海道に多くの集治監が作られた背景は、出所後も現地に留まらせ、当時少なかった人口の増加につなげる思いもあったと伝えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been said that as for the part of the reason that a lot of Shujikan was built in Hokkaido, there was an intention to keep prisoners to stay in Hokkaido after their release in order to increase population which was fewer at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the reason why many Shujikan were built in Hokkaido, it has been said that there was an intention to keep prisoners to stay in Hokkaido after their release in order to increase Hokkaido&apos;s population which was fewer at that time.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the reason why many Shujikan were built in Hokkaido, it has been said that there was an intention to keep prisoners to stay in Hokkaido after their release in order to increase Hokkaido&apos;s population which was fewer at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、実際は過酷な労働が原因で多くの者が命を落としたり、出所後は早々に故郷に逃げ帰る者が多く、人口の増加に貢献をすることは無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in fact, prisoners didn&apos;t contribute to the increase in population because many of them died due to hard work or run back to their home after their release.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in fact prisoners did not contribute to the increase of the population because many of them died due to hard work or ran back to their hometowns after release.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in fact prisoners did not contribute to the increase of the population because many of them died due to hard work or ran back to their hometowns after release.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later times</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>集治監に少なからず思想犯が収容されたことから、次第に世間の注目を浴びるようになり、強制労働的な使役は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since many ideological offenders were locked up in Shujikan, it gradually attracted public attention, making the forced labor abolish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since many ideological offenders were locked up in Shujikan, it gradually attracted public attention, which resulted in the abolition of forced labor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since many ideological offenders were locked up in Shujikan, it gradually attracted public attention, which resulted in the abolition of forced labor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、北海道では開拓事業や九州の炭鉱労働（三池集治監の三井三池炭鉱）の現場では労働力不足を穴埋めするように一般労働者を監禁して酷使するタコ部屋労働が発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Takobeya Rodo (labor camp), a form of labor under which general workers were placed in confinement and exploited to make up for the shortage of workforce, developed; for example, in a land reclamation project in Hokkaido, and at a labor site of coal mine (Mitsui Miike coal mine of Miike Shujikan) in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in land reclamation projects in Hokkaido and at the labor site of coal mines in Kyushu (the Mitsui Miike coal mine in relation with Miike Shujikan), Takobeya (labor camp) Rodo, a form of labor under which general workers were placed in confinement and exploited to make up for the shortage of workforce, developed.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすくするため表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in land reclamation projects in Hokkaido and at the labor site of coal mines in Kyushu (the Mitsui Miike coal mine in relation with Miike Shujikan), Takobeya (labor camp) Rodo, a form of labor under which general workers were placed in confinement and exploited to make up for the shortage of workforce, developed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Blizzardbreaker(id:248394), Tmizuk(id:38161), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 代言人(id:33675), Complex01(id:10454), Ho13(id:33287), NekoJaNekoJa(id:23311), 210.(id:9838), ASAMA501(id:91947), Sinryow(id:4485), めんたいこが好(id:156256), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>