<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>長浜三年寄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagahama sandoshiyori (Three influential families in Nagahama)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagahama sandoshiyori (Three influential families in Nagahama)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagahama sandoshiyori (Three influential families in Nagahama)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>長浜三年寄（ながはまさんどしより）とは、豊臣秀吉の命を受け長浜城下町（49町・10組）を整備した町人衆のうち、組を代表する町年寄の十家が長浜十人衆と呼ばれており、そのうち更に有力であった三家のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagahama sandoshiyori refers to townspeople who developed Nagahama castle town (49 towns, 10 wards) under the order from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and ten representative machi-doshiyori (ward wards) families among them were called Nagahama juhinshu (Ten influential families in Nagahama) and more influential three families among them were called sandoshiyori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagahama sandoshiyori refers to most influential three families among Nagahama juninshu (10 influential families in Nagahama), 10 representative families of machi-doshiyori (ward head) in townspeople who built the Nagahama-jo Castle town (49 towns and 10 wards) under the order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagahama sandoshiyori refers to most influential three families among Nagahama juninshu (10 influential families in Nagahama), 10 representative families of machi-doshiyori (ward head) in townspeople who built the Nagahama-jo Castle town (49 towns and 10 wards) under the order of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>十人衆に選ばれたのは、本町の宮部・西村・下村・田辺、呉服町の安藤、大手町の樋口・大依・川崎、魚屋町の今村、舟町の吉川家だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families chosen as juhinshu were Miyabi, Nishimura, Shimomura, Tanabe in Hon-cho, Ando in Gofuku-machi, Higuchi, Oyori, Kawasaki in Ote-machi, Imamura in Uwai-cho, and Yoshikawa in Funa-machi.</e>
<cmt>魚屋町、舟町の読み、「うわいちょう」、「ふなまち」としていますが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families chosen as the juninshu were the followings: Miyabe, Nishimura, Shimomura, Tanabe in Hon-cho, Ando in Gofuku-machi, Higuchi, Oyori, Kawasaki in Ote-machi, Imamura in Uoya-cho (魚屋町), and Yoshikawa in Funa-machi (舟町).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families chosen as the juninshu were the followings: Miyabe, Nishimura, Shimomura, Tanabe in Hon-cho, Ando in Gofuku-machi, Higuchi, Oyori, Kawasaki in Ote-machi, Imamura in Uoya-cho (魚屋町), and Yoshikawa in Funa-machi (舟町).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>三年寄は、舟町の吉川三左衛門家、本町の下村藤右衛門家、呉服町の安藤九郎右衛門家であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sandoshiyori were families of Sanzaemon YOSHIKAWA in Funa-machi, Touemon SHIMOMURA in Hon-cho, and Kuroemon ANDO in Gofuku-machi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sandoshiyori were families of Sanzaemon YOSHIKAWA in Funa-machi, Toemon SHIMOMURA in Hon-cho, and Kuroemon ANDO in Gofuku-machi.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sandoshiyori were families of Sanzaemon YOSHIKAWA in Funa-machi, Toemon SHIMOMURA in Hon-cho, and Kuroemon ANDO in Gofuku-machi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>江戸時代になると、宮部・西村・樋口・大依の四家が絶え、幕末には吉川三左衛門（五助）、下村藤右衛門（藤七）、田辺伝太夫（九太夫）、安藤九郎右衛門、川崎源兵衛、今村藤右衛門の六家となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, four families of Miyabi, Nishimura, Higuchi, and Oyori came to an end and in the end of the Edo period, there were six families of Sanzaemon YOSHIKAWA (Gosuke), Touemon SHIMOMURA (Toshichi), Dendayu TANABE (Kudayu), Genbe KAWASAKI, and Toemon IMAMURA left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, four families of Miyabe, Nishimura, Higuchi, and Oyori came to an end and in the end of the Edo period, six families of Sanzaemon (Gosuke) YOSHIKAWA, Toemon (Toshichi) SHIMOMURA, Dendayu (Kudayu) TANABE, Genbe KAWASAKI, and Toemon IMAMURA were left.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, four families of Miyabe, Nishimura, Higuchi, and Oyori came to an end and in the end of the Edo period, six families of Sanzaemon (Gosuke) YOSHIKAWA, Toemon (Toshichi) SHIMOMURA, Dendayu (Kudayu) TANABE, Genbe KAWASAKI, and Toemon IMAMURA were left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>現在、長浜市元浜町の安藤家は観光地として残っているが、吉川家・下村家は跡地として、縁戚関係にあった下郷傳平（初代）が購入しており、北船町の吉川家跡地が長浜市立長浜幼稚園、西本町の下村家跡地が滋賀県第一小学校（明治4年～7年・現長浜市立長浜小学校）を経て財団法人下郷共済会となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the present day, the Ando family remains as one of the sightseeing spots in Motohama-cho, Nagahama City, but the sites of the Yoshikswa family and Shimomura family were bought by Denbei SHIMOGO (the first) who had a relation to the families by marriage, and the site of the Yoshikawa family has been used as Nagahama municipal kindergarten, and the site of the Shimomura family has been used by Shingo Kyosaikai foundation after used as Shiga prefecture DAIICHI Elementary School (from 1871 to 1874, present day Nagahama municipal Elementary School).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the present day, the Ando family remains as one of the sightseeing spots in Motohama Town, Nagahama City, but the sites of the Yoshikawa and Shimomura families were bought by Denbei SHIMOGO (the first) who had a relation to the families by marriage, the site of the Yoshikawa family has been used as Nagahama municipal kindergarten, and the site of the Shimomura family has been used by Shimogo Kyosaikai foundation after used as Shiga prefectural Daiichi Elementary School (from 1871 to 1874, present day Nagahama municipal elementary school).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the present day, the Ando family remains as one of the sightseeing spots in Motohama Town, Nagahama City, but the sites of the Yoshikawa and Shimomura families were bought by Denbei SHIMOGO (the first) who had a relation to the families by marriage, the site of the Yoshikawa family has been used as Nagahama municipal kindergarten, and the site of the Shimomura family has been used by Shimogo Kyosaikai foundation after used as Shiga prefectural Daiichi Elementary School (from 1871 to 1874, present day Nagahama municipal elementary school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 踏蹟(id:51201), 松茸(id:27535), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>