<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>賎民</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senmin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senmin (humble or lowly people)</e>
<cmt>説明補足</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>賎民（せんみん）とは、通常の民衆よりも下位に置かれた身分またはその者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmin indicates a rank or a person of that rank placed lower than the usual people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senmin indicates a rank or a person of such rank who is placed lower than the common person.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senmin indicates a rank or a person of such rank who is placed lower than the common person.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>自己もしくは、自己の属する多数派集団と異なるものに対する警戒感である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is originated from a sense of vigilance to those different from oneself or the majority groups to which oneself belonged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated from a sense of vigilance to those different from oneself or the majority groups to which one belonged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated from a sense of vigilance to those different from oneself or the majority groups to which one belonged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>往々にして、他者は己と違った言語と習慣を有する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not infrequently other people possess the languages and customs different from oneself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frequently, other people possessed languages and customs that were different than one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frequently, other people possessed languages and customs that were different than one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>言語や習慣の異なる者に対して、古代人は畏敬の念と共に、不可触の念を抱いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient people felt awesome as well as untouchable to those who had different languages and customs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ancient people felt they conveyed a sense of awe, as if they were untouchable by those who had different languages and customs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ancient people felt they conveyed a sense of awe, as if they were untouchable by those who had different languages and customs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>農耕社会では、自己と同一の意識と生活を有する農民に対しては、警戒感は惹起しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the agrarian society, a sense of vigilance was not raised toward the peasants who possessed the same consciousness and living as those of oneself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the agrarian society, a sense of vigilance was not raised toward the peasants, who possessed the same consciousness and standard of living as one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the agrarian society, a sense of vigilance was not raised toward the peasants, who possessed the same consciousness and standard of living as one&apos;s own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、農民でなく、定住もしていない芸能人や手工業者に対しては、自己と異なる特別の世界に住む者として認識された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they recognized the non-peasants, and the unsettled entertainers and handicraftsmen as those who lived in a special world different from theirs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they recognized the non-peasants, as well as the unsettled entertainers and handicraftsmen, as people who lived in a special world that was different from theirs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they recognized the non-peasants, as well as the unsettled entertainers and handicraftsmen, as people who lived in a special world that was different from theirs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>インド</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">India</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">India</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">India</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>インド社会の根底にはヒンドゥー教の輪廻転生の原理がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the bottom of the Indian society, there is the principle of Rinne Tensho (all things being in flux through the endless circle of birth, death, and rebirth, the circle of transmigration) in the Hinduism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the root of Indian society, there is the principle of Rinne Tensho (all things being in flux through the endless circle of birth, death and rebirth, or the circle of transmigration) in Hinduism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the root of Indian society, there is the principle of Rinne Tensho (all things being in flux through the endless circle of birth, death and rebirth, or the circle of transmigration) in Hinduism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>無条件で輪廻転生できる聖職者のバラモンを頂点とし、厳しい条件（儀式）付きで輪廻転生できる多数の庶民が奴隷階級であり、両者の間に王族・平民（商人）の2階級があり、計4階級からカースト制度は成り立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brahman who are clergymen and can unconditionally perform Rinne Tensho is on top, many common people who can perform Rinne Tensho with strict conditions (rituals) are slaves, and there are two classes between them, which are the royal family and common people (merchants), and totally these four classes compose the caste system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Brahman, a clergymen who can unconditionally perform Rinne Tensho, is on top, and many common people who can perform Rinne Tensho with strict conditions (rituals) are slaves; there are two classes between them, which are the Royal Family and the common people (merchants), and in total these four classes comprise the caste system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Brahman, a clergyman who can unconditionally perform Rinne Tensho, is on top, and many common people who can perform Rinne Tensho with strict conditions (rituals) are slaves; there are two classes between them, which are the Royal Family and the common people (merchants), and in total these four classes comprise the caste system.</e>
<cmt>clergymen→clergyman</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらにこの4階級の下に絶対に輪廻転生できないとされる人々が賎民（アウト・カースト）とされて存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, those who are supposed definitely not to be able to perform Rinne Tensho exist under these four classes as Senmin (outcaste).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, those who are supposed definitely not to be able to perform Rinne Tensho exist under these four classes as Senmin (outcasts).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, those who are supposed definitely not to be able to perform Rinne Tensho exist under these four classes as Senmin (outcasts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>釈迦はこのような社会に登場し、すべての人々（牧畜業、漁業関係者などの生物の命を奪う職業の人々も含む）が輪廻転生可能であることを説き、信仰を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shakyamuni appeared in such a society and preached that every one (including those who had occupations to take lives of living things such as stockbreeders and fishermen) could perform Rinne Tensho, to whom beliefs gathered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shakyamuni appeared in such a society and preached that every one (including those whose occupations required that they take the lives of living things, such as stockbreeders and fishermen) could perform Rinne Tensho, to whom believers gathered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shakyamuni appeared in such a society and preached that every one (including those whose occupations required that they take the lives of living things, such as stockbreeders and fishermen) could perform Rinne Tensho, to whom believers gathered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため、結果として賎民とされる人々に仏教徒が多いという現象を生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it resulted in the phenomenon that there were many Buddhists among the people who were supposed to be Senmin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it resulted in the phenomenon that there were many Buddhists among the people who were supposed to be Senmin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it resulted in the phenomenon that there were many Buddhists among the people who were supposed to be Senmin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、キリスト教のように霊魂の不滅を信じたり、日本の神道のように祖霊を信ずる異教徒に対する差別が現在でも根深く存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, discrimination still deeply exists even nowadays toward the heretics who believe immortality of the spirits such as the Christianity and who believe ancestor&apos;s spirit such as the Japanese Shinto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, discrimination still deeply exists--even nowadays--toward the heretics who believe in the immortality of the spirit, such as in Christianity, and who believe in the spirits of ancestors, such as in Japanese Shinto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, discrimination still deeply exists--even nowadays--toward the heretics who believe in the immortality of the spirit, such as in Christianity, and who believe in the spirits of ancestors, such as in Japanese Shinto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（日本のように神道の祖先崇拝が「御先祖様」として仏教と混交している状態はインドではなかなか理解されない）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It is very difficult for the Indians to understand the status that ancestor worship of Shinto is mixed with the Buddhism as &quot;my dear ancestors&quot; in Japan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It is very difficult for Indians to understand that, in Japan, the ancestor worship of Shinto is mixed with Buddhism as &quot;my dear ancestors.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(It is very difficult for Indians to understand that, in Japan, the ancestor worship of Shinto is mixed with Buddhism as &apos;my dear ancestors.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>朝鮮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>賤民階級の中でも白丁が最下級とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakucho (the ordinary people or inferior servants) was placed in the lowest rank in the Senmin class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakucho (the ordinary person or inferior servant) was placed in the lowest rank of the Senmin class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakucho (the ordinary person or inferior servant) was placed in the lowest rank of the Senmin class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>李朝八賎のなかには仏教の僧侶も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist monks were also included in the eight Senmins of the Yi Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist monks were also included in the eight Senmins of the Yi dynasty.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist monks were also included in the eight Senmins of the Yi dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>漢陽（ソウル特別市）では城内には寺院も建てさせなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were not allowed to build even temples inside the castle of Hanyang (Seoul Special City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were not allowed to build even temples inside the castle of Hanyang (Seoul Special City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were not allowed to build even temples inside the castle of Hanyang (Seoul Special City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>賎民のなかには李氏朝鮮に敗北した地方豪族（将軍）の子孫も含まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The descendants of powerful local clans (generals) defeated by the Yi Dynasty were also included in Senmin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The descendants of powerful local clans (generals) defeated by the Yi dynasty were also included in Senmin.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The descendants of powerful local clans (generals) defeated by the Yi dynasty were also included in Senmin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その血統は明らかで、日本の落人伝説のようにあいまいなものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its blood line is apparent, and not ambiguous like the folklore of the fleeing Heike warriors in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its blood line is apparent instead of being ambiguous like the folklore of the fleeing Heike warriors in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its blood line is apparent instead of being ambiguous like the folklore of the fleeing Heike warriors in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="22">
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>奈良時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nara period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nara period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>律令制度で、賎民を制度化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmin was systematized in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senmin was systematized in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senmin was systematized in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>民衆を良民と賎民（五色の賤）とに分け、農民である良民には租・庸・調・納税・雑徭の義務を課した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people was divided into Ryomin (law-abiding people) and Senmin (Goshiki no sen, five lowly castes) and obligations of So (rice), Yo (capitation), Cho (textile products), tax payment, and zoyo (irregular corvee) were imposed to Ryomin, who were peasants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people were divided into Ryomin (law-abiding people) and Senmin (Goshiki no sen, five lowly castes), and the obligations of So (rice), Yo (capitation), Cho (textile products), tax payment, and zoyo (irregular corvee) were imposed upon Ryomin, who were peasants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people were divided into Ryomin (law-abiding people) and Senmin (Goshiki no sen, five lowly castes), and the obligations of So (rice), Yo (capitation), Cho (textile products), tax payment, and zoyo (irregular corvee) were imposed upon Ryomin, who were peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>賎民にはこれらの義務がなく、また良民だからと言って権利があるわけでもなく、不自由な良民よりも、自由な賎民を選択する者が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senmin had no obligations above and it was not that Ryomin had any rights, and consequently those who chose to be a free Senmin rather than an inconvenient Ryomin appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senmin had none of the above obligations, but the Ryomin had no rights, and consequently those who chose to be free Senmin instead of inconvenient Ryomin appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senmin had none of the above obligations, but the Ryomin had no rights, and consequently those who chose to be free Senmin instead of inconvenient Ryomin appeared one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="27">
<j>中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Medieval period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Medieval period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Medieval period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>律令制度が崩壊することにより、奈良時代の賎民制度は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Senmin system in the Nara period was abolished followed by the collapse of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The abolishment of the Senmin system in the Nara period was followed by the collapse of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The abolishment of the Senmin system in the Nara period was followed by the collapse of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかし、それ以後は、仏教思想を根拠にした賎民制度が登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Senmin system based on the Buddhistic thought appeared after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Senmin system based on Buddhistic thought appeared after that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Senmin system based on Buddhistic thought appeared after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>人の死に関わったり、病気・事故・戦争などでの死牛馬の処理に関わったりする者を、賎民とするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were related to the death of people and to the processing of the dead livestock due to diseases, accidents, wars, and others were defined as Senmin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who were related to the death of people and to the processing of dead livestock due to diseases, accidents, wars and others were defined as Senmin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who were related to the death of people and to the processing of dead livestock due to diseases, accidents, wars and others were defined as Senmin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>芸能人も、大道芸人と呼ばれ、つかみ所のない者として、賎民呼ばわりされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entertainers were called street performers and also defined as Senmin as they were pointless.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entertainers were called street performers and were also defined as Senmin, since they were considered pointless.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entertainers were called street performers and were also defined as Senmin, since they were considered pointless.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>士農工商の枠外に賤民階級が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Senmin class was placed outside the framework in the hierarchy of samurai, farmers, artisans, and merchants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Senmin class was placed outside the framework in the hierarchy of samurai, farmers, artisans and merchants.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Senmin class was placed outside the framework in the hierarchy of samurai, farmers, artisans and merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="34">
<j>ただし、各村の「村明細帳」などに「殺生人」と記される「漁師」・「猟師」などの曖昧な存在もあり、士農工商以外を単純に賎民とすることはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were also ambiguous existence such as &quot;fisherman&quot; and &quot;hunter&quot; described as &quot;in charge of butchery&quot; in the &quot;details of village&quot; and others in each village, and thereby it is not possible to simply call those other than the hierarchy Senmin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were also people of ambiguous existence such as fishermen and hunters, being described as &quot;in charge of butchery&quot; in the &quot;village details&quot; and others in each village, and therefore it wasn&apos;t possible to simply refer to them as being of the Senmin hierarchy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were also people of ambiguous existence such as fishermen and hunters, being described as &apos;in charge of butchery&apos; in the &apos;village details&apos; and others in each village, and therefore it wasn&apos;t possible to simply refer to them as being of the Senmin hierarchy.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また皇族や公家は賎民扱いしないが、僧侶・神職のなかには巫・巫覡として賎民の範疇に入れられた者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the imperial family and court nobles were not treated as Senmin, but some of the monks and priests were added to the Senmin category as kannagi or fugeki (female spiritual medium).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the Imperial Family and court nobles weren&apos;t treated as Senmin, but some of the monks and priests were added to the Senmin category as kannagi or fugeki (female spiritual mediums).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Imperial Family and court nobles weren&apos;t treated as Senmin, but some of the monks and priests were added to the Senmin category as kannagi or fugeki (female spiritual mediums).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>百姓・町人を平人と総称して賎民と区分することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occasionally the peasants and townspeople were distinguished from Senmin by collectively calling Heijin (common people).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Occasionally the peasants and townspeople were distinguished from Senmin by collectively calling Heijin (common people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Occasionally the peasants and townspeople were distinguished from Senmin by collectively calling Heijin (common people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="37">
<j>穢多は、死牛馬（「屠殺」は禁止されていた）の皮革加工、履物職人、非人の管理などを主な生業とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main regular occupations of Eta were leather processing of the dead livestock (&quot;slaughter&quot; was prohibited), and management of footwear craftsmen and Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main regular occupations of Eta were the leather processing of dead livestock (&quot;slaughter&quot; was prohibited) as well as the management of footwear craftsmen and Hinin (a group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main regular occupations of Eta were the leather processing of dead livestock (&apos;slaughter&apos; was prohibited) as well as the management of footwear craftsmen and Hinin (a group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>最下層ではないが、脱出の機会がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They did not belong to the lowest rank, but there was no opportunity to escape from it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They did not belong to the lowest rank, but there was no opportunity to escape from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They did not belong to the lowest rank, but there was no opportunity to escape from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>職業は時代によって差があり、井戸掘りや造園業、湯屋、医師、代言人（弁護士）、能役者（主役級）、歌舞伎役者、野鍛冶のように早期に脱賎化に成功した職業もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a difference in the occupations depending on the period and some of them were successfully escaped from Senmin at an early stage, such as well diggers, landscape gardeners, bathhouse, doctors, those who plead (lawyers), Noh performers (lead roles), Kabuki performers, and blacksmiths.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a difference in the occupations depending on the period, and some of them managed to escape from Senmin at an early stage, such as well diggers, landscape gardeners, bathhouse, doctors, those who pled (lawyers), Noh performers (lead roles), Kabuki performers and blacksmiths.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a difference in the occupations depending on the period, and some of them managed to escape from Senmin at an early stage, such as well diggers, landscape gardeners, bathhouse, doctors, those who pled (lawyers), Noh performers (lead roles), Kabuki performers and blacksmiths.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>諸職人（刀鍛冶や、石工、薬売り、紺屋、筆結、木樵、鎧細工、笠張り、仏師など）や舟渡、陰陽師、宿曜師、山伏、禰宜、巫女、白拍子、舞々、楽人、能役者（端役）、連歌師、俳諧師、通事（飜訳業）、瓦版売り、高利貸（銀行員）などのように地域・時代によっては賎民とされた職業もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some occupations were defined as Senmin depending on the region/period, such as various craftsmen (swordsmiths, masons, medicine peddlers, dyers, pen makers, wood cutters, armor makers, umbrella makers, sculptors of Buddhist statues, and others), boatmen, Yin yang masters, astrologers, mountain priests, shrine priests, shrine maidens, dancing girls, dancers, musicians, Noh performers (minor roles), linked-verse poets, haikai poets, interpreters (translators), news-sheet sellers, and usurers (bankers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some occupations were defined as Senmin depending on the region/period, such as various craftsmen (swordsmiths, masons, medicine peddlers, dyers, pen makers, wood cutters, armor makers, umbrella makers, sculptors of Buddhist statues and others), boatmen, Yin yang masters, astrologers, mountain priests, shrine priests, shrine maidens, dancing girls, dancers, musicians, Noh performers (minor roles), linked-verse poets, haikai poets, interpreters (translators), news-sheet sellers, and usurers (bankers).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some occupations were defined as Senmin depending on the region/period, such as various craftsmen (swordsmiths, masons, medicine peddlers, dyers, pen makers, wood cutters, armor makers, umbrella makers, sculptors of Buddhist statues and others), boatmen, Yin yang masters, astrologers, mountain priests, shrine priests, shrine maidens, dancing girls, dancers, musicians, Noh performers (minor roles), linked-verse poets, haikai poets, interpreters (translators), news-sheet sellers, and usurers (bankers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="41">
<j>非人は、心中の生き残り、近親相姦者、税金不納者、権力に収容された浮浪者（病人を含む）がこの身分に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who survived from joint suicide, inbreeds, tax delinquents, and street people accommodated by the authorities (including the sick) were placed in this rank of Hinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who survived from joint suicide, persons of inbreeding, tax delinquents and street people accommodated by the authorities (including the sick) were placed in this rank of Hinin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who survived from joint suicide, persons of inbreeding, tax delinquents and street people accommodated by the authorities (including the sick) were placed in this rank of Hinin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>身分制度では最下層だが、彼らには非人化から10年以内であれば脱出（足洗い）の機会が与えられることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though they were at the bottom in the rank system, occasionally an opportunity to escape (bail out) was given if it was within ten years after becoming Hinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though they were at the bottom in the system of rank, occasionally an opportunity to escape (bail out) was given if it was within ten years after becoming Hinin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though they were at the bottom in the system of rank, occasionally an opportunity to escape (bail out) was given if it was within 10 years after becoming Hinin.</e>
<cmt>ten→10</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>但し、非人の子として生まれた者は脱出の機会は無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there was no opportunity to escape for those who were born as a child of Hinin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for the one who was born as a child of Hinin there was no chance of escape.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for the one who was born as a child of Hinin there was no chance of escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>奴隷労働から脱走し、逮捕されると腕に入れ墨を入れられて脱走回数が記録された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were tattooed in the arm if escaping from slave labor and being caught, and the number of escapes was recorded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were tattooed on the arm if they escaped from slave labor and were caught, and the number of escapes was recorded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were tattooed on the arm if they escaped from slave labor and were caught, and the number of escapes was recorded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>3回の脱走で死刑となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were sentenced to death if they escaped three times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Death was the sentence levied for three escapes.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Death was the sentence levied for three escapes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>行刑役も非人が負わされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinin also had to undertake the role of prison administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinin also had to undertake the role of prison administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinin also had to undertake the role of prison administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>平人が無礼などを理由に非人を7人殺すと、平人1名を殺したのと同等の罪に問われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heijin was accused of the same crime as killing one Heijin if they killed seven Hinins because of impertinence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For a Heijin, the crime of killing one Heijin was equal to killing seven Hinins because of impertinence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For a Heijin, the crime of killing one Heijin was equal to killing seven Hinins because of impertinence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="48">
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The recent period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The recent period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>江戸時代の賎民制度は、四民平等をもって廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Senmin system in the Edo period was abolished after &quot;equality of all people&quot; was introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Senmin system in the Edo period was abolished after the concept of the &quot;equality of all people&quot; was introduced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Senmin system in the Edo period was abolished after the concept of the &quot;equality of all people&quot; was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし、民衆の間には、賎民に対する差別意識が根強く残り、平民の間から新平民との呼称が自然発生的に成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, sense of discrimination to Senmin was strongly remained in people and the name of Shin-Heimin (new commoner) was spontaneously established from Heimin (commoner).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a sense of discrimination toward Senmin was prevalent among the people, and the name &quot;Shin-Heimin (new commoner)&quot; was spontaneously established from Heimin (commoner).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a sense of discrimination toward Senmin was prevalent among the people, and the name &quot;Shin-Heimin (new commoner)&quot; was spontaneously established from Heimin (commoner).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>部落差別問題にも影響している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This has affected to the problem of Buraku (hamlet) discrimination problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This influenced the problem of Buraku (hamlet) discrimination.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This influenced the problem of Buraku (hamlet) discrimination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="52">
<j>江戸時代には家畜解体業や革細工などの専用の職業が与えられることで、結果的に生活の安定は最低限保障されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, lifestyle stability was accordingly guaranteed minimum by being given exclusive occupations such as slaughter of livestock, leather craft, and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, a minimum of lifestyle stability was guaranteed by being given exclusive occupations such as the slaughter of livestock as well as leather craft and others.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, a minimum of lifestyle stability was guaranteed by being given exclusive occupations such as the slaughter of livestock as well as leather craft and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし近代の四民平等は名目のみであり、その解消のための具体的な施策が行われなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the modern equality of all people was only nominal and no specific measures were not taken to dissolve that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the modern equality of all people was only nominal and no specific measures were taken to dissolve it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the modern equality of all people was only nominal and no specific measures were taken to dissolve it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>そのために他業種への転職が滞ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, job transfer to other industry sectors had been disrupted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the transfer of employment to another industry sector wasn&apos;t a smooth process.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the transfer of employment to another industry sector wasn&apos;t a smooth process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>その一方で穢多専用であった業種への新規参入する人々が現れ、市場競争が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, some people started to newly enter the industry sectors which had been occupied only by Eta, and consequently market competition had begun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, some people started to newly enter the industry sectors that had once been occupied only by Eta, and consequently market competition emerged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, some people started to newly enter the industry sectors that had once been occupied only by Eta, and consequently market competition emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>その結果、生活基盤が崩壊する賎民が続出して部落差別問題の深刻化の一因ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Senmin&apos;s living basis collapsed one after another, which contributed to the deepening of the Buraku discrimination problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, there occurred the collapse of livelihood for many Senmin, thus contributing to the deepening of the Buraku discrimination problem.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, there occurred the collapse of livelihood for many Senmin, thus contributing to the deepening of the Buraku discrimination problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Saintjust(id:21864), Kawai(id:5634), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), Loveless(id:129239), Aibot(id:104981), Point136(id:211299), Memosa(id:131221), TAKASUGI Shinji(id:19129), YODAFON(id:161109), Greenland4(id:114494), 朴明哲(id:63662), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>