<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宇陀松山藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uda-Matsuyama domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Uda-Matsuyama Domain</e>
<cmt>Domain を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Uda-Matsuyama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宇陀松山藩（うだまつやまはん）は、大和国に存在した藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uda-Matsuyama domain existed in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uda-Matsuyama Domain was a domain which existed in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と表現を統一しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uda-Matsuyama Domain was a domain which existed in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藩庁として松山（奈良県宇陀市大宇陀区）に陣屋が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They opened a Jinya (a regional government office) in Matsuyama (Ouda Ward Uda City, Nara Prefecture) as a government building of domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jinya (a regional government office) was placed in Matsuyama (Ouda Ward, Uda City, Nara Prefecture) as a government building of domain.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jinya (a regional government office) was placed in Matsuyama (Ouda Ward, Uda City, Nara Prefecture) as a government building of domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>藩史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of the domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the domain</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、一部小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>宇陀松山藩の藩祖は、有名な戦国時代 (日本)の大名・織田信長である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original forefather of the Uda-Matsuyama domain was Nobunaga ODA the well-known daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Sengoku period (the Warring States period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original forefather of the Uda-Matsuyama Domain was Nobunaga ODA, the well-known daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Sengoku period (the warring states period) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>Domain を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original forefather of the Uda-Matsuyama Domain was Nobunaga ODA, the well-known daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) in the Sengoku period (the warring states period) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>信長が1582年の本能寺の変で殺害された後、織田氏は信長の次男・織田信雄と三男・織田信孝の両統に分裂する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed at the Honnoji Incident in 1582, ODA clan split into two groups (one is of Nobukatsu ODA the second son, another is of Nobutaka ODA the third son).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobunaga was killed at the Honnoji Incident in 1582, Oda clan split into two groups (one is of Nobukatsu ODA, the second son, another is Nobutaka ODA, the third son).</e>
<cmt>Oda clan としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobunaga was killed at the Honnoji Incident in 1582, Oda clan split into two groups (one is of Nobukatsu ODA, the second son, another is Nobutaka ODA, the third son).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1583年の賤ヶ岳の戦いで信孝が豊臣秀吉の命により自刃を余儀なくされた後、織田氏は信雄系統が主役となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1583 after Nobutaka was forced to commit suicide with his sword by an order from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the Nobukatsu group took the initiative in ODA clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1583 after Nobutaka was forced to commit suicide with his sword by an order from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the Nobukatsu group took the initiative in Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>Oda clan としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1583 after Nobutaka was forced to commit suicide with his sword by an order from Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, the Nobukatsu group took the initiative in Oda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1584年の小牧・長久手の戦い以後は信雄自身が暗愚ということもあって、天下への表舞台の影響力を急速に失う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But after Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, due to his incapability as the lord of the Oda clan, Nobukatsu lost his influence quickly on the front stage of the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But after the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, the clan&apos;s power of influence plunged downward on the front stage of the world due to Nobukatsu&apos;s incapability.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But after the Battle of Komaki and Nagakute, the clan&apos;s power of influence plunged downward on the front stage of the world due to Nobukatsu&apos;s incapability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして小田原征伐後、信雄は尾張国から駿河国への移封を拒絶したため、信雄は所領を没収され、下野国に流罪とされてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the conquest and siege of Odawara, due to his refusal to change the territory from Owari Province to Suruga Province, Nobukatsu&apos;s territory was confiscated, then he was exiled to Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the conquest and siege of Odawara, due to his refusal to change the territory from Owari Province to Suruga Province, Nobukatsu&apos;s territory was confiscated, then he was exiled to Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the conquest and siege of Odawara, due to his refusal to change the territory from Owari Province to Suruga Province, Nobukatsu&apos;s territory was confiscated, then he was exiled to Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このとき、信雄は常真と号している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he accepted the deportation, Nobukatsu called himself Joshin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he accepted the deportation, Nobukatsu called himself Joshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he accepted the deportation, Nobukatsu called himself Joshin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>1600年の関ヶ原の戦いで信雄は西軍に与したため、戦後に改易された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600, since Nobukatsu took the side of TOYOTOMI at the Battle of Sekigahara, his territory was confiscated after the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, since Nobukatsu took the side of Toyotomi at the Battle of Sekigahara, his territory was confiscated after the battle.</e>
<cmt>Toyotomi 小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, since Nobukatsu took the side of Toyotomi at the Battle of Sekigahara, his territory was confiscated after the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかしその後、信長の子であるという所以から徳川家康の計らいにより、大和国と上野国両国内に合わせて5万石を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But with the reason he was a son of Nobunaga, Nobukatsu was given fifty thousands koku in total in Yamato Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But with the reason he was a son of Nobunaga, Nobukatsu was given 50,000 koku in total in Yamato Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>数字をアラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But with the reason he was a son of Nobunaga, Nobukatsu was given 50,000 koku in total in Yamato Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのうえ、大和の四品以上に昇進する大名家一覧も与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was also given daimyo family (feudal lord family) list to be ranked higher than Shihon (the fourth-ranked Imperial Prince) in Yamato province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was also given the rank of kokushu (kokushu daimyo, a rank of territorial lord in Edo period) in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>原文wikiを参照し、「四品以上に昇進する大名家一覧」→「国主格」となっておりましたので、左記のように変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was also given the rank of kokushu (kokushu daimyo, a rank of territorial lord in Edo period) in Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>この間、関ヶ原の戦いの功績により福島高晴が3万石余で伊勢国長島から加増転封されて入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, with the meritorious deed at the Battle of Sekigahara, Takaharu FUKUSHIMA moved in from Nagashima, Ise province with the added crop yields approximately thirty thousand koku as the local lord instead of Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, with the meritorious deed at the Battle of Sekigahara, Takaharu FUKUSHIMA moved in from Nagashima, Ise Province with the added crop yields approximately 30,000 koku as the local lord instead of Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>Province 大文字にしました。30,000　アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, with the meritorious deed at the Battle of Sekigahara, Takaharu FUKUSHIMA moved in from Nagashima, Ise Province with the added crop yields approximately 30,000 koku as the local lord instead of Nobukatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1615年の大坂夏の陣で豊臣氏に内通した嫌疑をかけられて改易され、信雄が再び入封する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, Takaharu was punished by being deprived of his rank or fief due to the suspicion of secret communication with TOYOTOMI clan at Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Siege of Osaka) in 1615, Nobukatsu reentered Yamato Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Takaharu was punished by being deprived of his rank or fief due to the suspicion of secret communication with Toyotomi clan in the Summer Siege of Osaka in 1615, and Nobukatsu reentered Yamato Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>and を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Takaharu was punished by being deprived of his rank or fief due to the suspicion of secret communication with Toyotomi clan in the Summer Siege of Osaka in 1615, and Nobukatsu reentered Yamato Province and Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>信雄は、上野の領地を四男の織田信良に与え、自身は大和2万8000石を領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobukatsu gave his territory in Kozuke Province to his forth son Nobuyoshi ODA, he began to rule Yamato Province where produced twenty eight thousand koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobukatsu gave his territory in Kozuke Province to his forth son Nobuyoshi ODA, he began to rule Yamato Province which produced 28,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobukatsu gave his territory in Kozuke Province to his forth son Nobuyoshi ODA, he began to rule Yamato Province which produced 28,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1630年の信雄死後、家督は六男の織田高長が継ぐ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1630 After the death of Nobukatsu, the sixth son, Takanaga ODA became the successor to ODA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1630 after the death of Nobukatsu, the sixth son, Takanaga ODA took over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>Oda 小文字にしました。家督を継ぐ→took over as head of the familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1630 after the death of Nobukatsu, the sixth son, Takanaga ODA took over as head of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その後、織田長頼・織田信武と続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ODA clan kept being succeeded changing the load Nagase to Nobutake.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Takanaga was succeeded by Nagayori ODA, who was then succeeded by Nobutake ODA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Takanaga was succeeded by Nagayori ODA, who was then succeeded by Nobutake ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>藩内に混乱が起こり信武は自殺（宇陀崩れ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, with the disorders in ODA clan, Nobutake committed suicide (Uda Disturbance).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nobutake committed suicide (Uda Disturbance) due to the disorders within the domain</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nobutake committed suicide (Uda Disturbance) due to the disorders within the domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>信長の血統であるということを重んじられて、信武の子・織田信休への家督相続こそ認められたが、所領を2万石に減らされた上で丹波国丹波柏原藩へ減移封。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the succession to family headship to Nobuyasu ODA (the son of Nobutake) was admitted because of the highly respected blood line of Nobunaga, Oda clan was forced to reduce their territory crop to two twenty thousand koku and change their territory to Kaibara Domain of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the succession to family headship to Nobuyasu ODA (the son of Nobutake) was admitted because of the highly respected blood line of Nobunaga, Oda clan was forced to reduce their territory crop to 20,000 koku and change their territory to Kaibara Domain of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the succession to family headship to Nobuyasu ODA (the son of Nobutake) was admitted because of the highly respected blood line of Nobunaga, Oda clan was forced to reduce their territory crop to 20,000 koku and change their territory to Kaibara Domain of Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>国主として扱われていた待遇も、このときに剥奪されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their position as the local load was deprived at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their position as the kokushu was deprived at the same time.</e>
<cmt>国主　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their position as the kokushu was deprived at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、宇陀松山藩もこれをもって廃藩となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Uda-Matsuyama domain was abolished as haihan(abolition of feudal domains)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Uda-Matsuyama Domain was abolished as well.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Uda-Matsuyama Domain was abolished as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴代藩主</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive lords of the domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive lords of the domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive lords of the domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>福島家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukushima family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fukushima family</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fukushima family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>外様大名 - 3万1717石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Non-Tokugawa daimyo (feudal lord) with thirty one thousand and seven hundred seventeen koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tozama (Non-Tokugawa) daimyo: 31,717 koku</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tozama (Non-Tokugawa) daimyo: 31,717 koku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>織田家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oda family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oda family</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oda family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>外様 - 2万8000石</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tozama (outside feudal lord) with twenty eight thousand koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tozama daimyo: 28,000 koku</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tozama daimyo: 28,000 koku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Mnd(id:15140), Yanahan(id:2437), Carbuncle(id:346), Kouko0515(id:100370), Reggaeman(id:6214), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>