<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>庶家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoke</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoke</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>庶家（しょけ）とは、宗家ないし本家より別れた一族のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoke refers to a family which was branched from the head of the family or the head house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoke refers to a family that branched off from the head of a family or the head of a household.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoke refers to a family that branched off from the head of a family or the head of a household.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>嫡流に対し庶流の家柄。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoke is a family of shoryu (illegitimate family lineage) as opposed to chakuryu (the direct line of descent).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoke is a family of shoryu (illegitimate family lineage) as opposed to chakuryu (the direct line of descent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoke is a family of shoryu (illegitimate family lineage) as opposed to chakuryu (the direct line of descent).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>主に日本の封建時代においてみられた血族集団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoke was a blood-relative group which was mainly present in the feudal period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoke was a blood-relative group which was mainly present during the feudal period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoke was a blood-relative group which was mainly present during the feudal period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>庶子家ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoke was also called Shosike.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoke was also called Shosike.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoke was also called Shoshike.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>庶家とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What Is Shoke?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What Is Shoke?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is Shoke?</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>庶家という概念は主に日本の封建時代、特に鎌倉時代から戦国時代 (日本)、江戸時代にかけて武家に見られた血族集団ないし階層のことをいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concept of Shoke refers to a blood-relative group or a blood-relative layer which was present in warriors in mainly the feudal period in Japan, especially from Kamakura Period to the Warring States (in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concept of Shoke refers to a blood-relative group or a blood-relative layer present amongst warriors in mainly the feudal period in Japan, especially from Kamakura Period to the period of Warring States (in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concept of Shoke refers to a blood-relative group or a blood-relative layer present amongst warriors in mainly the feudal period in Japan, especially from Kamakura period to the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States) (Japan) and Edo period.</e>
<cmt>戦国時代用語統一Edo period補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>宗家と庶家の関係はいわば本家と分家と同義であるが、一般的な分家と異なるのは、分家であれば本家と同姓を称するのが通例であるが、庶家という場合、その多くは宗家と同姓を用いることを避け、或いは禁じられその多くが別姓を称した家柄が多いという点にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relation between the head of a family and Shoke had the same meaning as that of the head house and a branch family in a sense and Shoke differed from an ordinary branch family in that a branch family ordinarily had the same family name as that of the head family while many of Shoke avoided or were prohibited from using the same family name as that of the heads of the families and each of many Shoke lineages used another family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between the head of a family and Shoke is the same as that of the head of a household and a branch family, Shoke differed from an ordinary branch family because a branch family ordinarily had the same family name as that of the head family while many Shoke avoided or were prohibited from using the same family name and instead used another family name.</e>
<cmt>grammar, wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between the head of a family and Shoke is the same as that of the head of a household and a branch family, Shoke differed from an ordinary branch family because a branch family ordinarily had the same family name as that of the head family while many Shoke avoided or were prohibited from using the same family name and instead used another family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>多くの武家では宗家と主従関係を結ばれた結果、宗家の一門としての待遇を離れ主家と祖先を同じくする家臣として位置づけられていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of establishing the relation between a lord and a vassal, many warriors left the treatment as a faction of the head of the family and were positioned as vassals from the same ancestors as those of the employer&apos;s house..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of establishing a relationship between a lord and vassal, many warriors relinquished being treated as the head of the family and positioned themselves as vassals from the same ancestors as those of their employer&apos;s house..</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of establishing a relationship between a lord and vassal, many warriors relinquished being treated as the head of the family and positioned themselves as vassals from the same ancestors as those of their employer&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>守護の家柄で代表的な例を上げると、武田信玄を出した武田氏が著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A typical example of a Shugo (a constable) linage is the Takeda clan which produced Shingen TAKEDA and which is prominent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A typical example of a Shugo (a constable) linage is the prominent Takeda clan which produced Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A typical example of a Shugo (a constable) linage is the prominent Takeda clan which produced Shingen TAKEDA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>武田氏の家臣団には、守護の兄弟子女、或いは女婿を中心とするご親類衆があるが、板垣氏や甘利氏など、同じ甲斐源氏を祖に持つ庶流の家柄にあるものは、主に武田氏の家老を務める御譜代衆、国衆として位置づけられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vassal groups of the Takeda clan included shinsekishu (a group of relatives) which mainly included siblings and children, and the husbands of daughters of shugo, and those who were in the shoke lineages whose origin was Kai-Genji (the Minamoto clan) similarly to the Takeda clan such as the Itagaki clan and the Amari clan were positioned as Gofudaishu (hereditary daimyo) and kunishu who mainly acted as the chief retainer of the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vassal groups of the Takeda clan included shinsekishu (a group of relatives) which mainly included siblings and children, and the husbands of daughters of shugo, and those who were in the shoke lineages whose origin was Kai-Genji (the Minamoto clan) similarly to the Takeda clan, such as the Itagaki and the Amari clans, were positioned as Gofudaishu (hereditary daimyo) and kunishu who mainly acted as chief retainers of the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vassal groups of the Takeda clan included shinsekishu (a group of relatives) which mainly included siblings and children, and the husbands of daughters of shugo, and those who were in the shoke lineages whose origin was Kai-Genji (the Minamoto clan) similarly to the Takeda clan, such as the Itagaki and the Amari clans, were positioned as Gofudaishu (hereditary daimyo) and kunishu who mainly acted as chief retainers of the Takeda clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>同じく戦国大名として活躍した毛利元就を出した毛利氏では、鎌倉時代以降毛利氏より輩出された安芸坂氏や福原氏などの庶子の一族が庶家衆として、毛利氏当主の兄弟子弟より構成された一門衆に準ずる地位に位置づけられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Mori clan which produced Motonari MORI who played an important role as a daimyo, similarly to the Takeda clan, a shoshi family such as the Akisaka clan and the Fukuhara clan produced from the Mori clan since the Kamakura period were positioned next to ichimonnshu which included the siblings and children of the family head of the Mori clan, as shokeshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Mori clan which produced Motonari MORI who played an important role as a daimyo, similarly to the Takeda clan, a shoshi family such as the Akisaka and the Fukuhara clans produced from the Mori clan since the Kamakura period were positioned next to ichimonnshu which included the siblings and children of the family head of the Mori clan, as shokeshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Mori clan which produced Motonari MORI who played an important role as a daimyo, similarly to the Takeda clan, a shoshi family such as the Akisaka and the Fukuhara clans produced from the Mori clan since the Kamakura period were positioned next to ichimonshu which included the siblings and children of the family head of the Mori clan, as shokeshu.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>伝統的権威を求心力とした時代、その重要な要素である血縁や格式が武士の心理において大きく作用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was the age when the traditional authority was used as a centripetal force, blood relations and the social standing which were the important elements of the traditional authority significantly acted on the psychology of the warriors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was an age when traditional authority was used as a centripetal force, blood relations and the social standing which were the important elements of traditional authority significantly acted on the psychology of the warriors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it was an age when traditional authority was used as a centripetal force, blood relations and the social standing which were the important elements of traditional authority significantly acted on the psychology of the warriors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それは実力がものをいう戦国時代においても同様である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was same in the Sengoku Period when the actual power mattered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was same during the Sengoku Period when actual power mattered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was same during the Sengoku Period when actual power mattered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>故に、こうした守護や国人などの家政において中枢を占めた庶家衆の多くは宗家たる主家と同族であることを誇りにし、主家に対する忠誠も厚かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, many of shokeshu who occupied the core in such Kasei by shugo and kokunin were proud of their being in the same family as the employer&apos;s house which was the head of the family, and were also very loyal to the employer&apos;s house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, many shokeshu who occupied the core in such Kasei by shugo and kokunin were proud of being in the same family as their employer&apos;s household, the head of the family, and were also very loyal to their employer&apos;s household.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, many shokeshu who occupied the core in such Kasei by shugo and kokunin were proud of being in the same family as their employer&apos;s household, the head of the family, and were also very loyal to their employer&apos;s household.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかし、それはあくまで主家との一定の自立を前提としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this occurred persistently on the premise that shokeshu was independent from the employer&apos;s house to some extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this occurred persistently on the premise that shokeshu was independent from the employer&apos;s household to some extent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this occurred persistently on the premise that shokeshu was independent from the employer&apos;s household to some extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それは、庶家も主家同様、領土と居城、家臣を養い、主家から一定の独立を保った者も少なくなく、主君と家臣という強固な主従関係というよりは、事実上、宗家を盟主とする同盟関係という性格が強いものであったことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because not a few shoke, similarly to the employer&apos;s house, maintained their territories, their castles as residences, and their vassals and kept their independence from the employer&apos;s house to some extent, and this relation was not the strong relation between a master and vassals but, in fact, tended to be a relation as an alliance with the head of the family as the alliance leader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because many shoke, similarly to the employer&apos;s household, maintained their territories, their castles as residences, and their vassals and kept their independence from their employer&apos;s household to some extent, and this relationship was not a strong one between master and vassals, but, in fact, tended to be more of an alliance with the head of the family as the alliance leader.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because many shoke, similarly to the employer&apos;s household, maintained their territories, their castles as residences, and their vassals and kept their independence from their employer&apos;s household to some extent, and this relationship was not a strong one between master and vassals, but, in fact, tended to be more of an alliance with the head of the family as the alliance leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>それだけに主家と利害対立が起こると、公然と反抗する者もあり、時として主家に攻め込んだり、或いは幕府に願い出て宗家からの自立を図ることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when confrontation concerning the interest occurred against the employer&apos;s house, some shoke publicly resisted against the employer&apos;s house and they sometimes attacked the employer&apos;s house or planned to become independent from the employer&apos;s house by asking Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for their independence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when confrontation concerning the interest occurred against the employer&apos;s household, some shoke publicly resisted against the employer&apos;s household and they sometimes attacked the employer&apos;s household or planned to become independent from the employer&apos;s household by asking the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for their independence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when confrontation concerning the interest occurred against the employer&apos;s household, some shoke publicly resisted against the employer&apos;s household and they sometimes attacked the employer&apos;s household or planned to become independent from the employer&apos;s household by asking the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for their independence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>特に戦国時代に入ると、その動きはより顕著となり、庶家の中にも主家に忠実かつ従順な者もいる一方で、主家を圧倒する者や主家の家政を牛耳る者、主家を追放し下剋上を起こす者も登場するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Sengoku Period started, this movement became more conspicuous, and some shoke were loyal and obedient to the employer&apos;s house while some shoke started to overwhelm the employer&apos;s house, control the domestic economy of the employer&apos;s house, and expel the employer&apos;s house and commit Gekokujo (supplanting of a lord by his retainer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Sengoku Period started, this movement became more conspicuous, and some shoke were loyal and obedient to the employer&apos;s household while some shoke started to overwhelm the employer&apos;s household, control the domestic economy of the employer&apos;s household, and expel the employer&apos;s household and commit Gekokujo (supplanting of a lord by his retainer).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Sengoku Period started, this movement became more conspicuous, and some shoke were loyal and obedient to the employer&apos;s household while some shoke started to overwhelm the employer&apos;s household, control the domestic economy of the employer&apos;s household, and expel the employer&apos;s household and commit Gekokujo (supplanting of a lord by his retainer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="19">
<j>主家の実権を掌握した庶家の代表例が室町幕府三管領のひとつ、細川氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical example of shoke which grasped the real authority of the employer&apos;s house was the Hosokawa clan which was one of the three kanrei (shogunal deputies) of Muromachi Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical example of shoke whio grabbed the real authority of the employer&apos;s household was the Hosokawa clan, one of the three kanrei (shogunal deputies) of Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical example of shoke who grabbed the real authority of the employer&apos;s household was the Hosokawa clan, one of the three kanrei (shogunal deputies) of Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>細川氏は足利将軍家同様、足利氏の流れを汲み、同じく将軍家と同族である斯波氏、畠山氏とともに、管領職を持ち回りで司ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly to the Ashikaga family positioned to accede to the shogunate, the Hosokawa clan was related to the linage of the Ashikaga clan and bore the role of kanrei in turns with the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan which were in the same family linage of the Ashikaga family similarly to the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like the Ashikaga family positioned to accede to the shogunate, the Hosokawa clan was related to the linage of the Ashikaga clan and bore the role of kanrei alternately with the Shiba and the Hatakeyama clans in the same family linage of the Ashikaga family like the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like the Ashikaga family positioned to accede to the shogunate, the Hosokawa clan was related to the linage of the Ashikaga clan and bore the role of kanrei alternately with the Shiba and the Hatakeyama clans in the same family linage of the Ashikaga family like the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、応仁の乱により将軍の権力が失墜すると、細川氏は三管領筆頭の斯波氏、畠山氏を圧倒し、幕政を牛耳るようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the shogun&apos;s power was lost because of Onin war, the Hosokawa clan overwhelmed the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan which were the heads of the three kanrei and started to control the politics of Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the shogun&apos;s power was lost in the Onin war, the Hosokawa clan overwhelmed the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan, that were the heads of the three kanrei, and started to control the politics of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the shogun&apos;s power was lost in the Onin War, the Hosokawa clan overwhelmed the Shiba clan and the Hatakeyama clan, that were the heads of the three kanrei, and started to control the politics of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>特に管領 細川政元は征夷大将軍足利義稙を追放し、次期将軍に幼い足利義澄を擁立しこれを傀儡化させ、幕政を牛耳っており、室町幕府は事実上、細川氏の政権となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially, Masamoto HOSOKAWA expelled Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (great general who subdued the barbarians), backed up Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA who was still very young to be the next shogun, made Yoshizumi a puppet, and controlled the politics of Bakufu, and Muromachi Bakufu, in fact, became the administration of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially, Masamoto HOSOKAWA expelled Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (great general who subdued the barbarians), backed up Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA who was still too young to become the next shogun, made Yoshizumi a puppet, and controlled the politics of the bakufu, and the Muromachi bakufu, and in fact, became the administration of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially, Masamoto HOSOKAWA expelled Yoshitane ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), backed up Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA who was still too young to become the next shogun, made Yoshizumi a puppet, and controlled the politics of the bakufu, and the Muromachi bakufu, in fact, became the administration of the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>and 削除&quot; (great general who subdued the barbarians)&quot;→&quot; (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、宗家たる主家に取って代わった例として出雲の戦国大名　尼子氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An example of shoke which substituted the employer&apos;s house which was the head of the family was the Amago clan which was a sengoku daimyo in Izumo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An example of shoke that substituted the employer&apos;s household, who was the head of the family, was the Amago clan, a sengoku daimyo in Izumo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An example of shoke that substituted the employer&apos;s household, who was the head of the family, was the Amago clan, a sengoku daimyo in Izumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>戦国時代、出雲国においては京極氏が出雲守護職に補任されてきたが、同氏が室町幕府において三管領に次ぐ四職の家柄にあり、北近江守護職を兼務していたことから、京極氏の庶流である尼子氏が、京極氏の守護代として出雲国を任されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Sengoku Period, in Izumo, the Kyogoku clan helped the duty of Izumo shugoshoku and the Kyogoku clan was the linage of the fourth post next to the three kanrei in Muromachi Bakufu and also acted as Kitaomi shugoshoku and, therefore, the Kyogoku clan left the province of Izumo no kuni to the Amago clan which was shoryu of the Kyogoku clan, as shugodai (deputy of Shugo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period, in Izumo, the Kyogoku clan helped with the duties of Izumo shugoshoku and the Kyogoku clan was the linage of the fourth post next to the three kanrei in the Muromachi bakufu and also acted as Kitaomi shugoshoku and, therefore, the Kyogoku clan left the province of Izumo no kuni to the Amago clan which was shoryu of the Kyogoku clan, as shugodai (deputy of Shugo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period, in Izumo, the Kyogoku clan helped with the duties of Izumo shugoshoku and the Kyogoku clan was the linage of the fourth post next to the three kanrei in the Muromachi bakufu and also acted as Kitaomi shugoshoku and, therefore, the Kyogoku clan left the Izumo Province to the Amago clan which was shoryu of the Kyogoku clan, as shugodai (deputy of Shugo).</e>
<cmt>province of Izumo no kuni→Izumo Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、守護 京極政経の代に入ると、政経は守護代 尼子経久と次第に対立を深め、政経が経久を追放すると、その翌年には尼子経久が奇襲を持って主家を攻め、主君より領土と実権を奪い、出雲守護となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the generation of shugo, Masatsune KYOGOKU started, Masatsune gradually deepened the confrontation against shugodai (the deputy of shugo), Tsunehisa AMAGO and, when Masatsune expelled Tsunehisa, Tsunehisa AMAGO made a surprise attack to the employer&apos;s house in the next year, usurped the territory and the authority from his master, and became shugo of Izumo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the generation of shugo, Masatsune KYOGOKU started, Masatsune gradually deepened confrontation against shugodai (the deputy of shugo), Tsunehisa AMAGO and, when Masatsune expelled Tsunehisa, Tsunehisa AMAGO made a surprise attack on the employer&apos;s household the following year, usurped the territory and the authority from his master, and became shugo of Izumo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the generation of shugo, Masatsune KYOGOKU started, Masatsune gradually deepened confrontation against shugodai (the deputy of shugo), Tsunehisa AMAGO and, when Masatsune expelled Tsunehisa, Tsunehisa AMAGO made a surprise attack on the employer&apos;s household the following year, usurped the territory and the authority from his master, and became shugo of Izumo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>このように、戦国時代に入ると主家を打倒或いは追放して主君の座を奪う者、主家から離反し他家に転ずる者、主家を傀儡化し家政を牛耳る者も現れるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, when Sengoku Period started, there emerged even those who usurped the position of the employer&apos;s house by destroying or expelling the employer&apos;s house, who resisted and left the employer&apos;s house and changed the employer to another, and who made the employer&apos;s house a puppet and controlled the politics of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, when the Sengoku Period started, there emerged even those who usurped the position of the employer&apos;s household, by destroying or expelling the employer&apos;s household, who resisted and left the employer&apos;s household and changed from one employer to another, and who made the employer&apos;s household a puppet and controlled the politics of the family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, when the Sengoku Period started, there emerged even those who usurped the position of the employer&apos;s household, by destroying or expelling the employer&apos;s household, who resisted and left the employer&apos;s household and changed from one employer to another, and who made the employer&apos;s household a puppet and controlled the politics of the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="27">
<j>このように、庶家は主家の中で非常に強い影響力を有したが、主家が戦国大名化するにつれ、領土経営に寄与する有能な人材が登用され、主君に忠実な家臣団、直臣団が編成されると、主家とは血縁関係もない、主従関係を結んでから日の浅い者も登用されるようになり、庶家の影響力が低下する例も少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though shoke had a very strong influence in the employer&apos;s house in this way, when efficient human resources who would contributed to the management of the territory were employed and vassal groups and groups of direct vassals who were royal to the master were organized as the employer&apos;s house became sengoku daimyo, those who had no blood relations with the employer&apos;s house and had a short history of the relation of a master and vassals were also employed and, therefore, not a few cases were seen where the influence of shoke was weakened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though shoke had a very strong influence in the employer&apos;s household, when efficient human resources were employed, contributing to the management of the territory and vassal groups who were loyal to the master were organized as the employer became a sengoku daimyo, those who had no blood relations with the employer or who had a short history as master and vassal, were also employed there were many examples seen where the influence of shoke was weakened.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although shoke had a very strong influence in the employer&apos;s household, when efficient human resources were employed, contributing to the management of the territory and vassal groups who were loyal to the master were organized as the employer became a sengoku daimyo, those who had no blood relations with the employer or who had a short history as master and vassal, were also employed there were many examples seen where the influence of shoke was weakened.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Though&quot;→&quot;Although&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>守護大名や守護代、国人領主が戦国大名になるためには、それは室町時代以前からの庶家や傘下の土豪とのゆるやかな同盟関係のしがらみを絶ち、強固な主従関係により結ばれた家臣団の獲得こそが大きな条件であったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order for shugo daimyo, shugodai, and kokujinryoshu to become sengoku daimyo, it can be said that the only major condition was to abolish the ties of their loose alliances with shoke and local clans under them which started before Muromachi period and to obtain vassal groups with which they were tied based on the strong relation of a master and vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order for shugo daimyo, shugodai, and kokujinryoshu to become a sengoku daimyo, it was necessary to abolish the ties of their loose alliances with shoke and local clans under them that began before the Muromachi period and then to obtain vassal groups with which they were tied based upon a strong relationship of master and vassal.</e>
<cmt>wordiness, redundancy, revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order for shugo daimyo, shugodai, and kokujinryoshu to become a sengoku daimyo, it was necessary to abolish the ties of their loose alliances with shoke and local clans under them that began before the Muromachi period and then to obtain vassal groups with which they were tied based upon a strong relationship of master and vassal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mobnoboka(id:35218), Number(id:103039), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>