<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伏見版</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimiban</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimiban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimiban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伏見版（ふしみばん）とは、江戸時代初頭に、徳川家康の命により、山城国伏見区の伏見学校の一角に建立された円光寺（現在地は、京都市左京区一乗寺）において開版された木活字版のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushimiban are block printing editions printed in Enko-ji Temple (now Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City) that was established on a corner of the Fushimi School in Fushimi Ward of Yamashiro Province by order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushimiban are block printed books printed at the Enko-ji Temple (now Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City), which was established on a corner of the Fushimi School in Fushimi Ward of Yamashiro Province by order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushimiban are block printed books printed at the Enko-ji Temple (now Ichijoji, Sakyo Ward, Kyoto City), which was established on a corner of the Fushimi School in Fushimi Ward of Yamashiro Province by order of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、円光寺版ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called, Enko-ji ban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also called Enko-ji ban.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also called Enko-ji ban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>伏見学校は、足利学校第9世の三要元佶を招請して創建したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ninth head of the Ashikaga School, Genkitsu SANYO, was invited to establish the Fushimi School.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth head of the Ashikaga School, Genkitsu SANYO, was invited to establish the Fushimi School.</e>
<cmt>余分な空白を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth head of the Ashikaga School, Genkitsu SANYO, was invited to establish the Fushimi School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>元佶が出版した書籍は、1599年の『孔子家語』、『六韜』、『三略』が最初である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genkitsu first published &quot;Koshi-kego (a chronicle of the sayings and doings of Confucius and his disciples)&quot;, &quot;Rikuto (an ancient Chinese strategy book)&quot; and &quot;Sanryaku (an ancient Chinese strategy book)&quot; in 1599.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genkitsu first published &quot;Koshi-kego (a chronicle of the sayings and doings of Confucius and his disciples)&quot;, &quot;Rikuto&quot;, and &quot;Sanryaku (ancient Chinese strategy books)&quot; in 1599.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genkitsu first published &quot;Koshi-kego&quot; (a chronicle of the sayings and doings of Confucius and his disciples), &quot;Rikuto,&quot; and &quot;Sanryaku&quot; (ancient Chinese strategy books) in 1599.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動コンマ位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>1600年には、西笑承兌により、『貞観政要』が出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1600, Jotai SAISHO published &quot;Joganseiyo (a book written about Taiso, the second Emperor of Tang Dynasty in China)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1600, Jotai SAISHO published &quot;Joganseiyo (a book written about Taiso, the second Emperor of the Tang Dynasty in China)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1600, Jotai SAISHO published &quot;Joganseiyo&quot; (a book written about Taiso, the second Emperor of the Tang Dynasty in China).</e>
<cmt>&quot;半角にして位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>1605年には、やはり西笑承兌により、『吾妻鏡』と『周易』が出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1605, again by Jotai SAISHO, &quot;Azuma kagami (a chronicle of the Kamakura bakufu from 1180 to 1266)&quot; and &quot;Shueki (the first book in China written in the Zhou Dynasty period)&quot; were published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1605 Jotai SAISHO also published &quot;Azuma kagami (a chronicle of the Kamakura bakufu from 1180 to 1266)&quot; and &quot;Shueki (the first book in China written in the Zhou Dynasty period)&quot; were published.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1605 Jotai SAISHO also published &quot;Azuma kagami&quot; (a chronicle of the Kamakura bakufu from 1180 to 1266) and &quot;Shueki&quot; (the first book in China written in the Zhou Dynasty period) were published.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="7">
<j>1606年には、元佶によって、武経七書が開版された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1606, the &quot;Bukei-shichisho (the seven classical strategy books in China)&quot; were published by Genkitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1606 Genkitsu published the &quot;Bukei-shichisho (seven classical strategy books of China)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1606 Genkitsu published the &quot;Bukei-shichisho&quot; (seven classical strategy books of China).</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この間に刊行された書籍は、8部80冊である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of books published in this period was 8 titles, total of 80 books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of books published in this period was 8 titles, a total of 80 books.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of books published in this period was 8 titles, a total of 80 books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>1612年の、開山である元佶の没後、臨済宗に属する円光寺は、相国寺の境内に移り、その後、寛文年間（1661年 - 1673年）には、愛宕郡修学院村（現在地）に移転している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1612, after the founding father Genkitsu died, Enko-ji Temple, belonging to the Rinzai Sect, was moved to within the premises of Shokoku-ji Temple and afterwards was located in Shugakuin Village, Otagi County during 1661 to 1673.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1612, after the founding father Genkitsu died, the Enko-ji Temple, belonging to the Rinzai Sect, was moved to within the premises of the Shokoku-ji Temple and afterwards was relocated to the Shugakuin Village, Otagi County during 1661 to 1673.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1612, after the founding father Genkitsu died, the Enko-ji Temple, belonging to the Rinzai Sect, was moved to within the premises of the Shokoku-ji Temple and afterwards was relocated to the Shugakuin Village, Otagi County during 1661 to 1673.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="10">
<j>伏見版に使用された木活字は、「円光寺由緒書」によれば、家康から拝領したものであったことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description in &quot;Enkoji-yuishogaki (a book written about the history of Enko-ji Temple)&quot;, the wooden type used for Fushimiban was given by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the description in &quot;Enkoji-yuishogaki (a book written about the history of Enko-ji Temple)&quot;, the wooden type used for Fushimiban was given by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the description in &apos;Enkoji-yuishogaki&apos; (a book written about the history of Enko-ji Temple), the wooden type used for Fushimiban was given by Ieyasu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、現にその木活字の一部は、円光寺活字として、寺に伝存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To this day, some of the wooden face canstill be found as the Enko-ji Temple Typeface, and can be found within the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To this day, some of the wooden face is still known as the Enko-ji Temple Typeface, and can be found within the temple.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To this day, some of the wooden face is still known as the Enko-ji Temple Typeface, and can be found within the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>但し、1815年に皆川允が拝借して亡父の遺稿集（『淇園文集』）などを出版した折に、不足の活字を補った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Mitsuru MINAGAWA borrowed the type to print his father&apos;s last work(&quot;Kien-bunshu (Kien writings, Kien is Mitsuru&apos;s father)&quot;) and added more type to recover them..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Mitsuru MINAGAWA borrowed the type to print his father&apos;s last work (&quot;Kien-bunshu (Kien writings, Kien is Mitsuru&apos;s father)&quot;) and added more type to compensate for mssing ones.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in 1815 Mitsuru MINAGAWA borrowed the type to print his father&apos;s last work (&quot;Kien-bunshu&quot; (Kien writings, Kien is Mitsuru&apos;s father)) and added more type to compensate for missing ones.</e>
<cmt>in 1815補足&quot;位置移動スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのために、新旧二種活字が現存することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore there are two types of characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore there are two types of characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore there are two types of characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Yanahan(id:2437), Kzhr(id:131), 遠藤(id:30275), HI(id:72996), D.h(id:79056), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>