<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>水蜘蛛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizugumo (&quot;water spider&quot;, a water-crossing device used by ninja)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizugumo (&quot;water spider&quot;, a water-crossing device used by ninja)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizugumo (&quot;water spider&quot;, a water-crossing device used by ninja)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>水蜘蛛（みずぐも）とは、忍者が用いる道具の1つとして伝えられる、堀や川など水上を渡る際に用いたという忍び道具。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizugumo, &quot;water spider&quot;, was one of the tools used by Ninja for crossing to water such as a moat or a river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizugumo (literally, water spider) was one of the tools used by Ninja for crossing waters, such as moat or river.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizugumo (literally, water spider) was one of the tools used by Ninja for crossing waters, such as moat or river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>伝承されているものは下駄の周囲に4分割された木製の輪上の浮きを縛り付けた履物であることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of Mizugumo handed down are footwear fastened 4 pieces of wooden float in a circle around Geta (Japanese wooden sandals).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of Mizugumo handed down up to the present are footwear, attaching four pieces of wooden float around a geta (Japanese wooden sandal).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of Mizugumo handed down up to the present are footwear, attaching four pieces of wooden float around a geta (Japanese wooden sandal).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>忍者がそれを履いて水面を歩くように渡ったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that Ninja, putting Mizugumo, crossed the surface of the water as if walking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this Mizugumo, it is assumed that Ninja walked on the surface of water as if walking on the ground.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this Mizugumo, it is assumed that Ninja walked on the surface of water as if walking on the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>分割されているのは携帯可能なように折りたたむためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason why wooden float was divided into 4 was that they folded it to be able to carry it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden float was divided into four parts so that they could be easily carried by folding them.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden float was divided into four parts so that they could be easily carried by folding them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>実物もいくつか伝わっているが、実際には履物程度の大きさの木片では浮力が足りず、人間1人を浮かせることは不可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some original Mizugumo are handed down, but it is impossible to float a person because its size is so small such as footwear that buoyancy is insufficient.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some original Mizugumo are handed down, but it is impossible for a person to float with them, as the float from the footwear is too small and thus the buoyancy is insufficient.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some original Mizugumo are handed down, but it is impossible for a person to float with them, as the float from the footwear is too small and thus the buoyancy is insufficient.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また大きく作ったとしても極めてバランスがとりづらく、歩くように渡るためには竿などの補助具が必要となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, even if Mizugumo are made greatly, it is hard to take balance, so using supporting tools such as pole is necessary to cross the water as if walking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, even if Mizugumo are made in a larger size, it is hard to keep a good balance; so it needs some supporting took, such as a walking stick, to walk on the surface of water.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, even if Mizugumo are made in a larger size, it is hard to keep a good balance; so it needs some supporting took, such as a walking stick, to walk on the surface of water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>甲賀の里忍術村主催の「全日本忍者選手権大会」では両足を大きく開かねばならないほどの大型の水蜘蛛を用い、杖を補助として池渡り競技を行なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;All Japan Ninja Championship&apos; organized by Koga-no-sato Ninjutsu-mura (Koga Ninja Village), competitors are required to cross the river using a big Mizugumo as they must open both legs greatly and a pole as supporting tool.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &apos;All Japan Ninja Championship&apos; organized by Koga-no-sato Ninjutsu-mura (Koga Ninja Village), competitors walk with so huge Mizugumo that they have to open their both legs greatly with a stick as a supporting tool.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &apos;All Japan Ninja Championship&apos; organized by Koga-no-sato Ninjutsu-mura (Koga Ninja Village), competitors walk with so huge Mizugumo that they have to open their both legs greatly with a stick as a supporting tool.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>本来はかんじきの様に、足場の不安定な場所を歩くために用いられていた忍具だったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, it is said that Mizugumo was Ninja&apos;s tool used for walk the unstable place of footing such as kanjiki (snow-shoes).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Mizugumo was originally a tool for Ninja to walk unstable surfaces of ground, as kanjiki was (snow-shoes).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Mizugumo was originally a tool for Ninja to walk unstable surfaces of ground, as kanjiki was (snow-shoes).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、浮き輪ほどのサイズで簡易ボートのように用いたものが誤って小さいサイズで伝わったのではないか、という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it is also said that originally its size was about an air bladder, but it was handed down with small size by fault.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, there is a story that the original size was bigger, like a swimming tube, and Mizugumo was used as a potable boat, but the size was wrongly passed down.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, there is a story that the original size was bigger, like a swimming tube, and Mizugumo was used as a potable boat, but the size was wrongly passed down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Afaz(id:64776), Ｋｓ(id:15319), Minor.B(id:152591), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>