<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>相馬御厨</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soma-mikuriya</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya (private estate of Soma ranch)</e>
<cmt>タイトルに補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>相馬御厨（そうまみくりや）は現在の茨城県取手市、守谷市、千葉県柏市、流山市、我孫子市のあたりにあった中世の荘園寄進地系荘園の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya was one of the medieval shoen holdings of the commendation type in areas that are today&apos;s Toride City and Moriya City, Ibaraki Prefecture, and Kashiwa City, Nagareyama City, and Abiko City, Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soma-mikuriya was one of the medieval shoen holdings of the commendation type in areas that are today&apos;s Toride City and Moriya City, Ibaraki Prefecture, and Kashiwa City, Nagareyama City, and Abiko City, Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya was one of the medieval shoen (manor in medieval Japan) holdings of the commendation type in areas that are today&apos;s Toride City and Moriya City, Ibaraki Prefecture, and Kashiwa City, Nagareyama City, and Abiko City, Chiba Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>荘園　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「御厨（みくりや）」は天皇家や伊勢神宮、下鴨神社の領地を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;mikuriya&quot; refers to a territorial land of the Imperial family, the Ise Jingu Shrine, or the Shimogamo Jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;mikuriya&quot; refers to a territorial land of the Imperial family, the Ise Jingu Shrine, or the Shimogamo Jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &apos;mikuriya&apos; refers to a territorial land of the Imperial Family, the Ise-jingu Shrine, or the Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。Ｉse-jingu, Shimogamo-jinja としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>相馬御厨は伊勢神宮の荘園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya was a shoen (manor in medieval Japan) of the Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soma-mikuriya was a shoen (manor in medieval Japan) of the Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya was a shoen of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>荘園　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>千葉常重によって成立した相馬御厨は伊勢神宮に寄進されたが、藤原親通や源義朝から脅かされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya, which was established by Tsuneshige CHIBA, was donated to the Ise Jingu Shrine but threatened by FUJIWARA no Chikamichi and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soma-mikuriya, which was established by Tsuneshige CHIBA, was donated to the Ise Jingu Shrine but threatened by FUJIWARA no Chikamichi and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya, which was established by Tsuneshige CHIBA, was donated to the Ise-jingu Shrine but threatened by FUJIWARA no Chikamichi and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>千葉常胤はこれを回復し、再度伊勢神宮に寄進するが、平家政権になると、佐竹義宗に奪い取られてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetane CHIBA recaptured Soma-mikuriya and donated it again to the Ise Jingu Shrine, but when the Heike government took over the regime, it was captured by Yoshimune SATAKE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetane CHIBA recaptured Soma-mikuriya and donated it again to the Ise Jingu Shrine, but when the Heike government took over the regime, it was captured by Yoshimune SATAKE.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetane CHIBA recaptured Soma-mikuriya and donated it again to the Ise-jingu Shrine, but when the Heike government took over the regime, it was captured by Yoshimune SATAKE.</e>
<cmt>Ise-jingu としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これを奪回するために、千葉常胤は源頼朝を利用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To recapture Soma-mikuriya, Tsunetane CHIBA used MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To recapture Soma-mikuriya, Tsunetane CHIBA used MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To recapture Soma-mikuriya, Tsunetane CHIBA used MINAMOTO no Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>相馬御厨をめぐる攻防が、治承・寿永の乱の原動力の1つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle over Soma-mikuriya served as one of the driving forces for the Jisho-Juei War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle over Soma-mikuriya served as one of the driving forces for the Jisho-Juei War.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle over Soma-mikuriya served as one of the driving forces for the Jisho-Juei War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>相馬御厨は在庁官人が在地領主に変貌していく過程で、国司や目代と激しく対立した事、在地領主層が脆弱な地位を守るために寄進を行った事、寄進による保護にも限界があり、鎌倉幕府の成立へとつながって行った事の例示としてよく取り上げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya is often raised as an exemplary case of: bitter struggles with kokushi (provincial governors) and mokudai (deputy kokushi, or a deputy provincial governor) during the transformation of local officials to local lords in the Heian and Kamakura periods; donation by the local lord classes to defend their vulnerable positions; and the limits of the protection by donation, which led to the establishment of Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>読点で終わる箇条書き文を挟んで主語と述語とが別々の文章に含まれていたため、３文を１文にまとめました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soma-mikuriya is often raised as an exemplary case of: bitter struggles with kokushi (provincial governors) and mokudai (deputy kokushi, or a deputy provincial governor) during the transformation of local officials to local lords in the Heian and Kamakura periods; donation by the local lord classes to defend their vulnerable positions; and the limits of the protection by donation, which led to the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soma-mikuriya is often raised as an exemplary case of: bitter struggles with kokushi (provincial governors) and mokudai (deputy kokushi, or a deputy provincial governor) during the transformation of local officials to local lords; donation by the local lord classes to defend their vulnerable positions; and the limits of the protection by donation, which led to the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>原文になかったため、 in the Heian and Kamakura periods　を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>相馬御厨の成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment of Soma-mikuriya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment of Soma-mikuriya</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment of Soma-mikuriya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>天治元年（1124年）6月、千葉氏の祖である平常重（以下千葉常重）は叔父・相馬五郎平常晴の養子とされ、相馬郡 (下総国)を譲られて、10月には相馬郡司となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1124, TAIRA no Tsuneshige (hereinafter &quot;Tsuneshige Chiba&quot;), who was a founder of the Chiba clan, was adopted by his uncle Goro SOMA, TAIRA no Tsuneharu and given the Soma county, Shimousa Province, and in November 1124, he became Soma gunji (district managers of the Soma county).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1124, TAIRA no Tsuneshige (hereinafter &quot;Tsuneshige Chiba&quot;), who was a founder of the Chiba clan, was adopted by his uncle Goro SOMA, TAIRA no Tsuneharu and given the Soma county, Shimousa Province, and in November 1124, he became Soma gunji (district managers of the Soma county).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1124, TAIRA no Tsuneshige (hereinafter &quot;Tsuneshige CHIBA&quot;), who was a founder of the Chiba clan, was adopted by his uncle Goro SOMA, TAIRA no Tsuneharu and given the Soma county, Shimosa Province, and in November 1124, he became Soma gunji (district managers of the Soma county).</e>
<cmt>Shimousa →　Shimosa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして6年後の大治 (日本)5年（1130年）6月11日、所領の「相馬郡布施郷」を伊勢神宮に寄進し、その下司職となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six years later, he donated his shoryo (territory) &quot;Fuse-go village, Soma county&quot; to the Ise-jingu shrine on July 24, 1130, and became a local official to manage it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six years later, he donated his shoryo (territory) &quot;Fuse-go village, Soma county&quot; to the Ise-jingu shrine on July 24, 1130, and became a local official to manage it.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six years later, he donated his shoryo (territory) &apos;Fuse-go village, Soma county&apos; to the Ise-jingu Shrine on July 24, 1130, and became a local official to manage it.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>その寄進の内容は、以下のようなもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details of the donation are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details of the donation are as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details of the donation are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「地利の上分」（田１段（反）につき1斗5升、畠１段につき5升、当時としてはかなりの高率）と、「土産のもの」（雉100羽、塩曳き鮭100尺）を、伊勢神宮に納める</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Donated to the Ise-jingu shrine were &quot;profits from use of the land,&quot; about 27 liters per 1 tan (an old unit indicating an area of land, which is 991.7 square meters) of a rice field and about 9 liters per 1 tan of a field of crops other than rice, which are significantly high rates for that time), and &quot;local products,&quot; 100 Japanese pheasants and 30.03 meters of salted salmon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Donated to the Ise-jingu shrine were &quot;profits from use of the land,&quot; about 27 liters per a tan (an old unit indicating an area of land, which is 991.7 square meters) of a rice field and about nine liters per a tan of a field of crops other than rice, which are significantly high rates for that time), and &quot;local products,&quot; 100 Japanese pheasants and 30.03 meters of salted salmon.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Donated to the Ise-jingu Shrine were &apos;profits from use of the land,&apos; (about 27 liters per a tan [an old unit indicating an area of land, which is 991.7 square meters] of a rice paddy and about nine liters per a tan of a field of crops other than rice, which are significantly high rates for that time), and &apos;local products,&apos; (100 Japanese pheasants and 30.03 meters of salted salmon).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。括弧内の括弧を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その半分を口入りの神主（領家に相当）・荒木田延明がとり、半分を供祭料の名目で一の禰宜（本家に相当）元親が取る</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuaki ARAKIDA, a mediator Shinto priest (corresponding to ryoke (a lord of the manor)) took a half of the donation, and the other half was taken in the form of offering of money for festivals by the top negi ((one comprehensive term for shrine priests) corresponding to the head) Motochika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuaki ARAKIDA, a mediator Shinto priest (corresponding to ryoke (a lord of the manor)) took half of the donation, and the other half was taken in the form of an offering of money for festivals by the top negi ((one comprehensive term for shrine priests) corresponding to the head) Motochika.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuaki ARAKIDA, a mediator Shinto priest (corresponding to ryoke [a lord of the manor]) took half of the donation, and the other half was taken in the form of an offering of money for festivals by the top negi ([one comprehensive term for shrine priests]; corresponding to the honke [head family]) Motochika.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>在地において仲介の役を果たした散位源友定を「預所」とする</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sani (courtier without post) MINAMOTO no Tomosada, who acted as a mediator in the local land, was appointed to &quot;azukaridokoro&quot; (a deputy of &quot;Shoen&quot; manor lord).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sani (courtier without post) MINAMOTO no Tomosada, who acted as a mediator in the local land, was appointed to &quot;azukaridokoro&quot; (a deputy of &quot;Shoen&quot; manor lord).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sani (courtier without post) MINAMOTO no Tomosada, who acted as a mediator in the local land, was appointed to &apos;azukari-dokoro&apos; (a deputy of shoen).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>常重は下司職となると同時に、「地主」として「田畠の加地子」を取る権利を認められ、常重の下司職と権利は子孫に相伝される</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When becoming the local official, Tsuneshige was permitted a privilege of taking &quot;kajishi&quot; (land rent) of fields of rice and other crops as a &quot;landlord,&quot; and the position of the local official and the privilege of Tsuneshige will be inherited by his descendents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When becoming the local official, Tsuneshige was permitted a privilege of taking &quot;kajishi&quot; (land rent) of fields of rice and other crops as a &quot;landlord,&quot; and the position of the local official and the privilege of Tsuneshige was to be inherited by his descendants.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When becoming the local official, Tsuneshige was permitted a privilege of taking &apos;kajishi&apos; (land rent) of fields of rice and other crops as a &apos;landlord,&apos; and the position of the local official and the privilege of Tsuneshige was to be inherited by his descendants.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この御厨は、同年8月に、下総守（藤原親通）の庁宣によって正式に認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Mikuriya was officially permitted in September 1130 by an official notice from the provincial governor of Shimousa Province, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Mikuriya was officially permitted in September 1130 by an official notice from the provincial governor of Shimousa Province, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Mikuriya was officially permitted in September 1130 by an official notice from the Shimosa no kami (provincial governor of Shimosa Province), FUJIWARA no Chikamichi.</e>
<cmt>下総守　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>下総守藤原親通の横槍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Interference by the provincial governor of Shimousa Province, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Interference by the provincial governor of Shimousa Province, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Interference by the Shimosa no kami, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi</e>
<cmt>下総守　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>これで、「相馬郡布施郷」（大雑把に茨城県北相馬郡）の千葉氏の領有権は確実なものになるはずだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foregoing was supposed to ensure the territorial right of the Chiba clan over the &quot;Fuse-go village, Soma county,&quot; which roughly corresponds to today&apos;s Kitasoma County, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foregoing was supposed to ensure the territorial right of the Chiba clan over the &quot;Fuse-go village, Soma county,&quot; which roughly corresponds to today&apos;s Kitasoma County, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foregoing was supposed to ensure the territorial right of the Chiba clan over the &apos;Fuse-go village, Soma county,&apos; which roughly corresponds to today&apos;s Kitasoma-gun, Ibaraki Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。Kitasoma-gun としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>しかし、保延2年（1136年）7月15日、下総守藤原親通は、相馬郡の公田からの官物が国庫に納入されなかったという理由で常重を逮捕・監禁。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on August 21, 1136, the provincial governor of Shimousa Province, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi arrested Tsuneshige and confined him, for the reason that kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) from koden (field administered directly by a ruler) of the Soma county was not paid to the national treasury.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on August 21, 1136, the provincial governor of Shimousa Province, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi arrested Tsuneshige and confined him, for the reason that kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) from koden (field administered directly by a ruler) of the Soma county was not paid to the national treasury.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on August 21, 1136, Shimosa no kami, FUJIWARA no Chikamichi arrested Tsuneshige and confined him, for the reason that kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) from koden (field administered directly by a ruler) of the Soma county was not paid to the national treasury.</e>
<cmt>下総守　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>それが何年分の未進というのかは不明だが、おそらくは、過去に遡ってのものであったろうといわれる（ただし、領地の囲い込みについては単純に善玉・悪玉とは出来ない面もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown for how many years the unpaid tributes were, but that is said to be probably retrospective (it should be noted, however, that there is an aspect that the enclosure of the estate cannot be judged good or bad simply.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown for how many years the unpaid tributes were, but it is said to be probably retrospective (it should be noted, however, that there is an aspect that the enclosure of the estate cannot be simply judged as good or bad).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown for how many years the unpaid tributes were, but it is said to be probably retrospective (it should be noted, however, that there is an aspect that the enclosure of the estate cannot be simply judged as good or bad).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして、常重から相馬郷・立花郷の両郷を官物に代わりに親通に進呈するという内容の新券（証文）を責め取って、自らの私領としてしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikamichi compelled Tsuneshige and acquired a deed stating that in place of kanmotsu, the Soma-go and Tachibana-go villages were offered to Chikamichi, thereby making the villages his private land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikamichi compelled Tsuneshige and acquired a deed stating that in place of kanmotsu, the Soma-go and Tachibana-go villages were offered to Chikamichi, thereby making the villages his private land.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikamichi compelled Tsuneshige and acquired a deed stating that in place of kanmotsu, the Soma-go and Tachibana-go villages were offered to Chikamichi, thereby making the villages his private land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>源義朝の介入と千葉常胤の反撃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Intervention by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and counterattack by Tsunetane CHIBA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Intervention by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and counterattack by Tsunetane CHIBA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Intervention by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and counterattack by Tsunetane CHIBA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>更に康治2年（1143年）に介入してきたのが源義朝（頼朝の父）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That was MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, the father of Yoritomo, who intervened in 1143.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, the father of Yoritomo, who intervened in 1143.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, the father of Yoritomo, who intervened in 1143.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>義朝はこのころ上総国の上総介常澄の処に居たが、義朝は上総介常澄の「浮言」を利用して、常重から相馬郡（または郷）の避状（さがりじょう：譲状）を責め取る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo, who was at the Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) Tsunezumi&apos;s place in the Kazusa Province at that time, compelled Tsuneshige and acquired an eviction notice, or a letter of transfer, for the Soma-gun village, or Soma-go village, using a &quot;groundless rumor&quot; of Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo, who was at the Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) Tsunezumi&apos;s place in Kazusa Province at the time, compelled Tsuneshige and acquired an eviction notice, or a letter of transfer, for the Soma-gun village, or Soma-go village, using a &quot;groundless rumor&quot; of Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo, who was at the Kazusa no suke (Assistant Governor of Kazusa Province) Tsunezumi&apos;s place in Kazusa Province at the time, compelled Tsuneshige and acquired an eviction notice, or a letter of transfer, for the Soma-gun village, or Soma-go village, using a &apos;groundless rumor&apos; of Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そして、「大庭御厨の濫妨」の翌年の天養2年（1145年）3月、義朝は、その相馬郷を伊勢内宮外宮に寄進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1145, which was the subsequent year of &quot;the disturbance in Obamikuriya estate,&quot; Yoshitomo donated this Soma-go village to the Inner Shrine and the Outer Shrine of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1145, which was the year after &quot;the disturbance in the Obamikuriya estate,&quot; Yoshitomo donated this Soma-go village to the Inner Shrine and the Outer Shrine of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1145, which was the year after &apos;the disturbance in the Obamikuriya estate,&apos; Yoshitomo donated this Soma-go village to the Inner Shrine and the Outer Shrine of the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>その領域は大治5年（1130年）の常重の寄進のときとほぼ同じと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area of the village is believed to be almost the same as that donated by Tsuneshige in 1130.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area of the village is believed to be almost the same as that donated by Tsuneshige in 1130.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area of the village is believed to be almost the same as that donated by Tsuneshige in 1130.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>ただ、このときの源義朝と、常重から相馬郷の新券（証文）を責め取った下総守藤原親通の利害関係はよく判らないが、元木泰雄は下総守藤原親通が摂関家に従属する位置にあったので、大殿・藤原忠実の権威を利用して押さえたと想定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is uncertain, however, what interests MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and the provincial governor of Shimousa Province FUJIWARA no Chikamichi, who compelled Tsuneshige to acquire a deed of the Soma-go village, had at that occasion, but it is inferred that since the provincial governor of Shimousa Province FUJIWARA no Chikamichi was at a position dependent from &quot;Sekkan-ke,&quot; the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, Yasuo MOTOKI contained him using the authority of his head master FUJIWARA no Tadazane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is uncertain, however, what interests MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and the provincial governor of Shimousa Province FUJIWARA no Chikamichi, who compelled Tsuneshige to acquire a deed of the Soma-go village, had at that occasion, but it is inferred that since the provincial governor of Shimousa Province FUJIWARA no Chikamichi was in a position dependent of &quot;Sekkan-ke,&quot; the families which produced the Regent and the Chief Adviser to the Emperor, Yasuo MOTOKI contained him using the authority of his head master FUJIWARA no Tadazane.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is uncertain, however, what interests MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo and the Shimosa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi, who compelled Tsuneshige to acquire a deed of the Soma-go village, had at that occasion, but Yasuo MOTOKI assumes that since the Shimosa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi was in a position dependent of Sekkan-ke (the families which produced the regent and the chief adviser to the Emperor), he captured the mikuriya using the authority of his head master FUJIWARA no Tadazane.</e>
<cmt>元木泰雄～　以降の翻訳を一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="27">
<j>こうした事態に対して常重の子・千葉常胤はそうした事態に必死で立ち向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunetane CHIBA, a son of Tsuneshige, struggled to fight back against such a circumstance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunetane CHIBA, a son of Tsuneshige, struggled to fight back against such a circumstance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunetane CHIBA, a son of Tsuneshige, struggled to fight back against such a circumstance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>久安2年（1146年）4月に、常胤はまず下総国衙から官物未進とされた分について「上品八丈絹参拾疋、下品七拾疋、縫衣拾弐領、砂金参拾弐両、藍摺布上品参拾段、中品五拾段、上馬弐疋、鞍置駄参拾疋」を納め、「其時国司以常胤可令知行郡務」と相馬郡司職を回復した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1146, Tsunetane first paid the unpaid kanmotsu according to Shimousa no Kokuga(local government of Shimousa), which were &quot;30 hiki (1 hiki is with a length of app. 10.6m and width app. 34cm) of high-quality silk cloths, 70 hiki of low-quality silk cloths, 12 ryo (an old unit of a weight) of clothes, 32 ryo of sakin (gold dust), 30 dan (an old unit of an area) of high-quality printed textile dyed with various shades of indigo blue, 50 dan of high-quality medium-quality printed textile dyed with various shades of indigo blue, 2 horses, and 30 saddled horses,&quot; and recovered &quot;其時国司以常胤可令知行郡務&quot; and the position of Soma gunji (district official of Soma).</e>
<cmt>一訳文一原文の例外対処　領→ryo [定訳不明です]　（「両」でしょうか？）; 両→ryo (an old unit of a weight) [定訳不明です], 段→dan (an old unit of an area)[定訳不明です]; 其時国司以常胤可令知行郡務 [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1146, Tsunetane first paid the unpaid kanmotsu according to Shimousa no Kokuga (local government of Shimousa), which was &quot;30 hiki (one hiki is approx. 10.6m in length and approx. 34Cm in width) of high-quality silk cloths, 70 hiki of low-quality silk cloths, 12 ryo (an old unit of a weight) of clothes, 32 ryo of sakin (gold dust), 30 dan (an old unit of area) of high-quality printed textile dyed with various shades of indigo blue, 50 dan of high-quality medium-quality printed textile dyed with various shades of indigo blue, two horses, and 30 saddled horses,&quot; and recovered &quot;其時国司以常胤可令知行郡務&quot; and the position of Soma gunji (district official of Soma).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1146, Tsunetane first paid the unpaid kanmotsu according to Shimosa no kokuga (local government of Shimosa), which was &apos;30 hiki (one hiki is approx. 10.6m in length and approx. 34 cm in width) of high-quality silk cloths, 70 hiki of low-quality silk cloths, 12 ryo (an old unit of a weight) of clothes, 32 ryo of sakin (gold dust), 30 dan (an old unit of area) of high-quality printed textile dyed with various shades of indigo blue, 50 dan of high-quality medium-quality printed textile dyed with various shades of indigo blue, two horses, and 30 saddled horses,&apos; and recovered &apos;其時国司以常胤可令知行郡務&apos; and the position of Soma gunji.</e>
<cmt>Shimousa →　Shimosa としました。&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また相馬郷については「且被裁免畢」と千葉氏のもとへの返却を実現するが、立花郷は戻ってこなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Restitution of the Soma-go village to the Chiba clan was &quot;且被裁免畢&quot; and realized, but the Tachibana-go village was not brought back.</e>
<cmt>一訳文一原文の例外対処　且被裁免畢 [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Restitution of the Soma-go village to the Chiba clan was &quot;且被裁免畢&quot; and realized, but the Tachibana-go village was not brought back.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Restitution of the Soma-go village to the Chiba clan was &apos;且被裁免畢&apos; and realized, but the Tachibana-go village was not brought back.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>立花郷は相馬郷や千葉荘から東に遠く離れた太平洋側にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tachibana-go village was located on the Pacific Ocean and far east from the Soma-go village and Chiba no sho (the private estate of the Chiba clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tachibana-go village was located on the Pacific Ocean and far east from the Soma-go village and Chiba no sho (the private estate of the Chiba clan).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tachibana-go village was located on the Pacific Ocean and far east from the Soma-go village and Chiba no sho (the private estate of the Chiba clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>相馬郡司の地位と相馬郷を回復した常胤は、8月10日、改めて相馬郡（郷？）を伊勢神宮に寄進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having recovered the position of Soma gunji and the Soma-go village, Tsunetane donated the Soma-gun (Soma-go?) village again to the Ise-jingu shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having recovered the position of Soma gunji and the Soma-go village, Tsunetane donated the Soma-gun (Soma-go?) village again to the Ise-jingu shrine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having recovered the position of Soma gunji and the Soma-go village, Tsunetane donated the Soma-gun (presumably, Soma-go) village again to the Ise-jingu Shrine on September 24.</e>
<cmt>? →Presumably としました。Shrine 大文字にしました。月日を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>その寄進状が残っていることから、そこからその間の事情が今に知られることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A letter of the donation is remained, which makes the circumstances during that occasion known to us today.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A letter of the donation remains, which makes the circumstances during that occasion known to us today.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A letter of the donation remains, which makes the circumstances during that occasion known to us today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>すでに天養2年（1145年）3月、義朝による寄進があったが、常胤は「親父常重契状」の通り、領主・荒木田神主正富（伊勢内宮神官）に供祭料を納め、加地子・下司職を常胤の子孫に相伝されることの新券を伊勢神宮へ奉じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the donation was already made by Yoshitomo in April 1145, Tsunetane offered money for festival to the feudal lord Masatomi of the Ise priest family, a Shinto priest of the Ise-naiku (inner shrine), in accordance with &quot;親父常重契状,&quot; and offered to the Ise-jingu shrine a deed stating that kajishi (land rent) and the position of a local official to manage a shoen estate would be inherited by his children and descendants.</e>
<cmt>親父常重契状 [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the donation was already made by Yoshitomo in April 1145, Tsunetane offered money for festivals to the feudal lord Masatomi of the Ise priest family, a Shinto priest of the Ise-naiku (inner shrine), in accordance with &quot;親父常重契状,&quot; and offered the Ise-jingu shrine a deed stating that kajishi (land rent) and the position of a local official to manage a shoen estate would be inherited by his children and descendants.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the donation was already made by Yoshitomo in April 1145, Tsunetane offered money for festivals to the feudal lord Masatomi of the Ise priest family, a Shinto priest of the Ise-naiku (inner shrine), in accordance with &apos;a deed of father Tsuneshige,&apos; and offered the Ise-jingu Shrine a deed stating that kajishi and the position of a local official to manage a shoen estate would be inherited by his children and descendants.</e>
<cmt>親父常重契状→a deed of father Tsuneshige としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>義朝と常胤の寄進の四至</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishi (The northern, southern, eastern, and western boundaries of a tract of land) of the donations of Yoshitomo and Tsunetane</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shishi (the northern, southern, eastern, and western boundaries of a tract of land) of the donations of Yoshitomo and Tsunetane</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shishi (the northern, southern, eastern, and western boundaries of a tract of land) of the donations of Yoshitomo and Tsunetane</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>ところで、このときの「四至」は、それまでの「四至」よりも南に大きく広がっていた形跡がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is evidence that the &quot;Shishi&quot; at that occasion was broader to the south than that in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, there is evidence that the &quot;Shishi&quot; of that occasion was broader to the south than in the past.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, there is evidence that the &apos;Shishi&apos; of that occasion was broader to the south than in the past.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>東西、そして北はそれまでとほぼ同じだが「限南小野上大路」と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the east, the west, and the north remained almost the same as those in the past, &quot;限南小野上大路.&quot;</e>
<cmt>限南小野上大路 [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the east, the west, and the north remained almost the same as those in the past, &quot;限南小野上大路.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the east, the west, and the north remained almost the same as those in the past, &apos;the south boundary is Onogami-oji Street (a road from Hitachi Province).&apos;</e>
<cmt>限南小野上大路→&apos;south boundary is Onogami-oji Street (a road from Hitachi Province).&apos;　としました（定訳不明です）。（参考：http://members.jcom.home.ne.jp/bamen/souke8.htm）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>これは、かつての寄進地が茨城県北相馬郡近辺であったものから、千葉県南相馬郡側に広がり、推定では、東西7km、南北20kmに及ぶ広大な地域となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the land donated in the past was around the Kitasoma-gun County, Ibaraki Prefecture, the area was extended toward the Minamisoma-gun County, Chiba Prefecture, which was presumed to be a broad region of 7 km in the east and the west and 20 km in the north and the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the land donated in the past was around the Kitasoma-gun County, Ibaraki Prefecture, the area was extended toward the Minamisoma-gun County, Chiba Prefecture, which was presumed to be a broad region of 7 km in the east and the west and 20 km in the north and the south.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the land donated in the past was around the Kitasoma-gun, Ibaraki Prefecture, the area was extended toward the Minamisoma-gun, Chiba Prefecture, which was presumed to be a broad region of 7 km in the east and the west and 20 km in the north and the south.</e>
<cmt>County 削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>保延2年（1136年）に受領・下総守藤原親通に郡司職（事実上の領主権）を奪われて以降、常胤一族は必死になってその南部を開発していたのかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the time when the position of gunji (de facto feudal rights) was captured by Zuryo and Shimousa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi, Tsunetane and his family might struggle to develop the southern part.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the time when the position of gunji (de facto feudal rights) was captured by Zuryo and Shimousa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi, Tsunetane and his family struggled to develop the southern part.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the time when the position of gunji (de facto feudal rights) was captured by zuryo (the head of the provincial governors) and Shimosa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi in 1136, Tsunetane and his family were likely to have struggled to develop the southern part.</e>
<cmt>受領　補足を追加しました。1136　追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>いずれにしても、ここに相馬御厨は別の人間から2重に寄進されたことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In any case, this shows the fact of double donation of Soma-mikuriya by different persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In any case, this shows the fact that donation of Soma-mikuriya by different persons occurred twice.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In any case, this shows the fact that donation of Soma-mikuriya by different persons occurred twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="40">
<j>このことから、義朝の行為は紛争の「調停」であったとする見方もあるが、その直後の千葉常胤の寄進状には「源義朝朝臣就于件常時男常澄之浮言、自常重之手、康治二年雖責取圧状之文」とあり、千葉常胤にとっては、源義朝もまた侵略者の一人であることが判る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, there is a point of view that Yoshitomo&apos;s action was &quot;mediation&quot; in the conflict, but since a deed of donation that was prepared by Tsunetane CHIBA immediately thereafter stated &quot;源義朝朝臣就于件常時男常澄之浮言,自常重之手,康治二年雖責取圧状之文,&quot; it can be inferred that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was also an invader for Tsunetane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>源義朝朝臣就于件常時男常澄之浮言、自常重之手、康治二年雖責取圧状之文　[読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, there is a point of view that Yoshitomo&apos;s action was &quot;mediation&quot; in the conflict, but since a deed of donation that was prepared by Tsunetane CHIBA immediately thereafter stated &quot;源義朝朝臣就于件常時男常澄之浮言,自常重之手,康治二年雖責取圧状之文,&quot; it can be inferred that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was also an invader for Tsunetane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, there is a point of view that Yoshitomo&apos;s action was &apos;mediation&apos; in the conflict, but since a deed of donation that was prepared by Tsunetane CHIBA immediately thereafter stated &apos;源義朝朝臣就于件常時男常澄之浮言,自常重之手,康治二年雖責取圧状之文,&apos; it can be inferred that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was also an invader for Tsunetane CHIBA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、野口実編『千葉氏の研究』に収録されている論文「古代末期の東国における開発領主の位置」において、黒田紘一郎は、源義朝はその段階では棟梁などではなく、同じレベルで領地を奪おうとした形跡があると論じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article &quot;Kodaimakki no togoku ni okeru kaihatsuryoshu no ichi&quot; (the Position of kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) in Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region) in the late ancient times) included in &quot;Chibashi no kenkyu&quot; (the Study of the Chiba Clan) edited by Minoru NOGUCHI, Koichiro KURODA discusses that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was not toryo (head of the clan) at that stage, and that there is evidence that he attempted to capture the territory as a person of the same level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article &quot;Kodaimakki no togoku ni okeru kaihatsuryoshu no ichi&quot; (the Position of kaihatsu-ryoshu [local notables who actually developed the land] in Togoku [the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region] in the late ancient times) included in &quot;Chibashi no kenkyu&quot; (the Study of the Chiba Clan) edited by Minoru NOGUCHI, Koichiro KURODA discusses that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was not toryo (head of the clan) at that stage, and that there is evidence that he attempted to capture the territory as a person of the same level.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article &apos;Kodaimakki no togoku ni okeru kaihatsuryoshu no ichi&apos; (the Position of kaihatsu-ryoshu [local notables who actually developed the land] in Togoku [the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region] in the late ancient times) included in &quot;Chibashi no kenkyu&quot; (the Study of the Chiba clan) edited by Minoru NOGUCHI, Koichiro KURODA discusses that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was not toryo (head of the clan) at that stage, and that there is evidence that he attempted to capture the territory as a person of the same level.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>源義朝が相馬御厨を寄進しえたということは、単なる書類上のことだけではなくて、現地での徴税の請負の意味をもっていた以上、事実上の在地支配を離れて可能であったはずはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also discusses that since the fact that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo could donate Soma-mikuriya was not just a piece of paper and indicated a contract of local collection of tax, the donation could not have been made independently from de facto land ruling.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also discusses that since the fact that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo could donate Soma-mikuriya, it was not just a piece of paper and indicated a contract for the local collection of tax, and the donation could not have been made independently from the de facto land ruling.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also discusses that since the fact that MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo could donate Soma-mikuriya, it was not just a piece of paper and indicated a contract for the local collection of tax, and the donation could not have been made independently from the de facto land ruling.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>事実上の支配があって、その支配を法的に保証するのが土地証文、と考えるべきだとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He further discusses that it should be understood that there was de fact domination and an act and a deed for land is to legally guarantee the domination.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He further discusses that it should be understood that there was a de facto domination and an act and a deed for land to legally guarantee the domination.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He further discusses that it should be understood that there was a de facto domination and an act and a deed for land to legally guarantee the domination.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="44">
<j>その後、千葉常胤と源義朝の間でどういう決着を見たのかは不明であるが、保元の乱では千葉常胤は源義朝の率いる関東の兵の中に、上総介常澄の子広常とともに名が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is unknown how Tsunetane CHIBA and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo were settled thereafter, but Tsunetane CHIBA&apos;s name appears, together with Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi&apos;s son Hirotsune, in the Kanto forces led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is unknown how Tsunetane CHIBA and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo were settled thereafter, but Tsunetane CHIBA&apos;s name appears, together with Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi&apos;s son Hirotsune, in the Kanto forces led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is unknown how Tsunetane CHIBA and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo were settled thereafter, but Tsunetane CHIBA&apos;s name appears, together with Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi&apos;s son Hirotsune, in the Kanto forces led by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo in the Hogen War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このことから、千葉常胤が、源義朝の傘下に入ることによって千葉常胤は領地の保全を図ったとの見方も可能である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is also possible to infer that Tsunetane CHIBA was affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo in an attempt to maintain his territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is also possible to infer that Tsunetane CHIBA was affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo in an attempt to maintain his territory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is also possible to infer that Tsunetane CHIBA was affiliated with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo in an attempt to maintain his territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="46">
<j>また、上総権介常澄の子で上総広常の弟に相馬九郎常清がおり、源義朝の寄進した旧来の相馬御厨（北相馬）と、千葉常胤が寄進したときに追加され、かつ千葉氏庶流の名字の地の多い南相馬とが、それぞれ分割支配されて、上総権介常澄の子・相馬九郎常清が源義朝支配地を管理していた可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there was Kuro Tsunekiyo SOMA, who was a son of Kazusa no Gon no suke (provisional assistant governor of the Kazusa province) Tsunezumi and a younger brother of Hirotsune, and there is a possibility that the old Soma-mikuriya (Kitasoma (northern Soma)), which was donated by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, and Minamisoma (southern Soma), which was added when Tsunetane CHIBA made the donation and include many regions with surnames of branch families of the Chiba clan, were separately dominated, and that Kazusa no Gon no suke Tsunezumi&apos;s son Kuro Tsunekiyo SOMA administered MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s regions of influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, there was Kuro Tsunekiyo SOMA, who was a son of Kazusa no Gon no suke (provisional assistant governor of Kazusa province) Tsunezumi and a younger brother of Hirotsune, and there is a possibility that the old Soma-mikuriya (Kitasoma (northern Soma)), which was donated by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, and Minamisoma (southern Soma), which was added when Tsunetane CHIBA made the donation and included many regions with surnames of branch families of the Chiba clan, were separately dominated, and that Kazusa no Gon no suke Tsunezumi&apos;s son Kuro Tsunekiyo SOMA administered MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s regions of influence.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, there was Kuro Tsunekiyo SOMA, who was a son of Kazusa no gon no suke (provisional assistant governor of Kazusa Province) Tsunezumi and a younger brother of Hirotsune KAZUSA, and there is a possibility that the old Soma-mikuriya (Kitasoma [northern Soma]), which was donated by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, and Minamisoma (southern Soma), which was added when Tsunetane CHIBA made the donation and included many regions with surnames of branch families of the Chiba clan, were separately dominated, and that Kazusa no gon no suke Tsunezumi&apos;s son Kuro Tsunekiyo SOMA administered MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo&apos;s regions of influence.</e>
<cmt>Province 大文字にしました。Kazusa no gon no suke と小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>例えば、後に佐竹義宗が強引に相馬御厨全域を支配したとき、その『源義宗寄進状』には「常澄常胤等何故可成妨哉、是背法令、大非常之上、大謀叛人前下野守義朝朝臣年来郎従等　凡不可在王土者也」と、上総介常澄、千葉介常胤、が共に反抗していることが伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, when later Yoshimune SATAKE aggressively dominated the entire region of Soma-mikuriya, he stated in &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshimune&apos;s letter of donation&quot; that &quot;常澄常胤等何故可成妨哉,是背法令,大非常之上,大謀叛人前下野守義朝朝臣年来郎従等 凡不可在王土者也,&quot; indicating that Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi and Chiba no suke Tsunetane both rebelled.</e>
<cmt>常澄常胤等何故可成妨哉、是背法令、大非常之上、大謀叛人前下野守義朝朝臣年来郎従等　凡不可在王土者也 [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, when Yoshimune SATAKE aggressively dominated the entire region of Soma-mikuriya later, he stated in &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshimune&apos;s letter of donation&quot; that &quot;常澄常胤等何故可成妨哉,是背法令,大非常之上,大謀叛人前下野守義朝朝臣年来郎従等 凡不可在王土者也,&quot; indicating that Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi and Chiba no suke Tsunetane both rebelled.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, when Yoshimune SATAKE aggressively dominated the entire region of Soma-mikuriya later, he stated in &quot;MINAMOTO no Yoshimune&apos;s letter of donation&quot; that &apos;常澄常胤等何故可成妨哉,是背法令,大非常之上,大謀叛人前下野守義朝朝臣年来郎従等 凡不可在王土者也,&apos; indicating that Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi and Chiba no suke Tsunetane both rebelled.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→ &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>開発領主の位置</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Position of kaihatsu-ryoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Position of kaihatsu-ryoshu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Position of kaihatsu-ryoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="48">
<j>この事件は、当時における在庁官人＝開発領主の変貌と、国司＝目代との対立の激しさ、とくに在地領主層の弱体と限界を如実に示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These affairs provide evidence of changes of zaichokanjin to kaihatsu-ryoshu and fierce conflicts between kokushi and mokudai, especially the local lord class&apos;s destabilization and limitations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These affairs provide evidence of changes of zaichokanjin to kaihatsu-ryoshu and fierce conflicts between kokushi and mokudai, especially the local lord class&apos;s destabilization and limitations.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These affairs provide evidence of changes of zaichokanjin to kaihatsu-ryoshu and fierce conflicts between kokushi and mokudai, especially the local lord class&apos;s destabilization and limitations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>まず、開発領主の領地領有とは、郡司、郷司という、役職において国衙から保証されたものだということ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, possession of a territory by kaihatsu-ryoshu was guaranteed by kokuga in association with the positions such as gunji and goji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, possession of a territory by kaihatsu-ryoshu was guaranteed by kokuga in association with the positions such as gunji and goji.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, possession of a territory by kaihatsu-ryoshu was guaranteed by kokuga in association with the positions such as gunji and goji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし、それが、郡司、郷司という、役職において保証されたものである限り、国司側はその任を解く権限を持っており、それは相馬郡において現実に行使された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since such possession was guaranteed in association with the positions such as gunji and goji, kokushi had a right to dismiss, which was in fact executed in the Soma-go village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since such possession was guaranteed in association with the positions such as gunji and goji, kokushi had a right to dismiss, which was in fact executed in the Soma-go village.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since such possession was guaranteed in association with the positions such as gunji and goji, kokushi had a right to dismiss, which was in fact executed in the Soma-go village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>更にその周囲には、他の開発領主が、隙あらばと狙っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, other kaihatsu-ryoshu around the regions were watching for a chance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, other kaihatsu-ryoshu around the regions were watching for a chance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, other kaihatsu-ryoshu around the regions were watching for a chance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>最初の段階では同族の上総介常澄、そして源義朝である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early stage was Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi of the same family, followed by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early stage was Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi of the same family, followed by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early stage was Kazusa no suke Tsunezumi of the same family, followed by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そして後には平家の権力を背景に、佐竹氏がその争奪戦に加わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the power of the Taira family, the Satake clan later took part in the scrambles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the power of the Taira family, the Satake clan later took part in the scrambles.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the power of the Taira family, the Satake clan later took part in the scrambles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>安定な状態を、確実なものにしようと、荘園の寄進を行うが、その段階で、自分の直接支配地だけでなく、郷の単位ぐらいに、周辺の公領も切り取って規模を拡大して立荘する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Donation of shoen was made to secure its stable state, and at this occasion, the area of the shoen was defined by inclusion of not only his regions of direct influence but also nearby public land cut off by about a village unit to increase the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A donation of shoen was made to secure its stable state, and on this occasion, the area of the shoen was defined by inclusion of not only their regions of direct influence but also nearby public land cut off by about a village unit to increase the area.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A donation of shoen was made to secure its stable state, and on this occasion, the area of the shoen was defined by inclusion of not only their regions of direct influence but also nearby public land cut off by about a village unit to increase the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>それは、根本私領だけでなく、郡司としての自分の支配、取り分を固定化しようとする行為と考えると解しやすい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is easy to understand if considered as an action to stabilize not only his original private land but also his domination and share as gunji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is easy to understand if considered as an action to stabilize not only their original private land but also their domination and share as gunji.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is easy to understand if considered as an action to stabilize not only their original private land but also their domination and share as gunji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>しかしその荘園寄進も、それだけで確実なものではないことは、この相馬御厨、そして大庭御厨の事件の中からも見てとれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is obvious from this affairs of Soma-mikuriya, and also affairs of Oba no mikuriya (private estate of Oba ranch), such domination of shoen was not sufficient to ensure the guarantee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is obvious from these affairs of Soma-mikuriya, and also affairs of Oba no mikuriya (private estate of Oba ranch), such domination of shoen was not sufficient to ensure the guarantee.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is obvious from these affairs of Soma-mikuriya, and also affairs of Oba no mikuriya (private estate of Oba ranch), such domination of shoen was not sufficient to ensure the guarantee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>相馬御厨も大庭御厨も、本所の伊勢神宮は必ずしも下司となった寄進主（開発領主）を保護出来きれなかった、自分の取り分が確保され、更には増えるのなら、下司職が、源義朝でも、千葉常胤でも構わなかったということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That indicates that honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) Ise-jingu shrine could not always protect donators, or kaihatsu-ryoshu, who became their local official, and rather, it did not matter to them whether the position of the local official was held by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo or Tsunetane CHIBA, as long as their share was guaranteed and, even more, increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That indicates that honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) Ise-jingu shrine could not always protect donators, or kaihatsu-ryoshu, who became their local official, and rather, it did not matter to them whether the position of the local official was held by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo or Tsunetane CHIBA, as long as their share was guaranteed and, even more, increased.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That indicates that honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) Ise-jingu Shrine could not always protect donators, or kaihatsu-ryoshu, who became their local official, and rather, it did not matter to them whether the position of the local official was held by MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo or Tsunetane CHIBA, as long as their share was guaranteed and, even more, increased.</e>
<cmt>Shrine 大文字としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>平家政権下での更なる不安定さ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Increased instability under the Heike government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Increased instability under the Heike government</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Increased instability under the Heike government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="58">
<j>その不安定さは、平治の乱以降、いよいよ高まったというのが、その後の平家側佐竹義宗の相馬御厨寄進として現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The donation of Soma-mikuriya by Yoshimune SATAKE, who was on the side of the Taira family, thereafter indicates the increasing instability since the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The donation of Soma-mikuriya by Yoshimune SATAKE, who was on the side of the Taira family, thereafter indicates the increasing instability since the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The donation of Soma-mikuriya by Yoshimune SATAKE, who was on the side of the Taira family, thereafter indicates the increasing instability since the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>永暦 (日本)2年（1161年)正月日の佐竹義宗の寄進状には、以下のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yoshimune SATAKE&apos;s letter of donation dated February 1161 states as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimune SATAKE&apos;s letter of donation dated February 1161 states as follows.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimune SATAKE&apos;s letter of donation dated February 1161 states as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>自国人平常晴今常澄父也、手譲平常重并嫡男常胤、依官物負累、譲国司藤原親通朝臣、彼朝臣譲二男親盛朝臣、而依匝瑳北条之由緒、以当御厨公験、所譲給義宗也、然者父常晴長譲渡他人畢所也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">自国人平常晴今常澄父也,手譲平常重并嫡男常胤,依官物負累,譲国司藤原親通朝臣,彼朝臣譲二男親盛朝臣,而依匝瑳北条之由緒,以当御厨公験,所譲給義宗也,然者父常晴長譲渡他人畢所也.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">自国人平常晴今常澄父也,手譲平常重并嫡男常胤,依官物負累,譲国司藤原親通朝臣,彼朝臣譲二男親盛朝臣,而依匝瑳北条之由緒,以当御厨公験,所譲給義宗也,然者父常晴長譲渡他人畢所也.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">自国人平常晴今常澄父也,手譲平常重并嫡男常胤,依官物負累,譲国司藤原親通朝臣,彼朝臣譲二男親盛朝臣,而依匝瑳北条之由緒,以当御厨公験,所譲給義宗也,然者父常晴長譲渡他人畢所也.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="61">
<j>しかし、実際には「所譲給義宗也」ではなく、ここでも奪いとったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, however, the land was not &quot;所譲給義宗也&quot; but was, again, captured.</e>
<cmt>所譲給義宗也 [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, however, the land was not &quot;所譲給義宗也&quot; but was, again, captured.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, however, the land was not &apos;given to Yoshimune,&apos; but was, again, captured by him.</e>
<cmt>漢字、文脈より想定し、所譲給義宗也→given to Yoshimune としました（定訳不明です）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>その後、実際には佐竹義宗が前下総守藤原親通が持っていた新券（証文）を親通の次男・藤原親盛 (下総守)から入手したものであり、これに基づいた寄進であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact was that Yoshimune SATAKE obtained a deed that the former Shimousa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi had, from Chikamichi&apos;s second son FUJIWARA no Chikamori, who was Shimousa no kami, and the donation was based on the deed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact was that Yoshimune SATAKE obtained a deed that the former Shimousa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi had, from Chikamichi&apos;s second son FUJIWARA no Chikamori, who was Shimousa no kami, and the donation was based on the deed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact was that Yoshimune SATAKE obtained a deed that the former Shimosa no kami FUJIWARA no Chikamichi had, from Chikamichi&apos;s second son FUJIWARA no Chikamori, who was Shimosa no kami, and the donation was based on the deed.</e>
<cmt>Shimousa →　Shimosa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>これを知った常胤も翌2月に再度伊勢神宮に寄進の意向を示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After learning this, Tsunetane expressed again in March 1161 to the Ise-jingu shrine his willingness to donate the land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After learning this, Tsunetane expressed again in March 1161 to the Ise-jingu shrine his willingness to donate the land.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After learning this, Tsunetane expressed again in March 1161 to the Ise-jingu Shrine his willingness to donate the land.</e>
<cmt>Shrine 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これまでの経緯からすれば、この新券は既に久安2年の時点で無効になったと考えられるが、親盛の娘は平重盛の側室であり、平氏側の支援を期待して提示したとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the past history, it is considered that the deed was already invalidated in 1146, but it is also considered that since Chikamori&apos;s daughter was a concubine of TAIRA no Shigemori, the deed was presented in an expectation of support from the Taira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the past history, it is considered that the deed was already invalidated in 1146, but it is also considered that since Chikamori&apos;s daughter was a concubine of TAIRA no Shigemori, the deed was presented in an expectation of support from the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the past history, it is considered that the deed was already invalidated in 1146, but it is also considered that since Chikamori&apos;s daughter was a concubine of TAIRA no Shigemori, the deed was presented in an expectation of support from the Taira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>このため、伊勢神宮側では常胤側の領主となっていた禰宜荒木田明盛（正富の一族）と義宗側の領主となっていた禰宜度会彦章の対立が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resulted in a conflict between Negi (one comprehensive term for shrine priests (shinshoku)) Akimori ARAKIDA, who was a member of the Masatomi&apos;s family and a feudal lord on the Tsunetane&apos;s side, and Negi Hikoaki WATARAI, who was a feudal lord on the Yoshimune&apos;s side, in the Ise-jingu shrine.</e>
<cmt>度会彦章→Hikoaki WATARAI [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted in a conflict between Negi (one comprehensive term for shrine priests (shinshoku)) Akimori ARAKIDA, who was a member of the Masatomi family and a feudal lord on Tsunetane&apos;s side, and Negi Hikoaki WATARAI, who was a feudal lord on Yoshimune&apos;s side, in the Ise-jingu shrine.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted in a conflict between the negi Akimori ARAKIDA, who was a member of the Masatomi family and a feudal lord on Tsunetane&apos;s side, and the negi Hikoaki WATARAI, who was a feudal lord on Yoshimune&apos;s side, in the Ise-jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Shrine 大文字にしました。禰宜　既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>その後、義宗が伊勢神宮に供祭料を負担して寄進状の約束を果たしたことが評価され、長寛元年（1163年）に義宗の寄進を是とする宣旨が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Yoshimune&apos;s donation of money for festivals to the Ise-jingu shrine to fulfill the promise of the letter of donation was appreciated, and an imperial decree was issued in 1163 to approve the Yoshimune&apos;s donation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Yoshimune&apos;s donation of money for festivals to the Ise-jingu shrine to fulfill the promise of the letter of donation was appreciated, and an imperial decree was issued in 1163 to approve Yoshimune&apos;s donation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Yoshimune&apos;s donation of money for festivals to the Ise-jingu Shrine to fulfill the promise of the letter of donation was appreciated, and an imperial decree was issued in 1163 to approve Yoshimune&apos;s donation.</e>
<cmt>Shrine 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>続いて永万2年6月18日に明盛から彦章に彦章の主張を認める事を示す契状を提出、仁安 (日本)2年6月14日付で和与状が作成された（『檪木文書』「仁安二年六月十四日付皇太神宮権祢宜荒木田明盛和与状」（『平安遺文』第7巻3425号所収））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on July 23, 1166, Akimori submitted to Hikoaki a deed to accept Hikoaki&apos;s assertion, and a composition deed was made on July 9, 1167 (&quot;The Kunugi Documents,&quot; &quot;Composition deed of Kotai jingu shrine Gonnegi (assistant senior priests) Akimori ARAKIDA dated July 9, 1167&quot; (printed in &quot;Heian ibun&quot; (Documents of the Heian Period), Vol. 7, No. 3425)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on July 23, 1166, Akimori submitted to Hikoaki a deed to accept Hikoaki&apos;s assertion, and a composition deed was made on July 9, 1167 (&quot;The Kunugi Documents,&quot; &quot;Composition deed of Kotai jingu shrine Gonnegi (assistant senior priests) Akimori ARAKIDA dated July 9, 1167&quot; (printed in &quot;Heian ibun&quot; (Documents of the Heian Period), Vol. 7, No. 3425)).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on July 23, 1166, Akimori submitted to Hikoaki a deed to accept Hikoaki&apos;s assertion, and a compromise deed was made on July 9, 1167 (&quot;The Kunugi Documents,&quot; &apos;Compromise deed of Kotai-jingu Shrine Gonnegi [assistant senior priests] Akimori ARAKIDA dated July 9, 1167,&apos; printed in &quot;Heian ibun&quot; [Documents of the Heian period], Vol. 7, No. 3425).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を変更しました。和与状→a compromise deed としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>当時において和与とは、合意に基づく所領や所職等権利の譲与を指しており、和与に基づく権利の移転は悔返を認めない法理（『法曹至要抄』）が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, a compromise indicated a consensus transfer of a right such as a territory and a position, and there was doctrine that did not allow Kuikaeshi (a right of claim for return in the Middle Ages&apos; Law) with respect to a consensus transfer of a right (&quot;Hossoshiyosho&quot; (The Essentials for the Judiciary)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a compromise indicated a consensus transfer of a right, such as territory or position, and there was doctrine that did not allow Kuikaeshi (a right of claim for return in the Middle Ages&apos; Law) with respect to a consensus transfer of a right (&quot;Hossoshiyosho&quot; (The Essentials for the Judiciary)).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a compromise indicated a consensus transfer of a right, such as territory or position, and there was doctrine that did not allow Kuikaeshi (a right of claim for return in the Middle Ages&apos; Law) with respect to a consensus transfer of a right (&quot;Hosso shiyosho&quot; [The Essentials for the Judiciary]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この和与によって荒木田明盛から権利一切を譲られた度会彦章による相馬御厨における伊勢神宮側の領主としての地位が確定したため、彼が下司とした佐竹義宗の勝訴が確定することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the position of Hikoaki WATARAI, who was given all rights from Akimori ARAKIDA by the compromise, was established, the winning of Yoshimune SATAKE, who was appointed as Hikoaki&apos;s local official, was determined.</e>
<cmt>度会彦章→Hikoaki WATARAI [読み方不明です]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the position of Hikoaki WATARAI, who was given all the rights from Akimori ARAKIDA by the compromise, was established, the winning of Yoshimune SATAKE, who was appointed as Hikoaki&apos;s local official, was determined.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the position of Hikoaki WATARAI, who was given all the rights from Akimori ARAKIDA by the compromise, was established, the winning of Yoshimune SATAKE, who was appointed as Hikoaki&apos;s local official, was determined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="70">
<j>佐竹氏と、千葉介、上総介一族との対立はここに始まり、それが解消するのは、治承4年（1180年）の源頼朝の旗揚げに、千葉介、上総介一族が合流し、富士川の戦いで平家を破ったあと、転じて佐竹氏を攻めて敗走させたときである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict between the Satake clan and the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke started there, and was solved when the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke joined MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s raising of army in 1180, defeated the Taira family at the Battle of Fujigawa, and then attacked the Satake clan to put them to flight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict between the Satake clan and the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke started there, and was solved when the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke joined MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s raising of an army in 1180, defeated the Taira family at the Battle of Fujigawa, and then attacked the Satake clan to put them to flight.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict between the Satake clan and the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke started there, and was solved when the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke joined MINAMOTO no Yoritomo&apos;s raising of an army in 1180, defeated the Taira family at the Battle of Fujigawa, and then attacked the Satake clan to put them to flight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="71">
<j>千葉介、上総介一族が、頼朝に加担したのは、『吾妻鏡』にいうような、両氏が累代の源氏の郎等であったからではなく、平家と結んだ下総の藤原氏、そして常陸の佐竹氏の侵攻に対して、頼朝を担ぐことによってそれを押し返し、奪い取られた自領を復活する為の起死回生の掛けであったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the reason why the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke joined Yoritomo was not because they were followers of the generations of the Genji family as stated in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), and they supported Yoritomo to fight back against the attacks by the Fujiwara clan of Shimousa, who was aligned with the Taira family, and the Satake clan of Hitachi in an attempt to recover their lost territories, which was a revival gamble.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the reason why the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke joined Yoritomo was not because they were followers of the generations of the Genji family as stated in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), and they supported Yoritomo to fight back against the attacks by the Fujiwara clan of Shimousa, who was aligned with the Taira family, and the Satake clan of Hitachi in an attempt to recover their lost territories, which was a revival gamble.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the reason why the families of Chiba no suke and Kazusa no suke joined Yoritomo was not because they were followers of the generations of the Genji family as stated in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East); rather, they supported Yoritomo to fight back against the attacks by the Fujiwara clan of Shimosa, who was aligned with the Taira family, and the Satake clan of Hitachi in an attempt to recover their lost territories, which was a revival gamble.</e>
<cmt>and they supported →; rather, they supported　としました。Shimousa →　Shimosa としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>特に千葉常胤にとっては、源義朝は「御恩」を感じるような相手ではないことは相馬御厨での経緯を見れば明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is obvious from the history of Soma-mikuriya that especially for Tsunetane CHIBA, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was not someone to feel an obligation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is obvious from the history of Soma-mikuriya that especially for Tsunetane CHIBA, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was not someone he felt obligated to.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is obvious from the history of Soma-mikuriya that especially for Tsunetane CHIBA, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was not someone he felt &apos;obligated to.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 長島左近(id:161003), Ktmchi(id:113301), Point136(id:211299), Otherde(id:205526), Andee(id:20421), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>