<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>切捨御免</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirisute gomen (a privilege granted to samurai warriors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirisute gomen (a privilege granted to samurai warriors)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirisute gomen (a privilege granted to samurai warriors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>切捨御免（きりすてごめん・斬捨御免）とは苗字帯刀と並ぶ江戸時代の武士の特権である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirisute gomen, as well as the rights to bear a surname and to wear a sword, is one of warrior&apos;s priiviledge in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirisute gomen, as well as the rights to bear a surname and to wear a sword, is one of a warrior&apos;s privileges in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirisute gomen, as well as the rights to bear a surname and to wear a sword, is one of a warrior&apos;s privileges in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>別名を無礼討とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;burei-uchi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Ok</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>統一用語</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>近世において武士が町人・百姓らから耐え難い無礼を受けた時は、斬殺しても処罰されない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In modern ages, when a worrior put townspeople or farmers to a sword because he was unbearably insulted by them, he was not punished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In modern ages, when a warrior put townspeople or farmers to a sword because he was unbearably insulted by them, he was not punished.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In modern ages, when a warrior put townspeople or farmers to a sword because he was unbearably insulted by them, he was not punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これは当時の江戸幕府の法律である『公事方御定書』71条追加条によって明記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was clearly written in the additional condition of Article 71 of &quot;Kujigata-osadamegaki (the law of Edo bakufu)&quot;, the law decided by Edo Bakufu in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was clearly written in the additional condition of Article 71 of &quot;Kujigata-osadamegaki&quot; (the law of Edo bakufu), the law decided by the Edo Bakufu in those days.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was clearly written in the additional condition of Article 71 of &quot;Kujigata-osadamegaki&quot; (the law of Edo bakufu), the law decided by the Edo Bakufu in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、無礼な行為によって武士の名誉が傷つけられる事を制止するための正当防衛的な行為と認識されており、無礼を働いた事自体への処罰ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered as a sort of justifiable defense to protect the honor of warriors and it did not mean a punishment to the insult itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was considered a type of justifiable defense to protect the honor of warriors and it did not mean a punishment to the insult itself.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was considered a type of justifiable defense to protect the honor of warriors and it did not mean a punishment to the insult itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>近代以前のヨーロッパの法律や近代法体系において、名誉の侵害に対する正当防衛は認められない、あるいは法益均衡の観点から生命の侵害をもって報いることは認められないと解されるのが通説（ただし、近代以前には決闘による名誉回復はあり得た）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the commonly accepted theory, before modern ages in Europe, any justifiable defense or requirement of life to protect the honor was not accepted from the viewpoint of legal equilibrium. (However, before modern ages, redeeming one&apos;s honor by dueling was possible.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the commonly accepted theory, before modern ages in Europe, any justifiable defense or requirement of life to protect one&apos;s honor was not accepted from the viewpoint of legal equilibrium. (However, before modern ages, redeeming one&apos;s honor by dueling was possible).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the commonly accepted theory, under laws that predate the modern age in Europe and modern legislation, justifiable defense or violation of the sanctity of life in order to protect one&apos;s honor was not accepted from the viewpoint of legal equilibrium. (Before the modern age, however, it was possible to redeem one&apos;s honor by dueling.)</e>
<cmt>「近代以前のヨーロッパの法律や近代法体系において」の訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これに対して日本の切捨御免には支配階層である武士の名誉と威厳を守る事によって武士を頂点とした当時の社会秩序が防衛されると考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, it was considered that helping to protect warriors&apos; honor and diginity by Japanese Kirisutegomen keep the social order, of which warriors were at the top.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, it was considered that helping to protect warriors&apos; honor and dignity by Japanese Kirisutegomen kept the social order, of which warriors were at the top.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it was considered that helping to protect warriors&apos; honor and dignity by Japanese Kirisutegomen kept the social order, of which warriors were at the top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>こうした観点より切捨御免が認められていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Kirisutegomen was admitted from that viewpoint.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Kirisutegomen was admitted from that viewpoint.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Kirisutegomen was admitted from that viewpoint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>あくまでも正当防衛の一環であると認識されているため、結果的に相手が死ぬことはあってもとどめを刺さないのが通例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it should be a sort of justifiable defense, usually warriors did not give the finishing blow to his contemnor(s) although the latter would die eventualy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was a type of justifiable defense, usually warriors did not give the finishing blow to his offender(s), although the latter would die eventually.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was a type of justifiable defense, usually warriors did not give the finishing blow to his offender(s), although the latter would die eventually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また無礼な行為とそれに対する切捨御免は連続している必要があり、以前行われた無礼を蒸し返しての切捨御免は処罰の対象となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kirisutegomen should be done immediately to an offenseful act and Kirisutegomen to an offenseful act that had been done before was punished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kirisutegomen should be done immediately to an offensive act and Kirisutegomen to an offensive act that had been done before was punished.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kirisutegomen should be done immediately to an offensive act and Kirisutegomen to an offensive act that had been done before was punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>切捨後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After killing contemnor(s) with a blade</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After killing offenders with a blade</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After killing offenders with a blade</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>斬った後は速やかに役所に届出を行うこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After killing contemnor(s) with a blade, the warrior should immediately report that to an office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After killing an offender with a blade, the warrior should immediately report it to an office.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After killing an offender with a blade, the warrior should immediately report it to an office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>どのような事情があったにせよ、人一人切った責任の重みゆえ、二十日以上に及ぶ自宅謹慎を申し付けられること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The warrior had to take responsibility of killing one person no matter what circumstances he faced, and he was ordered to stay at home for more than twenty days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The warrior had to take responsibility for killing someone regardless of what circumstances he faced, and he was ordered to stay at home for more than twenty days.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The warrior had to take responsibility for killing someone regardless of what circumstances he faced, and he was ordered to stay at home for more than twenty days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>斬った刀は、詮議に使う証拠品として検分のため一時押収されること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The blade used for killing was temporarily confiscated as the evidence for the investigation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The blade used for killing was temporarily confiscated as evidence for the investigation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The blade used for killing was temporarily confiscated as evidence for the investigation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>無礼な行為とそれに対する正当性を立証する証人も必要とされる</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An offenseful act had to be proven and a witness to prove it was required.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An offensive act had to be proven and a witness to prove it was required.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An offensive act had to be proven and a witness to prove it was required.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>など、適用の条件は厳格であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like this, the conditions for application were strict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Like this, the conditions for application were strict.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Like this, the conditions for application were strict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>証人がいないなど、切捨御免として認定されない場合、その武士は処分を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the killing was not admitted as Kirisutegomen, for example, because of the absense of a witness, the warrior was punished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the killing was not admitted as Kirisutegomen, for example, because of the absence of a witness, the warrior was punished.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the killing was not admitted as Kirisutegomen, for example, because of the absence of a witness, the warrior was punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>最悪、武士としたまま名誉の死を遂げる切腹も申し付けられず斬首刑を受け、お家断絶の可能性もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the worst case, the warrior was not given Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), the honorable death for warriors, but was beheaded and there was a possibility of Oie-danzetsu (dissociation of the family line),</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the worst case, the warrior was not given Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), the honorable death for warriors, but was beheaded and there was a possibility of Oie-danzetsu (disassociation from the family line).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the worst case, the warrior was not given Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment), the honorable death for warriors, but was beheaded and there was a possibility of Oie-danzetsu (disassociation from the family line).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため本人謹慎中は家人及び郎党など家来・仲間が証人を血眼になって探した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, while the worrier himself stayed at home, his family, servants and fellows looked for a witness desperately.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, while the warrior himself stayed at home, his family, servants and fellows looked for a witness desperately.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, while the warrior himself stayed at home, his family, servants and fellows looked for a witness desperately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>見つかりそうにない場合、体面を保つために評定の沙汰（裁判）を待たずして自ら切腹する者が絶えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When it was unlikely to find a witness, a lot of warriors killed themselves by disembowelment to keep their honor without waiting for the result of consultation (trial).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When it was unlikely to find a witness, a lot of warriors killed themselves by disembowelment to keep their honor without waiting for the result of consultation (trial).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When it was unlikely to find a witness, a lot of warriors killed themselves by disembowelment to keep their honor without waiting for the result of consultation (trial).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>無礼討のために刀を抜いたが、相手に逃亡された場合なども武士の不名誉とされ処罰の対象であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a warrior pulled his sword out for Bureiuchi but thecontemnor ran away, the warrior was punished because his deed was considered warriors&apos; dishonor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a warrior pulled his sword out for Bureiuchi but the offender ran away, the warrior was punished because his deed was considered a warrior&apos;s dishonor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a warrior pulled his sword out for Bureiuchi but the offender ran away, the warrior was punished because his deed was considered a warrior&apos;s dishonor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、上意討ち・無礼打ちに理不尽を感じた者は、両者にどのような身分差があれど（たとえ上司であっても）、脇差でならたとえ殺すことになっても刃向かうことも許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any person who felt Joiuchi (kill of offender) or Bureiuchi (kill of dishonor) outrageousness was allowed to fight against or even kill his enemy using a short sword however overcoming their status distinctions were (even the enemy was his superior).</e>
<cmt>無礼打ちの定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any person who felt Joiuchi (kill of offender) or Bureiuchi (kill of dishonor) outrageousness was allowed to fight against or even kill his enemy using a short sword however overcoming their status distinctions were (even the enemy was his superior).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any person who felt Joiuchi (kill of offender) or Bureiuchi (kill of dishonor) outrageousness was allowed to fight against or even kill his enemy using a short sword however overcoming their status distinctions were (even the enemy was his superior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>むしろ討たれる者が士分の場合、何も抵抗せずにただ無礼打ちされた場合は、国家鎮護守・外敵制征圧（軍事警察力）を担う兵（つわもの）である武家としての「不心得者である」とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When an attacked one was a warrior and was attacked in Bureiuchi without resisting the attacker, he was punished severely as an &apos;imprudent person&apos; since he was expected to be a soldier who worked for the protection of the nation and the conquer of outside enemies (military and police power).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the attacked was a warrior and was attacked in Bureiuchi without resisting the attacker, he was punished severely as an &apos;imprudent person&apos; since he was expected to be a soldier who worked for the protection of the nation and to conquer outside enemies (military and police power).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the attacked was a warrior and was attacked in Bureiuchi without resisting the attacker, he was punished severely as an &apos;imprudent person&apos; since he was expected to be a soldier who worked for the protection of the nation and to conquer outside enemies (military and police power).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>生き延びた場合でもお家の士分の剥奪、家財屋敷の没収など厳しい処分が待っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even when the attacked one survived, he was severly punished, including deprivation of samurai class and confiscation of his house and household articles.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even when the attacked survived, he was severely punished, including deprivation of samurai class and confiscation of his house and household articles.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even when the attacked survived, he was severely punished, including deprivation of samurai class and confiscation of his house and household articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのため、無礼打ちする方・受ける方双方命懸けで臨まねばならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both the attacker and the attacked one had to fight desperately.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the attacker and the attacked one had to fight desperately.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the attacker and the attacked one had to fight desperately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのため上司が上意討ちをする場合、まず討つ相手に脇差を持たせてけしかけ、刃向かわせてから即座に斬る、という場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the superior conducted Joiuchi, he sometimes had his man have a short sword, instigated him, and immediately killed him using a blade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the superior conducted Joiuchi, he sometimes had his man have a short sword, instigated him, and immediately killed him using a blade.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the superior conducted Joiuchi, he sometimes had his man have a short sword, instigated him, and immediately killed him using a blade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>ただしこのような騎士道的な態度が裏目に出ることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such a chivalrous attitude sometimes worked negatively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a chivalrous attitude sometimes worked negatively.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a chivalrous attitude sometimes worked negatively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>尾張藩家臣、朋飼佐平治は路上で町人と突き当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saheiji TOMOKAI, a vassal of Owari domain bumped into a townsman on a street.</e>
<cmt>朋飼佐平治の読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saheiji TOMOKAI, a vassal of Owari domain bumped into a townsman on the street.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saheiji TOMOKAI, a vassal of Owari domain bumped into a townsman on the street.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>佐平治が咎めたのにもかかわらず、町人は無視してそのまま立ち去ろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saheiji reproached the townsman, who tried to leave, ignoring Saheiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saheiji reproached the townsman, who tried to leave, ignoring Saheiji.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saheiji reproached the townsman, who tried to leave, ignoring Saheiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>佐平治は無腰の町人を手打ちにするのを不本意と考え、自らの脇差を相手に渡して果たし合いの形式をとろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sheiji was unwilling to kill the townsman without any arms, tried to fight like a dueling by giving him his short swaord.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saheiji was unwilling to kill the townsman without any arms, tried to fight like by dueling and giving him his short sword.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saheiji was unwilling to kill the townsman without any arms, tried to fight like by dueling and giving him his short sword.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、町人はその脇差を持ったまま遁走し、「余れ佐平治をふみたり（打ち負かす）｣と触れ回った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the townsman ran away with the short sword, and went around saying, &apos;I&apos;ve conquered Saheiji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the townsman ran away with the short sword, and went around saying, &apos;I&apos;ve conquered Saheiji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the townsman ran away with the short sword, and went around saying, &apos;I&apos;ve conquered Saheiji.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>悪評を立てられた佐平治は已む無く出奔を余儀なくされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Saheiji got bad reputation, he was forced to run away.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Saheiji got a bad reputation, he was forced to run away.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Saheiji got a bad reputation, he was forced to run away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>武士の一分を立てるために町人の家を突き止め女子供に至るまで殺害するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to keep his face, Saheiji found out where the townsman lived and killed not only him but also all the members of his family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to save face, Saheiji found out where the townsman lived and killed not only him but also all the members of his family.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to save face, Saheiji found out where the townsman lived and killed not only him but also all the members of his family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>また、他領の領民に対する危害行為は、たとえ正当防衛である切捨御免の結果であったとしても、その領民が属する封建領主への敵対的行為とされる恐れがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any harmful deed toward a person of another domain could be regarded as a hostile behavior to the suzerain to whom the killed person belonged, even it was the result of Kirisute gomen, justifiable defense.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any harmful deed toward a person of another domain could be regarded as hostile behavior to the suzerain to whom the killed person belonged, even if it was the result of Kirisute gomen, justifiable defense.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any harmful deed toward a person of another domain could be regarded as hostile behavior to the suzerain to whom the killed person belonged, even if it was the result of Kirisute gomen, justifiable defense.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>つまり幕府直轄地である江戸で町民に危害を加えた場合は、徳川幕府への反逆行為とみなされる恐れがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a warrior did harm to a townsman in Edo, directly-controlled land by Bakufu, it could be regarded as an attempt of rebellion against Tokugawa Bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a warrior did harm to a townsman in Edo, directly-controlled land by the Bakufu, it could be regarded as an attempt of rebellion against the Tokugawa Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a warrior did harm to a townsman in Edo, directly-controlled land by the Bakufu, it could be regarded as an attempt of rebellion against the Tokugawa Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>このため諸藩は江戸在勤者に対し、直接切捨御免には言及していないものの『町民とトラブルを起こさずにくれぐれも自重すべき』旨の訓令をたびたび発した記録が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, it was recorded in many domains that official directives saying &quot;You should respect yourself not to have trouble with townsmen,&quot; were issued many times, without directly mentionning Kirisutegomen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, it was recorded in many domains that official directives saying &quot;You should respect yourself not to have trouble with townsmen,&quot; were issued many times, without directly mentioning Kirisutegomen.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, it was recorded in many domains that official directives saying &quot;You should respect yourself not to have trouble with townsmen,&quot; were issued many times, without directly mentioning Kirisutegomen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>このため簡単には斬れない事情を知っていた町民の中には、粋を衒ったり、度胸試しのために故意に武士を挑発する言動をする者もいたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, some townsmen who knew that situation, deliberately challenged warriors in order to try to act strong or play chicken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, some townsmen who knew this situation, deliberately challenged warriors in order to try to act strong or play chicken.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, some townsmen who knew this situation, deliberately challenged warriors in order to try to act strong or play chicken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>もっとも町人から侮辱を受けたまま何もせずにいたところを朋輩に見られた場合、今度は「臆病者」との謗りを受け、これまた「士道不覚悟」で罰せられることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a warrior was seen insulted by a townsman without doing anything about it by his collegue(s), the warrior was denounced as &apos;a coward&apos; and was punished as &apos;not having the samurai spirit.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a warrior was seen insulted by a townsman without doing anything about it by his colleague(s), the warrior was denounced as &apos;a coward&apos; and was punished as &apos;not having the samurai spirit.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a warrior was seen insulted by a townsman without doing anything about it by his colleague(s), the warrior was denounced as &apos;a coward&apos; and was punished as &apos;not having the samurai spirit.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>従って武士は街中でこのような恥辱を受ける事を避けるために、供を付けず一人歩きするようなことは避ける必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a warrior had to avoid walking alone without his servant in order to avoid facing such shame on the streets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a warrior had to avoid walking alone without his servant in order to avoid facing such shame on the streets.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a warrior had to avoid walking alone without his servant in order to avoid facing such shame on the streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>特に芝居小屋のような、町人と密接な接触が想定される場に足を踏み入れることは、極力慎むことが求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was especially required that warriors should not enter a playhouse, where they were likely to have close contact with townspeople.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was especially required that warriors should not enter a playhouse, where they were likely to have close contact with townspeople.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was especially required that warriors should not enter a playhouse, where they were likely to have close contact with townspeople.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="40">
<j>以上のように切捨御免は武士の特権としては認められてはいたものの、気ままに実行出来るようなものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown above, although Kirisutegomen was admitted as a privilege granted to samurai warriors, it was impossible to use the privilege easily.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown above, although Kirisutegomen was admitted as a privilege granted to samurai warriors, it was impossible to use the privilege easily.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown above, although Kirisutegomen was admitted as a privilege granted to samurai warriors, it was impossible to use the privilege easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>正当なものと認定されなかった場合のリスクも高かった為、実際に切捨御免を行い、認められた事案はそれほど多くはない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there was a high probability that it was not admitted as legitimate, few warriors actually conducted Kirisutegomen and few were admitted as legitimate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there was a high probability that it would not be admitted as legitimate, few warriors actually conducted Kirisutegomen and few were admitted as legitimate.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there was a high probability that it would not be admitted as legitimate, few warriors actually conducted Kirisutegomen and few were admitted as legitimate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>主従関係と無礼討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relationship between lord and vassal and Bureiuchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationship between lord and vassal and Bureiuchi</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationship between lord and vassal and Bureiuchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>主人が不都合をしでかした家来を斬る場合も無礼討（上意討ち）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a lord killed his servant(s) who did something disadvantageous with a blade, it was called Bureiuchi (Joiuchi (kill of offender)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a lord killed his servant(s) who did something disadvantageous with a blade, it was called Bureiuchi (Joiuchi (killing of an offender)).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a lord killed his servant(s) who did something disadvantageous with a blade, it was called Bureiuchi (Joiuchi (killing of an offender)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>この場合の家来には武士のみならず中間や下男下女などの武士以外の奉公人も含まれた（理論的には日雇いの奉公人も対象となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, servants include not only warriors but also non-warrior servants such as Chugen, manservants and maid servants (theoretically, servants included day workers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, servants included not only warriors but also non-warrior servants such as Chugen, manservants, and maid servants (theoretically, servants included day workers).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, servants included not only warriors but also non-warrior servants such as Chugen, manservants, and maid servants (theoretically, servants included day workers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>主従関係に基づく無礼討ちでは主人が有する家臣への処罰権の行使と考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bureiuchi, which was based on the relationship between a lord and his vassals, was regarded as conducting a lord&apos;s punishment right to his vassals.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bureiuchi, which was based on the relationship between a lord and his vassals, was regarded as conducting a lord&apos;s punishment right to his vassals.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bureiuchi, which was based on the relationship between a lord and his vassals, was regarded as conducting a lord&apos;s punishment right to his vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>そのため上述のような厳格な規定は適用されず、殺害自体の刑事責任も問われなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The strict rules mentioned above were not applied to Bureiuchi, and the lord was not held criminally responsible for killing his vassal(s).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The strict rules mentioned above were not applied to Bureiuchi, and the lord was not held criminally responsible for killing his vassal(s).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The strict rules mentioned above were not applied to Bureiuchi, and the lord was not held criminally responsible for killing his vassal(s).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>但し家来に対する管理能力に問題があるとみなされ「家中不取締」として御役御免や閉門といった処分をうけることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when a lord was considered to have some problems in his ability to manage his vassals, he was sometimes regarded as &apos;unable to control his house&apos; and given such punishment as retirement or house confinement.</e>
<cmt>「家中不取締」の定訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when a lord was considered to have some problems in his ability to manage his vassals, he was sometimes regarded as &apos;unable to control his house&apos; and given such punishment as retirement or house confinement.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when a lord was considered to have some problems in his ability to manage his vassals, he was sometimes regarded as &apos;unable to control his house&apos; and given such punishment as retirement or house confinement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また正当防衛ではなく処罰であるためとどめも行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not justifiable defense but a punishment, so the final blow was often given.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not a justifiable defense but a punishment, so the final blow was often given.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not a justifiable defense but a punishment, so the final blow was often given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ピノキオ(id:245510), Lumi(id:101666), 玄史生(id:43670), Bergmann(id:85282), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), 逃亡者(id:14864), Tast(id:29478), Shimoxx(id:9332), Ryoske(id:34653), 千年伯爵(id:289276), How I Learned to Stop Worrying and Hate the Bomb(id:297350), Klobis(id:150573), Mycomp(id:168269), 幣原外交(id:97257), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>