<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>在庁官人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>在庁官人（ざいちょうかんじん）とは、日本の平安時代から鎌倉時代に、国衙行政の実務に従事した地方官僚の総称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjin is a general term for the local government official who undertook the practical business of &quot;kokuga&quot; (the local area) administration from the Heian period to the Kamakura period in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin is a general term for a local government official who undertakes the practical business of &quot;kokuga&quot; (local area) administration from the Heian period to the Kamakura period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin is a general term for a local government official who undertakes the practical business of kokuga (local area) administration from the Heian period to the Kamakura period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>在庁官人という名前の役職が存在したわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This does not mean that the official position called &quot;zaichokanjin&quot; existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This does not mean that an official position actually called &quot;zaichokanjin&quot; existed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This does not mean that an official position actually called &quot;zaichokanjin&quot; existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>在庁（ざいちょう）、庁官（ちょうのかん）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called as &quot;zaicho&quot; or &quot;chokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;zaicho&quot; or &quot;chokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;zaicho&quot; or &quot;chonokan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>ひらがな通りの読み方にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>中央派遣の国司が現地で採用する実務官僚であり、国司の側近としての性格があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjin was a practical government official who was locally employed by &quot;kokushi&quot; (government administrator sent from the central government), and was professionally an entourage of kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin was a practical government official who was locally employed by &quot;kokushi&quot; (government administrator sent from the central government), and was professionally an entourage of kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin was a practical government official who was locally employed by kokushi (government administrator sent from the central government), and was professionally an entourage of kokushi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development (or History)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development (or History)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>発生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>9世紀～10世紀の日本では、統治体制に大きな変化が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government system in Japan underwent a great change from the ninth century to the tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government system in Japan underwent a great change from the ninth century to the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government system in Japan underwent a great change from the ninth century to the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それ以前は、古代の戸籍制度・計帳・班田収授法などに立脚した律令制統治が行われていたが、この頃には、人民の浮浪・逃亡・偽籍が著しく増加したため、律令制統治が行き詰まりを見せていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that, Japan had been ruled by the &quot;ritsuryo&quot; system of governance (a constitutional form of governance) built on ancient family register system, tax book, &quot;handensyuju-no-hou&quot; (the law on the distribution and collection of farmlands) and so on, but at that time, the vagrancy, elopement, false family registration of the people dramatically increased and the &quot;ritsuryo&quot; system of governance ran into an impasse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that, Japan had been ruled by the &quot;ritsuryo&quot; system of governance (a constitutional form of governance) built on an ancient family register system, tax book, &quot;handensyuju-no-hou&quot; (law on the distribution and collection of farmlands) and so on, but at that time, vagrancy, elopement, false family registration of the people dramatically increased and the &quot;ritsuryo&quot; system of governance ran into an impasse.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that, Japan had been ruled by the ritsuryo system of governance (a constitutional form of governance) built on an ancient family register system, tax book, handenshuju-no-ho (law on the distribution and collection of farmlands) and so on, but at that time, vagrancy, elopement, false family registration of the people dramatically increased and the ritsuryo system of governance ran into an impasse.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一方、各地方では国司・郡司・有力百姓などを出自とする「富豪の輩」と呼ばれる階層が登場しており、国衙から名田の経営と租税徴収を請け負って、経済力をつけ始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the class called &quot;fugo-no-yakara&quot; (rich guy) originated from kokushi, gunshi (local government administrator sent from the central government, working under kokushi), leading people and so on appeared, undertook the management of &quot;myoden&quot; (rice field as a basic unit for tax levying) and the duty of tax collection from kokuga and began to be economically stronger.</e>
<cmt>この「有力百姓」ですが、ウィキペディアの「百姓」の項目に「この階層は現実には農業経営に従事する者のみならず、商業や手工業、漁業などの経営者も包括していた。」とあり、ここでは必ずしも「農民」とは限らないと判断し、英訳はfarmers とせずにpeopleとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the class called &quot;fugo-no-yakara&quot; (rich guy) originated from kokushi, gunshi (local government administrator sent from the central government, working under kokushi), leading people, appeared, managed &quot;myoden&quot; (rice fields as the basic unit for levying taxes) and the duty of tax collection from kokuga and began to be economically stronger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the class called &apos;fugo-no-yakara&apos; (rich guy) originated from kokushi, gunshi (local government administrator sent from the central government, working under kokushi), leading people, appeared, managed myoden (rice fields as the basic unit for levying taxes) and the duty of tax collection from kokuga and began to be economically stronger.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また彼らは古代以来の首長層に替わって、出挙を通じて公民を隷属下に収めていき、地方の人民支配の主体ともなりつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, they took the place of the headmen-class since ancient times, put the public people in a servile position through &quot;suikyo&quot; (land lease at interest) and became dominant local governors of the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, they took the place of the ruling-class since ancient times, forced the public into a servile position through &quot;suikyo&quot; (land lease at interest) and became dominant local governors of the people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, they took the place of the ruling-class since ancient times, forced the public into a servile position through suikyo (land lease at interest) and became dominant local governors of the people.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>こうした状況下で、朝廷は実情に適合した国政改革を進めていき（改革が最も進展したのは900年前後の寛平・延喜期）、地方行政の分野では、国司筆頭官（受領）に対して租税収取権・軍事権などの大幅な権限委譲が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such a situation, the imperial court practically advanced the national administration reform (the reform culminated during the Kanpyo and the Engi period around 900) and the authorities such as the right of tax collection, that of military affair and so on were widely transferred to the leaders of kokushi (&quot;zuryo&quot;) in the field of local administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such a situation, the imperial court practically advanced national administration reform (the reform culminated during the Kanpyo and the Engi period around 900) and authority such as the right of tax collection, military affairs and so on were widely transferred to the leaders of kokushi (&quot;zuryo&quot;) in the local administration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such a situation, the imperial court practically advanced national administration reform (the reform culminated during the Kanpyo and the Engi period around 900) and authority such as the right of tax collection, military affairs and so on were widely transferred to the leaders of kokushi (zuryo) in the local administration.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この権限拡大を背景として、受領たちは租税収取・軍事両面において統治を強化するため、旧来の補佐官で同一階層出自ゆえに一方的に使役しがたい掾（じょう）、目（さかん）に替えて、国内の豪族・有力者らを国衙の体制に組み入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the empowerment of zuryos, they incorporated the local ruling families and leading people into the kokuga government system, instead of the &quot;jo&quot; (the third-ranking local administrator) and &quot;sakan&quot; (the fourth-ranking local administrator) who were reluctant to accept the one-sided orders issued by them because jo and sakan were also old administrative aides from the same class, in order to strengthen the governance both in tax collection and in military affair.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the empowerment of zuryos, they incorporated the local ruling families leading the people into a kokuga government system, instead of the &quot;jo&quot; (the third-ranking local administrator) and &quot;sakan&quot; (the fourth-ranking local administrator) who were reluctant to accept the one-sided orders they issued because jo and sakan were also old administrative aides from the same class, in order to strengthen the governance of both tax collection and military affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the empowerment of zuryos, they incorporated the local ruling families leading the people into a kokuga government system, instead of the jo (the third-ranking local administrator) and sakan (the fourth-ranking local administrator) who were reluctant to accept the one-sided orders they issued because jo and sakan were also old administrative aides from the same class, in order to strengthen the governance of both tax collection and military affairs.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これが在庁官人である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>在庁官人は、前述した「富豪の輩」（田堵・負名層）から登用された者が多く、国衙領の経営・租税徴収を行うことで、国司の租税収取に貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many zaichokanjins were employed from the above-mentioned &quot;fugo-no-yakara&quot; (&quot;tato,&quot; leading farmer and &quot;fumyo,&quot; tax collector), took on the management of kokuga region and tax collection and contributed to the tax levying by kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many zaichokanjin were employed from the above-mentioned &quot;fugo-no-yakara&quot; (&quot;tato,&quot; leading farmer and &quot;fumyo,&quot; tax collector), took on the management of the kokuga region and tax collection and contributed to levying taxes by kokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many zaichokanjin were employed from the above-mentioned &apos;fugo-no-yakara&apos; (tato, leading farmer and fumyo, tax collector), took on the management of the kokuga region and tax collection and contributed to levying taxes by kokushi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>在庁官人の多くは土着国司・旧郡司層でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of zaichokanjins are from the class of local kokushi and old gunshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most zaichokanjin were from the class of local kokushi and old gunshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most zaichokanjin were from the class of local kokushi and old gunshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>土着国司やその子孫は中央では身分が比較的低い軍事貴族として摂関家などに仕え、また旧郡司層は健児として地方軍事力を支えてきた存在であり、ともに国司へ軍事力を提供する主体であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local kokushis and their offspring served &quot;sekkan-ke&quot; (five top court noble families of FUJIWARA family&apos;s offspring) as comparatively low-ranking military aristocrats, old gunshi class supported the local military forces as &quot;kondei&quot; (local military army), and both of them provided kokushis with the military forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local kokushis and their offspring served &quot;sekkan-ke&quot; (five top court noble families of FUJIWARA family&apos;s offspring) as comparatively low-ranking military aristocrats, old gunshi class supported the local military forces as &quot;kondei&quot; (local military army), and both provided kokushis with the military forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local kokushis and their offspring served sekkan-ke (five top court noble families of FUJIWARA family&apos;s offspring) as comparatively low-ranking military aristocrats, old gunshi class supported the local military forces as kondei (local military army), and both provided kokushis with the military forces.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>このように、在庁官人は租税収取のノウハウを知り、軍事にも通じた存在だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Like this, zaichokanjins knew how to collect taxes and were familiar with the military affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin knew how to collect taxes and were familiar with military affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin knew how to collect taxes and were familiar with military affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>後に彼らの中で治安維持の武功によって勲功を得、特に承平天慶の乱で勲功を認められた者たちが中核になって武士身分が形成されていくことになるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, among them, those who were distinguished by the military contribution to the maintenance of security, especially in the &quot;Johei-Tengyo-no-ran&quot; (the two wars in the middle of the Heian period), would become the bushi class as the core group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, those who were distinguished because of military contributions to maintain security, especially during the &quot;Johei-Tengyo-no-ran&quot; (the two wars during the middle of the Heian period), would become the bushi class as the core group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, those who were distinguished because of military contributions to maintain security, especially during the Johei and Tengyo War, would become the bushi class as the core group.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>10世紀中期頃、国衙行政は在庁官人の手で運営されるようになり、受領の中には任国へ赴任せず、在庁官人へ行政を任せる者も多くなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the middle of the tenth century, the administration of kokuga came to be managed by zaichokanjins, some of zuryos did not go to their place of assignment and often left the administration to zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the middle of the tenth century, the administration of kokuga came to be managed by zaichokanjins, some of the zuryos did not go to their place of assignment and often left administration to the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle of the tenth century, the administration of kokuga came to be managed by zaichokanjins, some of the zuryos did not go to their place of assignment and often left administration to the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これを遙任という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called &quot;yonin.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called &quot;yonin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called &quot;yonin.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>遙任国司は、自分の家人などを代理人として現地へ派遣し、在庁官人の監督に当たらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonin kokushis sent their retainers to the place of assignment as an agent who were assigned to supervise the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonin kokushis sent their retainers to their places of assignment as an agent to supervise the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonin kokushis sent their retainers to their places of assignment as an agent to supervise the zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この代理人を目代という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The agents were called &quot;mokudai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The agents were called &quot;mokudai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The agents were called &quot;mokudai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>在庁官人らは、目代の監督の下、国衙で租税収取・軍事などの実務に当たった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the supervision of mokudai, zaichokanjins undertook the practice of tax collection or military affair in kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the supervision of mokudai, zaichokanjins undertook the practice of tax collection or military affairs in kokuga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the supervision of mokudai, zaichokanjins undertook the practice of tax collection or military affairs in kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>在庁官人の職務と別の側面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Duties of zaichokanjin and the other aspects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Duties of zaichokanjin and other aspects</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Duties of zaichokanjin and other aspects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>国司のいない国衙は、留守所と呼ばれ、租税収取を所管する部署（税所（ぜいしょ・さいしょ等）、田所（たどころ）、大帳所（だいちょうしょ）、出納所（すいとうどころ）など）や、軍事を所管する部署（健児所（こんでいどころ）、検非違使所（けびいしどころ）、厩所（うまやどころ）など）、所務・雑務を所管する部署（政所（まんどころ）・調所（ちょうしょ）、細工所（さいくどころ）、膳所（ぜんどころ）など）が置かれ、在庁官人はこれらの部署に所属して実務に従事していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokuga without kokushi was called &quot;rusu dokoro,&quot; the department which handled tax collection called &quot;zeisho, saisho and so on,&quot; &quot;tadokoro,&quot; &quot;daichosho&quot; and &quot;suitodokoro and so on,&quot; the department which handled military affair called &quot;kondeidokoro,&quot; &quot;kebiishidokoro,&quot; &quot;umayadokoro and so on,&quot; and the department which oversaw miscellaneous duties called &quot;mandokoro,&quot; &quot;chosho,&quot; &quot;saikudokoro,&quot; &quot;zendokoro and so on,&quot; were set there and zaichokanjins belonged to these departments and did their juties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokuga without kokushi were called &quot;rusu dokoro,&quot; the department that handled tax collection called &quot;zeisho, saisho and so on,&quot; &quot;tadokoro,&quot; &quot;daichosho&quot; and &quot;suitodokoro and so on,&quot; the department that handled military affairs was called &quot;kondeidokoro,&quot; &quot;kebiishidokoro,&quot; &quot;umayadokoro and so on,&quot; and the department that oversaw miscellaneous duties was called &quot;mandokoro,&quot; &quot;chosho,&quot; &quot;saikudokoro,&quot; &quot;zendokoro and so on,&quot; were sent there and zaichokanjins belonged to these departments and performed their duties.</e>
<cmt>spelling, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokuga without kokushi were called &quot;rusu dokoro,&quot; the department that handled tax collection called &quot;zeisho,&quot; &quot;saisho&quot; and so on, &quot;tadokoro,&quot; &quot;daichosho&quot; and &quot;suitodokoro and so on,&quot; the department that handled military affairs was called &quot;kondeidokoro,&quot; &quot;kebiishidokoro,&quot; &quot;umayadokoro&quot; and so on, and the department that oversaw miscellaneous duties was called &quot;mandokoro,&quot; &quot;chosho,&quot; &quot;saikudokoro,&quot; &quot;zendokoro&quot; and so on, were sent there and zaichokanjins belonged to these departments and performed their duties.</e>
<cmt>&quot;位置調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>在庁官人の任務は多岐にわたっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjin has the wide-ranging duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin had a wide-range of responsibilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin had a wide-range of responsibilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>新たな荘園が認可されると、在庁官人は荘園側とともに境界確認を行い、境界を示す傍示を打った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When &quot;shoen&quot; (manor) was newly approved, zaichokanjin set the demarcation line with the shoen party and put the tag indicating the border.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When &quot;shoen&quot; (a manor) was newly approved, zaichokanjin set the demarcation line with the shoen party and placed tags indicating the bordesr.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When shoen (a manor) was newly approved, zaichokanjin set the demarcation line with the shoen party and placed tags indicating the borders.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>当時、国衙領からの租税収取を確保するために、国内が古代的な郡・郷から中世的な郡・郷・保という単位に再編成されていたが、これを管轄する郡司・郷司・保司に任命されたのも、主に在庁官人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time in Japan, to ensure the tax collection from the kokuga region, the ancient units such as &quot;gun&quot; and &quot;go&quot; were reorganized into the medieval units such as &quot;gun,&quot; &quot;go,&quot; and &quot;ho&quot;, and zaichokanjins were mainly appointed as &quot;gunshi,&quot; &quot;goshi&quot; and &quot;hoshi&quot; who supervised these units.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time in Japan, to ensure the tax collection from the kokuga region, ancient units such as &quot;gun&quot; and &quot;go&quot; were reorganized into medieval units such as &quot;gun,&quot; &quot;go,&quot; and &quot;ho,&quot; and zaichokanjin were mainly appointed as &quot;gunshi,&quot; &quot;goshi,&quot; and &quot;hoshi&quot; who supervised these units.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time in Japan, to ensure the tax collection from the kokuga region, ancient units such as gun and go were reorganized into medieval units such as gun, go, and ho, and zaichokanjin were mainly appointed as gunshi, goshi, and hoshi who supervised these units.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>国内の荘園・公領の領主・田地面積・作物等を記録した租税台帳である大田文の作成にも携わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjins also involved in the job on the tax book called &quot;otabumi&quot; which recorded shoens, the landlords of public domain, the square measures of rice fields, crops and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin were also involved as &quot;otabumi&quot; who recordedthe shoens, the landlords of the public domain, the square measures of rice fields, crops, and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin were also involved in preparing Ota bumi (cadastre), in which details regarding the shoens, landlords of public domains, dimensions of rice fields, crops, and so on were recorded.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また、国内で紛争が発生した場合、臨時の国単位の軍事司令官たる追捕使・押領使などに任命され、国内武士を統率して国内の治安維持に当たる武力として機能した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in the case of domestic conflicts, zaichokanjins were temporarily appointed as the military officers of kokuga units called &quot;tsuibushi&quot; or &quot;oryoshi&quot; and functioned as the military forces which radiated leadership over domestic bushis in order to maintain security.</e>
<cmt>ここで「国単位」の「国」ですが、「日本」ではなく「国衙」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in the case of domestic conflicts, zaichokanjin were temporarily appointed as military officers of kokuga units called &quot;tsuibushi&quot; or &quot;oryoshi&quot; and functioned as the military forces that provided leadership over domestic bushis in order to maintain security.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in the case of domestic conflicts, zaichokanjin were temporarily appointed as military officers of kokuga units called &quot;tsuibushi&quot; or &quot;oryoshi&quot; and functioned as the military forces that provided leadership over domestic bushis in order to maintain security.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また、平時にも国司館に結番・参勤していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in times of peace, they went to &quot;kokushi-kan&quot; (house of kokushi) and served by rotation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in times of peace, they went to &quot;kokushi-kan&quot; (house of kokushi) and served by rotation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in times of peace, they went to kokushi-kan (house of kokushi) and served by rotation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>以上のように見ると、在庁官人は国司の従順なしもべであるようにも思えるが、実態は決してそうではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering what is above mentioned, zaichokanjins seem to have been obedient servants of kokushi, but in fact, they were not at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the above, zaichokanjin seem to have been obedient servants of kokushi, but in fact, they were not.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the above, zaichokanjin seem to have been obedient servants of kokushi, but in fact, they were not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>在庁官人は元々、現地の有力者であり、中央の国司に対する地域の利益代表としての顔も持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjins were originally the leading men in the local region and were also the representative of the interests of the region against the kokushi sent from the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin were originally the leaders in the local region and were also the representing the interests of the region against the kokushi sent from the central government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin were originally the leaders in the local region and were also the representing the interests of the region against the kokushi sent from the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>そのため、彼らは婚姻を通して複雑なネットワークを形成し、国司の施策が自らの意向にそぐわなければ、国司へ反抗することもしばしば見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, they formed complicated networks through marriage and if the measures and policies by kokushi were inappropriate for their interests, they often resisted kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, they formed complicated networks through marriage and if the measures and policies by kokushi were inappropriate for their interests, they often resisted kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, they formed complicated networks through marriage and if the measures and policies by kokushi were inappropriate for their interests, they often resisted kokushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>特に東国では、有力者層の独自性が強く、在庁官人でありながら国司に逆らったり、武力紛争を起こしたりする者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the eastern regions, the class of leading men had a distinctive character and even though they were zaichokanjins, they often defied kokushi or caused the armed conflicts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the eastern regions, this class of leading men had a distinctive character and even though they were zaichokanjin, they often defied kokushi or caused armed conflicts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the eastern regions, this class of leading men had a distinctive character and even though they were zaichokanjin, they often defied kokushi or caused armed conflicts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>また、在庁官人は、郡司・郷司・保司に任命されると、郡・郷・保の公領・公田を自らの所領として扱う傾向があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And when zaichokanjins were appointed as gunshi, goshi and hoshi, they were likely to deal with public domains and public rice fields in gun, go and ho as their own lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And when zaichokanjin were appointed as gunshi, goshi, and hoshi, they were likely to deal with public domains and public rice fields in gun, go, and ho as their own lands.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And when zaichokanjin were appointed as gunshi, goshi, and hoshi, they were likely to deal with public domains and public rice fields in gun, go, and ho as their own lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>中には、高級貴族・有力寺社（権門勢家）へ寄進する者さえいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of them even donated to high-ranking aristocrats and leading temples and shrines (&quot;kenmon seika,&quot; socially privileged family or group).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of them even donated to high-ranking aristocrats and leading temples and shrines (&quot;kenmon seika,&quot; socially privileged family or group).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of them even donated to high-ranking aristocrats and leading temples and shrines (kenmon seika, socially privileged family or group).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>在庁官人には、在庁官人としての側面を持ちつつも、荘園の開発領主・荘官としての側面も併せ持つ者が少なくなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not a few zaichokanjins had the characteristics of developer-landlords or shoen managers as well as that of proper zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many zaichokanjin took on the role of developer-landlords or shoen managers as well as that of proper zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many zaichokanjin took on the role of developer-landlords or shoen managers as well as that of proper zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="36">
<j>こうして、平安中期以降（11世紀～12世紀）、在庁官人の多くは、在地領主として、そして武士として成長していくこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus many of zaichokanjins developed both as the local landlords and as bushis after the middle of the Heian period (from the eleventh century to the twelfth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus manyzaichokanjin developed into local landlords and as bushi after the middle of the Heian period (from the eleventh century to the twelfth).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus many zaichokanjin developed into local landlords and as bushi after the middle of the Heian period (from the eleventh century to the twelfth).</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その過程においては国衙と在庁官人層の出自母体たる田堵負名層の権益などを巡る経済的、軍事的緊張と、それによる武力紛争の多発が大きく関わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the developmental process, the economical and military tensions, concerning the interests of kokuga and &quot;tato and fumyo&quot; class from which most zaichokanjins were originated, were involved and so were the frequent occurrences of armed conflicts by these tensions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process of development, economic and military tensions, concerning the interests of kokuga and &quot;tato and fumyo&quot; classes from where most zaichokanjin originated, were involved and frequently armed conflicts broke out.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the process of development, economic and military tensions, concerning the interests of kokuga and tato and fumyo classes from where most zaichokanjin originated, were involved and frequently armed conflicts broke out.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>在庁官人はあるときは田堵負名層の利益代表として反乱側に、またあるときは朝廷・国衙ラインの権力を保証する戦士として田堵負名層を制圧する側に立ち、地域における実権を構築していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjins took the side of tato and fumyo class as the representative of their interests, and other times, took the side of those who oppressed tato and fumyo class as the soldiers to ensure the power of the imperial court and kokuga, and came to have real power in the local regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin took the side of the tato and fumyo classes representing their interests, and other times they took the side of those who oppressed tato and fumyo classes as soldiers to ensure the power of the imperial court and kokuga, and came to have the actual power in the local regions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin took the side of the tato and fumyo classes representing their interests, and other times they took the side of those who oppressed tato and fumyo classes as soldiers to ensure the power of the imperial court and kokuga, and came to have the actual power in the local regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その傾向は関東で特に強く、在地における国衙の目代や荘園の預所（あずかっそ）といった在庁官人を翻弄する権力の排除を志向する動きが鎌倉幕府の成立へとつながっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tendency was strong especially in the eastern regions and the move, which aimed to push out the power which was a nuisance to zaichokanjins such as mokudai in kokuga or &quot;azukaridokoko&quot; (management position in trust) in shoen, would lead to the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>「あずかっそ」とありますが、複数の読み名があるようなので、無難に「あずかりどころ」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tendency was strong, especially in the eastern regions, and movement aiming at pushing out the power that was a nuisance to zaichokanjin such as mokudai in kokuga or &quot;azukaridokoko&quot; (management position in trust) in shoen, would lead to the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tendency was strong, especially in the eastern regions, and movement aiming at pushing out the power that was a nuisance to zaichokanjin such as mokudai in kokuga or azukaridokoko (management position in trust) in shoen, would lead to the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>実際鎌倉幕府の有力御家人の多くは在庁官人出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, many of leading &quot;gokenin&quot; (retainers) of the Kamakura bakufu were from zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, many leading &quot;gokenin&quot; (retainers) of the Kamakura bakufu were from the zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, many leading gokenin (retainers) of the Kamakura bakufu were from the zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>在庁官人の地位</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status of zaichokanjins</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of zaichokanjin</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of zaichokanjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>在庁官人の間でも地位の差があったことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known that there were the disparities in social standing among zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that there were the disparities in social standing among zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that there were the disparities in social standing among zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>常陸国の場合、鎌倉時代ではあるが掾官、中座、書生、一分の他国舎人・国雑色・国掌・国承仕・御子と呼ばれる身分差があったことが文書から伺える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of the Hitachi province during the Kamakura period, we can see in the documents that there were status distinctions such as &quot;takokushajin,&quot; &quot;kunizoshiki,&quot; &quot;kokusho,&quot; &quot;kokushoji&quot; and &quot;miko&quot; in &quot;jokan,&quot; &quot;chuza,&quot; &quot;shosei&quot; and &quot;ichibun.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Hitachi province during the Kamakura period, we can see in documents that there were status distinctions such as &quot;takokushajin,&quot; &quot;kunizoshiki,&quot; &quot;kokusho,&quot; &quot;kokushoji&quot; and &quot;miko&quot; in &quot;jokan,&quot; &quot;chuza,&quot; &quot;shosei&quot; and &quot;ichibun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Hitachi Province during the Kamakura period, we can see in documents that there were status distinctions such as takokushajin, kunizoshiki, kokusho, kokushoji and miko in jokan, chuza, shosei and ichibun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>掾官はその名の通り掾や目といった下級国司の子孫が土着したものと見られ、衛門府の尉官などの官位を得ていることが多く、国衙で指導的立場にいたと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jokan is, as the name suggests, regarded as the localized lower-ranking kokushi&apos;s descendants such as &quot;jo&quot; or &quot;sakan,&quot; and jokan often got the official ranks such as &quot;ikan&quot; and so on in &quot;emonfu&quot; (bureaucracy in the &quot;ritsuryo&quot; system of governance) and seems to have been in a position of leadership in kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jokan is, as the name suggests, were regarded as localized lower-ranking kokush descendants such as &quot;jo&quot; or &quot;sakan,&quot; and jokan often attained official ranks such as &quot;ikan&quot; and so on in &quot;emonfu&quot; (bureaucracy in the &quot;ritsuryo&quot; system of governance) and seemed to have been in a position of leadership within the kokuga.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokan is, as the name suggests, were regarded as localized lower-ranking kokushi descendants such as jo or sakan, and jokan often attained official ranks such as ikan and so on in emonfu (bureaucracy in the ritsuryo system of governance) and seemed to have been in a position of leadership within the kokuga.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>中座、書生、一分はそれに次ぐ地位にあり、他国舎人・国雑色・国掌・国承仕・御子らは実務官僚であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chuza,&quot; &quot;shosei&quot; and &quot;ichibun&quot; were second to jokan and &quot;takokushajin,&quot; &quot;kunizoshiki,&quot; &quot;kunisho,&quot; &quot;kunishoji&quot; and &quot;miko&quot; are regarded as practical bureaucrats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chuza,&quot; &quot;shosei,&quot; and &quot;ichibun&quot; were second to jokan and &quot;takokushajin,&quot; &quot;kunizoshiki,&quot; &quot;kunisho,&quot; &quot;kunishoji,&quot; and &quot;miko&quot; are regarded as practical bureaucrats.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuza, shosei, and ichibun were second to jokan and takokushajin, kunizoshiki, kunisho, kunishoji, and miko are regarded as practical bureaucrats.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉期以降の在庁官人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zaichokanjins after the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zaichokanjin after the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zaichokanjin after the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>鎌倉期に入っても、在庁官人を中心とした国衙行政は継続していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the Kamakura period, the kokuga administration centering on zaichokanjins continued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even during the Kamakura period, the kokuga administration centering on zaichokanjin continued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even during the Kamakura period, the kokuga administration centering on zaichokanjin continued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>しかし、鎌倉幕府が各地に配置した地頭は、在庁官人の支配範囲へ侵出していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;jito&quot; (management post of shoen or public domain) located in various regions by the Kamakura bakufu came to penetrate the dominion of zaichokanjins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;jito&quot; (management post of shoen or public domain) located in various regions by the Kamakura bakufu began to penetrate the dominion of zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, jito (management post of shoen or public domain) located in various regions by the Kamakura bakufu began to penetrate the dominion of zaichokanjin.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>また、東国では多くの在庁官人が征夷大将軍と主従関係を結び御家人身分を獲得し、地頭にも任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in the eastern regions, many zaichokanjins formed the master-subordinate relationship with &quot;seii-tai-shogun&quot; (shogun in charge of conquering barbarian territories), got the status of &quot;gokenin&quot; (retainers) and were also appointed as jito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in the eastern regions, many zaichokanjin formed a master-subordinate relationship with &quot;seii-tai-shogun&quot; (shogun in charge of conquering barbarian territories), attained the status of &quot;gokenin&quot; (retainers) and were also appointed as jito.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in the eastern regions, many zaichokanjin formed a master-subordinate relationship with seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), attained the status of gokenin (retainers) and were also appointed as jito.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>鎌倉中期の元寇を契機として、幕府権力が西国へも浸透していき、在庁官人による国衙行政は次第に弱まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genko&quot; (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan) triggered the invasion of the power of the Kamakura bakufu towards the western regions and the administration of kokuga by zaichokanjins gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genko&quot; (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan) triggered the invasion of the power of the Kamakura bakufu towards the western regions and the administration of kokuga by zaichokanjin gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genko (Mongol invasion attempts against Japan) during the mid Kamakura period triggered the invasion of the power of the Kamakura bakufu towards the western regions and the administration of kokuga by zaichokanjin gradually weakened.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除during the mid Kamakura period補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="50">
<j>室町時代になると、守護に強力な権限が付与され、国衙は守護の支配下に置かれることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, the strong authority was assigned to &quot;shugo&quot; (local military commander) and kokuga was put under the governance of shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period, the strong authority was assigned to &quot;shugo&quot; (local military commander) and kokuga were put under the governance of shugo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the strong authority was assigned to shugo (local military commander) and kokuga were put under the governance of shugo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>国衙の権力は守護権力へと一元化され、国衙行政は消滅への道をたどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power of kokuga and that of shugo were unified and the administration of kokuga ceased to exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of kokuga and that of shugo were unified and the administration of kokuga ceased to exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power of kokuga and that of shugo were unified and the administration of kokuga ceased to exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>そうなると、在庁官人という地位も存立基盤を失うこととなり、在庁官人は国人と呼ばれる階層へ移行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, zaichokanjins lost their status and raison d&apos;etre and they were transferred to the class called &quot;kokujin&quot; (the bushi class originally from the jito class).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, zaichokanjin lost their status and raison d&apos;etre and were transferred to a class called &quot;kokujin&quot; (the bushi class originally from the jito class).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, zaichokanjin lost their status and raison d&apos;etre and were transferred to a class called &quot;kokujin&quot; (the bushi class originally from the jito class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="53">
<j>国人となった在庁官人は、その多くが守護の被官に組み込まれ、在庁官人の管理していた国衙領は守護の支配する守護領へ再編成されていき、守護領国制の確立へとつながっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of zaichokanjins who became kokujin were incorporated in the bureaucrats of shugo, kokuga regions managed by zaichokanjins were reorganized into the shugo regions governed by shugo and led to the establishment of &quot;shugo ryokoku sei&quot; (governmental system by shugo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many zaichokanjin who became kokujin were incorporated into the bureaucracy of shugo, kokuga regions managed by zaichokanjin were reorganized into the shugo regions governed by shugo and led to the establishment of &quot;shugo ryokoku sei&quot; (governmental system by shugo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many zaichokanjin who became kokujin were incorporated into the bureaucracy of shugo, kokuga regions managed by zaichokanjin were reorganized into the shugo regions governed by shugo and led to the establishment of shugo ryokoku sei (governmental system by shugo).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>一方で、守護支配下に入ることを嫌い、独自性を持った国人として存続を図った旧在庁官人もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, to avoid being under the control of shugo, some old zaichokanjins tried to struggle for existence as kokujin who had the independence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, to avoid becoming under the control of shugo, some old zaichokanjin tried to struggle to maintain an indepent existence as kokujin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, to avoid becoming under the control of shugo, some old zaichokanjin tried to struggle to maintain an independent existence as kokujin.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、南北朝時代 (日本)の混乱に乗じて、在庁官人から守護へ成長した者（例：大内氏）もいたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, taking the anarchy in the Nanbokucho period (Japan), some zaichokanjins grew up to be shugo (for example, the Ouchi clan).</e>
<cmt>「大内氏」ですが、Ochiか、Ouchiで迷いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, considering the anarchy in the Nanbokucho period (Japan), some zaichokanjin grew up to be shugo (for example, the Ouchi clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, considering the anarchy in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), some zaichokanjin grew up to be shugo (for example, the Ouchi clan).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 伏儀(id:142093), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>