<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊予親王の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iyo Shinno no Hen (Conspiracy of Imperial Prince Iyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iyo Shinno no Hen (Conspiracy of Imperial Prince Iyo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iyo Shinno no Hen</e>
<cmt>以下説明が続くので、英語説明を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊予親王の変（いよしんのうのへん）は、大同 (日本)2年（807年）に起こった政変。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iyo Shinno no Hen was a political change which occurred in the 2nd year of Daido era (Japan) (807).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iyo Shinno no Hen was a political change which occurred in the second year of the Daido era (Japan) (807).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iyo Shinno no Hen was a political change which occurred in 807.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藤原吉子・伊予親王母子が処罰され2人は自殺したが、後に無罪が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshiko and her son Imperial Prince Iyo were punished and committed suicide, but they were found not guilty later on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Yoshiko and her son Imperial Prince Iyo were punished and they committed suicide, but they were found not guilty later on.</e>
<cmt>grmmar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yoshiko and her son Imperial Prince Iyo were punished and they committed suicide, but they were found not guilty later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>桓武天皇の皇子である伊予親王は父桓武の生前深い寵愛を受けており、また、母吉子の兄藤原雄友は大納言として右大臣藤原内麻呂に次ぐ太政官の No.2の位置にあり、政治的にも有力な地位にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Imperial Prince Iyo, a prince of the Emperor Kanmu, was in his father Kanmu&apos;s favor while Kanmu was in life and his mother Yoshiko&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Otomo was, being as Dainagon (a chief councilor of state), the second-ranking official of Daijokan (Grand Council of State) next to udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Uchimaro and boasted of strong political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial Prince Iyo, prince of Emperor Kanmu, was in his father Kanmu&apos;s favor while Kanmu was in living and his mother Yoshiko&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Otomo was, being as Dainagon (a chief councilor of state), the second-ranking official of Daijokan (Grand Council of State) next to udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Uchimaro and boasted of strong political power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial Prince Iyo, prince of Emperor Kanmu, was in his father Kanmu&apos;s favor while Kanmu was in living and his mother Yoshiko&apos;s elder brother FUJIWARA no Otomo was, being as Dainagon (a chief councilor of state), the second-ranking official of Daijokan (Grand Council of State) next to udaijin (minister of the right) FUJIWARA no Uchimaro and boasted of strong political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>実際に、平城天皇朝においても、大同元年から中務卿兼大宰帥を務めて、皇族の重鎮となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the era of The Emperor Heijo, he served as Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) cum Dazai no sochi (Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) from the 1st year of Daido era and was actually the leader of Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the era of The Emperor Heijo, he served as Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) cum Dazai no sochi (Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) from the first year of the Daido era and was actually the leader of the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the era of the Emperor Heijo, he served as Nakatsukasa-kyo (Minister of the Ministry of Central Affairs) cum Dazai no sochi (Governor-General of the Dazai-fu offices) from 806 and was actually the leader of the Imperial Family.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>兄の平城天皇とも良好な関係を保っており、大同2年5月には、神泉苑に行幸した兄について献物を行い、終日宴会にも参加している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As he maintained good relationship with his elder brother the Emperor Heijo, he followed his elder brother on the occasion of Imperial visit to Shinsen-en Temple in the 5th month of the 2nd year of Daido era, made an offering and participated in the party throughout the day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As he maintained good a relationship with his elder brother Emperor Heijo, he followed his elder brother on the occasion of an Imperial visit to Shinsen-en Temple in the fifth month of the second year of the Daido era, made an offering and participated in a party throughout the day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As he maintained a good relationship with his elder brother Emperor Heijo, he followed his elder brother on the occasion of an Imperial visit to Shinsen-en Temple in June 807, made an offering and participated in a party throughout the day.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>ところが同年10月に藤原宗成が伊予親王に謀反を勧めているという情報を藤原雄友が察知し、これを右大臣藤原内麻呂に報告する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 10th month of the same year, however, FUJIWARA no Otomo scented the information that FUJIWARA no Munenari was instigating Imperial Prince Iyo to rebel and reported to that effect to udaijin FUJIWARA no Uchimaro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the tenth month of the same year, however, FUJIWARA no Otomo scented the information that FUJIWARA no Munenari was instigating Imperial Prince Iyo to rebel and reported to that effect to udaijin FUJIWARA no Uchimaro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the same year, however, FUJIWARA no Otomo scented the information that FUJIWARA no Munenari was instigating Imperial Prince Iyo to rebel and reported to that effect to udaijin FUJIWARA no Uchimaro.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一方、伊予親王も宗成に唆された経緯を平城天皇に報告する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Imperial Prince Iyo also reported the details of Munenari&apos;s instigation to the Emperor Heijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Imperial Prince Iyo also reported the details of Munenari&apos;s instigation to Emperor Heijo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Imperial Prince Iyo also reported the details of Munenari&apos;s instigation to Emperor Heijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで朝廷が宗成を尋問した所、宗成は伊予親王こそ首謀者だと自白した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Imperial court inquired of Munenari and Munenari confessed that Imperial Prince Iyo himself was a ringleader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, the Imperial court inquired of Munenari and Munenari confessed that Imperial Prince Iyo himself was a ringleader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, the Imperial court inquired of Munenari and Munenari confessed that Imperial Prince Iyo himself was a ringleader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この自白を聞いた平城天皇は安倍兄雄・巨勢野足に命じて、藤原吉子・伊予親王母子を逮捕し川原寺に幽閉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon hearing this confession, the Emperor Heijo ordered ABE no Anio and KOSE no Notari to arrest Fujiwara no Yoshiko and Imperial Prince Iyo and imprisoned them at Kawahara-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon hearing this confession, Emperor Heijo ordered ABE no Anio and KOSE no Notari to arrest Fujiwara no Yoshiko and Imperial Prince Iyo and imprisoned them at Kawahara-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon hearing this confession, Emperor Heijo ordered ABE no Anio and KOSE no Notari to arrest Fujiwara no Yoshiko and Imperial Prince Iyo and imprisoned them at Kawahara-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>二人は身の潔白を主張したが聞き入れられず、11月12日にそろって毒を飲んで心中したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though two persons insisted their innocence, it was not accepted and they poisoned themselves on the 12th day of the 11th month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though two persons insisted on their innocence, it was not accepted and they poisoned themselves on the twelfth day of the eleventh month.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though two persons insisted on their innocence, it was not accepted and they poisoned themselves on December 18.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後に二人の無罪が認められ、墓は山陵とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were found not guilty later on and their graves were designated as Imperial tombs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were found not guilty later on and their graves were designated as Imperial tombs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were found not guilty later on and their graves were designated as Imperial tombs.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>この事件で宗成は流刑となり、伊予親王の伯父藤原雄友も連座して伊予国に流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Munenari was banished due to this incident and Fujiwara no Otomo, an uncle of Imperial Prince Iyo, was also banished to Iyo Province as an accomplice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Munenari was banished due to this incident and Fujiwara no Otomo, an uncle of Imperial Prince Iyo, was also banished to Iyo Province as an accomplice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Munenari was banished due to this incident and Fujiwara no Otomo, an uncle of Imperial Prince Iyo, was also banished to Iyo Province as an accomplice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、この事件のあおりを受けて中納言藤原乙叡が解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Chunagon (middle counselor) FUJIWARA no Takatoshi was suffered the ripple effect of this incident and was removed from his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Chunagon (middle counselor) FUJIWARA no Takatoshi suffered the ripple effect of this incident and was removed from his position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Chunagon (middle counselor) FUJIWARA no Takatoshi suffered the ripple effect of this incident and was removed from his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この事件により大官が2人も罰せられた藤原南家の勢力が大幅に後退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As two high officials of the clan were punished due to this incident, the power of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan declined substantially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As two high officials of the clan were punished due to this incident, the power of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan declined substantially.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As two high officials of the clan were punished due to this incident, the power of the Southern House of the Fujiwara clan declined substantially.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、宗成は藤原仲成・薬子兄妹に唆されたともいわれているが、詳細は不明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is also said that Munenari was instigated by the siblings of Fujiwara no Nakanari and Kusuko, the details is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is also said that Munenari was instigated by the siblings of Fujiwara no Nakanari and Kusuko, the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is also said that Munenari was instigated by the siblings of Fujiwara no Nakanari and Kusuko, the details are not clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>但し、この事件以降平城天皇と仲成・薬子との結びつきはさらに強固なものとなったらしく、尚侍であった薬子の昇進を考慮して、事件の直後に尚侍の官位相当が従五位から従三位に引き上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it seems that the relationship between the Emperor Heijo and Nakanari/Kusuko became stronger and the court rank of Naishi no Kami (Principal Handmaid) was upgraded from Jugoi (Junior Fifth Grade) to Jusanmi (Junior Third Grade) soon after this incident taking into account the promotion of Kusuko, who was then Naishi no Kami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it seems that the relationship between Emperor Heijo and Nakanari/Kusuko became stronger and the court rank of Naishi no Kami (Principal Handmaid) was upgraded from Jugoi (Junior Fifth Grade) to Jusanmi (Junior Third Grade) soon after this incident taking into account the promotion of Kusuko, who was then Naishi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it seems that the relationship between Emperor Heijo and Nakanari/Kusuko became stronger and the court rank of Naishi no Kami (Principal Handmaid) was upgraded from Jugoi (Junior Fifth Grade) to Jusanmi (Junior Third Grade) soon after this incident taking into account the promotion of Kusuko, who was then Naishi no Kami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Snap55(id:89773), Ymatsui4(id:76324), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>