<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>丁子屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choji-ya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choji-ya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choji-ya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>丁子屋（ちょうじや）は、江戸時代にはすでに存在が確認されている、日本の古くからの屋号（商号）のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Choji-ya (丁子屋) is one of the oldest yago (trade name), which is confirmed its existence in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Choji-ya (丁子屋) is one of the oldest yago (trade name), which is confirmed to have already existed in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choji-ya (丁子屋) is one of the oldest yago (trade name), which is confirmed to have already existed in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「丁字屋」という表記ヴァリエーションも存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is another written variation of &apos;Choji-ya&apos;(丁字屋).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another writing variation for &apos;Choji-ya&apos; (丁字屋).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another writing variation for &apos;Choji-ya&apos; (丁字屋).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>丁子に由来する商号で、丁子の絵柄が含まれる家紋を持つ商家が名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The yago is a trade name derived from choji (a clove tree), and it was used by shoka (mercantile house) whose kamon (family crest) contained a design of cloves).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This trade name derived from choji (a clove tree), and it was used by shoka (mercantile house) whose kamon (family crest) contained a design of cloves.</e>
<cmt>主語を修正しました。不必要な)を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This trade name derived from choji (a clove tree), and it was used by shoka (mercantile house) whose kamon (family crest) contained a design of cloves.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、丁子に関する商売を行う者が屋号として使うケースもあった（丁子油・香料・漢方薬など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, there were cases that merchants whose business were related to choji (clove oil, perfume, herbal medicines, and so on) used the yago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there were cases that merchants whose business were related to choji (clove oil, perfume, and herbal medicines) used the yago.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there were cases that merchants whose business were related to choji (clove oil, perfume, and herbal medicines) used the yago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そこから広がって、植物に関係する職業（藍染屋）などでも、丁子屋の屋号は使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The usage of the yago of choji-ya had also spread to trades related to plants (indigo-dyeing shops).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The usage of the yago of choji-ya has also spread to trades related to plants (indigo-dyeing shops).</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The usage of the yago of choji-ya has also spread to trades related to plants (indigo-dyeing shops).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>丁子油は日本刀の手入れなどに使われるものであり、香料・漢方薬なども江戸時代には決して安いものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Including clove oil which is used to take care of a Japanese sword and so on, perfumes and herbal medicines and so on were also none too inexpensive during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clove oil was used to take care of Japanese swords and its perfumes and herbal medicines were also not cheap during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clove oil was used to take care of Japanese swords and its perfumes and herbal medicines were also not cheap during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>丁子屋を名乗る店は数多く存在したが、そういった事情である程度以上の商業資本家としての商家だったものも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, although there were a lot of shoke under the name of choji-ya, many of them had a certain level of business capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, although there were a lot of shoka under the name of choji-ya, many of them had a certain level of business capital.</e>
<cmt>商家のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, although there were a lot of shoka under the name of choji-ya, many of them had a certain level of business capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、明治維新以降も暖簾を守り続けている店も散見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, there are still such shops which are keeping their noren (a short, split curtain hung at the entrance of a room) from all over the place even after Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, there are still such shops which are keeping their noren (a short, split curtain hung at the entrance of a store, which now represents the stores&apos; goodwill and credit) in various places even after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。暖簾の説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, there are still such shops which are keeping their noren (a short, split curtain hung at the entrance of a store, which now represents the stores&apos; goodwill and credit) in various places even after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dseiande(id:175348), Nekosuki600(id:21263), 健ちゃん(id:60346), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>