<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>王朝国家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dynastic Polity</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>王朝国家（おうちょうこっか）は、日本が律令制から中世国家体制へ移行する過渡期の国家体制を表す歴史概念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Dynastic polity&quot; is the historical notion which refers to Japan&apos;s state regime in a transitional period during which it was in the process of transition from the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code) to the mediaeval national polity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Dynastic polity&quot; is the historical notion which refers to Japan&apos;s state regime in a transitional period during which it was in the process of transition from the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code) to the medieval national polity.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Dynastic polity&quot; is the historical notion which refers to Japan&apos;s state regime in a transitional period during which it was in the process of transition from the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the Ritsuryo code) to the medieval national polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>王朝国家体制とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Dynasty state regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called a Dynasty state regime.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called a Dynasty state regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>10世紀初頭に成立し、11世紀中期ないし12世紀後期までの期間に存続したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered this polity was established in early 10th century and continued to exist until mid-11th century or late 12th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered this polity was established in early 10th century and continued to exist until the mid-11th century or late 12th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered this polity was established in early 10th century and continued to exist until the mid-11th century or late 12th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>律令国家体制は、中央集権的な政治機構に立脚し、個別人身支配を人民支配・租税収取の原則としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the centralized political structure, Ritsuryo system&apos;s basic philosophy for ruling people/collecting tax was the people-based governance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the centralized political structure, Ritsuryo system&apos;s basic philosophy for ruling people/collecting tax was the people-based governance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the centralized political structure, Ritsuryo system&apos;s basic philosophy for ruling people/collecting tax was the people-based governance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、それらを実際に支えていたのは現地で人民支配・租税収取にあたる地方行政であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In reality, however, this system was supported by local administrative bodies which were in charge of ruling people/collecting tax in each region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In reality, however, this system was supported by local administrative bodies which were in charge of ruling people/collecting tax in each region.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In reality, however, this system was supported by local administrative bodies which were in charge of ruling people/collecting tax in each region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>9世紀後期に至って律令制的な人民支配・租税収取に限界が生じたため、10世紀初頭より、地方政治への大幅な統治委任や個別人身支配から土地課税原則への方針転換が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the limitation of people-based governance/tax collection under the Ritsuryo system became clear in late 9th century, policy changes, such as substantial delegation of authority to local administrative bodies and the switch from the principle of people-based governance to the principle of tax on land, were implemented in early 10th century,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the limitation of people-based governance/tax collection under the Ritsuryo system became clear in the late 9th century, policy changes, such as substantial delegation of authority to local administrative bodies and the switch from the principle of people-based governance to the principle of tax on land, were implemented in early 10th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the limitation of people-based governance/tax collection under the Ritsuryo system became clear in the late 9th century, policy changes, such as substantial delegation of authority to local administrative bodies and the switch from the principle of people-based governance to the principle of tax on land, were implemented in early 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>こうして新たに構築された統治体制が王朝国家体制であるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the new regime which was established through the above process was the Dynastic polity regime.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the new regime which was established through the above process was the Dynastic polity regime.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the new regime which was established through the above process was the Dynastic polity regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>11世紀中期から12世紀・13世紀初頭にかけて、荘園公領制の成立や院政・武家政治の登場などに対応した中世国家体制が漸進的に構築されていったため、この時期に王朝国家体制は終期を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the mediaeval national polity, which corresponded to the establishment of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) and the advent of cloister government/samurai government, was progressively built up during the period from mid-11th century to 12th century/early 13th century, the period of dynastic polity ended around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the medieval national polity, which corresponded to the establishment of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) and the advent of cloister government/samurai government, was progressively built up during the period from the mid-11th century to the 12th century/early 13th century, the period of dynastic polity ended around that time.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the medieval national polity, which corresponded to the establishment of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) and the advent of cloister government/samurai government, was progressively built up during the period from the mid-11th century to the 12th century/early 13th century, the period of dynastic polity ended around that time.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし、王朝国家の終期をめぐっては複数の説が提示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are several views on the time of dynastic polity&apos;s end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are several views on the time of dynastic polity&apos;s end.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are several views on the time of dynastic polity&apos;s end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>王朝の語は、戦前期より、鎌倉時代以降を武家時代と称したのに対し奈良時代・平安時代を王朝時代と称したことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;dynastic&quot; derives from the fact that the Nara period and the Heian period were collectively called Dynastic period in the pre-War period while the Kamakura period and subsequent periods were collectively called Feudal period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;dynastic&quot; derives from the fact that the Nara period and the Heian period were collectively called Dynastic periods in the pre-War period while the Kamakura period and subsequent periods were collectively called Feudal periods.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;dynastic&quot; derives from the fact that the Nara period and the Heian period were collectively called Dynastic periods in the pre-War period while the Kamakura period and subsequent periods were collectively called Feudal periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>戦後、日本史研究の進展に伴い、律令支配を原則としていた奈良期-平安前期と、律令を必ずしも支配原則としなくなった平安中期・後期とを別個の時代ととらえる考えが主流を占めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the study of Japanese history progressed after the War, the view which regards Nara/early Heian period, during which the Ritsuryo system was the basis of governance, and mid-Heian/late Heian period, during which the Ritsuryo system was not necessarily the basis of governance, as the separate periods became dominant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the study of Japanese history progressed after the War, the view which regards Nara/early Heian period, during which the Ritsuryo system was the basis of governance, and mid-Heian/late Heian period, during which the Ritsuryo system was not necessarily the basis of governance, as separate periods became dominant.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the study of Japanese history progressed after the War, the view which regards Nara/early Heian period, during which the Ritsuryo system was the basis of governance, and mid-Heian/late Heian period, during which the Ritsuryo system was not necessarily the basis of governance, as separate periods became dominant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それに伴い、前者の時代区分を律令時代、前者の国家体制を律令国家と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, the periodization of the former was named the Ritsuryo period and its state regime was named Ritsuryo polity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, the periodization of the former was named the Ritsuryo period and its state regime was named Ritsuryo polity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, the periodization of the former was named the Ritsuryo period and its state regime was named Ritsuryo polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これに対して、王朝時代は後者の時代区分として認識され、同様に後者の国家体制を指して王朝国家という語が使用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the periodization of the latter was named the Dynastic period and the term Dynastic polity, which refers to the state regime of the latter, became in use.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the periodization of the latter was named the Dynastic period and the term Dynastic polity, which refers to the state regime of the latter, became used.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the periodization of the latter was named the Dynastic period and the term Dynastic polity, which refers to the state regime of the latter, became used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief history</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>王朝国家の出現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advent of Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Advent of Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Advent of Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>8世紀初頭に確立した律令制は、個人を徴税単位とする個別人身支配（人別支配）を基本原則としており、高度に体系化された律令法典・官僚制度・地方制度や古代の戸籍制度・計帳などを基盤として存立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ritsuryo system, which was established in early 8th century, adopted the principle of people-based governance (ruling individuals) and existed on the basis of highly systemized Ritsuryo code of law/bureaucracy system/local administration system as well as family registration system/keicho (yearly tax registers) etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ritsuryo system, which was established in early 8th century, adopted the principle of people-based governance (ruling individuals) and existed on the basis of the highly systematized Ritsuryo code of law/bureaucracy system/local administration system as well as the family registration system/keicho (yearly tax registers) etc.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ritsuryo system, which was established in early 8th century, adopted the principle of people-based governance (ruling individuals) and existed on the basis of the highly systematized Ritsuryo code of law/bureaucracy system/local administration system as well as the family registration system/keicho (yearly tax registers) etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>特に、古くからの地域における首長層を再編した郡司層の首長権への精神面での服従構造と、経営の安定性を欠く零細百姓層の経営維持を保証する出挙は、本来古代日本とは異質な社会である唐代中国社会を成立背景とした律令制が、日本で成立する上で重要であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, the structure of mental obedience to the chieftaincy of Gunji (local magistrates), who used to be the chiefs of village community since the ancient times, as well as suiko (a kind of official loan system), which was supposed to guarantee the sustainable management of small-hold peasants, were quite important for maintaining the Ritsuryo system in Japan since this system was originally created in the context of Chinese society of Tang Dynasty, a quite different society from that of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the structure of mental obedience to the chieftaincy of Gunji (local magistrates), who used to be the chiefs of village community since ancient times, as well as suiko (a kind of official loan system), which was supposed to guarantee the sustainable management of small-hold peasants, were quite important for maintaining the Ritsuryo system in Japan since this system was originally created in the context of Chinese society of the Tang Dynasty, a quite different society from that of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the structure of mental obedience to the chieftaincy of Gunji (local magistrates), who used to be the chiefs of village community since ancient times, as well as suiko (a kind of official loan system), which was supposed to guarantee the sustainable management of small-hold peasants, were quite important for maintaining the Ritsuryo system in Japan since this system was originally created in the context of Chinese society of the Tang Dynasty, a quite different society from that of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、早くも8世紀後期頃から百姓の偽籍・浮浪・逃亡が見られ始め、個別人身支配体制にほころびが生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as early as from late 8th century, the regime of people-based governance started to fray at edges as the case of peasants&apos; false registration, vagrancy and escape increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as early as from late 8th century, the regime of people-based governance started to fray at the edges as the case of peasants&apos; false registration, vagrancy and escape increased.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as early as from late 8th century, the regime of people-based governance started to fray at the edges as the case of peasants&apos; false registration, vagrancy and escape increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、8世紀後期から9世紀を通じて律令制を維持または再構築しようとする試みが繰り返されたが、大多数の貧困百姓層とごく少数の富裕百姓層（富豪層）という百姓層内の階層分離はますます加速していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the measures aiming to maintain or restructure the Ritsuryo system were repeatedly implemented during the period from late 8th century to 9th century, peasants were increasingly split into a large majority of peasants in poverty and a small minority of wealthy peasants (wealthy peasants class).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although measures aiming to maintain or restructure the Ritsuryo system were repeatedly implemented during the period from late 8th century to 9th century, peasants were increasingly split into a large majority of peasants in poverty and a small minority of wealthy peasants (wealthy peasants class).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although measures aiming to maintain or restructure the Ritsuryo system were repeatedly implemented during the period from late 8th century to 9th century, peasants were increasingly split into a large majority of peasants in poverty and a small minority of wealthy peasants (wealthy peasants class).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>貧困層は偽籍・逃亡によって租税負担から逃れ、富豪層は墾田活動を通じて得分収取しうる田地を獲得し、逃亡したり私出挙によって負債を負わせた貧困百姓らを保護民、隷属民として囲い込んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While peasants in poverty evaded tax by false registration or escape, wealthy peasants acquired additional farmland through reclamation, which they were allowed to own privately, and made poor peasants, especially those escaped or were debt-burned due to private suiko, their subordinate people.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While peasants in poverty evaded tax by false registration or escape, wealthy peasants acquired additional farmland through reclamation, which they were allowed to own privately, and made poor peasants, especially those who escaped or were debt-burned due to private suiko, their subordinate people.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While peasants in poverty evaded tax by false registration or escape, wealthy peasants acquired additional farmland through reclamation, which they were allowed to own privately, and made poor peasants, especially those who escaped or were debt-burned due to private suiko, their subordinate people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="19">
<j>個別人身支配の基礎となっていたのは戸籍・計帳であったが、上記の状況は、もはや戸籍・計帳による人民支配租税収取が限界を迎えていたことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although family registration and keicho were the foundation of people-based governance, the above situation clearly demonstrated the limitation of people-based governance/tax collection that relied on family registration and keicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although family registration and keicho were the foundation of people-based governance, the above situation clearly demonstrated the limitation of people-based governance/tax collection that relied on family registration and keicho.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although family registration and keicho were the foundation of people-based governance, the above situation clearly demonstrated the limitation of people-based governance/tax collection that relied on family registration and keicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、個別人身支配を受けるべき個々の民は、かつてのように地域首長層の末裔たる郡司の首長権への精神的服従意識によって統率された存在ではなくなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, individuals who were supposed to be subject to people-based governance were no more the people who were led by mental obedience consciousness to the chieftaincy of Gunji, the descendants of the chiefs of village communities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, individuals who were supposed to be subject to people-based governance were no more the people who were led by mental obedience consciousness to the chieftaincy of Gunji, the descendants of the chiefs of village communities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, individuals who were supposed to be subject to people-based governance were no more the people who were led by mental obedience consciousness to the chieftaincy of Gunji, the descendants of the chiefs of village communities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>彼らは、生産基盤となる動産を集積し、安定経営を達成した富豪層の保護、隷属関係よって統率された存在に変質を遂げていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead, they had already changed into the subprdinates of wealthy peasants, who had hoarded movables necessary for farming and had achieved sustainable management.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead, they had already changed into the subordinates of wealthy peasants, who had hoarded movables necessary for farming and had achieved sustainable management.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead, they had already changed into the subordinates of wealthy peasants, who had hoarded movables necessary for farming and had achieved sustainable management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>こうした状況を受け、政府は、従前の個別人身支配に代わって租税収取を確保するための新たな支配体制を構築するため、大きな方針転換を迫られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the government was pressed to build up a new regime, in lieu of then existing people-based governance, which enable it to secure tax revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, the government was pressed to build up a new regime, in lieu of the then existing people-based governance, which enabled it to secure tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the government was pressed to build up a new regime, in lieu of the then existing people-based governance, which enabled it to secure tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>9世紀末～10世紀初年に醍醐天皇及び藤原時平が主導した律令制復活の最後の試みである延喜の治が失敗に終わると、次代の朱雀天皇及び藤原忠平は、個別人身支配を基調とする体制から土地課税基調の体制へと大きな政策転回を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Engi no chi (Reign of the Emperor Daigo), the last attempt for reviving the Ritsuryo system led by the Emperor Daigo and Fujiwara no Tokihira during the period from the end of 9th century to early 10th century, ended in failure, the emperor Suzaku, the succesor, and Fujiwara no Tadahira made a bold policy change from the principle of people-based governance to taht of tax on land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Engi no chi (Reign of the Emperor Daigo), the last attempt for reviving the Ritsuryo system led by the Emperor Daigo and Fujiwara no Tokihira during the period from the end of the 9th century to the early 10th century, ended in failure, the emperor Suzaku, his succesor, and Fujiwara no Tadahira made a bold policy change from the principle of people-based governance to that of tax on land.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Engi no chi (Reign of the Emperor Daigo), the last attempt for reviving the Ritsuryo system led by the Emperor Daigo and FUJIWARA no Tokihira during the period from the end of the 9th century to the early 10th century, ended in failure, the emperor Suzaku, his successor, and FUJIWARA no Tadahira made a bold policy change from the principle of people-based governance to that of tax on land.</e>
<cmt>人名修正スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>朱雀期以降、律令制的人別支配を前提とする班田収授が実施されていないことなどが、この政策転回の存在を示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This policy change is proved by the fact that the government ceased to conduct handen shuju (a system of periodic reallocations of rice land), whose premise was peopl-based governance under the Ritsuryo system, since Suzaku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This policy change was proven by the fact that the government ceased to conduct handen shuju (a system of periodic reallocations of rice land), whose premise was people-based governance under the Ritsuryo system, since the Suzaku era.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This policy change was proven by the fact that the government ceased to conduct handen shuju (a system of periodic reallocations of rice land), whose premise was people-based governance under the Ritsuryo system, since the Suzaku era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>個人を課税対象として把握する個別人身支配において、偽籍・逃亡が頻発すると課税対象である個人を把握することはできなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the principle of people-based governance, the government imposes tax on individuals, but it becomes impossible to grasp the name of taxable people if the case of false registration and/or escape occurs frequently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the principle of people-based governance, the government imposes tax on individuals, but it becomes impossible to grasp the name of taxable people if the case of false registration and/or escape occurs frequently.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the principle of people-based governance, the government imposes tax on individuals, but it becomes impossible to grasp the name of taxable people if the case of false registration and/or escape occurs frequently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、土地課税原則のもとでは、田地の存在さえ把握していればそこを実質的に経営している富豪層から収取すべき租税を収取することが十分可能となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the principle of tax on land, however, the government can collect tax from wealthy peasants who eventually manage the land in question only by confirming the existence of land.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the principle of tax on land, however, the government can collect tax from wealthy peasants who eventually manage the land in question only by confirming the existence of land.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the principle of tax on land, however, the government can collect tax from wealthy peasants who eventually manage the land in question only by confirming the existence of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>こうした考えが、政策方針の転回の背景にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above intention was the background of the policy change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The above intention was the background of the policy change.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The above intention was the background of the policy change.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="28">
<j>土地課税を重視する考えは9世紀前期の藤原冬嗣執政期の頃から存在していたが、個別人身支配の原則を覆すまでには至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the idea of emphasizing tax on land existed in the era when Fujiwara no Fuyutsugu was in power, it stoped short of reversing the principle of people-based governance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the idea of emphasizing tax on land existed in the era when Fujiwara no Fuyutsugu was in power, it stopped short of reversing the principle of people-based governance.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the idea of emphasizing tax on land existed in the era when FUJIWARA no Fuyutsugu was in power during the first half of the 9th century, it stopped short of reversing the principle of people-based governance.</e>
<cmt>人名修正during the first half of the 9th centry補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>10世紀初頭の朱雀期になって初めて個別人身支配が放棄された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principle of people-based governance was finally abandoned in Suzaku era, early 10th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principle of people-based governance was finally abandoned in the Suzaku era, early 10th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principle of people-based governance was finally abandoned in the Suzaku era, early 10th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ここに、律令国家体制期が終わり、土地課税を基本原則とする新たな支配体制、すなわち王朝国家体制が出現することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the system of the nation under the Ritsuryo codes ceased to exist and the new regime which adopted the principle of land on tax, namely Dynastic polity, was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the system of the nation under the Ritsuryo codes ceased to exist and the new regime which adopted the principle of tax on land, namely Dynastic polity, was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the system of the nation under the Ritsuryo codes ceased to exist and the new regime which adopted the principle of tax on land, namely Dynastic polity, was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>なお土地課税基調体制への移行の時期について、宇多天皇及び菅原道真の主導による寛平の治を王朝国家体制への転換準備期とし、延喜の治を時平による王朝国家体制への移行期であるとする意見（平田耿二,2000など）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the time when the old system shifted to the system based on tax on land, there is a view asserting that the era of Kanpyo no chi (Glorious rule in Kanpyo era), led by the Emperor Uda and Sugawara no Michizane, was the preparatory period for the transition to the Dynastic polity regime and Engi no chi (Reign of Emperor Daigo), led by Tokihira, was the transitional period to the Dynastic polity regime (Koji HIRATA, 2000).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the time when the old system shifted to the system based on tax on land, there is a view asserting that the era of Kanpyo no chi (Glorious rule in the Kanpyo era), led by the Emperor Uda and Sugawara no Michizane, was the preparatory period for the transition to the Dynastic polity regime and Engi no chi (Reign of Emperor Daigo), led by Tokihira, was the transitional period to the Dynastic polity regime (Koji HIRATA, 2000).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the time when the old system shifted to the system based on tax on land, there is a view asserting that the era of Kanpyo no chi (Glorious rule in the Kanpyo era), led by the Emperor Uda and SUGAWARA no Michizane, was the preparatory period for the transition to the Dynastic polity regime and Engi no chi (Reign of Emperor Daigo), led by Tokihira, was the transitional period to the Dynastic polity regime (Koji HIRATA, 2000).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>王朝国家の成立・発展</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment and development of dynastic polity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment and development of dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment and development of dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>王朝国家体制の特質は、律令国家体制が基調としていた個別人身支配を放棄し、土地に対する課税・支配を基調とした点にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What characterized the Dynastic polity regime was the adoption of the principle of tax on land as substitute for the principle of people-based governance, which had been the basic principle of the Ritsuryo regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What characterized the Dynastic polity regime was the adoption of the principle of tax on land as a replacement for the principle of people-based governance, which had been the basic principle of the Ritsuryo regime.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What characterized the Dynastic polity regime was the adoption of the principle of tax on land as a replacement for the principle of people-based governance, which had been the basic principle of the Ritsuryo regime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>すでに9世紀後期の頃から、実際に租税収取を担当する地方行政の現場では、戸籍・計帳を基盤に置いた課税方式が後退し、土地に対する課税が積極的に行われる傾向にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As early as from late 9th century, local administrative bodies, which were actually in charge of tax collection, tended to impose tax on land rather than collecting it based on family registration/keicho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As early as from the late 9th century, local administrative bodies, which were actually in charge of tax collection, tended to impose tax on land rather than collecting it based on family registration/keicho.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As early as from the late 9th century, local administrative bodies, which were actually in charge of tax collection, tended to impose tax on land rather than collecting it based on family registration/keicho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そうした地方行政の実情を国家体制の基本方針に採用したのが、10世紀初頭だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was early 10th century when the government adopted such actual situation of local administration as the basic policy of the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was early 10th century when the government adopted the actual situation of local administration as the basic policy of the nation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was early 10th century when the government adopted the actual situation of local administration as the basic policy of the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>土地課税が租税収取の基本原則とされるに当たり、租税体系の基礎とされたのが公田である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In adopting the principle of tax on land, Koden (field administered directly by a ruler) was the base of tax system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In adopting the principle of tax on land, Koden (field administered directly by a ruler) was the base of the tax system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In adopting the principle of tax on land, Koden (field administered directly by a ruler) was the base of the tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>律令制における租税（租庸調）は、個人に対して課せられていたが、新たな租税制度のもとでは公田に対して課税がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Soyocho, three kinds of taxes under the Ritsuryo system, were imposed on individuals, tax was imposed on Koden under the new tax system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Soyocho, three kinds of taxes under the Ritsuryo system, were imposed on individuals, tax was imposed on Koden under the new tax system.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Soyocho, three kinds of taxes under the Ritsuryo system, were imposed on individuals, tax was imposed on Koden under the new tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>10世紀初頭頃から、公田は名田と呼ばれる租税収取の基礎単位へ編成され、現地の富豪層（田堵・負名層）が名田経営と租税納入を請け負うという名体制が形成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In early 10th century, Koden was reorganized into the base for taxing called Myoden (rice field lots managed by a nominal holder) and the system called Myo-system, under which local wealthy peasants (Tato (cultivators)/Fumyoso (tiller of the public rice field)) were responsible for the management of Myoden as well as land tax payment, was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early 10th century, Koden was reorganized into the base for taxing called Myoden (rice field lots managed by a nominal holder) and the system called Myo-system, under which local wealthy peasants (Tato (cultivators)/Fumyoso (tiller of the public rice field)) were responsible for the management of Myoden as well as land tax payment, was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early 10th century, Koden was reorganized into the base for taxing called Myoden (rice field lots managed by a nominal holder) and the system called Myo-system, under which local wealthy peasants (Tato (cultivators)/Fumyoso (tiller of the public rice field)) were responsible for the management of Myoden as well as land tax payment, was established.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>この名体制は、王朝国家体制の基盤をなすものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Myo-system was the base of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Myo-system was the base of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Myo-system was the base of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>国内の公田を名田へ再編成していく過程で、従来の班田図は不必要とされ、新たに国内の公田台帳となる基準国図が作成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process of reorganizing Koden into Myoden, former handen map (map of allotted farmland) was abolished and instead, Kijunkokuzu (standardized map of provinces), a register of Koden, was made.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process of reorganizing Koden into Myoden, former handen maps (map of allotted farmland) were abolished and instead, Kijunkokuzu (standardized map of provinces), a register of Koden, was made.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the process of reorganizing Koden into Myoden, former handen maps (map of allotted farmland) were abolished and instead, Kijunkokuzu (standardized map of provinces), a register of Koden, was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>同時に、国司に検田権が付与されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, kendenken (the right of cadastral surveys) was given to kokushi (provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, kendenken (the right of cadastral surveys) was given to kokushi (provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, kendenken (the right of cadastral surveys) was given to kokushi (provincial governors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>これらは王朝国家体制の成立を示す指標と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are considered to be the indexes of the establishment of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are considered to be the indexes of the establishment of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are considered to be the indexes of the establishment of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="42">
<j>名体制を確立するため、現地支配に当たる国司の筆頭者の権限強化が求められるようになり、10世紀中頃には租税収取・軍事警察などの分野で中央政府から現地赴任筆頭国司への大幅な権限委譲が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As strengthening the authority of the head of kokushi, who were responsible for local administration, was required in order to maintain the above system, big transfer of authority from the central government to the head of kokushi was made in mid-10th century concerning tax collection and military police.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As strengthening the authority of the head of kokushi, who were responsible for local administration, was required in order to maintain the above system, a big transfer of authority from the central government to the head of kokushi was made in the mid-10th century concerning tax collection and military police.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As strengthening the authority of the head of kokushi, who were responsible for local administration, was required in order to maintain the above system, a big transfer of authority from the central government to the head of kokushi was made in the mid-10th century concerning tax collection and military police.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>こうして国内支配に大きな権限を有する国司、すなわち受領層が出現することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, kokushi who had great authority in the governance of provinces, namely zuryo (the head of the provincial governors), appeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, kokushi who had great authority in the governance of provinces, namely zuryo (the head of the provincial governors), appeared.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, kokushi who had great authority in the governance of provinces, namely zuryo (the head of the provincial governors), appeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>強力な権限を獲得した国司は、国内に自らの行政権をあまねく及ぼすため、行政機能の強化を目的として、国衙に政所（公文所）・田所・税所・検非違使所などの機関を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi who were given great authority established, with the aim of demonstrating their executive power and strengthening administrative function, various organs at kokuga (provincial government offices), including mandokoro (administrative board), kumonjo (administration office), zeidokoro (tax office) and kebiishi dokoro (police and judicial office) etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi who were given great authority established, with the aim of demonstrating their executive power and strengthening administrative function, various organs at kokuga (provincial government offices), including mandokoro (administrative board), kumonjo (administration office), zeidokoro (tax office) and kebiishi dokoro (police and judicial office) etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi who were given great authority established, with the aim of demonstrating their executive power and strengthening administrative function, various organs at kokuga (provincial government offices), including mandokoro (administrative board), kumonjo (administration office), tadokoro, zeidokoro (tax office) and kebiishi dokoro (police and judicial office) etc.</e>
<cmt>tadokoro補足　英語説明不明</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>こうした機関の実務官僚として、現地の富豪層・田堵負名層が採用され、在庁官人として地方行政の実務にあたるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local millionaires and tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager) were recruited as governmental official responsible for practical works at these offices and were in charge of local administrative jobs as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local millionaires and tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager) were recruited as governmental officials responsible for practical works at these offices and were in charge of local administrative jobs as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local millionaires and tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager) were recruited as governmental officials responsible for practical works at these offices and were in charge of local administrative jobs as Zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このような状況は10世紀から11世紀にかけて顕著となっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such situation became increasingly clear from 10th to 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such situations became increasingly clear from 10th to 11th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such situations became increasingly clear from 10th to 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="47">
<j>国司に付与された権限については、租税収取に関するものに注目が集まりやすいが、軍事警察の面でも大きな権限を獲得している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the authority for tax collection tends to be focused, kokushi was also given great authority for military police.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the authority for tax collection tends to be focused, kokushi were also given great authority for military police.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the authority for tax collection tends to be focused, kokushi were also given great authority for military police.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>従前の軍事制度は、個別人身支配を前提とする軍団 (古代日本)及び地方有力者（郡司層）に依存する健児を柱としていた。、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pillars of former millitary system were corps (ancient Japan), whose premise was people-based governance, and kondei system (regular soldiers guarding kokubu (ancient provincial offices) or sekisho (checking station)), which was dependent on locally influencial poepe (gunji).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pillars of the former military system were corps (ancient Japan), whose premise was people-based governance, and the kondei system (regular soldiers guarding kokubu (ancient provincial offices) or sekisho (checking station)), which was dependent on locally influential people (gunji).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pillars of the former military system were corps (ancient Japan), whose premise was people-based governance, and the kondei system (regular soldiers guarding kokubu (ancient provincial offices) or sekisho (checking station)), which was dependent on locally influential people (gunji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし、個別人身支配と郡司の首長権が崩壊すると両制度とも機能しなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these systems became non-functional after the people-based governance system and chieftaincy of gunji collapsed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these systems became non-functional after the people-based governance system and chieftaincy of gunji collapsed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these systems became non-functional after the people-based governance system and chieftaincy of gunji collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一方、9世紀後期頃から、富豪百姓層らが経済力や政治力、さらには私兵を擁しての軍事力すらをもつけてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From late 9th century, meanwhile, wealthy peasants class strengthened not only their economic and political power but also military power with private soldiers at their command.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late 9th century, meanwhile, the wealthy peasant class strengthened not only their economic and political power but also military power with private soldiers at their command.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late 9th century, meanwhile, the wealthy peasant class strengthened not only their economic and political power but also military power with private soldiers at their command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>これを背景として、富豪百姓間相互の紛争もしくは国司と富豪百姓層間の紛争が目立つようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, disputes among wealthy peasants or that of between kokushi and wealthy peasants increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, disputes among wealthy peasants or those between kokushi and wealthy peasants increased.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, disputes among wealthy peasants or those between kokushi and wealthy peasants increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>そこで10世紀前期頃から中央政府は、軍事警察権を国司に委任するという現実的な政策を採用し始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to cope with such situation, the central government started to adopt from early 10th century a realistic policy, meaning the delegation of military and police authorities to kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to cope with such situations, the central government started to adopt from the early 10th century a realistic policy, meaning the delegation of military and police authorities to kokushi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to cope with such situations, the central government started to adopt from the early 10th century a realistic policy, meaning the delegation of military and police authorities to kokushi.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>こうして成立したのが、国衙を中心とする軍制、すなわち国衙軍制である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the kokuga forces system, military system organized by kokuga, was established</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the kokuga forces system, military system organized by kokuga, was established</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the kokuga forces system, military system organized by kokuga, was established.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>国衙軍制成立の過程で武芸、すなわち軍事を専門とする諸大夫身分の貴族（軍事貴族）や侍身分の官人層が出現し、これらの層の上層身分たる軍事貴族層では、特に東国を中心として、自ら国司として現地赴任する者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process of establishing kakuga forces system. shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) (military aristocrat) or samurai officials who are specialized in military art appeared and some of military aristocrats went to various provinces, especially those of eastern Japan, in order to serve as kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process of establishing the kakuga forces system, shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) (military aristocrat) or samurai officials who specialized in military arts appeared and some of the military aristocrats went to various provinces, especially those of eastern Japan, in order to serve as kokushi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the process of establishing the kokuga forces system, shodaibu (aristocrat lower than Kugyo) (military aristocrat) or samurai officials who specialized in military arts appeared and some of the military aristocrats went to various provinces, especially those of eastern Japan, in order to serve as kokushi.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>軍事貴族などの武芸の家は桓武平氏・清和源氏・一部の藤原氏などから出たが、彼らの子孫が後の武士へと成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families of military art, such as military aristocrats, were born from Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan), Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and some of the Fujiwara clan and their descendants later became samurai (warrior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families of military art, such as military aristocrats, were born from Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan), Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and some of the Fujiwara clan and their descendants later became samurai (warrior).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families of military art, such as military aristocrats, were born from Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan), Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and some of the Fujiwara clan and their descendants later became samurai (warrior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="56">
<j>国司は、中央政府から支配権限の委任を受けた代わりに、当該国から中央への租税納入を負担しなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In return for being given governing authority by the central government, kokushi were obliged to pay tax to the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In return for being given governing authority by the central government, kokushi were obliged to pay tax to the central government.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In return for being given governing authority by the central government, kokushi were obliged to pay tax to the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この頃、個別人身支配から土地課税への転換に伴って、従来からあった租庸調・正税・雑徭・交易物などの税目が消え、新たに官物・臨時雑役などといった税目が出現していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the wake of the transition from the principle of people-based governance to the principle of tax on land, former taxes, such as Soyocho, shozei (the rice tax stored in provincial offices&apos; warehouse), zoyo (irregular corvee) and trading goods, were abolished and new items of taxation, such as kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and rinji zoyaku (general term for odd-job tasks), were introduced.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the wake of the transition from the principle of people-based governance to the principle of tax on land, former taxes, such as Soyocho, shozei (the rice tax stored in provincial offices&apos; warehouse), zoyo (irregular corvee) and trading goods, were abolished and new items of taxation, such as kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and rinji zoyaku (general term for odd-job tasks), were introduced.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the wake of the transition from the principle of people-based governance to the principle of tax on land, former taxes, such as Soyocho, shozei (the rice tax stored in provincial offices&apos; warehouse), zoyo (irregular corvee) and trading goods, were abolished and new items of taxation, such as kanmotsu (tribute goods paid as taxes or tithes) and rinji zoyaku (general term for odd-job tasks), were introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>国司はこれら新たな税目（官物・臨時雑役）の中央への納入を義務づけられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokushi were obliged to pay these newly introduced tax items (kanmotsu/rinji zoyaku) to the central government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokushi were obliged to pay these newly introduced tax items (kanmotsu/rinji zoyaku) to the central government.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokushi were obliged to pay these newly introduced tax items (kanmotsu/rinji zoyaku) to the central government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これらの租税を中央へ納入する過程で、国司（受領）は租税の一部を私財化し巨富を得ていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that kokusi (zuryo) embezzled a part of tax through the process of paying it to the central government and obtained big profit,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that kokushi (zuryo) embezzled taxes through the process of paying it to the central government and obtained big profits.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that kokushi (zuryo) embezzled taxes through the process of paying it to the central government and obtained big profits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>しかし、租税納入を怠った、あるいは規定額を達成できなかった受領は、受領功過定（ずりょうこうかさだめ）と呼ばれる人事評定によって厳しい審査・処分を受けていたのであり、受領を巨富が得られる官職と理解することに疑義も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some people assert that the position of zuryo should not be understood as such a profitable one because they were also subject to severe penalty, according to the result of personnel evaluation called zuryo koka sadame, if they failed to pay tax or failed to achieve pre-determined amount.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some people assert that the position of zuryo should not be understood as such a profitable one because they were also subject to severe penalty, according to the result of personnel evaluation called zuryo koka sadame, if they failed to pay taxes or failed to achieve a pre-determined amount.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some people assert that the position of zuryo should not be understood as such a profitable one because they were also subject to severe penalty, according to the result of personnel evaluation called zuryo koka sadame, if they failed to pay taxes or failed to achieve a pre-determined amount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="61">
<j>国内支配に大幅な権限を有した受領と、名経営や私領経営などを通じて経済力をつけてきた郡司・田堵負名層との間には、次第に経済的・政治的矛盾が生じるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gradually, economical and political contradiction became serious between zuryo, who had big authority for ruling provinces, and gunji/tato fumyo class, who had economic power gained through the management of myoden or private estates.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gradually, economical and political contradiction became serious between zuryo, who had big authority for ruling provinces, and gunji/tato fumyo class, who had economic power gained through the management of myoden or private estates.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gradually, economical and political contradiction became serious between zuryo, who had big authority for ruling provinces, and gunji/tato fumyo class, who had economic power gained through the management of myoden or private estates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>10世紀後期から両者間の対立が国司苛政上訴という形で顕在化するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From late 10th century, such contradiction became obvious in the form of Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late 10th century, such contradictions became obvious in the form of Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late 10th century, such contradictions became obvious in the form of Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="63">
<j>王朝国家体制論は主として中央政府がいかに租税収取を確保していったか、という観点で議論されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The arguments concerning the Dynastic polity theory are often made from the viewpoint of the central government&apos;s tax collection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The arguments concerning the Dynastic polity theory are often made from the viewpoint of the central government&apos;s tax collection.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The arguments concerning the Dynastic polity theory are often made from the viewpoint of the central government&apos;s tax collection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>租税収取の最前線はすなわち地方行政の現場であり、必然的に王朝国家に関する議論は地方行政のあり方が焦点となりがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the forefront of tax collection is local administrative offices, the arguments concerning the Dynastic polity tend to focus on those conrning local administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the forefront of tax collection is local administrative offices, the arguments concerning the Dynastic polity tend to focus on those concerning local administration.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the forefront of tax collection is local administrative offices, the arguments concerning the Dynastic polity tend to focus on those concerning local administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>それに対して、中央政府においても当然、王朝国家体制への移行に伴う何らかの行政機構変革があったとする見解が示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a view asserting that some administrative organization reform must have been implemented at the central government in association with the transition to the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there is a view asserting that some administrative organization reform must have been implemented at the central government in association with the transition to the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there is a view asserting that some administrative organization reform must have been implemented at the central government in association with the transition to the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>具体的に中央政府機構の変革についてはまだ明確となっていないが、例えば摂関政治の成立、官司請負制の登場などが、王朝国家体制に対応した中央政治の変化を表しているのではないかとする議論がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the concrete content of reform in the central government organization is not yet clear, some people assert that the establishment of sekkan-seiji (regency) and kanji ukeoisei (government office contract system) demonstrate the change in the central government corresponding to the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the concrete content of reform in the central government organization is not yet clear, some people assert that the establishment of sekkan-seiji (regency) and kanji ukeoisei (government office contract system) demonstrate the change in the central government corresponding to the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the concrete content of reform in the central government organization is not yet clear, some people assert that the establishment of sekkan-seiji (regency) and kanji ukeoisei (government office contract system) demonstrate the change in the central government corresponding to the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="67">
<j>かつては10世紀初頭以降の政治状況・社会状況を指して、中央政府が統治権をほとんど放棄し、地方の無秩序状態をきたした状態と評価されたこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, political/social situation in early 10th century was thought as the society where the central government abandoned almost of its ruling power and invited the state of chaos in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, political/social situations in the early 10th century was thought of as a society where the central government abandoned almost of its ruling power and invited the state of chaos in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, political/social situations in the early 10th century was thought of as a society where the central government abandoned almost of its ruling power and invited the state of chaos in the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>王朝国家論が唱えられ、史学的検証が進んでからは、以上に見るとおり、中央政府は積極的に社会実態に適合した統治体制（王朝国家体制）を構築していったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As explained above, it is now contemplated, thanks to the progress in the study of Dynastic polity and its historical verification, that the central government actively built up the governing structure which could adapt to the changing social situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As explained above, it is now contemplated, thanks to progress in the study of Dynastic polity and its historical verification, that the central government actively built up the governing structure which could adapt to changing social situation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As explained above, it is now contemplated, thanks to progress in the study of Dynastic polity and its historical verification, that the central government actively built up the governing structure which could adapt to changing social situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>王朝国家体制期には後の中世社会の基礎となる要素が多数生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lots of elements which later became the base of medieval society are included in the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lots of elements which later became the base of medieval society are included in the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lots of elements which later became the base of medieval society are included in the Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この時期は古代律令国家の残滓を見せつつも、次なる中世国家につながる時代性格も併せもっており、まさに古代から中世への過渡期に当たるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period is exactly a transitional period from the ancient times to the medieval times since it had the elements of precursor to the medieval national polity while keeping the vestiges of the ancient Ritsuryo-based nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This period is exactly a transitional period from ancient times to medieval times since it had elements of the precursor to the medieval national polity while keeping the vestiges of the ancient Ritsuryo-based nation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This period is exactly a transitional period from ancient times to medieval times since it had elements of the precursor to the medieval national polity while keeping the vestiges of the ancient Ritsuryo-based nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>王朝国家の再編成とその終期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reorganization and ending of the Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reorganization and ending of the Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reorganization and ending of the Dynastic polity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>上記に見た王朝国家体制のあり方に、11世紀中期頃から変質が見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status of Dynastic polity explained above started to change from mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of Dynastic polity explained above started to change from the mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of Dynastic polity explained above started to change from the mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>この時期の王朝国家の変質を示す指標としては、公田官物率法の制定、別名の積極的な設定、所領相論審判権の太政官への集中化などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What demonstrate the change of Dynastic polity occurred at that time are the establishment of Koden kanmotsu rippo (the law fixing the tax rate of kanmotsu, tribute), avtive establishment of bechimyo and the centralization of shoryo soron shinpanken (jurisdiction of the disputes concerning the ownership of land) to Dajokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What demonstrates the change of Dynastic polity occurred at that time are the establishment of Koden kanmotsu rippo (the law fixing the tax rate of kanmotsu, tribute), active establishment of bechimyo and the centralization of shoryo soron shinpanken (jurisdiction of the disputes concerning the ownership of land) to Dajokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What demonstrates the change of Dynastic polity occurred at that time are the establishment of Koden kanmotsu rippo (the law fixing the tax rate of kanmotsu, tribute), active establishment of bechimyo and the centralization of shoryo soron shinpanken (jurisdiction of the disputes concerning the ownership of land) to Dajokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>11世紀40年代ごろから太政官によって制定され始めた公田官物率法は、一国内の税率を固定化する内容を持っており国司に付与された租税収取権に大きな制限を加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koden kanmotsu rippo, which was established by Dajokan around 1140, restricted kokushi&apos;s right to collect tax since it included the provision which fixed the tax rate in a province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koden kanmotsu rippo, which was established by Dajokan around 1140, restricted kokushi&apos;s right to collect tax since it included the provision which fixed the tax rate in a province.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koden kanmotsu rippo, which was established by Dajokan around 1140, restricted kokushi&apos;s right to collect tax since it included the provision which fixed the tax rate in a province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>国司苛政上訴がこの時期までに消滅したのは、公田官物率法が国司の課税権限を抑制し、郡司・田堵負名層との利害関係が解消されたからだとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is contemplated that the reason why kokushi kasei joso disappeared around that time was because koden kanmotsu rippo restricted kokushi&apos;s right to collect tax and conflicts of interest between kokushi and gunji/tato fumyo were resolved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is contemplated that the reason why kokushi kasei joso disappeared around that time was because koden kanmotsu rippo restricted kokushi&apos;s right to collect tax and conflicts of interest between kokushi and gunji/tato fumyo were resolved.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is contemplated that the reason why kokushi kasei joso disappeared around that time was because koden kanmotsu rippo restricted kokushi&apos;s right to collect tax and conflicts of interest between kokushi and gunji/tato fumyo were resolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>また11世紀中期頃には、それまでの名田より遥かに大規模な名田＝別名（べちみょう）が盛んに設定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In mid-11th century, myoden which were far bigger than existing ones, called bechimyo, was actively established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid-11th century, myoden which were far bigger than existing ones, called bechimyo, were actively established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid-11th century, myoden which were far bigger than existing ones, called bechimyo, were actively established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>別名は、従来の地方行政組織であった郡・郷とは別個に設定され、そのため国-郡-郷という組織体系は崩れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As bechimyo was established independently from existing local administrative organizations, namely gun and go, the governing structure consisted of nation, gun and go collapsed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As bechimyo were established independently from existing local administrative organizations, namely gun and go, the governing structure consisted of nation, gun, and go collapsed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As bechimyo were established independently from existing local administrative organizations, namely gun and go, the governing structure consisted of nation, gun, and go collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>さらに、国の下に郡・郷・別名のほか、保・条・院などの租税収取単位が同列で併存するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the units for tax collection called ho, jo and in were created under the nation on a parallel with the existing structure consisted of nation, gun, go and bechimyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the units for tax collection called ho, jo, and in were created under the nation on a parallel with the existing structure consisting of nation, gun, go, and bechimyo.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the units for tax collection called ho, jo, and in were created under the nation on a parallel with the existing structure consisting of nation, gun, go, and bechimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>所領相論に係る裁判についても、それまで国・郡に裁判権が認められていたのが、11世紀中期以降は、太政官のみが裁判することとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, jurisdiction of shoryo soron, which was given to both the nation and gun up to then, was centralized to Dajokan from mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, jurisdiction of shoryo soron, which was given to both the nation and gun up to then, was centralized to Dajokan from the mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, jurisdiction of shoryo soron, which was given to both the nation and gun up to then, was centralized to Dajokan from the mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="79">
<j>こうした支配体制を改変する動きは、1040年代を中心とする11世紀中期になって非常に顕著に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These reforms of governing structure were actively implemented in mid-11th century, especially around 1040s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These reforms of governing structure were actively implemented in the mid-11th century, especially around 1040s.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These reforms of governing structure were actively implemented in the mid-11th century, especially around 1040s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>これらの動きがどのような性格を持つのかについては、様々な議論がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many opinions concerning the nature of the above-mentioned movement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many opinions concerning the nature of the above-mentioned movement.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many opinions concerning the nature of the above-mentioned movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>坂本賞三らはこの時期を王朝国家体制の変質期であるとして、同時期以前を前期王朝国家、以降を後期王朝国家と区分する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozo SAKAMOTO etc. define this period as the changing period of the Dynastic polity and based on it, they separate the Dynastic polity period into the early Dynastic polity period and the late Dynastic polity period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozo SAKAMOTO etc. defined this period as the changing period of the Dynastic polity and based on it, they separate the Dynastic polity period into the early Dynastic polity period and the late Dynastic polity period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozo SAKAMOTO etc. defined this period as the changing period of the Dynastic polity and based on it, they separate the Dynastic polity period into the early Dynastic polity period and the late Dynastic polity period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>そして、鎌倉幕府が成立した12世紀末を後期王朝国家の終期においている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also set the end of Dynastic polity period at the end of 12th century when Kamakura bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also set the end of Dynastic polity period at the end of 12th century when the Kamakura bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also set the end of Dynastic polity period at the end of 12th century when the Kamakura bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="83">
<j>11世紀中期に見られた体制変化・社会変化は、当時徐々に一円化を進め、著しい増加を見せていた荘園に対抗するための国衙側（公領側）の対応策であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The changes in the governing structure and the society occurred in mid-11th century were the countermeasures taken by kokuga side (public land side) in order to counter shoen (manor in medieval Japan), which was rapidly increasing at the time and proceeding with ichienka (realization of complete ownership).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The changes in the governing structure and society that occurred in the mid-11th century were countermeasures taken by kokuga side (public land side) in order to counter shoen (manor in medieval Japan), which were rapidly increasing at the time and proceeding with ichienka (realization of complete ownership).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The changes in the governing structure and society that occurred in the mid-11th century were countermeasures taken by kokuga side (public land side) in order to counter shoen (manor in medieval Japan), which were rapidly increasing at the time and proceeding with ichienka (realization of complete ownership).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>この流れの中で、それまで公田経営請負によって（つまり田堵・負名層となることで）武人としての経済基盤を与えられていたに過ぎなかった武士が、荘園と公領間の武力紛争の対処能力を期待されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the above trend, the ability of samurai, who had maintained their lives through the job of warrior under koden management contract (in other words, by becoming tato/fumyo), was increasingly expected in order to cope with the armed conflict between shoen and public land.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the above trend, the ability of samurai, who had maintained their lives through the job of warriors under koden management contract (in other words, by becoming tato/fumyo), was increasingly expected in order to cope with the armed conflict between shoen and public land.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the above trend, the ability of samurai, who had maintained their lives through the job of warriors under koden management contract (in other words, by becoming tato/fumyo), was increasingly expected in order to cope with the armed conflict between shoen and public land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>そして、国の下部組織である郡、郷、別名、保、条、院や、一円化してまとまった領域を形成するようになった荘園の管理者としての資格を得て、在地領主としての地位を獲得していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They obtained the status of the administrator of local organization of the nation, meaning gun, go, bechimyo, ho, jo and in, as well as that of shoen which had large territory through ichienka, and eventually they became local lords.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They obtained the status of administrator of the local organization of the nation, meaning gun, go, bechimyo, ho, jo, and in, as well as that of shoen which had a large territory through ichienka, and eventually they became local lords.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They obtained the status of administrator of the local organization of the nation, meaning gun, go, bechimyo, ho, jo, and in, as well as that of shoen which had a large territory through ichienka, and eventually they became local lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>これらの動きは、中世を通じて社会体制であり続けた荘園公領制の出現を意味するものであり、これと相前後して開始した院政と併せて、11世紀後期には既に中世に入っていたと見ることもできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These movements implies the arrival of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates), which was the social structure throughout the mediaeval age, and based on this fact together with the advent of cloister government, we can consider that the mediaeval age already arrived in late 11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These movements implies the arrival of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates), which was the social structure throughout the medieval age, and based on this fact together with the advent of cloister government, we can consider that the medieval age already arrived in late 11th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These movements implies the arrival of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates), which was the social structure throughout the medieval age, and based on this fact together with the advent of cloister government, we can consider that the medieval age already arrived in late 11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>そうした立場からは、古代から中世への過渡期に位置づけられるべき王朝国家体制期は、11世紀中期に終わったのだとする見解も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the above standpoint, some assert that the period of Dynastic polity, which should be regarded as the transitional period from the ancient times to the medieval age, ended in mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the above standpoint, some assert that the period of Dynastic polity, which should be regarded as the transitional period from the ancient times to the medieval age, ended in mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above standpoint, some assert that the period of Dynastic polity, which should be regarded as the transitional period from the ancient times to the medieval age, ended in mid-11th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="88">
<j>また一方では、王朝国家と呼ぶべき政治実態は、鎌倉幕府成立後の朝廷にも見られるとして、13世紀の朝廷による支配体制も王朝国家体制期に含める意見（佐藤進一,1983など）もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, some people assert that the ruling system adopted by the Imperial court in 13th century should be included in the Dynastic polity period on the ground that the regime which should be regarded as the Dynastic polity was seen after the establishment of Kamakura bakufu (Shinichi SATO, 1983 etc).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, some people assert that the ruling system adopted by the Imperial court in 13th century should be included in the Dynastic polity period on the ground that the regime which should be regarded as the Dynastic polity was seen after the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Shinichi SATO, 1983 etc).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, some people assert that the ruling system adopted by the Imperial court in 13th century should be included in the Dynastic polity period on the ground that the regime which should be regarded as the Dynastic polity was seen after the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Shinichi SATO, 1983 etc).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>研究史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of the research</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of the research</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of the research</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>王朝国家とは、古代律令国家がいかに中世国家へ移行したかを理解するために提示された概念であり、研究者の立場によって様々な位置づけが試みられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the notion of Dynastic polity was proposed in order to understand how the ancient Ritsuryo-based nation shifted to the medieval nation, varieties of views have been asserted by researchers depending on their standpoint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the notion of Dynastic polity was proposed in order to understand how the ancient Ritsuryo-based nation shifted to the medieval nation, varieties of views have been asserted by researchers depending on their standpoint.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the notion of Dynastic polity was proposed in order to understand how the ancient Ritsuryo-based nation shifted to the medieval nation, varieties of views have been asserted by researchers depending on their standpoint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="90">
<j>最初に王朝国家という概念を示したのは高尾一彦「荘園と公領」（『日本歴史講座』第2巻、1956年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazuhiko TAKAO firstly proposed the notion of Dynastic polity in his book &quot;Shoen and Koryo&quot; (manor and Imperial demesne) (&quot;Japanese history course &quot;, volume 2, 1956).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazuhiko TAKAO firstly proposed the notion of Dynastic polity in his book &quot;Shoen and Koryo&quot; (manor and Imperial demesne) (&quot;Japanese history course,&quot; volume 2, 1956).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazuhiko TAKAO firstly proposed the notion of Dynastic polity in his book &apos;Shoen and Koryo&apos; (manor and Imperial demesne) (&quot;Japanese history course,&quot; volume 2, 1956).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>ここで高尾は、王朝国家を田堵農民から生産物地代を収取する貴族たちの連合政権であり、生産物地代を収取する点において封建的な要素を持ち始めているとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this book, Takao asserted that the Dynastic polity was the coalition government of aristocrats who collected products from tato nomin (cultivating farmers) as land rent and in view of collecting products as land rent, the Dynastic polity had the element similar to that of feudal nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this book, Takao asserted that the Dynastic polity was the coalition government of aristocrats who collected products from tato nomin (cultivating farmers) as land rent and in view of collecting products as land rent, the Dynastic polity had an element similar to that of a feudal nation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this book, Takao asserted that the Dynastic polity was the coalition government of aristocrats who collected products from tato nomin (cultivating farmers) as land rent and in view of collecting products as land rent, the Dynastic polity had an element similar to that of a feudal nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>この後、戸田芳実らにより王朝国家は農奴などを抑圧する初期封建国家であるとの位置づけがなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Yoshimi TODA defined the Dynastic polity as the early feudal nation which oppressed serf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Yoshimi TODA defined the Dynastic polity as the early feudal nation which oppressed serf.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Yoshimi TODA defined the Dynastic polity as the early feudal nation which oppressed serf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="93">
<j>王朝国家体制論に大きな進展をもたらしたのは、坂本賞三（『日本王朝国家体制論』1972年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozo SAKAMOTO made a distinguished contribution to the progress of the Dynastic polity theory by his book &quot;The Theory of Japanese Dynastic Polity&quot; (1972).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozo SAKAMOTO made a distinguished contribution to the progress of the Dynastic polity theory with his book &quot;The Theory of Japanese Dynastic Polity&quot; (1972).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozo SAKAMOTO made a distinguished contribution to the progress of the Dynastic polity theory with his book &quot;The Theory of Japanese Dynastic Polity&quot; (1972).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>坂本は土地制度史の面から王朝国家体制の理論を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakamoto established the theory of Dynastic polity from the aspect of the history of land system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakamoto established the theory of Dynastic polity from the aspect of the history of land system.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakamoto established the theory of Dynastic polity from the aspect of the history of land system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>坂本によって名体制の成立と王朝国家の成立とが初めて有機的に理解されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to Sakamoto, the establishment of myo-system and that of Dynastic polity were coordinately understood for the first time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to Sakamoto, the establishment of the myo-system and that of Dynastic polity were coordinately understood for the first time.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to Sakamoto, the establishment of the myo-system and that of Dynastic polity were coordinately understood for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>また10世紀初頭に始まる前期王朝国家と11世紀40年代を画期とする後期王朝国家の登場が唱えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the division of the early Dynastic polity period, which started in early 10th century, and the late Dynastic polity period, which started 1140&apos;s, was also proposed by him.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, the division of the early Dynastic polity period, which started in early 10th century, and the late Dynastic polity period, which started in the 1140&apos;s, was also proposed by him.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, the division of the early Dynastic polity period, which started in early 10th century, and the late Dynastic polity period, which started in the 1140&apos;s, was also proposed by him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="97">
<j>坂本の議論は広範な支持を得るところとなり、その後の10世紀・11世紀史研究は坂本論を中心に展開し、坂本論の深化・批判という形で行われていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakamoto&apos;s theory received support from many researchers and since then, the study of 10th and 11th century has been conducted in the form of deepening/criticizing it with Sakamoto&apos;s theory at the starting point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakamoto&apos;s theory received support from many researchers and since then, the study of the 10th and 11th centuries has been conducted in the form of deepening/criticizing it with Sakamoto&apos;s theory as a starting point.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakamoto&apos;s theory received support from many researchers and since then, the study of the 10th and 11th centuries has been conducted in the form of deepening/criticizing it with Sakamoto&apos;s theory as a starting point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>王朝国家体制期における中央政治機構や軍制・荘園政策・負名体制に関する研究は著しい進展を見せ、さらには王朝国家に代わる新たな古代-中世移行論が唱えられ始めてはいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The study of central government organization, military system, shoen policy and local tax management system during the Dynastic polity period has marked significant progress and another theory concerning the transition from the ancient times to the medieval age was proposed in lieu of the theory of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The study of central government organization, military systems, shoen policy, and local tax management systems during the Dynastic polity period has marked significant progress and another theory concerning the transition from the ancient times to the medieval age was proposed in lieu of the theory of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The study of central government organization, military systems, shoen policy, and local tax management systems during the Dynastic polity period has marked significant progress and another theory concerning the transition from the ancient times to the medieval age was proposed in lieu of the theory of Dynastic polity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>それでも王朝国家体制論がこの時代の研究の中心に位置し続けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the theory of Dynastic polity still remains as the key issue of the study of that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the theory of Dynastic polity still remains as the key issue of study of the period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the theory of Dynastic polity still remains as the key issue of study of the period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>