<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>恒貞親王伝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunesada-Shino-den (Biography of Tsunesada-Shino)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunesada-Shino-den (Biography of Tsunesada-Shino)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunesada-Shino-den (Biography of Tsunesada-Shino)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>恒貞親王伝（つねさだしんのうでん）は、平安時代前期に書かれた漢文伝の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunesada-Shino-den was one of biographies in classical Chinese which was written in the early stage of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunesada-Shino-den was one of the biographies in classical Chinese which was written in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunesada-Shino-den was one of the biographies in classical Chinese which was written in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>承和の変で廃太子となった恒貞親王の生涯を描いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It depicted the life of Imperial prince Tsunesada who was deposed from Crown Prince as the result of the Jowa Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It depicted the life of Imperial prince Tsunesada who was deposed as Crown Prince as the result of the Jowa Incident.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It depicted the life of Imperial prince Tsunesada who was deposed as Crown Prince as the result of the Jowa Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>全1巻（ただし、現存する古写本及び『続群書類従』に採録されたものには冒頭部分と中途部分に欠落がある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One volume (however, some portions are missing from the top and middle part of the extant old manuscript and the one that was compiled in &quot; Zoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One volume (however, some portions are missing from the top and middle parts of the remaining old manuscript and the one that was compiled in &quot;Zoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One volume (however, some portions are missing from the top and middle parts of the remaining old manuscript and the one that was compiled in &quot;Zoku Gunsho Ruiju&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>著作年代や著者については不明であるが、親王が没してから時期を経ていない9世紀後期の作品と考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Neither the exact age of this book nor the author is known, but it is generally believed that this book was written in the late stage of the 9th century not so long after the death of Imperial prince.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Neither the exact age of this book nor the author is known, but it is generally believed that this book was written in the late 9th century not long after the death of the Imperial prince.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Neither the exact age of this book nor the author is known, but it is generally believed that this book was written in the late 9th century not long after the death of the Imperial prince.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>著者は古くから三善清行を著者とする説と紀長谷雄を著者とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There have been two opinions from long ago concerning its author, either Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI or KI no Haseo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There have been two opinions from long ago concerning its author, either Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI or KI no Haseo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There have been two opinions from long ago concerning its author, either Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI or KI no Haseo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>親王を擁護する立場から執筆されており以下のような故事などが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book was written from the viewpoint of a person who was in favor of Imperial prince and the following historical events etc. are seen in this book.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book was written from the viewpoint of a person who was in favor of the Imperial prince and the following historical events etc. are seen in this book.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book was written from the viewpoint of a person who was in favor of the Imperial prince and the following historical events etc. are seen in this book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>経学・歴史・音楽・書道・絵画に優れた才能を発揮して釈奠復興に努めるという優れた才能と実績を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being a person who had an exceptional talent in keigaku (study of Keisho in Confucianism), history, calligraphy and painting, he strived for the restoration of sekiten (ritual for Confucius) and achieved satisfactory results.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being a person who had an exceptional talent in keigaku (study of Keisho in Confucianism), history, calligraphy, and painting, he strived for the restoration of sekiten (ritual for Confucius) and achieved satisfactory results.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being a person who had an exceptional talent in keigaku (study of Keisho in Confucianism), music, history, calligraphy, and painting, he strived for the restoration of sekiten (ritual for Confucius) and achieved satisfactory results.</e>
<cmt>音楽（music）を補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>本人の意向に反して立太子された末に承和の変でその地位を追われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was formally installed as Crown Prince against his wish, but was deposed from Crown Prince as the result of the Jowa Incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was formally installed as Crown Prince against his wish, but was deposed as Crown Prince as the result of the Jowa Incident.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was formally installed as Crown Prince against his wish, but was deposed as Crown Prince as the result of the Jowa Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>出家後は仏道修行に専念し、大覚寺を創建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He concentrated on Buddhist practice after becoming a monk and founded Daikaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He concentrated on Buddhist practice after becoming a monk and founded Daikaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He concentrated on Buddhist practice after becoming a monk and founded Daikaku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>陽成天皇退位後に藤原基経によって皇位継承を要請されて辞退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Emperor Yozei abdicated the throne, he was asked by FUJIWARA no Mototsune to succeed, but he declined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Emperor Yozei abdicated the throne, he was asked by FUJIWARA no Mototsune to succeed, but he declined.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Emperor Yozei abdicated the throne, he was asked by FUJIWARA no Mototsune to succeed, but he declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>六国史にない記述も含まれており、史料としての評価も高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This book is highly appreciated as historical material since its contents include some records that are not found in Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This book is highly appreciated as historical material since its contents include some records that are not found in Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This book is highly appreciated as historical material since its contents include some records that are not found in Rikkokushi (the Six National Histories).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>