<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>伊奈氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ina Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ina Clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ina Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>伊奈氏（いなし）は、日本の氏族（武士）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ina clan was one of Japanese shizoku (clan, samurai family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ina clan was one of the Japanese shizoku (clans, or samurai families).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ina clan was one of the Japanese shizoku (clans, or samurai families).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>清和源氏源義国流足利氏系（異説あり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in the Ashikaga lineage of MINAMOTO no Yorikuni line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) (heresies are acknowledged).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in the Ashikaga lineage of the MINAMOTO no Yorikuni line of Seiwa-Genji (the Minamoto clan) (heresies are acknowledged).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in the Ashikaga lineage of the MINAMOTO no Yorikuni line of Seiwa-Genji (the Minamoto clan) (heresies are acknowledged).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>家紋は左頭二つ巴又は剣梅鉢。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family crest is 左頭二つ巴 or Kenumebachi.</e>
<cmt>「左頭二つ巴」読み方、定訳共に確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest is 左頭二つ巴, or Kenumebachi.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest is 左頭二つ巴, or Kenumebachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>足利氏の支流である戸賀崎氏の分家といわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ina clan was said to be a branch family of the Togasaki clan, a branch of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ina clan was said to be a branch family of the Togasaki clan, which was a branch of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ina clan was said to be a branch family of the Togasaki clan, which was a branch of the Ashikaga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>初め荒川氏を称してたが、荒川易氏のときに征夷大将軍足利義尚から信濃国伊那郡の一部を与えられ、易氏の孫の伊奈易次の代に伊奈熊蔵と号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the family first referred to themselves as Arakawa clan, Yasutsugu INA, a grandson of Yasuuji ARAKAWA who had been given a part of Ina County of Shinano Province by Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, called himself as Kumazo INA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the family first referred to itself as theArakawa clan, Yasutsugu INA, a grandson of Yasuuji ARAKAWA who had been given a part of Ina County, Shinano Province, by the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, called himself Kumazo INA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the family first referred to itself as the Arakawa clan, Yasutsugu INA, a grandson of Yasuuji ARAKAWA who had been given a part of Ina County, Shinano Province, by the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, called himself Kumazo INA.</e>
<cmt>theとArakawaの間にスペースを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>易次は叔父の易正との所領争いに敗れて居城を奪われたため、三河国に移り松平氏の家臣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Defeated in a territorial dispute against his uncle Yasumasa and stripped of his residential castle, Yasutsugu moved to Mikawa Province to become a vassal of the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasutsugu, having been defeated in a territorial dispute against his uncle Yasumasa and stripped of his residential castle, moved to Mikawa Province and became a vassal of the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasutsugu, having been defeated in a territorial dispute against his uncle Yasumasa and stripped of his residential castle, moved to Mikawa Province and became a vassal of the Matsudaira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その子伊奈忠基は松平広忠・徳川家康父子に仕えて三河国小島城（現在の愛知県西尾市）を居城とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamoto INA, Yasutsugu&apos;s son, served Hirotada MATSUDAIRA and his son Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, residing in Kojima-jo Castle in Mikawa Province (present Nishio City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamoto INA, Yasutsugu&apos;s son, served Hirotada MATSUDAIRA and his son Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, residing at Kojima-jo Castle in Mikawa Province (the present-day Nishio City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamoto INA, Yasutsugu&apos;s son, served Hirotada MATSUDAIRA and his son Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, residing at Kojima-jo Castle in Mikawa Province (the present-day Nishio City, Aichi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>忠基の嫡男伊奈貞政の系統は伊奈昭綱のときに断絶した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage of Sadamasa INA, Tadamoto&apos;s legitimate son, was ended at the time of Akitsuna INA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lineage of Sadamasa INA, Tadamoto&apos;s legitimate son, ended at the time of Akitsuna INA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lineage of Sadamasa INA, Tadamoto&apos;s legitimate son, ended at the time of Akitsuna INA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>もう一人の子の伊奈忠家の系統では、伊奈忠次が徳川家康に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the lineage of Tadaie INA, the other son of Tadamoto, Tadatsugu INA served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the lineage of Tadaie INA, the other son of Tadamoto, Tadatsugu INA, served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the lineage of Tadaie INA, the other son of Tadamoto, Tadatsugu INA, served Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>家康の関東入国に従って代官頭（関東郡代の前身）となり、徳川氏の関東領国支配の中心的役割を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Ieyasu entered Kanto region, Tadatsugu also followed him to become daikangashira (head of Edo-period prefectural governor (magistrate, bailiff)), the predecessor of Kanto gundai (a magistrate of Kanto region), playing a leading role in Tokugawa&apos;s rule of their Kanto territory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Ieyasu entered the Kanto region, Tadatsugu followed him to become daikangashira (head of Edo-period prefectural governorship (magistrate, bailiff)), the predecessor of Kanto gundai (a magistrate of the Kanto region), playing a leading role in Tokugawa&apos;s rule of their Kanto territory.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ieyasu entered the Kanto region, Tadatsugu followed him to become daikangashira (head of Edo-period prefectural governorship (magistrate, bailiff)), the predecessor of Kanto gundai (a magistrate of the Kanto region), playing a leading role in Tokugawa&apos;s rule of their Kanto territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>忠次はその後譜代大名として武蔵小室藩の初代藩主となり、長男の伊奈忠政が2代藩主となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Tadatsugu as a fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) became the first lord of Musashikomuro Domain, with his eldest son Tadamasa INA inherited him as the second lord.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, Tadatsugu, as a fudai daimyo (a daimyo as hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) became the first lord of the Musashikomuro Domain, with his eldest son Tadamasa INA inherited as the second lord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, Tadatsugu, as a fudai daimyo (a daimyo as hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) became the first lord of the Musashikomuro Domain, with his eldest son Tadamasa INA inherited as the second lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、3代伊奈忠勝の代で無嗣除封となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the 3rd lord Tadakatsu INA was deprived of his territory as he had no heir.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「無嗣除封」定訳不明。「deprived of his territory as he had no heir」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the third lord, Tadakatsu INA, was deprived of his territory because he had no heir.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the third lord, Tadakatsu INA, was deprived of his territory because he had no heir.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>忠次の次男伊奈忠治の系統は旗本となり関東郡代を世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lineage of Tadaharu INA, the second son of Tadatsugu, became a hatamoto (a direct retainer of the Shogun) family, inheriting Kanto gundai for generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lineage of Tadaharu INA, the second son of Tadatsugu, became a hatamoto (a direct retainer of the shogun) family, inheriting the post of Kanto gundai for generations.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lineage of Tadaharu INA, the second son of Tadatsugu, became a hatamoto (a direct retainer of the shogun) family, inheriting the post of Kanto gundai for generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>伊奈氏の出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Origin of the Ina Clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Origin of the Ina Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Origin of the Ina Clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>上記のように伊奈氏を足利氏の庶流と見る説が一般的だが、『寛政重修諸家譜』には藤原氏と記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Ina clan is generally regarded as a branch family of the Ashikaga clan as mentioned above, is was described as the Fujiwara clan in &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (A record of family trees of samurai warriors of Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Ina clan is generally regarded as a branch family of the Ashikaga clan, as mentioned above, it was described as the Fujiwara clan in &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (a record of the family trees of samurai warriors of the Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Ina clan is generally regarded as a branch family of the Ashikaga clan, as mentioned above, it was described as the Fujiwara clan in &quot;Kansei Choshu Shokafu&quot; (a record of the family trees of samurai warriors of the Edo bakufu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また清和源氏源満快流（満快の曾孫源為公の子孫）とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory is that the Ina clan was from MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan), or descendants of MINAMOTO no Tametomo, a great-grandson of Mitsuyoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory is that the Ina clan was from the MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) or were descendants of MINAMOTO no Tametomo, a great-grandson of Mitsuyoshi.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory is that the Ina clan was from the MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) or were descendants of MINAMOTO no Tametomo, a great-grandson of Mitsuyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 こぶまき(id:38278), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 編集仁王(id:208160), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>