<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>昌泰の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shotai Conspiracy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shotai Conspiracy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shotai Conspiracy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>昌泰の変（しょうたいのへん）は、901年（昌泰4年）1月、左大臣藤原時平の讒言により醍醐天皇が右大臣菅原道真を大宰権帥として大宰府へ左遷し、道真の子供や右近衛中将源善らを左遷または流罪にした事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shotai conspiracy (Shotai no hen in Japanese), which occurred in the first month of 901 (the fourth year of the Shotai era), was a coup in which Emperor Daigo, acting on the false charges of FUJIWARA no Takahira, the Minister of the Left, against SUGAWARA no Michizane, the Minister of the Right, demoted Michizane and sent him into de facto exile to Dazaifu (an outpost in faroff Kyushu) as Dazai Gon no Sochi (Deputy Commander of Dazaifu); also, Michizane&apos;s children as well as MINAMOTO no Yoshi, the Middle Captain of the Guardsmen of the Right, were either demoted or exiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shotai conspiracy (Shotai no hen in Japanese), which occurred in the first month of 901 (the fourth year of the Shotai era), was a coup in which Emperor Daigo, acting on the false charges of FUJIWARA no Takahira, the Minister of the Left, against SUGAWARA no Michizane, the Minister of the Right, demoted Michizane and sent him into de facto exile to Dazaifu (an outpost in faroff Kyushu) as Dazai Gon no Sochi (Deputy Commander of Dazaifu); also, Michizane&apos;s children as well as MINAMOTO no Yoshi, the Middle Captain of the Guardsmen of the Right, were either demoted or exiled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shotai Conspiracy (Shotai no hen in Japanese), which occurred in January 901, was a coup in which Emperor Daigo, acting on the false charges of FUJIWARA no Takahira, the Minister of the Left, against SUGAWARA no Michizane, the Minister of the Right, demoted Michizane and sent him into de facto exile to Dazaifu (an outpost in far off Kyushu) as Dazai Gon no Sochi (Deputy Commander of Dazaifu); also, Michizane&apos;s children as well as MINAMOTO no Yoshi, the Middle Captain of the Guardsmen of the Right, were either demoted or exiled.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的にその背景には時平と道真の確執が主な理由とされるが、それだけが理由ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the general background of this event, the main reason for the conspiracy is considered to be the antagonism between Tokihira and Michizane, but there were other reasons as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the general background of this event, the main reason for the conspiracy is considered to be the antagonism between Tokihira and Michizane, but there were other reasons as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the general background of this event, the main reason for the conspiracy is considered to be the antagonism between Tokihira and Michizane, but there were other reasons as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>宇多上皇（程なく宇多法皇になる）は醍醐天皇に譲位した後も、『寛平御遺誡』という君主の心構えを新帝に説くばかりでなく、道真を始め源善・中納言源希・蔵人頭平季長・侍従藤原忠平といったいわゆる「寛平の治」の推進役だった一種の側近集団を新帝の周囲に配置して新帝の政策を主導しようと図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after retired emperor Uta (who soon after became cloistered emperor Uta) abdicated the throne to Emperor Daigo, he went far beyond merely his written injunction, the Kampyo goyuikai--which advised the new emperor on how to prepare himself to rule--and actively planned to continue his leadership role in the new emperor&apos;s government by surrounding Emperor Daigo with the group of his closest aides and ministers who had been the driving force behind the administration of the Kampyo era, notably Michizane but also including MINAMOTO no Yoshi, the Chunagon (Middle Counselor) MINAMOTO no Mare, the Kuroudo no kami (Majordomo of the palace) TAIRA no Suenaga, and the Jiju (Chamberlain) FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after retired emperor Uta (who soon after became cloistered emperor Uta) abdicated the throne to Emperor Daigo, he went far beyond merely his written injunction, the Kampyo goyuikai--which advised the new emperor on how to prepare himself to rule--and actively planned to continue his leadership role in the new emperor&apos;s government by surrounding Emperor Daigo with the group of his closest aides and ministers who had been the driving force behind the administration of the Kampyo era, notably Michizane but also including MINAMOTO no Yoshi, the Chunagon (Middle Counselor) MINAMOTO no Mare, the Kuroudo no kami (Majordomo of the palace) TAIRA no Suenaga, and the Jiju (Chamberlain) FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after Retired Emperor Uda (who soon after became Cloistered Emperor Uta) abdicated the throne to Emperor Daigo, he went far beyond merely his written injunction, the Kanpyo goyuikai--which advised the new emperor on how to prepare himself to rule--and actively planned to continue his leadership role in the new emperor&apos;s government by surrounding Emperor Daigo with the group of his closest aides and ministers who had been the driving force behind the administration of the Kanpyo era, notably Michizane but also including MINAMOTO no Yoshi, the Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) MINAMOTO no Mare, the Kuroudo no kami (Majordomo of the palace) TAIRA no Suenaga, and the Jiju (Chamberlain) FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;Middle Counselor&quot; -&gt; &quot;vice-councilor of state&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これに対して時平や大納言源光 (公卿)ら上級貴族のみならず、藤原清貫・藤原菅根・三善清行ら中下級貴族を含めた激しい反発があったともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These efforts by Uta resulted in a strong backlash which was not limited only to high-ranking aristocrats like Tokihira and the Dainagon (Major Counselor) MINAMOTO no Hikaru (a court noble) but extended to middle- and lower-ranking nobles like FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura, FUJIWARA no Sugane, and Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These efforts by Uta resulted in a strong backlash which was not limited only to high-ranking aristocrats like Tokihira and the Dainagon (Major Counselor) MINAMOTO no Hikaru (a court noble) but extended to middle- and lower-ranking nobles like FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura, FUJIWARA no Sugane, and Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These efforts by Uda resulted in a strong backlash which was not limited only to high-ranking aristocrats like Tokihira and the Dainagon (chief councilor of state) MINAMOTO no Hikaru (a court noble) but extended to middle- and lower-ranking nobles like FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura, FUJIWARA no Sugane, and Kiyoyuki MIYOSHI as well.</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;Major Counselor&quot;　-&gt; &quot;chief councilor of state&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>やがて、宇多法皇が道真の娘婿でもある斉世親王を皇太弟に立てようとしているという風説が流れると、宇多上皇や道真の政治手法に密かに不満を抱いていた醍醐天皇と藤原時平、藤原菅根（折りしも病死した平季長の後任の蔵人頭に就任していた）らが政治の主導権を奪還せんとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, when rumors began to fly that cloistered emperor Uta was going to raise Michizane&apos;s son-in-law, the imperial prince Tokiyo, to the rank of Kotaitei (one rank below the heir apparent), those who were nursing secret resentment against Uta and Michizane for their political maneuvers, including Emperor Daigo, FUJIWARA no Tokihira, and FUJIWARA no Sugane (the new Majordomo of the palace following TAIRA no Hidenaga&apos;s recent death by illness), began to plan how to recover control over the government.</e>
<cmt>Because it would be confusing to have &quot;cloistered emperor Uta&quot; and &quot;retired emperor Uta&quot; in the same sentence, and because of the elliptical pattern used for names and titles in English, the second time I have written &quot;Uta&quot; only.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, when rumors began to fly that cloistered emperor Uta was going to raise Michizane&apos;s son-in-law, the imperial prince Tokiyo, to the rank of Kotaitei (one rank below the heir apparent), those who were nursing secret resentment against Uta and Michizane for their political maneuvers, including Emperor Daigo, FUJIWARA no Tokihira, and FUJIWARA no Sugane (the new Majordomo of the palace following TAIRA no Hidenaga&apos;s recent death by illness), began to plan how to recover control over the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, when rumors began to fly that Cloistered Emperor Uda was going to raise Michizane&apos;s son-in-law, the Imperial Prince Tokiyo, to the rank of Kotaitei (one rank below the heir apparent), those who were nursing secret resentment against Uda and Michizane for their political maneuvers, including Emperor Daigo, FUJIWARA no Tokihira, and FUJIWARA no Sugane (the new Majordomo of the palace following TAIRA no Hidenaga&apos;s recent death by illness), began to plan how to recover control over the government.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>この政変で道真・善（出雲国権守に左遷）を排斥、変の直後に連座を免れた源希も病死、同じく藤原忠平も政治の中枢から事実上追われることになり、醍醐天皇・藤原時平派の政治的勝利に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the coup, Michizane and Yoshi (who was demoted to vice-governor of Izumo province) were purged from the government, and immediately after the coup MINAMOTO no Mare, who had managed to avoid any demotion or other penalty, died of illness, while in the same vein, FUJIWARA no Tadahira was--in truth if not in name--ousted from his vital role at the center of government, meaning the coup ended in a decisive political victory for Emperor Daigo and FUJIWARA no Tokihira&apos;s faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the coup, Michizane and Yoshi (who was demoted to vice-governor of Izumo province) were purged from the government, and immediately after the coup MINAMOTO no Mare, who had managed to avoid any demotion or other penalty, died of illness, while in the same vein, FUJIWARA no Tadahira was--in truth if not in name--ousted from his vital role at the center of government, meaning the coup ended in a decisive political victory for Emperor Daigo and FUJIWARA no Tokihira&apos;s faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the coup, Michizane and Yoshi (who was demoted to vice-governor of Izumo Province) were purged from the government, and immediately after the coup MINAMOTO no Mare, who had managed to avoid any demotion or other penalty, died of illness, while in the same vein, FUJIWARA no Tadahira was--in truth if not in name--ousted from his vital role at the center of government, meaning the coup ended in a decisive political victory for Emperor Daigo and FUJIWARA no Tokihira&apos;s faction.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>天皇や時平は「延喜の治」と呼ばれる自らが主導するの政治改革を目指すものの、変からわずか8年後に時平が急死、続いて醍醐天皇も病気がちとなり、政治権力の中心は再度宇多法皇と藤原忠平の手中に帰する事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor and Tokihira planned political reforms to put themselves in direct leadership roles for the new administration, which was called &quot;Engi no chi&quot; (&quot;the (glorious) government during the Engi era&quot;), but only eight years after the coup, Tokihira died suddenly, and moreover Emperor Daigo became more and more prone to illness, which allowed de facto political power to shift back again under the control of retired emperor Uta and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor and Tokihira planned political reforms to put themselves in direct leadership roles for the new administration, which was called &quot;Engi no chi&quot; (&quot;the (glorious) government during the Engi era&quot;), but only eight years after the coup, Tokihira died suddenly, and moreover Emperor Daigo became more and more prone to illness, which allowed de facto political power to shift back again under the control of retired emperor Uta and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor and Tokihira planned political reforms to put themselves in direct leadership roles for the new administration, which was called &apos;Engi no chi&apos; (the (glorious) government during the Engi era), but only eight years after the coup, Tokihira died suddenly, and moreover Emperor Daigo became more and more prone to illness, which allowed de facto political power to shift back again under the control of Cloistered Emperor Uda and FUJIWARA no Tadahira.</e>
<cmt>法皇表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Sat666(id:127263), グラタン(id:94405), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>