<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>韓国併合</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Annexation of Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Annexation of Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Annexation of Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>韓国併合（かんこくへいごう）は、1910年8月22日、日韓併合条約に基づいて日本が大韓帝国（今日の大韓民国と朝鮮民主主義人民共和国に相当する地域）を併合した事を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The annexation of Korea means the Japanese annexation of the Korean Empire (which currently corresponds to the area of the Republic of Korea and the Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea), based on the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty on August 22, 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The annexation of Korea refers to the Japanese annexation of the Korean Empire (which currently corresponds to the area of the Republic of Korea and the Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea), based on the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty on August 22, 1910.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The annexation of Korea refers to the Japanese annexation of the Korean Empire (which currently corresponds to the area of the Republic of Korea and the Democratic People&apos;s Republic of Korea), based on the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty on August 22, 1910.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日韓併合（にっかんへいごう）、朝鮮合併（ちょうせんがっぺい）、日韓合邦（にっかんがっぽう）などの表記もある（韓国では韓日併合、中国では日韓併合と表記する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also expressed in Chinese characters as 日韓併合 (Nikkan heigo), 朝鮮合併 (Chosen gappei), 日韓合邦 (Nikkan gappo), etc. (It is written 韓日併合 in South Korea, and 日韓併合 in China).</e>
<cmt>漢字表記に言及していますので、漢字使用。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also expressed in Chinese characters as 日韓併合 (Nikkan heigo), 朝鮮合併 (Chosen gappei), 日韓合邦 (Nikkan gappo), etc. (It is written 韓日併合 in South Korea, and 日韓併合 in China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also expressed in Chinese characters as 日韓併合 (Nikkan heigo), 朝鮮合併 (Chosen gappei), 日韓合邦 (Nikkan gappo), etc. (It is written 韓日併合 in South Korea, and 日韓併合 in China).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>韓国併合によって大韓帝国は消滅し、日本はその領土であった朝鮮半島を領有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this annexation of Korea, the Korean Empire ceased to exist, and the Korean Peninsula that was its territory was occupied by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this annexation of Korea, the Korean Empire ceased to exist, and the Korean Peninsula that was its territory was occupied by Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this annexation of Korea, the Korean Empire ceased to exist, and the Korean Peninsula that was its territory was occupied by Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1945年の第二次世界大戦終戦に伴い実効支配を喪失し、1945年9月2日、ポツダム宣言の条項を誠実に履行することを約束した降伏文書調印によって、正式に日本による朝鮮支配は終了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan lost the effective control due to the end oaf the Second World War in 1945, and its rule of Korea officially ended by signing the Instrument of Surrender promising to fulfilling the provisions in the Potsdam Declaration in good faith on September 2, 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan effectively lost control due to the end of the Second World War in 1945, and its rule of Korea officially ended upon signing the Instrument of Surrender in which they promised to follow the provisions in the Potsdam Declaration in good faith on September 2, 1945.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan lost the effective control due to the end of the Second World War in 1945, and its rule of Korea officially ended upon signing the Instrument of Surrender in which they promised to follow the provisions in the Potsdam Declaration in good faith on September 2, 1945.</e>
<cmt>effectively lost control→lost the effective control 余分なスペースを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>併合条約の日韓の見解</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese and Korean Views on the Annexation Treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese and Korean Views on the Annexation Treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese and Korean Views on the Annexation Treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>日本側が韓国併合は現在において「もはや無効」であるという立場をとることで日韓併合条約の締結自体は合法であったという考えを内包している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan has adopted a stance that the annexation of Korea is &quot;no longer valid&quot; today, which implies the conclusion of the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty itself was legal.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan has adopted a stance that the annexation of Korea is &quot;no longer valid&quot; today, which implies the conclusion that the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty itself was legal.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan has adopted a stance that the annexation of Korea is &quot;no longer valid&quot; today, which implies the conclusion that the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty itself was legal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>それに対して、韓国・北朝鮮とも日韓併合条約は違法に結ばれた条約であるから同・条約と関連する条約のすべてが当初から違法・無効であり、日本の朝鮮領有にさかのぼってその統治がすべて違法・無効であるという立場を崩していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrary to that, both South and North Korea have maintained the stance that the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty and all the related treaties were illegal and invalid from the beginning, or the Japanese rule, extending back to its occupation of Korea, was totally illegal and invalid, because the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty was illegally concluded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrary to that, both South and North Korea have maintained the stance that the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty and all the related treaties were illegal and invalid from the beginning, and the Japanese rule, extending back to its occupation of Korea, was totally illegal and invalid, because the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty was illegally concluded.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrary to that, both South and North Korea have maintained the stance that the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty and all the related treaties were illegal and invalid from the beginning, and the Japanese rule, extending back to its occupation of Korea, was totally illegal and invalid, because the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty was illegally concluded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この点については65年に国交を回復した韓国と日本との間においても合意に達していない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">South Korea and Japan which resumed diplomatic relations in 1965 have not reached an agreement on this point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">South Korea and Japan, which resumed diplomatic relations in 1965, have not reached an agreement on this point.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">South Korea and Japan, which resumed diplomatic relations in 1965, have not reached an agreement on this point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>「韓国併合」というとき、大韓帝国が消滅し、朝鮮が日本の領土となった瞬間的事実だけではなく、併合の結果として朝鮮を領有した継続的事実を含意する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The annexation of Korea means not only a momentary fact that the Korean Empire disappeared and Korea became the Japanese territory, but also sometimes means a continuous fact that Korea had been occupied as a result of the annexation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The annexation of Korea refers not only to the momentary fact that the Korean Empire disappeared and Korea became a Japanese territory, but also sometimes refers to the continuous fact that Korea had been occupied as a result of the annexation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The annexation of Korea refers not only to the momentary fact that the Korean Empire disappeared and Korea became a Japanese territory, but also sometimes refers to the continuous fact that Korea had been occupied as a result of the annexation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>時代背景と日本・朝鮮の世論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical Backdrop and Public Opinions in Japan and Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical Backdrop and Public Opinions in Japan and Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Backdrop and Public Opinions in Japan and Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治維新後、急速に発展を遂げた日本は対外的な国防政策を考えた場合に朝鮮半島が地政学的に大きな意味があると考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, which achieved rapid progress after Meiji Restoration, believed the Korean Peninsula was geopolitically important, when it considered its national defense policy against foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, which achieved rapid progress after the Meiji Restoration, believed the Korean Peninsula was geopolitically important, when it considered its national defense policy against foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, which achieved rapid progress after the Meiji Restoration, believed the Korean Peninsula was geopolitically important, when it considered its national defense policy against foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>古来より永きに渡って琉球と並んで日本と大陸との交流におけるパイプ役を果たしてきた朝鮮半島が敵対国家に渡ることは、日本にとって戦略的に致命的な弱点を握られることを意味していると考えたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was because Japan thought if the Korean Peninsula, which had been acted as intermediary for exchanges between Japan and the continent from ancient times, together with Ryukyu, was possessed by an adversarial country, it would catch hold of the strategically fatal weakness of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because Japan thought if the Korean Peninsula, which had acted as an intermediary for exchanges between Japan and the continent since ancient times, together with Ryukyu, was possessed by an adversarial country, it would catch hold of a strategically fatal weakness of Japan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because Japan thought if the Korean Peninsula, which had acted as an intermediary for exchanges between Japan and the continent since ancient times, together with Ryukyu, was possessed by an adversarial country, it would catch hold of a strategically fatal weakness of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>当時、李氏朝鮮は清朝中国を中心とした冊封体制を堅持し、鎖国状態にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yi Dynasty Korea maintained a tributary system with the Qing Dynasty China as its center, and closed off to the outside world at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yi Dynasty Korea maintained a tributary system with the Qing Dynasty China as its center, and was closed off to the outside world at that time.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yi Dynasty Korea maintained a tributary system with the Qing Dynasty China as its center, and was closed off to the outside world at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>日本の開国・冊封体制からの離脱は、長らく東アジア国際秩序を保証していた中華秩序への挑戦であり、李氏朝鮮はこれに批判的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Japanese opening of the country to the world, and secession of the tributary system was a challenge to the Sinocentrist order that had assured East Asian international order for a long time, the Yi Dynasty Korea was critical of that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japanese opening of the country to the world, and secession from the tributary system was a challenge to the Sinocentrist order that had assured East Asian international order for a long time, the Yi Dynasty Korea was critical of that decision.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japanese opening of the country to the world, and secession from the tributary system was a challenge to the Sinocentrist order that had assured East Asian international order for a long time, the Yi Dynasty Korea was critical of that decision.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>日本による近代化の要請も内政干渉であると考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It regarded a request from Japan for modernization as interference in its domestic affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It regarded the request from Japan for modernization as interference in its domestic affairs.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It regarded the request from Japan for modernization as interference in its domestic affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また日本も善意か悪意かは別として干渉であることを自覚していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, aside from whether it was out of good will or not, Japan was aware that it was the interference.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, aside from whether it was out of good will or not, Japan was aware that it was an interference.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, aside from whether it was out of good will or not, Japan was aware that it was an interference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>日本の民間知識人による近代化の提言も、侵略的意図によるものと考えられるか朝鮮王朝内部における政争の具にしかならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese intellectual persons&apos; proposal for modernization was regarded the one for the invasive purpose, or used as a tool for political strives inside the Korean Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese intellectual persons&apos; proposal for modernization was regarded as having an invasive purpose, or used as a tool for political strife inside the Korean Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese intellectual persons&apos; proposal for modernization was regarded as having an invasive purpose, or used as a tool for political strife inside the Korean Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、西欧列強や日本は朝鮮半島の鎖国状態が続くことを許さず、日本は江華島事件を機に李氏朝鮮と日朝修好条規を締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, West European powers and Japan did not accept the continuation of isolation in the Korean Peninsula, and Japan took advantage of Ganghwa Island incident to conclude the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity with the Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, West European powers and Japan did not accept the continued isolation of the Korean Peninsula, and Japan took advantage of Ganghwa Island incident to conclude the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity with the Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, West European powers and Japan did not accept the continued isolation of the Korean Peninsula, and Japan took advantage of Ganghwa Island incident to conclude the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity with the Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>それを皮切りに李氏朝鮮は列強諸国と不平等条約を結ばされて開国を強いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this as a start, the Yi Dynasty Korea was forced to conclude unequal treaties with the powerful countries and to open up the country.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this as a start, the Yi Dynasty Korea was forced to enter into unequal treaties with these powerful countries and to open up their country.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this as a start, the Yi Dynasty Korea was forced to enter into unequal treaties with these powerful countries and to open up their country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その際、日本は「朝鮮は自主の邦」という文言に固執した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On that occasion, Japan held by the expression, &quot;Korea was an independent country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。用語集より、朝貢国 tributary countryの方を用います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On that occasion, Japan held by the expression, &quot;Korea was an independent country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On that occasion, Japan held by the expression, &quot;Korea was an independent country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかし、中華秩序において冊封を受けた朝貢国は元々「自主の邦」であるため、清朝の冊封体制から離脱させようという日本の意図は朝鮮王朝にとっても朝鮮の知識人にとって理解しがたいものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was difficult for the Korean dynasty and Korean intellectuals to understand the Japanese intention to force Korea to secede from the tributary system of the Qing dynasty, on the grounds that a tributary country, on which China had conferred sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors) in the Sinocentrism order, was originally an &quot;independent country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was difficult for the Korean dynasty and Korean intellectuals to understand the Japanese intention to force Korea to secede from the tributary system of the Qing dynasty, on the grounds that a tributary country, on which China had conferred sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors) in the Sinocentrism order, was originally an &quot;independent country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was difficult for the Korean dynasty and Korean intellectuals to understand the Japanese intention to force Korea to secede from the tributary system of the Qing dynasty, on the grounds that a tributary country, on which China had conferred sakuho (homage by Chinese emperors) in the Sinocentrism order, was originally an &quot;independent country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>誤解されがちだが、冊封体制下の国、すなわち「朝貢国」とは即、「属国・保護国」を意味するものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often misunderstood, but a country under the tributary system, i.e. &quot;a tributary country,&quot; does not directly means &quot;a subject state/protected state.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often misunderstood, but a country under the tributary system, i.e. &quot;a tributary country,&quot; does not directly imply &quot;a subject state/protected state.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often misunderstood, but a country under the tributary system, i.e. &apos;a tributary country,&apos; does not directly imply &apos;a subject state/protected state.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>朝貢国が政治的に中国に従属している度合いはきわめて多様であり、多くの場合は朝貢貿易の側面が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The degree to which tributary countries politically depended on China greatly varied, and in many cases, tributary trading was a principal duty in the system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The degree to which tributary countries politically depended on China greatly varied, and in many cases, tributary trading was a principal duty in the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The degree to which tributary countries politically depended on China greatly varied, and in many cases, tributary trading was a principal duty in the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>しかし、これが近代的な西欧的国際関係の論理に翻訳されたとき、日韓での認識の差が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when it was interpreted with the logic of modern West European international relationship, a difference in recognition between Japan and Korea occurred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when it was interpreted with the logic of modern West European international relationships, a difference in perception between Japan and Korea occurred.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when it was interpreted with the logic of modern West European international relationships, a difference in perception between Japan and Korea occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>開国後、甲申政変が起きるなど、李氏朝鮮の内部からも改革の要請は出ていたが、大院君、閔妃はあくまでも旧来の、李氏朝鮮王朝を守り通そうとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although requests for reform from within the Yi Dynasty Korea, such as Gapsin Coup that occurred after the opening of the country, came up, Daewongun and Empress Myeongseong wanted to maintain the traditional Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there were requests for reform from within the Yi Dynasty Korea, such as the Gapsin Coup that occurred after the opening of the country, Daewongun and Empress Myeongseong wanted to maintain the traditional Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there were requests for reform from within the Yi Dynasty Korea, such as the Gapsin Coup that occurred after the opening of the country, Daewongun and Empress Myeongseong wanted to maintain the traditional Yi Dynasty Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>日本は清国とともに朝鮮半島の政治改革を目論んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan planned a political reform in the Korean Peninsula, together with Qing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan planned a political reform in the Korean Peninsula, together with Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan planned a political reform in the Korean Peninsula, together with Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、清国はあくまでも朝鮮は冊封体制下の属邦であるとの主張を変えなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Qing did not change its view that Korea was its subject state under the tributary system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Qing did not change its view that Korea was its subject state under the tributary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Qing did not change its view that Korea was its subject state under the tributary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>日本と清とが緊張するなか、悪政と外国による侵略を排除すると唱えた農民反乱・甲午農民戦争が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Japan and Qing became tense, a peasant rebellion, Donghak Peasant Revolution, occurred, calling for the removal of the misrule and foreign invasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While tension arose between Japan and Qing, a peasant rebellion, the Donghak Peasant Revolution, occurred, calling for the removal of the misrule and foreign invasion.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While tension arose between Japan and Qing, a peasant rebellion, the Donghak Peasant Revolution occurred, calling for the removal of the misrule and foreign invasion.</e>
<cmt>コンマを一つ削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>日本と清の両国とも、その鎮圧を名目に朝鮮に出兵し、1894年日清戦争が勃発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Japan and Qing dispatched troops to Korea on the pretext of the suppression, and in 1894, the Sino-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Japan and Qing dispatched troops to Korea on the pretext of suppression, and in 1894, the Sino-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Japan and Qing dispatched troops to Korea on the pretext of suppression, and in 1894, the Sino-Japanese War broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>日清戦争で勝利した日本は、清国との間に下関条約を結んで李氏朝鮮が自主独立国であることを認めさせることで、朝鮮における清国の影響力を排除することに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, which won the Sino-Japanese War, succeeded in eliminating Qing&apos;s clout in Korea by concluding the Treaty of Shimonoseki to compel Qing to approve the Yi Dynasty Korea was an independent country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, which won the Sino-Japanese War, succeeded in eliminating Qing&apos;s clout in Korea by concluding the Treaty of Shimonoseki that compelled Qing to acknowledge Yi Dynasty Korea as an independent country.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, which won the Sino-Japanese War, succeeded in eliminating Qing&apos;s clout in Korea by concluding the Treaty of Shimonoseki that compelled Qing to acknowledge Yi Dynasty Korea as an independent country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>日清戦争直後の朝鮮半島では改革派の勢いが強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reformist group gained power in the Korean Peninsula immediately after the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reformist group gained power in the Korean Peninsula immediately after the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reformist group gained power in the Korean Peninsula immediately after the Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、日本が三国干渉に屈するのを見た王室をはじめとする保守派が勢力を回復してロシアに接近、政争が過激化した（閔妃暗殺も、この時期である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the conservatives, including the Royal family, recovered its power, when they found Japan surrendered to the Triple Intervention, and moved closer to Russia, which resulted in the more intensified political strife (The assassination of Empress Myeongseong occurred during this period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the conservatives, including the Royal family, recovered their power, when they found Japan had surrendered to the Triple Intervention, and moved closer to Russia, which resulted in more intensified political strife (The assassination of Empress Myeongseong occurred during this period).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the conservatives, including the Royal family, recovered their power, when they found Japan had surrendered to the Triple Intervention, and moved closer to Russia, which resulted in more intensified political strife (The assassination of Empress Myeongseong occurred during this period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>1896年に親露保守派が高宗_(朝鮮王)をロシア公使館に移して政権を奪取した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, the pro-Russia conservatives moved Gojong (Korean King) to the Russian Legation, and gained the reign of government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。用語集で、termコラムにある高宗→Gao Zongは唐の皇帝、高宗（李氏朝鮮） (King) Gojong (Joseon Dynasty) が正しいのではと思います。こちらを用います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, the pro-Russia conservatives moved Gojong (Korean King) to the Russian Legation, and gained control of the government.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, the pro-Russia conservatives moved Gojong (Korean King) to the Russian Legation, and gained control of the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>高宗はロシア公使館にて1年あまり政務を執った（露館播遷）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gojong attended to government affairs at the Russian Legation for over one year (Rokan Hasen [Royal refuge in the Russian Legation]).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。露館播遷は、Wiki英語版にAgwan Pacheonとありますが、日本語読み（及び英語説明）を用います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gojong attended to government affairs at the Russian Legation for over one year (Rokan Hasen [Royal refuge in the Russian Legation]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gojong attended to government affairs at the Russian Legation for over one year (Rokan Hasen [Royal refuge in the Russian Legation]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>これにより李氏朝鮮がロシアの保護国と見なされる危険性もあったと考え、日本は朝鮮への影響力を維持するため1897年に大韓帝国と国号を改めて独立の事実を明確にさせようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Considering it posed a risk that the Yi Dynasty Korea might be regarded as a Russian protected state, Japan tried to clarify the fact of its independence by changing its name to the Korean Empire in order to maintain Japan&apos;s clout on Korea in 1897.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Believing this posed the risk that the Yi Dynasty Korea might be regarded as a Russian protected state, Japan tried to clarify the fact of its independence by changing its name to the Korean Empire in order to maintain Japan&apos;s clout on Korea in 1897.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Believing this posed the risk that the Yi Dynasty Korea might be regarded as a Russian protected state, Japan tried to clarify the fact of its independence by changing its name to the Korean Empire in order to maintain Japan&apos;s clout on Korea in 1897.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>結局、大韓帝国成立後も実質的に李氏朝鮮王朝と同様の政体が朝鮮を支配することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, the constitution similar to the Yi Dynasty Korea, in fact, ruled Korea after the establishment of the Korean Empire.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, with a similar constitution, the Yi Dynasty Korea, in fact, ruled Korea after the establishment of the Korean Empire.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, with a similar constitution, the Yi Dynasty Korea, in fact, ruled Korea after the establishment of the Korean Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>進歩会（のちの一進会）などの改革派は弾圧され（改革派への弾圧を日本政府に依頼することすらあった）、開化は進まなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reformist groups, such as Shinpo-kai (pro-Japanese political organization in Korea) (later called, Isshin-kai) were oppressed (the Japanese government was sometimes even asked to oppress the reformists), and modernization did not progress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reformist groups, such as Shinpo-kai (pro-Japanese political organization in Korea) (later called, Isshin-kai) were oppressed (the Japanese government was sometimes even asked to oppress the reformists), and modernization did not progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reformist groups, such as Shinpo-kai (pro-Japanese political organization in Korea) (later called, Isshin-kai) were oppressed (the Japanese government was sometimes even asked to oppress the reformists), and modernization did not progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="37">
<j>日本国内では再び朝鮮半島への改革に介入すべきだとの世論が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A public opinion that Japan should intervene once more in the reform of the Korean peninsula came up in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A public opinion that Japan should intervene once more in the reform of the Korean peninsula arose in Japan.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A public opinion that Japan should intervene once more in the reform of the Korean peninsula arose in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、遅々として進まない朝鮮半島の政治改革に「日本が併合してでも改革を推し進めるべきだ」とする世論が台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, a public opinion stating &quot;Japan should promote the reform by the annexation&quot; emerged, because the political reform in the Korean Peninsula did not make much progress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, a public opinion stating &quot;Japan should promote the reform by the annexation&quot; emerged, because the political reform in the Korean Peninsula did not make much progress.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, a public opinion stating &apos;Japan should promote the reform by the annexation&apos; emerged, because the political reform in the Korean Peninsula did not make much progress.</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="39">
<j>桂太郎は「欧州に並ぶ強国になるには新たな領土が必要だ」という見地からこれを強力に推し進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taro KATSURA strongly moved ahead with it from the point of view that &quot;it required anew territory to be a powerful country comparable to Europe.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taro KATSURA strongly moved ahead with this from the point of view that &quot;They required a new territory to be a powerful country comparable to Europe.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taro KATSURA strongly moved ahead with this from the point of view that &apos;a new territory is required to be a powerful country comparable to Europe.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を改め、引用内容の文を受動態に改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>これにより朝鮮の自国領土への編入を望む日本政府と、日本世論とは合致した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this, the Japanese government wanting to incorporate Korea into its territory, and the Japanese public opinion came in tune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, the Japanese government wanting to incorporate Korea into its territory, and the Japanese public opinion came to be in agreement.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, the Japanese government wanting to incorporate Korea into its territory, and the Japanese public opinion came to be in agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>韓国統監であった伊藤博文と彼を中心とするグループは、「併合は時期尚早である」として反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirobumi ITO, Inspector General of Korea, and his group opposed to it, because &quot;the annexation was too early.&quot;</e>
<cmt>韓国統監の用語は確実ではありません。http://kotobank.jp/word/に韓国→李朝末の朝鮮の国号、大韓の通称。1897年から1910年の韓国併合まで用いられたとあります。韓国→Republic of Korea; South Koreaと定訳コラムにありますが、いずれでもないと思いますので、Inspector General of Koreaとします。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirobumi ITO, Inspector General of Korea, and his group were opposed to it, because &quot;the annexation was too early.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirobumi ITO, Inspector General of Korea, and his group were opposed to it, because &apos;the annexation was too early.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この反対論は、下記などから導き出された立場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This opposite opinion was based on the following.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This opposing opinion was based on the following.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This opposing opinion was based on the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>第一に朝鮮の統治政策に関して「将来、朝鮮で日本への抵抗・独立勢力になり得る芽を先に除去すべき時期である」と考えて抵抗勢力や反乱についての対策に腐心していたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Firstly, they were trying hard to take measures against the resistance forces and rebellions, believing that &quot;it was time to defuse potential resistance or independence forces beforehand2 for the policy on the rule of Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, in line with their policy on the rule of Korea, they were trying hard to take measures against the resistance forces and rebellions, believing that &quot;it was time to defuse potential resistance or independence forces beforehand&quot;.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, in line with their policy on the rule of Korea, they were trying hard to take measures against the resistance forces and rebellions, believing that &apos;it was time to defuse potential resistance or independence forces beforehand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>特に義兵活動が盛んなところでは村の大部分を焼き払う等の方法を用いた強引な弾圧を推し進める（吉田光男_2004134頁）などしていたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, they were conducting aggressive oppression, using measures such as burning down of large parts of villages in the area where gihei (irregular armies that fought against Japanese invasions into Korea) actions were active (Mitsuo YOSHIDA, 2004134 Page).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。（吉田光男_2004134頁）は意味不明確のため、そのまま訳します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, they were conducting aggressive oppression, using measures such as burning down large parts of villages in the area where gihei (irregular armies that fought against Japanese invasions into Korea) actions were active (Mitsuo YOSHIDA, 2004134 Page).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, they were conducting aggressive oppression, using measures such as burning down large parts of villages in the area where gihei (irregular armies that fought against Japanese invasions into Korea) actions were active (Mitsuo YOSHIDA, 2004134 Page).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>第二に日本国内に目を向けて「国内産業の育成に力を入れるべき時期だ」と考えていたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Secondly, they believed that &quot;it was time to make more efforts to nurture the domestic industries,&quot; paying more attention to the Japanese domestic affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Secondly, they believed that &quot;it was time to make more efforts to nurture the domestic industries,&quot; paying more attention to the Japanese domestic affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Secondly, they believed that &apos;it was time to make more efforts to nurture the domestic industries,&apos; paying more attention to the Japanese domestic affairs.</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>第三になにより対外的に「まだ国際社会の同意を得られない」と考えていたこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thirdly, above all, they thought that &quot;consent would not yet be obtained from the external international society.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirdly, above all, they thought that &quot;consent would not yet be obtained from the external international society.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirdly, above all, they thought that &quot;consent would not yet be obtained from the external international society.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>保護国化の進行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress into a Protected State</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress into a Protected State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress into a Protected State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>大韓帝国は冊封体制から離脱したものの、満州を手に入れたロシアが朝鮮半島に持つ利権を手がかりに明確な南下政策を取りつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Korean Empire seceded from the tributary system, Russia, which obtained Manchuria, was obviously making southward expansion, taking advantage of the interest it had in the Korean peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Korean Empire seceded from the tributary system, Russia, which obtained Manchuria, was obviously making southward expansion, taking advantage of the interest it had in the Korean peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Korean Empire seceded from the tributary system, Russia, which obtained Manchuria, was obviously making southward expansion, taking advantage of the interest it had in the Korean peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>当初、日本は外交努力で衝突を避けようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, Japan tried to avoid conflict through diplomatic efforts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning, Japan tried to avoid conflict through diplomatic efforts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning, Japan tried to avoid conflict through diplomatic efforts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>しかし、ロシアは強大な軍事力を背景に日本への圧力を増していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Russia increased pressure on Japan with its massive military power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Russia increased pressure on Japan with its massive military power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Russia increased pressure on Japan with its massive military power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>1904年、日露戦争の開戦である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1904, the Russo-Japanese War started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1904, the Russo-Japanese War started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1904, the Russo-Japanese War started.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>日本政府は開戦直後に朝鮮半島内における軍事行動の制約をなくすため、1904年2月23日に日韓議定書を締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan concluded the Japan-Korea Protocol on February 23, 1904 immediately after the start of the war to eliminate restrictions in its military actions in the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan concluded the Japan-Korea Protocol on February 23, 1904 immediately after the start of the war to eliminate restrictions in its military actions in the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan concluded the Japan-Korea Protocol on February 23, 1904 immediately after the start of the war to eliminate restrictions in its military actions in the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>また、李氏朝鮮による独自の改革を諦め韓日合邦を目指そうとした進歩会は、鉄道敷設工事などに5万人ともいわれる大量の人員を派遣するなど、日露戦争において日本への協力を惜しまなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Shinpo-kai, which gave up the independent reform by the Yi Dynasty Korea, and wanted to aim at the annexation of Korea and Japan, generously cooperated with Japan in the Russo-Japanese War by dispatching manpower as many as 50,000 for railway construction works, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Shinpo-kai, which gave up on the independent reform by Yi Dynasty Korea, and wanted to pursue the annexation of Korea and Japan, generously cooperated with Japan in the Russo-Japanese War by dispatching as many as 50,000 men for railway construction works, etc.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Shinpo-kai, which gave up on the independent reform by Yi Dynasty Korea, and wanted to pursue the annexation of Korea and Japan, generously cooperated with Japan in the Russo-Japanese War by dispatching as many as 50,000 men for railway construction works, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>8月には第一次日韓協約を締結し、財政顧問に目賀田種太郎、外交顧問にアメリカ人のドーハム・スティーブンスを推薦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, it concluded the first Japan-Korea Treaty, recommending Tanetaro MEGATA for the financial advisor, and Durham Stevens for the foreign affairs advisor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, the first Japan-Korea Treaty was concluded, recommending Tanetaro MEGATA for the financial advisor, and Durham Stevens for the foreign affairs advisor.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, the first Japan-Korea Treaty was concluded, recommending Tanetaro MEGATA for the financial advisor, and Durham Stevens for the foreign affairs advisor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>日本政府による推薦者を加えて影響力を確保し、他国への便宜供与を制約しようとの試みである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was an effort to secure its clout by adding the persons recommended by the Japanese government, and to restrict facilities offered to the other countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was an effort to secure its clout by adding the persons recommended by the Japanese government, and to restrict facilities offered to the other countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was an effort to secure its clout by adding the persons recommended by the Japanese government, and to restrict facilities offered to the other countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>他方で閔妃によってロシアに売り払われた関税権を買い戻すなど、その影響力を増していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, it increased its clout by buying back the customs right that had been sold to Russia by Empress Myeongseong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, it increased its clout by buying back the customs rights that had been sold to Russia by Empress Myeongseong.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, it increased its clout by buying back the customs rights that had been sold to Russia by Empress Myeongseong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>一方、高宗は日本の影響力をあくまでも排除しようと試み、日露戦争中においてもロシアに密書を送るなどの密使外交を展開していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Gojong tried to thoroughly eliminate Japan&apos;s clout, and conducted the diplomacy with secret envoys, such as sending secret letters to Russia during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>密使secret envoyを使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Gojong tried to thoroughly eliminate Japan&apos;s clout, and conducted diplomacy with secret envoys, such as sending secret letters to Russia during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Gojong tried to thoroughly eliminate Japan&apos;s clout, and conducted diplomacy with secret envoys, such as sending secret letters to Russia during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="57">
<j>この高宗の密使外交を排するために日本政府は日露戦争終結後の1905年11月に第二次日韓協約（韓国側では乙巳保護条約と呼ぶ）を締結し、12月には韓国統監府を設置して外交権をその支配下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese government concluded the second Japan-Korea Treaty (called Eulsa Protectorate Treaty in south Korea) in November, 1905 after the Russo-Japanese War to eliminate Gojong&apos;s diplomacy by secret envoys and established Korea Protection Agency in December to hold the diplomatic right under its control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese government concluded the second Japan-Korea Treaty (called Eulsa Protectorate Treaty in south Korea) in November, 1905 after the Russo-Japanese War to eliminate Gojong&apos;s diplomacy by secret envoys and established the Korea Protection Agency in December to hold diplomatic authority under its control.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese government concluded the second Japan-Korea Treaty (called Eulsa Protectorate Treaty in south Korea) in November, 1905 after the Russo-Japanese War to eliminate Gojong&apos;s diplomacy by secret envoys and established the Korea Protection Agency in December to hold diplomatic authority under its control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし第二次日韓協約の締結を認めない高宗は条約締結は強制であり無効であると訴えるため、1907年第2回万国平和会議に密使を派遣した（いわゆるハーグ密使事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Gojong, who did not accept the conclusion of the Eulsa Treaty, dispatched secret envoys to the second Hague Peace Conference in 1907 in order to denounce the conclusion of the treaty as compulsive and invalid (.so-called Hague Secret Envoy Incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Gojong, who did not accept the conclusion of the Eulsa Treaty, dispatched secret envoys to the second Hague Peace Conference in 1907 in order to denounce the conclusion of the treaty as compulsive and invalid (so-called Hague Secret Envoy Incident).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Gojong, who did not accept the conclusion of the Eulsa Treaty, dispatched secret envoys to the second Hague Peace Conference in 1907 in order to denounce the conclusion of the treaty as compulsive and invalid (so-called Hague Secret Envoy Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これに対して韓国統監であった伊藤をはじめとした日本政府首脳は激昂し、高宗を強制的に排除した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese heads of states, including ITO, who was the Inspector General of Korea, was enraged and forced Gojong out of office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese heads of state, including ITO, who was the Inspector General of Korea, were enraged and forced Gojong out of office.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese heads of state, including ITO, who was the Inspector General of Korea, were enraged and forced Gojong out of office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>李完用らの協力もあり、7月20日には半ば強制的に高宗は退位に追いこまれ、純宗_(朝鮮王)が第2代の大韓帝国皇帝として即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Lee Wan-Yong&apos;s cooperation, Gojong was half-compelled to abdicate from the crown on July 20, and Sunjong (Korean King) acceded to the throne of the second emperor of the Korean Empire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Lee Wan-Yong&apos;s cooperation, Gojong was half-compelled to abdicate from the crown on July 20th, and Sunjong (Korean King) acceded to the throne of the second emperor of the Korean Empire.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Lee Wan-Yong&apos;s cooperation, Gojong was half-compelled to abdicate from the crown on July 20th, and Sunjong (Korean King) acceded to the throne of the second emperor of the Korean Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>7月24日には第三次日韓協約を結んで内政権を掌握し、直後の8月1日には大韓帝国の軍隊を解散させるにまで至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 24, they concluded the third Japan-Korea Treaty to grasp the domestic administration right, and disbanded the army of the Korean Empire on August 1 immediately after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 24th, they concluded the third Japan-Korea Treaty to grasp domestic administration authority, and disbanded the army of the Korean Empire on August 1st immediately after that.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 24th, they concluded the third Japan-Korea Treaty to grasp domestic administration authority, and disbanded the army of the Korean Empire on August 1st immediately after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="62">
<j>これを不満とした元兵士などを中心として、抗日目的の反乱が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former soldiers and others who were dissatisfied with it raised an anti-Japanese rebellion.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former soldiers and others who were dissatisfied with this raised an anti-Japanese rebellion.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former soldiers and others who were dissatisfied with this raised an anti-Japanese rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>しかし、兵のほとんどが旧式の武装しか持たず、兵としての練度もなかったためにほどなく鎮圧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was soon suppressed, because most of the soldiers bore old arms, and had not been well trained as solders.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was soon suppressed, because most of the soldiers bore old arms, and had not been well trained as solders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was soon suppressed, because most of the soldiers bore old arms, and had not been well trained as solders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>もともと、軍隊としての存在意義が薄かったための解散でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army was disbanded, originally because their significance as the military force was low.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army was disbanded, because their significance as a military force was low to begin with.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army was disbanded, because their significance as a military force was low.</e>
<cmt>to begin withを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>残存兵力はその後の抗日義兵闘争に加わったともされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said the remaining soldiers participated in the later anti-Japanese gihei wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said the remaining soldiers participated in the later anti-Japanese gihei wars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said the remaining soldiers participated in the later anti-Japanese gihei wars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本統治時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of Japan&apos;s Rule</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of Japan&apos;s Rule</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of Japan&apos;s Rule</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>1909年7月に韓国併合の方針が閣議決定されたものの、韓国統監府を辞して帰国していた伊藤博文はあくまでも併合自体は将来的な課題として早期合併に抵抗を続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The policy on the annexation of Korea was decided at a cabinet meeting in July, 1909, but Hirobumi ITO, who resigned from Korea Protection Agency, and came back to Japan, continued to resist the early annexation, believing the annexation should be conducted later in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The policy on the annexation of Korea was decided at a cabinet meeting in July, 1909, but Hirobumi ITO, who resigned from the Korea Protection Agency, and came back to Japan, continued to resist the early annexation, believing the annexation should be conducted later in the future.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The policy on the annexation of Korea was decided at a cabinet meeting in July, 1909, but Hirobumi ITO, who resigned from the Korea Protection Agency, and came back to Japan, continued to resist the early annexation, believing the annexation should be conducted later in the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>しかし、10月26日に安重根によって伊藤博文が暗殺されたことにより早期併合に反対する有力な政治家がいなくなったこと、および初代首相であり元老のひとりでもあった伊藤を暗殺されたことによって日本の世論が併合に傾いていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Japanese public opinion moved closer to the annexation, because influential statesmen objecting to the early annexation disappeared due to the assassination of Hirobumi ITO by An Jung-geun on October 26, and ITO, who was the first prime minister and one of the elder statesmen, was assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Japanese public opinion grew in favor of the annexation, because an influential statesmen objecting to the early annexation disappeared due to the assassination of Hirobumi ITO by An Jung-geun on October 26th, and ITO, who was the first prime minister and one of the elder statesmen, was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Japanese public opinion grew in favor of the annexation, because an influential statesmen objecting to the early annexation disappeared due to the assassination of Hirobumi ITO by An Jung-geun on October 26th, and ITO, who was the first prime minister and one of the elder statesmen, was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>韓国併合に向けて着々と準備が進む中、1909年12月4日、突然韓国の一進会より「韓日合邦を要求する声明書」の上奏文が提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Isshin-kai in Korea suddenly presented a report to the throne, &quot;Statement calling for the annexation of Korea&quot; on December 4, 1909, while preparations for the annexation of Korea were being made steadily.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Isshin-kai in Korea suddenly presented a report to the throne, &quot;Statement calling for the annexation of Korea&quot; on December 4, 1909, while preparations for the annexation of Korea were being made steadily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Isshin-kai in Korea suddenly presented a report to the throne, &quot;Statement calling for the annexation of Korea&quot; on December 4, 1909, while preparations for the annexation of Korea were being made steadily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>韓国国内では国民大演説会などが開かれ、一気に一進会糾弾と排日気勢が高まり、在韓日本人新聞記者団からも一進会は猛烈な批判を浴びせられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Korea, citizens&apos; speech meetings were held, the denouncement of Isshin-kai and anti-Japanese trend rapidly increased, and Japanese newspaper reporters in Korea violently criticized Isshin-kai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Korea, citizens&apos; speech meetings were held, the denouncement of Isshin-kai and an anti-Japanese trend rapidly increased, and Japanese newspaper reporters in Korea violently criticized Isshin-kai.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Korea, citizens&apos; speech meetings were held, the denouncement of Isshin-kai and an anti-Japanese trend rapidly increased, and Japanese newspaper reporters in Korea violently criticized Isshin-kai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>そもそも「韓日合邦を要求する声明書」は韓国と日本が対等な立場で新たに一つの政府を作り、一つの大帝国を作るという、当時の現状から見ても日本にとっては到底受け入れられない提案であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first place, the &quot;Statement calling for the annexation of Korea&quot; said Korea and Japan would establish one government anew on a equal basis to create a large empire, which was not acceptable at all to Japan in view of the circumstances of those days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first place, the &quot;Statement calling for the annexation of Korea&quot; said Korea and Japan would establish one government anew on an equal basis to create a large empire, which was not acceptable at all to Japan in view of the circumstances of those days.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first place, the &quot;Statement calling for the annexation of Korea&quot; said Korea and Japan would establish one government anew on an equal basis to create a large empire, which was not acceptable at all to Japan in view of the circumstances of those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>また、無闇に韓国の世論を硬化させる結果を招き、統監府からは集会、演説の禁止命令が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, as it needlessly lead to the calcification of Korean public opinions, Korea Protection Agency prohibited its meetings and public speeches.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as it needlessly lead to the calcification of Korean public opinions, the Korea Protection Agency prohibited its meetings and public speeches.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as it needlessly lead to the calcification of Korean public opinions, the Korea Protection Agency prohibited meetings and public speeches.</e>
<cmt>itsを削除しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>韓国併合の閣議決定から1年、いろいろと紆余曲折はあったが、閣議決定どおり、1910年8月22日に日本は日韓併合条約により朝鮮半島を併合した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of several complications that occurred for one year after the annexation of Korea was decided at the cabinet meeting, Japan integrated the Korean Peninsula based on the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty on August 22, 1910, as decided in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of several complications that occurred for one year after this, the annexation of Korea was decided at the cabinet meeting, and Japan integrated the Korean Peninsula based on the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty on August 22, 1910, as decided in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of several complications that occurred for one year after the decision of annexation of Korea at the cabinet meeting, Japan integrated the Korean Peninsula based on the Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty on August 22, 1910, as decided in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>一部改変しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>これにより、大韓帝国は消滅し、朝鮮半島は第二次世界大戦（大東亜戦争、太平洋戦争）の終結まで日本の統治下に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this, the Korean Empire ceased to exist, and the Korean Peninsula was held under Japanese rule until the end of the Second World War (the Greater East Asian War, the Pacific War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, the Korean Empire ceased to exist, and the Korean Peninsula was held under Japanese rule until the end of the Second World War (the Greater East Asian War, the Pacific War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, the Korean Empire ceased to exist, and the Korean Peninsula was held under Japanese rule until the end of the Second World War (the Greater East Asian War, the Pacific War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>大韓帝国政府と韓国統監府は廃止され、かわって全朝鮮を統治する朝鮮総督府が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean Empire and Korea Protection Agency were discontinued, and instead, Chosen Sotoku-fu (Governor-General of Korea) was established to rule entire Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean Empire and Korea Protection Agency were discontinued, and instead, Chosen Sotoku-fu (Governor-General of Korea) was established to rule all of Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean Empire and Korea Protection Agency were discontinued, and instead, Chosen Sotoku-fu (Governor-General of Korea) was established to rule all of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>韓国の皇族は日本の皇族に準じる王公族に封じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean Imperial family was given the title of Okozoku (social position given to imperial family of former Korea) along the lines of the Japanese Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean Imperial family was given the title of Okozoku (social position given to imperial family of former Korea) along the lines of the Japanese Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean Imperial family was given the title of Okozoku (social position given to imperial family of former Korea) along the lines of the Japanese Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>また、韓国併合に貢献した韓国人は朝鮮貴族に封じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Koreans who contributed to the annexation of Korea were given the title of the Korean nobility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Koreans who contributed to the annexation of Korea were given the title of the Korean nobility.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Koreans who contributed to the annexation of Korea were given the title of the Korean nobility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="77">
<j>朝鮮総督府は1910年 - 1919年に土地調査事業に基づき測量を行ない、土地の所有権を確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chosen Sotoku-fu made a survey based on the land survey project from 1910 to 1919, and determined the ownership of land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chosen Sotoku-fu made a survey based on the land survey project from 1910 to 1919, and determined the ownership of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chosen Sotoku-fu made a survey based on the land survey project from 1910 to 1919, and determined the ownership of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>この際に申告された土地の99%以上は地主の申告通りに所有権が認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ownership of over 99% of the land declared on that occasion was approved, as reported by the landlords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ownership of over 99% of the land declared on that occasion was approved, as reported by the landlords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ownership of over 99% of the land declared on that occasion was approved, as declared by the landlords.</e>
<cmt>reported→declared</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>しかし、申告がなされなかった土地や、国有地と認定された土地（主に隠田などの所有者不明の土地とされるが、旧朝鮮王朝の土地を含むともいう）は接収され、東洋拓殖株式会社法（1909年法律第63号）によって設立され、朝鮮最大の地主となった東洋拓殖や、その他の日本人農業者に払い下げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the land not declared or land designated as state-owned land (it is said it was mainly the land of unknown owners, such as hidden rice fields, and included the land of the former Korean Dynasties) was taken over, and then sold to the Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd., which was founded according to the Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd. Law (1909 law No. 63) and became the largest landlord in Korea, as well as other Japanese farmers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the land not declared or land designated as state-owned land (it is said it was mainly the land of unknown owners, such as hidden rice fields, and included the land of the former Korean Dynasties) was taken over, and then sold to the Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd., which was founded according to the Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd. Law (1909 law No. 63) and became the largest landlord in Korea, as well as other Japanese farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the land not declared or land designated as state-owned land (it is said it was mainly the land of unknown owners, such as hidden rice fields, and included the land of the former Korean Dynasties) was taken over, and then sold to the Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd., which was founded according to the Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd. Law (1909 law No. 63) and became the largest landlord in Korea, as well as other Japanese farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>これを機に朝鮮では旧来の零細自作農民が小作農と化し大量に離村した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This triggered the transformation of small-hold land-owning farmers to tenant farmers and their massive departure from their villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This triggered the transformation of small-hold land-owning farmers into tenant farmers and their massive departure from their villages.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This triggered the transformation of small-hold land-owning farmers into tenant farmers and their massive departure from their villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>朝鮮総督府は東洋拓殖会社の一部の資金で朝鮮半島でチッソなどの財閥に各種の投資を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chosen Sotoku-fu made various investments in conglomerates, such as Chisso Corporation, in the Korean Peninsula, using part of the fund of Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chosen Sotoku-fu made various investments in conglomerates, such as Chisso Corporation, in the Korean Peninsula, using part of the fund of Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chosen Sotoku-fu made various investments in conglomerates, such as Chisso Corporation, in the Korean Peninsula, using part of the fund of Toyo Takushoku Co. Ltd.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>日本の統治下で、李朝時代の特権商人が時代に対処できず没落する一方、旧来の地主勢力の一部が乱高下する土地の売買などによって資金を貯め、新興資本家として台頭してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the rule of Japan, merchants privileged in the Yi Dynasty period went to ruin, while some conventional landlords who raised fund by buying and selling the land of which prices violently fluctuated gained power as emerging capitalists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the rule of Japan, merchants privileged in the Yi Dynasty period went to ruin, while some conventional landlords who raised funds by buying and selling the land of which prices violently fluctuated gained power as emerging capitalists.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the rule of Japan, merchants privileged in the Yi Dynasty period went to ruin failing to adapt to the trend of the era, while some conventional landlords who raised funds by buying and selling the land of which prices violently fluctuated gained power as emerging capitalists.</e>
<cmt>「時代に対処できず」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>これらの新興資本家の多くは総督府と良好な関係を保ち発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of those emerging capitalists grew, keeping good relationship with Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of those emerging capitalists grew, keeping good relationships with Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of those emerging capitalists grew, keeping good relationships with Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>大韓民国における日本統治時代の呼称</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naming of the Period of Japan&apos;s Rule in South Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naming of the period of Japan&apos;s rule in South Korea</e>
<cmt>Changed capitalization.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naming of the period of Japan&apos;s rule in South Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>日本統治時代を韓国側が日帝強占期（韓国の公営放送KBS＝韓国放送公社＝ではこの呼称に最近統一しようとしている）、日帝時代または日政時代などと呼ぶ事が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known the Period of Japan&apos;s Rule is called the Japanese forced occupation period (Korean public broadcasting, KBS, Korean Broadcasting System is trying to unifying the names into this), the Japanese Imperial period, or Japanese administration period by South Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known that the period of Japan&apos;s rule is called the Japanese forced occupation period (Korean public broadcasting, KBS, Korean Broadcasting System is trying to unify the names into this), the Japanese Imperial period, or Japanese administration period by South Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known that the period of Japan&apos;s rule is called the Japanese forced occupation period (Korean public broadcasting, KBS, Korean Broadcasting System is trying to unify the names into this), the Japanese Imperial period, or Japanese administration period by South Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>前者2つには、韓国併合の有効性、合法性を認めず、朝鮮半島に対する日本の支配を単なる軍事占領とする認識がうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first two shows a recognition that validity or legitimacy in the annexation of Korea and Japanese occupation of Korea is not accepted, and the Japanese rule of the Korean peninsula is seen as a mere military occupation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first two show a recognition that validity or legitimacy in the annexation of Korea and the Japanese occupation of Korea is not accepted, and the Japanese rule of the Korean peninsula is seen as a mere military occupation.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first two show a recognition that validity or legitimacy in the annexation of Korea and the Japanese occupation of Korea is not accepted, and the Japanese rule of the Korean peninsula is seen as a mere military occupation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>また、日本植民地時代という呼称も用いられるが、韓国併合条約、日本による朝鮮領有の合法性、有効性を示唆するものであるという認識から、近年では忌避される傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, the Japanese colony period is also used, but it tends to be avoided based on the recognition that it implies the legitimacy or validity in the treaty of the annexation of Korea and the Japanese occupation of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the Japanese colony period is also used, but it tends to be avoided based on the recognition that it implies the legitimacy or validity of the treaty of the annexation of Korea and the Japanese occupation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the Japanese colony period is also used, but recently it tends to be avoided based on the recognition that it implies the legitimacy or validity of the treaty of the annexation of Korea and the Japanese occupation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>「近年」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>大韓民国における日本統治時代の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Evaluation of the Period of Japan&apos;s Rule in Republic of Korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Evaluation of the period of Japan&apos;s rule in the Republic of Korea</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Evaluation of the period of Japan&apos;s rule in the Republic of Korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>独立後の韓国の歴史学者・学会は、日本による統治を正当化する日本側の歴史研究を「植民地史観」と呼び、これを強く批判することから出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calling the Japanese historical researches justifying the Japanese rule &quot;colonial historical view,&quot; South Korean historians/academic societies started from strong criticism of that after the independence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Calling the Japanese historical research justifying the Japanese rule &quot;colonial historical view,&quot; South Korean historians/academic societies started due to strong criticism of that after Korea&apos;s independence.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Calling the Japanese historical research justifying the Japanese rule &apos;colonial historical view,&apos; South Korean historians/academic societies started their research from the strong criticism of that after Korea&apos;s independence.</e>
<cmt>started their research fromと補訳しました引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>彼らの言うところの「植民地史観」に対抗して登場したのは民族史観であり、その後の歴史研究の柱となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ethnical historical view, which came up, opposing to what they called &quot;colonial historical view,&quot; served as the pillar of the later historical researches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ethnical historical view, which came up in opposition to what they called &quot;colonial historical view,&quot; served as the pillar of the later historical research.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ethnical historical view, which came up in opposition to what they called &apos;colonial historical view,&apos; served as the pillar of the later historical research.</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>そうした雰囲気もあって、日本統治時代に様々な近代化が行われたことを認めつつも、近代化の萌芽は李氏朝鮮の時代に既に存在しており、日本による統治はそれらの萌芽を破壊することで、結果的には近代化を阻害したとする近代化萌芽論が独立後に現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under those circumstances, the modernization germination theory, arguing modernization had already germinated in the Yi Dynasty Korea period, and the Japanese rule destroyed the germination, resulting in the impeded modernization, came up after the independence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under those circumstances, the modernization germination theory, arguing modernization had already germinated in the Yi Dynasty Korea period, and the Japanese rule destroyed the germination, resulting in the impeded modernization, appeared after Korea&apos;s independence</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under those circumstances, the modernization germination theory, arguing modernization had already germinated in the Yi Dynasty Korea period, and the Japanese rule destroyed the germination, resulting in the impeded modernization, appeared after Korea&apos;s independence in spite of recognizing that the various modernization during the Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>「日本統治時代に様々な近代化が行われたことを認めつつも」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>一方、評論家・作家の金完燮や日本の保守層を代弁する人物として、拓殖大学の教授で済州島出身呉善花などは日本による統治を肯定的に評価する本を執筆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Kim Wansop, a critic and writer, and O Seonhwa from Jeju, a professor of Takushoku University, who is a representative of the Japanese conservatives, wrote books in which the Japanese rule was positively evaluated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Kim Wansop, a critic and writer, and O Seonhwa from Jeju, a professor at Takushoku University, who is a representative of the Japanese conservatives, wrote books in which the Japanese rule was positively evaluated.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Kim Wansop, a critic and writer, and O Seonhwa from Jeju, a professor at Takushoku University and a representative of the Japanese conservatives, wrote books in which the Japanese rule was positively evaluated.</e>
<cmt>who is→and</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>またソウル大学教授の李栄薫などによる、日本の統治が近代化を促進したと主張する植民地近代化論も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there is the colony modernization theory by Lee Yong-hoon, a professor of Seoul University, and others, arguing the Japanese rule promoted modernization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there is the colony modernization theory by Lee Yong-hoon, a professor at Seoul University, and others, arguing that the Japanese rule promoted modernization.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there is the colony modernization theory by Lee Yong-hoon, a professor at Seoul University, and others, arguing that the Japanese rule promoted modernization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし、韓国人としては少数派である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they are minority in South Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they are the minority in South Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they are the minority in South Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>近年、李栄薫らは李氏朝鮮時代の資料を調査し李氏朝鮮時代の末期に朝鮮経済が急速に崩壊したことを主張し、近代化萌芽論を強く否定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently, Lee Yong-hoon studied materials in the Yi Dynasty Korea period, and stated Korean economy rapidly collapsed at the end of the Yi Dynasty Korea period, strongly denying the modernization germination theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently, Lee Yong-hoon studied materials from the Yi Dynasty Korea period, and stated that the Korean economy rapidly collapsed at the end of the Yi Dynasty Korea period, strongly denying the modernization germination theory.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recently, Lee Yong-hoon studied materials from the Yi Dynasty Korea period, and stated that the Korean economy rapidly collapsed at the end of the Yi Dynasty Korea period, strongly denying the modernization germination theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>また国外的には、ハーバード大学の朝鮮史教授カーター・J・エッカートも韓国での萌芽論は「論理ではなく日本を弾劾することが目的のもの」としており、近代化萌芽論を強く否定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, outside the country, Carter J. Eckert, a Korean history professor, Harvard University, regarded the germination theory in South Korea as &quot;not a logic, but a theory for the purpose of impeaching Japan,&quot; and strongly denied the modernization germination theory.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, outside the country, Carter J. Eckert, a Korean history professor, Harvard University, regarded the germination theory in South Korea as &quot;not logical, but a theory for the purpose of impeaching Japan,&quot; and strongly denied the modernization germination theory.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, outside the country, Carter J. Eckert, a Korean history professor, Harvard University, regarded the germination theory in South Korea as &quot;not logical, but a theory for the purpose of impeaching Japan,&quot; and strongly denied the modernization germination theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>韓国の資本主義は日本の植民地化の中で生まれ、特に戦後の韓国の資本主義や工業化は日本の近代化政策を模したものという研究結果を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He published the result of his study determining South Korean capitalism was born in Japanese colonization, and particularly the capitalism and industrialization in South Korea after the war was modeled after Japanese modernization policies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He published the results of his study determining South Korean capitalism was born during Japanese colonization, and particularly the capitalism and industrialization in South Korea after the war was modeled after Japanese modernization policies.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He published the results of his study determining South Korean capitalism was born during Japanese colonization, and particularly the capitalism and industrialization in South Korea after the war was modeled after Japanese modernization policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>同時に彼は日本統治そのものについては朴正煕政権との類似性などをあげ、軍事独裁の一形態であり、韓国の資本家に独裁政権への依存体質をもたらす原因になったとも述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he pointed out the similarity of the Japanese rule to Chung-hee PARK&apos;s government, and said it was one form of military dictatorship, and caused Korean capitalists&apos; dependence on dictatorship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he pointed out the similarity of the Japanese rule to Chung-hee PARK&apos;s government, and said it was one form of military dictatorship, and caused Korean capitalists&apos; dependence on dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he pointed out the similarity of the Japanese rule to Chung-hee PARK&apos;s government, and said it was one form of military dictatorship, and caused Korean capitalists&apos; dependence on dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>日本統治下の朝鮮を植民地と呼ぶかどうかについての論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Discussion on Whether Korea under the Rule of Japan can be Called a Colony or Not</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Discussion on whether Korea under the rule of Japan can be called a colony or not</e>
<cmt>Removed capitalization.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Discussion on whether Korea under the rule of Japan can be called a colony or not</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>植民地という呼称は、新規の領土を旧来の領土に比して特殊な政治制度の下におき政治的従属状態においているものを呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The naming of a colony is often used for a political subordination state of a new territory placed under a special political system, compared with the original territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The designation of a territory as a colony is often used for the political subordination of a new territory placed under a special political system, compared with the original territory.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The designation of a territory as a colony is often used for the political subordination of a new territory placed under a special political system, compared with the original territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>現実例から抽出されたモデルに現実に用いられた呼称を適用することからはじまったが、先行モデルを中心に価値判断を排除すべく概念規定されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It started from applying actually used names to models extracted from actual examples, and a concept is being determined to exclude value judgments mainly from prior models.</e>
<cmt>原文が前文とつながらないように思いますが、何か脱落しているかもしれません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It started from applying actually used names to models extracted from actual examples, and it was later determined to exclude value judgments mainly from prior models.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The naming started from applying actually used names to models extracted from actual examples, and the concept of colony is being determined to exclude value judgments mainly from prior models.</e>
<cmt>主語を明確化しましたit was later determined→the concept of colony is being determined</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>これは先行する事実をモデルにしないかぎり、名称をつけられず、議論も不可能であるためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because unless the prior facts have not been modeled, names can not be given, and discussions can not be held.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because unless the prior facts have not been modeled, names can not be given, and discussions can not be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because unless the prior facts have not been modeled, names can not be given, and discussions can not be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="100">
<j>ただし、欧米による先行のモデルとの差異を論じるべく日本型植民地支配がどのようなものであったかについては継続して議論が戦わされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the discussion on what the Japanese-style rule of the colony was like has continued to argue over the difference from prior models made by Europe and America.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the discussion on what the Japanese-style rule of the colony was like has continued in arguments over the difference from prior models made by Europe and America.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the discussion on what the Japanese-style rule of the colony was like has continued to argue over the difference from prior models made by Europe and America.</e>
<cmt>翻訳者の訳に戻しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>のみならず「日本の統治政策は同時代に欧米諸国の行った異民族統治とは異質で、善政である」「植民地という言葉は諸外国が異民族統治に対して行った悪政に使われる言葉である」という認識から、双方を一緒に植民地という言葉で形容することへの批判がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there is a criticism of the use of the word, colony, for both together, based on the recognition that &quot;the Japanese governing policy was different from the rule of different ethnic groups by Western countries, and was good politics,&quot; and &quot;the word, colony, is the word to express the misrule conducted by foreign countries to rule different ethnic groups.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there is criticism of the use of the word, colony, for both, based on the recognition that &quot;the Japanese governing policy was different from the rule of different ethnic groups by Western countries, and was good politics,&quot; and &quot;the word, colony, is the word to express the misrule conducted by foreign countries to rule different ethnic groups.&quot;</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there is criticism of using the word colony for both, based on the recognition that &apos;the Japanese governing policy was different from the rule of different ethnic groups by Western countries in the same era, and was good politics,&apos; and &apos;colony is the word to express the misrule conducted by foreign countries to rule different ethnic groups.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一部改変しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>この立場からは日本の朝鮮支配について「植民地」という呼称を用いるべきではないと主張されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is advocated from this position that the word, &quot;colony&quot; should not be used for the Japanese rule of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is advocated from this position that the word, &quot;colony&quot; should not be used for the Japanese rule of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is advocated from this position that the word &apos;colony&apos; should not be used for the Japanese rule of Korea.</e>
<cmt>引用符を改めました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="103">
<j>朝鮮を支配していた当時の日本政府は、法的には朝鮮に対して特別の呼称(植民地、外地など)を付さなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The then Japanese government that ruled Korea did not legally give any special naming (colony, overseas territory, etc.) for Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The then Japanese government that ruled Korea did not legally give any special designation (colony, overseas territory, etc.) for Korea.</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The then Japanese government that ruled Korea did not legally give any special designation (colony, overseas territory, etc.) for Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>ただし公文書では植民地、外地とも使用例が見られる([10][11]を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the use of both colony and overseas territory was seen in official documents (See).</e>
<cmt>(、を参照）は、語の脱落があります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the use of both colony and overseas territory was seen in official documents (See).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the use of both colony and overseas territory was seen in official documents (See [10][11]).</e>
<cmt>ウィキペディア版を参照し番号を補完し、併せて訳文も修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>在野の学者や思想家の間には朝鮮が植民地であるかどうかについて見解の相違があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a discrepancy in the opinions of independent scholars and thinkers on whether Korea was a colony or not.</e>
<cmt>在野の意味不明。Independentとします。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a discrepancy in the opinions of independent scholars and thinkers on whether Korea was a colony or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a discrepancy in the opinions of independent scholars and thinkers on whether Korea was a colony or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>憲法学者の美濃部達吉、植民政策学者の新渡戸稲造、矢内原忠雄など社会科学者は概ね植民地であると見なしていたが、歴史学者の田保橋潔や思想家の北一輝などは植民地ではないとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatsukichi MINOBE, a scholar of constitutional law, and Inazo NITOBE, a scholar of colonial policies, as well as social scientists such as Tadao YANAIHARA generally considered it as a colony, while Kiyoshi TABOBASHI, a historian, Ikki KITA, a thinker, and others did not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatsukichi MINOBE, a scholar of constitutional law, and Inazo NITOBE, a scholar of colonial policies, as well as social scientists such as Tadao YANAIHARA generally considered it as a colony, while Kiyoshi TABOBASHI, a historian, Ikki KITA, a thinker, and others did not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatsukichi MINOBE, a scholar of constitutional law, and Inazo NITOBE, a scholar of colonial policies, as well as social scientists such as Tadao YANAIHARA generally considered it as a colony, while Kiyoshi TABOBASHI, a historian, Ikki KITA, a thinker, and others did not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>戦後の日本の政治家の発言や日朝平壌宣言のような外交文書でも朝鮮が植民地であったとする表現がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An expression that Korea was a colony is seen in Japanese statesmen&apos;s comments after the war, and in some diplomatic documents, such as the Japan-North Korea Pyongyang Declaration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An expression that Korea was a colony is seen in Japanese statesmen&apos;s comments after the war, and in some diplomatic documents, such as the Japan-North Korea Pyongyang Declaration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An expression that Korea was a colony is seen in Japanese statesmen&apos;s comments after the war, and in some diplomatic documents, such as the Japan-North Korea Pyongyang Declaration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>しかし、これを日本政府の公式見解とするかどうかには議論がある(日本の戦争謝罪発言一覧も参照)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is an argument over whether this can be taken as Japanese government&apos;s official view or not (See the list of Japanese comments on apologies for the war).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is an argument over whether this can be taken as the Japanese government&apos;s official view or not (See the list of Japanese comments on apologies for the war).</e>
<cmt>reword</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is an argument over whether this can be taken as the Japanese government&apos;s official view or not (See the list of Japanese comments on apologies for the war).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>歴史認識の比較</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comparison of Historical Perceptions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comparison of Historical Perceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comparison of Historical Perceptions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>韓国併合史について、以下のような歴史認識の相違がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following difference is seen in the historical perceptions on the history of the annexation of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following difference is seen in the historical perceptions on the history of the annexation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following difference is seen in the historical perceptions on the history of the annexation of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>（なお、以下に示す「保守派」と「革新派」は、日本のマスコミなどでそのように表記されるグループの名称を使用したものであり、定義通りの保守、革新を表すものではない。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(&quot;The conservatives&quot; and &quot;the reformists&quot; shown below are the group names used by the Japanese media, and do not mean conservative or reformist, as defined.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(&quot;The conservatives&quot; and &quot;the reformists&quot; shown below are the group names used by the Japanese media, and do not mean conservative or reformist, as defined.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(&apos;The conservatives&apos; and &apos;the reformists&apos; shown below are the group names used by the Japanese media, and do not mean conservative or reformist, as defined.)</e>
<cmt>引用符を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 冬月(id:30384), Bill(id:11619), 22010515528(id:43149), Eskimbot(id:29676), Kamakura(id:472), Yukichi99(id:29402), Opponent(id:720), Hermeneus(id:380), Commonsenses(id:11185), PPP(id:22924), Boa(id:20845), Shin-改(id:9914), Croce(id:20876), Sea of Japan(id:3230), TRIBESMAN(id:4735), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Open-box(id:17893), Gett(id:21989), Yaky(id:22711), Arisu6(id:23983), Knightofathena(id:19058), 雷(id:25583), 異端審問官(id:92197), 狸うどん(id:3809), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Edgar(id:11830), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), R28Bot(id:177951), Kanjy(id:36859), Ikedat76(id:34218), Mine-Kansai(id:2080), NIKE(id:16342), 唐変木(id:17050), Naritab602(id:36470), Iosif(id:31044), Lover(id:24553), Straysheep(id:42448), Suguri F(id:11127), Kawai(id:5634), 阿修羅(id:29454), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Qazzx(id:8772), 矢刺幹人(id:10639), Johncapistrano(id:969), EULE(id:74209), Snow steed(id:9428), SAYAKO(id:38698), ２００６(id:36300), 氷鷺(id:73707), A6M4(id:14155), Dondokken(id:246411), 平 誠(id:2586), Bumpoff(id:13021), Nopira(id:29335), 119.asp(id:28071), Kozawa(id:672), LERK(id:4460), 違法着衣兵(id:35878), いいちこ(id:41288), Wilson Tam(id:17411), 雲居雁乃(id:15842), 見廻組(id:9996), Shinkansen(id:13703), Prefecture(id:26164), Sphl(id:122), Miya(id:1881), 榕樹(id:123252), Trek011(id:7105), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>