<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>庭訓往来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teikin Orai</e>
<cmt>DBに登録されている訳（2009/10/26付）を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teikin Orai (collection of letters used for family education)</e>
<cmt>Added meaning</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teikin Orai</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>庭訓往来（ていきんおうらい）とは、往来物（往復の手紙）の形式をとる、寺子屋で習字や読本として使用された初級の教科書の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teikin Orai was one of the elementary textbooks used as copybooks and readers at Terakoya (temple elementary schools during the Edo Period), written in an oraimono (exchange of letters) style.</e>
<cmt>「習字」は、文脈から「習字の手本帳」という意味で解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Written in an oraimono (exchange of letters) style, Teikin Orai was an elementary textbook used as a copybook and reader at Terakoya (temple elementary schools during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>Please thank the translator for providing helpful comments for the checkers and explanations in the text for the reader.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Written in an oraimono (exchange of letters) style, Teikin Orai was an elementary textbook used as a copybook and reader at Terakoya (temple elementary schools during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>南北朝時代_(日本)末期から室町時代前期の成立とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed to have formed between the late period of the Northern and Southern Courts and the early Muromachi Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed to have been put together between the later part of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts and the beginning of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed to have been put together between the later part of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts and the beginning of the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>著者は南北朝時代の僧玄恵とされるが、確証に乏しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although it is generally considered to have been authored by Gene, a monk in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, this is unconfirmed.</e>
<cmt>「玄恵」は、DBに登録されている訳を採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it is generally considered to have been authored by Gene, a monk who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, this has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it is generally considered to have been authored by Gene, a monk who lived during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, this has not been confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>擬漢文体で書かれ、衣食住、職業、領国経営、建築、司法、職分、仏教、武具、教養、療養など、多岐にわたる一般常識を内容とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Written in the pseudo-Chinese style, Teikin Orai covered a wide range of topics on general knowledge including lifestyle, vocation, territory management, architecture, law, duty, Buddhism, weapons, education, and medical treatment.</e>
<cmt>「擬漢文体」は、用語集に登録されている訳を採用しました。「衣食住」は、“housing, food, and clothing”という定訳もありますが、ここでは冗長となるため避け、また、並列関係を重視し、“lifestyle”としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Written in pseudo-Chinese style, Teikin Orai covered a wide range of topics on general knowledge including lifestyle, vocation, territory management, architecture, law, duty, Buddhism, weapons, education, and medical treatment.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Written in pseudo-Chinese style, Teikin Orai covered a wide range of topics on general knowledge including lifestyle, vocation, territory management, architecture, law, duty, Buddhism, weapons, education, and medical treatment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1年12ヶ月の往信返信各12通と8月13日の1通を加えた25通からなり、多くの単語と文例が学べるよう工夫されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consisted of 25 letters, which were 12 letters to send and another 12 to receive for all months of the year and an additional letter for August 13, designed to help learn many words and model sentences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consisted of 25 letters, 12 letters to send and another 12 to receive for the respective months of the year and an additional letter for August 13, designed to help students learn many words and model sentences.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consisted of 25 letters, 12 letters to send and another 12 to receive for the respective months of the year and an additional letter for August 13, designed to help students learn many words and model sentences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>写本や注釈本、絵入り本が多く存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A great number of shahon (manuscripts), chushakubon (commentaries) and eiribon (illustrated books) for Teikin Orai are known.</e>
<cmt>原文に不足しているとみられる「庭訓往来」を訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A great number of shahon (manuscripts), chushakubon (commentaries), and eiribon (illustrated books) for Teikin Orai are known.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A great number of shahon (manuscripts), chushakubon (commentaries), and eiribon (illustrated books) for Teikin Orai are known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>時代を超えて普遍的な社会常識も多く扱ったために江戸時代に入っても寺子屋などの教科書として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Teikin Orai dealt with common practices that were timeless and universal, it served as a textbook at Terakoya well into the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Teikin Orai dealt with common practices that were timeless and universal, it served as a textbook at Terakoya well into the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Teikin Orai dealt with common practices that were timeless and universal, it served as a textbook at Terakoya well into the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>古写本で30種、板本で200種に達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are about 30 kinds of koshabon (old manuscripts) and 200 kinds of itahon (books bound in Japanese style) for Teikin Orai.</e>
<cmt>「古写本」と「板本」は用語集に登録されている訳を採用しました。訳文で“about”を補っています。原文に不足しているとみられる「庭訓往来」を訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are about 30 kinds of koshabon (old manuscripts) and 200 kinds of itahon (books bound in Japanese style) for Teikin Orai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are about 30 kinds of koshabon (old manuscripts) and 200 kinds of itahon (books bound in Japanese style) for Teikin Orai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>尚、庭訓とは、『論語』季子篇の中にある孔子が庭を走る息子を呼び止め詩や礼を学ぶよう諭したという故事に因み、父から子への教訓や家庭教育を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &quot;teikin&quot; bases its origin on a historical event taken from the Ji Shi (Chief of the Ji Clan) section of &quot;the Analects of Confucius&quot; in which Confucius called to his son to stop running in a garden and encouraged him to learn poetry and etiquette, signifying teachings from father to son and home education.</e>
<cmt>※「礼」はWikipediaの“Li(Confucian)”のエントリーから訳をあてました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &quot;teikin&quot; originates from a historical event taken from the Ji Shi (Chief of the Ji Clan) section of &quot;the Analects of Confucius&quot; in which Confucius called to his son to stop running in a garden and encouraged him to learn poetry and etiquette, signifying teachings from father to son and home education.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &quot;teikin&quot; originates from a historical event taken from the Ji Shi (Chief of the Ji Clan) section of &quot;Rongo&quot; (the Analects of Confucius) in which Confucius called to his son to stop running in a garden and encouraged him to learn poetry and etiquette, signifying teachings from father to son and home education.</e>
<cmt>確実な定訳がないようなので、念のため読みを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>形式と内容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Form and Content</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Form and Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Form and Content</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>形式（手紙文の「書き出し」、生活上必要な「単語群」、手紙文の「締めくくり」、日付、差出人名、宛名の順序）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formed in the following order: &apos;introduction&apos; of a letter, &apos;word groups&apos; essential in everyday life, &apos;closing&apos; of a letter, date, sender&apos;s name, and address.</e>
<cmt>「　」は不要にも思えますが、‘ ’として残しています。英文として自然な訳となるよう原文の「～の順序」を文頭に移しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formatted in the following order: &apos;introduction&apos; of a letter, &apos;word groups&apos; essential in everyday life, &apos;closing&apos; of a letter, date, sender&apos;s name, and address.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formatted in the following order: &apos;introduction&apos; of a letter, &apos;word groups&apos; essential in everyday life, &apos;closing&apos; of a letter, date, sender&apos;s name, and address.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>単語群の題材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subjects for Word Groups</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subjects for Word Groups</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subjects for Word Groups</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>１月（新年の会遊）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January: New Year&apos;s meetings</e>
<cmt>「会遊」の定訳が見つからないため、“meeting”としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January: New Year&apos;s meetings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January: New Year&apos;s meetings</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>2月（花見詩歌の宴）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February: banquet for cherry blossom viewing and poetry reading.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February: banquet for cherry blossom viewing and poetry reading.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February: Banquet for cherry blossom viewing and poetry reading</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>3月（地方大名の領国統治、勧農、館の造り、果樹）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March: territory management by feudal lords, encouragement of agriculture, construction of houses, and fruit trees</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March: territory management by feudal lords, encouragement of agriculture, construction of houses, and fruit trees</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March: Territory management by feudal lords, encouragement of agriculture, construction of houses, and fruit trees</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>4月（領地の繁栄と為政の心得、市町の経営と諸職業人の招致、商取引の施設と業種、諸国特産品）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April: prosperity of territories, understanding of politics, administration of villages and towns, invitation of various professionals, facilities for commercial trades and types of business, and indigenous local products</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April: prosperity of territories, understanding of politics, administration of villages and towns, invitation of various professionals, facilities for commercial trades and types of business, and indigenous local products</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April: Prosperity of territories, understanding of politics, administration of villages and towns, invitation of various professionals, facilities for commercial trades and types of business, and indigenous local products</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>5月（家財家具、調理品名）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May: furniture and house articles, and names of cooking tools</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May: furniture and household articles, and names of cooking tools</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May: Furniture and household articles, and names of cooking tools</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>6月（盗賊討伐への出陣、武具乗馬の借用、出陣の命令系統と心得、武具・馬具の名称）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June: departure for the subjugation of robbers, borrowing of weapons and horses, knowledge of departure for battle and of its chain of command, and names of weapons and harness</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June: departure for the subjugation of robbers, borrowing of weapons and horses, knowledge of departure for battle and of the chain of command, and nomenclature of weapons and harness</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June: Departure for the subjugation of robbers, borrowing of weapons and horses, knowledge of departure for battle and of the chain of command, and nomenclature of weapons and harness</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>7月（競技会の衣装、諸具、諸器）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July: costume, various items and tools for competitions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July: costume, various items and tools for competitions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July: Costume, various items and tools for competitions</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>8月（司法制度、訴訟手続き、問注所・侍所の組織と職掌）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August: judicial system, law procedures, organization and management of monchujo (board of inquiry) and samurai-dokoro (board of retainers.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August: judicial system, law procedures, organization and management of monchujo (board of inquiry) and samurai-dokoro (board of retainers.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August: Judicial system, law procedures, organization and management of monchujo (board of inquiry) and samurai-dokoro (board of retainers.)</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>8月単状（将軍家若宮の行列の威容）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August (single letter): dignity of the procession of sons in the shogun family.</e>
<cmt>「若宮」は、将軍家の子という意味で訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August (single letter): dignity of the procession of sons in the shogun family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August (single letter): Dignity of the procession of sons in the shogun family.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>9月（大法会に寄せて、伽藍・仏像、法会の式次第、役僧、舞童、諸道具）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September: Buddhist temples, Buddha statues, programs for the Buddhist mass, sextons, dancing kids, and various items for the occasion of great Buddhist masses</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September: Buddhist temples, Buddha statues, programs for the Buddhist mass, sextons, dancing children, and various items for the occasion of great Buddhist masses</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September: Buddhist temples, Buddha statues, programs for the Buddhist mass, sextons, dancing children, and various items for the occasion of great Buddhist masses</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>10月（大斎の行事にちなんで、点心、寺家の諸役、僧位僧官の名称、布施物、点心用の食品・菓子・茶具・汁・菜などの食品食物）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October: refreshments, miscellaneous taxes in temples, names of soi and sokan (rank and position of Buddhist priest), offerings, food served as refreshments such as sweets, tea tools, soups and side dishes for the occasion of taisai (grand festival) events.</e>
<cmt>「点心」は仏教での「軽い食事」という意味で訳しています。一つ目の「点心」は、文脈から不要かと思いますが、残しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October: refreshments, miscellaneous taxes in temples, names of soi and sokan (ranks and positions of Buddhist priest), offerings, food served as refreshments such as sweets, tea utensils, soups and side dishes for the occasion of taisai (grand festival) events.</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October: Refreshments, miscellaneous taxes in temples, names of soi and sokan (ranks and positions of Buddhist priest), offerings, food served as refreshments such as sweets, tea utensils, soups and side dishes for the occasion of taisai (grand festival) events.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>11月（病気の種類と治療法、病気予防・健康保持のための禁忌）、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November: types of disease and its treatment, and taboos for the sake of preventing disease and staying healthy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November: types of diseases and their treatment, and taboos for the sake of preventing disease and staying healthy.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November: Types of diseases and their treatment, and taboos for the sake of preventing disease and staying healthy</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>１２月（地方行政の制度、着任の模様、行政管理の模様）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">December: system of local administration, descriptions of inauguration and government control</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">December: system of local administration, descriptions of inauguration and government control</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December: System of local administration, descriptions of inauguration and government control</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>刊本の種類について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of Kanpon (printed copies) for Teikin Orai</e>
<cmt>原文に不足しているとみられる「庭訓往来」を訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of Kanpon (printed copies) for Teikin Orai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of Kanpon (printed copies) for Teikin Orai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>刊本は、大きく分けて「手本系」・「読本系」・「注釈本系」・「絵抄系」の四つに分類できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanpon for Teikin Orai was broadly classified into four types: &apos;Tehon-kei&apos; (model handwriting-type), &apos;Tokuhon-kei&apos; (reader-type), &apos;Chushakubon-kei&apos; (commentary-type) and &apos;Esho-kei&apos; (illustrated commentary-type.)</e>
<cmt>原文に不足しているとみられる「庭訓往来」を訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanpon for Teikin Orai was broadly classified into four types: &apos;Tehon-kei&apos; (model handwriting-type), &apos;Tokuhon-kei&apos; (reader-type), &apos;Chushakubon-kei&apos; (commentary-type), and &apos;Esho-kei&apos; (illustrated commentary-type.)</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanpon for Teikin Orai was broadly classified into four types: &apos;Tehon-kei&apos; (model handwriting-type), &apos;Tokuhon-kei&apos; (reader-type), &apos;Chushakubon-kei&apos; (commentary-type), and &apos;Esho-kei&apos; (illustrated commentary-type).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>「手本系」というのは、習字を目的として編まれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tehon-kei&apos; was made for the purpose of teaching penmanship.</e>
<cmt>「習字」の訳として用語集に登録済みの“calligraphy”は「書道」の定訳と思われますので、意味的に原文により近い“penmanship”としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tehon-kei&apos; was made for the purpose of teaching penmanship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tehon-kei&apos; was made for the purpose of teaching penmanship.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>大きい型に製本してあり、字は大きく、行書体が常例で、生の手本そのままである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bound in large size, its characters were big, usually written in gyosho-tai (semi-cursive style of writing) and handwritten.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bound in large size, its characters were big, usually written in gyosho-tai (semi-cursive style of writing) and handwritten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bound in large size, its characters were big, usually written in gyosho-tai (semi-cursive style of writing) and handwritten.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>江戸中期を過ぎると、句点・返り点・送り仮名、さらには振り仮名をほどこしたものも現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the mid Edo Period, some of Teikin Orai started to contain kuten (punctuating points), kaeriten (signs to indicate reading order), okurigana (hiragana to accompany kanji) and furigana (hiragana to show pronunciation) started to be seen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the mid Edo Period, some Teikin Orai containing kuten (punctuation marks), kaeriten (signs to indicate reading order), okurigana (hiragana to accompany kanji), and furigana (hiragana to show pronunciation) started to be seen.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the mid Edo period, some Teikin Orai containing kuten (punctuation marks), kaeriten (signs to indicate reading order), okurigana (hiragana to accompany kanji), and furigana (hiragana to show pronunciation) started to be seen.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>「読本系」は、文字の一つ一つの読みを学習させようとしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokuhon-kei&apos; (Reader-type) attempted to assist in learning to read every single letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokuhon-kei&apos; (Reader-type) attempted to assist in learning to read every single letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokuhon-kei&apos; attempted to assist in learning to read every single letter.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除し、クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>元禄の頃には、本文の右側に読み下しに必要なふりがな、左にはそれぞれの文字が持つ、本文以外の読みについてのふりがなを振ったものが現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Genroku era saw the appearance of those that contained two kinds of furigana; one was necessary for reading body texts and placed to their right, and the other to the left showed another way of reading them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Genroku era saw the appearance of those that contained two kinds of furigana; one was necessary for reading body texts and placed to their right, and the other to the left showed another way of reading them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period from 1688 to 1703 saw the appearance of those that contained two kinds of furigana; one was necessary for reading body texts and placed to their right, and the other to the left showed another way of reading them.</e>
<cmt>和暦を西暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>また、本文以外の巻首・巻末・頭書などに、様々な教材を載せたものが出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, various teaching materials were seen in the beginning and the end of a book as well as in the space above the body texts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, various teaching materials were seen at the beginning and the end of a book as well as in the space above the body texts.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, various teaching materials were seen at the beginning and the end of a book as well as in the space above the body texts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>例えば、生花心得・詩歌・小謡・文書様作法・商売往来・筆を取る方法・筆づかい・十二月異名など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Represented in some of these materials were: appreciation of the art of flower arrangement, poetry, small pieces of song, manners for writing, business know-hows, penmanship, brushwork, and synonyms for the names of the months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Represented in some of these materials were: appreciation of the art of flower arrangement, poetry, small pieces of song, manners for writing, business know-how, penmanship, brushwork, and synonyms for the names of the months.</e>
<cmt>singular</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Represented in some of these materials were: Appreciation of the art of flower arrangement, poetry, small pieces of song, manners for writing, business know-how, penmanship, brushwork, and synonyms for the names of the months.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>初歩教材総合教科書と形容したくなるような体裁をとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were well-formed enough to be referred to as &quot;integrated elementary textbooks.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were sufficiently organized to be referred to as &quot;integrated elementary textbooks.&quot;</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were sufficiently organized to be referred to as integrated elementary textbooks.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>「注釈本系」は、単語や短句、文意について、「注」の形で解説を試みたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushakubon-kei&apos; (Commentary-type) attempted to give a commentary on words, phrases and sentence meanings in the form of &apos;book notes.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushakubon-kei&apos; (Commentary-type) attempted to give a commentary on words, phrases and sentence meanings in the form of &apos;book notes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushakubon-kei&apos; attempted to give a commentary on words, phrases and sentence meanings in the form of &apos;book notes.&apos;</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除し、クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1834年『庭訓往来具注鈔』という本では、一通の手紙文を数段にわけ、段ごとに割注（漢字かな交じり文・総ふりがな付き）を挿入、最後に必ず「文意」の項を設け、この段全般に及ぶ意味を要約している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 1834 book &quot;Teikin Orai Guchusho,&quot; each letter was broken down into several paragraphs and each paragraph had a let-in note that contained both kanji and kana with all kanji accompanied by furigana, always closing with a section on &apos;sentence meaning&apos; that summarized the whole paragraph.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1834 book &quot;Teikin Orai Guchusho,&quot; each letter was broken down into several paragraphs and each paragraph had a let-in note that contained both kanji and kana with all kanji accompanied by furigana, always closing with a section on &apos;sentence meaning&apos; that summarized the whole paragraph.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1834, the book &quot;Teikin Orai Guchusho&quot; (Commentary of Teikin Orai), each letter was broken down into several paragraphs and each paragraph had a let-in note that contained both kanji and kana with all kanji accompanied by furigana, always closing with a section on &apos;sentence meaning&apos; that summarized the whole paragraph.</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>「絵抄系」は、挿絵で理解をはやめ正確にしようとしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Esho-kei&apos; (Illustrated Commentary-type) attempted to help get a faster and accurate grasp of its texts with the aid of illustrations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Esho-kei&apos; (Illustrated Commentary-type) attempted to help the student get a faster and accurate grasp of its texts with the aid of illustrations.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Esho-kei&apos; attempted to help the student get a faster and accurate grasp of its texts with the aid of illustrations.</e>
<cmt>前出補足を削除し、クォーテーションを半角にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1688年『庭訓往来図讃』では、頭書に挿絵を509葉用意、それぞれの挿絵に要語略解をも付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 1688 book &quot;Teikin Orai Zusan&quot; contained 509 illustrations above the sentences, each supplied with simple comments on keywords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 1688 book &quot;Teikin Orai Zusan&quot; contained 509 illustrations above the sentences, each supplied with simple comments on keywords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1688, the book &quot;Teikin Orai Zusan&quot; (Home Education Textbook, the illustrated edition) contained 509 illustrations above the sentences, each supplied with simple comments on keywords.</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、用語補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 踏蹟(id:51201), せいすいえいこ(id:169927), Penpen(id:18815), えすぱ(id:12144), Whym(id:184209), 水野白楓(id:22811), はるひ(id:59079), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>