<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>院宣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>院宣（いんぜん）とは、太上天皇からの命令を受けた院司が、奉書形式で発給する文書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inzen is a document issued in a format of hosho (a document for informing lower-rank people of the decision of upper people such as an emperor or shogun) by an Inshi (official of the In no cho, or Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) who has received orders from Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inzen is a document issued in a format of hosho (a document for informing lower-rank people of the decision of upper people such as an emperor or shogun) by an Inshi (official of the In no cho, or Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) who has received orders from Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Inzen&quot; is a document which an Inshi (official of the In no cho, or Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) issues in a format of hosho (a document informing a decision of the upper ranked personages such as an emperor or shogun) upon direct orders from Daijo Tenno (the Retired Emperor).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Inzen にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。Innocho の表記を用語集に合わせてIn no cho に修正しました。アポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>天皇の発する宣旨に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to an imperial decree issued by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is equivalent to an imperial decree issued by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is equivalent to an imperial decree issued by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>院庁下文よりも私的な形式。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a more personal form than an innocho kudashibumi (a letter issued by innocho, the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) does.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a more personal form than an innocho kudashibumi (a letter issued by innocho, the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office) does.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It takes a more personal format in comparison to that of an innocho kudashibumi (a letter issued by the In no cho, the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。innocho の表記に the を追記した上で用語集に合わせて the In no cho に修正しました。アポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>『法曹至要抄』によれば、養老律令詐偽律の解釈を巡る明法家の先例の学説として「太上天皇宣」の偽造は詔書と同一の罪に当たるとする説を挙げており早くから知られていた可能性があるが、院宣に関する記録の初見は延長 (日本)7年（927年）の宇多天皇が伊勢神宮に宣旨を下されたことを受けて神宮側がその指示を神郡に向けて発した「延長七年大神宮勘注」（『大日本史料』一之六）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Hososhiyo-sho, in a precedented theory of Myobo-ke (Myobo-ka) in the interpretation of Yoro-ritsuryo Sagi-ritsu, a theory saying that fabricating Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor) Zen is guilty of this same crime as fabricating Shosho (imperial edict, decree) was introduced and had been possibly known from early on; however, the record of the oldest inzen is seen in &quot;Encho Shichi-nen Daijingu Kanchu&quot; (&quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (the Historical Materials of Japan) ichi-no-roku) that was issued by Ise Jingu Shrine as instructions of Emperor Uda to Shingun (district wherein was a sanctuary enjoying certain privileges under an Imperial charter) as Emperor Uda issued an imperial decree to Ise Jingu Shrine in 927.</e>
<cmt>「一之六」は、章名、項名などを表しているのではないかと考えましたが、明確にならなかったため、「ichi-no-roku」と致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Hososhiyo-sho, in a precedented theory by Myobo-ke (Myobo-ka) in the interpretation of Yoro-ritsuryo Sagi-ritsu, the theory holds that fabricating Daijo Tenno (the retired Emperor) Zen is a crime of the same degree as fabricating Shosho (imperial edict, decree) and had been possibly known from early on; however, the oldest inzen record is seen in &quot;Encho Shichi-nen Daijingu Kanchu&quot; (&quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (the Historical Materials of Japan) ichi-no-roku) that was issued by Ise Jingu Shrine as instructions of Emperor Uda to Shingun (district wherein was a sanctuary enjoying certain privileges under an Imperial charter) as Emperor Uda issued an imperial decree to Ise Jingu Shrine in 927.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hososhiyo-sho&quot;, when the Myobo-ke (judicial officials) interpreted Yororitsuryo Sagi-ritsu (punitive clause regarding fabrication of official documents and government properties under the Yororitsuryo code) earlier, it was described that the fabrication of the Daijo Tenno Zen (a decree by the Retired Emperor) is a crime comparable to the fabrication of the Shosho (an imperial decree), which shows that the concept of inzen could have been in use early in the history. Nonetheless, the first record which mentions the term inzen is &quot;Encho Shichi-nen Daijingu Kanchu&quot;, taken from &quot;Dai Nihon Shiryo&quot; (the Historical Materials of Japan) Vol.1, no.6, which was a document that, upon receipt of an imperial decree from Emperor Uda in 927, Ise-jingu Shrine issued as the Emperor Uda&apos;s instructions to Shingun (a district designated as a sanctuary which enjoyed certain privileges under an Imperial charter).</e>
<cmt>明法家は(judicial officials)としました。一原文一訳文の例外対処。FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションおよびアポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。Ise Jingu Shrine を Ise-jingu Shrine に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>院宣の重要度は、天皇の宣旨と同等、またはそれ以上とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The importance of an inzen is said to be equivalent to or higher than an imperial decree issued by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The importance of an inzen is said to be equivalent to or higher than an imperial decree issued by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An inzen was considered as important as, or more important than, an imperial decree issued by the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代後期に院政が始まると、治天の君（院政を行う上皇）は、院宣や院庁下文を発給することで、自らの政治意思を明示・具現化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the system of Insei (rule by the retired Emperor) started at the late Heian period, Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power) clearly defined and incorporated his own political intention by issuing inzen and innocho kudashibumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the system of Insei (rule by the retired Emperor) started at the late Heian period, Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power) clearly defined and incorporated his own political intention by issuing inzen and innocho kudashibumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the system of Insei (rule by the Retired Emperor) was enforced in the late Heian period, Chiten no kimi (the Retired Emperor in power) used inzen and innocho kudashibumi to strongly express and achieve his political intentions.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>院庁下文が、詔勅や太政官符などの政府として最終決定意思を表示する文書と、同等の効力が認められていたのに対し、院宣は形式の面でも効力の面でも、簡易なものとして発給されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While an innocho kudashibumi had efficacy equivalent to a document in which the intention for final decision of the government including Shochoku (imperial edict) and Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), inzen was issued in a simpler format in either formality or efficacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While an innocho kudashibumi was effectively equivalent to a document containing the intention for a final decision by the government including Shochoku (imperial edict) and Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), inzen was issued in a simpler format for efficiency and formality purposes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While an innocho kudashibumi, such as Shochoku (imperial edict) and Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State), was a document that expressed the final decision of the government, an inzen was considered a much simpler document from the point of view of its format and efficacy.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>すなわち、政府の重要事項については院庁下文で対応し、より即効的または柔軟な対応が必要なときは院宣を発給していたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, an innocho kudashibumi was issued for important matters of the government, and an inzen, on the other hand, was issued when more quick-impact or more flexible measures were needed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, an innocho kudashibumi was issued for important matters of the government, and an inzen, on the other hand, was issued when more quick-impact or more flexible measures were needed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, while an innocho kudashibumi was issued for important matters of the government, an inzen was used when immediate and flexible actions are required.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), でここ(id:9565), Shimoxx(id:9332), 経済準学士(id:22656), Greenland4(id:114494), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>