<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鉄砲伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Introduction of firearms into Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Introduction of Firearms into Japan</e>
<cmt>Changed to capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Introduction of Firearms into Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鉄砲伝来（てっぽうでんらい）とは、15世紀にヨーロッパから東アジアへ火縄銃型の銃が伝わったこと、狭義には日本の種子島に伝来した事件を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Teppo Denrai&quot; (introduction of firearms) generally refers to the introduction of matchlock guns from Europe into East Asia in the 15th century, and in a more limited sense it means the introduction of matchlock guns into Tanegashima Island, Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Teppo Denrai&quot; (introduction of firearms) generally refers to the introduction of matchlock guns from Europe into East Asia in the 15th century, and in a more limited sense it means the introduction of matchlock guns into Tanegashima Island, Japan.</e>
<cmt>Changed font. Should &quot;Tanegashima Island&quot; be written &quot;Tanega-shima Island&quot; as per instructions? I have not changed it and left as is throughout the document</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Teppo Denrai&quot; (introduction of firearms) generally refers to the introduction of matchlock guns from Europe into East Asia in the 15th century, and in a more limited sense it means the introduction of matchlock guns into Tanegashima Island, Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鉄砲現物のほか、その製造技術や射撃法なども伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only actual guns but also manufacturing technology and shooting skills were introduced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only were actual guns introduced, but also manufacturing technology and shooting skills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only were actual guns introduced, but also manufacturing technology and shooting skills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>「鉄砲」とは日本においてはじめは火縄銃をさす言葉として使われ、後に小銃から大砲まで火器一般を意味する名称となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the term &quot;teppo&quot; was first used only for matchlock guns, later the term referred to general firearms including rifles and cannons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the term &quot;teppo&quot; was first used only for matchlock guns, the term later referred to general firearms including rifles and cannons.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, while the term &quot;teppo&quot; was first used only for matchlock guns, the term later referred to general firearms including rifles and cannons.</e>
<cmt>「日本において」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>種子島以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the introduction into Tanegashima Island</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the introduction into Tanegashima Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the introduction into Tanegashima Island</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>東アジアから東南アジアにおいて、15世紀には中国の明が海禁政策を行い、また日本の室町幕府との日明貿易（勘合貿易）が途絶した事などにより倭寇（後期倭寇）による私貿易、密貿易が活発になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Ming Dynasty in China strictly controlled overseas trade in East and South East Asia during the 15th century and the tally trade between the Muromachi shogunate and the Ming Dynasty had been disrupted, koki wako (the 16th-century wako pirate-traders) actively engaged in private and illicit trades.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the Ming Dynasty in China strictly controlled overseas trade in East and South East Asia during the 15th century and the tally trade between the Muromachi shogunate and the Ming Dynasty had been disrupted, &quot;koki wako&quot; (16th-century wako pirate-traders) actively engaged in private and illicit trades.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Ming Dynasty in China strictly controlled overseas trade in East and South East Asia during the 15th century and the tally trade between the Muromachi shogunate and the Ming Dynasty had been disrupted, wako (koki wako, or 16th-century wako pirate-traders) actively engaged in private and illicit trades.</e>
<cmt>wakoを補完しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本や琉球王国においても原始的な火器は使用されていて、火器は倭寇勢力等により日本へも持ち込まれていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Primitive firearms were already in use in Japan and the Kingdom of Ryukyu around that time and it is thought that wako was a major player who brought those firearms into Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Primitive firearms were already in use in Japan and the Kingdom of Ryukyu around this time and it is thought that &quot;wako&quot; were major players who brought these firearms into Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Primitive firearms were already in use in Japan and the Kingdom of Ryukyu around this time, and it is thought that wako was one of the major players who brought these firearms into Japan.</e>
<cmt>一部改変しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>鉄砲の伝来は、初期の火縄銃の形式が東南アジアの加圧式火鋏を持った鳥銃に似ている事や東南アジアにおいても先行して火縄銃が使われていた事などから、種子島への鉄砲伝来に代表されるようなヨーロッパ経由でなく倭寇などの密貿易によって東南アジア方面から持ち込まれたとする説がある（宇田川武久説）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the facts that the mechanism of early matchlock guns is similar to that of the choju (guns for bird hunting) of Southeast Asia with a pressurized serpentine arm and that use of matchlock guns in Southeast Asia preceded to Japan, some researchers (such as Takehisa UDAGAWA) argue that matchlock guns were introduced into Japan not via Europe, as typified by the introduction of firearms to Tanegashima Island, but through the illicit trades with Southeast Asia by wako.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the facts that the mechanism of early matchlock guns is similar to that of the choju (guns for bird hunting) of Southeast Asia with a pressurized serpentine arm and the use of matchlock guns in Southeast Asia preceded to use in Japan, some researchers (such as Takehisa UDAGAWA) argue that matchlock guns were introduced into Japan not via Europe, as typified by the introduction of firearms to Tanegashima Island, but through illicit trades with Southeast Asia by &quot;wako&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the facts that the mechanism of early matchlock guns is similar to that of the choju (guns for bird hunting) of Southeast Asia with a pressurized serpentine arm and the use of matchlock guns in Southeast Asia preceded to use in Japan, some researchers (such as Takehisa UDAGAWA) argue that matchlock guns were introduced into Japan not via Europe, as typified by the introduction of firearms to Tanegashima Island, but through illicit trades with Southeast Asia by wako.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし欧米や日本の研究者の中には、欧州の瞬発式メカが日本に伝えられて改良発展したものが、オランダによって日本から買い付けられて東南アジアに輸出され、それらが手本となって日本式の機構が東南アジアに広まったとする説をとる者も少なくなく、宇田川説を否定的にみる意見も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, other researchers in Japan, Europe and America doubt UDAGAWA&apos;s theory, pointing that instantaneous mechanism of European guns was first introduced to and improved in Japan and then Dutch purchased and exported Japanese guns to the Southeast Asia, resulting in the spread of the Japanese-style mechanism in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, other researchers in Japan, Europe and America doubt UDAGAWA&apos;s theory, pointing out that the instantaneous mechanism of European guns was first introduced to and improved in Japan and then Dutch purchased and exported Japanese guns to Southeast Asia, resulting in the spread of the Japanese-style mechanism in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, other researchers in Japan, Europe and America doubt UDAGAWA&apos;s theory, pointing out that the instantaneous mechanism of European guns was first introduced to and improved in Japan and then Dutch purchased and exported Japanese guns to Southeast Asia, resulting in the spread of the Japanese-style mechanism in Southeast Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>種子島への鉄砲伝来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Introduction of firearms into Tanegashima Island, Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Introduction of firearms into Tanegashima Island, Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Introduction of firearms into Tanegashima Island, Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>『鉄炮記』によれば、種子島への鉄砲伝来は天文 (元号)12年8月25日 (旧暦)（ユリウス暦1543年9月23日）の出来事で、大隅国（鹿児島県）種子島西之浦湾に漂着した中国船に乗っていた「五峰」と名乗る明の儒生が西村織部と筆談で通訳を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Teppoki&quot; (a history book on the introduction of guns), firearms were first brought to Tanegashima Island on October 3, 1543 by a Chinese ship tossed ashore on Nishinoura Bay of Tanegashima Island, Osumi Province (Kagoshima Prefecture) and a Confucian scholar from Ming on board, who identified himself Goho, worked as a translator for Oribe NISHIMURA by using written messages.</e>
<cmt>ユリウス暦の1543年9月23日はグレゴリオ暦1543年10月3日に相当。ここ以外ではユリウス暦は使用されていないので、あえてグレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Teppoki&quot; (a history book on the introduction of guns), firearms were first brought to Tanegashima Island on October 3, 1543 by a Chinese ship tossed ashore on Nishinoura Bay of Tanegashima Island, Osumi Province (Kagoshima Prefecture) and a Confucian scholar from Ming onboard, who identified himself as Goho, worked as a translator for Oribe NISHIMURA by using written messages.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Teppoki&quot; (a history book on the introduction of guns), firearms were first brought to Tanegashima Island on October 3, 1543 by a Chinese ship tossed ashore on Nishinoura Bay of Tanegashima Island, Osumi Province (Kagoshima Prefecture) and a Confucian scholar from Ming onboard, who identified himself as Goho, worked as a translator for Oribe NISHIMURA by using written messages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同乗していたポルトガル人（「牟良叔舎」、「喜利志多佗孟太」）が火縄銃を所持しており、鉄砲の実演を行い種子島島主である種子島恵時・種子島時尭親子がそのうち2挺を購入して研究を重ね、刀鍛冶の八板金兵衛に命じて複製を研究させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two Portuguese on board (probably Francisco Zeimot and Antonio da Motta) had matchlock guns and gave a demonstration for Masatoki TANEGASHIMA and his son Tokitaka TANEGASHIMA, who purchased two of them and ordered Kinbei YAITA, a swordsmith, to investigate and replicate them.</e>
<cmt>『「牟良叔舎」、「喜利志多佗孟太」』の部分は、当時のポルトガル語に音を当てようとしたものなので、漢字の音価ではなく、この名前が指していると推測されるポルトガル人の名前をそのまま記載した。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two Portuguese onboard (probably Francisco Zeimot and Antonio da Motta) had matchlock guns and gave a demonstration for Masatoki TANEGASHIMA and his son Tokitaka TANEGASHIMA, who purchased two of them and ordered Kinbei YAITA, a swordsmith, to investigate and replicate them.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two Portuguese onboard (probably Francisco Zeimot and Antonio da Motta) had matchlock guns and gave a demonstration for Masatoki TANEGASHIMA and his son Tokitaka TANEGASHIMA, who purchased two of them and ordered Kinbei YAITA, a swordsmith, to investigate and replicate them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その頃種子島に在島していた堺の橘屋又三郎と、紀州根来寺の僧津田算長が本土へ持ち帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matasaburo TACHIBANAYA of Sakai and Kazunaga TSUDA, a priest of Negoroji Temple, Kishu Province, who were at the island around this time, took home the guns and a matchlock gun was also presented to the Ashikaga shogunate around the same time, indicating that the technology of gun manufacturing was introduced into the mainland through several routes in a short period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matasaburo TACHIBANAYA of Sakai and Kazunaga TSUDA, a priest of Negoroji Temple, Kishu Province, who were at the island around this time, took the guns home. A matchlock gun was also presented to the Ashikaga shogunate around the same time, indicating that the technology of gun manufacturing was introduced into the mainland through several routes in a short period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matasaburo TACHIBANAYA of Sakai and Kazunaga TSUDA, a priest of Negoroji Temple, Kishu Province, who were at the island around this time, took the guns home.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>さらには足利将軍家にも献上されたことなどから、鉄砲製造技術は短期間のうちに複数のルートで本土に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A matchlock gun was also presented to the Ashikaga shogunate around the same time, indicating that the technology of gun manufacturing was introduced into the mainland through several routes in a short period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>やがて鉄砲鍛冶が成立し、戦場における新兵器として火器が導入され、日本の天下統一を左右することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then gunsmith industry was established and guns started to be used in the battlefield as a new weapon, even affecting the unification of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gunsmith industry was then established and guns started to be used in the battlefield as a new weapon, even affecting the unification of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gunsmith industry was then established and guns started to be used in the battlefield as a new weapon, even affecting the unification of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>室町時代以降も日本の武器製造技術は進歩し、その主要輸出先はオスマントルコであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese manufacturing technology of firearms continued to improve after the Muromachi period and Ottoman Turks was a major importer of Japanese firearms (After the establishment of the Tokugawa shogunate, export of arms was prohibited in Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese manufacturing technology of firearms continued to improve after the Muromachi period, and Ottoman Turks were a major importer of Japanese firearms. (After the establishment of the Tokugawa shogunate, export of arms was prohibited in Japan.)</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese manufacturing technology of firearms continued to improve after the Muromachi period, and Ottoman Turks were a major importer of Japanese firearms.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（後に徳川家康による覇権の成立後、日本は武器輸出を禁止した。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(After the establishment of the Tokugawa shogunate, export of arms was prohibited in Japan.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>伝来当初は猟銃としてであったがすぐに戦場で用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although right after the introduction the guns were used for hunting, soon they started to be used in battle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although right after the introduction the guns were used for hunting, soon they started to be used in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although right after the introduction the guns were used for hunting, soon they started to be used in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>当時の鉄砲はマッチロック式であり、火縄銃と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The guns of this time was matchlock type and called &quot;hinawaju (matchlock gun)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The guns of this time were matchlock type and called &quot;hinawaju&quot; (matchlock gun).</e>
<cmt>Wording and font.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The guns of this time were matchlock type and called hinawaju (matchlock gun).</e>
<cmt>引用符</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>やがて早合と呼ばれる弾と火薬を一体化させる工夫がなされ、すぐに装填できるよう改良された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then a technology called hayago (cartridge) was invented in which a bullet and gunpowder were set together to be loaded quickly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A technology called hayago (cartridge) was then invented in which a bullet and gunpowder were set together to be loaded quickly.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A technology called hayago (cartridge) was then invented in which a bullet and gunpowder were set together to be loaded quickly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>実戦での最初の使用は、薩摩国の島津氏家臣の伊集院忠朗による大隅国の加治木城攻めであるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the first use of guns in battle was seen in the attack on the Kajiki Castle of Osumi Province by Tadaaki IJUIN, a vassal of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the first use of guns in battle was seen in the attack on Kajiki-jo Castle in Osumi Province by Tadaaki IJUIN, a vassal of the Shimazu clan.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Corrected as per instructions.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the first use of guns in battle was seen in the attack on Kajiki-jo Castle in Osumi Province by Tadaaki IJUIN, a vassal of the Shimazu clan from Satsuma Province.</e>
<cmt>「薩摩国の」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>九州や中国地方の戦国大名から、やがて天下統一事業を推進していた尾張国の織田信長が1575年（天正3年）に武田氏との長篠の戦いをはじめとする戦で、鉄砲を有効活用したとされ、鉄砲が戦争における主力兵器として活用される軍事革命が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Use of guns spread from Kyushu and Chugoku region to the eastern part of Japan and Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province, who was promoting the unification of Japan, strategically used guns in battles including the Battle of Nagashino, opening the new era of military technology in which firearms became the main weapon in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The use of guns spread from the Kyushu and Chugoku regions to the eastern part of Japan, and Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province, who was promoting the unification of Japan, strategically used guns in battles including the Battle of Nagashino, opening the new era of military technology in which firearms became the main weapon in battle.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The use of guns spread from the Kyushu and Chugoku regions to the eastern part of Japan, and Nobunaga ODA of Owari Province, who was promoting the unification of Japan, strategically used guns in battles including the Battle of Nagashino in 1575, opening the new era of military technology in which firearms became the main weapon in battle.</e>
<cmt>原文に「1575年（天正3年）」を補完し、併せて英訳も修正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>『鉄炮記』について・その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About &quot;Teppoki&quot;/others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Teppoki&quot;/Others</e>
<cmt>Wording and font.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Teppoki&quot;/Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>『鉄炮記』は鉄砲伝来を記す唯一資料であるが、江戸時代の慶長年間（1606年）に種子島氏が鉄砲伝来を記念して記させたもので、歴史学においては、その記述を無条件に信用するわけにはいかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although &quot;Teppoki&quot; is the only historical material recording the いntroduction of firearms into Japan, we should be careful of reading it as a historical record because it was compiled by the Tanegashima Clan in 1606 to commemorate the introduction of firearms into Tanegashima Island.</e>
<cmt>慶長年間は1596年から1615年まで。この間に記されたものなのか、1606年という特定の年に記されたものなのかが不明だが、ここでは後者に従います。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although &quot;Teppoki&quot; is the only historical material recording the ntroduction of firearms into Japan, we should be careful of reading it as a historical record because it was compiled by the Tanegashima clan in 1606 to commemorate the introduction of firearms into Tanegashima Island.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although &quot;Teppoki&quot; is the only historical material recording the introduction of firearms into Japan, we should be careful of reading it as a historical record because it was compiled by the Tanegashima clan in Keicho era (1606) to commemorate the introduction of firearms into Tanegashima Island.</e>
<cmt>ntroduction→introduction「慶長年間」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>『鉄炮記』には「天文 (元号)癸卯」（1543年）と記されているが、一方でポルトガル側の史料には鉄砲の伝来を記さないものや、イエズス会の『日本教会史』には1542年（天文11年）の出来事、フェルナン・メンデス・ピントの『東洋遍歴記』には1545年（天文14年）の出来事であると記されているなど年代には諸説が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While &quot;Teppoki&quot; records firearms were introduced into Japan in 1543, some materials from Portuguese side do not even cover the event and &quot;Nihon Kyokai Shi&quot; (História Da Igreja Do Japão) compiled by the Society of Jesus mentions that it was in 1542 and the &quot;Toyo Henreki Ki&quot; (Peregrinacao) by Fernão Mendes Pinto describes that it was in 1545.</e>
<cmt>originalの年代が2か所抜けている。Wikipediaをもとに訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While &quot;Teppoki&quot; records firearms that were introduced into Japan in 1543, some materials from the Portuguese side do not even cover the event and &quot;Nihon Kyokai Shi&quot; (História Da Igreja Do Japão) compiled by the Society of Jesus mentions that it was in 1542 and the &quot;Toyo Henreki Ki&quot; (Peregrinacao) by Fernão Mendes Pinto states that it was in 1545.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While &quot;Teppoki&quot; records firearms that were introduced into Japan in 1543, several theories about the date exist including some materials from the Portuguese side do not even cover the event and &quot;Nihon Kyokai Shi&quot; (História Da Igreja Do Japão) compiled by the Society of Jesus mentions that it was in 1542 and the &quot;Toyo Henreki Ki&quot; (Peregrinacao) by Fernão Mendes Pinto states that it was in 1545.</e>
<cmt>「年代には諸説が存在する」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、『鉄炮記』に「五峰」と記されている人物は、日本の平戸市や五島列島を拠点に活動していた倭寇の頭領である王直の号と同じであり、またポルトガル史料にはジャンク (船)であったと記されていることなどから同一人物であるとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The man called Goho in &quot;Teppoki&quot; and Ochoku, the leader of wako based on today&apos;s Hirado City and the Goto Islands, are considered to be the same person because the name &quot;Goho&quot; coincides with the byname of Ochoku and, according to the record in Portugal, the vessel Goho was on board was a junk ship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The man called Goho in &quot;Teppoki&quot;, along with Ochoku, the leader of &quot;wako&quot; based in present-day Hirado City and the Goto Islands, are considered to be the same person because the name &quot;Goho&quot; coincides with the byname of Ochoku and, according to the record in Portugal, the vessel Goho was on board was a junk ship.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The man called &apos;Goho&apos; in &quot;Teppoki&quot; is considered to be the same person as Ochoku who was the leader of wako based on today&apos;s Hirado City and the Goto Islands, because Goho coincides with the byname of Ochoku and the record in Portugal shows the ship was a junk one.</e>
<cmt>改変しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>種子島氏に伝わる記録には、ポルトガル人により持ち込まれた鉄砲は明治の西南戦争の際に消失したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a record of the Tanegashima clan, the guns brought by Portuguese were lost during the Seinan War in Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a record of the Tanegashima clan, the guns brought by the Portuguese were lost during the Seinan War in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a record of the Tanegashima clan, the guns brought by the Portuguese were lost during the Seinan War in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、国産第1号と伝わる鉄砲が存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They also have a gun handed down as the first domestic gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They also have a gun handed down as the first domestic gun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They also have a gun handed down as the first domestic gun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="25">
<j>鉄砲の記述</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical description about guns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical Description of Guns</e>
<cmt>Ok</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Description of Guns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>『北条五代記』に、関八州に鉄炮はじまる事、という記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot; describes that the production of guns started from the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot; states that the production of guns started from the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot; states that the production of guns started from the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>ここでは、1510年（永正7年）に唐（中国）から渡来したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also mentions that guns were introduced from China in 1510.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also mentions that guns were introduced from China in 1510.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also mentions that guns were introduced from China in 1510.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="28">
<j>見しは昔、相州小田原に玉瀧坊と云て年よりたる山伏有。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Long time ago there was an old yamabushi (a mountain priest) named Gyokuryubo in Odawara of Soshu Province.</e>
<cmt>玉瀧坊が北条五代記の作者である若き三浦浄心に語っているという設定。背景がわからなければ、この後の人物関係がわからない可能性があります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A long time ago there was an old yamabushi (mountain priest) named Gyokuryubo in Odawara, Soshu Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A long time ago there was an old yamabushi (mountain priest) named Gyokuryubo in Odawara, Soshu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>愚老若き頃、其山臥物　語せられしは、我関東より毎年大峯へのぼる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When I was young, the yamabushi said to me &quot;I used to visit the Mount Omine every year&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When I was young, the yamabushi said to me &quot;I used to visit Mount Omine every year&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Font</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When I was young, the yamabushi said to me &quot;I used to visit Mount Omine from Kanto every year&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「関東」よりを訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>享禄はじまる年、和泉の堺へ下りしに、あらけなく鳴物の声する、是は何事ぞやととへば、鉄炮と云物、唐国より永正七年に初て渡りたると云て、目当てと　うつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;During my visit to Sakai, Izumi Province around the beginning of Kyoroku era, surprised by a huge sound, I asked a person what happened and he said this was teppo (gun) which was first introduced from china in 1510 and then he showed me how to shoot it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>最初に鉄砲を撃った人物、鉄砲について説明してくれた人物、撃って見せてくれた人物が同一人物かどうか、誰だったのかが文中からは不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;During my visit to Sakai, Izumi Province around the beginning of the Kyoroku era, surprised by a huge sound, I asked a person what happened and he said this was &quot;teppo&quot; (gun) which was first introduced from China in 1510. He then showed me how to shoot it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording and font.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;During my visit to Sakai, Izumi Province around the beginning of the Kyoroku era, surprised by a huge sound, I asked a person what happened and he said this was &quot;teppo&quot; (gun) which was first introduced from China in 1510. He then showed me how to shoot it.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>我是を見、扨も不思議奇特　成物かなとおもひ、此鉄炮を一挺買て、関東へ持て下り、屋形氏綱公へ進上す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;I was so surprised and impressed by the teppo that I purchased one, and then took it back to the Kanto region and presented to our lord, Ujitsuna HOJO.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;I was so surprised and impressed by the &quot;teppo&quot; that I purchased one, and then took it back to the Kanto region and presented it to our lord, Ujitsuna HOJO.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording and font.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;I was so surprised and impressed by the &quot;teppo&quot; that I purchased one, and then took it back to the Kanto region and presented it to our lord, Ujitsuna HOJO.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>（中略）氏康時代、堺より国康といふ鉄炮張りの名人をよび下し給ひぬ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">*snip* &quot;During the reign of Ujiyasu, he invited a master gunsmith named Kuniyasu from Sakai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Omission) &quot;During the reign of Ujiyasu, he invited a master gunsmith named Kuniyasu from Sakai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Wording and font.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Omission) &quot;During the reign of Ujiyasu, he invited a master gunsmith named Kuniyasu from Sakai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>扨又根来法師に、杉房・二王坊・岸和田などといふ者下りて、関東をかけまはつて鉄炮ををしへしが、今見れば人毎に持し、と申されし</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Priests of Negoroji Temple such as Sugibo, Niobo, and Kishiwada traveled around the Kanto region to teach gun manufacturing but today everyone has a gun&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「今見れば人毎に持し、と申されし」の部分の意味がわからず。「今となっては全員が鉄砲を持っている」の意味で訳出したが、「申され」たのが誰なのかが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Priests of Negoro-ji Temple such as Sugibo, Niobo, and Kishiwada traveled around the Kanto region to teach gun manufacturing but today everyone has a gun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Correct as per instructions.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Priests of Negoro-ji Temple such as Sugibo, Niobo, and Kishiwada traveled around the Kanto region to teach gun manufacturing but today everyone has a gun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>大久保忠教の『三河物語』では、松平清康が、熊谷が城へ押し寄せた際に、四方鉄砲を打ち込むと記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadataka OKUBO says in &quot;Mikawa Monogatari&quot; that Kiyoyasu Matsudaira shot guns all the direction when Sanenaga KUMAGAI&apos;s force surged in the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadataka OKUBO says in &quot;Mikawa Monogatari&quot; that Kiyoyasu MATSUDAIRA shot guns in all directions when Sanenaga KUMAGAI&apos;s force surged the castle.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadataka OKUBO says in &quot;Mikawa Monogatari&quot; that Kiyoyasu MATSUDAIRA shot guns from all directions when Sanenaga KUMAGAI&apos;s force surged the castle.</e>
<cmt>in→from</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1530年（享禄3年）のこととされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought to be in 1530.</e>
<cmt>originalの年代が抜けているので、Wikipediaをもとに補完しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to be in 1530.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to be in 1530.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また、今川殿の名代として、北条早雲が松平方の西三河の岩津城を攻撃した際に、四方鉄砲を放つとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it mentions that Soun HOJO shot guns all the directions when he invaded Matsudaira&apos;s Iwadu-jo Castle of West Mikawa Province, while the publisher comments that this battle was in 1506 and guns could not have been used at this time, supporting &quot;Teppoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>出版社の～の下りは日本語が不自然。出版社とは何を指すのかが不明。また、originalの年代が抜けているのでWikipediaより補完。「四方鉄砲を放つとある」の後は読点になっているが、句点ダと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also mentions that Soun HOJO shot guns in all directions when he invaded Matsudaira&apos;s Iwadu-jo Castle in West Mikawa Province, while the publisher comments that this battle was in 1506 and guns could not have been used at this time, supporting &quot;Teppoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also mentions that Soun HOJO shot guns from all directions when he invaded Matsudaira&apos;s Iwazu-jo Castle in West Mikawa Province as a representative of Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処Iwadu-jo→Iwazu-jo「今川殿の名代として」を訳出しました</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>出版社の欄外の解説には、この役は、1506年（永正3年）のことで、鉄砲はこのときないとして、『鉄炮記』の記述を支持している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The publisher comments that this battle was in 1506 and guns could not have been used at this time, supporting &quot;Teppoki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="38">
<j>鉄砲伝来諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various theories on the Introduction of firearms into Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Theories on the Introduction of Firearms into Japan</e>
<cmt>Changed to capital letters.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Theories on the Introduction of Firearms into Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>『中古治亂記』には、1501年（文亀元年）に、南蛮国から伝来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chuko Chiranki&quot; mentions that guns were introduce into Japan in 1501 from Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>『中古治亂記』の読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chuko Chiranki&quot; mentions that guns were introduce into Japan in 1501 from Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>Font. Please check the way of reading 中古治亂記.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Chuko Chiranki&quot; mentions that guns were introduced into Japan in 1501 from Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>『中古治亂記』の読み方不明でしたintroduce→introduced</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="40">
<j>『北條五代記』、『甲陽軍鑑』、『重編応仁記』では、1510年（永正7年）に伝来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot;, &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; and &quot;Juhen Oninki&quot;, guns were first brought to Japan in 1510.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot;, &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; and &quot;Juhen Oninki&quot;, guns were first brought to Japan in 1510.</e>
<cmt>Font</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hojo Godaiki&quot;, &quot;Koyo Gunkan&quot; and &quot;Juhen Oninki&quot;, guns were first brought to Japan in 1510.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="41">
<j>『國友鐵砲記』には、1501年（文亀元年）、1510年（永正7年）、1539年（天文8年）、の3回に渡り、南蛮から伝来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kunitomo Teppoki&quot; describes that guns were introduced in three times in 1501, 1510 and 1539 from Western Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kunitomo Teppoki&quot; states that guns were introduced three times, in 1501, 1510 and 1539 from Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kunitomo Teppoki&quot; states that guns were introduced three times, in 1501, 1510 and 1539 from Western Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="42">
<j>『國友鐵砲鍛冶由緒書』、『國友紀行』には1544年（天文13年）に伝来。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kunitomo Teppo Kaji Yuishosho&quot; and &quot;Kunitomo Kiko&quot; mention that the Introduction of guns was in 1544.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kunitomo Teppo Kaji Yuishosho&quot; and &quot;Kunitomo Kiko&quot; mention that the introduction of guns into Japan was in 1544.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kunitomo Teppo Kaji Yuishosho&quot; and &quot;Kunitomo Kiko&quot; mention that the introduction of guns into Japan was in 1544.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="43">
<j>と諸説あり、鉄砲記の伝来年以前とするものもあり、はっきりしない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As we mentioned above, there are various theories about the time of the introduction of guns into Japan and some records say it was before the introduction into the Tanegashima.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned above, there are various theories about the time of the introduction of guns into Japan, and some records say it was before the introduction into Tanegashima Island.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned above, there are various theories about the time of the introduction of guns into Japan such as some records saying it was before the introduction into Tanegashima Island, thus the precise time is not clear.</e>
<cmt>一部改変しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Izayohi(id:13095), Straysheep(id:42448), 水田(id:32389), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Aityanlove(id:203908), K66星雲(id:16609), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), Kawai(id:5634), Himazin(id:22034), Clara(id:10579), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 寒漁夫(id:99134), Hiruandon(id:427), でここ(id:9565), Tsk(id:1153), Yukichin(id:725), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Yosemite(id:5808), BBB(id:112), Chev(id:35857), Hotsuregua(id:99069), Mylovelove(id:196147), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>