<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>糸割符</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Itowappu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Itowappu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Itowappu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>糸割符（いとわっぷ）とは、江戸時代の日本における生糸輸入の方式である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Itowappu (yarn guild) was the procedure for the importation of raw silk thread during Japan&apos;s Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Itowappu is a system of importing raw silk threads in Japan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Itowappu is a system of importing raw silk threads in Japan during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸幕府が特定の商人集団（糸割符仲間）に独占的輸入権と国内商人への独占的卸売権を与えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the Edo Bakufu administration which gave this specific merchant group [Itowappu nakama (the thread tally union)] &apos;monopolistic importing rights&apos; and &apos;the monopolistic whole sale rights to merchants inside the nation.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The merchants who imported raw silk threads in this system were called itowappa nakama (guild of raw silk thread importers) and it was the Edo Shogunate that gave this specific group of Japanese merchants called itowappu nakama the right to monopolize for buying raw silk threads from foreign merchants and the right to monopolize for selling the imported raw silk threads by wholesale to the domestic merchants.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The merchants who imported raw silk threads in this system were called itowappa nakama (guild of raw silk thread importers) and it was the Edo Shogunate that gave this specific group of Japanese merchants called itowappu nakama the right to monopolize for buying raw silk threads from foreign merchants and the right to monopolize for selling the imported raw silk threads by wholesale to the domestic merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代初期、日本において最も重要な輸入品は、中国産の生糸（白糸）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the most important goods of import to Japan were the Chinese raw silk threads (white threads).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, the most important goods of import to Japan were the Chinese raw silk threads (white threads).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the most important goods of import to Japan were the Chinese raw silk threads (white threads).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>だが、生糸の輸入に関し外国商人が値段決定の主導権を有して利益を独占していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for importation of these same raw silk threads, foreign merchants took the initiative in pricing decisions and monopolized the profits.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, at that time foreign merchants had the initiative in pricing decisions in importing raw silk threads and they monopolized the profits.</e>
<cmt>「same」にあたる単語が原文にありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, at that time foreign merchants had the initiative in pricing decisions in importing raw silk threads and they monopolized the profits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、これを抑える必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, Japan needed to restrain this foreign merchant practice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Edo Shogunate needed to restrain these activities conducted by foreign merchants.</e>
<cmt>単数になっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Edo Shogunate needed to restrain these activities conducted by foreign merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>一方、外国商人側も文禄・慶長の役の失敗や関ヶ原の戦いの影響によって生じた日本の国内経済の混乱による販売不振に悩まされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the foreign merchant&apos;s side had suffered from sales slumps due to Japanese financial issues, which were directly related to failures in the Bunroku-Keicho War and the effects from the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the foreign merchants&apos; side also had suffered from sales slumps owing to the economic chaos in Japan which resulted from Japan&apos;s failure in the Bunroku-Keicho War and the effects of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>「外国商人」が単数になっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the foreign merchants&apos; side also had suffered from sales slumps owing to the economic chaos in Japan which resulted from Japan&apos;s failure in the Bunroku-Keicho War and the effects of the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>そこで幕府は1604年（慶長9年）、御用商人茶屋四郎次郎を主導者として京都・堺市・長崎の特定商人に糸割符仲間をつくらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of these circumstances, in &apos;1604&apos;, the Bakufu administration gave main leadership to the Shirojiro CHAYA, a goyo-shonin (chartered merchants); this was for the formation of the Itowappu nakama (the thread tally union) by a specific group of merchants in the Kyoto, Sakai, and Nagasaki regions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereupon, in 1604 the Edo Shogunate established itowappu system by having selected merchants from Kyoo, Sakai, and Nagasaki form itowappu nakama (guild of raw silk threads importers); in forming the itowappu nakama, the Edo Shogunate made Shirojiro CHAYA, the government contractor, the leader.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の「1604年」にはカギ括弧が付いていません。 2. Shirojiro CHAYAの前に「the」は要りません。 3. 「茶屋四郎次郎」は単数です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereupon, in 1604 the Edo Shogunate established itowappu system by having selected merchants from Kyoo, Sakai, and Nagasaki form itowappu nakama (guild of raw silk threads importers); in forming the itowappu nakama, the Edo Shogunate made Shirojiro CHAYA, the government contractor, the leader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その糸割符仲間に輸入生糸の価格決定と一括購入を許し、それを個々の商人に分配させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was at this point when the Edo Bbakufu administration permitted the Itowappu nakama to set prices on the importation of raw silk threads, and bulk purchases; then, individual merchants of the Itowappu nakama were permitted to distribute those same threads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Shogunate allowed the member merchants of the itowappu nakama to decide the prices of the imported raw silk threads and to buy in bulk and made them distribute the imported raw silk threads to individual merchants.</e>
<cmt>「same」という訳語を使う必然性がありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Shogunate allowed the member merchants of the itowappu nakama to decide the prices of the imported raw silk threads and to buy in bulk and made them distribute the imported raw silk threads to individual merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当初3ヶ所であったが、後に1631年（寛永8年）に江戸・大阪を加え5ヵ所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Itowappu organization was first established in three locations, later the two locations of Edo and Osaka were added in &apos;1631&apos;; so, the total number of locations within the Itowappu organization increased to five.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The itowappu nakama (guild of raw silk threads importers) was located in three places at first, but in 1631 Edo and Osaka were added that total number of itowappu nakama became five.</e>
<cmt>1. この文の主語は「糸割符仲間」です。 2. 「1631年」にカギ括弧はついていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The itowappu nakama (guild of raw silk threads importers) was located in three places at first, but in 1631 Edo and Osaka were added that total number of itowappu nakama became five.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当初はポルトガル商人だけであったが、1633年（寛永10年）に中国（明→清）商人、1635年（寛永12年）にはオランダ商人にも適用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning this procedure only applied to the merchants of Portugal, it was then later applied to the Chinese (Ming dynasty to Qing dynasty) merchants in &apos;1633&apos;, and then applied to the Dutch merchants in &apos;1635&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first the foreign merchants the itowappu nakama negotiated were Portuguese merchants only, but in 1633 Chinese merchants (Ming Dynasty to Qing Dynasty) and in 1635 Dutch merchants came to export raw silk threads under the itowappu system.</e>
<cmt>「1633年」と「1635年」にはカギ括弧が付いていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first the foreign merchants the itowappu nakama negotiated were Portuguese merchants only, but in 1633 Chinese merchants (Ming Dynasty to Qing Dynasty) and in 1635 Dutch merchants came to export raw silk threads under the itowappu system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、1641年（寛永18年）には貿易港としての地位を失った代償として平戸も加えられて6ヶ所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, in &apos;1641&apos; Hirado was allowed to join the Itowappu organization in return for vacated their position as a port of trade; so, the total numbers of Itowappu organizations expanded to six locations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, in 1641 Hirado was allowed to become the member of the itowappu nakama in return for vacating their position as a port of trade; so, the total numbers of Itowappu nakama expanded to six locations.</e>
<cmt>1. 「1641年」にはカギ括弧が付いていません。 2. 「前置詞は名詞またはその相当語句の前に置かれます。」（「詳解英文法辞典」、開拓社）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, in 1641 Hirado was allowed to become the member of the itowappu nakama in return for vacating their position as a port of trade; so, the total numbers of Itowappu nakama expanded to six locations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後には博多などの平戸以外の九州諸都市にも配分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Itowappu organization expanded to Hakata and other cities of the Kyushu region, other than Hirado.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, apart from Hirado, itowappu nakama came to be placed in various cities in Kyushu including Hakata.</e>
<cmt>主語は「糸割府仲間」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, apart from Hirado, itowappu nakama came to be placed in various cities in Kyushu including Hakata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これらは、従来の5ヶ所から分離され、「分国配分」と呼ばれる規定外の枠組みとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These places were considered separate from the previously established five; and so, were treated as outside the provisional framework and referred to as &quot;Bunkoku haibun.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Itowappu nakama (guild of raw silk threads importers) were considered separate from the previously established five; accordingly they were treated as outside the established framework and this treatment was called &apos;bunkoku haibun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「provisional」よりも「established」のほうがふさわしいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Itowappu nakama (guild of raw silk threads importers) were considered separate from the previously established five; accordingly they were treated as outside the established framework and this treatment was called &apos;bunkoku haibun.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>糸割符に参加できた都市はいずれも天領都市であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those cities which were able to participate in the Itowappu were all tenryo (a shogunal demesne).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those cities which were able to participate in the Itowappu were all tenryo (a shogunal demesne).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those cities which were able to participate in the Itowappu were all tenryo (a shogunal demesne).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>唯一の例外であった平戸藩にある平戸の場合も同藩に莫大な収入を与え続けていたオランダとの貿易の権利を幕府が剥奪した代償であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only exception in this was Hirado of the Hirado Domain, but it was a trade off in compensation for the Edo Bakuf&apos;s seizing of their trading rights to the Netherlands, which provided enormous revenue to the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only exception in this was Hirado of the Hirado Domain, but it was a trade off in compensation for the Edo Bakuf&apos;s seizing of their trading rights to the Netherlands, which provided enormous revenue to the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only exception in this was Hirado of the Hirado Domain, but it was a trade off in compensation for the Edo Bakuf&apos;s seizing of their trading rights to the Netherlands, which provided enormous revenue to the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その代償としては余りに安い対価であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The effect of this inequitable financial consideration was a despicable loss of value to the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The effect of this inequitable financial consideration was a despicable loss of value to the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The effect of this inequitable financial consideration was a despicable loss of value to the Hirado Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これは幕府とその影響下にある商人による貿易利益の独占を図ったものであるとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is apparent in practice, the Itowappu system under the Edo Bakufu, through merchant influence; there was an attempt to monopolize the trading profits for themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be said that the Shogunate planned to monopolize the profit gained by trading of raw silk threads by themselves and the merchants under their influence through the Itowappu system.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be said that the Shogunate planned to monopolize the profit gained by trading of raw silk threads by themselves and the merchants under their influence through the Itowappu system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>1655年（明暦元年）中国商人の抵抗（この背景には鄭成功がいたと言われている）を受け糸割符仲間は解散し、市法売買となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;1655&apos;, Itowappu nakama was dissolved because of Chinese merchant protest [It was said that there was Seiko TEI (&quot;Zheng Chenggong&quot; in Chinese) in this protest background.] and was replaced with market regulated trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1655 Itowappu nakama was dissolved owing to the protest the Shogunate received from the Chinese merchants; (it is said that there existed Seiko TEI [Zheng Chenggon]) in the background of this protest; afterwards, the Shogunate controlled the trade of raw silk threads by trade control called &apos;shibo baibai&apos; in which appraisers selected from the merchants from the above mentioned 5 cities appraised the goods brought by foreign merchants and trade was executed with the set price based on those appraisals.</e>
<cmt>1. 原文の1655には「」が付いていません。2, 正確性に問題があります。「市法売買」の定義については以下のウェブサイトを参考にして訳しました： http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/%E9%95%B7%E5%B4%8E%E8%B2%BF%E6%98%93/</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1655 Itowappu nakama was dissolved owing to the protest the Shogunate received from the Chinese merchants; (it is said that there existed Seiko TEI [Zheng Chenggon]) in the background of this protest; afterwards, the Shogunate controlled the trade of raw silk threads by trade control called &apos;shibo baibai&apos; in which appraisers selected from the merchants from the above mentioned 5 cities appraised the goods brought by foreign merchants and trade was executed with the set price based on those appraisals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1685年（貞享2年）に復活（ただし、平戸以下の分国配分は復活させず）されて幕末まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &apos;685&apos; the Itowappu system was revived (But the &quot;bunkoku haibun&quot; including the Hirada was not revived.) and continued to operate until the end of the Edo Bakufu period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1685, the Itowappu system was revived and the merchants under this system existed until the end of the Edo period; but the Itowappu nakama having the treatment of bunkoku habibun (outside the established framework) located in Hirado, Hakata and other cities in the Kyushu region were excluded from this revival.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1685, the Itowappu system was revived and the merchants under this system existed until the end of the Edo period; but the Itowappu nakama having the treatment of bunkoku habibun (outside the established framework) located in Hirado, Hakata and other cities in the Kyushu region were excluded from this revival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>が、日本国内における生糸の生産が増加し、輸入生糸の重要性（新しい糸割符制度は日本国内産生糸を保護と生糸の輸入制限の意図を兼ね備えていた）が低下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, raw silk thread production in Japan was increased, and the importance (A new Itowappu system was establishment, aiming to protect domestic raw silk thread production in Japan and to limit the importing of raw silk thread.) of raw silk thread decreased proportionally.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the production of raw silk threads increased in Japan; therefore, the importance of importing raw silk threads decreased; (the function of the new itowappu system included to protect the raw silk threads made in Japan as well as to limit the amount of raw silk threads to be imported to Japan.)</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the production of raw silk threads increased in Japan; therefore, the importance of importing raw silk threads decreased; (the function of the new itowappu system included to protect the raw silk threads made in Japan as well as to limit the amount of raw silk threads to be imported to Japan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そのことから次第に有名無実化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the newly established Itowappu system gradually came to exist in name only.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the Itowappu system gradually came to exist only in name.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があったので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the Itowappu system gradually came to exist only in name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nerimaman(id:61206), Straysheep(id:42448), Ispar(id:66258), ZassouTori(id:136771), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), ネッツ(id:150295), 水野白楓(id:22811), Hatsune(id:26654), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>