<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大和時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamato Period</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamato Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大和時代（やまとじだい）は、日本の歴史の時代区分の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato period (Yamamato jidai) is one of the period divisions in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamato Period is a period in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamato Period is a period in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的には4世紀頃から6世紀頃までを指すが、時に飛鳥時代（6世紀後半 - 7世紀）をも含め、弥生時代の後、奈良時代の前をいうこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, it indicates the period from about 4 century to about 6 century, but sometimes it refers to the period including the Asuka period (latter half of 6 century to 7 century), after Yayoi period and before Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, this term refers to a period of Japanese history lasting from the 4th century to the 6th century, but it can sometimes refer to a period lasting from after the Yayoi Period to just before the Nara Period, and includes the Asuka Period, which lasted until the beginning of the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>Added for clarity, grammar, punctuation, word order. End of Asuka Period altered to fit that in article 12979_飛鳥時代</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, this term refers to a period of Japanese history lasting from the 4th century to the 6th century, but it can sometimes refer to a period lasting from after the Yayoi Period to just before the Nara Period, including the Asuka Period (from the latter half of the 6 century to the 7 century).</e>
<cmt>飛鳥時代の時代区分は6世紀末から7世紀前半とするのが普通ですので、変更しないほうがいいように思われます。また、「飛鳥時代も含めた一時期」という限定ですので、左記の通りに致しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>但し、近年では時代が重なる古墳時代の方が一般的となり、余り使われなくなった時代区分でもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in recent years, this period division has not been used so often and the designation &quot; Kofun period &quot;, which coincides with Yamato period, has come to be used generally (Kofun means ancient burial mounds).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, however, this term has become used less often, and the term &quot;Kofun Period&quot;, which coincides with the Yamato Period, is now commonly used (kofun is the Japanese word for ancient burial mounds).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation, changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, however, this term has become used less often, and the term &quot;Kofun Period&quot;, which coincides with the Yamato Period, is now commonly used (kofun is the Japanese word for ancient burial mounds).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ヤマト王権による支配が強まり、壮大な古墳（前方後円墳・円墳）が盛んに作られ、古代国家の基礎が整えられた時期にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period corresponds to the one, in which the control by Yamato royal authority grew strong, grand burial mounds (burial mounds, square at one end and rounded at the other, and round burial mounds), were frequently built and the base of ancient state was settled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period is marked by a strengthening of Yamato royal authority and control, the frequent construction of grand burial mounds (round burial mounds, and those square at one end and rounded at the other), and the settlement of the basis of the ancient Japanese state.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period is marked by a strengthening of Yamato royal authority and control, the frequent construction of grand burial mounds (round burial mounds, and those square at one end and rounded at the other), and the settlement of the basis of the ancient Japanese state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>前期は大伴氏・物部氏・蘇我氏の各豪族が先後して実権を握っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first half term of Yamato period, the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan and the Soga clan paralleled each other, and held real power respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first half of the Yamato Period, the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan and the Soga clan held real power at different times.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first half of the Yamato Period, the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan and the Soga clan held real power at different times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、聖徳太子の法律(十七条憲法)・官制改革(冠位十二階)を経て、大化の改新（645年）後、天皇中心の政治へ変換していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But through the Prince Shotoku&apos;s law (the Seventeen Article of Constitution in the Asuka period) and government organization reform (the system of twelve courtly ranks), after the Taika Reform in 645, the political system shifted to the emperor-centered system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But through a law introduced by Prince Shotoku (the Seventeen Article Constitution of the Asuka Period) and government organizational reform (the system of twelve courtly ranks), after the Taika Reform of 645 the political system shifted to an emperor-centered system.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But through a law introduced by Prince Shotoku (the Seventeen Article Constitution of the Asuka Period) and government organizational reform (the system of twelve courtly ranks), after the Taika Reform of 645 the political system shifted to an emperor-centered system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>朝廷はそれまでの氏姓制度を改め、公地公民制や統一的税制（租庸調制など）を施行し、地方行政機構を改組して中央集権化するなど、律令制の導入を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court made efforts to introduce the system of centralized government based on the Ritsu Ryo codes through reforming the system of clans and hereditary titles till that time, enforcing the ownership of all lands and serfs by the emperor and uniform tax system (tax system in produce and labor, etc.), centralizing government power and so on</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court made efforts to introduce a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo codes by reforming the system of clans and hereditary titles, enforcing the ownership of all lands and serfs by the emperor, and introducing a uniform tax system based on production and labor.</e>
<cmt>Repetition removed, grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court made efforts to introduce a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo codes by reforming the system of clans and hereditary titles, enforcing the ownership of all lands and serfs by the emperor, and introducing a uniform tax system (taxes in kind or service).</e>
<cmt>租庸調の定訳はtaxes in kind or serviceのようですので、戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>また、6世紀前半には仏教が朝鮮半島より伝来し(日本の仏教の項を参照)、さらに遣隋使・遣唐使の派遣もあって、農業・鍛鉄・建築など多方面にわたって技術が発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Buddhism was introduced into Japan from the Korea Peninsula in the first half of sixth century (cf. the article of Japanese Buddhism) and through dispatches of mission to Sui and Tang-Dynasties China, technology was made progress in many areas including agriculture, tempering iron, architecture, etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Buddhism was introduced into Japan from the Korean Peninsula in the first half of the 6th century (cf. the article on Japanese Buddhism) and through dispatches of missions to Sui and Tang Dynasty China technological developments were made in many areas including agriculture, iron working, and architecture.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation, word choice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Buddhism was introduced into Japan from the Korean Peninsula in the first half of the 6th century (cf. the article on Japanese Buddhism) and through dispatches of missions to Sui and Tang Dynasty China technological developments were made in many areas including agriculture, iron working, and architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>なかでも仏教美術は発達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially Buddhist art made progress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist art was an area which displayed particular progress.</e>
<cmt>Rewritten.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist art was an area which displayed particular progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BOTarate(id:185620), Albambot(id:195288), Andre Engels(id:202), Forestfarmer(id:59407), TuvicBot(id:64131), 水野白楓(id:22811), PixelBot(id:166734), Robbot(id:3063), WarddrBOT(id:105894), Tribot(id:186681), OKBot(id:143139), Gombe(id:27), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Shikai shaw(id:14306), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), NDR(id:5500), FlaBot(id:30804), SieBot(id:126695), Zippin(id:9885), Binh Giang(id:79801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>