<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>第16師団 (日本軍)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dai Juroku Shidan (Sixteenth Division) of the Imperial Japanese Army</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dai Juroku Shidan (Sixteenth Division) of the Imperial Japanese Army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dai Juroku Shidan (Sixteenth Division) of the Imperial Japanese Army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>第16師団（だいじゅうろくしだん）は、大日本帝国陸軍の師団の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sixteenth Division was one of the divisions of the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sixteenth Division was one of the divisions of the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sixteenth Division was one of the divisions of the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>1905年（明治38年）7月18日に京都府で編成された大日本帝国陸軍の師団である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a division of the Imperial Japanese Army established in Kyoto Prefecture on July 18, 1905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a division of the Imperial Japanese Army established in Kyoto Prefecture on July 18, 1905.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a division of the Imperial Japanese Army established in Kyoto Prefecture on July 18, 1905.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日露戦争で日本は従来の師団総てを動員した為、本土駐留師団がなくなる事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japan mobilized all of the former divisions in Russo-Japanese War, it resulted in the situation where there were no army divisions stationed in the mainland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Japan mobilized all of the former divisions in Russo-Japanese War, it resulted in a situation where there were no army divisions stationed on the mainland.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Japan mobilized all of the former divisions in the Russo-Japanese War, it resulted in a situation where there were no army divisions stationed on the mainland.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そこで第16師団を含む4個師団が創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four divisions were creating including the Sixteenth Division to solve this situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four divisions were created including the Sixteenth Division to solve this situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four divisions including the Sixteenth Division were created to solve this situation.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>第16師団の他、1905年（明治38年）4月1日に第13師団 (日本軍)と第15師団 (日本軍)が、同年7月6日に第14師団 (日本軍)が創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than the Sixteenth Division, Thirteenth and Fifteenth Divisions (Imperial Japanese Army) were established on April 1, 1905, and Fourteenth Division (Imperial Japanese Army) was established on July 6 of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than the Sixteenth Division, the Thirteenth and Fifteenth Divisions (Imperial Japanese Army) were established on April 1, 1905, and Fourteenth Division (Imperial Japanese Army) was established on July 6 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than the Sixteenth Division, the Thirteenth and Fifteenth Divisions (Imperial Japanese Army) were established on April 1, 1905, and Fourteenth Division (Imperial Japanese Army) was established on July 6 of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日露戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>第16師団は、1905年（明治38年）7月18日に編成され直ちに満州に派遣されたが、戦闘は概ね終結しており9月5日には講和条約（ポーツマス条約）が締結された為、戦闘には加わっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sixteenth Division was dispatched to Manchuria on July 18, 1905 immediately after its formation but did not join the battle since it already ended and the peace treaty (Treaty of Portsmouth) was signed on September 5.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sixteenth Division was dispatched to Manchuria on July 18, 1905 immediately after its formation but did not join the battle since it already ended and the peace treaty (Treaty of Portsmouth) was signed on September 5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sixteenth Division was dispatched to Manchuria on July 18, 1905 immediately after its formation but did not join the battle since it already ended and the peace treaty (Treaty of Portsmouth) was signed on September 5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>日露戦争後1919年（大正8年）から師団は満州駐剳を命ぜられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The division was ordered to stay in Manchuria from 1919 after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The division was ordered to stay in Manchuria from 1919 after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The division was ordered to stay in Manchuria from 1919 after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後一旦帰国するが、1929年（昭和4年）と1934年（昭和9年）にも満州駐剳任務に就いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It temporarily returned to Japan but was assigned to be stationed in Manchuria in 1929 and 1934.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It temporarily returned to Japan, but was assigned to be stationed in Manchuria in 1929 and 1934.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It temporarily returned to Japan, but was assigned to be stationed in Manchuria in 1929 and 1934.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日中戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sino-Japanese War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sino-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sino-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>1937年（昭和12年）7月に日中戦争が勃発すると、師団は西尾寿造中将司令官の第2軍 (日本軍)戦闘序列に編入され華北戦線に投入、同年11月上海派遣軍隷下上海市戦線に転じ南京攻略戦に参戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The division was incorporated into the second army (Imperial Japanese Army) under Toshizo NISHIO, who had the title of Chujo (Middle Captain) commander when the Sino-Japanese War broke out in July 1937, and it was placed in the frontlines of Northern China battle line before joining Shanghai Expeditionary Army in Shanghai City battle line in November of the same year to participate in the Battle of Nanking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The division was incorporated into the second army (Imperial Japanese Army) under Toshizo NISHIO, who held the title of Chujo (Middle Captain) commander when the Sino-Japanese War broke out in July 1937, and it was placed in the frontlines of the Northern China battle line before joining the Shanghai Expeditionary Army on the Shanghai City battle line in November of the same year to participate in the Battle of Nanking.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The division was incorporated into the second army (Imperial Japanese Army) under Toshizo NISHIO, who held the title of Chujo (Middle Captain) commander when the Sino-Japanese War broke out in July 1937, and it was placed in the frontlines of the Northern China battle line before joining the Shanghai Expeditionary Army on the Shanghai City battle line in November of the same year to participate in the Battle of Nanking.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1938年（昭和13年）1月から北支那方面軍隷下徐州会戦に参戦し、同年7月再び第2軍隷下となり武漢作戦攻略戦に参戦、12月には第11軍 (日本軍)に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It participated in the Japanese Northern China Area Army to fight the Battle of Xuzhou from January 1938 and followed the Second Army again in July of the same year to fight in the Battle of Wuhan and incorporated into the Eleventh Army (Imperial Japanese Army) in December.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It participated in the Japanese Northern China Area Army to fight the Battle of Xuzhou from January 1938 and followed the Second Army again in July of the same year to fight in the Battle of Wuhan and was incorporated into the Eleventh Army (Imperial Japanese Army) in December.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It participated in the Japanese Northern China Area Army to fight in the Battle of Xuzhou from January 1938 and followed the Second Army again in July of the same year to fight in the Battle of Wuhan and was incorporated into the Eleventh Army (Imperial Japanese Army) in December.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>翌1939年（昭和14年）8月に復員する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It demobilized itself in August of the following year of 1939.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It demobilized itself in August of the following year of 1939.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It demobilized itself in August of the following year of 1939.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この時豊橋の歩兵第38連隊が新設の第29師団 (日本軍)に編入されることになり、第16師団は三単位制師団に改編された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the Thirty-eighth Infantry Regiment of Toyohashi was incorporated into the new Twenty-Ninth Division (Imperial Japanese Army), and the Sixteenth Division was reorganized into santani-sei Shidan (Shidan comprised of three infantries).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the Thirty-eighth Infantry Regiment of Toyohashi was incorporated into the new Twenty-Ninth Division (Imperial Japanese Army), and the Sixteenth Division was reorganized into santani-sei Shidan (Shidan comprised of three infantries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the Thirty-eighth Infantry Regiment of Toyohashi was incorporated into the new Twenty-Ninth Division (Imperial Japanese Army), and the Sixteenth Division was reorganized into santani-sei Shidan (Shidan comprised of three infantries).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、それまでは第16師団は京都市を衛戍地とする常設師団であったが、1940年（昭和15年）7月に師団の衛戍地が満州となり、永久駐屯することが決まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sixteenth Division made Kyoto City as its permanent base, but it shifted to Manchuria in July 1940.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sixteenth Division made Kyoto City its permanent base, but it shifted to Manchuria in July 1940.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sixteenth Division made Kyoto City its permanent base, but it shifted to Manchuria in July 1940 and that became its permanent base.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>太平洋戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Pacific War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Pacific War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Pacific War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>太平洋戦争では1941年（昭和16年）11月6日に第14軍 (日本軍)戦闘序列に編入され、緒戦のフィリピンの戦い (1941-1942年)に参戦し、マニラ陥落後フィリピンに駐屯した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fourteenth Division (Imperial Japanese Army) was dispatched to the front lines on November 6, 1941 and fought at the beginning of war in Philippines (1941-1942) stationed there after Manila fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fourteenth Division (Imperial Japanese Army) was dispatched to the front lines on November 6, 1941 and fought at the beginning of the war in the Philippines (1941-1942) stationed there after Manila fell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fourteenth Division (Imperial Japanese Army) was dispatched to the front lines on November 6, 1941 and fought at the beginning of the war in the Philippines (1941-1942), and stationed there after Manila fell.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>1944年（昭和19年）8月からは第35軍 (日本軍)隷下となりレイテ島に移駐した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It went under the commands of the Thirty-fifth Army (Imperial Japanese Army) from August 1944 and stationed itself on Layt Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It went under the commands of the Thirty-fifth Army (Imperial Japanese Army) from August 1944 and stationed itself on Layt Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It went under the commands of the Thirty-fifth Army (Imperial Japanese Army) from August 1944 and stationed itself on Layt Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この年の10月20日連合国軍がレイテ島に上陸し、大本営はレイテ島の戦いを予定したが第16師団は壊滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Allies invaded the Layt Island on October 20 of this year, and the Imperial headquarter planned the battle on Layt Island, but the Sixteenth Division was annihilated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Allies invaded Layt Island on October 20 of that year, and the Imperial headquarters planned the battle on Layt Island, but the Sixteenth Division was annihilated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Allies invaded Layt Island on October 20 of that year, and the Imperial headquarters were planning the battle on Layt Island while the Sixteenth Division was annihilated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当初13,000名で臨んだレイテ決戦も生還者は僅か620名で、3人の連隊長が戦死しており、牧野四郎師団長も1945年（昭和20年）8月10日自決した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among thirteen thousand soldiers that participated in the battle on Layt Island, only six hundred twenty survived, and three regimental commanders died at the battle, and Shiro MAKINO, who was the head of the division also committed suicide on August 10, 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among thirteen thousand soldiers that participated in the battle on Layt Island, only six hundred twenty survived, and three regimental commanders died in the battle, and Shiro MAKINO, who was the head of the division also committed suicide on August 10, 1945.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among thirteen thousand soldiers that participated in the battle on Layt Island, only six hundred twenty survived, and three regimental commanders died in the battle, and Shiro MAKINO, who was the head of the division committed suicide on August 10, 1945.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>遺構等</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structural Remnants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structural Remnants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structural Remnants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>師団司令部ならびに一部の隷下部隊・施設は京都市伏見区内に設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the soldier units and facilities were located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City beside the headquarter for the division commander.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the soldier units and facilities were located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City beside the headquarters for the division commander.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the soldier units and facilities were located in Fushimi Ward, Kyoto City beside the headquarters for the division commander.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1908年（明治41年）に完成した第16師団司令部庁舎は後に学校法人聖母女学院が法人本部として利用、師団練兵場は龍谷大学が利用する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dormitory of the commanders of the Sixteenth Division was later used as the main headquarter of Seibo Jogakuin School Corporation, and the division drill court was used by Ryukoku University.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dormitory of the commanders of the Sixteenth Division was later used as the main headquarters of Seibo Jogakuin School Corporation, and the division drill court was used by Ryukoku University.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dormitory of the commanders of the Sixteenth Division whose construction was completed in 1908 was later used as the main headquarters of Seibo Jogakuin School Corporation, and the division drill court was used by Ryukoku University.</e>
<cmt>whose construction was completed in 1908補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>また京阪電気鉄道藤森駅は開業当初師団前という名称であった（1941年（昭和16年）に現名称に改称）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Fuji no Mori Station of Keihan Electric Railway Corporation had the name, Shidan mae (front of division) during the time it was established (it was renamed to the current name in 1941).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Fuji no Mori Station of Keihan Electric Railway Corporation had the name, Shidan mae (front of division) during the time it was established (it was renamed to the current name in 1941).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Fuji no Mori Station of Keihan Electric Railway Corporation had the name, Shidan mae (front of division) around the time it was established (it was renamed to the current name in 1941).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この藤森駅付近の師団街道という道路や、琵琶湖疏水に架かる師団橋という橋梁も第16師団の設置に伴い整備されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The streets and bridges such as the Shidan-kaido Road (Division Road) and Shidan Bridge (Division Bridge) over the river that flowed from Lake Biwa were established at the time the Sixteenth Division was stationed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The streets and bridges such as the Shidan-kaido Road (Division Road) and Shidan Bridge (Division Bridge) over the river that flowed from Lake Biwa were established at the time the Sixteenth Division was stationed there.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The streets and bridges such as the Shidan-kaido Road (Division Road) and Shidan Bridge (Division Bridge) over the river that flowed from Lake Biwa were established at the time the Sixteenth Division was stationed there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 がめら(id:12392), Tangmo(id:86444), Si-take.(id:91094), Wiki0825(id:34646), Sweeper tamonten(id:183520), Panpulha(id:42950), Daisydaisy(id:48776), 219.106の者(id:151047), 前場慶彦(id:117769), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), どんどん(id:172259), 代言人(id:33675), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), IwaimBot(id:190695), SUPER REXTON(id:216948), Snlf1(id:187217), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>