<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>封建制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoken system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoken system</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoken system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>封建制（ほうけんせい）とは、中国など漢字文化圏における政治思想において主張された、周王朝を規範とする政治制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoken system is a political system modeling Shu Dynasty in China, which was advocated in the political thought of Kanji culture area including China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hoken system is a political system modeled after the Shu Dynasty in China, which was advocated in the political thought of Kanji using nations, such as China.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hoken system is a political system modeled after the Shu Dynasty in China, which was advocated in the political thought of Kanji using nations, such as China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>転じて近現代になると西欧中世社会を特徴づける社会経済制度であるフューダリズム（Feudalism）の訳語にも援用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the modern and present-day era, it also came to be used as a Japanese equivalent for Feudalism, the socioeconomic system characterizing the medieval European society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the modern and present-day era, it also came to be used as a Japanese equivalent for Feudalism, the socioeconomic system characterizing medieval European society.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the modern and present-day era, it also came to be used as a Japanese equivalent for Feudalism, the socioeconomic system characterizing medieval European society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>両者は本質的に異なる概念であるため、詳細はそれぞれの節に記す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the two concepts are substantially different, they are detailed respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the two concepts are substantially different, they are detailed respectively.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the two concepts are substantially different, they are detailed respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中世封建制度（フューダリズム）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoken system in the medieval ages (Feudalism)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoken system in the medieval ages (Feudalism)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoken system in the medieval ages (Feudalism)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>フューダリズム（Feudalism）とは歴史学において中世ヨーロッパ社会特有の支配形態を指した用語であり、「封建制」と訳出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudalism is a historical term referring to the system of government unique to the midieval European society, and is translated as &apos;Hoken System.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudalism is a historical term referring to the system of government unique to medieval European society, and is translated as &apos;Hoken System.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudalism is a historical term referring to the system of government unique to medieval European society, and is translated as &apos;Hoken System.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>土地を媒介とした国王・領主・家臣の間の緩い主従関係により形成され、近世以降の絶対王政の中で消失した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consisted of loose, land mediated relations of master to servant among king, feudal lord, and retainer, and disappeared under the absolute monarchy in the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consisted of loose, land mediated relations of master to servant among king, feudal lord, and retainer, and disappeared under absolute monarchy in the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consisted of loose, land mediated relations of master to servant among king, feudal lord, and retainer, and disappeared under absolute monarchy in the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>マルクス主義歴史学（唯物史観）においては、生産力と生産関係の矛盾を基盤として普遍的な歴史法則を見いだそうとするため、この理論的枠組みを非ヨーロッパ地域にも適用して説明が試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Marxist history (materialistic concept of history) tries to find out an universal rule of history based on the contradiction between productive force and the relation of production, and the logical framework was applied to non-European regions for explanation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Marxist history (materialistic concept of history) tries to find out a universal rule of history based on the contradiction between the productive force and the relation of production, and the logical framework was applied to non-European regions as an explanation.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Marxist history (materialistic concept of history) tries to find out a universal rule of history based on the contradiction between the productive force and the relation of production, and the logical framework was applied to non-European regions as an explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この場合、おおよそ古代の奴隷制が生産力の進歩によって覆され、領主が生産者である農民を農奴として支配するようになったと解釈される社会経済制度のことを示す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, it means the sociopolitical system considered to have been established after the overturn of the ancient slavery with the improvement of productivity, under which feudal lords ruled productive peasants as serf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, it means the socio-political system considered to have been established after the overturn of ancient slavery with the improvement of productivity, under which feudal lords ruled productive peasants as serfs.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, it means the socio-political system considered to have been established after the overturn of ancient slavery with the improvement of productivity, under which feudal lords ruled productive peasants as serfs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>ヨーロッパ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Europe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Europe</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>古ゲルマン人社会の従士制度（軍事的奉仕）と、ローマ帝国末期の恩貸地制度（土地の保護）に起源を見いだし、これらが結びつき成立したと説明されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retainer system (military duties) in the ancient German society and the land loan system (land protection) in the later Roman Empire are often seen as the origin, and it is often explained that the two systems were combined to form the feudalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retainer system (military duties) in the ancient German society and the land loan system (land protection) in the later Roman Empire are often seen as the origin, and it is often explained that the two systems were combined to form feudalism.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The retainer system (military duties) in the ancient German society and the land loan system (land protection) in the later Roman Empire are often seen as the origin, and it is often explained that the two systems were combined to form feudalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>国王が諸侯に領地の保護（防衛）をする代償に忠誠を誓わせ、諸侯も同様の事を臣下たる騎士に約束し、忠誠を誓わせるという制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the system, a king makes feudal lords pledge loyalty in return for the protection of their domains, and the feudal lords make the same promise with retainers and make them pledge loyalty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the system, a king makes feudal lords pledge loyalty in return for the protection of their domains, and the feudal lords make the same promise with retainers and make them pledge loyalty.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the system, a king makes feudal lords pledge loyalty in return for the protection of their domains, and the feudal lords make the same promise with retainers and make them pledge loyalty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この主従関係は騎士道物語などのイメージから誠実で奉仕的な物と考えられがちだが、実際にはお互いの契約を前提とした現実的なもので、また両者の関係が双務的であった事もあり、主君が臣下の保護を怠ったりした場合は短期間で両者の関係が解消されるケースも珍しくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This relationship of master and servant is often connected with the image of chivalric tales and seen as faithful and self-sacrificing, but it is in fact, a realistic relationship based on a mutual agreeement, and the relationship was reciprocal and sometimes dissolved in a short term when the lord fails to protect his retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This relationship of master and servant is often connected with the image of chivalric tales and seen as faithful and self-sacrificing, but it is in fact, a realistic relationship based on a mutual agreement, and the relationship was reciprocal and sometimes dissolved in shortly when the lord failed to protect his retainer.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This relationship of master and servant is often connected with the image of chivalric tales and seen as faithful and self-sacrificing, but it is in fact, a realistic relationship based on a mutual agreement, and the relationship was reciprocal and sometimes dissolved in shortly when the lord failed to protect his retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>更に「臣下の臣下は臣下でない」という語に示されるように、直接に主従関係を結んでいなければ「臣下の臣下」は「主君の主君」に対して主従関係を形成しなかった為、複雑な権力構造が形成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, as indicated by the saing &apos;retainer&apos;s retainer is not a retainer&apos;, &apos;retainer&apos;s retainer&apos; did not have the master to servant relationship with &apos;master&apos;s master&apos;, therefore, a complicated power structure was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, as indicated by the saying &quot;a retainer&apos;s retainer is not a retainer,&quot; &quot;a retainer&apos;s retainer&quot; did not have the master to servant relationship with &quot;a master&apos;s master,&quot; therefore, a complicated power structure was formed.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, as indicated by the saying &quot;a retainer&apos;s retainer is not a retainer,&quot; &quot;a retainer&apos;s retainer&quot; did not have the master to servant relationship with &quot;a master&apos;s master,&quot; therefore, a complicated power structure was formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これは中世社会が（今日的な視点で見れば）極めて非中央集権的な社会となる要因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This made the medieval society extremely decentralized (from today&apos;s point of view).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This made medieval society extremely decentralized (from today&apos;s point of view).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This made medieval society extremely decentralized (from today&apos;s point of view).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>西欧中世においては、特にその初期においてノルマン人、イスラーム教徒、マジャール人などの外民族のあいつぐ侵入に苦しめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the medieval Europe, particularly in its early days, people were suffered from repeated invasion by foreigners such as Normans, Muslims and Magyars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In medieval Europe, particularly in its early days, people suffered from repeated invasion by foreigners such as the Normans, Muslims and Magyars.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In medieval Europe, particularly in its early days, people suffered from repeated invasion by foreigners such as the Normans, Muslims and Magyars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのため、本来なら一代限りの契約であった主従関係が、次第に世襲・固定化されていくようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the master-and-servant relationship, which is originally an agreement for just one generation, gradually became hereditary and fixed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the master-and-servant relationship, which is originally an agreement for just one generation, gradually became hereditary and fixed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the master-and-servant relationship, which is originally an agreement for just one generation, gradually became hereditary and fixed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こうして、農奴制とフューダリズムを土台とした西欧封建社会が成熟していった（ただし、実際には各農村ごとにかなり相違があったと考えられている上、多くの農村では農奴だけでなく自由農民も相当数存在していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the European society of Hoken system based on serfdom and Feudalism became mature (but the situation was quite different from village to village and most villages had a large number of free peasants as well as serfs.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the Western European Hoken society based on serfdom and Feudalism matured (but the situation was quite different from village to village and most villages had a large number of free peasants as well as serfs).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the Western European Hoken society based on serfdom and Feudalism matured (but the situation was quite different from village to village and most villages had a large number of free peasants as well as serfs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>ヨーロッパでのフューダリズム（封建制）が、外民族の移動・侵入などと強く結び付いて形成されたのに比し、日本の封建制はむしろ武士による統治などの国内的要因が主となって形成された（天皇を始めとする貴族は武士の権威を根拠付ける存在である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Europe, the formation of Feudalism (Hoken system) was closely related to foreigners&apos; migration and invasion, Hoken system in Japan, on the other hand, the formation was mainly triggered by domestic factors including samurai ruling (nobility including the Emperor is the existence authorizing the power of samurai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Europe, the formation of Feudalism (Hoken system) was closely related to foreigners&apos; migration and invasion, the Hoken system in Japan, on the other hand, was mainly triggered by domestic factors including samurai ruling (nobility, including the Emperor, authorized the power of samurai).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Europe, the formation of Feudalism (Hoken system) was closely related to foreigners&apos; migration and invasion, the Hoken system in Japan, on the other hand, was mainly triggered by domestic factors including samurai ruling (nobility, including the Emperor, authorized the power of samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>西欧のフューダリズムで複数の契約関係や、短期間での契約破棄・変更がみられたのと同様、日本でも実際のところ戦国時代 (日本)まで主従関係は流動的なものであり、「二君にまみえず」という語に示されるような主君への強い忠誠が求められたのは、江戸時代に入ってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar to the Western feudalism, under which multiple contractual relationships and dissolution/alteration of contracts were seen, in Japan, the master-snd-servant relationship was fluid and the unshaken loyalty as shown in the saying &apos; A faithful retainer will nit serve two masters.&apos; was not required until the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar to the Western feudalism, under which multiple contractual relationships and dissolution/alteration of contracts were seen, in Japan, the master-and-servant relationship was fluid and unshaken loyalty as shown in the saying &apos; A faithful retainer will never serve two masters&apos; was not required until the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar to the Western feudalism, under which multiple contractual relationships and dissolution/alteration of contracts were seen, in Japan, the master-and-servant relationship was fluid and unshaken loyalty as shown in the saying &apos; A faithful retainer will never serve two masters&apos; was not required until the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>日本の封建制の成立をめぐっては、いくつかの説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are several views about the formation of Hoken system in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are several views about the formation of the Hoken system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are several views about the formation of the Hoken system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>鎌倉幕府の成立によって御恩と奉公からなる封建制が成立したとする説で、戦前以来、ほとんどの概説書で採用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One view is that the Go-on (obligation) and Hoko (duty) -based Hoken system was completed with the establishment of Kamakura bakufu, ant this view has been adopted in most introductory books since prewar periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One view is that the Go-on (obligation) and Hoko (duty) -based Hoken system was completed with the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu, and this view has been adopted in most introductory books since prewar periods.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One view is that the Go-on (obligation) and Hoko (duty) -based Hoken system was completed with the establishment of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and this view has been adopted in most introductory books since prewar periods.</e>
<cmt>Kamakura bakufu → (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この考え方では、古代律令社会の解体から各地に形成された在地領主の発展を原動力として、領主層の独自の国家権力として鎌倉幕府が形成されたとみなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this view, the Kamakura bakufu was formed as an independent state power of feudal lords driven by the development of local feudal lords in various places after the breakup of the ancient society based on the ancient Ritsuryo codes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this view, the Kamakura bakufu was formed as an independent state power of feudal lords driven by the development of local feudal lords in various places after the breakup of ancient society based on the ancient Ritsuryo codes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this view, the Kamakura bakufu was formed as an independent state power of feudal lords driven by the development of local feudal lords in various places after the breakup of ancient society based on the ancient Ritsuryo codes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>従って承平天慶の乱（承平5年、935年）がその初期の現われとみなされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Johei and Tenkyo War (in 935) is regarded as an early sign of it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Johei and Tenkyo War (in 935) is regarded as an early sign of it.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Johei and Tenkyo War (in 935) is regarded as an early sign of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>日本中世史と日本近世史の間で、1953年から1960年代にかけて日本封建制成立論争が展開した（太閤検地論争とも呼ばれる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a controversy between medieval history and early-modern history on the establishment of Hoken system in Japan from 1953 through 1960&apos;s (it is also called the controversy on Taiko-kenchi (cadastral survey instituted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a controversy between medieval history and early-modern history on the establishment of the Hoken system in Japan from 1953 through the 1960&apos;s (it is also called the controversy of Taiko-kenchi (cadastral survey instituted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)).</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a controversy between medieval history and early-modern history on the establishment of the Hoken system in Japan from 1953 through the 1960&apos;s (it is also called the controversy of Taiko-kenchi (cadastral survey instituted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その口火を切った安良城盛昭は、太閤検地実施前後の時期の分析から荘園制社会を家父長的奴隷制社会（＝古代）とし、太閤検地を画期として成立する幕藩体制を日本の封建制と規定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moriaki ARAKI, who sparked the controversy, considered the manorial system-based society to be a patriarchal slavery society (=the ancient times), and defined the shogunate system established with Taiko-kenchi as the Hoken system in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moriaki ARAKI, who sparked the controversy, considered the manorial system-based society to be a patriarchal slavery society (=the ancient times), and defined the shogunate system established with Taiko-kenchi as the Hoken system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moriaki ARAKI, who sparked the controversy, considered the manorial system-based society to be a patriarchal slavery society (=the ancient times), and defined the shogunate system established with Taiko-kenchi as the Hoken system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、激しい反論を生み、院政期以降を成立期とする説（戸田芳実など）、南北朝時代 (日本)内乱期を成立期とする説（永原慶二など）が提起された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his idea invited pointed objections and Yoshimi TODA and his group proposed the theory that the system was established after the period of the government ruled by the retired Emperor, and Keiji NAGAHARA and his group proposed another theory that the system was established in the Northern and Southern Dynasties period (in Japan), the civic war period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his idea invited pointed objections and Yoshimi TODA and his group proposed the theory that the system was established after the period of the government ruled by the retired Emperor, and Keiji NAGAHARA and his group proposed another theory that the system was established in the Northern and Southern Dynasties period (in Japan), the civil war period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his idea invited pointed objections and Yoshimi TODA and his group proposed the theory that the system was established after the period of the government ruled by the retired Emperor, and Keiji NAGAHARA and his group proposed another theory that the system was established in the Northern and Southern Dynasties period (in Japan), the civil war period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>歴史学の関心が拡散する中でこの論争は明確な解答を得ぬまま終息した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interest of historical science became diffused and the controversy came to an end without any clear result.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interest of historical science became diffused and the controversy came to an end without any clear result.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interest of historical science became diffused and the controversy came to an end without any clear result.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>日本の領主の封建制は「税の徴収権」に過ぎず（参照→職の体系）、つまり西欧に見られるような領地の私有と領民への農奴としての隷属的支配権は存在しなかったので、本当の意味の封建制は存在しなかったとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a view that the Hoken system in its true sense did not exist in Japan, because Hoken system of feudal lords was just &apos;the right to collect taxes&apos; (see Shiki system), and there was no private ownership of land and rights of control over the people as serfs in the domain, which were commonly seen in the West.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a view that the Hoken system in its true sense did not exist in Japan, because the Hoken system of feudal lords was just &apos;the right to collect taxes&apos; (see Shiki system), and there was no private ownership of land and rights of control over the people as serfs in the domain, which were commonly seen in the West.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a view that the Hoken system in its true sense did not exist in Japan, because the Hoken system of feudal lords was just &apos;the right to collect taxes&apos; (see Shiki system), and there was no private ownership of land and rights of control over the people as serfs in the domain, which were commonly seen in the West.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>中国における発展段階論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development stage theory in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development stage theory in China</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Development stage theory in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="27">
<j>周の封建制（後述）とは別に、中国史において唯物史観的発展段階論を適用した場合の封建制について述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from the Hoken system in Zhou (which will be described later), Hoken system will be described in view of the development stage theory based on materialistic conception of history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from the Hoken system in Zhou (which will be described later), the Hoken system will be described in view of the development stage theory based on materialistic conception of history.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from the Hoken system in Zhou (which will be described later), the Hoken system will be described in view of the development stage theory based on materialistic conception of history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>近代以降、中国史を専攻する学者たちは、カール・マルクスにより押された、「アジア的停滞」の烙印を何とかして剥がそうと試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the modern era, scholars specializing in Chinese history have been trying to clear the label, &apos;Asian stagnation&apos; put by Karl Marx.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the modern era, scholars specializing in Chinese history have been trying to clear the label, &apos;Asian stagnation&apos; put forth by Karl Marx.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the modern era, scholars specializing in Chinese history have been trying to clear the label, &apos;Asian stagnation&apos; put forth by Karl Marx.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>そのさきがけとなったのが郭沫若である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That movement was initiated by Guo Moruo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That movement was initiated by Guo Moruo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That movement was initiated by Guo Moruo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>郭沫若はその著書『中国古代社会史研究』の中に於いて中国史に発展段階論を適用し、周を奴隷制の時代とし、春秋時代以降を封建制とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Guo Moruo applied the development stage theory to Chinese history in his book &quot;Studies on the Ancient Society of China &quot; and defined Zhou as a slavery period and Hoken system took hold after the Chunqiu period.</e>
<cmt>中国の王朝名は中国語の読みを採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Guo Moruo applied the development stage theory to Chinese history in his book &quot;Studies on the Ancient Society of China&quot; and defined Zhou as a slavery period and the Hoken system took hold after the Chunqiu period.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Guo Moruo applied the development stage theory to Chinese history in his book &quot;Studies on the Ancient Society of China&quot; and defined Zhou as a slavery period and the Hoken system took hold after the Chunqiu period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これに対して呂振羽は殷を奴隷制、周代を封建制の社会だとして反論し、この論争は結論を見ないままに終わることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lu Zhenyu opposed the idea, insisting that Yin is a slavery society and Zhou is Hoken system-based society, but the argument ended without conclusion.</e>
<cmt>中国人名は中国語読みを採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lu Zhenyu opposed the idea, insisting that Yin was a slavery society and Zhou was a Hoken system-based society, but the argument ended without conclusion.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lu Zhenyu opposed the idea, insisting that Yin was a slavery society and Zhou was a Hoken system-based society, but the argument ended without conclusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>これに対して日本では内藤湖南により魏晋南北朝時代・隋唐時代を封建制の時代とすべきと言う論が出された（唐宋変革論）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, Konan NAITO in Japan proposed the view that the period of Wei and Jin in the Northern and Southern Dynasties and the period of Sui and Tang should be regarded as the period of Hoken system (the Tang-Song Transition Thesis).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, Konan NAITO in Japan proposed the view that the period of Wei and Jin in the Northern and Southern Dynasties and the period of Sui and Tang should be regarded as periods of the Hoken system (the Tang-Song Transition Thesis).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Konan NAITO in Japan proposed the view that the period of Wei and Jin in the Northern and Southern Dynasties and the period of Sui and Tang should be regarded as periods of the Hoken system (the Tang-Song Transition Thesis).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これに対して唐末期から五代十国時代を奴隷制から封建制へ切り替わりと捉える前田直典の論が出され、戦前から1970年代に渡って激しい論争が繰り広げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Naonari MAEDA proposed a view that the social system changed from slavery to Hoken system during the era ranging from the closing years of Tang period through the Wudai Shiguo period, and the argument was heated from the prewar period through 1970&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Naonari MAEDA proposed a view that the social system changed from slavery to the Hoken system during the era ranging from the closing years of the Tang period through the Wudai Shiguo period, and the argument was heated from the prewar period through the 1970&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Naonari MAEDA proposed a view that the social system changed from slavery to the Hoken system during the era ranging from the closing years of the Tang period through the Wudai Shiguo period, and the argument was heated from the prewar period through the 1970&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>これらの論の基準となる所は封建制の特徴とされる農奴の存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These views are based on the existence of serfs which are said to be characteristic of Hoken system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These views are based on the existence of serfs which are said to be characteristic of the Hoken system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These views are based on the existence of serfs which are said to be characteristic of the Hoken system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>魏晋南北朝時代を封建制と捉える立場からは後漢の豪族たちによって使われていた小作農たちを奴隷とみなし、後漢の滅亡によりそれが変化したと見る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the standpoint that the period of Wei and Jin in the Northern and Southern Dynasties was the time of Hoken system, tenant peasants used by local ruling families were slaves, and the situation changed with the downfall of the Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the standpoint that the period of Wei and Jin in the Northern and Southern Dynasties was a time of the Hoken system, tenant peasants used by local ruling families were slaves, and the situation changed with the downfall of the Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the standpoint that the period of Wei and Jin in the Northern and Southern Dynasties was a time of the Hoken system, tenant peasants used by local ruling families were slaves, and the situation changed with the downfall of the Later Han Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>宋以後を封建制と見る立場からは均田制の下におかれた農民たちを奴隷とみなし、宋に入って登場した佃戸制を農奴とみなす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the standpoint that Hoken system became prevalent after the Song period, peasants under the Equal-field system were slaves and Tien Hu system which firstly appeared in the Song period was regarded as serfdom.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明（漢字を中国語読みにしています）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the standpoint that the Hoken system became prevalent after the Song period, peasants under the Equal-field system were slaves and the Tien Hu system which first appeared in the Song period was regarded as a serfdom.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the standpoint that the Hoken system became prevalent after the Song period, peasants under the Equal-field system were slaves and the Tien Hu system which first appeared in the Song period was regarded as a serfdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>長い論争が繰り広げられたが、結局明確な結論は出ないまま論争は下火になり、現在ではほとんど行われていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a long dispute but it cooled down with no clear conclusion and is virtually of no existence now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a long dispute but it cooled down with no clear conclusion and is virtually nonexistent now.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a long dispute but it cooled down with no clear conclusion and is virtually nonexistent now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>理由はいろいろ考えられるが、最も大きな理由はマルクス主義の魅力が薄れ、中国史に発展段階論を当てはめることの意義を疑い始めたからであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various reasons can be cited, but the biggest reason is that the Marxism became less appealing and people are now skeptical about the significance of applying development stage theory to Chinese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various reasons can be cited, but the biggest reason is that Marxism became less appealing and people are now skeptical about the significance of applying development stage theory to Chinese history.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various reasons can be cited, but the biggest reason is that Marxism became less appealing and people are now skeptical about the significance of applying development stage theory to Chinese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、マルクス主義の立場をとる研究者からも、在地の地主に裁判権などの権力が備わっておらず、それらが国家権力の手に集中されており、封建制の重要な内容である領主権力が存在しないため、中国史における封建制概念を否定する見解が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even some Marxist scholars denied the concept of Hoken system in Chinese history based on the fact that local land lords had no such powers as jurisdiction, and those powers were controlled by the state and there was no seigniory that was an important aspect of Hoken system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even some Marxist scholars denied the concept of the Hoken system in Chinese history based on the fact that local land lords had no powers such as jurisdiction, and those powers were controlled by the state and there was no seniority that was an important aspect of the Hoken system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even some Marxist scholars denied the concept of the Hoken system in Chinese history based on the fact that local land lords had no powers such as jurisdiction, and those powers were controlled by the state and there was no seniority that was an important aspect of the Hoken system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>封建制に代わる、中国史上の経済制度を特徴づける概念や歴史像はいまだ構築されていないが、最近では階級構造を描き出そうとする従来の方法に代わって、地域社会の中における地主の役割に注目した研究がなされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concepts and views of history which characterize the economic system in the Chinese history have yet to be constructed, but recently, more studies are focusing on the role of landlords in a local community, instead of describing the class structure by conventional methods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concepts and views of history which characterize the economic system in Chinese history have yet to be constructed, but recently, more studies are focusing on the role of landlords in a local community, instead of describing the class structure by conventional methods.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concepts and views of history which characterize the economic system in Chinese history have yet to be constructed, but recently, more studies are focusing on the role of landlords in a local community, instead of describing the class structure by conventional methods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>中国史における「封建制」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoken system in the Chinese history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoken system&apos; in Chinese history</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoken system&apos; in Chinese history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>中国王朝でおこなわれた封建制は君主が貴族に領域支配を名目的に認める制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Hoken system operated under Chinese dynasties, a monarchy nominally authorizes the nobility to rule the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Hoken system operated under Chinese dynasties, a monarchy nominally authorizes the nobility to rule the domain.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Hoken system operated under Chinese dynasties, a monarchy nominally authorizes the nobility to rule the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>同時に封建された貴族は君主の名目的な支配下に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the authorized nobility falls under the control of the monarchy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the authorized nobility falls under the control of the monarchy.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the authorized nobility falls under the control of the monarchy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>西洋の法的な封建制度であるレーエン制とは異なり、軍事奉仕を期待するものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the fiefdom, the Western legal Hoken system, no military duties were expected.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike the fiefdom, the Western legal Hoken system, no military duties were expected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike the fiefdom, the Western legal Hoken system, no military duties were expected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>一定の領地と観念的に結びついた爵位が授与されるが、それが土地支配権を伴うとは限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peerage which conceptually linked to a certain domain was given, but that did not necessarily involve the right of control over the land.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peerage which conceptually linked to a certain domain was given, but that did not necessarily involve the right of control over the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peerage which conceptually linked to a certain domain was given, but that did not necessarily involve the right of control over the land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>したがって血縁的な関係の延長上に形成されたとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in a different view, it was formed as an extension of blood relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in a different view, it was formed as an extension of blood relations.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in a different view, it was formed as an extension of blood relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>殷・周</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yin and Zhou</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yin and Zhou</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yin and Zhou</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>殷代からすでに封建がおこなわれてたという指摘がされているが、殷代封建制については詳しいことはわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is indicated that the Hoken system was already used in the Yin period, but the details of the system in the period are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is indicated that the Hoken system was already used in the Yin period, but the details of the system in the period are unknown.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is indicated that the Hoken system was already used in the Yin period, but the details of the system in the period are unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>殷代には封建された国とは別に方国という国が存在しており、これらを外様あるいは異民族の国とする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, in the Yin period, there was another type of countries called Fangguo apart from the granted countries, and these are the countries of foreigners or different races.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明（漢字を中国語読みにしています）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, in the Yin period, there was another type of country called Fangguo apart from the granted countries, and these were the countries of foreigners or different races.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, in the Yin period, there was another type of country called Fangguo apart from the granted countries, and these were the countries of foreigners or different races.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>殷を方国の連盟の盟主と見る場合、封建された国はより殷の支配の強い国々であったと考えられ、したがって殷代には同族や直接支配下にあった部族の有力者が封建されたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If Yin was the leader of the Hokoku league of countries, those granted countries must have been strongly controlled by Yin, therefore, in the Yin period, the sovereignty over the country should have been given by the Zhou Dynasty to the same families and clans directly under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the Yin were the leaders of the Hokoku league of countries, those granted countries must have been strongly controlled by the Yin, therefore, in the Yin period, the sovereignty over the country should have been given by the Zhou Dynasty to the same families and clans directly under control.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the Yin were the leaders of the Hokoku league of countries, those granted countries must have been strongly controlled by the Yin, therefore, in the Yin period, the sovereignty over the country should have been given by the Zhou Dynasty to the same families and clans directly under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>殷代の封建された土地について地名を特定しようという研究が続いており、さまざまな説が唱えられているがはっきりしたことはわからない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Studies have been going on to identify the name of lands granted in the Yin period and various views are advocated but nothing clear is known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Studies have been going on to identify the name of lands granted in the Yin period and various views are advocated, but nothing clear is known.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Studies have been going on to identify the name of lands granted in the Yin period and various views are advocated, but nothing clear is known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>周の時代には中国的な封建制度は活期を迎えたと考えられており、各地に邑を基盤とした血族共同体が広汎に現れ、周はこれらと実際に血縁関係をむすんだり、封建的な関係をむすぶことによって擬制的に血縁関係をつくりだし、支配下に置いたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the Chinese Hoken system was at its peak in the Zhou period, and blood relative communities based on Mura (large village) broadly emerged in many places, and Zhou formed fictitious blood relations to control them by making actual blood relations or feudalistic relations with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that the Chinese Hoken system was at its peak in the Zhou period, and blood relative communities based on Mura (large village) broadly emerged in many places, and Zhou formed fictitious blood relations to control them by making actual blood relations or feudalistic relations with them.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that the Chinese Hoken system was at its peak in the Zhou period, and blood relative communities based on Mura (large village) broadly emerged in many places, and Zhou formed fictitious blood relations to control them by making actual blood relations or feudalistic relations with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>長子相続を根幹とした血族共同体を基礎としたこの関係を宗族制度といい、宗族制度と封建制度が密接に関係していたであろうことは概ね認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This relationships based on the blood family community with primogeniture at its core is called Sozoku System, and it is generally accepted that the Sozoku system and Hoken system were closely related to each other.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These relationships based on the blood family community with primogeniture at its core is called the Sozoku System, and it is generally accepted that the Sozoku system and Hoken system were closely related to each other.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These relationships based on the blood family community with primogeniture at its core is called the Sozoku System, and it is generally accepted that the Sozoku system and Hoken system were closely related to each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>しかし、邑制国家の実態および宗族制度がいつごろ一般的となったかについては定説がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no established theories for what Mura-based states were and when Sozoku system became common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are no established theories for what Mura-based states were and when the Sozoku system became common.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are no established theories for what Mura-based states were and when the Sozoku system became common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>このような周の封建制度を西洋的なフューダリズムと比較することはよくおこなわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such Hoken system in Zhou is often compared with the Western feudalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a Hoken system in Zhou is often compared with Western feudalism.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a Hoken system in Zhou is often compared with Western feudalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>たとえばマルクス主義的な発展段階論においては周代中国を奴隷社会であるか古代荘園社会であるかが論争となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, in the development stage theory of Marx, it is argued whether China in the Zhou period was slavery society or the ancient manor-based society. therefore, it is not easy to settle the dispute.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, in the development stage theory of Marx, it is argued whether China in the Zhou period was a slavery society or an ancient manor-based society, therefore, it is not easy to settle the dispute.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, in the development stage theory of Marx, it is argued whether China in the Zhou period was a slavery society or an ancient manor-based society, therefore, it is not easy to settle the dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これは周代におこなわれたという井田制の解釈と密接に関連しており、実在を疑う向きさえある井田制の性格があまりはっきりしない以上決着をつけることは容易でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is closely related to the interpretation of Jinghu system which was applied in the Zhou period. The nature of Iden system, whose existence is questionable, is unclear,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　　　定訳不明（漢字を中国語読みにしています）　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is closely related to the interpretation of the Jinghu system which was applied in the Zhou period and the nature of the Iden system, whose existence is questionable, is unclear.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is closely related to the interpretation of the Jinghu system which was applied in the Zhou period and the nature of the Iden system, whose existence is questionable, is unclear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>春秋・戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chunqiu and Zhanguo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chunqiu and Zhanguo period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chunqiu and Zhanguo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>宗族組織の解体とともに中国的な封建制度が崩壊していったことは、おおむね認められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is generally accepted that the Chinese Hoken system collapsed with the breakdown of Sozoku organization</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is generally accepted that the Chinese Hoken system collapsed with the breakdown of Sozoku organization</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is generally accepted that the Chinese Hoken system collapsed with the breakdown of Sozoku organization</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>宗族制度がいつごろ活期を迎えたかについては定説がないが、春秋あるいは戦国初期のころには原始共同体が完全に解体され、邑を中心として貴族支配が確立されていたとする見方が一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no accepted theory on when the Sozoku system reached the zenith, but the generally accepted view is that the system was broken down in Chunqiu or Zhangguo period and the rule by nobility was established with Mura at its core.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no accepted theory on when the Sozoku system reached its zenith, but the generally accepted view is that the system broke down in the Chunqiu or Zhangguo period and rule by nobility was established with Mura at its core.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no accepted theory on when the Sozoku system reached its zenith, but the generally accepted view is that the system broke down in the Chunqiu or Zhangguo period and rule by nobility was established with Mura at its core.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>戦国中期頃から核家族の存在が確認されはじめ、客や遊侠といった誠実関係を中心とした支配-被支配の関係が見出されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nuclear families were confirmed in the middle of the Zhangguo period and rulers and subjects relations base on sincere relationships such as Ke and Youxia.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明（漢字を中国語読みにしています）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nuclear families were confirmed in the middle of the Zhangguo period and rulers and subjects relations base on sincere relationships such as Ke and Youxia.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nuclear families were confirmed in the middle of the Zhangguo period and rulers and subjects relations base on sincere relationships such as Ke and Youxia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>宗族的関係も儀礼を中心としたものに変質したとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory is that the Sozoku-based relations became ceremonial.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory is that the Sozoku-based relations became ceremonial.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory is that the Sozoku-based relations became ceremonial.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="61">
<j>また春秋時代には会盟政治と呼ばれる政治形態が出現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Chunqiu period, a political form called Kaimei-seiji (politics by pledge of feudal lords) emerged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Chunqiu period, a political form called Kaimei-seiji (politics by pledge of feudal lords) emerged.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Chunqiu period, a political form called Kaimei-seiji (politics by pledge of feudal lords) emerged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>これは覇者とよばれる盟主的国家によってほかの封建国家に誠実関係を築くものであるが、従来の封建関係以上に強力な支配-被支配を生み出すものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the political system, a leading state called Hasha (hegemon) builds sincere relationships with other Hoken states, which is thought to produce more rigid rulers-and-subjects relations than that of conventional Hoken relations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the political system, a leading state called Hasha (hegemony) builds sincere relationships with other Hoken states, which is thought to produce more rigid rulers-and-subjects relations than that of conventional Hoken relations.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the political system, a leading state called Hasha (hegemony) builds sincere relationships with other Hoken states, which is thought to produce more rigid rulers-and-subjects relations than that of conventional Hoken relations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>会盟の誓約は神の権威を借りて会盟参加者に命令をできる関係を築くものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the oath of Kaimei establishes relations with members of Kaimei, under which the leader can give orders to the members by taking advantage of god&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the oath of Kaimei establishes relations with members of Kaimei, under which the leader can give orders to the members by taking advantage of god&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the oath of Kaimei establishes relations with members of Kaimei, under which the leader can give orders to the members by taking advantage of god&apos;s authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし覇者の性格については定説がなく、あらたに台頭した後進地域の指導者あるいは異民族支配者であるとする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there is no established view on the nature of Hasha, and according to one theory, Hasha means a local leader or an ethnic ruler.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there is no established view on the nature of Hasha, and according to one theory, Hasha means a local leader or an ethnic ruler.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there is no established view on the nature of Hasha, and according to one theory, Hasha means a local leader or an ethnic ruler.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>五覇については五行思想との関連から戦国時代になってから形成されたものであるという見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another version has it that Goha (five strong feudal lords in the Chunqiu period) was formed in the Zhangguo period due to the connection with Gogyo shiso (Five Elements Theory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another version has it that Goha (five strong feudal lords in the Chunqiu period) was formed in the Zhangguo period due to the connection with Gogyo shiso (Five Elements Theory).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another version has it that Goha (five strong feudal lords in the Chunqiu period) was formed in the Zhangguo period due to the connection with Gogyo shiso (Five Elements Theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>秦以後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Qin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Qin</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Qin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>戦国末期には宗族組織はほとんど崩壊あるいは変質していたため、諸侯は支配地の住民を宗族に基づいて支配するのではなく、個別人身的な支配関係を構築していったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the end of the Zhangguo period, Sozoku organizations collapsed or changed its nature, therefore, lords started to build rulers-and-subjects relations with people in their domain individually instead of ruling them based on Sozoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the end of the Zhangguo period, Sozoku organizations collapsed or changed their nature, therefore, lords started to build rulers-and-subjects relations with people in their domain individually instead of ruling them based on Sozoku.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the end of the Zhangguo period, Sozoku organizations collapsed or changed their nature, therefore, lords started to build rulers-and-subjects relations with people in their domain individually instead of ruling them based on Sozoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>封建制度は意味をなさなくなり、郡県制に置き換えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoken system became meaningless and was replaced by Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hoken system became meaningless and was replaced by the Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hoken system became meaningless and was replaced by the Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>秦の始皇帝は中国を統一すると全国全てを郡と県に分け、中国全土を完全な中央集権的郡県制で支配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After unifying China, Shikotei, the first Qin Emperor, divided the state into gun and ken, and ruled the whole state with the complete centralized system of gun and ken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After unifying China, Shikotei, the first Qin Emperor, divided the state into gun and ken, and ruled the whole state with the completely centralized system of gun and ken.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After unifying China, Shikotei, the first Qin Emperor, divided the state into gun and ken, and ruled the whole state with the completely centralized system of gun and ken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>その秦を滅ぼした前漢では郡県を布く地方と新たに諸侯王を封建する地方とに分ける郡国制を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Former Han, which overthrew the Qin Dynasty, adopted Gun Koku system which separated places of newly appointed lords from places using Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Han, which overthrew the Qin Dynasty, adopted the Gun Koku system which separated places of newly appointed lords from places using the Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Han, which overthrew the Qin Dynasty, adopted the Gun Koku system which separated places of newly appointed lords from places using the Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>当初郡国制では諸侯に貨幣鋳造権や軍事権が認められていたが、徐々にこのような権力は回収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Gun Ken system, the right of coinage and the military right were granted at first, but those rights were gradually forfeited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Gun Ken system, the right of coinage and military right were granted at first, but those rights were gradually forfeited.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Gun Ken system, the right of coinage and military right were granted at first, but those rights were gradually forfeited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>後漢時代にはすでに恩給と変わらないものとなっており、それも形骸化して、爵位だけを授ける封爵制として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Later Han period, it virtually became a pension system, turning into a formality, and continued as a system to grant peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Later Han period, it virtually became a pension system, turning into a formality, and continued as a system to grant peerage.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Later Han period, it virtually became a pension system, turning into a formality, and continued as a system to grant peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="72">
<j>周の礼制を規範とする儒教では周の封建制を重視するが、官僚となり中央集権政治を担うようになった儒者たちにとって大きな矛盾をはらみ、たびたび封建論あるいは郡県論として論議された（ここでいう封建制・郡県制は歴史学上の実際のものではなく儒教思想上の理念として語られたものである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confucianism, which follows the example of the Li system of Zhou, put importance on Hoken system of Zhou, but for confucianist who began to take part in the centralized politics, hoken system was very contradictory and was often discussed in the form of essay on Hoken or Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confucianism, which follows the example of the Li system of Zhou, put importance on the Hoken system of Zhou, but for confucianists who began to take part in centralized politics, the hoken system was very contradictory and was often discussed in the form of essay on the Hoken or Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confucianism, which follows the example of the Li system of Zhou, put importance on the Hoken system of Zhou, but for confucianists who began to take part in centralized politics, the hoken system was very contradictory and was often discussed in the form of essay on the Hoken or Gun Ken system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>特に明の東林党や遺老の学が有名であり、そこでは官僚が責任者として自発的に地方統治を行うための制度として封建制が議論された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, Donglin movement and Iro no gaku in the Min period are famous, where hoken system was discussed as a system for bureaucrats to voluntarily govern local areas as the responsible.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, the Donglin movement and Iro no gaku in the Min period are famous, where the hoken system was discussed as a system for bureaucrats to voluntarily govern local areas as their responsibility.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, the Donglin movement and Iro no gaku in the Min period are famous, where the hoken system was discussed as a system for bureaucrats to voluntarily govern local areas as their responsibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>顧炎武は「封建の意を郡県に寓す」という郡県制のなかに封建制を組み込ませ、地方分権型の政治体制を主張している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ko Enbu incorporates the Hoken system into Gun Ken system as the saying goes &apos;Using the gist of Hoken as a pretext of Gun ken&apos;, advocating the centralized political form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ko Enbu incorporates the Hoken system into the Gun Ken system as the saying goes &apos;Using the gist of Hoken as a pretext of Gun ken,&apos; advocating the centralized political form.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ko Enbu incorporates the Hoken system into the Gun Ken system as the saying goes &apos;Using the gist of Hoken as a pretext of Gun ken,&apos; advocating the centralized political form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 JAnDbot(id:66507), ターミネーター(id:294793), Straysheep(id:42448), BOTarate(id:185620), Nnh(id:474), MelancholieBot(id:31942), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Tuny(id:90002), Greenland4(id:114494), OKBot(id:143139), Yuu6676(id:86667), Mantis(id:17383), らりた(id:1327), Hermeneus(id:380), SGreen(id:20681), Rei-bot(id:94097), Hasi(id:17934), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Shimoxx(id:9332), 竹麦魚(id:11012), FlaBot(id:30804), Mig(id:3428), Mnd(id:15140), けふこえて(id:17107), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Juyukichi(id:16958), Complex01(id:10454), S kitahashi(id:10307), ビック(id:11930), コータ(id:22095), Setomanko(id:3051), BodhisattvaBot(id:185411), 樒(id:35770), Alecs.bot(id:194707), SuisuiBot(id:10165), R28Bot(id:177951), Nerimaman(id:61206), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 伏儀(id:142093), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Louperibot(id:128971), Kanbun(id:37114), Bokka7568(id:275377), SieBot(id:126695), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>