<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>油小路事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aburanokoji Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aburanokoji Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aburanokoji Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>油小路事件（あぶらのこうじじけん）は、新選組参謀・伊東甲子太郎らが暗殺された事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an incident in which Kashitaro ITO, a staff officer of the Shinsengumi, and others were assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An incident in which Kashitaro ITO, a staff officer of the Shinsengumi, and others were assassinated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An incident in which Kashitaro ITO, a staff officer of the Shinsengumi (a group who guarded Kyoto during the end of Tokugawa Shogunate), and others were assassinated.</e>
<cmt>新撰組の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>新選組最後の内部抗争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the last of a feud within the Shinsengumi organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the last feud within the Shinsengumi organization.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the last feud within the Shinsengumi organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>伊東甲子太郎の暗殺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assassination of Kashitaro ITO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Assassination of Kashitaro ITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Assassination of Kashitaro ITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>慶応3年3月10日 (旧暦)（1867年4月14日）、新選組を離脱し御陵衛士（高台寺党）を結成した伊東甲子太郎は勤王倒幕運動に勤しみ、薩摩と通謀して近藤勇を暗殺しようとたくらんでいる事が、新選組が間諜として潜り込ませていた斎藤一によって明らかとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 14, 1867 (March 10 according to the old calendar), a plan by Kashitaro ITO, who broke away from the Shinsengumi and organized the Goryo Eji (a splinter group of the Shinsengumi) and led a movement to revere for the emperor and overthrow the shogunate, to assassinate Isamu KONDO (head of the Shinsengumi) together with Satsuma was discovered by a spy that was sent from the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 14, 1867 (March 10 according to the old calendar), a plan by Kashitaro ITO(who broke away from the Shinsengumi and organized the Goryo Eji (a splinter group of the Shinsengumi) and led a movement to revere the emperor and overthrow the shogunate) to assassinate Isamu KONDO (head of the Shinsengumi) together with Satsuma was outed by a spy that was sent from the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 14, 1867 (March 10 according to the old calendar), a plan by Kashitaro ITO (who broke away from the Shinsengumi and organized the Goryo-eji (guards of Imperial mausoleums, also known as Kodaiji-to) and led a movement to revere the emperor and overthrow the shogunate) to assassinate Isami KONDO (head of the Shinsengumi) together with Satsuma was outed by Hajime SAITO, a spy that was sent from the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>Isamu→Isami御陵衛士の定訳斎藤一、高台寺党、追記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>ただし、当時の伊東の書簡は対話を重んじるものばかりで、伊東自身も人を斬った記録が油小路事件以外には無く、さらには近藤勇を暗殺しようとしたものがないため、近藤暗殺計画自体が存在しなかったとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, documents left behind by Ito talked only about the importance of communication, and there is no record of him killing anyone, other than during the Aburanokoji Incident, nor are there any records of him trying to assassinate Isami KONDO, which led to the theory that plans for the assassination never existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, documents left behind by Ito only placed importance on a conversation, and there is no record of him killing anyone, other than during the Aburanokoji Incident, nor are there any records of him trying to assassinate Isami KONDO, which led to the theory that plans for the assassination never existed.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, documents left behind by Ito only placed importance on a conversation, and there is no record of him killing anyone, other than during the Aburanokoji Incident, nor are there any records of him trying to assassinate Isami KONDO, which led to the theory that plans for the assassination never existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>同年11月18日 (旧暦)（12月13日）、近藤勇は資金の用立て・国事の相談があるとの口実で七条の妾宅に伊東を招いて酒宴を張った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 13 of the same year (November 18 according to the old calendar), Isami KONDO asked Ito over to his mistress&apos; home in Shichijo, to discuss a loan and national affairs, entertaining Ito with alcohol.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 13 of the same year (November 18 according to the old calendar), Isami KONDO asked Ito over to his mistress&apos; home in Shichijo, to discuss a loan and national affairs, and served Ito alcohol.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 13 of the same year (November 18 according to the old calendar), Isami KONDO asked Ito over to his mistress&apos; home in Shichijo, to discuss a loan and national affairs, and served Ito alcohol.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>帰路に大石鍬次郎らが待ち伏せて槍を以って伊東を暗殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On his way home, Ito was killed by Kuwajiro OISHI in an ambush.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On his way home, Ito was killed by Kuwajiro OISHI in an ambush.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On his way home, Ito was killed by Kuwajiro OISHI in an ambush.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>伊東は深手であったが一太刀敵に浴びせ、「奸賊ばら」と叫んで絶命したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ito received a fatal wound, but he was able to deliver a blow to his assassin and died calling out &quot;Kanzokubara (traitor)&quot;</e>
<cmt>Kanzokubaraは「自分の都合で、同じ主義主張の仲間を簡単に裏切る連中」と言う意味らしいのですが、これを全訳すると長くなるので、補足として裏切り者だけを入れています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ito received a fatal wound, but he was able to deliver a blow to his assassin and died calling out &quot;Kanzokubara (traitor)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ito received a fatal wound, but he was able to deliver a blow to his assassin and died calling out &quot;Kanzokubara (traitor)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>御陵衛士の粛清</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Purge of the Goryo Eji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Purge of the Goryo Eji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Purge of the Goryo-eji</e>
<cmt>Goryo Eji→Goryo-eji</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>新選組は油小路通七条通の辻に伊東の遺骸を放置し、その周りに伏せ、遺体を引き取りにきた同志をまとめて粛清しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsengumi abandoned Ito&apos;s corpse on the streets of Aburanokoji, hid themselves so that they could kill all the other members of Ito&apos;s group who would be coming to collect Ito&apos;s body.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsengumi abandoned Ito&apos;s corpse on the streets of Aburanokoji, hiding themselves so that they could kill all the other members of Ito&apos;s group who would be coming to collect Ito&apos;s body.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsengumi abandoned Ito&apos;s corpse on the streets of Aburanokoji, hiding themselves so that they could kill all the other members of Ito&apos;s group who would be coming to collect Ito&apos;s body.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>遺骸を引き取りにきた同志は、藤堂平助・篠原泰之進・鈴木三樹三郎・服部武雄・毛内有之助・加納道之助・富山弥兵衛の7名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seven Goryo Eji members coming to pick up the body were Heisuke TODO, Tainoshin SHINOHARA, Mikisaburo SUZUKI, Takeo HATTORI, Arinosuke MONAI, Michinosuke KANO, and Yahei TOYAMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seven Goryo Eji members who came to pick up the body were Heisuke TODO, Tainoshin SHINOHARA, Mikisaburo SUZUKI, Takeo HATTORI, Arinosuke MONAI, Michinosuke KANO, and Yahei TOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seven Goryo Eji members who came to pick up the body were Heisuke TODO, Tainoshin SHINOHARA, Mikisaburo SUZUKI, Takeo HATTORI, Arinosuke MONAI, Michinosuke KANO, and Yahei TOYAMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この待ち伏せによって、新選組結盟以来の生え抜き隊士で元八番隊組長を務めた藤堂平助のほかに、服部武雄・毛内有之助の3名が討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three of them were killed in the ambush; Heisuke TODO, who had been the first member of the Shinsengumi and was the former leader of the eighth squad, Takeo HATTORI and Arinosuke MONAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three of them were killed in the ambush; Heisuke TODO, who had been the first member of the Shinsengumi and was the former leader of the eighth squad, Takeo HATTORI and Arinosuke MONAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three of them were killed in the ambush; Heisuke TODO, who was an original member of the Shinsengumi and was the former leader of the eighth squad, Takeo HATTORI and Arinosuke MONAI.</e>
<cmt>had been→was「生え抜き」→an original member</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>藤堂に関しては、試衛館以来の同志である永倉新八・原田左之助が逃がそうと試みたものの、うまくゆかず他の隊士に斬られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpatchi NAGAKURA and Sanosuke HARADA, who had been friends with Todo since they trained together at the Shieikan training hall, tried to save him by letting him get away, but Todo was killed by another member of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpatchi NAGAKURA and Sanosuke HARADA, who had been friends with Todo since they trained together at the Shieikan training hall, tried to save him by letting him get away, but Todo was killed by another member of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpatchi NAGAKURA and Sanosuke HARADA, who had been friends with Todo since they trained together at the Shieikan training hall, tried to save him by letting him get away, but Todo was killed by another member of the Shinsengumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>毛内有之助の遺体は五体バラバラで無惨だったらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Arinosuke MONAI was cut into five pieces and the corpse was in a decrepit state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Arinosuke MONAI was cut into five pieces, leaving the corpse in a horrifying state.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Arinosuke MONAI was cut into pieces, leaving the corpse in a horrifying state.</e>
<cmt>「五体バラバラ」は five pieces とは限らないと思い, pieces としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>服部武雄は隊内でも相当な二刀流の使い手として鳴らしていたため、服部の孤軍奮闘は鬼気迫るものがあったというが、最後は服部の刀が折れたスキを狙って原田左之助が繰り出した槍によって、落命したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeo HATTORI was famous as being skillful in using two swords at once, and his bloodcurdling air overwhelmed the men he fought against; however, he was killed by Sanosuke HARADA&apos;s spear when his sword broke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeo HATTORI was famous as being skillful in using two swords at once, and his bloodcurdling presence overwhelmed the men he fought against; however, he was killed by Sanosuke HARADA&apos;s spear when his sword broke.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeo HATTORI was famous as being skillful in using two swords at once, and his bloodcurdling presence of fighting alone overwhelmed the men he fought against; however, he was killed by Sanosuke HARADA&apos;s spear when his sword broke.</e>
<cmt>「孤軍奮闘」追記して書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="16">
<j>残りの同志は逃げ延び、薩摩藩邸にかくまわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other members escaped and found shelter in the residence of Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other members escaped and found shelter in the residence of Satsuma Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other members escaped and found shelter in the residence of Satsuma Clan.</e>
<cmt>Domain→Clan</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="17">
<j>伊東らの遺体はしばらく放置してあしてあったが、光縁寺に埋葬したあと戒光寺に改葬された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their bodies were left for some time, and later buried at Koenji Temple and reburied at Kaikoji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their bodies were left for some time, and later buried at Koenji Temple and reburied at Kaikoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their bodies were left for some time, and later buried at Koenji Temple and reburied at Kaikoji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="18">
<j>後日譚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tale told at a later date</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tale told at a later date</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tale told at a later date</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1ヶ月後の12月18日 (旧暦)、篠原ら御陵衛士の生き残りは伏見街道の民家に伏せ、二条城からの帰りの近藤勇を狙撃、右肩に重症を負わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One month later on December 18 (by the old calendar), the remaining Goryo Eji, led by Shinohara, hid in a private residence along the Fushimi-kaido and attacked Isami KONDO on his way back from Nijo Castle and Kondo&apos;s right shoulder was seriously injured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One month later on December 18 (by the old calendar), the remaining Goryo Eji, led by Shinohara, hid in a private residence along the Fushimi-kaido and attacked Isami KONDO on his way back from Nijo Castle and Kondo&apos;s right shoulder was seriously injured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One month later on December 18 (old calendar), the remaining Goryo-eji including Shinohara, hid in a private residence along the Fushimi-kaido Road and sniped at Isami KONDO on his way back from Nijo-jo Castle and Kondo&apos;s right shoulder was seriously injured.</e>
<cmt>by the old calendar→old calendarGoryo Eji→Goryo-eji led by→including 街道にRoad追記狙撃なのでattacked→snipedNijo→Nijo-jo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、その後の戊辰戦争時、劣勢となった近藤勇は越谷で大久保大和と称して新政府軍に出頭したが、新政府軍に加わっていた加納道之助に正体を看破されて捕縛され、ついに斬首となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, during the Boshin Civil War, Isami KONDO, finding himself in an inferior position, joined the new government troop under the alias of Yamato OKUBO at Koshigaya; however, his identity was revealed by Michinosuke KANO and he was captured and beheaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, during the Boshin Civil War, Isami KONDO, finding himself in an inferior position, joined the new government troops under the alias of Yamato OKUBO at Koshigaya; however, his identity was revealed by Michinosuke KANO and he was captured and beheaded.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, during the Boshin Civil War, Isami KONDO, finding himself in an inferior position, turned himsel in the new government troops under the alias of Yamato OKUBO at Koshigaya; however, his identity was revealed by Michinosuke KANO who had joined the troops, and he was captured and beheaded.</e>
<cmt>「出頭」ですので、joined→turned himself in「新政府軍に加わっていた」追記。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Hideyuki(id:9577), 講師(id:71860), Nnh(id:474), 下総大納言(id:43461), Πrate(id:11329), 土方　誠(id:3651), Maakun(id:16735), パチンコ藤澤(id:125672), Daichikyu(id:176596), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>