<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>受領</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuryo (The Head of The Provincial Governors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuryo (The Head of The Provincial Governors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zuryo (The Head of The Provincial Governors)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>受領（ずりょう）とは、地方官の呼称に関する日本史用語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zuryo (受領) is a term used in the history of Japan related to a name of provincial governors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zuryo (受領) is a term used in the history of Japan related to a name of provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Zuryo&quot; (受領) is a Japanese historical terminology referring to provincial governors.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Zuryo にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>本稿にて詳述。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Details will be described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Details will be described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Details are described below.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>受領（じゅりょう）とは、物やサービスを受けること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juryo (受領) means to receive an article or a service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Juryo (受領) means to receive an article or a service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Juryo&quot; (受領) is a term referring to the receipt of goods or services.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Juryo にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法律用語として受領遅滞等の局面で用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is used as a legal term in such a situation as a delay of receipt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is used as a legal term to refer to situations involving delays in receipt.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is used as a legal term referring to situations such as delayed deliveries.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>まれに、1.に引きずられ「ずりょう」と読む人があるが、一般に用いられる「じゅりょう」と読み分ける必要性も根拠もない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While some people may pronounce it &quot;zuryo&quot; dragged by 1., there is no need or reason to distinguish from the common pronunciation &quot;juryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While some people may pronounce it &quot;zuryo&quot; dragged by 1., there is no need or reason to distinguish it from the common pronunciation &quot;juryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some people read it as &quot;zuryo&quot;, influenced by the reading of the number 1 above, there is no need or reason to be distinguished from the common reading &quot;juryo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。“zuryo,” “juryo.”半角クォーテーションに修正し、カンマ、ピリオドをそれぞれクォーテーション外に移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>受領（ずりょう）とは、国司四等官のうち、現地に赴任して行政責任を負う筆頭者を平安時代以後に呼んだ呼称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of kokushi shitokan (four officials of the provincial governor) dispatched to an appointed province with administrative responsibility were called zuryo in Heian period and later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of kokushi shitokan (four officials of the provincial governor) dispatched to an appointed province with administrative responsibility were called zuryo during the Heian period and onwards.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period and onwards, &quot;zuryo&quot; referred to the head of kokushi shitokan (four officials of the provincial governor), who was dispatched to an appointed province with administrative responsibility.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。zuryo にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>通常長官である守（かみ）、及び権守（ごんのかみ）であるが、親王任国の上野国、常陸国、上総国など守、権守が現地赴任しない国では次官の介（すけ）、権介（ごんのすけ）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The zuryo was usually a kami (守, governor) or a gon no kami (権守, provisional governor) being a kami (長官, director), but it was a suke (介, vice governor of provincial offices) or a Gon no suke (権介, provisional vice governor) being a suke (次官, assistant director), in shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) where the kami or the gon no kami was not dispatched like Kozuke Province, Hitachi Province, and Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>読みが同じ「かみ」と「すけ」があるので、漢字を並記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The zuryo was usually a kami (守, governor) or a gon no kami (権守, provisional governor) being a kami (長官, director), but it was a suke (介, vice governor of provincial offices) or a Gon no suke (権介, provisional vice governor) being a suke (次官, assistant director), in shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes) where the kami or the gon no kami was not dispatched like Kozuke Province, Hitachi Province, and Kazusa Province.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zuryo was usually a position taken by a kami (長官, director) who was also a kami (守, governor) or a gon no kami (権守, provisional governor), but in shinno ninkoku (provinces whose gubernatorial posts were reserved as sinecures for imperial princes, and where the kami or the gon no kami was not dispatched), such as the provinces of Kozuke, Hitachi, and Kazusa, the position was fulfilled by a jikan (次官, assistant director) who was also a suke (介, vice governor of provincial offices) or a Gon no suke (権介, provisional vice governor).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>おおよそ四位、五位どまりの下級貴族である諸大夫がこの任に当てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo) being lower-ranking nobles in shii (fourth rank) or goi (fifth rank) at most were appointed to this position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo) being lower-ranking nobles in shii (fourth rank) or goi (fifth rank) at most were appointed to this position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lower-ranking aristocrats called Shodaibu, who belonged to no more than the shii (fourth rank)or goi (fifth rank), were usually appointed to this position.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>彼らの補佐官を務める掾（じょう）、目（さかん）は任用（にんよう）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jo (secretary of provincial offices) and sakan (clerk of provincial offices) that served them as assistants were called ninyo (low-ranking &quot;commissioned&quot; provincial officers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jo (secretary of provincial offices) and sakan (clerk of provincial offices) who served as assistants to the Shodaibu were called ninyo (low-ranking &quot;commissioned&quot; provincial officers).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jo (secretary of provincial offices) and sakan (clerk of provincial offices) who served as assistants to the Shodaibu were called ninyo (low-ranking &quot;commissioned&quot; provincial officers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、任官されながら実際に任国に赴かず官職に伴う給付だけを受ける国司を遥任と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A kokushi (provincial governor) just receiving benefits for the government post without going to the place of appointment despite the appointment is called yonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A kokushi (provincial governor) who simply received benefits according to the government post without needing to go to the place of appointment despite the appointment was called yonin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &quot;yonin&quot; was a kokushi (provincial governor) who received all the benefits as the governmental officer without having ever gone to the place of appointment.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。遙任 yonin にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>9世紀中期～10世紀頃になると、従来の律令制（編戸制・班田制など）による統治に限界が見られるようになり、中央政府は租税収入を確保するため、社会の実情に即した国制改革を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid 9th century to the 10th century, a limitation to the conventional administration based on the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) (henko-sei (the organization of the people), handen-sei (Ritsuryo land-allotment system)) began to be visible, and the central government promoted a reformation of the national system to match the actual society in order to maintain the tax revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid 9th century to the 10th century, a limitation on the conventional administration based on the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) (henko-sei (the organization of the people), handen-sei (Ritsuryo land-allotment system)) began to be visible, and the central government promoted a reform of the national system to match the actual society in order to maintain the tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the mid 9th century to the 10th century, the conventional administration based on the ritsuryo system (such as henko-sei, the organization of the citizens, and handen-sei, the ritsuryo land-allotment system) faced its organizational limit, and the central government promoted a nation-wide reform of the system to reflect the actual social situations in order to maintain the level of the tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>編戸制はthe organization of the citizensとしました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その改革は、地方官（国司）へ租税収取や軍事などの権限を大幅に委譲するというもので、国司は中央へ確実に租税を上納する代わりに、自由かつ強力に国内を支配する権利を得たのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reformation was to transfer a great part of the power of imposing and collecting taxes and the military power to the local official (kokushi), by which the kokushi became eligible for freely and strongly govern his province in exchange for making sure to pay the tax to the central government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reform involved transfering a great part of the power of imposing and collecting taxes and the military power to the local official (kokushi), by which the kokushi became eligible to freely and strongly govern his province in exchange that he ensured that he paid taxes to the central government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reform involved transferring a great part of the power to impose and collect taxes as well as the military power to the local officials (kokushi); in return for the secure payment of taxes to the central government, the kokushi gained the freedom to govern the province at his will.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>国司は、国内の国衙領（公田）を名田へ再編成し、当時台頭していた富豪層へ名田の経営と租税徴収を請け負わせることで、租税を確実に収取するようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kokushi rearranged kokugaryo (field administered directly by a ruler) in the province to form myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder), and made sure to impose and collect the taxes by contracting management of the myoden and tax collection to the rich class rising at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kokushi rearranged kokugaryo (field administered directly by a ruler) in the province to form myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder), and ensured that taxes were imposed and collected by contracting management of the myoden and carrying out tax collection towards the rising rich.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kokushi reorganized the kokugaryo (public fields administered directly by a ruler) in the province into the myoden (rice field lots in charge of a nominal holder), and by entrusting the myoden and tax management to the newly-influential wealthy class, they ensured the collection of taxes.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この租税収取システムが軌道に乗ると、国司は現地へ赴任する必要がなくなり、特に上位官である守の多くは遥任するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the system of imposing and collecting the taxes got on the right track, the kokushi did not have to go to the province anymore, and especially most of the kami in the higher rank became the yonin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the system of imposing and collecting taxes finally was on track, the kokushi no longer needed to go to the province, and most of the kami in the higher rank became the yonin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the system of tax-management apparently became successful, the kokushi, and especially the higher ranking kami, was no longer required to be present in the appointed province</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>すると、現地赴任する国司の筆頭者に、様々な責任やそれに伴う権限が集中するようになり、事実上の国衙行政の最高責任者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various responsibilities and accompanying powers were then concentrated in the head of the kokushi actually dispatched to the province, who became a virtually highest officer in the kokuga government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various responsibilities and accompanying powers were then concentrated in the head of the kokushi actually dispatched to the province, who became virtually the highest ranked officer in the kokuga government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the kokushi, who was actually dispatched to the appointed province, started to assume various responsibilities as well as powers, which made him virtually the highest ranked officer in the kokuga administration.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>当時、国司交替の際に、後任の国司が、適正な事務引継を受けたことを証明する解由状という文書を前任の国司へ発給する定めとなっており、実際に現地で解由状を受領する国司を「受領」と呼ぶようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a provision at the time that, when the kokushi changes, the successor should issue a document called geyujo (discharge certificates) to his predecessor, and the kokushi that actually received the geyujo was later called &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a provision at the time that, when the kokushi changes, the successor should issue a document called geyujo (discharge certificates) to his predecessor, and the kokushi that actually received the geyujo was later called &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a provision at the time that, when the kokushi changes, the successor issues a document called geyujo (discharge certificates) to his predecessor; the kokushi who received the geyujo in the province was then called &quot;zuryo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。 “zuryo.” のダブルクォーテーションを半角にし、ピリオドをクォーテーションの外に出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これが「受領」という呼称の起源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the origin of the name &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the origin of the name &quot;zuryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the origin of the name &apos;zuryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に※&apos;zuryo.&apos; FBにはありませんが、ダブルクォーテーションに統一して &quot;zuryo&quot;. とピリオドをダブルクォーテーションから出した方がよろしいかと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>受領が強大な権限を得た一方で、補佐官である任用たちは権限を奪われ、受領の私的従者のように使役されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the zuryo retained the strong power, the ninyo as assistants lost the power and they were used like a private servant of the zuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the zuryo retained most of the power, the ninyo as assistants lost power and were used like a private servant to the zuryo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the zuryo retained most of the power, the ninyo, who were assistants to the zuryo, lost their influences and were treated like private servants to the zuryo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>こうした状況に不満を募らせた任用の中には、現地の有力者である富豪層（田堵層）と結んで受領を襲撃する者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the ninyo who aggravated complaints about the situation attacked against the zuryo in collusion with the rich class (tato class) that was the local major force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the ninyo who carried out complaints about the situation attacked the zuryo in collusion with the rich class (tato class) that was a local major force.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the ninyo who had been aggravating a grievance, attacked the zuryo by collaborating with the locally influential wealthy class of tato.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>9世紀末から10世紀初頭にかけて紛争の火種となる任用たちの現地赴任は行われなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late 9th century to the early 10th century, the dispatch of the ninyo, which caused the conflict, was terminated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late 9th century to the early 10th century, the dispatch of the ninyo, which caused the conflict, was terminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the late 9th century to the early 10th century, the ninyo, who were more likely to cause conflicts, were no longer employed to be dispatched to the provinces.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>受領のみが任国に赴任し、京から伴った私的な側近を目代に任命し、また現地の有力富豪層を在庁官人に任命して国衙の実務に当たるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the zuryo was dispatched to the province and did the practical business of the kokuga by appointing his private aides brought from Kyoto to mokudai (deputy kokushi, or a deputy provincial governor) and appointing the local major rich class to zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the zuryo was dispatched to the province and carried out the practical business of the kokuga by appointing his private aides brought from Kyoto to mokudai (deputy kokushi, or a deputy provincial governor) and appointed the local major rich class to zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zuryo alone was dispatched to the province and carried out the practical business as the kokuga by appointing his private aides brought from Kyoto to the post of mokudai (deputy kokushi, or a deputy provincial governor); he also employed the locally influential and wealthy people as the zaichokanjin (the local officials).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>受領は、その強大な権限を背景に、莫大な蓄財を行うことも可能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against the backdrop of its great powers, the zuryo was able to store immense property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With his immense power, the zuryo was able to store immense property.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By utilizing his immense influence, the zuryo was able to accumulate immense wealth.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>事実、受領になると巨額の富を得ることができたため、国司に任命されるために人事権に強い影響を及ぼしうる摂関家へ取り入る者が後を絶たなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the zuryo was actually able to obtain the immense property, it is said that an endless stream of people ingratiated themselves to sekke (line of regents and advisers), who had a great influence over the personnel issues, to become the kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the zuryo was actually able to obtain an immense amount of property, it is said that an endless stream of people ingratiated themselves to sekke (line of regents and advisers), who had a great influence over personnel issues, to become the kokushi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, since the zuryo was in the position to accumulate an immense amount of wealth, it is said that an endless stream of people ingratiated themselves to the sekkanke (the aristocratic families of regents and advisers), which had a great influence over personnel issues, in order to attain the post of the kokushi.</e>
<cmt>摂関家はthe sekkanke (the aristocratic families of regents and advisers)と訳しました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、蓄財によって任国へ根を生やした受領の中には、任期後、そのまま任国へ土着した者も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, some of the zuryo settled in the appointed province by storing the property remained there even after termination of their term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, some of the zuryo settled in the appointed province by storing property that remained there even after termination of their term.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, many zuryo, who accumulated wealth, remained and settled themselves in the appointed province after termination of their term.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>また10世紀ごろから、国内の公田を名田へ再編成し、田堵に名田経営と租税納入を請け負わせる負名体制へと移行していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 10th century and later, the field administered directly by a ruler in the province was rearranged to form the myoden, and the local tax manager system was transferred to fumyo system, in which the tato undertook the management of the myoden and the tax payment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 10th century onwards, the field administered directly by a ruler in the province was rearranged to form the myoden, and the local tax manager system was transferred to the fumyo system, in which the tato undertook the management of the myoden and tax payment.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 10th century onwards, the koden (the field administered directly by a ruler) in the province was reorganized as the myoden, and the fumyo system, in which the tato undertook the management of the myoden and tax, became more and more common.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>各地域の実情に合わせて、各名田ごとに異なる税率・税目などが設定されることがあり、これは「先例」として各国司と田堵負名の間で固定化しつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tax rate and the tax items may have varied among the myoden depending on the local conditions, which became fixed as a &quot;precedent&quot; between the kokushi and the tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tax rate and the tax items may have varied among the myoden depending on the local conditions, which became fixed as a &quot;precedent&quot; between the kokushi and the tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were instances in which the different tax rate and tax items were decided for each myoden depending on the local conditions; such cases came to be accepted as &quot;precedents&quot; between the kokushi and the tato fumyo (cultivator/tax manager).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。“precedents”　のダブルクォーテーションを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>しかしこの先例は、国司・田堵負名の間の個人的な約定であるともいえたため、新たに赴任した受領が前任者の先例を無視して、規定どおりの租税を田堵負名らに賦課することもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the precedent could be aust a personal agreement between the kokushi and tato fumyo, sometimes a new zuryo ignored the precedent made by the predecessor to impose a prescribed tax to the tato fumyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the precedent could be just a personal agreement between the kokushi and tato fumyo, sometimes a new zuryo ignored the precedent made by the predecessor to impose a prescribed tax to the tato fumyo.</e>
<cmt>Edited for spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since such precedents could have been merely a personal agreements between the kokushi and tato fumyo, a new zuryo could ignore the precedent made by his predecessor to impose a prescribed tax to the tato fumyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>もっとも、中には私欲のために規定以上の租税賦課を行う受領もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were indeed some zuryos who imposed more tax than prescribed to pursue their own interests.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were indeed some zuryos who imposed more tax than prescribed to further their own interests.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were indeed some zuryo who imposed more tax than is prescribed in order to further their own interests.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>しかしこうして10世紀後期以降、受領と田堵負名層との間に紛争がしばしば見られるようになり、受領の施策に不満の田堵負名層が中央政府へ訴え出ることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, frequent conflicts were seen between the zuryo and the tato fumyo class in the late 10th century and later, and sometimes the tato fumyo class having complaints about measures taken by the zuryo appealed to the central government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, frequent conflicts were seen between the zuryo and the tato fumyo class in the late 10th century and onwards, and sometimes the tato fumyo class having complaints about measures taken by the zuryo appealed to the central government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from the late 10th century and onwards, there were frequent conflicts between the zuryo and the tato fumyo, and in some cases, the tato fumyo appealed to the central government about measures taken by the zuryo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>これを国司苛政上訴といい、尾張国司藤原元命の事例などが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is called Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi taken by farmers), among which the case of FUJIWARA no Motonaga, the kokushi in Owari Province, is well known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is called Kokushi kasei joso (appeals or armed struggles against kokushi taken by farmers), among which the case of FUJIWARA no Motonaga, the kokushi in Owari Province, is well known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such cases are called Kokushi kasei joso (peasants&apos; appeals or armed struggles against kokushi), among which the case of FUJIWARA no Motonaga, the kokushi in Owari Province, is well known.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。peasants’のアポストロフィを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>このような事例を受領層の苛政の表れと評価する意見もあるが、個別の事例を見ると受領が法令どおりに課税した例が圧倒的に多く、むしろ受領の方が遵法的であり、田堵負名層が私益を主張していることが判っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there is an opinion that such a case represents harsh governance by the zuryo class, each case tells that a great majority of the zuryo imposed the tax according to the law, which explains that the zuryos were more law-abiding and the tato fumyo class rather insisted on their own interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there is an opinion that such cases represents harsh governance by the zuryo class, each case tells that a great majority of the zuryo imposed the tax according to the law, which explains that the zuryos were more law-abiding while the tato fumyo class insisted on their own interests.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there is an opinion that such cases reveal the harsh governance by the zuryo, when each case is looked at closely, clearly a great majority of the zuryo imposed tax according to the regulations, which shows that the zuryo were more law-abiding while the tato fumyo pursued their own interests.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>田堵負名層とは決して零細な農民などではなく、隷属民を多数抱え、莫大な富を蓄積して農業など諸産業を大規模に経営し、多数の私兵すら擁していた富豪百姓だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tato fumyo class were never poor farmers but rich farmers that held a lot of slaves, managed a large scale of business such as agriculture while storing the immense property, and even owned a large private army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tato fumyo class were never poor farmers but rich farmers that held many slaves, managing large scale business such as agriculture while accumulating immense amounts of property, while even owning a large private army.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Far from being poor, the tato fumyo were indeed wealthy peasants who kept many servants, managed large scale businesses such as agriculture, and owned even many private warriors while accumulating immense wealth.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="33">
<j>説話集にも受領の実相が描かれており、『今昔物語集』の信濃国守藤原陳忠の説話（「受領は倒るるところに土をつかめ」という文句が知られている）や、『宇治拾遺物語』の藤原利仁の説話（芥川龍之介の『芋粥』の元となった）などの例が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Realities of zuryo are written in collections of anecdotes, such as an anecdote of FUJIWARA no Nobutada, Shinano no kuni no kami (Governor of Shinano Province) in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) &quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past, a phrase &quot;a zuryo must grasp even dirt where he falls&quot; is known), and that of FUJIWARA no Toshihito in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji, inspired Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA to write &quot;Imogayu&quot; (Sweet-Potato Broth).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Real stories concerning the zuryo are written in collections of anecdotes, such as one concerning FUJIWARA no Nobutada, Shinano no kuni no kami (Governor of Shinano Province) in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari (Shu) &quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past, a phrase &quot;a zuryo must grasp even dirt where he falls&quot; is known), and that of FUJIWARA no Toshihito in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales from Uji, inspired Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA to write &quot;Imogayu&quot; (Sweet-Potato Broth).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many realistic episodes about the zuryo in collections of tales, such as an episode about FUJIWARA no Nobutada, Shinano no kuni no kami (Governor of Shinano Province) in &quot;Konjaku Monogatari-shu&quot; (The Tale of Times Now Past), in which a phrase &quot;a zuryo must grasp even dirt where he falls&quot; is included, and that of FUJIWARA no Toshihito in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (Collected Tales from Uji), which later inspired Ryunosuke AKUTAGAWA to write &quot;Imogayu&quot;(Sweet-Potato Gruel).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションを全て全角から半角に修正しました。 &quot;Uji Shui Monogatai&quot; を &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), けふこえて(id:17107), Tomzo(id:16777), Nnh(id:474), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Shimoxx(id:9332), 青山コロハ(id:118527), 伏儀(id:142093), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>