<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>本圀寺の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Incident of Honkoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Incident of Honkoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Incident of Honkoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>本圀寺の変（ほんこくじのへん・本國寺の変）とは、永禄12年1月5日 (旧暦)（1569年1月21日）に三好三人衆が京都本圀寺（当時の呼称は「本國寺」）に仮の御所（六条御所）を置いていた室町幕府征夷大将軍・足利義昭を襲撃した事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Incident of Honkoku-ji Temple, on January 21, 1569, was an attack of Miyoshi-sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, who was in his temporary residence (Rokujo Palace) in Kyoto Honkoku-ji Temple (it was called &apos;Honkoku-ji&apos; then).</e>
<cmt>三好三人衆→miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Incident of Honkoku-ji Temple, on January 21, 1569, was an attack of Miyoshi-sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, the Shogun of the Muromachi bakufu, who was in his temporary residence (Rokujo Palace) in Kyoto Honkoku-ji Temple (it was called &apos;Honkoku-ji&apos; then).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Incident of Honkoku-ji Temple, on January 31, 1569, was an attack of Miyoshi sanninshu (three chief retainers of the Miyoshi clan) on Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who was in his temporary residence (Rokujo Palace) in Kyoto Honkoku-ji Temple (it was called &apos;Honkoku-ji&apos; then).</e>
<cmt>征夷大将軍が将軍となっているため訂正。幕府の定訳Miyoshi-sanninshu のハイフン削除永禄12年1月5日はグレゴリオ暦では西暦1569年1月31日なのでJanuary 21→January 31に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>六条合戦とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called the battle of Rokujo.</e>
<cmt>the battle of Rokujo(六条合戦）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the battle of Rokujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the battle of Rokujo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>前年9月に織田信長に擁立されて上洛して将軍に就いた足利義昭は永禄の変で焼失した御所の代わりに本圀寺を仮の御所としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who assumed the Shogun in September of the previous year after going up to the capital with a backup of Nobunaga ODA, had his temporary residence in Honkoku-ji Temple instead of Gosho (the Imperial Palace) which had been burnt down in the Eiroku Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who assumed the title of Shogun in September of the previous year after going up to the capital while being backed by Nobunaga ODA, had his temporary residence in Honkoku-ji Temple instead of Gosho (the Imperial Palace) which had been burnt down in the Eiroku Incident.</e>
<cmt>Robert: &quot; had his temporary residence in Honkoku-ji Temple instead of Gosho&quot; doesn&apos;t make sense: had his residence &lt;what&gt; instead of Gosho?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA, who assumed the title of Shogun in September of the previous year after going up to the capital while being backed by Nobunaga ODA, made Honkoku-ji Temple as his temprorary residence instead of Gosho (the Imperial Palace) because it had been burnt down in the Eiroku Incident.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がわかりやすいように変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その後、信長は京都の安定を見計らって本拠である美濃国岐阜城に一旦帰国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga, after assuring the peace in Kyoto, returned once to his base Gifu-jo Castle in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga, after assuring the peace in Kyoto, returned once to his base Gifu-jo Castle in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga, after assuring the peace in Kyoto, returned once to his base Gifu-jo Castle in Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>ところが、先に信長によって京都より追放されて摂津国に逃れていた三好三人衆が京都への復権を目指して、信長不在で正月で義昭周辺の気の緩んでいるところを突いて本圀寺を攻撃したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Miyoshi-sanninshu, who were in exile in Settsu Province expelled by Nobunaga from Kyoto earlier, with the aim of gaining power in Kyoto again, attacked Honkoku-ji Temple when the guards of Yoshiaki were too relaxed in the New Year and with Nobunaga&apos;s absence in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Miyoshi-sanninshu, who were in exile in Settsu Province expelled by Nobunaga from Kyoto earlier, with the aim of gaining power in Kyoto again, attacked Honkoku-ji Temple while Nobunaga was absent from Kyoto, and when the guards of Yoshiaki let their guard down during the New Year.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Miyoshi sanninshu, who were in exile in Settsu Province expelled by Nobunaga from Kyoto earlier, with the aim of gaining power in Kyoto again, attacked Honkoku-ji Temple while Nobunaga was absent from Kyoto, and when the guards of Yoshiaki let their guard down during the New Year.</e>
<cmt>Miyoshi-sanninshu ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、予想に反して義昭側近の細川幽斎・明智光秀らが奮戦し、更に翌日には池田勝正や三好義継・伊丹親興が救援に駆けつけたために挟撃される格好となった三好三人衆は敗走したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However against the odds, because Yoshiaki&apos;s close aids Yusai HOSOKAWA and Mitsuhide AKECHI fought a good fight, and Katsumasa IKEDA and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI arrived to rescue them the next day, Miyoshi-sanninshu took to flight to escape from the pincer movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However against all odds, because Yoshiaki&apos;s close aids Yusai HOSOKAWA and Mitsuhide AKECHI fought a good fight, and Katsumasa IKEDA and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI arrived to rescue them the next day, Miyoshi-sanninshu took escaped the pincer movement.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However against all odds, because Yoshiaki&apos;s close aids Yusai HOSOKAWA and Mitsuhide AKECHI fought a good fight, and Katsumasa IKEDA and Yoshitsugu MIYOSHI arrived to rescue them the next day, Miyoshi sanninshu took escaped the pincer movement.</e>
<cmt>Miyoshi-sanninshu ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>事件の5日後に急遽京都入りした信長は、この事件の背景に堺の町衆がいると考えて、堺に矢銭を課してその自治権を制限したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga hurriedly returned to Kyoto after five days, and thought that merchants of Sakai were pulling strings behind the scene before imposing yasen (war funds) on Sakai to restrict their autonomy.</e>
<cmt>矢銭→yasen (war funds)(矢銭）[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga hurriedly returned to Kyoto after five days, and thought that merchants of Sakai were pulling strings behind the scene before imposing yasen (war funds) on Sakai to restrict their autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga hurriedly returned to Kyoto after five days, and thought that merchants of Sakai were pulling strings behind the scene before imposing yasen (war funds) on Sakai to restrict their autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 松茸(id:27535), Harublue(id:167697), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>