<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>九州の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Kyushu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Kyushu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Kyushu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>九州の役（きゅうしゅうのえき）は、天正14年（1586年）7月から同15年（1587年）4月にかけて行われた、豊臣秀吉（1586年9月9日、豊臣賜姓）と島津氏との戦いの総称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Kyushu was a general name for battles between Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (surname &quot;Toyotomi&quot; was bestowed on September 9, 1586) and the Shimazu clan from July 1586 to April 1587.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Kyushu was a general name for battles between Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (surname &quot;Toyotomi&quot; was bestowed on September 9, 1586) and the Shimazu clan from July 1586 to April 1587.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Kyushu was a general name for battles between Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI (surname &quot;Toyotomi&quot; was bestowed on September 9, 1586) and the Shimazu clan from August and September 1586 to May and June 1587.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ歴に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>秀吉の九州攻め・九州平定・九州征伐などの名称で呼ばれることもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Kyushu, the subjugation of Kyushu, and the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Kyushu, the subjugation of Kyushu, and the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Kyushu, the subjugation of Kyushu, and the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>島津氏の九州統一</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unification of Kyushu by the Shimazu clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unification of Kyushu by the Shimazu clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unification of Kyushu by the Shimazu clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>九州地方は当時、薩摩国の島津氏が日向国の伊東氏、肥後国の相良氏、阿蘇氏、肥前国の有馬氏、龍造寺氏などを下していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time in Kyushu, the Shimazu clan in Satsuma Province had defeated the Ito clan in Hyuga Province, the Sagara clan and the Aso clan in Higo Province, the Arima clan and the Ryuzoji clan n Hizen Province, and the like.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time in Kyushu, the Shimazu clan in Satsuma Province had defeated the Ito clan in Hyuga Province, the Sagara clan and the Aso clan in Higo Province, the Arima clan and the Ryuzoji clan n Hizen Province, and the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyushu at that time, the Shimazu clan in Satsuma Province had defeated the Ito clan in Hyuga Province, the Sagara and Aso clans in Higo Province, and the Arima and the Ryuzoji clans in Hizen Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>さらに大友氏の重鎮立花道雪の死により大友氏の支配が緩んだ筑後国の諸国人衆も傘下に収め、九州統一を目前にしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the Shimazu clan drew local lords under its wing in Chikugo Province where the domination by the Otomo clan was loosened by death of Dosetsu TACHIBANA, the grand person of the Otomo clan, and the unification of Kyushu was close at hand.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the Shimazu clan drew local lords under its wing in Chikugo Province where domination by the Otomo clan was loosened by the death of Dosetsu TACHIBANA, the grand person of the Otomo clan, and the unification of Kyushu was close at hand.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having also conquered the territories of local lords in Chikugo Province, where the domination by the Otomo clan had weakened as the result of the death of Dosetsu TACHIBANA, a powerful leader of the Otomo clan, the Shimazu clan was just about to establish its rule over the entire island of Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>豊後国の大友義鎮は、島津氏の圧迫を回避するため、当時近畿、四国、中国地方を平定し天下統一の道を歩んでいた羽柴秀吉に助けを求める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to avoid the pressure from the Shimazu clan, Yoshishige OTOMO in Bungo Province asked for help of Hideyoshi HASHIBA, who had suppressed Kinki, Shikoku, and Chugoku regions aiming at the unification of the whole country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to avoid pressure from the Shimazu clan, Yoshishige OTOMO in Bungo Province asked for the help of Hideyoshi HASHIBA, who had suppressed Kinki, Shikoku, and Chugoku regions aiming at the unification of the whole country.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to avoid pressure from the Shimazu clan, Yoshishige OTOMO in Bungo Province asked for the help of Hideyoshi HASHIBA, who had suppressed Kinki, Shikoku, and Chugoku regions aiming at the unification of the whole country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>これを受け、関白となった秀吉は、1585年（天正13年）10月島津氏と大友氏に朝廷権威を以て停戦を命令（惣無事令）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, Hideyoshi who had become a chancellor ordered the Shimazu clan and the Otomo clan to cease fire by authority of the imperial court (sobuji rei (Peace edicts)) in October 1585.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, Hideyoshi who had become a chancellor, ordered the Shimazu clan and the Otomo clan to cease fire by authority of the imperial court (sobuji rei - Peace edicts) in October 1585.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, Hideyoshi who had become a chancellor, ordered the Shimazu clan and the Otomo clan to cease fire by authority of the imperial court (sobuji rei - Peace edicts) in October 1585.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし島津氏はこれを黙殺して九州統一戦を進めたため、秀吉は九州攻めに踏み切った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Shimazu clan advanced the battle for unification of Kyushu ignoring the order, and therefore Hideyoshi decided to invade Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Shimazu clan advanced the battle for unification of Kyushu ignoring the order, and therefore Hideyoshi decided to invade Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Shimazu clan ignored the order and continued to fight battles in order to establish its rule over Kyushu, which made Hideyoshi decide to invade Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>島津氏は九州統一の総仕上げとして、大友氏所領である豊前国・豊後と筑前国への侵攻を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To finish the unification of Kyushu, the Shimazu clan started to invade Buzen, Bungo, and Chikuzen Provinces, which were territories of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To finish the unification of Kyushu, the Shimazu clan started to invade Buzen, Bungo, and Chikuzen Provinces, which were territories of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To finish the unification of Kyushu, the Shimazu clan started to invade Buzen, Bungo, and Chikuzen Provinces, which were territories of the Otomo clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>筑前の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of Chikuzen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle of Chikuzen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle of Chikuzen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>岩屋城の戦いも参照</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">See the battle of Iwaya castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">See the battle of Iwaya castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">See the battle of Iwaya-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>城表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>秀吉の到着前に九州統一を成し遂げたかった島津義弘は1586年（天正14年）6月筑前侵攻を開始、筑前の西半を制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who desired to accomplish the unification of Kyushu before arrival of Hideyoshi, started to invade Chikuzen in June 1568, and brought the western half of Chikuzen under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who desired to accomplish the unification of Kyushu before arrival of Hideyoshi, started to invade Chikuzen in June 1568, and brought the western half of Chikuzen under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who intended to establish his rule over Kyushu before Hideyoshi arrived, started to invade Chikuzen Province in June 1598 and brought the western half of the province under his control.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>残るは高橋紹運の守る岩屋城、立花宗茂の守る立花城、立花直次の守る宝満山城のみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What remained for him were Iwaya-jo Castle defended by Joun TAKAHASHI, Tachibana-jo Castle defended by Muneshige TACHIBANA, and Homanyama-jo Castle defended by Naotsugu TACHIBANA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What remained for him were Iwaya-jo Castle defended by Joun TAKAHASHI, Tachibana-jo Castle defended by Muneshige TACHIBANA, and Homanyama-jo Castle defended by Naotsugu TACHIBANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What remained for him were Iwaya-jo Castle defended by Joun TAKAHASHI, Tachibana-jo Castle defended by Muneshige TACHIBANA, and Homanyama-jo Castle defended by Naotsugu TACHIBANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>7月、3万以上の大軍で岩屋城を攻めた島津軍だったが、高橋紹運の抵抗によって攻めあぐねた末、なんとか攻略する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, though the Shimazu&apos;s army attacked Iwaya-jo Castle with more than 30,000 soldiers, they struggled against the resistance of Joun TAKAHASHI, and finally managed to capture it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, Shimazu&apos;s army attacked Iwaya-jo Castle with more than 30,000 soldiers, they struggled against the resistance of Joun TAKAHASHI, and finally managed to capture it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, Shimazu&apos;s army attacked Iwaya-jo Castle with more than 30,000 soldiers, they struggled against the resistance of Joun TAKAHASHI, and finally managed to capture it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>島津方は上井覚兼が負傷、死者数千の損害を出す大誤算だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a large miscalculation for the Shimazu side that Kakuken(Satokane) UWAI got injured and thousands of the soldiers were killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a large miscalculation for the Shimazu side because Kakuken (Satokane) UWAI was wounded and thousands of the samurai were killed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a large miscalculation for the Shimazu side because Kakuken (Satokane) UWAI was wounded and thousands of the samurai were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>直後に宝満山も陥落させたが立花城は諦め包囲を解き、豊後侵攻へ方針を転換した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shimazu&apos;s army made Homanyama-jo Castle fall immediately after that, but gave up Tachibana-jo Castle to raise the siege, and changed the course to invade Bungo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu&apos;s army made Homanyama-jo Castle fall immediately after that, but gave up Tachibana-jo Castle in order to raise the siege, and changed course to invade Bungo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army made Homanyama-jo Castle fall immediately after that, but gave up Tachibana-jo Castle in order to raise the siege, and changed course to invade Bungo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この際立花宗茂は撤退する島津軍を追い高鳥居城、岩屋城、宝満山城を奪還している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Muneshige TACHIBANA ran after the withdrawing army of Shimazu, and retrieved Takatorii-jo Castle, Iwaya-jo Castle, and Homanyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Muneshige TACHIBANA ran after the Shimazu&apos;s retreating army, and retrieved Takatorii-jo Castle, Iwaya-jo Castle, and Homanyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Muneshige TACHIBANA ran after the Shimazu&apos;s retreating army, and retrieved Takatorii-jo Castle, Iwaya-jo Castle, and Homanyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>豊後の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Bungo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Bungo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Bungo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>一方、秀吉は同年9月に毛利氏に出陣を命じ豊前へ向かわせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Hideyoshi ordered the Mori clan to charge forward to Buzen in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Hideyoshi ordered the Mori clan to charge forward to Buzen in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Hideyoshi ordered the Mori clan to charge forward to Buzen in September of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また十河氏・長宗我部氏にも豊後へ出陣させ大友氏と合流、島津氏の豊後侵攻軍と正面衝突することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also made the Sogo clan and the Chosokabe clan charge forward to Bungo, and they joined the Otomo clan to head on against Shimazu&apos;s army sent to invade Bungo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also made the Sogo clan and the Chosokabe clan charge forward to Bungo, and they joined the Otomo clan against Shimazu&apos;s army sent to invade Bungo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also made the Sogo clan and the Chosokabe clan charge forward to Bungo, and they joined the Otomo clan against Shimazu&apos;s army sent to invade Bungo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>最初のうちは大友氏の内訌等もあり、島津氏優勢に進行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, Shimazu clan took advantage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, the Shimazu clan had the advantage.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning, the Shimazu clan had the advantage with problems in the Otomo clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>with problems in the Otomo clan, etc補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>特に12月の戸次川の戦いにおいて、仙石秀久を軍監とする豊臣方は長宗我部信親、十河存保などの有力武将を失う大敗を喫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the Battle of Hetsugigawa in December, the Toyotomi&apos;s side led by Hidehisa SENGOKU, Assistant Deputy General suffered a crushing defeat losing powerful busho (Japanese military commanders) including Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially in the Battle of Hetsugigawa in December, Toyotomi&apos;s side led by Hidehisa SENGOKU, Assistant Deputy General suffered a crushing defeat losing powerful busho (Japanese military commanders) including Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in the Battle of Hetsugigawa in December, Toyotomi&apos;s side led by Hidehisa SENGOKU, Assistant Deputy General suffered a crushing defeat losing powerful busho (Japanese military commanders) including Nobuchika CHOSOKABE and Masayasu SOGO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>島津軍は勢いづき大友義統が放棄した府内城を陥落させて、宗麟の守る丹生島城を包囲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimazu&apos;s army gained force to capture Funai-jo Castle abandoned by Yoshimune OTOMO and besieged Nyushima-jo Castle defended by Sorin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimazu&apos;s army gained force to capture Funai-jo Castle abandoned by Yoshimune OTOMO and besieged Nyushima-jo Castle defended by Sorin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Encouraged by their victory, the Shimazu army captured Funai-jo Castle, which had been abandoned by Yoshimune OTOMO, and besieged Nyushima-jo Castle, which was defended by Sorin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>丹生島城は、宗麟がポルトガルより輸入し「国崩し」と名付けた仏郎機砲（石火矢）の射撃もあり、なんとか持ち堪えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nyushima-jo Castle managed to sustain itself because of shooting Furankiho (Ishibiya) (Ishibiya is literally, stone fire arrow) that Sorin imported from Portugal and named Kunikuzushi (literally, destroying a nation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nyushima-jo Castle managed to sustain itself using Furankiho (Ishibiya) (Ishibiya is literally, stone fire arrow) that Sorin imported from Portugal and called Kunikuzushi (literally, destroying a nation).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nyushima-jo Castle managed to sustain itself using Furankiho (Ishibiya) (Ishibiya is literally, stone fire arrow) that Sorin imported from Portugal and called Kunikuzushi (literally, destroying a nation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>豊臣軍の出動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mobilization of Toyotomi&apos;s army</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mobilization of Toyotomi&apos;s army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mobilization of Toyotomi&apos;s army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>宗麟は秀吉に出馬を何度も促し、翌天正15年（1587年）正月、秀吉は九州侵攻の軍令を下し、3月には自らも出陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Sorin repeatedly encouraged Hideyoshi to move forward, Hideyoshi issued a military order of invading Kyushu in January 1587, and he dispatched himself in March.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Sorin repeatedly encouraged Hideyoshi to move forward, Hideyoshi issued a military order to invade Kyushu in January 1587, and he dispatched himself in March.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Sorin repeatedly encouraged Hideyoshi to move forward, Hideyoshi issued a military order to invade Kyushu in February and March 1587, and he dispatched himself in April and May.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ歴に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>肥後方面を秀吉が、日向方面を弟の豊臣秀長が率い、合わせて20万を数える圧倒的な物量と人員で進軍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With Hideyoshi aiming for Higo and his brother Hidenaga TOYOTOMI aiming for Hyuga, Toyotomi&apos;s army advanced with overwhelming amount of materials and soldiers over 200,000 people in total.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With Hideyoshi aiming for Higo and his brother Hidenaga TOYOTOMI aiming for Hyuga, Toyotomi&apos;s army advanced with an overwhelming amount of material and samurai, over 200,000 people in total.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With Hideyoshi aiming for Higo and his brother Hidenaga TOYOTOMI aiming for Hyuga, Toyotomi&apos;s army advanced with an overwhelming amount of material and samurai, over 200,000 people in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>秀吉上陸を察知した島津軍は北部九州を半ば放棄、島津氏の支配が表面的な占領軍政に過ぎなかったこともあり、瞬く間に島津氏の支配している城を陥落させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon sensing the landing of Hideyoshi, Shimazu&apos;s army almost abandoned the northern Kyushu, and Hideyoshi captured castles ruled by the Shimazu clan in a moment, partly because the rule by the Shimazu clan was nothing more than a formal rule by the occupation forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon sensing the landing of Hideyoshi, Shimazu&apos;s army almost abandoned northern Kyushu, and Hideyoshi captured castles ruled by the Shimazu clan instantly, partly because the rule by the Shimazu clan was nothing more than a formal rule by occupation forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon sensing the landing of Hideyoshi, Shimazu&apos;s army almost abandoned northern Kyushu, and Hideyoshi captured castles ruled by the Shimazu clan instantly, partly because the rule by the Shimazu clan was nothing more than a formal rule by occupation forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>島津氏は、後退を続け薩摩の守りを固める方針に変更する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shimazu clan kept withdrawing, and changed the course to strengthen its defense of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shimazu clan kept withdrawing, and changed course to strengthen its defense of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shimazu clan kept withdrawing, and changed course to strengthen its defense of Satsuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="31">
<j>秀長率いる軍は豊後を経由し日向に入ると県を経由し山田有信の守る高城 (新納院)を包囲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army led by Hidenaga entered Hyuga via Bungo, and then sieged Taka-jo Castle (Niiroin) defended by Arinobu YAMADA via Agata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army led by Hidenaga entered Hyuga via Bungo, and then sieged Taka-jo Castle (Niiroin) defended by Arinobu YAMADA via Agata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army led by Hidenaga entered Hyuga via Bungo, and then sieged Taka-jo Castle (Niiroin) defended by Arinobu YAMADA via Agata.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>島津義弘が救援に向かうが、根白坂の戦いで島津忠隣が戦死するなどの大敗を喫し、高城は陥落する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Yoshihiro SHIMAZU went to the rescue, he suffered a crushing defeat losing Tadachika SHIMAZU and so on in the Battle of Nejirozaka, and Taka-jo Castle fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yoshihiro SHIMAZU went to the rescue, he suffered a crushing defeat losing Tadachika SHIMAZU and in the Battle of Nejirozaka, and Taka-jo Castle fell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro SHIMAZU, who went to the rescue, suffered a crushing defeat and lost Tadachika SHIMAZU in the battle of Nejirozaka, and Taka-jo Castle was seized by Hidenaga.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>さらに豊臣秀次は都於郡城を攻略し小林市と野尻町の境界にある岩牟礼城まで侵攻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI conquered Tonokori-jo Castle and advanced to Iwamure-jo Castle on the border between Kobayashi City and Nojiri-cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI conquered Tonokori-jo Castle and advanced to Iwamure-jo Castle on the border between Kobayashi City and Nojiri-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI conquered Tonokori-jo Castle and advanced to Iwamure-jo Castle on the border between Kobayashi City and Nojiri-cho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>義弘は飯野城に籠り徹底抗戦を装った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro kept in Iino-jo Castle pretending a do-or-die resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro stayed in Iino-jo Castle pretending a do-or-die resistance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro stayed in Iino-jo Castle, pretending to put up determined resistance against Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="35">
<j>一方秀吉は秋月種実の岩石城を攻略、島原方面では有馬晴信の調略に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Hideyoshi conquered Ganjaku-jo Castle owned by Tanezane AKIZUKI, and succeeded in a stratagem against Harunobu ARIMA in Shimabara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Hideyoshi conquered Ganjaku-jo Castle owned by Tanezane AKIZUKI, and succeeded in a stratagem against Harunobu ARIMA in Shimabara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Hideyoshi conquered Tanezane AKIZUKI&apos;s Ganjaku-jo Castle and succeeded in persuading Harunobu ARIMA in Shimabara to surrender.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>島津忠辰は高田を放棄して出水にまで撤退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadatoki SHIMAZU abandoned Takada and withdrew to Izumi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadatoki SHIMAZU abandoned Takada and withdrew to Izumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadatoki SHIMAZU abandoned Takada and withdrew to Izumi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>秀吉は八代、水俣を経て島津方の予想を上回る速さで出水にまで進軍し、出水城主島津忠辰を降伏させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi advanced to Izumi via Yatsushiro and Minamata faster than expected by the Shimazu side, and made Tadatoki SHIMAZU, the lord of Izumi-jo Castle, surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi advanced to Izumi via Yatsushiro and Minamata faster than expected by the Shimazu side, and made Tadatoki SHIMAZU, the lord of Izumi-jo Castle, surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi advanced to Izumi via Yatsushiro and Minamata faster than expected by the Shimazu side, and made Tadatoki SHIMAZU, the lord of Izumi-jo Castle, surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>さらに島津忠長を蹴散らし川内の泰平寺 (薩摩川内市)に本陣を置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi further blew up Tadatoki Shimazu, and settled the headquarters of his army in Taihei-ji Temple of Sendai (Satsumasendai City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi further blew up Tadatoki Shimazu, and settled the headquarters of his army in Taihei-ji Temple of Sendai (Satsumasendai City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi further blew up Tadanaga SHIMAZU, and settled the headquarters of his army in Taihei-ji Temple of Sendai (Satsumasendai City).</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>4月、島津義久が泰平寺に赴き降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, Yoshihisa SHIMAZU visited Taihei-ji Temple to surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, Yoshihisa SHIMAZU visited Taihei-ji Temple to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, Yoshihisa SHIMAZU visited Taihei-ji Temple to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>戦後処理</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Post-war process</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Post-war process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Post-war process</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>義久が降った後も、飯野城に籠った島津義弘、婿養子の忠隣を殺された島津歳久らの抵抗が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the surrender of Yoshihisa, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU kept in Iino-jo Castle and Toshihisa SHIMAZU, whose adopted son-in-law was killed, continued the resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the surrender of Yoshihisa, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU stayed in Iino-jo Castle and Toshihisa SHIMAZU, whose adopted son-in-law was killed, continued resistance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the surrender of Yoshihisa, Yoshihiro SHIMAZU stayed in Iino-jo Castle and Toshihisa SHIMAZU, whose adopted son-in-law, Tadachika, was killed, continued resistance.</e>
<cmt>Tadachika補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>最終的に島津氏は九州の大部分を没収されたが、石田三成と伊集院忠棟による戦後処理の結果、薩摩・大隅国の2国を安堵され九州征伐は終了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Shimazu clan was finally deprived of most part of Kyushu, as a result of the post-war process by Mitsunari ISHIDA and Tadamune IJUIN, two provinces of Satsuma and Osumi were provided at the end of the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Shimazu clan was finally deprived of most parts of Kyushu, as a result of the post-war process by Mitsunari ISHIDA and Tadamune IJUIN, two provinces of Satsuma and Osumi were provided at the end of the Kyushu Conquest.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Shimazu clan was finally deprived of most of its territories in Kyushu, it was granted the right to rule Satsuma and Osumi Provinces as a result of the post-war actions taken by Mitsunari ISHIDA and Tadamune IJUIN.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="43">
<j>秀吉は秀長を通じて戸次川の戦いで嫡男信親を失った長宗我部元親に大隅一国を与えようとしたが、元親は固辞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi intended to provide the whole Osumi Province to Motochika CHOSOKABE who lost his heir Nobuchika in the Battle of Hetsugigawa, but Motochika firmly declined the offer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi intended to provide the whole Osumi Province to Motochika CHOSOKABE who lost his heir Nobuchika in the Battle of Hetsugigawa, but Motochika firmly declined the offer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi intended to provide the whole Osumi Province to Motochika CHOSOKABE who lost his heir Nobuchika in the Battle of Hetsugigawa, but Motochika firmly declined the offer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="44">
<j>その他、島津氏と結んでいた筑前の秋月種実が日向に移封され、大村氏との対立から長崎港の襲撃や南蛮船からの通行料徴収を強要などを繰り返していた深堀純賢を海賊禁止令違反として所領没収にするなどの処分が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Tanezane AKIZUKI in Chikuzen who colluded with the Shimazu clan was transferred to Hyuga, and Sumimasa FUKABORI, who repeatedly attacked Nagasaki Port and charged transport dues on the early European ships because of his confrontation with the Omura clan, was punished by depriving him of his territory for violation of Ban on Piracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Tanezane AKIZUKI in Chikuzen who colluded with the Shimazu clan was transferred to Hyuga, and Sumimasa FUKABORI, who repeatedly attacked Nagasaki Port and charged transport dues on the early European ships because of his confrontation with the Omura clan, was punished by depriving him of his territory for violation of Ban on Piracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Tanezane AKIZUKI in Chikuzen who colluded with the Shimazu clan was transferred to Hyuga, and Sumimasa FUKABORI, who repeatedly attacked Nagasaki Port and charged transport dues on the early European ships because of his confrontation with the Omura clan, was punished by depriving him of his territory for violation of Ban on Piracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="45">
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>豊臣秀吉は西国を平定し、朝鮮や琉球への服属を求めた接触を始めることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI suppressed Saigoku (western part of Japan (especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki)), he started to contact Korea and Ryukyu to make them subordinate states.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI suppressed Saigoku (western part of Japan - especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki), he started to contact Korea and Ryukyu to make them subordinate states.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI suppressed Saigoku (western part of Japan - especially Kyushu, but ranging as far east as Kinki), he started to contact Korea and Ryukyu to make them subordinate states.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>また、残す東国の平定を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also aimed to suppress remaining Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also aimed to suppress the remaining Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also aimed to suppress the remaining Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>そして関東の後北条氏、奥州の伊達氏へと矛先を移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He turned his fire on the Gohojo clan in Kanto and the Date clan in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He turned his fire on the Gohojo clan in Kanto and the Date clan in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He turned his fire on the Gohojo clan in Kanto and the Date clan in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa provinces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海蛇(id:225797), Tomzo(id:16777), Non-stop24(id:10471), Yasumi(id:44933), 雨季雨季(id:89363), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), Paranoid android(id:9248), 219.106の者(id:151047), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Yanahan(id:2437), 蚯蚓(id:254651), R463(id:150079), 219市115丁223番151号(id:15789), Hesolla(id:207896), Kagetudo(id:163875), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Arawodas(id:213174), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Maakun(id:16735), Chao35(id:34986), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Tokugawa(id:61656), 明鳳寺清松(id:220607), 美濃蝮(id:288102), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>