<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>下馬 (作法)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geba (dismounting a horse as a manner)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geba (dismounting a horse as a manner)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geba (dismounting a horse as a manner)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>下馬（げば）は、貴人の前で、社寺の境内で、また城内に入る前に、敬意を表わすために、騎（の）っているウマから下りることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Geba&quot; meant to dismount one&apos;s horse in order to salute in front of nobles, in the precincts of shrines and temples, or before entering into a castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Geba&quot; means to dismount one&apos;s horse in order to salute in front of nobles, in the precincts of shrines and temples, or before entering a castle.</e>
<cmt>「下馬」は広辞苑にも現在載っている単語なので、特に過去形にする必要はないと考え、meant → means に訂正しました。文法間違い：Entering into → entering に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Geba&quot; means to dismount one&apos;s horse in order to salute in front of nobles, in the precincts of shrines and temples, or before entering a castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>同じように輿車から降りる場合は、「下乗」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same manner, getting out of a palanquin is called &quot;gejo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same manner, getting out of a palanquin is called &quot;gejo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same manner, getting out of a palanquin is called &quot;gejo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「法曹至要抄」には、三位以下の者が路上で親王に会えば下馬するのをはじめとして、位階に応じてそれぞれ下馬の令制を載せ、有位者でない場合も賤者、少者は貴人、老人に対して同様にすべきであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hososhiyo-sho&quot; (a legal book compiled by the Sakanoue clan between the end of the Heian Period and the early Kamakura Period), which described rules and regulations on dismounting a horse depending on his court rank based on the Ritsuryo Law system (an ancient administrative law system in Japan), a person of the third court rank or the lower had to dismount his horse when he met any imperial prince on the road, as well as any lower-ranked or younger person without Ikai (a court rank) had to follow the same manner toward the nobilities and aged persons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hososhiyo-sho&quot; (a legal book compiled by the Sakanoue clan between the end of the Heian period and the early Kamakura period), which described rules and regulations on dismounting a horse depending on his court rank based on the Ritsuryo Law system (an ancient administrative law system in Japan), a person of the third court rank or the lower had to dismount his horse when he met any imperial prince on the road, and even any lower-ranked or younger person without Ikai (a court rank) had to follow the same manner toward the nobilities and the elderly.</e>
<cmt>あえて大文字で始める必要はないのではと考え、Period → period に変更しました。 as well as で節を結ぶのは文法間違いではないかと考え、and even に訂正しました。aged persons をすぐ前のnobilities に合うように、the elderly に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hososhiyo-sho&quot; (a legal book compiled by the Sakanoue clan between the end of the Heian period and the early Kamakura period), which described rules and regulations on dismounting a horse depending on his court rank based on the Ritsuryo Law system (an ancient administrative law system in Japan), a person of the third court rank or the lower had to dismount his horse when he met any imperial prince on the road, and even any lower-ranked or younger person without Ikai (a court rank) had to follow the same manner toward the nobilities and the elderly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>令制に背くと笞罪に処せられたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If such rules and regulations were not observed, the offenders are said to have been punished with whippings.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If such rules and regulations were not observed, the offenders are said to have been punished with whippings.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If such rules and regulations were not observed, the offenders are said to have been punished with whippings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これがいつまで、どの程度行なわれたか、明らかでない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clearly known how long period and to what extent these rules and regulations had been observed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clearly known how long and to what extent these rules and regulations had been observed.</e>
<cmt>不必要ではと考え、how long の後のperiod は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clearly known how long and to what extent these rules and regulations had been observed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「貞丈雑記」には、「輿にめしたる人に行あひ、又は人の犬追物、笠懸、やぶさめ、大的、小的など射らるる場所近き辺を通るとき、又は野山にて幕などうち遊興せらるるあたりを通るとき、または神社仏寺の前を通るとき、また三職などの門前を通るとき、または川狩鷹狩など人のするところを通るとき、また鷹すゑたる人鵜つかひに行あひたるとき、いづれも我知らぬ人なりとも、必ず下馬して通る也」とあり、武家時代を通じて、礼儀として厳存した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this custom of dismounting a horse had surely existed as a courtesy during Buke-jidai (the feudal period), as described in &quot;Teijo-zakki&quot; (a book on ancient courtly traditions and etiquettes, written by Sadatake Ise in the Edo Period) that a person had to dismount his horse without fail when he encountered with any person on a palanquin, or when he passed by a place where inuoimono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery), kasagake (archery competion on horseback), yabusame (the art of arrow shooting on horseback), and other arrow shooing competitions with omato and komato (big and small sized shooing targets) were being played, or when he went around a shrouded place for pleasure in hills and fields, or when he passed in front of shrines and temples, or when he passed in front of the gates of Sanshoku (three important offices), or when he passed through a place where people were enjoying river fishing or falconry and met with &quot;Takasuetaru Hitou-tsukai&quot; (a cormorant fisher or an astringer), in each case no matter whom he met with were strangers or not.</e>
<cmt>「鷹すえたる人鵜つかひ」の意味不明。一応推測で、「鵜匠または鷹匠」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this custom of dismounting a horse had surely existed as a courtesy during Buke-jidai (the feudal period), as described in &quot;Teijo-zakki&quot; (a book on ancient courtly traditions and etiquettes, written by Sadatake Ise in the Edo Period) that a person had to dismount his horse without fail when he encountered any person on a palanquin, or when he passed by a place where inuoimono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery), kasagake (archery competition on horseback), yabusame (the art of arrow shooting on horseback), and other arrow shooing competitions with omato and komato (big and small sized shooing targets) were being played, or when he went around a shrouded place for pleasure in hills and fields, or when he passed in front of shrines and temples, or when he passed in front of the gates of Sanshoku (three important offices), or when he passed through a place where people were enjoying river fishing or falconry or when an astringer bumped into a cormorant fisher, in each case no matter whom he met with were strangers or not.</e>
<cmt>「貞丈雑記」が、a book on ancient courtly traditions and etiquettes, written by Sadatake Ise in the Edo Period と丁寧に説明されていますが、原文にはありません。念のため。　　encountered with → encountered に訂正しました。「笠懸」の注釈中のcompetion はスペルミスのため competition に訂正しました。「鷹すえたる人鵜つかひ」の部分はわかる範囲で訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this custom of dismounting a horse had surely existed as a courtesy during Buke-jidai (the feudal period), as described in &quot;Teijo-zakki&quot; (a book on ancient courtly traditions and etiquettes, written by Sadatake Ise in the Edo Period) that a person had to dismount his horse without fail when he encountered any person on a palanquin, or when he passed by a place where inuoimono (dog-hunting event, a skill of an archery), kasagake (archery competition on horseback), yabusame (the art of arrow shooting on horseback), and other arrow shooing competitions with omato and komato (big and small sized shooing targets) were being played, or when he went around a shrouded place for pleasure in hills and fields, or when he passed in front of shrines and temples, or when he passed in front of the gates of Sanshoku (three important offices), or when he passed through a place where people were enjoying river fishing or falconry or when an astringer bumped into a cormorant fisher, in each case no matter whom he met with were strangers or not.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>訪問においては、参朝はいうまでもなく、宮門で下乗、下馬をさせ、寺社もまたそれに準じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To visit the imperial court, needless to say, people had to dismount their horses or alight from their palanquins at Miyamon gate (a court gate), which manner was followed by visitors to shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To visit the imperial court, needless to say, people had to dismount their horses or alight from their palanquins at Miyamon gate (a court gate), which manner was followed by visitors to shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To visit the imperial court, needless to say, people had to dismount their horses or alight from their palanquins at Miyamon gate (a court gate), which manner was followed by visitors to shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代には、城外に「下馬札」を立てて、城中では将軍以外はその身分に応じて下馬の制限を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo Period, &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; (a bulletin board to notify prohibitiion of entering on a horse) was put up outside of the castle, and every body inside the castle, except Shogun, was restricted in riding a horse depending on their ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; (a sign to notify prohibitiion of entering on a horse) was put up outside of the castle, and inside the castle, everybody except Shogun was restricted in riding a horse depending on their ranks.</e>
<cmt>Edo Period → Edo period に変更しました。「下馬札」の後にある注釈の bulletin board は「張り紙をするための掲示板」という感じがするので、sign に置き換えました。 every body → everybody に訂正しました。   &quot;everybody inside the castle&quot; だと、城内にいる（場内で働く・住む）すべての人々という感じがするので、everybody の位置をexcept の前に訂正しました。Shogun の後のコンマは必要ないと考え、削除しました。　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, a &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; (a sign notifying horse riders that they are prohibited from entering the area indicated while mounted on a horse) was put up outside of a castle, and inside the castle, everybody except the shogun was, depending on their rank, obliged to dismount from their horse.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>たとえば、親王、大納言以上でも、中門で下乗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, even Imperial Princes and other nobles ranked higher than Dainagon (a major councillor of state) had to get down from their palanquin at Chumon gate (an inner gate in the castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, even imperial princes and other nobles ranked higher than Dainagon (a major councilor of state) had to get down from their palanquin at Chumon gate (an inner gate in the castle).</e>
<cmt>Imperial Princes → imperial princes：複数なので、大文字を小文字に変えました。 スペルミス： councillor → councilor に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, even imperial princes and other nobles ranked higher than Dainagon (a major councilor of state) had to get down from their palanquin at Chumon gate (an inner gate in the castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>幕末、下馬、下乗の廃れたが、明治維新後、明治元年閏4月の下乗下馬の制から始まり、明治12年までに変遷はあるが、宮城、離宮、諸官省、社寺などに一定の制があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo Period, this custom of dismounting a horse or getting down from a palanquin had once died out, but after the Meiji Restoration, the same system resumed in leap April, 1868, and lasted to a certain extent until 1879, through some changes, at Kyujo (imperial palaces), Rikyu (imperial villas), various ministries and some temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, this custom of dismounting a horse or getting down from a palanquin had once died out, but after the Meiji Restoration, the same system resumed in leap April, 1868, and lasted until 1879, going through some changes, at Kyujo (imperial palaces), Rikyu (imperial villas), various ministries and some temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>Edo Period → Edo period に訂正しました。   Lasted の後に to a certain extent が入ると文がぼやけてしまうので、削除しました。Through だけではわかりづらいような気がするので、going を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, this custom of dismounting a horse or getting down from a palanquin had once died out, but after the Meiji Restoration, the same system resumed in leap April, 1868, and lasted until 1879, going through some changes, at Kyujo (imperial palaces), Rikyu (imperial villas), various ministries and some temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治21年に諸官庁においては便宜に任され、滅んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In various ministries, this system collapsed in 1888, leaving the matters to convenience.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In various ministries, this system was left to people&apos;s convenience and collapsed in 1888.</e>
<cmt>原文の順序通りに語順を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In various ministries, this system was left to people&apos;s convenience and collapsed in 1888.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>下馬札</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geba-fuda (a bulletin board to notify prohibition to enter on horse)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geba-fuda (a sign to notify prohibition to enter on horse)</e>
<cmt>前述のように、bulletin board をsign に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geba-fuda (a sign to notify prohibition to enter on horse)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>下乗、下馬には成文があるが、下馬札の成文は見当たらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The terms of &quot;Gejo&quot; and &quot;Geba&quot; (dismounting a horse and alighting from a palanquin) were described in statutory laws, but there was no statutory law that referred to the term &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; (a bulletin board to instruct Gejo and Geba).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The terms &quot;Gejo&quot; and &quot;Geba&quot; (dismounting a horse and alighting from a palanquin) can be seen in a document, but the term &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; (a sign to instruct Gejo and Geba) was not found.</e>
<cmt>terms of → terms： of を削除しました。　　広辞苑によると「成文」の意味は「文章に書き表すこと。また、その文章」とされており、「法律」の意味合いはありません。したがって、were described → can be seen, statutory laws → a document としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The terms &quot;Gejo&quot; and &quot;Geba&quot; (dismounting a horse and alighting from a palanquin) can be seen in a document, but the term &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; (a sign to instruct Gejo and Geba) was not found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その起源は明らかでないが、「大唐西域記」に、釈迦が霊鷲山で説法する時、退凡下乗の卒塔婆を建てたことが見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; is not known, but it was described in &quot;The Great Tang Dynasty Record of the Western Regions&quot; that, when Shakyamuni (Buddha) was preaching at Ryojusen Mountain, he had put up Sotoba (a tall, narrow wooden tablet) to notify all nobles to get down from their palanquins or dismount their horses and all ordinary people not to enter into the area secured for his preaching.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; is not known, but it was described in &quot;The Great Tang Dynasty Record of the Western Regions&quot; that, when Shakyamuni (Buddha) was preaching at Ryojusen Mountain, he put up Sotoba (a tall, narrow wooden tablet) to notify all nobles to get down from their palanquins or dismount their horses and all ordinary people not to enter into the area secured for his preaching.</e>
<cmt>he had put up → he put up、enter into → enter に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of &quot;Geba-fuda&quot; is not known, but it was described in &quot;The Great Tang Dynasty Record of the Western Regions&quot; that, when Shakyamuni (Buddha) was preaching at Ryojusen Mountain, he put up Sotoba (a tall, narrow wooden tablet) to notify all nobles to get down from their palanquins or dismount their horses and all ordinary people not to enter into the area secured for his preaching.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「一話一言」によれば、正安3年、権大僧都永瑜が建てた高雄の下馬碑が最古であるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Ichiwa Ichigen&quot; (a book of essays written by Nanpo OTA in the late Edo Period), the oldest Geba-hi (a monument with inscription of Geba) was put up in Takao by Gon-dai-sozu Eiyu (Junior Prelate Eiyu) in 1301.</e>
<cmt>「永瑜」の読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Ichiwa Ichigen&quot; (a book of essays written by Nanpo OTA in the late Edo period), the oldest Geba-hi (a monument with inscription of Geba) was put up in Takao by Gon-dai-sozu Eiyu (Junior Prelate Eiyu) in 1301.</e>
<cmt>Edo Period → Edo period に訂正しました。「永瑜」の読み方不明。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Ichiwa Ichigen&quot; (a book of essays written by Nanpo OTA in the late Edo period), the oldest Geba-hi (a monument with inscription of Geba) was put up in Takao by Gon-dai-sozu Eiyu (Junior Prelate Eiyu) in 1301.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸城の諸門外には下馬札が立てられ、社寺にもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geba-fuda (a bulletin board to notify prohibition to enter on horse) was put up outside of every gate of the Edo-jo Castle, and the same could be seen at shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geba-fuda (a bulletin board to notify prohibition to enter on horse) was put up outside of every gate of the Edo-jo Castle, and the same could be seen at shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>bulletin board → sign に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geba-fuda (a bulletin board to notify prohibition to enter on horse) was put up outside of every gate of the Edo-jo Castle, and the same could be seen at shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>明治2年8月、神宮、官国幣社に皇族の参拝のある時、下馬下乗の場所を指定するよう教部省から令されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1869, Kyobusho (the Ministry of Religion) issued an ordinance for Jingu Shrine and other Kankoku Heisha (a general term for high-ranked shrines under direct control of the central government) to designate places to dismount a horse or to alight from a palanquin in their precincts when Imperial families visit there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August, 1869, Kyobusho (the Ministry of Religion) issued an ordinance for Jingu Shrine and other Kankoku Heisha (a general term for high-ranked shrines under direct control of the central government) to designate places to dismount a horse or to alight from a palanquin in their precincts when Imperial families would visit there.</e>
<cmt>時制を整えるため、visit の前にwould を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August, 1869, Kyobusho (the Ministry of Religion) issued an ordinance for Jingu Shrine and other Kankoku Heisha (a general term for high-ranked shrines under direct control of the central government) to designate places to dismount a horse or to alight from a palanquin in their precincts when Imperial families would visit there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その規定や書法については江戸時代、青蓮院に筆法が伝わるなど取扱いがやかましかったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prescriptions on Geba-fuda including ways of painting were so fastidious to deal with that the way of painting was traditionally inherited by Shoren-in Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government was so fastidious about dealing with Geba-fuda and how to write it that the way of painting Geba-fuda was conveyed inside Shoren-in Temple esoterically.</e>
<cmt>fastidious という単語は主語が人や団体などの場合にしか使えないのではないかと思います。しかしながら、この文の主語は不明なので一応 The government としておきました。したがって、その他の文も大幅に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government was so fastidious about dealing with Geba-fuda and how to write it that the way of painting Geba-fuda was conveyed inside Shoren-in Temple esoterically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tribot(id:186681), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>