<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>移配</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ihai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ihai</e>
<cmt>語頭を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ihai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>移配（いはい）とは、8世紀から9世紀にかけて、当時の日本の律令政府（朝廷）が現在の東北地方に居住していた蝦夷を内地（関東地方以西の本州・四国・九州）に強制移住させた政策のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ihai is a policy that the ancient Japanese government of centralized governance (Imperial court) forced Ezo (northeners) who were living in Tohoku area today to move to western areas from Kanto like Honshu, Shikoku and Kyushu from the 8th to the 9th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ihai is a policy under which the Ritsuryo-seifu Government (the ancient Japanese government of centralized governance) (Imperial court) forced Emishi (northerners), who lived in present-day Tohoku area, to move to Kanto region and to the west of Honshu, Shikoku and Kyushu from the 8th to the 9th century.</e>
<cmt>括弧内の余分な空白を削除しました。Ritsuryo-seifu Government を追記しました。（蝦夷が「えぞ」と呼ばれるようになったのは平安中期以降のことなので（http://d.hatena.ne.jp/keyword/%B2%DC%B0%D0）、Ezo を Emishi に修正しました。who were living in Tohoku area today to move to western areas from Kanto like Honshu を who lived in present-day Tohoku area to move to Kanto region and to the west of Honshu に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ihai is a policy under which the Ritsuryo-seifu Government (the ancient Japanese government of centralized governance) (Imperial court) forced Emishi (northerners), who lived in present-day Tohoku area, to move to Kanto region and to the west of Honshu, Shikoku and Kyushu from the 8th to the 9th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>7世紀中期以後、ヤマト王権による蝦夷の従属化が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the middle of the 7th century Yamato Dynasty tried to subordinate Emishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the middle of the 7th century, Yamato Dynasty tried to subordinate Emishi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処冒頭の余分なスペースを削除しました。Century の後にコロンを追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the middle of the 7th century, Yamato Dynasty tried to subordinate Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、律令制が確立していくにつれて、唐を「隣国」、新羅・渤海_(国)を「蕃国」、そして蝦夷を「化外の民」として隼人とともに「夷狄」として、天皇の統治下にある日本内地の王民と峻別する一種の小中華思想を掲げた「小帝国」が成立することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the ancient government of centralized governance being established, the government became to construct a small dynasty, in which inland Japanese people under the emperor&apos;s control were discriminated against Emishi as well as Hayato (ancient tribe in Kyushu) who were social outcasts. Tang was called a neighbor country and Silla and Balhae were called foreign countries. (the idea is from building a small China)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was established, a &apos;small empire&apos; came to be established with a kind of Sino-centrism, which distinguished people in inland Japan under the Emperor&apos;s rule from Tang as a neighbor country, Silla and Balhae as foreign countries, and Emishi as barbarians as well as Hayato (ancient tribe in Kyushu) looking upon them as social outcasts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、この前の部分は切り離して一文とし、残りの部分は一文に統合しました。）全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) was established, a &apos;small empire&apos; came to be established with a kind of Sino-centrism, which distinguished people in inland Japan under the Emperor&apos;s rule from Tang as a neighbor country, Silla and Balhae as foreign countries, and Emishi as barbarians as well as Hayato (ancient tribe in Kyushu) looking upon them as social outcasts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>石上英一以来歴史学者の間で唱えられた蝦夷・隼人と日本人は同じ倭人（倭の地に住む人間）であるにも関わらず、日本という国家成立を急ぐために本来は全ての倭人を内国（内地）化・王民化しなければならない辺境の人民をいまだ支配できていない現実を隠蔽して、逆にそれを利用して内国の王民を統治・支配する「小帝国」を形成してきたとする見解が一定の支持を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following view was given by Eiichi ISHIGAMI and some other historians have supported his idea since then: Ezo, Hayato andJapanese were Wajin, because they lived in the land of Wa. But these people, Ezo and Hayato, were not obedient to the government. Since the government was in a hurry to establish the nation of Japan,they concealed this fact. Moreover making use of it, the government tried to control and unite the people living in inland of Japan and built a small dynasty..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following view given by Eiichi ISHIGAMI and other historians has been supported to a certain extent: under the circumstances, hastening to establish Japan as a nation by bringing all the people and lands in Japan under the Emperor&apos;s rule, although Emishi, Hayato and other Japanese were the same Wajin (people who lived in the Wa country [Japan]), the government concealed the reality that it was not yet able to control these frontier people, and making the best of a difficult situation, established a &apos;small empire&apos; to include all people who were currently under the Emperor&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文になっていませんでした。全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following view given by Eiichi ISHIGAMI and other historians has been supported to a certain extent: under the circumstances, hastening to establish Japan as a nation by bringing all the people and lands in Japan under the Emperor&apos;s rule, although Emishi, Hayato and other Japanese were the same Wajin (people who lived in the Wa country [Japan]), the government concealed the reality that it was not yet able to control these frontier people, and making the best of a difficult situation, established a &apos;small empire&apos; to include all people who were currently under the Emperor&apos;s control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これによって蝦夷・隼人は「化外」の民として「化内」の民である王民からは蔑視・排除される存在とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Ezo and Hayato were thought to be barbarians by the inland people, then they were excluded and despised by the inland people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Emishi and Hayato were thought to be barbarians by the &apos;inland&apos; people; they were despised and excluded by the people under the Emperor&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>Ezo を Emishi に修正しました。&apos;inland people&apos; は 本州に住んでいた Emishi と区別するために &apos;&apos; を追記しました。後半修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Emishi and Hayato were thought to be barbarians by the &apos;inland&apos; people; they were despised and excluded by the people under the Emperor&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、その一方で陸奥国・越後国（後に北部が分離して出羽国）は、この政策の維持のために常に不安定な状況に置かれることになり、事あるごとに対蝦夷政策は揺れることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Mutsu Province and Echigo Province (later the northern part became Dewa) were in the unstable condition in order to maintain this policy. Whenever troubles happened, they had to change their policy to control Ezo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Mutsu Province and Echigo Province (later the northern part was separated off as Dewa Province) became unstable as a result of this policy, which led in turn to the Emishi policy being unsettled all the time.</e>
<cmt>括弧内、修正しかつ余分な空白を削除しました。一原文一訳文になっていなかったので、一文にし、後半修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Mutsu Province and Echigo Province (later the northern part was separated off as Dewa Province) became unstable as a result of this policy, which led in turn to the Emishi policy being unsettled all the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>だが、律令政府は「化外」の民との対立の際には蝦夷征伐というかたちで軍事力を行使して、その勢力圏を北へと広げることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ancient Japanese government used military power when it had conflict with socially outcast people under the pretext of conquering Ezo and expanded itsr power in the north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the pretext of fighting social outcasts the Ritsuryo-seifu Government used military power to conquer Emishi and expand its power to the north.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the pretext of fighting social outcasts the Ritsuryo-seifu Government used military power to conquer Emishi and expand its power to the north.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その結果、多くの蝦夷（居留民及び捕虜）をその支配地に抱え込むことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result the government began to control many Ezo including its residents and captives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the government had many Emishi (residents and captives) under their control.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the government had many Emishi (residents and captives) under their control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これを俘囚と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were called Hushu,barbarians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were called Fushu (subjected barbarians).</e>
<cmt>Hushu,barbarians.を Fushu (subjected barbarians) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were called Fushu (subjected barbarians).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>彼らは律令政府に従っていたものの、外側の夷俘と呼ばれる従来通りのまま未だに排除された状況にある蝦夷と通じる可能性も存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though they followed the centralized government, they might have had contact with Ezoi who were called Ifu and still excluded as barbarians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though they followed Ritsuryo-seifu Government, it is possible that they had contacts with other Emishi, called Ifu, who were still excluded as barbarians.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though they followed Ritsuryo-seifu Government, it is possible that they had contacts with other Emishi, called Ifu, who were still excluded as barbarians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そこで神亀2年（725年）に律令政府はこうした俘囚のうち、130名を伊予国に、578名を筑紫（九州）に、15名を和泉監に移すこととした（『続日本紀』神亀2年閏正月己丑条）のである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in 725 the government decided to move 130 barbarians to Iyo (Shikoku) and 578 barbarians toTsukushi (kyushu) and 15 to Izumi.(excerpt from Shoku Nihongi).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, in 725, the government decided to move 130 such subjected barbarians to Iyo (Shikoku) and 578 to Chikushi (Kyushu) and 15 to Izumi (article on February 25, 725 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; [Chronicle of Japan Continued]).</e>
<cmt>Then を Accordingly に修正しました。the government を Ritsuryo-seifu Government に修正しました。130 barbarians を 130 in such subjected barbarians Tsukushi (kyushu) を Chikushi (Kyushu) に修正しました。(excerpt from Shoku Nihongi) を (article on February 25, 725 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; [Chronicle of Japan Continued]) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, in 725, the government decided to move 130 such subjected barbarians to Iyo (Shikoku) and 578 to Chikushi (Kyushu) and 15 to Izumi (article on February 25, 725 in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; [Chronicle of Japan Continued]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これが最初の移配に関する記録である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the first record of Ihai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the first record of Ihai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the first record of Ihai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これは続いて天平10年（738年）にも115名が駿河国を経由して摂津国に送られたことが駿河国の正税帳によって確認できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in 738, 115 barbarians were sent to Settsu Province (Osaka today) by way of Suruga Province (Shizuoka today), which was confirmed in the official tax record of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following that, in 738, 115 subjected barbarians were sent to Settsu Province (Osaka Prefecture today) via Suruga Province (Shizuoka Prefecture today), which was confirmed in the official tax record of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>Then を Following that に、barbarians を subjected barbarians に修正しました。括弧内の余分な空白を削除し、Prefecture を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following that, in 738, 115 subjected barbarians were sent to Settsu Province (Osaka Prefecture today) via Suruga Province (Shizuoka Prefecture today), which was confirmed in the official tax record of Suruga Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この俘囚集団を護送していたのは、防人の護送を担当していた防人部領使であったことが確認でき、彼らが最終的に防人の配備先である筑紫（九州）に送られて同様の任務についていたものと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was confirmed that the guards for Sakimori (soldiers deployed for border defense) escorted this group of barbarians. Therefore, it is estimated that they were finally sent to their destination,Chikushi (Kyushu),to work as Sakimori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was confirmed that the guards for Sakimori (soldiers deployed for border defense) escorted this group of subjected barbarians, which suggests that they were sent to Chikushi (Kyushu) in the end, where Sakimori were stationed, to engage in similar work to the Sakimori.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文になっていなかったので、一文に修正しました。stationed 以降を修正しました。括弧内の余分な空白を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was confirmed that the guards for Sakimori (soldiers deployed for border defense) escorted this group of subjected barbarians, which suggests that they were sent to Chikushi (Kyushu) in the end, where Sakimori were stationed, to engage in similar work to the Sakimori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、宝亀5年（774年）にいわゆる「三十八年戦争」が始まった頃から、急激に俘囚の移配が増加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 774, from around the time when &quot; the 38 years&apos; war &quot; began, Ihai rapidly increased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, from around the time when the so called &quot;38 years&apos; War&quot; began in 774, the Ihai policy rapidly intensified.</e>
<cmt>However を追記し、in 774 を began の後に移しました。so called を追記しました。余分な空白を削除しました。War の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, from around the time when the so called &quot;38 years&apos; War&quot; began in 774, the Ihai policy rapidly intensified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかも、中には夷俘に分類されていた者までが移配され、その移配先も関東地方など全国各地に広がっていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, even barbarians classified as ihu were sent to places throughout the nation including Kanto area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, even barbarians classified as Ifu were moved, and they were sent further afield across the nation, including Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>ihu を Ifu に修正しました。他、後半修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, even barbarians classified as Ifu were moved, and they were sent further afield across the nation, including Kanto area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その原因としては以下のように諸説あるものの、結論は出ていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are some reasons for it. One opinion is that due to the great efforts by Tamuramaro SAKANOUE, major opposing powers were removed, which produced many subordinate people. The rapid increase of them threatened the government with their control or unification in these areas. Another opinion is that Fushu allowance provided for their education was not enough in Mutsu Province and Dewa Province. Another opinion is that through this battle the government tried to control throughout Ou area for the stablility of the nation and Fushu were encouraged to become inland people. Another one is opposit to this opinion: after conquering Ou area, in order to maintain a small dynasty as before, the special residential areas were designated for the outcasts. No conclusion has been made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some theories about why this was, such as the ones below, but no conclusion has been reached.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some theories about why this was, such as the ones below, but no conclusion has been reached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>坂上田村麻呂らの活躍によって蝦夷の主だった抵抗勢力が排除されたために大量の服属民が生み出されたためにその急激な増加によって現地における支配・統治に不安がもたれたからとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory is that due to the great efforts by SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, major opposing powers within Emishi were removed, which produced many subordinate groups, the rapid increase of which was a threat to order in certain places.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）Tamuramaro SAKANOUE を SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro に修正しました。他、数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory is that due to the great efforts by SAKANOUE no Tamuramaro, major opposing powers within Emishi were removed, which produced many subordinate groups, the rapid increase of which was a threat to order in certain places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>教化のために支給された俘囚料が地元の陸奥・出羽ではまかないきれなくなったからとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory is that Mutsu Province and Dewa Province were unable to afford the Fushu allowance anymore which provided for the re-education of the barbarians.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory is that Mutsu Province and Dewa Province were unable to afford the Fushu allowance anymore which provided for the re-education of the barbarians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この戦いを通じて国内の安定のために奥羽全域の平定を目指す方向に路線転換をしたために王民化を促進するためとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A third theory is that the government&apos;s aim during this war changed to controlling the Ou area for the sake of the stability of the nation, and there were attempts to bring Fushu under the Emperor&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A third theory is that the government&apos;s aim during this war changed to controlling the Ou area for the sake of the stability of the nation, and there were attempts to bring Fushu under the Emperor&apos;s rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>逆に奥羽全域の平定後も従来通りの「小帝国」を維持するために内地に「化外」の居住区を人為的に作るためとする説。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fourth theory is the opposite of the previous theory: after conquering the Ou area, in order to maintain the &apos;small empire&apos; as before special residential areas were created for the outcasts.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fourth theory is the opposite of the previous theory: after conquering the Ou area, in order to maintain the &apos;small empire&apos; as before special residential areas were created for the outcasts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>なお、弘仁4年（813年）には令制国の国司に「俘囚専当」を兼任させて俘囚の監督と教化・保護養育に当たらせ、その翌年には蝦夷の王民化の方針を打ち出した勅令が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 813 the imperial order was issued. It said that Kokushi (governor today) under the centralized government was in charge of managing barbarians besides his regular work and made him educate and nourish barbarians and in the next year issued a policy to make barbarians become inland people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 813 an imperial order was issued, under which provincial governors in ryoseikoku (provinces) took on the additional responsibility of managing subjected barbarians, making them civilized, and protecting and nourishing them; the following year another imperial order was issued, making the Emishi the Emperor&apos;s people.</e>
<cmt>一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、一文に統一しました。数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 813 an imperial order was issued, under which provincial governors in ryoseikoku (provinces) took on the additional responsibility of managing subjected barbarians, making them civilized, and protecting and nourishing them; the following year another imperial order was issued, making the Emishi the Emperor&apos;s people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>また、律令政府では弱体化した防人や軍団 (古代日本)に替わって蝦夷を用いる構想などを打ち出している（貞観 (日本)11年（859年）12月5日付太政官符（『類聚三代格』））。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government had an idea to use Ezo to work for Sakimori and the army that had become weak. But in fact in 811 a request from Mutsu Province to controll barbarians in the place was accepte, since they dind not beome familiar to the place they were sent to and caused troubles. After this request was accepted, a large scale of Ihai was not carried out. Instead the barbarians already sent to other places were sent again to new places in small groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the government set forth the idea of using Emishi in place of Sakimori and the army (of ancient Japan) which had become weak (Daijokanpu [official documents from Daijokan to local governments] on 14 January, 859, &quot;Ruiju sandai kaku [Assorted regulations from Three Reigns]&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）貞観 (日本)11年が原文では859年となっていますが、ウェブ（http://maechan.net/kanreki/）で調べたところ、869年でした。さらに同年の12月5日は870年になります。英訳は原文に従い859年としましたが、この点ご検討ください。他、数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the government set forth the idea of using Emishi in place of Sakimori and the army (of ancient Japan) which had become weak (Daijokanpu [official documents from Daijokan to local governments] on 14 January, 859, &quot;Ruiju sandai kaku [Assorted regulations from Three Reigns]&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、実際には俘囚・夷俘は移配先に馴染めずにたびたび地域との衝突や反乱を起こしたために、弘仁2年（811年）に陸奥国より俘囚を現地に止めて支配を行う旨の奏請が行われて受理された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, however, because barbarians did not adapt themselves to the places they were sent, and had conflicts with and rose against the locals quite often, a petition from Mutsu Province to keep and control barbarians in their original place was created in 811, and was accepted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割しました。）数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, however, because barbarians did not adapt themselves to the places they were sent, and had conflicts with and rose against the locals quite often, a petition from Mutsu Province to keep and control barbarians in their original place was created in 811, and was accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>以後、大規模な移配は行われなくなり、代わって既に移配された俘囚・夷俘を小規模集団単位で二次移配する事例が増加する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this petition was accepted, Ihai was no longer carried out on a large scale; instead, the barbarians who had already been sent to other places were sent again to new places in small groups.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（一原文に対し数訳文になっていたので、分割し、かつ二文を一文に統合しました。）数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this petition was accepted, Ihai was no longer carried out on a large scale; instead, the barbarians who had already been sent to other places were sent again to new places in small groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>やがて、寛平9年（897年）には移配した蝦夷を奥羽へ送還する政策を打ち出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 897 the policy to send back Ezo, who had been brought to other places, to Oshu area was worked out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 897, a policy was announced to send Emishi back to the Ou region.</e>
<cmt>Ezo を Emishi に修正しました。 Changed a bit.Oshu area を Ou region に修正しました。他、数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 897, a policy was announced to send Emishi back to the Ou region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これにより全国へ移配されていた蝦夷のほとんどは奥羽へ還住することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this policy most Ezo who had been sent to the areas throughout the nation went back to Oshu and lived there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this policy, most Emishi who had been sent throughout the nation went back to the Ou region and lived there again.</e>
<cmt>Ezo を Emishi に修正しました。to the areas を削除しました。Oshu を Ou region に修正しました。他、数か所修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this policy, most Emishi who had been sent throughout the nation went back to the Ou region and lived there again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Metromint(id:236339), Fryed-peach(id:63402), 軽功(id:40602), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>