<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紙屋院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamiyain (紙屋院)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamiyain (紙屋院)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamiyain</e>
<cmt>漢字削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紙屋院（かみやいん）は律令制における図書寮の別所（付属機関）で朝廷で用いる紙の製造を扱った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As an affiliate department of Zushoryo (the Bureau of Drawings and Books) under the Ritsuryo system, Kamiyain manufactured paper used in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As an affiliate department of Zushoryo (the Bureau of Drawings and Books) under the Ritsuryo system, Kamiyain manufactured paper used in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As an affiliate department of Zushoryo (the Bureau of Drawings and Books) under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), Kamiyain manufactured paper used in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>律令制の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「紙屋」と略する場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was sometimes abbreviated to &apos;Kamiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was sometimes abbreviated to &apos;Kamiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was sometimes abbreviated to &apos;Kamiya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>朝廷などで公私の用向きに充てる新規の和紙や中古和紙である漉返紙（宿紙）などの製造にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It produced new paper for public or private use in the Imperial Court, and recycled paper called sukigaeshi-gami (paper made from dissolved old paper), or shuku-gami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It produced new paper for public or private use in the Imperial Court, and recycled paper called sukigaeshi-gami (paper made from dissolved old paper), or shuku-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It produced new paper for public or private use in the Imperial Court, and recycled paper called sukigaeshi-gami (paper made from dissolved old paper), or shuku-gami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>紙屋院で作られた和紙は紙屋紙と呼ばれて、神亀5年（728年）にその名称が見られる（「正倉院文書」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paper manufactured by Kamiyain was called kamiyashi, which is found in a record of 728 (&apos;Shoso-in monjo&apos; (Documents of Shoso-in)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paper manufactured by Kamiyain was called kamiyashi, which was found in a record from 728 (&apos;Shoso-in monjo&apos; (Documents of Shoso-in)).</e>
<cmt>Edited forflow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paper manufactured by Kamiyain was called kamiyashi, which was found in a record from 728 (&apos;Shoso-in monjo&apos; (Documents of Shoso-in)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>養老律令によれば、図書寮に属した技術者にあたる造紙手（ぞうししゅ）4名とその下で働く品部の紙戸が山背国（後の山城国）に50戸置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Yoro Ritsuryo Code (code promulgated in the Yoro era), there were four zoshishu, or paper making technicians, who belonged to Zushonoryo, and fifty kamiko (hereditary artisans for paper making under the government management) belonging to Shinabe (a rank of technicians in offices), who worked under zoshishu, were placed in Yamashiro no Kuni.</e>
<cmt>造紙手→zoshishu (paper making technicians)[定訳不明]品部→Shinabe (a rank of technicians in offices)[定訳不明]紙戸→kamiko (hereditary artisans for paper making under government management)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Yoro Ritsuryo Code (code promulgated in the Yoro era), there were four zoshishu, or paper making technicians, who belonged to Zushonoryo, and fifty kamiko (hereditary artisans for paper making under the government management) belonging to Shinabe (a rank of technicians in offices), who worked under zoshishu, were placed in Yamashiro no Kuni.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the Yoro Ritsuryo Code (code promulgated in the Yoro era), there were four zoshishu, or paper making technicians, who belonged to Zushonoryo, and 50 kamiko (hereditary artisans for paper making under the government management) belonging to Shinabe (a rank of technicians in offices), who worked under zoshishu, were placed in Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>Yamashiro no Kuni→the Yamashiro Provincefifty→50</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安京遷都に伴い、嵯峨野の天神川沿いに移されて設備の充実が図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the establishment of Heiankyo, Kamiyain was moved to a riverside of Tenjin-gawa River in Sagano, and its facilities were improved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the establishment of Heiankyo, Kamiyain was moved to a riverside of Tenjin-gawa River in Sagano, and its facilities were improved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the establishment of Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), Kamiyain was moved to a riverside of Tenjin-gawa River in Sagano, and its facilities were improved.</e>
<cmt>平安京の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>延喜式によれば、布紙・穀紙・麻紙・斐紙・苦参紙など毎年合わせて2万枚を漉いて内蔵寮に納める規定となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) stipulated that a total of twenty thousand sheets of paper such as fushi (cloth made of paper threads), kokushi (paper made from paper Mulberry tree), mashi (paper made of hemp), hishi (high-quality paper made from Gampi tree), and kujinshi (paper made from Sophora plant) should be produced, and delivered to Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses) every year.</e>
<cmt>布紙→fushi (cloth made of paper threads)[定訳不明]穀紙→kokushi (paper made from paper Mulberry tree)[定訳不明]麻紙→mashi (paper made of hemp)[定訳不明]斐紙→hishi (high-quality paper made from Gampi tree)[定訳不明]苦参紙→kujinshi (paper made from Sophora plant)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) stipulated that a total of twenty thousand sheets of paper such as fushi (cloth made of paper threads), kokushi (paper made from paper Mulberry tree), mashi (paper made of hemp), hishi (high-quality paper made from Gampi tree), and kujinshi (paper made from Sophora plant) should be produced, and delivered to Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses) every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) stipulated that a total of twenty thousand sheets of paper such as fushi (cloth made of paper threads), kokushi (paper made from paper mulberry tree), mashi (paper made from hemp), hishi (high-quality paper made from gampi tree), and kujinshi (paper made from sophora plant) should be produced, and delivered to Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses) every year.</e>
<cmt>of hemp→from hempMulberry→mulberryGampi→gampiSophora→sophora</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>南北朝時代_(日本)に紙屋院そのものは廃絶したが、その職人と技術はそのまま京都における製紙業者に引き継がれ、蔵人所を本所として結成した紙座（和紙の製造・販売者による座）である宿紙上座は、その流れを汲んでいるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Kamiyain was abolished during the period of Northern and Southern Dynasties, paper manufacturers in Kyoto took over Kamiyain&apos;s artisans and technology intact, and Shukushikamiza, which was kamiza (a trading association of paper manufacturers and distributors) with Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) as its honjo (proprietor or guarantor), is said to have been one of their descendants.</e>
<cmt>本所→honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor)[定訳不明]紙座→kamiza (trading association of paper manufacturers and distributors)[定訳不明]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Kamiyain was abolished during the period of Northern and Southern Dynasties, paper manufacturers in Kyoto took over Kamiyain&apos;s artisans and technology intact, and Shukushikamiza, which was kamiza (a trading association of paper manufacturers and distributors) with Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) as its honjo (proprietor or guarantor), is said to have been one of their descendants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Kamiyain was abolished during the period of Northern and Southern Courts, paper manufacturers in Kyoto took over Kamiyain&apos;s artisans and technology intact, and Shukushikamiza, which was kamiza (a trading association of paper manufacturers and distributors) with Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) as its honjo (proprietor or guarantor), is said to have been one of their descendants.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>