<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>高札</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosatsu (street bulletin board in important streets and crossings)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosatsu (street bulletin board in important streets and crossings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosatsu (street bulletin board in important streets and crossings)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>高札（こうさつ）とは、古代から明治時代初期にかけて行われた法令（一般法、基本法）を板面に記して往来などに掲示して民衆に周知させる方法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosatsu is the method of public notification by setting up a street bulletin board with written laws and ordinances (general law/the fundamental law) on a board, commonly utilized in Japan since ancient periods until early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosatsu is the method of public notification by setting up a street bulletin board with written laws and ordinances (general law/the fundamental law) on a board, commonly utilized in Japan since ancient periods until early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosatsu is the method of public notification by setting up a street bulletin board with written laws and ordinances (general law/the fundamental law) on a board, commonly utilized in Japan since ancient periods until early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、特定の相手や事柄を対象として制定された法令（特別法）を記した同様の掲示を制札（せいさつ）と呼ぶが、その実際の運用上は厳密に区別されていたとは言い難かったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar method of notifying specific act and laws issued to a specific person, or the laws issued for particular incident was called Seisatsu, although it was difficult to clearly distinguish between Kousatsu and Seisatsu in actual circumstances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar bulletin board with written laws and ordinances (special law) issued to a specific person and for particular incident was called Seisatsu but it was difficult to clearly distinguish between Kousatsu and Seisatsu in actual circumstances.</e>
<cmt>前半部分を上記の文と合わせ修正、although→but　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar bulletin board with written laws and ordinances (special law) issued to a specific person and for particular incident was called Seisatsu but it was difficult to clearly distinguish between Kousatsu and Seisatsu in actual circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>その起源は確かでないものの、延暦元年（782年）の太政官符に官符の内容を官庁や往来に掲示して、民衆に告知するように命じた指示が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the origin of Kousatsu has not been clearly identified, Dajo kanpu (official documents from Dajokan, or Great Council of State) issued in 782 describes about the order of notifying the contents of kanpu to general public by setting up Kosatsu at government offices or on major streets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the origin of Kousatsu has not been clearly identified, Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State) issued in 782 describes the order of notifying the contents of kanpu to general public by setting up Kosatsu at government offices or on major streets.</e>
<cmt>「太政官符」を用語集の通りに修正しました。about を除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the origin of Kousatsu has not been clearly identified, Daijokanpu (official documents issued by Daijokan, Grand Council of State) issued in 782 describes the order of notifying the contents of kanpu to general public by setting up Kosatsu at government offices or on major streets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>以後、武家政権でも同様の方法が取られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, later military or feudal governments adapted the same method of public notification.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, military or feudal governments adapted the same method of public notification.</e>
<cmt>later を除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, military or feudal governments adapted the same method of public notification.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>だが、これを最も良く用いて全国的な制度として確立したのは江戸幕府及び藩であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and feudal clans, which utilized this method as a nation-wide notification system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and feudal clans which utilized this method as a nation-wide notification system.</e>
<cmt>コンマを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and feudal clans which utilized this method as a nation-wide notification system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>高札制度の目的としては、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purposes of Kosatsu system were considered to be as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purposes of Kosatsu system were considered to be as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purposes of Kosatsu system were considered to be as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>新しい法令を民衆に公示する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to make a public notification of new acts and laws;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to notify the public of new acts and laws;</e>
<cmt>make a public notification→notify the public としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to notify the public of new acts and laws;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>民衆に法の趣旨の周知徹底を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to thoroughly notify the aim of the acts and laws to general public;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to thoroughly notify the aim of the acts and laws to general public;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to thoroughly notify the aim of the acts and laws to general public;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>基本法である事を明示する（違反者は「天下の大罪」であるとして、違反者は死罪などの重い刑に処せられることが多かった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to make clear that the acts and laws were the fundamental laws; (the violator of the laws were severely punished by death penalty or other severe penalties for his/her &quot;great crime of the realm&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to make clear that the acts and laws were the fundamental laws; (the violator of the laws were severely punished by death penalty or other severe penalties for his/her &apos;great crime of the realm&apos;)</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to make clear that the acts and laws were the fundamental laws; (the violator of the laws were severely punished by death penalty or other severe penalties for his/her &apos;great crime of the realm&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>民衆の遵法精神の涵養を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to cultivate the law-abiding spirit of general public to the acts and laws</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to cultivate the law-abiding spirit of general public to the acts and laws</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to cultivate the law-abiding spirit of general public to the acts and laws</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>民衆からの告訴（謂わば密告）の奨励（特にキリシタン札（切支丹札）などには高額の賞金が掲げられた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to encourage general public to file a complaint for finding criminals; (as it were, an anonymous tip. High reward was offered for particular complaint, such as to accuse Christian)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to encourage general public to file a complaint for finding criminals; (as it were, an anonymous tip. High reward was offered for particular complaint, such as to accuse Christian.)</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to encourage general public to file a complaint for finding criminals; (as it were, an anonymous tip. High reward was offered for particular complaint, such as to accuse Christian.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>幕府や大名の存在感の誇示。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was to represent the influence and power of Bakufu or local clan/feudal lord;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was to represent the influence and power of Bakufu and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord);</e>
<cmt>「大名」を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was to represent the influence and power of Bakufu and daimyo (Japanese feudal lord);</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>などが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those can be considered as the reasons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those can be considered as the reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those can be considered as the reasons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="14">
<j>主な代表的な高札としては、寛文元年（1661年）の5枚の高札（撰銭、切支丹、火事場、駄賃、雑事）や正徳 (日本)元年（1711年）の5枚の高札（忠孝、切支丹、火付、駄賃、毒薬）、明治維新とともに新政府から出された五榜の掲示などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most commonly known Kosatsu are 5 boards of Kosatsu published in 1661 (&quot;Erizeni&quot; for eliminating low quality money, &quot;Kirishitan,&quot; (Christian) the ban of &quot;Christianity,&quot; &quot;Kajiba,&quot; the law at the scene of a fire for preventing theft at the scene, &quot;Dachin,&quot; the law for money or goods for the purpose of reward, &quot;Zatsuji,&quot; the law for personal affairs) or 5 boards of Kosatsu published in 1771 (&quot;Chuko,&quot; the loyalty and filial piety, &quot;Kirishitan,&quot; the ban of Christianity, &quot;Hitsuke,&quot; the law at the scene of a fire, &quot;Dachin,&quot; the law for money or goods for the purpose of reward, &quot;Dokuyaku, &quot;the law for treating poisons) and 5 posts on the streets released by a new government after the Meiji restoration.</e>
<cmt>定訳だと一部不自然なため他のフレーズにて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most commonly known Kosatsu are 5 boards of Kosatsu published in 1661 (&quot;Erizeni&quot; for eliminating low quality money, &quot;Kirishitan,&quot; [Christian] the ban of &quot;Christianity,&quot; &quot;Kajiba,&quot; the law at the scene of a fire for preventing theft at the scene, &quot;Dachin,&quot; the law for money or goods for the purpose of reward and &quot;Zatsuji,&quot; the law for personal affairs), 5 boards of Kosatsu published in 1771 (&quot;Chuko,&quot; the loyalty and filial piety, &quot;Kirishitan,&quot; the ban of Christianity, &quot;Hitsuke,&quot; the law at the scene of a fire, &quot;Dachin,&quot; the law for money or goods for the purpose of reward and &quot;Dokuyaku, &quot;the law for treating poisons) and 5 posts on the streets released by a new government after the Meiji restoration.</e>
<cmt>(Christian)→[Christian]にし、括弧内にそれぞれand を加え、or 5 boards～→, 5 boards～にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most commonly known Kosatsu are 5 boards of Kosatsu published in 1661 (&quot;Erizeni&quot; for eliminating low quality money, &quot;Kirishitan,&quot; [Christian] the ban of &quot;Christianity,&quot; &quot;Kajiba,&quot; the law at the scene of a fire for preventing theft at the scene, &quot;Dachin,&quot; the law for money or goods for the purpose of reward and &quot;Zatsuji,&quot; the law for personal affairs), 5 boards of Kosatsu published in 1771 (&quot;Chuko,&quot; the loyalty and filial piety, &quot;Kirishitan,&quot; the ban of Christianity, &quot;Hitsuke,&quot; the law at the scene of a fire, &quot;Dachin,&quot; the law for money or goods for the purpose of reward and &quot;Dokuyaku, &quot;the law for treating poisons) and 5 posts on the streets released by a new government after the Meiji restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>高札場（制札場）と庶民教育への利用</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Set up of the official Kosatsu site (Seisatsu site) and the usage of Kosatsu for instructional purpose of general public</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Set up the official Kosatsu site (Seisatsu site) and the use for the education of common people.</e>
<cmt>Set up of→Set up, usage→use, of Kosatsu for～→for the education～　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Set up the official Kosatsu site (Seisatsu site) and the use for the education of common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>幕府は人々の往来の激しい地点や関所や港、大きな橋の袂、更には町や村の入り口や中心部などの目立つ場所に高札場（制札場）と呼ばれる設置場所を設けて、諸藩に対してもこれに倣うように厳しく命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakufu established a particular site for setting up Kosatsu (Seisatsu) at obvious, noticeable locations for general public, such as the busy corner of the streets, sekisho, (checking station) nearby at a large bridge, or at the gates or the center of a town or a village, and Bakufu strictly ordered each domain to follow the method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakufu established a particular site for setting up Kosatsu (Seisatsu) at obvious, noticeable locations for general public, such as the busy corner of the streets, sekisho (checking station), nearby at a large bridge, and at the gates or the center of a town or a village, and Bakufu strictly ordered each domain to follow the method.</e>
<cmt>sekisho, (checking station)→sekisho (checking station), or at the gates→and at the gates としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu established a particular site for setting up Kosatsu (Seisatsu) at obvious, noticeable locations for general public, such as the busy corner of the streets, sekisho (checking station), nearby at a large bridge, and at the gates or the center of a town or a village, and Bakufu strictly ordered each domain to follow the method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これに従って諸藩でも同様の措置を取ると同時に自藩の法令を併せて掲示して自藩の法令の公示に用いた（代表的な高札場としては江戸日本橋 (東京都中央区)、京都三条大橋、大坂高麗橋、金沢橋場町、仙台芭蕉辻などが挙げられる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the Bakufu order, each domain took the similar measure, while Kosatsu was also utilized for the public notification of the act of each domain. (Major examples of the set up location of Kosatsu can be mentioned as follows; Edo Nihonbashi, (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture) Kyoto Sanjo O-hashi Bridge, Osaka Korai-bashi Bridge, Kanazawa Hashiba-cho, Sendai Bashotsuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the Bakufu order, each domain took the similar measure, while Kosatsu was also utilized for the public notification of the act of each domain. (Major examples of the set up location of Kosatsu can be mentioned as follows; Edo Nihonbashi [Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture], Kyoto Sanjo O-hashi Bridge, Osaka Korai-bashi Bridge, Kanazawa Hashiba-cho, Sendai Bashotsuji and so on.)</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧、コンマの位置を修正、and so on を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the Bakufu order, each domain took the similar measure, while Kosatsu was also utilized for the public notification of the act of each domain. (Major examples of the set up location of Kosatsu can be mentioned as follows; Edo Nihonbashi [Chuo Ward, Tokyo Prefecture], Kyoto Sanjo O-hashi Bridge, Osaka Korai-bashi Bridge, Kanazawa Hashiba-cho, Sendai Bashotsuji and so on.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また、宿場においても多く設置され、各宿村間の里程測定の拠点ともされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kosatsu was also commonly set up at various posting stations, which became the measurement footholds of the distance between each station.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kosatsu was also commonly set up at various posting stations, which became the measurement footholds of the distance between each station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kosatsu was also commonly set up at various posting stations, which became the measurement footholds of the distance between each station.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このため、移転はもとより、高札の文字が不明になったときでも、領主の許可なくしては墨入れ（高札は墨で書かれていたため、風雨には大変弱かった）もできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For its official nature of the board, it was not allowed to relocate or reprint the written notes (because Kosatsu was written in black ink, it was very weak against winds and rains) without the permission of feudal lord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For its official nature of the board, it was not allowed to relocate or reprint the written notes (because Kosatsu was written in black ink, it was very weak against winds and rains) without the permission of feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For its official nature of the board, it was not allowed to relocate or reprint the written notes (because Kosatsu was written in black ink, it was very weak against winds and rains) without the permission of feudal lord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その代わりに幕府や諸藩では「高札番」という役職を設けて常時、高札場の整備・管理に務めさせ、高札の修繕や新設にあたらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of requesting the permission for some minor issues, bakufu and domains provided the position called &quot;Kosatsuban&quot; (the manager of notice boards) to manage the Kosatsu site in full-time base, for repairing or setting up Kosatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of requesting the permission for some minor issues, bakufu and domains provided the position called &apos;Kosatsuban&apos; (the manager of notice boards) to manage the Kosatsu site in full-time base, for repairing or setting up Kosatsu.</e>
<cmt>クオーテーションマークを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of requesting the permission for some minor issues, bakufu and domains provided the position called &apos;Kosatsuban&apos; (the manager of notice boards) to manage the Kosatsu site in full-time base, for repairing or setting up Kosatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また、この民衆への周知徹底の為に高札の文面には、一般の法令では使われない簡易な仮名交じり文や仮名文が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to thoroughly deliver the contents of the notes to general public, the notes on Kosatsu was written in easily understandable mixed writing (characters and kana) or kana sentences, differentiated from the sentence style used for describing general law in code books.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to thoroughly deliver the contents of the notes to the people, the notes of Kosatsu was written in easily understandable mixed writing (characters and kana) or kana sentences, differentiated from the sentence style used for describing general law in code books.</e>
<cmt>general public→the people, on→of としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to thoroughly deliver the contents of the notes to the people, the notes of Kosatsu was written in easily understandable mixed writing (characters and kana) or kana sentences, differentiated from the sentence style used for describing general law in code books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>更には当時の幕府は法律に関する出版を厳しく禁じる方針を採っていたにも関らず、高札に掲示された法令に関しては「万民に周知の事」と言う理由で簡単に出版が許されたばかりでなく、高札の文章は寺子屋の書き取りの教科書としても推奨されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even though bakufu had maintained the policy of prohibiting the publication regarding any general laws, a permission of publishing the act and laws noted on Kosatsu was obtained easily in order to thoroughly notify those act and laws to general public; the sentences noted on Kosatsu were even recommended for terakoya study, (a private elementary school in the Edo period) for those student to practice dictation skills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though bakufu had maintained the policy of prohibiting the publication regarding any general laws, a permission of publishing the act and laws noted on Kosatsu was not only allowed to publish easily in order to thoroughly &apos;notify those act and laws to all the people&apos;, but also the sentences noted on Kosatsu were recommended as textbooks for Terakoya (temple elementary school during the Edo period) to practice dictation skills.</e>
<cmt>「寺子屋」を用語集の通りに修正、obtain→not only allowed to publish、general public→all the people、the sentences～even→but also the sentences～　として、study、 those studentsを除き、「教科書として」as textbooksを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though bakufu had maintained the policy of prohibiting the publication regarding any general laws, a permission of publishing the act and laws noted on Kosatsu was not only allowed to publish easily in order to thoroughly &apos;notify those act and laws to all the people&apos;, but also the sentences noted on Kosatsu were recommended as textbooks for Terakoya (temple elementary school during the Edo period) to practice dictation skills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>高札・制札の廃止</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The abolition of Kosatsu and Seisatsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The abolition of Kosatsu and Seisatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The abolition of Kosatsu and Seisatsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="22">
<j>だが、明治7年（1874年）に高札の廃止が決定され、2年後には完全に撤去された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Meiji government decided to discontinue Kosatsu system in 1874, and entire Kosatsu were removed completely from public locations within two years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Meiji government decided to discontinue Kosatsu system in 1874, and entire Kosatsu were removed completely from public locations within two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Meiji government decided to discontinue Kosatsu system in 1874, and entire Kosatsu were removed completely from public locations within two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その理由としては公式には「庶民への周知徹底が図られた」事を理由とし、また背景には「切支丹札（キリスト教禁止）に対する欧米の反発」と言われているが、実際の理由としては、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officially announced reason of this decision was that its purpose to notify the general laws to the common people was fulfilled enough, while there was also a background that Western countries expressed objection toward the ban of Christianity in Japan; the actual reasons for the abolition of Kosatsu would have been as follows;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officially announced reason of this decision was that its purpose to notify the general laws to the common people was fulfilled enough, while there was also a background that Western countries expressed objection toward the ban of Christianity in Japan; the actual reasons for the abolition of Kosatsu would have been as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officially announced reason of this decision was that its purpose to notify the general laws to the common people was fulfilled enough, while there was also a background that Western countries expressed objection toward the ban of Christianity in Japan; the actual reasons for the abolition of Kosatsu would have been as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>明治維新とともに法令が一変して、手続が追いつかない事（また、長く掲げる事を目的とした高札の「固定性」も漸進的に法令を改正していく新政府の方針にそぐわなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The slow procedure of setting up Kosatsu could not follow the complete changes in the general acts and laws promoted by the Meiji Restoration; (the stationary nature of Kosatsu system for long-term posting of notes in public also did not meet the policy of the new Meiji government who wanted to drastically change and restore the general laws)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The slow procedure of setting up Kosatsu could not follow the complete changes in the general acts and laws promoted by the Meiji Restoration; (the stationary nature of Kosatsu system for long-term posting of notes in public also did not meet the policy of the new Meiji government who wanted to drastically change and restore the general laws)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The slow procedure of setting up Kosatsu could not follow the complete changes in the general acts and laws promoted by the Meiji Restoration; (the stationary nature of Kosatsu system for long-term posting of notes in public also did not meet the policy of the new Meiji government who wanted to drastically change and restore the general laws)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>当時の財政難の政府には維持費が出せなかった事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the economic difficulties that the government of the day could not manage the preservation cost of Kosatsu;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the economic difficulties that the government of the day could not manage the preservation cost of Kosatsu;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the economic difficulties that the government of the day could not manage the preservation cost of Kosatsu;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="26">
<j>新しい警察・司法制度の確立や教育制度や新聞などの普及によって、高札に依存しなくても法令の周知徹底を図る手段が新たに登場した事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new methods for thoroughly notifying general laws to the public without depending on Kosatsu system were developed, by newly founded police and judicial systems, education system, and the popularized mass media such as newspapers;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new methods for thoroughly notifying general laws to the public without depending on Kosatsu system were developed, by newly founded police and judicial systems, educational system, and the popularized mass media such as newspapers;</e>
<cmt>education→educational　に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new methods for thoroughly notifying general laws to the public without depending on Kosatsu system were developed, by newly founded police and judicial systems, educational system, and the popularized mass media such as newspapers;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>近代的な欧米の法体系が流入して「法律（法体系）の一元化」が求められた結果、全く同趣旨の法令でありながら官吏向けの法令と一般向けの高札が並存するのは明らかに異質であったこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The inflow of a modern European judicial system promoted the &quot;unification of the legal system in Japan,&quot; therefore it was obviously an awkward situation that two variants of a single code co-existed in a government official version and in Kosatsu version for general public;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The inflow of a modern European judicial system promoted the &apos;unification of the law (legal system),&apos; therefore it was obviously an awkward situation that two variants of a single code co-existed in a government official version and in Kosatsu version for general public;</e>
<cmt>「法律（法体系）の一元化」の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The inflow of a modern European judicial system promoted the &apos;unification of the law (legal system),&apos; therefore it was obviously an awkward situation that two variants of a single code co-existed in a government official version and in Kosatsu version for general public;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>などがあったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those could have been the actual reasons of the discontinuation of Kosatsu system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those could have been the actual reasons of the discontinuation of Kosatsu system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those could have been the actual reasons of the discontinuation of Kosatsu system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), ととりん(id:31982), A6M4(id:14155), Shin-改(id:9914), 経済準学士(id:22656), AEONseven&amp;i(id:89677), 水野白楓(id:22811), Onething(id:65263), IwaimBot(id:190695), Wakkubox(id:30396), Extrahitz(id:26245), Toto-tarou(id:16648), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>