<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>改易</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaieki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaieki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaieki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>改易（かいえき）とは、律令制度では現職者の任を解き新任者を補任することをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the term kaieki referred to removing someone from the current post and appointing someone new to that position, and in the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, the term kaieki referred to making changes in duties of Shugo and Jito (military governors and estate stewards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the term kaieki referred to removing someone from their current post and appointing someone new to that position. In the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, the term kaieki referred to making changes to the duties of Shugo and Jito (military governors and estate stewards).</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), the term kaieki referred to removing someone from their current post and appointing someone new to that position.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉時代・室町時代には守護・地頭の職の変更を意味した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, the term kaieki referred to making changes to the duties of Shugo and Jito (military governors and estate stewards).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代においては大名、旗本などの武士に課せられた刑罰を意味し、武士の身分を剥奪して所領と城・屋敷を没収することをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the term kaieki referred to punishments to samurai such as Daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) and Hatamoto (direct vassals of the shogun) where they were ousted as samurai, and their lands, castles, or residences were confiscated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the term kaieki referred to punishments to samurai such as Daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) and Hatamoto (direct vassals of the shogun) where they were ousted as samurai, and their lands, castles, or residences were confiscated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the term kaieki referred to a punishment to samurai, including territorial lords (called &quot;daimyo&quot;) and direct vassals of the shogun (called &quot;hatamoto&quot;), by which they were deprived of their status as samurai, along with their territories, castles and residences.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>除封ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keieki can also be expressed as the Japanese word jofu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keieki can also be expressed as the Japanese word jofu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaieki can also be expressed as the Japanese word jofu.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また所領を削減されることを減封という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, having the size of lands in possession reduced is called genpo in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, having the size of lands in possession reduced is called genpo in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, having the size of lands in possession reduced is called genpo in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以下、江戸時代の改易について叙述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaieki in the Edo period is described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaieki in the Edo period is described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaieki in the Edo period is described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>江戸時代の大名家の改易</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaieki applied to Daimyo families in the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaieki applied to Daimyo families in the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaieki applied to Daimyo families in the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代、大名家が改易されると、何らかの重い罪を受けての場合は大名は斬首（島原の乱の松倉勝家）または切腹（元禄赤穂事件の浅野長矩など）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, when a Daimyo family became subject to kaieki, they were beheaded (Katsuike MATSUKURA in the Shimabara War, for example) or were forced to carry out Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) (Naganori ASANO in the Genroku Ako Incident, for example) if they committed a serious crime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, when a Daimyo family became subject to kaieki, they were beheaded (Katsuike MATSUKURA in the Shimabara War, for example) or were forced to carry out Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) (Naganori ASANO in the Genroku Ako Incident, for example) if they committed a serious crime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, when a Daimyo family became subject to kaieki, they were beheaded (Katsuike MATSUKURA in the Shimabara War, for example) or were forced to carry out Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) (Naganori ASANO in the Genroku Ako Incident, for example) if they committed a serious crime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>それ以外でも他の大名家などへお預けとなり、厳しい監視の下で蟄居させられる（松平忠直・松平忠輝など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Or, they may have been forced to stay with a different Daimyo family to live under strict surveillance (Tadanao MATSUDAIRA and Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, for example).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Or, they may have been forced to stay with a different Daimyo family to live under strict surveillance (Tadanao MATSUDAIRA and Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, for example).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Or, they may have been forced to stay with a different Daimyo family to live under strict surveillance (Tadanao MATSUDAIRA and Tadateru MATSUDAIRA, for example).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>城と領地は没収となり、多くの家臣は禄を失って浪人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castles and lands were confiscated, and so many vassals could no longer receive a stipend and became ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castles and lands were confiscated, and so many vassals could no longer receive a stipend and became ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castles and lands were confiscated, and so many vassals could no longer receive a stipend and became ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし、改易の処分を受けても後に許され、大名本人または子孫や一族の者が小大名や旗本に取り立てられ家名が存続することも少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note, however, quite a lot of Daimyo were forgiven after receiving the kaieki decision and continued their family line as they or some of their descendents were appointed to feudal lords or direct vassals of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note, however, many Daimyo were forgiven after receiving the kaieki decision and continued their family line as they or some of their descendents were appointed as feudal lords or direct vassals of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note, however, many Daimyo were forgiven after receiving the kaieki decision and continued their family line as they or some of their descendents were appointed as feudal lords or direct vassals of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>譜代・親藩の中には、改易処分のあとに許されて、その子孫が旧知とほぼ同じ待遇で、復帰した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there were some cases where Fudai and Shinpan (hereditary daimyo and relatives of the Tokugawa family) were forgiven after receiving the kaieki decision, and their descendents returned to the original positions to receive the same stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, there were some cases where Fudai and Shinpan (hereditary daimyo and relatives of the Tokugawa family) were forgiven after receiving the kaieki decision, and their descendents returned to the original positions to receive the same stipend.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, there were some cases where Fudai and Shinpan (hereditary daimyo and relatives of the Tokugawa family) were forgiven after receiving the kaieki decision, and their descendents returned to the original positions to receive almost the same stipend.</e>
<cmt>almost補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>関ヶ原の戦いの戦後処理により石田三成（近江）、小西行長（肥後）、宇喜多秀家（備前岡山）、長宗我部盛親（土佐）を始め西軍についた88の大名家が改易され、毛利氏（毛利輝元）、上杉氏（上杉景勝）など5大名家が大幅な減封を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, 88 Daimyo families that joined the West army, such as Mitsunari ISHIDA (Omi), Yukinaga KONISHI (Higo), Hideie UKITA (Bizen Okayama), and Morichika CHOSOKABE (Tosa), were subjected to kaieki, and also, 5 Daimyo families such as the Mori clan (Terumoto MORI) and Uesugi clan (Kagekatsu UESUGI) were subjected to a severe genpo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, 88 Daimyo families that joined the West army, such as Mitsunari ISHIDA (Omi), Yukinaga KONISHI (Higo), Hideie UKITA (Bizen Okayama), and Morichika CHOSOKABE (Tosa), were subjected to kaieki, and also, 5 Daimyo families such as the Mori clan (Terumoto MORI) and Uesugi clan (Kagekatsu UESUGI) were subjected to a severe genpo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, 88 Daimyo families that joined the West army, such as Mitsunari ISHIDA (Omi), Yukinaga KONISHI (Higo), Hideie UKITA (Bizen Okayama), and Morichika CHOSOKABE (Tosa), were subjected to kaieki, and also, 5 Daimyo families such as the Mori clan (Terumoto MORI) and Uesugi clan (Kagekatsu UESUGI) were subjected to a severe genpo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>大坂の役以後、戦争が無くなると、世嗣断絶と幕法違反による改易が主なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the no-war period after the Siege of Osaka, kaieki was mainly applied as punishments for extinction of a family line or breach of the Shogunate law, and as a result, many Daimyo families were subjected to kaieki for letting their family line become extinct as matsugo yoshi, or adopting a son when a Daimyo was on his deathbed, was now prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the war-free period after the Siege of Osaka, kaieki was mainly applied as punishments for the extinction of a family line or breach of the Shogunate law. As a result, many Daimyo families were subjected to kaieki for letting their family line become extinct as matsugo yoshi, or adopting a son when a Daimyo was on his deathbed, was now prohibited.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the war-free period after the Siege of Osaka, kaieki was mainly applied as punishments for the extinction of a family line or breach of the Shogunate law.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>末期養子（大名が危篤になってから養子を願い出ること）が禁止されていたため、多くの大名家が世嗣断絶により改易となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was prohibited for a Daimyo to apply for an adoption of a son after becoming seriously ill, many Daimyo families suffered kaieki as a result of the extinction of lineages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また福島正則は広島城無断修築を咎められた幕法違反により改易されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Masanori FUKUSHIMA was subjected to kaieki for violation of the Shogunate law when he tried to repair the Hiroshima-jo Castle without permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Masanori FUKUSHIMA was subjected to kaieki for violation of the Shogunate law when he tried to repair Hiroshima-jo Castle without permission.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Masanori FUKUSHIMA was subjected to kaieki for violation of the Shogunate law when he tried to repair Hiroshima-jo Castle without permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>大久保忠隣や本多正純のように幕府内部の権力闘争に敗れて改易された大名もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there were Daimyo such as Tadachika OKUBO and Masazumi HONDA who were subject to kaieki because they lost the power struggle inside the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there were Daimyo such as Tadachika OKUBO and Masazumi HONDA who were subject to kaieki because they lost the power struggle inside the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there were Daimyo such as Tadachika OKUBO and Masazumi HONDA who were subject to kaieki because they lost the power struggle inside the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="18">
<j>江戸時代初期には旧豊臣系大名を中心に大名廃絶政策が取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the Daimyo system abolishment measure was implemented mainly targeting Daimyo of the former Toyotomi family, and as a result, during the three Tokugawa generations of Ieyasu, Hidetada, and Iemitsu, 82 Tozama Daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) families and 49 Fudai and Shinpan (hereditary daimyo and relatives of the Tokugawa family) families were subject to kaieki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Edo period, the Daimyo system abolishment measure was implemented mainly targeting Daimyo of the former Toyotomi family. As a result, during the three Tokugawa generations of Ieyasu, Hidetada, and Iemitsu, 82 Tozama Daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) families and 49 Fudai and Shinpan (hereditary daimyo and relatives of the Tokugawa family) families were subject to kaieki.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Edo period, the Daimyo system abolishment measure was implemented mainly targeting Daimyo of the former Toyotomi family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そのために、徳川家康、徳川秀忠、徳川家光の三代の時代に外様大名82家、親藩・譜代大名49家が改易された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, during the three Tokugawa generations of Ieyasu, Hidetada, and Iemitsu, 82 Tozama Daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) families and 49 Fudai and Shinpan (hereditary daimyo and relatives of the Tokugawa family) families were subject to kaieki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>江戸幕府は改易、減封によって生じた空白地を天領（直轄地）にし、親藩・譜代大名を新たに配置して、外様大名を遠隔地に転封するなどして幕府権力の絶対優位を確立していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu turned lands that became unused as a result of kaieki or genpo into tenryo (bakufu-owned land), allocated Fudai and Shinpan to these lands, and transferred Tozama Daimyo to remote areas in order to maximize the control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu turned disused lands as a result of kaieki or genpo into tenryo (bakufu-owned land), allocated Fudai and Shinpan to these lands, and transferred Tozama Daimyo to remote areas in order to maximize the control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo shogunate gradually established its domination by turning territories that were left unoccupied as a result of kaieki or genpo into shogunate territories and by allocating these territories to the relatives and hereditary vassals of the Tokugawa family and transferring feudal lords unrelated to the family to remote territories.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、改易によって大量の浪人が生じて社会不安につながり、浪人による反乱未遂事件（慶安の変）が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, however, there were many ronin because of kaieki, and this caused social unrest to grow and finally resulted in a rebellion (Keian Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, however, there were many ronin because of kaieki, and this caused social unrest to grow and finally resulted in a rebellion (Keian Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, however, there were many ronin because of kaieki, and this caused social unrest to grow and finally resulted in a rebellion (Keian Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このため幕府は政策を見直し、4代徳川家綱の時代に末期養子の禁は緩和された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the bakufu reviewed its policy and the Matsugo yoshi no kin (ban on adoptation of a son on one&apos;s deathbed) was loosened during the time of the fourth shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the bakufu reviewed its policy and the Matsugo yoshi no kin (ban on adoption of a son on one&apos;s deathbed) was loosened during the time of the fourth shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the bakufu reviewed its policy and the Matsugo yoshi no kin (ban on adoption of a son on one&apos;s deathbed) was loosened during the time of the fourth shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>5代徳川綱吉の時代には廃絶政策は譜代大名に向けられ27家が改易された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the time of the fifth shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the target of the Daimyo abolishment measure shifted to Fudai Daimyo (a daimyo of a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), and as a result, 27 families were subjected to kaieki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the time of the fifth shogun, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the target of the Daimyo abolishment measure shifted to Fudai Daimyo (a daimyo of a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), and as a result, 27 families were subjected to kaieki.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the time of the fifth shogun, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the target of the Daimyo abolishment measure shifted to Fudai Daimyo (a daimyo of a hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family), and as a result, 27 families were subjected to kaieki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>これ以後は幕藩体制が確立して改易、転封は減少して大名は固定化されるようになり、幕末に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate system was established afterwards and accordingly, application of kaieki and transfers decreased, and allocation of Daimyo was fixed until the end of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate system was established afterwards and accordingly, the application of kaieki and transfers decreased, and the allocation of Daimyo was fixed until the end of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate system was established afterwards and accordingly, the application of kaieki and transfers decreased, and the allocation of Daimyo was fixed until the end of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い以降、江戸時代を通じて外様大名127家、親藩・譜代大名121家の計248家が改易されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara through the Edo period, a total of 248 families consisting of 127 Tozama Daimyo families and 121 Shinpan and Fudai Daimyo families were subject to kaieki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara through the Edo period, a total of 248 families consisting of 127 Tozama Daimyo families and 121 Shinpan and Fudai Daimyo families were subject to kaieki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara through the Edo period, a total of 248 families consisting of 127 Tozama Daimyo families and 121 Shinpan and Fudai Daimyo families were subject to kaieki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大坂の役で豊臣氏が滅ぼされて以後、武力抵抗をした大名は皆無であり、全て無抵抗で城と領地を幕府へ明渡している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Toyotomi clan was destroyed in the Siege of Osaka, no more Daimyo attempted armed resistance and all handed over their castles and lands to the bakufu without resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Toyotomi clan was destroyed in the Siege of Osaka, no more Daimyo attempted armed resistance and all handed over their castles and lands to the bakufu without resistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Toyotomi clan was destroyed in the Siege of Osaka, no more Daimyo attempted armed resistance and all handed over their castles and lands to the bakufu without resistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="27">
<j>幕末に長州藩が幕府軍に武力抵抗して打ち勝ち（長州征伐）、幕府の弱体化が顕になって大名への絶対的統制は崩れ、鳥羽伏見の戦い以後の戊辰戦争により幕藩体制は終焉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, the Choshu clan defeated the bakufu army through armed resistance (the Choshu Conquest), the bakufu dramatically lost its power and absolute control over the Daimyo, and the shogunate system was destroyed as a result of the Boshin War that occurred after the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of the Edo period, the Choshu clan defeated the bakufu army through armed resistance (the Choshu Conquest), the bakufu dramatically lost its power and absolute control over the Daimyo, and the shogunate system was destroyed as a result of the Boshin War that occurred after the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of the Edo period, the Choshu clan defeated the bakufu army through armed resistance (the Choshu Conquest), the bakufu dramatically lost its power and absolute control over the Daimyo, and the shogunate system was destroyed as a result of the Boshin War that occurred after the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="28">
<j>戊辰戦争後、明治新政府により1家（請西藩）が改易され、会津藩、仙台藩など22家が減封の処分を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Boshin War, the new Meiji government subjected one family (Jozai clan) to kaieki and 22 families such as the Aizu and Sendai clans to genpo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Boshin War, the new Meiji government subjected one family (Jozai clan) to kaieki and 22 families, such as the Aizu and Sendai clans, to genpo.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Boshin War, the new Meiji government subjected one family (Jozai clan) to kaieki and 22 families, such as the Aizu and Sendai clans, to genpo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>なお、廃藩置県直前に福岡藩の黒田長知が偽札事件を理由に藩知事を更迭されて代わりに有栖川宮熾仁親王が任命されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note that, immediately before Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) occurred, Nagatomo KURODA of the Fukuoka domain was forced to resign as the governor of the domain due to the fake bill incident and Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito was appointed to take over the position, and this was generally considered to be kaieki because the governor position could be hereditary like the lord position even after lands and people were returned to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note that, immediately before Haihan-chiken (abolition of fuedal domains and establishment of prefectures) occurred, Nagatomo KURODA of the Fukuoka domain was forced to resign as the governor of the domain due to the fake bill incident and Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito was appointed to take over the position. This was generally considered to be kaieki because the governor position could be hereditary like the lord position even after lands and people were returned to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note that, immediately before Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) occurred, Nagatomo KURODA of the Fukuoka Domain was forced to resign as the governor of the domain due to the fake bill incident and Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito was appointed to take over the position.</e>
<cmt>スペル一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかし、版籍奉還後の藩知事にも藩主同様の世襲が認めれていたことから、事実上の改易であったと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was generally considered to be kaieki because the governor position could be hereditary like the lord position even after lands and people were returned to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="31">
<j>改易の主な理由</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major reasons for applying kaieki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major reasons for applying kaieki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major reasons for applying kaieki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>軍事的理由（関ヶ原の戦い、大坂の役）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military reasons (the Battle of Sekigahara and the Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military reasons (the Battle of Sekigahara and the Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military reasons (the Battle of Sekigahara and the Siege of Osaka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>世嗣断絶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extinction of a family line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extinction of a family line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extinction of a family line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>幕法（武家諸法度）違反（城郭の違法な増改築、違法婚姻等）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Breach (illegal extension or reconstruction of castles or illegal marriage) of the Shogunate law (Buke Shohatto (code for the warrior households))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Breach (illegal extension or reconstruction of castles or illegal marriage) of the Shogunate law (Buke Shohatto [code for the warrior households])</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Breach (illegal extension or reconstruction of castles or illegal marriage) of the Shogunate law (Buke Shohatto [code for the warrior households])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>領内統治の不行届（御家騒動、百姓一揆）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Failure to properly control territories (family troubles or peasant revolts)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Failure to properly control territories (family troubles or peasant revolts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Failure to properly control territories (family troubles or peasant revolts)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>乱行、乱心</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misconduct or outrageous behavior due to mental instability</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misconduct or outrageous behavior due to mental instability</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misconduct or outrageous behavior due to mental instability</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="37">
<j>関ヶ原合戦で敗れた大名家の改易・減封</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaieki or genpo applied to Daimyo families that lost in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaieki or genpo applied to Daimyo families that lost in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaieki or genpo applied to Daimyo families that lost in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>関ヶ原戦の敗戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Loss in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Loss in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Loss in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="39">
<j>関ヶ原戦で西軍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being in the West army in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being in the West army in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being in the West army in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="40">
<j>関ヶ原戦で逃亡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Escaped from the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Escaped from the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Escaped from the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>関ヶ原戦で中立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remained neutral in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remained neutral in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remained neutral in the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="42">
<j>江戸時代に改易に遭った大名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo that were subjected to kaieki during the Edo era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo that were subjected to kaieki during the Edo era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo that were subjected to kaieki during the Edo era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>備考</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remarks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>大名における実例はないものの、一般の武士における改易の理由として多いものに当主・隠居の欠落（出奔・無断脱藩）によるものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there have been no examples with Daimyo, one of the most common reasons for kaieki of general samurai was loss of the head of the family or elders who had retired (through running away or leaving the domain without notice).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there have been no examples with Daimyo, one of the most common reasons for kaieki of general samurai was loss of the head of the family or elders who had retired (through running away or leaving the domain without notice).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although we have no examples of Daimyo being subjected to kaieki, one of the most common reasons for the kaieki of ordinary samurai was the running away (flight or escape from one&apos;s domain) of the current or former heads of households.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>この場合には後継者がいても改易され、捕らえられた場合には「不忠」を理由に処刑される事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When this occurred, kaieki was applied even though there was a successor, and when those who had run away were captured, they were sometimes executed because they were &apos;not loyal.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When this occurred, kaieki was applied even though there was a successor, and when those who had run away were captured, they were sometimes executed because they were &apos;not loyal.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When this occurred, kaieki was applied even though there was a successor, and when those who had run away were captured, they were sometimes executed because they were &apos;not loyal.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="45">
<j>なお、一旦改易された者が恩赦などを受ける場合もあったが、この場合の効果は改易される前の主君への再仕官が認められるという程度であり、改易前の禄高で復帰できた例は少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were some cases where those who were once subject to kaieki received amnesty, but it would only allow them to serve the lord that they had served before kaieki, and there were only a few cases in which they returned to their services and received the same amount of stipend as they had received before kaieki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were some cases where those who were once subject to kaieki received amnesty, but it would only allow them to serve the lord that they had served before kaieki, and there were only a few cases in which they returned to their services and received the same amount of stipend as they had received before kaieki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were some cases where those who were once subject to kaieki received amnesty, but it would only allow them to serve the lord that they had served before kaieki, and there were only a few cases in which they returned to their services and received the same amount of stipend as they had received before kaieki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 模様砂漠(id:254067), Los688(id:12316), 花蝶風月雪月花警部(id:163674), Horlicks(id:62133), Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Extrahitz(id:26245), Rikumio(id:99645), 味っ子(id:17086), Yanahan(id:2437), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), Rusk(id:9895), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), An-chan(id:14590), 怪蘇(id:45514), Nerimaman(id:61206), 伏儀(id:142093), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), Kusune(id:110977), 立志堂(id:132177), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>