<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>能の歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Noh</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Noh</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Noh</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>能の歴史とは、日本の伝統芸能である能の発展史のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Noh means the history of the development of Japanese traditional art Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Noh means the history of the development of Japanese traditional art of Noh.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Noh means the history of the development of Japanese traditional art of Noh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>能の起源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of Noh</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of Noh</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of Noh</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>能の起源について正確なことはわかってはいないが、7世紀頃に中国大陸より日本に伝わった日本最古の舞台芸能である伎楽や、奈良時代に大陸より伝わった散楽に端を発するのではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the origin of Noh is not clear, it is generally believed that Noh originated from gigaku (ancient pantomime in which performers wear masks), Japan&apos;s oldest theatrical art that was introduced from China in the seventh century, and sangaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the 11th to 14th century) introduced from the Asian continent in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the origin of Noh is not clear, it is generally believed that Noh originated from gigaku (ancient pantomime in which performers wear masks), Japan&apos;s oldest theatrical art that was introduced from China during the seventh century, and sangaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the eleventh to the fourteenth century) introduced from the Asian continent during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the origin of Noh is not clear, it is generally believed that Noh originated from gigaku (ancient pantomime in which performers wear masks), Japan&apos;s oldest theatrical art that was introduced from China during the seventh century, and sangaku (form of theater popular in Japan during the eleventh to the fourteenth century) introduced from the Asian continent during the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>散楽は当初、雅楽と共に朝廷の保護下にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sangaku was initially under the protection of the Imperial Court along with gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sangaku was initially under the protection of the Imperial Court along with gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sangaku was initially under the protection of the Imperial Court along with gagaku (ancient Japanese court dance and music).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>やがて民衆の間に広まり、それまでにあった古来の芸能と結びつき、物まねなどを中心とした滑稽な笑いの芸・寸劇に発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it became popular among ordinary people and developed into comical performance/short play centered on mimics after it combined with previously-existing ancient art.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, it became popular among ordinary people and developed into a comical performance/short play centered on mimics after it combined with a previously-existing ancient art.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, it became popular among ordinary people and developed into a comical performance/short play centered on mimics after it combined with a previously-existing ancient art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それらはやがて猿楽と呼ばれるようになり、現在一般的に知られる能の原型がつくられていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such art came to be called &quot;sarugaku&quot; before long and became the prototype of the art which is currently known as Noh.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such art came to be called &quot;sarugaku&quot; before long and became the prototype of the art which is currently known as Noh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such art came to be called &quot;sarugaku&quot; before long and became the prototype of the art which is currently known as Noh.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>一方、平安時代中期頃より、神道的宗教行事が起源の田楽や、仏教の寺院で行われた延年などの芸能も興り、それぞれ発達していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Apart from the above, dengaku, which originated from the ceremony of Shinto religion, and ennen, which was performed at Buddhist temples, were created in the middle of Heian period and they also developed independently.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apart from the above, dengaku, which originated from the ceremony of Shinto religion, and ennen, which was performed at Buddhist temples, were created in the middle of Heian period and they also developed independently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apart from the above, dengaku, which originated from the ceremony of Shinto religion, and ennen, which was performed at Buddhist temples, were created in the middle of Heian period and they also developed independently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これらの演者は元々農民や僧侶だったが、平安末期頃から専門的に演じる職業集団も成立していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performers of such art were originally farmers or Buddhist monks, but some of them were organized into professional artists groups in the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Performers of such art were originally farmers or Buddhist monks, but some of them were organized into professional artists groups at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Performers of such art were originally farmers or Buddhist monks, but some of them were organized into professional artists groups at the end of Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>観阿弥・世阿弥の登場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appearance of Kanami and Zeami</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appearance of Kanami and Zeami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appearance of Kanami and Zeami</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>猿楽・田楽・延年は、互いに影響を及ぼし合い発展していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sarugaku, dengaku and ennen developed while being influenced mutually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sarugaku, dengaku and ennen developed while being mutually influenced.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sarugaku, dengaku and ennen developed while being mutually influenced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>12世紀・13世紀頃から同業組合として「座」が生まれ、寺社の保護を受けるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the 12th to 13th century, &quot;Za&quot;, a kind of trade organization, was organized and protected by temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the twelfth to thirteenth century, &quot;Za&quot;, a kind of trade organization, was organized and protected by temples.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the twelfth to thirteenth century, &apos;Za&apos;, a kind of trade organization, was organized and protected by temples.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>14世紀になると、代わって武家が田楽を保護するようになり、衣装や小道具・舞台も豪華なものになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 14th century, samurai family, instead of temples, came to protect dengaku and its theatrical costumes, properties and stages became luxurious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the fourteenth century, samurai families, instead of temples, came to protect dengaku and its theatrical costumes, properties and stages became luxurious.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the fourteenth century, samurai families, instead of temples, came to protect dengaku and its theatrical costumes, properties and stages became luxurious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのような状況のなか、大和猿楽の一座である結崎座より 観阿弥（觀阿彌）が現れ、旋律にとんだ「曲舞（くせまい）」（白拍子の芸）などを導入して従来の猿楽に大きな革新をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Kanami of Yusakiza, a troupe of Yamato sarugaku, introduced melodious &quot;kusemai&quot; (music and dance with a fan along with a tuzumi, a Japanese traditional drum) (the art of shirabyoshi (a woman who play Japanese traditional dance called shirabyoshi)) and innovated traditional sarugaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, Kanami of Yusakiza, a troupe of Yamato sarugaku, introduced melodious &quot;kusemai&quot; (music and dance with a fan along with a tuzumi, a Japanese traditional drum) (the art of shirabyoshi - a woman who performs Japanese traditional dance called shirabyoshi) and innovated traditional sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Kanami of Yusakiza, a troupe of Yamato sarugaku, introduced melodious &apos;kusemai&apos; (music and dance with a fan along with a tsuzumi, a Japanese traditional hand drum) (the art of shirabyoshi - a woman who performs Japanese traditional dance called shirabyoshi) and innovated traditional sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。tuzumiをtsuzumiに変更しました。drumの前にhandを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>このような革新の背景の一つと考えられているのが、当時行われていた「立ち会い能」と呼ばれる催しである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of the background of the above innovation is considered to be &quot;Tachiai Noh&quot; which was often held at the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the background of the above innovation is considered to be &quot;Tachiai Noh&quot; which was often held at the time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the background of the above innovation is considered to be &apos;Tachiai Noh&apos; which was often held at the time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これは猿楽や田楽の座がお互いに芸を競い、勝負を決するというもので、「立ち会い能」で勝ち上がることは座の世俗的な成功にを競いしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a competition in which troupes of sarugaku and dengaku compete with each other over their skill and advancing in &quot;Tachiai Noh&quot; directly linked with the secular success of a troupe in question.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a competition where sarugaku and dengaku troupes compete with each other over their skills and advances in &quot;Tachiai Noh&quot; directly linked with the secular success of a troupe in question.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a competition where sarugaku and dengaku troupes compete with each other over their skills and advances in &apos;Tachiai Noh&apos; directly linked with the secular success of a troupe in question.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>観世座における猿楽の革新も、この「立ち会い能」を勝ち上がる為という側面があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a sense, Kanzeza aimed to advance in &quot;Tachiai Noh&quot; by innovating its sarugaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a sense, Kanzeza aimed to advance in &quot;Tachiai Noh&quot; by innovating its sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a sense, Kanzeza aimed to advance in &apos;Tachiai Noh&apos; by innovating its sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>1375年、将軍足利義満は、京都の今熊野において、観阿弥とその息子の世阿弥（世阿彌）による猿楽を鑑賞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1375, shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA watched Nohgaku performed by Kannami and his son Zeami (Zeami) at Imakumano in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1375, shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA watched Nohgaku performed by Kannami and his son Zeami (Zeami) at Imakumano in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1375, shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA watched Nohgaku performed by Kannami and his son Zeami (Zeami) at Imakumano in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>彼らの芸に感銘を受けた義満は、観阿弥・世阿弥親子の結崎座（観世座）を庇護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being impressed by their performance, Yoshimitsu protected Yusakiza (Kanzeza) headed by Kannami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being impressed by their performance, Yoshimitsu protected Yusakiza (Kanzeza) headed by Kannami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being impressed by their performance, Yoshimitsu protected Yusakiza (Kanzeza) headed by Kannami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この結果、彼らは足利義満という庇護者、そして武家社会という観客を手に入れることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, they got a patron, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, as well as audience, people of samurai society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, they gained a patron, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, as well as an audience, the people of the samurai society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, they gained a patron, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, as well as an audience, the people of the samurai society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>また二条良基をはじめとする京都の公家社会との接点も生まれ、これら上流階級の文化を取り入れることで、彼らは猿楽をさらに洗練していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, they also got the contact with the people of court nobles society in Kyoto, including Yoshimoto NIJO, and further refined sarugaku by absorbing the culture of the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, they also made contact with the people of the court noble society in Kyoto, including Yoshimoto NIJO, and further refined sarugaku by absorbing the culture of the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, they also made contact with the people of the court noble society in Kyoto, including Yoshimoto NIJO, and further refined sarugaku by absorbing the culture of the aristocracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また足利義教も世阿弥の甥音阿弥を高く評価し、その庇護者となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinori ASHIKAGA also highly appreciated Onami, Zeami&apos;s nephew, and became his patron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinori ASHIKAGA also highly appreciated Onami, Zeami&apos;s nephew, and became his patron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinori ASHIKAGA also highly appreciated Onami, Zeami&apos;s nephew, and became his patron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>こうして歴代の観世大夫たちは時の権力と結びつきながら、現在の能の原型を完成させていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, successive Kanze Dayu (a chief of Kanzeza) completed the prototype of contemporary Noh while linking themselves to the power of the time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, successive Kanze Dayu (a chief of Kanzeza) completed the prototype of contemporary Noh while linking themselves to the power of the times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, successive Kanze Dayu (a chief of Kanzeza) completed the prototype of contemporary Noh while linking themselves to the power of the times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、室町期に成立した大和猿楽の外山座（とびざ）・結崎座（ゆうさきざ）・坂戸座（さかどざ）・円満井座（えんまいざ）を大和四座（やまとしざ）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, four troupes of Yamato sarugaku which were organized in the Muromachi period, Tobiza, Yusakiza, Sakadoza and Enmaiza, are collectively called Yamato-shiza.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, four troupes of Yamato sarugaku which were organized in the Muromachi period, Tobiza, Yusakiza, Sakadoza and Enmaiza, are collectively called Yamato-shiza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, four troupes of Yamato sarugaku which were organized in the Muromachi period, Tobiza, Yusakiza, Sakadoza and Enmaiza, are collectively called Yamato-shiza.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>それぞれ、後の宝生座・観世座・金剛座・金春座につながるとする説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory asserting that each of the above troupe later became Hoshoza, Kanzeza, Kongoza and Konparuza respectively is being widely accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory asserting that each of the above troupes later became Hoshoza, Kanzeza, Kongoza, and Konparuza respectively is being widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory asserting that each of the above troupes later became Hoshoza, Kanzeza, Kongoza, and Konparuza respectively is being widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>織豊期の能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh in the Shokuho period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh in the Shokuho period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh in the Shokuho period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)には能の芸の内容に大きな発展は無かったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the arts of Noh didn&apos;t make particular progress in the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the arts of Noh didn&apos;t make any particular progress during the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the arts of Noh didn&apos;t make any particular progress during the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし能は織田信長や豊臣秀吉ら時の権力者に引き続き愛好されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Noh was continuously favored by the person of power at the time such as Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Noh was continuously favored by the person of power at the time such as Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Noh was continuously favored by the person of power at the time such as Nobunaga ODA and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>『宇野主水日記』によると、信長は1582年に安土の総見寺で徳川家康とともに梅若家の猿楽を鑑賞しており、自身も小鼓をたしなんだと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Uno Mondo Nikki&quot;, Nobunaga, together with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, watched sarugaku performed by Umewaka family at Soken-ji Temple in Azuchi in 1582 and it is said that he himself was fond of kotsuzumi (a Japanese traditional drum).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Uno Mondo Nikki,&quot; Nobunaga, together with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, watched sarugaku performed by the Umewaka family at Soken-ji Temple in Azuchi in 1582 and it is said that he himself was fond of kotsuzumi (a Japanese traditional drum).</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Uno Mondo Nikki,&quot; Nobunaga, together with Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, watched sarugaku performed by the Umewaka family at Soken-ji Temple in Azuchi in 1582 and it is said that he himself was fond of kotsuzumi (a Japanese traditional small hand drum).</e>
<cmt>drumの前にsmall handを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>また信長の長男の織田信忠は自ら能を舞ったとの記録がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, according to a record, Nobunaga&apos;s eldest son Nobutada ODA performed Noh by himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, according to records, Nobunaga&apos;s eldest son Nobutada ODA performed Noh by himself.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, according to the records, Nobunaga&apos;s eldest son Nobutada ODA performed Noh by himself.</e>
<cmt>recordsの前にtheを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>信長に続き日本の最高権力者となった豊臣秀吉は、晩年熱心に能を演じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who became a person of supreme power in Japan after Nobunaga, performed Noh eagerly in his last days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who became a person of supreme power in Japan after Nobunaga, performed Noh eagerly during his last days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, who became a person of supreme power in Japan after Nobunaga, performed Noh eagerly during his last days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1593年10月には秀吉は後陽成天皇の前で3日間連続で何番もの能や狂言を演じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October 1593, Hideyoshi performed several Noh and kyogen (farce played during a Noh play cycle) in front of the Emperor Goyozei for three consecutive days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October 1593, Hideyoshi performed several Noh and kyogen (farce played during a Noh play cycle) in front of Emperor Goyozei for three consecutive days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October 1593, Hideyoshi performed several Noh and kyogen (farce played during a Noh play cycle) in front of Emperor Goyozei for three consecutive days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>しかしその一方で、秀吉は大和四座以外の猿楽には興味を示さなかった為、この時期に多くの猿楽の座が消滅していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, however, Hideyoshi was not interested in sarugaku performed by other troupes than Yamato-shiza, and as a result many of sarugaku troupes ceased to exist during that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, however, Hideyoshi was not interested in sarugaku performed by troupes other than Yamato-shiza, and as a result many sarugaku troupes ceased to exist during that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, however, Hideyoshi was not interested in sarugaku performed by troupes other than Yamato-shiza, and as a result many sarugaku troupes ceased to exist during that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>言わば、秀吉によって現在に続く能がそれ以外の猿楽から選別されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, existent schools of Noh are the ones that were selected by Hideyoshi out of many schools of sarugaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the existing schools of Noh are the ones that were selected by Hideyoshi out of the many schools of sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the existing schools of Noh are the ones that were selected by Hideyoshi out of the many schools of sarugaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>江戸期の能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh in the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh during the Edo period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh during the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>江戸期には徳川家康や徳川秀忠、徳川家光など歴代の将軍が能を好んだ為、猿楽は武家社会の文化資本として大きな意味合いを持つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As successive shogun, including Ieyasu Tokugawa, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, favored Noh, sarugaku had a big implication in the Edo period as the culture of samurai society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As successive shogun, including Ieyasu Tokugawa, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, favored Noh, sarugaku had a big implication during the Edo period as the culture of the samurai society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As successive shogun, including Ieyasu Tokugawa, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, favored Noh, sarugaku had a big implication during the Edo period as the culture of the samurai society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また猿楽は武家社会における典礼用の正式な音楽（式楽）も担当することとなり、各藩がお抱えの猿楽師を雇うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Sarugaku became the official music (shikigaku (the music and plays for official ceremonies)) for the ceremonies in samurai society, and each domain employed their own sarugaku-shi (sarugaku player).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Sarugaku became the official music (shikigaku - the music and plays for official ceremonies) for ceremonies held in samurai society, and each domain employed their own sarugaku-shi (sarugaku player).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Sarugaku became the official music (shikigaku - the music and plays for official ceremonies) for ceremonies held in samurai society, and each domain employed their own sarugaku-shi (sarugaku player).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>猿楽師出身でありながら大名にまで出世した間部詮房という人物も知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akifusa MANABE is well-known as a person who was eventually promoted to daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) though he was originally sarugaku-shi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akifusa MANABE is well-known as a person who was eventually promoted to daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) though he was originally sarugaku-shi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akifusa MANABE is well-known as a person who was eventually promoted to daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) though he was originally sarugaku-shi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="37">
<j>なお、徳川家も秀吉と同じく大和四座を保護していたが、秀忠は大和四座を離れた猿楽師であった喜多七太夫長能に保護を与え、元和年間に喜多流の創設を認めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As with Hideyoshi, the Tokugawa family protected Yamato-shiza, but Hidetada protected Kita Shichidayu Nagayoshi, sarugaku-shi who seceded from Yamato-shiza, and approved the establishment of Kita school in the Genna era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As with Hideyoshi, the Tokugawa family protected Yamato-shiza, but Hidetada protected Kita Shichidayu Nagayoshi, sarugaku-shi who seceded from Yamato-shiza, and approved the establishment of the Kita school during the Genna era.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As with Hideyoshi, the Tokugawa family protected Yamato-shiza, but Hidetada protected Kita Shichidayu Nagayoshi, sarugaku-shi who seceded from Yamato-shiza, and approved the establishment of the Kita school during the Genna era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="38">
<j>徳川家康は観世座を好み、秀忠や家光は喜多流を好んだとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA favored Kanzeza while Hidetada and Iemitsu favored Kita school.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA favored Kanzeza while Hidetada and Iemitsu favored the Kita school.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that Ieyasu TOKUGAWA favored Kanzeza while Hidetada and Iemitsu favored the Kita school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし、徳川綱吉は宝生流を好んだ為、綱吉の治世に加賀藩や尾張藩がお抱え能楽師を金春流から宝生流に入れ替えたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, however, preferred Hosho school, and it is said that the Kaga domain and Owari domain replaced their sarugaku-shi belonged to Konparu school by those belonged to Hosho school in the period of Tsunayoshi&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, however, preferred the Hosho school, and it is said that the Kaga and Owari domain replaced their sarugaku-shi belonging to the Konparu school by those belonging to the Hosho school during the period of Tsunayoshi&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, however, preferred the Hosho school, and it is said that the Kaga and Owari domain replaced their sarugaku-shi belonging to the Konparu school by those belonging to the Hosho school during the period of Tsunayoshi&apos;s administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>この結果、現在でも石川県や名古屋は宝生流が盛んな地域である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Hosho school is thriving in Ishikawa Prefecture and Nagoya City even at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the Hosho school is thriving in Ishikawa Prefecture and Nagoya City, even at present.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the Hosho school is thriving in Ishikawa Prefecture and Nagoya City, even at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>その一方、猿楽が武家社会の式楽となった結果、庶民が猿楽を見物する機会は徐々に少なくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, ordinary people&apos;s chances to watch sarugaku gradually decreased because it became the shikigaku of samurai society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, ordinary people&apos;s chances to watch sarugaku gradually decreased because it became the shikigaku of samurai society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, ordinary people&apos;s chances to watch sarugaku gradually decreased because it became the shikigaku of samurai society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>しかし、謡曲は町人の習い事として流行し、多くの謡本が出版された（寺子屋の教科書に使われた例もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, yokyoku (Noh song) became popular among merchant class people as a subject of learning and many books on yokyoku were published (some of them were used as a textbook at terakoya (temple elementary school during the Edo period)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, yokyoku (Noh song) became popular among merchant class people as a subject of learning and many books on yokyoku were published (some of them were used as a textbook at terakoya - temple elementary school during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, yokyoku (Noh song) became popular among merchant class people as a subject of learning and many books on yokyoku were published (some of them were used as a textbook at terakoya - temple elementary school during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>実際に見る機会は少ないながらも、庶民の関心は強く、寺社への寄進を集める目的の勧進能が催されると多くの観客を集めたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although they had few chances to watch, ordinary people were very interested in Noh, and it is said that Kanjin Noh, which was held to raise subscriptions for the construction of temples/shrines, attracted many spectators.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although they had few chances to watch, ordinary people were very interested in Noh, and it is said that Kanjin Noh, which was held to raise subscriptions for the construction of temples/shrines, attracted many spectators.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although they had few chances to watch, ordinary people were very interested in Noh, and it is said that Kanjin Noh, which was held to raise subscriptions for the construction of temples/shrines, attracted many spectators.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="44">
<j>近代の能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh in the modern times</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh in the modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh in the modern times</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="45">
<j>幕府の儀式芸能であった能は、維新後、廃絶の危機に瀕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji restoration, Noh faced the crisis of elimination since it was bakufu&apos;s ceremonial art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji restoration, Noh faced a crisis of elimination since it was the bakufu&apos;s ceremonial art.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji restoration, Noh faced a crisis of elimination since it was the bakufu&apos;s ceremonial art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>1869年にはエジンバラ公爵の来日に際して能が演じられたが、1872年（明治5年）には能・狂言の「皇上ヲ模擬シ、上ヲ猥涜」するものが禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Noh performance was conducted when The Duke of Edinburgh visited Japan in 1869, a government order was issued in 1872 by which Noh/kyogen that &quot;mocks or insults the Emperor&quot; was prohibitted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Noh performance was conducted when The Duke of Edinburgh visited Japan in 1869, a government order was issued in 1872 by which Noh/kyogen that &quot;mocks or insults the Emperor&quot; was prohibitted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Noh performance was conducted when The Duke of Edinburgh visited Japan in 1869, a government order was issued in 1872 by which Noh/kyogen that &apos;mocks or insults the Emperor&apos; was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。prohibittedをprohibitedに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>さらに、「勧善懲悪ヲ主トス」ることも命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, it was ordered that the story of Noh should be based on &quot;the concept of kanzen choaku&quot; (rewarding good and punishing evil).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, it was ordered that the story of Noh should be based on &quot;the concept of kanzen choaku&quot; (rewarding good and punishing evil).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, it was ordered that the story of Noh should be based on &apos;the concept of kanzen choaku&apos; (rewarding good and punishing evil).</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、明治天皇は1878年には青山御所に能舞台を設置し、数々の能を鑑賞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji, however, constructed Noh stage at Aoyama Palace in 1878 and watched a lot of Noh performace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Meiji, however, constructed Noh stage at Aoyama Palace in 1878 and watched a lot of Noh performaces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji, however, constructed Noh stage at Aoyama Palace in 1878 and watched a lot of Noh performances.</e>
<cmt>performacesをperformancesに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また 岩倉具視は1879年にはユリシーズ・グラントを自邸に招いて能を上演させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomomi IWAKURA got Noh actors to play Noh in 1879 when he invited Ulysses Grant to his residence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomomi IWAKURA got Noh actors to perform Noh in 1879 when he invited Ulysses Grant to his residence.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomomi IWAKURA got Noh actors to perform Noh in 1879 when he invited Ulysses Grant to his residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>更に能楽社（のちの能楽会）の設立や芝能楽堂（1881年落成）の建設を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, he established Nohgakusha (Noh Association) and constructed Shiba Nohgakudo (Noh theater) (completed in 1881).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, he established Nohgakusha (the Noh Association) and constructed Shiba Nohgakudo (Noh theater) (completed in 1881).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, he established Nohgakusha (the Noh Association) and constructed Shiba Nohgakudo (Noh theater) (completed in 1881).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="51">
<j>こうして明治維新直後の危機は過ぎ去ったが、やがて各流派はお互いに排他的姿勢を見せるようになり、流派間の交流や共演は消滅していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the crisis right after Meii Restoration was over, but each school became increasingly exclusive with each other and the exchange between schools or joint performance vanished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the crisis right after Meii Restoration was over, but each school became increasingly exclusive and the exchanges between schools or joint performances vanished.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the crisis right after Meiji Restoration was over, but each school became increasingly exclusive and the exchanges between schools or joint performances vanished.</e>
<cmt>MeiiをMeijiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="52">
<j>戦時中の能</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Noh in wartime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Noh in wartime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Noh in wartime</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>その後、軍国主義が激しさを増すと、天皇家を多く題材とした能には厳しい目が注がれるようになり、1939年（昭和14年）、警視庁保安課は不敬を理由に「大原御幸」を上演禁止とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With militarism gained momentum, Noh came under scrutiny since many of its stories featured the Imperial family and the Safety Division of Metropolitan Police Department banned in 1939 the performance of &quot;Ohara Goko&quot; on the ground of irreverence for the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With militarism gaining momentum, Noh came under scrutiny since many of its stories featured the Imperial family and the Safety Division of the Metropolitan Police Department banned in 1939 the performance of &quot;Ohara Goko&quot; on the grounds of irreverence for the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With militarism gaining momentum, Noh came under scrutiny since many of its stories featured the Imperial family and the Safety Division of the Metropolitan Police Department banned in 1939 the performance of &apos;Ohara Goko&apos; on the grounds of irreverence for the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その一方で、日清戦争、日露戦争、第二次世界大戦を題材とした新作能も作られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, shinsaku Noh (new Noh) which featured Sino-Japanese War, Russo-Japanese War and the Second World War was also created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, shinsaku Noh (new Noh) which featured the Sino-Japanese War, Russo-Japanese War, and the Second World War was also created.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, shinsaku Noh (new Noh) which featured the Sino-Japanese War, Russo-Japanese War, and the Second World War were also created.</e>
<cmt>wasをwereに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="55">
<j>戦後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Second World War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Second World War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Second World War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>第二次世界大戦の敗戦は能界に大きな転機をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The defeat in the Second World War was a great turning point for Noh world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The defeat in the Second World War was a great turning point for the Noh world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The defeat in the Second World War was a great turning point for the Noh world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>戦災によって多くの能舞台が焼失した為、それまで流派ごとに分かれて演能を行っていた能楽師たちが、流派の違いを超えて焼け残った能舞台で共同で稽古を行いだしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because many Noh stages were burnt down during the war, Noh actors, who separately played Noh based on their schools until then, began to conduct joint practice beyond the difference of schools using Noh stages that remained unburned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because many Noh stages were burnt down during the war, Noh actors, who separately played Noh based on their schools until then, began to conduct joint practice beyond the difference of schools using Noh stages that remained unburned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because many Noh stages were burnt down during the war, Noh actors, who separately played Noh based on their schools until then, began to conduct joint practice beyond the difference of schools using Noh stages that remained unburned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>その為、若手の能楽師たちは他流派の優秀な能楽師からも教えを受けることが多くなり、大いに刺激を受けるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, young Noh actors had an opportunity to learn from excellent Noh actors of other schools and got a lot of stimulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, young Noh actors had an opportunity to learn from excellent Noh actors of other schools and received a lot of stimulation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, young Noh actors had an opportunity to learn from excellent Noh actors of other schools and received a lot of stimulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>観世銕之丞家の次男であった観世栄夫は、この時、観世流と他流の身体論の違いに大きな衝撃を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Hideo KANZE, who was the second son of Tetsunojo KANZE, was shocked by the difference in the body theory of Kanze school and that of other schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Hideo KANZE, who was the second son of Tetsunojo KANZE, was shocked by the difference in the body theory of the Kanze school compared to that of other schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Hideo KANZE, who was the second son of Tetsunojo KANZE, was shocked by the difference in the body theory of the Kanze school compared to that of other schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>結果的に芸養子という形で喜多流に転流して喜多六平太の養子となり、後藤栄夫を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, he changed to Kita school as geiyoshi (talented disciple adopted as a child of the master) of Roppeita KITA and called himself Hideo GOTO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, he changed to the Kita school as geiyoshi (talented disciple adopted as a child of the master) of Roppeita KITA and called himself Hideo GOTO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, he changed to the Kita school as geiyoshi (talented disciple adopted as a child of the master) of Roppeita KITA and called himself Hideo GOTO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また栄夫の弟で八世観世銕之丞となった観世静夫も、この時期の他流との交流開始の衝撃の大きさを語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shizuo Kanze, who was a younger brother of Hideo and became Tetsunojo KANZE Ⅷ, also mentioned about the the depth of shock caused by the exchange with other schools which took place at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shizuo Kanze, who was the younger brother of Hideo, who became Tetsunojo KANZE Ⅷ, also mentioned about the the depth of shock caused by the exchange with other schools which took place at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shizuo KANZE, who was the younger brother of Hideo, who became Tetsunojo KANZE Ⅷ, also mentioned about the depth of shock caused by the exchange with other schools which took place at that time.</e>
<cmt>KanzeをKANZEに変更しました。重複したtheを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="62">
<j>なお、この時期にこうした交流の場となった能舞台としては多摩川能舞台（現在は銕仙会能楽研修所に移築）などが挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One of Noh stages where such exchanges took place at the time was Tamagawa Noh stage (it is now located at Tessankai Nohgaku Kenshujo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One of the Noh stages where such exchanges took place at the time was Tamagawa Noh stage (it is now located at Tessankai Nohgaku Kenshujo).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One of the Noh stages where such exchanges took place at the time was Tamagawa Noh stage (it is now located at Tessankai Nohgaku Kenshujo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Peachkiller(id:99202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>