<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>問丸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toimaru (Specialized Wholesale Merchant)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toimaru (Specialized Wholesale Merchant)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toimaru (specialized wholesale merchant)</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>問丸（といまる）は、年貢米の陸揚地である河川・港の近郊の都市に居住し、運送、倉庫、委託販売業を兼ねる組織。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toimaru is an organization engaged in transport, warehousing and commission sales, with a residence in a suburban city of the river or port for landing nengumai (rice paid as land tax.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toimaru was an organization engaged in transport, warehousing and commission sales, which resided in suburban cities located by rivers or ports that dealt in nengumai (rice paid as land tax.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Toimaru&quot; were organizations specialized in transport, warehousing and commission sales, which based themselves in cities by the rivers and ports where nengumai (rice paid as land tax) was unloaded.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。Toimaru にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>鎌倉時代頃から組織され、取扱うのは主に荘園からの年貢米。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toimaru were organized in around Kamakura Period, and have been handling mainly nengumai. (rice paid as land tax) from manors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toimaru were organized around the Kamakura Period, and mainly handled nengumai. (rice paid as land tax) from manors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toimaru, which came to be organized during the Kamakura period, mainly handled nengumai brought forward by manors.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>最初は、荘官らが必要上始めたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, Toimaru started their business to meet the necessity of administrators of manors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, Toimaru were started to meet the requirements of administrators of manors.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the administrators of manors originally began organizing the Toimaru for reasons of expediency.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>問（とい）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called Toi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were also known as Toi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also known as Toi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代末になると問丸は、港湾を所有する領主に隷属して仕事をするだけではなく、その港湾を利用する他の領主の要求にも応じ、年貢米の輸送管理を引き受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kamakura Period, Toimaru worked not only under the rule of the territorial lord (the port owner), but also catered to any request of other lords who were using the port, by undertaking transport management of their nengumai (rice paid as land tax.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kamakura Period, Toimaru worked not only under the rule of the territorial lord (the port owner), but also catered to the requests of other lords who were using the port, by managing the transport of their nengumai (rice paid as land tax.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the late Kamakura period, Toimaru functioned not only as subordinates to the landlords who owned the ports, but also as agents which managed the transports of nengumai as to meet the demands of other manor owners who used the ports.</e>
<cmt>「港湾を所有する領主」はthe territorial lord (the port owner)からthe landlords who owned the portsの表現に変更しました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>港湾所有領主への隷属を脱し、仲介業者または運送業者として独立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, Toimaru could get rid of enslavement to the lord of port owner and became an independent broker or carrier (forwarder.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, Toimaru were able to rid themselves of ownership by the port owner and became an independent broker or carrier (forwarder.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus Toimaru managed to break away from the exclusive ties with port-owners and became independent agents and carriers.</e>
<cmt>運送業者はbroker or carrier (forwarder）からagents and carriersに変更しました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後には、様々な展開を見せ始め、一般の商品も取り扱うようになって室町時代には問屋へと展開するものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of expansion of their business, Toimaru began handling other general goods, and by the Muromachi period, some of them had also started the wholesale business.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また現地の港湾からの流通に対する独占的権利を確立して港湾支配を確立したものの、逆に特権によって他者の流通を妨げる存在に成長したために楽市楽座政策によって座とともに解体に追い込まれたものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were also some Toimaru which monopolized the rights over the transport business in ports, and there were even some which, under the policy of the &quot;rakuichi-rakuza&quot; (Free Market, Free Guilds), were forced to dissolve their business and guild that had become far too powerful for the smooth and fair operations of transportation business in the ports.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションを全角から半角に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Gappei2006(id:69935), Non-stop24(id:10471), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Croce(id:20876), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>