<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>祠堂銭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shidosen (mortuary funds)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shidosen (mortuary funds)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shidosen (mortuary funds)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>祠堂銭（しどうせん）とは、故人の冥福を祈るために祠堂（御霊屋・持仏堂とも）の管理・修繕費用あるいは供養費用として寺院に寄進する金銭のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shidosen was the funds donated to temples for memorial services for the deceased and for the management and upkeep of shido (also known as mitamaya (a place where spirits are enshrined) or jibutsu-do hall).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shidosen were funds donated to temples for memorial services for the deceased and for the management and upkeep of shido (also known as mitamaya (a place where spirits are enshrined) or jibutsu-do hall).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;was the&quot; to &quot;were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shidosen were funds donated to temples for memorial services for the deceased and for the management and upkeep of shido (also known as mitamaya (a place where spirits are enshrined) or jibutsu-do hall).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中世においては、祠堂銭を元手とした寺院による金融のことも指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In medieval times, the term Shidosen also referred to the financing provided by temples using Shidosen as the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In medieval times, the term Shidosen also referred to the financing provided by temples using Shidosen as capital.</e>
<cmt>eliminated &quot;the&quot; before &quot;capital&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In medieval times, the term Shidosen also referred to the financing provided by temples using Shidosen as capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>祠堂銭は古代より存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shidosen existed from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shidosen had existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>fixed tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shidosen had existed since ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>祠堂銭として集められた金銭を資金として寺院の内外に貸付を行い、その利息により寺院の管理・運営の維持を図ったり、社会事業の財源などとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using the funds pooled as Shidosen, monks engaged in moneylending both inside and outside the temples, and used the interests for social works, as well as continuously managing and maintaining the temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Using gathered Shidosen funds, monks engaged in moneylending both inside and outside of the temples, using the interest for social work in addition to continuously managing and maintaining the temples.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Using gathered Shidosen funds, monks engaged in moneylending both inside and outside of the temples, using the interest for social work in addition to continuously managing and maintaining the temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>特に中世に入り新興宗派である禅宗が広まると、伝統宗派の荘園に代わる財源を祠堂銭の利息に求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially in the early medieval times when Zen sect, an emerging religious sect, spread, monks turned to interests on Shidosen to take the place of shoen (manor in medieval Japan) which was the financial resource of the traditional religious sects,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially during the early medieval period, as Zen became an emerging religious sect, monks turned to interest gained from Shidosen in place of shoen (manors in medieval Japan) which had been the financial resource for traditional religious sects.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar; changed &quot;manor&quot; to &quot;manors&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially during the early medieval period, as Zen became an emerging religious sect, monks turned to interest gained from Shidosen in place of shoen (manors in medieval Japan) which had been the financial resource for traditional religious sects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当初、朝廷や幕府は祠堂銭を禁止する姿勢を取ったが、後には仏教保護の一環として反対に祠堂銭を徳政令の対象外とするなど、容認・保護の姿勢に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning, the Imperial court and the bakufu banned Shidosen but later came to accept and protect it by exempting shidosen from Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) as part of protection of Buddhism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) banned Shidosen at first, but later on accepted it, protecting Buddhism by exempting shidosen from Tokuseirei (ordering a return of sold land and a dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; added description for bakufu to follow the word list; capitalized &quot;Court&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court and the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) banned Shidosen at first, but later on accepted it, protecting Buddhism by exempting shidosen from Tokuseirei (ordering a return of sold land and a dissolution of debts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このため、禅宗以外の寺院を含めて本来の祠堂銭だけではなく、余剰資金の運営手段として貸付を行うようになり、室町時代に入る頃には寺院は営利目的の金融業と同じようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, temples other than those of Zen sect began to lend money as a way to manage surplus fund as well as Shidosen, and at the beginning of the Muromachi period, temples were operating like for-profit financial institutions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, temples other than those of the Zen sect began to lend money as a way to manage surplus funds as well as Shidosen, and in the early Muromachi period, temples were operating similar to for-profit financial institutions.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;at the beginning of the Muromachi&quot; to &quot;in the early Muromachi&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, temples other than those of the Zen sect began to lend money as a way to manage surplus funds as well as Shidosen, and in the early Muromachi period, temples were operating similar to for-profit financial institutions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>実態は営利目的であったものの、表向きはあくまでも寺院の管理や故人の供養のための経費捻出を目的としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official purpose of the moneylending was to generate the funds for management of the temple and memorial services for the deceased although in reality the purpose was profit-making.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even though the official purpose of the moneylending was to generate funds to manage the temples and have memorial services for the deceased, the real purpose was for profit-making.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even though the official purpose of the moneylending was to generate funds to manage the temples and have memorial services for the deceased, the real purpose was for profit-making.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのために、利息は2文子（元金100文につき月利2文）という低利のために利用者が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the interest was as low as two monshi (monthly interest of two mon per 100 mon), and there were many users.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the interest for such occasions was as low as two monshi (monthly interest of two mon per one-hundred mon) there were many who depended on this system.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;many users&quot; to &quot;many who depended on this system&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the interest for such occasions was as low as two monshi (monthly interest of two mon per one-hundred mon) there were many who depended on this system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>更に当時の政情不安から信仰に救いを求めた人々からの金銭などの寄進が相次いだこと、同様の理由で防備が頑丈な寺院の倉庫に財物を預ける人々も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, due to the political instability, there was a flurry of donations from those who turned to religion while many people entrusted their properties to the secure, well-built warehouse of a temple, and as a result, many temples invested these funds as the capital for Shidosen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, due to political instability, a flurry of donations came in from people turning to religion and entrusting their properties to secure, well-built temple warehouses. As a result, many temples invested these funds as capital for Shidosen.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences since it was uncomfortably long as one; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, due to political instability, a flurry of donations came in from people turning to religion and entrusting their properties to secure, well-built temple warehouses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その結果、そうした資金を祠堂銭の元手として運用する寺院も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many temples invested these funds as capital for Shidosen.</e>
<cmt>同上</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>更に寺院の財物である祠堂銭は本来は仏の所有物であり、返済を怠れば死後の成仏もままならないのではという利用者の信仰心に由来する不安感が祠堂銭の返済に対する心理的圧力として働いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Shidosen was the property of the temple, people were afraid that they might not be able to rest in peace after death if they failed to repay, which worked as the psychological pressure to repay Shidosen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On account of Shidosen being the property of a temple, people were afraid of being unable to rest in peace after death if they failed to repay their debts, which worked as psychological pressure to repay Shidosen.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On account of Shidosen being the property of a temple, people were afraid of being unable to rest in peace after death if they failed to repay their debts, which worked as psychological pressure to repay Shidosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>それでも、やはり利用者がどうしても返せない場合もあり、祠堂銭を運営する寺院が私徳政を求める徳政一揆の攻撃対象となる場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet, in some cases the users could not repay, and when the temple managing Shidosen sought Private acts of Virtuous Government, it sometimes became the target of Tokusei uprising.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even so, there were some who were unable to pay for their debts and when temples managing Shidosen sought Private Acts of Virtuous Government, they were sometimes targeted in Tokusei uprisings.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; capitalized &quot;Acts&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even so, there were some who were unable to pay for their debts and when temples managing Shidosen sought Private Acts of Virtuous Government, they were sometimes targeted in Tokusei uprisings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>近世に入ると、江戸幕府による寺院統制の影響もあって祠堂銭も下火となっていくが、なおも寺院・檀家間などで祠堂銭・名目金の貸付が行われる事も珍しくはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early modern times, Shidosen started to die down because the Edo bakufu controlled temples, but still lending of Shidosen and loans between temples and supporters were not unusual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it became the early modern era, Shidosen began to fade out due to the Edo bakufu controlling the temples. However, Shidosen lending and loans between temples and supporters was not unusual.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became the early modern era, Shidosen began to fade out due to the Edo bakufu controlling the temples,However, but still Shidosen lending and loans between temples and supporters was not unusual.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>江戸幕府が民事裁判の制限を定めた相対済令においては利息付の金融に関する裁判を幕府は取り上げないこととなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under aitai sumashi rei (mutual settlement decree) established by the Edo bakuru, the bakufu would not take up trials concerning interest-bearing loans.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Aitai Sumashi Rei (Mutual Settlement Decree) established by the Edo bakufu, the bakufu would not take up trials concerning interest-bearing loans.</e>
<cmt>capitalized decree</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Aitai Sumashi Rei (Mutual Settlement Decree) specifying restriction of civil actions established by the Edo bakufu, the bakufu would not take up trials concerning interest-bearing loans.</e>
<cmt>「民事裁判の制限を定めた」を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>祠堂銭については寺院の維持・供養などを目的としたものについては、利息付の貸出の場合でも同令の対象外とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Shidosen to pay for the upkeep of the temple and memorial services was exempt from the decree even when it was put out at interest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Shidosen that was to pay for the upkeep of a temple and memorial services was exempt from the decree, even when it was put out at interest.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Shidosen that was to pay for the upkeep of a temple and memorial services was exempt from the decree, even when it was put out at interest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), Kaboyose-DSD(id:123658), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>