<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寄船</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorifune (drifting ships and wreckage)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorifune (drifting ships and wreckage)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorifune (drifting ships and wreckage)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寄船（よりふね）とは、中世・近世の日本における遭難による漂流船・漂着船及びその搭載物のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yorifune&quot; meant ships drifting or drifted ashore and their wreckage after having met with some mishaps in the medieval and modern times in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yorifune&quot; meant ships drifting or drifted ashore and their loads after having met with some mishaps in the medieval and modern times in Japan.</e>
<cmt>搭載物なので、wreckage ではなく、loadsではないかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yorifune&quot; meant ships drifting or drifted ashore and their loads after having met with some mishaps in the medieval and modern times in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>これに対して漂流物一般を寄物（よりもの）と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the otherhand, driftage in general was called &quot;Yorimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, driftage in general was referred to as &quot;Yorimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>called ⇒　referred to as に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, driftage in general was referred to as &quot;Yorimono.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>更に漂流船を流船と呼んで、寄船を漂着船のみに限定する考え方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also said that drifting ships were particularly called &quot;nagarebune&quot; while only ships drifted ashore were called &quot;Yorifune.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it is also said that drifting ships were particularly referred to as &quot;nagarebune&quot; while only ships drifted ashore were referred to as &quot;Yorifune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>called ⇒　referred to as に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it is also said that drifting ships were particularly referred to as &quot;nagarebune&quot; while only ships drifted ashore were referred to as &quot;Yorifune.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では古代からそもそも船の遭難そのものを神罰として捉え、漂流船・漂着船は発見者・救出者によって略奪・捕獲の対象になると考えられてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since ancient times in Japan, people considered a shipwreck itself as a divine punishment, so that any ship drifting or drifted ashore might be looted and captured by a person or persons who found it or rescued somebody from it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since ancient times in Japan, people considered a shipwreck itself as a divine punishment, so that any ship drifting or drifted ashore might be looted and captured by a person or persons who found it or rescued somebody from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since ancient times in Japan, people considered a shipwreck itself as a divine punishment, so that any ship drifting or drifted ashore might be looted and captured by a person or persons who found it or rescued somebody from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>慣習法では地元領主あるいは住民の所有物もしくは地域の共有物とされてきたが、しばしば権利を巡る争いを引き起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to common law, any ship drifting or drifted ashore was regarded as a property owned by a local feudal lord or the local people or as a common property of the resident, but its ownership often triggered conflicts among the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to common law, any ship drifting or drifted ashore was regarded as a property owned by a local feudal lord or the local people or as a common property of the region, but its ownership often triggered conflicts among the people.</e>
<cmt>地域の共有物なので、resident を　regionに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to common law, any ship drifting or drifted ashore was regarded as a property owned by a local feudal lord or the local people or as a common property of the region, but its ownership often triggered conflicts among the people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>こうした争いを回避するために各種法令が出された他、寺社などに寄進して紛争防止と宗教的恩恵の両方を得ようとすることも行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to evade such conflicts, various decrees were issued, beside that people donated the ship to a shrine or temple intending to avoid conflicts among them and obtain religious benefits at the same time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to evade such conflicts, various decrees were issued, beside that people donated the ship to a shrine or temple intending to avoid conflicts among them and obtain religious benefits at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to evade such conflicts, various decrees were issued, beside that people donated the ship to a shrine or temple intending to avoid conflicts among them and obtain religious benefits at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>博多に近い宗像大社は鎌倉時代の段階で過去数百年間の修理費用を寄船・寄物の寄進のみで賄ってきたという（寛喜3年4月5日官宣旨）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Already in the Kamakura Period, Munakata Taisha Shrine near Hakata was said to have purveyed its repairing costs for the past several hundred years from donation of Yoribune (ships drifted ashore) and Yorimono (driftage) only, according to Kansenji (an edict from Daijokan (the Grand Council of State)) dated May 15, 1231.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Already in the Kamakura Period, Munakata Taisha Shrine near Hakata was said to have purveyed its repairing costs for the past several hundred years from donation of Yoribune (ships drifted ashore) and Yorimono (driftage) only, according to Kansenji (an edict from Daijokan (the Grand Council of State)) dated May 15, 1231.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Already in the Kamakura Period, Munakata Taisha Shrine near Hakata was said to have purveyed its repairing costs for the past several hundred years from donation of Yoribune (ships drifted ashore) and Yorimono (driftage) only, according to Kansenji (an edict from Daijokan (the Grand Council of State)) dated May 15, 1231.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>室町時代に海賊衆の慣習法が鎌倉幕府制定法に仮託されて法としてまとめられたとされる廻船式目によれば、寄船に生存者がいた場合や船主が明らかな場合には無断の押収を禁じ、無主物のみを認めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Kaisen Shikimoku (the oldest sea law of Japan), common law of Kaizoku-shu (pirates) on the pretense of statutory law of Kamakura Bakufu Government, confiscation of a wrecked ship was allowed only when no survivor nor owner of the ship was found but otherwise prohibited without consensus of survivors or shipowners, if any.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Kaisen Shikimoku (the oldest sea law of Japan), common law of Kaizoku-shu (pirates) drafted on the pretense of statutory law of Kamakura Bakufu Government in the Mromachi Period, confiscation of a wrecked ship was allowed only when no survivor nor owner of the ship was found but otherwise prohibited without consensus of survivors or shipowners, if any.</e>
<cmt>「室町時代に」と「法としてまとめられたとされる」の訳漏れ。それぞれ付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Kaisen Shikimoku (the oldest sea law of Japan), common law of Kaizoku-shu (pirates) drafted on the pretense of statutory law of Kamakura Bakufu Government in the Mromachi Period, confiscation of a wrecked ship was allowed only when no survivor nor owner of the ship was found but otherwise prohibited without consensus of survivors or shipowners, if any.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これは、今川仮名目録などの戦国時代 (日本)の分国法にも継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This regulation was inherited by provincial laws of the Sengoku Period (the Period of Warring States in Japan), such as Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (literally, &quot;list of regulations of Imagawa clan written in kana characters&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This regulation was inherited by bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain) of the Sengoku Period (the Period of Warring States in Japan), such as Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (Kana List of Articles of the Imagawa).</e>
<cmt>登録された用語を使用していなかったため、分国法を　bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain)、今川仮名目録をImagawa Kana Mokuroku (Kana List of Articles of the Imagawa)に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This regulation was inherited by bunkokuho (the law individual sengoku-daimyo enforced in their own domain) of the Sengoku Period (the Period of Warring States in Japan), such as Imagawa Kana Mokuroku (Kana List of Articles of the Imagawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>だが、実際には故意に他人の船を沈めて積荷を寄船の搭載物であるとして奪う者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in fact, there were some people who intentionally sank others&apos; ships and looted the loaded goods as driftage..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in fact, there were some people who intentionally sank others&apos; ships and looted the loaded goods as driftage of yorifune.</e>
<cmt>文の最後にof yorifuneを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in fact, there were some people who intentionally sank others&apos; ships and looted the loaded goods as driftage of yorifune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、豊臣政権・徳川政権によって不法行為の取締が強化される一方、分一などの発見者・救出者への法定による一定の権利保障が定められて問題の解決が図られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toyotomi and Tokugawa governments tightened control of unlawful acts, but at the same time they tried to solve problems by instituting such laws as to assure Buichi and other particular rights of a finder or rescuer of drifting/drifted ships.</e>
<cmt>「分一」の意味不明。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toyotomi and Tokugawa governments tightened control of unlawful acts, but at the same time they tried to solve problems by instituting such laws as to assure Buichi and other particular rights of a finder or rescuer of drifting/drifted ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toyotomi and Tokugawa governments tightened control of unlawful acts, but at the same time they tried to solve problems by instituting such laws as to assure Buichi and other particular rights of a finder or rescuer of drifting/drifted ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sapphire123(id:147732), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>