<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>地方改良運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movement to Improve Rural Areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movement to Improve Rural Areas</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movement to Improve Rural Areas</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>地方改良運動（ちほうかいりょううんどう）とは、日露戦争後に荒廃した地方社会と市町村の改良・再建を目指す官製運動のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Movement to Improve Rural Areas was government-regulated and aimed to improve and reconstruct regional societies, cities, towns and villages which had been devastated after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Movement to Improve Rural Areas was government-regulated movement which aimed to improve and reconstruct regional societies, cities, towns and villages which had been devastated after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>was government-regulated and aimed to→government-regulated movement which aimed to</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Movement to Improve Rural Areas was government-regulated movement which aimed to improve and reconstruct regional societies, cities, towns and villages which had been devastated after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>第2次桂内閣の元で出された戊申詔書をきっかけに内務省 (日本)を中心として遂行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the publication of Boshin Shosho by the Second Katsura Cabinet, the implementation of the movement was led by the pre-war Ministry of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the publication of Boshin Shosho under the Second Katsura Cabinet, the implementation of the movement was led by the pre-war Ministry of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt>・by→under</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the publication of Boshin Shosho under the Second Katsura Cabinet, the implementation of the movement was led by the pre-war Ministry of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本は日露戦争によって列強の地位を手に入れたが、戦時財政の元で行われた増税などによって地方財政は破綻寸前に追い込まれ、地方の疲弊・荒廃ぶりは深刻となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Japan gained the status as a major power through the Russo-Japanese War, tax increases as part of the war-time fiscal policy left local finances near collapse and rural areas in ruins and serious devastation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Japan gained the status as a major power through the Russo-Japanese War, tax increases as part of the war-time fiscal policy left local finances in a state of near collapse, and rural areas became seriously ruined and devastated.</e>
<cmt>&quot;left&quot;以下を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Japan gained the status as a major power through the Russo-Japanese War, tax increases as part of the war-time fiscal policy left local finances in a state of near collapse, and rural areas became seriously ruined and devastated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そこで1908年10月13日に出された戊申詔書のもとで地方とくに市町村財政の立て直しと財政基盤の整備、人員育成を進め、合わせて国民教化の推進を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Boshin Shosho published on October 13, 1908 tried to restore the finances of cities, towns and villages, reestablish fiscal basis, educate the public and at the same time, enlighten the public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Boshin Shosho published on October 13, 1908 tried to restore the finances of rural regions, especially cities, towns and villages, reestablish fiscal basis, educate the people and at the same time, enlighten the public.</e>
<cmt>・「地方とくに」を訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Boshin Shosho published on October 13, 1908 tried to restore the finances of rural regions, especially cities, towns and villages, reestablish fiscal basis, educate the people and at the same time, enlighten the public.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>