<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>新撰姓氏録</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen Shojiroku (Newly Compiled Register of Clan Names and Titles of Nobility)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>新撰姓氏録（しんせんしょうじろく）は、平安時代初期のに、嵯峨天皇の命により編纂された古代氏族名鑑。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinsen Shojiroku is an ancient clan name register or directory which was compiled by an order from Emperor Saga in the early Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinsen Shojiroku is an ancient clan-name register or directory that was compiled by an order from Emperor Saga in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinsen Shojiroku is an ancient clan-name register or directory that was compiled by an order from Emperor Saga in the early Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『新撰姓氏録』は、平安京および畿内に住む1182氏を、その出自により「皇別」・「神別」・「諸蕃」に分類してその祖先を明らかにし、氏名（うじな）の由来、分岐の様子などを記述するものであるが、主として氏族の改賜姓が正確かどうかを判別するために編まれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For 1182 clans who lived in Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto) and the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; describes the origin of their family names, how the pedigrees branched, and other information by classifying the clans, based on the place of origin, into &quot;Kobetsu&quot; (clans branched out from the Imperial family), &quot;Shinbetsu&quot; (clans branched out of a family of god), and &quot;Shoban&quot; (clans coming from foreign lands) to clarify their ancestors; however, it was compiled mainly to determine whether the changed family names of the clans are accurate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the 1182 clans that lived in Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in the current Kyoto) and the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; describes the origin of their family names, how the pedigrees branched and other information by classifying the clans, based on the place of origin, into &quot;Kobetsu&quot; (clans that branched out from the Imperial Family), &quot;Shinbetsu&quot; (clans the branched out of the family of god) and &quot;Shoban&quot; (clans coming from foreign lands) to clarify their ancestors; however, it was compiled mainly to determine whether the changed family names of the clans were accurate.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the 1182 clans that lived in Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in the current Kyoto) and the Kinai region (the five capital provinces surrounding the ancient capitals of Nara and Kyoto), &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; describes the origin of their family names, how the pedigrees branched and other information by classifying the clans, based on the place of origin, into &apos;Kobetsu&apos; (clans that branched out from the Imperial Family), &apos;Shinbetsu&apos; (clans the branched out of the family of god) and &apos;Shoban&apos; (clans coming from foreign lands) to clarify their ancestors; however, it was compiled mainly to determine whether the changed family names of the clans were accurate.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>後述するように、記載氏族が限られているとはいえ、日本古代氏族あるいは日本古代史全般の研究に欠かせない史料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As will be described later, although the number of clan names included in Shinsen Shojiroku is limited, it is an obviously indispensable historical material for the study of Japanese ancient clans and ancient history of Japan in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As will be described later, although the number of clan names included in Shinsen Shojiroku is limited, it is clearly an indispensable historical material for the study of Japanese ancient clans and the ancient history of Japan in general.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As will be described later, although the number of clan names included in Shinsen Shojiroku is limited, it is clearly an indispensable historical material for the study of Japanese ancient clans and the ancient history of Japan in general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>現存する『新撰姓氏録』は、目録だけの抄記（抜き書き）であって本文は残っていないが、所々にその残滓が認められるとともに、若干の逸文が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; has only a list of excerption and no body text, but some remnants can be seen in several places and a few itsubun (compositions previously existed but doesn&apos;t exist now) are known.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; has only a list of excerpts but no body text; however, some remnants can be seen in several places and a few itsubun (compositions that previously existed but no longer do) are known.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing &quot;Shinsen Shojiroku&quot; has only a list of excerpts but no body text; however, some remnants can be seen in several places and a few itsubun (compositions that previously existed but no longer do) are known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、本書の対象とする範囲は京（左京・右京）と五畿内に住む姓氏に限られており、また「序」にはそれすらも過半が登載されていないと記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scope of this document includes clans who lives in Kyo (Sakyo and Ukyo) and the Gokinai capital region; however, its introduction section describes that still more than half the target clan names are not registered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scope of this document includes clans that lived in Kyo (Sakyo and Ukyo) and the Gokinai capital region; however, its introductory section states that still more than half the target clan names hadn&apos;t been registered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scope of this document includes clans that lived in Kyo (Sakyo and Ukyo) and the Gokinai capital region; however, its introductory section states that still more than half the target clan names hadn&apos;t been registered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>なお、書名に『新撰』とつくのは、企画倒れで終わった『氏族志』のやりなおしという意味であって、『新撰姓氏録』以前に『姓氏録』が存在していたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the reason why the title includes &quot;Shinsen&quot; (Newly Compiled) is because it meant to indicate re-compiling of Shizoku-shi (a book that includes information on the clans) which ended up just as a plan, and thus it does not mean that any previous edition of the clan name register had been present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the reason the title includes &quot;Shinsen&quot; (newly compiled) is that it meant to indicate the re-compilation of Shizoku-shi (a book containing information on the clans), which ended up just as a plan; consequently, it doesn&apos;t infer the existence of any previous edition of the clan-name register.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the reason the title includes &quot;Shinsen&quot; (newly compiled) is that it meant to indicate the re-compilation of &quot;Shizoku-shi&quot; (a book containing information on the clans), which ended up just as a plan; consequently, it doesn&apos;t infer the existence of any previous edition of the clan-name register.</e>
<cmt>原文の『』にあわせて&quot;&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="8">
<j>皇別・神別・諸蕃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobetsu, Shinbetsu, and Shoban</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobetsu, Shinbetsu and Shoban</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobetsu, Shinbetsu and Shoban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>本書には、全部で1182氏姓が記録され、その出自により「皇別」・「神別」・「諸蕃」に3分類されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this register, a total of 1182 clan names are recorded and they are classified the into three types, &quot;Kobetsu,&quot; &quot;Shinbetsu, &quot; and &quot;Shoban,&quot; based on the place of origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This register records a total of 1182 clan names, being classified the into three types--&quot;Kobetsu,&quot; &quot;Shinbetsu &quot; and &quot;Shoban&quot;--based on the place of origin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This register records a total of 1182 clan names, being classified the into three types　-　&apos;Kobetsu,&apos; &apos;Shinbetsu&apos; and &apos;Shoban&apos; - based on the place of origin.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;にスペース補足/削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>皇別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kobetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kobetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kobetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>筆頭にあげられた「皇別」の姓氏とは、神武天皇以降、天皇家から分かれた氏族のことで、335氏が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names of clans of Kobetsu, which were listed at the top of the register, were clans which had branched out from the Imperial family after the time of Emperor Jimmu and included 335 clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 335 clan names of Kobetsu, which were listed at the top of the register, comprised clans that had branched out from the Imperial Family after the time of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 335 clan names of &apos;Kobetsu&apos;, which were listed at the top of the register, comprised clans that had branched out from the Imperial Family after the time of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせて&apos; &apos;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>代表的なものは、清原氏、橘氏、源氏などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the representative examples include the Kiyohara clan, the Tachibana clan, and the Minamoto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the representative examples include the Kiyohara, Tachibana and Minamoto clans.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the representative examples include the Kiyohara, Tachibana and Minamoto clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>皇別氏族は、さらに、皇親（「真人」のカバネをもつ氏族）とそれ以外の姓をもつ氏族に分かれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans branched out from the Imperial family are further divided into Koshin (Emperor&apos;s families who had the official status title (called &quot;kabane&quot;) of &quot;Mahito&quot;) and the other clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans branched out from the Imperial Family are further divided into Koshin (Emperor&apos;s families that had the official status title (called &quot;kabane&quot;) of &quot;Mahito&quot;), as well as other clans.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans branched out from the Imperial Family are further divided into Koshin (Emperor&apos;s families that had the official status title (called kabane) of &apos;Mahito&apos;), as well as other clans.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に原文に『』がないので&quot; &quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>神別</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinbetsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinbetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinbetsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「神別」の姓氏とは、神武天皇以前の神代に別れ、あるいは生じた氏族のことで、404氏が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans of &quot;Shinbetsu&quot; were clans which had branched out from the age of the gods or appeared before the time of Emperor Jimmu, and included 404 clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 404 clans of &quot;Shinbetsu&quot; were clans that had branched out from the age of the gods or appeared before the time of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 404 clans of &apos;Shinbetsu&apos; were clans that had branched out from the age of the gods or appeared before the time of Emperor Jimmu.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>神別姓氏は、さらに、ニニギが天孫降臨した際に付き随った神々の子孫を「天神」とし、瓊瓊杵尊から3代の間に分かれた子孫を「天孫」とし、天孫降臨以前から土着していた神々の子孫を「地祇」として3分類している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans of Shinbetsu are further divided into three types; &quot;Tenjin,&quot; descendants of gods who had come with Ninigi for tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess), &quot;Tenson&quot; (the grandson of the sun goddess), descendants who branched out in three generations from Ninigi-no Mikoto, and &quot;Chigi,&quot; descendants of gods who had been on the earth since before tensonkorin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans of Shinbetsu are further divided into three types: &quot;Tenjin,&quot; descendants of gods that had come with Ninigi for tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess); &quot;Tenson&quot; (the grandson of the sun goddess); descendants who branched out in three generations from Ninigi-no Mikoto; and &quot;Chigi,&quot; descendants of gods that had been on earth since before tensonkorin.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans of Shinbetsu are further divided into three types: &apos;Tenjin,&apos; descendants of gods that had come with Ninigi for tensonkorin (the descent to earth of the grandson of the sun goddess); &apos;Tenson&apos; (the grandson of the sun goddess); descendants who branched out in three generations from Ninigi-no Mikoto; and &apos;Chigi,&apos; descendants of gods that had been on earth since before tensonkorin.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>「天神」に分類された姓氏は藤原氏、大中臣氏など246氏、「天孫」は尾張氏、出雲氏など128氏（隼人系の氏族は天孫に分類される。）、「地祇」は安曇氏、弓削氏など30氏がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans classified as &quot;Tenjin&quot; include 246 clans including the Fujiwara clan and the Onakatomi clan, those classified as &quot;Tenson&quot; include 128 clans including the Owari clan and the Izumo clan (clans of the Hayato family are classified as Tenson), and those classified as &quot;Chigi&quot; include 30 clans including the Azumi clan and the Yuge clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans classified as &quot;Tenjin&quot; include 246 clans. including the Fujiwara and Onakatomi clans; those classified as &quot;Tenson&quot; include 128 clans, among which are the Owari and Izumo clans (clans of the Hayato family are classified as Tenson); and those classified as &quot;Chigi&quot; include 30 clans including the Azumi and Yuge clans.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans classified as &apos;Tenjin&apos; include 246 clans including the Fujiwara and Onakatomi clans; those classified as &apos;Tenson&apos; include 128 clans, among which are the Owari and Izumo clans (clans of the Hayato family are classified as Tenson); and those classified as &apos;Chigi&apos; include 30 clans including the Azumi and Yuge clans.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;にピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>諸蕃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoban</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoban</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「諸蕃」の姓氏とは、渡来人系の氏族で、秦氏、大蔵氏など326氏が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans of &quot;Shoban&quot; were clans of toraijin (people from overseas, especially from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Continental culture to the Japanese) and include 326 clans including the Hata clan and the Ookura clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans of &quot;Shoban&quot; were clans of toraijin (people from overseas, particularly from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Asian continental culture to the Japanese) and include 326 clans, among which are the Hata and Ookura clans.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans of &apos;Shoban&apos; were clans of toraijin (people from overseas, particularly from China and Korea, who settled in early Japan and introduced Asian continental culture to the Japanese) and include 326 clans, among which are the Hata and Ookura clans.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>諸蕃氏族は、さらに5分類され、「漢」として163氏、「百済」として104氏、「高麗」（高句麗を指す）として41氏、「新羅」として9氏、「任那」として9氏がそれぞれ挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans of Shoban are further divided into five types; &quot;Han&quot; which includes 163 clans, &quot;Kudara&quot; which includes 104 clans, &quot;Goryeo&quot; (meaning &quot;Goguryeo&quot;) which includes 41 clans, &quot;Silla&quot; which includes 9 clans, and &quot;Mimana&quot; which includes 9 clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans of Shoban are further divided into five types: &quot;Han,&quot; which includes 163 clans; &quot;Kudara,&quot; which includes 104 clans; &quot;Goryeo&quot; (meaning &quot;Goguryeo&quot;), which includes 41 clans; &quot;Silla,&quot; which includes nine clans; and &quot;Mimana,&quot; which also includes nine clans.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans of Shoban are further divided into five types: &apos;Han,&apos; which includes 163 clans; &apos;Kudara,&apos; which includes 104 clans; &apos;Goryeo&apos; (meaning Goguryeo), which includes 41 clans; &apos;Silla,&apos; which includes nine clans; and &apos;Mimana,&apos; which also includes nine clans.</e>
<cmt>原文は「」なので&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に原文に『』がないので&quot; &quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、これらのどこにも属さない氏族として、117氏が挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to this, there are 117 clans which do not belong to any category.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there are 117 clans that do not belong to any category.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there are 117 clans that do not belong to any category.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Murasagi(id:79122), 月下薄氷(id:47743), Nnh(id:474), Bendono(id:85524), お直し係(id:76245), 水野白楓(id:22811), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Trek011(id:7105), 胡亂堂(id:263343), 小太刀(id:18154), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>