<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>道中諸法度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dochu Shohatto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dochu Shohatto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dochu Shohatto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>道中諸法度（どうちゅうしょはっと）は、道中条目（どうちゅうじょうもく）とも呼ばれ、江戸幕府が大名・公家や幕府役人などの特定身分の者に対して出した交通法規。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dochu Shohatto, also called Dochu Jomoku, is traffic regulation issued by the Edo bakufu to people of specific status, such as daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), Court nobles and officials of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dochu Shohatto, also referred to as Dochu Jomoku, is traffic regulation issued by the Edo bakufu to people of specific status, such as daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), Court nobles and officials of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>called ⇒　referred to asに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dochu Shohatto, also referred to as Dochu Jomoku, is traffic regulation issued by the Edo bakufu to people of specific status, such as daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), Court nobles and officials of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、広義においては江戸幕府及び諸藩が一般民衆をも含めて対象とした各種の交通法規を総称したものを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, Dochu Shohatto is a collective term for various kinds of traffic regulations issued by the Edo bakufu and domains to people (including common people).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, Dochu Shohatto is a collective term for various kinds of traffic regulations issued by the Edo bakufu and domains to people (including common people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, Dochu Shohatto is a collective term for various kinds of traffic regulations issued by the Edo bakufu and domains to people (including common people).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>寛永3年（1626年）及び同11年（1634年）に行われた征夷大将軍上洛の際に供奉者の道中作法を定め、違反者には死罪 (江戸時代)を含めた厳しい処罰を課すこととした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In preparation for journeys of Seii Taishogun to Kyoto by road, conducted in 1626 and 1634, regulations on accompanying people&apos;s manners during the journey were established and it was stipulated that those who violated the regulations were punished severely, and sometimes sentenced to death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In journeys of Seii Taishogun to Kyoto conducted in 1626 and 1634, regulations on accompanying people&apos;s manners during the journey were established and it was stipulated that those who violated the regulations were punished severely, and sometimes sentenced to death (Edo period).</e>
<cmt>preferation for と　by road　は特に必要ないと思われますので、削除しました。また、（江戸時代）が訳漏れでしたので、付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In journeys of Seii Taishogun to Kyoto conducted in 1626 and 1634, regulations on accompanying people&apos;s manners during the journey were established and it was stipulated that those who violated the regulations were punished severely, and sometimes sentenced to death (Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>同12年（1635年）の武家諸法度で参勤交代が法制化された際にはあわせて大名行列の従者制限が定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) was established in Buke Shohatto (code for the warrior households) in 1635, the number of followers of Daimyo-gyoretsu (feudal lord&apos;s costumed procession) was limited as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) was established in Buke Shohatto (code for the warrior households) in 1635, the number of followers of Daimyo-gyoretsu (feudal lord&apos;s costumed procession) was limited as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) was established in Buke Shohatto (code for the warrior households) in 1635, the number of followers of Daimyo-gyoretsu (feudal lord&apos;s costumed procession) was limited as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同19年（1642年）に将軍の日光社参が行われると、上洛の例にあわせた供奉規定が設けられ、供奉規定制定が以後日光社参時の恒例とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Shogun visited Nikko in 1642, regulations on accompanying people, as established at the time of Shogun&apos;s journeys to Kyoto, were established, and after that the establishment of regulations on accompanying people was regarded as established practice associated with Shogun&apos;s visits to Nikko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Shogun visited Nikko in 1642, regulations on accompanying people, as established at the time of Shogun&apos;s journeys to Kyoto, were established, and after that the establishment of regulations on accompanying people was regarded as usual practice for Shogun&apos;s visits to Nikko.</e>
<cmt>established practice ⇒　usual practice に訂正しました。また、associated with をfor に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Shogun visited Nikko in 1642, regulations on accompanying people, as established at the time of Shogun&apos;s journeys to Kyoto, were established, and after that the establishment of regulations on accompanying people was regarded as usual practice for Shogun&apos;s visits to Nikko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、明暦2年（1656年）には二条番衆に対する道中作法定書が出され、翌年には大坂番衆を含める形で改正された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, in 1656, a law on manners during journeys was issued for Niban Banshu (guards), and in 1657 the law was revised to include Osaka Banshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in 1656, a law on manners during journeys was issued for Nijo Banshu (guards), and in 1657 the law was revised to include Osaka Banshu as well.</e>
<cmt>Niban ⇒ Nijoに訂正し、文の最後にas wellを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, in 1656, a law on manners during journeys was issued for Nijo Banshu (guards), and in 1657 the law was revised to include Osaka Banshu as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>更に宝永元年（1704年）には参勤交代における供奉者・人馬利用・宿泊に関する道中規制が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, regulations on accompanying people, usage of a man or a horse, and accommodation during sankinkotai were established in 1704.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, regulations on accompanying people, usage of a man or a horse, and accommodation during sankinkotai were established in 1704.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, regulations on accompanying people, usage of a man or a horse, and accommodation during sankinkotai were established in 1704.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>これらの法制の集大成が正徳 (日本)2年（1712年）に出された道中筋条目である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dochosuji Jomoku, issued in 1712, is the culmination of such laws and regulations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dochosuji Jomoku (articles), issued in 1712, is the culmination of such laws and regulations.</e>
<cmt>Jomoku の後にわかりやすくするために、（article)を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dochosuji Jomoku (articles), issued in 1712, is the culmination of such laws and regulations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらは大名・旗本・在番衆・町奉行・遠国奉行などを対象とし、添人馬利用・賃金不払・通日雇人足の非分・三度飛脚や町人請負荷物の過貫目をはじめとして各種不法行為を取締るものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These articles were applied to daimyo, hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), zaibanshu, machi-bugyo and ongoku-bugyo (the collective name of the magistrates placed at important areas directly controlled by the government in the Edo period) and controlled various illegal acts including use of 添人馬, nonpayment of wages, 非分 of ninsoku (coolie, laborer) hired for a whole day, overloading of sando-hikyaku or townspeople carriers.</e>
<cmt>読み方不明、定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Jomoku (articles) were applied to daimyo, hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), zaibanshu, machi-bugyo and ongoku-bugyo (the collective name of the magistrates placed at important areas directly controlled by the government in the Edo period) and controlled various illegal acts including use of 添人馬, nonpayment of wages, unreasonableness of ninsoku (coolie, laborer) hired for a whole day, overloading of sando-hikyaku or townspeople carriers.</e>
<cmt>articles の前にJomokuを加えました。　非分は、「道理に合わないこと、非理」（広辞苑より）の意味だと思われるので、unreasonablness　を入れておきました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Jomoku (articles) were applied to daimyo, hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), zaibanshu, machi-bugyo and ongoku-bugyo (the collective name of the magistrates placed at important areas directly controlled by the government in the Edo period) and controlled various illegal acts including use of 添人馬, nonpayment of wages, unreasonableness of ninsoku (coolie, laborer) hired for a whole day, overloading of sando-hikyaku or townspeople carriers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ほぼ同時に五街道など主要道の宿駅・助郷の村々にも添条目を付けて通知された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were announced to shukueki (post town, relay station, stage) and villages of sukego (labor which was imposed to the neighboring village to help the primarily imposed village) along the main roads including Go-kaido Roads, along with the attached articles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dochosuji Jomoku were announced to shukueki (post town, relay station, stage) and villages of sukego (labor which was imposed to the neighboring village to help the primarily imposed village) along the main roads including Go-kaido Roads, along with the attached articles.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくするために、they　を　Dochosuji Jomokuに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dochosuji Jomoku were announced to shukueki (post town, relay station, stage) and villages of sukego (labor which was imposed to the neighboring village to help the primarily imposed village) along the main roads including Go-kaido Roads, along with the attached articles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>道中筋条目はその後、延享4年（1747年）、宝暦8年（1758年）、寛政元年（1789年）と改正され、文政4年（1821年）10月には道中制法・道中取締触書と3点セットにして公布された（ただし、道中取締触書の実際の公布は11月）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dochosuji Jomoku was revised in 1747, 1758 and 1789, and in October, 1821 it was announced in combination with Dochu Seiho and Dochu Torishimari Furegaki (which was actually announced in November).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Dochosuji Jomoku was revised in 1747, 1758 and 1789, and in October, 1821 it was announced officially in combination with Dochu Seiho and Dochu Torishimari Furegaki (which was actually announced officially in November).</e>
<cmt>文頭に、after that を追加しました。また、announce の後にofficcially を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Dochosuji Jomoku was revised in 1747, 1758 and 1789, and in October, 1821 it was announced officially in combination with Dochu Seiho and Dochu Torishimari Furegaki (which was actually announced officially in November).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その他にも享保6年（1721年）には参勤交代の供奉者を禄高別に規制した他、天保7年（1836年）には前述の道中取締触書の改正を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the bakufu regulated people accompanying sankinkotai based on rokudaka (stipend) in 1721, and revised Dochu Torisihari Furegaki in 1836.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the bakufu regulated people accompanying sankinkotai based on rokudaka (stipend) in 1721, and revised Dochu Torisihari Furegaki mentioned above in 1836.</e>
<cmt>「前述の」が訳漏れのため、mentioned aboveを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the bakufu regulated people accompanying sankinkotai based on rokudaka (stipend) in 1721, and revised Dochu Torisihari Furegaki mentioned above in 1836.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>また、こうした幕府の動きに合わせて諸藩でも自主的に道中の行動を規制する規則（名称は藩によって異なる）を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In accordance with such a policy of the bakufu, domains voluntarily established regulations on people&apos;s behavior during journeys (The name of the regulations varied according to domains).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In accordance with such a policy of the bakufu, domains voluntarily established regulations on people&apos;s behavior during journeys (The name of the regulations varied according to domains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In accordance with such a policy of the bakufu, domains voluntarily established regulations on people&apos;s behavior during journeys (The name of the regulations varied according to domains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>