<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>臨時給</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinjikyu (bonus)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinjikyu (bonus)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinjikyu</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>臨時給（りんじきゅう）とは、規定外の年官を臨時に給与すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rinjikyu was provisional payment of extra nenkan (a regular nenkan means: a right granted as a stipend to members of the Imperial family (including the emperor), consorts of the emperor, some Court nobles, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain government post conferred to them on the occasion of the annual installation of them as government officials.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rinjikyu was provisional payment of extra nenkan (a regular nenkan means: a right granted as a stipend to members of the Imperial family (including the emperor), consorts of the emperor, some Court nobles, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain government post conferred to them on the occasion of the annual installation of them as government officials.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rinjikyu was provisional payment of extra nenkan (a regular nenkan means: a right granted as a stipend to members of the Imperial Family [including the emperor], consorts of the emperor, some court nobles, and so forth to nominate a person for a certain government post conferred to them on the occasion of the annual installation of them as government officials).</e>
<cmt>括弧を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代中期頃から見られるが、当初は親王・女御などの生計に資するために判官以下の官職に限って給したが、後には太上天皇や三宮 (后妃)、大臣などに支給対象が広げられ、支給される役職も権守や介などにも広げられた（ただし大臣は掾・大舎人に制限された）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom had been observed from the mid Heian period: at first, it was limited to the government posts at the rank of hangan (inspector (third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period)) and below in order to support Imperial Princes and consorts financially; and later, it was extended to Daijo Tenno (retired emperors), Sangu (the Empress, the Dowager Empress, the Grand Dowager Empress), and ministers (however, it was limited to jo (secretary of provincial offices) and Otoneri (royal attendant) among ministers), also to Gon no kami (provisional governor) and suke (provincial governor) as the government posts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom had been observed from the mid Heian period: at first, it was limited to the government posts at the rank of hangan (inspector (third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period)) and below in order to support Imperial Princes and consorts financially; and later, it was extended to Daijo Tenno (retired emperors), Sangu (the Empress, the Dowager Empress, the Grand Dowager Empress), and ministers (however, it was limited to jo (secretary of provincial offices) and Otoneri (royal attendant) among ministers), also to Gon no kami (provisional governor) and suke (provincial governor) as the government posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom had been observed from the mid Heian period: at first, it was limited to the government posts at the rank of hangan (inspector [third highest of the four administrative ranks of the ritsuryo period]) and below in order to support Imperial Princes and consorts financially; later it was extended to Daijo Tenno (retired emperors), Sangu (the Empress, the Dowager Empress, the Grand Dowager Empress), and ministers (however, it was limited to jo [secretary of provincial offices] and Otoneri [royal attendant] among ministers), and the government posts granted were also extended to gon no kami (provisional governor) and suke (provincial governor) other than hangan.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。括弧を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>これは正規の年官であった目 (国司)や史生などへの応募者が減少したことにより、そこから上がる任料収入の不足に対応したものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was because, since the applicants for sakan (kokushi) and shisho (a person doing miscellaneous duties about documents) of the regular nenkan decreased, rinjikyu was devised to cope with the shortage of ninryo (fee for getting an official rank) income.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was because, since the applicants for sakan (kokushi) and shisho (a person doing miscellaneous duties concerning documents) of the regular nenkan decreased, rinjikyu was devised to cope with the shortage of ninryo (fee for getting an official rank) income.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was because, since the applicants for sakan (kokushi) and shisho (a person doing miscellaneous duties concerning documents) of the regular nenkan decreased, rinjikyu was devised to cope with the shortage of ninryo (fee for getting an official rank) income.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また京官の判官や武官などには武士や下級官人からの志望が多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the applicants for hangan and bukan (military officer) of kyokan (an official of the Capital) were samurai (warriors) and lower-ranking government officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the applicants for hangan and bukan (military officer) of kyokan (an official of the Capital) were samurai (warriors) and lower-ranking government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the applicants for hangan and bukan (military officer) of kyokan (an official of the Capital) were samurai (warriors) and lower-ranking government officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), ベルゼブブ(id:184141), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>