<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>冥加</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoga</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>冥加（みょうが）とは、江戸時代に山野河海などを利用したり、営業などの免許の代償として江戸幕府や藩に対して支払った租税の1種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoga means a kind of tax in the Edo period that was paid to the Edo bakufu or domains in consideration of the use of mountains/fields/rivers/seas or the grant of business licence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoga means a kind of tax in the Edo period that was paid to the Edo bakufu or domains in consideration for the use of mountains/fields/rivers/seas or to grant a business license</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoga means a kind of tax in the Edo period that was paid to the Edo bakufu or domains in consideration for the use of mountains/fields/rivers/seas or to grant a business license</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>金銭で支払われることが多かったために、冥加金（みょうがきん）・冥加永（みょうがえい、「永」＝永楽通宝）とも呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since it was usually paid in cash, it was also called Myogakin/Myogaei (ei means Eiraku-tsuho (bronze coins)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since it was usually paid in cash, it was also called Myogakin/Myogaei (ei means Eiraku-tsuho (bronze coins)).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since it was usually paid in cash, it was also called Myogakin/Myogaei (ei means Eiraku-tsuho (bronze coins)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>本来、「冥加」とは冥利と同義語で、神仏からの加護の意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, a term Myoga was the synonym of myori, which means divine protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the term Myoga was a synonym for myori, which means divine protection.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the term Myoga was a synonym for myori, which means divine protection.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>冥加の祈願あるいは冥加を受けたことに対する謝礼として寺院や神社に奉納された金銭や物資のことも「冥加」と称するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Money and goods that were offered to temples/shrines as gratuity for the prayer of Myoga or receiving Myoga also came to be called &quot;Myoga&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Money and goods that were offered to temples/shrines as gratuity for a Myoga prayer or receiving Myoga also came to be known as &quot;Myoga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Money and goods that were offered to temples/shrines as gratuity for a Myoga prayer or receiving Myoga also came to be known as &quot;Myoga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に領主権力も自己を領民の庇護者としての恩恵（国恩）を強調した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, feudal lords claimed to be the protectors of the people of the domain and stressed the benefit of the existence of such protectors (kokuon (benefit given by the lord of domain)).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, feudal lords claimed to be the protectors of the people of the domain and stressed the benefit of the existence of such protectors (kokuon (benefit given by the lord of domain)).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, feudal lords claimed to be the protectors of the people of the domain and stressed the benefit of the existence of such protectors (kokuon (benefit given by the lord of domain)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これを口実に年貢を納めない商工業者に対して農民の年貢に相当する冥加を求めるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the pretext of the above, feudal lords imposed Myoga, which corresponded to nengu (land tax) imposed on farmers, on merchants and traders who were not required to pay nengu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the above pretext, feudal lords imposed Myoga, which corresponded to nengu (land tax) imposed on farmers, on merchants and traders who were not required to pay nengu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the above pretext, feudal lords imposed Myoga, which corresponded to nengu (land tax) imposed on farmers, on merchants and traders who were not required to pay nengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>更に領主権力の許可が必要とされる鉱山労働や鯨などの捕獲など領主が支配する山野河海から何らかの利益を得た者にからも冥加を徴収するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, they imposed Myoga on people who gained profit from the business that required the license of the domain, such as mine workers, as well as people who gained profit from mountains/fields/rivers/seas that were under the rule of lords, such as whale fishermen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, they imposed Myoga on people who gained profit from business that required a license from the domain, such as mine workers, as well as people who gained profit from mountains/fields/rivers/seas that were under the rule of the lords, such as whale fishermen.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, they imposed Myoga on people who gained profit from business that required a license from the domain, such as mine workers, as well as people who gained profit from mountains/fields/rivers/seas that were under the rule of the lords, such as whale fishermen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これは農民が領主が支配する田畑で労働行為（耕作）を行って年貢を納める代償として領主からの庇護を受けるという関係をその他の領民に拡大したものとも言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a sense, the above was modeled after the relation between lords and farmers under which farmers worked at farmlands (cultivation) that were under the rule of lords and pay nengu while being protected by lords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a sense, the above was modeled after the relation between lords and farmers under which farmers worked at farmlands (cultivation) that were under the rule of lords and pay nengu while being protected by the lords.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a sense, the above was modeled after the relation between lords and farmers under which farmers worked at farmlands (cultivation) that were under the rule of lords and pay nengu while being protected by the lords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>似たような租税に運上が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There existed similar tax called Unjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A similar tax called Unjo also existed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar tax called Unjo also existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>運上も商工業者などに課された租税であるが、その違いについては以下のような説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unjo was also imposed on merchants and traders, and there are following views on the differences between the two taxes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unjo was also imposed on merchants and traders, and there are following views on the differences between the two taxes.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unjo was also imposed on merchants and traders, and there are following views on the differences between the two taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「運上は最初から一定の金額を納付するように定められているが冥加にはそれがない」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;While the amount of Unjo was prefixed, no fixed amount existed for Myoga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;While the amount of Unjo was fixed, no fixed amount existed for Myoga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;While the amount of Unjo was fixed, no fixed amount existed for Myoga.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「運上は領主が負担者に命じて納めさせるものであるが、冥加は負担者が領主による冥加である国恩に対する自主的な奉納の体裁を採っていた（もっともそれが本当に自主的であるかどうかは別問題である）」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;While Unjo was paid by tax payers according to the order of lords, Unjo was paid voluntarily in the form of the offering for kokuon, Myoga given by lords (however, it is another matter whether it was really paid voluntarily).&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;While Unjo was paid by tax payers according to the order of lords, Unjo was paid voluntarily in the form of an offering for kokuon, Myoga given by the lords (however, it is another matter whether it was really paid voluntarily).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;While Unjo was paid by tax payers according to the order of lords, Myoga was paid voluntarily in the form of an offering for kokuon, Myoga given by the lords (however, it is another matter whether it was really paid voluntarily).&quot;</e>
<cmt>Unjo→Nyoga（文意に合うように訂正しました）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「小物成・運上は幕藩制初期からの租税で、冥加は株仲間結成をはじめとして後世に新たに賦課されたものである」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;While Komononari (miscellaneous tax) and Unjo existed since the early stage of shogunate system, Myoga was newly imposed later when kabunakama (merchant guild) was established.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;While Komononari (miscellaneous tax) and Unjo existed since the early stage of shogunate system, Myoga was newly imposed later when kabunakama (merchant guild) was established.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;While Komononari (miscellaneous tax) and Unjo existed since the early stage of shogunate system, Myoga was newly imposed later when kabunakama (merchant guild) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>実態は冥加に対しても一定額が定められる場合もあり、「運上と云も冥加永というも同様たり（中略）、何れを唱へても苦しからず」とした『地方凡例録』の記述が近いものであったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In view of the fact that there were cases where a fixed amount was set for Myoga, the reality might be similar to the description of &quot;Jikata hanreiroku&quot; saying &quot;Unjo and Myogaei are the same ones, (snip) you may use whichever&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In view of the fact that there were cases where a fixed amount was set for Myoga, the reality might be similar to the description of &quot;Jikata hanreiroku&quot; saying &quot;Unjo and Myogaei are the same, (snip) you may use them interchangeably.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In view of the fact that there were cases where a fixed amount was set for Myoga, the reality might be similar to the description of &quot;Jikata hanreiroku&quot; saying &quot;Unjo and Myogaei are the same, (snip) you may use them interchangeably.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="15">
<j>もっとも代表的なものとして株仲間の結成時に領主から独占的な営業特権を認められた代償として納める冥加がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The representative example of Myoga was the one that was imposed by lords in consideration of the exclusive business right of kabunakama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most well known example of Myoga was the one that was imposed by lords in for the exclusive business right of kabunakama.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most well known example of Myoga was the one that was imposed by lords in for the exclusive business right of kabunakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>認可の最初の年には多額の冥加を納付（初年金/初年銀）して、以後は少額の冥加を毎年納付（年々金/年々銀）することとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the amount of Myoga was big for the year of initial permission (shonenkin/shonengin (down payment)), a small amount of Myoga was imposed annually (nennenkin/nennengin (annual payment)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the amount of Myoga was big for the first year of permission (shonenkin/shonengin (down payment)), a small amount of Myoga was imposed annually (nennenkin/nennengin (annual payment)).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the amount of Myoga was big for the first year of permission (shonenkin/shonengin (down payment)), a small amount of Myoga was imposed annually (nennenkin/nennengin (annual payment)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>納付方法としては金貨による金建・銀貨による銀建及び必要に応じての両者の混合の場合があり、負担は仲間に入った各構成員が共同で負担した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoga was paid either in gold coin, silver coin or both if necessary, and the members of kabunakama jointly bore the cost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoga was paid either in gold coin, silver coin or both if necessary, and the members of kabunakama jointly bore the cost.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoga was paid either in gold coin, silver coin or both if necessary, and the members of kabunakama jointly bore the cost.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>天保の改革の際に株仲間が一時廃止された際に冥加も免除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoga was abolished when kabunakama was once abolished in the process of Tenpo Reform.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoga was abolished when kabunakama was once abolished in the process of Tenpo Reform.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoga was abolished when kabunakama was once abolished in the process of Tenpo Reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>後に株仲間は再興されたが株仲間に対する冥加の賦課は行われなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though kabunakama was revived later, Myoga was no more imposed on kabunakama.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though kabunakama was revived later, Myoga was no longer imposed on kabunakama.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though kabunakama was revived later, Myoga was no longer imposed on kabunakama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>株仲間以外にも市中の空地に家を建築したり、川岸を水揚げ場として占有する場合の地子として冥加を納める例があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other than kabunakama, there were cases where Myoga was imposed on people who constructed a house at an open space inside a town or those who used a river bank for landing space.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than kabunakama, there were cases where Myoga was imposed on people who constructed houses in an open space inside town or those who used river banks for docking space.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other than kabunakama, there were cases where Myoga was imposed on people who constructed houses in an open space inside town or those who used river banks for docking space.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>明治維新の際の「商法大意」に基づいて廃止され、後に運上として復活するものや近代的な営業税などの形で賦課されるものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoga was abolished based on &quot;Shoho taii&quot; (a kind of commercial code) enacted in the process of Meiji Restoration, but some of them later revived as Unjo or modern trade tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoga was abolished based on &quot;Shoho taii&quot; (a kind of commercial code) enacted in the process of the Meiji Restoration, but some of them were later revived as Unjo or modern trade tax.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoga was abolished based on &quot;Shoho taii&quot; (a kind of commercial code) enacted in the process of the Meiji Restoration, but some of them were later revived as Unjo or modern trade tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Avanzare(id:34657), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>