<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>手島氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Teshima clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Teshima clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the Teshima clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>手島氏（てしまし）は、日本の氏族の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Teshima clan is one of the clans in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Teshima clan is one of the clans in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Teshima clan is one of the clans in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>手島氏は摂津源氏の一族である能瀬高頼（多田行綱の弟）の後裔である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Teshima clan is a descendant of Takayori NOSE (a younger brother of Yukitsuna TADA), who was a family of Settsu Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Teshima clan descended from Takayori NOSE (younger brother of Yukitsuna TADA), who was a member of the Settsu Genji family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Teshima clan descended from Takayori NOSE (younger brother of Yukitsuna TADA), who was a member of the Settsu Genji family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>他流に摂津国豊島郡発祥の神武天皇後裔多臣族手島連、桓武平氏、藤原氏秀郷流久賀氏族などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are another lineage for the clan such as the descendant-of-Emperor-Jinmu Onomi family Teshima no muraji, which originated from Toshima county in Settsu Province, Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) and the Koga clan from FUJIWARA no Hidesato house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is another lineage for the clan as a descendant-of-Emperor-Jinmu Onomi family Teshima no muraji, originating from Toshima county in Settsu Province, Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) and the Koga clan from FUJIWARA no Hidesato house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is another lineage for the clan as a descendant-of-Emperor-Jinmu Onomi family Teshima no muraji, originating from Toshima County in Settsu Province, Kanmu-Heishi (Taira clan) and the Koga clan from FUJIWARA no Hidesato house.</e>
<cmt>countyをCountyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>