<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>軍役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunyaku (or, Guneki, Military Service)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunyaku (or, Guneki, Military Service)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunyaku</e>
<cmt>(or, Guneki, Military Service)後列で説明があるので削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>軍役（ぐんやく、ぐんえき）は、戦時、武士が主君に拠出すべく課せられる軍事力や兵糧その他である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gunyaku was a military service and provisions that was imposed by the lord on a samurai retainer to offer in wartime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gunyaku was a military service and provisions that was imposed by the lord on a samurai retainer to offer in wartime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gunyaku (also known as Guneki) was a military service and provisions that was imposed by the lord on a retainer to offer in wartime.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Middle Ages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>軍役は広義には民衆に課せられる夫役のうちの兵役なども含まれるが、狭義には封建制度における「御恩と奉公」の関係において、知行地の安堵（御恩）と引き替えに主君に軍事的奉公を行うことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a broad sense, gunyaku covered a meaning of conscription included in buyaku (the labor service) which was imposed on the people; but in a narrow sense, gunyaku meant samurai retainer&apos;s offering of a military service to the lord in exchange for ando (安堵, recognition and guarantee) (go-on, 御恩, debt) of ownership of chigyochi (fief) in the relationship of &apos;go-on to hoko (debts and service)&apos; in the feudal system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a broad sense, gunyaku meant conscription which included buyaku (the labor service) that was imposed on the people; but in a narrow sense, gunyaku referred to a samurai retainer&apos;s offering of military service to the lord in exchange for ando (安堵, recognition and guarantee) (go-on, 御恩, debt) of ownership of chigyochi (fief) in the relationship of &apos;go-on to hoko (debts and service)&apos; in the feudal system.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a broad sense, gunyaku meant conscription which included the labor service that was imposed on the people; but in a narrow sense, gunyaku referred to a retainer&apos;s offering of military service to the lord in exchange for recognition and guarantee of ownership of the fief (debt) in the relationship of &apos;debts and service&apos; in the feudal system.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>中世の土地支配権は近世のような「一つの土地に一人の領主」は確立されておらず、その支配体系も近世のものよりずっと複雑であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sway over lands in the middle ages had not been evolved to &apos;one lord in one land&apos; as in the Early-Modern period yet, and the swaying system was much more complicated than that of the Early-Modern ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sway over lands in the middle ages had not been evolved to &apos;one lord in one land&apos; as in the Early-Modern period yet, and the swaying system was much more complicated than that of the Early-Modern ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sway over lands in the middle ages had not been evolved to &apos;one lord in one land&apos; as in the Early-Modern period yet, and the swaying system was much more complicated than that of the Early-Modern ages.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>土地には耕作権を意味する「作職」、年貢徴収請負権の「名主」、荘園領主への年貢納入を請け負う「地頭職」などが重層に存在し、さらに国衙や守護職が令制国単位で影響力を及ぼしていたため、武士の主従関係も一対一の単純なものであるとは限られていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a multilayered structure of rights claimed for a land such as &apos;saku-shiki (the right of the cultivator)&apos; which meant the right of cultivation, &apos;myoshu (landholder)&apos; which meant the right of contracting to collect land taxes, and &apos;jito-shiki (the stewardship rights)&apos; which was for contracting to pay the land taxes to shoen-ryoshu (the lord of the manor); besides, as kokuga (provincial government office) and shugoshoku (military governor) had influences on each ryoseikoku (province), master-servant relationships among samurai were not necessarily a simple one-to-one relationship.</e>
<cmt>「名主」myoshuは「名主職」myoshu-shiki (the rights of landholders to part of the produce)の誤りと思われますが、原文通りに訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a multilayered structure of rights claimed for a land such as &apos;saku-shiki (the right of the cultivator)&apos; which meant the right of cultivation, &apos;myoshu (landholder)&apos; which referred to the right to collect land taxes, and &apos;jito-shiki (the stewardship rights)&apos; which was for contracting to pay out land taxes to shoen-ryoshu (the lord of the manor); besides, as kokuga (provincial government office) and shugoshoku (military governor) possessed influence on each ryoseikoku (province), master-servant relationships among samurai were not necessarily a simple one-to-one relationship.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a multilayered structure of rights claimed for a land including &apos;saku-shiki&apos; which meant the right of cultivation, &apos;myoshu&apos; which referred to the right to collect land taxes, and &apos;jito-shiki&apos; which was responsible for paying out land taxes to the lord of the manor; besides, as the provincial government office and the military governor possessed influence on each province, master-servant relationships among samurai were not necessarily a simple one-to-one relationship.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>武士はやがて荘園を蚕食していき、自らの土地支配を保証する実効力を持った有力な上層武士に、年貢に代わって軍役を負担することでその支配を確立していくようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, samurai began encroaching shoen (manor in medieval Japan), and gradually established sway over shoen by paying influential higher ranking samurai who was able to warrant the samurai the sway over the land, in a military service instead of land tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, samurai began encroaching shoen (manor in medieval Japan), and gradually established sway over shoen by paying an influential higher ranking samurai who was able to warrant the samurai the sway over the land, in a military service instead of land tax.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, samurai began encroaching the manors and gradually established contrrol over the manors by paying an influential higher ranking samurai, who was able to warrant the samurai the control over the land, in a military service instead of land tax.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安時代には武士の支配を法的に保証するのは荘園領主たる「領家」「本所」であり、開発領主たちはその所領を孜々として寄進し、名簿（みょうぼ）を奉って子弟を近侍させ、猟官活動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, &apos;ryoke&apos; or &apos;honjo&apos; which was the shoen-ryoshu legally warranted samurai the sway over shoen; on the other hand, kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) did office-seeking by assiduously contributing shoryo (territory), offering myobu (a certificate given to the leader with the retainer&apos;s name on it) and having had his sons be retainers.</e>
<cmt>名簿（みょうぼ）は、「みょうぶ」とも読むようです。インターネットではmyobuで検索すると、ここでの意味に該当する言葉がヒットします。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, &apos;ryoke&apos; or &apos;honjo&apos; which was the shoen-ryoshu legally warranted samurai the sway over shoen; on the other hand, kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) did office-seeking by assiduously contributing shoryo (territory), offering myobu (a certificate given to the leader with the retainer&apos;s name on it) and had his sons be retainers.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Heian period, the lord of the manor called &apos;ryoke&apos; or &apos;honjo&apos; legally warranted samurai the control over the manor; on the other hand, the local notables who actually developed the land did office-seeking by assiduously contributing their territory, offering a certificate given to the leader with the retainer&apos;s name on it and had his sons be retainers.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一方で開発領主たちは国衙や郡衙から令制国住人として軍役を課せられ、在庁官人として出仕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, kaihatsu-ryoshu, as a resident of the ryoseikoku, was imposed to offer military service by kokuga or gunga (district government office) and presented himself for duty as Zaicho-kanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, kaihatsu-ryoshu, as a resident of the ryoseikoku, was made to offer military service by kokuga or gunga (district government office) and presented himself for duty as Zaicho-kanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, the local nobles who developed the land, as a resident of the province, was made to offer military service by the district government office and presented himself for duty as the local officials.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>武士の軍役としてもっとも古い形はこれらの領家への近侍や国衙への出仕における軍事的奉仕であったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest style of military service imposed on samurai supposed to have been military corvee when samurai served to the ryoke as a retainer or presented himself for duty at the kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest style of military service imposed on samurai was supposed to have been military corvee when samurai served the ryoke as a retainer or presented himself for duty at the kokuga.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest style of military service imposed on samurai was supposed to have been military service when samurai served the lord of the manor as a retainer or presented himself for duty at the provincial government office.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>やがて彼らの土地の保証は源氏、平家といった、貴種に連なる上級武家に委ねられ、下級、中級の武士は「給人」と呼ばれて、主君から恩給された土地の見返りに、平時、戦時における主君への軍事的奉仕を行う構造が出来上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the higher ranking samurai families such as Minamoto clan or Taira family which had relationship with persons of noble birth were entrusted to warrant samurai the land, and a system was established in which middle and lower ranking samurai were called &apos;kyunin&apos; and offered military services to the lord not only in peacetime but also in wartime in exchange for the land which the lord granted them as onkyu (stipend).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the higher ranking samurai families such as Minamoto clan or Taira family which had relationships with persons of noble birth were entrusted to warrant samurai the land, and a system was established in which middle and lower ranking samurai were called &apos;kyunin&apos; who offered military services to the lord not only in peacetime but also in wartime in exchange for the land which the lord granted them as onkyu (stipend).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the higher ranking samurai families such as the Minamoto clan or the Taira family, which had relationships with persons of noble birth were entrusted to warrant the local nobles their developed lands, and a system was established in which middle and lower ranking samurai were called &apos;kyunin&apos; who offered military services to the lord not only in peacetime but also in wartime in exchange for the land which the lord granted them as stipend.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ただし前述のごとく土地への影響力は重層構造であったため、在地領主は自らの土地を守るべく、将軍家のほか、有力公家、国守や守護、あるいは在地の有力武家にその安堵を求めることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since there was the multilayered structure of influences put on a land as mentioned above, zaichi-ryoshu (resident landholder) sometimes asked not only the shogunate but also influential court nobles, kokushu (governor of a province) or shugo (military governor), or resident influential samurai family for ando (安堵) of the ownership of the land, for the purpose of protecting the ownership of his land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since there was a multilayered structure of influence put on a land as mentioned above, zaichi-ryoshu (resident landholder) sometimes asked not only the shogunate but also influential court nobles, kokushu (governor of a province) or shugo (military governor), or resident influential samurai family for ando (安堵) of the ownership of the land, for the purpose of protecting the ownership of his land.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since there was a multilayered structure of influence put on a land as mentioned above, the resident landholder sometimes asked not only the shogunate but also influential court nobles, the governor of a province or the military governor, or resident influential samurai family for recognition and gurantee of the ownership of the land, for the purpose of protecting the ownership of his land.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉期の幕府御家人に課せられた軍役は、大番役や追捕などであり、戦時には「いざ鎌倉」とはせ参じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military service imposed on bakufu-gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) in the Kamakura period included obanyaku (guard duty in Kyoto and Kamakura), tsuibu (to search and capture) and the like, and in a wartime, they rushed to the place, &apos;Iza Kamakura (To Kamakura with haste)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「追捕」は「追捕使」の誤りである可能性があります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military service imposed on bakufu-gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) in the Kamakura period included obanyaku (guard duty in Kyoto and Kamakura), tsuibu (to search and capture) and the like, and in wartime, they would summarily rush to the place, &apos;Iza Kamakura (To Kamakura with haste)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military service imposed on the immediate vassals of the shogunate in the Kamakura period included the guard duty in Kyoto and Kamakura, to search and capture and the like, and in wartime, they would summarily rush to the place, &apos;Iza Kamakura&apos; (To Kamakura with haste).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、これらの軍役は後世のように所領の大きさや収穫量に基づいたものではなく、動員兵力は各々の御家人に委ねられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military services were based neither on the area of shoryo nor crop yields, and the military force to mobilize was left to each gokenin&apos;s discretion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military services were based neither on the area of shoryo nor crop yields, and the military force to mobilize was left to each gokenin&apos;s discretion.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military services were based neither on the area nor crop yields of of territories, and the military force to mobilize was left to the discretion of each of the immediate vassals of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>元寇では過重な軍役に比して所領の加増が少なかったことが鎌倉得宗への不満として蓄積し、鎌倉幕府滅亡の遠因になったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since shoryo was not increased as much as excessive military services imposed during the Mongolian Expeditions against Japan, dissatisfaction built up among the samurai retainers with the Tokuso (head of the Hojo clan) regent of the Kamakura shogunate, which supposedly formed a remote cause of the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since shoryo was not increased as much as excessive military services imposed during the Mongolian Expeditions against Japan, dissatisfaction built up among the samurai retainers with the Tokuso (head of the Hojo clan) regent of the Kamakura shogunate, which supposedly formed a remote cause of the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the territory was not increased as much as excessive military services imposed during the Mongolian Expeditions against Japan, dissatisfaction built up among the samurai retainers with the the head of the Hojo clan regent of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), which supposedly formed a remote cause of the fall of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>戦乱期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warring Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warring Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warring Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)になると、各国の中小武士団は新たな源氏の棟梁、足利氏のほか、半済令以後勢力を蓄えた守護大名、南朝、北朝方の有力武家らに所領安堵を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), small and medium bushidan (samurai warrior band) in provinces asked not only the new head of the government, Genji-descent Ashikaga clan, but also Shugo Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) which had increased its influence after hanzeirei (order allowing military governors, or Shugo, to collect half of the taxes from manors and demesnes as military fund) was issued, influential samurai families on the side of the Southern Court or the Northern Court for ando of the ownership of their lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), small and medium bushidan (samurai warrior band) in provinces asked not only the new head of the government, Genji-descent Ashikaga clan, but also Shugo Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) which had increased its influence after hanzeirei (order allowing military governors, or Shugo, to collect half of the taxes from manors and demesnes as military fund) was issued, influential samurai families on the side of the Southern Court or the Northern Court for ando of the ownership of their lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), small and medium samurai warrior band in provinces asked not only the new head of the government, the Genji-descent Ashikaga clan, but also the territorial lord as provincial constable, which had increased its influence after the order allowing military governors or Shugo to collect half of the taxes from manors and demesnes as military fund was issued, and influential samurai families on the side of the Southern Court or the Northern Court for recognition and gurantee of the ownership of their lands.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>幕府は守護大名庶家や足利氏譜代から奉公衆を編成し、在京奉公を課したが、一方で守護大名は国内の在地領主（国人）に対する支配を強め、その所領に応じた軍役を課すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi shogunate formed Hokoshu (military guard of the shogunate) from branch families of Shugo Daimyo and hereditary vassals of Ashikaga clan and imposed service in Kyoto on them; on the other hand, Shugo Daimyo tightened control over zaichi-ryoshu (kokujin; local lord) in their provinces and imposed military services on them according to their shoryo.</e>
<cmt>話題が先の鎌倉時代から室町時代に移ったので、「幕府」を「室町幕府」と訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi shogunate formed Hokoshu (military guard of the shogunate) from branch families of Shugo Daimyo and hereditary vassals of Ashikaga clan and imposed service in Kyoto on them; on the other hand, Shugo Daimyo tightened control over zaichi-ryoshu (kokujin; local lord) in their provinces and imposed military services on them according to their shoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu formed the military guard of the shogunate from branch families of the territorial lords as provincial constable and hereditary vassals of Ashikaga clan and imposed service in Kyoto on them; on the other hand, the territorial lords as provincial constable tightened control over the local lords in their provinces and imposed military services on them according to their territories.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>戦術が単騎による個人戦から集団戦闘へと変遷するに従い、軍役は所領や収穫量を基準としたものになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the strategy changed from one-to-one duels by horsemen to party battle and army battle, the military service had been based on the area of shoryo and the crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the strategy changed from one-to-one duels by horsemen to party and army battle, the military service had been based on the area of shoryo and the crop yields.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the military strategy changed from the one-to-one duels by horsemen to the party and army battle, the military service had been based on the area and the crop yields of the territory.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>軍役は半農半士の土豪・地侍にも課せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military service was also imposed on local clans and jizamurai (local samurai) which live partly on farming and partly on samurai warrior stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military service was also imposed on local clans and jizamurai (local samurai) which lived partly on farming and partly on a samurai warrior stipend.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military service was also imposed on local clans and local samurai, both of which lived partly on farming and partly on a samurai warrior stipend.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>武田家菩提寺、恵林寺領の例を見ると家臣団の末端に位置して武芸を専らとする「同心衆」のほかに、年貢の一部負担を免除された「軍役衆」の存在が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the example of the estate of Erin-ji Temple, the Takeda family&apos;s ancestral temple, in addition to a &apos;doshin-shu&apos; band which was the smallest unit of the vessels organization and devoted themselves to military arts, there was &apos;gunyaku-shu&apos; band which was exempt from a part of their land taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the example of the estate of Erin-ji Temple, the Takeda family&apos;s ancestral temple, in addition to a &apos;doshin-shu&apos; band which was the smallest unit of the vessels organization and devoted themselves to military arts, there was &apos;gunyaku-shu&apos; band which was exempt from a part of their land taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the example of the estate of Erin-ji Temple, the Takeda family&apos;s ancestral temple, in addition to the smallest unit of the lowest position of vassals devoted themselves to military arts, there were a band of farmers exempt from a part of their land taxes.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>彼らはいわゆる惣百姓（一般名主）とは異なり、年貢や夫役の一部を免除されるかわりに、戦時においては武田家への軍役を担ったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike so-called Sobyakusho (member of soson village system) (common landholder), they contributed military services to Takeda family in a wartime in exchange for being exempt from a part of their land taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike so-called Sobyakusho (member of soson village system) (common landholder), they contributed military services to Takeda family in wartime in exchange for being exempt from a part of their land taxes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike common landholders, they contributed military services to the Takeda family in wartime in exchange for being exempt from part of their land taxes and labor services.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>似た制度は兵農未分離の時代にあって各戦国大名家にみられ、太閤検地の実施で兵農分離が進められるまで、各大名家の戦力の一部を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar systems were found in the age of warriors and peasants unseparated in the families of Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period (Warring States period), and they contributed the military forces to the families of Daimyo until taiko-kenchi (cadastral surveys instituted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) was enforced and the warriors and peasants were separated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar systems were found in the age of warriors and peasants unseparated from the families of Daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku period (Warring States period), and contributed to the military forces of Daimyo families until taiko-kenchi (cadastral surveys instituted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) was enforced and warriors and peasants were separated.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar systems were found in each of the domains of the territorial lords during the Warring States period, during the age when the warriors and the peasants were unseparated; the band of farmers contributed to the military forces of each of the territorial lords&apos; families until the cadastral surveys instituted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI was enforced and warriors and peasants were separated.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>大名家における家臣への軍役が貫高基準（貫高制）から近世に入って石高基準（石高制）へと移っていくのも特徴的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also characteristic that the military service imposed on the vessels in the families of Daimyo changed from the Kandaka standard (Kandaka system; money taxation system) to the Kokudaka standard (Kokudaka system; food taxation system) in the Early-Modern period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also characteristic that the military service imposed on the vessels in the families of Daimyo changed from the Kandaka standard (Kandaka system; money taxation system) to the Kokudaka standard (Kokudaka system; food taxation system) in the Early-Modern period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis for the military service imposed on the vessels in the terrritorial lords&apos;s families was changed from the money taxation system to the food taxation system in the Early-Modern period, which is another characteristic of gunyaku system.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>大名などの主君から給人へ課せられる軍役は「馬上○騎、弓○張、鉄砲○挺、鑓○本、旗○本」といった具合であったが、これに小荷駄隊や下人などの人夫もあわせた総人数が規定されることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military services imposed on kyunin by the lord such as Daimyo were listed like &apos;the number of Mounted Warrior:, the number of Bows:, the number of Muskets:, the number of Spears:, and the number of Banners: &apos;, to which manpower including the numbers of such laborers as konidatai (caravan of men and animals carrying supplies) and low ranked people was sometimes additionally defined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military services imposed on kyunin by lords such as Daimyo were listed like &apos;the number of Mounted Warrior:, the number of Bows:, the number of Muskets:, the number of Spears:, and the number of Banners: &apos;, to which manpower including the numbers of such laborers as konidatai (caravan of men and animals carrying supplies) and low ranked people was sometimes additionally defined.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military services imposed on the middle and lower ranking samurai who offered military services to the lord by lords such as the territorial lords were defined by &apos;the number of Mounted Warriors, the number of Bows, the number of Muskets, the number of Spears, and the number of Banners,&apos; to which manpower including the numbers of such laborers as caravan of men and animals carrying supplies and low ranked people was sometimes additionally defined.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>安土桃山時代、豊臣氏の規定した軍役「1万石に付き250人」といったようなものはこういった内容であっただろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, the military service defined by the Toyotomi clan such as &apos;two hundred fifty men per one million koku&apos; may have been made up like that shown above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, the military service defined by the Toyotomi clan such as &apos;two hundred fifty men per one million koku&apos; may have been made up like that shown above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Azuchi-Momoyama period, the military service defined by the Toyotomi clan such as &apos;250 men per 1,000,000 koku&apos; may have been made up like that shown above.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>江戸初期の軍役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military Service in the Early Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military Service in the Early Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military service in the early Edo period</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>鎌倉時代、室町時代は時に応じて課せられ、一定の基準はなかったが、江戸幕府においてはこれを一定させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military service was not based on a certain standard and imposed for each occasion in the Kamakura period and the Muromachi period; and the Edo shogunate standardized that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military service was not based on a certain standard and imposed for each occasion in the Kamakura period and the Muromachi period; and the Edo shogunate standardized that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military service was not based on a certain standard and imposed for each occasion during the Kamakura and the Muromachi periods; and the Edo shogunate standardized that.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1615年（元和 (日本)元年）、大坂の陣にあたり、徳川秀忠は軍令を発して諸軍の部署を定めるとともに軍役を定めてこれを課した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1615, upon fighting Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Battle of Osaka), Hidetada TOKUGAWA issued the military order to appoint armies to their posts and to define the military service and imposed them on the army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1615, upon fighting Osaka Natsu no Jin (Summer Battle of Osaka), Hidetada TOKUGAWA issued the military order to appoint armies to their posts and to define the military service and imposed them on the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1615, upon fighting the Summer Battle of Osaka, Hidetada TOKUGAWA issued the military order to appoint armies to their posts and to define the military service and imposed them on the army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>そのときの制はつぎのとおり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Order was as below:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Order was as below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system at that time is shown below.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>500石 - 鉄砲1丁、鑓3本持鑓共</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">500 koku - one Musket, and three Spears with held spears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">500 koku - one Musket, and three Spears with held spears</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">500 koku - one Musket, three Spears including spear owned by Mounted Warrior</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>1000石 - 鉄砲2丁、弓1張、鑓5本持鑓共、馬上1騎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1000 koku - two Muskets, one Bow, five Spears with held spears, and one Mounted Warrior</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1000 koku - two Muskets, one Bow, five Spears with held spears, and one Mounted Warrior</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1000 koku - two Muskets, one Bow, five Spears including spears owned by Mounted Warriors, one Mounted Warrior</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>2000石 - 鉄砲3丁、弓2張、鑓10本持鑓共、馬上3騎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2000 koku - three Muskets, two Bows, ten Spears with held spears, and three Mounted Warriors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2000 koku - three Muskets, two Bows, ten Spears with held spears, and three Mounted Warriors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2000 koku - three Muskets, two Bows, ten Spears including spears owned by mounted warriors, three mounted Warriors</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>3000石 - 鉄砲5丁、弓3張、鑓15本持鑓共、馬上4騎（旗1本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3000 koku - five Muskets, three Bows, fifteen Spears with held spears, and four Mounted Warriors (one Banner)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3000 koku - five Muskets, three Bows, fifteen Spears with held spears, and four Mounted Warriors (one Banner)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3000 koku - five Muskets, three Bows, fifteen Spears including spears owned by Mounted Warriors, four Mounted Warriors (one Banner)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>4000石 - 鉄砲6丁、弓4張、鑓20本持鑓共、馬上6騎（旗2本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4000 koku - six Muskets, four Bows, twenty Spears with held spears, and six Mounted Warriors (two Banners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4000 koku - six Muskets, four Bows, twenty Spears with held spears, and six Mounted Warriors (two Banners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4000 koku - six Muskets, four Bows, twenty Spears including spears owned by mounted warriors, six Mounted Warriors (two Banners)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>5000石 - 鉄砲10丁、弓5張、鑓25本持鑓共、馬上7騎（旗2本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5000 koku - ten Muskets, five Bows, twenty-five Spears with held spears, and seven Mounted Warriors (two Banners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5000 koku - ten Muskets, five Bows, twenty-five Spears with held spears, and seven Mounted Warriors (two Banners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5000 koku - ten Muskets, five Bows, twenty-five Spears including spears owned by mounted warriors, seven Mounted Warriors (two Banners)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>10000石 - 鉄砲20丁、弓10張、鑓50本持鑓共、馬上14騎（旗□本）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10000 koku - twenty Muskets, ten Bows, fifty Spears with held spears, and fourteen Mounted Warriors (Banners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">10000 koku - twenty Muskets, ten Bows, fifty Spears with held spears, and fourteen Mounted Warriors (Banners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">10000 koku - twenty Muskets, ten Bows, fifty Spears including spears owned by mounted warriors, fourteen Mounted Warriors (Banners)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="34">
<j>1616年（元和2年）6月改正後の制はつぎのとおり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Order after the Revision in June 1616 was as below:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Order after the Revision in June 1616 was as below:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system after the Revision in June 1616 is as below.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>500石 - 鉄砲1、鑓3但持鑓共</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">500 koku - one Muskets, and three Spears with the proviso with held spears</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">500 koku - one Muskets, and three Spears with the proviso for held spears</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">500 koku - one Muskets, and three Spears including spear owned by horse soldier</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="36">
<j>1000石 - 鉄砲2、鑓5但持鑓共、弓1、騎馬1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1000 koku - two Muskets, five Spears with the proviso with held spears, one Bow, and one Horse-Rider</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1000 koku - two Muskets, five Spears with the proviso for held spears, one Bow, and one Horse-Rider</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1000 koku - two Muskets, five Spears including spears owned by horse soldiers, one Bow, one Horse Soldier</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="37">
<j>2000石 - 鉄砲3、鑓5（15?）但持鑓共、弓2、騎馬3</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">2000 koku - three Muskets, five (or fifteen?) Spears with the proviso with held spears, two Bows, and three Horse-Riders</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2000 koku - three Muskets, five (or fifteen?) Spears with the proviso for held spears, two Bows, and three Horse-Riders</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2000 koku - three Muskets, five (or fifteen?) Spears including spears owned by horse soldies, two Bows, three Horse Soldiers</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="38">
<j>3000石 - 鉄砲5、鑓15但持鑓共、弓3、騎馬4、旗1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">3000 koku - five Muskets, fifteen Spears with the proviso with held spears, three Bows, four Horse-Riders, and one Banner</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3000 koku - five Muskets, fifteen Spears with the proviso for held spears, three Bows, four Horse-Riders, and one Banner</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3000 koku - five Muskets, fifteen Spears including spears owned by horse soldies, three Bows, four Horse Soldiers, one Banner</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="39">
<j>4000石 - 鉄砲6、鑓20但持鑓共、弓4、騎馬6、旗1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4000 koku - six Muskets, twenty Spears with the proviso with held spears, four Bows, six Horse-Riders, and one Banner</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4000 koku - six Muskets, twenty Spears with the proviso for held spears, four Bows, six Horse-Riders, and one Banner</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4000 koku - six Muskets, twenty Spears including spears owned by horse soldies, four Bows, six Horse Soldiers, one Banner</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="40">
<j>5000石 - 鉄砲10、鑓25但持鑓共、弓10、騎馬14、旗3</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">5000 koku - ten Muskets, twenty-five Spears with the proviso with held spears, ten Bows, fourteen Horse-Riders, and three Banners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">5000 koku - ten Muskets, twenty-five Spears with the proviso for held spears, ten Bows, fourteen Horse-Riders, and three Banners</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">5000 koku - ten Muskets, twenty-five Spears including spears owned by horse soldies, ten Bows, fourteen Horse Soldiers, three Banners</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="41">
<j>10000石 - 鉄砲20、鑓50但持鑓共、弓10、騎馬14、旗3</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10000 koku - twenty Muskets, fifty Spears with the proviso with held spears, ten Bows, fourteen Horse-Riders, and three Banners</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">10000 koku - twenty Muskets, fifty Spears with the proviso for held spears, ten Bows, fourteen Horse-Riders, and three Banners</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">10000 koku - twenty Muskets, fifty Spears including spears owned by horse soldies, ten Bows, fourteen Horse Soldiers, three Banners</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), Balmung0731(id:99201), NOBU(id:42645), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>