<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>第1次伊藤内閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Ito Cabinet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Ito Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Ito Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>第1次伊藤内閣（だい1じ いとう ないかく）は、参議の伊藤博文が初代内閣総理大臣に任命され、12月22日から4月30日まで続いた内閣 (日本)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Ito Cabinet was a Cabinet lasting December 22 to April 30 as Hirobumi ITO,Sangi (councilor),was assigned as the first prime minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Ito Cabinet was launched when Sangi (councilor), Hirobumi ITO was assigned as the first prime minister and lasted from December 22 to April 30.</e>
<cmt>一部書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Ito Cabinet was launched when Sangi (councilor), Hirobumi ITO was assigned as the first prime minister and lasted from December 22 to April 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>在任期間は、861日間。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His administration was 861days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His administration lasted for 861 days.</e>
<cmt>そのままでも良いようにも思えましたが、「続いた」と考えてlastedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His administration lasted for 861 days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>太政官達第69号により太政官制を廃止し、代わりに創設された内閣制に基づいて成立した日本最初の内閣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the first Japanese Cabinet based on the cabinet system founded after abolishing the System of Departments of State by Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) number 69.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the first Japanese Cabinet based on the cabinet system founded after abolishing the System of Departments of State by Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) number 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the first Japanese Cabinet based on the cabinet system founded after abolishing the System of Departments of State by Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) number 69.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>内閣制の発足と同時にその運営について規定した内閣職権が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cabinet authority which prescribed its administration was established at the same time the Cabinet system was launched.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cabinet authority which prescribed its administration was established at the same time the Cabinet system was launched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cabinet authority which prescribed its administration was established at the same time the Cabinet system was launched.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>来るべき、立憲君主制に備えた国家機構の確立を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its aim was to establish the national mechanism which prepared for forthcoming constitutional monarchy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its aim was to establish the national mechanism which prepared for forthcoming constitutional monarchy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its aim was to establish the national mechanism which prepared for forthcoming constitutional monarchy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>いわゆる藩閥出身者が殆どを占め、長州藩・薩摩藩出身者が各4名ずつ入閣させる（ただし、薩摩閥の中核と見られていた黒田清隆は当初入閣せず）などのバランス重視型の布陣となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its was formed emphasizing balance,consisted of mostly people from domain clique and taken 4 people from Choshu Domain and Satsuma Domain respectively (however,Kiyotaka KURODA,who was thought to be the center of Satsuma clique didn&apos;t get into the Cabinet at the time).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was organized focusing on balanced assignment; it consisted of people mostly from domain clique and 4 people from Choshu Domain and Satsuma Domain respectively were taken into the cabinet (however, Kiyotaka KURODA, who was thought to be the center of Satsuma clique didn&apos;t get into the Cabinet at the time).</e>
<cmt>一部書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Organized with an emphasis on balanced assignment, the cabinet consisted mainly of people from domain cliques, with 4 people from the Choshu Domain and four from the Satsuma Domain being inducted into the cabinet (however, Kiyotaka KURODA, who was thought to be the central figure of the Satsuma clique, did not get a place in the Cabinet at that time).</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>大日本帝国陸軍のドイツ式組織への改革や帝国大学令・小学校令などの制定に代表される教育改革、市町村制の確立などが行われ、伊藤自身も井上毅・金子堅太郎・伊東巳代治と大日本帝国憲法草案を作成するなど、立憲体制への準備が着々と進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The preparation for constitutional system progressed steadily as the reform of Imperial Japanese Army into German-style system,education reform such as Imperial University Law and Primary School Order and establishment of local authority system were carried out,and Ito himself made the draft of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan along with Kowashi INOUE,Kentaro KANEKO,and Miyoji ITO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The preparation for constitutional system progressed steadily as the reform of Imperial Japanese Army toward German-style system, education reform such as Imperial University Law and Primary School Order and establishment of local authority system were carried out, and Ito himself made the draft of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan along with Kowashi INOUE, Kentaro KANEKO, and Miyoji ITO.</e>
<cmt>「～への改革」をreform towardとし、語と語の間に半角スペースがない箇所は入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The preparation for constitutional system progressed steadily as the reform of Imperial Japanese Army toward German-style system, education reform such as Imperial University Law and Primary School Order and establishment of local authority system were carried out, and Ito himself made the draft of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan along with Kowashi INOUE, Kentaro KANEKO, and Miyoji ITO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>だが、伊藤の盟友である井上馨外務大臣 (日本)が進めた条約改正案にあった「外国人裁判官」制度と鹿鳴館に代表される欧化政策が内外の反感を買い、自由民権運動による三大事件建白書や大同団結運動、保守中正派（天皇親政派）と見られた谷干城農商務大臣の辞任を招くなど、政府批判が一気に高まった（「明治20年の危機」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However,the policy of Europeanization such as &apos;a foreigner judge&apos;system which was included in the treaty revision plan progressed by Ito&apos;s sworn ally Kaoru INOUE,Minister of Foreign Affairs (Japan),and Rokumeikan antagonized within and without,and criticism of the government was set up rapidly due to the petition of three major affairs by democratic-rights movement, the movement to unite for a common purpose and the resignation of Tateki TANI,Minister of Agriculture and Commerce,who was thought to be a member of conservative political party (direct rule by the emperor party) ([The crisis of the 20th year of the Meiji era]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the policy of Europeanization represented by Rokumeikan and &apos;a foreigner judge&apos; system, which was included in the amendment of the treaty promoted by Ito&apos;s sworn ally Kaoru INOUE, Minister of Foreign Affairs (Japan), antagonized inside and outside Japan, and criticism of the government was mounted rapidly due to the petition of three major affairs by democratic-rights movement, the movement to unite for a common purpose and the resignation of Tateki TANI, Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, who was thought to be a member of conservative political party (direct rule by the emperor party) ([The crisis of the 20th year of the Meiji era]).</e>
<cmt>「鹿鳴館に代表される」のくだりが訳抜けだったので加えました。「条約改正」をamendmentに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the policy of Europeanization represented by Rokumeikan and &apos;a foreigner judge&apos; system, which was included in the amendment of the treaty promoted by Ito&apos;s sworn ally Kaoru INOUE, Minister of Foreign Affairs (Japan), antagonized inside and outside Japan, and criticism of the government was mounted rapidly due to the petition of three major affairs by democratic-rights movement, the movement to unite for a common purpose and the resignation of Tateki TANI, Minister of Agriculture and Commerce, who was thought to be a member of conservative political party (direct rule by the emperor party) ([The crisis of the 20th year of the Meiji era]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そこで伊藤はやむなく井上を辞任させて、政敵と言える大隈重信と黒田清隆をそれぞれ外務大臣・農商務大臣として入閣させ、保安条例を制定して自由民権派の弾圧に乗り出したが、憲法・旧皇室典範の制定事業に専念するために、総理大臣を辞して新設の枢密院議長に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Which forced Ito to make Inoue resign and took Shigenobu OKUMA and Kiyotaka KURODA who were political enemies into cabinet as a Minister of Foreign Affair and a Minister of Agriculture and Commerce respectively,starting to suppress the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement Party,however,he resigned from prime minister,assuming as Chairman of the Privy Council to concentrate on the establishment of constitution and Former Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So Ito was obliged to have Inoue step down and took his political enemies Shigenobu OKUMA and Kiyotaka KURODA into cabinet as a Minister of Foreign Affair and a Minister of Agriculture and Commerce respectively, and set out to suppress the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement Party, however, he resigned from prime minister to assume as Chairman of the Privy Council with the view to concentrating on the establishment of constitution and Former Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt>「そこで伊藤は」Whichがどういう意味なのか不明だったのでSo It was obliged toと変えました。「乗り出す」をset out toにしました。又、後半にtoが多くなってしまったので「～するために」をwith the view to -ingにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So Ito was obliged to have Inoue step down and took his political enemies Shigenobu OKUMA and Kiyotaka KURODA into cabinet as a Minister of Foreign Affair and a Minister of Agriculture and Commerce respectively, and set out to suppress the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement Party, however, he resigned from prime minister to assume as Chairman of the Privy Council with the view to concentrating on the establishment of constitution and Former Imperial House Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>国務大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minister of State</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minister of State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minister of State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他の人事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The other personnel affairs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other personnel affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other personnel affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Monaneko(id:28864), PANYNJ(id:38638), MIsogi(id:20599), 水野白楓(id:22811), 鹿両性証明(id:71252), 松茸(id:27535), Complex01(id:10454), Tom-spring(id:42457), Dumpty-Humpty(id:222368), 唐棣色(id:64681), Robert De Smith(id:28533), STB-1(id:8775), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>