<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紙背文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihai monjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihai monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihai monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紙背文書（しはいもんじょ）とは、和紙の使用済みの面を反故（ほご）として、その裏面を利用して別の文書（古文書）が書かれた場合に、先に書かれた面の文書のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihai monjo refers to monjo (a document) written on one side of washi (Japanese paper) before another monjo (an ancient document) was written on the other side of the used paper, which was regarded as a scrap paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihai monjo refers to the monjo (ancient document) written on washi (Japanese paper) before another monjo was then written on the other side of that same piece of paper.</e>
<cmt>全文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihai monjo refers to the monjo (ancient document) written on washi (Japanese paper) before another monjo was then written on the other side of that same piece of paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後で書かれた文書が主体となるので、先に書かれた文書が紙背（裏）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because monjo written later was considered the main document, monjo written first became the document written on the back side of the paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the monjo written later was considered the main one, the one written first was regarded as being written on the back side of the paper.</e>
<cmt>全文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the monjo written later was considered the main one, the one written first was regarded as being written on the back side of the paper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>裏文書（うらもんじょ）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shihai monjo is also called ura monjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shihai monjo is also called ura monjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shihai monjo is also called ura monjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>古くは和紙が貴重品であったために、使用済みの面を反故として、白紙の状態である裏面を利用して別の筆記を行っており、漉返紙と並んで和紙の再利用法として活用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since washi was a valuable item in ancient times, the used side of the paper was made into a scrap paper and the back side of the used paper, which was blank, was reused for other writings; this method for recycling washi was used for shihai monjo, as well as sukigaeshi gami (paper made from dissolved old paper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since washi (Japanese paper) was valuable in ancient times, once paper was used, the back side of the paper, which was blank, was reused for other writing; this method for recycling Japanese paper was utilized along with sukigaeshi gami (paper made by redissolving used paper).</e>
<cmt>全文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since washi (Japanese paper) was valuable in ancient times, once paper was used, the back side of the paper, which was blank, was reused for other writing; this method for recycling Japanese paper was utilized along with sukigaeshi gami (paper made by redissolving used paper).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、奈良時代から具注暦の余白部分に日記を書く習慣が生まれたが、書ききれなかった部分を紙背に追記して記述した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, writing a diary on the blank space of guchureki (annotated calendar) had been practiced since the Nara period and when more space was needed, the extra lines were added on the back side of the calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, writing a diary on the blank space of guchureki (annotated calendar) had been practiced since the Nara period and when more space was needed, extra lines were added on the back side of the calendar.</e>
<cmt>extra lines の前の the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, writing a diary on the blank space of guchureki (annotated calendar) had been practiced since the Nara period and when more space was needed, extra lines were added on the back side of the calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>他に、後日、補筆・清書作業を行うことを考慮し、そのための参考内容を調達の容易な紙背を利用して執筆した文書などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides these, there are monjo composed of the references written on the back side of the paper which was easy to procure, to be used later for adding extra lines or making a fair copy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides these, there are monjo composed of casual references written on the back side of used paper (which was relatively easy to procure), to be turned later into a fuller version with new parts or from which a fair copy could be made.</e>
<cmt>数か所修正および明確化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides these, there are monjo composed of casual references written on the back side of used paper (which was relatively easy to procure), to be turned later into a fuller version with new parts or from which a fair copy could be made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>万葉仮名、仮名消息など、かなの発達史上、重要な紙背文書が多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many important shihai monjo in the history of development of kana (syllabic Japanese scripts) related to manyo-gana (an ancient form of Japanese kana using Chinese characters to represent Japanese sounds) and kanashosoku (a letter written in kana).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many important shihai monjo in the history of the development of kana (syllabic Japanese scripts) related to manyo-gana (an ancient form of Japanese kana using Chinese characters to represent Japanese sounds) and kanashosoku (a letter written in kana).</e>
<cmt>development の前に the を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many important shihai monjo in the history of the development of kana (syllabic Japanese scripts) related to manyo-gana (an ancient form of Japanese kana using Chinese characters to represent Japanese sounds) and kanashosoku (a letter written in kana).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>主な紙背文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Main shihai monjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Main shihai monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Main shihai monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>正倉院文書</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin monjo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin monjo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>正倉院の中倉に納められている文書を正倉院文書という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monjo kept in the middle section of the Shosoin (the treasure house) are called shosoin monjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents kept in the middle section of the Shosoin (the Treasure House) are called shosoin monjo.</e>
<cmt>Monjo を Documents に、the treasure house を the Treasure House に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents kept in the middle section of the Shosoin (the Treasure House) are called shosoin monjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>戸籍などの律令制の公文書が反故として東大寺に渡り、その紙背を東大寺は記録紙などに利用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After koseki (Japanese family registry) and other official documents under the ritsuryo system (the historical law system based on the philosophies of Confucianism and Chinese Legalism in Japan) ended up at the Todai-ji Temple as scrap papers, the back side of those papers was used as a recording paper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After koseki (Japanese family registry) and other official documents under the ritsuryo system (the historical law system based on the philosophies of Confucianism and Chinese Legalism in Japan) ended up at Todai-ji Temple as scrap paper, the back side of that paper was used for creating records.</e>
<cmt>Todai-ji Temple の前の the を削除しました。papers を paper に修正しました。（paper は不加算名詞です。）those papers was used as a recording paper を that paper was used for creating records に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After koseki (Japanese family registry) and other official documents under the ritsuryo system (the historical law system based on the philosophies of Confucianism and Chinese Legalism in Japan) ended up at Todai-ji Temple as scrap paper, the back side of that paper was used for creating records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>『装潢手実』、『正倉院万葉仮名文書』など数多くの紙背文書がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many types of shihai monjo including &quot;Sokoshujitsu (voucher issued by a bookbinder)&quot; and &quot;Shosoin manyo-gana monjo (two sets of monjo exclusively written in manyo-gana stored in the Shosoin Treasure House).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many types of shihai monjo including &quot;Sokoshujitsu&quot; (voucher issued by a bookbinder) and &quot;Shosoin Manyo-gana Monjo&quot; (two sets of monjo exclusively written in manyo-gana stored in the Shosoin Treasure House).</e>
<cmt>括弧をクォーテーションマークの外に出しました。タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many types of shihai monjo including &quot;Sokoshujitsu&quot; (voucher issued by a bookbinder) and &quot;Shosoin Manyo-gana Monjo&quot; (two sets of monjo exclusively written in manyo-gana stored in the Shosoin Treasure House).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>装潢手実</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sokoshujitsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sokoshujitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sokoshujitsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>正倉院万葉仮名文書（「和可夜之奈比乃（わがやしなひの）…」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin manyo-gana monjo (&apos;和可夜之奈比乃 [waga yashinahino]...&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin Manyo-gana Monjo (&apos;和可夜之奈比乃 [waga yashinahino]...&apos;)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin Manyo-gana Monjo (&apos;和可夜之奈比乃 [waga yashinahino]...&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>正倉院万葉仮名文書（「布多止己呂乃（ふたところの）…」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shosoin manyo-gana monjo (&apos;布多止己呂乃 [futa tokorono]...&apos;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shosoin Manyo-gana Monjo (&apos;布多止己呂乃 [futa tokorono]...&apos;)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shosoin Manyo-gana Monjo (&apos;布多止己呂乃 [futa tokorono]...&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>因幡国司解案紙背仮名消息</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inaba no kokushi no gean shihai kana shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a draft letter written by kokushi (official) in Inaba Province</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inaba no Kokushi no Gean Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a draft letter written by a kokushi [official] in Inaba Province)</e>
<cmt>括弧を書き換えました。タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。Kokushi の前に a を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inaba no Kokushi no Gean Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a draft letter written by a kokushi [official] in Inaba Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>虚空蔵菩薩念誦次第紙背仮名消息</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokuzo Bosatsu nenju shidai shihai kana shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the procedures for reciting a prayer to Kokuzo Bosatsu [Akasagarbha Bodhisattva])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokuzo Bosatsu Nenju Shidai Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the procedures for reciting a prayer to Kokuzo Bosatsu [Akasagarbha Bodhisattva])</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokuzo Bosatsu Nenju Shidai Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the procedures for reciting a prayer to Kokuzo Bosatsu [Akasagarbha Bodhisattva])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>稿本北山抄紙背仮名消息</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kohon hokuzan sho shihai kana shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the manual on courtly etiquette, volume 10)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kohon Hokuzan Sho Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a manual on courtly etiquette, volume 10)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。 a manual に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kohon Hokuzan Sho Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a manual on courtly etiquette, volume 10)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>九条家本延喜式紙背仮名消息</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujo iemoto engishiki shihai kana shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of paper used for the manuscripts of engishiki [laws and regulations] kept in the Kujo family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujo Iemoto Engishiki Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of paper used for manuscripts of engishiki [laws and regulations] kept in the Kujo family)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。manuscripts の前の the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujo Iemoto Engishiki Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of paper used for manuscripts of engishiki [laws and regulations] kept in the Kujo family)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>三宝感応要録紙背仮名消息</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanbo kanno yoroku shihai kana shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the response records on Sanbo [three treasures of Buddhism: Buddha, sutras and priesthood])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanbo Kanno Yoroku Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the response records on Sanbo [three treasures of Buddhism: Buddha, sutras and priesthood])</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanbo Kanno Yoroku Shihai Kana Shosoku (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the response records on Sanbo [three treasures of Buddhism: Buddha, sutras and priesthood])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>諷誦文紙背仮名手紙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fujumon shihai kana tegami (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for the recital to be chanted by the priest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fujumon Shihai Kana Tegami (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a recital to be chanted by a priest)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。the recital を a recital に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fujumon Shihai Kana Tegami (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for a recital to be chanted by a priest)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>五部大乗経紙背仮名手紙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gobudaijokyo shihai kana tegami (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for five volume of Mahayana sutra)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gobudaijokyo Shihai Kana Tegami (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for five volumes of Mahayana sutras)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。 volumes および sutras に修正しました。Mahayana の前の a を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gobudaijokyo Shihai Kana Tegami (letter written in kana with the back side of the paper used for five volumes of Mahayana sutras)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>宝積経要品紙背短冊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoshaku kyoyohon shihai tanzaku (Combined form of long and narrow cards with the back side of the paper used for poetry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoshaku Kyoyohon Shihai Tanzaku (Japanese poetry written in a combined form of long and narrow cards with the back side of the paper used for a copy of the Daihoshaku-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt>タイトル内の各単語の頭文字を大文字に修正しました。括弧内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoshaku Kyoyohon Shihai Tanzaku (Japanese poetry written in a combined form of long and narrow cards with the back side of the paper used for a copy of the Daihoshaku-kyo Sutra)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>手紙</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letters</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letters</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>千葉氏が用いた行政文書を、千葉氏の家臣富木常忍が日蓮に譲り、日蓮が弟子檀那への手紙などに使った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyosei monjo (an administrative written material) used by the Chiba clan was given to Nichiren by Tsunenobu TOKI, a vassal of the Chiba clan, and Nichiren used this paper to write a letter to his disciples and patrons of the temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren used the back side of Gyosei monjo (administrative written materials) which were used by the Chiba clan and given to Nichiren by Tsunenobu TOKI, a vassal of the Chiba clan, to write letters to his disciples and patrons of the temple.</e>
<cmt>全文を書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren used the back side of Gyosei monjo (administrative written materials) which were used by the Chiba clan and given to Nichiren by Tsunenobu TOKI, a vassal of the Chiba clan, to write letters to his disciples and patrons of the temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>中山法華経寺などに所蔵されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those letters are kept in the Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple and other places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those letters are kept in Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple and other places.</e>
<cmt>the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those letters are kept in Nakayama Hokekyo-ji Temple and other places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>日記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diaries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diaries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diaries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>平安時代から江戸時代にかけて書かれた公家や僧侶の日記。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diaries written by the kuge (court nobles) and the Buddhist monks from the Heian to Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diaries written by court nobles and Buddhist monks from the Heian to Edo period.</e>
<cmt>the kuge および Buddhist monks の the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diaries written by court nobles and Buddhist monks from the Heian to Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>平信範の『兵範記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heihanki (diary of TAIRA no Nobunori)&quot; by TAIRA no Nobunori</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heihanki&quot; (Diary of TAIRA no Nobunori) by TAIRA no Nobunori</e>
<cmt>括弧をクォーテーションマークの外に出し、diary の語頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Heihanki&quot; (Diary of TAIRA no Nobunori) by TAIRA no Nobunori</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>藤原定家の『明月記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Meigetsuki (chronicle of the bright moon)&quot; by FUJIWARA no Teika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) by FUJIWARA no Teika</e>
<cmt>括弧をクォーテーションマークの外に出し、各語頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Meigetsuki&quot; (Chronicle of the Bright Moon) by FUJIWARA no Teika</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>万里小路時房の『建内記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kennaiki (diary of Tokifusa MADENOKOJI)&quot; by Tokifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kennaiki&quot; (Diary of Tokifusa MADENOKOJI) by Tokifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>括弧をクォーテーションマークの外に出し、diary の語頭を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kennaiki&quot; (Diary of Tokifusa MADENOKOJI) by Tokifusa MADENOKOJI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="20">
<j>尋尊の『大乗院寺社雜事記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Daijo-in jisha zojiki (notes of the Daijo-in on various matters of the shrine-temple multiplex)&quot; by Jinson</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Daijo-in Jisha Zojiki&quot; (Notes of Daijo-in on Various Matters of the Shrine-temple Multiplex) by Jinson</e>
<cmt>括弧をクォーテーションマークの外に出し、各語頭を大文字にしました。Daijo-in の the を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Daijo-in Jisha Zojiki&quot; (Notes of Daijo-in on Various Matters of the Shrine-temple Multiplex) by Jinson</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>三条西実隆の『実隆公記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Sanetaka koki (journal of Sanetaka SANJONISHI) by Sanetaka SANJONISHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Sanetaka Koki&quot; (Journal of Sanetaka SANJONISHI) by Sanetaka SANJONISHI</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークをとじ、括弧内の語頭を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Sanetaka Koki&quot; (Journal of Sanetaka SANJONISHI) by Sanetaka SANJONISHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>山科言継の『言継卿記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tokitsugu kyoki (dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) by Tokitsugu YAMASHINA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tokitsugu-kyo ki&quot; (Diary of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) by Tokitsugu YAMASHINA</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークをとじ、括弧内の語頭を大文字に修正しました。Tokitsugu kyoki を Tokitsugu-kyo ki に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Tokitsugu-kyo ki&quot; (Diary of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) by Tokitsugu YAMASHINA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>義演の『義演准后日記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gien jugo nikki (diary of Gien, who was given the title Jugo [an honorary rank next to Emperor, Empress Dowager, and Empress]) by Gien</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gien Jugo Nikki&quot; (Diary of Gien, who was given the title Jugo [an honorary rank next to Emperor, Empress Dowager, and Empress]) by Gien</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークをとじ、diary の語頭を大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gien Jugo Nikki&quot; (Diary of Gien, who was given the title Jugo [an honorary rank next to Emperor, Empress Dowager, and Empress]) by Gien</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 岡部碩道(id:182846), 巴屋(id:128785), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>