<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>紫衣事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shie Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shie Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shie Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>紫衣事件（しえじけん）とは、江戸時代初期における、江戸幕府の朝廷に対する圧迫と統制を示す朝幕間の対立事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shie Incident occurred in the early Edo Period and was a conflict between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court that shows the oppression and control of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) towards the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shie Incident occurred in the early Edo Period and was a conflict between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court that shows the oppression and control exercised by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。（動詞を変更）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shie Incident occurred in the early Edo period and was a conflict between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court that shows the oppression and control exercised by the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) on the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸時代初期における朝幕関係上、最大の不和確執とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered the most serious discord or feud between the the Shogunate and the Imperial Court in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered the most serious discord or feud between the the Shogunate and the Imperial Court in the early Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered the most serious discord or feud between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court in the early Edo period.</e>
<cmt>余分なthe削除。period小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後水尾天皇はこの事件をきっかけに退位を決意したとも考えられており、朝幕関係に深刻な打撃を与える大きな対立であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this incident was the trigger that led to Emperor Gomizunoo deciding to abdicate, and was a serious blow towards the relationship between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this incident was the trigger that led to Emperor Gomizunoo deciding to abdicate, and was a serious blow to the relationship between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。（前置詞を変更）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this incident was the trigger that led to Emperor Gomizunoo deciding to abdicate, and was a serious blow to the relationship between the Shogunate and the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>紫衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shie (Purple Robe)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shie (Purple Robe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shie (Purple Robe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>紫衣とは、紫色の法衣や袈裟（けさ）をいい、古くから宗派を問わず高徳の僧・尼が朝廷から賜った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shie indicates the clerical garment or surplice robe worn by Buddhist priests that were worn by monks and nuns of high virtue regardless of their religious branch and had been traditionally presented by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shie indicates the clerical garment or surplice robe worn by Buddhist priests that were worn by monks and nuns of high virtue regardless of their religious branch and had been traditionally presented by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shie indicates the clerical garment or surplice robe worn by Buddhist priests that were worn by monks and nuns of high virtue regardless of their religious branch and had been traditionally presented by the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>僧・尼の尊さを表す物であると同時に、朝廷にとっては収入源の一つでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Not only could it indicate the high virtue of the monk or nun, but also an income source for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Not only did it indicate the high virtue of the monk or nun, but also an income source for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。（動詞を変更）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Not only did it indicate the high virtue of the monk or nun, but also an income source for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>事件に至る事情</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background that led to the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background of the incident</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1613年、幕府は、寺院・僧侶の圧迫および朝廷と宗教界の関係相対化を図って、「勅許紫衣竝に山城大徳寺妙心寺等諸寺入院の法度」（「勅許紫衣法度」「大徳寺妙心寺等諸寺入院法度」）を定め、さらにその2年後には禁中並公家諸法度を定めて、朝廷がみだりに紫衣や上人号を授けることを禁じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1613, the bakufu aimed to oppress the temples and monks and balance the relationship between the Imperial Court and the religious groups and decreed &quot;Chokkyo(imperial sanction) Shie tome and Yamashiro Daitoku-ji Temple Myoshin-ji Temple to Shoji Nyuin Hatto&quot;(&quot;Chokkyo Shie Hatto&quot; &quot;Daitoku-ji Temple Myoshin-ji Temple to Shoji Nyuin Hatto&quot;) and established the Kinchu Narabani Kuge Shohatto(Various Regulations for the Imperial Court and Court Nobles) 2 years later and prohibited the Imperial Court from easily presenting Shie and Shonin names.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1613, the bakufu aimed to oppress the temples and monks and balance the relationship between the Imperial Court and the religious groups, decreed &quot;Chokkyo (imperial sanction) Shie tome and Yamashiro Daitoku-ji Temple Myoshin-ji Temple to Shoji Nyuin Hatto&quot; (&quot;Chokkyo Shie Hatto&quot; and &quot;Daitoku-ji Temple Myoshin-ji Temple to Shoji Nyuin Hatto&quot;) and established the Kinchu Narabani Kuge Shohatto (Various Regulations for the Imperial Court and Court Nobles) 2 years later and prohibited the Imperial Court from easily presenting Shie and Shonin names.</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエイションを変更しました。全角文字を半角にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1613, the bakufu aimed to oppress the temples and monks and balance the relationship between the Imperial Court and the religious groups, decreed &apos;Chokkyo (imperial sanction) Shie tome and Yamashiro Daitoku-ji Temple Myoshin-ji Temple to Shoji Nyuin Hatto&apos; (&apos;Chokkyo Shie Hatto&apos; and &apos;Daitoku-ji Temple Myoshin-ji Temple to Shoji Nyuin Hatto&apos;) and established the Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (Various Regulations for the Imperial Court and Court Nobles) 2 years later and prohibited the Imperial Court from easily presenting Shie and Shonin names.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Narabiniスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>一　紫衣の寺住持職、先規希有の事也。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In previous times, monks in purple robes were rare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In previous times, monks in purple robes were rare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In previous times, monks in purple robes were rare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>近年猥りに勅許の事、且つは臈次を乱し、且つは官寺を汚し、甚だ然るべからず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In recent times, imperial sanctions have been issued without reason, disrupting roji and defiling state-sponsored temples, and this is very unsuitable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent times, imperial sanctions have been issued without reason, disrupting roji and defiling state-sponsored temples, and this is very unsuitable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent times, imperial sanctions have been issued without reason, disrupting roji and defiling state-sponsored temples, and this is very unsuitable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>向後に於ては、其の器用を撰び、戒臈相積み智者の聞へ有らば、入院の儀申し沙汰有るべき事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From now on, monks should be selected for their virtue and have enough experience and knowledge before asking for the Nyuin ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From now on, monks should be selected for their virtue and have enough experience and knowledge before asking for the Nyuin ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From now on, monks should be selected for their virtue and have enough experience and knowledge before asking for the Nyuin ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>（禁中並公家諸法度・第16条）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Kinchu Narabani Kuge Shohatto, Article 16)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Kinchu Narabani Kuge Shohatto, Article 16)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Kinchu Narabani Kuge Shohatto, Article 16)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>事件の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary of the Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of the Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of the Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このように、幕府が紫衣の授与を規制したにもかかわらず、後水尾天皇は従来の慣例通り、幕府に諮らず十数人の僧侶に紫衣着用の勅許を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the bakufu regulated the presenting of Shie, Emperor Gomizunoo followed the previous tradition of giving Imperial decrees allowing the wearing of Shie by about 15 Buddhist monks without asking for the bakufu&apos;s opinion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the bakufu regulated the presenting of Shie, Emperor Gomizunoo followed the previous tradition of giving Imperial decrees, allowing the wearing of Shie by about 15 Buddhist monks without asking for the bakufu&apos;s opinion.</e>
<cmt>パンクチュエイションを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the bakufu regulated the presenting of Shie, Emperor Gomizunoo followed the previous tradition of giving Imperial decrees, allowing the wearing of Shie by about 15 Buddhist monks without asking for the bakufu&apos;s opinion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これを知った幕府、3代将軍・徳川家光は、1627年、事前に勅許の相談がなかったことを法度違反とみなして多くの勅許状の無効を宣言し、京都所司代・板倉重宗に法度違反の紫衣を取り上げるよう命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1627, when the bakufu, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun learned of this, since there was no pre-consultation and he therefore considered this a violation of the law and annulled many of the Imperial decrees and ordered Shigemune ITAKURA of the Kyoto Shoshidai to confiscate any illegal Shies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1627, when the bakufu, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun learned of this, and since there was no consultation in advance he therefore considered this a violation of the law and annulled many of the Imperial decrees and ordered Shigemune ITAKURA of the Kyoto Shoshidai to confiscate any illegal Shies.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1627, when the bakufu, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the third Shogun learned of this, and since there was no consultation in advance he therefore considered this a violation of the law and annulled many of the Imperial decrees and ordered Shigemune ITAKURA of the Kyoto Shoshidai to confiscate any illegal Shies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>幕府の強硬な態度に対して朝廷は、これまでに授与した紫衣着用の勅許を無効にすることに強く反対し、また、大徳寺住職・沢庵宗彭（たくあんそうほう）や、妙心寺の東源慧等ら大寺の高僧も、朝廷に同調して幕府に抗弁書を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against the strong-handed stance of the bakufu, the Imperial court strongly objected to the annulment of Imperial decrees allowing the wearing of Shie and high priests of major temples such as Soho TAKUAN, the resident priest of Daitoku-ji Temple and Eto TOGEN of Myoshin-ji Temple also agreed with the Imperial Court and submitted a document of complaint.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against the strong-handed stance of the bakufu, the Imperial court strongly objected to the annulment of Imperial decrees allowing the wearing of Shie and high priests of major temples such as Soho TAKUAN, the resident priest of Daitoku-ji Temple and Eto TOGEN of Myoshin-ji Temple also agreed with the Imperial Court and submitted a document of complaint.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against the strong-handed stance of the bakufu, the Imperial Court strongly objected to the annulment of Imperial decrees allowing the wearing of Shie and high priests of major temples such as Takuan Soho, the resident priest of Daitoku-ji Temple and Eto TOGEN of Myoshin-ji Temple also agreed with the Imperial Court and submitted a document of complaint.</e>
<cmt>Court大文字にしました。Takuan Sohoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>1629年、幕府は、沢庵ら幕府に反抗した高僧を出羽国や陸奥国への流罪に処した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1629, the bakufu exiled Takuan and other high priests who rebelled against the bakufu to the Provinces of Dewa and Mutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1629, the bakufu exiled Takuan and other high priests who rebelled against the bakufu to the Provinces of Dewa and Mutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1629, the bakufu exiled Takuan and other high priests who rebelled against the bakufu to the Provinces of Dewa and Mutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Myopia(id:9335), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 遠藤(id:30275), Nonomura(id:72557), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>