<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>第1次西園寺内閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first Saionji&apos;s Cabinet</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Saionji&apos;s Cabinet</e>
<cmt>first を First に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Saionji&apos;s Cabinet</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日露戦争中に桂太郎との間で交わされた約束によって立憲政友会総裁である西園寺公望が後継に就任した（なお、この禅譲は元老の干渉を恐れた桂が事前に西園寺の後見人である伊藤博文と井上馨の許可を取ったのみで、元老会議は召集されなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinmochi SAIONJI, the president of Rikken Seiyukai, became Prime Minister, succeeding to Taro KATSURA, based on the promise made between them during the Russo-Japanese War (since Katsura was afraid of Genro (elder statesmen)&apos;s interference, he didn&apos;t assemble Council of Genro: he only got the approval from Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, both of whom were SAIONJI&apos;s guardians, for that transfer of power).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinmochi SAIONJI, the president of Rikken Seiyukai (Friends of Constitutional Government Party), became Prime Minister, succeeding to Taro KATSURA, based on the promise made between them during the Russo-Japanese War (since Katsura was afraid of Genro [elder statesmen]&apos;s interference, he didn&apos;t assemble Council of Genro: he only got the approval from Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, both of whom were Saionji&apos;s guardians, for that transfer of power).</e>
<cmt>Rikken Seiyukai に (Friends of Constitutional Government Party) を追記しました。 (elder statesmen) を [elder statesmen] に修正しました。SAIONJI&apos;s を Saionji&apos;s に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinmochi SAIONJI, the president of Rikken Seiyukai (Friends of Constitutional Government Party), became Prime Minister, succeeding to Taro KATSURA, based on the promise made between them during the Russo-Japanese War (since Katsura was afraid of Genro [elder statesmen]&apos;s interference, he didn&apos;t assemble Council of Genro: he only got the approval from Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, both of whom were Saionji&apos;s guardians, for that transfer of power).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>だが、桂と元老は人事や政策に条件を付けて制約をかけ、西園寺も自分の両腕と言える原敬と松田正久の2人だけを入閣させる条件で折り合った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KATSURA and Genro restricted SAIONJI&apos;s power by making conditions on policies and personnel affairs; SAIONJI came to terms with them on the condition that Takashi HARA and Masahisa MATSUDA, the two most trusted assistants, would be in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsura and Genro restricted Saionji&apos;s power by making conditions on policies and personnel affairs; Saionji came to terms with them on the condition that Takashi HARA and Masahisa MATSUDA, the two most trusted assistants, would be in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>苗字のみの表記を語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsura and Genro restricted Saionji&apos;s power by making conditions on policies and personnel affairs; Saionji came to terms with them on the condition that Takashi HARA and Masahisa MATSUDA, the two most trusted assistants, would be in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>桂はこの内閣の後見人を自負して、政権運営にまで関与しようとしたために内務大臣 (日本)原敬との微妙な政治的駆け引きを行うこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KATSURA considered himself as the guardian of the cabinet and tried to influence SAIONJI&apos;s handling of the government, which led to the delicate politics with Takashi HARA, Minister of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsura considered himself as the guardian of the cabinet and tried to influence Saionji&apos;s handling of the government, which led to the delicate politics with Takashi HARA, Minister of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt>苗字のみの表記を語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsura considered himself as the guardian of the cabinet and tried to influence Saionji&apos;s handling of the government, which led to the delicate politics with Takashi HARA, Minister of Home Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>鉄道国有化や第3次日韓協約・日露協約・日仏協約の締結など、山縣有朋ら元老や桂の意に沿った政策を遂行する一方で、山縣の支持基盤である内務省 (日本)改革のために郡制の廃止を計画して失敗したり、貴族院議員の入閣を実現させるなど、政党政治実現に向けた努力は続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the cabinet pursued the policy complying with Aritomo YAMAGATA and Genro, such as making The Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty, Russo-Japanese Agreement and French-Japanese Agreement, it continued to make efforts in order to realize party politics; in order to reform Ministry of Home Affairs, which was the power base for YAMAGATA, the cabinet tried to abolish the County system, only to fail; the cabinet succeeded in taking members of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) into the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>「郡制」の定訳が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the cabinet pursued the policy complying with Genro like Aritomo YAMAGATA and Katsura, such as making The Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty, Russo-Japanese Agreement and French-Japanese Agreement, it continued to make efforts in order to realize party politics; in order to reform Ministry of Home Affairs, which was the power base for Yamagata, the cabinet tried to abolish the County system, only to fail; the cabinet succeeded in taking members of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) into the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>苗字のみの表記を語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。「桂の」訳漏れのため、Aritomo YAMAGATA and Genro を Genro like Aritomo YAMAGATA and Katsura に修正して対応しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the cabinet pursued the policy complying with Genro like Aritomo YAMAGATA and Katsura, such as making The Japan-Korea Annexation Treaty, Russo-Japanese Agreement and French-Japanese Agreement, it continued to make efforts in order to realize party politics; in order to reform Ministry of Home Affairs, which was the power base for Yamagata, the cabinet tried to abolish the County system, only to fail; the cabinet succeeded in taking members of Kizokuin (the House of Peers) into the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、閣内では政友会は少数派であり閣内は円滑ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the politics inside the cabinet did not go smoothly since the Seiyu Party was a minority in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the politics inside the cabinet did not go smoothly since the Seiyukai was a minority in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>Seiyu Party を Seiyukai に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the politics inside the cabinet did not go smoothly since the Seiyukai was a minority in the cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>成立から2ヶ月後に加藤高明外務大臣 (日本)が鉄道国有化に反対して辞任した。（ただし、実際には健康問題が絡んでいたとされている。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two months after the establishment of the cabiet, Takaaki KATO, Minister of Foreign Affairs, resigned because he was against the nationalization of railways. (However, it is said that, in fact, he resigned because of his health problem.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two months after the establishment of the cabinet, Takaaki KATO, Minister of Foreign Affairs, resigned because he was against the nationalization of railways (in fact, however, he is said to have resigned due to his health problem).</e>
<cmt>cabiet を cabinet に修正しました後半部のカッコ内を全文修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two months after the establishment of the cabinet, Takaaki KATO, Minister of Foreign Affairs, resigned because he was against the nationalization of railways (in fact, however, he is said to have resigned due to his health problem).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>続いて山縣伊三郎逓信大臣と阪谷芳郎大蔵大臣が鉄道予算の問題で対立して共に辞表を明治天皇に提出しようとした際には、両名を天皇の前に連れてくるだけの西園寺までが辞表を提出してしまい、原と寺内正毅陸軍大臣が必死に説得して西園寺の辞表のみを撤回させる騒ぎも起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When both Isaburo YAMAGATA, the Minister of Correspondence and Yoshio SAKATANI, Minister of Finance, were going to hand in their resignationletters to Emperor Meiji, after their conflict over the railway budget problem, SAIONJI, who was only expected to take them to the emperor, handed in his own letter of resignation; Hara and Masatake TERAUCHI, Minister of Army, worked very hard to persuade Saionji to take back his resignation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処 「逓信大臣」の定訳が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, when both Isaburo YAMAGATA, the Minister of Correspondence and Yoshio SAKATANI, Minister of Finance, were going to hand in their resignationletters to the Emperor Meiji after their conflict over the railway budget problem, Saionji, who was only expected to take them to the emperor, handed in his own letter of resignation; Hara and Masatake TERAUCHI, Minister of Army, worked very hard to persuade Saionji to take back his resignation.</e>
<cmt>「続いて」訳漏れのため After that, を追記して対応しました。苗字のみの表記を語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。Emperor Meiji に the を追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, when both Isaburo YAMAGATA, the Minister of Correspondence and Yoshio SAKATANI, Minister of Finance, were going to hand in their resignationletters to the Emperor Meiji after their conflict over the railway budget problem, Saionji, who was only expected to take them to the emperor, handed in his own letter of resignation; Hara and Masatake TERAUCHI, Minister of Army, worked very hard to persuade Saionji to take back his resignation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>第10回衆議院議員総選挙において過半数に迫る187議席を獲得したものの、政友会の基盤が確固たるものになることを警戒した山縣有朋から財政政策の不備と社会主義取締の緩さを問題視する上奏が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the tenth general election of members of the House of Representatives, the Seiyu Party won 187 seats, and almost became the majority; Aritomo YAMAGATA, who feared the stability of the party, reported to the throne that the cabinet was not effective in its financial policy or regulation of socialism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the tenth general election of members of the House of Representatives, the Seiyu party won 187 seats, and almost became the majority; Aritomo YAMAGATA, who feared the stability of the party, reported to the throne that the cabinet was not effective in its financial policy or regulation of socialism.</e>
<cmt>Party を party に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the tenth general election of members of the House of Representatives, the Seiyu party won 187 seats, and almost became the majority; Aritomo YAMAGATA, who feared the stability of the party, reported to the throne that the cabinet was not effective in its financial policy or regulation of socialism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これを松田（蔵相）と原（内相）の更迭要求と見た西園寺はこれを機に総辞職をすることとなった（近年では、桂による反政友会工作の発覚や井上馨による増税による財政再建要求が実現困難であったことも原因として挙げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAIONJI regarded it as YAMAGATA&apos;s demand to replace MATSUDA (MOF) and HARA (Interior Minister) and his cabinet resigned en masse. (Recently, the following are considered as the reasons of the resignation: the anti-Seiyu party maneuver by KATSURA was revealed; it would be difficult to carry out Kaoru INOUE&apos;s demand for financial reconstruction by increasing tax revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saionji regarded it as Yamagata&apos;s demand to replace Matsuda (Minister of Finance) and Hara (Interior Minister) and his cabinet resigned en masse (recently, the following are considered as the reasons of the resignation: the anti-Seiyuto maneuver by Katsura was revealed; it would be difficult to carry out Kaoru INOUE&apos;s demand for financial reconstruction by increasing tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saionji regarded it as Yamagata&apos;s demand to replace Matsuda (Minister of Finance) and Hara (Interior Minister) and his cabinet resigned en masse (recently, the following are considered as the reasons of the resignation: the anti-Seiyuto maneuver by Katsura was revealed; it would be difficult to carry out Kaoru INOUE&apos;s demand for financial reconstruction by increasing tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>なお、原たちは総辞職の上奏が行われるまでその事実を知らされていなかった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was not until the resign en masse was reported to the throne that HARA and others were informed of the fact.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hara and others were not informed of the resign en mess until it was reported to the throne).</e>
<cmt>全文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hara and others were not informed of the resign en mess until it was reported to the throne).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、閣内少数派であったとは言え、政友会党員が閣僚の殆どを占めながら終始混乱で終わった第4次伊藤内閣と比較すれば、官界や貴族院にも支持勢力を形成出来た事など、政友会にとっては大きな成果も伴った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seiyu party in that cabinet achieved great results, compared with the fourth ITO&apos;s cabinet, most of which were the members of the Seiyu party and did nothing except giving chaos; in other words, the party in the first Saionji&apos;s cabinet established support in the bureaucracy and the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seiyu party in that cabinet achieved great results, compared with the fourth Ito&apos;s cabinet, most of which were the members of the Seiyu party and did nothing except giving chaos; in other words, the party in the first Saionji&apos;s cabinet established support in the bureaucracy and the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>苗字のみの表記を語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seiyu party in that cabinet achieved great results, compared with the fourth Ito&apos;s cabinet, most of which were the members of the Seiyu party and did nothing except giving chaos; in other words, the party in the first Saionji&apos;s cabinet established support in the bureaucracy and the House of Peers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、徳富蘇峰は「（西園寺は）仏（桂）を頼んで地獄（総辞職）に落ちた」と評し（『大正政局史論』）、西園寺の度を越えた「盟友」桂への依存が政権崩壊の真の原因と評している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soho TOKUTOMI attributed the true failure of the cabinet to SAIONJI&apos;s excessive dependence on KATSURA, his &apos;sworn friend&apos;; Soho criticized the cabinet by saying, &apos;(SAIONJI) depended on Buddha (KATSURA) and went down to the hell (resign en masse).&apos; (&quot;An essay on history of the Taisho-period political situation&quot;)</e>
<cmt>『大正政局史論』の定訳が確認できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soho TOKUTOMI attributed the true failure of the cabinet to Saionji&apos;s excessive dependence on Katsura, his &apos;sworn friend&apos;; Soho criticized the cabinet by saying, &apos;(SAIONJI) depended on Buddha (KATSURA) and went down to the hell (resign en masse).&apos; (Taisho seikyoku shiron [A Political History of the Taisho Era])</e>
<cmt>苗字のみの表記を語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。『大正政局史論』の定訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soho TOKUTOMI attributed the true failure of the cabinet to Saionji&apos;s excessive dependence on Katsura, his &apos;sworn friend&apos;; Soho criticized the cabinet by saying, &apos;(SAIONJI) depended on Buddha (KATSURA) and went down to the hell (resign en masse).&apos; (Taisho seikyoku shiron [A Political History of the Taisho Era])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>国務大臣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minister of State</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minister of State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Minister of State</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Dumpty-Humpty(id:222368), Monaneko(id:28864), 唐棣色(id:64681), BAKU(id:55205), MIsogi(id:20599), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>