<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>幕政改革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reforms Of The Shogunate Regime</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reformation Of The Shogunate Government</e>
<cmt>間違いではありませんが、用語集に登録されている訳に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reformation Of The Shogunate Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>幕政改革（ばくせいかいかく）は、江戸幕府で行われた、財政および政治制度その他の諸改革を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reforms of the shogunate regime refer to the reforms of the financial, political, and other systems implemented under Edo &quot;bakufu&quot; (Japanese feudal regime headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reformation of the shogunate government refers to the reforms of the financial, political, and other systems implemented under the Edo &quot;bakufu&quot; (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>幕政改革の訳を用語集に登録されているものに変更しました。Edo &quot;bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。用語統一シートの指示に従い、江戸幕府の説明部分の regime を government に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reformation of the shogunate government refers to the reforms of the financial, political, and other systems implemented under the Edo &quot;bakufu&quot; (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>俗に、享保の改革・寛政の改革・天保の改革をもって「江戸幕府の三大改革」と呼ばれるが、これ以外にも、大規模な財政・制度改革は幾度にも渡って行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commonly, Kyoho Reforms, Kansei Reforms, and Tenpo Reforms are called Three Big Reforms under Edo bakufu, and besides, large-scale financial and institutional reforms were implemented many times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commonly, Kyoho Reforms, Kansei Reforms, and Tenpo Reforms are called Three Big Reforms under the Edo bakufu, and besides, large-scale financial and institutional reforms were implemented many times.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commonly, Kyoho Reforms, Kansei Reforms, and Tenpo Reforms are called Three Big Reforms under the Edo bakufu, and besides, large-scale financial and institutional reforms were implemented many times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>幕藩体制の成立期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of establishment of the shogunate and domain system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of establishment of the shogunate and domain system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of establishment of the shogunate and domain system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>初代将軍徳川家康、2代徳川秀忠、3代徳川家光の時代は、江戸幕府体制の確立期にあたり、この期間における諸改革は「改革」というよりもむしろ「体制固め」というべきであるため、幕政改革には含まれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reigns of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the first shogun), Hidetada TOKUGAWA (the second shogun), and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA (the third shogun) fell under the period of establishment of Edo bakufu, so various policies during this period were done for setting up the regime rather than implementing reforms, so these policies are not included in the reforms of the shogunate regime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reigns of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the first Shogun), Hidetada TOKUGAWA (the second Shogun), and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA (the third Shogun) fell under the period of establishment of the Edo bakufu, so various policies during this period were done for setting up the regime rather than implementing reforms, so these policies are not included in the reforms of the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。タイトルに合わせて、&quot;shogunate regime&quot; から &quot;shogunate government&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reigns of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA (the first Shogun), Hidetada TOKUGAWA (the second Shogun), and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA (the third Shogun) fell under the period of establishment of the Edo bakufu, so various policies during this period were done for setting up the regime rather than implementing reforms, so these policies are not included in the reforms of the shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家康・秀忠の2代において（大御所時代も含む）、江戸時代幕藩体制の基本的骨格が創作されていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic framework of the shogunate and domain system in the Edo period was created under the rule of Ieyasu and Hidetada - as a shogun or an &quot;ogosho&quot; (a title of honor given to the former shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic framework of the shogunate and domain system in the Edo period was created under the rule of Ieyasu and Hidetada - as a shogun or an &quot;ogosho&quot; (a title of honor given to the former shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic framework of the shogunate and domain system in the Edo period was created under the rule of Ieyasu and Hidetada - as a shogun or an &quot;ogosho&quot; (a title of honor given to the former shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その中身は以下のとおりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the contents were as follows :</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the contents were as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the contents were as follows :</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>第一に大名統制（武家諸法度、参勤交代、改易）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Firstly, they established the system for controlling &quot;daimyo&quot; (Japanese territorial lord), such as &quot;Buke Shohatto&quot; (Decree for the Military Houses), &quot;Sankinkotai&quot; (the system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo), and &quot;kaieki&quot; (forfeiture of a rank and properties of a samurai);</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, they established the system for controlling &quot;daimyo&quot; (Japanese territorial lord), such as &quot;Buke Shohatto&quot; (Decree for the Military Houses), &quot;Sankinkotai&quot; (the system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo), and &quot;kaieki&quot; (forfeiture of a rank and properties of a samurai);</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, they established the system for controlling &quot;daimyo&quot; (Japanese territorial lord), such as &quot;Buke Shohatto&quot; (Decree for the Military Houses), &quot;Sankinkotai&quot; (the system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo), and &quot;kaieki&quot; (forfeiture of a rank and properties of a samurai);</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>第二に農民統制（宗門改め）、及び宗教政策（切支丹禁令、寺院諸法度）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">secondly, they took control of farmers and peasants with &quot;shumon aratame&quot; (originally, an inquisition for suppressing Christianity, but later, it became like a general research on residents), and took religious policies as well, such as a ban of Christianity and issuance of &quot;Jiin Shohatto&quot; (the regulations for Buddhist temples in the Edo period);</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（注）・・・「宗門改め」については「もともとはキリシタン抑圧のための取り調べ手続きだったが、後に一般的な住民調査の制度になった」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">secondly, they took control of farmers and peasants with &quot;shumon aratame&quot; (originally, an inquisition for suppressing Christianity, but later, it became like a general research on residents), and took religious policies as well, such as a ban of Christianity and issuance of &quot;Jiin Shohatto&quot; (the regulations for Buddhist temples in the Edo period);</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">secondly, they took control of farmers and peasants with &quot;shumon aratame&quot; (originally, an inquisition for suppressing Christianity, but later, it became like a general research on residents), and took religious policies as well, such as a ban of Christianity and issuance of &quot;Jiin Shohatto&quot; (the regulations for Buddhist temples in the Edo period);</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>さらに朝廷政策（禁中並公家諸法度）、海禁政策（いわゆる一連の鎖国令）、譜代大名による幕政の独占などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">besides, they issued &quot;Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto&quot; (a set of regulations applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles) for controlling the Imperial Court, and established the policy that forbade private people to trade with foreign countries through a series of so-called the Decrees of Seclusion, and they also set the precedent that &quot;fudai daimyo&quot; (Japanese territorial lords in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) monopolized the politics of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">besides, they issued &quot;Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto&quot; (a set of regulations applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles) for controlling the Imperial Court, and established the policy that forbade private people to trade with foreign countries through a series of so-called the Decrees of Seclusion, and they also set the precedent that &quot;fudai daimyo&quot; (Japanese territorial lords in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) monopolized the politics of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">besides, they issued &quot;Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto&quot; (a set of regulations applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles) for controlling the Imperial Court, and established the policy that forbade private people to trade with foreign countries through a series of so-called the Decrees of Seclusion, and they also set the precedent that &quot;fudai daimyo&quot; (Japanese territorial lords in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) monopolized the politics of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>こうして基本的な幕府の政治制度が整えられていき、一応の完成を見たのは3代徳川家光の時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the basic political system was built and roughly completed during the reign of the third shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, the basic political system was built and roughly completed during the reign of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the basic political system was built and roughly completed during the reign of the third Shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>続く4代徳川家綱の時代は、松平信綱・酒井忠勝 (若狭国小浜藩主)ら有能な老中らに恵まれ、安定した幕府政治が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the reign of the next fourth shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the politics was stable thanks to the competent &quot;roju&quot; (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), such as Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Tadakatsu SAKAI (the feudal lord of Obama Domain, Wakasa Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the reign of the next fourth Shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the politics was stable thanks to the competent &quot;roju&quot; (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), such as Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Tadakatsu SAKAI (the feudal lord of the Obama Domain, Wakasa Province).</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。&quot;Obama Domain&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the reign of the next fourth Shogun Ietsuna TOKUGAWA, the politics was stable thanks to the competent &quot;roju&quot; (member of shogun&apos;s council of elders), such as Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA and Tadakatsu SAKAI (the feudal lord of the Obama Domain, Wakasa Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>綱吉の政治と正徳の治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s politics and the Shotoku Reforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s politics and the Shotoku Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s politics and the Shotoku Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし、安定した幕府政治も完璧という訳ではなく、様々な矛盾は当初から内包され、次第に問題化していくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spite of being stable, the politics of Edo bakufu was far from perfect, so various contradictions inherent in the regime became problematic year by year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of being stable, the politics of the Edo bakufu was far from perfect, so various contradictions inherent in the regime became problematic year by year.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of being stable, the politics of the Edo bakufu was far from perfect, so various contradictions inherent in the regime became problematic year by year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>とりわけ幕府財政の危機は、諸国の幕府直轄金山・銀山の枯渇傾向、長崎における海外交易赤字による金銀の流出、明暦の大火・大地震・富士山の噴火などの災害復興事業による出費などから、いち早く訪れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly, the financial crisis came early for various causes, such as depletion of gold and silver mines under direct control of Edo bakufu, outflow of gold and silver from Nagasaki that resulted from a deficit in trade with foreign countries, and expense for reconstruction projects after disasters, including the Great Fire of Meireki, some big earthquakes, and eruption of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Particularly, the financial crisis came early for various causes, such as depletion of gold and silver mines under direct control of the Edo bakufu, outflow of gold and silver from Nagasaki that resulted from a deficit in trade with foreign countries, and expense for reconstruction projects after disasters, including the Great Fire of Meireki, some big earthquakes, and eruption of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Particularly, the financial crisis came early for various causes, such as depletion of gold and silver mines under direct control of the Edo bakufu, outflow of gold and silver from Nagasaki that resulted from a deficit in trade with foreign countries, and expense for reconstruction projects after disasters, including the Great Fire of Meireki, some big earthquakes, and eruption of Mt. Fuji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>5代将軍となった徳川綱吉は、儒教による理念的な政治思想を掲げつつも、財政改革の必要に迫られ、勘定奉行に荻原重秀を抜擢して解決を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation compelled the fifth shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to implement a financial reform, so he tried to do it by selecting Shigehide OGIWARA as chief financial official - incidentally, Tsunayoshi waved the banner of ideological ideas by adopting Confucianism into his politics.</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・「儒教による理念的な政治理想を掲げつつも」の部分は、前後の文脈から見て内容的にやや唐突であり、英訳では文章の後半に回しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation compelled the fifth Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to implement a financial reform, so he tried to do it by selecting Shigehide OGIWARA as kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) - incidentally, Tsunayoshi waved the banner of ideological ideas by adopting Confucianism into his politics.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。「勘定奉行」の訳を用語集に登録されているものに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation compelled the fifth Shogun Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to implement a financial reform, so he tried to do it by selecting Shigehide OGIWARA as kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance) - incidentally, Tsunayoshi waved the banner of ideological ideas by adopting Confucianism into his politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>荻原は元禄小判による貨幣改鋳（金含有率を減らして貨幣流通量を増やす）によって財政問題を一時的に解決するが、結果として元禄期のインフレーション状況を生じることとなり、物価の高騰を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ogiwara tentatively resolved the financial crisis by reminting an old coin into &quot;Genroku koban&quot; (the oval gold coin minted in the Genroku era) - he reduced the percentage of gold in the old coin, and increased the number of coins in circulation as a whole - but as a result, his policy caused inflation and a surge of commodity prices in the Genroku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogiwara tentatively resolved the financial crisis by reminting an old coin into &quot;Genroku koban&quot; (the oval gold coin minted in the Genroku era) - he reduced the percentage of gold in the old coin, and increased the number of coins in circulation as a whole - but as a result, his policy caused inflation and a surge of commodity prices in the Genroku era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogiwara tentatively resolved the financial crisis by reminting an old coin into &quot;Genroku koban&quot; (the oval gold coin minted in the Genroku era) - he reduced the percentage of gold in the old coin, and increased the number of coins in circulation as a whole - but as a result, his policy caused inflation and a surge of commodity prices in the Genroku era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、財政以外の改革では生類憐れみの令が知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the financial reform, a decree forbidding cruelty to all living things is known to have been implemented during this era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the financial reform, Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) is known to have been implemented during this era.</e>
<cmt>「生類憐れみの令」の訳を用語集に登録されているものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the financial reform, Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) is known to have been implemented during this era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>6代将軍となった徳川家宣は、もと甲府藩主から将軍職となったが、甲府時代から政治改革に実績のあった側用人間部詮房や学者の新井白石を起用し、改革を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sixth shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA had been formerly the feudal lord of Kofu Domain, and so, in order to carry out his reforms, he promoted Akifusa MANABE and a scholar Hakuseki ARAI, both of whom had had achievements in political reforms in Kofu Domain, to his grand chamberlain and personal staff respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sixth Shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA had been formerly the feudal lord of Kofu Domain, and so, in order to carry out his reforms, he promoted Akifusa MANABE and a scholar Hakuseki ARAI, both of whom had had achievements in political reforms in the Kofu Domain, to his grand chamberlain and personal staff respectively.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。&quot;Kofu Domain&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sixth Shogun Ienobu TOKUGAWA had been formerly the feudal lord of Kofu Domain, and so, in order to carry out his reforms, he promoted Akifusa MANABE and a scholar Hakuseki ARAI, both of whom had had achievements in political reforms in the Kofu Domain, to his grand chamberlain and personal staff respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>間部・新井が主導した改革を年号をとって「正徳の治」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reform led by Manabe and Arai is called the Shotoku Reforms after the name of the era that the reform was implemented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reform led by Manabe and Arai is called the Shotoku Reforms after the name of the era that the reform was implemented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reform led by Manabe and Arai is called the Shotoku Reforms after the name of the era that the reform was implemented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>綱吉時代の政策は否定され、生類憐れみの令は撤回、勘定吟味役の創設、正徳金銀発行（デフレーション政策）による綱吉時代の財政矛盾の解決などを行ったが、将軍家宣・7代徳川家継があいついで早世したため、改革は中途半端に終わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s policies were denied in the reforms, so, for example, the decree forbidding cruelty to all living things was revoked, &quot;kanjo ginmiyaku&quot; (a post to support the chief financial official) was newly established, and the financial contradiction in the Tsunayoshi age was tried to resolve by issuing Shotoku gold and silver coins as a deflationary policy, but the reforms ended halfway on the road after Ienobu and his successor Ietsugu TOKUGAWA (the seventh shogun) died young.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunayoshi&apos;s policies were denied in the reforms, so, for example, Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) was revoked, &quot;kanjo ginmiyaku&quot; (a post to support kanjo bugyo) was newly established, and the financial contradiction in the Tsunayoshi age was tried to resolve by issuing Shotoku gold and silver coins as a deflationary policy, but the reforms ended halfway on the road after Ienobu and his successor Ietsugu TOKUGAWA (the seventh Shogun) died young.</e>
<cmt>「生類憐れみの令」の訳を用語集に登録されているものに修正しました。「勘定奉行」の訳を用語集に登録されているものに変更しました。用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunayoshi&apos;s policies were denied in the reforms, so, for example, Shorui-Awaremi-no-rei (ordinances of animal protection) was revoked, &quot;kanjo ginmiyaku&quot; (a post to support kanjo bugyo) was newly established, and the financial contradiction in the Tsunayoshi age was tried to resolve by issuing Shotoku gold and silver coins as a deflationary policy, but the reforms ended halfway on the road after Ienobu and his successor Ietsugu TOKUGAWA (the seventh Shogun) died young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>享保の改革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoho Reforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoho Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoho Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>8代将軍となった徳川吉宗は、紀州徳川家の出身であり、それまでの幕政を主導してきた譜代大名に対して遠慮することなく、大胆に政治改革を主導することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA came from the Kishu Tokugawa family (a branch of Tokugawa family), so he had the courage to lead the political reforms without hesitation toward &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; who had led politics of Edo bakufu until then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth Shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA came from the Kishu Tokugawa family (a branch of Tokugawa family), so he had the courage to lead the political reforms without hesitation toward &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; who had led politics of the Edo bakufu until then.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth Shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA came from the Kishu Tokugawa family (a branch of Tokugawa family), so he had the courage to lead the political reforms without hesitation toward &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; who had led politics of the Edo bakufu until then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>将軍吉宗自ら主導した改革を「享保の改革」と呼ぶ（1716年 - 1745年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reforms led by Shogun Yoshimune himself is called Kyoho Reforms (from A.D. 1716 to 1745).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reforms led by Shogun Yoshimune himself is called Kyoho Reforms (from A.D. 1716 to 1745).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reforms led by Shogun Yoshimune himself is called Kyoho Reforms (from A.D. 1716 to 1745).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>吉宗が最も心を砕いたのは米価の安定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He directed his attention toward stabilizing the rice price more than anything else.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He directed his attention toward stabilizing the rice price more than anything else.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He directed his attention toward stabilizing the rice price more than anything else.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>商品流通・貨幣経済の発展に伴い、諸物価の基準であった米価は江戸時代を通じて下落を続け、「米価安の諸色高」と言われた状況にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As goods distribution and a monetary economy developed, the rice price, which served as a standard of other commodities&apos; price, continued falling throughout the Edo period, so people then said that rice price was low while other commodities&apos; was high.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As goods distribution and a monetary economy developed, the rice price, which served as a standard of other commodities&apos; price, continued falling throughout the Edo period, so people then said that rice price was low while other commodities&apos; was high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As goods distribution and a monetary economy developed, the rice price, which served as a standard of other commodities&apos; price, continued falling throughout the Edo period, so people then said that rice price was low while other commodities&apos; was high.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>これが米収入を俸禄の基本とする旗本・下級武士の困窮に直接つながっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And this directly led to the poverty of &quot;hatamoto&quot; (direct retainers of Edo bakufu) and lower-ranking samurai whose stipends were based on a rice harvest.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And this directly led to the poverty of &quot;hatamoto&quot; (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) and lower-ranking samurai whose stipends were based on a rice harvest.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And this directly led to the poverty of &quot;hatamoto&quot; (direct retainers of the Edo bakufu) and lower-ranking samurai whose stipends were based on a rice harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そのため吉宗は、倹約令で消費を抑える一方、新田開発による米増産、定免法採用による収入の安定、上米令、堂島米会所の公認など、米に関する改革を多く行ったため、「米将軍」の異名を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, while controlling people&apos;s consumption with sumptuary decrees, Yoshimune implemented many rice-related reforms, such as development of new rice fields for increasing the rice harvest, adoption of &quot;Jomen ho&quot; (the taxation system whose rate was determined by calculating the average rice harvest over the past 5, 10, or 20 years) for stabilizing the income of Edo bakufu, issuance of &quot;Agemai-rei&quot; (the decree ordering &apos;daimyo&apos; to pay 100 koku rice for every 10 thousand koku it had), and permission for Dojima Rice Exchange, so Yoshimune was given a nickname of &quot;Rice Shogun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・①「定免法（じょうめんほう）」については「過去5年、10年、または20年の収穫高の平均から年貢率を割り出して課税する制度」、②「上米令（あげまいれい）」については「大名に対し石高一万石ごとに100石の米を納めさせた制度」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, while controlling people&apos;s consumption with sumptuary decrees, Yoshimune implemented many rice-related reforms, such as development of new rice fields for increasing the rice harvest, adoption of &quot;Jomen ho&quot; (the taxation system whose rate was determined by calculating the average rice harvest over the past 5, 10, or 20 years) for stabilizing the income of the Edo bakufu, issuance of &quot;Agemai-rei&quot; (the decree ordering &apos;daimyo&apos; to pay 100 koku rice for every 10 thousand koku it had), and permission for Dojima Rice Exchange, so Yoshimune was given a nickname of &quot;Rice Shogun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, while controlling people&apos;s consumption with sumptuary decrees, Yoshimune implemented many rice-related reforms, such as development of new rice fields for increasing the rice harvest, adoption of &quot;Jomen ho&quot; (the taxation system whose rate was determined by calculating the average rice harvest over the past 5, 10, or 20 years) for stabilizing the income of the Edo bakufu, issuance of &quot;Agemai-rei&quot; (the decree ordering &apos;daimyo&apos; to pay 100 koku rice for every 10 thousand koku it had), and permission for Dojima Rice Exchange, so Yoshimune was given a nickname of &quot;Rice Shogun.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>吉宗は米価対策の他にも目安箱の設置、足高制による人材抜擢制度の整備を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he set a complaints box for the public, and introduced meritocracy by adopting &quot;Ashidaka system&quot; (the system which took talented people into bakufu, who had been unable to assume the important posts until then owing to their low stipends).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（注）・・・「足高制」については「従来なら禄高が低いために幕府の要職に就けなかった者でも能力次第で登用する制度」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he set a complaints box for the public, and introduced meritocracy by adopting &quot;Ashidaka system&quot; (the system which took talented people into bakufu, who had been unable to assume the important posts until then owing to their low stipends).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he set a complaints box for the public, and introduced meritocracy by adopting &quot;Ashidaka system&quot; (the system which took talented people into bakufu, who had been unable to assume the important posts until then owing to their low stipends).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>更には江戸の都市政策（町火消の創設、小石川養生所の設置）、西洋知識禁制の緩和（漢訳洋書禁輸の緩和、甘藷栽培など）、商人対策（相対済まし令、株仲間の公認など）などの諸改革も行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And moreover, he implemented various reforms, such as renewing Edo city through establishing local fire brigades and Koishikawa Hospital, mitigating prohibition of Western knowledge through various measures (lifting an embargo on the import of Western books translated into Chinese characters, permitting cultivation of sweet potatoes, and so on), and handling matters about merchants (issuing Mutual Settlement Decree on money matters, permitting &quot;kabu nakama&quot; [a kind of cartel formed by wholesalers and other merchants], and so on).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処（注）・・・「株仲間」については「問屋などが形成した一種のカルテル」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And moreover, he implemented various reforms, such as renewing Edo city through establishing local fire brigades and Koishikawa Hospital, mitigating prohibition of Western knowledge through various measures (lifting an embargo on the import of Western books translated into Chinese characters, permitting cultivation of sweet potatoes, and so on), and handling matters about merchants (issuing Mutual Settlement Decree on money matters, permitting &quot;kabu nakama&quot; [a kind of cartel formed by wholesalers and other merchants], and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And moreover, he implemented various reforms, such as renewing Edo city through establishing local fire brigades and Koishikawa Hospital, mitigating prohibition of Western knowledge through various measures (lifting an embargo on the import of Western books translated into Chinese characters, permitting cultivation of sweet potatoes, and so on), and handling matters about merchants (issuing Mutual Settlement Decree on money matters, permitting &quot;kabu nakama&quot; [a kind of cartel formed by wholesalers and other merchants], and so on).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>幕府財政は一部で健全化し、1744年には江戸時代を通じて最高の税収となったが、税率変更や倹約の徹底により百姓・町民からの不満を招き百姓一揆・打ちこわしなどが頻発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the reforms, the financial condition of Edo bakufu turned for the better, and in A.D. 1744, the income of bakufu reached its peak throughout the Edo period, but Yoshimune&apos;s change of tax rate and thorough frugality policy caused frequent uprisings and destructive riots of discontented peasants and merchants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the reforms, the financial condition of the Edo bakufu turned for the better, and in 1744, the income of bakufu reached its peak throughout the Edo period, but Yoshimune&apos;s change of tax rate and thorough frugality policy caused frequent uprisings and destructive riots of discontented peasants and merchants.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。年号の A.D. は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the reforms, the financial condition of the Edo bakufu turned for the better, and in 1744, the income of bakufu reached its peak throughout the Edo period, but Yoshimune&apos;s change of tax rate and thorough frugality policy caused frequent uprisings and destructive riots of discontented peasants and merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>もはや米作収入に依存する財政は矛盾を解消できない段階に到達しつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shows that Edo bakufu then became unable to resolve its financial contradictions if it continued depending on rice harvest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows that the Edo bakufu then became unable to resolve its financial contradictions if it continued depending on rice harvest.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows that the Edo bakufu then became unable to resolve its financial contradictions if it continued depending on rice harvest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>田沼時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanuma age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanuma period</e>
<cmt>用語集に登録されている訳語に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanuma period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>吉宗が行った享保の改革によっても幕府の財政赤字の根本的解決には程遠く、続く9代徳川家重の時代に持ち越される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite Yoshimine&apos;s Kyoho Reforms, a budget deficit of Edo bakufu was far from a thorough resolution, so it was carried over to the reign of the next ninth shogun Ieshige TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite Yoshimune&apos;s Kyoho Reforms, a budget deficit of the Edo bakufu was far from a thorough resolution, so it was carried over to the reign of the next ninth Shogun Ieshige TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Yoshimine→Yoshimune のスペルミスを修正しました。&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite Yoshimune&apos;s Kyoho Reforms, a budget deficit of the Edo bakufu was far from a thorough resolution, so it was carried over to the reign of the next ninth Shogun Ieshige TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>家重時代の末期から続く10代徳川家治時代にかけて幕政を主導し財政を立て直したのが、側用人から老中となった田沼意次である（なお、これ以後の幕政改革は、ほぼ老中が主導することになる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was Okitsugu TANUMA who got promoted from the grand chamberlain to &quot;roju,&quot; and who took the initiative in reconstructing the bakufu finance from the last days of Ieshige&apos;s reign to the next tenth shogun Ieharu TOKUGAWA&apos;s one; incidentally, the reforms of politics after that were mostly led by &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it was Okitsugu TANUMA who got promoted from the grand chamberlain to &quot;roju,&quot; and who took the initiative in reconstructing the bakufu finance from the last days of Ieshige&apos;s reign to the next tenth Shogun Ieharu TOKUGAWA&apos;s one; incidentally, the reforms of politics after that were mostly led by &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it was Okitsugu TANUMA who got promoted from the grand chamberlain to &quot;roju,&quot; and who took the initiative in reconstructing the bakufu finance from the last days of Ieshige&apos;s reign to the next tenth Shogun Ieharu TOKUGAWA&apos;s one; incidentally, the reforms of politics after that were mostly led by &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>田沼が政治改革を主導した時期を「田沼時代」と呼ぶ（1760年代 - 1786年頃）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The age that Tanuma led the political reforms is called the Tanuma age (from 1760s to around 1786)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period that Tanuma led the political reforms is called the Tanuma period (from 1760s to around 1786)</e>
<cmt>セクションタイトルに合わせて、age→period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period that Tanuma led the political reforms is called the Tanuma period (from 1760s to around 1786)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>田沼は、それまでの農業依存の幕府経済を改め、重商主義的な改革を行うことによって財政の立て直しを図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanuma tried to reconstruct finance of Edo bakufu by reducing its conventional dependence on agriculture and implementing mercantilistic reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanuma tried to reconstruct finance of the Edo bakufu by reducing its conventional dependence on agriculture and implementing mercantilistic reforms.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanuma tried to reconstruct finance of the Edo bakufu by reducing its conventional dependence on agriculture and implementing mercantilistic reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>株仲間の奨励策による運上金・冥加金の徴収、町人資本による印旛沼・手賀沼の干拓事業を行ういっぽう、長崎貿易の推奨（特に俵物など輸出商品の増産）など、積極的に改革を推し進め、幕府財政を立て直すことに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He aggressively pushed forward his reforms, such as collecting business taxes and forced contribution in exchange for promoting &quot;kabu nakama,&quot; doing reclamation works of Inba-numa Lake and Tega-numa Lake with merchants&apos; funds, and promoting trade with foreign countries at Nagasaki - particularly through production increase of goods for export, including &quot;tawara mono&quot; (goods in straw bags), thereby succeeding in reconstruction of bakufu finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He aggressively pushed forward his reforms, such as collecting business taxes and forced contribution in exchange for promoting &quot;kabu nakama,&quot; doing reclamation works of Inba-numa Lake and Tega-numa Lake with merchants&apos; funds, and promoting trade with foreign countries at Nagasaki - particularly through production increase of goods for export, including &quot;tawara mono&quot; (goods in straw bags), thereby succeeding in reconstruction of bakufu finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He aggressively pushed forward his reforms, such as collecting business taxes and forced contribution in exchange for promoting &quot;kabu nakama,&quot; doing reclamation works of Inba-numa Lake and Tega-numa Lake with merchants&apos; funds, and promoting trade with foreign countries at Nagasaki - particularly through production increase of goods for export, including &quot;tawara mono&quot; (goods in straw bags), thereby succeeding in reconstruction of bakufu finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また、蘭学の奨励、工藤平助らの提案による蝦夷地調査、アイヌを通じた対ロシア帝国交易の模索など、海外政策の改革も行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also implemented foreign policy reforms, such as promoting Western learning, surveying &quot;Ezochi&quot; (the Ainu-dwelling area in Matsumae Domain) proposed by Heisuke KUDO and others, and seeking trade with the Russian Empire via the Ainu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also implemented foreign policy reforms, such as promoting Western learning, surveying &quot;Ezochi&quot; (the Ainu-dwelling area in the Matsumae Domain) proposed by Heisuke KUDO and others, and seeking trade with the Russian Empire via the Ainu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Matsumae Domain&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also implemented foreign policy reforms, such as promoting Western learning, surveying &quot;Ezochi&quot; (the Ainu-dwelling area in the Matsumae Domain) proposed by Heisuke KUDO and others, and seeking trade with the Russian Empire via the Ainu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>その一方で、重商主義から来る金銭崇拝的傾向が瀰漫し、賄賂政治が横行したとされ、また幕府伝統の重農主義を重んずる松平定信ら譜代大名から反撥されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, his mercantilism is said to have caused prevalence of mammonism and graft, and this began to meet a resentment of &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; including Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, who put a high value on physiocracy that Edo bakufu conventionally had taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, his mercantilism is said to have caused prevalence of mammonism and graft, and this began to meet a resentment of &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; including Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, who put a high value on physiocracy that the Edo bakufu conventionally had taken.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, his mercantilism is said to have caused prevalence of mammonism and graft, and this began to meet a resentment of &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; including Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA, who put a high value on physiocracy that the Edo bakufu conventionally had taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>子の田沼意知暗殺や印旛沼干拓事業の失敗、浅間山の噴火・天明の大飢饉発生および後ろ盾であった将軍家治の死などの不運が重なったことにより、田沼が失脚したことで田沼政治は終局する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Okitsugu repeatedly met with misfortunes, such as the assassination of his son Okitomo TANUMA, failure of the reclamation work of Inba-numa Lake, eruption of Mt. Asama, the Tenmei Famine, and the death of the shogun Ieharu who supported Okitsugu, so he lost his position and his politics came to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Okitsugu repeatedly met with misfortunes, such as the assassination of his son Okitomo TANUMA, failure of the reclamation work of Inba-numa Lake, eruption of Mt. Asama, the Tenmei Famine, and the death of the Shogun Ieharu who supported Okitsugu, so he lost his position and his politics came to an end.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Okitsugu repeatedly met with misfortunes, such as the assassination of his son Okitomo TANUMA, failure of the reclamation work of Inba-numa Lake, eruption of Mt. Asama, the Tenmei Famine, and the death of the Shogun Ieharu who supported Okitsugu, so he lost his position and his politics came to an end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>しかし、この一連の田沼による改革は、いわゆる三大改革に勝るとも劣らぬ重要な意義をもった改革であったといえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, a series of reforms implemented by Okitsugu can be said to have been no less important than so-called Three Big Reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a series of reforms implemented by Okitsugu can be said to have been no less important than so-called Three Big Reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a series of reforms implemented by Okitsugu can be said to have been no less important than so-called Three Big Reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>寛政の改革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansei Reforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansei Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansei Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>11代将軍となった徳川家斉の初期を補佐した老中が松平定信である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA who aided the 11th shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA in its early reign as &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA who aided the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA in its early reign as &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Sadanobu MATSUDAIRA who aided the 11th Shogun Ienari TOKUGAWA in its early reign as &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>彼は田沼時代の弛緩した雰囲気を粛正すべく寛政の改革をスタートすることとなった（1787年 - 1793年、さらに1817年まで寛政の遺老によって政策は継続）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He implemented Kansei Reforms (from A.D. 1787 to 1793) to tighten the loose atmosphere in the Tanuma age, and his policies were continued by his Kansei senior vassals until 1817.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He implemented Kansei Reforms (from 1787 to 1793) to tighten the loose atmosphere in the Tanuma period, and his policies were continued by his Kansei senior vassals until 1817.</e>
<cmt>特に指示がないので年号の A.D. は削除しました。用語集の登録訳語に合わせて、Tanuma age→Tanuma period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He implemented Kansei Reforms (from 1787 to 1793) to tighten the loose atmosphere in the Tanuma period, and his policies were continued by his Kansei senior vassals until 1817.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>定信は将軍吉宗の孫にあたり、吉宗の改革を理想としたため、田沼時代のインフレを収めるため、質素倹約・風紀取り締まりを進め、超緊縮財政で臨んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadanobu, the grandson of the eighth shogun Yoshimune, regarded Yoshimune&apos;s reforms as ideal ones, so he encouraged frugality, watched over public morals, and drew up an extremely reduced budget in order to put an end to inflation from the Tanuma age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadanobu, the grandson of the eighth Shogun Yoshimune, regarded Yoshimune&apos;s reforms as ideal ones, so he encouraged frugality, watched over public morals, and drew up an extremely reduced budget in order to put an end to inflation from the Tanuma period.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。用語集の登録訳語に合わせて、Tanuma age→Tanuma period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadanobu, the grandson of the eighth Shogun Yoshimune, regarded Yoshimune&apos;s reforms as ideal ones, so he encouraged frugality, watched over public morals, and drew up an extremely reduced budget in order to put an end to inflation from the Tanuma period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この改革の性格は田沼時代の全否定である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In nature, Sadanobu&apos;s reforms were the complete denial of the Tanuma age.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In nature, Sadanobu&apos;s reforms were the complete denial of the Tanuma period.</e>
<cmt>用語集の登録訳語に合わせて、Tanuma age→Tanuma period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In nature, Sadanobu&apos;s reforms were the complete denial of the Tanuma period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>すなわち重商主義政策は抑えられ株仲間は解散を命じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So he reversed Tanuma&apos;s mercantilistic policy, which is exemplified by his order of disbandment of &quot;kabu nakama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So he reversed Tanuma&apos;s mercantilistic policy, which is exemplified by his order of disbandment of &quot;kabu nakama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So he reversed Tanuma&apos;s mercantilistic policy, which is exemplified by his order of disbandment of &quot;kabu nakama.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>他方大名に囲米を義務づけ、江戸へ流入した百姓を出身地へ強制的に帰還させ（旧里帰農令）、また棄捐令を発して旗本・御家人らの救済を図るなど、保守的な傾向が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he implemented various conservative policies, such as compelling &quot;daimyo&quot; to take &quot;kakoimai&quot; (rice storage system in case of emergency), issuing &quot;Kyurikino-rei&quot; (the decree that forced peasants flowing into Edo to return to their hometowns) and &quot;Kien-rei&quot; (the decree to relieve &apos;hatamoto&apos; and &apos;gokenin&apos; [an immediate vassal of the shogunate] from their economic difficulties).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he implemented various conservative policies, such as compelling &quot;daimyo&quot; to take &quot;kakoimai&quot; (rice storage system in case of emergency), issuing &quot;Kyurikino-rei&quot; (the decree that forced peasants flowing into Edo to return to their hometowns) and &quot;Kien-rei&quot; (the decree to relieve &apos;hatamoto&apos; and &apos;gokenin&apos; [an immediate vassal of the shogunate] from their economic difficulties).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he implemented various conservative policies, such as compelling &quot;daimyo&quot; to take &quot;kakoimai&quot; (rice storage system in case of emergency), issuing &quot;Kyurikino-rei&quot; (the decree that forced peasants flowing into Edo to return to their hometowns) and &quot;Kien-rei&quot; (the decree to relieve &apos;hatamoto&apos; and &apos;gokenin&apos; [an immediate vassal of the shogunate] from their economic difficulties).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また蘭学を再び厳しく取り締まり、出版統制や風紀粛正を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, he restarted cracking down on Western learning, put the publication of books under his control, and tightened public morals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, he restarted cracking down on Western learning, put the publication of books under his control, and tightened public morals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, he restarted cracking down on Western learning, put the publication of books under his control, and tightened public morals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>また学問分野では寛政異学の禁で朱子学を公式の学問とし、林家の私塾であった昌平坂学問所（昌平黌）を官立とするなど文武の奨励を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the academic field, he issued &quot;Kansei Igaku no Kin&quot; (Prohibition of heterodoxies in the Kansei era) and authorized &quot;Shushigaku&quot; (Neo-Confucianism) as the official study, nationalized &quot;Shoheizaka Gakumonsho&quot; (or called &apos;Shoheiko,&apos; which had been the private school of Hayashi family), and took other measures to encourage literary and military arts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the academic field, he issued &quot;Kansei Igaku no Kin&quot; (Prohibition of heterodoxies in the Kansei era) and authorized &quot;Shushigaku&quot; (Neo-Confucianism) as the official study, nationalized &quot;Shoheizaka Gakumonsho&quot; (or called &apos;Shoheiko,&apos; which had been the private school of the Hayashi family), and took other measures to encourage literary and military arts.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Hayashi family&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the academic field, he issued &quot;Kansei Igaku no Kin&quot; (Prohibition of heterodoxies in the Kansei era) and authorized &quot;Shushigaku&quot; (Neo-Confucianism) as the official study, nationalized &quot;Shoheizaka Gakumonsho&quot; (or called &apos;Shoheiko,&apos; which had been the private school of the Hayashi family), and took other measures to encourage literary and military arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>対外対策では、林子平の蝦夷地対策を発禁処分として処罰し、漂流者大黒屋光太夫を届けたロシアのアダム・ラクスマンに対し交易を完全に拒絶するなど、強硬姿勢で臨んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the field of foreign policy, he was a hawk, for he prohibited the sale of books written by Shihei HAYASHI about the need to protect &quot;Ezochi&quot; from the Russian Empire and punished Shihei, and bluntly rejected the request for trade of Adam Kirillovich Laksman, the Russian who saw Kodayu DAIKOKUYA - Kodayu had been drifted away to Russia by accident - back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>（注）原文1行目の「蝦夷地対策を」の後に「論じた本を」と補って訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the field of foreign policy, he was a hawk, for he prohibited the sale of books written by Shihei HAYASHI about the need to protect &quot;Ezochi&quot; from the Russian Empire and punished Shihei, and bluntly rejected the request for trade of Adam Kirillovich Laksman, the Russian who saw Kodayu DAIKOKUYA - Kodayu had been drifted away to Russia by accident - back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the field of foreign policy, he was a hawk, for he prohibited the sale of books written by Shihei HAYASHI about the need to protect &quot;Ezochi&quot; from the Russian Empire and punished Shihei, and bluntly rejected the request for trade of Adam Kirillovich Laksman, the Russian who saw Kodayu DAIKOKUYA - Kodayu had been drifted away to Russia by accident - back to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>都市政策としては先述の旧里帰農令に加え、人足寄場の設置などを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the field of urban renewal, he issued the above-mentioned &quot;Kyurikino-rei,&quot; established &quot;Ninsoku Yoseba&quot; (the facilities to support self-sustenance of a criminal of a minor offence or a person likely to commit a crime), and took other measures as well.</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・「人足寄場」については「軽罪人あるいは虞犯者の自立支援施設」と解説しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the field of urban renewal, he issued the above-mentioned &quot;Kyurikino-rei,&quot; established &quot;Ninsoku Yoseba&quot; (the facilities to support self-sustenance of a criminal of a minor offence or a person likely to commit a crime), and took other measures as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the field of urban renewal, he issued the above-mentioned &quot;Kyurikino-rei,&quot; established &quot;Ninsoku Yoseba&quot; (the facilities to support self-sustenance of a criminal of a minor offence or a person likely to commit a crime), and took other measures as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>全体として町人・百姓に厳しく、武士を優遇する改革でもあり、人心は定信の理想についていけないままであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But people could not catch up with the Sadanobu&apos;s high ideal, partly because his reforms as a whole favored samurai while being strict on merchants and peasants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But people could not catch up with the Sadanobu&apos;s high ideal, partly because his reforms as a whole favored samurai while being strict on merchants and peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But people could not catch up with the Sadanobu&apos;s high ideal, partly because his reforms as a whole favored samurai while being strict on merchants and peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また重商主義政策の放棄により、田沼時代に健全化した財政は再び悪化に転じ、もはや倹約令ごときでは回復不能であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And his abandonment of mercantilistic policy turned bakufu finance, which had been healthy in the Tanuma age, for the worse once again, and the finance was degraded to the level that was not reversible merely by a sumptuary decree or the like.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And his abandonment of mercantilistic policy turned bakufu finance, which had been healthy in the Tanuma period, for the worse once again, and the finance was degraded to the level that was not reversible merely by a sumptuary decree or the like.</e>
<cmt>用語集の登録訳語に合わせて、Tanuma age→Tanuma period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And his abandonment of mercantilistic policy turned bakufu finance, which had been healthy in the Tanuma period, for the worse once again, and the finance was degraded to the level that was not reversible merely by a sumptuary decree or the like.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>結局、改革も人心収攬に失敗し、また尊号一件などにより家斉の不興を買ったことで、定信は改革わずか6年目にして失脚して老中を辞任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, his reforms failed to win the hearts of the people, and also earned Ienari&apos;s displeasure in &quot;Songo ikken&quot; (Songo Incident) and others, so he resigned &quot;roju&quot; after only six years from the start of his reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, his reforms failed to win the hearts of the people, and also earned Ienari&apos;s displeasure in &quot;Songo ikken&quot; (Songo Incident) and others, so he resigned &quot;roju&quot; after only six years from the start of his reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, his reforms failed to win the hearts of the people, and also earned Ienari&apos;s displeasure in &quot;Songo ikken&quot; (Songo Incident) and others, so he resigned &quot;roju&quot; after only six years from the start of his reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ただしその後継としては、松平定信派の松平信明 (三河吉田藩主)が老中首座となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Nobuaki MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of Mikawa Yoshida Domain), who took the side of Sadanobu in Edo bakufu, succeeded Sadanobu as chief &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Nobuaki MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Mikawa Yoshida Domain), who took the side of Sadanobu in the Edo bakufu, succeeded Sadanobu as chief &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mikawa Yoshida Domain&quot; と &quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Nobuaki MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Mikawa Yoshida Domain), who took the side of Sadanobu in the Edo bakufu, succeeded Sadanobu as chief &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>信明をはじめ戸田氏教、本多忠籌ら定信が登用した老中たちが幕政を主導することになり、これを「寛政の遺老」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu politics became led by Nobuaki and other &quot;roju&quot; promoted by Sadanobu (such as Ujinori TODA and Tadakazu HONDA), who are called &quot;Kansei senior vassals.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu politics became led by Nobuaki and other &quot;roju&quot; promoted by Sadanobu (such as Ujinori TODA and Tadakazu HONDA), who are called &quot;Kansei senior vassals.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu politics became led by Nobuaki and other &quot;roju&quot; promoted by Sadanobu (such as Ujinori TODA and Tadakazu HONDA), who are called &quot;Kansei senior vassals.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これによって寛政の改革の政策は実質的に継続することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kansei Reforms were substantially continued by these people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kansei Reforms were substantially continued by these people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kansei Reforms were substantially continued by these people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>しかし1817年に信明が死去すると、これに前後して他の遺老たちも引退してこの政権も終焉を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Nobuaki died in A.D. 1817, and other vassals retired around then, which put an end to the reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Nobuaki died in 1817, and other vassals retired around then, which put an end to the reforms.</e>
<cmt>特に指示がないので、年号から　A.D. を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Nobuaki died in 1817, and other vassals retired around then, which put an end to the reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>天保の改革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpo Reforms</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenpo Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpo Reforms</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>松平信明が死去すると将軍家斉（のち隠居して大御所）が自ら政権の表に立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Nobuaki MATSUDAIRA died, Ienari himself came to the center stage of the administration as a shogun (and later, as an &quot;ogosho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Nobuaki MATSUDAIRA died, Ienari himself came to the center stage of the administration as a shogun (and later, as an &quot;ogosho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Nobuaki MATSUDAIRA died, Ienari himself came to the center stage of the administration as a shogun (and later, as an &quot;ogosho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>ただし実際には、側近である老中水野忠成が幕政を壟断し、田沼時代を上回る空前の賄賂政治が横行した（→大御所時代）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in reality, his aide Tadaakira MIZUNO, who assumed &quot;roju,&quot; monopolized bakufu politics, so graft became rampant more than any other time, let alone in the Tanuma age (cf. the section of &quot;Ogosho age&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in reality, his aide Tadaakira MIZUNO, who assumed &quot;roju,&quot; monopolized bakufu politics, so graft became rampant more than any other time, let alone in the Tanuma period (cf. the section of &quot;Ogosho period&quot;).</e>
<cmt>用語集の登録に合わせて、age→period に修正しました。&quot;Ogosho period&quot; の部分はリンクになっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in reality, his aide Tadaakira MIZUNO, who assumed &quot;roju,&quot; monopolized bakufu politics, so graft became rampant more than any other time, let alone in the Tanuma period (cf. the section of &quot;Ogosho period&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>その水野忠成が死し、大御所家斉も没した後、12代徳川家慶が幕政改革に意欲を見せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadaakira MIZUNO and Ogosho Ienari died, the 12th shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA became keen on the reforms of bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadaakira MIZUNO and Ogosho Ienari died, the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA became keen on the reforms of bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadaakira MIZUNO and Ogosho Ienari died, the 12th Shogun Ieyoshi TOKUGAWA became keen on the reforms of bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>老中として改革を主導したのは忠成の同族の水野忠邦であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was Tadakuni MIZUNO, who belonged to the same family as Tadaakira, that led the reforms as &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it was Tadakuni MIZUNO, who belonged to the same family as Tadaakira, that led the reforms as &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it was Tadakuni MIZUNO, who belonged to the same family as Tadaakira, that led the reforms as &quot;roju.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>忠邦が主導した諸改革を天保の改革と呼ぶ（1841年 - 1843年）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reforms led by Tadakuni is called Tenpo Reforms (from A.D. 1841 to 1843).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reforms led by Tadakuni is called Tenpo Reforms (from 1841 to 1843).</e>
<cmt>特に指示がないので、A.D. 部分を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reforms led by Tadakuni is called Tenpo Reforms (from 1841 to 1843).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>江川英龍（英龍）・遠山景元・鳥居耀蔵（燿蔵）ら実務派の官僚が採用されたが、内容自体は田沼時代を受けた寛政の改革の再来ともいえ、新味は無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakuni promoted practical bureaucrats, such as Hidetatsu EGAWA, Kagemoto TOYAMA, and Yozo TORII, but the very contents of the reforms could be said just the revival of Kansei Reforms after the Tanuma age, so they lacked novelty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakuni promoted practical bureaucrats, such as Hidetatsu EGAWA, Kagemoto TOYAMA, and Yozo TORII, but the very contents of the reforms could be said just the revival of Kansei Reforms after the Tanuma period, so they lacked novelty.</e>
<cmt>用語集の登録訳語に合わせて、Tanuma age→Tanuma period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakuni promoted practical bureaucrats, such as Hidetatsu EGAWA, Kagemoto TOYAMA, and Yozo TORII, but the very contents of the reforms could be said just the revival of Kansei Reforms after the Tanuma period, so they lacked novelty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>主な改革としては、綱紀粛正・倹約令徹底による消費の抑制、人返し令による都市住民の農村への帰還、株仲間の解散令、棄捐令などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadakuni&apos;s major reforms were, for example, control of people&apos;s consumption through tightening public morals and implementing a sumptuary decree strictly, issuance of &quot;Hitogaeshi-rei&quot; (the decree to force peasants dwelling in urban areas to return to their hometowns), an order on &quot;kabu nakama&quot; to disband itself, and issuance of &quot;Kien-rei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadakuni&apos;s major reforms were, for example, control of people&apos;s consumption through tightening public morals and implementing a sumptuary decree strictly, issuance of &quot;Hitogaeshi-rei&quot; (the decree to force peasants dwelling in urban areas to return to their hometowns), an order on &quot;kabu nakama&quot; to disband itself, and issuance of &quot;Kien-rei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadakuni&apos;s major reforms were, for example, control of people&apos;s consumption through tightening public morals and implementing a sumptuary decree strictly, issuance of &quot;Hitogaeshi-rei&quot; (the decree to force peasants dwelling in urban areas to return to their hometowns), an order on &quot;kabu nakama&quot; to disband itself, and issuance of &quot;Kien-rei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>また対外政策では、大御所時代に出された異国船打払令を改め、無用の戦を避けるため薪水給与令が出され、江川や高島秋帆による西洋砲術導入による国防策も図られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In foreign policy, he revised the decree issued in Ogosho age which ordered expelling foreign vessels, newly issued the decree that permitted providing foreign vessels with fuel and water in order to avoid an unnecessary war, and tried to build national defense by having Egawa and Shuhan TAKASHIMA introduce Western artillery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In foreign policy, he revised the decree issued in Ogosho period which ordered expelling foreign vessels, newly issued the decree that permitted providing foreign vessels with fuel and water in order to avoid an unnecessary war, and tried to build national defense by having Egawa and Shuhan TAKASHIMA introduce Western artillery.</e>
<cmt>用語集の登録に合わせて、age→period に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In foreign policy, he revised the decree issued in Ogosho period which ordered expelling foreign vessels, newly issued the decree that permitted providing foreign vessels with fuel and water in order to avoid an unnecessary war, and tried to build national defense by having Egawa and Shuhan TAKASHIMA introduce Western artillery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>背景には同時期に清国で勃発した阿片戦争による危機感があったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the background of his foreign policy, there seems to have been a sense of crisis aroused by Opium Wars (waged and won by Britain, and after this China became like a colony of Western countries) that broke out in Qing dynasty China around then.</e>
<cmt>（注）なぜ忠邦が危機感を抱いたのかが伝わるよう、「阿片戦争」につき「イギリスが仕掛け勝ちを収めた戦争で、これ以降中国は西洋諸国の植民地のようになる」と補っています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the background of his foreign policy, there seems to have been a sense of crisis aroused by Opium Wars (waged and won by Britain, and after this China became like a colony of Western countries) that broke out in Qing dynasty China around then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the background of his foreign policy, there seems to have been a sense of crisis aroused by Opium Wars (waged and won by Britain, and after this China became like a colony of Western countries) that broke out in Qing dynasty China around then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>ただし、水野の腹心・鳥居燿蔵は蘭学を嫌い、蛮社の獄を起こした人物でもあり、政権内で不協和音となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Yozo TORII, the vassal trusted most by Mizuno, hated Western learning and carried out &quot;Bansha no Goku&quot; (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning), which caused discord within the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Yozo TORII, the vassal trusted most by Mizuno, hated Western learning and carried out &quot;Bansha no Goku&quot; (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning), which caused discord within the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Yozo TORII, the vassal trusted most by Mizuno, hated Western learning and carried out &quot;Bansha no Goku&quot; (Imprisonment of scholars of Western learning), which caused discord within the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>数々の改革も財政の健全化には結びつかず、また倹約令の徹底によって庶民の恨みも買ったことから、水野の求心力は急速に低下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A number of reforms did not lead to healthy finance, and strict implementation of a sumptuary decree earned the public resentment, so the moving force of the reforms declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A number of reforms did not lead to healthy finance, and strict implementation of a sumptuary decree earned the public resentment, so the moving force of the reforms declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A number of reforms did not lead to healthy finance, and strict implementation of a sumptuary decree earned the public resentment, so the moving force of the reforms declined rapidly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>また、国防上の必要性から江戸・大坂の大名・旗本領を幕府に召し上げようとする上知令を推進しようとしたところ、大名・商人らの猛反撥を招くこととなり、将軍家慶自ら撤回を命ずる事態となり、水野は失脚し、天保の改革はわずか2年にして崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Agechi-rei&quot; (the decree he was going to implement for national defense, whose contents were to take away the territory of &apos;daimyo&apos; and &apos;hatamoto&apos; in Edo and Osaka) caused fierce resistance of &quot;daimyo&quot; and merchants, so Shogun Ieyoshi himself was made withdraw the decree and Mizuno lost his position, when Tenpo Reforms ended with a span of just two years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &quot;Agechi-rei&quot; (the decree he was going to implement for national defense, whose contents were to take away the territory of &apos;daimyo&apos; and &apos;hatamoto&apos; in Edo and Osaka) caused fierce resistance of &quot;daimyo&quot; and merchants, so Shogun Ieyoshi himself was made withdraw the decree and Mizuno lost his position, when Tenpo Reforms ended with a span of just two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Agechi-rei&quot; (the decree he was going to implement for national defense, whose contents were to take away the territory of &apos;daimyo&apos; and &apos;hatamoto&apos; in Edo and Osaka) caused fierce resistance of &quot;daimyo&quot; and merchants, so Shogun Ieyoshi himself was made withdraw the decree and Mizuno lost his position, when Tenpo Reforms ended with a span of just two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>翌年、対外政策の紛糾により、再度老中に任命されたものの、相変わらず幕閣・大名の不信は強く、1年にして辞任に追い込まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, the complication of foreign policy pushed him up to &quot;roju&quot; once again, but the distrust toward him from the cabinet officials of the shogunate and from &quot;daimyo&quot; was so strong that he was forced to resign in a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, the complication of foreign policy pushed him up to &quot;roju&quot; once again, but the distrust toward him from the cabinet officials of the shogunate and from &quot;daimyo&quot; was so strong that he was forced to resign in a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, the complication of foreign policy pushed him up to &quot;roju&quot; once again, but the distrust toward him from the cabinet officials of the shogunate and from &quot;daimyo&quot; was so strong that he was forced to resign in a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>幕末の改革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reforms in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reforms in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reforms in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>天保の改革が失敗に終わったことにより、幕府は財政・体制ともに壊滅的危機を迎える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Failure of Tenpo Reforms drove Edo bakufu on the verge of collapse in both finance and regime itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Failure of Tenpo Reforms drove the Edo bakufu on the verge of collapse in both finance and regime itself.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Failure of Tenpo Reforms drove the Edo bakufu on the verge of collapse in both finance and regime itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>また、諸外国からの開国要求も盛んとなっていったため、対外政策に関しても改革を行う必要が叫ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the West frequently requested Japan to open itself, so reforms in foreign policy were called for.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the West frequently requested Japan to open itself, so reforms in foreign policy were called for.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the West frequently requested Japan to open itself, so reforms in foreign policy were called for.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>水野忠邦失脚後の政局は土井利位、ついで阿部正弘が担うことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Tadakuni MIZUNO lost his position, it was Toshitsura DOI, and then Masahiro ABE, who shouldered politics of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Tadakuni MIZUNO lost his position, it was Toshitsura DOI, and then Masahiro ABE, who shouldered politics of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Tadakuni MIZUNO lost his position, it was Toshitsura DOI, and then Masahiro ABE, who shouldered politics of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="71">
<j>嘉永6年（1853年）にマシュー・ペリー艦隊が来航した直後、将軍家慶が死去し、病弱な13代徳川家定が後を嗣ぎ、翌年の日米和親条約締結に伴う政治的混乱の中で、阿部主導による安政の改革が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun Ieyoshi died soon after the fleet of Commodore Matthew Perry came to Japan in A.D. 1853, and Ieyoshi&apos;s successor Iesada TOKUGAWA (the 13th shogun) was sickly, so Abe led Ansei Reforms in the midst of political confusion that resulted from conclusion of the Japan-US Amity Treaty in the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun Ieyoshi died soon after the fleet of Commodore Matthew Perry came to Japan in 1853, and Ieyoshi&apos;s successor Iesada TOKUGAWA (the 13th Shogun) was sickly, so Abe led Ansei Reforms in the midst of political confusion that resulted from conclusion of Treaty of Peace and Amity between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan in the next year.</e>
<cmt>日米和親条約の訳を用語集に登録されているものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun Ieyoshi died soon after the fleet of Commodore Matthew Perry came to Japan in 1853, and Ieyoshi&apos;s successor Iesada TOKUGAWA (the 13th Shogun) was sickly, so Abe led Ansei Reforms in the midst of political confusion that resulted from conclusion of Treaty of Peace and Amity between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan in the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>阿部は外様大名（薩摩藩の島津斉彬）や親藩・御三家（越前藩の松平慶永や水戸藩の徳川斉昭など）の幕政への参入を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abe opened politics of Edo bakufu to &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; (a &apos;daimyo&apos; who was not a hereditary vassal of Tokugawa family), such as Nariakira SHIMAZU (the feudal lord of Satsuma Domain), to &quot;daimyo&quot; of &quot;shinpan&quot; (relatives of Tokugawa family), such as Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of Echizen Domain), and to &quot;daimyo&quot; of &quot;gosanke&quot; (three privileged branches of Tokugawa family), such as Nariaki TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abe opened politics of the Edo bakufu to &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; (a &apos;daimyo&apos; who was not a hereditary vassal of the Tokugawa family), such as Nariakira SHIMAZU (the feudal lord of the Satsuma Domain), to &quot;daimyo&quot; of &quot;shinpan&quot; (relatives of the Tokugawa family), such as Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Echizen Domain), and to &quot;daimyo&quot; of &quot;gosanke&quot; (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family), such as Nariaki TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot;、藩の名前、&quot;Tokugawa family&quot; にそれぞれ定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abe opened politics of the Edo bakufu to &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; (a &apos;daimyo&apos; who was not a hereditary vassal of the Tokugawa family), such as Nariakira SHIMAZU (the feudal lord of the Satsuma Domain), to &quot;daimyo&quot; of &quot;shinpan&quot; (relatives of the Tokugawa family), such as Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA (the feudal lord of the Echizen Domain), and to &quot;daimyo&quot; of &quot;gosanke&quot; (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family), such as Nariaki TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また長崎の海軍伝習所の設置なども行ったが、阿部は安政4年（1857年）、39の若さで死去してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abe also established Japanese Naval School in Nagasaki, but he died as young as the age of 39 in A.D. 1857.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Abe also established Japanese Naval School in Nagasaki, but he died as young as the age of 39 in 1857.</e>
<cmt>年号から A.D. を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abe also established Japanese Naval School in Nagasaki, but he died as young as the age of 39 in 1857.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="74">
<j>阿部死後は堀田正睦が改革を主導する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Abe died, Masayoshi HOTTA led the reforms of bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Abe died, Masayoshi HOTTA led the reforms of bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Abe died, Masayoshi HOTTA led the reforms of bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>だが条約勅許をめぐる朝廷との対立や、病弱な将軍の後継を巡る一橋派（徳川慶喜・後の15代を推す勢力）と南紀派（徳川家茂・後の14代を推す勢力）との対立、また外様や御三家の幕政介入に反撥した譜代大名の筆頭井伊直弼が大老に就任したことにより改革は挫折した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But his reforms suffered setbacks, such as a conflict between bakufu and Imperial Court over Imperial permission to the treaty concluded with US, a conflict within bakufu over the successor to the sickly shogun between &quot;Hitotsubashi group&quot; (the group that recommended Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA [later, the 15th shogun]) and &quot;Nanki group&quot; (the group that recommended Iemochi TOKUGAWA [later, the 14th shogun]), and Naosuke II&apos;s assumption of &quot;Tairo&quot; (Chief Minister of bakufu) - Naosuke II was at the top of &quot;fudai daimyo&quot; and was against the participation of &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; and &quot;gosanke&quot; in bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But his reforms suffered setbacks, such as a conflict between bakufu and Imperial Court over Imperial permission to the treaty concluded with US, a conflict within bakufu over the successor to the sickly shogun between &quot;Hitotsubashi group&quot; (the group that recommended Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA [later, the 15th Shogun]) and &quot;Nanki group&quot; (the group that recommended Iemochi TOKUGAWA [later, the 14th Shogun]), and Naosuke Ii&apos;s assumption of &quot;Tairo&quot; (Chief Minister of bakufu) - Naosuke Ii was at the top of &quot;fudai daimyo&quot; and was against the participation of &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; and &quot;gosanke&quot; in bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>用語統一シートの指示に従い、「将軍」はタイトルであるため、S を大文字にしました。Naosuke II→Naosuke Ii (2 箇所) に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But his reforms suffered setbacks, such as a conflict between bakufu and Imperial Court over Imperial permission to the treaty concluded with US, a conflict within bakufu over the successor to the sickly shogun between &quot;Hitotsubashi group&quot; (the group that recommended Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA [later, the 15th Shogun]) and &quot;Nanki group&quot; (the group that recommended Iemochi TOKUGAWA [later, the 14th Shogun]), and Naosuke Ii&apos;s assumption of &quot;Tairo&quot; (Chief Minister of bakufu) - Naosuke Ii was at the top of &quot;fudai daimyo&quot; and was against the participation of &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; and &quot;gosanke&quot; in bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>そして反動的に井伊による安政の大獄を招くこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Hotta&apos;s reforms caused Ii&apos;s &quot;Ansei no Taigoku&quot; (the Ansei Purge) as a reaction.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Hotta&apos;s reforms caused Ii&apos;s &quot;Ansei no Taigoku&quot; (the Ansei Purge) as a reaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Hotta&apos;s reforms caused Ii&apos;s &quot;Ansei no Taigoku&quot; (the Ansei Purge) as a reaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>しかし井伊は桜田門外の変で暗殺され、老中久世広周・安藤信正らに主導権は移る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ii was assassinated in the Sakurada Mongai Incident, and then it was Hirochika KUZE, Nobumasa ANDO and other &quot;roju&quot; who took the lead in bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ii was assassinated in the Sakurada Mongai Incident, and then it was Hirochika KUZE, Nobumasa ANDO and other &quot;roju&quot; who took the lead in bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ii was assassinated in the Sakurada Mongai Incident, and then it was Hirochika KUZE, Nobumasa ANDO and other &quot;roju&quot; who took the lead in bakufu politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>幕府権威の低下を防ぐため、安藤らは将軍徳川家茂と皇女和宮の婚姻で公武合体による幕権強化策を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To prevent bakufu authority from declining, Ando and others tried &quot;kobu-gattai&quot; (integration of the Imperial Court and the shogunate) through the marriage of Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA and Imperial Princess Kazunomiya.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To prevent bakufu authority from declining, Ando and others tried &quot;kobu-gattai&quot; (integration of the Imperial Court and the shogunate) through the marriage of Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA and Imperial Princess Kazunomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To prevent bakufu authority from declining, Ando and others tried &quot;kobu-gattai&quot; (integration of the Imperial Court and the shogunate) through the marriage of Shogun Iemochi TOKUGAWA and Imperial Princess Kazunomiya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>だが折から澎湃として沸き起こった尊王攘夷運動の志士たちから反撥を受け、坂下門外の変により安藤が失脚、公武合体は頓挫する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, royalists in the movement of &quot;Sonno Joi&quot; (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), which was then rising like a flood tide, went against &quot;kobu-gattai,&quot; and some of them attacked Ando in the Sakashita Mongai Incident, so Ando lost his position and &quot;kobu-gattai&quot; came to a sudden stop.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, royalists in the movement of &quot;Sonno Joi&quot; (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), which was then rising like a flood tide, went against &quot;kobu-gattai,&quot; and some of them attacked Ando in the Sakashita Mongai Incident, so Ando lost his position and &quot;kobu-gattai&quot; came to a sudden stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, royalists in the movement of &quot;Sonno Joi&quot; (19th century slogan advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners), which was then rising like a flood tide, went against &quot;kobu-gattai,&quot; and some of them attacked Ando in the Sakashita Mongai Incident, so Ando lost his position and &quot;kobu-gattai&quot; came to a sudden stop.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>もはや幕政の混乱、幕府権威の低下は誰の目にも明らかであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Now confusion of bakufu politics and decline of its authority became obvious to anybody.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Now confusion of bakufu politics and decline of its authority became obvious to anybody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Now confusion of bakufu politics and decline of its authority became obvious to anybody.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="81">
<j>そんな中、文久2年（1862年）薩摩藩主の父島津久光が朝廷を動かして勅使（大原重徳）を出させ、幕府に改革を迫るという事態が発生する（→文久の改革）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the circumstances, Hisamitsu SHIMAZU (the father of the feudal lord of Satsuma Domain) moved Imperial Court to send a messenger (Shigetomi OHARA), who urged Edo bakufu to implement reforms (cf. Bunkyu Reforms).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the circumstances, Hisamitsu SHIMAZU (the father of the feudal lord of the Satsuma Domain) moved Imperial Court to send a messenger (Shigetomi OHARA), who urged the Edo bakufu to implement reforms (cf. Bunkyu Reform).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Satsuma Domain&quot; &quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。リンク先のタイトルに合わせて、&quot;Bunkyu Reforms&quot;→&quot;Bunkyu Reform&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the circumstances, Hisamitsu SHIMAZU (the father of the feudal lord of the Satsuma Domain) moved Imperial Court to send a messenger (Shigetomi OHARA), who urged the Edo bakufu to implement reforms (cf. Bunkyu Reform).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>政事総裁職（松平慶永）・将軍後見職（徳川慶喜）・京都守護職（会津藩主松平容保）などが新設される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, Edo bakufu newly established some positions, such as &quot;Seiji-sosaishoku&quot; (Chief Administrative Officer, assumed by Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA), &quot;Shogun-kokenshoku&quot; (Guardian of Shogun, assumed by Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA), and &quot;Kyoto-shugoshoku&quot; (Military Governor of Kyoto, assumed by Katamori MATSUDAIRA [the feudal lord of Aizu Domain]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, Edo bakufu newly established some positions, such as &quot;Seiji-sosaishoku&quot; (Chief Administrative Officer, assumed by Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA), &quot;Shogun-kokenshoku&quot; (Guardian of Shogun, assumed by Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA), and &quot;Kyoto-shugoshoku&quot; (Military Governor of Kyoto, assumed by Katamori MATSUDAIRA [the feudal lord of the Aizu Domain]).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Aizu Domain&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Edo bakufu newly established some positions, such as &quot;Seiji-sosaishoku&quot; (Chief Administrative Officer, assumed by Yoshinaga MATSUDAIRA), &quot;Shogun-kokenshoku&quot; (Guardian of Shogun, assumed by Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA), and &quot;Kyoto-shugoshoku&quot; (Military Governor of Kyoto, assumed by Katamori MATSUDAIRA [the feudal lord of the Aizu Domain]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>しかし、外様大名や朝廷の介入による幕政改革の強制は幕府権威をいっそう低下させ、これにより幕府崩壊の方向性は決定的となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, intervention of &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; and Imperial Court in politics of Edo bakufu and their enforcement of reforms on it further decreased its authority, so its collapse became almost inevitable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, intervention of &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; and Imperial Court in politics of the Edo bakufu and their enforcement of reforms on it further decreased its authority, so its collapse became almost inevitable.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, intervention of &quot;tozama daimyo&quot; and Imperial Court in politics of the Edo bakufu and their enforcement of reforms on it further decreased its authority, so its collapse became almost inevitable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>また翌年、将軍家茂が上洛すると、幕府権力が京都と江戸で分裂することになり、京都政界を主導する徳川慶喜・松平容保らと、江戸の留守を守る譜代大名・旗本らとの亀裂も生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the next year, when Shogun Iemochi went to Kyoto, power of Edo bakufu split into two - one was in Kyoto and another was in Edo - and a discord began to be seen between political leaders in Kyoto (Yoshinobu, Katamori, and others) and those who were keeping Edo safe, such as &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; &quot;hatamoto,&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the next year, when Shogun Iemochi went to Kyoto, power of the Edo bakufu split into two - one was in Kyoto and another was in Edo - and a discord began to be seen between political leaders in Kyoto (Yoshinobu, Katamori, and others) and those who were keeping Edo safe, such as &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; &quot;hatamoto,&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the next year, when Shogun Iemochi went to Kyoto, power of the Edo bakufu split into two - one was in Kyoto and another was in Edo - and a discord began to be seen between political leaders in Kyoto (Yoshinobu, Katamori, and others) and those who were keeping Edo safe, such as &quot;fudai daimyo,&quot; &quot;hatamoto,&quot; and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="85">
<j>二度に及ぶ長州征伐が失敗に終わり、将軍家茂の病死によって慶喜が将軍となると、慶応3年（1867年）に、最後の改革となる慶応の改革が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the two Choshu Expeditions ended in failure and Shogun Iemochi died from an illness, Yoshinobu became the next shogun and implemented in A.D. 1867 Keio Reforms, the last ones in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the two Choshu Conquests ended in failure and Shogun Iemochi died from an illness, Yoshinobu became the next shogun and implemented in 1867 Keio Reforms, the last ones in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「長州征伐」の訳を、用語集に登録されているものに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the two Choshu Conquests ended in failure and Shogun Iemochi died from an illness, Yoshinobu became the next shogun and implemented in 1867 Keio Reforms, the last ones in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>これにより、陸軍・海軍・国内事務・外国事務・会計の各総裁が置かれるなど官制の変更やナポレオン3世の援助によるフランス軍制の導入が行われたが、もはや焼け石に水であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinobu changed regulations for regime organization, in which he newly established the posts of the chief of the army, navy, internal affairs, foreign affairs, and accounting, and he also introduced French military system with help of Napoleon Ⅲ, but these were just a drop in a bucket.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinobu changed regulations for regime organization, in which he newly established the posts of the chief of the army, navy, internal affairs, foreign affairs, and accounting, and he also introduced French military system with help of Napoleon Ⅲ, but these were just a drop in a bucket.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinobu changed regulations for regime organization, in which he newly established the posts of the chief of the army, navy, internal affairs, foreign affairs, and accounting, and he also introduced French military system with help of Napoleon Ⅲ, but these were just a drop in a bucket.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>同年10月、慶喜は大政奉還を行い、江戸幕府は270年に及ぶ歴史に幕を降ろした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of the year, Yoshinobu carried out &quot;Taisei Hokan&quot; (the return of political power to the Emperor), which brought the curtain down on the history of Edo bakufu that lasted as long as about 270 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November of the year, Yoshinobu carried out &quot;Taisei Hokan&quot; (the return of political power to the Emperor), which brought the curtain down on the history of the Edo bakufu that lasted as long as about 270 years.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Edo bakufu&quot; に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November of the year, Yoshinobu carried out &quot;Taisei Hokan&quot; (the return of political power to the Emperor), which brought the curtain down on the history of the Edo bakufu that lasted as long as about 270 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 目白梅(id:141468), くっちゃめ(id:86793), BitBucket(id:30999), トホホ川(id:50502), Hddsd(id:99893), Greenland4(id:114494), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>