<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>半済</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hanzei,&quot; half payment of the tax</e>
<cmt>&quot;half payment&quot; of the taxは文字通りの訳であり、定訳ではないため「はんぜい」という日本語をアルファベット表記し、その後ろに、その文字通りの訳を説明として入れるという方法が良いと判断いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hanzei&quot;, half payment of taxes</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanzei (Half Payment of Taxes)</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;削除。説明を括弧書きに、タイトルなので大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>半済（はんぜい）は、室町幕府が荘園・公領の年貢半分の徴収権を守護に認めたことを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hanzei &quot;means that the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) has given the power of collection of half of the customs or taxes on production from manors and lands under the control of the feudal government to the provincial constables.</e>
<cmt>「公領」に関しましては、「幕府・大名などの支配する土地の呼び名」ですので、「duchy」＝「公爵領、公国、英国の王族公領」という意味ですので、定訳は見つかりませんでしたが、ここでの意味に合うように用語を作成致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hanzei&quot;means that the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) gave the power of collection of half of the customs or taxes on production from manors and lands under the control of the feudal government to the provincial constables.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hanzei&quot;means that the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) gave the power of collection of half of the customs or taxes on production from manors and lands under the control of the feudal government to the provincial constables.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>半済を認める法令を半済令または半済法という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A law that ratifies &quot;Hanzei&quot; is called the hanzei law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law that ratified &quot;Hanzei&quot; is called the hanzei law.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law that ratified &quot;Hanzei&quot; is called the hanzei law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元来、半済とは「年貢の半分を納付する」という意味より百姓の年貢の半分を免除することを意味していたが、南北朝時代 (日本)頃から、守護が軍費・兵糧を現地調達するために、荘園・公領の年貢の半分を軍勢に預け置くことが、半済として行われ始め、1352年に最初の半済令が幕府から出された（なお、南北朝・室町時代においても年貢の半分免除の意味で「半済」という言葉が用いられる場合も存在しており注意を要する）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hanzei&quot; originally means &quot;paying half of the tax&quot; and thus meant, at that time, absolving peasants of half in customs or taxes; however, in about the Northern and Southern Courts Period (Japan), &quot;Hanzei&quot; was used to mean that half of the customs or taxes on the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government were deposited in the troops in order for provincial constables to source military expenditure and provisions locally, and the first hanzei law was enforced by the feudal government in 1352 (Note that &quot;Hanzei&quot; was also used to mean absolving of half of the customs or taxes in the Northern and Southern Courts Period and the Muromachi Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hanzei&quot; originally meant &quot;paying half of the tax&quot; and thus meant, at that time, absolving peasants of half of their customs or taxes; however, in the Northern and Southern Courts Period (Japan), &quot;Hanzei&quot; was used to mean that half of the customs or taxes on the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government were submitted to the troops in order for provincial constables to cover military expenditure and provisions locally, and the first hanzei law was enforced by the feudal government in 1352 (Note that &quot;Hanzei&quot; was also used to mean absolving peasants of half of their customs or taxes in the Northern and Southern Courts Period and the Muromachi Period).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hanzei&quot; originally meant &apos;paying half of the tax&apos; and thus meant, at that time, absolving peasants of half of their customs or taxes; however, in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, &quot;Hanzei&quot; was used to mean that half of the customs or taxes on the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government were submitted to the troops in order for provincial constables to cover military expenditure and provisions locally, and the first hanzei law was enforced by the feudal government in 1352 (Note that &quot;Hanzei&quot; was also used to mean absolving peasants of half of their customs or taxes in the Northern and Southern Courts period and the Muromachi period).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。period小文字にしました。南北朝時代→the period of the Northern and Southern Courtsとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これを契機に、守護による荘園・公領への侵蝕が本格化し、守護領国制・守護大名の誕生へとつながっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the encroachment of provincial constables into the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government had been notably accelerated, resulting in advent of Shugo-ryogokusei and Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the encroachment of provincial constables into the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government accelerated notably, resulting in advent of Shugo-ryogokusei and the Shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the encroachment of provincial constables into the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government accelerated notably, resulting in advent of Shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a Shugo dominates a manor) and Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable).</e>
<cmt>守護領国制→Shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a Shugo dominates a manor)としました。守護大名→Shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>現存する最初の半済令は、1352年（観応3年/正平 (日本)7年）7月に室町幕府から発布された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest hanzei law in existence was published by the Muromachi bakufu in July 1352.</e>
<cmt>「室町幕府」は「Muromachi bakufu」の後ろに「the feudal government of Japan (1338-1573) under the Ashikaga shoguns」というような説明を入れようかとも考えましたが、余分な情報になるかとも考え、入れませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest hanzei law in existence was published by the Muromachi bakufu in July 1352.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest hanzei law in existence was published by the Muromachi bakufu in July 1352.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当時、全国的な争乱（観応の擾乱）が続いており、兵糧調達のため、激戦地であった近江国（守護：六角氏）・美濃国（守護：土岐頼康）・尾張国（守護：土岐頼康）の本所領（荘園）を対象として、その年の収穫に限り、守護に年貢半分の徴発を認めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the government allowed provincial constables to requisition half of the taxes only from the production of the year to obtain provisions in the midst of a nationwide disturbance (the Kanno Disturbance), aiming at the manors of the Province of Omi (provincial constable: Rokkaku clan), the Province of Mino (provincial constable: Yoriyasu TOKI) and the Province of Owari (provincial constable: Yoriyasu TOKI) all of which were the bloodiest battlefields in the disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the government allowed provincial constables to requisition half of the taxes from the production of the year to obtain provisions in the midst of a nationwide disturbance (the Kanno Disturbance), aiming at the manors of the Province of Omi (provincial constable: Rokkaku clan), the Province of Mino (provincial constable: Yoriyasu TOKI) and the Province of Owari (provincial constable: Yoriyasu TOKI) all of which were the bloodiest battlefields in the disturbance.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the government allowed provincial constables to requisition half of the taxes from the production of the year to obtain provisions in the midst of a nationwide disturbance (the Kanno Disturbance), aiming at the manors of the Province of Omi (provincial constable: Rokkaku clan), the Province of Mino (provincial constable: Yoriyasu TOKI) and the Province of Owari (provincial constable: Yoriyasu TOKI) all of which were the bloodiest battlefields in the disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その対象となった荘園・公領を特に「兵粮料所」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The target manors and lands under the control of the feudal government were called &quot;Hyoro-ryosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The target manors and lands under the control of the feudal government were called &quot;Hyoro-ryosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The target manors and lands under the control of the feudal government were called &quot;Hyoro-ryosho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>周辺国の守護も半済の適用を求め、翌8月には、河内国（守護：高師直）・和泉国（守護：細川氏）・伊賀国（守護：仁木義長）・伊勢国（守護：仁木義長）・志摩国（守護：仁木義長）へと半済が拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, provincial constables of neighboring provinces started seeking for the application of &quot;Hanzei,&quot; and the permission for &quot;Hanzei&quot; spread to the Province of Kawachi (provincial constable: KO no Moronao), the Province of Izumi (provincial constable: the Hosokawa clan), the Province of Iga (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI), the Province of Ise (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI) and the Province of Shima (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI) by August of the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, provincial constables of neighboring provinces started seeking approval for the application of &quot;Hanzei,&quot; and permission for &quot;Hanzei&quot; spread to the Province of Kawachi (provincial constable: KO no Moronao), the Province of Izumi (provincial constable: the Hosokawa clan), the Province of Iga (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI), the Province of Ise (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI) and the Province of Shima (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI) by August of the following year.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, provincial constables of neighboring provinces started seeking approval for the application of &quot;Hanzei,&quot; and permission for &quot;Hanzei&quot; spread to the Province of Kawachi (provincial constable: KO no Moronao), the Province of Izumi (provincial constable: the Hosokawa clan), the Province of Iga (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKI), the Province of Ise (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKKI) and the Province of Shima (provincial constable: Yoshinaga NIKI) by August of the following year.</e>
<cmt>仁木→NIKIとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>1355年（文和4年/正平10年）、幕府は半済の拡大を防ぐため、戦乱の収まった国の半済を停止するとともに、戦乱国においても、守護が年貢半分を直接徴収するのではなく、本所（荘園領主）から守護へ納入させることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1355, to prevent the spread of the hanzei law, the feudal government exempted provinces in which the disturbance had settled from its application and made the Honjo (lord of the manor) pay half of the customs or taxes to the provincial constable, instead of letting the provincial constable directly collect the customs or taxes from peasants even in the provinces in which the disturbance was still continuing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1355, to prevent the spread of the hanzei law, the feudal government exempted provinces in which the disturbance had settled from its application and made the Honjo (lord of the manor) pay half of the customs or taxes to the provincial constable, instead of letting the provincial constable directly collect the customs or taxes from peasants even in the provinces in which the disturbance was still continuing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1355, to prevent the spread of the hanzei law, the feudal government exempted provinces in which the disturbance had settled from its application and made the Honjo (lord of the manor) pay half of the customs or taxes to the provincial constable, instead of letting the provincial constable directly collect the customs or taxes from peasants even in the provinces in which the disturbance was still continuing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、守護及びその傘下武士たちは、半済を既得権として、荘園・公領へ不当な介入を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some provincial constables and their subordinate samurais treated the hanzei law as their established right and continued to intervene in the taxes on manors and lands under the control of the feudal government unreasonably.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some provincial constables and their subordinate samurais treated the hanzei law as their established right and continued to intervene in the taxes on manors and lands under the control of the feudal government unreasonably.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some provincial constables and their subordinate samurais treated the hanzei law as their established right and continued to intervene in the taxes on manors and lands under the control of the feudal government unreasonably.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当時の流動的で争乱の続く状況の中で、幕府は、武士層だけでなく貴族・寺社層も存立基盤としており、貴族・寺社層の権利保全を図るため、武士による半済の抑制に努めることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the fluid situation of the midst of the continuing disturbance, the feudal government treated the noble class and the temple/shrine class as well as the samurai class as a basis of the nation&apos;s existence, and thus began controlling the abusive use of samurais&apos; hanzei authority to protect the authority of the noble class and the temple/shrine class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the fluid situation in the midst of the continuing disturbance, the feudal government treated the noble class and the temple/shrine class as well as the samurai class, and thus began controlling the abusive use of samurais&apos; hanzei authority in order to protect the authority of the noble class and the temple/shrine class.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the fluid situation in the midst of the continuing disturbance, the feudal government treated the noble class and the temple/shrine class as well as the samurai class, and thus began controlling the abusive use of samurais&apos; hanzei authority in order to protect the authority of the noble class and the temple/shrine class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>1368年（応安元年/正平23年）6月、幕府は総括的な半済令（応安の半済令）を発布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1368, the feudal government issued a general hanzei law (the hanzei law of Oan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1368, the feudal government issued a general hanzei law (the hanzei law of Oan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1368, the feudal government issued a general hanzei law (the hanzei law of Oan).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>皇族・寺社・摂関領などを例外として、全ての荘園年貢について、本所側と守護側武士（半済給付人という）とで均分することを永続的に認めるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law recognized the right of samurais who were employed to serve the provincial constables (hanzei beneficiary) to divide all customs and taxes on the manors equally with Honjo on a permanent basis, except for customs and taxes on the lands of the imperial family, temples and shrines, and regent to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law recognized the right of samurais who were employed to serve the provincial constables (hanzei beneficiaries) to divide all customs and taxes on the manors equally with Honjo on a permanent basis, except for customs and taxes on the lands of the imperial family, temples and shrines, and regent to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law recognized the right of samurais who were employed to serve the provincial constables (hanzei beneficiaries) to divide all customs and taxes on the manors equally with Honjo on a permanent basis, except for customs and taxes on the lands of the Imperial family, temples and shrines, and regent to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Imperial 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この法令により、守護は荘園・公領の半分の支配権を主張することとなり、各地で荘園・公領が分割され、守護の権益が拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This law strengthened provincial constables&apos; claim of the right to rule half of the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government, and manors and lands under the control of the feudal government became divided in various regions, and accordingly the interests of provincial constables expanded gradually.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This law strengthened the provincial constables&apos; claim of the right to rule half of the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government, and manors and lands under the control of the feudal government became divided in various regions, and accordingly the interests of provincial constables expanded gradually.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This law strengthened the provincial constables&apos; claim of the right to rule half of the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government, and manors and lands under the control of the feudal government became divided in various regions, and accordingly the interests of provincial constables expanded gradually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influences</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>半済令に伴う影響としては、荘園が解体への第一歩を踏み始めた点が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most noticeable influence of the practice of the hanzei law was it triggered the first step to demise of manors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most noticeable influence of the practice of the hanzei law was that it triggered the first step to demise of manors.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most noticeable influence of the practice of the hanzei law was that it triggered the first step to demise of manors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>応安の半済令により、守護は実質的に荘園・公領の半分を簒奪することとなり、荘園の解体が緩やかに進行していくこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the practice of the hanzei law of Oan, provincial constables disfranchised half of the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government virtually, thereby resulting in the gradual demise of manors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the practice of the hanzei law of Oan, provincial constables disfranchised half of the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government virtually, thereby resulting in the gradual demise of manors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the practice of the hanzei law of Oan, provincial constables disfranchised half of the manors and lands under the control of the feudal government virtually, thereby resulting in the gradual demise of manors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>鎌倉時代の守護が国内の軍事警察権を持つにとどまっていたのに対し、室町期の守護は、半済で得た権益を元に、軍事警察権のみならず荘園領主や国衙の権能を吸収していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While provincial constables in the Kamakura Period simply had military police powers, those in the Muromachi Period gradually absorbed powers of the lords of the manors and the Kokugas as well as the military police powers based on the interests obtained in &quot;Hanzei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While provincial constables in the Kamakura Period simply had military police powers, those in the Muromachi Period gradually absorbed the powers of the lords of manors and the Kokugas as well as the military police powers, based on the interests obtained in &quot;Hanzei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While provincial constables in the Kamakura period simply had military police powers, those in the Muromachi period gradually absorbed the powers of the lords of manors and the kokuga (provincial government offices) as well as the military police powers, based on the interests obtained in &quot;Hanzei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。国衙→kokuga (provincial government offices)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>それと並行して、守護は領国内の武士（国人という。）の統制・支配も進めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In parallel with that, provincial constables began controlling and governing samurais (called Kokujin) in his/her own territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In parallel with that, provincial constables began controlling and governing samurais (called Kokujin) in their own territories.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In parallel with that, provincial constables began controlling and governing samurais (called Kokujin) in their own territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このようにして、守護は半済を契機として、管轄する国内一円（これを領国という）にわたる支配権を確立していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, provincial constables established their authorities that could be exerted in his/her own territory (ryogoku) by taking advantage of the practice of the hanzei law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, provincial constables established their authority that could be exerted in their own territories (ryogoku) by taking advantage of the practice of the hanzei law.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, provincial constables established their authority that could be exerted in their own territories (ryogoku) by taking advantage of the practice of the hanzei law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そこで、鎌倉期の守護と区別するために、室町期の守護を守護大名とし、守護大名による領国支配体制を守護領国制と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To distinguish provincial constables in the Kamakura Period from those in the Muromachi Period, provincial constables in the Muromachi Period are called &quot;Shugo Daimyo,&quot; the provincial constable feudal lord, and the system in which Shugo-Daimyo governed his/her own territory is called &quot;Shugo-ryogokusei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To distinguish the provincial constables in the Kamakura Period from those in the Muromachi Period, provincial constables in the Muromachi Period are called &quot;Shugo Daimyo&quot;, the provincial constable feudal lord, and the system in which Shugo-Daimyo governed their own territories is called &quot;Shugo-ryogokusei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To distinguish the provincial constables in the Kamakura period from those in the Muromachi period, provincial constables in the Muromachi period are called &quot;Shugo daimyo,&quot; the provincial constable feudal lord, and the system in which Shugo daimyo governed their own territories is called Shugo-ryogoku system.</e>
<cmt>period小文字にしました。,の位置訂正しました。守護領国制→Shugo-ryogoku system としました。守護大名→Shugo daimyo としました。&quot; &quot;削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Shimoxx(id:9332), Nalc(id:139567), Yonoemon(id:55450), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>