<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>貴穀賤金</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kikokusenkin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kikokusenkin</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kikokusenkin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>貴穀賤金（きこくせんきん）は、江戸時代の経済思想のひとつで、米穀をとうとび、貨幣をいやしめるというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kikokusenkin refers to one of economic thoughts during Edo period, which respected rice and abhorred money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kikokusenkin refers to one of the economic thoughts during the Edo period, which respected rice and abhorred money.</e>
<cmt>冠詞を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kikokusenkin refers to one of the economic thoughts during the Edo period, which respected rice and abhorred money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>農本的な思想から派生したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to have developed from agricultural fundamentalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to have developed from agricultural fundamentalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to have developed from agricultural fundamentalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「貴穀賤金」という語句は、佐藤信淵の「物価余論簽書」に大久保一翁が題したもので、佐藤による造語ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word &apos;kikokusenkin&apos; was written by Ichio OKUBO in &apos;Supplementary theory on Prices&apos; by Nobuhiro SATO, which means that it was not Sato&apos;s word coinage.</e>
<cmt>「物価余論簽書」を、&apos;Supplementary theory on Prices&apos;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word &apos;kikokusenkin&apos; was created by Ichio OKUBO and written on the &apos;Supplementary theory on Prices&apos; by Nobuhiro SATO, which means that it was not Sato&apos;s word coinage.</e>
<cmt>「題する」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word &apos;kikokusenkin&apos; was created by Ichio OKUBO and written on the &apos;Supplementary theory on Prices&apos; by Nobuhiro SATO, which means that it was not Sato&apos;s word coinage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>佐藤は「貴金賤穀の弊」という語句は用いたが、「賤金貴穀」という語句は用いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SATO used the phrase &apos;negative effect of kikinsenkoku&apos; (the thought which respected money and abhorred rice), but did not use the one &apos;senkinkikoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SATO used the phrase &apos;negative effect of kikinsenkoku&apos; (the thought which respected money and abhorred rice,) but did not use &apos;senkinkikoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SATO used the phrase &apos;negative effect of kikinsenkoku&apos; (the thought which respected money and abhorred rice,) but did not use &apos;senkinkikoku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そして賤金貴穀を唱えたのは佐藤が最初ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was not SATO who firstly proposed senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SATO was not the first one to propose senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SATO was not the first one to propose senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>最初に賤金貴穀を唱えたのは熊沢蕃山である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Banzan KUMAZAWA who firstly proposed senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Banzan KUMAZAWA who proposed senkinkikoku first.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Banzan KUMAZAWA who proposed senkinkikoku first.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>熊沢はその『集義外書』に次のように言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Shugigaisho,&quot; KUMAZAWA wrote,</e>
<cmt>『集義外書』、不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Shugigaisho,&quot; KUMAZAWA wrote,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Shugigaisho,&quot; KUMAZAWA wrote the following.</e>
<cmt>文尾の「と言って」をここにまとめ「次のように言った」としました。 the followingを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>「タカラヲ賤ンズルトテ、ナゲスツルニハアラズ、五穀ヲ第一トシテ、金銀コレヲ助ケ、五穀下ニミチミチテ、上ノ用ニ達スルヲ貨ヲ賤ズトイフナリ」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Abhorring money does not mean throwing money away, gokoku (five kinds of grain) are the most important and gold and silver help them and gokoku flourish to be used over money,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">abhorring money does not mean throwing money away, it just places the most importance on gokoku (five kinds of grain) and gold and silver are to help gokoku flourish on the ground, so that money is abhorred for gokoku to flourish,&apos;</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Abhorring money does not mean throwing money away, it just places the most importance on gokoku (five kinds of grain) and gold and silver are to help gokoku flourish on the ground, so that money is abhorred for gokoku to flourish,&apos;</e>
<cmt>abhorrin→Abhorrin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>徹底した形ではないが、いわゆる賤金貴穀の説を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and proposed the theory of senkinkikoku though it was not a radical one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and proposed the theory of senkinkikoku though it was not a radical one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He proposed the theory of senkinkikoku though it was not a radical one.</e>
<cmt>and →He</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>享保年間には、荻生徂徠・太宰春台も同じようなことを唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Kyoho era Sorai OGYU and Shundai DAZAI proposed the similar idea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Kyoho era, Sorai OGYU and Shundai DAZAI proposed similar ideas.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。全角のスペースを半角にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Kyoho era, Sorai OGYU and Shundai DAZAI proposed similar ideas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>天明年間に、林子平は『海国兵談』八で、次のように明白に賤金貴穀の弊を論じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Tenmei era, in &quot;Strategic theory for maritime defense,&quot; Shihei HAYASHI clearly argued about harmful results of senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt>『海国兵談』を、&quot;Strategic theory for maritime defense&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During Tenmei era, in &quot;Strategic theory for maritime defense,&quot; Shihei HAYASHI clearly argued about harmful results of senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During Tenmei era, in &quot;Strategic theory for maritime defense,&quot; Shihei HAYASHI wrote the following and clearly argued about harmful results of senkinkikoku.</e>
<cmt>文尾の「次のように明白に賤金貴穀の弊を論じた。」をこちらにまとめました。 the followingを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「常世は上下共に穀を賤しんで金を貴ぶなり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this world both the upper and lower abhor rice and respect money.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this world, both the upper and lower abhor rice and respect money.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this world, both the upper and lower abhor rice and respect money.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「此故に金銀を第一として穀を心とせざるは甚だ危き心掛なり、其故に三四ヶ国の饑饉なれば、有年の国のより饑饉の国へ廻し遣はす米穀も有べきなれども、もし、二三十ヶ国も一統に饑饉せば廻し遣はす米穀も有べからず。その時に至て、金銀を煎じて飲むとも命は助る間敷なり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason it is dangerous to respect gold and silver and abhor rice, and thus, if three or four Provinces are in famine, Provinces with rice to spare can help them, but, if twenty or thirty Provinces are simultaneously in famine, there is not enough rice to spare. Then, it is not possible for people to survive by drinking decocted gold and silver.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is dangerous to respect gold and silver and abhor rice like this because if three or four Provinces are in famine, Provinces with rice to spare can help them, but, if twenty or thirty Provinces are simultaneously in famine, there will not be enough rice to spare. In such a time, it is not possible for people to survive by drinking decocted gold and silver.&apos;</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is dangerous to respect gold and silver and abhor rice like this because if three or four Provinces are in famine, Provinces with rice to spare can help them, but, if twenty or thirty Provinces are simultaneously in famine, there will not be enough rice to spare. In such a time, it is not possible for people to survive by drinking decocted gold and silver.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>「此所を能く呑込んで、金銀は命を救ふ第二番の物なることを知て米穀を第一、金銀を第二と心得て、平日食糧になるべき物を蓄ふることを勤むべし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You should understand that rice is the most important, and gold and silver are the second for surviving and try hard to store everyday food,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You should understand that rice is the most important, and gold and silver are the second for surviving and try hard to store everyday food,&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You should understand that rice is the most important, and gold and silver are the second for surviving and try hard to store everyday food,&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>林は飢饉のことを言うが、実際は兵備の点から論じたものであり、佐藤の貴穀賤金論が物価の平準化を目的としているのとは異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HAYASHI wrote on famine but in fact he discussed it from a viewpoint of security and his theory was different from SATO&apos;s theory of kikokusenkin, which aimed for leveling-off of prices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HAYASHI wrote on famine but in fact he discussed it from a viewpoint of security and his theory was different from SATO&apos;s theory of kikokusenkin which aimed for leveling-off of prices.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HAYASHI wrote on famine but in fact he discussed it from a viewpoint of security and his theory was different from SATO&apos;s theory of kikokusenkin which aimed for leveling-off of prices.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>佐藤は『物価余論』で以下のように言い、高い米価を維持することを論じている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SATO wrote in &quot;Supplementary theory on Prices,&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SATO wrote in &quot;Supplementary theory on Prices,&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SATO wrote the following in &quot;Supplementary theory on Prices&quot; and argued about maintaining a high rice price.</e>
<cmt>文尾の「と言い、高い米価を維持することを論じている。」をこちらにまとめました。 the followingを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="18">
<j>「米を蓄るときは鼠喰或は虫付、ふけ米等の出来て減ずること多きも、金を蓄ふるときは、利息出来て、増すこと多きが故に、年貢も金納を多くし、米を払ひて、金にするを良とするとは、小人の利術にして、君子の所為にあらず。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When storing rice, it often decreases by being infested with rats or insects, or with defective rice, but when storing money, it often increases with interest, and thus, nengu (annual tribute, land tax) is paid more by money by exchanging rice with money, which, however, is the way of a man of stupid, not a man of virtue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When storing rice, it often decreases by being infested with rats or insects, or by being damaged, but when storing money, it often increases with interest, and thus, nengu (annual tribute, land tax) is paid more by money by exchanging rice with money, which, however, is the way of a man of stupid, not a man of virtue.</e>
<cmt>ふけ米の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When storing rice, it often decreases by being infested with rats or insects, or by being damaged, but when storing money, it often increases with interest, and thus, nengu (annual tribute, land tax) is paid more by money by exchanging rice with money, which, however, is the way of a man of stupid, not a man of virtue.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」をつけました。&apos;&apos;をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「士農米穀を蓄へざるが故に、工商是を卑みて金銀を貴ぶなり、もし士農金銀を卑み、米穀を貴てこれを蓄積するときは、工商は士農に役せられて常に米穀を求むること急なり、然るに士人米を卑みて蓄積せず特に金のみを貴ぶが故に富商の鼻息を仰で憂喜をなすに至る。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As samurai and farmers do not store rice, artisans and merchants despise this and respect gold and silver, and if samurai and farmers despise gold and silver and respect and store rice, then artisans and merchants always hurriedly ask for rice, but samurai despise rice and do not store them and respect only money and thus fluctuate between hope and despair, governed by rich merchants and artisans and merchants are rich and samurai and farmers are poor, which is like putting the cart before the horse, and in order to improve this negative effect, if artisans and merchants are made to be always short of rice and are asking for samurai and farmers, then the price will be naturally leveled off.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As samurai and farmers do not store rice, artisans and merchants despise rice and respect gold and silver, but if samurai and farmers despise gold and silver and respect and store rice, then artisans and merchants would always hurriedly ask for rice, but the fact is that samurai despise rice and do not store rice, respecting only money, which forces them to fluctuate between hope and despair depending on the temper of rich merchants and artisans.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As samurai and farmers do not store rice, artisans and merchants despise rice and respect gold and silver, but if samurai and farmers despise gold and silver and respect and store rice, then artisans and merchants would always hurriedly ask for rice, but the fact is that samurai despise rice and do not store rice, respecting only money, which forces them to fluctuate between hope and despair depending on the temper of rich merchants and artisans.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」をつけました。&apos;&apos;をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「工商豊かにして、士農困む是れ上下地を易る根原なり、此弊を改むるときは工商常に米穀に困み、士農を仰でその業を励むに至れば、物価は自然に平準なるべし」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merchants and artisans are rich and samurai and farmers are poor, which causes all the people to despise the ground, so this negative effect will be overcome when artisans and merchants are always short of rice and respect samurai and farmers, then the price will be naturally leveled off.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処。Trans1は原文の解釈に誤解があるようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merchants and artisans are rich and samurai and farmers are poor, which causes all the people to despise the ground, so this negative effect will be overcome when artisans and merchants are always short of rice and respect samurai and farmers, then the price will be naturally leveled off.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」をつけました。&apos;&apos;をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="21">
<j>井上四明は、『経済十二論』で、貴穀という節を設けて、次のように論じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimei INOUE wrote in the section of kikoku in his &quot;Economics twelve theories,&quot;</e>
<cmt>『経済十二論』を、&quot;Economics twelve theories&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimei INOUE wrote in the section of kikoku in his &quot;Twelve economics theories,&quot;</e>
<cmt>『経済十二論』はTwelve economics theoriesの方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimei INOUE wrote the following in the section of kikoku in his &quot;Twelve economics theories,&quot;</e>
<cmt>the followinを追加しました。「次のように論じた」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「珠玉雖レ宝、而餒不レ可レ食、金銀雖レ財、而凍不レ可レ衣、世皆不レ貴二穀粟一、而貴二金銀珠玉一者何也」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">money is a treasure, but can not be eaten, and gold and silver are wealth, but can not be worn, and in this world rice is the most important and gold, silver and money are the second important.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">money is a treasure, but cannot be eaten, and gold and silver are wealth, but cannot be worn, and in this world, rice is the most important and gold, silver and money are the second most important.&apos;</e>
<cmt>can not&apos;は&apos;cannot&apos;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Money is a treasure, but cannot be eaten, and gold and silver are wealth, but cannot be worn, and in this world, rice is the most important and gold, silver and money are the second most important.&apos;</e>
<cmt>money→Money</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>「近世熊伯〔熊沢蕃山を指す〕亦論二貴粟一、伯継多二善政一、国民至レ今便焉貴粟之政、独不レ行二於当時一、可レ歎哉、今欲二富レ士仰一レ商、無レ如下貴二穀粟一而賤中金銀上、欲レ貴二穀粟一、無レ如二以レ穀代一レ幣、而行二於天下一也」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recently Mr. Banzan KUMAZAWA</e>
<cmt>すみません、意味が分かりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recently Mr. Banzan KUMAZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">近世熊伯〔熊沢蕃山を指す〕亦論二貴粟一,伯継多二善政一,国民至レ今便焉貴粟之政,独不レ行二於当時一,可レ歎哉,今欲二富レ士仰一レ商,無レ如下貴二穀粟一而賤中金銀上,欲レ貴二穀粟一,無レ如二以レ穀代一レ幣,而行二於天下一也&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>熊沢の米遣いの説が実際には行なわれなかったことを嘆いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he deplored that the theory of the use of rice by KUMAZAWA was not done really.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he deplored that the theory of the use of rice by KUMAZAWA was not practiced really.</e>
<cmt>単語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he deplored that the theory of the use of rice by KUMAZAWA was not practiced really.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="25">
<j>頼山陽は「通議」で次のように述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanyo RAI wrote the following in &apos;Tsugi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanyo RAI wrote the following in &apos;Tsugi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanyo RAI wrote the following in &apos;Tsugi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="26">
<j>「若二夫銭幣一有レ之不レ飽、有レ之不レ暖、故穀帛穀不レ可二一日無一、而銭幣可二百年無一」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>すみません、意味が分かりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">若二夫銭幣一有レ之不レ飽,有レ之不レ暖,故穀帛穀不レ可二一日無一,而銭幣可二百年無一&apos;</e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="27">
<j>賤金論者は上のような漢学者のみに限らない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theorists of abhorring money were not limited to the above scholars of the Chinese classics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theorists of abhorring money were not limited to the above scholars of the Chinese classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theorists of abhorring money were not limited to the above scholars of the Chinese classics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>たとえば本居宣長は「秘本玉くしげ」で、次のように述べた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Norinaga MOTOORI wrote in &apos;Secret book Tamakushige,&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Norinaga MOTOORI wrote in &apos;Secret book Tamakushige,&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, Norinaga MOTOORI wrote the following in &apos;Secret book Tamakushige,&apos;</e>
<cmt>「次のように述べた。」を補足しました。 the followingを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>「右の子細〔貨幣流通の弊害を指す〕どもをつねづねよく心得居て、総体正物にて取引すべき事は少々不便利はありとも、やはり正物にて取引をして金銀の取引のすぢをばなるべきだけはこれを省き、なほまたさまざまの金銀のやりくりなどをも、なるべきだけは随分これを止め、またなすべきことを金銀にて仕切るやうのすぢはなほ更無用にあらまほしきことなり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">You should always understand the above details (the negative effect of money circulation) and generally when in transaction, you should deal with the real things though a little inconvenient and avoid the transaction by gold and silver as much as possible, and should stop various treatments of gold and silver as much as possible, and also, hopefully, the transaction by gold and silver should not done for everything.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">You should always keep in mind the above details (the negative effect of money circulation) and deal in real things though it is a little inconvenient to deal in real things all the time, and avoid the transaction by gold and silver as much as possible, and stop to handle gold and silver as much as possible, and also, it is desirable that gold and silver would not limit what you have to do.&apos;</e>
<cmt>解釈に誤解があったようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">You should always keep in mind the above details (the negative effect of money circulation) and deal in real things though it is a little inconvenient to deal in real things all the time, and avoid the transaction by gold and silver as much as possible, and stop to handle gold and silver as much as possible, and also, it is desirable that gold and silver would not limit what you have to do.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>そして貨幣取引に制限を加えるべきであるとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He insisted on adding the limitation on money transaction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He insisted on adding limitation on money transaction.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He insisted on adding limitation on money transaction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>本居は正物の取引を言い、貴穀の論であるとは言いにくいが、賤金論ではある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MOTOORI discussed the transaction by real things and it is difficult to call his idea the theory of kikoku (respecting rice), but it is the theory of senkin (abhorring money).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MOTOORI advocated the transaction by real things and although it is difficult to call his idea the theory of kikoku (respecting rice), but it is the theory of senkin (abhorring money).</e>
<cmt>単語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MOTOORI advocated the transaction by real things and although it is difficult to call his idea the theory of kikoku (respecting rice), but it is the theory of senkin (abhorring money).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="32">
<j>おしなべて江戸時代の漢学者・儒学者は、貨幣制度と封建制度との、矛盾するとは言わないまでも、相両立したがいこと、貨幣経済が物品経済に戻りにくいことをおぼろげには感じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, Japanese scholars of the Chinese classics and the Confucian scholars during Edo period vaguely understood that monetary system and feudal system were incompatible, though not contradictory, and it was difficult for money economy to return to object economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, Japanese scholars of the Chinese classics and the Confucianism during the Edo period vaguely understood that the monetary system and the feudal system were hardly compatible, though not contradictory, and that it was difficult for the money economy to return to the object economy.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。ニュアンスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, Japanese scholars of the Chinese classics and the Confucianism during the Edo period vaguely understood that the monetary system and the feudal system were hardly compatible, though not contradictory, and that it was difficult for the money economy to return to the object economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Straysheep(id:42448), 春秋君(id:174988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>