<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>分国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunkoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunkoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunkoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>分国（ぶんこく）とは、日本のに中世おける1国の単位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bunkoku&quot; is a unit used to delineate province-sized areas during the medieval period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>I think perhaps the original should read &quot;nihon no chusei ni okeru&quot;!</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bunkoku&quot; is a unit used to delineate province-sized areas during the medieval period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bunkoku&quot; is a unit used to delineate province-sized areas during the medieval period in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>平安時代の知行国にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term applied to Heian-era chigyo-koku (province-wide fiefs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term applied to Heian-era chigyo-koku (province-wide fiefs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term applied to Heian-period chigyo-koku (province-wide fiefs).</e>
<cmt>era→ period　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中期以降の太上天皇や法皇、皇族の所領となった院宮御分国、源頼朝の知行国である関東御分国、南北朝時代 (日本)以降の守護大名の知行した領国などが当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting in the mid-Heian period, &quot;Bungaku&quot; also appears in the term &quot;ingu onbungaku,&quot; which refers to the province-sized territories controlled by (Retired) Emperor Daijo, the Cloistered Emperors, and the Imperial family, as well as in the term &quot;kanto bungaku,&quot; referring to the bloc of provinces MINAMOTO no Yoritomo controlled in the Kanto (eastern Japan); starting in the Nanbokucho period, &quot;bungaku&quot; was additionally used to describe the provinces controlled as feudal domains by the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting in the mid-Heian period, &quot;Bungaku&quot; also appears in the term &quot;ingu onbungaku,&quot; which refers to the province-sized territories controlled by (Retired) Emperor Daijo, the Cloistered Emperors, and the Imperial family, as well as in the term &quot;kanto bungaku,&quot; referring to the bloc of provinces MINAMOTO no Yoritomo controlled in the Kanto (eastern Japan); starting in the Nanbokucho period, &quot;bungaku&quot; was additionally used to describe the provinces controlled as feudal domains by the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting in the mid-Heian period, &quot;Bunkoku&quot; also appears in the term &quot;ingu gobunkoku,&quot; which refers to the province-sized territories controlled by the Retired Emperors, the Cloistered Emperors, and the Imperial Family, as well as in the term &quot;kanto gobunkoku,&quot; referring to the bloc of provinces MINAMOTO no Yoritomo controlled in the Kanto (eastern Japan); starting in the period of Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), &quot;bunkoku&quot; was additionally used to describe the provinces controlled as feudal domains by the shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords).</e>
<cmt>御分国→ gobunkoku としました。太上天皇→the Retired Emperor　としました。守護大名　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>戦国時代には、戦国大名は領内を対象とした分国法を制定して統治。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo during the Sengoku (warring states) period would come to rule their provinces by establishing an internal law called the Bungokuho, which had effect only within their own individual domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo during the Sengoku (warring states) period would come to rule their provinces by establishing an internal law called the Bungokuho, which had effect only within their own individual domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) would come to rule their provinces by establishing an internal law called the Bungokuho, which had effect only within their own individual domains.</e>
<cmt>戦国大名　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), でここ(id:9565), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>