<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>志士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishi (supporter of a noble cause, patriot)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shishi (Patriot)</e>
<cmt>説明を簡単にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shishi (Patriot)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>志士（しし）とは、一般に日本の江戸時代後期の幕末において活動した在野の人物を差す歴史用語である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, Shishi, a patriot is a historical term that designate non-Government people who worked in the late Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shishi is a historical term describing a commoner in the late Edo Period who actively contributed to the country.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shishi is a historical term describing a commoner in the late Edo Period who actively contributed to the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>論語にある「志士仁人（ししじんじん）は（…）身を殺して以て仁をなすなり」が語源である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Shishi is derived from a phrase in &apos;The Analects (of Confucius)&apos; that was &apos;Shishi, a person of virtue accumulates virtues by killing himself&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Shishi is derived from a phrase in &apos;The Analects (of Confucius)&apos; that was &apos;Shishi, a person of virtue accumulates virtues by killing himself&apos;.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Shishi is derived from a phrase in &apos;The Analects (of Confucius)&apos; that was &apos;Shishi, a person of virtue accumulates virtues by killing himself&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>天下国家のため正しいと信じたことを、生命をかけて貫く人物像を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It designated a person who stood up for what he believed in, risking his life for his counrty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It describes a character who places his life on the line for what he believes is right for his country.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It describes a character who places his life on the line for what he believes is right for his country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>多くは尊皇攘夷の思想を持って政治運動を行った者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mostly they were political agitators who had the idea of the &apos;Sonno-joi&apos; (revere the emperor and expel the barbarians)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term was frequently used for the political activists who held to ideal of &quot;Sonno-joi (Reverence of the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term was frequently used for the political activists who held to ideal of &quot;Sonno-joi (Reverence of the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>草奔とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were also referred to as &apos;Somo&apos; (non-Government).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were also referred to as &quot;Somo (non-government citizens)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were also referred to as &quot;Somo (non-government citizens)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>また，比喩的に他の時代の人物や外国人に対しても使われることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is figuratively used to people in different times and countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also used figuratively for people in different eras and countries.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also used figuratively for people in different eras and countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>第二次世界大戦中日本に亡命していたスバス・チャンドラ・ボースなどのインド独立運動家を指して「インド独立の志士」とも呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subhas Chandra Bose, a leader in the Indian independence movement who was had defected to Japan during the World War 2, was also called as &apos;Shishi of the Indian independence&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subhas Chandra Bose, a leader in the Indian independence movement who fled to Japan during the World War 2, was also called a &quot;&quot;Shishi&apos; of the Indian independence movement&quot;.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subhas Chandra Bose, a leader in the Indian independence movement who fled to Japan during the World War 2, was also called a &quot;&quot;Shishi&apos; of the Indian independence movement&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>尊王志士の活躍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Performing of Sonno (advocate of imperial rule) Shishi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Acts by the Sonno (advocate of imperial rule) Shishi</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Acts by the Sonno (advocate of imperial rule) Shishi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>鎖国と攘夷に揺れた幕末から明治国家建設の先駆けとなったのが、尊王志士である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later Edo Shogunate that were tumultuous time by the national isolationism and exclusionism, the Sono Shishi were pioneers of the foundation of the Meiji period nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the late Edo Period, the &quot;Sono Shishi&quot; pioneered the structure for the Meiji government while the Shogunate was still in a state of tumult over the expulsion of foreigners and anti-foreign sentiments.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the late Edo Period, the &quot;Sono Shishi&quot; pioneered the structure for the Meiji government while the Shogunate was still in a state of tumult over the expulsion of foreigners and anti-foreign sentiments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>当初彼等は尊皇攘夷の下で、異国との交わりを忌み嫌い、天皇を中心とした国家の建設が不可欠だとして、幕府に対して、尊皇攘夷の履行を徹底すべきと考えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, under the concept of Sonno Joi (Sonno, the reverence for the emperor and Joi, antiforeigner), they opposed to intercourse with forign countries and asked the Edo Shogunate to implement Sono Joi to establish the emperor-centered country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning they adhered to the ideal of &quot;Sonno Joi (&quot;Sonno&quot;is the principle of revering the emperor, while &quot;Joi&quot; stands for anti-foreigner sentiments)&quot;, opposed all interactions with foreigners, believed that it was imperative to establish a emperor-centered government, and believed that the government should implement this ideal.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning they adhered to the ideal of &quot;Sonno Joi (&quot;Sonno&quot;is the principle of revering the emperor, while &quot;Joi&quot; stands for anti-foreigner sentiments)&quot;, opposed all interactions with foreigners, believed that it was imperative to establish a emperor-centered government, and believed that the government should implement this ideal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、やがて幕府の求心力が急速に低下すると、これを打倒し、江戸幕府に代わる天皇を中心とした統一政体の確立を望んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the centripetal force of the Edo Shogunate reduced rapidly, they wanted to overthrow the current government to establish the emperor-centered, integrated government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But when the Edo Shogunate began to rapidly lose it&apos;s power to unify the country, they hoped to overthrow the government and replace it with an integrated government centered around the emperor.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But when the Edo Shogunate began to rapidly lose it&apos;s power to unify the country, they hoped to overthrow the government and replace it with an integrated government centered around the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸幕府と長州藩の幕長戦争などで有力な大名家である雄藩が幕府と対立を深めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Bakucho War of the Edo Shogunate VS. the Choshu Domain caused deep conflict between the Edo Shogunate and the Yuhan, powerful domains consisted of famous daimyo families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Bakucho War, in which the Edo Shogunate fought against the Choshu Domain, caused deep rifts between the Shogunate and the Yuhan, a powerful daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Bakucho War, in which the Edo Shogunate fought against the Choshu Domain, caused deep rifts between the Shogunate and the Yuhan, a powerful daimyo family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>結果、薩摩藩と長州藩による薩長連合の成立によってついに戊辰戦争によって倒幕を成し遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the union of the Satsuma Domain and the Choshu Domain finally succeeded to overthrow the Shogunate in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alliance between the Satsuma Domain and the Choshu Domain resulted in the fall of the Shogunate at the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alliance between the Satsuma Domain and the Choshu Domain resulted in the fall of the Shogunate at the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>政治運動に命をかけるという人物モデルにもなり、自由民権運動の活動家や、明治社会主義者の一部にも「志士」という理想像が共有されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shishi became a model of person who risked his life on politics, and the idea of &apos;Shishi&apos; was shared with activists of the Movement for Civic Rights and Freedomsome and socialists in the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Shishi&quot; came to symbolize a person who puts his life towards political activity, such as the activists for Civic Rights, and Meiji Period socialists.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味がよりよく伝わるように訳文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Shishi&quot; came to symbolize a person who puts his life towards political activity, such as the activists for Civic Rights, and Meiji Period socialists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), VolkovBot(id:105371), Nnh(id:474), 海衛士(id:19229), An-chan(id:14590), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Loveless(id:129239), YukkeBot(id:251107), せくそろじすと(id:9002), 認定者(id:99098), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>