<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>中古 (時代区分)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuko (Middle Ages)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuko</e>
<cmt>eliminated (Middle Ages) since it is written directly below</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuko (periodization)</e>
<cmt>&quot;(時代区分)&quot;を訳出</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>中古（ちゅうこ）とは、時代区分に用いられる表現の1つで、上古・中古・近古の三分法を用いた際の2番目に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuko (middle ages) is a word to describe a time period, and it is the second one of the three (trichotomy) which are joko (ancient times), chuko (middle ages), and kinko (early modern age).</e>
<cmt>中古「なかむかし」とも読むようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuko (Middle Ages) is a word used to represent a time period, and is the second of the three words: joko (ancient times), chuko (middle ages), and kinko (early modern age).</e>
<cmt>capitalized &quot;Middle Ages&quot;; changed &quot;to describe&quot; to &quot;used to represent&quot;; added colon; fixed to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuko (Middle Ages) is a word used to represent a time period, and is the second of the three words: joko (ancient times), chuko (middle ages), and kinko (early modern age).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>本来は、中世と同じ意味である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chuko means the same as the Middle Ages</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuko carries the same meaning as the &quot;Middle Ages.&quot;</e>
<cmt>added quotation marks</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuko carries the same meaning as the &quot;Middle Ages.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>日本文学史においては「中古六歌仙」・「中古三十六歌仙」などの語が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japanese literary history, the word chuko was used in &apos;chuko rokkasen (six Japanese poets presented in the prelude of Kokinshu, A Collection of Ancient and Modern Poetry in the early Heian period)&apos; and &apos;chuko sanjurokkasen (36 Japanese poets of Nochi no Rokurokusen selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japanese literary history, the word chuko is used in the &quot;Chuko Rokkasen&quot; (six Japanese poets presented in the prelude of Kokinshu, A Collection of Ancient and Modern Poetry in the early Heian period) and the &quot;Chuko Sanjurokkasen&quot; (Thirty-six Japanese poets of Nochi no Rokurokusen selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;36&quot; to &quot;Thirty-six&quot;; fixed quotation marks; capitalized titles; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japanese literary history, the word chuko is used in the &apos;Chuko Rokkasen&apos; (six Japanese poets presented in the prelude of Kokinshu, A Collection of Ancient and Modern Poetry in the early Heian period) and the &apos;Chuko Sanjurokkasen&apos; (Thirty-six Japanese poets of Nochi no Rokurokusen selected by FUJIWARA no Norikane).</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そのため、国文学界においては平安時代（794年-1192年）を指して用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, chuko is regarded as a word meaning the Heian period (794-1192) in Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chuko is therefore regarded as a word used to refer to the Heian period (794 - 1192) in Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chuko is therefore regarded as a word used to refer to the Heian period (794 - 1192) in Japanese literature.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その一方で国文学界が鎌倉時代以後を本来は同じ意味である「中世」という語で表現する事に対して疑問も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the time period after the Kamakura period is expressed as the &apos;Middle Ages,&apos; the word having the same meaning as chuko, in Japanese literature, and appropriateness of this practice has been questioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Japanese literature also uses the term &quot;chusei&quot; to refer to the time period after the Kamakura period which has the same meaning as chuko, and the appropriateness of this practice has been questioned.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;At the same time&quot; to &quot;On the other hand&quot; for &quot;その一方で&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Japanese literature also uses the term &apos;chusei&apos; to refer to the time period after the Kamakura period which has the same meaning as chuko, and the appropriateness of this practice has been questioned.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このため、近年では「中古」という語を用いない傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the word &apos;chuko&apos; is not used much any more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is for this reason that there is a tendency to avoid the use of the word &quot;chuko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is for this reason that there is a tendency to avoid the use of the word &apos;chuko.&apos;</e>
<cmt>シングルクォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>