<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明応の政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meio Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meio Incident</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meio Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明応の政変（めいおうのせいへん）は、室町時代の1493年（明応2年）に起こった足利征夷大将軍廃立事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meio Incident was an enthronement and dethronement of the Ashikaga seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) that occurred in the Muromachi period in 1493.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meio Incident involved the enthronement and dethronement of the Ashikaga seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and occurred in the Muromachi period in 1493.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meio Incident involved the enthronement and dethronement of the Ashikaga seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) and occurred in the Muromachi period in 1493.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、近年の日本史学界においては戦国時代_(日本)の始期をこの事件に求める有力説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the field of Japanese history in recent years, there is an influential theory that regards this incident as the beginning of the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, in the field of Japanese history there is an influential theory that regards this incident as the beginning of the Warring States period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, in the field of Japanese history there is an influential theory that regards this incident as the beginning of the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>戦国時代→the Sengoku period (period of warring states)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>将軍位を巡る争い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A conflict over the post of shogun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conflict over the post of shogun</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conflict over the post of shogun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>足利義稙は、応仁の乱で西軍の盟主に擁立された足利義視の嫡子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was the heir of Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, who was given backing by the leader of Western forces during the Onin War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was the heir of Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, who was backed by the leader of Western forces during the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitane ASHIKAGA was the heir of Yoshimi ASHIKAGA, who was backed by the leader of Western forces during the Onin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>乱が西軍劣勢で収束すると、父とともに土岐成頼を頼って美濃国へ逃れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the war was resolved with the Western forces being outnumbered, he and his father escaped to Mino province, trusting in Shigeyori TOKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the war was resolved as the Western forces were outnumbered, he and his father escaped to Mino province, relying on Shigeyori TOKI.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the war was resolved as the Western forces were outnumbered, he and his father escaped to Mino Province, relying on Shigeyori TOKI.</e>
<cmt>Province 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>9代将軍足利義尚は守護大名や奉公衆を率い、六角討伐のため近江国へ親征するが、1489年（延徳元年）に近江で病死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ninth shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, at the head of a force of provincial military governors turned daimyo and shogunal guards, led a campaign against the Rokkaku in Omi province, but died of an illness there in 1489.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ninth shogun, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, at the head of a force of provincial military governors turned daimyo and shogunal guards, led a campaign against the Rokkaku in Omi province, but died there in 1489 of an illness.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ninth shogun, Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA, at the head of a force of provincial military governors turned daimyo and shogunal guards, led a campaign against the Rokkaku in Omi Province, but died there in 1489 of an illness.</e>
<cmt>Province 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>義材は義視とともに上洛して10代将軍に推挙されるが、足利義政や細川政元などは、堀越公方足利政知の子で天龍寺香厳院主となっていた清晃（足利義澄）を推す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiki went back to Kyoto with Yoshimi and was put forward as the tenth shogun, but some, including Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA and Masamoto HOSOKAWA, supported Seiko (Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA), the son of Masatomo ASHIKAGA who was Horikoshi Governor-General, and was the head of the Kyogon-in of Tenryu-ji Temple at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiki returned to Kyoto with Yoshimi and was put forward as the tenth shogun, but some people, including Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA and Masamoto HOSOKAWA, supported Seiko (Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA), the son of Masatomo ASHIKAGA who was the Horikoshi Governor-General, and was the head of the Kyogon-in of Tenryu-ji Temple at that time.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiki returned to Kyoto with Yoshimi and was put forward as the tenth shogun, but some people, including Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA and Masamoto HOSOKAWA, supported Seiko (Yoshizumi ASHIKAGA), the son of Masatomo ASHIKAGA who was the Horikoshi Governor-General, and was the head of the Kyogon-in of Tenryu-ji Temple at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、日野富子が甥である義材を後援し、また、翌1490年（延徳2年）に義政が死去すると、義視の出家などを条件として義材の10代将軍就任が決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Tomiko HINO supported her nephew Yoshiki, and after the death of Yoshimasa the next year, in 1490, Yoshiki was chosen to be the tenth shogun on, among others, the condition of Yoshimi&apos;s becoming a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Tomiko HINO supported her nephew Yoshiki, and after the death of Yoshimasa the following year, in 1490, Yoshiki was chosen to be the tenth shogun on, among others, the condition of Yoshimi becoming a monk.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Tomiko HINO supported her nephew Yoshiki, and after the death of Yoshimasa the following year, in 1490, Yoshiki was chosen to be the tenth shogun on, among others, the condition of Yoshimi becoming a monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>この決定に反対した政元や伊勢貞宗らは、義視父子と対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto, Sadamune ISE and others who had been against this decision opposed Yoshimi and his son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto, Sadamune ISE and others who had been against this decision opposed Yoshimi and his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto, Sadamune ISE and others who had been against this decision opposed Yoshimi and his son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>義材は前将軍義尚の政策を踏襲し、丹波国、山城国など、畿内における国一揆に対応するため、1491年（延徳3年）、六角討伐を継承するなど軍事的強化を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiki followed the policies of the former shogun Yoshihisa and tried to increase his military strength, such as by taking over the campaign against the Rokkaku house in 1491 to deal with uprisings like in Tanba and Yamashiro provinces in the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiki followed the policies of the former shogun Yoshihisa and tried to increase his military strength, by taking over the campaign against the Rokkaku house in 1491 to deal with uprisings like in Tanba and Yamashiro provinces in the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiki followed the policies of the former shogun Yoshihisa and tried to increase his military strength, by taking over the campaign against the Rokkaku house in 1491 to deal with uprisings like in Tanba and Yamashiro provinces in the Kinai region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>クーデター</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Coup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Coup d&apos;etat</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Coup d&apos;etat</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>1493年（明応2年）、畠山政長は敵対する畠山義豊（畠山義就の子）の討伐のため、義材に河内国親征を要請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1493, Masanaga HATAKEYAMA requested that Yoshiki subjugate Kawachi province to defeat his opponent, Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA (the son of Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1493, Masanaga HATAKEYAMA requested that Yoshiki subjugate Kawachi province to defeat his opponent, Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA (the son of Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1493, Masanaga HATAKEYAMA requested that Yoshiki subjugate Kawachi Province to defeat his opponent, Yoshitoyo HATAKEYAMA (the son of Yoshinari HATAKEYAMA).</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>政元はこれに反対するが、畠山氏の家督問題を解決させるため、義材は討伐軍を進発させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Masamoto was against this request, Yoshiki marched off with a punitive force to settle the issue of the succession to the head of Hatakeyama clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Masamoto was against this request, Yoshiki marched off with a punitive force to settle the issue of the succession to the head of Hatakeyama clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Masamoto was against this request, Yoshiki marched off with a punitive force to settle the issue of the succession to the head of Hatakeyama clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>政元は、義材に不満を抱き始めた富子や赤松政則を抱き込み、清晃を還俗させて11代将軍に擁立してクーデターを決行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamoto gained the cooperation of Tomiko and Masanori AKAMATSU, who had begun to feel dissatisfied with Yoshiki, then pulled off a coup by making Seiko return to secular life and helping him become the eleventh shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamoto gained the cooperation of Tomiko and Masanori AKAMATSU, who had begun to feel dissatisfied with Yoshiki, and then pulled off a coup d&apos;etat by making Seiko return to secular life and helping him become the eleventh shogun.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamoto gained the cooperation of Tomiko and Masanori AKAMATSU, who had begun to feel dissatisfied with Yoshiki, and then pulled off a coup d&apos;etat by making Seiko return to secular life and helping him become the eleventh shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに京都を制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, he brought Kyoto under his control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also brought Kyoto under his control.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also brought Kyoto under his control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>この報によって義材勢は分裂。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiki&apos;s force was divided by this news.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiki&apos;s forces were divided by this news.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiki&apos;s forces were divided by this news.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>政長が敗死すると、義材は投降して京都竜安寺にて幽閉されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masanaga died in a losing cause, Yoshiki surrendered and it was decided that he was to be confined in Ryoan-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Masanaga died, Yoshiki surrendered and it was decided that he was to be confined in Ryoan-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Masanaga died, Yoshiki surrendered and it was decided that he was to be confined in Ryoan-ji Temple in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>同年6月、幽閉されていた義材は、側近らの手引きで越中国射水郡放生津へ下向し、政長の重臣であった婦負郡・射水郡分郡守護代・神保長誠を頼った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year, Yoshiki, who had been confined, went away from Kyoto into Hojo-du, Izumi county, Ecchu province with the help of his close aides, tusting in Naganobu JINBO, a chief vassal of Masanaga and deputy of the divided counties Nei and Izumi who had been appointed by a shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year, Yoshiki, who had been confined, went from Kyoto to Hojo-du, Izumi county, Ecchu province with the help of his close aides, relying on Naganobu JINBO, a chief vassal of Masanaga and deputy of the divided counties Nei and Izumi who had been appointed by a shugo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year, Yoshiki, who had been confined, went from Kyoto to Hojo-du, Izumi county, Ecchu Province with the help of his close aides, relying on Naganobu JINBO, a chief vassal of Masanaga and deputy of the divided counties Nei and Izumi who had been appointed by a shugo.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>さらに、義材派の幕臣・昵近公家衆・禅僧ら70人余りが越中下向につき従った（越中公方）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, over 70 people including vassals of the shogun, Jikkin Kugeshu(昵近公家衆), Zen monks, etc., who were close to Yoshiki, followed his move to Ecchu (the Ecchu Governor-General).</e>
<cmt>昵近衆は武家時代に将軍またはその使者が上洛した時の接待役（大辞泉）ですが、昵近公家衆がこれと同じものかどうかは調べがつきませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, over 70 people including vassals of the shogun, Jikkin Kugeshu(昵近公家衆), Zen monks, etc., who were close to Yoshiki, followed his move to Ecchu (the Ecchu Governor-General).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, over 70 people including vassals of the shogun, Jikkin Kugeshu (昵近公家衆), Zen monks, etc., who were close to Yoshiki, followed his move to Ecchu (the Ecchu Governor-General).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>この政変で政元は幕政を掌握し、奉公衆などの軍事的基盤が崩壊した将軍権力は、幕府公権の二分化により弱体化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this incident, Masamoto took over shogunal administration, and the authority of the shogun whose military foundations, such as shogunal guards, has broken down, got weaker because of bakufu&apos;s governmental authority being divided in two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this incident, Masamoto took over shogunal administration, and the authority of the shogun whose military foundations, such as shogunal guards, had broken down, became weaker because of the bakufu&apos;s governmental authority being divided into two.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this incident, Masamoto took over shogunal administration, and the authority of the shogun whose military foundations, such as shogunal guards, had broken down, became weaker because of the bakufu&apos;s governmental authority being divided into two.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これにより、二流に分かれた将軍家を擁した抗争が各地で続くこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This caused conflicts all over the country among supports of the shogunal family that had divided into two lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This caused conflicts all over the country among supporters of the shogunal family that divided into two lines.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This caused conflicts all over the country among supporters of the shogunal family that divided into two lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>以後、幕政は細川氏の権力により支えられる事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, shogunal administration was supported by the Hosokawa clan&apos;s power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, shogunal administration was supported by the Hosokawa clan&apos;s power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, shogunal administration was supported by the Hosokawa clan&apos;s power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>また、これに関連して義材派の山城守護・伊勢貞陸（貞宗の子）が、山城国一揆を主導してきた国人層を懐柔して政元への抵抗を試み、また、政元も対抗策として同様の措置を採った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, connected to this, the military governor of Yamashiro, Sadamichi ISE (the son of Sadamune), who was close to Yoshiki, won over the local samurai class who had led the uprising in Yamashiro province and tried to resist Masamoto, and Masamoto did the same as a countermeasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, in connection to this, the military governor of Yamashiro, Sadamichi ISE (the son of Sadamune), who was close to Yoshiki, won over the local samurai class who had led an uprising in Yamashiro province and tried to resist Masamoto, and Masamoto used the same technique as a countermeasure.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, in connection to this, the military governor of Yamashiro, Sadamichi ISE (the son of Sadamune), who was close to Yoshiki, won over the local samurai class who had led an uprising in Yamashiro Province and tried to resist Masamoto, and Masamoto used the same technique as a countermeasure.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>このため、国人層は伊勢派と細川派に分裂してしまい、翌年には山城国一揆は解散に追い込まれる事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owing to that, the local samurai class divided into an Ise faction and a Hosokawa faction, and the next year the uprising in Yamashiro province was forced to disband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, the local samurai class divided into an Ise faction and a Hosokawa faction, and the following year the uprising in Yamashiro province was forced to disband.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, the local samurai class divided into an Ise faction and a Hosokawa faction, and the following year the uprising in Yamashiro Province was forced to disband.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに近年では、同年に発生した今川氏家臣北条早雲（北条早雲）の伊豆国侵攻が、義澄と対立関係にあった異母兄である堀越公方・足利茶々丸を倒すために、政元や上杉定正と連携して行われたとする見方が有力になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, recently there is an influential theory that holds that the invasion of Izu province that occurred in the same year by Soun HOJO, a vassal of Imagawa clan, was intended to defeat Chachamaru ASHIKAGA, who was the Horikoshi Governor-General and Yoshizumi&apos;s brother by a different mother, and was at loggerheads with Yoshizumi, in cooperation with Masamoto and Sadamasa UESUGI.</e>
<cmt>原文「今川氏家臣北条早雲（北条早雲）」と、北条早雲の名前がダブっておりましたので、2度目を（）ごと削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, recently there is an influential theory that the invasion of Izu province by Soun HOJO, a vassal of the Imagawa clan, that occurred in the same year, in cooperation with Masamoto and Sadamasa UESUGI, was intended to defeat Chachamaru ASHIKAGA, who was the Horikoshi Governor-General and Yoshizumi&apos;s brother by a different mother, and opposed Yoshizumi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, recently there is an influential theory that the invasion of Izu Province by Soun HOJO, a vassal of the Imagawa clan, that occurred in the same year, in cooperation with Masamoto and Sadamasa UESUGI, was intended to defeat Chachamaru ASHIKAGA, who was the Horikoshi Governor-General and Yoshizumi&apos;s brother by a different mother, and opposed Yoshizumi.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="24">
<j>このように、明応の政変は中央だけのクーデター事件ではなく、全国、特に東国で戦乱と下克上の動きを恒常化させる契機となる、重大な分岐点であり、戦国時代の始期とする説が近年の日本史学界では有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, there is an influential theory among historians of Japan in recent years, saying that the Meio Incident was not only a coup in the central government but also a critical turning point, which gave an opportunity that made the disturbance of war and the reversal where the low dominate the high constants all over the country, especially in the eastern provinces, and that it was the initial stage of the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly, in recent years there is an influential theory among Japanese historians, that the Meio Incident was not only a coup d&apos;etat in the central government but also a critical turning point, which led to social upheaval and rebellions agains the ruling classes, especially in the eastern provinces, and was the initial stage of the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly, in recent years there is an influential theory among Japanese historians, that the Meio Incident was not only a coup d&apos;etat in the central government but also a critical turning point, which led to social upheaval and rebellions against the ruling classes, especially in the eastern provinces, and was the initial stage of the Warring States period.</e>
<cmt>againstスペル訂正しました、</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>史料</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical Sources</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical Sources</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical Sources</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>『大乗院寺社雑事記』 - 興福寺の尋尊、政覚らの日記。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine) - a diary written by Jinson, Seikaku and others at Kofukuji-Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo Temple and Shrine) - a diary written by Jinson, Seikaku and others at Kofukuji-Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Daijoin jisha zojiki&quot; (Miscellaneous Records of the Daijo-in Temple and Shrine): a diary written by Jinson, Seikaku and others at Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、:+スペースに訂正しました。-in補足。Kofuku-ji Templeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>190巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has 190 volumes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are 190 volumes.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are 190 volumes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), 水野白楓(id:22811), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Sh(id:2707), でここ(id:9565), MDR-SK(id:192066), Kurz(id:1601), らりた(id:1327), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), オタスケマン(id:117461), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), KMT at univ(id:8782), 怪蘇(id:45514), Shimoxx(id:9332), Ponsaku(id:31417), Greenishpurplr(id:39890), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>