<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三左衛門事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">San-saemon Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">San-saemon Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">San-saemon Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三左衛門事件（さんさえもんじけん）とは、一条能保・一条高能父子の遺臣が権大納言土御門通親襲撃を企てたとして捕らえられた事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The San-saemon incident was the incident in which former retainers of Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and Takayoshi ICHIJO, the dead father and son, were captured for the reason that they attempted to attack Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The San-saemon incident was the incident in which former retainers of the deceased father and son, Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and Takayoshi ICHIJO, were arrested for attempting to attack Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>the dead father and son を the deceased father and son に、captured を arrested に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The San-saemon incident was the incident in which former retainers of the deceased father and son, Yoshiyasu ICHIJO and Takayoshi ICHIJO, were arrested for attempting to attack Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, Gon Dainagon (provisional major counselor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この事件は源頼朝死去の翌月に発生し、鎌倉幕府を揺るがせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident occurred in the month following the month when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo died, and shook the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident occurred in the month following the death of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and shook the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the month when MINAMOTO no Yoritomo died&quot; を 簡潔に書換えました。また幕府の解説を書き添えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident occurred in the month following the death of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and shook the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「三左衛門」とは、首謀者とされた3名がいずれも左衛門尉であったことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of &quot;San-saemon&quot; originated in the fact all of the three leaders of the attempt were at the Saemon no jo post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;San-saemon&quot; originated due to the fact that all of the three (san in Japanese) leaders of the attempt held the position of Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>in the fact を due to the fact に書換え、three の 日本語読みを追記、左衛門の解説を書き添えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;San-saemon&quot; originated due to the fact that all of the three (san in Japanese) leaders of the attempt held the position of Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>建久10年1月20日 (旧暦)（1199年2月16日）、13日に発生した鎌倉幕府初代征夷大将軍源頼朝急逝の報が京都に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 16, 1199, the report that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the first Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who was to subdue the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu died suddenly on February 9 reached Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 23, 1199, word reached Kyoto that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the first Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdued the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu, died suddenly on February 16.</e>
<cmt>日付表示をグレゴリオ暦に訂正しました。　the report を word に変更しました。　who was to subdue を who subdued に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 23, 1199, word reached Kyoto that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, the first Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdued the barbarians&quot;) of the Kamakura bakufu, died suddenly on February 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後鳥羽院の院別当としてその院政を支えていた土御門通親は、長年頼朝やその盟友である九条兼実らと対立関係にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, who had supported Insei (the government by the retired emperor) as In no betto (chief administrator of the retired Emperor&apos;s office) to Gotoba-in (the Retired Emperor Gotoba), had confronted Yoritomo and Kanezane KUJO, Yoritomo&apos;s close associate, for many years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, who had supported Insei (the government by the retired emperor) as In no betto (chief administrator of the retired Emperor&apos;s office) to Gotoba-in (the Retired Emperor Gotoba), had been in confrontation with Yoritomo and Kanezane KUJO, Yoritomo&apos;s close associate, for many years.</e>
<cmt>had confronted を had been confrontation に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, who had supported Insei (the government by the retired emperor) as In no betto (chief administrator of the retired Emperor&apos;s office) to Gotoba-in (the Retired Emperor Gotoba), had been in confrontation with Yoritomo and Kanezane KUJO, Yoritomo&apos;s close associate, for many years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>それを知ると直ちに自らは右近衛大将に就任して空席となった左近衛中将に頼朝の後継者源頼家の推挙を実現させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Getting this news, he immediately assumed the post of Ukonoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) by himself, and successfully recommended MINAMOTO no Yoriie, the successor of Yoritomo, to the Sakonoe no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) post that had been vacated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon getting this news, he immediately assumed the post of Ukonoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and successfully recommended MINAMOTO no Yoriie, Yoritomo&apos;s successor, to the Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) post that had been vacated.</e>
<cmt>文頭に Upon を追記しました。句読点を訂正しました（、から,）Sakonoe を Sakoneに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon getting this news, he immediately assumed the post of Ukonoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards), and successfully recommended MINAMOTO no Yoriie, Yoritomo&apos;s successor, to the Sakone no chujo (Middle Captain of the Left Division of Inner Palace Guards) post that had been vacated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが、2月14日 (旧暦)（同年3月12日）に、突然一条家 (中御門流)の郎党であった中原政経・後藤基清・小野義成が土御門通親の襲撃・暗殺を計画したとして拘束された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, on March 12, the same year, Masatsune NAKAHARA, Motokiyo GOTO, and Yoshinari ONO, all of who were retainers of the Ichijo family (in the lineage of the Nakamikado family), were suddenly arrested for the reason that they attempted to attack and kill Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, on March 12, the same year, Masatsune NAKAHARA, Motokiyo GOTO, and Yoshinari ONO, all of whom were retainers of the Ichijo family (in the lineage of the Nakamikado family), were suddenly arrested for attempting to attack and kill Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>arrested for the reason that they attempted to attack and kill Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO を arrested for attempting to attack and kill Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO に言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, on March 12, the same year, Masatsune NAKAHARA, Motokiyo GOTO, and Yoshinari ONO, all of whom were retainers of the Ichijo family (in the lineage of the Nakamikado family), were suddenly arrested for attempting to attack and kill Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一条家は源頼朝の縁戚で、2年前に死去した一条能保は頼朝の妹婿、その翌年（すなわち拘束の5ヶ月前）に急逝した息子・高能は頼朝の甥にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ichijo family was a relative of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, with Yoshiyasu ICHIJO, who died two years before, being the husband of Yoritomo&apos;s younger sister, and with Takayoshi, who was Yoshiyasu&apos;s son and died suddenly in the next year (or in fie months before the arrest) being a nephew of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ichijo family were relatives of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo: Yoshiyasu ICHIJO, who died two years before, was the husband of Yoritomo&apos;s younger sister and Takayoshi, Yoshiyasu&apos;s son who died suddenly the following year (or five months before the arrest) was a nephew of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>The Ichijo family was a relative of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo 以下を コロンで区切り、with を削除した上で文を続けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ichijo family were relatives of MINAMOTO no Yoritomo: Yoshiyasu ICHIJO, who died two years before, was the husband of Yoritomo&apos;s younger sister and Takayoshi, Yoshiyasu&apos;s son who died suddenly the following year (or five months before the arrest) was a nephew of Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>いずれも京都守護として活躍し、3名は一条家の郎党であるとともに、在京御家人でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of them played a distinguished role as Shugo (a constable) in Kyoto, and the three persons were not only retainers of the Ichijo family but gokenin (immediate retainers of the shogun) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of them played a distinguished role as Shugo (a constable) in Kyoto, and the three persons were not only retainers of the Ichijo family but gokenin (immediate retainers of the shogun) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of them played a distinguished role as Shugo (a constable) in Kyoto, and the three persons were not only retainers of the Ichijo family but gokenin (immediate retainers of the shogun) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>換言すれば、一条親子の職務を補佐していた言わば鎌倉幕府の京都における代表の一員とも言うべき人物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, assisting the jobs of the father and son of the Ichijo family, the three were the persons that could be said to べrepresentatives of the Kamakura bakufu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, assisting the jobs of the father and son of the Ichijo family, the trio were those that could be said to be representatives of the Kamakura bakufu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「べ」 を 「be」 に訂正しました。the three were the persons を the trio were those に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, assisting the jobs of the father and son of the Ichijo family, the trio were those that could be said to be representatives of the Kamakura bakufu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>従って、鎌倉幕府が通親暗殺を計画していたという疑惑が持ち上がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the suspicion that the Kamakura bakufu might have attempted to kill Michichika was raised.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the suspicion was raised that the Kamakura bakufu might have attempted to kill Michichika.</e>
<cmt>the suspicion 以下の構文を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the suspicion was raised that the Kamakura bakufu might have attempted to kill Michichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これに危機感を抱いた頼家ら鎌倉幕府首脳は奉行人である中原親能を上洛させて弁明に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this situation, the leaders of Kamakura bakufu, including Yoriie, had a sense of crisis, and sent Chikayoshi NAKAHARA to Kyoto to explain the situation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this situation, the leaders of the Kamakura bakufu, including Yoriie, felt a sense of crisis, and sent Chikayoshi NAKAHARA, the government commissioner, to Kyoto to explain the situation.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ　奉行人 the government commissioner を記述しました。　For this situation を During this situation に置換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this situation, the leaders of the Kamakura bakufu, including Yoriie, felt a sense of crisis, and sent Chikayoshi NAKAHARA, the government commissioner, to Kyoto to explain the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その結果、朝廷は幕府の弁明を受け入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, the Imperial court accepted the explanation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result, the Imperial court accepted the explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the result, the Imperial court accepted the explanation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかしながら、三左衛門（中原・後藤・小野）は所領没収の上に鎌倉に送還、後藤基清が兼ねていた讃岐国守護を免職された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the San-saemon officers (Nakahara, Goto, Ono) had their territoties confiscated and were made to return to Kamakura, and Motokiyo GOTO was also dismissed from the Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki) post that he had assumed additionally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the San-saemon officers (Nakahara, Goto, Ono) had their territories confiscated and were made to return to Kamakura, and Motokiyo GOTO was also dismissed from the Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki) post that he had also assumed.</e>
<cmt>additionally を also で言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the San-saemon officers (Nakahara, Goto, Ono) had their territories confiscated and were made to return to Kamakura, and Motokiyo GOTO was also dismissed from the Sanuki no kuni no kami (Provincial Governor of Sanuki) post that he had also assumed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>一条家と関係の深かった西園寺公経（能保の娘婿）・持明院保家（能保の従兄弟・猶子）・源隆保の3名の公卿・官人も出仕を止められて失脚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three persons of Kintsune SAIONJI (Yoshiyasu&apos;s son-in-law), Yasuie JIMYOIN (Yoshiyasu&apos;s male cousin and adopted son) and MINAMOTO no Takayasu, all of who had a close relationship with the Ichijo family, were prohibited from entering the Imperial court as Kugyo (court nobles) nor government officers, losing their power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The trio (court nobles and government officers) of Kintsune SAIONJI (Yoshiyasu&apos;s son-in-law), Yasuie JIMYOIN (Yoshiyasu&apos;s cousin and adopted son) and MINAMOTO no Takayasu, all of whom had a close relationship with the Ichijo family, were prohibited from entering the Imperial court and lost their power.</e>
<cmt>The tio の意味合いを補足しました。　either as Kugyo (court nobles) or government officers, thus losing their power. を割愛し、lost their prwer で文章を括りました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The trio (court nobles and government officers) of Kintsune SAIONJI (Yoshiyasu&apos;s son-in-law), Yasuie JIMYOIN (Yoshiyasu&apos;s cousin and adopted son) and MINAMOTO no Takayasu, all of whom had a close relationship with the Ichijo family, were prohibited from entering the Imperial court and lost their power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>更に一条家や鎌倉幕府と親交が厚かった僧侶文覚も佐渡国に流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, priest Mongaku who was intimate with the Ichijo family as well as the Kamakura bakufu was exiled to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, priest Mongaku who was intimate with the Ichijo family as well as the Kamakura bakufu was exiled to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, priest Mongaku who was intimate with the Ichijo family as well as the Kamakura bakufu was exiled to Sado Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これによって、朝廷内の親鎌倉幕府派は一時的に壊滅的な打撃を蒙った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the Kamakura bakufu-supporting group in the Imperial court temporarily was damaged fatally.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the Kamakura bakufu faction in the Imperial court was temporarily fatally damaged.</e>
<cmt>the Kamakura bakufu-supporting group は the Kamakura bakufu faction に言い換えました。　temporarily was damaged fatally の語順を変え、temporarily fatally damaged としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the Kamakura bakufu faction in the Imperial court was temporarily fatally damaged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>この事件の裏には土御門通親がいたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO existed in the background of this incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO was somewhere in the background of this incident.</e>
<cmt>considered を thought にｍ、 existed を was somewhere に置換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO was somewhere in the background of this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかしながら、九条兼実の弟・慈円が著した『愚管抄』には、源頼家に近い有力御家人の梶原景季の京都滞在中に事件が起きたこと、鎌倉幕府政所別当の大江広元が通親の方人（同志）であったと記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), written by Jien, a young brother of Kanezane KUJO includes the descriptions that the incident occurred while Kagesue KAJIWARA, a powerful gokenin (retainer of the shogun) close to MINAMOTO no Yoriie was staying in Kyoto and that OE no Hiromoto, Mandokoro betto (Director of the Administrative Board) in the Kamakura bakufu was an associate of Michichika.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), written by Jien, a young brother of Kanezane KUJO includes the descriptions that the incident occurred while Kagesue KAJIWARA, a powerful gokenin (retainer of the shogun) close to MINAMOTO no Yoriie was staying in Kyoto and that OE no Hiromoto, Mandokoro betto (Director of the Administrative Board) in the Kamakura bakufu was an associate of Michichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Jottings of a Fool), written by Jien, a young brother of Kanezane KUJO includes the descriptions that the incident occurred while Kagesue KAJIWARA, a powerful gokenin (retainer of the shogun) close to MINAMOTO no Yoriie was staying in Kyoto and that OE no Hiromoto, Mandokoro betto (Director of the Administrative Board) in the Kamakura bakufu was an associate of Michichika.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これについて、河内祥輔は九条兼実の日記『玉葉』建久9年正月6日・7日条に源頼朝が、後鳥羽天皇（当時）退位後の後継者として、天皇の同母兄で頼朝の遠縁にあたる持明院陳子を妃としていた守貞親王を推挙する意向を示していることを記していることを指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning this matter, Shosuke KOUCHI points out as follows: The article on February 20 and 21, 1198, in &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; a diary written by Kanezane KUJO, describes that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had an intention of recommending Imperial Prince Morisada, an elder brother of the emperor and a remote relative of Yoritomo, as the successor to Emperor Gotoba (at that time) after the emperor abdicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning this matter, Shosuke KOUCHI points out as follows: The article on February 20 and 21, 1198, in &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; a diary written by Kanezane KUJO, describes that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had the intention of recommending Imperial Prince Morisada, an elder brother of the Emperor and a distant relative of Yoritomo, as the successor to Emperor Gotoba (at that time) after the Emperor abdicated.</e>
<cmt>an intention を the intention に、 a remote relative を a distant relative に、the emperor を the Emperor に訂正しました。in &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; の余分な空白を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning this matter, Shosuke KOUCHI points out as follows: The article on February 20 and 21, 1198, in &quot;Gyokuyo,&quot; a diary written by Kanezane KUJO, describes that MINAMOTO no Yoritomo had the intention of recommending Imperial Prince Morisada, an elder brother of the Emperor and a distant relative of Yoritomo, as the successor to Emperor Gotoba (at that time) after the Emperor abdicated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>後鳥羽天皇はこれを無視して同月11日に実子の為仁親王（土御門天皇）を立太子して即日に譲位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ignoring this, Emperor Gotoba made Imperial Prince Tamehito (later Emperor Tsuchimikado), his biological child, the Crown Prince on the eleventh of the same month and abdicated the throne in favor of Tamehito on the same day.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ignoring this, Emperor Gotoba made Imperial Prince Tamehito (later Emperor Tsuchimikado), his biological child, the Crown Prince on the eleventh of the same month and abdicated the throne in favor of Tamehito on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ignoring this, Emperor Gotoba made Imperial Prince Tamehito (later Emperor Tsuchimikado), his biological child, the Crown Prince on the eleventh of the same month and abdicated the throne in favor of Tamehito on the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかしながら、この頼朝の提案が事実とすれば為仁親王の外祖父である土御門通親は勿論のこと、守貞に譲位されれば治天の資格を喪失することになる後鳥羽院はともに強く反発したと予想され、朝幕関係は極めて緊張したと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if Yoritomo&apos;s proposal was a fact, it is supposed that not only Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, the maternal grandfather of Imperial Prince Tamehito, but also Gotoba-in (the Retired Emperor Gotoba), who would lose the power to control the nation if Morisada became emperor, opposed it strongly, and it is considered that the relations between the Imperial court and the bakufu was strained seriously.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if Yoritomo&apos;s proposal was true, it is supposed that not only Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, the maternal grandfather of Imperial Prince Tamehito, but also Gotoba-in (the Retired Emperor Gotoba), who would lose the power to control the nation if Morisada became Emperor, opposed it strongly: it is also thought that relations between the Imperial court and the bakufu were seriously strained at this time.</e>
<cmt>a fact を true に、considered を thought に、the relations between the Imperial court and the bakufu was strained seriously を relations between the Imperial court and the bakufu were seriously strained at this time に訂正しました。opposed it strongly をコロンで区切り文を続けました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if Yoritomo&apos;s proposal was true, it is supposed that not only Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO, the maternal grandfather of Imperial Prince Tamehito, but also Gotoba-in (the Retired Emperor Gotoba), who would lose the power to control the nation if Morisada became Emperor, opposed it strongly: it is also thought that relations between the Imperial court and the bakufu were seriously strained at this time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>河内説は広元・景季が頼朝の死をきっかけに守貞擁立構想の責任を中御門流一条家及び同族の持明院家に転嫁することによって、新将軍頼家と後鳥羽院の関係を一から再構築しなおして事態の収拾を図ったとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on Kouchi&apos;s theory, the situation was as follows: Taking the opportunity when Yoritomo died, Hiromoto and Kagesue tried to shift the responsibility of having considered making Morisada emperor onto the Ichijo family and the Jimyoji family, in order to get the situation under control and to reconstruct relationships between Yoriie, the new shogun, and Gotoba-in from scratch</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on Kouchi&apos;s theory, the situation was as follows: taking advantage of the death of Yoritomo, Hiromoto and Kagesue tried to shift the responsibility of having considered making Morisada Emperor onto the Ichijo family and the Jimyoji family, as a means of getting the situation under control and to rebuild relationships between Yoriie, the new shogun, and Gotoba-in.</e>
<cmt>Taking the opportunity when Yoritomo died, を taking advantage of the death of Yoritomo,に簡潔に書換え、in order to get を as a means of getting に置換え、reconstruct … from scrach を rebuild 一語で言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on Kouchi&apos;s theory, the situation was as follows: taking advantage of the death of Yoritomo, Hiromoto and Kagesue tried to shift the responsibility of having considered making Morisada Emperor onto the Ichijo family and the Jimyoji family, as a means of getting the situation under control and to rebuild relationships between Yoriie, the new shogun, and Gotoba-in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>建仁2年（1202年）の土御門通親の病没から2ヶ月後、九条兼実の子九条良経が摂政となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In two months after Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO died in 1202, Yoshitsune KUJO, a son of Yoshitsune KUJO, was appointed to the Sessho (regent) post.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two months after Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO died in 1202, Yoshitsune KUJO, son of Yoshitsune KUJO, was appointed to the Sessho (regent) post.</e>
<cmt>In two months after を Two months after に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two months after Michichika TSUCHIMIKADO died in 1202, Yoshitsune KUJO, son of Yoshitsune KUJO, was appointed to the Sessho (regent) post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これをきっかけに九条家と縁戚関係にあった3名の公卿・官人は政界に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, the three kugyo or government officer, who were relatives of the Kujo family, returned to the national political world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking this opportunity, the three kugyo (court nobles) or government officers, who were relatives of the Kujo family, returned to the national political world.</e>
<cmt>kugyo の英訳追加と government officer を複数記述しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, the three kugyo (court nobles) or government officers, who were relatives of the Kujo family, returned to the national political world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>一条家の当主一条信能（能保の子）やその甥の一条頼氏（高能の子）も後鳥羽院の院近臣に取り立てられ、三左衛門も赦免を受けたが、後鳥羽院に疎まれていた文覚のみは現地で客死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyoshi ICHIJO (Yoshiyasu&apos;s son), the head of the Ichijo family, and Yoriuji ICHIJO (Takayoshi&apos;s son), his nephew, were also employed as trusted personnel of Gotoba-in, and the San-saemon persons were pardoned as well, but Mongaku alone, who was disliked by Gotoba-in, died in the exile.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyoshi ICHIJO (Yoshiyasu&apos;s son), the head of the Ichijo family, and his nephew, Yoriuji ICHIJO (Takayoshi&apos;s son), were also employed as trusted personnel of Gotoba-in: the San-saemon trio were pardoned as well, but Mongaku alone, who was disliked by Gotoba-in, died in exile.</e>
<cmt>Yoriuji ICHIJO (Takayoshi&apos;s son), his nephew の表記を、his nephew, Yoriuji ICHIJO (Takayoshi&apos;s son) に変更しました。Gotoba-in 以下をコロンで区切り文を続けました。文末の余分な余白を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyoshi ICHIJO (Yoshiyasu&apos;s son), the head of the Ichijo family, and his nephew, Yoriuji ICHIJO (Takayoshi&apos;s son), were also employed as trusted personnel of Gotoba-in: the San-saemon trio were pardoned as well, but Mongaku alone, who was disliked by Gotoba-in, died in exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>後鳥羽院は依然として鎌倉幕府に不満を抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotoba-in still had complaints against the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotoba-in still had complaints against the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotoba-in still had complaints against the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかしながら、親幕府派とされた九条家・西園寺家・中御門流一条家が後鳥羽院政を支える構造の形成と親朝廷派とみなされた源実朝の将軍就任によって幕府と対立する表立った理由が失われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Gotoba-in&apos;s government structure based on the support of the Kujo family, the Saionji family, and the Ichijo family in the lineage of the Nakamikado family became to be formed, and as MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, considered belonging to the Imperial court group, assumed the shogun post, the Imperial court lost the reasons to confront the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as Gotoba-in&apos;s government structure came to be formed (based on the support of the Kujo family, the Saionji family, and the Ichijo family in the lineage of the Nakamikado family), and as MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who was considered to belong to the Imperial court faction, assumed the shogun post, the Imperial court lost reasons to confront the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処がなされているため、原文の「理由が失われ、」を「理由が失われた。」にしました。　as Gotoba-in&apos;s government structure based on the support of the Kujo family, the Saionji family, and the Ichijo family in the lineage of the Nakamikado family became to be formed, を as Gotoba-in&apos;s government structure came to be formed (based on the support of the Kujo family, the Saionji family, and the Ichijo family in the lineage of the Nakamikado family), と書換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as Gotoba-in&apos;s government structure came to be formed (based on the support of the Kujo family, the Saionji family, and the Ichijo family in the lineage of the Nakamikado family), and as MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, who was considered to belong to the Imperial court faction, assumed the shogun post, the Imperial court lost reasons to confront the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>そして、実朝暗殺事件までは、朝廷と鎌倉幕府の関係は一応の安定期に入る事となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the relationships between the Imperial court and the Kamakura bakufu remained stable anyhow until MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relationships between the Imperial court and the Kamakura bakufu remained stable until MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>同理由で、原文に「そして、」を加えました。　Then the を削除しました。until と MINAMOTO 間にある余分な空白を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relationships between the Imperial court and the Kamakura bakufu remained stable until MINAMOTO no Sanetomo was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="30">
<j>なお事件発覚の際に、文覚が保証人となることで一命を救われていた平六代（平維盛の子）も文覚に連座して処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Rokudai (a son of TAIRA no Koremori), who escaped death due to Mongaku&apos;s guarantee when the incident was exposed, was killed together with Mongaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Rokudai (a son of TAIRA no Koremori), who escaped death due to Mongaku&apos;s guarantee when the incident was exposed, was killed together with Mongaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Rokudai (a son of TAIRA no Koremori), who escaped death due to Mongaku&apos;s guarantee when the incident was exposed, was killed together with Mongaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この事件のとばっちりを受ける形で、無関係であった平家一門の嫡流は断絶することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In repercussions of this incident, the direct descendant family of the Taira clan became extinct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As repercussions for this incident, the direct descendant family of the Taira clan, which had nothing to do with the incident, ended up breaking off.</e>
<cmt>In repercussions を As repercussions に訂正、the Taira clan 以下を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As repercussions for this incident, the direct descendant family of the Taira clan, which had nothing to do with the incident, ended up breaking off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Greenland4(id:114494), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>