<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>彦根城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikone-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikone-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikone-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>天守、 櫓、門、塀、馬屋、石垣、土塁、堀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">tenshu (castle tower), yagura (turret), mon (gate), hei (wall), umaya (stable), ishigaki (stone wall), dorui (earthwork), hori (moat)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">tenshu (castle tower), yagura (turret), mon (gate), hei (wall), umaya (stable), ishigaki (stone wall), dorui (earthwork), hori (moat)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">tenshu (castle tower), yagura (turret), mon (gate), hei (wall), umaya (stable), ishigaki (stone wall), dorui (earthwork), hori (moat)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goten (palace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goten (palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goten (palace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>国宝（天守等2棟）国の重要文化財（櫓、門、馬屋等5棟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure (tenshu and a structure), national important cultural property (five structures including yagura, mon, umaya)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National treasures (two structures including tenshu) and national important cultural properties (five structures including yagura, mon, umaya)</e>
<cmt>複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National treasures (two structures including tenshu) and national important cultural properties (five structures including yagura, mon, umaya)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>彦根城（ひこねじょう）は、日本の滋賀県彦根市金亀町にあった城である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikone-jo Castle is a castle that existed in Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikone-jo Castle is a castle that existed in Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikone-jo Castle is a castle that existed in Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代および明治2年（1869年）の版籍奉還後から明治4年（1871年）廃藩置県まで彦根藩の役所が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo Period and from Hansekihokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) in 1869 through Haihanchiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefecture) in 1871, the office of Hikone Domain was placed in the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo Period and from Hansekihokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) in 1869 through Haihanchiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in 1871, the office of Hikone Domain was placed in the castle.</e>
<cmt>prefecture→prefectures</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo Period and from Hansekihokan (return of lands and people to the emperor) in 1869 through Haihanchiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in 1871, the office of Hikone Domain was placed in the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>近世にあたる江戸時代に滋賀県彦根市金亀町にある彦根山に、鎮西を担う井伊氏の拠点として置かれた平山城である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is hirayamajiro (castles built on a hill or low mountain surrounded by a plain) and was built on Mt. Hikone in present Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture in Edo Period, which is early modern time in Japan, as the castle for foothold of II clan that served as a defense against the western domains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is hirayamajiro (castles built on a hill or low mountain surrounded by a plain) and was built on Mt. Hikone in present Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture in the Edo Period, which is early modern time in Japan, as the castle for foothold of Ii clan that served as a defense in Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu).</e>
<cmt>II→Ii冠詞「鎮西を担う」の訳を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is hirayamajiro (castles built on a hill or low mountain surrounded by a plain) and was built on Mt. Hikone in present Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture in the Edo Period, which is early modern time in Japan, as the castle for foothold of Ii clan that served as a defense in Chinzei (nickname of Kyushu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>山は「金亀山」との異名を持つため、城は金亀城（こんきじょう）とも称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle is also called Konki-jo Castle because the mountain has a nickname of Mt. Konki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle is also called Konki-jo Castle because the mountain has a nickname of Mt. Konki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle is also called Konki-jo Castle because the mountain has a nickname of Mt. Konki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>多くの大老を輩出した譜代大名である井伊氏14代の居城であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the castle of 14 generations of fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) Ii clan that turned out many Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the castle of fourteen generation of fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) Ii clan that turned out many Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>数字のスペルアウトgenerations→generation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the castle of fourteen generation of fudai daimyo (a daimyo in hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) Ii clan that turned out many Tairo (chief minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>明治初期の廃城令に伴う破却を免れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle escaped the demolition by haijorei (an order for abandoning castles) in early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle escaped the demolition by haijorei (an order for abandoning castles) in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle escaped the demolition by haijorei (an order for abandoning castles) in the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>国宝の天守、附櫓（つけやぐら）および多聞櫓（たもんやぐら）のほか、安土桃山時代 - 江戸時代の櫓・門など5棟が現存し、国の重要文化財に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides its tenshu, tsuke-yagura (Connecting Tower), tamon yagura (a continuous covered gallery or wall tower which ran along the top of the stone walls between the corner towers of a Japanese castle, which provided protection to the castle&apos;s defenders), there are five structures designated national important cultural property including yagura and mon from Azuchi Momoyama through Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides its tenshu, tsuke-yagura (connecting tower), tamon yagura (hall turrets), there are five structures designated national important cultural properties including yagura and mon from the Azuchi Momoyama through the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>「多聞櫓」の定義を用語集に合わせて変更冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides its tenshu, tsuke-yagura (connecting tower), tamon yagura (hall turrets), there are five structures designated national important cultural properties including yagura and mon from the Azuchi Momoyama through the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中でも馬屋は重要文化財指定物件として全国的に稀少であり、国の特別史跡に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the structures umaya is designated national important cultural property, and it is also designated government-designated special historic site.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the structures umaya is rare because it is a structure designated a national important cultural property, and it is also designated a special historic site.</e>
<cmt>「全国的に稀少であり」の訳抜け</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the structures umaya is rare because it is a structure designated a national important cultural property, and it is also designated a special historic site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一説では、大隈重信の上奏によりに建物が保存されることとなったのだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one estimate, the preservation of the structure was decided by Shigenobu OKUMA&apos;s report to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one estimate, the preservation of the structure was decided by Shigenobu OKUMA&apos;s report to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one estimate, the preservation of the structure was decided by Shigenobu OKUMA&apos;s report to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>日本で12箇所の安土桃山時代から江戸時代に建造された天守が現存する城郭の一つ（現存天守現存12天守）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the twelve castles that have existing tenshu (called juni genzon tenshu) built from Azuchi-Momoyama through Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is one of the twelve castles that have existing tenshu (called juni genzon tenshu) built from the Azuchi-Momoyama through the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is one of the twelve castles that have existing tenshu (called juni genzon tenshu) built from the Azuchi-Momoyama through the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その内、国宝に指定された現存天守のある国宝四城の一つに数えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also one of the four castles designated as National Treasure that have existing tenshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also one of the four castles designated as National Treasure that have existing tenshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also one of the four castles designated as National Treasure that have existing tenshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>日本の世界遺産暫定リストにも記載されているが、世界遺産登録は大変厳しい状況にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been on Japan&apos;s Tentative List of World Heritage, but the prospect that it will be registered as one of World Heritage seems to be very difficult.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been on Japan&apos;s Tentative List of World Heritage Site, but the prospect that it would be registered as one of World Heritage Sites seems to be very unlikely.</e>
<cmt>difficult→unlikelywill→would</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been on Japan&apos;s Tentative List of World Heritage Site, but the prospect that it would be registered as one of World Heritage Sites seems to be very unlikely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>滋賀県下で唯一、城郭建築が保存された（歴史・沿革を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is only castle in Shiga Prefecture that the castle architecture has been preserved. (refer to History)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is only castle in Shiga Prefecture that the castle architecture has been preserved (refer to History).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is only castle in Shiga Prefecture that the castle architecture has been preserved (refer to History).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>構造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Structure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>城の形式は連郭式平山城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle&apos;s form of structure is renkakushiki (renkaku style, which has the hon maru in the center with the ni no maru and the san no maru on either side. When building a castle of this style, it was necessary to provide extra protection for the more exposed hon maru.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle is hirayamajiro of renkakushiki (renkaku style, which has the hon maru in the center with the ni no maru and the san no maru on either side. When building a castle of this style, it was necessary to provide extra protection for the more exposed hon maru.).</e>
<cmt>「形式」の部分を簡略「平山城」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle is hirayamajiro of renkakushiki (renkaku style, which has the hon maru in the center with the ni no maru and the san no maru on either side. When building a castle of this style, it was necessary to provide extra protection for the more exposed hon maru.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>また、現存例の少ない倭城築城の技法である「登り石垣」が良好な形で保存されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Nobori-ishigaki stone walls, which are rare and built by a method of building Wajo (Japanese-style castle), are preserved in good shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Nobori-ishigaki stone walls, which are rare and built by a method of building Wajo (Japanese-style castle), are preserved in good shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Nobori-ishigaki stone walls, which are rare and built by a method of building Wajo (Japanese-style castle), are preserved in good shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、城の北側には玄宮園・楽々園という大名庭園が配されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, on the north side of the castle, Daimyo Garden called Genkyu-en Garden and Rakuraku-en Garden are placed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, on the north side of the castle, Daimyo Garden called Genkyu-en Garden and Rakuraku-en Garden are placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, on the north side of the castle, Daimyo Garden called Genkyu-en Garden and Rakuraku-en Garden are placed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これらは国指定の名勝である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The gardens are government-designated place of scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gardens are government-designated places of scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>複数形</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gardens are government-designated places of scenic beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>地理特性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geographical Features</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geographical Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geographical Features</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>湖と山の間、5kmほどの狭い平地に立地する彦根は、中山道と北陸道（俗に北国街道と称）が合流し、水陸から京都に至る東日本と西日本の結節点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikone, located in a narrow plain area stretching about five kilometers between a lake and a mountain, is the joining point that Eastern and Western Japan meet and two roads Nakasen-do Road and Hokuriku-do (commonly called Hokkoku-kaido Road) join together, and from this point the roads to Kyoto by land or water begins.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikone, located in a narrow plain area stretching about five kilometers between a lake and a mountain, is the point where Eastern and Western Japan meet and two roads Nakasen-do Road and Hokuriku-do (commonly called Hokkoku-kaido Road) join together, and from this point the roads to Kyoto by land or water begins.</e>
<cmt>スペースjoiningを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikone, located in a narrow plain area stretching about five kilometers between a lake and a mountain, is the point where Eastern and Western Japan meet and two roads Nakasen-do Road and Hokuriku-do (commonly called Hokkoku-kaido Road) join together, and from this point the roads to Kyoto by land or water begins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>壬申の乱（672年）・姉川の戦い（1570年）・賤ヶ岳の戦い（1583年）・関ヶ原の戦い（1600年）等、古来、多くの合戦がこの地域で繰り広げられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and around this area, many battles such as Jinshin War (in 672), the Battle of Anegawa (in 1570), the Battle of Shizugatake (in 1583) and the Battle of Sekigahara (in 1600) were fought from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and around this area many battles, such as Jinshin War (in 672), the Battle of Anegawa (in 1570), the Battle of Shizugatake (in 1583) and the Battle of Sekigahara (in 1600), were fought from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>カンマ</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and around this area many battles, such as Jinshin War (in 672), the Battle of Anegawa (in 1570), the Battle of Shizugatake (in 1583) and the Battle of Sekigahara (in 1600), were fought from the ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>戦略拠点としてその点に注目され、織田信長は佐和山城に丹羽長秀を入れ、ほど近い長浜城 (近江国)を豊臣秀吉に与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Hikone attracted many warlords&apos; attention as their strategic point, Nobunaga ODA placed Nagahide NIWA in Sawayama Castle and gave Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI Nagahama Castle (in Omi Province) which was near NIWA&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Hikone attracted many warlords&apos; attention as their strategic point, Nobunaga ODA placed Nagahide NIWA in Sawayama-jo Castle and gave Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI Nagahama-jo Castle (in Omi Province) which was near NIWA&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>城の表記を統一用語集に合わせて変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Hikone attracted many warlords&apos; attention as their strategic point, Nobunaga ODA placed Nagahide NIWA in Sawayama-jo Castle and gave Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI Nagahama-jo Castle (in Omi Province) which was near NIWA&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="24">
<j>また、豊臣秀吉と徳川家康はそれぞれ譜代筆頭の石田三成と井伊直政を、この地に配置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA placed their fudai hitto (chief vassal) Mistunari ISHIDA and Naomasa Ii in this place respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA placed their fudai hitto (chief vassal) Mitsunari ISHIDA and Naomasa Ii in this place respectively.</e>
<cmt>三成のスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI and Ieyasu TOKUGAWA placed their fudai hitto (chief vassal) Mitsunari ISHIDA and Naomasa Ii in this place respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>彦根城の建築物には、大津城からの天守を始め、佐和山城から佐和口多門櫓（非現存）と太鼓櫓門、小谷城から西ノ丸三重櫓、観音寺城からや、どこのものかは不明とされているが太鼓門、等の移築伝承が多くある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many transmissions of reconstruction in a new location about the structures of Hikone-jo Castle such as tenshu from Otsu-jo Castle, Sawaguchi Tamon-yagura (corridor-style gate acted as a stonehouse and defense post at the entrance to the second enclosure) (not existent) and Taiko-yagura Mon (Drum Tower Gate) from Sawayama-jo Castle, nishi no maru sanju yagura (three-storied tower located at the northwest corner of nishi no maru) from Odani-jo Castle and Taiko-mon Gate (Drum Gate) from Kannonji Castle or not known from where.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many structures transferred from other castles in Hikone-jo Castle such as tenshu from Otsu-jo Castle, Sawaguchi Tamon-yagura (corridor-style gate acted as a stonehouse and defense post at the entrance to the second enclosure) (not existent) and Taiko-yagura Mon (Drum Tower Gate) from Sawayama-jo Castle, nishi no maru sanju yagura (three-storied tower located at the northwest corner of nishi no maru) from Odani-jo Castle and Taiko-mon Gate (Drum Gate) from Kannonji-jo Castle or not known from where.</e>
<cmt>城の表記を統一用語集に合わせて変更「移築伝承」の訳を変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many structures transferred from other castles in Hikone-jo Castle such as tenshu from Otsu-jo Castle, Sawaguchi Tamon-yagura (corridor-style gate acted as a stonehouse and defense post at the entrance to the second enclosure) (not existent) and Taiko-yagura Mon (Drum Tower Gate) from Sawayama-jo Castle, nishi no maru sanju yagura (three-storied tower located at the northwest corner of nishi no maru) from Odani-jo Castle and Taiko-mon Gate (Drum Gate) from Kannonji-jo Castle or not known from where.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>建物や石材の移築転用はコスト削減と工期短縮のために行われたもので、名古屋城や岡山城や姫路城、福岡城など多くの城に同様の伝承が伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relocation and reuse of structures and stones was for cost reduction and shortening work period, and Nagoya-jo Castle, Okayama-jo Castle, Himeji Castle and Fukuoka-jo Castle and other castles have similar transmission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relocation and reuse of structures and stones was for cost reduction and shortening work period, and Nagoya-jo Castle, Okayama-jo Castle, Himeji-jo Castle and Fukuoka-jo Castle and other castles have had similar transfers.</e>
<cmt>城の表記を統一用語集に合わせて変更「伝承」の訳</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relocation and reuse of structures and stones was for cost reduction and shortening work period, and Nagoya-jo Castle, Okayama-jo Castle, Himeji-jo Castle and Fukuoka-jo Castle and other castles have had similar transfers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>時代劇の撮影などでも使われる天秤櫓は、長浜城 (近江国)から移築したといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Tenbin-yagura (Balancing-scale Tower) often used for shooting of jidaigeki (historical play) was relocated from Nagahama-jo Castle (in Omi Province) and rebuild in Hikone-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Tenbin-yagura (Balancing-scale Tower) often used for shooting of jidaigeki (historical play) was relocated from Nagahama-jo Castle (in Omi Province) and rebuilt in Hikone-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>rebuild→rebuilt</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Tenbin-yagura (Balancing-scale Tower) often used for shooting of jidaigeki (historical play) was relocated from Nagahama-jo Castle (in Omi Province) and rebuilt in Hikone-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この天秤櫓は、堀切の上の掛橋を渡った突き当たりにあたる、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Tenbin-yagura is at the far end of the kakehashi (bridge) over horikiri (moat with water surrounding castle to keep off the invasion of emenies).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Tenbin-yagura is at the far end of the kakehashi (bridge) over horikiri (moat with water surrounding castle to keep off the invasion of enemies).</e>
<cmt>enemiesのスペルミスを修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Tenbin-yagura is at the far end of the kakehashi (bridge) over horikiri (moat with water surrounding castle to keep off the invasion of enemies).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>長い多聞の左右の端に2重2階の一対の隅櫓を構え、あたかも天秤ばかりのような独特な形をしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the both the right and left end of Tamon (corridor style tower) there are a pair of two-storied and two floor style of sumi yagura (corner tower) forming the distinctive shape, giving the impression as if it were a balancing scales.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the both right and left ends of Tamon (corridor style tower) there are a pair of two-storied and two floor style of sumi yagura (corner tower) forming the distinctive shape, giving the impression as if it were a balancing scale.</e>
<cmt>scales→scale</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the both right and left ends of Tamon (corridor style tower) there are a pair of two-storied and two floor style of sumi yagura (corner tower) forming the distinctive shape, giving the impression as if it were a balancing scale.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>通し柱を用いず、各階ごとに積み上げられた天守は、三層三階地下一階の複合式望楼型で「ごぼう積み」と云われる石垣で支えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tenshu (with three layers, three stories and a basement) built without using toshi bashira (through pillar) belongs to multi-layered borogata (a type of castle tower for lookout on the building with a gabled, hipped roof) and is supported with stone walls called gobozumi (a method of piling up stone wall, piling up with deep stones of which bonder side faces front).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenshu (with three layers, three stories and a basement) built without using toshi bashira (through pillar) belongs to the multi-layered borogata style (a type of castle tower for lookout on the building with a gabled, hipped roof) and is supported with stone walls called gobozumi (a method of piling up stone wall, piling up with deep stones of which bonder side faces front).</e>
<cmt>NC-Check(through pillar)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenshu (with three layers, three stories and a basement) built without using toshi bashira (through pillar) belongs to the multi-layered borogata style (a type of castle tower for lookout on the building with a gabled, hipped roof) and is supported with stone walls called gobozumi (a method of piling up stone wall, piling up with deep stones of which bonder side faces front).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>二重目以上の窓はすべて華頭窓を配し、最上階には実用でない外廻り縁と高欄を付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the windows in second and third layer, kato-mado (foliate-top window) are arranged, and in the top layer ornamental sotomawaribuchi (long and rod-like dressed lumber put in the part of ceiling surface and wall surface meeting) and koran (banister) are attached.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For all windows in the second and third layers, kato-mado (foliate-top window) are arranged, and in the top layer ornamental sotomawaribuchi (long and rod-like dressed lumber put in the part of ceiling surface and wall surface meeting) and koran (banister) are attached.</e>
<cmt>先頭にforを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For all windows in the second and third layers, kato-mado (foliate-top window) are arranged, and in the top layer ornamental sotomawaribuchi (long and rod-like dressed lumber put in the part of ceiling surface and wall surface meeting) and koran (banister) are attached.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>各重に千鳥破風、切妻破風、唐破風、入母屋破風を詰め込んだように配置しており、変化に富む表情を見せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In each layer, chidori hafu (dormer and plover gable), kirizuma hafu (gable on the ridge roof), kara hafu (undulating gable) and irimoya hafu (gable of the half-hipped roof) are arranged as if they were packed, and the arrangement shows varied appearances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In each layer, chidori hafu (dormer and plover gable), kirizuma hafu (gable on the ridge roof), kara hafu (undulating gable) and irimoya hafu (gable of the half-hipped roof) are arranged as if they were packed, and the arrangement shows a variety of appearances.</e>
<cmt>varied appearances→a variety of　appearances</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In each layer, chidori hafu (dormer and plover gable), kirizuma hafu (gable on the ridge roof), kara hafu (undulating gable) and irimoya hafu (gable of the half-hipped roof) are arranged as if they were packed, and the arrangement shows a variety of appearances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>大津城天守（4重5階）を3重に縮小して移築したといわれ、昭和の天守解体修理（-）のときに、天守の用材から転用されたものと見られる部材が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tenshu of Hikone-jo Castle was built by transferring and rebuilding Otsu-jo Castle (four layers, five stories) with reducing it to three-layers, and at the taking apart and repairing of Showa (1957-1960) the apparently diverted components in the materials of the tenshu were found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tenshu of Hikone-jo Castle was built by transferring and rebuilding Otsu-jo Castle (four layers, five stories) by reducing it to three-layers, and at the renovation (1957-1960) in the Showa period the apparently diverted components in the materials of the tenshu were found.</e>
<cmt>「解体修理」の訳with→by</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tenshu of Hikone-jo Castle was built by transferring and rebuilding Otsu-jo Castle (four layers, five stories) by reducing it to three-layers, and at the renovation (1957-1960) in the Showa period the apparently diverted components in the materials of the tenshu were found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>歴史・沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>徳川四天王の一人・井伊直政は、関ヶ原の戦いの後、その軍功により18万石にて近江国北東部に封ぜられ、西軍指揮官・石田三成の居城であった佐和山城に入城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Naomasa II, one of Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu, was given the land in northeastern part of Omi Province with 180 thousand goku crop yields by his distinguished military service, and entered Sawayama-jo Castle that had belonged to Mitsunari ISHIDA, his enemy and the commander of West camp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Naomasa II, one of Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu, was given the land in northeastern part of Omi Province with 180 thousand goku crop yields by his distinguished military service, and entered Sawayama-jo Castle that had belonged to Mitsunari ISHIDA, his enemy and the commander of West camp.</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Battle of Sekigahara, Naomasa II, one of Tokugawa-shitenno (four generals serving Tokugawa Ieyasu, was given the land in northeastern part of Omi Province with 180 thousand goku crop yields by his distinguished military service, and entered Sawayama-jo Castle that had belonged to Mitsunari ISHIDA, his enemy and the commander of West camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>佐和山城は石田三成が改築した後は「三成に過ぎたるもの…」の一つともいわれたが、直政は、中世的な古い縄張りや三成の居城であったことを嫌った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was said that the castle was one of &apos;the too good things for Mitsunari&apos; after the rebuilding by Mistunari ISHIDA, but Naomasa disliked its medieval nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures) and the fact that it had been Mitsunari&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was said that the castle was one of &apos;the too good things for Mitsunari&apos; after the rebuilding by Mistunari ISHIDA, but Naomasa disliked its medieval nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures) and the fact that it had been Mitsunari&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was said that the castle was one of &apos;the too good things for Mitsunari&apos; after the rebuilding by Mistunari ISHIDA, but Naomasa disliked its medieval nawabari (castle plan; general term for the layout of a castle and its component structures) and the fact that it had been Mitsunari&apos;s castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>湖岸に近い磯山（現・米原市磯）に居城を移すことを計画していたが、関ヶ原の際の戦傷が癒えずに死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naomasa was planning to move and build his castle in the area close to Lake Biwa, but he couldn&apos;t recover from the battle injury at the Battle of Sekigahara and died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naomasa was planning to move and build his castle in the area close to Lake Biwa, but he couldn&apos;t recover from the battle injury at the Battle of Sekigahara and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naomasa was planning to move and build his castle in the area close to Lake Biwa, but he couldn&apos;t recover from the battle injury at the Battle of Sekigahara and died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>その後井伊直継が家督を継いだが、幼少であった</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After his death Naotsugu II took over as head of the family, but he was too young.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After his death Naotsugu II took over as head of the family, but he was too young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After his death Naotsugu II took over as head of the family, but he was too young.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>このため、直政の遺臣が彼の遺志を継ぎ、再検討の末、琵琶湖に浮かぶ彦根山（金亀山、現在の彦根城の場所）に彦根城の築城を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, Naomasa&apos;s surviving retainers took over the wishes of the deceased, and after the reexamination, they started building the castle on Mt. Hikone (Mt. Konki, present place for Hikone Castle) on Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, Naomasa&apos;s surviving retainers took over the wishes of the deceased, and after the reexamination, they started building the castle on Mt. Hikone (Mt. Konki, present place for Hikone Castle) on Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, Naomasa&apos;s surviving retainers took over the wishes of the deceased, and after the reexamination, they started building the castle on Mt. Hikone (Mt. Konki, present place for Hikone Castle) on Lake Biwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>築城には公儀御奉行3名が付けられ、尾張藩や越前藩など7か国12大名（15大名とも）が手伝いを命じられる天下普請であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In building the castle, three kogiobugyo (shogunate administrator) were appointed, and the construction was tenka bushin (daimyo from every province helping the castle construction under the order of bakufu, shogunate) in which twelve daimyo (or 15 daimyo) in seven countries was ordered to help by Tokugawa government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In building the castle, three kogiobugyo (shogunate administrator) were appointed, and the construction was tenka bushin (daimyo from every province helping the castle construction under the order of bakufu, shogunate) in which twelve daimyo (or fifteen daimyo) in seven provinces including Owari Domain and Echizen Domain was ordered to help.</e>
<cmt>「尾張藩や越前藩」を追加by Tokugawa governmentを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In building the castle, three kogiobugyo (shogunate administrator) were appointed, and the construction was tenka bushin (daimyo from every province helping the castle construction under the order of bakufu, shogunate) in which twelve daimyo (or fifteen daimyo) in seven provinces including Owari Domain and Echizen Domain was ordered to help.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>1606年（慶長11年）2期までの工事が完了し、同年の天守完成と同じ頃に直継が入城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1606 the second-phase construction was completed, and in the same year Naotsugu entered the castle at about the same time of completion of building the tenshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1606 the second-phase construction was completed, and in the same year Naotsugu entered the castle at about the same time of completion of building the tenshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1606 the second-phase construction was completed, and in the same year Naotsugu entered the castle at about the same time of completion of building the tenshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>1616年（元和2年）彦根藩のみの手により第3期工事が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1616 the third-phase construction was started by only Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1616 the third-phase construction was started by only Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1616 the third-phase construction was started by only Hikone Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>この時に御殿が建造され、すべての工事が完了し、彦根城が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Goten (palace) was built at this time and all the construction was finished, Hikone-jo Castle was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Gnoten (palace) was built at this time and all the construction was finished, Hikone-jo Castle was completed.</e>
<cmt>After→When</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Gnoten (palace) was built at this time and all the construction was finished, Hikone-jo Castle was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>その後、井伊氏は加増を重ね、最終的にには譜代最高となる35万石を得るに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, II clan increased its property and at the end attained 350 thousand goku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Ii clan increased its property and at the end attained 350 thousand goku.</e>
<cmt>II→Ii</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Ii clan increased its property and at the end attained 350 thousand goku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>なお、筆頭家老・木俣家は1万石を領しているが、陣屋を持たなかったため、月20日は西の丸三重櫓で執務を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Kimata family that served as the head of chief retainers spent 20 days a month carrying out his work in nishi no maru sanju yagura (three-storied tower located at the northwest corner of nishi no maru) because he did not have his jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the head of the Kimata family that served as the head of chief retainers spent 20 days a month carrying out his work in nishi no maru sanju yagura (three-storied tower located at the northwest corner of nishi no maru) because he did not have his jinya (regional government office) although he had been granted ten thousand goku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>「一万石を領しているが」を追加家老との整合性を取るため、the head of Kimata familyに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the head of the Kimata family that served as the head of chief retainers spent 20 days a month carrying out his work in nishi no maru sanju yagura (three-storied tower located at the northwest corner of nishi no maru) because he did not have his jinya (regional government office) although he had been granted ten thousand goku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>これは、徳川統治下の太平の世においては、城郭というものがすでに軍事施設としての役目を終えて、その存在理由が、権勢の象徴物へと変じたためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because in peace time under the reign of Tokugawa government castles finished their original purpose as military facility and its reason for existence changed to the symbol of the power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because in peace time under the reign of the Tokugawa government castles finished their original purpose as military facility and its reason for existence changed to the symbol of the power.</e>
<cmt>冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because in peace time under the reign of the Tokugawa government castles finished their original purpose as military facility and its reason for existence changed to the symbol of the power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>徳川幕府の西国への重要な備えとしての役割を担う彦根城も、彦根藩の各組織の管轄で天守以下倉庫等として徳川時代の大半を過ごした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hikone-jo Castle that had taken the purpose as important defense wall toward Saigoku spent most of the time in Tokugawa Period as a warehouse and others under the jurisdiction of organizations in the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hikone-jo Castle that had taken the purpose as important defense wall toward Saigoku (western part of Japan) spent most of the time in the Tokugawa Period as a warehouse and others under the jurisdiction of organizations in the domain.</e>
<cmt>「西国」の定義を追加冠詞</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hikone-jo Castle that had taken the purpose as important defense wall toward Saigoku (western part of Japan) spent most of the time in the Tokugawa Period as a warehouse and others under the jurisdiction of organizations in the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="47">
<j>1854年（安政元年）に天秤櫓の大修理が行われ、その際、石垣の半分が積み直された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1854 great repairs of tenbin yagura was conducted, when half of the stones in the stonewall was piled up again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1854 great repairs of tenbin yagura was conducted, when half of the stones in the stonewall was piled up again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1854 great repairs of tenbin yagura was conducted, when half of the stones in the stonewall was piled up again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="48">
<j>向かって右手が築城当初からの「ごぼう積み」、左手が新たに積み直された「落し積み」となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stones in the stone wall on the observer&apos;s right were piled up by the method of original &apos;gobozumi&apos;, and stones on the left were newly piled up with the method of &apos;otoshizumi&apos; (a method of piling up stone wall, putting rectangular stone on the angle for leaning over on the next stone).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stones in the stone wall on the observer&apos;s right were piled up by the method of original &apos;gobozumi&apos;, and stones on the left were newly piled up with the method of &apos;otoshizumi&apos; (a method of piling up stone wall, putting rectangular stone on the angle for leaning over on the next stone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stones in the stone wall on the observer&apos;s right were piled up by the method of original &apos;gobozumi&apos;, and stones on the left were newly piled up with the method of &apos;otoshizumi&apos; (a method of piling up stone wall, putting rectangular stone on the angle for leaning over on the next stone).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="49">
<j>幕末における幕府の大老を務めた井伊直弼は、藩主となるまでをこの城下で過ごしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naosuke II who served as Tairo (chief minister) during the end of Tokugawa Period had spent his time until he became the lord of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naosuke II who served as Tairo (chief minister) during the end of the Edo Period had spent his time at this castle town until he became the lord of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Tokugawa Period→Edo Period「城下で」を追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naosuke II who served as Tairo (chief minister) during the end of the Edo Period had spent his time at this castle town until he became the lord of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>直弼が青春時代を過ごした屋敷は「埋木舎（うもれぎのや）」として現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The residence called &apos;Umoreginoya (Dwelling of Buried Wood) in which he spent his youth still exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The residence called &apos;Umoreginoya (Dwelling of Buried Wood) in which he spent his youth still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The residence called &apos;Umoreginoya (Dwelling of Buried Wood) in which he spent his youth still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>近現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern times and the present day</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern times and the present day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern times and the present day</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>1951年天守等7棟がに重要文化財に指定、うち2棟（天守、附櫓、および、多聞櫓）がに国宝に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1951seven structures of the castle including tenshu were designated as Important Cultural Property, and among them two structures (tenshu, tsuke-yagura (Connecting Tower) and Tamon yagura (hall turrets) were designated as National Treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1951seven structures of the castle including tenshu were designated as Important Cultural Property, and among them two structures (tenshu, tsuke-yagura (Connecting Tower) and Tamon yagura (hall turrets)) were designated as National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>かっこを追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1951seven structures of the castle including tenshu were designated as Important Cultural Property, and among them two structures (tenshu, tsuke-yagura (Connecting Tower) and Tamon yagura (hall turrets)) were designated as National Treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="52">
<j>姫路城とともに遺構をよく遺している城郭で、1951年6月9日に国の特別史跡に指定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle well preserves its ancient structural remnants like Himeji-jo Castle, and it was designated as Special Historic Site on June 6, 1951.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle well preserves its ancient structural remnants like Himeji-jo Castle, and it was designated as Special Historic Site on June 6, 1951.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle well preserves its ancient structural remnants like Himeji-jo Castle, and it was designated as Special Historic Site on June 6, 1951.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>これは姫路城の指定よりも5年早い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The designation was five years earlier than Himeji-jo Castle&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The designation was five years earlier than Himeji-jo Castle&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The designation was five years earlier than Himeji-jo Castle&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="54">
<j>1987年、彦根市市制50周年として御殿が復元され、「彦根城博物館」として藩政時代の調度品・武具などが展示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1987, as a part of Hikone City&apos;s 50th anniversary events, Goten residence was restored as &apos;Hikone Castle Museum&apos; which displays furnishing goods and arms during the period of domain duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1987, as a part of Hikone City&apos;s 50th anniversary events, Goten residence was restored as &apos;Hikone Castle Museum&apos; which displays furnishing goods and arms during the period of domain duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1987, as a part of Hikone City&apos;s 50th anniversary events, Goten residence was restored as &apos;Hikone Castle Museum&apos; which displays furnishing goods and arms during the period of domain duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="55">
<j>2006年4月6日には日本100名城（50番）に選定され、6月から全国規模の日本100名城スタンプラリーが開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 6, 2006 the castle was selected the 50th Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 6, 2006 the castle was selected the 50th Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) and the nationwide stamp rally of Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) started in June.</e>
<cmt>「6月から全国規模の日本100名城スタンプラリーが開始された。」の訳抜け</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 6, 2006 the castle was selected the 50th Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) and the nationwide stamp rally of Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) started in June.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural properties</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="56">
<j>国宝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Treasure</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>天守</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="58">
<j>附櫓、および、多聞櫓（1棟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuke-yagura and Tamon-yagura (one structure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuke-yagura and Tamon-yagura (one structure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuke-yagura and Tamon-yagura (one structure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="59">
<j>重要文化財</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Important Cultural Property</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="60">
<j>天秤櫓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenbin-yagura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenbin-yagura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenbin-yagura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="61">
<j>太鼓門、および、続櫓（1棟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiko-mon and tsuzuki yagura (a wall tower of a Japanese castle which was usually only a single story in height, which functioned as a connecting tower or gallery running along the top of the ishigaki, from which the defenders protected the walls), (one structure).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiko-mon and tsuzuki yagura (a wall tower of a Japanese castle which was usually only a single story in height, which functioned as a connecting tower or gallery running along the top of the ishigaki, from which the defenders protected the walls), (one structure).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiko-mon and tsuzuki yagura (a wall tower of a Japanese castle which was usually only a single story in height, which functioned as a connecting tower or gallery running along the top of the ishigaki, from which the defenders protected the walls), (one structure).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="62">
<j>西の丸三重櫓、および、続櫓（1棟）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi no maru sanju yagura and tsuzuki yagura (one structure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi no maru sanju yagura and tsuzuki yagura (one structure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi no maru sanju yagura and tsuzuki yagura (one structure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="63">
<j>二の丸佐和口多聞櫓</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninomaru Sawaguchi Tamon-yagura (corridor-style gate of Sawaguchi in the outer citadel, acted as a stonehouse and defense post at the entrance to the second enclosure)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninomaru Sawaguchi Tamon-yagura (corridor-style gate of Sawaguchi in the outer citadel, acted as a stonehouse and defense post at the entrance to the second enclosure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninomaru Sawaguchi Tamon-yagura (corridor-style gate of Sawaguchi in the outer citadel, acted as a stonehouse and defense post at the entrance to the second enclosure)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="64">
<j>馬屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Umaya (Stable)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Umaya (Stable)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Umaya (Stable)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>探訪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Touring</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Touring</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Touring</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>その他の事象</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miscellaneous</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>外堀には水戸市から贈られた複数のコクチョウが飼育されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In sotobori (outer moat of castle) some black swans presented from Mito City are raised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In sotobori (outer moat of castle) some black swans presented from Mito City are raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In sotobori (outer moat of castle) some black swans presented from Mito City are raised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>大衆文化のなかの彦根城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikone-jo Castle in the popular culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikone-jo Castle in the popular culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikone-jo Castle in the popular culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>文学</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literature</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="66">
<j>井伊直弼が藩主の座に就くまでに先の藩主やその候補者の多くが夭折（ようせつ）していることから、神秘的な物語の舞台に採り上げられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle is often picked up as the stage for mysterious story because the previous lord of the domain and potential lords had died prematurely before Naosuke II took the position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle is often featured as the stage for mysterious story because the previous lord of the domain and potential lords had died prematurely before Naosuke II took the position.</e>
<cmt>picked up→featured</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle is often featured as the stage for mysterious story because the previous lord of the domain and potential lords had died prematurely before Naosuke II took the position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="67">
<j>なお、国宝・彦根城築城400年の開催を機に、、2007年（平成19年）、小説を対象に、舟橋聖一文学賞が創設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 2007 on the 400th anniversary of Hikone-jo Castle Seiichi FUNAHASHI Literature Prize focused on novels was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 2007 on the 400th anniversary of Hikone-jo Castle Seiichi FUNAHASHI Literature Prize focused on novels was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 2007 on the 400th anniversary of Hikone-jo Castle Seiichi FUNAHASHI Literature Prize focused on novels was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>映像文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Audiovisual Culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Audiovisual Culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Audiovisual Culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>城内は『梟の城梟の城 owl’s castle』、『武士の一分』、『大奥 (映画)』など数多くの映画や、テレビドラマのロケ地として頻繁に使われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area inside the castle is often used as a location site for many movies such as &quot;Fukuro no shiro (Owls&apos; Castle),&quot; &quot;Bushi no ichibu (Love and Honor)&quot; and O-oku, and for many TV dramas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area inside the castle is often used as a location site for many movies such as &quot;Fukuro no shiro (Owls&apos; Castle),&quot; &quot;Bushi no ichibu (Love and Honor)&quot; and O-oku, and for many TV dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area inside the castle is often used as a location site for many movies such as &quot;Fukuro no shiro (Owls&apos; Castle),&quot; &quot;Bushi no ichibu (Love and Honor)&quot; and O-oku, and for many TV dramas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>東映京都撮影所や京都映画撮影所から場所が近いことから、姫路城とともに時代劇のロケが頻繁に行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is often used as a location site for period dramas as well as Himeji-jo castle because it is close to Kyoto Movie Studio Toei and Kyoto Film Studio.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is often used as a location site for period dramas as well as Himeji-jo castle because it is close to Kyoto Movie Studio Toei and Kyoto Film Studio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is often used as a location site for period dramas as well as Himeji-jo castle because it is close to Kyoto Movie Studio Toei and Kyoto Film Studio.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>江戸城の代わりとして用いられる事が多い姫路城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himeji-jo Castle is often used as the Edo Castle for shooting.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himeji-jo Castle is often used as the Edo Castle for shooting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himeji-jo Castle is often used as the Edo Castle for shooting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>それに対して、それより小規模な本城は無名の小城という設定での撮影が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand Hikone-jo Castle is often used for setting as unknown smaller castles than Himeji-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand Hikone-jo Castle is often used for setting as unknown smaller castles.</e>
<cmt>than Himeji-jo Castleを削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand Hikone-jo Castle is often used for setting as unknown smaller castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>観光</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sightseeing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sightseeing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sightseeing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>所在地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Address</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>滋賀県彦根市金亀町1-1</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1-1 Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1-1 Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1-1 Konki-cho, Hikone City, Shiga Prefecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>利用情報</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Information</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Information</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>日本100名城スタンプラリーのスタンプは、彦根城表門券売所に設置されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The stamp for stamp rally of Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) is placed in the ticket office at the front gate of Hikone-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The stamp for stamp rally of Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) is placed in the ticket office at the front gate of Hikone-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The stamp for stamp rally of Nihon 100 meijo (100 great castles in Japan) is placed in the ticket office at the front gate of Hikone-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>東海旅客鉄道・西日本旅客鉄道 東海道新幹線 米原駅から車で約20分、もしくは、東海道本線に連絡。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">20 minutes&apos; drive from Maibara Station of Central Japan Railway Company, West Japan Railway, Tokaido Shinkansen, or transfer to Tokaido Main Line</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">20 minutes&apos; drive from Maibara Station of Central Japan Railway Company, West Japan Railway, Tokaido Shinkansen, or further train ride on the Tokaido Main Line</e>
<cmt>transfer　to→further train ride on</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">20 minutes&apos; drive from Maibara Station of Central Japan Railway Company, West Japan Railway, Tokaido Shinkansen, or further train ride on the Tokaido Main Line</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="78">
<j>JR西日本 東海道本線（琵琶湖線） 彦根駅から徒歩約15分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">15 minutes&apos; walk from Hikone Station of West Japan Railway Company and Tokaido Main Line (Biwako Line)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">15 minutes&apos; walk from Hikone Station of West Japan Railway Company, Tokaido Main Line (Biwako Line)</e>
<cmt>andをカンマに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">15 minutes&apos; walk from Hikone Station of West Japan Railway Company, Tokaido Main Line (Biwako Line)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="79">
<j>自動車道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expressway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expressway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expressway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>名神高速道路 彦根インターチェンジから車で約5分。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About five minutes&apos; drive from Hikone Interchange of Meishin Expressway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About five minutes&apos; drive from Hikone Interchange of Meishin Expressway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About five minutes&apos; drive from Hikone Interchange of Meishin Expressway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="81">
<j>国道8号 ：彦根市・外町交差点で306号と交差。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Route 8 crosses with National Route 6 at To-machi crossing in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Route 8 crosses with National Route 6 at To-machi crossing in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Route 8 crosses with National Route 6 at To-machi crossing in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="82">
<j>国道306号 ：彦根市・外町交差点が終点。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Route 6 ends at To-machi crossing in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Route 6 ends at To-machi crossing in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Route 6 ends at To-machi crossing in Hikone City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="83">
<j>国道307号 ：彦根市・原町交差点が起点。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National Route 7 starts at Hara-cho crossing in Hikone City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National Route 7 starts at Hara-cho crossing in Hikone City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National Route 7 starts at Hara-cho crossing in Hikone City</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Cyclops(id:210075), ミュール(id:16863), BOTarate(id:185620), Bakkai(id:7233), Nnh(id:474), カテゴリ整理専用(id:146185), 経済準学士(id:22656), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), Eskimbot(id:29676), PATMAN(id:145791), ブレイズマン(id:183852), Roga246(id:53246), あほんだらぁめが！(id:32195), ムカイ(id:72972), 寒漁夫(id:99134), CB750(id:10261), Opponent(id:720), 下総大納言(id:43461), Chengshi(id:57028), Pochacco562000(id:70889), Satoshin(id:157319), Rei-bot(id:94097), ロロ(id:104252), Qje(id:160294), Point136(id:211299), Masabb(id:71275), こぶまき(id:38278), Yas(id:739), Yosemite(id:5808), Sumaru(id:20609), Kouko0515(id:100370), ダイキチ(id:95604), Mnd(id:15140), BoB774(id:148281), Kazov(id:9237), SINOBU(id:28887), たね(id:10372), こおりやんま(id:108912), 今出川(id:136848), Y.o-ji-nn(id:39866), Ro-(id:36890), Aboshi(id:9318), Kamitani(id:30757), Rusk(id:9895), Special rapid(id:96013), Monado(id:53906), Yonoemon(id:55450), Nnn(id:26535), 貘(id:106080), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), Klaus Tennstedt(id:25513), 663highland(id:18755), Salmoides(id:156586), みっくる(id:108144), 宗治(id:111540), Snowchild-152(id:265254), Lincun(id:22742), Louperibot(id:128971), これきん(id:51592), Atsasebo(id:95407), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>