<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>殿司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tonomorizukasa (housekeeping branch of the Imperial Household Ministry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tonomo no Tsukasa (Palace Equipment and Upkeep Office)</e>
<cmt>原文表記に基づき、Tonomo no Tsukasaとし、補足修正 (参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=BSmMbQhafJoC&amp;pg=PA454&amp;dq=tonomo+no+tsukasa&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=u0lATIXfG5PevQPy_onmDA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAQ#)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonomo no Tsukasa (Palace Equipment and Upkeep Office)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>殿司（とのものつかさ）は、後宮十二司の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tonomorizukasa was one of kokyu junishi (twelve offices belonging to kokyu, empress&apos;s residence).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tonomo no tsukasa was one of the kokyu junishi (twelve offices belonging to kokyu, empress&apos;s residence).</e>
<cmt>原文表記に基づき、Tonomo no tsukasaとし、one of the kokyu junishiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tonomo no tsukasa was one of the kokyu junishi (twelve offices belonging to kokyu, empress&apos;s residence).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後宮の清掃、輿などの乗り物、灯油・火燭・炭薪などの内部の照明などを掌った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They cleaned empress&apos; residence and was in charge of interior lightings for the vehicle like a palanquin, lamp oil, kashoku, charcoal fuelwood and so on.</e>
<cmt>「火燭」が意味不明でしたが、読みはkashokuとしました。「炭薪」をcharcoal fuelwoodとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They cleaned empress&apos; residence and were in charge of interior lightings for the vehicle like a palanquin, lamp oil, kashoku, charcoal fuelwood and so on.</e>
<cmt>was→wereに修正</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They cleaned empress&apos; residence and were in charge of interior lightings for the vehicle like a palanquin, lamp oil, kashoku, charcoal fuelwood and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>職員には尚殿（従六位従六位相当）1名・典殿（従八位相当）2名・女孺6名で構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the staffs, it consisted of one Tonomonokami (corresponding to Jurokui (Junior Sixth Rank) and Jurokui) and two Tonomonosuke (corresponding to Jurokui and Juhachii (Junior Eighth Rank)) and six nyoju (a court lady in a lower rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the staffs, it consisted of one Tonomo no kami (corresponding to Jurokui [Junior Sixth Rank]) and two Tonomo no suke (corresponding to Juhachii [Junior Eighth Rank]) and six nyoju (a court lady in a lower rank).</e>
<cmt>Tonomo no kami、Tonomo no sukeとし、重複表記のため and Jurokui削除、カッコ表記修正*「従六位従八位」→リンク先の単語と混ざっており、ウェブ記載の「従八位」を転記し、訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the staffs, it consisted of one Tonomo no kami (corresponding to Jurokui [Junior Sixth Rank]) and two Tonomo no suke (corresponding to Juhachii [Junior Eighth Rank]) and six nyoju (a court lady in a lower rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>平安時代中期以後の後宮の再編と十二司の解体に伴い、主殿寮に吸収されて同署より内侍司に対して派遣される形となり、こうした女官を主殿司あるいは主殿女官と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the reorganization of kokyu and the demise of kokyu junishi after the middle of Heian period, Tonomorizukasa was incorporated into Tonomoryo (Imperial Palace Keeper&apos;s Bureau) and Tonomoryo began to send the staffs in Tonomorizukasa to Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendants) and such a court lady was called court servant or court lady servant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the reorganization of kokyu and the demise of kokyu junishi after the middle of the Heian period, Tonomo no tsukasa was incorporated into Tonomoryo (Imperial Palace Keeper&apos;s Bureau) and Tonomoryo began to send the staffs in Tonomo no tsukasa to Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendants) and such a court lady was called court servant or court lady servant.</e>
<cmt>the Heian period、Tonomorizukasa→Tonomo no Tsukasaとしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the reorganization of kokyu and the demise of kokyu junishi after the middle of the Heian period, Tonomo no tsukasa was incorporated into Tonomoryo (Imperial Palace Keeper&apos;s Bureau) and Tonomoryo began to send the staffs in Tonomo no tsukasa to Naishi no tsukasa (female palace attendants) and such a court lady was called court servant or court lady servant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>主殿司は12世紀前半には定員が9名であったが、後期には12名であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fixed number of court servants was 9 during the first half of twelfth century, but during the last half, seems to have been 12.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fixed number of court servants was 9 during the first half of twelfth century, but during the last half, seems to have been 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fixed number of court servants was 9 during the first half of twelfth century, but during the last half, seems to have been 12.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>