<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>士分</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>士分（しぶん）とは、江戸時代の武士のうち正規の武士身分を持った者を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibun was the term for persons with the full social rank as bushi (warrior) class among the bushi during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibun was the term for persons with the full social rank as bushi (warrior) class among the bushi during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibun was the term for persons with the full social rank as bushi (warrior) class among the bushi during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>士格とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called Shikaku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called Shikaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called Shikaku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>一般に公的に苗字を名乗り刀剣を帯びることが許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, they were officially allowed to have a family name and carry swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, they were officially allowed to have a family name and carry swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, they were officially allowed to have a family name and carry swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>（→苗字帯刀）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myojitaito</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myojitaito</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myojitaito (being permitted to adopt a surname and wear a pair of swords)</e>
<cmt>カッコ内を追加</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>諸藩には「上士・徒士（かち）・卒または足軽」と藩士を3階級に分ける制が見られるが、このうち上層2身分（騎士と徒士）が士分とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some domains, retainers were classified into 3 classes, Joshi, Kachi, Sotu or Ashigaru, but the top two classes (Kishi and Kachi) were considered Shibun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some domains, retainers were classified into 3 classes, Joshi, Kachi, Sotu or Ashigaru, but the top two classes (Kishi and Kachi) were considered Shibun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some domains, retainers were classified into 3 classes, &apos;Joshi, Kachi, Sotsu or Ashigaru,&apos; but the top two classes (Kishi and Kachi) were considered Shibun.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォートsotu→sotsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>騎士（上士）は騎乗を許された上層武士であり、例えば広島藩の場合、百石以上の知行を与えられた武士がこれに当たるとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishi(Joshi) were upper class bushi who were allowed to be on horseback and for example, in the case of the Hiroshima domain, bushi who were given more than one hundred koku were considered as belonging to this class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishi (Joshi) were upper class bushi who were allowed to ride horses and, for example, in the case of the Hiroshima domain, bushi who were given more than one hundred koku were considered to belong to this class.</e>
<cmt>spacing; be on horseback-&gt;ride horses; as belonging-&gt;to belong</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishi (Joshi) were upper class bushi who were allowed to ride horses and, for example, in the case of the Hiroshima domain, bushi who were given more than one hundred koku were considered to belong to this class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>徒士（下士）は公的に騎乗を認められない下層武士であり、卒は歩卒を原義としており足軽を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachi (Geshi) were lower class bushi who were not officially allowed on horseback, and Sotu were in principle foot soldiers and was the term for Ashigaru.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kachi (Geshi) were lower class bushi who were not officially allowed on horseback, and Sotu were in principle foot soldiers, and this was the term for Ashigaru.</e>
<cmt>added “this”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kachi (Kashi) were lower class bushi who were not officially allowed to ride horses, and Sotsu were in principle foot soldiers, and this was the term for Ashigaru (common foot soldier).</e>
<cmt>geshi→kashisotu→sotsu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>騎士は知行取り、御目見得であるのに対し、徒士は蔵米取り、御目見得以下とされており、幕府でいえば旗本が騎士、御家人が徒士に対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishi were given chigyo (enfeoffment) and vassal with the privilege to have an audience with the Shogun, whereas Kachi were given kuramai (rice preserved in a depository by Edo Shogunate and domains) and did not have the privilege to have an audience with the Shogun, and in the bakufu(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Hatamoto corresponded to Kishi and Gokenin corresponded to Kachi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishi with a fief and vassals were allowed to have an audience with the Shogun, whereas Kachi were given kuramai (rice preserved in a depository by Edo Shogunate and domains) and were not allowed to have an audience with the Shogun, and in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Hatamoto corresponded to Kishi and Gokenin corresponded to Kachi.</e>
<cmt>have a privilege to-&gt;be allowed to; spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishi with a fief and vassals were allowed to have an audience with the Shogun, whereas Kachi were given kuramai (rice preserved in a depository by Edo Shogunate and domains) and were not allowed to have an audience with the Shogun, and in the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), Hatamoto corresponded to Kishi and Gokenin corresponded to Kachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>足軽以下は「軽輩」などと呼ばれ、士分とは見なされないため、両者の間には大きな境界線があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ashigaru and below were called Keihai (a person of low rank) and were not considered Shibun, so there was a large difference between to two.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ashigaru and below were called Keihai (a person of low rank) and were not considered Shibun, so there was a large difference between the two.</e>
<cmt>to-&gt;the</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ashigaru and below were called &apos;Keihai&apos; (a person of low rank) and were not considered Shibun, so there was a large difference between the two.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>また足軽の下位には士分の者に私的に雇用された中間、小者等と呼称された武家奉公人があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Below the Ashigaru class were servants of a bushi family called Chugen(rank below common soldier), Komono who were privately hired by Shibun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Below the Ashigaru class were servants of a bushi family called Chugen (rank below common soldier), Komono who were privately hired by Shibun.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Below the Ashigaru class were servants of a bushi family called Chugen (rank below common soldier), Komono (a lower servant) who were privately hired by Shibun.</e>
<cmt>(a lower servant) を追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>足軽には苗字帯刀を許されたものもおり、功績によっては徒士への昇格も許されていたが、中間以下にはそういったことが一切許可されないなど、この両者の間にもはっきりとした境界線があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Ashigaru were allowed Myojitaito, and depending upon their achievements, some were allowed to rise as Kachi, but Chugen and below were never allowed such privileges and there was a clear boundary between these two as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Ashigaru were allowed Myojitaito, and depending upon their achievements, some were allowed to rise to Kachi, but Chugen and below were never allowed such privileges and there was a clear boundary between these two as well.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Ashigaru were allowed Myojitaito, and depending upon their achievements, some were allowed to rise to Kachi, but Chugen and below were never allowed such privileges and there was a clear boundary between these two as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>藩の構成員（藩士）とは厳密には士分を持つものを指し、拡大解釈した場合でも足軽までを指したのであって、中間、小者は藩の構成員とはみなされていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Domain constituents (retainers) strictly indicated those that had Shibun, and even in a wide definition may have included Ashigaru, but Chugen and Komono were never considered as retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Domain constituents (retainers) strictly indicated those that had Shibun, and even in a wide definition may have included Ashigaru, but Chugen and Komono were never considered retainers.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Domain constituents (retainers) strictly indicated those that had Shibun, and even in a wide definition may have included Ashigaru, but Chugen and Komono were never considered retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>庶民の中には、大商人や藩財政に貢献があったものなどに士分が与えられ、苗字帯刀を許されるものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some commoners who helped domain finances or were wealthy merchants were given Shibun and allowed Myojitaito.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some commoners who helped domain finances or were wealthy merchants were given Shibun and allowed Myojitaito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some commoners who helped domain finances or were wealthy merchants were given Shibun and allowed Myojitaito.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これには一代許可・永代許可・苗字または帯刀のみの許可などの別があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were differences such as privileges for one generation only or for all subsequent generation, only family names or only carrying swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were differences such as privileges for one generation only or for all subsequent generations, only family names or only carrying swords.</e>
<cmt>plural generations</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were differences such as privileges for one generation only or for all subsequent generations, only family names or only carrying swords.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、農民や町人も苗字なしでは家の区別がつかなかったため、地形地物の名などを苗字として私称することが公然と行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it would have been difficult distinguish between houses if farmers and townspeople had no family nam, the unofficial practice of using landmarks, etc. as their family name was common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it would have been difficult distinguish between houses if farmers and townspeople had no family name, the unofficial practice of using landmarks etc. as family names was common.</e>
<cmt>spacing; spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it would have been difficult distinguish between houses if farmers and townspeople had no family name, the unofficial practice of using landmarks etc. as family names was common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>赤穂四十七士のうち寺坂吉右衛門ただ一人は士分を有さない足軽身分であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the 47 Akaho warriors, only Kichiemon TERASAKA was not Shibun but Ashigaru class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the 47 Akaho warriors, only Kichiemon TERASAKA was not Shibun but Ashigaru class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the 47 Akaho warriors, only Kichiemon TERASAKA was not Shibun but Ashigaru class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>当時の作法では切腹は士分の者にしか許されず、足軽は斬首と定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom at that time was that only people of Shibun were allowed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and Zanshu (beheading) was for Ashigaru upon execution.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom at that time was that only people of Shibun were allowed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and Zanshu (beheading) was for Ashigaru upon execution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom at that time was that only people of Shibun were allowed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and Zanshu (beheading) was for Ashigaru upon execution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>大石内蔵助はそのことを不憫に思い、討ち入りの後、寺坂吉右衛門を伝達役として生き延びさせたといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuranosuke OISHI thought this was unfortunate and was said to let Kichiemon TERASAKA be the messenger and survive after the raid.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuranosuke OISHI thought this was unfortunate and was said to let Kichiemon TERASAKA be the messenger and survive after the raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuranosuke OISHI thought this was unfortunate and was said to let Kichiemon TERASAKA be the messenger and survive after the raid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>士分は明治維新後、士族に、卒は卒族に編入されたが、のち世襲の卒は士族に、一代抱えの卒は平民とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Shibun became Shizoku and Sotu were taken into Sotuzoku, but later hereditary Sotu became Shizoku and one generation only Sotu were considered commoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, Shibun became Shizoku and Sotu were taken into Sotuzoku, but later hereditary Sotu became Shizoku and single generation Sotu were considered commoners.</e>
<cmt>one-&gt;single</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, Shibun became Shizoku and Sotsu were taken into Sotsuzoku, but later hereditary Sotsu became Shizoku and one generation only Sotsu were considered commoners.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 うぃき野郎(id:53567), Straysheep(id:42448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>