<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>信貴山縁起</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigisan Engi (Legends of Mt. Shigi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigisan Engi (Legends of Mt. Shigi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigisan Engi</e>
<cmt>(Legends of Mt. Shigi)→次文に移動</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>信貴山縁起（しぎさんえんぎ）は、平安時代末期の絵巻物で、2006年現在、日本の国宝に指定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigisan Engi is a set of picture scrolls made in the late Heian period, and is designated as national treasure as of 2006.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigisan Engi is a set of picture scrolls made in the late Heian period, and was designated as a national treasure in 2006.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigisan Engi (Legends of Mt. Shigi) is a set of picture scrolls made in the late Heian period, and was designated as a national treasure in 2006.</e>
<cmt>(Legends of Mt. Shigi)追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>『源氏物語絵巻』、『鳥獣人物戯画』、『伴大納言絵詞』と並ぶ四大絵巻物の1つと称される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is referred to as one of four great picture scrolls along with &quot;Genji Monogatari emaki&quot;, &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot;, and &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is referred to as one of four great picture scrolls, along with &quot;Genji Monogatari emaki,&quot; &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga,&quot; and &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is referred to as one of four great picture scrolls, along with &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (Illustrated Handscroll of the Tale of Genji), &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot; (Caricatures of Frolicking Birds, Animals and Humans), and &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; (The Story of the Courtier Ban Dainagon).</e>
<cmt>『源氏物語絵巻』『鳥獣人物戯画』『伴大納言絵詞』→頭文字を大文字に変更、補足追加、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>朝護孫子寺が所蔵（原本は奈良国立博物館に寄託されており、霊宝館では複製を展示）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is possessed by Chogosonshi-ji Temple (but the original is housed at the Nara National Museum and its replica is displayed at the treasure hall of the temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is possessed by Chogosonshi-ji Temple (but the original is housed at the Nara National Museum and its replica is displayed in the treasure hall of the temple).</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is possessed by Chogosonshi-ji Temple (but the original is housed at the Nara National Museum and its replica is displayed in the treasure hall of the temple).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「信貴山縁起絵巻」とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Shigisan Engi Emaki&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also known as &apos;Shigisan Engi Emaki&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also known as &apos;Shigisan Engi Emaki.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後述のごとく、表題は寺社縁起絵に属するものであるが、内容は高僧伝絵の範疇に入る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As described below, the title falls into the genre of Jisha Engi-e (literally, illustrated origins of shrines and temples), but the story itself belongs to the genre of Kosoden-e (illustrated biographies of notable Buddhist monks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As described below, the title falls into the genre of Jisha Engi-e (literally, illustrated origins of shrines and temples), but the story itself belongs to the genre of Kosoden-e (illustrated biographies of notable Buddhist monks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As described below, the title falls into the genre of Jisha Engi-e (literally, illustrated origins of shrines and temples), but the story itself belongs to the genre of Kosoden-e (illustrated biographies of notable Buddhist monks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="6">
<j>この絵巻の成立は、平安時代後期の12世紀頃とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The set of picture scrolls are said to have been made in the late Heian period, at around 12th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The set of picture scrolls is said to have been made in the late Heian period, at around 12th century.</e>
<cmt>subject-verb agreement</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The set of picture scrolls is said to have been made in the late Heian period, at around 12th century.</e>
<cmt>12thとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『伴大納言絵詞』や『源氏物語絵巻』と同様に、後白河法皇が関与した、という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is also said that the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa was involved in the making of it as well as &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; and &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is also said that the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa was involved in the making of it as well as &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; and &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is also said that Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa was involved in the making of it as well as &quot;Ban Dainagon Ekotoba&quot; and &quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa→Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawaに修正、全角クォーテーションを半角に修正、ピリオドの位置を移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>内容は、概要で述べるごとく、信貴山の中興である命蓮を主人公とした霊験譚である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As written in the summary, this it the tales of miraculous efficacy whose main character, Myoren was the restorer of Mt. Shigi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As written in the summary, these are the tales of miraculous efficacy whose main character, Myoren, was the restorer of Mt. Shigi.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As written in the summary, these are the tales of miraculous efficacy whose main character, Myoren, was the restorer of Mt. Shigi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>延喜加持の巻で、醍醐天皇の病気を命蓮の加持祈祷の法力で治したという話が語られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The story depicted on the scroll of Engi Kaji no Maki (Exorcism of the Emperor) is that Myoren healed the Emperor Daigo of a disease with the miraculous power of incantation and prayer.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The story depicted on the scroll of Engi Kaji no Maki (Exorcism of the Emperor) is that Myoren healed the Emperor Daigo of a disease with the miraculous power of incantation and prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The story depicted on the scroll of Engi Kaji no Maki (Exorcism of the Emperor) is that Myoren healed the Emperor Daigo of a disease with the miraculous power of incantation and prayer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ほぼ一致する説話が『宇治拾遺物語』、『今昔物語』にも収められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost identical stories are contained in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales of Uji) and &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (The tales of Times Now Past).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Almost identical stories are contained in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales of Uji) and &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (The tales of Times Now Past).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost identical stories are contained in &quot;Uji Shui Monogatari&quot; (a collection of the Tales of Uji) and &quot;Konjaku Monogatari&quot; (The tales of Times Now Past).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、『扶桑略記』にも同様の記事が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A similar description is found in &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Short History of Japan), too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A similar description is also found in &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Short History of Japan).</e>
<cmt>word choice</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A similar description is also found in &quot;Fuso Ryakki&quot; (A Short History of Japan).</e>
<cmt>全角クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>通常の寺社縁起のごとく、開山の縁起を記したものではなく、平安時代中期に信貴山で修行して当山の中興の祖とされる命蓮に関する説話を描く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike other Jisha Engi picture scrolls which generally depict origins of shrines and temples, it depicts stories related to Myoren, the restoration patriarch of the mountain, who trained himself in Mt.Shigi in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike other Jisha Engi picture scrolls, which generally depict origins of shrines and temples, it depicts stories related to Myoren, the restoration patriarch of the mountain, who trained himself in Mt.Shigi in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike other Jisha Engi picture scrolls, which generally depict origins of shrines and temples, it depicts stories related to Myoren, the restoration patriarch of the mountain, who trained himself in Mt. Shigi in the middle of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>スペース追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>山崎長者の巻、延喜加持の巻、尼公の巻の3巻からなる絵巻である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The picture scrolls consist of three titles: Yamazaki Choja no Maki (literally, a rich man in Yamazaki), Engi Kaji, and Amagimi (literally, a Buddhist nun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The picture scrolls consist of three titles: Yamazaki Choja no Maki (literally, a rich man in Yamazaki), Engi Kaji, and Amagimi (literally, a Buddhist nun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The picture scrolls consist of three titles: Yamazaki Choja no Maki (literally, a rich man in Yamazaki), Engi Kaji, and Amagimi (literally, a Buddhist nun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>作者は不明ながら、人物の表情や躍動感を軽妙な筆致で描いた絵巻の一大傑作であり、『鳥獣人物戯画』とともに、日本の漫画文化のルーツとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the authorship is unclear, this is a masterpiece of emaki, depicting people&apos;s faces and dynamic movements in a light and easy style, and along with &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga&quot;, it is regarded as an origin of Japanese manga culture.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the authorship is unclear, this is a masterpiece of emaki, depicting people&apos;s faces and dynamic movements in a light and easy style, and along with &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga,&quot; it is considered to be an origin of Japanese manga culture.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the authorship is unclear, this is a masterpiece of emaki, depicting people&apos;s faces and dynamic movements in a light and easy style, and along with &quot;Choju Jinbutsu Giga,&quot; it is considered to be an origin of Japanese manga culture.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィー、クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>山崎長者の巻（飛倉の巻） 31.7cm×879.9cm</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamazaki Choja no Maki (Flying Granary) 31.7 cm X 879.9 cm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamazaki Choja no Maki (Flying Granary) 31.7 cm X 879.9 cm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamazaki Choja no Maki (Flying Granary) 31.7 cm X 879.9 cm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>命蓮が神通力を行使して、山崎の長者のもとに托鉢に使用する鉢を飛ばし、その鉢に校倉造りの倉を乗せて飛ばし、信貴山に居る命蓮の所まで持って来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoren makes a bowl used to ask for alms fly to the granary of a rich man in Yamazaki and carry it back to the mountain by using his supernatural power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoren uses his supernatural power to make a bowl used to ask for alms fly to the granary of a rich man in Yamazaki and return to the mountain.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoren uses his supernatural power to make a bowl used to ask for alms fly to the granary of a rich man in Yamazaki and return to the mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>長者が中に収められていた米俵だけでも返してくれと訴えたので、今度は、鉢に乗せた米俵を先頭にし、米俵を数珠繋ぎにして飛ばし、長者のもとまで飛ばす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rich man appeals to Myoren to just give him back rice bags in the granary, and then Myoren makes a string of rice bags following one on the bowl fly back to the original place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rich man appeals to Myoren to just give him back rice bags in the granary, and then Myoren makes a rice bag on the bowl, followed by a string of other rice bags, fly back to their original place.</e>
<cmt>rewordingnot confident of accuracy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rich man appeals to Myoren to just give him back rice bags in the granary, and then Myoren makes a rice bag on the bowl, followed by a string of other rice bags, fly back to their original place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>延喜加持の巻 31.7cm×1290.8cm</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Engi Kaji no Maki 31.7 cm X 1290.8 cm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Engi Kaji no Maki 31.7 cm X 1290.8 cm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Engi Kaji no Maki 31.7 cm X 1290.8 cm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>命蓮の加持祈祷の力で、病の床にあった醍醐天皇の病いが平癒する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Daigo recovers from his illness with the power of incantation and prayer by Myoren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Daigo recovers from his illness with the power of incantation and prayer by Myoren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Daigo recovers from his illness with the power of incantation and prayer by Myoren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>「剣の護法」（童子）が、空を飛び、転輪聖王の金輪を転がし、後ろに飛行機雲のような細長い雲を残して、天皇のいる清涼殿に現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ken no Goho&apos; (a child acolyte of Buddhism) flies in the air, rolls the gold ring of Tenrinjo-o (literally, wheel rolling holy king), and then comes Seiryoden, the Emperor&apos;s residence leaving a long, narrow contrail-like cloud behind.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ken no Goho&apos; (a child acolyte of Buddhism) flies in the air, rolls the gold ring of Tenrinjo-o (literally, wheel rolling holy king), and then comes Seiryoden, the Emperor&apos;s residence, leaving a long, narrow contrail-like cloud behind.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ken no Goho&apos; (a child acolyte of Buddhism) flies in the air, rolls the gold ring of Tenrinjo-o (literally, wheel rolling holy king), and then comes Seiryoden, the Emperor&apos;s residence, leaving a long, narrow contrail-like cloud behind.</e>
<cmt>全角アポストロフィー、クォーテーションを半角に修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>尼公（あまぎみ）の巻 31.7cm×1424.1cm</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagimi no Maki 31.7 cm X 1424.1 cm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagimi no Maki 31.7 cm X 1424.1 cm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagimi no Maki 31.7 cm X 1424.1 cm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>命蓮の生国である信濃国から姉の尼公が、はるばる信貴山まで命蓮を訪ねてやって来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagimi, the elder sister of Myoren comes all the way from Shinano no kuni (now Nagano Prefecture), the birth place of Myoren to Mt. Shigi to see him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagimi, the elder sister of Myoren, comes all the way from Shinano no kuni (now Nagano Prefecture), the birth place of Myoren, to Mt. Shigi to see him.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagimi, the older sister of Myoren, comes all the way from Shinano Province (now Nagano Prefecture), the birth place of Myoren, to Mt. Shigi to see him.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに基づき、elder sister→older sisterとし、Shinano no kuni→Shinano Provinceに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>東大寺の東大寺盧舎那仏像前で祈りかつまどろむ尼公のさまを描いた部分が、異時同図法を用いた圧巻として知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It depicts Amagimi praying while half asleep before the Great Statue of Buddha of Todai-ji Temple, and this part of the picture is known as the highlight depicted by Ijidozu-ho Method (a compositional method used to show successive events in a single picture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It depicts Amagimi praying while half asleep before the Great Statue of Buddha of Todai-ji Temple, and this part of the picture is known as the highlight depicted by Ijidozu-ho Method (a compositional method used to show successive events in a single picture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It depicts Amagimi praying while half asleep before the Great Statue of Buddha of Todai-ji Temple, and this part of the picture is known as the highlight depicted by Ijidozu-ho Method (a compositional method used to show successive events in a single picture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>巻末では、飛倉の巻で登場した倉の朽ち果てたさまが描かれ、それによって主人公である命蓮の臨終を暗示して終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of the scroll shows the dilapidated granary of the Flying Granary, which implies the death of the main character, Myoren.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end of the scroll shows the dilapidated granary of the Flying Granary, which implies the death of the main character, Myoren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end of the scroll shows the dilapidated granary of the Flying Granary, which implies the death of the main character, Myoren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 663highland(id:18755), Mooko(id:36162), ととりん(id:31982), 日陰猫Joga(id:9749), Kstigarbha(id:13376), 二八(id:10408), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>