<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御恩と奉公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goon (favors) and hoko (services)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goon (favors) and hoko (services)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goon (favors) and hoko (services)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御恩と奉公（ごおんとほうこう）とは、中世日本において、主に武士の主従関係を構成した要素・概念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goon and hoko indicate factors and concepts that constituted the master-servant relationships among samurai in the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goon and hoko indicate factors and concepts that constituted master-servant relationships among samurai during medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goon and hoko indicate factors and concepts that constituted master-servant relationships among samurai during medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中世の武士間の主従関係は、決して片務的なものではなく、主人・従者が相互に利益を与え合う互恵的な関係で成り立っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The master-servant relationships among samurai in the medieval period were not one-sided but were established based on mutually beneficial ones in which benefits were not only given by a mater and received by his servant but also given by a servant and received by the master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The master-servant relationships among samurai during the medieval period were not one-sided but were established based upon mutually beneficial ones in which benefits were not only given by a master and received by his servant, but also given by a servant and received by the master.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The master-servant relationships among samurai during the medieval period were not one-sided but were established based upon mutually beneficial ones in which benefits were not only given by a master and received by his servant, but also given by a servant and received by the master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>ここで、主人が従者へ与えた利益を御恩といい、従者が主人へ与えた利益を奉公といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, the benefits a master gave his servant was called goon, and the benefits given by his servant to the master hoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, the benefits a master gave his servant was called goon, and the benefits given by his servant to the master hoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, the benefits a master gave his servant was called goon, and the benefits given by his servant to the master hoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>平安時代中期～後期から武士層に「御恩と奉公」の関係が徐々に形成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationships of &quot;goon and hoko&quot; had been formed gradually in the middle to the latter half era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationships of &quot;goon and hoko&quot; had been formed gradually during the middle to the latter half era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationships of &apos;goon and hoko&apos; had been formed gradually among samurai class during the middle to the latter half era of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;among samurai class補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかしながら、本格的に「御恩と奉公」が成立したのは、源頼朝が関東武士の盟主＝鎌倉殿となってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was after MINAMOTO no Yoritomo became the leader of samurai in the Kanto area, or Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura), that the relationships of &quot;goon and hoko&quot; were established firmly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was after MINAMOTO no Yoritomo became the leader of the samurai in the Kanto area, or Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura), that the relationships of &quot;goon and hoko&quot; were firmly established.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was after MINAMOTO no Yoritomo became the leader of the samurai in the Kanto area, or Kamakura-dono (lord of Kamakura), that the relationships of &apos;goon and hoko&apos; were firmly established.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以降、御恩と奉公の関係性は、鎌倉幕府の成立基盤として機能し続け、その後の室町幕府や江戸幕府にも引き継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the relationships of &quot;goon and hoko&quot; continued functioning as a base for establishing the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and were inherited by the later Muromachi bakufu and Edo bakufu as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the relationships of &quot;goon and hoko&quot; continued functioning as a base for establishing the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and were inherited by the later Muromachi bakufu and Edo bakufu as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the relationships of &apos;goon and hoko&apos; continued functioning as a base for establishing the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and were inherited by the later Muromachi bakufu and Edo bakufu as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>御恩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>御恩の具体的な内容は、主人が従者の所領支配を保障すること、又は新たな土地給与を行うことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specifically, goon indicated that a master guaranteed control of an area by his servant or that a master awarded an area newly to his servant..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, goon indicated that a master guaranteed control of an area by his servant or that a master awarded an area newly to his servant..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, goon indicated that a master guaranteed control of an area by his servant or that a master awarded an area newly to his servant.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>前者は本領安堵（ほんりょうあんど）と呼ばれ、後者は新恩給与（しんおんきゅうよ）と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former benefit was called honryoando and the latter sinonkyuyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former benefit was called honryoando and the latter sinonkyuyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former benefit was called honryoando and the latter sinonkyuyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>鎌倉幕府が成立すると、鎌倉殿が御家人を地頭へ任命するという形で本領安堵・新恩給与、すなわち御恩がほどこされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kamakura bakufu was established, the benefit of honryoando or sinonkyuyo, or that of goon, was given by Kamakura-dono to gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) in the form that Kamakura-dono appointed them to jito (the managers and lords of manors).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kamakura bakufu was established, the benefit of honryoando or sinonkyuyo, or that of goon, was given by Kamakura-dono to gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) in the form that Kamakura-dono appointed them to jito (the managers and lords of manors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kamakura bakufu was established, the benefit of honryoando or sinonkyuyo, or that of goon, was given by Kamakura-dono to gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) in the form that Kamakura-dono appointed them to jito (the managers and lords of manors).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>奉公</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>奉公の具体的な内容は、従者が主人に対して負担した軍役・経済負担などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoko specifically indicated the military role that a servant should play for his mater and the economical burden that the servant should bear for his master.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoko specifically indicated the military role that a servant should play for his master and the economical burden that the servant should bear for his master.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoko specifically indicated the military role that a servant should play for his master and the economical burden that the servant should bear for his master.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉幕府が成立すると、御家人は鎌倉殿に対して、緊急時の軍役、内裏や幕府を警護する大番役、その他異国警護番役や長門警護番役などの軍役奉仕のほか、関東御公事と言われる武家役を果たした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kamakura bakufu was established, gokenin played, for the Kamakura-dono, the economical roles as samurai, called Kanto-mikuji, in addition to the services of military roles, such as military roles in emergency, the Oban-yaku role for guarding the imperial court and bakufu, the Ikoku keigo ban-yaku role (the role for guarding against attacks from foreign countries) and the Nagato keigo ban-yaku role (also the role for guarding against attacks from foreign countries at a station placed in Nagato, present Yamaguchi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kamakura bakufu was established, gokenin played, for the Kamakura-dono, the economical roles as samurai, called Kanto-mikuji, in addition to the services of military roles, such as military roles in emergency, the Oban-yaku role for guarding the imperial court and bakufu, the Ikoku keigo ban-yaku role (the role for guarding against attacks from foreign countries) and the Nagato keigo ban-yaku role (also the role for guarding against attacks from foreign countries at a station placed in Nagato, present Yamaguchi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kamakura bakufu was established, gokenin played, for the Kamakura-dono, the economical roles as samurai, called Kanto-mikuji, in addition to the services of military roles, such as military roles in emergency, the Oban-yaku role for guarding the imperial court and bakufu, the Ikoku keigo ban-yaku role (the role for guarding against attacks from foreign countries) and the Nagato keigo ban-yaku role (also the role for guarding against attacks from foreign countries at a station placed in Nagato, present Yamaguchi Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>平安期の10世紀頃、大きな社会変化を背景として、朝廷は、徴税・軍事をもはや官司機構で担うのではなく、国司や富豪などへ請け負わせる官司請負制への転換を進めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In around the tenth century in the Heian period when a large social change occurred, the Imperial court abandoned the policy of entrusting tax-collecting affairs and military affairs solely to the central government system and promoted to entrust these affairs to kokushi (provincial governors) or rich persons, or to introduce the kanshiukeoi-sei system in other words.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the tenth century during the Heian period when a large social change occurred, the Imperial court abandoned the policy of entrusting tax-collecting affairs and military affairs solely to the central government system and promoted to entrust these affairs to kokushi (provincial governors) or rich persons, or, in other words, to introduce the kanshiukeoi-sei system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the tenth century during the Heian period when a large social change occurred, the Imperial court abandoned the policy of entrusting tax-collecting affairs and military affairs solely to the central government system and promoted to entrust these affairs to kokushi (provincial governors) or rich persons, or, in other words, to introduce the kanshiukeoi-sei system.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>特に争乱の多かった関東では、在地の富豪や豪族が公的な軍事力を担うようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, in the Kanto region where fights occurred frequently, local rich persons or powerful clans had become to bear public military burdens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, in the Kanto region where fighting occurred frequently, local rich persons or powerful clans had come to bear public military burdens.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, in the Kanto region where fighting occurred frequently, local rich persons or powerful clans had come to bear public military burdens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>こうした状況下で、関東を中心に武士団が形成されていったが、武士団では主人がトップに立ち、家子・郎党と呼ばれる従者たちを率いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under these situations, samurai groups became formed centered on the Kanto region, and in such a group, its master took its top position and led his servants called Ienoko or roto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such situations, samurai groups formed being centered in the Kanto region, and in such a group, the master took top position and led his servants called Ienoko or roto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such situations, samurai groups formed being centered in the Kanto region, and in such a group, the master took top position and led his servants called Ienoko or roto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こうした主従関係を結びつける契機となったのが、御恩と奉公の関係性である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A factor that enabled connecting a master with his servants in such a situation was relationships between goon and hoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A factor that enabled connecting a master with his servants in such a situation was the relationship between goon and hoko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A factor that enabled connecting a master with his servants in such a situation was the relationship between goon and hoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>主人・従者の両者は、御恩と奉公という互恵関係を結ぶことで、一定の共同体（武士団）を作っていったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A master and his servants became to form a certain union (samurai group) through establishing mutually beneficial relationships called goon and hoko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A master and his servants formed a certain union (samurai group) by establishing mutually beneficial relationships called goon and hoko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A master and his servants formed a certain union (samurai group) by establishing mutually beneficial relationships called goon and hoko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>ただし、当時の主従関係は割とルーズなもので、複数の主人に仕える、一時的にだけ主従関係を結ぶ、といったことも多く見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the master-servant relationship was rather loose, and it often happened that a samurai served more than one master or established a master-servant relationship with a master only temporarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the master-servant relationship was rather loose, and it often happened that a samurai served more than one master or established a master-servant relationship with a master only temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the master-servant relationship was rather loose, and it often happened that a samurai served more than one master or established a master-servant relationship with a master only temporarily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>平安最末期に関東武士全体を代表する鎌倉殿という地位が登場すると、御恩と奉公に基づく主従関係は、次第に排他的（鎌倉殿以外の主人を持たない）かつ永続的なものとなり、一層強固になっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Towards the end of the Heian period when the position heading all samurai in the Kanto region, called Kamakura-dono, was introduced, the master-servant relationship based on goon and hoko gradually became exclusive (not allowed to have any master other than kamakura-dono) and permanent, making the relationship stronger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards the end of the Heian period when the position heading all samurai in the Kanto region, called Kamakura-dono, was introduced, the master-servant relationship based on goon and hoko gradually became exclusive (not allowed to have any master other than the kamakura-dono) and permanent, making the relationship stronger.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards the end of the Heian period when the position heading all samurai in the Kanto region, called Kamakura-dono, was introduced, the master-servant relationship based on goon and hoko gradually became exclusive (not allowed to have any master other than the kamakura-dono) and permanent, making the relationship stronger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>その後、御恩と奉公は明治維新まで続く武家社会の基本的な成立要素として機能した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, goon and hoko functioned as a basic factor constituting the samurai society that continued until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, goon and hoko functioned as a basic factor constituting samurai society that continued until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, goon and hoko functioned as a basic factor constituting samurai society that continued until the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、御恩と奉公による主従関係について、中世ヨーロッパに見られた封建制(feudalism)との共通点に着目して、封建的主従関係と理解する見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the way, concerning the master-servant relationship based on goon and hoko, there is an opinion that the relationship is interpreted as the same as the feudal master-servant relationship, because when it is compared with the feudalism found in the Medieval Europe, there are common points.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the way, concerning the master-servant relationship based on goon and hoko, there is an opinion that the relationship is interpreted the same as the feudal master-servant relationship, because when it is compared with feudalism found in Medieval Europe, there are some common points.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the way, concerning the master-servant relationship based on goon and hoko, there is an opinion that the relationship is interpreted the same as the feudal master-servant relationship, because when it is compared with feudalism found in Medieval Europe, there are some common points.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>その一方、ヨーロッパ封建制と本質的に異なる、日本独自の主従関係であるとする見解も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, another opinion has been proposed that the master-servant relationship is specific to Japan, being fundamentally different from that in the European feudalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, another opinion has been proposed that the master-servant relationship is specific to Japan, being fundamentally different from that found in European feudalism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, another opinion has been proposed that the master-servant relationship is specific to Japan, being fundamentally different from that found in European feudalism.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Shimoxx(id:9332), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>