<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大隈財政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma Finance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma Finance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma Finance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>大隈財政（おおくまざいせい）とは、明治初期に大蔵卿大隈重信（参議兼務）によって推進された財政政策のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma finance refers to the financial policy promoted by Shigenobu OKUMA, the Minister of the Treasury (doubling as the Councilor) in early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma finance refers to the financial policy promoted by Shigenobu OKUMA, the Minister of the Treasury (concurrently filled a post of Councilor) in early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>補足の（参議兼務）を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma finance refers to the financial policy promoted by Shigenobu OKUMA, the Minister of the Treasury (concurrently filled a post of Councilor) in early Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>事実上の後任である松方正義の「松方財政」との対比として用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is compared to &apos;Matsukata finance&apos; by Masayoshi MATSUKATA, de facto successor of Okuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term is used as a comparison to &apos;Matsukata finance&apos; promoted by Masayoshi MATSUKATA, who was an actual successor of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>「It is compared to」を、「The term is used as a comparison to」と変更しました。by を promoted by　と変更しました。「事実上の」が訳漏れです。de facto を変更します。（法律文書に使用されることの多いラテン語です）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term is used as a comparison to &apos;Matsukata finance&apos; promoted by Masayoshi MATSUKATA, who was an actual successor of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>大隈の大蔵卿在任時期は1873年10月25日 ‐ 1880年2月28日であるが、実際には1869年8月15日（旧暦明治2年7月8日 (旧暦)）に近代大蔵省創立とともに大蔵大輔に就任して以来事実上の大蔵省の最高責任者であり、大蔵卿退任も伊藤博文が進めた「参議・省卿分離案」によって参議専念の合意が成立したこと（後任大蔵卿佐野常民は大隈直系）によるもので、実際には1881年10月11日の御前会議による参議免官（明治14年の政変）まで大蔵省及び日本財政の責任者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma served as Minister of the Treasury from October 25, 1873 to February 28, 1880, but he had effectively been the highest officer of the Ministry since he assumed the post of senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury upon the launch of the modern Minister of the Treasury on August 15, 1869, and he continued to be in charge of the Minister of the Treasury and the Japanese financial policy until he was dismissed as the councilor during a conference in the presence of the Emperor on October 11, 1881 (Political Change of 1881), since his resignation as the Minister of the Treasury was due because the agreement to serve exclusively as councilor was reached by &apos;Proposal to Separate Councilor and Minister&apos; promoted by Hirobumi ITO (successor Minister of the Treasury was Tsunetami SANO, Okuma&apos;s direct subordinate).</e>
<cmt>「参議・省卿分離案」の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma served as the Minister of the Treasury from October 25, 1873 to February 28, 1880, but he had effectively been the highest officer of the Ministry of Treasury since he assumed the post of senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury upon the launch of the modern Ministry of Treasury on August 15, 1869, therefore he continued to be in charge of the Ministry of Treasury and the Japanese financial policy until he was dismissed as the councilor during a conference in the presence of the Emperor on October 11, 1881 (Political Change of 1881), however his resignation as the Minister of the Treasury was because an agreement to serve exclusively as a councilor was reached by &apos;Proposal to Separate Councilor and Minister&apos; promoted by Hirobumi ITO (a successor Minister of the Treasury was Tsunetami SANO, Okuma&apos;s direct subordinate).</e>
<cmt>Since を howeverと変更しました。原文には、しかし、などの言葉はありませんが、ニュアンスとして、退任についても、参議専念の合意が成立したことで、権力また地位として下がったわけではないということなので、文の流れとしてHoweverを使用します。Was due because を was because と変更しました。the agreement をan agreementと変更しました。ほか前置詞など変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma served as the Minister of the Treasury from October 25, 1873 to February 28, 1880, but he had effectively been the highest officer of the Ministry of Treasury since he assumed the post of senior assistant minister of the Ministry of Treasury upon the launch of the modern Ministry of Treasury on August 15, 1869, therefore he continued to be in charge of the Ministry of Treasury and the Japanese financial policy until he was dismissed as the councilor during a conference in the presence of the Emperor on October 11, 1881 (Political Change of 1881), however his resignation as the Minister of the Treasury was because an agreement to serve exclusively as a councilor was reached by &apos;Proposal to Separate Councilor and Minister&apos; promoted by Hirobumi ITO (a successor Minister of the Treasury was Tsunetami SANO, Okuma&apos;s direct subordinate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>元来、外国官（後の外務省）にいた肥前藩出身の大隈が財政を扱うようになったのは、江戸幕府及び明治政府及び諸藩による大量の悪金（贋金）発行の事実が発覚し、諸外国より抗議が殺到したことにより、明治政府の貨幣改革に一転して外交交渉が付随することになった特殊事情によるものである（高輪談判）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma, who was from Hizen Province and used to work for Office of Foreign Affairs (later Ministry of Foreign Affairs), became to handle financial matters when revelation of a mass issuance of bad money (false currency) by the Edo Shogunate, the Meiji government and domains triggered a flood of anger by foreign countries, and thus diplomatic negotiation suddenly became necessary for the currency reform of the Meiji government (Takanawa negotiation).</e>
<cmt>外国官の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma, who was from Hizen Province and used to work for Office of Foreign Affairs (later Ministry of Foreign Affairs), started to handle financial matters, as a revelation of a mass issuance of bad money (false currency) by the Edo Shogunate, the Meiji government and various domains triggered a flood of protests from foreign countries, and thus diplomatic negotiation suddenly became necessary for the currency reform of the Meiji government (Takanawa negotiation).</e>
<cmt>became to handle　を　started to handle　と変更しました。Whenを, as aと変更しました。諸藩をvarious domainsとしました。抗議をanger byからprotests fromと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma, who was from Hizen Province and used to work for Office of Foreign Affairs (later Ministry of Foreign Affairs), started to handle financial matters, as a revelation of a mass issuance of bad money (false currency) by the Edo Shogunate, the Meiji government and various domains triggered a flood of protests from foreign countries, and thus diplomatic negotiation suddenly became necessary for the currency reform of the Meiji government (Takanawa negotiation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大隈は当初は参議木戸孝允の支援を受け、木戸と同じ長州藩出身の伊藤博文・井上馨や旧幕臣の渋沢栄一らを登用して、新貨条例制定、予算制度導入、造幣局 (日本)・印刷局の建設、廃藩置県・地租改正の実施などに尽力する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma initially made efforts toward the enactment of the New Currency Regulation, introduction of budget system, construction of Mint Bureau (Japan) and Printing Bureau, and implementation of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) and land-tax reform with support from Takayoshi KIDO, Councilor, and by employing Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, who were from the same Choshu Domain as Ido, and Eichi SHIBUSAWA, a former retainer of shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma initially made efforts toward the enactment of the New Currency Regulation, introduction of budget system, construction of Mint Bureau (Japan) and Printing Bureau, implementation of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) and land-tax reform with support from a councilor Takayoshi KIDO and by employing Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, who were from the same Choshu Domain as Kido, and Eichi SHIBUSAWA, a former retainer of shogun.</e>
<cmt>and を一つ削除しました。「Takayoshi KIDO, Councilor,」　を、「a councilor Takayoshi KIDO」と変更しました。Idoとなっていましたが、Kidoの間違いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma initially made efforts toward the enactment of the New Currency Regulation, introduction of budget system, construction of Mint Bureau (Japan) and Printing Bureau, implementation of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) and land-tax reform with support from a councilor Takayoshi KIDO and by employing Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, who were from the same Choshu Domain as Kido, and Eichi SHIBUSAWA, a former retainer of shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>こうした急進的な木戸・大隈路線に大久保利通は警戒を強め、得能良介・松方正義ら薩摩藩出身者を大蔵省に入れて大隈を牽制しようとした</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO got so alarmed by the radical line of Kido and Okuma that he attempted to put a brake on Okuma by bringing Ryosuke TOKUNO and Masayoshi MATSUKATA into the Ministry of Treasury, but he later made a compromise with their line which let Okuma double as Councilor in 1870 and succeed the post of Minister of Treasury from Okubo in 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimichi OKUBO got so alarmed by the radical line of Kido and Okuma, therefore he brought Ryosuke TOKUNO and Masayoshi MATSUKATA into the Ministry of Treasury in attempted to put a brake on Okuma.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処上記処理のため一部書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimichi OKUBO got so alarmed by the radical line of Kido and Okuma, therefore he brought Ryosuke TOKUNO and Masayoshi MATSUKATA into the Ministry of Treasury in attempted to put a brake on Okuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、後には木戸・大隈路線に譲歩し、1870年に大隈は参議を兼ね、1873年に大久保が兼ねていた大蔵卿を譲られることになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However he later made a compromise with Kido and Okuma line; Okuma concurrently filled post of a councilor in 1870 and succeed to the post of Minister of Treasury from Okubo in 1873.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処上記処理のため一部書き換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However he later made a compromise with Kido and Okuma line; Okuma concurrently filled post of a councilor in 1870 and succeed to the post of Minister of Treasury from Okubo in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>大隈の政策は廃藩置県・地租改正・秩禄処分を通じて明治政府の財政基盤を安定させ、近代的な商工業育成（殖産興業）のために官営工場を建設するとともに、国立銀行_(明治)を通じて政府資金を導入して民間事業者の育成に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma tried to stabilize the Meiji Government&apos;s financial base by Haihan-chiken, land-tax reform and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend), to promote a modern trade and craft industry (encouragement of new industry) by building government-owned factories, and to develop private entrepreneurs by injecting government funds through National Bank (Meiji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma&apos;s policies were to stabilize the Meiji Government&apos;s financial base by Haihan-chiken, land-tax reform and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend), to promote a modern trade and craft industry (encouragement of new industry) by building government-owned factories, and to develop private entrepreneurs by injecting government funds through National Bank (Meiji).</e>
<cmt>「政策は」が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma&apos;s policies were to stabilize the Meiji Government&apos;s financial base by Haihan-chiken, land-tax reform and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend), to promote a modern trade and craft industry (encouragement of new industry) by building government-owned factories, and to develop private entrepreneurs by injecting government funds through National Bank (Meiji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これによって国際収支を改善するとともに、日本の金融・経済・産業の近代化を図ろうとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He aimed at modernizing Japanese financial, economic and industrial sectors as well as improving the balance of payments through these policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He aimed at modernizing Japanese financial, economic and industrial sectors as well as improving the balance of international payments through these policies.</e>
<cmt>「国際収支」が「balance of payments」となっていますが、「balance of international payments」と変更します。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He aimed at modernizing Japanese financial, economic and industrial sectors as well as improving the balance of international payments through these policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>ところが、この政策を推進するためには多額の資金が必要であり、国債や外国公債による資金や不換紙幣の大量発行に一時的に依存せざるを得なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But these policies required a large amount of funds and forced him to temporarily rely on government bonds and foreign government bonds and large-scale issuance of inconvertible paper currency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But these policies required a large amount of funds, which forced him to temporarily rely on government bonds, foreign government bonds and large-scale issuance of inconvertible paper currency.</e>
<cmt>「and forced him to」を「, which forced him to」と変更し、（trans1の）2つ目のandを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But these policies required a large amount of funds, which forced him to temporarily rely on government bonds, foreign government bonds and large-scale issuance of inconvertible paper currency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>更に佐賀の乱や西南戦争などの士族反乱によって予定外の財政支出が生じたため、1878年以後にインフレーションに悩まされることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is more, he had to face inflation from 1878 because revolts by family or person with samurai ancestors, such as Saga War and Seinan War, caused unexpected financial spending.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, he had to face inflation from 1878 because revolts by family or person with samurai ancestors, such as Saga War and Seinan War, caused unexpected financial spending.</e>
<cmt>What is moreをmoreoverと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, he had to face inflation from 1878 because revolts by family or person with samurai ancestors, such as Saga War and Seinan War, caused unexpected financial spending.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>奇しくもこの年に大久保が暗殺され、筆頭参議となった大隈は大久保の後を受けて内務卿となった伊藤博文とともに、右大臣岩倉具視を擁しながら政府を運営することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unfortunately, Okubo was assassinated in the same year, which led Okuma, head Councilor, to run the government in cooperation with Hirobumi ITO, who succeeded the post of Secretary of Interior from Okubo, with Tomomi IWAKURA as the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By a curious coincidence, Okubo was assassinated in the same year, which led Okuma, who became the head Councilor, to run the government in cooperation with Hirobumi ITO, who succeeded the post of Secretary of Interior from Okubo, with Tomomi IWAKURA as the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>「奇しくも」をUnfortunatelyとしていますが、偶然にも/不思議にもという意味なので、「By a curious coincidence,」　と変更しました。head Councilorをwho became the head Councilorと変更しました（head counsilorになったのは大久保が暗殺された後なので）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By a curious coincidence, Okubo was assassinated in the same year, which led Okuma, who became the head Councilor, to run the government in cooperation with Hirobumi ITO, who succeeded the post of Secretary of Interior from Okubo, with Tomomi IWAKURA as the Minister of the Right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>大隈はインフレーションに対応するための公債・紙幣の整理策を求められ、同年に「公債及び紙幣償還概算書」を作り1905年までの償還を計画したものの、翌年にはこれを改訂した「国債紙幣償却方法」（「減債方策」）を作成して、地方への支出抑制、間接税の増加、横浜正金銀行の設立などを行って政府資金の蓄積に尽くした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okuma was pressed to trim public bonds and paper money in order to deal with the inflation, so he drew up &apos;Estimate of redemption of public bond and paper money&apos; in 1878 to stipulate a redemption plan which would be completed by 1905, but he revised it the very next year to create &apos;Measures to redeem government bonds and paper money&apos; ([Measures to reduce bond]) and committed himself in saving government funds by curbing spending on local issues, increasing indirect tax and establishing Yokohama Specie Bank.</e>
<cmt>「公債及び紙幣償還概算書」と「国債紙幣償却方法」（「減債方策」）の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma was pressed to trim public bonds and paper money in order to deal with the inflation, so he drew up &apos;Estimate of redemption of public bond and paper money&apos; in 1878 to stipulate a redemption plan which would be completed by 1905, but he revised it the very next year to create &apos;Measures to redeem government bonds and paper money&apos; (&apos;Measures to reduce bond&apos;) and committed himself in saving government funds by curbing spending on local issues, increasing indirect tax and establishing Yokohama Specie Bank.</e>
<cmt>[Measures to reduce bond]　を　&apos;Measures to reduce bond&apos; と変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma was pressed to trim public bonds and paper money in order to deal with the inflation, so he drew up &apos;Estimate of redemption of public bond and paper money&apos; in 1878 to stipulate a redemption plan which would be completed by 1905, but he revised it the very next year to create &apos;Measures to redeem government bonds and paper money&apos; (&apos;Measures to reduce bond&apos;) and committed himself in saving government funds by curbing spending on local issues, increasing indirect tax and establishing Yokohama Specie Bank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>同時に官有物の払い下げによって官営工場の民間移管を表明したが、大隈は殖産興業政策そのものは放棄せず、殖産興業を大久保の遺志と考える薩摩藩出身の高官や大隈の下で大蔵省に起用された肥前藩出身の若手官僚（石丸安世・石橋重朝ら）も同調した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, he announced to transfer the control of government-owned factories to private sector as part of disposition of government property, but he did not abandon the encouragement of new industry policy itself which was echoed by high officers from Satsuma Domain, who believed the encouragement of new industry was the wish of Okubo, and the young bureaucrats (including Yasuyo ISHIMARU and Shigetomo ISHIBASHI) from Hizen Domain, who entered the Ministry of the Treasury under the leadership of Okuma.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, he announced to transfer the control of government-owned factories to private sector as part of disposition of government property, but he did not abandon the encouragement of new industry policy itself which was aligned with high officers from Satsuma Domain, who believed the encouragement of new industry was the wish of Okubo, and the young bureaucrats (including Yasuyo ISHIMARU and Shigetomo ISHIBASHI) from Hizen Domain, who entered the Ministry of the Treasury under the leadership of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>echoed by を aligned withと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, he announced to transfer the control of government-owned factories to private sector as part of disposition of government property, but he did not abandon the encouragement of new industry policy itself which was aligned with high officers from Satsuma Domain, who believed the encouragement of new industry was the wish of Okubo, and the young bureaucrats (including Yasuyo ISHIMARU and Shigetomo ISHIBASHI) from Hizen Domain, who entered the Ministry of the Treasury under the leadership of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="15">
<j>1880年2月に伊藤博文の提案で参議と卿の分離が実施され、大隈は同郷の佐野常民を後任として自らを「会計部分掌」（財政担当）参議とすることでこれを受け入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, 1880, the posts of Councilor and Minister were separated at the proposal of Ito which Okuma showed his approval by appointing Tsunetami SANO as his successor and assigning himself to &apos;Officer of accounting section&apos; (administrator of fiscal policy).</e>
<cmt>「会計部分掌」の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1880, the posts of Councilor and Minister were separated at the proposal of Ito, which Okuma showed his approval by appointing Tsunetami SANO as his successor and assigning himself to &apos;Kaikeibu Bunsho (a officer of accounting section)&apos; (administrator of fiscal policy).</e>
<cmt>February, 1880のカンマを削除しました。先行詞（節）とwhichの間に「、」を加えました。「会計部分掌」をローマ字表記にし、括弧で補足しました（定訳不明のため）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1880, the posts of Councilor and Minister were separated at the proposal of Ito, which Okuma showed his approval by appointing Tsunetami SANO as his successor and assigning himself to &apos;Kaikeibu Bunsho (a officer of accounting section)&apos; (administrator of fiscal policy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>一方、薩摩藩出身ながら抜本的な財政改革に踏み切らない大隈に不満を抱いていた大蔵大輔の松方正義は佐野の大蔵卿就任と同時に伊藤の後任の内務卿に転じて大蔵省を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, Masayoshi MATSUKATA, from Satsuma Domain, discontent with Okuma who would not carry out a radical financial reform, left the Ministry of the Treasury to take the position of Minister of Interior to replace Ito at the occasion of Sano&apos;s assumption of Minister of the Treasury.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, Masayoshi MATSUKATA, from Satsuma Domain, discontent with Okuma who would not carry out a radical financial reform, left the Ministry of the Treasury to take the position of Minister of Interior to replace Ito at the occasion of Sano&apos;s assumption of Minister of the Treasury.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, Masayoshi MATSUKATA, from Satsuma Domain, discontent with Okuma who would not carry out a radical financial reform, left the Ministry of the Treasury to take the position of Minister of Interior to replace Ito at the occasion of Sano&apos;s assumption of Minister of the Treasury.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>5月14日、大隈は大蔵卿時代に作成した抜本的な紙幣整理案を提案した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 14, Okuma proposed a radical paper money consolidation plan which he had drawn in his Minister of the Treasury age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 14, Okuma proposed a radical paper money consolidation plan which he had drawn in his Minister of the Treasury age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 14, Okuma proposed a radical paper money consolidation plan which he had drawn in his Minister of the Treasury age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これによれば行財政整理とともに新たに5,000万円の外債を募集して一気に不換紙幣を償却するというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This proposed administration and financial adjustment as well as to raise loan of 50-million-yen foreign government bond to redeem all the inconvertible paper money at once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This proposed administration and financial adjustment as well as to raise loan of 50-million-yen worth foreign government bonds to redeem all the inconvertible paper money at once.</e>
<cmt>worthと加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This proposed administration and financial adjustment as well as to raise loan of 50-million-yen worth foreign government bonds to redeem all the inconvertible paper money at once.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これに太政官の閣議は紛糾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dajokan (Grand Council of state) meeting got tangled with this proposal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dajokan (Grand Council of state) meeting got tangled with this proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dajokan (Grand Council of state) meeting got tangled with this proposal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>伊藤博文は5,000万円は当時の財政収入の8割・地租収入の1.3倍にあたり過大すぎると反対し、内務卿に転じていた松方も紙幣整理の方法としては不適切として反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirobumi ITO opposed it saying that 50 million yen corresponded to the 80% of the financial revenue at the time and 1.3 times the land tax income, and Matsukata too, who had made transition to the Minister of Interior, opposed it by calling it inappropriate as a measure to consolidate paper money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirobumi ITO opposed it saying that 50 million yen corresponded to the 80% of the financial revenue at the time and 1.3 times the land tax income, and Matsukata too, who had made transition to the Minister of Interior, opposed it by calling it inappropriate as a measure to consolidate paper money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirobumi ITO opposed it saying that 50 million yen corresponded to the 80% of the financial revenue at the time and 1.3 times the land tax income, and Matsukata too, who had made transition to the Minister of Interior, opposed it by calling it inappropriate as a measure to consolidate paper money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そして、意外にも大隈直系の佐野大蔵卿も反対を表明、更に明治天皇側近の佐々木高行が天皇の意思を奉じて、前年に明治天皇が出した「勤倹の聖旨」と本提案は矛盾すると申し入れを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unexpectedly, Sano, the Minister of the Treasury who was in direct line from Okuma, expressed objection, besides Takayuki SASAKI, close advisor to the Emperor Meiji embracing the will of the Emperor, lodged a protest that the proposal contradicted with the &apos;Emperor&apos;s Thoughts on Diligence and Thriftiness&apos; announced by the Emperor Meiji the year before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unexpectedly, Sano, the Minister of the Treasury who was in direct line from Okuma, expressed objection, besides Takayuki SASAKI, close advisor to the Emperor Meiji embracing the will of the Emperor, lodged a protest that the proposal contradicted with the &apos;Emperor&apos;s Thoughts on Diligence and Thriftiness&apos; announced by the Emperor Meiji the year before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unexpectedly, Sano, the Minister of the Treasury who was in direct line from Okuma, expressed objection, besides Takayuki SASAKI, close advisor to the Emperor Meiji embracing the will of the Emperor, lodged a protest that the proposal contradicted with the &apos;Emperor&apos;s Thoughts on Diligence and Thriftiness&apos; announced by the Emperor Meiji the year before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>岩倉具視は佐々木の天皇の意向を直接利用した方法には反対であったが、自分に相談無く政策を進める参議（伊藤・大隈）への牽制を目的にこれに乗る形で6月3日に明治天皇の勅諭を得ることによって大隈案を否定したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Implying to warn against Councilors (Ito and Okuma), who carried out policies without consulting him, Tomomi IWAKURA denied Okuma proposal by winning Emperor Meiji&apos;s instructions on June 3, taking advantage of Sasaki&apos;s move even though Iwakura opposed to Sasaki&apos;s way of directly exploiting Emperor&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Implying to warn against Councilors (Ito and Okuma), who carried out policies without consulting him, Tomomi IWAKURA denied Okuma proposal by winning Emperor Meiji&apos;s instructions on June 3, taking advantage of Sasaki&apos;s move even though Iwakura opposed to Sasaki&apos;s way of directly exploiting Emperor&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Implying to warn against Councilors (Ito and Okuma), who carried out policies without consulting him, Tomomi IWAKURA denied Okuma proposal by winning Emperor Meiji&apos;s instructions on June 3, taking advantage of Sasaki&apos;s move even though Iwakura opposed to Sasaki&apos;s way of directly exploiting Emperor&apos;s will.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>だが、岩倉による代案が地租の米納復帰と言う江戸時代の年貢への復帰という提案であっために、黒田清隆ら一部の支持を得たのみでこれも否決され、最終的に大隈と伊藤が代案を作成するという結論に落ち着いたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Iwakura&apos;s alternative plan too was rejected, which gained only a little support from Kiyotaka KURODA and a few others because it suggested to pay land tax by rice which means a return to nengu (annual tribute, land tax) system of Edo Period, so Okuma and Ito ended up drawing another alternative plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Iwakura&apos;s alternative plan too was rejected, which gained only a little support from Kiyotaka KURODA and a few others because it suggested to pay land tax by rice which means a return to nengu (annual tribute, land tax) system of Edo Period, so Okuma and Ito ended up drawing another alternative plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Iwakura&apos;s alternative plan too was rejected, which gained only a little support from Kiyotaka KURODA and a few others because it suggested to pay land tax by rice which means a return to nengu (annual tribute, land tax) system of Edo Period, so Okuma and Ito ended up drawing another alternative plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="24">
<j>ところが、立憲制導入を巡る大隈の左大臣有栖川宮熾仁親王への密奏と議院内閣制の導入提案が岩倉の態度を硬化させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Iwakura stiffened his attitude when he heard of Okuma&apos;s secret report to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, Minister of the Left, concerning the introduction of constitutional monarchy and of Okuma&apos;s proposal for the introduction of parliamentary cabinet system, and also he took the proposal by Yasuyo ISHIMARU and Shigetomo ISHIBASHI to call off the disposal of Hokkaido Development Commissioner&apos;s property for its &apos;unjustifiably low price&apos; as Okuma&apos;s conspiracy with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, so a conference in the presence of the emperor was convened by request from Iwakura where the dismissal of Okuma as Councilor, removal of Sano as Minister of the Treasury, and transference of Matsukata as Secretary of Interior were decided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However Iwakura stiffened his attitude when he heard of Okuma&apos;s secret report to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, Minister of the Left, concerning the introduction of constitutional monarchy and of Okuma&apos;s proposal for the introduction of parliamentary cabinet system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処But を Howeverと変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However Iwakura stiffened his attitude when he heard of Okuma&apos;s secret report to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, Minister of the Left, concerning the introduction of constitutional monarchy and of Okuma&apos;s proposal for the introduction of parliamentary cabinet system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>さらに開拓使官有物払下げ事件に際して出された石丸安世・石橋重朝の「不当廉価」を理由とした払い下げ中止の提議が、自由民権運動と結んだ大隈の謀略として受け止められ、岩倉らの要求によって御前会議が招集され、大隈の参議免官と佐野大蔵卿の更迭、後任に松方内務卿の転任が決定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura also took the proposal by Yasuyo ISHIMARU and Shigetomo ISHIBASHI to call off the disposal of Hokkaido Development Commissioner&apos;s property for its &apos;unjustifiably low price&apos; as Okuma&apos;s conspiracy with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, so a conference in the presence of the Emperor was convened by request from Iwakura where the dismissal of Okuma as Councilor, removal of Sano as Minister of the Treasury, and transference of Matsukata as Secretary of Interior were decided.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処the Emperorと修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura also took the proposal by Yasuyo ISHIMARU and Shigetomo ISHIBASHI to call off the disposal of Hokkaido Development Commissioner&apos;s property for its &apos;unjustifiably low price&apos; as Okuma&apos;s conspiracy with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, so a conference in the presence of the Emperor was convened by request from Iwakura where the dismissal of Okuma as Councilor, removal of Sano as Minister of the Treasury, and transference of Matsukata as Secretary of Interior were decided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>これによって大隈財政は終わりを告げることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This marked the end of Okuma finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This marked the end of Okuma finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This marked the end of Okuma finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>