<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>地侍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ji-zamurai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ji-zamurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ji-zamurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>地侍（じざむらい）は、室町時代から安土桃山時代にかけて見られた侍身分の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ji-zamurai is a rank of samurai seen from Muromachi period to Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ji-zamurai is a rank of samurai seen from Muromachi period to Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ji-zamurai is a rank of samurai seen from Muromachi period to Azuchi Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>もともとは、名主などの有力百姓だった者が、守護大名や在地の国人領主などと主従関係を結び、侍身分を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, powerful farmers such as Myoshu (officer of the field) made master-servant relationship with Shugo Daimyo (provincial governors) and Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai governors) and got the position of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, powerful farmers such as Myoshu (officer of the field) made master-servant relationship with Shugo Daimyo (provincial governors) and Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai governors) and achieved the position of samurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, powerful farmers such as Myoshu (officer of the field) made master-servant relationship with Shugo Daimyo (provincial governors) and Kokujin Ryoshu (local samurai governors) and achieved the position of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「土豪」と呼ばれることもあるが、土豪＝地侍ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is sometimes called &apos;Dogo&apos; but Dogo is not equal to Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is sometimes called &apos;Dogo&apos; but Dogo is not equal to Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is sometimes called &apos;Dogo&apos; but Dogo is not equal to Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>土豪とは広義には、広域を支配する領主や在地の大豪族に対して、特定の「土地の小豪族」、その地域の「在地の小豪族」という意味もあり、その場合は、地侍の主筋になる在地領主も含まれるからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is because, compared to Ryoshu and large Gozoku (powerful families) who govern wide regions, Dogo in a broader sense has a meaning of &apos;small Gozoku specific in the regions&apos;, in which case Dogo includes Zaichi Ryoshu, the lord of the manors of Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>「特定の「土地の小豪族」、その地域の「在地の小豪族」の部分はほとんど繰り返しになるため、1度だけ訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is because, compared to Ryoshu and large Gozoku (powerful families) who govern wide regions, Dogo in a broader sense has a meaning of &apos;small Gozoku specific in the regions&apos;, in which case Dogo includes Zaichi Ryoshu, the lord of the manors of Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is because, compared to Ryoshu and large Gozoku (powerful families) who govern wide regions, Dogo in a broader sense has a meaning of &apos;small Gozoku specific in the regions,&apos; in which case Dogo includes Zaichi Ryoshu, the lord of the manors of Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>コンマの位置を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>地侍たちは、侍身分となることで、中央の守護や、在地の国人のような領国支配者の下で小領主となることを指向していたが、支配者から見れば、地侍は在地百姓の有力者に過ぎず、被支配者と見なされがちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ji-zamurai intended to become small lords under the rule of central and provincial governors, but they were regarded as subjects since they were just powerful farmers from the perspective of governors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ji-zamurai intended to become small lords under the rule of central and provincial governors, but they were regarded as subjects since they were just powerful farmers from the perspective of governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ji-zamurai intended to become small lords under the rule of central and provincial governors, but they were regarded as subjects since they were just powerful farmers from the perspective of governors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>土一揆の時代には一揆の中核として活躍し、中には、村落から離脱して、自らの地位を武士に特化する地侍もおり、戦国時代 (日本)に入ると、戦国大名やその幕下の大身の国人領主の家臣として系列化された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the period of Doikki (peasant uprising), they performed an active role as the core of the uprising, some of whom left the village to emphasize on their position as samurai and they were organized as subordinate warriors under Sengoku Daimyo (warring lords) and Kokujin Ryoshu in Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of Doikki (peasant uprising), they performed an active role as the core of the uprising, some of whom left the village to emphasize on their position as samurai and they were organized as subordinate warriors under Sengoku Daimyo (warring lords) and Kokujin Ryoshu in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of Doikki (peasant uprising), they performed an active role as the core of the uprising, some of whom left the village to emphasize on their position as samurai and they were organized as subordinate warriors under Sengoku Daimyo (warring lords) and Kokujin Ryoshu in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>地侍層は、戦国大名や国人領主から加地子（地代＝中間得分）の徴収権を保証される代わりに、家臣となり、戦時には軍役を果たす義務を負った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ji-zamurai undertake obligations of serving as a part of military at the time of war in return for the privilege to collect Kajishi (intermediate taxes) guaranteed by Sengoku Daimyo and Kokujin Ryoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ji-zamurai undertook obligations of serving as a part of military at the time of war in return for the privilege to collect Kajishi (intermediate taxes) guaranteed by Sengoku Daimyo and Kokujin Ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ji-zamurai undertook obligations of serving as a part of military at the time of war in return for the privilege to collect Kajishi (intermediate taxes) guaranteed by Sengoku Daimyo and Kokujin Ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代の大名・旗本には、このような地侍を出自とする家も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Daimyo (direct retainers of the lords) and Hatamoto in Edo period originated from these Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Daimyo (direct retainers of the lords) and Hatamoto during the Edo period originated from these Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Daimyo (direct retainers of the lords) and Hatamoto during the Edo period originated from these Ji-zamurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、大多数の地侍は、侍身分でありながら村落に在住し、村落の指導者としてあり続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the majority of Ji-zamurai stayed in their villages being leaders there despite their position as samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the majority of Ji-zamurai stayed in their villages being leaders there despite their position as samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the majority of Ji-zamurai stayed in their villages being leaders there despite their position as samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>こうした地侍たちは、安土桃山期の兵農分離（刀狩など）によって郷士や再度、百姓身分に戻り、庄屋・名主・肝煎・番頭など村の指導者としての地位に就くことが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, these Ji-zamurai returned to the position of farmers due to the separation policy of samurai and farmers such as sword hant in Azuchi Momoyama period and took the leaders&apos; position of the villages such as Shoya, Nanushi, Kimoiri and Banto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, these Ji-zamurai returned to the position of farmers due to the separation policy of samurai and farmers such as the sword hunt during the Azuchi Momoyama period and took the leaders&apos; position of the villages such as Shoya, Nanushi, Kimoiri, and Banto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, these Ji-zamurai returned to the position of farmers due to the separation policy of samurai and farmers such as the sword hunt during the Azuchi Momoyama period and took the leaders&apos; position of the villages such as Shoya, Nanushi, Kimoiri, and Banto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 海衛士(id:19229), Tetsusaburou(id:58913), NPD(id:58640), Zorac(id:28001), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), Kotoito(id:21045), 伏儀(id:142093), Junger(id:10282), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>