<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日露戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russo-Japanese War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>日露戦争（にちろせんそう、露語 ルースカ・イポーンスカヤ・ヴァイナー、1904年（明治37年）2月6日 - 1905年（明治38年）9月5日）は、大日本帝国とロシア帝国（ロシアと同盟していたモンテネグロ（当時はモンテネグロ公国）も宣戦布告するも、実際の戦闘には参加せず）との間で朝鮮半島と満州（中国東北部）南部を主戦場として発生した戦争である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War (Русско-японская война in Russian, February 6, 1904 - September 5, 1905) was a war which broke out between the Great Empire of Japan and the Russian Empire (Although Montenegro (Principate of Montenegro at that time) in alliance with Russia declared war against Japan, it did not participate in the real battles) in the Korean Peninsula and southern part of Manchuria (Northeastern part of China) as the principal battleground.</e>
<cmt>「ルースカ・イポーンスカヤ・ヴァイナー」のロシア語は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%97%A5%E9%9C%B2%E6%88%A6%E4%BA%89　「大日本帝国」の英文は、研究社　新和英大辞典第５版から引用いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Russo-Japanese War (Русско-японская война in Russian, February 6, 1904 - September 5, 1905) was a war which broke out between the Great Empire of Japan and the Russian Empire (Although Montenegro, (Then known as the Principate of Montenegro) which was in an alliance with Russia declared war against Japan, it did not participate battle.) and was primarily fought on the Korean Peninsula and southern Manchuria (northeastern China).</e>
<cmt>Style &amp; Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War (Русско-японская война in Russian, February 6, 1904 - September 5, 1905) was a war which broke out between the Great Empire of Japan and the Russian Empire (Although Montenegro, [Then known as the Principate of Montenegro] which was in an alliance with Russia declared war against Japan, it did not participate battle.) and was primarily fought on the Korean Peninsula and southern Manchuria (northeastern China).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>戦争目的と動機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War objectives and motive</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Purpose and Motives for War</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Purpose and Motives for War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>三国干渉および北清事変後中国東北部(満州)を勢力圏としていたロシア帝国による朝鮮半島への南下（朝鮮支配）を防ぎ、日本の安全保障と半島での利権を確保することを目的とした戦争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a war to assure the security of Japan and secure Japanese rights and interests in the peninsula by preventing the Russian Empire, which held the Northeastern part of China (Manchuria) under its influence after the Triple Intervention and the Boxer Rebellion, from advancing southward to the Korean Peninsula (Domination of Korea).</e>
<cmt>「北清事変」の英文名は、新和英大辞典第５版から引用いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a war to protect the sovereignty of Japan and secure Japanese rights and interests in the peninsula by preventing the southward expansion of the Russian Empire (the domination of Korea), which established a presence in Northeastern part of China (Manchuria) after the Triple Intervention and the Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Style &amp; Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a war to protect the sovereignty of Japan and secure Japanese rights and interests in the peninsula by preventing the southward expansion of the Russian Empire (the domination of Korea), which established a presence in Northeastern part of China (Manchuria) after the Triple Intervention and the Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>中国遼東半島の旅順、大連租借権等の確保と中国東北部および朝鮮における自国権益の維持・拡大を目的とした戦争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each country sought to secure concessions in Lushun and Dalian in China&apos;s Liaodong peninsula and maintain and expand their rights and interests in the other parts of Northeastern China and Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each country sought to secure concessions in Lushun and Dalian in China&apos;s Liaodong peninsula and maintain and expand their rights and interests in the other parts of Northeastern China and Korea.</e>
<cmt>Style &amp; Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each country sought to secure concessions in Lushun and Dalian in China&apos;s Liaodong peninsula and maintain and expand their rights and interests in the other parts of Northeastern China and Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>ロシアと日本の対立の場となった朝鮮半島</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean Peninsula became a place where Russia and Japan confronted each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia and Japan confronted each other on the Korean peninsula.</e>
<cmt>Style &amp; Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia and Japan confronted each other on the Korean peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>大韓帝国は冊封体制から離脱したものの、満州を勢力下においたロシアが朝鮮半島に持つ利権を手がかりに南下政策を取りつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Korean Empire broke away from the tributary system, Russia which held Manchuria under its influence proceeded with southward expansion using its interest in the Korean Peninsula as a lead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Korean Empire broke away from the tributary system, Russia which held Manchuria under its sphere of influence, took advantage of its interests in Korea to proceed with its southward expansion.</e>
<cmt>Style &amp; Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Korean Empire broke away from the tributary system, Russia which held Manchuria under its sphere of influence, took advantage of its interests in Korea to proceed with its southward expansion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ロシアは閔妃を通じ売り払われた鍾城・鏡源の鉱山採掘権や朝鮮北部の森林伐採権、関税権などの国家基盤を取得し朝鮮半島での影響力を増したが、ロシアの進める南下政策に危機感を持っていた日本がこれらを買い戻し回復させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Russia acquired the basis of a state including the mining rights for Chongsŏng and Kyogen sold by Empress Myeongseong, the felling right for forests in the northern part of Korea and the tariff right and increased its influence in the Korean Peninsula, Japan which was alarmed by Russia&apos;s southward expansion bought back and restored these rights.</e>
<cmt>「鍾城」の読みは、下記サイトから引用しました。http://www.weblio.jp/content/%E9%8D%BE%E5%9F%8E%E9%83%A1　「鏡源」の読みは、用語集、サイトでも見つからず、定かではありません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan became alarmed when Russia enhanced its grip and influence over the Korean peninsula by acquiring vital state assets such as the mining rights in Chongsong and Gyeongwon sold off by Empress Myeongsong, timber rights in the north, and tariff rights, and purchased many of these back.</e>
<cmt>Style. 「買い戻し回復させた」?Really? Korean place names were elided in the translation, I have included them my correction.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan became alarmed when Russia enhanced its grip and influence over the Korean peninsula by acquiring vital state assets such as the mining rights in Chongsong and Gyeongwon sold off by Empress Myeongsong, timber rights in the north, and tariff rights, and purchased back and restored many of these.</e>
<cmt>「買い戻し回復させた」many of these back→back and restored many of theseとしました。「and Gyeongwon」「timber rights」のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当初、日本は外交努力で衝突を避けようとしたが、ロシアは強大な軍事力を背景に日本への圧力を増していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Japan tried to avoid a conflict by diplomatic efforts, however, Russia backed by its massive military force continued to increase its pressure toward Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Japan sought to avoid a conflict through diplomatic efforts; however, Russia backed by its massive military force continued to increase its pressure toward Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Japan sought to avoid a conflict through diplomatic efforts; however, Russia backed by its massive military force continued to increase its pressure toward Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>1904年2月23日、開戦前に「局外中立宣言」をした大韓帝国における軍事行動を可能にするために日韓議定書を締結し、開戦後8月には第一次日韓協約を締結、大韓帝国の財政、外交に顧問を置き条約締結に日本政府との協議をすることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 23, 1904, Japan concluded Japanese-Korean Protocol to make it possible for Japan to take military action in the Korean Empire which had made the &apos;Declaration of neutrality&apos; before the start of the war, and, in August after the start of the war, Japanese-Korean Treaty of 1904, by which Japan assigned advisers to Korean financial and foreign departments and Korea was to make prior consultation with the Japanese Government before concluding treaties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 23rd, 1904, Japan concluded the Japan-Korean Protocol enabling Japan to take military action in the Korea in spite of the fact that the Korean Empire had announced a &apos;Declaration of neutrality&apos; prior to the outbreak of the war; This made the way for the conclusion of the Japan-Korea Treaty in August 1904 in which Japan assigned advisers to Korean financial and foreign affairs departments to ensure that they consulted the Japanese government prior to concluding treaties with foreign powers.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 23rd, 1904, Japan concluded the Japan-Korean Protocol enabling Japan to take military action in the Korea in spite of the fact that the Korean Empire had announced a &apos;Declaration of neutrality&apos; prior to the outbreak of the war; This made the way for the conclusion of the Japan-Korea Treaty in August 1904 in which Japan assigned advisers to Korean financial and foreign affairs departments to ensure that they consulted the Japanese government prior to concluding treaties with foreign powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>大韓帝国内でも李氏朝鮮による旧体制が維持されている状況では独自改革が難しいと判断した進歩会は日韓合邦を目指そうと鉄道敷設工事などに5万人ともいわれる大量の人員を派遣するなど、日露戦争において日本への協力を惜しまなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpo-kai, which determined its own reform was difficult under the situation where the old system of the Yi Dynasty Korea still remained in the Korean Empire, aimed at a political union with Japan and willingly cooperated with Japan in the Russo-Japanese War, for instance, by sending a workforce of reportedly 50,000 persons for track-laying work and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shinpo-kai, which determined that the pursuit of reforms was difficult under systems of the former Yi Dynasty sought political union with Japan and voluntarily collaborated in support of Japan during the Russo-Japanese War; for instance, it reportedly deployed 50,000 people to construct railways.</e>
<cmt>Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shinpo-kai, which determined that the pursuit of reforms was difficult under systems of the former Yi Dynasty sought political union with Japan and voluntarily collaborated in support of Japan during the Russo-Japanese War; for instance, it reportedly deployed 50,000 people to construct railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>一方、高宗や両班などの旧李朝支配者層は日本の影響力をあくまでも排除しようと試み、日露戦争中においてもロシアに密書を送るなどの外交を展開していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the ruling classes including Gojong and Yanban in the old Yi Dynasty insisted on making efforts to remove the Japanese influence, and conducted diplomatic actions like sending secret letters to Russia during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Emperor Gojong and the yangban elite of the former Yi Dynasty insisted on the removal of Japanese influence, and carried out diplomatic maneuvers such as sending secret letters to Russia during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Style. (Yanban--&gt; YangbanGojon--&gt; Gojong.Let&apos;s get our Korean right here!Gojong was the Emperor of Korean.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Emperor Gojong and the yangban elite of the former Yi Dynasty insisted on the removal of Japanese influence, and carried out diplomatic maneuvers such as sending secret letters to Russia during the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日英同盟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anglo-Japanese Alliance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anglo-Japanese Alliance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anglo-Japanese Alliance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>ロシア帝国は、不凍港を求めて南下政策を採用し、露土戦争 (1877年)などの勝利によってバルカン半島における大きな地歩を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Russian Empire proceeded with its southward expansion seeking non-freezing ports and built up a strong foothold in the Balkan Peninsula by the victory in the Russo-Turkish Wars (1877) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its pursuit of warm-water ports, the Russian Empire preceded with its southward expansion and acquried a significant foothold in the Balkan peninsula through its victory against the Ottoman Empire in the Russo-Turkish Wars (1877).</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its pursuit of warm-water ports, the Russian Empire preceded with its southward expansion and acquried a significant foothold in the Balkan peninsula through its victory against the Ottoman Empire in the Russo-Turkish Wars (1877).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ロシアの影響力の増大を警戒するドイツ帝国の宰相オットー・フォン・ビスマルクは列強の代表を集めてベルリン会議 (1878年)を主催し、露土戦争の講和条約であるサン・ステファノ条約の破棄とベルリン条約 (1878年)の締結に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otto von Bismarck, Chancellor of the German Empire,alarmed by the increasing influence of Russia, held the Congress of Berlin (1878) getting representatives of the great powers and succeeded in the denunciation of the San Stefano Treaty, the peace treaty of the Russo-Turkish Wars and the signing of the Berlin Treaty (1878).</e>
<cmt>「宰相オットー・フォン・ビスマルク」の英文は、新和英大辞典第５版から引用いたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alarmed by the increasing influence of Russia, Otto von Bismarck, Chancellor of the German Empire hosted the Congress of Berlin (1878) and succeeded in gathering the representatives of the great powers to denounce the Treaty of San Stefano, the peace treaty of the Russo-Turkish Wars and conclude the Treaty of Berlin (1878).</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alarmed by the increasing influence of Russia, Otto von Bismarck, Chancellor of the German Empire hosted the Congress of Berlin (1878) and succeeded in gathering the representatives of the great powers to denounce the Treaty of San Stefano, the peace treaty of the Russo-Turkish Wars and conclude the Treaty of Berlin (1878).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これによりロシアはバルカン半島での南下政策を断念し、進出の矛先を極東地域に向けることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By that, Russia gave up the idea of southward expansion in the Balkan Peninsula and changed the direction of an expansion to the Far East area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Russia abandoned its southward expansion in the Balkan peninsula and shifted its direction towards expansion in the Far East.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Russia abandoned its southward expansion in the Balkan peninsula and shifted its direction towards expansion in the Far East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>近代国家の建設を急ぐ日本では、朝鮮半島を自国の独占的な勢力下におく必要があるとの意見が大勢を占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan which tried to construct a modern state as soon as possible, opinions that it was necessary to put the Korean Peninsula under its own exclusive influence held a preponderance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its rush to establish a modern nation state the opinion that the Korean peninsula should be placed under the exclusive influence of Japan held sway.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its rush to establish a modern nation state the opinion that the Korean peninsula should be placed under the exclusive influence of Japan held sway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>朝鮮を属国としていた清との日清戦争に勝利し、朝鮮半島への影響力を排除したものの、中国への進出を目論むロシア、フランス、ドイツからの三国干渉によって、下関条約で割譲を受けた遼東半島は清に返還された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-&apos;95, Japan defeated Qing which held Korea under its rule, removing Qing&apos;s influence to the Korean Peninsula, however, was forced to return to Qing the Liaodong Peninsula ceded to Japan under the Shimonoseki Peace Treaty, on the basis of the Triple Intervention by Russia, France and Germany which planned to expand to China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-&apos;95, Japan defeated the Qing Dynasty, and removed its influence over its formal vassal Korea; However, in spite of the fact that the Liaodong Peninsula was ceded to Japan by the Qing under the Treaty of Shimonoseki, Japan was prompted to return Liaodong to the Qing under pressure from the Triple Intervention of Russia, France, and Germany that sought to secure their own ambitions in China.</e>
<cmt>phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-&apos;95, Japan defeated the Qing Dynasty, and removed its influence over its formal vassal Korea; However, in spite of the fact that the Liaodong Peninsula was ceded to Japan by the Qing under the Treaty of Shimonoseki, Japan was prompted to return Liaodong to the Qing under pressure from the Triple Intervention of Russia, France, and Germany that sought to secure their own ambitions in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>世論においてはロシアとの戦争も辞さずという強硬な意見も出たが、当時の日本には列強諸国と戦えるだけの力は無く、政府内では伊藤博文ら戦争回避派が主流を占めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there were strong public opinions of being ready to go to war with Russia, Japan at that time did not have power to fight against the great powers, and the group opposing war including Hirobumi ITO were the mainstream in the Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Japanese public opinon was strongly in favor of declarling war on Russia, Japan still did not have the strength to fight a great power such as Russia, and a faction opposing war prevailed in the government.</e>
<cmt>phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Japanese public opinon was strongly in favor of declarling war on Russia, Japan still did not have the strength to fight a great power such as Russia, and a faction opposing war prevailed in the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ところがロシアは露清密約を結び、日本が手放した遼東半島の南端に位置する旅順・大連市を1898年に租借し、旅順に旅順艦隊（第一太平洋艦隊）を配置するなど、満洲への進出を押し進めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia, however, concluded a secret agreement with Qing, obtained leases in 1898 on Lushun and Dalian City at the southern tip of Liaodong Peninsula which Japan was forced to return, and proceeded with expansion to Manchuria making Lushun a naval base for Lushun Fleet (The first Pacific Fleet).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia, however, concluded a secret agreement with the Qing and obtained leases for the cities of Lushun and Dalian at the southern tip of the Liaodong peninsula which Japan was forced to return, and proceeded to expand its presence in Manchuria constructing a naval base in Lushun for the First Pacific Fleet (Lushun Fleet).</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia, however, concluded a secret agreement with the Qing and obtained leases for the cities of Lushun and Dalian at the southern tip of the Liaodong peninsula which Japan was forced to return, and proceeded to expand its presence in Manchuria constructing a naval base in Lushun for the First Pacific Fleet (Lushun Fleet).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>1900年にロシアは清で発生した義和団事変（義和団事件）の混乱収拾を名目に満州へ侵攻し、全土を占領下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, Russia invaded Manchuria under the pretext of settling the chaos of the Boxer Uprising (the Boxer Incident) which occurred in Qing, and put Manchuria under its occupation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1900, Russia invaded Manchuria under the pretext of settling the chaos of the Boxer Uprising (the Boxer Incident), which occurred in the Qing Dynasty, and placed all of Manchuria under its authority.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900, Russia invaded Manchuria under the pretext of settling the chaos of the Boxer Uprising (the Boxer Incident), which occurred in the Qing Dynasty, and placed all of Manchuria under its authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>ロシアは満洲の植民地化を既定事実化しようとしたが、日英米がこれに抗議しロシアは撤兵を約束した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Russia tried to make the occupied Manchuria an established fact, Japan, England and the United States protested to Russia, which promised to withdraw its troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Russia attempted to secure Manchuria through colonization, Japan, England, and the United States protested, and Russia subsequently promised to withdraw its troops.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Russia attempted to secure Manchuria through colonization, Japan, England, and the United States protested, and Russia subsequently promised to withdraw its troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ところがロシアは履行期限を過ぎても撤退を行わず駐留軍の増強を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia, however, did not withdraw its troops even after the promised deadline passed, and on the contrary it reinforced the occupation troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russsia, however, did not withdraw its troops even after the promised deadline had passed; on the contrary, it planned to reinforce its occupation.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russsia, however, did not withdraw its troops even after the promised deadline had passed; on the contrary, it planned to reinforce its occupation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ロシアの南下が自国の権益と衝突すると考えたイギリスは危機感を募らせ、1902年に長年墨守していた孤立政策（栄光ある孤立）を捨て、日本との同盟に踏み切った（日英同盟）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">England, alarmed by the southward expansion of Russia which would possibly violate its own interests, abandoned the isolationist policy (Splendid Isolation) it had adhered to for many years and decided to enter into an alliance with Japan (the Anglo-Japanese Alliance) in 1902.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">England became alarmed that Russia&apos;s southward expansion could clash with its own interests, abandoned the isolationist policy (Splendid Isolation) it had adhered to for many years, and decided to enter into an alliance with Japan in 1902 (Anglo-Japanese Alliance).</e>
<cmt>Phrasing; &quot;splendid isolation&quot;?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">England became alarmed that Russia&apos;s southward expansion could clash with its own interests, abandoned the isolationist policy (Splendid Isolation) it had adhered to for many years, and decided to enter into an alliance with Japan in 1902 (Anglo-Japanese Alliance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>日本政府内では小村寿太郎、桂太郎、山縣有朋らの対露主戦派と、伊藤博文、井上馨ら戦争回避派との論争が続き、民間においても日露開戦を唱えた戸水寛人ら七博士の意見書（七博士建白事件）や、万朝報紙上での幸徳秋水の非戦論といった議論が発生していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While a dispute was kept going in the Japanese Government between the group advocating war against Russia including Jutaro KOMURA, Taro KATSURA and Aritomo YAMAGATA and the group opposing war including Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, a written petition (Seven professors&apos; Petition Incident) was submitted by seven professors including Hirondo TOMIZU who advocated war against Russia and an antiwar argument by Shusui KOTOKU was discussed on Yorozuchoho (a daily newspaper).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While debates continued within the Japanese government between factions including KOMURA Jutao, KATSURA Taro, and YAMAGATA Aritomo and an anti-war faction including ITO Hirobumi and INOUE Kaoru, these discussions were mirrored in the public sphere by an pro-war petition circulated by seven professors (Seven Professor&apos;s Petition) including TOMIZU Hirondo and an anti-war argument and discussion by KOTUKU Shusui which was published in the Yorozuchoho (a daily newspaper).</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While debates continued within the Japanese government between factions including Jutaro KOMURA, Taro KATSURA, and Aritomo YAMAGATA and an anti-war faction including Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, these discussions were mirrored in the public sphere by an pro-war petition circulated by seven professors (Seven Professor&apos;s Petition) including Hirondo TOMIZU and an anti-war argument and discussion by Shusui KOTUKU which was published in the Yorozuchoho (a daily newspaper).</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>1903年4月21日に京都にあった山縣の別荘・無鄰庵で伊藤・山縣・桂・小村による「無鄰庵無鄰菴会議」が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 21, 1903, &apos;the Murinan conference&apos; was held in Murinan residence, Yamagata&apos;s villa in Kyoto with Ito, Yamagata, Katsura and Komura attended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 21st, 1903 the &quot;Murinan Conference&quot; was convened at the Murinan residence, YAMAGATA&apos;s villa in Kyoto with ITO, YAMAGATA, KATSURA, and KOMURA attending.</e>
<cmt>Names Capitalized</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 21st, 1903 the &quot;Murinan Conference&quot; was convened at the Murinan residence, Yamagata&apos;s villa in Kyoto with Ito, Yamagata, Katsura, and Komura attending.</e>
<cmt>名字単体の記載のため、頭文字のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>桂は、「満州問題に対しては、我に於て露國の優越権を認め、之を機として朝鮮問題を根本的に解決すること」、「此の目的を貫徹せんと欲せば、戦争をも辞せざる覚悟無かる可からず」という対露交渉方針について伊藤と山縣の同意を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsura obtained consent of Ito and Yamagata on the following policy for negotiation with Russia: &apos;We will give priority to Russia on the Manchuria issue and taking advantage of it, we will make the Korean issue thoroughly settled,&apos; &apos;If we want this purpose achieved, we must be prepared to go to war.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KATSURA received approval from ITO and YAMAGATA on the following policies to be negotiated with RUssia &quot;We will recognize the rights of Russia concerning the issue of Manchuria, and we would like to use this opportunity to decisively settle the issue of Korea,&quot; &quot;If we want to achieve this, we must be prepared to go to war.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsura received approval from Ito and Yamagata on the following policies to be negotiated with Russia &quot;We will recognize the rights of Russia concerning the issue of Manchuria, and we would like to use this opportunity to decisively settle the issue of Korea,&quot; &quot;If we want to achieve this, we must be prepared to go to war.&quot;</e>
<cmt>名字単体の記載のため、頭文字のみ大文字に修正しました。RUssia→Russia</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>桂は後にこの会談で日露開戦の覚悟が定まったと書いているが、実際の記録類ではむしろ伊藤の慎重論が優勢であったようで、後の日露交渉に反映されることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, Katsura wrote that they made up their mind in that conference to go to war against Russia, however, Ito&apos;s opposition to risk seems to have been rather leading according to real records, which ended up being reflected on the later negotiation with Russia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although it was recorded afterward that KATSURA was already prepared to declare war on Russia, actual records reveal that cooler head prevaileds, as reflected afterwards in the negotiations with Russia.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although it was recorded afterward that Katsura was already prepared to declare war on Russia, actual records reveal that Ito&apos;s cooler head prevailed, as reflected afterwards in the negotiations with Russia.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れの「伊藤の」＝Ito&apos;sを追加しました。名字単体の記載のため、頭文字のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>直前交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Last-minute negotiation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Last-minute Negotiations</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Last-minute Negotiations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>1903年8月からの日露交渉において、日本側は朝鮮半島を日本、満洲をロシアの支配下に置くという妥協案、いわゆる満韓交換論をロシア側へ提案した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the negotiation with Russia from August 1903, Japan proposed to Russia to put the Korean Peninsula under the Japanese control and Manchuria under the Russian control, which was a compromise so-called Settlement by exchange of Manchuria with Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the negotiation with Russia from August 1903, Japan proposed that the Korean Peninsula under the Japanese control and Manchuria under the Russian control, in a compromise known as the Manchuria-Korea Trade-off.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the negotiation with Russia from August 1903, Japan proposed that the Korean Peninsula under the Japanese control and Manchuria under the Russian control, in a compromise known as the Manchuria-Korea Trade-off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、積極的な主戦論を主張していたロシア海軍や関東州総督のエヴゲーニイ・アレクセーエフらは、朝鮮半島でも増えつつあったロシアの利権を妨害される恐れのある妥協案に興味を示さなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Russian navy and Евгений Алексеев, the governor-general of the Kwantung Leased Territory, both of which positively advocated war did not show interest in the compromise proposal which may have interfere with the increasing Russian interests in the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>「エヴゲーニイ・アレクセーエフ」のロシア語は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%A8%E3%83%B4%E3%82%B2%E3%83%BC%E3%83%8B%E3%82%A4%E3%83%BB%E3%82%A2%E3%83%AC%E3%82%AF%E3%82%BB%E3%83%BC%E3%82%A8%E3%83%95</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fearing that the expansion of Russian interests on the Korean peninsula would be impeded, neither the Russian navy, which advocated war, nor Евгений Алексеев, the governor-general of the Kwantung Leased Territory expressed interest in the settlement.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fearing that the expansion of Russian interests on the Korean peninsula would be impeded, neither the Russian navy, which advocated war, nor Евгений Алексеев, the governor-general of the Kwantung Leased Territory expressed interest in the settlement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>さらにニコライ2世やアレクセイ・クロパトキン陸軍大臣も主戦論に同調した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Nicholai II and Aleksei Kuropatkin, Minister of Army aligned themselves with the advocates of war.</e>
<cmt>「アレクセイ・クロパトキン」の英文名は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%A2%E3%83%AC%E3%82%AF%E3%82%BB%E3%82%A4%E3%83%BB%E3%82%AF%E3%83%AD%E3%83%91%E3%83%88%E3%82%AD%E3%83%B3</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, both Nicholai II and the Minister of the Army, Aleksei Kuropatkin advocated war.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, both Nicholai II and the Minister of the Army, Aleksei Kuropatkin advocated war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>常識的に考えれば、強大なロシアが日本との戦争を恐れる理由は何も無かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From a commonsense point of view, the powerful Russiahad no reason to fear of war against Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They believed that a country as powerful and large as Russia had nothing to fear in a war against Japan.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They believed that a country as powerful and large as Russia had nothing to fear in a war against Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="29">
<j>セルゲイ・ヴィッテ首相は、戦争によって負けることはないにせよロシアが疲弊することを恐れ、戦争回避論を展開したが、これは皇帝達によって退けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prime Minister Sergei Witte, for fear that Russia would become exhausted if not defeated, asserted to avoid war, however, rejected by the Emperor and others.</e>
<cmt>「セルゲイ・ヴィッテ」の英文は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%BB%E3%83%AB%E3%82%B2%E3%82%A4%E3%83%BB%E3%83%B4%E3%82%A3%E3%83%83%E3%83%86</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prime Minister Sergei Witte expressed opposition to the war in the fear that though Russia would not lose, it would could exhaust the country; However, his assertions were rejected by the Emperor and others.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prime Minister Sergei Witte expressed opposition to the war in the fear that though Russia would not lose, it would could exhaust the country; However, his assertions were rejected by the Emperor and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ロシアは日本側への返答として、朝鮮半島の北緯39度以北を中立地帯とし、軍事目的での利用を禁ずるという提案を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia proposed, as its reply to Japan, to make the Korean Peninsula north of the 39th parallel a neutral zone where no military use is allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its reply to Japan, Russia proposed making the Korean peninsula north of the 39th parallel a neutral demilitarized zone.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its reply to Japan, Russia proposed making the Korean peninsula north of the 39th parallel a neutral demilitarized zone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>日本側では、この提案では朝鮮が事実上ロシアの支配下となり、日本の独立も危機的な状況になりかねないと判断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan judged that the proposal would put Korea substantially under the control of Russia and could endanger the independence of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan judged that the Russian proposal would effectively place Korea under the control of the Russians, and would inevitably pose a threat to the Japanese sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan judged that the Russian proposal would effectively place Korea under the control of the Russians, and would inevitably pose a threat to the Japanese sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>またシベリア鉄道が全線開通するとヨーロッパに配備されているロシア軍の極東方面への派遣が容易となるの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the whole line of the Trans-Siberian Railway was completed, it would become easier to send troops stationed in Europe to the Far East area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the completion of the Trans-Siberian Railway would easily enable the Russian military to rapidly deploy their forces to the Far East.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the completion of the Trans-Siberian Railway would easily enable the Russian military to rapidly deploy their forces to the Far East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その前の対露開戦へと国論が傾いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That guided public opinion towards going to war against Russia before it happened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public opinion swayed towards declaring war on Russia.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public opinion swayed towards declaring war on Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>そして1904年2月6日、日本の外務大臣小村寿太郎は当時のロシアのロマン・ローゼン公使を外務省に呼び、国交断絶を言い渡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, on February 6, 1904, Jutaro KOMURA, Japanese Foreign Minister called Roman Rosen, the Russian Minister to Japan to the Foreign Ministry and notified him of the severance of diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>「ロマン・ローゼン」の英文は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%AD%E3%83%9E%E3%83%B3%E3%83%BB%E3%83%AD%E3%83%BC%E3%82%BC%E3%83%B3</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, on February 6th, 1904, KOMURA Jutaro, the Japanese Foreign Minister called Roman Rosen, the Russian Minister to Japan to the Foreign Ministry and notified him of the severance of diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, on February 6th, 1904, Jutaro KOMURA, the Japanese Foreign Minister called Roman Rosen, the Russian Minister to Japan to the Foreign Ministry and notified him of the severance of diplomatic relations.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="35">
<j>ロシア側にとって、この通告がいかに突然であったかを知るには、ローゼン公使の対応を見てもわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">How that notification was sudden for Russia could be known by the response of Minister Rosen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">How the notification caught Russia off-guard is visible in the response of Minister Rosen.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">How the notification caught Russia off-guard is visible in the response of Minister Rosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>ローゼンは戦争が起きるとは想像していなかったらしく、この国交断絶通告を受け取った際、「この通告が戦争を意味するものか」と小村寿太郎に聞いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rosen seems not to have thought a war would start and when he received the notice of the severance of diplomatic relations, he asked Jutaro KOMURA, &apos;Does this notice mean going to war?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rosen did not expect a war to erupt between the two countries, and had to ask KOMURA Jutaro &quot;Does this notification mean we are going to war?&quot;</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rosen did not expect a war to erupt between the two countries, and had to ask Jutaro KOMURA &quot;Does this notification mean we are going to war?&quot;</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>ニコライ2世も「わがロシア帝国と日本との戦争は有り得ない。なぜなら朕がそれを欲しないから」といい、日本は戦争を決断しないだろうと考えていたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nicholai II said, &apos;A war is absolutely impossible between the Russian Empire and Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nicholai II said, &quot;A war between the Russian Empire and Japan is impossible. I do not desire to go to war,&quot; and he thought that Japan would not decide to go to war.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nicholai II said, &quot;A war between the Russian Empire and Japan is impossible. I do not desire to go to war,&quot; and he thought that Japan would not decide to go to war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これに対し小村寿太郎は、「この行為は戦争を意味するものではない」と返答。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jutaro KOMURA said, in reply to the question, &apos;This action does not mean a war.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KOMURA Jutaro said, in replied to Minister Rosen that &quot;[t]his action does not mean war.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jutaro KOMURA said, in replied to Minister Rosen that &quot;[this action does not mean war.&quot;</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>（司馬遼太郎『坂の上の雲』より）この返答は、国際法上の解釈から言えば違法と言えるものではないが、この状態ではどの外交ルートもあるわけではなく、実質的には戦争開始の通告である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(From &quot;Saka no ue no Kumo&quot; (Cloud above the hill) by Ryotaro SHIBA) While this reply was not to be said unlawful in view of interpretation of the international law, it is understood to have been substantial notice to declare war, as there were no diplomatic routes in that situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(From &quot;Saka no ue no Kumo&quot; (Clouds Above the Hill) by SHIBA Ryotaro) While this reply is not unlawful from the perspective of international law, in this particular situation where there were no other diplomatic routes available, it was in effect, a declaration of war.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(From &quot;Saka no ue no Kumo&quot; [Clouds Above the Hill] by Ryotaro SHIBA) While this reply is not unlawful from the perspective of international law, in this particular situation where there were no other diplomatic routes available, it was in effect, a declaration of war.</e>
<cmt>括弧の中の括弧を[]に修正しました。姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>かくしてニコライ2世は、1904年2月10日、アレクセーエフに対し日本との戦闘行為を容認。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And thus Nicholai II permitted Алексеев to engage in military action against Japan on February 10, 1904.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hence, Nicholai II permitted Алексеев militarily engage Japanese forces on February 10th, 1904.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hence, Nicholai II permitted Алексеев militarily engage Japanese forces on February 10th, 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>戦争を決断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He decided to go to war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He decided to declare war.</e>
<cmt>go to war→declare war</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He decided to declare war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>各国の思惑</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Expectations of various countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Expectations of Each Country</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Expectations of Each Country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>南アジアおよび清に権益を持つイギリスは、日英同盟に基づき日本への軍事、経済的支援を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">England which had interests in the South Asia and Qing provided military support and economic aid to Japan on the basis of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">England which held substantial interests across South Asia and Qing China offered military and economic support to Japan in accordance to the Anglo-Japanese Alliance.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">England which held substantial interests across South Asia and Qing China offered military and economic support to Japan in accordance to the Anglo-Japanese Alliance.</e>
<cmt>改行を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>露仏同盟を結びロシアへ資本を投下していたフランスと、ヴィルヘルム2世 (ドイツ皇帝)とニコライ2世とが縁戚関係にあるドイツは心情的にはロシア側であったが具体的な支援は行っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">France which invested capital into Russia under the Franco-Russian Alliance and Germany whose Emperor Wilhelm II (the Kaiser) was a relative of Nicholai II were emotionally on the Russian side, however, provided no specific assistances to Russia.</e>
<cmt>「ヴィルヘルム2世」の英文は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%B4%E3%82%A3%E3%83%AB%E3%83%98%E3%83%AB%E3%83%A02%E4%B8%96_(%E3%83%89%E3%82%A4%E3%83%84%E7%9A%87%E5%B8%9D)</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">France which invested capital into Russia under the Franco-Russian Alliance and Germany whose Emperor Wilhelm II (the Kaiser) was a relative of Nicholai II were sympathetic of Russia, but offered no specific assistance to Russia.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">France which invested capital into Russia under the Franco-Russian Alliance and Germany whose Emperor Wilhelm II (the Kaiser) was a relative of Nicholai II were sympathetic of Russia, but offered no specific assistance to Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>戦費調達</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Raising war funds</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Financing War</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Financing War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>戦争遂行には膨大な物資の輸入が不可欠であり、日本銀行副総裁高橋是清は日本の勝算を低く見積もる当時の国際世論の下で戦費調達に非常に苦心した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it was essential to import massive amount of goods to prosecute war, Korekiyo TAKAHASHI, the Deputy Governor of the Bank of Japan had difficulty in raising war funds under the international opinion in those days underestimating prospects of Japanese victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was critical to import a vast amount of resources to carry out war, and TAKAHASHI Korekiyo, the Deputy Governor of the Bank of Japan had difficulty in raising such funds because international opinon underestimated the prospects of a Japanese victory.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was critical to import a vast amount of resources to carry out war, and Korekiyo TAKAHASHI, the Deputy Governor of the Bank of Japan had difficulty in raising such funds because international opinion underestimated the prospects of a Japanese victory.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>開戦とともに日本の既発の外債は暴落しており、初回に計画された1000万ポンドの外債発行もまったく引き受け手が現れない状況であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the start of the war, the price of marketed Japanese foreign bond plunged and no bond buyers appeared for the issue of foreign bond amounting to 10 million pounds which was planned as the first issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The price of Japanese bonds issued abroad plummetted, and noone was willing to purchase the 10 million pounds in bonds initially planned.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The price of Japanese bonds issued abroad plummetted, and noone was willing to purchase the 10 million pounds in bonds initially planned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>是清はまず渡米するもアメリカの銀行家からはまったく相手にされなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korekiyo first went to the United States, however, no American bankers listened to him at all.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korekiyo first visited the United States, but did not receive any attention at all from American financiers.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korekiyo first visited the United States, but did not receive any attention at all from American financiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>次いで渡英して、額面100ポンド (通貨)に対して発行価格を93ポンドまで値下げし、日本の関税収入を抵当とする好条件を提示。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, he went to England, where he made an attractive proposal to reduce the issue price of the bond to 93 pounds per 100-pound (Currency) face value and to offer the Japanese revenue from the tariffs as a security.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, he went to England, where he made an attractive proposal to reduce the issue price of the bond to 93 pounds per 100-pound (Currency) face value, and offered a cut of Japanese revenue from tariffs as a security.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he went to England, where he made an attractive proposal to reduce the issue price of the bond to 93 pounds per 100-pound (Currency) face value, and offered a cut of Japanese revenue from tariffs as a security.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>イギリスの銀行家たちと1ヶ月以上交渉の末、ようやくロンドンでの500万ポンドの外債発行に成功することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He finally succeeded in issuing foreign bonds amounting to five million pounds in London after the negotiations with the British bankers for more than a month.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of more than one month of negotiating with British bankers, he succeeded in issuing 5 million pounds in foreign bonds in London.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of more than one month of negotiating with British bankers, he succeeded in issuing 5 million pounds in foreign bonds in London.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="49">
<j>直後、再度渡米して、帝政ロシアを敵視するアメリカ合衆国のユダヤ人銀行家ジェイコブ・シフと接触し、残額500万ポンドの外債引き受けおよび追加融資を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He went to the United States again immediately after that, contacted Jacob Schiff, a Jewish banker of the United States of America who regarded the Tsarist Russia as an enemy and secured another five million pounds from him by acceptance of foreign bond and an additional loan.</e>
<cmt>「ジェイコブ・シフ」の英文は下記サイトから引用しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%B8%E3%82%A7%E3%82%A4%E3%82%B3%E3%83%96%E3%83%BB%E3%82%B7%E3%83%95</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korekiyo travelled back to the United States immediately afterwards and contacted Jacob Schiff, a Jewish banker in the United Stateswho regarded Tsarist Russia as an enemy, and secured another 5 million pounds from him in the form of foreign bonds and additional loans.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korekiyo travelled back to the United States immediately afterwards and contacted Jacob Schiff, a Jewish banker in the United Stateswho regarded Tsarist Russia as an enemy, and secured another 5 million pounds from him in the form of foreign bonds and additional loans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>一転、1904年5月に鴨緑江の渡河作戦でロシアを圧倒して日本が勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making a sudden change, Japan overpowered and defeated Russia in the crossing operation over the Oryokko River (the Yalu River (Chinese) or the Amnok River (Korean)).</e>
<cmt>「鴨緑江」は、新和英大辞典第５版から引用しました。以後「the Oryokko River」で統一いたします。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A turning-point was reached in the Oryokko River Crossing Operation in May 1904, where Japanese forces overpowerd their Russian opponents (The Oryokko river is also referred to as the Yalu River (Chinese) or the Amnok River (Korean).).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A turning-point was reached in the Oryokko River Crossing Operation in May 1904, where Japanese forces overpowered their Russian opponents (The Oryokko river is also referred to as the Yalu River [Chinese] or the Amnok River [Korean]).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に修正しました。括弧内の文章が独立しているため、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>国際市場で日本外債は急騰し、第2次から第4次の外債発行により、合計で10億円超の資金を調達した（当時の国家予算は約7億円）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, the Japanese foreign bond jumped in the international market and Japan raised over one billion yens in total by making the second to fourth issues of the foreign bond (National budget of Japan in those days was about 700 million yens).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese foreign bond spiked on the international market, and Japan raised over 1 billion Yen in funds between the second and fourth issuance (To put the amount raised by foreign bonds into relative perspective, the amount raised was greater than the Japan&apos;s GDP, which was 700 million Yen.).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese foreign bond spiked on the international market, and Japan raised over 1 billion Yen in funds between the second and fourth issuance (To put the amount raised by foreign bonds into relative perspective, the amount raised was greater than the Japan&apos;s GDP, which was 700 million Yen).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progression</e>
<cmt>Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progression</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>開戦時の両軍の基本戦略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basic strategy of both military forces at the start of war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strategies of the Respective Countries at the Outbreak of the War</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strategies of the Respective Countries at the Outbreak of the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="52">
<j>日本側 陸軍は第一軍で朝鮮半島へ上陸、鴨緑江を渡河しつつ、在朝鮮のロシア軍と第一会戦を交えた後に満洲へ進撃。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese side According to the plan of the Army, the First Troops effect a landing on the Korean Peninsula, have the first encounter with the Russian army stationing in Korea crossing the Oryokko River and advance on to Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>「戦略」に関して、動詞は原形を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-side: The army would land their First Army on the Korean Peninsula and climb northwards and engage occupying Russian forces and assault Manchuria by crossing the Oryokko River.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-side: The army would land their First Army on the Korean Peninsula and climb northwards and engage occupying Russian forces and assault Manchuria by crossing the Oryokko River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>第二軍をもって遼東半島へ橋頭堡を立て旅順を孤立させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Second Troops establish a bridgehead in the Liaodong Peninsula to isolate Lushun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Second Troops establish a bridgehead in the Liaodong Peninsula to isolate Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Troops establish a bridgehead in the Liaodong Peninsula to isolate Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>そののち、満洲平野にて第三軍、第四軍を加えた四個軍でもって、ロシア軍主力を早めに殲滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the four troops with the Third Troops and the Fourth Troops added annihilate earlier the main force of the Russian army in the Manchuria Plains.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the Fourth Army would regroup with the Fourth Army and annihilate Russia&apos;s main force in the Manchurian plains.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the Fourth Army would regroup with the Third Army and annihilate Russia&apos;s main force in the Manchurian plains.</e>
<cmt>with the Fourth Army→with the Third Army</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>のちに沿海州へ進撃し、ウラジオストックの攻略まで想定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese forces advance on to Enkai shu ((Russian) maritime provinces) and capture Vladivostok.</e>
<cmt>「想定」は上記「According to the plan of the Army」に含まれるものとし、ここでは訳しておりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese forces advance would then advance into the Russian Maritime Provinces and capture Vladivostok.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese forces advance would then advance into the Russian Maritime Provinces and capture Vladivostok.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>海軍は旅順及びウラジオストックにいるロシア太平洋艦隊を黄海上にて殲滅した後に、ヨーロッパより回航してくるバルチック艦隊と決戦し、殲滅する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Navy planned to annihilate the Pacific Fleet of Russia stationed in Lushun and Vladivostok on the Huang Hai (Yellow Sea) and then fight a decisive battle against the Baltic Fleet coming from Europe and annihilate it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Navy planned to destroy the Russian Pacific Fleet stationed in Lushun and Vladivostok on the Yellow Sea, and engage and annihilate the Russian Baltic Fleet on route from Europe in a final engagement.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Navy planned to destroy the Russian Pacific Fleet stationed in Lushun and Vladivostok on the Yellow Sea, and engage and annihilate the Russian Baltic Fleet on route from Europe in a final engagement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>軍令機関が陸海軍並列対等となった初めての戦争であることに留意。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It should be noted that it was the first war in which the military orders of the Army and the Navy came to be on the parallel and equal basis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It should be noted that this was the first war in which military commanders issued directives towards and between the Army and the Navy on a parallel and equal basis.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It should be noted that this was the first war in which military commanders issued directives towards and between the Army and the Navy on a parallel and equal basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="58">
<j>ロシア側 黄海の制海権確保の前提に基づき、日本側の上陸を朝鮮半島南部と想定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia side On the basis of its plan to hold command of the Huang Hai (Yellow Sea), Russia assumed that the Japanese forces would land on the southern area of the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia-side: Premised on their capability to maintain naval superiority on the Yellow Sea, Russia assumed that the Japanese would land their forces on the southern Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia-side: Premised on their capability to maintain naval superiority on the Yellow Sea, Russia assumed that the Japanese would land their forces on the southern Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>鴨緑江付近に軍を集結させ、北上する日本軍を迎撃させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia concentrate its troops around the Oryokko River and make it intercept the Japanese army coming up north.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia would concentrate its troops around the Oryokko River, and intercept Japanese forces climbing northwards.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia would concentrate its troops around the Oryokko River, and intercept Japanese forces climbing northwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>失敗した場合は日本軍を引き付けて、順次ハルビンまで後退して、補給線の延びきった日本軍を殲滅するという戦略に変わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of failure, Russia change its plan and make its forces retreat successively as far as Harbin drawing the Japanese army in as near as possible and annihilate it when its supply line is fully extended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event of failure, they would switch their strategy and engage Japanese forces as they purposely fell back towards Harbin, in a bid to eliminate Japanese forces by overextending their supply-lines.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event of failure, they would switch their strategy and engage Japanese forces as they purposely fell back towards Harbin, in a bid to eliminate Japanese forces by overextending their supply-lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>開戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Start of the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commencement of Hostilities</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commencement of Hostilities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>日露戦争の戦闘は、1904年2月8日、旅順港に配備されていたロシア旅順艦隊（太平洋艦隊 (ロシア帝国海軍)）に対する日本海軍駆逐艦の奇襲攻撃に始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battles of the Russo-Japanese War started with a surprise attack on February 8, 1904 by destroyers of the Imperial Japanese Navy against the Lushun Fleet of Russia (The Pacific Fleet (the Russian Empire Navy) stationed in the Lushun Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russo-Japanese War started was initiated by Japan with a surprise attack on the Russian Pacific Fleet (Lushun Fleet) stations in the port of Lushun on February 8th, 1904.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russo-Japanese War started was initiated by Japan with a surprise attack on the Russian Pacific Fleet (Lushun Fleet) stations in the port of Lushun on February 8th, 1904.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>この攻撃ではロシアの戦艦に損傷を与えたが大きな戦果はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That attack damaged Russian battleships, however, it did not achieve great things militarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the attack damaged Russian warships, it did was insignificant in the larger order of battle.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the attack damaged Russian warships, it did was insignificant in the larger order of battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>同日、日本陸軍先遣部隊の第12師団 (日本軍)木越旅団が朝鮮の仁川広域市に上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the same day, the advance troops of the Japanese Army, the Kigoshi Brigade of the 12th Division landed on Incheon Metropolitan City of Korea.</e>
<cmt>「(日本軍)」はその前の「日本陸軍」とダブるので訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the same day, the frontline Japanese troops, the Kigoshi Brigade of the 12th Division, landed on the city of Incheon.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the same day, the frontline Japanese troops, the Kigoshi Brigade of the 12th Division, landed on the city of Incheon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>瓜生外吉少将率いる日本海軍第三艦隊 (日本海軍)の巡洋艦群は、同旅団の護衛を終えたのち、2月9日、仁川港外にて同地に派遣されていたロシアの巡洋艦ヴァリャーグ (防護巡洋艦)と砲艦コレーエツ (航洋砲艦)を攻撃し損傷を与えた（仁川沖海戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cruisers of the Third Fleet of the Imperial Japanese Navy under Rear-Admiral Sotokichi URYU, after having escorted the Brigade, attacked on February 9 a Russian cruiser, Варяг(Escort cruiser) and a gunboat, Кореец (Oceangoing gunboat) outside Incheon Port where the Russian battleships had been sent to (The Battle off Incheon).</e>
<cmt>「少将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）から引用しました。「（日本海軍）」は、その前の「日本海軍」と重複してしまうため省略いたしました。「ヴァリャーグ」「コレーエツ」のロシア語は、下記サイトから引用いたしました（英文がなく、ロシア語しかありません）。http://cardmodel.blog54.fc2.com/blog-entry-138.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After providing amphibious support to the abovementioned brigade, the cruisers of the IJN Third Fleet under the command of Rear-Admiral URYU Sotokichi, engaged the Russian cruiser Варяг(Escort cruiser), and a gunboat Кореец (Oceangoing gunboat) outside the port of Incheon Port on February 9th, and inflicted damage on them (The Battle off Incheon).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After providing amphibious support to the abovementioned brigade, the cruisers of the IJN Third Fleet under the command of Rear-Admiral Sotokichi URYU, engaged the Russian cruiser Варяг(Escort cruiser), and a gunboat Кореец (Oceangoing gunboat) outside the port of Incheon Port on February 9th, and inflicted damage on them (The Battle off Incheon).</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>2月10日には日本政府からロシア政府への宣戦布告がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 10, the Japanese Government declared war against the Russian Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 10th, the Japanese Government declared war against the Russian Government.</e>
<cmt>10→10th</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 10th, the Japanese Government declared war against the Russian Government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="66">
<j>ロシア旅順艦隊は日本の連合艦隊との正面決戦を避けて旅順港に待機した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Lushun Fleet of Russia avoided a head-on battle against the Japanese Combined Fleet and stood by in the Lushun Port.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Lushun Fleet of Russia sough to avoid a head-on battle against the Japanese Combined Fleet and remained anchored in Port Arthur (Lushun Port).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Lushun Fleet of Russia sough to avoid a head-on battle against the Japanese Combined Fleet and remained anchored in Port Arthur (Lushun Port).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>もしロシアのバルチック艦隊（第二・第三太平洋艦隊）が極東に回航して旅順艦隊と合流すれば戦力は圧倒的となり、制海権はロシアに奪われることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If the Baltic Fleet of Russia (The Second and the Third Pacific fleets) came to the Far East and joined the Lushun Fleet which would make its fighting strength overpowering, Russia would end up holding command of the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If the Baltic Fleet of Russia (The Second and the Third Pacific fleets) arrived in the Far East and joined the Lushun Fleet, their overwhelming firepower would enable Russia to claim naval superiority.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If the Baltic Fleet of Russia (The Second and the Third Pacific fleets) arrived in the Far East and joined the Lushun Fleet, their overwhelming firepower would enable Russia to claim naval superiority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>連合艦隊は2月から5月にかけて、旅順港の出入り口に古い船舶を沈めて封鎖しようとしたが、失敗に終わった（旅順港閉塞作戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Combined Fleet tried, from February to May, to blockade the Lushun Port by sinking old vessels at the entrance of the port, which ended in failure (Lushun Port Blockade Operation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Between February and March, the IJN Combined Fleet attempted to blockade Port Arthur by sinking older vessels at the entrance of the port, but this plan ended in failure (Port Arthur Blockade Operation).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Between February and March, the IJN Combined Fleet attempted to blockade Port Arthur by sinking older vessels at the entrance of the port, but this plan ended in failure (Port Arthur Blockade Operation).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>4月13日、連合艦隊の敷設した機雷が旅順艦隊の戦艦ペトロパヴロフスク (戦艦・初代)を撃沈、旅順艦隊司令長官シュテファン・オシュポヴィッチ・マカロフ中将を戦死させるという戦果を上げたが、5月15日には逆に日本海軍の戦艦「八島 (戦艦)」と「初瀬 (戦艦)」がロシアの機雷によって撃沈される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Imperial Japanese Navy achieved such military results that the mines laid by the Japanese Combined Fleet sunk a battleship Петропавловск (The first) of the Lushun Fleet on April 13 and the Vice-Admiral Stepan Osipovich Makarov, the Commander-in-Chief of the Lushun Fleet was killed, the battleships of the Imperial Japanese Navy, &apos;Yashima&apos; and &apos;Hatsuse&apos; were conversely sunk by the mines of Russia on May 15.</e>
<cmt>「ペトロパヴロフスク」のロシア語は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%9A%E3%83%88%E3%83%AD%E3%83%91%E3%83%B4%E3%83%AD%E3%83%95%E3%82%B9%E3%82%AF%E7%B4%9A%E6%88%A6%E8%89%A6 「シュテファン・オシュポヴィッチ・マカロフ」については、下記サイトにロシア語とラテン文字転写がありましたので、後者を引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%B9%E3%83%86%E3%83%91%E3%83%B3%E3%83%BB%E3%83%9E%E3%82%AB%E3%83%AD%E3%83%95　「中将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）の旧海軍のものを引用しました（ロシア海軍における名称は出ておりません）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Imperial Japanese Navy succeeded in sinking the battleship Петропавловск (Battleship/The first) of the Lushun Fleet on April 13th, with a mine laid earlier by the IJN, killing Vice-Admiral Stepan Osipovich Makarov, the Commander-in-Chief of the Lushun Fleet; the IJN battleships &apos;Yashima&apos; and &apos;Hatsuse&apos; were conversely sunk by Russian mines on May 15th.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Imperial Japanese Navy succeeded in sinking the battleship Петропавловск (Battleship/The first) of the Lushun Fleet on April 13th, with a mine laid earlier by the IJN, killing Vice-Admiral Stepan Osipovich Makarov, the Commander-in-Chief of the Lushun Fleet; the IJN battleships &apos;Yashima&apos; and &apos;Hatsuse&apos; were conversely sunk by Russian mines on May 15th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>一方で、ウラジオストクに配備されていたロシアのウラジオストク巡洋艦隊は、積極的に出撃して通商破壊を展開する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Vladivostok Cruiser Fleet of Russia deployed in Vladivostok made sorties actively and carried out commerce destruction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Russian Vladivostok Cruiser Fleet stationed in Vladivstok proactively carried out sorties to destroy commercial shipping.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Russian Vladivostok Cruiser Fleet stationed in Vladivstok proactively carried out sorties to destroy commercial shipping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>4月25日には日本軍の輸送艦金州丸を撃沈するなど、日本近海を縦横無尽に行き来した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fleet moved back and forth in Japanese territorial waters with unrestricted freedom in all directions and on April 25 sunk Kinshu-maru, a transport ship of the Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fleet patrolled Japanese territorial waters unchallenged, and sank the IJN transport ship Kinshu-maru on April 25th.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fleet patrolled Japanese territorial waters unchallenged, and sank the IJN transport ship Kinshu-maru on April 25th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これを追う日本の上村中将率いる第二艦隊 (日本海軍)を右往左往させ、船舶による補給に頼る日本軍を悩ませた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above, the Second Fleet (the Imperial Japanese Navy) under the command of Vice-Admiral Kamimura chasing after the fleet was made to move back and forth and the Imperial Japanese Navy depending on supply by ships was troubled.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「中将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Vladivostok Cruiser Fleet prompted Vice-Admiral Kamimura commmanding the IJN Second Fleet to give chase, in order to resolve the supply issues of the Japanese Army which was reliant on supplies delivered by transport vessels.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Vladivostok Cruiser Fleet prompted Vice-Admiral Kamimura commmanding the IJN Second Fleet to give chase, in order to resolve the supply issues of the Japanese Army which was reliant on supplies delivered by transport vessels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>黄海海戦・遼陽会戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of the Yellow Sea and Battle of Liaoyang</e>
<cmt>「黄海海戦・遼陽会戦」の英語訳は、新和英大辞典第５版から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of the Yellow Sea and Battle of Liaoyang</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of the Yellow Sea and Battle of Liaoyang</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="73">
<j>黒木為楨大将率いる日本陸軍の第1軍 (日本軍)は朝鮮半島に上陸し、4月30日-5月1日、安東（現・丹東）近郊の鴨緑江岸でロシア軍を破った（鴨緑江会戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The First Troops of the Imperial Japanese Army under the command of General Tamemoto KUROKI landed on the Korean Peninsula and defeated the Russian army at the shore of the Oryokko River near Anton (present Tanton) from April 30 to May 1 (Battle of the Oryokko River).</e>
<cmt>「大将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）旧陸軍から引用しました。　「安東（現・丹東）」は、中国語の読みがサイトでも見当たらず、日本語の音読みを変更したものといたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Troops of the Imperial Japanese Army under the command of General KUROKI Tamemoto landed on the Korean Peninsula and defeated the Russian army on the shores of the Oryokko River near Anton (present Tanton) in an engagement that lasted between April 30th and May 1st (Battle of the Oryokko River).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Troops of the Imperial Japanese Army under the command of General Tamemoto KUROKI landed on the Korean Peninsula and defeated the Russian army on the shores of the Oryokko River near Anton (present Tanton) in an engagement that lasted between April 30th and May 1st (Battle of the Oryokko River).</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>続いて奥保鞏大将率いる第2軍 (日本軍)が遼東半島の塩大墺に上陸し、5月26日、旅順半島の付け根にある南山のロシア軍陣地を攻略した（南山の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Second Troops (the Japanese Army) under the command of General Yasukata OKU landed on Entaio of the Liaodong Peninsula and on May 26 captured the Russian army position in Nanzan on the joint of the Lushun Peninsula (the Battle of Nanzan).</e>
<cmt>「塩大墺」は、日本語の音読みにいたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Second Troops (the Japanese Army) under the command of General OKU Yasukata landed on Yandayu on the Liaodong Peninsula and captured the Russian position in Nanshan May 26th (Battle of Nanshan).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Troops (the Japanese Army) under the command of General Yasukata OKU landed on Yandayu on the Liaodong Peninsula and captured the Russian position in Nanshan May 26th (Battle of Nanshan).</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>南山は旅順要塞のような本格的要塞ではなかったが堅固な陣地で、第二軍は死傷者4,000の損害を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Nanzan was not such a full-scale fortress as Lushun Fortress, it was a strong position and the Second Troops suffered the casualties reaching 4,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Nanzan was not as fortified as the Lushun Fortress, it was a heavily defended position, and the Second Army received 4,000 casualties in taking it.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Nanzan was not as fortified as the Lushun Fortress, it was a heavily defended position, and the Second Army received 4,000 casualties in taking it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>東京の大本営は損害の大きさに驚愕し、桁を一つ間違えたのではないかと疑ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial headquarters in Tokyo was astonished by the magnitude of the casualties and reportedly wondered if it had been one less zero.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Imperial command in Tokyo was astonished by the magnitude of the casualties and reportedly wondered if there was a typo in the casualty report.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Imperial command in Tokyo was astonished by the magnitude of the casualties and reportedly wondered if there was a typo in the casualty report.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>第二軍は大連市占領後、第1師団 (日本軍)を残し、遼陽を目指して北上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After occupied Dalian City, the Second Troops advanced north to Liaoyang leaving the First Division (the Japanese Army).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After entering the city of Dalian, the Second Army advanced northwards to Liaoyang leaving the First Division (the Japanese Army) behind to secure the city.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After entering the city of Dalian, the Second Army advanced northwards to Liaoyang leaving the First Division (the Japanese Army) behind to secure the city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>6月14日、旅順援護のため南下してきたロシア軍部隊を得利寺の戦いで撃退、7月23日には大石橋の戦いで勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 14 in the Battle of Tokuriji, the Second Troops repulsed a unit of the Russian Army moving south to back up Lushun and on July 23, won a victory in the Battle of Oishibashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Second Army advanced southwards to support units in Lushun, and repulsed a Russian Army unit at the Battle of Tokuriji on June 14th, and on July 23rd they one a second victory at the battle of Oishibashi.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Army advanced southwards to support units in Lushun, and repulsed a Russian Army unit at the Battle of Tokuriji on June 14th, and on July 23rd they one a second victory at the battle of Oishibashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="79">
<j>6月6日、乃木希典大将率いる第3軍 (日本軍)が大連に上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 6, the Third Troops (the Japanese Army) under the command of General Maresuke NOGI landed on Dalian City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 6th, the IJA Third Army led by General NOGI Maresuke landed in Dalian.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 6th, the IJA Third Army led by General Maresuke NOGI landed in Dalian.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>しかし、陸軍の旅順攻略参戦を頑なに拒む海軍の意向を受け、満洲軍総司令部の指示により旅順に向けて漸進を余儀なくさせられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Third Troops was forced to move gradually to Lushun under the direction of the General Headquarters of the Japanese Army in Manchuria which accepted the Navy&apos;s intention to firmly reject the participation of the Army in the Lushun capture operations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Third Troops was forced to move gradually to Lushun under orders of the General Headquarters of the Japanese Army in Manchuria, which accepted the Navy&apos;s rejection of the participation of the Army in the capture of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Third Troops was forced to move gradually to Lushun under orders of the General Headquarters of the Japanese Army in Manchuria, which accepted the Navy&apos;s rejection of the participation of the Army in the capture of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>海軍陸戦隊が旅順要塞への砲撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Naval Landing Forces opened fire on the Lushun Fortress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Naval amphibious forces shell the Lushun Fortress.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Naval amphibious forces shell the Lushun Fortress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>これを受けて旅順艦隊は旅順から出撃、8月10日、東郷平八郎大将率いる連合艦隊との間で黄海海戦 (日露戦争)となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against that attack, the Lushun Fleet sortied and on August 10, the Battle of the Yellow Sea (the Russo-Japanese War) started between the Lushun Fleet and the Combined Fleet under the command of Admiral Heihachiro TOGO.</e>
<cmt>「大将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）旧海軍から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provoked by the shelling, the Lushun Fleet set sail on August 10th, and engaged the IJN Combined Fleet under the command of Admiral TOGO Heihachiro in the Battle of the Yellow Sea.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provoked by the shelling, the Lushun Fleet set sail on August 10th, and engaged the IJN Combined Fleet under the command of Admiral Heihachiro TOGO in the Battle of the Yellow Sea.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>この海戦で連合艦隊は旅順艦隊の巡洋艦3隻他を撃沈したが、主力艦を撃沈することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that naval battle, the Combined Fleet sunk three cruisers and others of the Lushun Fleet, but was not able to sink the capital ships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Combined Fleet sank three cruisers and others vessels of the Lushun Fleet, but was not able to sink any of its capital ships.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Combined Fleet sank three cruisers and others vessels of the Lushun Fleet, but was not able to sink any of its capital ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>そのころロシアのウラジオストク艦隊は、6月15日に輸送船常陸丸を撃沈するなど（常陸丸事件）活発な通商破壊戦を続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the Vladivostok Fleet of Russia kept actively carrying out such trade breaking attacks as sinking a transport ship, Hitachi-maru on June 15 (Hitachi-maru Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the Vladivostok Fleet of Russia continued to attack shipping, sinking the transport ship, Hitachi-maru on June 15th (Hitachi-maru Incident).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the Vladivostok Fleet of Russia continued to attack shipping, sinking the transport ship, Hitachi-maru on June 15th (Hitachi-maru Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>8月14日、上村彦之丞中将率いる日本海軍第二艦隊は蔚山沖でようやくウラジオストク艦隊を捕捉し、大損害を与えその後の活動を阻止した（蔚山沖海戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 14, the Second Fleet of Imperial Japanese Navy under the command of Vice Admiral Hikonojo KAMIMURA caught up with the Vladivostok Fleet off Urusan and caused heavy damage to it holding its activities in check after that (the Battle off Urusan).</e>
<cmt>「中将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）旧海軍から引用しました。　「蔚山沖海戦」は、下記サイトの読みをローマ字化及び翻訳しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E8%94%9A%E5%B1%B1%E6%B2%96%E6%B5%B7%E6%88%A6</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 14th, the IJN Second Fleet under the command of Vice Admiral KAMIMURA Hikonojo intercepted the Vladivostok Fleet off Urusan and inflicted heavy damage and interdicted its anti-shipping operations (Battle off Urusan).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 14th, the IJN Second Fleet under the command of Vice Admiral Hikonojo KAMIMURA intercepted the Vladivostok Fleet off Urusan and inflicted heavy damage and interdicted its anti-shipping operations (Battle off Urusan).</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>他方陸軍は7月の大本営通達を受けて、第三軍は旅順攻囲戦の第一回総攻撃を8月19日に開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Third Troops of the Army under the direction of the Imperial headquarters started the first all-out attack in the Lushun siege warfare on August 19.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 19th, the IJA Third Army under the directives of Imperial headquarters initiated its first all-out seige of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 19th, the IJA Third Army under the directives of Imperial headquarters initiated its first all-out seige of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>だがロシアの近代的要塞の前に死傷者1万5,000という大きな損害を受け失敗に終わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it ended in failure with such heavy casualties as 15,000 soldiers attacking the modern fortress of Russia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the seige on a modern Russian fortress ended in heavy casualties of 15,000 for the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the seige on a modern Russian fortress ended in heavy casualties of 15,000 for the Imperial Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>8月末、日本の第一軍、第二軍および野津道貫大将率いる第4軍 (日本軍)は、満洲の戦略拠点遼陽へ迫った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of August, the Japanese First Troops, the Second Troops and the Fourth Troops (the Japanese Army) under the command of General Michitsura NOZU closed in on Liaoyang, a strategic foothold of Manchuria.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of August, the IJA First and Second Armies under the command of General Nozu Michitsura closed in on Liaoyang, a strategic location in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of August, the IJA First, Second and Fourth Armies under the command of General Michitsura NOZU closed in on Liaoyang, a strategic location in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ「第4軍」＝and Fourthを追加しました。姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>8月24日-9月4日の遼陽会戦では、第二軍が南側から正面攻撃をかけ、第一軍が東側の山地を迂回し背後へ進撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Liaoyang from August 24 to September 4, the Second Troops made a frontal attack from the south, and the First Troops went around the mountainous region on the east side and made a rear attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Liaoyang from August 24th and September 4th, the IJA Second Army mounted a frontal attack from the south, and the IJA First Army circumscribed a mountainous area in the East and attacked the enemies flank.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Liaoyang from August 24th and September 4th, the IJA Second Army mounted a frontal attack from the south, and the IJA First Army circumscribed a mountainous area in the East and attacked the enemies flank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>ロシア軍の司令官アレクセイ・クロパトキン大将は全軍を撤退させ、日本軍は遼陽を占領したもののロシア軍の撃破には失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General Aleksei Kuropatkin, the commander of the Russian Army made a full-scale withdrawal of the whole troops, and the Japanese army occupied Liaoyang, however, failed in defeating the Russian troops.</e>
<cmt>ロシア陸軍の「大将」の英文は不明ですので、日本の旧陸軍のものを使用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attack prompted General Aleksei Kuropatkin, the commander of the Russian Army to order a full-scale retreat enabling Japanese forces to occupy Liaoyang, but the Japanese failed to annhilate Russian forces.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The attack prompted General Aleksei Kuropatkin, the commander of the Russian Army to order a full-scale retreat enabling Japanese forces to occupy Liaoyang, but the Japanese failed to annhilate Russian forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>10月9日-10月20日にロシア軍は攻勢に出るが、日本軍の防御の前に失敗に終わる（沙河会戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Russian Army took the offensive from October 9 to October 20, it ended in failure under the defense of the Japanese army (the Battle of Saka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Russian Army went on the offensive between October 9th through to October 20th, it ended in failure in the face of staunch resistance put up by the Japanese Army (The Battle of Saka).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Russian Army went on the offensive between October 9th through to October 20th, it ended in failure in the face of staunch resistance put up by the Japanese Army (The Battle of Saka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>こののち、両軍は遼陽と奉天（現・瀋陽）の中間付近を流れる沙河の線で対陣に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the two armies started to confront each other across the Saka river flowing around halfway between Liaoyang and Fengtian (present Shenyang).</e>
<cmt>「沙河」の読みは下記サイトから引用しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%B2%99%E6%B2%B3%E4%BC%9A%E6%88%A6</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this battle, the respective armies established a front along the Saka river flowing between Liaoyang and Fengtian (present-day Shenyang).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this battle, the respective armies established a front along the Saka river flowing between Liaoyang and Fengtian (present-day Shenyang).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>旅順攻略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Capture of Lushun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seige of Lushun</e>
<cmt>Capture→The Seige</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seige of Lushun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>第3軍 (日本軍)は旅順攻囲戦を続行中であったが、旅順要塞に対する10月26日からの第二回総攻撃は失敗し、11月26日からの第三回総攻撃も苦戦に陥る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Third Troops (the Japanese army) was still in the Lushun siege warfare, and failed in the second all-out attack from October 26 and forced to engage in a bitterly fought struggle in the third all-out attack from November 26.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The IJA Third Army was still laying siege to Lushun, but failed to failed in its second all-out offensive against the Lushun Fortress on October 26tyh, and failed again in its third consecutive assault on the fortress commenced on November 26th.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The IJA Third Army was still laying siege to Lushun, but failed to failed in its second all-out offensive against the Lushun Fortress on October 26th, and failed again in its third consecutive assault on the fortress commenced on November 26th.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。26tyh→26th</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>戦況を懸念した満州軍 (日本軍)総参謀長兒玉源太郎大将は、大山巌元帥の指示を受け旅順方面へ着任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">General Gentaro Kodama, the Chief of Staff of the Japanese Army in Manchuria who felt concern about the war situation moved to the Lushun area under the direction of Field Marshal Iwao OYAMA.</e>
<cmt>「元帥」の英文は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）旧海軍から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IJA Chief of Staff in Manchuria General KODAMA Gentaro, who was concerned with the war situation was deployed to the Lushun under the direction of Field Marshal OYAMA Iwao.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IJA Chief of Staff in Manchuria General Gentaro KODAMA, who was concerned with the war situation was deployed to the Lushun under the direction of Field Marshal Iwao OYAMA.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>大本営と海軍の執拗な主張を受け入れ、攻撃目標を要塞北西の203高地に絞り込む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He accepted an obstinate insistence by the Imperial headquarters and the Navy, and narrowed the target for attack into the Nihyakusan Kochi (the 203 Highlands) to the northwest of the fortress.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accepting the obstinate insistence of Imperial headquarters and the Navy, he narrowed his objective to 203 Highlands northwest of the fortress.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accepting the obstinate insistence of Imperial headquarters and the Navy, he narrowed his objective to 203 Highlands northwest of the fortress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="96">
<j>日露両軍ともに戦死5,000、戦傷者10,000以上を出す激戦のすえ、第三軍は12月4日に203高地を占領し、ロシア軍は戦力を決定的に消耗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a fierce battle which left the war dead of over 5,000 and the war wounded of over 10,000 from each of the two armies, the Third Troops captured the 203 Highlands on December 4 and the Russian Army decisively drained its fighting strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a fierce battle which claimed approximately 5,000 Japanese and Russian lives and over 10,000 wounded, the IJA Third Army captured the 203 Highlands on December 4th, and exacted a decisive blow to Russian forces.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a fierce battle which claimed approximately 5,000 Japanese and Russian lives and over 10,000 wounded, the IJA Third Army captured the 203 Highlands on December 4th, and exacted a decisive blow to Russian forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>その後第三軍は、満洲軍総司令部の当初からの攻撃目標であった要塞東北正面の堡塁群を攻略し、1905年1月1日にロシア軍旅順要塞司令官のアナトーリイ・ステッセリ中将は降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the Third Troops attacked a group of forts in the northeastern front of the fortress which had been the original target for attack on the part of the General Headquarters of the Japanese Army in Manchuria, and on January 1, 1905, Lieutenant General Anatolii Stoessel, the Russian commander of the Lushun Fortress surrendered.</e>
<cmt>「アナトーリイ・ステッセリ」の英文は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%A2%E3%83%8A%E3%83%88%E3%83%BC%E3%83%AA%E3%82%A4%E3%83%BB%E3%82%B9%E3%83%86%E3%83%83%E3%82%BB%E3%83%AA　「中将」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）旧陸軍から引用しました（ロシア軍の階級の訳が見当たらないため）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the IJA Third Army attacked a group of bastions in the northeastern face of the fortress which had been the initial objective set by the General Headquarters of the Japanese Army in Manchuria, and on January 1st, 1905, the Lieutenant General Anatolii Stoessel, the Russian commander of the Lushun Fortress surrendered.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the IJA Third Army attacked a group of bastions in the northeastern face of the fortress which had been the initial objective set by the General Headquarters of the Japanese Army in Manchuria, and on January 1st, 1905, the Lieutenant General Anatolii Stoessel, the Russian commander of the Lushun Fortress surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="98">
<j>沙河では両軍の対陣が続いていたが、ロシア軍は新たに前線に着任したオスカル・フェルディナント・グリッペンベルク大将の主導のもと、1月25日に日本軍の最左翼に位置する黒溝台方面で攻勢に出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the confrontation across the Saka river continued, the Russian Army took the offensive on January 25 under the command of General Oskar-Ferdinand Grippenberg newly assigned to the front line in the Kokkodai area located on the extreme left wing of the Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>「黒溝台」の読みは、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E9%BB%92%E6%BA%9D%E5%8F%B0%E4%BC%9A%E6%88%A6</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the confrontation across the Saka river continued, the Russian Army took the offensive on January 25 under the command of General Oskar-Ferdinand Grippenberg newly assigned to the front line in the Kokkodai area located on the extreme left wing of the Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the confrontation across the Saka river continued, the Russian Army took the offensive on January 25 under the command of General Oskar-Ferdinand Grippenberg newly assigned to the front line in the Kokkodai area located on the extreme left wing of the Japanese Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>一時、日本軍は戦線崩壊の危機に陥ったが、秋山好古少将、立見尚文中将らの奮戦により危機を脱した（黒溝台会戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Japanese army temporarily plunged into a crisis of the battle line collapse, however, passed through the crisis due to the desperate fights by Major General Yoshifuru AKIYAMA, Lieutenant General Naobumi TATSUMI and others (the Battle of Kokkodai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Japanese army temporarily plunged into a crisis with a breach of a major front, it was able to overcome the crisis due to the fierce resistence put up by Major General AKIYAMA Yoshifuru and Lieutenant General TATSUMI Naobumi and others (the Battle of Kokkodai).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Japanese army temporarily plunged into a crisis with a breach of a major front, it was able to overcome the crisis due to the fierce resistance put up by Major General Yoshifuru AKIYAMA and Lieutenant General Naobumi TATSUMI and others (the Battle of Kokkodai).</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>2月には旅順攻略を完遂した第三軍が戦線に到着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, the Third troops which had completed the capture of Lushun arrived at the front line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, the IJA Third Army arrived to complete the capture of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, the IJA Third Army arrived to complete the capture of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>奉天会戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Fengtian</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Fengtian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Fengtian</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="101">
<j>日本軍は、ロシア軍の拠点・奉天へ向けた大作戦を開始する（奉天会戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army entered upon a major action toward Fengtian which was a foothold of the Russian Army (the Battle of Fengtian).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army initiate a major offensive towards the Russian Army position in Fengtian (the Battle of Fengtian).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army initiate a major offensive towards the Russian Army position in Fengtian (the Battle of Fengtian).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>2月21日に日本軍右翼が攻撃を開始。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 21, the right-wing of the Japanese Army opened an attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 21st, the right-wing of the Japanese Army commence the attack.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 21st, the right-wing of the Japanese Army commence the attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>3月1日から、左翼の第三軍と第二軍が奉天の側面から背後へ向けて前進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From March 1, the Third Troops on the left wing and the Second Troops advanced from the flank to the rear of Fengtian.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From March 1st, the IJA Third Army and Second Army on the left wing advance to flank Russian positions in Fengtian.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From March 1st, the IJA Third Army and Second Army on the left wing advance to flank Russian positions in Fengtian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>ロシア軍は予備を投入し、第三軍はロシア軍の猛攻の前に崩壊寸前になりつつも前進を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Russian Army sent the reserves and the Third Troops kept advancing even on the brink of collapse withstanding ruthless attacks by the Russian Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Russian Army deploy reserve forces and wittle down the IJA Third Army with fierce resistence, but the Third Army continued to advance in spite of sustaining heavy casualities.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russian Army deploy reserve forces and wittle down the IJA Third Army with fierce resistence, but the Third Army continued to advance in spite of sustaining heavy casualities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>3月9日、ロシア軍の司令官クロパトキン大将は撤退を指示。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 9, General Kuropatkin, the commander of the Russian Army ordered a withdrawal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 9th, General Kuropatkin, the commander of the Russian Army ordered a withdrawal.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 9th, General Kuropatkin, the commander of the Russian Army ordered a withdrawal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>日本軍は3月10日に奉天を占領したが、またもロシア軍の撃破には失敗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army occupied Fengtian on March 10, however, failed again in defeating the Russian Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army occupied Fengtian on March 10th; however, it failed to inflict a decisive blow on the Russian Army.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army occupied Fengtian on March 10th; however, it failed to inflict a decisive blow on the Russian Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>一連の戦いで両軍とも大きな損害を受け作戦継続が困難となったため、その後は終戦まで四平街付近での対峙が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a series of battles, both armies suffered so heavy damage that it became difficult to continue military operations, so after that the two armies continued to confront near Shiheigai to the end of the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both armies suffered massive casualties in a series of battles, and it became difficult for either army to continue their operations; thereafter the two armies spent the remainder of the war facing off along a front near the city of Siping.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both armies suffered massive casualties in a series of battles, and it became difficult for either army to continue their operations; thereafter the two armies spent the remainder of the war facing off along a front near the city of Siping.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>日本海海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Tsushima</e>
<cmt>下記サイトの説明に従いました。また、新和英大辞典第５版でもこの訳が記載されています。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E6%97%A5%E6%9C%AC%E6%B5%B7%E6%B5%B7%E6%88%A6</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Tsushima</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Tsushima</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="108">
<j>戦争の決着をつけたのは海戦であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a naval battle that brought the war to an end.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a naval battle that brought the war to a decisive end.</e>
<cmt>to and end→to a decisive end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a naval battle that brought the war to a decisive end.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>バルト海沿岸を本拠地とするロシアのバルチック艦隊（第二・第三太平洋艦隊）は、旅順（旅順陥落の後はウラジオストク）へ向けてリエパヤ港を出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Baltic Fleet (the Second and Third Pacific fleets) of Russia homeported at the coast of the Baltic Sea left the Liepaja Port for Lushun (After the fall of Lushun, for Vladivostok.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Baltic Fleet (the Second and Third Pacific fleets) stationed in the Russian port of Liepaja facing the Baltic Sea set sail for Vladivostok after the fall of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Baltic Fleet (the Second and Third Pacific fleets) stationed in the Russian port of Liepaja facing the Baltic Sea set sail for Vladivostok after the fall of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>そして、地球を半周する航海を続け、1905年5月27日-5月28日の日本海海戦において日本軍連合艦隊と激突した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, the Fleet sailed half way round the globe and crashed against the Combined Fleet of the Japanese Navy from May 27 to May 28, 1905 at the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fleet sailed half way round the globe and confronted the IJN Combined Fleet between May 27th and May 28th, 1905 in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fleet sailed half way round the globe and confronted the IJN Combined Fleet between May 27th and May 28th, 1905 in the Battle of Tsushima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>連合艦隊は、東郷平八郎司令長官の優れた戦術、二人の参謀（秋山真之、佐藤鉄太郎）による見事な作戦、上村彦之丞将軍率いる第二艦隊（巡洋艦を中心とした艦隊）による追撃、鈴木貫太郎の駆逐隊による魚雷攻撃作戦、下瀬火薬（世界最強火薬）、伊集院信管、新型無線機、世界初の斉射戦術、世界最高水準の高速艦隊運動などによって、欧州最強と言われたバルチック艦隊を圧倒、これを殲滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Combined Fleet overwhelmed and annihilated the Baltic Fleet which was said to be the strongest in Europe, by the excellent tactics of the commander Heihachiro TOGO, the outstanding strategy of the two staff officers (Saneyuki AKIYAMA and Tetsutaro SATO), the pursuit of the enemy by the Second Fleet (a fleet based on cruisers) under the command of General Hikonojo KAMIMURA, the torpedo attacking operations with destroyers by Kantaro SUZUKI, the Simose gunpowder (the world&apos;s strongest gunpowder), the Ijuin fuse, the new-type radio sets, the world&apos;s first volley tactics, the activities of the world&apos;s highest-speed fleet and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Combined Fleet overwhelmed and annihilated the Baltic Fleet which was said to be the strongest in Europe through the superior tactics of the commander TOGO Heihachiro, the outstanding strategy of his two staff officers (AKIYAMA Saneyuki and SATO Tetsutaro), the pursuit of the enemy by the Second Fleet (a cruiser fleet) under the command of General KAMIMURA Hikonojo, torpedo operations with destroyers led by SUZUKI Kantaro, and the use of Shimose gunpowder (What was then the world&apos;s most powerful gunpowder), Ijuin fuse, cutting-edge radio sets, the invention and application of volley tactics, and the deployment of the world&apos;s fastest fleet in battle among several other factors.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Combined Fleet overwhelmed and annihilated the Baltic Fleet which was said to be the strongest in Europe through the superior tactics of the commander Heihachiro TOGO, the outstanding strategy of his two staff officers (Saneyuki AKIYAMA and Tetsutaro SATO), the pursuit of the enemy by the Second Fleet (a cruiser fleet) under the command of General Hikonojo KAMIMURA, torpedo operations with destroyers led by Kantaro SUZUKI, and the use of Shimose gunpowder (What was then the world&apos;s most powerful gunpowder), Ijuin fuse, cutting-edge radio sets, the invention and application of volley tactics, and the deployment of the world&apos;s fastest fleet in battle among several other factors.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。「, cutting-edge」のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>なお、当日、日本軍連合艦隊には、4名のイギリス観戦武官が同船しており、元来イギリスの戦法であるT字戦法に関しての補佐・指導を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four British military officers were on board ships in the Combined Fleet of the Japanese Navy, and assisted and instructed on the Crossing the T tactics which was originally a British tactic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four British military officers were on board ships in the Combined Fleet of the Japanese Navy, and assisted and instructed on the Crossing the T tactics which was originally a British tactic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four British military officers were on board ships in the Combined Fleet of the Japanese Navy, and assisted and instructed on the Crossing the T tactics which was originally a British tactic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="113">
<j>バルチック艦隊の司令部は司令長官を含めてまるごと日本軍の捕虜となるほど、連合艦隊の一方的な圧勝であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Combined Fleet so overwhelmingly defeated the Baltic Fleet that the whole of the staff of headquarters of the latter including the Commander-in-Chief were taken captives by the Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Combined Fleet overwhelmed the Baltic Fleet to the extent that all the commanding staff including the Baltic Fleet became captive of the IJN Combined Fleet, and so overwhelmingly defeated the Baltic Fleet that the whole of the staff of headquarters of the latter including the Commander-in-Chief were taken captives by the Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Combined Fleet overwhelmed the Baltic Fleet to the extent that all the commanding staff including the Baltic Fleet became captive of the IJN Combined Fleet, and so overwhelmingly defeated the Baltic Fleet that the whole of the staff of headquarters of the latter including the Commander-in-Chief were taken captives by the Japanese Navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>世界のマスコミの予想に反する結果に、列強諸国を驚愕させ、ロシアの脅威に怯える国々を熱狂させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surprising result contrary to the world&apos;s media&apos;s expectations astonished the great powers and excited the countries which were frightened by the threat of Russia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The unexpected results caught the world&apos;s media by surprise, astonished the great powers, and enthralled countries that feared the threat of Russia.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The unexpected results caught the world&apos;s media by surprise, astonished the great powers, and enthralled countries that feared the threat of Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>この結果、日本側の制海権が確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Japan gained command of the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, Japan&apos;s command of the seas was confirmed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;command of the seas&quot; can alternatively be referred to as &quot;naval superiority,&quot; but this does not have the same nuance because it does not contain the word sea. By contrast 制空権 is often translated as &quot;air-superiority.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, Japan&apos;s command of the seas was confirmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>樺太攻略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Capture of Sakhalin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Capture of Sakhalin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Capture of Sakhalin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>日露戦争の終結直前の段階で日本軍は樺太攻略作戦を実施し、全島を占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the stage immediately before the end of the Russo-Japanese War, the Japanese army conducted the Sakhalin capturing operations and occupied the whole island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the closing phase of the Russo-Japanese War, the Japanese army carried out the Capture of Sakhalin peninsula and occuppied the entire island.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the closing phase of the Russo-Japanese War, the Japanese army carried out the Capture of Sakhalin peninsula and occuppied the entire island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>この占領が後の講和条約で南樺太の日本への割譲をもたらすこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That occupation ended up bringing cession of southern half of Sakhalin to Japan in the subsequent peace treaty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this occupation and the subsequent peace treaty, Japan was ceded the southern half of the Sakhalin peninsula.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this occupation and the subsequent peace treaty, Japan was ceded the southern half of the Sakhalin peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>講和へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toward Peace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Towards Peace</e>
<cmt>(American--&gt; British English)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Towards Peace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="118">
<j>ロシアでは、相次ぐ敗北と、それを含めた帝政に対する民衆の不満が増大し、1905年1月9日には血の日曜日事件 (1905年)が発生していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Russia, dissatisfaction of the people increased toward the Czarist regime including a succession of its defeat and the Bloody Sunday Incident (1905) occurred on January 9, 1905.</e>
<cmt>「血の日曜日」は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。また、当サイトによりますと、「1月9日」はロシア旧暦であって、グレゴリオ暦では、「1月22日」となっています。沢山の年号が出てきており、整合性を欠く事があってはなりませんので、あえてグレゴリオ暦に変更することは控えます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Russia, the successive defeats exacerbated popular dissatisfaction towards the Czarist regime, leading to the Bloody Sunday Incident on January 9th, 1905.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Russia, the successive defeats exacerbated popular dissatisfaction towards the Czarist regime, leading to the Bloody Sunday Incident on January 9th, 1905.</e>
<cmt>「the Czarist」のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>日本軍の明石元二郎大佐による革命運動への支援工作がこれに拍車をかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The support maneuvering performed by Colonel Motojiro Akashi of the Japanese army toward revolutionary movements gave impetus to the above circumstances.</e>
<cmt>「大佐」は、軍隊階級表（新和英大辞典第５版）旧陸軍から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Colonel Akashi Motojiro&apos;s support of the revolutionary movements in Russia spurred the aforementioned situation.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Colonel Motojiro AKASHI&apos;s support of the revolutionary movements in Russia spurred the aforementioned situation.</e>
<cmt>姓を大文字にし、名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>日本も、当時の乏しい国力を戦争で使い果たしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan also used up its poor national strength at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan had also exhausted what little national resources it had.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan had also exhausted what little national resources it had.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>両国はアメリカ合衆国の仲介の下で終戦交渉に臨み、1905年9月5日に締結されたポーツマス条約により講和した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two countries sat down at the negotiating table for the termination of the war through the mediation of the United States of America and made peace with each other under the Treaty of Portsmouth concluded on September 5, 1905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two countries entered into peace negotiations mediated by the United States, and concluded signed the Treaty of Portsmouth on September 5th, 1905.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two countries entered into peace negotiations mediated by the United States, and concluded signed the Treaty of Portsmouth on September 5th, 1905.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="122">
<j>日本は19か月の戦争期間中に戦費17億円を投入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan put war funds of 1.7 billion yens during the war period of 19 months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan expended 1.7 billion Yen during the 19 months of hostilities.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan expended 1.7 billion Yen during the 19 months of hostilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>戦費のほとんどは戦時国債によって調達された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost all of the funds was raised by issuing wartime bonds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war was funded almost exclusively by issuing wartime bonds.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war was funded almost exclusively by issuing wartime bonds.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>当時の日本軍の常備兵力20万人に対して、総動員兵力は109万人に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against the standing force of 200,000 soldiers of the Japanese army at that time, the mobilized force reached 1.09 million soldiers in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan mobilized approximately 1.09 million soldiers, which far exceeded its standing army of 200,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan mobilized approximately 1.09 million soldiers, which far exceeded its standing army of 200,000 soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>戦死傷者は38万人、うち死亡者8万7,983人に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The casualties were 380,000 soldiers, out of which 87,983 soldiers were killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Out of the 380,000 casualties, 87,983 soldiers were killed in action.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Out of the 380,000 casualties, 87,983 soldiers were killed in action.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="126">
<j>なお開戦時、麦飯派の寺内正毅が陸軍大臣であった（麦飯を主張する軍医部長がいた）にもかかわらず、大本営が「勅令」として指示した戦時兵食は、日清戦争と同じ白米飯（精白米6合）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, when the war started, Masatake TERAUCHI, an advocate of rice boiled with barley happened to be the Minister of Army (There was a high-ranking army surgeon who recommended rice boiled with barley), however, the war-time food for soldiers instructed by the Imperial headquarters as an &apos;imperial edict&apos; was boiled polished rice (Six Go of polished rice) which was the same as in the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-&apos;95.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In spite of the fact that TERAUCHI Masatake, an advocate of rice boiled with barley, was the Minister of Army (There was a high-ranking army surgeon who recommended rice boiled with barley); however, the rations provisioned by the Imperial headquarters through an &quot;imperial edict&quot; was cooked rice (Six Go of polished rice) which was the same as in the Sino-Japanese War (1894-&apos;95).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In spite of the fact that Masatake TERAUCHI, an advocate of rice boiled with barley, was the Minister of Army (There was a high-ranking army surgeon who recommended rice boiled with barley); however, the rations provisioned by the Imperial headquarters through an &quot;imperial edict&quot; was cooked rice (Six Go of polished rice) which was the same as in the Sino-Japanese War (1894-&apos;95).</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>結果的に、そのレーションの不備と輸送能力・インフラ整備の問題（輸送中に一万石の挽割麦の大半が変敗したという記録がある）等により、陸軍は約25万人の脚気患者を出し、うち約2万7,800人が病死したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the Army reported beriberi patients of about 250,000 soldiers, out of which about 27,800 soldiers were said to have died, due to the inadequate ration and the problems of transporting capacity and infrastructure improvement (Most of the 10,000 koku (approximately 1.8 million liters of crop yield) of barley groats was reportedly decomposed during transportation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approximately 27,800 of 250,000 army beriberi patients are said to have died due to improper rationing, and logistics and infrastructure problems (Records reveal that most of the 10,000 koku (approximately 1.8 million liters of crop yield) of barley groats spoiled in transit.).</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approximately 27,800 of 250,000 army beriberi patients are said to have died due to improper rationing, and logistics and infrastructure problems (Records reveal that most of the 10,000 koku [approximately 1.8 million liters of crop yield] of barley groats spoiled in transit).</e>
<cmt>括弧内の括弧を[]に修正しました。ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>また国内で、脚気患者の大量発生と軍医不足という悲惨な状況が知られはじめると、陸軍衛生部さらに大本営の大本営組織、小池正直（陸軍省医務局）に対する批判が高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, when such disastrous situations as a mass outbreak of beriberi patients and the shortage of army surgeons started to be known, the Medical Department of the Army, the headquarter-organizations of the Imperial headquarters and Masanao KOIKE (Medical Affairs Bureau of Ministry of Army) came under increasing criticism.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Medical Department of the Army, Imperial Headquarters Executive Command, and KOIKE Masanao (Medical Affairs Bureau of Ministry of Army) came under increasing criticism when tragic news of the beriberi epidemic and the shortage of army surgeons became known in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Medical Department of the Army, Imperial Headquarters Executive Command, and Masanao KOIKE (Medical Affairs Bureau of Ministry of Army) came under increasing criticism when tragic news of the beriberi epidemic and the shortage of army surgeons became known in Japan.</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>戦後も小池が辞任するまで『医海時報』に陸軍批判の投稿がつづいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the war, articles to criticize the Army continued to be contributed to &quot;Ikai Jiho&quot; (Medical Newsletter) until Koike&apos;s resignation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the war, articles criticizing the Army continued to be published in the &quot;Ikai Jiho&quot; (Medical Newsletter) until Koike&apos;s resignation.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the war, articles criticizing the Army continued to be published in the &quot;Ikai Jiho&quot; (Medical Newsletter) until Koike&apos;s resignation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>脚気の原因がわからなかった時代の日清・日露戦争は、まさに脚気との闘いでもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sino-Japanese War of 1894-&apos;95 and the Russo-Japanese War which occurred in the ages when the cause of beriberi was unknown, were exactly fights against beriberi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It could be said that the Sino-Japanese War (1894-&apos;95) and the Russo-Japanese War, which were fought in an age when the causes for beriberi were unknown, were indeed, also struggles against beriberi.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It could be said that the Sino-Japanese War (1894-&apos;95) and the Russo-Japanese War, which were fought in an age when the causes for beriberi were unknown, were indeed, also struggles against beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>（脚気ビタミン欠乏説が確定していた昭和期も、1938年まで毎年、国民の脚気死亡者数が1万人から2万人の間で推移しており、脚気が完全に根絶されたのは1952年以降）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Even in the Showa Period when it was already determined that beriberi was caused by shortage of vitamins, the number of the Japanese people who died of beriberi hovered from 10,000 to 20,000 per year until 1938 and it was after 1952 that beriberi was completely exterminated)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Even in the Showa Period when it was concluded that vitamin deficiency caused beriberi, until 1952, 10,000 to 20,000 citizens succumbed to beriberi on an annual basis, and it was not until after 1952 that beriberi was exterminated.)</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Even in the Showa Period when it was concluded that vitamin deficiency caused beriberi, until 1938, 10,000 to 20,000 citizens succumbed to beriberi on an annual basis, and it was not until after 1952 that beriberi was exterminated.)</e>
<cmt>until 1952→until 1938</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>陸軍とは対照的に麦飯を用いた海軍では、脚気死亡者がほとんどなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike the Army, the Navy which fed rice boiled with barley had few to die of beriberi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In stark contrast to the Army, the Navy which rationed its sailors rice with barley had almost no deaths due to beriberi.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In stark contrast to the Army, the Navy which rationed its sailors rice with barley had almost no deaths due to beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>ただし、兵食の問題（実は航海食がビタミン欠乏状態）等により、海軍の脚気患者は、1928年1,153人、1937年から1941年まで1,000人を下回ることがなく、12月に太平洋戦争が勃発した1941年は3,079人の脚気患者が出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the problem of soldiers&apos; foods (In reality, foods at sea were short of vitamins) and so on, the number of the beriberi patients in the Navy was 1,153 in 1928 and did not fall below 1,000 from 1937 to 1941, and in 1941 when the Pacific War broke out in December, 3,079.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, rations for sailors had its problems (In reality, food at sea lacked vitamin content) as even in 1928, there were 1,153 beriberi patients in the Navy, and this did not fall below 1,000 between 1937 to 1941; In fact, when the Pacific War broke out in December, there were 3,079 beriberi patience.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, rations for sailors had its problems (In reality, food at sea lacked vitamin content) as even in 1928, there were 1,153 beriberi patients in the Navy, and this did not fall below 1,000 between 1937 to 1941; In fact, when the Pacific War broke out in December, there were 3,079 beriberi patience.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="134">
<j>ロシア帝国の南下を抑えることに成功し、加えて戦後に日露協約が成立したことで、相互の勢力圏を確定することができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan succeeded in containing the advance southward of the Russian Empire and in addition determined each other&apos;s influence area by the establishment of the Russo-Japanese Treaty after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan succeeded in containing the southward advance of the Russian Empire and confirming their respective spheres of influence through the Russo-Japanese Treaty.</e>
<cmt>I think it is fairly obvious that the Russo Japanese treaty was concluded after the war, so that part was elided in the translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan succeeded in containing the southward advance of the Russian Empire and confirming their respective spheres of influence through the Russo-Japanese Treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>こうして日本は朝鮮半島の権益を確保できた上、新たに東清鉄道の一部である南満州鉄道の獲得など満洲（中国東北部）における権益を得ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to secure the interests in the Korean Peninsula, Japan ended up newly obtaining interests in Manchuria (Northeastern area of China) including the South Manchuria Railways, a part of the Chinese Eastern Railway.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to securing interests in the Korean Peninsula, Japan also acquired concessions in Manchuria (Northeastern China) including the South Manchuria Railways- a part of the Chinese Eastern Railway.</e>
<cmt>Minor Grammar, Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to securing interests in the Korean Peninsula, Japan also acquired concessions in Manchuria (Northeastern China) including the South Manchuria Railways- a part of the Chinese Eastern Railway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>またロシアに勝利したことは、列強諸国の日本に対する評価を高め、明治維新以来の課題であった不平等条約改正の達成に大きく寄与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the fact that Japan defeated Russia raised the reputation of Japan with the great powers and greatly contributed to Japan&apos;s success in revising the unequal treaties which had been a challenge since the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s victory over Russia raised the repute of Japan among the great powers and greatly contributed to Japan&apos;s objective to revise the unequal treaties which had been a priority issue for the Japanese government since the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s victory over Russia raised the repute of Japan among the great powers and greatly contributed to Japan&apos;s objective to revise the unequal treaties which had been a priority issue for the Japanese government since the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="137">
<j>ポーツマス条約の内容は、賠償金を取れないなど、多くの国民にとって予想外に厳しい内容だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Treaty of Portsmouth was so unexpectedly worse in contents for most of the general public as Japan got no reparations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many citizens were disappointed by the Treaty of Portsmouth, which did not grant Japan any reparations.</e>
<cmt>This sentence is exceptionally hard to translate with phrases like 予想外に厳しい内容. 内容 &quot;content&quot; is a fluff word in my opinion, and can be elided.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many citizens were disappointed by the Treaty of Portsmouth, which did not grant Japan any reparations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>そのため、日比谷焼打事件をはじめとして各地で暴動が起こり、戒厳令が敷かれるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the above, popular uprisings broke out in various places including the Hibiya Incendiary Incident, which were put under martial law.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Popular uprisings broke out in various places beginning with the Hibiya Incendiary Incident, and martial law was declared.</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation of はじめとして corrected.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Popular uprisings broke out in various places beginning with the Hibiya Incendiary Incident, and martial law was declared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>これは、ロシア側へいかなる弱みともなることをも秘密にしようとした日本政府の政策に加え、新聞以下マスコミ各社が日清戦争を引き合いに出して戦争に対する国民期待を否応なしに煽ったために修正がきかなくなっていたこともあり、国民の多くは戦争をしている国力の実情を知らされず、目先の勝利によってロシアが簡単に屈服させられたように錯覚した反動から来ているものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above situation derived from the people&apos;s reaction to the following facts: (1) The Japanese Government adopted a policy to keep secret anything which would indicate Japanese weak points, (2) The media including newspapers so unavoidably stirred up in the populace a sense of expectation referring to the Sino-Japanese War of 1894-&apos;95 that correction came to be of no use and (3)most of the general public were kept unknown about the actual circumstances of the war in terms of national strength and were deluded by immediate victories that Russians were easily subdued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The discrepancy between popular sentiment and government policy is due to the fact that the Japanese Government adopted a stringent policy of secrecy to keep any information that could reveal national weaknesses from falling into Russian hands; The media including newspapers used the example of the Japanese victory in the Sino-Japanese War to fan the flames of war without regard to national sentiment, and inadvertantly built up jingoistic mood which could not be easily reversed; and finally, the majority of citizens were not aware of the true nature of Japan&apos;s national strength and erroneously believed that Japan easily defeated Russia in battle.</e>
<cmt>Structure and style altered</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The discrepancy between popular sentiment and government policy is due to the fact that the Japanese Government adopted a stringent policy of secrecy to keep any information that could reveal national weaknesses from falling into Russian hands; The media including newspapers used the example of the Japanese victory in the Sino-Japanese War to fan the flames of war without regard to national sentiment, and inadvertantly built up jingoistic mood which could not be easily reversed; and finally, the majority of citizens were not aware of the true nature of Japan&apos;s national strength and erroneously believed that Japan easily defeated Russia in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="140">
<j>この戦争において日本軍および政府は、旅順要塞司令官のステッセルが降伏した際に帯剣を許すなど、武士道精神に則り敗者を非常に紳士的に扱ったほか、戦争捕虜を非常に人道的に扱い、日本赤十字社もロシア兵戦傷者の救済に尽力した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that war, the Japanese military forces and the Government treated the losers in so gentlemanly manner in conformity with the samurai spirit as allowed Stoessel, the Russian commander of the Lushun Fortress to wear a sword when he surrendered, treated war prisoners very humanely, and the Japanese Red Cross Society worked hard to relieve Russian injured soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Russo-Japanese War, the Japanese military forces and the Government treated their adversaries in a gentlemanly manner in accordance to the way and mentality of bushido (&quot;way of the samurai.&quot;) and mentality of the samurai; for instance, the Russian commander of the Lushun Fortress wore his sword when formalizing the surrender of Lushun, and prisoners of war were treated very humanely, and the Japanese Red Cross Society worked hard to treat injured Russian soldiers.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Russo-Japanese War, the Japanese military forces and the Government treated their adversaries in a gentlemanly manner in accordance to the way and mentality of bushido (&quot;way of the samurai.&quot;) and mentality of the samurai; for instance, the Russian commander of the Lushun Fortress wore his sword when formalizing the surrender of Lushun, and prisoners of war were treated very humanely, and the Japanese Red Cross Society worked hard to treat injured Russian soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>日本軍は国内各地に捕虜収容所を設置したが、愛媛県の松山にあった施設が著名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army founded prisoner&apos;s camps in various parts of the country, among which the facilities in Matsuyama City in Ehime Prefecture was well-known.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army established prisoner&apos;s camps in various parts of Japan, among which the facilities in Matsuyama City in Ehime Prefecture were the most well known.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army established prisoner&apos;s camps in various parts of Japan, among which the facilities in Matsuyama City in Ehime Prefecture were the most well known.</e>
<cmt>「, among」のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>そのため、ロシア兵側では降伏することを「マツヤマ、マツヤマ」と勘違いしたというエピソードもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, there was an episode that Russian soldiers mistook &apos;Matsuyama, Matsuyama&apos; for a surrender.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an episode in which Russian soldiers mistook &quot;Matsuyama, Matsuyama&quot; to mean surrender.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an episode in which Russian soldiers mistook &quot;Matsuyama, Matsuyama&quot; to mean surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="143">
<j>ファイル永久防塁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Permanent fortress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Permanent fortress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Permanent fortress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>また、元老でありながら参謀総長として戦争を指揮した山縣有朋の発言力が高まり、陸軍は「大陸帝国」論とロシアによる「復讐戦」の可能性を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Futhermore, the influence of Aritomo YAMAGATA who took command in the war as the Chief of the General Staff though he was a Genro (elder statesman) was enhanced and the Army advocated the possibility of the &apos;Continental Empire&apos; theory and the &apos;Revenge War&apos; by Russia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war increased the influence of YAMAGATA Aritomo who took command in the war as the Chief of the General Staff, even though he was also a Genro (elder statesman), and the Army raised the possibility that Russia could develop into a &quot;Continental Empire&quot; or pursue a &quot;War of Revenge.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war increased the influence of Aritomo YAMAGATA who took command in the war as the Chief of the General Staff, even though he was also a Genro (elder statesman), and the Army raised the possibility that Russia could develop into a &quot;Continental Empire&quot; or pursue a &quot;War of Revenge.&quot;</e>
<cmt>姓名順を名姓順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>1907年には山縣の主導によって平時25師団体制を確保するとした「帝国国防方針」案が纏められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1907, under the leadership of Yamagata, the &apos;Defense Policy of the Empire&apos; proposal was prepared to secure 25 divisions in time of peace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the leadership of YAMAGATA, the &quot;Imperial Defence Policy&quot; proposal was prepared to secure a 25 division formation during times of peace.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1907, under the leadership of Yamagata, the &quot;Imperial Defense Policy&quot; proposal was prepared to secure a 25 division formation during times of peace.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れの「1907年には」＝In 1907,を追加しました。名字単体の記載のため、語頭のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>だが、戦後の財政難から師団増設は順調にはいかず、18師団を20師団にすることの是非を巡って有名な2個師団増設問題が発生することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the plan to increase the number of divisions did not go well due to financial difficulties after the war and ended up with the well-known issue of Additional Two Divisions on the appropriateness of increasing the number of divisions from 18 to 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the plan to increase the number of divisions did not go well due to post-war financial difficulties, leading to the famous debacle over whether to increase the number of divisions from 18 to 20.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the plan to increase the number of divisions did not go well due to post-war financial difficulties, leading to the famous debacle over whether to increase the number of divisions from 18 to 20.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="147">
<j>日露戦争において旅順要塞での戦闘に苦しめられた陸軍は、戦後、ロマン・コンドラチェンコによって築かれていた旅順要塞の堡塁を模倣し、永久堡塁 (習志野)と呼ばれた演習用構造物を陸軍習志野錬兵場内に構築、演習などを行い要塞戦の戦術について研究した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, the Army which was harassed in the battle at the Lushun Fortress in the Russo-Japanese War founded a structure for military exercises called permanent fortress (Narashino) in the Narashino drill ground of the Army, imitating the forts in the Lushun Fortress constructed by Roman Kondratenko, and studied tactics for the fortress battles by conducting military exercises.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「ロマン・コンドラチェンコ」の英文は下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%83%95%E3%82%A1%E3%82%A4%E3%83%AB:Kondratenko.jpg</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, the Army which experienced difficulties in the siege of the Lushun Fortress constructed a replica of the Lushun Fortress constructed by Roman Kondratenko for military exercises called the &quot;permanent fortress,&quot; and researched tactics for fortress warfare.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, the Army which experienced difficulties in the siege of the Lushun Fortress constructed a replica of the Lushun Fortress constructed by Roman Kondratenko for military exercises called the &quot;permanent fortress,&quot; and researched tactics for fortress warfare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>上記のようなエピソードが残されており、当時の陸軍に与えた影響の大きさを物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above episode remains today, which indicates that the war greatly influenced the Army at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Events such as the abovementioned episode reveal the influence of Russo-Japanese War over post-war developments in the army.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Events such as the abovementioned episode reveal the influence of Russo-Japanese War over post-war developments in the army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="149">
<j>この戦争により、陸軍においては白兵突撃至上主義が、海軍においては艦隊決戦至上主義が確立され、後の太平洋戦争まで両者共に大きく影響を及ぼすことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of that war, a sword assault supreme policy was established in the Army and a fleet decisive battle supreme policy in the Navy, which ended up being greatly influential until the Pacific War later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Russo-Japanese War cemented the centrality of charge tactics in the army, and decisive encounter between fleets in the navy tactics that would significantly influence both institutions until the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russo-Japanese War cemented the centrality of charge tactics in the army, and decisive encounter between fleets in the navy tactics that would significantly influence both institutions until the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="150">
<j>なお、賠償金が取れなかったことから、日本帝国はジェイコブ・シフのクーン・ローブに対して金利を払い続けることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due not to getting reparations, the Great Empire of Japan ended up continuing payment of interest to Kuhn Loeb &amp; Co. of Jacob Schiff.</e>
<cmt>「クーン・ローブ」の英文は下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%AF%E3%83%BC%E3%83%B3%E3%83%BB%E3%83%AD%E3%83%BC%E3%83%96</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan continued to pay interest to Kuhn Loeb &amp; Co. of Jacob Schiff, because it did not receive reparations from Russia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan continued to pay interest to Kuhn Loeb &amp; Co. of Jacob Schiff, because it did not receive reparations from Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>「日露戦争で最も儲けた」シフは、ロシア帝国のポグロム（反ユダヤ主義)への報復が融資の動機といわれ、のちレーニンやトロツキーにも資金援助をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schiff who &apos;profited most out of the Russo-Japanese War&apos; is said to have financed Japan being motivated by his retaliation against pogrom (anti-Semitism) in the Russian Empire and later supported Lenin and Trotsky with funds.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schiff who is said to have &quot;profited the most from the Russo-Japanese War,&quot; is said to have financed Japan out of retaliation for Russian pogrom (anti-Semitic purges), and is known to have financed Lenin and Trotsky.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schiff who is said to have &quot;profited the most from the Russo-Japanese War,&quot; is said to have financed Japan out of retaliation for Russian pogrom (anti-Semitic purges), and is known to have financed Lenin and Trotsky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>ロシア</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="152">
<j>伝統的な南下政策がこの戦争の動機の一つであったロシア帝国は、この敗北を期に極東への南下を断念した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Russian Empire entered into the war partly motivated by its southward expansion, but took the opportunity of that defeat to give up the idea of its southward expansion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Russian Empire&apos;s entry into the war was motivated by its traditional policy of southward expansion, this defeat prompted it to abandon this policy in the Far East.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Russian Empire&apos;s entry into the war was motivated by its traditional policy of southward expansion, this defeat prompted it to abandon this policy in the Far East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>南下の矛先は再びバルカンに向かい、ロシアは汎スラヴ主義を全面に唱えることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russia changed the direction of southward expansion again to the Balkans and ended up advocating Pan-Slavism in every aspect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russia refocussed its southward expansion to the Balkans, advocating Pan-Slavism in the process.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russia refocussed its southward expansion to the Balkans, advocating Pan-Slavism in the process.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>このことが汎ゲルマン主義を唱えるドイツや、同じくバルカンへの侵略を企むオーストリアとの対立を招き、第一次世界大戦の引き金となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That brought about its opposition to Germany which advocated Pan-Germanism and to Austria which planned to invade the Balkans, which triggered off the World War I.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led Russia into a direct confrontation with Germany, which advocated Pan-Germanism and Austria which planned to invade the Balkans the conditions that would set off the First World War was set.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led Russia into a direct confrontation with Germany, which advocated Pan-Germanism and Austria which planned to invade the Balkans the conditions that would set off the First World War was set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>また、戦争による民衆の生活苦から血の日曜日事件 (1905年)やポチョムキン＝タヴリーチェスキー公 (戦艦)の叛乱等より始まるロシア第一革命が誘発され、ロシア革命の原因となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the war induced the Russian First Revolution starting from Bloody Sunday Incident (1905) resulting from the people&apos;s hardships of life caused by the war and the rebellion of Knyaz&apos; Potemkin-Tavricheskiy (battleship) and triggered the Russian Revolution.</e>
<cmt>「ポチョムキン＝タヴリーチェスキー公」の英文は、下記サイトから引用いたしました。http://wpedia.mobile.goo.ne.jp/wiki/173307/%83%7C%83%60%83%87%83%80%83L%83%93%81%81%83%5E%83%94%83%8A%81%5B%83%60%83F%83X%83L%81%5B%8C%F6+(%90%ED%8A%CD)/11/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The popular resentment over the hardships endured by the populace during the war manifest itself in the First Russian Revolution, which began with the Bloody Sunday Incident (1905) and the mutiny on the Knyaz&apos; Potemkin-Tavricheskiy (battleship), setting the stage for the Russian Revolution.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The popular resentment over the hardships endured by the populace during the war manifest itself in the First Russian Revolution, which began with the Bloody Sunday Incident (1905) and the mutiny on the Knyaz&apos; Potemkin-Tavricheskiy (battleship), setting the stage for the Russian Revolution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>李氏朝鮮（大韓帝国）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yi Dynasty Korea (The Korean Empire)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yi Dynasty Korea (The Korean Empire)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yi Dynasty Korea (The Korean Empire)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="156">
<j>開戦前の大韓帝国では、日本派とロシア派での政争が継続していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Korean Empire before the war, the political strife between the pro-Japanese group and the pro-Russian group continued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Political conflict between pro-Japanese factions and pro-Russian factions continued before the the war.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Political conflict between pro-Japanese factions and pro-Russian factions continued before the the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>日本の戦況優勢を見て、東学党の系列から一進会が1904年に設立され、大衆層での親日的独立運動から、日本の支援を受けた合邦運動へ発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recognizing Japan&apos;s superior position in the military situation, Isshinkai deriving from a group of the Togaku-to Party was established in 1904, which was developed into a political union campaign from a pro-Japanese independence movement on the general public level.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recognizing that Japan had the upperhand in the war, the Iljinhoe was established from the Donghak Party in 1904, developing from a grass-roots pro-Japanese independence movement into an pro-annexation movement that received support from Japan.</e>
<cmt>I think this is suppose to be Korean. Iljinhoe / Donghakdo or Donghak party</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recognizing that Japan had the upperhand in the war, the Iljinhoe was established from the Donghak Party in 1904, developing from a grass-roots pro-Japanese independence movement into an pro-annexation movement that received support from Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>ただし当初の一進会の党是は韓国の自主独立であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the original party platform of Isshinkai was the sovereign independence of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Iljinhoe&apos;s original party platform was to secure the independence and sovereignty of Korea.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Iljinhoe&apos;s original party platform was to secure the independence and sovereignty of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>西欧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western Europe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western Europe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="159">
<j>日露戦争をきっかけに日露関係、英露関係が急速に改善し、それぞれ日露協約、英露協商を締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Russo-Japanese War, the relationship between Japan and Russia and that between England and Russia were rapidly improved, resulting in conclusions of the Russo-Japanese Treaty and the Anglo-Russian Entente respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relations between Russo-Japanese, and Anglo-Russian relations rapidly improved as a result of the Russo-Japanese War, leading to the conclusion of the Russo-Japanese Treaty and the Anglo-Russian Entente.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relations between Russo-Japanese, and Anglo-Russian relations rapidly improved as a result of the Russo-Japanese War, leading to the conclusion of the Russo-Japanese Treaty and the Anglo-Russian Entente.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>既に締結されていた英仏協商と併せて、欧州情勢は日露戦争以前の英・露仏・独墺伊の三勢力が鼎立していた状況だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Europe before the Russo-Japanese War, there was a three-cornered contest between the three powers of England, Russia/France and Germany/Austria/Italy, while there was the Entente Cordiale between England and France concluded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Russo-Japanese War, Europe was alligned into three major blocs of England, Russia/France, and Germany/Austria/Italy, underlined by an Entente Cordiale concluded between England and France.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Russo-Japanese War, Europe was alligned into three major blocs of England, Russia/France, and Germany/Austria/Italy, underlined by an Entente Cordiale concluded between England and France.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>それが、英仏露の三国協商と独墺伊の三国同盟 (1882年)の対立へと向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The above situation was moving toward a confrontation between the Triple Entente of England/France/Russia and the Triple Alliance (1882) of Germany/Austria/Italy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This alignment moved towards a confrontation between the Triple Entente consisting England, France, and Russia and the Triple Alliance (1882) composed of Germany, Austria, and Italy.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This alignment moved towards a confrontation between the Triple Entente consisting England, France, and Russia and the Triple Alliance (1882) composed of Germany, Austria, and Italy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>こうしてイギリスは仮想敵国をロシアからドイツに切り替え、ドイツはイギリスとの建艦競争を拡大してゆく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that way, England changed its imaginary enemy from Russia to Germany which was expanding a naval armaments race against England.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">England shifted its projected rival from Russia to Germany, and the two countries became locked in an ever-expanding naval arms race.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">England shifted its projected rival from Russia to Germany, and the two countries became locked in an ever-expanding naval arms race.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>アメリカ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The United States of America</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The United States of America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The United States of America</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="163">
<j>アメリカ合衆国はポーツマス条約の仲介によって漁夫の利を得、満洲に自らも進出することを企んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The United States of America easily obtained good opportunity by acting as an intermediary for the Treaty of Portsmouth and contemplated advancing into Manchuria itself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The United States of America took advantage of its intermediary stance, and sought to advance its own ambitions in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>Phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The United States of America took advantage of its intermediary stance, and sought to advance its own ambitions in Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>しかし、思惑とは逆に日英露三国により中国権益から締め出されてしまう結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the United States was, contrary to its expectation, driven out of the Chinese interests by the three countries of Japan, England and Russia in the end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in contrary to its expectations, the United States was blocked out from receiving privileges in China by Japan, England, and Russia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in contrary to its expectations, the United States was blocked out from receiving privileges in China by Japan, England, and Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>以後もアメリカは「門戸開放政策」を掲げて中国進出を意図したが、結局上手くいかず、対日感情が悪化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the United States intended to expand into China also after that under the slogan of &apos;Open-door policy,&apos; it did not go well after all and American feeling toward Japan became worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The United State&apos;s efforts to expand their presence in China through the &apos;Open-door Policy&apos; failed to bear fruit, and led to rising tensions with Japan.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The United State&apos;s efforts to expand their presence in China through the &apos;Open-door Policy&apos; failed to bear fruit, and led to rising tensions with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>これは日英同盟の解消や軍縮の要求などにつながり、黄禍論の高まりと共に、後の第二次世界大戦を引き起こす日米対立の第一歩となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That situation led to the cancellation of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance and the arms reduction demand and, along with a surge of the Yellow Peril opinion, marked the first step towards the confrontation between Japan and the United States which triggered the consequent World War II.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation led to the termination of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance, demands for arms reduction, along with a rise in anti-immigration sentiments reflected in popular hysteria over the &quot;Yellow Peril,&quot; which set the stage for a series of confrontations between Japan and the United States that would lead to the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation led to the termination of the Anglo-Japanese Alliance, demands for arms reduction, along with a rise in anti-immigration sentiments reflected in popular hysteria over the &quot;Yellow Peril,&quot; which set the stage for a series of confrontations between Japan and the United States that would lead to the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="167">
<j>当時の大統領セオドア・ルーズベルトは、ポーツマス条約締結に至る日露の和平交渉への貢献が評価され、1906年のノーベル平和賞を受賞した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The then U.S. President Theodore Roosevelt was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1906 in recognition of his contribution to peace talks between Japan and Russia leading to the conclusion of the Treaty of Portsmouth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The then U.S. President Theodore Roosevelt was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1906 in recognition of his contribution to the peace talks between Japan and Russia that led to the conclusion of the Treaty of Portsmouth.</e>
<cmt>Minor fix.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The then U.S. President Theodore Roosevelt was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1906 in recognition of his contribution to the peace talks between Japan and Russia that led to the conclusion of the Treaty of Portsmouth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>清朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing Dynasty</e>
<cmt>Capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="168">
<j>日露戦争の戦場であった満州（東三省・現在の中国東北部）は清の主権下にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manchuria (Tosansho, the northeastern part of the present China), the battlefield of the Russo-Japanese War was under the Qing sovereignty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Manchuria (Dongsan Province, part of present day northeastern China), where the Russo-Japanese War was fought over was Qing territory.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Manchuria (Dongsan Province, part of present day northeastern China), where the Russo-Japanese War was fought over was Qing territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>満州族による王朝である清は建国以来、父祖の地である満洲には漢民族を入れないという封禁政策を取り、中国内地のような目の細かい行政制度も採用しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing, a dynasty of the Manchurians, since the founding of the nation, took the exclusion policy that it never allow the Han race to enter Manchuria, its inherited land and did not adopt such detailed administrative systems as in the inland China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing Dynasty was established by the Manchu, who forbade the ethnic Han from migrating into their native lands through an exclusion policy, and did not adopt specifically delineated administrative policies as they in Manchuria as they had in China.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing Dynasty was established by the Manchu, who forbade the ethnic Han from migrating into their native lands through an exclusion policy, and did not adopt specifically delineated administrative policies as they in Manchuria as they had in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>開発も最南部の遼東半島・遼西を除き進んでおらず、こうしたことも原因となって19世紀末のロシアの進出に対して対応が遅れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manchuria was behind in development except the southernmost Liaodong Peninsula and Liaoxi, which partly caused Manchuria to delay coping with the Russian expansion at the end of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exception of the southernmost areas in the Liaodong peninsula and Liaoxi, most of Manchuria was underdeveloped; Hence, the Qing could not mount a response to Russian expansionism at the end of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of the southernmost areas in the Liaodong peninsula and Liaoxi, most of Manchuria was underdeveloped; Hence, the Qing could not mount a response to Russian expansionism at the end of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>そのため、東清鉄道やハルピンを始めとする植民都市の建設まで許すこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For that reason, Manchuria ended up allowing Russia to construct not only the Chinese Eastern Railway but also the colonies including Harbin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is for this reason that they acquiesced to the construction the Eastern Manchurian Railway and colonial cities beginning with Harbin.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is for this reason that they acquiesced to the construction the Eastern Manchurian Railway and colonial cities beginning with Harbin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>さらに義和団の乱の混乱の中で満洲は完全にロシアに制圧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Manchuria was brought completely under the Russian control in a state of disorder caused by the Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Manchuria was completely brought under Russian control during the confusion of the Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Manchuria was completely brought under Russian control during the confusion of the Boxer Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>1901年の北京議定書締結後もロシアの満洲占拠が続いたために、張之洞や袁世凱は東三省の行政体制を内地と同一とするなどの統治強化を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the Boxer Protocol (Peking) was concluded in 1901, Russia kept occupying Manchuria and so Zhang Zhidong and Yuan Shikai insisted on tightening control by setting the administrative system of Tosansho to the same system as the inland China.</e>
<cmt>「張之洞」「袁世凱」の英文は、新和英大辞典第５版から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Russians continued their occupation of Manchuria even after the Boxer Protocol was concluded in 1901, prompting Zhang Zhidong and Yuan Shikai to assert Qing sovereignty over Dongsan Province by claiming that it should treated as an internal affair.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russians continued their occupation of Manchuria even after the Boxer Protocol was concluded in 1901, prompting Zhang Zhidong and Yuan Shikai to assert Qing sovereignty over Dongsan Province by claiming that it should treated as an internal affair.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>しかし清朝の対応は遅れ、そうしているうちに日露両国が開戦し、自国の領土で他国同士が戦うという事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, while the Qing dynasty was slow in responding to the suggestions, Japan and Russia started a war, and Qing ended up inviting a situation in which the foreign military forces fought against each other in its own territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the Qing Dynasty Russo-Japanese War erupted before the Qing could mount a coherent response, leading to a situation in which two foreign countries fought on Qing territory.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the Qing Dynasty Russo-Japanese War erupted before the Qing could mount a coherent response, leading to a situation in which two foreign countries fought on Qing territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="175">
<j>終戦後は、日本は当初唱えていた満洲に於ける列国の機会均等の原則を翻し、日露が共同して利権を分け合うことを画策した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, Japan changed its originally-advocated principle of equal opportunity for all countries in Manchuria and planned to split the interests between Japan and Russia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, Japan reversed its original stance to seek equality among the great powers when it concerns Manchuria, and planned to share rights equally with Russia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, Japan reversed its original stance to seek equality among the great powers when it concerns Manchuria, and planned to share rights equally with Russia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>こうした状況に危機感をつのらせた清朝は直隷・山東からの漢民族の移民を奨励して人口密度の向上に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing dynasty which felt mounting sense of crisis with such situation made efforts to increase the population density by encouraging the Han race in Chokurei and Santo to immigrate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「直隷・山東」の家分はサイトでも見当たらず日本語読みにいたしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing Dynasty felt increasingly uneasy with this situation and sought to increase the population density in Manchuria by promoting an emigration of ethnic Han towards Zhili and Shandong.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing Dynasty felt increasingly uneasy with this situation and sought to increase the population density in Manchuria by promoting an immigration of ethnic Han from Zhili and Shandong to Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>原文では「直隷・山東からの漢民族の移民」となっていますので、以下のように修正しました。an emigration of ethnic Han towards Zhili and Shandong→an immigration of ethnic Han from Zhili and Shandong to Manchuria</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>そして、終戦の翌々年の1907年には内地と同じ「省・府・県」による行政制度を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1907, two years after the end of the war, the Qing dynasty established an administrative system identical to that of the inland by &apos;Sho, Fu and Ken.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「省・府・県」は、日本語読みに致しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1907, two years after the end of the Russo-Japanese war, the Qing Dynasty established an administrative system using the categories of &apos;Sho, Fu and Ken&apos; identical to that which was used to govern China proper.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1907, two years after the end of the Russo-Japanese war, the Qing Dynasty established an administrative system using the categories of &apos;Sho, Fu and Ken&apos; identical to that which was used to govern China proper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>ある推計によると、1880年から1910年にかけて、東三省の人口は743万4千人から1783万6千人まで膨れ上がっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A certain estimation indicates that the population of Tosansho increased as far as to 17,836,000 from 7,434,000 from 1880 to 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Certain estimates indicate that the population of Dongsan Province actually grew to 17,836,000 from 7,434,000 between 1880 and 1910.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Certain estimates indicate that the population of Dongsan Province actually grew to 17,836,000 from 7,434,000 between 1880 and 1910.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>さらに同年には袁世凱の北洋軍閥の一部が満洲に駐留し、警察力・防衛力を増強するとともに、日露の行動への歯止めをかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, in the same year, a part of the Beiyang Group of Yuan Shikai started to be stationed in Manchuria and built up its police force and defense capacity putting the brakes on the activities of Japan and Russia.</e>
<cmt>「北洋軍閥」の英文は、新和英大辞典第５版から引用しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, part of the Beiyang Military faction led by Yuan Shikai was deployed to Manchuria to reinforce policing and security, and offer a bulwark against Japanese and Russian movements.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in the same year, part of the Beiyang Military faction led by Yuan Shikai was deployed to Manchuria to reinforce policing and security, and offer a bulwark against Japanese and Russian movements.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れの「同年には」＝in the same year, を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>また、日露の持つ利権に対しては、アメリカ資本を導入して相互の勢力を牽制させることで対抗を図ったが、袁世凱の失脚や日本側の工作もあり、うまくいかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the Qing Dynasty introduced American capitals to let them confront the interests held by Japan and Russia making both sides discourage each other, however, it did not go well due to the downfall of Yuan Shikai and the maneuvering by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing Dynasty also sought to introduce American capital and play them off against Japanese and Russian rights, but this failed to the downfall of Yuan Shikai and maneuvering by Japan.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing Dynasty also sought to introduce American capital and play them off against Japanese and Russian rights, but this failed due to the downfall of Yuan Shikai and maneuvering by Japan.</e>
<cmt>failed to the downfall→failed due to the downfall</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>また、1917年のロシア帝国崩壊後は日本が一手に利権の扶植に走り、ついに1932年には自身の傀儡国家である満州国を建国した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, after the disintegration of the Russian Empire, Japan exclusively got wrapped up in establishing its interests and finally founded Manchukuo, its own puppet state in 1932.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan immediately sought to fill the vacuum after the disintegration of the Russian Empire in 1917, and finally established the puppet state of Manchukuo in 1932.</e>
<cmt>I agree with the initial translation, using the old Wade-Giles spelling for the puppet state of &quot;Manchukuo&quot; rather than the pinyin &quot;Manzhouguo.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan immediately sought to fill the vacuum after the disintegration of the Russian Empire in 1917, and finally established the puppet state of Manchukuo in 1932.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>太平洋戦争で日本が敗れて撤退すると、代わって進駐したソ連が満洲侵略に乗じて日本の残したインフラを持ち去り、旅順・大連の租借権を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japan was defeated in the Pacific War and withdrew from Manchuria, the Soviet Union occupied the land in place of Japan and took away the infrastructures constructed in Manchuria by Japan, and claimed the lease of Lushun and Dalian City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Japan was defeated in the Pacific War and withdrew from Manchuria, the Soviet Union replaced the Japanese presence and stripped the region of the industrial infrastructure constructed by the Japanese, and claimed the concessions of Lushun and Dalian.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Japan was defeated in the Pacific War and withdrew from Manchuria, the Soviet Union replaced the Japanese presence and stripped the region of the industrial infrastructure constructed by the Japanese, and claimed the concessions of Lushun and Dalian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>中華人民共和国が中国東北部を完全に掌握したのは1955年のことであり、日露戦争から50年後のことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in 1955 that the People&apos;s Republic of China put the northeastern part of China completely under its control, and it was 50 years after the Russo-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not until 1955 that the People&apos;s Republic of China reassumed full control over northeastern China -over fifty years after the Russo- Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not until 1955 that the People&apos;s Republic of China reassumed full control over northeastern China -over fifty years after the Russo- Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>その他各国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other countries</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other Countries</e>
<cmt>Capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other Countries</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="184">
<j>当時、欧米列強の支配下にあり、後に独立した国々の指導者達の回顧録に下記のような、植民地時代における感慨の記録が数多く見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In memoirs written by the leaders of the independent countries which used to be under the control of the Western powers in those days, there are many records of deep emotion looking back on the period under colonial rule as below.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the memoirs written by the leaders of countries formerly colonized by western countries refer to the Russo-Japanese War with great excitement.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the memoirs written by the leaders of countries formerly colonized by western countries refer to the Russo-Japanese War with great excitement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>「有色人種の小国が白人の大国に勝ったという前例のない事実が、アジアやアフリカの植民地になっていた地域の独立の気概に弾みをつけたり人種差別下にあった人々を勇気付けた」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;The unprecedented fact that a small nonwhite state defeated a great Caucasian state stimulated the spirit of independence of the colonized regions in Asia and Africa and encouraged the peoples under the racial discrimination.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The unprecedented victory of a small country of yellow people over a large country of white people has galvanized the spirit of people seeking independence across the colonies throughout Asia and Africa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The unprecedented victory of a small country of yellow people over a large country of white people has galvanized the spirit of people seeking independence across the colonies throughout Asia and Africa.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="186">
<j>また、第一次エチオピア戦争で、エチオピア帝国がイタリア王国に勝利した先例があるが、 これは英仏の全面的な軍事的支援によるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was a precedent that the Ethiopian Empire defeated the Kingdom of Italy in the First Italo–Ethiopian War, it was thanks to full military support of England and France.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was a precedent set by the Ethiopian Empire when it defeated the Kingdom of Italy in the First Italo–Ethiopian War, they succeeded in ousting the Italian with the full military support of England and France.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was a precedent set by the Ethiopian Empire when it defeated the Kingdom of Italy in the First Italo–Ethiopian War, they succeeded in ousting the Italian with the full military support of England and France.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>そのため、日露戦争における日本の勝利は、有色人種国家独自の軍隊による、白色人種国家に対する近代初の勝利と言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the victory for Japan in the Russo-Japanese War can be regarded as the first victory in the modern times for a nonwhite state with its own military forces against a Caucasian state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Japanese victory over Russia in the Russo-Japanese War can be regarded as the first modern war in which a non-western state defeated a western state.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Japanese victory over Russia in the Russo-Japanese War can be regarded as the first modern war in which a non-western state defeated a western state.</e>
<cmt>「which a」のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="188">
<j>また、絶対君主制（ツァーリズム）を続ける国に対する立憲君主国の勝利という側面もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there was an aspect of a victory for a constitutional monarchy against an absolute monarchy(czarism).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the Russo-Japanese War could also be viewed as a victory of a constitutional monarchy over an absolute monarchy (czarism).</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the Russo-Japanese War could also be viewed as a victory of a constitutional monarchy over an absolute monarchy (czarism).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>いずれにしても日露戦争における日本の勝利が及ぼした世界的影響は計り知れず、歴史的大事件であったことには変わりない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At any rate, the victory for Japan in the Russo-Japanese War impacted incalculably on the world and it was indisputably one of the major historic incidents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no doubt that the Japanese victory in the Russo-Japanese War was a major historic event that changed the course of history.</e>
<cmt>Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no doubt that the Japanese victory in the Russo-Japanese War was a major historic event that changed the course of history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="190">
<j>日露戦争の影響を受けて、ロシアの植民地であった地域やアジアで特に独立・革命運動が高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the influence of the Russo-Japanese War, independence and revolutionary movementswere enhanced in the regions colonized by Russia and more especially in Asia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Former Russian colonies sought independence in the aftermath of the Russo-Japanese War, and independence and revolutionary movements became active throughout Asia.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Former Russian colonies sought independence in the aftermath of the Russo-Japanese War, and independence and revolutionary movements became active throughout Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>清朝における孫文の辛亥革命、オスマン帝国における青年トルコ革命、カージャール朝におけるイラン立憲革命や、仏領インドシナにおけるファン・ボイ・チャウの東遊運動、インド帝国におけるインド国民会議国民会議カルカッタ大会等に影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It influenced the Xinhai Revolution by Sun Yat-sen, theYoung Turks Revolution in the Ottoman Empire, the Iranian Constitutional Revolution in the period of the Kajar dynasty, the Dong Du Movement (Look-Japan Movement) by Phan Boi Chau in the French Indochina, the Calcutta Conference of the Indian National Congress in the Indian Empire and so on.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「ファン・ボイ・チャウ」の英文は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phan_Boi_Chau「東遊運動」は、下記サイト他から引用しました。http://my.opera.com/dangnhu/blog/　「インド国民会議」は、下記サイトから引用しました。http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/%E3%82%A4%E3%83%B3%E3%83%89%E5%9B%BD%E6%B0%91%E4%BC%9A%E8%AD%B0</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It influenced the Sun Yatsen&apos;s Xinhai Revolution, the Young Turks Revolution in the Ottoman Empire, the Iranian Constitutional Revolution, Phan Boii Chau&apos;s Dong Du Movement (Look-Japan Movement) in French Indochina, and the Indian National Congress&apos;s Calcutta Conference.</e>
<cmt>Grammar and Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It influenced the Sun Yatsen&apos;s Xinhai Revolution, the Young Turks Revolution in the Ottoman Empire, the Iranian Constitutional Revolution, Phan Boii Chau&apos;s Dong Du Movement (Look-Japan Movement) in French Indochina, and the Indian National Congress&apos;s Calcutta Conference.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>発行物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Publications</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Publications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Publications</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="192">
<j>特殊切手として（1906年4月29日）、1銭5厘、3銭の切手が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two kinds of postage stamps of one-sen five-rin and three-sen were issued as special commemorative stamps (April 29, 1906).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A one-sen five-rin postage stamp and a three-sen postage stamp were issued in commemoration of the victory (April 29, 1906).</e>
<cmt>Style Grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A one-sen five-rin postage stamp and a three-sen postage stamp were issued in commemoration of the victory (April 29, 1906).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Okome(id:98), 経済準学士(id:22656), 0null0(id:582), ヨースケ(id:130176), おはぐろ蜻蛉(id:8405), Lupinoid(id:68), Sonicwave123(id:216867), ПРУСАКИН(id:23195), Episteme(id:32386), Yonidebot(id:247998), Tsk(id:1153), Jugger90(id:17088), らりた(id:1327), 俊(id:14924), WikipReview(id:251029), Point136(id:211299), Rabbit(id:12621), F.V.E(id:33231), YukkeBot2(id:251491), Ihcumikitna(id:245036), EKS(id:69869), Nesnad(id:13756), Sweeper tamonten(id:183520), Atanare(id:185207), TEy(id:32722), Nikai(id:1648), Rxk14007(id:144284), Xqbot(id:273540), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), SuisuiBot(id:10165), おきた(id:18906), 完璧主義(id:24971), TAKASUGI Shinji(id:19129), DYLAN LENNON(id:23921), Suisui(id:69), Wushi(id:107127), 伊達政宗(id:112070), Socalaki(id:206942), Spa生(id:71699), Sheepech(id:111676), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), Zdime(id:49424), Michu(id:987), ゆっこ:(id:61782), 肉牛(id:802), Kadzuwo(id:3701), Wkpda(id:50685), Pinkpastel(id:238480), ロロ(id:104252), Chobot(id:20846), Kone(id:377), Fugue(id:43540), 絵鞠(id:56670), Yosemite(id:5808), Setuzoku2(id:191045), KASAGI(id:24405), LERK(id:4460), 水野白楓(id:22811), Race(id:131322), Daranome(id:1429), Cuaxdon(id:217395), Aboshi(id:9318), Daidouji(id:59718), Kazukiokumura(id:142935), ぴらんこ(id:213280), 矢吹城(id:126243), Miya(id:1881), CarsracBot(id:217884), BotSottile(id:188404), こいつぅ(id:2105), Lebit(id:11805), アユ(id:58197), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), っ(id:4481), Los688(id:12316), Lusheeta(id:11139), Trudi3194(id:283128), Libertas(id:40611), Musya(id:28458), Eskimbot(id:29676), 22010515528(id:43149), Jazzy(id:3202), Shalmaneser(id:167217), Gombe(id:27), 中尉(id:23829), Opponent(id:720), 石垣(id:121151), Hermeneus(id:380), Boa(id:20845), Kk8998982(id:43060), 代言人(id:33675), あなひろ(id:45821), Mnd(id:15140), ArthurBot(id:265089), Deepimpact(id:129352), Luh(id:16361), 砂場(id:27896), 赤い飛行船(id:120211), Kibayashit(id:602), 曹洞(id:110074), Nightmare11(id:150160), Spirituelle(id:654), 敷島健一(id:270317), Pondehiyo0000(id:182620), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Kanjy(id:36859), Партизан ФК(id:14780), Cotton5(id:127398), Tonbi ko(id:27171), 一言虎児(id:100290), 三日月(id:19540), Lib 1964(id:30789), Locust-of-abaddon(id:221039), 唐変木(id:17050), TT(id:46431), JAnDbot(id:66507), Straysheep(id:42448), MIsogi(id:20599), Kawai(id:5634), Fukupulio(id:287222), 邪馬台国(id:83702), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 味っ子(id:17086), 花鳥(id:240256), Continent(id:17704), Iderukuti(id:19367), Kurz(id:1601), A6M4(id:14155), 平 誠(id:2586), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), 大日本(id:72531), Nopira(id:29335), Mig(id:3428), Amagase(id:108940), Izayohi(id:13095), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Oyoyoyo(id:196287), 劉英迅(id:45909), Aphaia(id:3132), 廿粁(id:219234), Cave cattum(id:41235), 瑠璃川(id:108322), Ajtnk(id:18368), Tanuki Z(id:612), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kaba(id:17904), GNR-Patience(id:89951), Fromm(id:71291), Trek011(id:7105), Ciro(id:4058), Saaki(id:43602), Boxingowl(id:101997), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>