<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>所当</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">shoto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoto</e>
<cmt>Capitalized.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>所当（しょとう）とは、中世の田畠にかけられた租税のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoto was the tax levied on paddy field and dry field in the Medieval era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoto was the tax levied on paddy fields and dry fields in the Medieval era.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoto was the tax levied on paddy fields and dry fields in the Medieval period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>公事と対に扱われ、年貢と同一視される場合もあるが本来は異なるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was treated as a pair with kuji (pubic duties), and considered to be the same as nengu (land tax), but they were different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was treated as a pair with kuji (pubic duties), and seen generally to be the same as nengu (land tax), but they were infact different.</e>
<cmt>Changed for clarity.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was treated as a pair with kuji (pubic duties), and seen generally to be the same as nengu (land tax), but they were originally different.</e>
<cmt>用語を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元来は「相当すること」「当を得ている」という意味で用いられていた言葉でその意味でも長く一般に用いられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The word was originally used as &apos;corresponding to&apos; &apos;correct&apos;, which meaning had been used in general for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The word originally meant &apos;corresponding to&apos;, or &apos;correct&apos;, and this meaning had been used in general for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Grammar.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The word originally meant &apos;corresponding to,&apos; or &apos;correct,&apos; and this meaning had been used in general for a long time.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>租税としての「所当」も本来は適切に賦課された官物・雑役・地子などの租税のことを指していたが、12世紀初頭頃より、単に「所当」をもって（公事や臨時雑役などの臨時の賦課に対する）正規の賦課を意味する言葉となったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoto&apos;, which meant tax, originally indicated taxes properly levied such as kanmotsu (produce tax), zoyaku (miscellaneous labor services), and jishi (land tax); but from the beginning of the 12th century, &apos;shoto&apos; solely meant a regular levy (in contrast to such extraordinary levies as kuji and extraordinary odd-jobs.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoto&apos;, which meant tax, originally indicated taxes properly levied such as kanmotsu (produce tax), zoyaku (miscellaneous labor services), and jishi (land tax); but from the beginning of the 12th century, &apos;shoto&apos; solely meant a regular levy (in contrast to such extraordinary levies as kuji and extraordinary odd-jobs).</e>
<cmt>Punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoto,&apos; which meant tax, originally indicated taxes properly levied such as kanmotsu (produce tax), zoyaku (miscellaneous labor services), and jishi (land tax); but from the beginning of the 12th century, &apos;shoto&apos; solely meant a regular levy (in contrast to such extraordinary levies as kuji and extraordinary odd-jobs).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションの位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>更に鎌倉時代には田畠にかけられた正規の賦課に限定されるようになり、本来そうした意味を有していた言葉であった「年貢」と混用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the word limitedly meant a regular levy on paddy fields and dry fields, and began to be interchanged with &apos;nengu&apos; which originally had the similar meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura Period, the word meant a regular levy on paddy fields and dry fields, and began to be interchanged with &apos;nengu&apos; which originally had a similar meaning.</e>
<cmt>Grammar, punctuation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the word meant a regular levy on paddy fields and dry fields, and began to be interchanged with &apos;nengu&apos; which originally had a similar meaning.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>