<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>富国強兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukoku kyohei (fortifying the country, strengthening the military)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>富国強兵（ふこくきょうへい）とは、国家の経済を発展させて軍事力の増強を促す政策をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukoku kyohei refers to a policy that makes state economics grow and encourages reinforcement of military forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukoku kyohei refers to a policy that makes state economics grow and encourages reinforcement of military forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukoku kyohei refers to a policy that makes state economics grow and encourages reinforcement of military forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>中国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>中国では、春秋戦国時代に諸侯の国が行った政策を「富国強兵」といい、『戦国策』秦策に用例が見える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, a policy which was carried out in lords&apos; countries at the Spring and Autumn period and the Warring States period was called &quot;Fukoku kyohei &quot;, and the examples could be seen in &quot;Sengoku (warlike period) plan&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, the policies that were carried out in lords&apos; countries at the Spring and Autumn period and the Warring States period were called &apos;Fukoku kyohei&apos;, and some examples were given in Shinsaku (Qin strategies) of &quot;Sengoku (warlike period) strategies&quot;.</e>
<cmt>二重引用符を一重引用符にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, the policies that were carried out in lords&apos; countries at the Spring and Autumn period and the Warring States period were called &apos;Fukoku kyohei&apos;, and some examples were given in Shinsaku (Qin strategies) of &quot;Sengoku (warlike period) strategies&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この時代には各国が諸子百家と呼ばれる思想家たちから人材を登用し、騎馬戦術やチャリオットなどの新兵器を導入して軍事改革を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period each countries appointed thinkers called Shoshi-hyakka (general term of scholars and schools in China), and they introduced new weapons such as Cavalry Operations and chariots, and conducted military reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this period each country appointed thinkers called Shoshi-hyakka (general term of scholars and schools in China), and they introduced new weapons, such as Cavalry Operations and chariots, and conducted military reforms.</e>
<cmt>each countriesをeach countryに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period each country appointed thinkers called Shoshi-hyakka (general term of scholars and schools in China), and they introduced new weapons, such as Cavalry Operations and chariots, and conducted military reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>日本で明治政府の国策の基本を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a basic national policy of the Meiji government in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a basic national policy of the Meiji government in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a basic national policy of the Meiji government in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代の鎖国が原因で欧米列強に国力で大きな差をつけられ、これが安政五カ国条約という新国家を後々まで苦しめる結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, which fell far behind the Western powers due to the national isolation policy in the Edo era, found itself, as a result, heavily burdened under the Ansei Five-Power Treaties, which continued to agonize the nation until long after its fresh start as a renewed nation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, which fell far behind the Western powers due to its national isolation policy in the Edo era, was heavily burdened by the Ansei Five-Power Treaties long after its start as a renewed nation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, which fell far behind the Western powers due to its national isolation policy in the Edo era, was heavily burdened by the Ansei Five-Power Treaties long after its start as a renewed nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これを教訓とした日本は、地租改正や殖産興業で経済力をつけ（＝富国）、徴兵制や軍制改革により軍備を増強（＝強兵）して、列強に追いつくことにより条約改正と国家の保全を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Learning from such lessons, Japan aimed to materialize revision of the treaties and improvement of national security by strengthening its economic power with land-tax reform and encouragement of industries (= to be a rich country), and military power with the conscription system and reformation of the military system (=to be a powerful army) to be equal with other great powers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Learning a lesson from this, Japan aimed to revise the treaties and improve national security by strengthening its economic power with land-tax reform and encouragement of industries (national enrichment), and military power with the conscription system and reformation of the military system (strengthening of the military) to catch up with other great powers.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Learning a lesson from this, Japan aimed to revise the treaties and improve national security by strengthening its economic power with land-tax reform and encouragement of industries (national enrichment), and military power with the conscription system and reformation of the military system (strengthening of the military) to catch up with other great powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), Los688(id:12316), もらとりあむ(id:768), 東 遥(id:37435), PANYNJ(id:38638), ぬんむる(id:3671), Koya2koya3(id:88515), Areare(id:119960), Cave cattum(id:41235), Johncapistrano(id:969), 杉山真大(id:2297), 白居烏(id:192756), Jugger90(id:17088), SuisuiBot(id:10165), トホホ川(id:50502), SieBot(id:126695), Tatsujin28(id:9300), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>