<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>青松葉事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aomatsuba Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aomatsuba Incident</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aomatsuba Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>青松葉事件（あおまつばじけん）とは、慶応4年（1868年）1月20日から25日にかけて発生した尾張藩内での佐幕派弾圧事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aomatsuba Incident was Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) crackdown incident which happened in Owari Domain from January 20 to 25 in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aomatsuba Incident was Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) crackdown incident which happened in the Owari Domain from February 13 to 18 in 1868.</e>
<cmt>The Aomatsuba Incident、in the Owari Domainとし、旧暦→新暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aomatsuba Incident was Sabaku-ha (supporters of the Shogun) crackdown incident which happened in the Owari Domain from February 13 to 18 in 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>弾圧の対象者は重臣から一般藩士まで及び、斬首14名、処罰20名にのぼった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The targets of crackdown ranged from senior vassals to common feudal retainers and the fourteen were decapitated and the twenty were punished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The targets of crackdown ranged from senior vassals to common feudal retainers and the fourteen were decapitated and the twenty were punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The targets of crackdown ranged from senior vassals to common feudal retainers and the fourteen were decapitated and the twenty were punished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>それまで京都で大政奉還後の政治的処理を行っていた14代藩主徳川慶勝が帰国し、その日のうちに弾圧の命令が出ていることから、何らかの密命を朝廷より下されたと思われるが、真相はいまだにはっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourteenth shogun Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA returned from Kyoto after political treatments of Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor) and on the day the order of crackdown was issued, which suggests that a sort of secret order was issued from Imperial Court but the truth is not clear even now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourteenth shogun Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA returned from Kyoto after political treatments of the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor) and on the day the order of crackdown was issued, which suggests that a sort of secret order was issued from the Imperial Court but the truth is not clear even now.</e>
<cmt>the Taisei Hokan、the Imperial Courtとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourteenth shogun Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA returned from Kyoto after political treatments of the Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor) and on the day the order of crackdown was issued, which suggests that a sort of secret order was issued from the Imperial Court but the truth is not clear even now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事件名の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin of the incident</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>事件名は、処刑された重臣のうちの筆頭格である渡辺在綱の家が「青松葉」といわれていたことからとっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name of the incident comes from &apos;Aobamatsu&apos; which was the name of Aritsuna WATANABE who was the head of the executed vassals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of the incident comes from &apos;Aomatsuba&apos; which was the name of the house of Aritsuna WATANABE who was the head of the executed vassals.</e>
<cmt>Aobamatsu→Aomatsubaに修正、「渡辺在綱の家」とあるため、the name of Aritsuna WATANABE→the name of the house of Aritsuna WATANABEに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of the incident comes from &apos;Aomatsuba&apos; which was the name of the house of Aritsuna WATANABE who was the head of the executed vassals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>渡辺家はもともと徳川家康の家来で「槍の半蔵」の異名を取った渡辺守綱（天文 (元号)11年(1542年) - 元和 (日本)6年(1620年)）の末裔であるが、鉄砲にも興味を持ち、その鋳造に用いる火を起こすのに青松葉を使ったとか、知行地から年貢を受け取るとき、青松葉を俵に挿して数えた、などという逸話が多いことから「青松葉の渡辺」といわれていたらしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watanabe family was originally descendants of Moritsuna WATANABE (1542 - 1620), whose imyo (another name) was &apos;Hanzo of Spear&apos; and was a retainer of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and there were many anecdotes such as that the family was also interested in teppo (gun) and aobamatsu (blue pine needle) was used for starting a fire to cast it or that when taking nengu (land tax) from chigyo-chi (territory) they were counted with aobamatsu inserted in the bales, which is why they were called &apos;WATANABE of aobamatsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Watanabe family was originally a descendant of Moritsuna WATANABE (1542 - 1620), whose imyo (another name) was &apos;Hanzo of Spear&apos; and was a retainer of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and there were many anecdotes such as that the family was also interested in teppo (gun) and aomatsuba (blue pine needle) was used for starting a fire to cast it or that when taking nengu (land tax) from chigyo-chi (territory) they were counted with aomatsuba inserted in the bales, which is why they were called &apos;WATANABE of aomatsuba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>The Watanabe familyとし、descendants→a descendant、aobamatsu→aomatsubaに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Watanabe family was originally a descendant of Moritsuna WATANABE (1542 - 1620), whose imyo (another name) was &apos;Hanzo of Spear&apos; and was a retainer of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, and there were many anecdotes such as that the family was also interested in teppo (gun) and aomatsuba (blue pine needle) was used for starting a fire to cast it or that when taking nengu (land tax) from chigyo-chi (territory) they were counted with aomatsuba inserted in the bales, which is why they were called &apos;WATANABE of aomatsuba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>発生までの経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background of the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background of the incident</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>徳川御三家である尾張徳川家、紀州徳川家、水戸徳川家には、御附家老というものが存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There existed otsukegaro (karo assigned directly by the shogun when the sons of the Tokugawa became daimyo) in Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged braches of Tokugawa family) such as the Owari Tokugawa family, the Kishu Tokugawa family and the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There existed otsukegaro (karo assigned directly by the shogun when the sons of the Tokugawa became daimyo) in the Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) such as the Owari Tokugawa family, the Kishu Tokugawa family and the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>the Tokugawa gosanke、the Tokugawa familyとし、branchesのスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There existed otsukegaro (karo assigned directly by the shogun when the sons of the Tokugawa became daimyo) in the Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) such as the Owari Tokugawa family, the Kishu Tokugawa family and the Mito Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>御附家老とは、単純に言えば将軍家から派遣された藩主のお目付け役であり、尾張では成瀬隼人正（なるせはやとのかみ）家と竹腰兵部少輔（たけのこしひょうぶしょうゆう）家が知行高も大きく著名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Simply, otsukegaro was Ometsuke (chief inspector of the Edo shogunate) for the lord of domain, sent from Shogun family, and in Owari Inuyama Domain Narusehayato no kami family and Imao Domain Takenokoshi hyobushoyu family were well-known and their Chigyo daka (a stipend in terms of rice production of the fief) were large.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Simply, otsukegaro was Ometsuke (chief inspector of the Edo bakufu, Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for the lord of a domain, sent from the Shogun family, and in the Owari Domain, the Narusehayato no kami family and the Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu family were well-known and their Chigyo daka (a stipend in terms of rice production of the fief) were large.</e>
<cmt>Edo shogunate→Edo bakufuに修正、bakufuの補足を追加、domain→a domain、Shogun family→the Shogun family、in Owari→in the Owari Domainとし、表記統一のため、hyobushoyu→Hyobu shoyuとしました。*「犬山藩」「今尾藩」→ウェブで確認したところリンク先の単語が記載されているため、元の単語をウェブより転記・訳文を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Simply, otsukegaro was Ometsuke (chief inspector of the Edo bakufu, Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for the lord of a domain, sent from the Shogun family, and in the Owari Domain, the Narusehayato no kami family and the Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu family were well-known and their Chigyo daka (a stipend in terms of rice production of the fief) were large.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>藩主も遠慮しなければならない家柄からその権力は強大であり、藩内は自然、成瀬派と竹腰派に分かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family lineage, which even the lord of domain had to show constraint, meant the very powerful authority and naturally the domain was divided into Naruse side and Takenokoshi side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family lineage, which even the lord of the domain had to show constraint, meant the very powerful authority and naturally the domain was divided into Naruse side and Takenokoshi side.</e>
<cmt>lord of domain→lord of the domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family lineage, which even the lord of the domain had to show constraint, meant the very powerful authority and naturally the domain was divided into Naruse side and Takenokoshi side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このうち、より幕府に近い立場を取り続けたのが竹腰派であり、古くは幕府に反抗的だった7代藩主徳川宗春を隠居謹慎に追い込んだこともあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them the Takenokoshi side took a stance nearer to bakufu and formerly they forced the seventh lord of domain Muneharu TOKUGAWA, who had a rebellious attitude to bakufu, to be secluded and suspended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them the Takenokoshi side took a stance nearer to bakufu and formerly they forced the seventh lord of the Owari Domain Muneharu TOKUGAWA, who had a rebellious attitude to the bakufu, to be secluded and suspended.</e>
<cmt>徳川宗春は「尾張藩」の7代藩主のため、seventh lord of domain→seventh lord of the Owari Domainとし、bakufu→the bakufuとしました。(参考: http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~me4k-skri/han/toukai/owari-nagoya.html)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them the Takenokoshi side took a stance nearer to bakufu and formerly they forced the seventh lord of the Owari Domain Muneharu TOKUGAWA, who had a rebellious attitude to the bakufu, to be secluded and suspended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>幕末のこの時期、藩内は尊皇攘夷を唱える「金鉄組」と、佐幕的な立場を執る「ふいご党」とに分かれ、成瀬家は金鉄組、竹腰家はふいご党に近かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time during the end of Edo period, the domain was divided into &apos;Kanetetsu group&apos; who were in Sonno-joi-ha (a group of activists who admired the Emperor and hated foreigners, advocating the need for expelling them from Japan) and &apos;Fuigo party&apos; who were in Sabaku-ha, and Naruse family was near to Kanetetsu group and Takenokoshi family near to Fuigo party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time during the end of the Edo period, the domain was divided into the &apos;Kanetetsu group&apos; who were in Sonno-joi-ha (a group of activists who admired the Emperor and hated foreigners, advocating the need for expelling them from Japan) and the &apos;Fuigo party&apos; who were in Sabaku-ha, and the Naruse family was near to the Kanetetsu group and the Takenokoshi family near to the Fuigo party.</e>
<cmt>the Edo period、the Kanetstsu group、the Fuigo party、the Naruse family、the Takenokoshi familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time during the end of the Edo period, the domain was divided into the &apos;Kanetetsu group&apos; who were in Sonno-joi-ha (a group of activists who admired the Emperor and hated foreigners, advocating the need for expelling them from Japan) and the &apos;Fuigo party&apos; who were in Sabaku-ha, and the Naruse family was near to the Kanetetsu group and the Takenokoshi family near to the Fuigo party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>14代藩主徳川慶勝は就任以来尊皇攘夷の立場をとり、特に黒船来航以来藩政の刷新を進める中で竹腰家を初めとするふいご党と対立することが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourteenth lord of domain Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA took stance of Sonno-joi-ha and especially since the arrival of the Black Ships, he was often opposed to Fuigo party like Takenokoshi family during the reform of administration of the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourteenth lord of the Owari Domain Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA took stance of Sonno-joi-ha and especially since the arrival of the Black Ships, he was often opposed to the Fuigo party like the Takenokoshi family during the reform of administration of the domain.</e>
<cmt>lord of domain→lord of the Owari Domainとしました。(参考: http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~me4k-skri/han/toukai/owari-nagoya.html)the Fuigo party、the Takenokoshi familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourteenth lord of the Owari Domain Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA took stance of Sonno-joi-ha and especially since the arrival of the Black Ships, he was often opposed to the Fuigo party like the Takenokoshi family during the reform of administration of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大老井伊直弼の弾圧により慶勝が隠居すると、金鉄組は没落し、竹腰兵部少輔が新藩主徳川茂徳のもとで藩政を取り仕切ったが、桜田門外の変以降竹腰兵部少輔は失脚、慶勝が隠居の身ながら藩政の前面に出、金鉄組とともに頻繁に上洛して政局にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The crackdown on Tairo (chief minister) Nosuke II forced Yoshikatsu to be secluded and Kanetetsu group was on decline and under the new lord of domain Shigenori TOKUGAWA, Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu took domain duties, but after the Sakuradamongai Incident, Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu was toppled and Yoshikatsu advanced to administration of the domain though he was in retirement and he often went to the capital (Kyoto) with Kanetetsu group to take the helm of state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The crackdown on Tairo (chief minister) Nosuke II forced Yoshikatsu to be secluded and the Kanetetsu group was on decline and under the new lord of the domain Mochinaga TOKUGAWA, Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu took domain duties, but after the Sakuradamongai no Hen (The Incident Outside the Sakurada-mon Gate), Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu was toppled and Yoshikatsu advanced to administration of the domain though he was in retirement and he often went to the capital (Kyoto) with the Kanetetsu group to take the helm of state.</e>
<cmt>Shigenori TOKUGAWA→Mochinaga TOKUGAWAに修正 (参照: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%BE%B3%E5%B7%9D%E8%8C%82%E5%BE%B3)、lord of the domain、the Kanetetsu groupとし、Sakuradamongai Incident→「桜田門外」の意味を明確にするため、Sakuradamongai no Hen (The Incident Outside the Sakurada-mon Gate)としました。（参照: http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=wQZIAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=sakuradamongai-no-hen&amp;dq=sakuradamongai-no-hen&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=Gy5qTI3hDpDgugPg-KCDAQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The crackdown on Tairo (chief minister) Nosuke II forced Yoshikatsu to be secluded and the Kanetetsu group was on decline and under the new lord of the domain Mochinaga TOKUGAWA, Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu took domain duties, but after the Sakuradamongai no Hen (The Incident Outside the Sakurada-mon Gate), Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu was toppled and Yoshikatsu advanced to administration of the domain though he was in retirement and he often went to the capital (Kyoto) with the Kanetetsu group to take the helm of state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その間、茂徳が隠居して慶勝の子徳川義宜が藩主となり、ふいご党は日の目を見なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Shigenori went into retirement and Yoshinori TOKUGAWA, the son of Yoshikatsu, became the lord of domain and Fuigo party languished in obscurity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Mochinaga went into retirement and Yoshinori TOKUGAWA, the son of Yoshikatsu, became the lord of the domain and the Fuigo party languished in obscurity.</e>
<cmt>Shigenori→Mochinagaに修正、lord of the domain、the Fuigo partyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Mochinaga went into retirement and Yoshinori TOKUGAWA, the son of Yoshikatsu, became the lord of the domain and the Fuigo party languished in obscurity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>大政奉還後、慶応4年1月3日から5日にかけての鳥羽・伏見の戦いで幕府軍が敗北した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Taisei Hokan the army of bakufu was defeated in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi from January 3 to 5 in 1868.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Taisei Hokan the army of the bakufu was defeated in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi from January 27 to 29 in 1868.</e>
<cmt>After the Taisei Hokan、the bakufuとし、旧暦→新暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Taisei Hokan the army of the bakufu was defeated in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi from January 27 to 29 in 1868.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その一報が名古屋城に届くと、京都に派兵するかどうかで、派兵を主張する金鉄組と派兵に慎重なふいご党との対立が深まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the news reached Nagoya-jo castle, regarding whether to dispatch troops or not, the confrontation deepened between Kanetetsu group insisting on the dispatch and Fuigo party in a guarded stance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the news reached Nagoya-jo Castle, regarding whether to dispatch troops or not, the confrontation deepened between the Kanetetsu group insisting on the dispatch and the Fuigo party in a guarded stance.</e>
<cmt>castleの頭文字を大文字に変更、the Kanetetsu group、the Fuigo partyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the news reached Nagoya-jo Castle, regarding whether to dispatch troops or not, the confrontation deepened between the Kanetetsu group insisting on the dispatch and the Fuigo party in a guarded stance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>このとき、京都にいた慶勝は、手勢を率いて上洛した監察吉田知行から、城代間宮正萬の言付けという形で尾張藩内の情勢を聞き、1月15日に京都をたち、20日に帰国している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Yoshikatsu in Kyoto heard the situation in Owari Domain from the supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA with his own soldiers in the form of a letter from the castle keeper Shoman MAMIYA, and he left Kyoto on January 15 and returned to his province on 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then Yoshikatsu in Kyoto heard the situation in the Owari Domain from the supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA with his own soldiers in the form of a letter from the castle keeper Shoman MAMIYA, and he left Kyoto on February 8 and returned to his province on 13.</e>
<cmt>in the Owari Domainとし、余分なスペースを消去、旧暦→新暦に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then Yoshikatsu in Kyoto heard the situation in the Owari Domain from the supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA with his own soldiers in the form of a letter from the castle keeper Shoman MAMIYA, and he left Kyoto on February 8 and returned to his province on 13.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>そして、事件は発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the incident happened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the incident happened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the incident happened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>青松葉事件の全容</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whole contents of Aobamatsu Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whole contents of the Aomatsuba Incident</e>
<cmt>Aobamatsu Incident→the Aomatsuba Incidentに修正、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whole contents of the Aomatsuba Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>この事件による処罰者は以下のとおり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The punished ones are as follow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The punished ones are as follows.</e>
<cmt>follow→followsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The punished ones are as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>いずれも弁明の機会を与えられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">No chance for excuse was given to them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No chance for excuse was given to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No chance for excuse was given to them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>1月20日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 20.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2010/02/13</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2010/02/13</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>［斬首］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>御年寄列、二千五百石、内五百石足高　渡辺新左衛門在綱(49)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otoshiyori line, 2500 koku and 500 koku tashidaka (a wage system established by Edo bakufu) Shinzaemon Aritsuna WATANABE (49).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otoshiyori line, 2500 koku, 500 out of 2500 koku tashidaka (a wage system established by the Edo bakufu) Shinzaemon Aritsuna WATANABE (49).</e>
<cmt>「内」→訳漏れのため訳出、the Edo bakufuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoshiyori line, 2500 koku, 500 out of 2500 koku tashidaka (a wage system established by the Edo bakufu) Shinzaemon Aritsuna WATANABE (49).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>大御番頭、千五百石、内四百石足高　榊原勘解由正帰(59)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omike head clerk at a mercantile establishment, 1500 koku, 400 koku tashidaka Kayuge Shoki SAKAKIBARA (59).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogoban-gashira (captains of the great guards), 1500 koku, 400 out of 1500 koku tashidaka, Kageyu Shoki SAKAKIBARA (59).</e>
<cmt>「大御番頭」の表記を修正、「内」→訳漏れのため訳出、Kayuge→Kageyuに修正、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogoban-gashira (captains of the great guards), 1500 koku, 400 out of 1500 koku tashidaka, Kageyu Shoki SAKAKIBARA (59).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>大御番頭格、千石　石川内蔵允照英(42)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omike head clerk at a mercantile establishment, 1000 koku Kura no suke shoei ISHIKAWA (42).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogoban-gashira status, 1000 koku Kura no suke Shoei ISHIKAWA (42).</e>
<cmt>「大御番頭格」の表記を修正、shoei→Shoeiとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogoban-gashira status, 1000 koku Kura no suke Shoei ISHIKAWA (42).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>1月21日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 21.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2010/02/14</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2010/02/14</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>［斬首］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>御手筒頭格、御書物奉行、二百俵、内五十俵足高　冢田愨四郎有志(61)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tezutsu head, gosho bugyo (writing magistrate), 200 bales, 50 bales tashidaka Soshiro Yushi IEDA (61).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tezutsu head status, Goshomotsu bugyo (writing magistrate), 200 bales, 50 bales out of 200 tashidaka Soshiro Yushi IEDA (61).</e>
<cmt>status追加、gosho bugyo→Goshomotsu bugyoに修正、「内」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tezutsu head status, Goshomotsu bugyo (writing magistrate), 200 bales, 50 bales out of 200 tashidaka Soshiro Yushi IEDA (61).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>錦織奉行格、表御番、二百五十俵、内百八十俵足高　安井長十郎秀親(52)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishikiori bugyo (magistrate), Omotegoban, 250 bales, 180 bales tashidaka Chojuro Hidechika YASUI (52).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishikiori bugyo (magistrate) status, Omotegoban, 250 bales, 180 out of 250 bales tashidaka Chojuro Hidechika YASUI (52).</e>
<cmt>Nishikiori bugyoにstatusを追加、「内」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishikiori bugyo (magistrate) status, Omotegoban, 250 bales, 180 out of 250 bales tashidaka Chojuro Hidechika YASUI (52).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>御使番格、表御番、百五十石　寺尾竹四郎基之(54)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield), Omotegoban, 150 koku Takeshiro Motoyuki TERAO (54).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) status, Omotegoban, 150 koku Takeshiro Motoyuki TERAO (54).</e>
<cmt>Otsukaibanにstatusを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) status, Omotegoban, 150 koku Takeshiro Motoyuki TERAO (54).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>寄合、二百石　馬場市右衛門信広(26)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriai (a meeting), 200 koku Ichiemon Nobuhiro BABA (26).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriai (a family rank of high-ranking hatamoto, direct vassal of the shogun), 200 koku Ichiemon Nobuhiro BABA (26).</e>
<cmt>Yoriaiの補足が内容に沿わないため修正しました。（参考:http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%AF%84%E5%90%88、および用語集)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriai (a family rank of high-ranking hatamoto, direct vassal of the shogun), 200 koku Ichiemon Nobuhiro BABA (26).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>1月23日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2010/02/16</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2010/02/16</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>［斬首］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>二百石、御手筒頭格武野新五郎父、隠居　武野新左衛門信邦(77)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">200 koku, Tezutsu head Shingoro TAKENO father, retirement Shinzaemon Nobukuni TAKENO (77).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">200 koku, Tezutsu head status, Shingoro TAKENO&apos;s father, in retirement, Shinzaemon Nobukuni TAKENO (77).</e>
<cmt>status追加、Shingoro TAKENO father→Shingoro TAKENO&apos;s father、retirement→in retirementに修正、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">200 koku, Tezutsu head status, Shingoro TAKENO&apos;s father, in retirement, Shinzaemon Nobukuni TAKENO (77).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>二百五十石、御馬廻組光太郎父、隠居　成瀬正順(62)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">250 koku, Oumamawashi Mitsutaro KAIGUMI father retirement Masayori NARUSE (62).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">250 koku, Oumamawarigumi (horse guards) Mitsutaro&apos;s father, in retirement, Masayori NARUSE (62).</e>
<cmt>Oumamawashi Mitsutaro KAIGUMI father→Oumamawarigumi (horse guards) Mitsutaro&apos;s father、retirement→in retirementに修正、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">250 koku, Oumamawarigumi (horse guards) Mitsutaro&apos;s father, in retirement, Masayori NARUSE (62).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>［家名断絶、御預け］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Kamei-Danzetsu (to forfeit a family name), Confinement]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Kamei-Danzetsu (to forfeit a family name), Confinement]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Kamei-Danzetsu (to forfeit a family name), Confinement]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>中奥御小姓格　竹居新吉郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">nakaoku (middle inner) page Shinkichiro TAKEI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nakaoku (Middle Interior) page status, Shinkichiro TAKEI.</e>
<cmt>nakaoku (middle inner) page→Nakaoku (Middle Interior) page statusとし、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nakaoku (Middle Interior) page status, Shinkichiro TAKEI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>大御番組　武野新五郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omike group Shingoro TAKENO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ogobangumi (Great guard units) Shingoro TAKENO.</e>
<cmt>Omike group→Ogobangumiに修正、補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ogobangumi (Great guard units) Shingoro TAKENO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>御馬廻組　成瀬光太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oumamawari Mitsutaro NARUSE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oumamawarigumi Mitsutaro NARUSE.</e>
<cmt>Oumamawari→Oumamawarigumiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oumamawarigumi Mitsutaro NARUSE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>1月24日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 24.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2010/02/17</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2010/02/17</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>［永蟄居］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>鈴木嘉十郎父、隠居謹慎中　鈴木丹後守重到</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kajuro SUZUKI father, in retirement and house arrest Tango no kami Shigeto SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kajuro SUZUKI&apos;s father, in retirement and house arrest, Tango no kami (Governor of Tango Province) Shigeto SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>Kajuro SUZUKI father→Kajuro SUZUKI&apos;s fatherに修正、Tango no kamiの補足追加、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kajuro SUZUKI&apos;s father, in retirement and house arrest, Tango no kami (Governor of Tango Province) Shigeto SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>成瀬比佐之丞父、隠居謹慎中　成瀬豊前守正植</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisanojo NARUSE father, in retirement and house arrest Buzen no kami Masaue NARUSE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisanojo NARUSE&apos;s father, in retirement and house arrest, Buzen no kami (Governor of Buzen Province) Masaue NARUSE.</e>
<cmt>Hisanojo NARUSE father→Hisanojo NARUSE&apos;s fatherに修正、Buzen no kamiの補足追加、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisanojo NARUSE&apos;s father, in retirement and house arrest, Buzen no kami (Governor of Buzen Province) Masaue NARUSE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>［減知、隠居、永蟄居］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Cutdown of territory, retirement, permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Cutdown of territory, retirement, permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Cutdown of territory, retirement, permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>御年寄列　鈴木嘉十郎重熈</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otoshiyori line Kajuro Shigehiro SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otoshiyori line Kajuro Shigehiro SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otoshiyori line Kajuro Shigehiro SUZUKI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>［減知］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Cutdown of territory]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Cutdown of territory]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Cutdown of territory]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>成瀬比佐之丞</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hisanojo NARUSE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hisanojo NARUSE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hisanojo NARUSE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>1月25日</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 25.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2010/02/18</e>
<cmt>旧暦→新暦に修正、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2010/02/18</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>［斬首］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Decapitation]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>千五百石、横井孫太郎父、隠居謹慎中、寄合　横井孫右衛門時足(44)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1500 koku Magotaro YOKOI father, in retirement and house arrest, yoriai (meeting) Magoemon Tokitari YOKOI (44).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1500 koku Magotaro YOKOI&apos;s father, in retirement and house arrest, yoriai Magoemon Tokitari YOKOI (44).</e>
<cmt>Magotaro YOKOI father→Magotaro YOKOI&apos;s fatherに修正、yoriaiの補足削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1500 koku Magotaro YOKOI&apos;s father, in retirement and house arrest, yoriai Magoemon Tokitari YOKOI (44).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>八百石、沢井溢也父、隠居、寄合　沢井小左衛門貞増(44)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">800 koku, Itsuya SAWAI father, retirement, yoriai Shozaemon Sadamasu SAWAI (44).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">800 koku, Itsuya SAWAI&apos;s father, in retirement, yoriai Shozaemon Sadamasu SAWAI (44).</e>
<cmt>Itsuya SAWAI father→Itsuya SAWAI&apos;s father、retirement→in retirementに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">800 koku, Itsuya SAWAI&apos;s father, in retirement, yoriai Shozaemon Sadamasu SAWAI (44).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>四千石、御老列横井伊折介総領、謹慎中　横井右近時保(51)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">4000 koku, Goro line Iori no suke YOKOI eldest child, house arrest Ukon Tokiyasu YOKOI (51).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">4000 koku, Goro line Iori no suke YOKOI&apos;s eldest child, under house arrest, Ukon Tokiyasu YOKOI (51).</e>
<cmt>Iori no suke YOKOI eldest child→Iori no suke YOKOI&apos;s eldest child、house arrest→under house arrest に修正、カンマ追加</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">4000 koku, Goro line Iori no suke YOKOI&apos;s eldest child, under house arrest, Ukon Tokiyasu YOKOI (51).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>御普請奉行格、二百俵、内百四十六俵足高　松原新七直富(41)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fushin bugyo (shogunate administrator of activities by a community, such as cleaning or fixing stone wall), 200 bales, 146 bales tashidaka Shinshichi Naotomi MATSUBARA (41).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fushin bugyo (shogunate administrator of activities by a community, such as cleaning or fixing stone wall) status, 200 bales, 146 out of 200 bales tashidaka Shinshichi Naotomi MATSUBARA (41).</e>
<cmt>Fushin bugyoにstatuesを追加、「内」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fushin bugyo (shogunate administrator of activities by a community, such as cleaning or fixing stone wall) status, 200 bales, 146 out of 200 bales tashidaka Shinshichi Naotomi MATSUBARA (41).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>御先手物頭格表御番三百石、内五十石足高　林信政(40)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakite Monogashira (Spearhead Military Commanders) 300 koku, 50 koku tashidaka Nobumasa HAYASHI (40).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakite Monogashira (Spearhead Military Commanders) status, Omote-goban, 300 koku, 50 out of 300 koku tashidaka Nobumasa HAYASHI (40).</e>
<cmt>status追加、「表御番」(定訳不明) 「内」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakite Monogashira (Spearhead Military Commanders) status, Omote-goban, 300 koku, 50 out of 300 koku tashidaka Nobumasa HAYASHI (40).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>［蟄居］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[House arrest]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[House arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[House arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>大寄合滝川亀松父、隠居　滝川伊勢守忠雄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ooyoriai (a big meeting) Kamematsu TAKIGAWA father, retirement Ise no kami (Governor of Ise Province) Tadao TAKIGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oyoriai status Kamematsu TAKIGAWA&apos;s father, in retirement, Ise no kami (Governor of Ise Province) Tadao TAKIGAWA.</e>
<cmt>Ooyoriai→Oyoriai statusとし補足削除、Kamematsu TAKIGAWA father→Kamematsu TAKIGAWA&apos;s father、retirement→in retirementに修正、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oyoriai status Kamematsu TAKIGAWA&apos;s father, in retirement, Ise no kami (Governor of Ise Province) Tadao TAKIGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>平右衛門父、隠居　千村十郎左衛門仲冬</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heiemon TAIRA, retirement Jurozaemon Nakafuyu CHIMURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heiemon&apos;s father, in retirement, Jurozaemon Nakafuyu CHIMURA.</e>
<cmt>Heiemon TAIRA→Heiemonとし、「父」→訳漏れのため訳出、retirement→in retirementに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiemon&apos;s father, in retirement, Jurozaemon Nakafuyu CHIMURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>［隠居、減知、永蟄居］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Retirement, cutdown of territory, permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Retirement, cutdown of territory, permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Retirement, cutdown of territory, permanent house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>三千石以上寄合　大道寺主水直良</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriai more than 3000 koku Mondo Naoyoshi Daido-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriai more than 3000 koku Mondo Naoyoshi DAIDOJI.</e>
<cmt>Naoyoshi Daido-ji Temple→Naoyoshi DAIDOJIに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriai more than 3000 koku Mondo Naoyoshi DAIDOJI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>［隠居］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Retirement]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Retirement]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Retirement]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>五十俵、寄合　若井鍬吉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">50 bales, yoriai Kuwakichi WAKAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">50 bales, yoriai Kuwakichi WAKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">50 bales, yoriai Kuwakichi WAKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>［隠居、蟄居］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Retirement, house arrest]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Retirement, house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Retirement, house arrest]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>御用人御側掛、寄合　松井市兵衛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goyonin (officer handling domestic economy) hanging yoriai Ichibei MATSUI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goyonin (officer handling domestic economy) hanging yoriai Ichibei MATSUI.</e>
<cmt>hanging→「御側掛」の訳として正しいか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lord chamberlain, yoriai Ichibei MATSUI.</e>
<cmt>御側掛は「おそばがかり」と読み、hangingとは関係ないようです。御側御用人（おそば ごようにん）と解釈して、lord chamberlainとしました。Goyonin (officer handling domestic economy) hanging →lord chamberlain</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>御使番　進八郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) Shinhachiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) Shinhachiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Otsukaiban (a person responsible for order and patrol in the battlefield) Shinhachiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>寄合　天野儀兵衛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriai Gihei AMANO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriai Gihei AMANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriai Gihei AMANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>武野新左衛門二男、中奥御小姓格　名倉鉞之介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzaemon TAKENO second son, nakaoku (middle inner) servant Etsu no suke NAGURA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzaemon TAKENO&apos;s second son, Nakaoku page status, Etsunosuke NAGURA.</e>
<cmt>Shinzaemon TAKENO second son→Shinzaemon TAKENO&apos;s second son、nakaoku (middle inner) servant→Nakaoku page status、Etsu no suke→Etsunosukeとし、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzaemon TAKENO&apos;s second son, Nakaoku page status, Etsunosuke NAGURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>御書院番頭格　加藤五郎左衛門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshoinban (the shogun&apos;s body guard or the castle guard) leader Gorozaemon KATO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshoinban-gashira (leader of the shogun&apos;s body guard or the castle guard) status Gorozaemon KATO.</e>
<cmt>Gashoinban→Goshoinban-gashiraとし、leaderを補足内に移動、statusを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshoinban-gashira (leader of the shogun&apos;s body guard or the castle guard) status Gorozaemon KATO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>寿操院様御用役　本間太左衛門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The officer in Jusoin Futozaemon HONMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The officer for Jusoin, Futozaemon HONMA.</e>
<cmt>in Jusoin→for Jusoinとし、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The officer for Jusoin, Futozaemon HONMA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>錦織奉行格　本杉録兵衛</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishikiori bugyo (magistrate) Rokube MOTOSUGI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishikiori bugyo status, Rokube MOTOSUGI.</e>
<cmt>bugyo→既出のため補足削除、status追加、カンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishikiori bugyo status, Rokube MOTOSUGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>［隠居謹慎、減知］</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">[Abdication of the headship of a family and suspension from the office, cutdown of territory]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">[Abdication of the headship of a family and suspension from the office, cutdown of territory]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">[Abdication of the headship of a family and suspension from the office, cutdown of territory]</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>横井孫右衛門嫡子、千石以上寄合　横井孫太郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Magoemon YOKOI the legitimate child, yoriai more that 1000 koku Magotaro YOKOI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Magoemon YOKOI&apos;s legitimate child, yoriai more than 1000 koku Magotaro YOKOI.</e>
<cmt>Magoemon YOKOI the legitimate child→Magoemon YOKOI&apos;s legitimate childに修正、thanのスペルミス修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Magoemon YOKOI&apos;s legitimate child, yoriai more than 1000 koku Magotaro YOKOI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>沢井小左衛門嫡子、寄合　沢井溢也</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shozaemon SAWAI the legitimate child, yoriai Itsuya SAWAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shozaemon SAWAI&apos;s legitimate child, yoriai Itsuya SAWAI.</e>
<cmt>Shozaemon SAWAI the legitimate child→Shozaemon SAWAI&apos;s legitimate childに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shozaemon SAWAI&apos;s legitimate child, yoriai Itsuya SAWAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>発生原因諸説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The various theories on the cause and origin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The various theories on the cause and origin</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The various theories on the cause and origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>ふいご党の幕府軍加勢説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Fuigo party&apos;s back up for bakufu army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of the Fuigo party&apos;s back up for the bakufu army</e>
<cmt>the Fuigo party、the bakufu armyとし、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of the Fuigo party&apos;s back up for the bakufu army</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>江戸在府中の竹腰兵部少輔の呼びかけに応じ、ふいご党が幼君義宜を擁して江戸へ向かい、幕府軍に加勢する、という動きがあったというもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory says that due to the call from Hyobu shoyu TAKENOKOSHI, Fuigo party went down to Edo with princeling Yoshinori and supported for bakufu army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory says that due to the call from Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu, the Fuigo party went down to Edo with princeling Yoshinori and supported for the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>表記統一のため、Hyobu shoyu TAKENOKOSHI→Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyuとし、the Fuigo party、the bakufu armyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory says that due to the call from Takenokoshi Hyobu shoyu, the Fuigo party went down to Edo with princeling Yoshinori and supported for the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>監察吉田知行が城代間宮正萬の内報として慶勝に知らせた内容がこれである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the contents that supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA told Yoshikatsu as a tip from the castle keeper Shoman MAMIYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the contents that supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA told Yoshikatsu as a tip from the castle keeper Shoman MAMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the contents that supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA told Yoshikatsu as a tip from the castle keeper Shoman MAMIYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>岩倉具視と金鉄組による謀略説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conspiracy theory by Tomomi IWAKURA and Kanetetsu group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conspiracy theory by Tomomi IWAKURA and the Kanetetsu group</e>
<cmt>the Kanetetsu groupとし、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conspiracy theory by Tomomi IWAKURA and the Kanetetsu group</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>当時、慶勝は徳川慶喜の辞官納地問題に際し、領地返上に反対の立場をとっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, Yoshikatsu took the stance to oppose to giving up the territories on Jikan nochi (an order for surrendering the Shogunate post and domains to the Imperial court) of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, Yoshikatsu took the stance to oppose to giving up the territories on Jikan nochi (an order for surrendering the Shogunate post and domains to the Imperial Court) of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>前出の表記に合わせ、Imperial court→Imperial Courtとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, Yoshikatsu took the stance to oppose to giving up the territories on Jikan nochi (an order for surrendering the Shogunate post and domains to the Imperial Court) of Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>これに対して業を煮やした岩倉具視が、上の加勢説を尾張藩金鉄組の家臣と共謀してでっちあげ、または噂を利用し、朝命の名の下に慶勝に旗幟を鮮明にするよう脅迫した、というもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Exasperated by this, Tomomi IWAKURA conspired with the retainers of Kanetetsu group in Owari Domain to make up the above back-up theory or used the rumor, and in the name of order of Imperial court, threatened Yoshikatsu to show a bold front.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Exasperated by this, Tomomi IWAKURA conspired with the retainers of the Kanetetsu group in the Owari Domain to make up the above back-up theory or used the rumor, and in the name of order of the Imperial Court, threatened Yoshikatsu to show a bold front.</e>
<cmt>the Kanetetsu group、the Owari Domain、the Imeprial Courtとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Exasperated by this, Tomomi IWAKURA conspired with the retainers of the Kanetetsu group in the Owari Domain to make up the above back-up theory or used the rumor, and in the name of order of the Imperial Court, threatened Yoshikatsu to show a bold front.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>長州藩の復讐説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Choshu Domain&apos;s revenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of the Choshu Domain&apos;s revenge</e>
<cmt>the Choshu Domainとし、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of the Choshu Domain&apos;s revenge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>第一次長州征伐において、慶勝は征長総督を務めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first conquest of Choshu Yoshikatsu became Sotoku of Seicho (governor conquering of Choshu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first conquest of Choshu Yoshikatsu became Sotoku of Seicho (governor conquering of Choshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first conquest of Choshu Yoshikatsu became Sotoku of Seicho (governor conquering of Choshu).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>戦争そのものは長州藩が謝罪して終わったものの、長州藩家老3人と藩士11人が切腹し、征長軍は2度にわたり首実検を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war itself was over with the apology of Choshu Domain, but the three chief retainers and eleven feudal retainers of domain committed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and conquering army of Choshu identified severed heads two times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war itself was over with the apology of the Choshu Domain, but the three chief retainers and eleven feudal retainers of the domain committed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and conquering army of Choshu identified severed heads twice.</e>
<cmt>the Choshu Domain、the domainとし、two times→twiceに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war itself was over with the apology of the Choshu Domain, but the three chief retainers and eleven feudal retainers of the domain committed Seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) and conquering army of Choshu identified severed heads twice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>これが2度も辱めを与えた、として長州藩が恨みを持っていた、というもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This gave two humiliations and Choshu Domain bore a grudge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This gave two humiliations and the Choshu Domain bore a grudge.</e>
<cmt>the Choshu Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This gave two humiliations and the Choshu Domain bore a grudge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>ちなみに、本事件で斬首になったのは重臣3人、藩士11人で、奇妙なことに符合している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact in this incident, the number of senior vassals who were decapitated was three and the one of feudal retainers was eleven, which were of one accord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact in this incident, the number of senior vassals who were decapitated was three and the one of feudal retainers was eleven, which were of one accord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact in this incident, the number of senior vassals who were decapitated was three and the one of feudal retainers was eleven, which were of one accord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="83">
<j>薩摩藩の復讐説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Satsuma Domain&apos;s revenge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of the Satsuma Domain&apos;s revenge</e>
<cmt>the Satsuma Domainとし、ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of the Satsuma Domain&apos;s revenge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>宝暦4年（1754年）から5年（1755年）にかけて、薩摩藩は美濃国木曽三川の治水工事を命ぜられたが、幕府側による再三の工事変更命令、地元名士の非協力などに苦しめられ、完成までに切腹51名、病死33名を出し、総指揮者の家老平田靱負も全責任を負って自決するという悲劇を生んだ（宝暦治水事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1754 to 1755 Satsuma Domain was ordered to do flood prevention works of Kisosansen in Mino Province, but the bakufu changed the order repeatedly and Satsuma Domain suffered from no cooperation of the local prominent figures, and until the completion the fifty-one committed Seppuku and the thirty-three died of sickness and the chief retainer and general manager, Yukie HIRATA tragically committed suicide to take his responsibility (the Horeki flood control Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1754 to 1755 the Satsuma Domain was ordered to do flood prevention works of Kiso-sansen (Kiso Three Rivers) in Mino Province, but the bakufu changed the order repeatedly and the Satsuma Domain suffered from no cooperation of the local prominent figures, and until the completion the fifty-one committed Seppuku and the thirty-three died of sickness and the chief retainer and general manager, Yukie HIRATA tragically committed suicide to take his responsibility (the Horeki flood control Incident).</e>
<cmt>the Satsuma Domainとし、Kisosansen→Kiso-sansenとし、補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1754 to 1755 the Satsuma Domain was ordered to do flood prevention works of Kiso-sansen (Kiso Three Rivers) in Mino Province, but the bakufu changed the order repeatedly and the Satsuma Domain suffered from no cooperation of the local prominent figures, and until the completion the fifty-one committed Seppuku and the thirty-three died of sickness and the chief retainer and general manager, Yukie HIRATA tragically committed suicide to take his responsibility (the Horeki flood control Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>このとき、治水工事地域を藩領としていたのが尾張藩であったので、その恨みを持たれていた、というもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time the area of flood prevention works was in the land of Owari Domain, which caused the grudge on them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time the area of flood prevention works was in the land of the Owari Domain, which caused the grudge on them.</e>
<cmt>the Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time the area of flood prevention works was in the land of the Owari Domain, which caused the grudge on them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="86">
<j>徳川慶勝の保身説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA&apos;s self-protection.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA&apos;s self-protection</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory of Yoshikatsu TOKUGAWA&apos;s self-protection</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>尾張藩は御三家筆頭、その名古屋城は幕府の西に対する防御施設であったため、いくら慶勝が朝廷よりの姿勢をとっても常に疑いの目で見られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Owari Domain was the head of gosanke (three privileged branches) and the Nagoya-jo Castle was the bakufu&apos;s defending facility against the west, Yoshikatsu was always seen with suspicion though he took the stance near to Imperial court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Owari Domain was the head of gosanke (three privileged branches) and the Nagoya-jo Castle was the bakufu&apos;s defending facility against the west, Yoshikatsu was always seen with suspicion though he took the stance near to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>the Owari Domain、the Imperial Courtとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Owari Domain was the head of gosanke (three privileged branches) and the Nagoya-jo Castle was the bakufu&apos;s defending facility against the west, Yoshikatsu was always seen with suspicion though he took the stance near to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>よって、倒幕後の自分の立場を守るために、あえて藩内の佐幕派を一掃する必要があった、というもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, in order to defend his position after overthrowing the Shogunate, he had to clear Sabaku-ha away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, in order to defend his position after overthrowing the Shogunate, he had to clear Sabaku-ha in the domain away.</e>
<cmt>「藩内の」→訳漏れのため訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, in order to defend his position after overthrowing the Shogunate, he had to clear Sabaku-ha in the domain away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>しかしこれは、まだ幕府の敗北が固まった時期ではないため、少々疑わしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this is a bit suspicious because of the time when the bakufu was not yet overthrown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this is a bit suspicious because of the time when the bakufu was not yet overthrown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is a bit suspicious because of the time when the bakufu was not yet overthrown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that</e>
<cmt>ピリオド削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>この事件の結果、尾張藩は官軍の一員として各地で幕府軍と戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this incident, Owari Domain fought with the army of bakufu in various places as members of Imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this incident, the Owari Domain fought with the army of the bakufu in various places as members of Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>the Owari Domain、the bakufuとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this incident, the Owari Domain fought with the army of the bakufu in various places as members of Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>しかし、それによって得た果実はあまりに少なかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they got little fruit by the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they got little fruit by the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they got little fruit by the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>まず、成瀬家、竹腰家がともに大名として認められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Firstly, Naruse family, Takenokoshi family were both admitted as daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, the Naruse family and Takenokoshi family were both admitted as daimyo.</e>
<cmt>the Naruse family and Takenokoshi familyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, the Naruse family and Takenokoshi family were both admitted as daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>これは尾張藩にとって思いもかけないことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a surprise for Owari Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a surprise for the Owari Domain.</e>
<cmt>the Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a surprise for the Owari Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>特に竹腰家は、青松葉事件の対象であるふいご党の領袖であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially Takenokoshi family was the leader of Fuigo party which was the object of Aomatsuba Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially the Takenokoshi family was the leader of the Fuigo party which was the object of Aomatsuba Incident.</e>
<cmt>the Takenokoshi family、the Fuigo partyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially the Takenokoshi family was the leader of the Fuigo party which was the object of Aomatsuba Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この矛盾した措置に、尾張藩は混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owari Domain was confused by this contradictory measure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Owari Domain was confused by this contradictory measure.</e>
<cmt>The Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Owari Domain was confused by this contradictory measure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="96">
<j>次に新政府内での立場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the position in a new government was also a problem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the position in a new government was also a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the position in a new government was also a problem.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>めぼしい官職には尾張藩士の姿はほとんどなく、薩長土肥に独占された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notable government post had little Owari clansman and was dominated by the men of Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa, Hizen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notable government post had little Owari clansman and was dominated by the men of Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa, Hizen.</e>
<cmt>一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Few members of the Owari clan held notable government posts, with these being dominated by members of the Satsuma, Choshu, Tosa, Hizen clans.</e>
<cmt>little →few</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>その後も、大臣までにのぼったのは、田中不二麿（国之輔）と加藤高明だけであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that it was only Fujimaro TANAKA (Kuni no suke) and Takaaki KATO who went up to the ministers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that it was only Fujimaro (Kuninosuke) TANAKA and Takaaki KATO who went up to the ministers.</e>
<cmt>Kuni no suke→Kuninosukeとし、位置を移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that it was only Fujimaro (Kuninosuke) TANAKA and Takaaki KATO who went up to the ministers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="99">
<j>また、廃藩置県においても冷遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And they were treated unkindly in Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And they were treated unkindly in Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And they were treated unkindly in Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>他の官軍の藩（鹿児島藩、山口藩、高知藩、佐賀藩、広島藩、秋田藩など）は軒並み県名には藩都の名が採用されたにもかかわらず、名古屋の名は県名に採用されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the other Imperial army&apos;s Domains (Kagoshima Domain, Yamaguchi Domain, Kochi Domain, Saga Domain, Hiroshima Domain, Akita Domain and so on), the names of capital city in Domain were equally adopted for the names of Prefecture, but the name of Nagoya was not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the other Imperial army&apos;s Domains (Kagoshima Domain, Yamaguchi Domain, Kochi Domain, Saga Domain, Hiroshima Domain, Akita Domain and so on), the names of each domain&apos;s capital city were equally adopted for the names of each prefecture, but the name of Nagoya was not.</e>
<cmt>the names of capital city in Domain→the names of each domain&apos;s capital city、the names of Prefecture→the names of each prefectureとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of Nagoya, the name of the capital city in an imperial army domain was adopted as the name of the prefecture (e.g. Kagoshima, Yamaguchi, Kochi, Saga, Hiroshima, and Akita).</e>
<cmt>一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>特に官軍として活躍したわけではない紀州藩が和歌山県の名を残したのとは対照的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Contrastively the name of Wakayama remained in Kishu Domain which did not make a strong showing as Imperial army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrastively the name of Wakayama remained in the Kishu Domain which did not make a strong showing as Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>the Kishu Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrastively the name of Wakayama remained in the Kishu Domain which did not make a strong showing as Imperial army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="102">
<j>結局、尾張藩は御三家筆頭という立場に安住しすぎ、幕末において政治・外交力を発揮する機会をことごとく逃し、常に事後処理に追われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, Owari Domain felt too safe in the position of the leader of gosanke to lose every opportunity of exerting the political and diplomatic power in the end of Edo period and was constantly forced to wind up matters after.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, the Owari Domain felt too safe in the position of the leader of gosanke to lose every opportunity of exerting the political and diplomatic power in the end of the Edo period and was constantly forced to wind up matters after.</e>
<cmt>the Owari Domain、the Edo periodとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, the Owari Domain felt too safe in its position as leader of the gosanke to lose any opportunity to exert its political and diplomatic power toward the end of the Edo period, and was constantly being forced to resolve matters thereafter.</e>
<cmt>一部修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>逆にその威光を幕府側にも官軍側にも利用され、利用価値がなくなれば省みられなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, the prestige was exploited both by bakufu side and Imperial army side and when the utility value was lost, Owari Domain was deserted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, the prestige was exploited both by the bakufu side and the Imperial army side and when the utility value was lost, the Owari Domain was deserted.</e>
<cmt>the bakufu side、the Imperial army side、the Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, the prestige was exploited both by the bakufu side and the Imperial army side and when the utility value was lost, the Owari Domain was deserted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>尾張藩にはそれを見返す力もなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Owari Domain had no power to go over it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Owari Domain had no power to go over it.</e>
<cmt>The Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Owari Domain had no power to go over it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>青松葉事件の発生も、尾張藩の拙劣な政治・外交の結果であり、その犠牲者数の割には、歴史に与えた影響度合いが小さかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aomatsuba Incident was a result of poor politics and diplomacy of Owari Domain and for the number of victims it had little influence on history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Aomatsuba Incident was a result of poor politics and diplomacy of the Owari Domain and for the number of victims it had little influence on history.</e>
<cmt>The Aomatsuba Incident、the Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Aomatsuba Incident was a result of poor politics and diplomacy of the Owari Domain and for the number of victims it had little influence on history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="106">
<j>なお後年、慶勝による北海道八雲町開拓のため移住した士族たちは、京都にいた慶勝に尾張藩の情勢を告げた監察吉田知行をはじめ、この事件に関係した者も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And later, among shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors), who moved to Yakumo cho in Hokkaido following the development by Yoshikatsu, there were many of those who were involved with this incident, such as a supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA who told the situation of Owari Domain to Yoshikatsu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And later, among shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors), who moved to Yakumo-cho in Hokkaido following the development by Yoshikatsu, there were many of those who were involved with this incident, such as a supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA who told the situation of the Owari Domain to Yoshikatsu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Yakumo-cho、the Owari Domainとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And later, among shizoku (family or person with samurai ancestors), who moved to Yakumo-cho in Hokkaido following the development by Yoshikatsu, there were many of those who were involved with this incident, such as a supervision Tomoyuki YOSHIDA who told the situation of the Owari Domain to Yoshikatsu in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 目白梅(id:141468), Yonoemon(id:55450), 下総大納言(id:43461), たね(id:10372), Reggaeman(id:6214), KAMUI(id:9330), Kahyoe(id:178277), 松茸(id:27535), Nonomura(id:72557), Klaus Tennstedt(id:25513), Point136(id:211299), Yanahan(id:2437), Hddsd(id:99893), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>