<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>御注孝経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; (annotated edition of Kokyo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; (Annotated Edition of the Kokyo)</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyochukokyo</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションを削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>御注孝経（ぎょうちゅうこうきょう）とは、唐の玄宗 (唐)によって撰述された『孝経』の注釈書。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; is the commentaries for &quot;Kokyo&quot; (the book of filial piety) compiled by Genso (Tang).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; is a collection of commentaries on the &quot;Kokyo&quot; (Classic of Filial Piety) compiled by Genso (Tang).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; is a collection of commentaries on the &quot;Kokyo&quot; (Classic of Filial Piety) compiled by Genso (Emperor Xuanzong [Tang]).</e>
<cmt>玄宗　に補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>開元10年（720年）に著された開元始注本と天宝 (唐)2年（743年）に改訂して3年後に頒布した天宝重注本の2種類があるが、現存しているのは後者である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were two kinds of Gyochukokyo; one was &quot;Kaigenshichubon&quot; (annotated edition by Kaigenshi) written in 720 and the other was Tenhojuchubon (annotated edition by Tenhoju) revised in 743 and distributed three years later, but only the latter is existing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were two kinds of Gyochukokyo, one being &quot;Kaigenshichubon&quot; (annotated edition by Kaigenshi), which was written in 720, and the other being Tenhojuchubon (annotated edition by Tenhoju), which was revised in 743 and distributed three years later; however, only the latter remains in existence.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were two kinds of Gyochukokyo, one being &quot;Kaigenshichubon&quot; (annotated edition by Genso), which was written in 720, and the other being Tenhojuchubon (revised edition of Kaigenshichubon), which was revised in 743 and distributed three years later; however, only the latter remains in existence.</e>
<cmt>開元始注本は、玄宗自らが注釈したものであるようですので、annotated edition by Genso と補足をしました。天宝重注本は、上記を改良したものであるようですので、revised edition of Kaigenshichubon としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>全1巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Single volume.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Single volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Single volume.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>『孝経』は、焚書坑儒の煽りを受けて一時所在が不明となり、前漢に入って2種類の系統の本が再発見され、その字体から「古文」・「今文」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kokyo&quot; had once not been located as a result of the Burning of books and burying of scholars, and two types of editions were rediscovered in the Former Han period, and called &quot;Kinbun&quot; and &quot;Kobun&quot; respectively from their character style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kokyo&quot; had once disappeared as a result of the &quot;Burning of books and burying of scholars&quot; in Ancient China; however, two editions were rediscovered during the Former Han period, and were called &quot;Kinbun&quot; and &quot;Kobun,&quot; respectively, due to their font style.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kokyo&quot; had once disappeared as a result of the &quot;Burning of books and burying of scholars&quot; in Ancient China; however, two editions were rediscovered during the Former Han period, and were called &apos;Kobun&apos; and &apos;Kinbun,&apos; respectively, due to their font style.</e>
<cmt>一部 &quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後に「古文」には孔安国の、「今文」には鄭玄による注釈が付けられて広く用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, commentaries were added to &quot;Kinbun&quot; by Ko Ankoku and to &quot;Kobun&quot; by Teigen and they became widely-used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commentaries were later added to &quot;Kinbun&quot; by Ko Ankoku and to &quot;Kobun&quot; by Teigen, and both became widely used.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commentaries were later added to &apos;Kobun&apos; by Ko Ankoku (Kong Anguo) and to &apos;Kinbun&apos; by Teigen (Zheng Xuan), and both became widely used.</e>
<cmt>孔安国、鄭玄　読みを追加しました。「古文」「今文」　逆になっておりますので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>ところが、「古文」・「今文」ともに再発見の経緯から「偽書」であるとする疑惑を抱えており、特に唐代に入ると、どちらを『孝経』の正本と考えるかという認識の違いから、「古文」派と「今文」派に分かれて相手の系統を「偽書」とする攻撃を繰り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were suspicions of apocryphal book for both &quot;Kinbun&quot; and &quot;Kobun&quot; due to the situation of their rediscovery, and especially in the period of Tang Dynasty, people split into the Kinbun school and the Kobun school and accused each other of being an &quot;apocryphal book&quot; as there was a big perception gap between them of which one they regarded as the original Kokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were suspicions of the books being apocryphal due to the fact that they were rediscovered, and especially during the period of Tang Dynasty, two distinct schools were formed, the Kinbun school and the Kobun school, both accused the other of being the apocryphal book.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were suspicions that the books may be fake due to the circumstances in which they were rediscovered, and during the Tang Dynasty, two distinct schools were formed—the &apos;Kobun&apos; school and the &apos;Kinbun&apos; school—as a result of a difference in opinion regarding which was the authentic &quot;Kokyo&quot; book, with both accused the other of following a &apos;forged book.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「古文」「今文」　逆になっておりますので、修正しました。「再発見の経緯」→situation in which they were rediscovered としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そこで玄宗は両派の儒学者を集めて論争を行わせたものの、決着が付かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So Genso got together Confucian scholars of both schools and made them debate but ended in inconclusive results.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To remediate this problem, Genso brought together Confucian scholars of both schools and had them hold a debate, which ended with inconclusive results.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To remediate this problem, Genso brought together Confucian scholars of both schools and had them hold a debate, which ended with inconclusive results.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで、学識に優れた玄宗自らが公定の注釈書を作成して事態の収拾を図ろうとしたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Genso, who was a person of great attainments, tried to settle the situation by developing an official commentary himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a distinguished scholar, Genso himself tried to settle the situation by forming an official commentary.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a distinguished scholar, Genso himself tried to settle the situation by forming an official commentary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>玄宗は「今文」を基本としながらも、孔安国・鄭玄・韋昭・王粛らの注釈のうち優れたものを採用し、これら諸説を斟酌しながら注釈を加えたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genso was said that he thought &quot;Kinbun&quot; as the basic but he adopted the best commentaries among those by Ko Ankoku, Teigen, I Sho, or O Shuku, and added his commentary taking these theories into consideration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genso believed the &quot;Kinbun&quot; to be the base, and he wrote his commentaries while adopting those written by Ko Ankoku, Teigen, I Sho, and O Shuku.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genso believed the &apos;Kinbun&apos; to be the base, and he wrote his commentaries while adopting those written by Ko Ankoku, Teigen, I Sho (Wei Zhao), and O Shuku (Wang Su).</e>
<cmt>韋昭・王粛　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>玄宗は君主が率先して孝を行うことを天下を安定させ、臣下はそうした主君の振舞いを見習うことを責務として考え、「君徳の涵養」と「主従の分別」を重要視したものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genso thought that a ruler should take the lead in doing filial duty and stabilize the country and retainers were responsible for emulating the load&apos;s behaviors, so he placed special emphasis on &quot;Kuntoku no Kanyo&quot; (cultivation by virtue) and &quot;Shuju no Funbetsu&quot; (discretion to the relation between master and servant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genso believed that a ruler taking the lead in displaying filial piety is able to stabilize the country, and that retainers are obliged to emulate the load&apos;s behaviors, so he placed particular emphasis on &quot;Kuntoku no Kanyo&quot; (fostering of virtue) and &quot;Shuju no Funbetsu&quot; (categorization of master and servant).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genso believed that a ruler taking the lead in displaying filial piety is able to stabilize the country, and that retainers are obliged to emulate the lord&apos;s behaviors, so he placed particular emphasis on &apos;Kuntoku no Kanyo&apos; (fostering of virtue) and &apos;Shuju no Funbetsu&apos; (categorization of master and servant).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これが同書を「天子の書」と看做すようになった所以である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the root cause why his edition has been regarded as &quot;Tenshi no sho&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s book).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the main reason why his edition has been regarded as the &quot;Tenshi no sho&quot; (the Emperor&apos;s book).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the main reason why his edition has been regarded as the &apos;Tenshi no sho&apos; (the Emperor&apos;s book).</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>同書の頒布以後、公式の場での『孝経』講義・解釈は全てこれに従うようになり、既存の注釈は廃れていく事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After distribution of this edition, all the lectures and commentaries of &quot;Kokyo&quot; followed this and the existing commentaries started to become obsolete.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After distribution of this edition, all lectures and commentaries of &quot;Kokyo&quot; followed suit, and conventional commentaries became obsolete.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After distribution of this edition, all lectures and commentaries of &quot;Kokyo&quot; followed suit, and conventional commentaries became obsolete.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>だが、同書は注釈部分が全部で約2,800字であり、鄭玄注釈の約2,000字よりは多いものの、孔安国注釈の約8,800字よりは遥かに少なく注釈書として決して十分なものといえなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the commentary part of the edition had 2,800 characters in total and had more characters than Teigen&apos;s of 2000 characters, it was much fewer than Ko Ankoku&apos;s, about 8,800 characters, and was far from adequate commentaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the commentary of this edition had 2,800 characters in total, and had more than Teigen&apos;s 2000 characters, it was much fewer than Ko Ankoku&apos;s, which was about 8,800 characters, and was far from being an adequate commentary.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the commentary of this edition had 2,800 characters in total, and had more than Teigen&apos;s 2,000 characters, it was much fewer than Ko Ankoku&apos;s, which was about 8,800 characters, and was far from being an adequate commentary.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そこで、北宋の真宗 (宋)の命を受けた邢昺が注疏を作成（「十三経十三経注疏本」）し、これを『孝経正義』と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Kei Hei who received an order from Zhenzong of Song of Northern Song Dynasty developed chuso (&quot;Jusankyo chuso&quot; (annotation and interpretation learning of Thirteen Classics)) and named this &quot;Kokyoseigi.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Kei Hei, who received an order from Zhenzong of Song of Northern the Song Dynasty, created the chuso (&quot;Jusankyo chuso&quot; (annotation and interpretation learning of Thirteen Classics)) and named it &quot;Kokyoseigi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Kei Hei (Xing Bing), who received an order from Shinso (Zhenzong) (Song) of Northern Song Dynasty, created the chuso (&apos;Jusankyo chuso&apos; [annotation and interpretation learning of Thirteen Classics]) and named it &quot;Kokyoseigi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>邢昺、真宗 (宋)　読みを追加しました。　&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>日本では、平安時代の貞観 (日本)2年10月16日（860年11月2日）に、大学博士大春日雄継の働きかけによって、今後『孝経』の注釈には学令において『孝経』の注釈書として定められた孔安国・鄭玄の注を用いずに『御注孝経』を用いる詔が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, on November 2, 860, with an appeal by OKASUGA no Otsugu, Daigaku hakase (university professor), a Mikotonori (imperial edict) was issued to decide to use &quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; for the commentaries of &quot;Kokyo&quot; from then on and not to use the commentaries by Ko Ankoku and Teigen that had been set as the commentaries of &quot;Kokyo&quot; under the order of school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, on November 2, 860, with an appeal by Daigaku hakase (university professor) OKASUGA no Otsugu, a Mikotonori (imperial edict) was issued to use the &quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; for commentaries of the &quot;Kokyo&quot; henceforth, and not to use the commentaries by Ko Ankoku and Teigen that had been set under the school&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, on November 6, 860, with an appeal by Daigaku hakase (university professor) OKASUGA no Otsugu, a Mikotonori (imperial edict) was issued to use the &quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; for commentaries of the &quot;Kokyo&quot; henceforth, and not to use the commentaries by Ko Ankoku and Teigen that had been set under the school&apos;s order.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、これに先立って同年2月から12月にかけて、大春日雄継によって当時12歳の清和天皇に対して『御注孝経』の講義が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to that, from February to December of the same year, OKASUGA no Otsugu gave lectures on &quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; to the-twelve-year-old Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to this, from February to December of the same year, OKASUGA no Otsugu gave lectures on &quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; to the twelve year old Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to this, from March of the same year to January of the next year, OKASUGA no Otsugu gave lectures on &quot;Gyochukokyo&quot; to the 12-year-old Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その背景について、幼少の清和天皇が外祖父藤原良房の政治権力によって、異母兄惟喬親王を推す世論に反して擁立されたことに由来する政治基盤の不安定さを克服するために、幼い天皇の君徳の涵養を図るとともに、天皇への忠誠を官人教育を通じて強く認識させる目的によって、藤原良房と大春日雄継が導入を図ったものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind this, it is believed that FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and OKASUGA no Otsugu adopted the edition with the purpose to give government official (esp. one of low to medium rank) an official education to foster allegiance to the Emperor as well as to cultivate &quot;Kuntoku no Kanyo&quot; (cultivation by virtue) for young Emperor Seiwa and tried to conquer instability of political foundation which was caused by enthroning infant Emperor Seiwa with the backing of the political power of his maternal grandfather, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa against the public opinion that pushed for his half brother, Imperial Prince Koretaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and OKASUGA no Otsugu adopted this edition with the purpose of giving government officials an official education to foster allegiance to the Emperor, as well as to foster &quot;Kuntoku no Kanyo&quot; (foster of virtue) in the young Emperor Seiwa, thereby tried to overcome the instability of political foundation, which was caused by the enthroning of the infant Emperor Seiwa, with the help of the political power of his maternal grandfather, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, though against public opinion that pushed for his half-brother, Imperial Prince Koretaka.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa and OKASUGA no Otsugu adopted this edition with the purpose of giving government officials an official education to foster allegiance to the Emperor, as well as to foster &quot;Kuntoku no Kanyo&quot; in the young Emperor Seiwa, thereby tried to overcome the instability of political foundation, which was caused by the enthroning of the infant Emperor Seiwa, with the help of the political power of his maternal grandfather, FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa, against public opinion that pushed for his paternal older half-brother, Imperial Prince Koretaka.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を追加しました。異母兄　表現を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、同詔では漢詩などの文学材料としても用いられていた孔安国の注釈に関しては、天皇及び皇族の教育以外の場では引き続き使用が認められており、この導入が大学寮全体の支持すら得られていなかった政治的なものであったことを裏付けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Mikotonori, the commentaries by Ko Ankoku that were used as a literature material such as Chinese poetry were permitted to use continually in other than an education of Emperors and the Imperial family, which supported the fact that this adoption was only for seeking political advantage and had not gained support of the entire Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Mikotonori, the commentaries by Ko Ankoku that were used as a literary reference, such as in Chinese poetry, were permitted to be continually used in education other than that of Emperors and the Imperial family, which supports the fact that this adoption was only to seek political advantage and did not gain support of the whole Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education under the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Mikotonori, the commentaries by Ko Ankoku that were used as a literary reference, such as in Chinese poetry, were permitted to be continually used in education other than that of Emperors and the Imperial Family, which supports the fact that this adoption was only to seek political advantage and did not even gain support of the whole Daigakuryo (Bureau of Education under the Ritsuryo system).</e>
<cmt>他記事と統一して、Daigakuryo としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), Mooko(id:36162), Clarin(id:60278), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>