<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>茨木童子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ibaraki Doji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ibaraki Doji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ibaraki Doji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>茨木童子（いばらきどうじ）は、平安時代に大江山を本拠に京都を荒らし回ったとされる「鬼」の一人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ibaraki Doji was a Heian-period oni (a mythical creature resembling a demon or ogre) who supposedly went on a rampage in Kyoto from his lair on Mt. Oe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ibaraki Doji was a Heian-period oni (a mythical creature resembling a demon or ogre) who supposedly went on a rampage in Kyoto from his lair on Mt. Oe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ibaraki Doji was a Heian-period oni (a mythical creature resembling a demon or ogre) who supposedly went on a rampage in Kyoto from his lair on Mt. Oe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>酒呑童子（しゅてんどうじ）の最も重要な家来であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was the most powerful henchman of the infamous Shuten Doji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was the most powerful henchman of the infamous Shuten Doji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was the most powerful henchman of the infamous Shuten Doji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>出生地には、摂津国（大阪府茨木市水尾、または兵庫県尼崎市富松）という説と、越後国（新潟県旧栃尾市、現在の長岡市の軽井沢集落）という説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two theories about his birthplace: one claims he was born in Settsu province (either in Mizuo in the city of Ibaraki in modern-day Osaka Prefecture, or in Tomimatsu in the city of Amagasaki in present-day Hyogo Pref.), while the other holds that he was born in Echigo province (specifically in the town of Karuizawa, which is located in the city of Nagaoka--formerly known as Tochigo--in modern-day Niigata Pref.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two theories about his birthplace: one claims he was born in Settsu province (either in Mizuo in the city of Ibaraki in modern-day Osaka Prefecture, or in Tomimatsu in the city of Amagasaki in present-day Hyogo Pref.), while the other holds that he was born in Echigo province (specifically in the town of Karuizawa, which is located in the city of Nagaoka--formerly known as Tochigo--in modern-day Niigata Pref.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two theories about his birthplace: one claims he was born in Settsu Province (either in modern-day Mizuo, Ibaraki City, Osaka Prefecture, or in Tomimatsu, Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture), while the other holds that he was born in Echigo Province (specifically in the town of Karuizawa, which is located in Nagaoka City--formerly known as Tochio--in modern-day Niigata Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>場所表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>生まれた頃から歯が生え揃っていた、巨体であったなど周囲から恐れられ、鬼と化した後は酒呑童子と出会い舎弟となり、共に京を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Legend has it that his most fearsome characteristics included having all his teeth at birth and being of enormous size, which struck fear into the hearts of all his neighbors; after transforming into an oni, he encountered Shuten Doji and became his underling, and then together they plotted to terrorize the capital (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Legend has it that his most fearsome characteristics included having all his teeth at birth and being of enormous size, which struck fear into the hearts of all his neighbors; after transforming into an oni, he encountered Shuten Doji and became his underling, and then together they plotted to terrorize the capital (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Legend has it that his most fearsome characteristics included having all his teeth at birth and being of enormous size, which struck fear into the hearts of all his neighbors; after transforming into an oni, he encountered Shuten Doji and became his underling, and then together they plotted to terrorize the capital (Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>酒呑童子一味は大江山（丹波国にあったとされるが、現在の京都市と亀岡市の境にある大枝山という説もある）を拠点にし、京の貴族の子女を誘拐するなど乱暴狼藉をはたらいたが、源頼光と4人の家臣たち（頼光四天王）によって滅ぼされたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lair of Shuten Doji and his gang was on Mt. Oe (which is generally thought to have been located in Tanba province, but a competing theory holds that &quot;Mt. Oe&quot; actually refers to the Mt. Oe on the border of the modern-day cities of Kyoto and Kameoka); according to legend, they committed various outrages, for example kidnapping the children of noblemen in Kyoto, until they were laid low by MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu and his four retainers (known as &quot;Yorimitsu&apos;s Four Heavenly Warriors&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Although literally the term would be &quot;Four Heavenly Kings,&quot; it is their martial prowess being celebrated, so I translated it &quot;Four Heavenly Warriors.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lair of Shuten Doji and his gang was on Mt. Oe (which is generally thought to have been located in Tanba province, but a competing theory holds that &quot;Mt. Oe&quot; actually refers to the Mt. Oe on the border of the modern-day cities of Kyoto and Kameoka); according to legend, they committed various outrages, for example kidnapping the children of noblemen in Kyoto, until they were laid low by MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu and his four retainers (known as &quot;Yorimitsu&apos;s Four Heavenly Warriors&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lair of Shuten Doji and his gang was on Mt. Oe (which is generally thought to have been located in Tanba Province, but a competing theory holds that &quot;Mt. Oe&quot; in fact refers to the Mt. Oe on the border of the modern-day cities of Kyoto and Kameoka); according to legend, they committed various outrages, for example kidnapping the children of noblemen in Kyoto, until they were laid low by MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu and his four retainers (known as &quot;Yorimitsu&apos;s Four Heavenly Warriors&quot;).</e>
<cmt>スペル&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし茨木童子は逃げ延びたとされ、その後も頼光四天王の一人である渡辺綱と一条戻り橋や羅生門で戦った故事が後世の説話集や能、謡曲、歌舞伎などで語り継がれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it is said that Ibaraki Doji managed to escape, and accounts of his subsequent duels with WATANABE no Tsuna, one of Yorimitsu&apos;s Four Heavenly Warriors, on Ichijo modoribashi bridge and at Rashomon gate have been passed down over the years as entries in collections of setsuwa tales as well as in Noh plays, Noh songs, and Kabuki plays.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it is said that Ibaraki Doji managed to escape, and accounts of his subsequent duels with WATANABE no Tsuna, one of Yorimitsu&apos;s Four Heavenly Warriors, on Ichijo modoribashi bridge and at Rashomon gate have been passed down over the years as entries in collections of setsuwa tales as well as in Noh plays, Noh songs, and Kabuki plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it is said that Ibaraki Doji managed to escape, and accounts of his subsequent duels with WATANABE no Tsuna, one of Yorimitsu&apos;s Four Heavenly Warriors, on Ichijo modoribashi bridge and at Rashomon gate have been passed down over the years as entries in collections of setsuwa tales as well as in Noh plays, Noh songs, and Kabuki plays.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theories of where he was born</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theories of where he was born</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theories of where he was born</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>越後説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory that he was born in Echigo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory that he was born in Echigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory that he was born in Echigo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>茨木童子（ここでは茨城童子とも書く）は酒呑童子と同じく越後国出身との説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory holds that Ibaraki Doji (the &quot;Ibaraki&quot; in this telling is also sometimes written with alternate characters) was born, like Shuten Doji, in Echigo province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory holds that Ibaraki Doji (the &quot;Ibaraki&quot; in this telling is also sometimes written with alternate characters) was born, like Shuten Doji, in Echigo province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory holds that Ibaraki Doji (the &quot;Ibaraki&quot; in this telling is also sometimes written with alternate characters) was born, like Shuten Doji, in Echigo Province.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>酒呑童子は蒲原郡の砂子塚（現・新潟県分水町砂子塚）生まれで国上寺の稚児だったが、茨木童子は古志郡の山奥の軽井沢（現・新潟県長岡市軽井沢）の生まれでやはり弥彦神社に預けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shuten Doji was born in Sunakozuka in Kanbara county (modern-day Sunakozuka in the town of Bunsui in Niigata Pref.) and served as a page-boy of Kokujoji temple, whereas Ibaraki Doji was supposedly born deep in the mountains at Karuizawa in Koshi county (today&apos;s Karuizawa in Nagaoka city, Niigata Pref.) and his upbringing entrusted to Yahiko jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shuten Doji was born in Sunakozuka in Kanbara county (modern-day Sunakozuka in the town of Bunsui in Niigata Pref.) and served as a page-boy of Kokujoji temple, whereas Ibaraki Doji was supposedly born deep in the mountains at Karuizawa in Koshi county (today&apos;s Karuizawa in Nagaoka city, Niigata Pref.) and his upbringing entrusted to Yahiko jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shuten Doji was born in Sunakozuka in Kanbara county (modern-day Sunakozuka, Bunsui-cho, Niigata Prefecture) and served as a page-boy of Kokujo-ji Temple, whereas Ibaraki Doji was supposedly born deep in the mountains at Karuizawa in Koshi county (today&apos;s Karuizawa in Nagaoka City, Niigata Prefecture) and his upbringing entrusted to Yahiko-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>場所表記寺表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同地には酒呑童子と茨木童子が相撲を取った場所があり、茨木童子を祀る祠がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The places where Shuten Doji and Ibaraki Doji were said to have learned sumo wrestling are in that same general area; currently there is a small shrine on the latter spot, at which Ibaraki Doji has been deified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The places where Shuten Doji and Ibaraki Doji were said to have learned sumo wrestling are in that same general area; currently there is a small shrine on the latter spot, at which Ibaraki Doji has been deified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The places where Shuten Doji and Ibaraki Doji were said to have learned sumo wrestling are in that same general area; currently there is a small shrine on the latter spot, at which Ibaraki Doji has been deified.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>またこの地区は「茨木」姓が多く、茨木姓の家では節分に豆をまかない習わしがあり、また家の屋根に破風を作るとその家では不良が出るので作らないという言い伝えがあるという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there were many people in this region whose family name was &quot;Ibaraki,&quot; and tradition among Ibaraki families of the area holds that they not throw soy beans at Setsubun (a demon-exorcising holiday elsewhere known throughout Japan for the custom of throwing beans), and that gables not be built on houses, since the building of gables on houses is was thought to bring misfortune on the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there were many people in this region whose family name was &quot;Ibaraki,&quot; and tradition among Ibaraki families of the area holds that they not throw soy beans at Setsubun (a demon-exorcising holiday elsewhere known throughout Japan for the custom of throwing beans), and that gables not be built on houses, since the building of gables on houses was thought to bring misfortune on the family.</e>
<cmt>Edited for grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there were many people in this region whose family name was &apos;Ibaraki,&apos; and tradition among Ibaraki families of the area holds that they not throw soy beans at Setsubun (a demon-exorcising holiday elsewhere known throughout Japan for the custom of throwing beans), and that gables not be built on houses, since the building of gables on houses was thought to bring misfortune on the family.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>美男子で知られ娘たちから山ほど恋文を送られていた外道丸こと酒呑童子同様、茨木童子も美少年として多くの女性に言い寄られ、将来を案じた母親に弥彦神社に送られることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Much like Shuten Doji (known in his boyhood as &quot;Gedomaru,&quot; meaning &quot;Apostate Boy&quot;), who was famous for his good looks and received huge numbers of love-letters from the girls in the neighborhood, Ibaraki Doji was also said to be a very handsome youth, wooed by many young ladies in his area, leading his mother, anxious over his spiritual future, to send him off to Yahiko jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Much like Shuten Doji (known in his boyhood as &quot;Gedomaru,&quot; meaning &quot;Apostate Boy&quot;), who was famous for his good looks and received huge numbers of love-letters from the girls in the neighborhood, Ibaraki Doji was also said to be a very handsome youth, wooed by many young ladies in his area, leading his mother, anxious over his spiritual future, to send him off to Yahiko jinja shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Much like Shuten Doji (known in his boyhood as &quot;Gedomaru,&quot; meaning &quot;Apostate Boy&quot;), who was famous for his good looks and received huge numbers of love-letters from the girls in the neighborhood, Ibaraki Doji was also said to be a very handsome youth, wooed by many young ladies in his area, leading his mother, anxious over his spiritual future, to send him off to Yahiko-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>神社表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ところがある時弥彦神社から実家に帰ると、母が行李の中に隠した「血塗の恋文」を見つけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, however, while he was home from Yahiko jinja shrine visiting his mother, she discovered a &quot;bloodstained love-letter&quot; hidden away in his school trunk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, however, while he was home from Yahiko jinja shrine visiting his mother, she discovered a &quot;bloodstained love-letter&quot; hidden away in his school trunk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, however, while he was home from Yahiko-jinja Shrine visiting his mother, she discovered a &apos;bloodstained love-letter&apos; hidden away in his school trunk.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その血を指で一舐めするとたちどころに彼は形相が変わり鬼となり、梁をつたい破風を壊して逃げていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When just one finger was dipped into that blood, Ibaraki instantly transformed into an oni, scampered up the ceiling beam, tore off the gable on the roof and ran away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When just one finger was dipped into that blood, Ibaraki instantly transformed into an oni, scampered up the ceiling beam, tore off the gable on the roof and ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When just one finger was dipped into that blood, Ibaraki instantly transformed into an oni, scampered up the ceiling beam, tore off the gable on the roof and ran away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そのころ外道丸こと酒呑童子は、恋文の返事が来ないと悲観して死んだ娘のことを聞き、読まなかった恋文の入ったつづらを開けてみると異様な煙が立ち昇って気を失い、気づくと鬼へと変わり果てて寺から逃げて悪の限りを尽くすようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, Gedomaru (that is, Shuten Doji) heard of a girl who had died of grief due to his failure to send a reply to her love-letter, and upon opening the tsuzura (package) included in her letter--which he had never read--a strange vapor rose from it, causing him to lose consciousness; when he came to, he transformation into an oni was already complete, so he fled from the temple and set his heart on reaching the very limits of evil.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, Gedomaru (that is, Shuten Doji) heard of a girl who had died of grief due to his failure to send a reply to her love-letter, and upon opening the tsuzura (package) included in her letter--which he had never read--a strange vapor rose from it, causing him to lose consciousness; when he came to, he transformation into an oni was already complete, so he fled from the temple and set his heart on reaching the very limits of evil.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, Gedomaru (that is, Shuten Doji) heard of a girl who had died of grief due to his failure to send a reply to her love-letter, and upon opening the tsuzura (package) included in her letter--which he had never read--a strange vapor rose from it, causing him to lose consciousness; when he came to, his transformation into an oni was already complete, so he fled from the temple and set his heart on reaching the very limits of evil.</e>
<cmt>he→his</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>酒呑童子と意気投合した茨木童子は舎弟となり共に周囲の村々を襲っていたが、そのうわさを聞いた母が、彼の幼い頃の産着を着けて茨木童子の前に立つと、茨木童子は急に子供の頃の想い出が甦ったか、「二度とこの地を踏まぬ」と約束して、酒呑童子とともに信州戸隠山などを経て京へと向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ibaraki Doji, who had found such a kindred spirit in Shuten Doji, also became his henchman, and together they began raiding the villages nearby; Ibaraki&apos;s mother, after hearing rumors of his misdeeds, draped herself in his baby clothes and appeared before him, which suddenly caused him to be flooded with memories of his childhood, so he vowed that &quot;never shall I set foot in this region again,&quot; and together with Shuten Doji, began to make his way towards the capital (Kyoto), passing through Mt. Togakushi in Shinano (Nagano).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ibaraki Doji, who had found such a kindred spirit in Shuten Doji, also became his henchman, and together they began raiding the villages nearby; Ibaraki&apos;s mother, after hearing rumors of his misdeeds, draped herself in his baby clothes and appeared before him, which suddenly caused him to be flooded with memories of his childhood, so he vowed that &quot;never shall I set foot in this region again,&quot; and together with Shuten Doji, began to make his way towards the capital (Kyoto), passing through Mt. Togakushi in Shinano (Nagano).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ibaraki Doji, who had found such a kindred spirit in Shuten Doji, also became his henchman, and together they began raiding the villages nearby; Ibaraki&apos;s mother, after hearing rumors of his misdeeds, draped herself in his baby clothes and appeared before him, which suddenly caused him to be flooded with memories of his childhood, so he vowed that &apos;never shall I set foot in this region again,&apos; and together with Shuten Doji, began to make his way towards the capital (Kyoto), passing through Mt. Togakushi in Shinano (Nagano).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>摂津説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory that he was born in Settsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory that he was born in Settsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The theory that he was born in Settsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>酒呑童子の出生地にはほかにも伊吹山麓など有力な説があるが、茨木童子の出生地についても兵庫県尼崎市や大阪府茨木市の説もあり、『摂津名所図会』・『摂陽研説』・『摂陽群談』などの資料ではこれらを採っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Much as there are several competing theories about Shuten Doji&apos;s birthplace, including a compelling case that he was born at the foot of Mt. Ibuki, there are several about Ibaraki Doji&apos;s birthplace as well, like the view that he was born in Amagasaki city in Hyogo Prefecture or that which holds he was born in Ibaraki city in Osaka Prefecture; these competing theories are described in various documents, including the &quot;Settsu meisho zue&quot; (Illustrated Guide to Famous Places in Settsu Province), the &quot;Setsuyo kensetsu,&quot; and the &quot;Setsuyo gundan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Much as there are several competing theories about Shuten Doji&apos;s birthplace, including a compelling case that he was born at the foot of Mt. Ibuki, there are several about Ibaraki Doji&apos;s birthplace as well, like the view that he was born in Amagasaki city in Hyogo Prefecture or that which holds he was born in Ibaraki city in Osaka Prefecture; these competing theories are described in various documents, including the &quot;Settsu meisho zue&quot; (Illustrated Guide to Famous Places in Settsu Province), the &quot;Setsuyo kensetsu,&quot; and the &quot;Setsuyo gundan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Much as there are several competing theories about Shuten Doji&apos;s birthplace, including a compelling case that he was born at the foot of Mt. Ibuki, there are several about Ibaraki Doji&apos;s birthplace as well, like the view that he was born in Amagasaki City in Hyogo Prefecture or that which holds he was born in Ibaraki City in Osaka Prefecture; these competing theories are described in various documents, including the &quot;Settsu meisho zue&quot; (Illustrated Guide to Famous Places in Settsu Province), the &quot;Setsuyo kensetsu,&quot; and the &quot;Setsuyo gundan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>地名表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>1701年刊行の『摂陽群談』では、 摂津国の富松の里（現・兵庫県尼崎市）で生まれ、茨木の里（茨木市）に産着のまま捨てられていたところを酒呑童子に拾われ茨木の名をつけて養われたとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Setsuyo gundan,&quot; published in 1701, he was born in the village of Tomimatsu in Settsu province (the modern-day city of Amagasaki in Hyogo Pref.) and abandoned, while still in his baby clothes, in the village of Ibaraki (today&apos;s Ibaraki city), where he was picked up by Shuten Doji, who raised him and gave him the nickname &quot;Ibaraki.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Setsuyo gundan,&quot; published in 1701, he was born in the village of Tomimatsu in Settsu province (the modern-day city of Amagasaki in Hyogo Pref.) and abandoned, while still in his baby clothes, in the village of Ibaraki (today&apos;s Ibaraki city), where he was picked up by Shuten Doji, who raised him and gave him the nickname &quot;Ibaraki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Setsuyo gundan,&quot; published in 1701, he was born in the village of Tomimatsu in Settsu Province (the modern-day Amagasaki City, Hyogo Prefecture) and abandoned, while still in his baby clothes, in the village of Ibaraki (today&apos;s Ibaraki City), where he was picked up by Shuten Doji, who raised him and gave him the nickname &quot;Ibaraki.&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペル地名表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>また『摂陽研説』では、茨木童子は川邊郡留松村（富松と同じく尼崎市の一部）の土民の子であったが、生まれながらに牙が生え、髪が長く、眼光があって成人以上に力があったので、一族はこの子を怖れて島下郡茨木村の辺りに捨て、酒呑童子に拾われたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in the &quot;Setsuyo kensetsu&quot; Ibaraki Doji is described as the child of natives of Tameatsu village in Kawabe county (which, like Tomimatsu, is part of modern-day Amagasaki city), but right from birth his teeth were all grown in, his hair long, his gaze piercing, and his strength beyond that of a fully grown man; consequently, his family were terrified of him and abandoned him near Ibaraki village in Shimashimo county, where he was picked up by Shuten Doji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in the &quot;Setsuyo kensetsu&quot; Ibaraki Doji is described as the child of natives of Tameatsu village in Kawabe county (which, like Tomimatsu, is part of modern-day Amagasaki city), but right from birth his teeth were all grown in, his hair long, his gaze piercing, and his strength beyond that of a fully grown man; consequently, his family were terrified of him and abandoned him near Ibaraki village in Shimashimo county, where he was picked up by Shuten Doji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in the &quot;Setsuyo kensetsu&quot; Ibaraki Doji is described as the child of natives of Tamematsu village in Kawabe county (which, like Tomimatsu, is part of modern-day Amagasaki City), but right from birth his teeth were all grown in, his hair long, his gaze piercing, and his strength beyond that of a fully grown man; consequently, his family were terrified of him and abandoned him near Ibaraki village in Shimashimo county, where he was picked up by Shuten Doji.</e>
<cmt>スペル地名表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>茨木市の伝承では、茨木童子は水尾村（現・茨木市）の生まれだが、16ヶ月の難産の末に生まれたときにはすでに歯が生え揃い、生まれてすぐに歩き出して、母の顔を見て鋭い目つきで笑ったため母はショックで亡くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the version of the legend handed down in Ibaraki city itself, Ibaraki Doji was born in Mizuo village (today&apos;s Ibaraki city) after a sixteen-month pregnancy and a very difficult delivery; by birth, he had already acquired his teeth, and began to walk almost immediately thereafter, and looking on his mother&apos;s face, he smiled and gazed with such a piercing stare that his mother died of shock.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the version of the legend handed down in Ibaraki city itself, Ibaraki Doji was born in Mizuo village (today&apos;s Ibaraki city) after a sixteen-month pregnancy and a very difficult delivery; by birth, he had already acquired his teeth, and began to walk almost immediately thereafter, and looking on his mother&apos;s face, he smiled and gazed with such a piercing stare that his mother died of shock.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the version of the legend handed down in Ibaraki City itself, Ibaraki Doji was born in Mizuo village (today&apos;s Ibaraki City) after a sixteen-month pregnancy and a very difficult delivery; by birth, he had already acquired his teeth, and began to walk almost immediately thereafter, and looking on his mother&apos;s face, he smiled and gazed with such a piercing stare that his mother died of shock.</e>
<cmt>地名表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>父は鬼のような赤子を持て余し、隣の茨木村の九頭神（くずがみ）の森近くにある髪結いの前に捨て、以後茨木童子は子のいなかった床屋夫妻の子として育った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His father, deciding he wouldn&apos;t raise a baby so demonic, abandoned him in front of a barber&apos;s near the woods of Kuzugami, in the neighboring village of Ibaraki, so thereafter Ibaraki Doji was raised by the barber and his wife, who had no children of their own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His father, deciding he wouldn&apos;t raise a baby so demonic, abandoned him in front of a barber&apos;s near the woods of Kuzugami, in the neighboring village of Ibaraki, so thereafter Ibaraki Doji was raised by the barber and his wife, who had no children of their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His father, deciding he wouldn&apos;t raise a baby so demonic, abandoned him in front of a barber&apos;s near the woods of Kuzugami, in the neighboring village of Ibaraki, so thereafter Ibaraki Doji was raised by the barber and his wife, who had no children of their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>幼くして体格も力も大人を凌いだ童子を床屋も持て余したが、床屋の仕事を教えて落ち着かせることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even while still a young child Doji&apos;s physical stature and strength surpassed that of a grown man&apos;s, leading the barber at a loss as to how to raise him, but he decided to train him in hair-cutting, thereby hoping to calm his disposition.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even while still a young child Doji&apos;s physical stature and strength surpassed that of a grown man&apos;s, leading the barber at a loss as to how to raise him, but he decided to train him in hair-cutting, thereby hoping to calm his disposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even while still a young child Doji&apos;s physical stature and strength surpassed that of a grown man&apos;s, leading the barber at a loss as to how to raise him, but he decided to train him in hair-cutting, thereby hoping to calm his disposition.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>ところがある日、童子はかみそりで客の顔を傷つけてしまい、あわてて指で血をぬぐったものの、指をきれいにしようと血をなめるとその味が癖になってしまい、以後わざと客の顔を傷つけては血をすするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One day, however, Doji nicked a customer&apos;s face with his razor, and after hurriedly wiping away the blood with his finger, he tried to clean that finger by licking off the blood, only to find the taste of blood addictive; thereafter, he began deliberately cutting the customers&apos; faces and licking up the resulting blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One day, however, Doji nicked a customer&apos;s face with his razor, and after hurriedly wiping away the blood with his finger, he tried to clean that finger by licking off the blood, only to find the taste of blood addictive; thereafter, he began deliberately cutting the customers&apos; faces and licking up the resulting blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One day, however, Doji nicked a customer&apos;s face with his razor, and after hurriedly wiping away the blood with his finger, he tried to clean that finger by licking off the blood, only to find the taste of blood addictive; thereafter, he began deliberately cutting the customers&apos; faces and licking up the resulting blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>床屋に怒られた童子は気落ちして近くの小川の橋にもたれてうつむいていると、水面に写る自分の顔がすっかり鬼になってしまっているのに気づき、床屋には帰らずに北の丹波の山に逃げ、やがて酒呑童子と出会い家来となったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being scolded by the irate barber, Doji was feeling despondent and wandered aimlessly down to the bridge over a nearby stream, hanging his head, only to notice that his face, reflected in the water, had completely transformed into that of an oni, whereupon he fled north, without ever returning home to the barber&apos;s, into the mountains of Tanba, where he eventually encountered Shuten Doji and became his henchman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being scolded by the irate barber, Doji was feeling despondent and wandered aimlessly down to the bridge over a nearby stream, hanging his head, only to notice that his face, reflected in the water, had completely transformed into that of an oni, whereupon he fled north, without ever returning home to the barber&apos;s, into the mountains of Tanba, where he eventually encountered Shuten Doji and became his henchman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being scolded by the irate barber, Doji was feeling despondent and wandered aimlessly down to the bridge over a nearby stream, hanging his head, only to notice that his face, reflected in the water, had completely transformed into that of an oni, whereupon he fled north, without ever returning home to the barber&apos;s, into the mountains of Tanba, where he eventually encountered Shuten Doji and became his henchman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その橋は「茨木童子貌見橋（すがたみばし）」と呼ばれていたが現存せず、跡地に碑が立っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That bridge was called &quot;Ibaraki Doji Sugatami Bashi&quot; (&quot;the bridge where Ibaraki Doji looked on his own appearance&quot;) but does not survive today; there is a stone monument on the site where the bridge once stood, however.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That bridge was called &quot;Ibaraki Doji Sugatami Bashi&quot; (&quot;the bridge where Ibaraki Doji looked on his own appearance&quot;) but does not survive today; there is a stone monument on the site where the bridge once stood, however.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That bridge was called &apos;Ibaraki Doji Sugatami Bashi&apos; (&apos;the bridge where Ibaraki Doji looked on his own appearance&apos;) but does not survive today; there is a stone monument on the site where the bridge once stood, however.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>大江山の鬼退治</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The extermination of the oni on Mt. Oe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The extermination of the oni on Mt. Oe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The extermination of the oni on Mt. Oe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>酒呑童子の一味による被害があまりにも大きく、源頼光が鬼退治に行くこととなり、配下の頼光四天王（渡辺綱・坂田金時・碓井貞光・卜部季武）や友人の藤原保昌ら、総勢五十数名とともに大江山に向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The damage inflicted by Shuten Doji and his gang was very severe, which prompted MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu to go on a mission to exterminate the oni; together with his main followers, the Four Great Warriors of Yorimitsu (WATANABE no Tsuna, SAKATA no Kintoki, Sadamitsu USUI, and URABE no Suetake) and other friends including FUJIWARA no Yasumasa, he set out for Mt. Oe leading a force of more than fifty warriors in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The damage inflicted by Shuten Doji and his gang was very severe, which prompted MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu to go on a mission to exterminate the oni; together with his main followers, the Four Great Warriors of Yorimitsu (WATANABE no Tsuna, SAKATA no Kintoki, Sadamitsu USUI, and URABE no Suetake) and other friends including FUJIWARA no Yasumasa, he set out for Mt. Oe leading a force of more than fifty warriors in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The damage inflicted by Shuten Doji and his gang was very severe, which prompted MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu to go on a mission to exterminate the oni; together with his main followers, the Four Great Warriors of Yorimitsu (WATANABE no Tsuna, SAKATA no Kintoki, Sadamitsu USUI, and URABE no Suetake) and other friends including FUJIWARA no Yasumasa, he set out for Mt. Oe leading a force of more than fifty warriors in total.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>山伏の姿になった一行はさまざまな人々の助けを得ながら、一晩の宿を求める振りをして酒呑童子の本拠にはいることに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The group, dressed as mountain monks, received the help of all manner of people on their journey until they successfully infiltrated Shuten Doji&apos;s lair by posing as travelers seeking lodging for the night.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The group, dressed as mountain monks, received the help of all manner of people on their journey until they successfully infiltrated Shuten Doji&apos;s lair by posing as travelers seeking lodging for the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The group, dressed as mountain monks, received the help of all manner of people on their journey until they successfully infiltrated Shuten Doji&apos;s lair by posing as travelers seeking lodging for the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>その晩は酒盛り上がり、深夜、酔って動かなくなった酒呑童子の一味の鬼たちを頼光らは残らず退治した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That night, Yorimitsu and his compatriots held a drinking bout together with their hosts and then waited until late at night, when Shuten Doji and his gang were all so drunk they could barely move, before exterminating every last one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That night, Yorimitsu and his compatriots held a drinking bout together with their hosts and then waited until late at night, when Shuten Doji and his gang were all so drunk they could barely move, before exterminating every last one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That night, Yorimitsu and his compatriots held a drinking bout together with their hosts and then waited until late at night, when Shuten Doji and his gang were all so drunk they could barely move, before exterminating every last one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ただし、茨木童子のみは渡辺綱と戦っていたところ、酒呑童子の討たれるのを見てこれはかなわないと退却し、唯一逃げるのに成功したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Ibaraki Doji, while fighting a duel with WATANABE no Tsuna and seeing Shuten Doji struck down, decided the cause was lost and retreated, making him the sole oni who managed to escape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Ibaraki Doji, while fighting a duel with WATANABE no Tsuna and seeing Shuten Doji struck down, decided the cause was lost and retreated, making him the sole oni who managed to escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Ibaraki Doji, while fighting a duel with WATANABE no Tsuna and seeing Shuten Doji struck down, decided the cause was lost and retreated, making him the sole oni who managed to escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>渡辺綱と茨木童子の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The duels between WATANABE no Tsuna and Ibaraki Doji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The duels between WATANABE no Tsuna and Ibaraki Doji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The duels between WATANABE no Tsuna and Ibaraki Doji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="29">
<j>渡辺綱と茨木童子の物語は</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monogatari (tales) that describe the fights between WATANABE no Tsuna and Ibaraki Doji include:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monogatari (tales) that describe the fights between WATANABE no Tsuna and Ibaraki Doji include:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monogatari (tales) that describe the fights between WATANABE no Tsuna and Ibaraki Doji include:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>『平家物語・劔巻』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Heike monogatari, tsurugi-kan&quot; (Tale of the Heike (Taira), tsurugi (sword) volume)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Heike monogatari, tsurugi-kan&quot; (Tale of the Heike (Taira), tsurugi (sword) volume)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Heike monogatari, tsurugi-kan&quot; (Tale of the Heike (Taira), tsurugi (sword) volume)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>『太平記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (Record of the Great Peace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>『前太平記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Zentaiheiki&quot; (Record of the Earlier Great Peace)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Zentaiheiki&quot; (Record of the Earlier Great Peace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Zentaiheiki&quot; (Record of the Earlier Great Peace)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>『源平盛衰記』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Genpei seisuiki&quot; (The Rising and Falling Fortunes of the Genji (Minamoto) and the Heike (Taira))</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Genpei seisuiki&quot; (The Rising and Falling Fortunes of the Genji (Minamoto) and the Heike (Taira))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Genpei seisuiki&quot; (The Rising and Falling Fortunes of the Genji (Minamoto) and the Heike (Taira))</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>などに出てくるほか、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">but also appears in the following:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">but also appears in the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">but also appears in the following:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>『御伽草子』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; (a book of ghost stories)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; (a book of ghost stories)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Otogi zoshi&quot; (a book of ghost stories)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>『茨木』（歌舞伎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kabuki play &quot;Ibaraki&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kabuki play &quot;Ibaraki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kabuki play &quot;Ibaraki&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>『戻橋』（歌舞伎）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kabuki play &quot;Modoribashi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kabuki play &quot;Modoribashi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kabuki play &quot;Modoribashi&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>『羅生門』（能）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Noh play &quot;Rashomon&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Noh play &quot;Rashomon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Noh play &quot;Rashomon&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>『綱館』（長唄）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Tsunayakata&quot; (a nagauta, or long epic song/poem, on the House of Tsuna)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Tsunayakata&quot; (a nagauta, or long epic song/poem, on the House of Tsuna)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Tsunayakata&quot; (a nagauta, or long epic song/poem, on the House of Tsuna)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>にも登場し、それぞれ細部が異なっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and yet in each such appearance, the details are different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">and yet in each such appearance, the details are different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">and yet in each such appearance, the details are different.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>おおむね、「渡辺綱が茨木童子の腕を切り落とすが、茨木童子は腕を取り戻しに綱の元へやってくる」というものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most, however, do include a storyline that is something along the lines of &quot;WATANABE no Tsuna cuts off Ibaraki Doji&apos;s arm, and so Ibaraki Doji then makes his way to Tsuna&apos;s house to take back his arm.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most, however, do include a storyline that is something along the lines of &quot;WATANABE no Tsuna cuts off Ibaraki Doji&apos;s arm, and so Ibaraki Doji makes his way to Tsuna&apos;s house to take back his arm.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most, however, do include a storyline that is something along the lines of &apos;WATANABE no Tsuna cuts off Ibaraki Doji&apos;s arm, and so Ibaraki Doji makes his way to Tsuna&apos;s house to take back his arm.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>また上記の伝承を元に木原敏江が1978年タイトル「大江山花伝」で漫画化、同作は1986年宝塚歌劇団雪組本公演で柴田侑宏脚色・演出で舞台化（茨木童子役は平みち）されたほか、島田まゆが1996年タイトル「IBARAGI茨木」で舞台を現代に移して、渡辺綱の子孫である高校生と茨木童子（この作品では女性である）のエピソードを創作している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in 1978 Toshie KIHARA used the above-mentioned texts as sources for her manga (comic) version of these events, entitled &quot;Oeyama kaden&quot; (the Legend of Mt. Oe), and in 1986 this manga, in Yukihiro SHIBATA&apos;s theatrical version, was adapted for the stage by the winter performance troupe of the Takarazuka Revue Company (with Michi TAIRA in the role of Ibaraki Doji), and in addition to these adaptations, Mayu SHIMADA also created a play in 1996 entitled &quot;Ibaraki Ibaraki,&quot; which shifted the setting of the story to the present day and focuses on the relationship between WATANABE no Tsuna&apos;s grandson, a high school student, and Ibaraki Doji (who is female in this version).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in 1978 Toshie KIHARA used the above-mentioned texts as sources for her manga (comic) version of these events, entitled &quot;Oeyama kaden&quot; (the Legend of Mt. Oe), and in 1986 this manga, in Yukihiro SHIBATA&apos;s theatrical version, was adapted for the stage by the winter performance troupe of the Takarazuka Revue Company (with Michi TAIRA in the role of Ibaraki Doji), and in addition to these adaptations, Mayu SHIMADA also created a play in 1996 entitled &quot;Ibaraki Ibaraki,&quot; which shifted the setting of the story to the present day and focuses on the relationship between WATANABE no Tsuna&apos;s grandson, a high school student, and Ibaraki Doji (who is female in this version).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in 1978 Toshie KIHARA used the above-mentioned texts as sources for her manga (comic) version of these events, entitled &apos;Oeyama kaden&apos; (the Legend of Mt. Oe), and in 1986 this manga, in Yukihiro SHIBATA&apos;s theatrical version, was adapted for the stage by the winter performance troupe of the Takarazuka Revue Company (with Michi TAIRA in the role of Ibaraki Doji), and in addition to these adaptations, Mayu SHIMADA also created a play in 1996 entitled &apos;Ibaraki Ibaraki,&apos; which shifted the setting of the story to the present day and focuses on the relationship between WATANABE no Tsuna&apos;s grandson, a high school student, and Ibaraki Doji (who is female in this version).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>一条戻橋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ichijo modoribashi bridge</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ichijo modoribashi bridge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ichijo modoribashi bridge</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>茨木童子が出現するのは、堀川にかかる一条戻橋の上というパターン。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In theatrical and other versions, Ibaraki Doji generally makes his first appearance on the Ichijo modoribashi bridge over the Hori river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In theatrical and other versions, Ibaraki Doji generally makes his first appearance on the Ichijo modoribashi bridge over the Hori river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In theatrical and other versions, Ibaraki Doji generally makes his first appearance on the Ichijo modoribashi bridge over the Hori river.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>若い美女が道に困っていたため、渡辺綱が馬に乗せてやると、女は突然鬼の姿になって綱の髪の毛を掴み、空中に飛び上がって愛宕山 (京都市)に連れ去ろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A young, beautiful woman standing on the bridge appears to have lost her way, but when WATANABE no Tsuna pulls her up behind him on his steed, she suddenly transforms into an oni, grabs him by his (long) hair, and tries to fly away with him, in the direction of Mt. Atago (in present-day Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A young, beautiful woman standing on the bridge appears to have lost her way, but when WATANABE no Tsuna pulls her up behind him on his steed, she suddenly transforms into an oni, grabs him by his (long) hair, and tries to fly away with him, in the direction of Mt. Atago (in present-day Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A young, beautiful woman standing on the bridge appears to have lost her way, but when WATANABE no Tsuna pulls her up behind him on his steed, she suddenly transforms into an oni, grabs him by his (long) hair, and tries to fly away with him, in the direction of Mt. Atago (in present-day Kyoto City).</e>
<cmt>City補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>綱は慌てず名刀・髭切で鬼の腕を切って難を逃れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Tsuna keeps his cool, and manages to escape his predicament by slicing off the oni&apos;s arm with his legendary sword, Higekiri (Beard-slicer).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Tsuna keeps his cool, and manages to escape his predicament by slicing off the oni&apos;s arm with his legendary sword, Higekiri (Beard-slicer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Tsuna keeps his cool, and manages to escape his predicament by slicing off the oni&apos;s arm with his legendary sword, Higekiri (Beard-slicer).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="46">
<j>綱は、切り取った鬼の腕を源頼光に見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuna then shows the oni&apos;s severed arm to MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuna then shows the oni&apos;s severed arm to MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuna then shows the oni&apos;s severed arm to MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>頼光が陰陽師（安倍晴明だとする話もある）に相談したところ、「必ず鬼が腕を取り返しにやって来るから、七日の間家に閉じこもり物忌みをし、その間は誰も家の中に入れないように」と言われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimitsu then consults with an onmyoji (a Heian-period sorcerer; in some accounts, the onmyoji he speaks to is none other than the famous ABE no Seimei), who informs Tsuna that &quot;The oni will definitely come here seeking to recover his arm, so shut yourself away in your house for seven days of ritual confinement, and do not allow anyone else to enter the house during this time.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimitsu then consults with an onmyoji (a Heian-period sorcerer; in some accounts, the onmyoji he speaks to is none other than the famous ABE no Seimei), who informs Tsuna that &quot;The oni will definitely come here seeking to recover his arm, so shut yourself away in your house for seven days of ritual confinement, and do not allow anyone else to enter the house during this time.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimitsu then consults with an onmyoji (a Heian-period sorcerer; in some accounts, the onmyoji he speaks to is none other than the famous ABE no Seimei), who informs Tsuna that &apos;The oni will definitely come here seeking to recover his arm, so shut yourself away in your house for seven days of ritual confinement, and do not allow anyone else to enter the house during this time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>それから数日間、茨木童子はあらゆる手を用いて綱の屋敷へ侵入しようとするが、綱の唱える仁王経や護符の力で入ることができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sure enough, over the next several days, Ibaraki Doji employs all manner of strategems trying to gain entry into Tsuna&apos;s house, but thanks to the power of the Sutra of the Benevolent Kings Tsuna chants, as well as the protective charms he possesses, Ibaraki Doji is unable to enter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sure enough, over the next several days, Ibaraki Doji employs all manner of strategems trying to gain entry into Tsuna&apos;s house, but thanks to the power of the Sutra of the Benevolent Kings Tsuna chants, as well as the protective charms he possesses, Ibaraki Doji is unable to enter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sure enough, over the next several days, Ibaraki Doji employs all manner of stratagems trying to gain entry into Tsuna&apos;s house, but thanks to the power of the Sutra of the Benevolent Kings Tsuna chants, as well as the protective charms he possesses, Ibaraki Doji is unable to enter.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="49">
<j>ついに七日目の晩になって、摂津の国から綱の伯母・真柴（伯母ではなく養母が来るという話もある）が綱の屋敷にやってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, on the seventh day Tsuna&apos;s aunt Mashiba (or in some versions, his foster mother) comes to visit him from Settsu province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, on the seventh day Tsuna&apos;s aunt Mashiba (or in some versions, his foster mother) comes to visit him from Settsu province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, on the seventh day Tsuna&apos;s aunt Mashiba (or in some versions, his foster mother) comes to visit him from Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>綱は事情を話し決して伯母を屋敷に入れなかったが、年老いた伯母は「幼いころ大切に育てた報いがこの仕打ちか」と嘆き悲しんだので綱は仕方なく言いつけを破って伯母を屋敷に入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuna explains the situation and steels his heart to refuse to let his aunt enter, but the elderly woman tearfully reproaches him, saying &quot;is this how you repay me for all the loving care I lavished on you when I was raising you as a child?&quot; which leaves Tsuna no choice but to break his vow and allow his aunt to enter the house.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuna explains the situation and steals his heart to refuse to let his aunt enter, but the elderly woman tearfully reproaches him, saying &quot;is this how you repay me for all the loving care I lavished on you when I was raising you as a child?&quot; which leaves Tsuna no choice but to break his vow and allow his aunt to enter the house.</e>
<cmt>Spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuna explains the situation and steals his heart to refuse to let his aunt enter, but the elderly woman tearfully reproaches him, saying &apos;is this how you repay me for all the loving care I lavished on you when I was raising you as a child?&apos; which leaves Tsuna no choice but to break his vow and allow his aunt to enter the house.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ところが、この伯母は実は茨木童子の化けた姿だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the aunt is actually none other than a transformed Ibaraki Doji, wearing her guise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the aunt is actually none other than a transformed Ibaraki Doji, in disguise.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the aunt is in fact none other than a transformed Ibaraki Doji, in disguise.</e>
<cmt>actually -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>伯母の姿のまま、綱が切り取ったと言う鬼の腕を見たいと言い、封印された唐櫃から出されてきた腕を手にとってじっくり見ていると、突然伯母は鬼の姿に戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remaining in the shape and guise of Tsuna&apos;s aunt, Doji asked to see the arm Tsuna had cut off of the oni, so Tsuna retrieves it from the sealed Chinese-style chest and hands it to her; yet even as he carefully watches her, Doji suddenly returns to his true oni shape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remaining in the shape and guise of Tsuna&apos;s aunt, Doji asked to see the arm Tsuna had cut off of the oni, so Tsuna retrieves it from the sealed Chinese-style chest and hands it to her; yet even as he carefully watches her, Doji suddenly returns to his true oni shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remaining in the shape and guise of Tsuna&apos;s aunt, Doji asked to see the arm Tsuna had cut off of the oni, so Tsuna retrieves it from the sealed Chinese-style chest and hands it to her; yet even as he carefully watches her, Doji suddenly returns to his true oni shape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>そして腕を持ったまま飛び上がり、破風を破って空の彼方に消えたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, still clutching the arm, Doji bursts into flight, blasting through the gable on the roof and vanishing into the night sky.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then, still clutching the arm, Doji bursts into flight, blasting through the gable on the roof and vanishing into the night sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then, still clutching the arm, Doji bursts into flight, blasting through the gable on the roof and vanishing into the night sky.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>羅生門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rashomon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rashomon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rashomon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="54">
<j>渡辺綱が茨木童子の腕を切り落とすのは羅生門という筋のものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another version of the story has WATANABE no Tsuna cutting off Ibaraki Doji&apos;s arm at Rashomon (a famous gate in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another version of the story has WATANABE no Tsuna cutting off Ibaraki Doji&apos;s arm at Rashomon (a famous gate in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another version of the story has WATANABE no Tsuna cutting off Ibaraki Doji&apos;s arm at Rashomon (a famous gate in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="55">
<j>大江山の鬼退治が終わってしばらくした頃、源頼光以下四天王たちが集った酒宴の席で、近頃羅生門に鬼が出るという話になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A while after the successful extermination of the oni on Mt. Oe, MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu and his followers, including the Four Great Warriors, are all gathered at a banquet when word reaches them that an oni has appeared at the nearby Rashomon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A while after the successful extermination of the oni on Mt. Oe, MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu and his followers, including the Four Great Warriors, are all gathered at a banquet when word reaches them that an oni has appeared at the nearby Rashomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A while after the successful extermination of the oni on Mt. Oe, MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu and his followers, including the Four Great Warriors, are all gathered at a banquet when word reaches them that an oni has appeared at the nearby Rashomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="56">
<j>ならばと全員で度胸試しに出かけると、綱の番になって門に入ると鬼に出会ってしまい、格闘の末、鬼の腕を切り落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They all rush out, eager to prove their mettle against the oni if the rumor of its presence are true, and it happened to be Tsuna&apos;s turn, so he entered under the gate, encountered the oni, and fought a duel with him, the end result of which was that he managed to slice off the oni&apos;s arm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They all rush out, eager to prove their mettle against the oni if the rumor of its presence are true, and it happened to be Tsuna&apos;s turn, so he entered under the gate, encountered the oni, and fought a duel with him, the end result of which was that he managed to slice off the oni&apos;s arm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They all rush out, eager to prove their mettle against the oni if the rumor of its presence are true, and it happened to be Tsuna&apos;s turn, so he entered under the gate, encountered the oni, and fought a duel with him, the end result of which was that he managed to slice off the oni&apos;s arm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="57">
<j>まさか鬼の生き残りがいるわけがないと思った綱が羅生門に行ってみると、そこには茨木童子（または美女にばけた茨木童子）がいて、やはり格闘の末、鬼の腕を切り落とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsuna had been certain that no oni had survived the earlier purge, yet sure enough, as soon as he reached Rashomon, there stood Ibaraki Doji (in some versions Ibaraki Doji had taken the form of a beautiful maiden), and indeed the result of their duel was that Ibaraki Doji had his arm cut off.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsuna had been certain that no oni had survived the earlier purge, yet sure enough, as soon as he reached Rashomon, there stood Ibaraki Doji (in some versions Ibaraki Doji had taken the form of a beautiful maiden), and indeed the result of their duel was that Ibaraki Doji had his arm cut off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsuna had been certain that no oni had survived the earlier purge, yet sure enough, as soon as he reached Rashomon, there stood Ibaraki Doji (in some versions Ibaraki Doji had taken the form of a beautiful maiden), and indeed the result of their duel was that Ibaraki Doji had his arm cut off.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="58">
<j>その後、同様に茨木童子は姿を変え、腕を取り戻しに現れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, much like in other versions of the story, Ibaraki Doji transforms again and later appears in an attempt to get his arm back.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, much like in other versions of the story, Ibaraki Doji transforms again and later appears in an attempt to get his arm back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, much like in other versions of the story, Ibaraki Doji transforms again and later appears in an attempt to get his arm back.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>茨木童子のその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What became of Ibaraki Doji after he took back his arm</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What became of Ibaraki Doji after he took back his arm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What became of Ibaraki Doji after he took back his arm</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>腕を取り戻した後の茨木童子の行方は定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no standard tale for where Ibaraki Doji went after he took back his arm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no standard tale for where Ibaraki Doji went after he took back his arm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no standard tale for where Ibaraki Doji went after he took back his arm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>摂津の民話では、しばしば実家に帰った話や、実家に帰ったが追い返された話などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are a number of folk legends in Settsu concerning what became of him, including that he returned to his parents&apos; home once more, or that he tried to return there only to be driven away.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are a number of folk legends in Settsu concerning what became of him, including that he returned to his parents&apos; home once more, or that he tried to return there only to be driven away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are a number of folk legends in Settsu concerning what became of him, including that he returned to his parents&apos; home once more, or that he tried to return there only to be driven away.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 逃亡者(id:14864), Rusk(id:9895), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Bergmann(id:85282), Nopira(id:29335), K-Phil(id:53114), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>