<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>公地公民制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kochi Komin sei (system of complete state ownership of land and citizens)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kochi Komin sei (system of complete state ownership of land and citizens)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kochi Komin sei (system of complete state ownership of land and citizens)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>公地公民制（こうちこうみんせい）とは、日本の飛鳥時代～奈良時代までの律令制が構築される過程において発生したとされる、全ての土地と人民は公 - すなわち天皇に帰属するとした制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kochi Komin sei&quot; is a system believed to have been instituted in the process of development of the Ritsuryo system from the Asuka Period to the Nara period, and under the system of Kochi Komin sei, it was provided for that all land and citizens should belong to the public, in other words, to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kochi Komin sei&quot; is a system believed to have been instituted in the process of development of the Ritsuryo system from the Asuka Period to the Nara period, and under the system of Kochi Komin sei, it was provided for that all land and citizens should belong to the public, in other words, to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kochi Komin sei&quot; is a system believed to have been instituted in the process of development of the Ritsuryo system from the Asuka Period to the Nara period, and under the system of Kochi Komin sei, it was provided for that all land and citizens should belong to the public, in other words, to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本では、第二次世界大戦以降、公地公民制について、古代律令制の基盤を形成した最重要の制度であると理解されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">AfterWorld War II, Kochi Komin sei was appreciated as the most important system that had constituted the basis of the ancient Ritsuryo system, in Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">AfterWorld War II, Kochi Komin sei was appreciated as the most important system that had constituted the basis of the ancient Ritsuryo system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>コンマを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">AfterWorld War II, Kochi Komin sei was appreciated as the most important system that had constituted the basis of the ancient Ritsuryo system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>が、20世紀末期頃からその存在が疑問視されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the end of the twentieth century, however, the existence of the system has been doubted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the end of the 20th century, however, the existence of the system has been doubted.</e>
<cmt>twentieth→20th としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the end of the 20th century, however, the existence of the system has been doubted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>従来の見解</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conventional view</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Traditional view</e>
<cmt>Conventional→Traditional</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Traditional view</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>646年（大化1）、前年の乙巳の変により即位した孝徳天皇は、新たな施政方針を改新の詔として示した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 646, Emperor Kotoku, having been enthroned through Isshi no hen (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) that occurred in the previous year, proclaimed an edict called Kaishin no Mikotonori as his new administrative policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 646, Emperor Kotoku who was enthroned through Isshi Coup (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) that occurred in the previous year proclaimed an imperial edict called Kaishin no Mikotonori as his new administrative policy.</e>
<cmt>Isshi no hen→Isshi Coup, having been→ who was、 余分なスペース、コンマを除きました。 edict→imperial edictとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 646, Emperor Kotoku who was enthroned through Isshi Coup (the Murder in the Year of Isshi) that occurred in the previous year proclaimed an imperial edict called Kaishin no Mikotonori as his new administrative policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>詔は大きく4か条の主文からと副文から構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The edict consisted of four main sections each of which was accompanied by subsections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The edict consisted of four main sections with those subsections.</e>
<cmt>each of～の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The edict consisted of four main sections with those subsections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>第1条には「従前の天皇等が立てた子代の民と各地の屯倉、そして臣・連・伴造・国造・村首の所有する部曲の民と各地の田荘は、これを廃止する。」と定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Section 1 provided that &quot;all of Koshiro people groups ruled by past emperors, Miyake lands set up by past emperors, and Kakibe people groups and Tadokoro lands controlled by their owners titled Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko and Mura no obito should be abolished.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 1 provided that &quot;all of Koshiro people groups ruled by the previous emperors, Miyake lands set up by the previous emperors, and Kakibe people groups and Tadokoro lands controlled by their owners titled Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko and Mura no obito should be abolished.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Section→ Article、 past→ the previous、余分なスペースを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 1 provided that &quot;all of Koshiro people groups ruled by the previous emperors, Miyake lands set up by the previous emperors, and Kakibe people groups and Tadokoro lands controlled by their owners titled Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko and Mura no obito should be abolished.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>（原文 罷昔在天皇等所立子代之民処々屯倉及臣連伴造国造村首所有する部曲之民処々田荘。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Original text: All of the Koshiro and Miyake established by the past emperors and all of the Kakibe and Tadokoro owned by Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko and Mura no obito shall be abolished.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Original text: All of the Koshiro and Miyake established by the previout emperors and all of the Kakibe and Tadokoro owned by Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko and Mura no obito shall be abolished.)</e>
<cmt>past→ previous</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Original text: All of the Koshiro and Miyake established by the previout emperors and all of the Kakibe and Tadokoro owned by Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko and Mura no obito shall be abolished.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>大化以前は、天皇や豪族らは各自で私的に土地・人民を所有・支配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Taika era, the emperors and gozoku (powerful families) privately owned and ruled lands and people respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Taika era, the emperors and Gozoku (local ruling family) privately owned and ruled lands and people respectively.</e>
<cmt>「豪族」を用語集に載っているものに修正、余分なスペースを消去しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Taika era, the emperors and Gozoku (local ruling family) privately owned and ruled lands and people respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>天皇・王族は、私的所有地である屯倉と私的支配民である名代・子代などを保有し、豪族らは、私的所有地である田荘と私的支配民である部曲などを保有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The emperors and royal families owned Miyake as their privately-owned domains and Nashiro and Koshiro as their privately-ruled citizens while gozoku families owned Tadokoro as their privately-owned domains and Kakibe as their privately-ruled citizens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The emperors and royal families owned Miyake as their privately-owned domains and Nashiro and Koshiro as their privately-ruled people while gozoku families owned Tadokoro as their privately-owned domains and Kakibe as their privately-ruled people.</e>
<cmt>他の文では人民をpeopleとしてあるので、citizens→peopleとしました。余分なスペースを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The emperors and royal families owned Miyake as their privately-owned domains and Nashiro and Koshiro as their privately-ruled people while gozoku families owned Tadokoro as their privately-owned domains and Kakibe as their privately-ruled people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ところが、改新の詔第1条は、こうした私的所有・支配を禁止し、全ての土地・人民は天皇（公）が所有・支配する体制の確立、すなわち私地私民制から公地公民制への転換を宣言するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Section 1 of the Kaishin no Mikotonori edict, however, banned such private ownership and control of lands and people and declared establishment of a system that the emperor (the public) should own and rule all the lands and citizens, in other words, conversion of Shichi Shimin sei (private ownership) to Kochi Komin sei (public ownership).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 1 in the Kaishin no Mikotonori edict, however, banned such private ownership and control of lands and people and declared the establishment of a system that the emperor (the public) should own and rule all the lands and pelple, in other words, the conversion of Shichi Shimin sei (private ownership) to Kochi Komin sei (public ownership).</e>
<cmt>Sction→Article, citizens→people, estblishment, conversionにそれぞれ冠詞をつけ、数箇所余分なスペースを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 1 in the Kaishin no Mikotonori edict, however, banned such private ownership and control of lands and people and declared the establishment of a system that the emperor (the public) should own and rule all the lands and pelple, in other words, the conversion of Shichi Shimin sei (private ownership) to Kochi Komin sei (public ownership).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>公地公民の原則に従って、朝廷は班田収授法に基づき人民へ口分田を与え、租税を納める義務を課した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the principle of Kochi Komin sei, the Imperial Court allotted kubunden (allotted rice fields) to citizens and imposed on them an obligation to pay land taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the principle of Kochi Komin sei, the Imperial Court allotted kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) to people and imposed on them an obligation to pay land taxes.</e>
<cmt>口分田の補足説明を用語集に載っていたものに修正、余分なスペースを消去、citizens→peopleに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the principle of Kochi Komin sei, the Imperial Court allotted kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) to people and imposed on them an obligation to pay land taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>この原則は、701年に制定された大宝律令にも継承され、律令制の根幹原則となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This principle, having been succeeded to by the Taiho Code enacted in 701, constituted the basic principle of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This principle succeeded to the Taiho Code which enacted in 701 to constitute the basic principle of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>having～by→succeeded to, enacted→which enacted, constituted→to constitute　に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This principle succeeded to the Taiho Code which enacted in 701 to constitute the basic principle of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>しかし、奈良時代に入ると三世一身法や墾田永年私財法により、人民による土地の私有が認められると、土地の公有という公地公民の原則が次第に形骸化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were enacted to permit citizens to privately own lands in the Nara Period, the Kochi Komin principle of public land ownership gradually became a dead letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were enacted to permit people to privately own lands in the Nara Period, the Kochi Komin principle of the public ownership of the lands gradually became a dead letter.</e>
<cmt>citizens→people, public land～の部分を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were enacted to permit people to privately own lands in the Nara Period, the Kochi Komin principle of the public ownership of the lands gradually became a dead letter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そして、土地私有によって荘園が盛行すると公地公民制は崩壊し、公地公民を原則とする律令制も瓦解への道をたどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, when the system of Shoen (manors) gathered stream, Kochi Komin sei collapsed, resulting in the demise of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, when the system of Shoen (manors) gathered stream by private owenership of the lands, Kochi Komin sei collapsed, resulting in the demise of the Ritsuryo system on the basis of Kochi Komin principle.</e>
<cmt>Further→Furthermore,「土地私有によって」「公地公民を原則とする」の部分の訳漏れ。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, when the system of Shoen (manors) gathered stream by private owenership of the lands, Kochi Komin sei collapsed, resulting in the demise of the Ritsuryo system on the basis of Kochi Komin principle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>新たな見解</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New view</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New view</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New view</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>上記のような公地公民論は、次第に疑問視される傾向にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There has been a growing trend that discredits the above view on Kochi Komin system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tendency to doubt the above view on Kochi Komin system is gradually increasing.</e>
<cmt>discredit→doubt, There has～→The tendency～increasing　に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tendency to doubt the above view on Kochi Komin system is gradually increasing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>まず、大化以前の支配体制とされる私地私民制について、屯倉が王権を支える経営拠点であるように、田荘もまた豪族の政治的地位を支える農業経営拠点であると解される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, in Shichi Shimin sei believed to have been the ruling system employed before the Taika era, tadokoro is understood to be the base for agricultural management that supported the political status of gozoku families as miyake was the management base that supported the sovereignty of the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, in Shichi Shimin sei believed to have been the ruling system employed before the Taika era, tadokoro is understood to be the base for agricultural management that supported the political status of gozoku families as miyake was the management base that supported the sovereignty of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, in Shichi Shimin sei believed to have been the ruling system employed before the Taika era, tadokoro is understood to be the base for agricultural management that supported the political status of gozoku families as miyake was the management base that supported the sovereignty of the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>屯倉と田荘は、天皇や豪族らの経営拠点であって、必ずしも天皇や豪族らの私有地を意味するものではなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Miyake and tadokoro, which served as management bases of the emperors and gozoku families, do not necessarily mean private domains owned by the emperors or gozoku families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Miyake and tadokoro which served as management bases of the emperors and gozoku families did not necessarily mean private domains owned by the emperors or gozoku families.</e>
<cmt>コンマを取り、do→didに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Miyake and tadokoro which served as management bases of the emperors and gozoku families did not necessarily mean private domains owned by the emperors or gozoku families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>また、豪族による田荘・部曲の支配は、改新の詔で禁止されたはずだったが、その後も朝廷が田荘・部曲の領有を豪族へ認めた事例が散見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, although the Kaishin no Mikotonori edict was to ban gozoku families from ruling tadokoro and kakibe, there have been found several examples where the Imperial Court permitted ownership of tadokoro and kakibe even after the edict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, although the Kaishin no Mikotonori edict was to ban gozoku families from ruling tadokoro and kakibe, several examples that the Imperial Court permitted ownership of tadokoro and kakibe even after the edict was announced have been found.</e>
<cmt>there have～、文の最後の部分を修正。 where→that、余分なスペースを消去しました。　</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, although the Kaishin no Mikotonori edict was to ban gozoku families from ruling tadokoro and kakibe, several examples that the Imperial Court permitted ownership of tadokoro and kakibe even after the edict was announced have been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>つまり、土地・人民の所有禁止は実際には発令されなかったか、もしくは所有禁止の実効性がなかなか各地へ浸透しなかったことを表す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, such examples evidences that the ban on private ownership of lands and citizens was not officially announced or that effects of the ban could not easily spread nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, such examples evidences that the ban on private ownership of lands and people was not officially announced or that effects of the ban could not easily spread nationwide.</e>
<cmt>citizens→ people、余分なスペースを消去しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, such examples evidences that the ban on private ownership of lands and people was not officially announced or that effects of the ban could not easily spread nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>これは、公地公民の原則が、当時の社会へ強力に貫徹していた訳ではなく、あくまで理念として掲げられていた側面が強かったことを示唆する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This suggests that the Kochi Komin principle did not penetrate the society at that time but that the principle was rather used as a banner in advocating the ideal,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This suggests that the Kochi Komin principle did not penetrate into the society at that time but that the principle was rather used as a banner in advocating the ideal.</e>
<cmt>penetrate→ penetrate into、終わりのコンマをピリオドに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This suggests that the Kochi Komin principle did not penetrate into the society at that time but that the principle was rather used as a banner in advocating the ideal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに、従来、公地と考えられてきた口分田は、律令施行の当時、実際のところ、私田・私地と認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, although kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer) have been conventionally considered as publicly-owned lands, they were, in fact, regarded as privately-owned lands or rice fields at the time when the laws of the Ritsuryo system were enacted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, kubunden that had been conventionally considered as publicly-owned lands were, in fact, regarded as privately-owned lands or rice fields at the time when the laws of the Ritsuryo system were enacted.</e>
<cmt>既に口分田という単語は出ているので、補足の部分は省きました。 although kubunden have→kubunden that had～に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, kubunden that had been conventionally considered as publicly-owned lands were, in fact, regarded as privately-owned lands or rice fields at the time when the laws of the Ritsuryo system were enacted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>公地公民制の基礎と言える「公地」の概念は、当時存在しておらず、口分田が「公田」と認識されるのは、墾田永年私財法（743年）以降である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The concept of &quot;Kochi&quot; (publicly-owned land) believed to have been the basis of Kochi Komin sei did not exist at that time and it was after the Konden Einen Shizai Law (743) that kubunden was recognized as state-owned rice field.</e>
<cmt>公田：用語検索の訳では a ruler の意味が国家支配者であるなのか私的支配者なのか曖昧になるので使いませんでした、</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The concept of &quot;Kochi&quot; (publicly-owned land) believed as the basis of Kochi Komin sei did not exist at that time and it was after the Konden Einen Shizai Law (enacted in 743) that kubunden was recognized as &quot;Koden&quot; (state-owned rice field).</e>
<cmt>to have been→as, (743)を修正。前半に&quot;Kochi&quot;とあるので、state-owned rice field→&quot;Koden&quot; (state-owned rice field)としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The concept of &quot;Kochi&quot; (publicly-owned land) believed as the basis of Kochi Komin sei did not exist at that time and it was after the Konden Einen Shizai Law (enacted in 743) that kubunden was recognized as &quot;Koden&quot; (state-owned rice field).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>すなわち、奈良時代当時、三世一身法や墾田永年私財法の施行によって、公地公民制や律令制に大きな破綻が訪れるという意識は存在していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, when Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were enacted in the Nara Period, these Laws were not regarded as leading to collapse of Kochi Komin sei and the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, when Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were enacted in the Nara Period, these Laws were not regarded as leading to collapse of Kochi Komin sei and the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, when Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were enacted in the Nara Period, these Laws were not regarded as leading to collapse of Kochi Komin sei and the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>そもそも当時、公地公民制という概念が存在していなかった可能性が高く、また三世一身法・墾田永年私財法は、むしろ律令制を補強することを目的として制定されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a high possibility that the notion of Kochi Komin sei did not exist at that time and therefore, institution of Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were rather aimed at reinforcing the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a high possibility that the notion of Kochi Komin sei did not exist at that time and therefore, institution of Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were rather aimed at reinforcing the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a high possibility that the notion of Kochi Komin sei did not exist at that time and therefore, institution of Sanze-isshin Law and Konden Einen Shizai Law were rather aimed at reinforcing the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="25">
<j>上記のように、公地公民制が律令制の根幹をなすという従来の通説は、大きく見直されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As discussed above, significant revision has been made on the conventional view that Kochi Kominsei formed the foundation of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As discussed above, significant revision has been made on the traditional view that Kochi Komin sei formed the foundation of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>conventional→ traditional、 Kominsei→ Komin sei　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As discussed above, significant revision has been made on the traditional view that Kochi Komin sei formed the foundation of the Ritsuryo system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), ArthurBot(id:265089), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>