<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>帝国財政革新会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai (conference on reform of imperial financial affairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai (conference on reform of imperial financial affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai (conference on reform of imperial financial affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>帝国財政革新会（ていこくざいせいかくしんかい）は、明治中期に設立された政治団体。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai was a political group established in the middle of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai was a political group established in the middle of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai was a political group established in the middle of the Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>1894年に須藤時一郎・田口卯吉・尾崎三良らが、税制を整理して減税を行い、地方や国民負担の軽減を唱えて結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1894, Tokiichiro SUDO, Ukichi TAGUCHI, and Saburo OZAKI formed this political group with political assertions of restructuring the tax system for tax reduction and reducing the tax burden on the provinces and poeple.</e>
<cmt>文意を明確にするために、「地方や国民負担の軽減を唱えて結成した」のところを、「地方や国民の租税負担の軽減を唱えてこの政治団体を結成した」の意味で訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiichiro SUDO, Ukichi TAGUCHI, and Saburo OZAKI formed this political group in 1894 with political assertions of restructuring the tax system for tax reduction to lessen the burden on the provinces and people.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。peopleがpoepleになってました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiichiro SUDO, Ukichi TAGUCHI, and Saburo OZAKI formed this political group in 1894 with political assertions of restructuring the tax system for tax reduction to lessen the burden on the provinces and people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>主に東京府会議員や財界人の支援を受け、3月23日に内務省 (日本)から設立許可を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the support of councilors of Tokyo Prefecture and businessmen of the financial world mainly, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai was approved by prewar Ministry of Home Affairs on March 23, 1894.</e>
<cmt>主語および西暦を追加して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It gained the main support from Tokyo Prefecture Assembly and bussinessmen before being approved for establishment by the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs on March 23.</e>
<cmt>単語調査では、東京府会議員はTokyo Prefecture Assemblyになっており、文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It gained the main support from Tokyo Prefecture Assembly and bussinessmen before being approved for establishment by the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs on March 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>設立経緯により東京府を中心とした都市部で活動し、地租軽減は訴えても営業税などの商工業者への課税の軽減には積極的とは言えなかった民党に代わる受け皿としての期待から、同年の第4回衆議院議員総選挙では須藤・田口ら4名が当選した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai operated in urban areas around Tokyo Prefecture due to its reason for establishment, and four candidates including SUDO and TAGUCHI were elected in the fourth general election of members of the House of Representatives in 1894 in the hope of taking over minto (general term of the political parties such as Liberal Party, Progressive Party and so on which conflicted with a han-dominated government when the Imperial Diet was inaugurated) which was reluctant to assert a reduction in taxation such as business taxes on commercial and industrial men while asserting a reduction in land taxes.</e>
<cmt>主語を追加して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai operated in urban areas around Tokyo Prefecture due to its reason for establishment, and its four candidates including SUDO and TAGUCHI were elected in the fourth general election of members of the House of Representatives in 1894 in the hopes of changing from Minto (general term of the political parties such as Liberal Party, Progressive Party and so on which conflicted with a domain government when the Imperial Diet was inaugurated) that was reluctant to reduce business taxes of commercial and industrial men while asserting a reduction in land taxes.</e>
<cmt>文章を滑らかにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai operated in urban areas around Tokyo Prefecture due to its reason for establishment, and its four candidates including SUDO and TAGUCHI were elected in the fourth general election of members of the House of Representatives in 1894 in the hopes of changing from Minto (general term of the political parties such as Liberal Party, Progressive Party and so on which conflicted with a domain government when the Imperial Diet was inaugurated) that was reluctant to reduce business taxes of commercial and industrial men while asserting a reduction in land taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>人権擁護と税制・財政改革を唱える一方で、日清戦争では積極的に政府支持に回る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While asserting protection of human rights and reform of taxation and finance, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai aggressively supported the government for Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt>主語を追加して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While asserting protection of human rights and taxation and finance reforms, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai enthusiastically supported the government during the Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt>積極的は、aggressivelyよりenthusiasticallyの方が良いと判断しました。文法も少々編集しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While asserting protection of human rights and taxation and finance reforms, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai enthusiastically supported the government during the Japanese-Sino War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、下関条約と三国干渉に対する反発から民党との連携路線に転じ、1896年の進歩党 (明治)結成に合流するために解散した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai shifted its policy to cooperation with minto due to the opposition to the Treaty of Shimonoseki and &quot;Sangoku Kansho&quot; (intervention by France, the German Empire and Russian Empire regarding returning Liaodong Bandao to Quing), and then dissolved to join the formation of the Progressive Party called &quot;Shinpo-To&quot; (Meiji Period) of 1896.</e>
<cmt>主語を追加して訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai shifted its policy to cooperate with minto due to the opposition to the Treaty of Shimonoseki and the Triple Intervention, and dissolved to join the formation of the Shinpo-to (Progressive Party of the Meiji Period) in 1896.</e>
<cmt>単語調査では三国干渉はTriple Interventionです。文章を短縮しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Teikokuzaiseikakushin kai shifted its policy to cooperate with minto due to the opposition to the Treaty of Shimonoseki and the Triple Intervention, and dissolved to join the formation of the Shinpo-to (Progressive Party of the Meiji Period) in 1896.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Fxcxt(id:21803), 水野白楓(id:22811), Complex01(id:10454), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>