<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三沢氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji (Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji (Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misawa clan</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三沢氏（みさわし、みさわうじ）は、信濃源氏の後裔で、信濃国飯島郷地頭の一族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji (Misawa clan) was a clan of estate steward in Iijima district, Shinano Province, and was the descendants of Shinano-Genji (Minamoto clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji (Misawa clan) was a clan of estate steward in Iijima district, Shinano Province, and was the descendants of Shinano-Genji (Minamoto clan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misawa clan (which is read Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji) was a clan acting as estate steward in Iijima District, Shinano Province, which were the descendants of Shinano-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>出雲三沢氏が宗家であり、その他の流れは傍流にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo Misawa clan was the head family, while the other clans were all branche families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo Misawa clan was the head family, while the other clans were all branche families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo Misawa clan was the head family, while other clans were all branch families.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>出自・家系</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Place of origin and lineage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Place of origin and lineage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Place of origin and lineage</e>
<cmt>語頭小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>出雲国の国人領主であった三沢氏の出自は、清和源氏木曾義仲を祖とする木曽系、同じく清和源氏満快流の飯島系と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji was one of kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords,) and its origin was reportedly the Kiso lineage founded by Yoshinaka KISO of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto Clan,) or the Iijima lineage linked to MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi of the same Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misawa-shi or Misawa-uji was one of kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords,) and its origin was reportedly the Kiso lineage founded by Yoshinaka KISO of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto Clan,) or the Iijima lineage linked to MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi of the same Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Misawa clan, a kokujin ryoshu (local samurai lords) of Izumo Province, was reportedly oriignated from the Kiso line descended from Yoshinaka KISO of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto Clan), or the Iijima line descded from MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi who was also from Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>木曾系の説は木曽義仲の孫木曾為仲を三沢氏の祖としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The theory of Kiso lineage insists that the founder of Misawa clan was KISO Tamenaka, a grandson of KISO Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>「木曽為仲」を説明する資料が見つかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The theory of Kiso lineage insists that the founder of Misawa clan was KISO Tamenaka, a grandson of KISO Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opinion supporting Kiso line states that the founder of Misawa clan was KISO Tamenaka, a grandson of KISO Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それに対して、長府藩に仕えた三沢家に伝わる史料では、同じ源氏でも、源満快の流れを汲んだ信濃国伊那郡飯島を本領とした飯島為国を祖としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, according to the historical data reserved by Misawa Family, who was retained by Chofu domain, the founder of Misawa clan was Tamekuni IIJIMA whose main domain was Iijima, Ina county, Shinano Province and who was linked to MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi of the same Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>「飯島為国」を説明する資料が見つかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, according to the historical data reserved by Misawa Family, who was retained by Chofu domain, the founder of Misawa clan was Tamekuni IIJIMA whose main domain was Iijima, Ina county, Shinano Province and who was linked to MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi of the same Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, according to the historical data reserved by Misawa family, who was retained by Chofu Domain, the founder of Misawa clan was Tamekuni IIJIMA whose main domain was Iijima, Ina county, Shinano Province and who was descded from MINAMOTO no Mitsuyoshi of the same Seiwa-Genji.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出雲三沢氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izumo Misawa-shi or Izumo Misawa-uji (Izumo Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izumo Misawa-shi or Izumo Misawa-uji (Izumo Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izumo Misawa clan</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>承久3年（1221年）の承久の乱で戦功を挙げた三沢為光は、出雲国三沢荘を与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MISAWA Tamemitsu was awarded with Misawa manor in Izumo Province afer his distinguished military services in the Jokyu War in 1221.</e>
<cmt>「三沢為光」を説明する資料がみつかりません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MISAWA Tamemitsu was awarded with Misawa manor in Izumo Province after his distinguished military servicein the Jokyu War in 1221.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamemitsu MISAWA was awarded the Misawa manor in Izumo Province after his distinguished military service in the Jokyu War in 1221.</e>
<cmt>姓名の順番入れ替えスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その後の1302年に三沢為長（為仲）が、因幡国鹿野町を経て往来し、この地で良質な砂鉄を採取して野たたら製鉄を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lator, in 1302, Tamenaga (Tamenaka) MISAWA often visited this manor via Shikano-cho, Inaba Province, and started iron making by means of no-tatara-seitetsu (a kind of iron manufacturing method) using good iron sands obtainable in this area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, in 1302, Tamenaga (Tamenaka) MISAWA often visited this manor via Shikano-cho, Inaba Province, and started iron making by means of no-tatara-seitetsu (a kind of iron manufacturing method) using good iron sand which could be obtained in the area.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1302, Tamenaga (also known as Tamenaka) MISAWA often visited this manor through Shikano-cho, Inaba Province, and started iron manufacturing by means of &apos;no-tatara-seitetsu&apos; (iron manufacturing method) using high quality iron sand which could be obtained in the area.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>野たたら製鉄、山野開拓により力をつけ、嘉元3年（1305年）、仁多郡内をはじめ島根半島までも一望できる要衝の地・鴨倉山に当城、要害山三沢城を築城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became so powerful by iron manufacturing as well as exploitation of nearby fields and mountains, that he constructed in 1305 Yogaisan Mizawa-jo (Mizawa Castle on Mt. Yogaisan) on Mt. Kamokura-yama (later renamed to Mt. Yogaisan,) a place of strategic importance which commanded a panoramic view of Nita county and even Shimane Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became so powerful through iron manufacturing as well as exploiting nearby fields and mountains, that he constructed in 1305 Yogaisan Mizawa-jo (Mizawa Castle on Mt. Yogaisan) on Mt. Kamokura-yama (later renamed to Mt. Yogaisan,) a place of strategic importance which commanded a panoramic view of Nita county and even Shimane Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became so powerful by iron manufacturing and exploiting nearby fields and mountains, that he constructed Yogaisan Mizawa-jo (Mizawa Castle on Mt. Yogaisan) on Mt. Kamokura, later renamed to Mt. Yogaisan, in 1305, a place of strategic point which commanded a panoramic view of Nita county and also the Shimane Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>同時に信濃から当地に移り、以後、名字も三沢と改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, Tamenaga shifted his residence from Shinano to this place, after which he renewed his family name to MISAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Tamenaga shifted his residence from Shinano to this place, after which he renewed his family name to MISAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Tamenaga moved his residence from Shinano to this place, after which he changed his family name to MISAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これが出雲三沢氏の始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This marked the beginning of Izumo Misawa Clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処置</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This marked the beginning of Izumo Misawa Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This marked the beginning of the Izumo Misawa clan.</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、木曾系を出自とすると、三沢為仲が三沢に入って三沢氏を称したのが始まりとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, if we presume Kiso lineage as the origin of Misawa Clan, it should be considered to be the beginning of Izumo Misawa Clan that Tamenaka MISAWA entered into MISAWA and proclaimed MISAWA as his clan&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, if we presume Kiso lineage as the origin of Misawa Clan, it should be considered to be the beginning of Izumo Misawa Clan that Tamenaka MISAWA entered into MISAWA and proclaimed MISAWA as his clan&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If it is presumed that the Kiso line was the origin of the Misawa clan, the beginning of the Izumo Misawa clan is considered to be Tamenaka MISAWA&apos;s entrance into MISAWA and proclamation of MISAWA as his clan&apos;s name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>室町時代には出雲国を支配していた山名氏の傘下に入り、1391年には出雲守護山名満幸に従って明徳の乱に出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi Period, Misawa Clan became affiliated with Yamana Clan, then ruler of Izumo Province, and then accompanied Mitsuyuki YAMANA, who was shugo (a provincial constable) of Izumo Province, to fight in Meitoku War in 1391.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi Period, Misawa Clan became affiliated with Yamana Clan, then ruler of Izumo Province, and then accompanied Mitsuyuki YAMANA, who was shugo (a provincial constable) of Izumo Province, to fight in Meitoku War in 1391.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period, the Misawa clan became affiliated with the Yamana clan, then ruler of Izumo Province, and accompanied Mitsuyuki YAMANA, who was a provincial constable of Izumo Province, to fight in the Meitoku War in 1391.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>当主の三沢為忠は討死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tametada MISAWA, the head of Misawa Clan, died in the battle of Meitoku War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tametada MISAWA, the head of Misawa Clan, died in the battle of Meitoku War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tametada MISAWA, the head of Misawa clan, died in battle during the Meitoku War.</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>室町時代末期には、新守護の京極氏に従い、出雲国の有力国人として成長を遂げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At a late stage of the Muromachi Period, Misawa Clan achieved considerable growth as kokujin (local samurai) under a new provincial constable, Kyogoku Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At a late stage of the Muromachi Period, Misawa Clan achieved considerable growth as kokujin (local samurai) under a new provincial constable, Kyogoku Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late in the Muromachi period, the Misawa clan achieved considerable growth as local samurai of Izumo Province under a new provincial constable, the Kyogoku clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)になると守護京極氏の所領を奪った尼子氏とは対立関係となり、尼子経久追放の中心として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Sengoku Period (the period of warring states) in Japan, the provincial constable Kyogoku Clan was deprived of its manor by Amago Clan with whom Misawa Clan came into collision playing an active role as a central figure to deport Tsunehisa Amago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku Period (the period of warring states) in Japan, the provincial constable Kyogoku Clan was deprived of its manor by Amago Clan with whom Misawa Clan came into collision playing an active role as a central figure to deport Tsunehisa Amago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of warring states, the provincial constable Kyogoku clan was taken over its manor by the Amago clan which clashed with the Misawa clan by playing an active and central role in deporting Tsunehisa AMAGO.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし1488年に三沢為国は尼子経久と戦って敗れ、その傘下に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in 1488, Tamekuni MISAWA was defeated by Tsunehisa AMAGO and became under the control of Amago Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in 1488, Tamekuni MISAWA was defeated by Tsunehisa AMAGO and became under the control of Amago Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1488, Tamekuni MISAWA was defeated by Tsunehisa AMAGO and came under the control of the Amago clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、経久三男の塩冶興久の率いる反尼子同盟に加わり、興久の反乱に加担したため、1531年に尼子経久に藤ヶ瀬城が再度攻撃を受け、三沢為国らは捕虜となる事態も起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, since Tamekuni joined and sided with an ally in a rebellion against Amago Clan, which was led by Okihisa ENYA, the third son of Tsunehisa AMAGO, Tamekuni&apos;s Fujigase-jo Castle was again attacked by Tsunehisa AMAGO in 1531 and Tamekuni MISAWA and his followers were held captive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, since Tamekuni joined and sided with an ally in a rebellion against Amago Clan, which was led by Okihisa ENYA, the third son of Tsunehisa AMAGO, Tamekuni&apos;s Fujigase-jo Castle was again attacked by Tsunehisa AMAGO in 1531 and Tamekuni MISAWA and his followers were held captive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Tamekuni joined and sided with an ally in a rebellion against the Amago clan, which was led by Okihisa ENYA, the third son of Tsunehisa AMAGO, Tamekuni&apos;s Fujigasejo Castle was again attacked by Tsunehisa AMAGO in 1531 and Tamekuni MISAWA and his followers were held captive.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これは当主の三沢為幸の手引きによる行動で、独立した動きを取る兄と弟を封じ込める策であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, this was a trick of Tameyuki MISAWA, the head of MISAWA Clan, who tried to contain independent movements of his elder and younger sons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, this was a trick of Tameyuki MISAWA, the head of MISAWA Clan, who tried to contain the independent movements of his elder and younger sons.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a scheme by Tameyuki MISAWA, the head of MISAWA clan, who tried to contain the independent movements by his elder and younger sons.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>三沢為幸はその後も尼子氏に従い、1540年の吉田郡山城の戦いに出陣し、吉田郡山城の戦い青山土取場の戦いで討死を遂げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tameyuki MISAWA continued to submit Amago Clan, and went to Yoshida Koriyama-jo no Tatakai (the battle of Yoshida Koriyama-jo Castle) in 1540, where he died on the battlefield of Aoyama Tsuchitoriba no Tatakai (the battle at Aoyama borrow pit.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tameyuki MISAWA continued to submit Amago Clan, and went to Yoshida Koriyama-jo no Tatakai (the battle of Yoshida Koriyama-jo Castle) in 1540, where he died on the battlefield of Aoyama Tsuchitoriba no Tatakai (the battle at Aoyama borrow pit.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, Tameyuki MISAWA continued to submit to the Amago clan, and participated in the Battle of Yoshida Koriyamajo Castle in 1540, where he died in a Battle at Aoyama Borrow Pit.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="20">
<j>跡を継いだ三沢為清は大内氏に従属したが、月山富田城の戦いで吉川氏らと共に尼子氏に寝返り、大内軍敗退の一因を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamekiyo MISAWA, successor of Tameyuki MISAWA, was subordinate to Ouchi Clan, but, in Gassan Toda-jo no Tatakai (the Battle of Gassan Toda-jo Castle,) his Misawa Clan and Yoshikawa Clan together defected to the enemy, Amago Clan and contributed to the defeat of Ouchi side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamekiyo MISAWA, successor of Tameyuki MISAWA, was subordinate to Ouchi Clan, but, in Gassan Toda-jo no Tatakai (the Battle of Gassan Toda-jo Castle,) his Misawa Clan and Yoshikawa Clan together defected to the enemy, Amago Clan and contributed to the defeat of Ouchi side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamekiyo MISAWA, a successor of Tameyuki MISAWA, was subordinate to the Ouchi clan, but, in the Battle of Gassan Todajo Castle, the Misawa and Yoshikawa clans jointly defected to the enemy, the Amago clan, and contributed to the defeat of Ouchi.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし三沢氏の独立性は高く、尼子氏の軍役を拒否して尼子氏との戦いに及んだ場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, Misawa Clan maintained its strong independence, as seen in the case of its rejection to offer military services to Amago Clan, which induced a fighting between the two clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, Misawa Clan maintained its strong independence, as seen in the case of its rejection to offer military services to Amago Clan, which induced a fighting between the two clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, the Misawa clan maintained its strong independence, as seen in the rejection to offer military services to the Amago clan, which induced fighting between the two clans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>尼子晴久は自分の娘を為清に嫁がせ、三沢氏の懐柔を図った上で、更には横田荘の三沢氏領地や砂鉄産地・たたら製鉄場を取り上げ直轄化するなど、経久に比べて強硬的な姿勢で三沢氏と統治している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haruhisa AMAGO controlled Misawa Clan in tougher attitude than Tsunehisa, in such ways as extorting the Yokota manor and locality of iron sands and tatara iron making site to put them under his direct control, after marrying off his daughter to Tamekiyo MISAWA with the intention to win Misawa Clan over to his side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haruhisa AMAGO controlled Misawa Clan in tougher attitude than Tsunehisa, in such ways as extorting the Yokota manor and locality of iron sands and tatara iron making site to put them under his direct control, after marrying off his daughter to Tamekiyo MISAWA with the intention to win Misawa Clan over to his side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haruhisa AMAGO controlled the Misawa clan with an attitude which was much tougher than Tsunehisa, by bringing the Yokota manor, the areas where iron sand could be obtained, and tatara iron making sites, under his direct control after marrying off his daughter to Tamekiyo MISAWA with the intention of winning the Misawa clan over to his side.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>1561年、大内領であった周防国・長門国を完全に制圧した毛利元就が出雲への本格的な侵攻を開始すると、赤穴氏、三刀屋氏とともに三沢氏も毛利氏に降伏した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1561, when Motonari MORI launched a full-scale invasion into Izumo, after completely conquering Provinces of Suo and Nagato that had been domains of Ouchi Clan, Misawa, Akana and Mitoya Clans surrendered to Mori Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1561, when Motonari MORI launched a full-scale invasion into Izumo, after completely conquering Provinces of Suo and Nagato that had been domains of Ouchi Clan, Misawa, Akana and Mitoya Clans surrendered to Mori Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Motonari MORI launched a full-scale invasion into Izumo after completely conquering the Provinces of Suo and Nagato, which had been domains of the Ouchi clan, in1561, the Misawa, Akana and Mitoya clans surrendered to Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後の出雲侵攻には毛利軍の主力として活動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Mori&apos;s further invasion into Izumo, Misawa Clan acted as a main force of Mori army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Mori&apos;s further invasion into Izumo, Misawa Clan acted as a main force of Mori army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon Mori&apos;s further invasion into Izumo, the Misawa clan acted as the main force behind the Mori army.</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>尼子氏の滅亡後に、山中幸盛や尼子勝久が尼子再興軍として出雲への侵攻を図り、旧尼子家臣団にも動揺が走り、再興軍に加わる国人や豪族が続出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After demolition of Amago Clan, Yukimori YAMANAKA and Katsuhisa AMAGO organized an army to invade Izumo for restoration of Amago Clan, which caused commotion among old Amago retainers and induced kokujin (local land lords) and gozoku (local ruling families) to join the restoration army one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the fall of the Amago Clan, Yukimori YAMANAKA and Katsuhisa AMAGO organized an army to invade Izumo for restoration of Amago Clan, which caused a commotion among the old Amago retainers and induced kokujin (local land lords) and gozoku (local ruling families) to join the restoration army one after another.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the fall of the Amago clan, Yukimori YAMANAKA and Katsuhisa AMAGO organized an army to invade Izumo for the restoration of the Amago clan, which raised the morale among the old Amago retainers and induced local land lords and local ruling families to join the restoration army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その中で三沢為清は一貫して毛利氏に従い、尼子再興軍の撃退に活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Tamekiyo MISAWA consistently obeyed Mori Clan and played an active role in repelling the Amago restoration army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, Tamekiyo MISAWA consistently obeyed the Mori Clan and played an active role in repelling the Amago restoration army.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, Tamekiyo MISAWA consistently followed the Mori clan and played an active role in repelling the Amago restoration army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="27">
<j>為清死後の1589年、息子の三沢為虎は毛利輝元に謀られ、幽閉の身となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1589 after Tamekiyo died, his son Tametora MISAWA was placed under confinement through a design of Terumoto MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1589 after Tamekiyo died, his son Tametora MISAWA was placed under confinement through a design of Terumoto MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1589 after Tamekiyo died, his son Tametora MISAWA was placed under confinement through a plot of Terumoto MORI.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>その後解放されて長門国厚狭郡古帳に10000石を領する身となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, he was released from confinement and allowed a domain of ten thousand koku in 古帳, Asa-gun (Asa county,) Nagato Province</e>
<cmt>「古帳」の読みが不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, he was released from confinement and allowed a domain of ten thousand koku in 古帳, Asa-gun (Asa county,) Nagato Province</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, he was released from confinement and allowed a domain of ten thousand koku in 古帳, Asa-gun (Asa county,) Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この幽閉劇は、毛利氏による旧尼子家臣団への締め付けと出雲国の支配強化が狙いであり、三沢氏同様、旧尼子家臣団でもあった三刀屋久扶も追放の憂き目にあっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This dramatic confinement was designed by Mori Clan to increase its pressure on the retainers of old Amago Clan and to strengthen its lordship over Izumo Province, so that Hisasuke MITOYA who had been a member of old Amago&apos;s retainer group also suffered from exile in the same way as retainers of Misawa Clan suffered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This dramatic confinement was designed by Mori Clan to increase its pressure on the retainers of old Amago Clan and to strengthen its lordship over Izumo Province, so that Hisasuke MITOYA who had been a member of old Amago&apos;s retainer group also suffered from exile in the same way as retainers of Misawa Clan suffered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This dramatic confinement was designed by the Mori clan to increase its pressure on the retainers of the old Amago clan and strengthen its lordship over Izumo Province, such that Hisasuke MITOYA who had been a member of the old Amago&apos;s retainer group also suffered exile in the same manner as those of the Misawa clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>三沢為虎はその能力を買われており、追放されなかっただけ三刀屋氏よりはましであったかもしれない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tametora MISAWA might have suffered less than Mitoya Clan only because he was not exiled thanks to his talent being appreciated by Mori Clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tametora MISAWA might have suffered less than Mitoya Clan only because he was not exiled thanks to his talent being appreciated by Mori Clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tametora MISAWA might have suffered less than the Mitoya clan only because he was not exiled due to his talent being appreciated by Mori clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="31">
<j>為虎は翌年の豊臣秀吉の小田原征伐にも参加し、文禄・慶長の役でも毛利軍の一員として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next year, Tametora joined Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to go on an expedition against Odawara, and took an active part as a member of Mori&apos;s force also in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, Tametora joined Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to go on an expedition against Odawara, and also took an active part as a member of Mori&apos;s force in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, Tametora joined Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to go on an expedition against Odawara, and also took an active part as a member of Mori&apos;s force in the Bunroku-Keicho War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="32">
<j>1600年の関ヶ原の戦いでは赤間関を守備。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he took charge of defence of Akamagaseki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he took charge in the defence of Akamagaseki.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, he took charge in the defense of Akamagaseki.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>敗戦の後、三沢為虎は長府藩の家老職となり、三沢氏は江戸時代を長府藩士として続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being defeated in the Battle of Sekigahara, Tametora MISAWA took a post of chief retainer of Chofu domain, while Misawa Clan continued to exist as statesmen of the Chofu domain during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being defeated in the Battle of Sekigahara, Tametora MISAWA took a post as chief retainer of Chofu domain, while Misawa Clan continued to exist as statesmen of the Chofu domain during the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being defeated in the Battle of Sekigahara, Tametora MISAWA took a post as chief retainer of Chofu Domain, while the Misawa clan continued to exist as statesmen of the Chofu Domain during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字domain語頭大文字period語頭小文字</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>陸奥三沢氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mutsu Misawa-shi or Mutsu Misawa-uji (Mutsu Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mutsu Misawa-shi or Mutsu Misawa-uji (Mutsu Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mutsu Misawa clan</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字他の記事と合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>三沢為虎の息子・三沢為基が長府藩を出奔して、仙台藩伊達氏に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamemoto MISAWA, a son of Tametora MISAWA, vanished from the Chofu domain to be retained by Date Clan of Sendai domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamemoto MISAWA, a son of Tametora MISAWA, vanished from the Chofu domain to be retained by Date Clan of Sendai domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamemoto MISAWA, a son of Tametora MISAWA, vanished from the Chofu Domain to be retained by the Date clan of Sendai Domain.</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字domain語頭大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>為基の息子三沢清長は娘・初子が藩主伊達綱宗の側室（伊達綱村生母・綱宗には正室はいなかった） となった事から重臣の待遇を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyonaga MISAWA, a son of Tamemoto, was treated as a senior vassal because his daughter Hatsuko became a concubine of Tsunamune DATE, the head of Date domain, who had no legal wife (so, Hatsuko was the real mother of Tsunamura DATE.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyonaga MISAWA, a son of Tamemoto, was treated as a senior vassal because his daughter Hatsuko became a concubine of Tsunamune DATE, the head of Date domain, who had no legal wife (so, Hatsuko was the real mother of Tsunamura DATE.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyonaga MISAWA, a son of Tamemoto, was treated as a senior vassal because his daughter Hatsuko became a concubine of Tsunamune DATE, the head of the Date Domain, who had no legal wife (Hatsuko was the real mother of Tsunamura DATE).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>伊達綱村、伊達村和、伊達宗贇は、伊達綱村と三沢初子との間にできた子である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunamura DATE, Murayori DATE and Muneyoshi DATE were born between Tsunamune DATE and Hatsuko MISAWA.</e>
<cmt>「・・・伊達綱村と三沢初子との間にできた子である」の「伊達綱村」はあきらかに「伊達綱宗」の誤りです。原文を「伊達綱宗」に訂正した上で訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunamura DATE, Murayori DATE and Muneyoshi DATE were born between Tsunamune DATE and Hatsuko MISAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunamura, Murayori, and Muneyoshi DATE were born to Tsunamune DATE and Hatsuko MISAWA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="37">
<j>三沢氏の血は亀田藩岩城氏、宇和島藩伊達氏にも流れており、出雲三沢氏の母系の子孫は奥州でも繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Misawa Clan was blood-related to Iwaki Clan of Kameda domain and Date Clan of Uwajima domain, while matrilineal descendants of Izumo Misawa Clan thrived also in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa Provinces.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Misawa Clan was blood-related to Iwaki Clan of Kameda domain and Date Clan of Uwajima domain, while matrilineal descendants of Izumo Misawa Clan thrived also in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa Provinces.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Misawa clan was related by blood to the Iwaki clan of the Kameda Domain and the Date clan of the Uwajima Domain, while matrilineal descendants of the Izumo Misawa clan also thrived in Oshu (Northern Honshu, the region encompassing Mutsu and Dewa Provinces).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>因幡三沢氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inaba Misawa-shi or Inaba Misawa-uji (Inaba Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inaba Misawa-shi or Inaba Misawa-uji (Inaba Misawa Clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inaba Misawa clan</e>
<cmt>clan語頭小文字他の記事と合わせる</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="38">
<j>三沢為虎の息子・三沢為朝が鳥取藩池田氏に仕えて因幡三沢氏の祖となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tametomo MISAWA, a son of Tametora MISAWA, founded Inaba Misawa Clan when he served Ikeda Clan of Tottori domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tametomo MISAWA, a son of Tametora MISAWA, founded Inaba Misawa Clan when he served Ikeda Clan of Tottori domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tametomo MISAWA, a son of Tametora MISAWA, founded the Inaba Misawa clan when he served the Ikeda clan of the Tottori Domain.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 WhiteWing(id:135913), やりたこ(id:113528), Kuma83(id:31177), Flatbarker(id:119836), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>