<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>短陌</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanhaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanhaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanhaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>短陌（たんはく、省陌（しょうはく）とも）は、近代以前の東アジア地域で行われてきた商慣習で、100枚以下の一定枚数によって構成された銅銭の束を銅銭100枚と同一の価値として扱う事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanhaku (also called shohaku) is a business custom which had been conducted in East Asia, with this custom, a bundle of copper coins consisting of certain number of coins less than 100 is treated as equal value with 100 copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanhaku (also called shohaku) is a business custom which had been conducted in East Asia, with this custom, a bundle of copper coins consisting of a certain number of coins less than 100 is treated as equal value to 100 copper coins.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanhaku (also called shohaku) is a business custom which had been conducted in East Asia before the early modern times; with this custom, a bundle of copper coins consisting of a certain number of coins less than 100 is treated as equal value to 100 copper coins.</e>
<cmt>近世以前　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>唐代以後、中国王朝が発行する銅銭は高い信用価値をもって通用されて日本をはじめとする周辺諸国においても自国通貨に代わって用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the period of Tang Dynasty, copper coins issued by Chinese dynasty were prevailed with high creditworthiness, then Japan and other neighboring countries started use them instead of local currency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the period of the Tang Dynasty, copper coins issued by the Chinese dynasty were prevailed with high creditworthiness, so Japan and other neighboring countries started using them instead of the local currency.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the period of the Tang Dynasty, copper coins issued by the Chinese dynasty were prevailed with high creditworthiness, so Japan and other neighboring countries started using them instead of the local currency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>だが中国の銅の生産能力は決して高いとは言えない上に、経済の急速な発展から銅銭の需要が銅銭発行量を上回るペースで高まったために、結果的には市中に流通する銅銭が慢性的に不足すると言う銭荒現象が生じるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Chinese copper production capacity was not high enough and a demand for copper coins increased at a pace surpassing the amount of copper coin issue due to the rapid economic development, a phenomenon called senko that the quantity of circulating copper coins was chronically short occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Chinese copper production capacity was not high enough and a demand for copper coins increased at a pace surpassing the amount of copper coins issued due to rapid economic development, a phenomenon called senko that the quantity of circulating copper coins was chronically short occurred.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Chinese copper production capacity was not high enough and a demand for copper coins increased at a pace surpassing the amount of copper coins issued due to rapid economic development, a phenomenon called senko that the quantity of circulating copper coins was chronically short occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="4">
<j>そのため、銅銭の実際の価値が公定の価格以上に上昇して経済的に大きな影響を与えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the actual value of copper coin became higher than official value and it had a major impact on the economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the actual value of the copper coin became higher than the official value and it had a major impact on the economy.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the actual value of the copper coin became higher than the official value and it had a major impact on the economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、唐代末期以後に銅銭の穴に紐をとおして纏めた束一差しに一定枚数があればそれをもって100枚と見なすという短陌の慣習が形成されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the custom of considering a bundle of copper coins consisting of certain number of coins as 100 coins, which was called tanhaku, was formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, the custom of considering a bundle of copper coins consisting of a certain number of coins as 100 coins, which was called tanhaku, was formed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the custom of tanhaku, in which a bundle of a certain number of copper coins held together by a piece of string was considered to be 100 coins, became established from around the end of the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="6">
<j>これは、実質上の通貨の切り上げになると同時に銅銭を多く取り扱う大商人に有利な制度として定着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This meant actual revaluation of currency and at the same time, it became established as a favorable system for merchant princes who handled a great number of copper coins.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This meant actual revaluation of currency and at the same time, it became established as a favorable system for merchant princes who handled a great number of copper coins.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This meant actual revaluation of currency and at the same time, it became established as a favorable system for merchant princes who handled a great number of copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>五代十国の一つである後漢_(五代)の宰相であった王章 (五代)は、77枚をもって銅銭100枚として見なす事を公的に許すようになり、宋 (王朝)以後の王朝でも採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Osho (王章) who was the prime minister of the Later Han Dynasty, one of Wudai Shiguo officially permitted to consider 77 copper coins equal to 100 and it was also adopted in the dynasties after Sung.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osho (王章) who was the prime minister of the Later Han Dynasty, one of Wudai Shiguo officially permitted to consider 77 copper coins equal to 100 and it was also adopted in the dynasties after the Sung.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osho (王章) (Five Dynasties period) who was the prime minister of the Later Han Dynasty (Five Dynasties period), one of Godai-Jikkoku (Wudai Shiguo) period, officially permitted to consider 77 copper coins equal to 100 and it was also adopted in the dynasties after the Sung.</e>
<cmt>(五代）　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>民間では更に少ない枚数での短陌レートが設けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For civilians, the rate of tanhaku with less number of coins was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For civilians, the rate of tanhaku with fewer coins was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For civilians, the rate of tanhaku with fewer coins was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これに対して、短陌を用いずに銅銭100枚をもって支払うことを中国では「足銭」、日本では「長銭」・「調陌」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A payment made with 100 copper coins instead of tanhaku is called &apos;足銭&apos; in Chinese and &apos;chosen (長銭)&apos; or &apos;chohaku (調陌)&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A payment made with 100 copper coins instead of tanhaku is called &apos;足銭&apos; in Chinese and &apos;chosen (長銭)&apos; or &apos;chohaku (調陌)&apos; in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A payment made with 100 copper coins instead of tanhaku is called &apos;足銭&apos; in Chinese and &apos;chosen&apos; (長銭) or &apos;chohaku&apos; (調陌) in Japanese.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションマークの場所を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>短陌は銅銭不足であった当時の経済状況に合わせた慣習であり、銅銭の輸送の不便さを軽減する上では歓迎された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanhaku was a custom fit for the economic situation at that time and hailed as a method to reduce the inconvenience of delivering copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanhaku was a custom fit for the economic situation at that time and hailed as a method to reduce the inconvenience of delivering copper coins.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanhaku was a custom fit for the economic situation at that time and hailed as a method to reduce the inconvenience of delivering copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>だが、銅銭を多く保有して多額の取引を行う大商人には実質上の資産価値の増大に繋がる一方、短陌を外してしまうと銅銭本来の公定価値に戻ってしまう（宋代の公定価値を元にすると、短陌を外した銅銭を全て合わせても77枚分の価値しか有しないために、23枚分の損となる）ために、日常生活において小額の取引がほとんどである庶民にとっては大変不利な制度でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, while it led to the increase in property value of merchant princes who owned a lot of copper coins and carried out a trading, it was very unfavorable system for ordinary people whose trading was mostly with small amount of money in daily life because if tanhaku wasn&apos;t adopted, the value returned to primary official value of copper coin (if it was calculated based on the official value in the age of Sung, the total value of coppers without tanhaku would be just the value of 77 coins, thus it resulted in loss of 23 coins).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, while it led to the increase in property value of merchant princes who owned a lot of copper coins and carried out trading, it was a very unfavorable system for ordinary people whose trading was mostly with a small amount of money in daily life because if tanhaku wasn&apos;t adopted, the value returned to the primary official value of the copper coin (if it was calculated based on the official value in the age of Sung, the total value of coppers without tanhaku would be just the value of 77 coins, thus it resulted in a loss of 23 coins).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, while it led to the increase in property value of merchant princes who owned a lot of copper coins and carried out trading, it was a very unfavorable system for ordinary people whose trading was mostly with a small amount of money in daily life because if tanhaku wasn&apos;t adopted, the value returned to the primary official value of the copper coin (if it was calculated based on the official value in the age of Sung, the total value of coppers without tanhaku would be just the value of 77 coins, thus it resulted in a loss of 23 coins).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>日本においては、室町時代に銅銭97枚をもって100枚とみなす商慣習があったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, it is said that there was a business custom with which 97 copper coins were considered as 100 coins in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, it is said that there was a business custom with which 97 copper coins were considered as 100 coins in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, it is said that there was a business custom with which 97 copper coins were considered as 100 coins in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>江戸時代に銅銭96枚（＝96文）の束をもって銭100文と見なした慣習も短陌の一つと見なされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The custom with which a bundle of 96 copper coins was considered as 100 coins in the Edo period is regarded as one of tanhaku.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The custom with which a bundle of 96 copper coins was considered as 100 coins in the Edo period is regarded as one of tanhaku.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The custom with which a bundle of 96 copper coins (equal to 96 mon [an old currency unit in Japan]) was considered as 100 coins in the Edo period is regarded as one of tanhaku.</e>
<cmt>96文　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その慣習は戦国時代 (日本)初期の永正2年（1505年）の室町幕府による撰銭令の中において、（銅銭96枚を100文とすることを前提として）100文の1/3を32文として換算する規定が見られ、こうした慣行を九六銭（くろくせん）とも呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This custom is found in the ban on use of poor-quality currency issued by the Muromachi bakufu in the early Sengoku period (period of warring states), 1505, saying (on the assumption that 96 cooper coins is considered as 100 mon) all figures must be converted at 32 mon to one third of 100 mon, such custom was also called kurokusen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This custom is found in the ban on use of poor-quality currency issued by the Muromachi bakufu in the early Sengoku period (period of warring states), 1505, saying (on the assumption that 96 cooper coins is considered as 100 mon) all figures must be converted at 32 mon to one third of 100 mon, such a custom was also called kurokusen.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This custom is found in the ban on use of poor-quality currency issued by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in the early Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan), 1505, saying (on the assumption that 96 cooper coins is considered as 100 mon) all figures must be converted at 32 mon to one third of 100 mon, and such a custom was also called kurokusen (&quot;ku&quot; means 9, &quot;roku&quot; means 6 and &quot;sen&quot; means money).</e>
<cmt>九六銭　の補足を追加しました。幕府　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nopira(id:29335), R28Bot(id:177951), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>