<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三事兼帯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanji kentai</e>
<cmt>[定訳不明]http://s.luna.tv/search.aspx?client=lunascape&amp;s=0&amp;gl=jp&amp;hl=ja&amp;q=sanji kentai</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanji kentai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanji Kentai</e>
<cmt>語頭大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三事兼帯（さんじけんたい）とは、五位蔵人・弁官・検非違使佐を兼帯すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Sanji kentai means concurrently assuming the positions of Goi no kurodo (Kurodo with the fifth rank), Benkan (officials of the Dajokan (Grand Council of State)) and Kebiishi no suke (assistant official of the Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>兼帯　http://www.eudict.com/?lang=jpkeng&amp;word=%E5%85%BC%E5%B8%AF</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Sanji kentai means concurrently assuming the positions of Goi no kurodo (Kurodo with the fifth rank), Benkan (officials of the Dajokan - Grand Council of State)) and Kebiishi no suke (assistant official of the Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Sanji kentai means concurrently assuming the positions of Goi no kurodo (Kurodo with the fifth rank), Benkan (officials of the Dajokan - Grand Council of State)) and Kebiishi no suke (assistant official of the Police and Judicial Chief).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>蔵人佐（五位蔵人で検非違使佐を兼ねる）が弁官に就任して、実現されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of such cases occurred when a person of Kurandonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) (who assumed the positions of Goi no kurodo and Kebiishi no suke concurrently) assumed the office of Benkan.</e>
<cmt>[定訳不明]http://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/e-rekihaku/108/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of such cases occurred when a person of Kurandonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) (who assumed the positions of Goi no kurodo and Kebiishi no suke concurrently) assumed the office of Benkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of such cases occurred when a person of Kurandonosuke (assistant official of kurodo) (who assumed the positions of Goi no kurodo and Kebiishi no suke concurrently) assumed the office of Benkan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>延喜5年（905年）の藤原清貫が初例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First case ocuurred when FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura assumed three positions in 905.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first case ocuurred when FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura assumed three positions in 905.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first case occurred when FUJIWARA no Kiyotsura assumed three positions in 905.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>蔵人頭・五位蔵人が弁官を兼帯したり、五位・六位蔵人が検非違使を兼帯することはしばしばあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cases were ofthe seen where a person of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)/Goi no kurodo concurrently assumed the position of Benkan or a person of Goi no kurodo/Rokui no kurodo (kurodo with the Sixth Rank) assumed the position of Kebiishi no suke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cases were often seen where a person of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)/Goi no kurodo concurrently assumed the position of Benkan or a person of Goi no kurodo/Rokui no kurodo (kurodo with the Sixth Rank) assumed the position of Kebiishi no suke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cases were often seen where a person of Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)/Goi no kurodo concurrently assumed the position of Benkan or a person of Goi no kurodo/Rokui no kurodo (kurodo with the Sixth Rank) assumed the position of Kebiishi no suke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし一人で三つの官職を同時に兼帯することは稀であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, cases where a person assumed three official positions concurrently were seldom seen.</e>
<cmt>平安京　http://www.jnto.go.jp/eng/indepth/featuredarticles/worldheritage/c_5_nara.html　一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, cases where a person assumed three official positions concurrently were seldom seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, cases where a person assumed three official positions concurrently were seldom seen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>特に宮中において天皇に近侍する蔵人・太政官において行政事務を担当する弁官・平安京の司法・警察・民政の実務を行う検非違使佐は仕事量が多く重要な官職であったこのため、それらの職務を同時にこなすことは実務能力に優れた官僚でなければ不可能だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Kurodo who valeted the Emperor at court, Benkan who was in charge of administrative jobs at Dajokan and Kebiishi no suke who was responsible for the jobs of judiciary/police/civil affairs in Heiankyo (Kyoto) were particularly important official positions with heavy workload, it was impossible for an official to assume these three positions concurrently unless he had excellent business ability.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Kurodo who valeted the Emperor at court, Benkan in charge of administrative jobs at Dajokan and Kebiishi no suke responsible for judiciary/police/civil affairs in Heiankyo (Kyoto) were particularly important official positions with a heavy workload, it was impossible for an official to assume these three positions concurrently unless he had an excellent business ability.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Kurodo who valeted the Emperor at court, Benkan in charge of administrative jobs at Dajokan and Kebiishi no suke responsible for judiciary/police/civil affairs in Heiankyo (Kyoto) were particularly important official positions with a heavy workload, it was impossible for an official to assume these three positions concurrently unless he had an excellent business ability.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>『権記』寛仁元年（1017年）正月7日条には、藤原資業（日野家の祖）について「三司兼帯」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary) dated January 7 of the first year of Kannin era (1017), FUJIWARA no Sukenari (the founder of the Hino family) was recorded as &quot;Sanji kentai &quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Gonki&quot; (FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary) dated January 7 of the first year of Kannin era (1017), FUJIWARA no Sukenari (founder of the Hino family) was recorded as &quot;Sanji kentai &quot;.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Gonki&quot; (The FUJIWARA no Yukinari&apos;s diary) dated January 7 of the first year of Kannin era (1017), FUJIWARA no Sukenari (founder of the Hino family) was recorded as &apos;Sanji kentai.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語統一ピリオド位置移動&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>11世紀後半の白河天皇に藤原為房・平時範が三事兼帯を果たすと、藤原顕隆・藤原顕頼（為房の子孫）、平実親・範家（時範の子孫）も父祖に倣って三事兼帯となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Fujiwara no Tamefusa and TAIRA no Tokinori became Sanji kentai holder under the Emperor Shirakawa in the late 11th century, FUJIWARA no Akitaka/FUJIWARA no Akiyori (descendants of Tamefusa) as well as TAIRA no Sanechika/Noriie (descendants of Tokinori) became Sanji kentai holder in the wake of their forefathers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Fujiwara no Tamefusa and TAIRA no Tokinori became Sanji kentai holder under Emperor Shirakawa in the late eleventh century, FUJIWARA no Akitaka/FUJIWARA no Akiyori (descendants of Tamefusa) as well as TAIRA no Sanechika/Noriie (descendants of Tokinori) became Sanji kentai holder in the wake of their forefathers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After FUJIWARA no Tamefusa and TAIRA no Tokinori became Sanji kentai holder under Emperor Shirakawa in the late eleventh century, FUJIWARA no Akitaka/FUJIWARA no Akiyori (descendants of Tamefusa) as well as TAIRA no Sanechika/Noriie (descendants of Tokinori) became Sanji kentai holder in the wake of their forefathers.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>12世紀に実務官僚の家が勧修寺流・日野家・高棟流平氏に固定化したことに伴い、三事兼帯も自然とこの三家に限定された（例外は信西の子、藤原俊憲・貞憲のみ）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the families of officials in charge of practical business became restricted to Kajuji-ryu (the Kanjuji line), the Hino Family and Takamune-ryu Heishi (Taira clan of Takamune group) in the 12th century, persons who became Sanji kentai holder also came to be limited to those who were the members of these three families (exceptions were FUJIWARA no Toshinori/Sadanori, sons of Shinzei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the families of officials in charge of practical business became restricted to Kajuji-ryu (the Kanjuji line), the Hino Family and Takamune-ryu Heishi (Taira clan of Takamune group) in the twelvth century, persons who became Sanji kentai holder also came to be limited to those who were the members of these three families (exceptions were FUJIWARA no Toshinori/Sadanori, sons of Shinzei).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the families of officials in charge of practical business became restricted to Kajuji-ryu (the Kanjuji line), the Hino family and Takamune-ryu Heishi (Taira clan of Takamune group) in the twelfth century, persons who became Sanji kentai holder also came to be limited to those who were the members of these three families (exceptions were FUJIWARA no Toshinori/Sadanori, sons of Shinzei).</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>12世紀末に吉田経房・九条光長・定長の兄弟が三事兼帯を果たしたことについて、中山忠親は次のように記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the brothers of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and Mitsunaga and Sadanaga KUJO became Sanji kentai holder in the late 12th century, Tadachika NAKAYAMA wrote as &quot;Three brothers of Tsunefusa, Mitsunaga and Sadanaga became Sanji kentai holder. This is an unprecedented event and a great pleasure for the family) (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; (diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA) dated 18th day, 9th month of the first year of Genryaku era)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the brothers of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and Mitsunaga and Sadanaga KUJO became Sanji kentai holder in the late twlefth century, Tadachika NAKAYAMA wrote as &quot;Three brothers of Tsunefusa, Mitsunaga and Sadanaga became Sanji kentai holder. This is an unprecedented event and a great pleasure for the family) (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; - diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA) dated eighteenth day, nineth month of the first year of Genryaku era)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the brothers of Tsunefusa YOSHIDA and Mitsunaga and Sadanaga KUJO became Sanji kentai holder in the late twelfth century, Tadachika NAKAYAMA wrote as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「経房卿、光長朝臣、定長兄弟三人」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three brothers of Tsunefusa, Mitsunaga and Sadanaga became Sanji kentai holder.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「歴三事、古今更無此例、誠是家之余慶也」（『山槐記』元暦元年9月18日条）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is an unprecedented event and a great pleasure for the family&apos; (&quot;Sankaiki&quot; - The Diary by Tadachika NAKAYAMA) dated eighteenth day, ninth month of the first year of Genryaku era).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この事から、三事兼帯が実務官僚にとっての名誉と認識されていたことがうかがえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the above, we can gather that Sanji kentai was regarded as honor among officials in charge of practical jobs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the above, we can gather that Sanji kentai was regarded as an honor among officials in charge of practical jobs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the above, we can gather that Sanji kentai was regarded as an honor among officials in charge of practical jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>鎌倉期になると低年齢化と在職期間の短縮が進み、19歳で就任・在職期間一ヶ月という例まで現れ、実態とはかけ離れていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With lowering in the age of becoming Sanji kentai holder as well as shortening of term in office became apparent in the Kamakura Period, an exreme case occurred where a person became Sanji kentai holder at the age of 19 and was in office for a month and Sanji kentai gradually became the one that didn&apos;t represent the actual situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the lowering in the age of becoming Sanji kentai holder as well as the shortening of terms in office became apparent during the Kamakura Period, an exreme case occurred where a person became Sanji kentai holder at the age of nineteen and was in office for a month and Sanji kentai gradually became the one that didn&apos;t represent the actual situation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the lowering in the age of becoming Sanji kentai holder as well as the shortening of terms in office became apparent during the Kamakura period, an extreme case occurred where a person became Sanji kentai holder at the age of nineteen and was in office for a month and Sanji kentai gradually became the one that didn&apos;t represent the actual situation.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>やがて、三事兼帯は名家 (公家)の嫡流であることを示す指標となり、形式的・象徴的なものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, Sanji kentai became superficial and symbolic one as the index to prove that a family was the direct descendant of a distinguished family (court noble).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, Sanji kentai became the superficial and symbolic one as the index to prove that a family was the direct descendant of a distinguished family (court noble).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, Sanji kentai became the superficial and symbolic one as the index to prove that a family was the direct descendant of a distinguished family (court noble).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>主な三事兼帯者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Principal Sanji kentai holders</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Principal Sanji kentai holders</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Principal Sanji kentai holders</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Andee(id:20421), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>