<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>冠位十二階</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">System of twelve courtly ranks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Twelve Cap Rank System</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Twelve Cap Rank System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>冠位十二階（かんいじゅうにかい）は、推古11年(603年)12月5日 (旧暦)に定められた位階制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of twelve courtly ranks (Kanijunikai) is the court rank system which was established in 603.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelve cap rank system (kani-junikai) was a court rank system established in 603.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelve cap rank system (kani-junikai) was a court rank system established January 14, 604.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』では「十二月 戊辰朔壬申 始行冠位 大德 小德 大仁 小仁 大禮 小禮 大信 小信 大義 小義 大智 小智 并十二階 並以當色絁縫之 頂撮總如囊 而著縁焉 唯元日著髻華 髻華 此云　十二年春正月 戊戌朔 始賜冠位於諸臣 各有差」と記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;&quot; Chronicles of Japan, &quot;&quot; with regard to the system of twelve courtly ranks, it is described in the following sentence,&apos;十二月 戊辰朔壬申 始行冠位 大德 小德 大仁 小仁 大禮 小禮 大信 小信 大義 小義 大智 小智 并十二階 並以當色絁縫之 頂撮總如囊 而著縁焉 唯元日著髻華 髻華 此云 十二年春正月 戊戌朔 始賜冠位於諸臣 各有差&apos;</e>
<cmt>漢字の部分、定訳不明、意味不明、英訳不可能</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) gives the start date of the system and lists the twelve ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) gives the start date of the system and lists the twelve ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>『上宮聖徳法王帝説』では、「爵十二級、大徳、少徳、大仁、少仁、大礼、□□大信、少信、大義、少義、大智、少智」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot; &quot;Jokyu shotoku houo teisetsu,&quot;&quot; it is described in the following sentence, &quot;Daitoku,Shotoku, Dainin,Shonin,Daiai, □□Daishin, Shoshin, Daigi, Shogi, Daichi, Shochi&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Jogu Shotoku Ho-o Teisetsu&quot;, a biography of Prince Shotoku, the ranks are given as &quot;Daitoku, Shotoku, Dainin, Shonin, Dairai, □□, Daishin, Shoshin, Daigi, Shogi, Daichi, Shochi&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Jogu Shotoku Ho-o Teisetsu,&quot; a biography of Prince Shotoku, the ranks are given as &quot;Shaku Juniku, Daitoku, Shotoku, Dainin, Shonin, Dairai, XX Daishin, Shoshin, Daigi, Shogi, Daichi, Shochi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>カンマ位置移動しました。クォーテーション調整記号をXXに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>なお□□は欠字。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Note:□□are omitted words)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(□□ denotes omitted characters)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(XX denotes omitted characters)</e>
<cmt>記号をXX に変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>『隋書』卷81　列傳第46　東夷　俀國では、(俀王多利思比孤は「」。なお『新唐書』では「」とある）、「」とあり隋にも知られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;&quot;Sui book &quot;&quot;, vol.81, biography No.46, eastern barbarians, Japan,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The section on &apos;Eastern Barbarians, Kingdom of Wa&apos; (the ancient name for Japan), in the &quot;Sui Shu&quot; (Book of Sui), Volume 81, Liezhuan No.46, (the King of Wa is referred to as Tarashihiko, whereas the New Book of Tang calls him &quot;…&quot;) states &quot;…&quot;, showing that the system was known in Sui Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>*The original Wikipedia page shows that cells B12 and B13 are one sentence so joined them together. Left the missing quotes untranslated</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The section on &apos;Eastern Barbarians, Kingdom of Wa&apos; (the ancient name for Japan), in the &quot;Sui Shu&quot; (Book of Sui), Volume 81, Liezhuan No.46, (the King of Wa is referred to as Tarashihiko, whereas the New Book of Tang calls him &quot;...&quot;) states &quot;...&quot;, showing that the system was known in Sui Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>中黒を変更一文に戻す</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>『日本書紀』の記述には主語はないが、『上宮聖徳法王帝説』では聖徳太子と蘇我馬子が「共に天下の政を輔けて」と記されていることから、この二人の事蹟と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot; Chronicles of Japan,&quot; there is no description about who established the system of twelve courtly ranks, but according to &quot;&quot; Jokyu shotoku houo teisetsu,&quot;&quot; there is a description that Prince Shotoku and Umako SOGA &quot; together supported the administrative power of the whole country,&quot; therefore, it is considered that the system of twelve courtly ranks was the achievement of these two persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; makes no mention of who established the twelve cap rank system, but from a description in the &quot;Jogu Shotoku Ho-o Teisetsu&quot; that Prince Shotoku and SOGA no Umako &quot;together reinforced rule over the whole country,&quot; it is believed that the system was a legacy of these two.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; makes no mention of who established the twelve cap rank system, but from a description in the &quot;Jogu Shotoku Ho-o Teisetsu&quot; that Prince Shotoku and SOGA no Umako &apos;together reinforced rule over the whole country,&apos; it is believed that the system was a legacy of these two.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>豪族を序列化し、また氏や姓にとらわれることなく優秀な人材を登用することを目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this system, the Imperial Court aimed to impose a ranking among powerful regional clans and take talented people to government posts free from clan and family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system aimed to impose ranks on powerful clans and to appoint talented people, regardless of their clan or title, to government posts.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system aimed to impose ranks on powerful clans and to appoint talented people, regardless of their clan or title, to government posts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また官位の任命を天皇が行うことにより、豪族に対する天皇の権威向上を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the Imperial Court sought to improve the emperor&apos;s authority toward regional clans through appointing persons to office and rank by the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also sought to increase the Emperor&apos;s authority over powerful clans by having the Emperor directly appoint ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also sought to increase the Emperor&apos;s authority over powerful clans by having the Emperor directly appoint ranks.</e>
<cmt>アポストロフィ ’→ &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ただしこの制度は言わば移行期の制度であり、大臣 (日本)や連といった最上級の姓に属する豪族は依然として大徳よりも上位に置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this was the system, as it was, in transition period and the clans in the highest rank such as Ouomi and Muraji were still placed above Daitoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the system was, as it were, in transition and the highest hereditary titles, such as O-omi and Muraji, were still placed above the rank of daitoku.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the system was, as it were, in transition and the highest hereditary titles, such as O-omi and Muraji, were still placed above the rank of daitoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、現存している記録に残された冠位とその人物が属している姓の水準が一致している例が多い（臣・連以外の姓より大徳が輩出された例は無く、村主・首以下の姓で小徳を輩出した例は無い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, there are many examples that the courtly rank coincided with the family levelto which the person was belonging. (there was no example that the person who belonged to the family other than Omi and Muraji, was promoted to the post of Daitoku, and the person in the rank under Suguri and Kashira was promoted to Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many examples of courtly rank coinciding with the hereditary title level to which the person belonged (there are no examples of people with titles other than Omi and Muraji being awarded the rank of Daitoku, or of people below Suguri and Kashira being awarded the rank of Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many examples of courtly rank coinciding with the hereditary title level to which the person belonged (there are no examples of people with titles other than Omi and Muraji being awarded the rank of Daitoku, or of people below Suguri and Kashira being awarded the rank of Shotoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、遣隋使で活躍した小野妹子が大徳に昇進した例外を除いては冠位の昇進の記録がわずかであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, with a few exceptions including Ono no Imoko who played an active role as an envoy to Sui Dynasty China, there were few records of promotion of courtly ranks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, with a few exceptions, including ONO no Imoko, who played an active role as an envoy to Sui Dynasty China, there were few records of promotion up the ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, with a few exceptions, including ONO no Imoko, who played an active role as an envoy to Sui Dynasty China, there were few records of promotion up the ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>こうした事から、氏姓によって与えられる位階に一定の制約があったとする見方も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From these examples, some people have the view that there were a certain restrictions on giving courtly ranks depending on the clans and families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, some people have the view that there were certain restrictions on giving courtly ranks depending on clan and rank.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, some people have the view that there were certain restrictions on giving courtly ranks depending on clan and rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>冠位十二階の制度は、第一回遣隋使を推古8年（600年）に派遣した時の教訓から編み出されたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of twelve courtly ranks was established from the lesson learned at the time when the Imperial Court sent the first envoy to Sui Dynasty in 600.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelve cap rank system was established following lessons learned from the first Imperial envoy sent to the Sui Dynasty in 600.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelve cap rank system was established following lessons learned from the first Imperial envoy sent to the Sui Dynasty in 600.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>7世紀の東アジア情勢を考えると、倭国にとって隋との国交を開いておくことが是非必要であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was considered by all means necessary for Japan to open the diplomatic relations with Sui, considering the situation in eastern Asia in the 7th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Considering the situation in east Asia in the 7th century, it was considered extremely necessary for Japan to open diplomatic relations with Sui.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Considering the situation in east Asia in the 7th century, it was considered extremely necessary for Japan to open diplomatic relations with Sui.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>冠位十二階制は高句麗・百済を通して北朝・南朝両方のものが伝わったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the system of twelve courtly ranks was introduced through Kokuryo and Paekche</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the twelve cap rank system was introduced via Kokuryo and Paekche.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the twelve cap rank system of Northern and Southern Dynasties was introduced via Kokuryo and Paekche.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>冠位十二階制は、日本で初めてつくられた冠位制であり、この後の諸冠位制を経て、様々な紆余曲折を経て律令位階制へ移行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of twelve courtly ranks is the one established for the first time in Japan, and this system developed to Ritsuryo court rank system through various court system changes and after many twists and turns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelve cap rank system was the first such system established in Japan and, following various court system changes and many twists and turns, developed into the Ritsuryo court rank system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelve cap rank system was the first such system established in Japan and, following various court system changes and many twists and turns, developed into the Ritsuryo court rank system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="18">
<j>位階と冠の色</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Court and color of crown</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ranks and Cap Colors</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ranks and cap colors</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>『日本書紀』の603年に冠位十二階を定めたときの記述には、12の位階の名前は書かれているが、それぞれの位階に対応する色の名前が書かれていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the description of Chronicles of Japan, in 603 when the system of twelve courtly ranks was established, the name of twelve ranks were written, but crown colors corresponding to each rank were not written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The description in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; of the establishment in 603 of the twelve cap rank system gives the names of twelve ranks but not the color of the caps corresponding to each rank.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The description in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; of the establishment in 603 of the twelve cap rank system gives the names of twelve ranks but not the color of the caps corresponding to each rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>ある考証によると、12の位階の冠の色は次のようなものであった可能性が高いと推定されるが、断定はできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a study of historical evidence, it is presumed that crown colors for twelve ranks were as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the study of historical evidence, it is presumed, though it can not be affirmed, that the colors for the twelve ranks were as stated below.</e>
<cmt>*I don&apos;t think B33 and B34 needed to be split so rejoined them</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the study of historical evidence, it is presumed, though it can not be affirmed, that the colors for the twelve ranks were as stated below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>地位の高い位階から順に、位階の名前と冠の色を次に列挙する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following list, we enumerate the name of each rank and the color of each crown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following list gives the name of each rank and the color of each cap, from highest to lowest.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following list gives the name of each rank and the color of each cap, from highest to lowest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="22">
<j>大徳 （だいとく）（濃紫■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daitoku (big virtue) (deep purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daitoku (Greater Virtue) (deep purple)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daitoku (Greater Virtue) (deep purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="23">
<j>小徳 （しょうとく）（薄紫■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shotoku (small virtue) (light purple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shotoku (Lesser Virtue) (light purple)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shotoku (Lesser Virtue) (light purple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="24">
<j>大仁 （だいにん）（濃青■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dainin (big charity) (dark blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dainin (Greater Charity) (dark blue)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dainin (Greater Charity) (dark blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="25">
<j>小仁 （しょうにん）（薄青■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shonin (small charity) (light blue)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shonin (Lesser Charity) (light blue)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shonin (Lesser Charity) (light blue)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="26">
<j>大礼 （だいらい）（濃赤■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dairai (big courtesy) (dark red)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dairai (Greater Courtesy) (dark red)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dairai (Greater Courtesy) (dark red)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="27">
<j>小礼 （しょうらい）（薄赤■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shorai (small courtesy) (light red)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shorai (Lesser Courtesy) (light red)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shorai (Lesser Courtesy) (light red)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="28">
<j>大信 （だいしん）（濃黄■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daishin (big faith) (dark yellow)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daishin (Greater Sincerity) (dark yellow)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daishin (Greater Sincerity) (dark yellow)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="29">
<j>小信 （しょうしん）（薄黄■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoshin (small faith) (light yellow)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoshin (Lesser Sincerity) (light yellow)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoshin (Lesser Sincerity) (light yellow)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="30">
<j>大義 （だいぎ）（濃白□）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daigi (big justice) (pure white)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daigi (Greater Justice) (pure white)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daigi (Greater Justice) (pure white)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="31">
<j>小義 （しょうぎ）（薄白□）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogi (small justice) (dimly white)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogi (Lesser Justice) (off white)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogi (Lesser Justice) (off white)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="32">
<j>大智 （だいち）（濃黒■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daichi (big intellect) (deep black)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daichi (Greater Knowledge) (black)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daichi (Greater Knowledge) (black)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="33">
<j>小智 （しょうち）（薄黒■）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochi (small intellect) (dark)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shochi (Lesser Knowledge) (grey)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shochi (Lesser Knowledge) (grey)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="34">
<j>古代の青は紫に近い色である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Blue in ancient times was close to purple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Blue in ancient times was close to purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Blue in ancient times was close to purple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="35">
<j>（但し位階の大と小の色を、色の濃度の違いで区別するように制度が変わったのは、冠位十二階を定めたときよりも後である。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(but it was after the time of the establishment of the system of twelve courtly ranks that the system was changed so as to distinguish the difference between dai (big) and sho (small) by the diffrence of color shade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(However, the system was changed to using different shades to distinguish between &apos;Greater&apos; and &apos;Lesser&apos; after the twelve cap rank system had already been established.)</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(However, the system was changed to using different shades to distinguish between &apos;Greater&apos; and &apos;Lesser&apos; after the twelve cap rank system had already been established.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="36">
<j>冠位のことを行う</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of courtly ranks was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of cap ranks was introduced.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system of cap ranks was introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>『日本書紀』推古十一年十二月条</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;&quot; Chronicle of Japan &quot;&quot; in December, 603.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon Shoki&quot;, the twelfth month of 603</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Shoki,&quot; the twelfth month of 603</e>
<cmt>カンマ位置移動しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="38">
<j>十二月戊辰（ぼしん）朔壬申（じんしん）、始めて冠位のことを行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, 603, the system of courtly ranks was performed for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the fifth day of the twelfth month, the system of cap ranks was introduced for the first time.</e>
<cmt>*I think &quot;戊辰朔壬申&quot; is the 5th day</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the fifth day of the twelfth month, the system of cap ranks was introduced for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>大徳・小徳・大仁・小仁・大礼・小礼・大信・小信・大義・小義・大智・小智、併せて十二階、並びに当色の絁（あしぎぬ）を以てこれを縫う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Crowns for; Daitoku, Shotoku, Dainin, Shonin, Dairei, Shorei, Daishin, Shoshin, Daigi, Shogi, Daichi, Shochi; twelve ranks in total, were produced with silk fabrics of each color corresponding to the rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelve ranks were Daitoku, Shotoku, Dainin, Shonin, Dairai, Shorai, Daishin, Shoshin, Daigi, Shogi, Daichi, Shochi, with silk fabrics of each color corresponding to the rank.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The twelve ranks were Daitoku, Shotoku, Dainin, Shonin, Dairai, Shorai, Daishin, Shoshin, Daigi, Shogi, Daichi, Shochi, with silk fabrics of each color corresponding to the rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>頂（いただき）は撮（と）り総（すべ）て嚢（のう）の如くにして、縁（もとはり）を着く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The top of the cap was put together to form a pauch-like shape and the hem of the cap was where the head was placed.</e>
<cmt>訳出しましたが、縁を着く、というのは当たり前のことのようにも思えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>唯だ元日には髻華（うず）を著す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only exception was that on New Year&apos;s day, the decoration was put on caps.</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>「髻華、此をば宇孺（うず）という」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This decoration was called Uzu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="43">
<j>十二年春正月戊戌（ぼじゅつ）、始めて冠位を諸臣に賜うこと各差（おのおのしな）あり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In spring, 603, court ranks were granted to subjects for the first time and there were differences of rank among subjects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Spring, the first month of 604, cap ranks were granted to subjects for the first time and there were differences of rank among subjects.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Spring, the first month of 604, cap ranks were granted to subjects for the first time and there were differences of rank among subjects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="44">
<j>ここでは、具体的な色を書いていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Chronicle of Japan, specific colors were not written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; does not mention specific colors.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; does not mention specific colors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>色の深浅の区別は、養老令からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Difference of light and shade in colors began after the promulgation of Yoro law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The different shades of colors were introduced after the promulgation of the Yoro Code.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The different shades of colors were introduced after the promulgation of the Yoro Code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>「当色」は、位階相当の色として、五行思想に基づいた五常の徳目（仁・礼・信・義・智）の青・赤・黄・白・黒が考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot; Colors &quot; to be used are considered blue, red, yellow, white, and black corresponding to the 5 virtue items (charity, courtesy, faith, justice, intellect) based on the Chinese doctrine of 5 Elements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;colors&quot; mentioned in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; are believed to have been blue, red, yellow, white, and black corresponding to the five Confucian virtues (charity, courtesy, sincerity, justice, knowledge), which was based on the Wu Xing (Five Phases).</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;colors&apos; mentioned in the &quot;Nihon Shoki&quot; are believed to have been blue, red, yellow, white, and black corresponding to the five Confucian virtues (charity, courtesy, sincerity, justice, knowledge), which was based on the Wu Xing (Five Phases).</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>徳は、五常の徳目を統べる意があることから、漢代以降、帝王の色として尊ばれた「紫」を充てた推測できる（『漢書』天文志）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for virtue, since it is intended to govern 5 virtue items, it is presumed that they applied &quot; purple &quot; as the color valued as the color for a sovereign (emperor) after the Han dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As &quot;toku&quot; (virtue) governs the other five virtues, it is presumed that it was allocated &quot;purple&quot; since that had been valued as the color of the sovereign (emperor) since the Han dynasty.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As &quot;toku&quot; (virtue) governs the other five virtues, it is presumed that it was allocated &apos;purple&apos; since that had been valued as the color of the sovereign (emperor) since the Han dynasty (Tenmonshi of &quot;Kanjo&quot; (Historical records of the Han Dynasty)).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="48">
<j>「白」の濃淡はどうして見分けるのだろうかと疑問視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is looked on with suspicion how to distinguish pure white and dimly white.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is questionable how the two shades of white were distinguished.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is questionable how the two shades of &apos;white&apos; were distinguished.</e>
<cmt>記号補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="49">
<j>冠位十二階の衣服については、高松塚古墳壁画の人物群像が参考になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the clothing for twelve courtly ranks, the human figures on the mural of the Takamatsuzuka tomb are informative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The depictions of people in the murals of the Takamatsuzuka tomb are useful for information on clothing for the twelve cap ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The depictions of people in the murals of the Takamatsuzuka tomb are useful for information on clothing for the twelve cap ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>この壁画の人物図は、およそ7世紀後期から8世紀前期の風俗を伝えるものと推測されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed that the drawings of these human figures inform us the dressing customs from the latter half of the 7th century to the first half of the 8th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is presumed that the drawings of these human figures provide information on dressing customs from the latter half of the 7th century to the first half of the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is presumed that the drawings of these human figures provide information on dressing customs from the latter half of the 7th century to the first half of the 8th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="51">
<j>冠位制の変遷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changes of courtly rank system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes to the Cap Rank System</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes to the cap rank system</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>701年（大宝元）に官位制に切り替わる間に冠位制は何度か改訂が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period till the year of 701 when it was changed to official rank system, court rank system was evised several times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cap rank system was revised many times until it was replaced in 701 by the &quot;kan&apos;i&quot; court rank system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cap rank system was revised many times until it was replaced in 701 by the official rank system.</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="53">
<j>最初の大幅な改訂は、647年（大化3）の冠位十三階である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first major revision was the system of thirteen courtly ranks in 647.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first major revision was the thirteen cap rank system in 647.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first major revision was the thirteen cap rank system in 647.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="54">
<j>649年（大化5年）冠位十九階に改められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 649, it was revised to nineteen courtly ranks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 649, it was revised to nineteen cap ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 649, it was revised to nineteen cap ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>冠位十九階は、冠位十三階を基本とし、中間の冠位を細かく分けたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nineteen courtly rank system was the one in which courtly ranks in the middle part were divided in smaller pieces. (</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the thirteen cap ranks, the extra ranks were made by dividing the middle ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the thirteen cap ranks, the extra ranks were made by dividing the middle ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="56">
<j>664年（天智3）には更に細分化された、冠位二十六階に改訂されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 664, it was divided in still smaller pieces and revised to twenty-six courtly ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 664, it was divided into still smaller pieces and revised to twenty-six cap ranks.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 664, it was divided into still smaller pieces and revised to twenty-six cap ranks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>これらは、冠位十二階に組み込まれなかった大臣 (日本)（おおおみ）などを冠位制の序列に組み込もうとした試みだと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These systems are considered to be the trials to fit ranks such as omi (minister) into the hierarchy of the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These revisions are considered to be attempts to fit hereditary titles, such as O-omi, that had been left out of the twelve cap ranks into the hierarchy of the system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These revisions are considered to be attempts to fit hereditary titles, such as O-omi, that had been left out of the twelve cap ranks into the hierarchy of the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかしながら大臣は依然として旧冠を使用していたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is said that the ouomi (minister) still used the old crown</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is said that the O-omi continued to used the old caps.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is said that the O-omi continued to used the old caps.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="59">
<j>685年（天武14）諸王以上十二階、諸臣四十八階が導入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 685, twelve ranks for persons in the rank higher than shoo, and forty-eight ranks for persons in shoshin were introduced.</e>
<cmt>shoo諸王、shoshin諸臣</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 685, twelve ranks for Princes and above, and forty-eight ranks for high-ranking officials were introduced.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 685, twelve ranks for Princes and above, and forty-eight ranks for high-ranking officials were introduced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="60">
<j>親王や諸王も冠位制の中に組み込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinno (prince) and shoo were also fit into the courtly ranks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Princes with the rank of Shinno and Shoo were also incorporated into the cap rank system.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Princes with the rank of Shinno and Shoo were also incorporated into the cap rank system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="61">
<j>701年（大宝元）に、冠位制は廃止され、律令制太政官に移行している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 701, the system of courtly ranks was abolished and transferred to the system of Grand Council of the State based on the Ritsuryo codes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 701, the cap rank system was abolished and transferred to the Grand Council of the State based on the Ritsuryo codes.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 701, the cap rank system was abolished and transferred to the Grand Council of the State based on the Ritsuryo codes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>基本となっているのは冠位四十八階であるが、名称を正一位、従三位などとわかりやすく改訂した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this system, the basis was forty-eight courtly crown ranks, but the rank names were revised to the ones more easier to understand, such as senior grade of the first Court rank and junior grade of the third Court rank in the Court hierarchy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This new system was based on the forty-eight cap ranks, but the rank names were revised to ones that were easier to understand, such as senior grade of the first Court rank and junior grade of the third Court rank.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This new system was based on the forty-eight cap ranks, but the rank names were revised to ones that were easier to understand, such as Shoichii (Senior First Rank) and Jusanmi (Junior Third Rank).</e>
<cmt>用語統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>四十八階を三十階に減らしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And number of courtly ranks was reduced to thirty from forty-eight.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of ranks was also reduced from forty-eight to thirty.</e>
<cmt>Revised for clarity</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of ranks was also reduced from forty-eight to thirty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lusheeta(id:11139), Arufu(id:733), Non-stop24(id:10471), 経済準学士(id:22656), Cureless(id:85558), Ons(id:21830), Kurz(id:1601), Shinobar(id:42025), 新芽(id:50924), Bcxfu75k(id:56477), 秀の介(id:490), しょかい(id:73826), Loveless(id:129239), Kanoe(id:17203), Anarchy(id:6229), Mnd(id:15140), デーモン博士(id:99293), Izayohi(id:13095), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 水野白楓(id:22811), Seibuabina(id:37532), 葉月(id:25674), トルメキア(id:121880), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 彩華1226(id:64711), Madprof0421(id:65638), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ヤマト(id:8425), 海衛士(id:19229), Alexbot(id:157199), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>