<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>関東御分国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto Gobunkoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>関東御分国（かんとうごぶんこく）とは、日本の鎌倉時代において将軍家(鎌倉殿）が支配した知行国を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku is the group of provinces ruled and administered by Shogun families (Kamakuradono) during Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto Gobunkoku was the group of provinces ruled and administered by Shogun families (Kamakuradono) during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku was the group of provinces ruled and administered by Shogun families (Kamakuradono) during the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、室町時代において鎌倉府が支配した国々をも指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku also included the provinces ruled by Kamakura regional government installed by Muromachi shogunate in Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto Gobunkoku also included the provinces ruled by the Kamakura regional government, installed by the Muromachi shogunate in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku also included the provinces ruled by the Kamakura regional government, installed by the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>英語説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>関東知行国・関東分国とも言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called as Kanto Chigyoukoku or Kanto Bunkoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Kanto Chigyoukoku or Kanto Bunkoku.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Kanto Chigyokoku or Kanto Bunkoku.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>なお、ここで言う関東とは鎌倉幕府の所有という意味で、東国のという意味ではなく、西日本にも数多くあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the word &quot;Kanto&quot; in this case indicates the Kamakura shogunate itself rather than the location of the provinces, (today, &quot;Kanto&quot; specify the central-eastern region of Japan including Tokyo, and Kamakura, where shogunate was also established) therefore Kanto Gobunkoku meant not just the provinces located in the eastern region, but also the provinces located in the western part of Japan under the ruling of Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>この原文は、関東の意味を知っている人でないと直訳では何を言おうとしているのかすらわからないのではないかと思います。まず「関東」の漢字の意味がわかって初めて理解できる意味ないようです。仕方がありませんので説明を加えています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the word &quot;Kanto&quot; in this case indicates the Kamakura shogunate itself rather than the location of the provinces, (today, &quot;Kanto&quot; specifys the central-eastern region of Japan including Tokyo, and Kamakura, where the shogunate was also established) therefore Kanto Gobunkoku meant not just the provinces located in the eastern region, but also the provinces located in the western part of Japan under the ruling of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the word &quot;Kanto&quot; in this case indicates the Kamakura bakufu itself rather than the location of the provinces, (today, &quot;Kanto&quot; specifies the central-eastern region of Japan including Tokyo, and Kamakura, where the bakufu was also established) therefore Kanto Gobunkoku meant not just the provinces located in the eastern region, but also the provinces located in the western part of Japan under the ruling of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代の関東御分国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku during Kamakura period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanto Gobunkoku during the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanto Gobunkoku during the Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>鎌倉時代の関東御分国は、将軍家が知行国主として支配し、一族や御家人を朝廷に推挙して国司に任じ、国衙領（公領）を支配するとともに、国衙領からの収入を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form of Kanto Gobunkoku in Kamakura period was that the family/clan members or the retainers of Kamakura shogunate were recommended to the Imperial Court for the nomination of the provincial officials, in order to rule the provinces as the officials of Kokugaryo (Imperial province) and properly earn the revenue from the province.</e>
<cmt>多少「run-on」ですが、原文が分割しづらいためそのママ役しました。直訳的になっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The form of Kanto Gobunkoku in the Kamakura period was that the family/clan members or the retainers of the Kamakura shogunate were recommended to the Imperial Court for nomination as provincial officials, in order to rule the provinces as the officials of Kokugaryo (Imperial province) and properly earn revenue from the province.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form of Kanto Gobunkoku in the Kamakura period was that the family/clan members or the retainers of the Kamakura bakufu were recommended to the Imperial Court for nomination as provincial officials, in order to rule the provinces as the officials of Kokugaryo (Imperial province) and properly earn revenue from the province.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>文治元年（1185年）には9ヵ国に達したが、源実朝の時代には4ヵ国に減少する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1185, the number of Kanto Gobunkoku reached the highest to 9, although the number of Kanto Gobunkoku decreased to 4 during the reign of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, the third and the last shogun of Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>説明補填のため、源実朝について、第三代、鎌倉幕府最終将軍である旨追加しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1185, the number of Kanto Gobunkoku reached the highest at 9, although the number of Kanto Gobunkoku decreased to 4 during the reign of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, the third and last shogun of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1185, the number of Kanto Gobunkoku reached the highest at 9, although the number of Kanto Gobunkoku decreased to 4 during the reign of MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, the third and last shogun of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>幕府成立当初は東国支配確立のため制度的保障としての意義があったが、幕府体制の安定に伴い役割が低下したためと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kanto Gobunkoku played a a great role for securing the ruling of Kamakura shogunate during its incipient time, its importance was reduced once the shogunate order was established and stabilized, and the number of the province gradually decreased.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kanto Gobunkoku played a a great role in securing the rule of the Kamakura shogunate during it`s time, it`s importance was reduced once the shogunate order was established and stabilized, and the number of provinces gradually decreased.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kanto Gobunkoku played a great role in securing the rule of the Kamakura bakufu during it&apos;s time, it&apos;s importance was reduced once the shogunate order was established and stabilized, and the number of provinces gradually decreased.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府滅亡時まで御分国だったのは駿河国・相模国・武蔵国・越後国で、相模・武蔵の国司には執権・連署が任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanto Gobunkoku remained until the fall of Kamakura shogunate were Suruga Province, Sagami Province, Musashi Province, Echigo Province, while the officials assigned to Sagami Province and Musashi Province were regent/cosignatory of Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanto Gobunkoku that remained until the fall of the Kamakura shogunate were Suruga Province, Sagami Province, Musashi Province and Echigo Province, while the officials assigned to Sagami Province and Musashi Province were regents/cosignatorys of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanto Gobunkoku that remained until the fall of the Kamakura bakufu were Suruga Province, Sagami Province, Musashi Province and Echigo Province, while the officials assigned to Sagami Province and Musashi Province were regents/cosignatories of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 現代の魔女(id:136024), Non-stop24(id:10471), DDR(id:27381), 橄欖岩(id:24996), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shimoxx(id:9332), こいつぅ(id:2105), Ultratomio(id:1090), 伏儀(id:142093), 李(id:10582), BAKU(id:55205), Dwy(id:13375), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>