<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徴兵令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徴兵令（ちょうへいれい、太政官布告無号）（明治22年法律第1号）は、1873年（明治6年）に制定され、国民の兵役義務を定めた日本の法令。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance (Edict of Dajokan [Grand Council of state] Non-number) (1889 Law No.1) was enacted in 1873, which stipulated the obligation of all Japanese citizens to military service.</e>
<cmt>太政官布告無号→Edict of Dajokan [Grand Council of state] Non-number明治22年法律第1号→1889 Law No.1定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Conscription Ordinance (Edict of Dajokan [Grand Council of state] Non-number) (1889 Law No.1) was enacted in 1873, which stipulated the obligation of Japanese citizens to military service.</e>
<cmt>全国民ではないのでallは削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance (Edict of Dajokan [Grand Council of state] Non-number) (1889 Law No.1) was enacted in 1873, which stipulated the obligation of Japanese citizens to military service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>明治22年に全面改正され、1927年（昭和2年）、兵役法に移行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was fully revised in 1889 and shifted to the Military Service Law in 1927.</e>
<cmt>兵役法→Military Service Law</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was fully revised in 1889 and shifted to the Military Service Law in 1927.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was fully revised in 1889 and shifted to the Military Service Law in 1927.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History before the Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History before the Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History before the Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>戊辰戦争における官軍、すなわち明治新政府の軍は、長州藩・薩摩藩・土佐藩など諸藩の軍の集合で、大村益次郎、西郷隆盛、板垣退助らがそれぞれ指揮しており、政府が独自に徴兵して組織した軍はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial army in the Boshin War, that is the army in the Meiji new government, consisted of the armies from the various domains such as Choshu, Satsuma and Tosa under the commands of Masujiro OMURA, Takamori SAIGO and Taisuke ITAGAKI, respectively, and there had been no army the government recruited and organized on its own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial army which fought the Boshin War, that is the army of the Meiji new government, consisted of the armies from various domains such as Choshu, Satsuma and Tosa under the commands of Masujiro OMURA, Takamori SAIGO and Taisuke ITAGAKI, respectively, and there had been no army the government recruited and organized on its own.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial army which fought the Boshin War, that is the army of the Meiji new government, consisted of the armies from various domains such as Choshu, Satsuma and Tosa under the commands of Masujiro OMURA, Takamori SAIGO and Taisuke ITAGAKI, respectively, and there had been no army the government recruited and organized on its own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治政府直属の御親兵も、長州藩の一部部隊を元に諸藩の在京の浪人を集めて組織されたものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Goshinpei (army to convoy the Emperor) under the direct command of the Meiji Government was organized based on a part of the Choshu domain&apos;s army with recruited ronin (samurai with no lord) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Goshinpei (army to convoy the Emperor) under the direct command of the Meiji Government was organized based on a part of the Choshu domain&apos;s army with recruited ronin (samurai with no lord) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Goshinpei (army to convoy the Emperor) under the direct command of the Meiji Government was organized based on a part of the Choshu domain&apos;s army with recruited ronin (samurai with no lord) in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>大村や西郷従道、山縣有朋（論主一賦兵）らは、早くから「国民皆兵」の必要性を唱えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omura, Tsugumichi SAIGO, Aritomo YAMAGATA (&quot;Ronshu ichifuhei&quot;) and others had been advocating the necessity of universal conscription since early days.</e>
<cmt>論主一賦兵→Ronshu ichifuhei山縣の意見書ですが、定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omura, Tsugumichi SAIGO, Aritomo YAMAGATA (Ronshu ichifuhei) and others had been advocating the necessity of universal conscription since early days.</e>
<cmt>「論主一賦兵」定訳不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omura, Tsugumichi SAIGO, Aritomo YAMAGATA (Ronshu ichifuhei) and others had been advocating the necessity of universal conscription since early days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これは、近世的な個人的武技に頼る戦闘では、近代戦において勝利を得るのが困難であることを理解していたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because they understood that a combat depending on personal fighting ability like the one used in the early modern times was difficult to win in the modern war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because they understood that an army depending on personal fighting ability like the one used in the early modern times would be difficult to win modern wars.</e>
<cmt>単語を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is because they understood that an army depending on personal fighting ability like the one used in the early modern times would be difficult to win modern wars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、これには身分・家格を廃して四民平等を導入せねばならず、すなわち江戸時代の特権階級のうち最大の人口を占める武士の解体を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the universal conscription required to abolish the social and family status and introduce the equality of all people, which meant nothing but the dissolution of the samurai class that accounted for the largest of the privileged class in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>「これ」では意味が不明瞭なため「国民皆兵は」としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the universal conscription required to abolish the social and family status and introduce the equality of all people, which meant nothing but the dissolution of the samurai class that accounted for the largest part of the privileged class in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>語句を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the universal conscription required to abolish the social and family status and introduce the equality of all people, which meant nothing but the dissolution of the samurai class that accounted for the largest part of the privileged class in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、政府内にも島津久光を筆頭に前原一誠・桐野利秋ら保守的な反対論者を多数抱えており、また西郷隆盛も「壮兵」といって、中下層士族の立場を考慮した志願兵制度を構想していて徴兵制には消極的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there were a lot of conservative people opposing against it within the government, with Hisamitsu SHIMAZU as a leader, Issei MAEBARA, Toshiaki KIRINO and others, and Takamori SAIGO took a passive stance for conscription because he had his own plan of the volunteer (&quot;sohei&quot;) military system in consideration of the middle to lower class samurai.</e>
<cmt>壮兵→sohei壮兵は志願兵の意味で英語で違いを訳出できないため、そのまま&quot;sohei”としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there were a lot of conservative people against it within the government, with Hisamitsu SHIMAZU as the leader, Issei MAEBARA, Toshiaki KIRINO and others, and Takamori SAIGO took a passive stance for conscription because he had his own plan of the volunteer &apos;sohei&apos; military system in consideration of the middle to lower class samurai.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there were a lot of conservative people against it within the government, with Hisamitsu SHIMAZU as the leader, Issei MAEBARA, Toshiaki KIRINO and others, and Takamori SAIGO took a passive stance for conscription because he had his own plan of the volunteer &apos;sohei&apos; military system in consideration of the middle to lower class samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのうち、大村が暗殺された事もあって構想は一旦は挫折する事となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually the conscription plan miscarried once, partially due to the assassination of Omura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, the conscription plan was miscarried once, partially due to the assassination of Omura.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, the conscription plan was miscarried once, partially due to the assassination of Omura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>明治3年11月13日_(旧暦)（新暦：1871年1月3日）に山縣有朋の構想のもと、徴兵規則（ちょうへいきそく）が制定され、各府藩県より士族・卒・庶人にかかわらず1万石につき5人を徴兵することを定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 13, 1870 (old calendar) (January 3, 1871 in new calendar), the conscription regulation was enacted based on Aritomo YAMAGATA&apos;s plan, which stipulated to recruit five people for every one million koku in each domain irrespective of shizoku (person with samurai ancestors), low ranking samurai or commoner.</e>
<cmt>士族　shizoku (family with samurai ancestors)卒　low-ranking samurai(単語林より）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 3, 1871, the conscription regulation was enacted based on Aritomo YAMAGATA&apos;s plan, which stipulated to recruit five people for every one million koku in each domain irrespective of shizoku (person with samurai ancestors), low ranking samurai or commoner.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 3, 1871, the conscription regulation was enacted based on Aritomo YAMAGATA&apos;s plan, which stipulated to recruit five people for every one million koku in each domain irrespective of shizoku (person with samurai ancestors), low ranking samurai or commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>続いて翌明治4年2月13日_(旧暦)（新暦：1871年4月2日）には、西郷の構想の一部をも取り込む形で三藩（薩摩・長州・土佐）の軍が親兵として編成され、この兵力を背景に同年7月廃藩置県が断行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, on February 13, 1871 (old calendar) (April 2, 1871 in new calendar), the joined army from three domains (Satsuma, Choshu and Tosa) was formed as Shinpei (imperial guard), with adoption of a part of Saigo&apos;s plan, and in July of the same year, with the backing of this military strength the Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was carried out.</e>
<cmt>親兵　imperial guard</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, on April 2, 1871, the armies from three domains (Satsuma, Choshu and Tosa) was organized as Shinpei (imperial guard,) adopting a part of Saigo&apos;s idea and, in July of the same year, the Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was carried out with the backing of this military strength.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は削除しました。単語を修正しました。語順を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, on April 2, 1871, the armies from three domains (Satsuma, Choshu and Tosa) was organized as Shinpei (imperial guard,) adopting a part of Saigo&apos;s idea and, in July of the same year, the Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was carried out with the backing of this military strength.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>続いて、中央集権体制の近代国家にとって国民軍の創出が必要と認識され、西郷隆盛も最終的には山縣の考え方を支持して、山城屋事件で山縣が辞職に追い込まれた後も、西郷は桐野利秋らの反対論を退けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently the necessity to creation a national army for a modern nation under centralized administrative framework was recognized, and Takamori SAIGO finally supported Yamagata&apos;s opinion and turned down the opposing opinions by Toshiaki KIRINO and others, even after Yamagata was forced into resignation due to the Yamashiroya incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the necessity to create a national army for a modern nation under centralized administrative framework was recognized, and Takamori SAIGO finally supported Yamagata&apos;s opinion and turned down the opposing opinions by Toshiaki KIRINO and others, even after Yamagata was forced into resignation due to the Yamashiroya incident.</e>
<cmt>文法とスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the necessity to create a national army for a modern nation under centralized administrative framework was recognized, and Takamori SAIGO finally supported Yamagata&apos;s opinion and turned down the opposing opinions by Toshiaki KIRINO and others, even after Yamagata was forced into resignation due to the Yamashiroya incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>明治5年11月28日_(旧暦)（新暦：1872年12月28日）に徴兵告諭が出され、翌明治6年（1873年）1月10日（新暦）に徴兵令が施行。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 28, 1872 (old calendar) (December 28, 1872 in new calendar), the proclamation of conscription was issued and on January 10, 1873 (new calendar), the Conscription Ordinance became effective.</e>
<cmt>徴兵告諭　Proclamation of Conscription定訳不明http://www.meijigakuin.ac.jp/~pmjs/resources/bungo/12_choheikokuyu.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 28, 1872, the proclamation of conscription was issued and, on January 10, 1873, the Conscription Ordinance became effective.</e>
<cmt>旧暦は削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 28, 1872, the proclamation of conscription was issued and, on January 10, 1873, the Conscription Ordinance became effective.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>以後、毎年徴兵による新兵の入営日となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then the above date was the day the new soldiers joined the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the above date of enforcement became the day the new soldiers entered the army every year.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the above date of enforcement became the day the new soldiers entered the army every year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、全国的な徴兵制を敷くことを可能にした前提条件として、明治4年制定の戸籍法に基づいて翌明治5年壬申に壬申戸籍が編製されたことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a precondition to realize the nationwide conscription, the creation of Jinshin-koseki (family registries in Jinshin) in 1872 following the Family Registration Law enacted in 1871 should be mentioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a precondition to realize the nationwide conscription, the creation of Jinshin-koseki (family registries in Jinshin) in 1872 following the Family Registration Law enacted in 1871 should be mentioned.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a precondition to realize the nationwide conscription, the creation of Jinshin-koseki (family registries in Jinshin) in 1872 following the Family Registration Law enacted in 1871 should be mentioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>徴兵令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conscription Ordinance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>徴兵令では、満20歳の男子から抽選で3年の兵役（常備軍）とすることを定め、常備軍終了後は後備軍とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance required all male at the age of 20 to be selected by lottery and to serve in the army (standing army) for three years and to serve in reserve after finishing the service at standing army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Conscription Ordinance required all male at the age of 20 to be selected by lottery and to serve in the army for three years (standing army) and to serve in reserve after finishing the service at standing army.</e>
<cmt>語順を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance required all male at the age of 20 to be selected by lottery and to serve in the army for three years (standing army) and to serve in reserve after finishing the service at standing army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>国民皆兵を理念とはしたが、体格が基準に達しない者や病気の者などは除かれ、また制度の当初、「一家の主人たる者」や「家のあとを継ぐ者」、「嗣子並に承祖の孫」（承継者）、「代人料（270円）を支払った者」、「官省府県の役人、兵学寮生徒、官立学校生徒」、「養家に住む養子」は徴兵免除とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the idea was a universal conscription, those who did not meet the physical standard or were ill were exempted, and the other exemption included &quot;masters of the family&quot;, &quot;heirs and grandsons to succeed directly from their grandfather&quot; (collectively successors), &quot;those who had paid proxy fee (270 yen)&quot;, &quot;officials of central and local governments, students of military schools and public schools&quot;, &quot;adopted children living in their foster parents.&quot;</e>
<cmt>代人料→fee by proxy（定訳不明）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the idea was universal conscription, those who did not meet the physical standard or were ill were exempted, and the other exemptions included &apos;masters of the family,&apos; &apos;heirs,&apos; &apos;grandsons to succeed directly from their grandfather&apos; (collectively successors,) &apos;those who had paid proxy fee (270 yen),&apos; &apos;officials of central and local governments, students of military schools and public schools,&apos; and &apos;adopted children living in their foster parents.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「」は&apos; &apos;に修正しました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the idea was universal conscription, those who did not meet the physical standard or were ill were exempted, and the other exemptions included &apos;masters of the family,&apos; &apos;heirs,&apos; &apos;grandsons to succeed directly from their grandfather&apos; (collectively successors,) &apos;those who had paid proxy fee (270 yen),&apos; &apos;officials of central and local governments, students of military schools and public schools,&apos; and &apos;adopted children living in their foster parents.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このため、徴兵逃れに養子になる等の徴兵忌避者が続出し、徴兵免除の解説書まで出版されたりもした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, draft dodgers appeared one after another by being adopted in order to evade conscription, and even the instruction manual on how to evade conscription were published.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, draft dodgers appeared one after another by being adopted in order to evade conscription, and even the instruction manuals on how to evade conscription were published.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, draft dodgers appeared one after another by being adopted in order to evade conscription, and even the instruction manuals on how to evade conscription were published.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この結果、二十歳以上の男子の3%～4%くらいしか徴兵できなかった（もともと政府の財政難により、成人男子全員を徴兵することは到底無理ではあった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, only about 3 to 4% of the male aged 20 and over could be drafted (though it was never possible to draft all adult males due to the government&apos;s financial difficulty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, only about 3 to 4% of the male aged 20 and over were drafted (though it was never possible to draft all adult males due to the government&apos;s financial difficulty).</e>
<cmt>ニュアンスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, only about 3 to 4% of the male aged 20 and over were drafted (though it was never possible to draft all adult males due to the government&apos;s financial difficulty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>さらに各地で徴兵令反対の一揆が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, uprisings against the conscription ordinance broke out in various regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, uprisings against the conscription ordinance broke out in various regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, uprisings against the conscription ordinance broke out in various regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>徴兵告諭に「血税」という言葉があったためとされ、「血税一揆」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was assumedly because the proclamation of conscription included the word &quot;ketsuzei&quot; (blood tax), and the uprising was called &quot;ketsuzei ikki&quot; (blood tax uprising).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was assumedly because the proclamation of conscription included the word &apos;ketsuzei&apos; (blood tax,) and the uprising was called &apos;ketsuzei ikki&apos; (blood tax uprising.)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was assumedly because the proclamation of conscription included the word &apos;ketsuzei&apos; (blood tax,) and the uprising was called &apos;ketsuzei ikki&apos; (blood tax uprising.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>この一揆、特に岡山県で激しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The uprisings were fierce especially in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uprisings were fierce especially in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uprisings were fierce especially in Okayama Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>「血税」とは、フランス語の「impôt du sang」の直翻訳であり、「impôt」が「税」、「sang」が「血」の意である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ketsuzei&quot; was a direct translation from the French word &quot;impôt du sang&quot; (&quot;impôt&quot; means &quot;tax&quot; and &quot;sang&quot; means &quot;blood.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ketsuzei&apos; was a direct translation from the French word &apos;impôt du sang&apos; (&apos;impôt&apos; means &apos;tax&apos; and &apos;sang&apos; means &apos;blood.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ketsuzei&apos; was a direct translation from the French word &apos;impôt du sang&apos; (&apos;impôt&apos; means &apos;tax&apos; and &apos;sang&apos; means &apos;blood.&apos;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="25">
<j>「徴兵告諭」の一節：「人たるもの固（もと）より心力を尽し国に報ひざるべからず。西人（西洋人）之を称して血税と云ふ。其生血を以て国に報するの謂なり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One passage of &quot;Proclamation of Conscription&quot;: A man should devote himself to the nation mentally and physically. The Westerners call it blood tax. This means a man should devote himself to his country with his own blood.</e>
<cmt>次のパラグラフにかかるので「　を削除しました。定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One passage of &apos;Proclamation of Conscription&apos;: &apos;A man should devote himself to the nation mentally and physically. The Westerners call it blood tax. This means a man should devote himself to his country with his own blood.&apos;</e>
<cmt>パラグラフが間違った位置で切れていましたので、3つの文を一つにしました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One passage of &apos;Proclamation of Conscription&apos;: &apos;A man should devote himself to the nation mentally and physically. The Westerners call it blood tax. This means a man should devote himself to his country with his own blood.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>また当時「徴兵、懲役、一字の違い、腰にサーベル鉄鎖」という句が流行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, a verse became popular: &quot;徴兵 (&quot;chohei&quot; meaning conscription) and 懲役 (&quot;choeki&quot; meaning imprisonment) are only one-word different - saber at a waist or chain at a waist.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, a verse became popular: &apos;徴兵 (&apos;chohei&apos; meaning conscription) and 懲役 (&apos;choeki&apos; meaning imprisonment)are only one-word different - saber at a waist or chain at a waist.&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, a verse became popular: &apos;徴兵 (&apos;chohei&apos; meaning conscription) and 懲役 (&apos;choeki&apos; meaning imprisonment)are only one-word different - saber at a waist or chain at a waist.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>強制に基づく徴兵は監獄に行くのと同じであり嫌だ、という反抗の表れとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This verse is considered to reflect the people&apos;s resentment that being drafted forcedly was the same with being imprisoned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This verse is considered to reflect the people&apos;s resentment that being drafted forcedly was the same with being imprisoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This verse is considered to reflect the people&apos;s resentment that being drafted forcedly was the same with being imprisoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="28">
<j>当初は民の抵抗の多かった徴兵制度も、軍人勅諭や教育勅語による国防思想の普及、日清戦争・日露戦争の勝利などを経て、組織的な抵抗はなくなったものの、徴兵忌避の感情は自然の感情であるので、さまざまな徴兵忌避対策が庶民レベルで繰り広げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conscription, initially subject to the people&apos;s resistance, was eventually accepted and there was no organized resistance thanks to the prevailed awareness of national defense among the people by the Imperial Rescript to Soldiers and Sailors and the Imperial Rescript to Education, the victories of the Japanese-Sino War and the Japanese-Russo War and so on, but the sentiment of conscription evasion was a matter of natural sentiment so various measures for conscription evasion were developed among the common people.</e>
<cmt>逐語訳では不自然なので英文では「（徴兵制度も）受け入れられて」を追加しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conscription, initially subject to the people&apos;s resistance, was eventually accepted and organized resistance ceased thanks to the awareness of the need for national defense prevailing among the people by the Imperial Rescript to Soldiers and Sailors and the Imperial Rescript to Education, and the victories of the Japanese-Sino War and the Japanese-Russo War and so on, but the sentiment of conscription evasion was a matter of natural sentiment so that various measures for conscription evasion were developed among the common people.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conscription, initially subject to the people&apos;s resistance, was eventually accepted and organized resistance ceased thanks to the awareness of the need for national defense prevailing among the people by the Imperial Rescript to Soldiers and Sailors and the Imperial Rescript to Education, and the victories of the Japanese-Sino War and the Japanese-Russo War and so on, but the sentiment of conscription evasion was a matter of natural sentiment so that various measures for conscription evasion were developed among the common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>創設当初にあった徴兵免除の規定も徐々に縮小・廃止され、1889年に大改正が行われ、ほぼ国民皆兵制となった（ただし、中等学校以上の卒業後に志願したものは現役期間を1年としたり、師範学校を出て教員になったものは現役6週間とするなどの特例があった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The initial exemption conditions of conscription were gradually reduced or abolished, and in 1889 a major revision was made for universal conscription (however, there were special cases including those who volunteered after graduating from secondary school or higher education might serve for one year or those who became teacher after graduating from school for teacher training might serve for six weeks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The initial exemption conditions of conscription were gradually reduced or abolished and,in 1889, a major revision was made for universal conscription (however, there were special cases, for example, those who volunteered after graduating from secondary school or higher education served for one year and those who became teacher after graduating from school for teacher training served for six weeks.)</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The initial exemption conditions of conscription were gradually reduced or abolished and,in 1889, a major revision was made for universal conscription (however, there were special cases, for example, those who volunteered after graduating from secondary school or higher education served for one year and those who became teacher after graduating from school for teacher training served for six weeks.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="30">
<j>1927年、徴兵令を全部改正し、兵役法が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance was fully revised and the Military Service Law became effective in 1927.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Conscription Ordinance was fully revised and the Military Service Law became effective in 1927.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Conscription Ordinance was fully revised and the Military Service Law became effective in 1927.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>不況下においては兵役もまた生活の糧を得る手段として考えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military service was considered as a measure to earn a living under depression.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military service was considered as a measure to earn a living under depression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military service was considered as a measure to earn a living under depression.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、兵役における近代的なシステムや生活が地方に伝播するのに貢献したと言う面も否めない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the contribution of conscription cannot be denied as it helped the modern system or living in the military service to spread in the local areas..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the contribution of conscription cannot be denied as it helped the modern system or living in the military service to spread to the local areas.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the contribution of conscription cannot be denied as it helped the modern system or living in the military service to spread to the local areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>農民にとっては（暴力を振るわれても）農作業よりも楽であり、白米が食べられることから、明治時代には「軍隊に行くとなまけ者になる」という評判があったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peasants thought serving military (even they received violence) was easier than farming and they could eat white rice, so it was said that &quot;a man who entered the military became lazy&quot; in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peasants thought serving military was easier than farming (even they received violence) and they could eat even white rice in military, so it was said that &apos;a man who entered the military became lazy&apos; in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>訳を補いました。記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peasants thought serving military was easier than farming (even they received violence) and they could eat even white rice in military, so it was said that &apos;a man who entered the military became lazy&apos; in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Los688(id:12316), Pacifist(id:63219), Mobnoboka(id:35218), Nnh(id:474), Bletilla(id:38919), 22010515528(id:43149), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), HI(id:72996), 219.106の者(id:151047), Yanahan(id:2437), でここ(id:9565), らりた(id:1327), Shin-改(id:9914), 廬舎那憂(id:168188), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), Worldtraveler(id:197286), トホホ川(id:50502), たーじゃん(id:80884), Suisui(id:69), 一騎当千(id:56448), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>