<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>所務沙汰</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomusata (trial dealing with land-related issues)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomusata (trial dealing with land-related issues)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomusata (trial dealing with land-related issues)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>所務沙汰（しょむさた）は、中世日本で使用された用語であり、所領や年貢に関する相論や訴訟・裁判のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shomusata&quot; is a term used in medieval Japan and refers to disputes, suits, and trials over shoryo (territory) and nengu (land tax).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shomusata&quot; is a term used in medieval Japan referring to disputes, suits, and trials over shoryo (territory) and nengu (land tax).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shomusata&quot; is a term used in medieval Japan referring to disputes, suits, and trials over shoryo (territory) and nengu (land tax).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>所務とは、元来、務めるところという字義どおり仕事・職務を意味する言葉だったが、平安時代の荘園公領制の展開に伴い、荘園や公領の管理職務に付随する権利・義務を表すようになり、鎌倉時代頃には転じて所領等の不動産管理を意味した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the word &quot;shomu&quot; meant jobs and duties as suggested by the letters which mean &quot;the place for work&quot;; however, with the development of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) in the Heian Period, the word came to refer to the rights and obligations pertaining to the executive jobs in soen (a manor in medieval Japan) and koryo (an Imperial demesne); then around the Kamakura Period, the word was extended to mean management of property such as shoryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the word &quot;shomu&quot; meant jobs and duties as suggested by the letters which mean &quot;the place for work;&quot; however, with the development of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) in the Heian Period, word came to refer to the rights and obligations pertaining to the executive jobs in soen (a manor in medieval Japan) and koryo (an Imperial demesne); then around the Kamakura Period, the word was extended to mean management of property such as shoryo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the word &quot;shomu&quot; meant jobs and duties, as suggested by the characters which mean &quot;work that is related to the place&quot;; however, with the development of shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) during the Heian period, the word came to express the concept for the rights and obligations pertaining to the managerial work in shoen (manors) and koryo (the imperial teritories), and further during the Kamakura period, the word was extended to mean the property management of domains such as shoryo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。ダブルクォーテーションを全角から半角に修正しました。soen を shoen に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その後、更に転じて所領からの収益管理を意味するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later by further extension, the word came to mean management of earnings from shoryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later by further extension, the word came to mean management of earnings from shoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By further extension, the word came to refer to the management of proceeds from shoryo.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>所領からの収益とは即ち年貢のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earnings from shoryo means, in other words, nengu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earnings from shoryo means, in other words, nengu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The proceeds from the shoryo correspond to the nengu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>（日葡辞書によると、所務は年貢を徴収すること、とある。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(According to a Japanese – Portuguese dictionary, shomu means collection of nengu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(According to a Japanese – Portuguese dictionary, shomu means collection of nengu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(According to a Japanese - Portuguese dictionary, &quot;shomu&quot; means to collect the nengu.)</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。shomu にダブルクォーテーションを追記しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>中世日本の経済で大きなウェイトを占めていた農業生産の元手（資本）となるのは農地である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agricultural land was the sinews (capital) of agricultural production which carried considerable weight in the economy of medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agricultural land was the sinews (capital) of agricultural production which carried considerable weight in the economy of medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agricultural lands were the sinews (capital) of the agricultural production which carried considerable weight in the economy of medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その農地の所有権・支配権を握ることが支配階級の生命線であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To own and take control of the agricultural land became the lifeline for the ruling class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To own and take control of agricultural land became the lifeline for the ruling class.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To own and to take control of agricultural lands was the lifeline for the ruling class.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで、鎌倉幕府では所務沙汰を適正に裁判するため、非常に精緻な訴訟処理システムを確立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, in order to judge shomusata appropriately, Kamakura bakufu had established a very detailed system for settling lawsuits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, in order to judge shomusata appropriately, Kamakura bakufu had established a very detailed system for settling lawsuits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, in order to judge shomusata appropriately, Kamakura bakufu had established a very detailed system for settling lawsuits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>所務沙汰を取り扱うのは引付衆であり、それは次のような手順で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shomusata was handled by hikitsukeshu (coadjustor of the High Court), and the following procedures were taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shomusata was handled by hikitsukeshu (co-adjustor of the High Court), and the following procedures were taken.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomusata was handled by hikitsukeshu (co-adjustor of the High Court), as the following procedure was carried out.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>訴人（原告）からの訴状を問注所が受理し、引付衆へ進達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monchujo (a court of justice in Kamakura Period) accepted a complaint from the sonin (plaintiff) and delivered it to hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monchujo (a court of justice during the Kamakura Period) accepts a complaint from the sonin (plaintiff) and delivers it to hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt>tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Monchujo (the court of justice) accepted a complaint from the sonin (plaintiff) and delivered it to the hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>引付衆は訴状を論人（被告）へ開示した上で、書面（陳状）で反論させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikitsukeshu disclosed the complaint to the ronnin (defendant) and had ronnin make a written argument (statement).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikitsukeshu discloses the complaint to the ronnin (defendant) and has ronnin make a written argument (statement).</e>
<cmt>tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hikitsukeshu disclosed the complaint to the ronnin (defendant), and had ronnin make a written argument (statement).</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>陳状は引付衆を介して訴人へ渡された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statement was delivered to the sonin through hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statement is delivered to the sonin through hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt>tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statement was delivered to the sonin via the hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この後、訴人から書面で2回反駁を加え、論人からも書面で2回反論できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, sonin was able to make written arguments twice, and the ronnin was also able to make written arguments twice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterwards, sonin is able to make written arguments twice, and the ronnin are also able to make written arguments twice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sonin then wrote conter-arguments twice, and the ronnin were also entitled to write further counter-arguments twice.</e>
<cmt>反駁・反論はcounter-argumentsとしました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>このように原告・被告から三回ずつ相手方に書面で主張できるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the system enabled each plaintiff and defendant to make written assertions to the other party three times, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, the system enabled each plaintiff and defendant to make written assertions to the other party three times, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the plaintiff and the defendant were both given opportunities to make written allegations to the other party three times.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これを三問三答という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called &quot;sanmon santo&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called &quot;sanmon santo&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called sanmon santo.</e>
<cmt>原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="16">
<j>その上で当事者を招集し、引付衆の眼前で直接互いに相論をさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the parties were convened and made to argue directly with each other before the hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the parties convene and are made to argue directly with each other before the hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the parties were convened and were made to argue directly with each other before the hikitsukeshu.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>引付衆はその結果を評定会議へ上申し、評定衆で判決を行った後、勝訴人へ下知状を交付した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikitsukeshu escalated the result to the assessment assembly, and after giving a decision among the hyojoshu (a member of the Council of State), issued the verdict to the prevailing party in a gechijo (samurai document).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikitsukeshu escalates the results to the assessment assembly, and after providing a decision among the hyojoshu (a member of the Council of State), issues the verdict to the prevailing party in a gechijo (samurai document).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hikitsukeshu submitted the results to the assessment assembly, and after a decision among the hyojoshu (a member of the Council of State) was made, the verdict was issued to the prevailing party as a gechijo (notification).</e>
<cmt>下知状の説明文は(notification)としました。FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="18">
<j>以上から判るとおり、裁判結果が決して一方の主張に偏ることなく、特定の権力者の意向が反映しないよう、透明性と公平性が確保されたシステムが構築されていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As explained above, a system which ensured transparency and fairness was established so as to prevent the outcome of trial from being one-sided, or from reflecting the inclinations of a particular person of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As explained above, a system which ensured transparency and fairness was established so as to prevent the outcome of a trial from being one-sided, or from reflecting the inclinations of a particular person of power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As explained above, the system ensured transparency and fairness in order to prevent the outcome of a trial to be one-sided or to reflect the inclinations of a particular influential individual.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Shimoxx(id:9332), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Singing(id:134656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>