<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>施薬院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seyaku-in</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seyaku-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seyaku-in</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>施薬院（せやくいん/やくいん）は、奈良時代に設置された令外官である庶民救済施設・薬園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seyaku-in (Pharmacy Institution), which was established in the Nara period as Ryogenokan (extra statutory office), was a rescue facility for common people as well as a medical plant garden.</e>
<cmt>「令外官」は官職の一つであり、施薬院とイコールにはならないと思われましたので「as」でつなぎました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seyaku-in (pharmacy institution), which was established in the Nara period as a ryogenokan (extra statutory office), was a rescue facility for common people as well as a garden of medicinal plants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seyaku-in (the pharmacy institution), which was established in the Nara period as a ryogenokan (extra statutory office), was a rescue facility for common people as well as a garden of medicinal plants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この項目で説明。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Description is made in this item.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A description is made in this item.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The description is made in this section.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>施薬院（せやくいん）は、聖徳太子が仏教の慈悲の思想に基づき、その地に薬草を栽培し、怪我や病気で苦しむ人を救うために四天王寺内に作ったと言われる施設。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seyaku-in was a facility, which Prince Shotoku, based on the Buddhism philosophy of mercy, had allegedly erected inside of the Shitenno-ji Temple territory where medical herbs were cultivated to relieve people suffering from injury or diseases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seyaku-in was a facility that Prince Shotoku, based on the Buddhist philosophy of mercy, had allegedly erected within the premises of Shitenno-ji Temple, where medical herbs were cultivated to relieve people who suffered from injuries or diseases.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seyaku-in was a facility that Prince Shotoku, based on the Buddhist philosophy of mercy, had allegedly erected within the premises of Shitenno-ji Temple, where medical herbs were cultivated to relieve people who suffered from injuries or diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>推古天皇元年（593年）、聖徳太子が大阪に日本最古の官寺・四天王寺を建立の際、四箇院の一つとして建てられたのが日本での最初とする伝承があり（四箇院とは施薬院に悲田院・敬田院・療病院を合せたものである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tradition has it that in 593 when the Prince Shotoku erected Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka, which was the oldest kanji (state-sponsored temples) of Japan, he erected the Seyaku-in as one of the Shikain (four institutions) which included Hiden-in, Keiden-in, Ryobyoin, and Seyaku-in.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tradition has it that in 593, when the Prince Shotoku erected Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka, which was the original kanji (state-sponsored temple) in Japan, he erected the Seyaku-in as one of the Shikain (four institutions) which included Hiden-in, Keiden-in, Ryobyoin and Seyaku-in.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tradition has it that in 593, when the Prince Shotoku erected Shitenno-ji Temple in Osaka, which was the original kanji (state-sponsored temple) in Japan, he erected the Seyaku-in as one of the Shikain (four institutions) which included Hiden-in, Keiden-in, Ryobyo-in and Seyaku-in.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>社会福祉のはしりとして紹介される場合がある（収容型施設のはしりであることには間違いない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Seyaku-in has been sometimes introduced as the beginning of social welfare and was actually the beginning of facility of accommodation-type.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Seyaku-in has occasionally been described as the beginning of social welfare and actually marked the establishment of accommodation facilities.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Seyaku-in has occasionally been described as the beginning of social welfare and actually marked the establishment of housing facilities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>現在は大阪市天王寺区にある勝鬘院が施薬院跡として、四天王寺病院が施薬療病院として継承されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present there has been existing Aizen-do Hall of Shoman-in Temple in Tennoji Ward, Osaka City at the site where Seyaku-in used to be, and Shitennoji Hospital where Seyakuryobyoin used to be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today there exists the Aizen-do Hall of Shoman-in Temple in Tennoji Ward, Osaka City, at the site where Seyaku-in used to be, and Shitennoji Hospital stands where Seyakuryobyoin once was.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today there exists the Aizen-do Hall of Shoman-in Temple in Tennoji Ward, Osaka City, at the site where Seyaku-in used to be, and Shitennoji Hospital stands where Seyakuryobyoin once was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>施薬院（せやくいん/やくいん）は、奈良時代に設置された令外官である庶民救済施設・薬園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seyaku-in, which was established in the Nara period as Ryogenokan, was a rescue facility for common people as well as a medical plant garden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seyaku-in, which was established in the Nara period as a ryogenokan, was a rescue facility for common people as well as a garden of medicinal plants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seyaku-in, which was established in the Nara period as a ryogenokan, was a rescue facility for common people as well as a garden of medicinal plants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「施」の字はなぜか読まれないことが多く、中世以降は主に「やくいん」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For no reason the first character of &quot;se (施)&quot; is often silent and Seyaku-in has been generally referred as &quot;Yakuin&quot; since the medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Apparently for no reason, the first character of &quot;se (施)&quot; is often silent, and Seyaku-in has been generally referred to as &quot;Yakuin&quot; since the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Apparently for no reason, the first character of &apos;se (施)&apos; is often silent, and Seyaku-in has been generally referred to as &apos;Yakuin&apos; since the medieval period.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>天平2年（730年）、光明皇后の発願により、悲田院とともに創設され、病人や孤児の保護・治療・施薬を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 730 it was established together with Hiden-in by the suggestion of the Empress Komyo to accommodate, relieve, and dispense medicine for sick people and orphans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 730 it was established together with Hiden-in based on the suggestion of Empress Komyo to accommodate, provide relief and dispense medicine for sick people and orphans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 730 Seyaku-in and Hiden-in were established together based on the wish of Empress Komyo to accommodate, provide relief and dispense medicine for sick people and orphans.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>諸国から献上させた薬草を無料で貧民に施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It provided medical plants which had been presented from all over the Japan for the poor without charge.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It provided to the poor, without charge, medicinal plants that had been presented from all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seyaku-in provided to the poor, without a fee, medicinal plants that had been presented from all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>東大寺正倉院所蔵の人参や桂心などの薬草も供されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It offered medical plants such as ginseng and cinnamon cortex which had been stored in the Shosoin, Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It offered medical plants such as ginseng and cinnamon cortex, which had been stored in the Shosoin, Todai-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seyaku-in offered medical plants including ginseng and cinnamon cortices, which had been stored in the Todaiji Shosoin.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また、光明皇后自ら病人の看護を行ったとの伝説も残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A legend says that the Empress Komyo herself nursed sick people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A legend says that Empress Komyo herself nursed sick people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a legend, Empress Komyo nursed sick people by herself.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>ただし、施しを目当てに物乞いが暗躍したこともあり、また本当に苦しんでいる者が物乞い扱いされ、無下にされたこともあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it has been said that beggars expanded behind the scenes asking for help, and sometimes people who really needed such aids were considered as beggars and ignored coldly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it has been said that beggars crowded behind the scenes asking for help, and sometimes people who really needed assistance were considered as beggars and were treated coldly.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, it is said that beggars crowded asking for help, and sometimes people who really needed assistance were considered to be beggars and were treated bluntly.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>光明皇后崩御の後は知院事2名が置かれ、平安京へ遷都後も、施薬院は五条室町近くに移されて続行し、山城国乙訓郡に施薬院用の薬園が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following the death of the Empress Komyo two Chiinji were placed, and after the national capital had transferred to the city of Heian-kyo the Seyaku-in was also moved to the vicinity of Gojo-Muromachi to continue its work and private medical plant garden was established in Otokuni-gun,Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following the death of Empress Komyo, two Chiinji were installed, and after the transfer of the national capital to the city of Heian-kyo the Seyaku-in was also moved to the vicinity of Gojo-Muromachi in order to continue its work, and consequently a private medicinal plant garden was established in Otokuni-gun, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following the death of Empress Komyo, two directors were installed; after the transfer of the national capital to the city of Heian-kyo, the Seyaku-in was also moved to the neighborhood of Gojo-Muromachi in order to continue the work; consequently, a private medicinal plant garden was established in Otokuni-gun, Yamashiro Province.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天長2年（825年）には、別当、院使、判官、主典、医師の各1名を置く職制が定められ、延喜式でも継続された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 825, an office rank system was instituted, consisting of a betto (a groom), an Inshi, a Hangan, a Sakan (secretary), and a doctor and this system was succeeded in &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 825, an office-rank system was instituted, consisting of a betto (a groom), the Inshi, a hangan, a sakan (secretary) and a doctor, and this system was described in &quot;the Engishiki&quot; (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 825, an office-rank system was instituted, consisting of a groom, an administrator, a secretary, a clerk and a doctor, and this system was described in the Engishiki (an ancient book for codes and procedures on national rites and prayers).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし、中世に入ると施薬院は衰微し、次第に形骸化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the middle ages, the Seraku-in declined and gradually lost its substances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the middle ages the Seraku-in declined and gradually lost its substance.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the middle ages, the Seyaku-in declined and gradually lost its substances.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>11世紀頃から院使は、丹波氏が世襲するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the eleventh century, the Inshi had been succeeded hereditary by the Tanba clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the eleventh century, the Inshi was hereditarily succeeded by the Tanba clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the eleventh century, the administrator was hereditarily succeeded by the Tanba clan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>鎌倉時代からは和気氏もこれに加わり、両家の間で争いが起きる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Kamakura period, the Wake clan also attempted to succeed it, causing conflictions between the two families.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequent to the Kamakura period, the Wake clan also attempted to succeed it, causing conflicts between the two families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequent to the Kamakura period, the Wake clan also became to succeed it, causing conflicts between the two families.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかし、実務自体はほとんど無くなっており、形式的な職位に過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, the Inshi lost its significance and it became only a pro forma rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, the Inshi lost its significance and became only a pro-forma rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar and punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the administrator lost all content and became merely a pro-forma rank.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)に、丹波氏の後裔である施薬院全宗が、豊臣秀吉に側近として仕え、正親町天皇より勅命で施薬院使に任ぜられ、形骸化していた施薬院を復興する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States), Zenso YAKUIN, a descendant of the Tanba clan, served for Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as a close adviser and was appointed the Yakuinshi by the Emperor Ogimachi as an imperial order to reconstruct the Seyakuin which had lost substances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sengoku (Warring States) period, Zenso YAKUIN, a descendant of the Tanba clan, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as a close adviser and was appointed as Yakuinshi by Emperor Ogimachi as an imperial order so as to reconstruct the Seyakuin, which had lost its substance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Warring States period, Zenso YAKUIN, a descendant of the Tanba clan, served Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI as a close adviser and was appointed as the Yakuinshi by Emperor Ogimachi as an imperial order so as to reconstruct the Seyakuin that had lost its substances.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>同時に「施薬院」を姓とするようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time he entitled himself &quot;Seyakuin&quot; as the family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrently, he entitled himself &quot;Seyakuin&quot; as the family name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he took &apos;Seyakuin&apos; as his family name.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>以後江戸時代は、この施薬院氏が院使を世襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period, the Seyakuin clan succeeded the Inshi heredetarily.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period, the Seyakuin clan succeeded to the Inshi hereditarily.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period, the Seyakuin clan succeeded to the administrator for generations.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 与左衛門(id:159462), 新アルパカ(id:65850), Nevylax(id:38464), 水野白楓(id:22811), R28Bot(id:177951), Law soma(id:45202), トホホ川(id:50502), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>