<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>観応の擾乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanno Disturbance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>観応の擾乱（かんのうのじょうらん）は、南北朝時代 (日本)の1350年-1352年の観応年間に頂点に達した室町幕府内の権力闘争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance was a power struggle within the Muromachi bakufu that reached its height during the Kanno era from 1350 to 1352 of the Southern and Northern Dynasty Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanno Disturbance was a power struggle within the Muromachi bakufu that reached its height during the Kanno era from 1350 to 1352 of the Southern and Northern Dynasty Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance was a power struggle within the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) that reached its height during the Kanno era from 1350 to 1352 of the Northern and Southern Court period.</e>
<cmt>(Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) 補足南北朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ここではこの騒乱に付随して一時的に生じた南朝 (日本)側による南北朝の統一である「正平一統」（しょうへい(の)いっとう）についても併せて解説する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This article will also explain the Shohei Itto (Unification of Shohei) by the Southern Dynasty that temporarily happened in relation to this disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This article will also explain the Shohei Itto (Unification of Shohei) by the Southern Dynasty that temporarily happened in relation to this disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This article will also explain the Shohei Itto (Unification of Shohei) by the Southern Court that temporarily happened in relation to this disturbance.</e>
<cmt>南朝表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>高師直の台頭と足利直義との対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rise of KO no Moronao and conflict with Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rise of KO no Moronao and conflict with Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rise of KO no Moronao and conflict with Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>北朝を擁立し、京都で成立した初期の足利幕府においては統治機構が未整備で、足利家の家政機関を利用しての統治が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The governance system in the early Ashikaga bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which supported the Northern Dynasty and was established in Kyoto was not yet functional and governance used the kasei (vassal) system of the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The governance system in the early Ashikaga bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which supported the Northern Dynasty and was established in Kyoto was not yet functional and governance used the kasei (vassal) system of the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The governance system in the early Ashikaga shogunate (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which supported the Northern Court and was established in Kyoto was not yet functional and governance used the kasei (vassal) system of the Ashikaga family.</e>
<cmt>足利幕府用語統一北朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>征夷大将軍の足利尊氏は、鎌倉幕府の討幕や、建武の新政からの離反などにおいて尊氏を積極的に補佐した実弟の足利直義に政務を任せており、訴訟関係をはじめとする幕政は直義が司っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Takauji ASHIKAGA left Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, who actively supported Takauji during his plans to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu and departure from the Kenmu Restoration, to manage the administration and Tadayoshi was in charge of the shogunate administration such as litigations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Takauji ASHIKAGA left Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, who actively supported Takauji during his plans to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu and departure from the Kenmu Restoration, to manage administration and Tadayoshi was in charge of shogunate administration such as litigation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) Takauji ASHIKAGA left Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, who actively supported Takauji during his plans to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu and departure from the Kenmu Restoration, to manage administration and Tadayoshi was in charge of shogunate administration such as litigation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>尊氏は足利家当主としての地位や軍事的指揮権は保持し、政所や侍所などの家政機関は管轄下に置いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji kept the position as the family head of the Ashikaga and the military command, and held the mandokoro (The Administrative Board) and samurai dokoro (The Board of Retainers) under his control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji kept the position as the family head of the Ashikaga and the military command, and held the mandokoro (The Administrative Board) and samurai dokoro (The Board of Retainers) under his control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji kept the position as the family head of the Ashikaga and the military command, and held the mandokoro (The Administrative Board) and samurai dokoro (The Board of Retainers) under his control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この政治権力の分立状態は「両将軍」と評された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This separation of political power was called &quot;Ryoshogun&quot;(two shoguns).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This separation of political power was called &quot;Ryoshogun&quot; (two shoguns).</e>
<cmt>word spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This separation of political power was called &apos;Ryoshogun&apos; (two shoguns).</e>
<cmt>“” →&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>高氏は足利家譜代の被官で、高師直は執事を務め、軍事指揮官としても関東地方の南朝勢力を掃討して、関東を平定し幕府の支配下に置くなど軍事的大功を立てる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ko clan had for generations been retainers of Ashikaga and KO no Moronao acted as steward, fighting the Southern dynasty forces in the Kanto region as the military commander and gained military success by placing the Kanto region under the control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ko clan had for generations been retainers of Ashikaga and KO no Moronao acted as a steward, fighting the Southern dynasty forces in the Kanto region as the military commander and gained military success by placing the Kanto region under the control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ko clan had for generations been retainers of Ashikaga and KO no Moronao acted as a steward, fighting the Southern Court forces in the Kanto region as the military commander and gained military success by placing the Kanto region under the control of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>兄弟の高師泰も新田義貞、北畠顕家を討つなど軍事的功績を挙げ、幕府の中枢に参画するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His brother Moroyasu KO was also militarily successful by defeating Yoshisada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE and participated as a core member of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His brother Moroyasu KO was also militarily successful by defeating Yoshisada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE and participated as a core member of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His brother Moroyasu KO was also militarily successful by defeating Yoshisada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE and participated as a core member of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>足利直義は立場上、武家によって自領である荘園を蚕食された公家や寺社の訴えを扱うことが多く、鎌倉時代のように、公家や寺社の領地である荘園については半済令の受け入れと引き換えに独立性を認め武家の支配下に置かないことで、公家・寺社と武家との対立を避けようとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA handled many lawsuits raised by the aristocracy, temples and shrines who had their shoen (private estates) taken by the buke (military class), and he tried to avoid conflict between kuge/temples/shrines and buke by preventing the control by buke by recognizing the independence of the shoen of kuge, temples and shrines in exchange of accepting the Hanzei rei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA handled many lawsuits raised by the aristocracy, temples and shrines who had their shoen (private estates) taken by the buke (military class), and he tried to avoid conflict between kuge/temples/shrines and buke by preventing control by buke by recognizing the independence of the shoen of kuge, temples and shrines in exchange for accepting the Hanzei rei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA handled many lawsuits raised by the aristocracy, temples and shrines who had their shoen (private estates) taken by the buke (military class), and he tried to avoid conflict between kuge/temples/shrines and buke by preventing control by buke by recognizing the independence of the shoen of kuge, temples and shrines in exchange for accepting the Hanzei rei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>一方、師直は、武士たちが幕府に敵対したり南朝側についたりしないよう、十分な恩賞を与える必要を感じ、守護・地頭やその配下という形で公家や寺社の荘園を実際に管理している武家が土地支配者となるべきであると考えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Moronao felt it necessary to give sufficient rewards to the bushi to prevent them from confronting the bakufu or supporting the Southern Dynasty, and thought that the buke who had been the actual managers of the shoen of kuge, temples and shrines as shugo (constable) or jito (land steward) should become the landlord.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Moronao felt it necessary to give sufficient reward to bushi to prevent them from confronting the bakufu or supporting the Southern Dynasty, and thought that buke who had been the actual managers of the shoen of kuge, temples and shrines as shugo (constable) or jito (land steward) should become the landlord.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Moronao felt it necessary to give sufficient reward to bushi to prevent them from confronting the bakufu or supporting the Southern Court, and thought that buke who had been the actual managers of the shoen of kuge, temples and shrines as shugo (constable) or jito (land steward) should become the landlord.</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>このため、直義を支持する一派と、師直を中心とする一派が、幕府の主導権をめぐって対立を深める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, a conflict over the supremacy of the bakufu arose between the group supporting Tadayoshi and the group supporting Moronao.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, a conflict over the supremacy of the bakufu arose between the group supporting Tadayoshi and the group supporting Moronao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, a conflict over the supremacy of the bakufu arose between the group supporting Tadayoshi and the group supporting Moronao.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>尊氏は傍観的立場を取ろうとするが、次第に師直派に取り込まれていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji tried to take a third-party attitude, but was gradually taken in by the Moronao group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji tried to take a third-party attitude, but was gradually taken in by the Moronao group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji tried to take a third-party attitude, but was gradually taken in by the Moronao group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その中で高師直が塩冶高貞を殺害する事件を起こし、各地の武士の間にも動揺が走った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, KO no Moronao killed Takasada ENYA, which shocked the bushi nationwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, KO no Moronao killed Takasada ENYA, which shocked bushi nationwide.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, KO no Moronao killed Takasada ENYA, which shocked bushi nationwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="16">
<j>1347年（正平 (日本)2年/貞和3年）に入ると、南朝 (日本)（吉野朝廷）が京都奪還の動きを見せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1347, the Southern Dynasty (Yoshino Court) started movements towards regaining Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1347, the Southern Dynasty (Yoshino Court) started a movement to regain Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1347, the Southern Court (Yoshino Court) started a movement to regain Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>足利直義は尊氏の意向を受けて細川顕氏らを派遣してこれを討とうとするも失敗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA accepted Takauji&apos;s request to send Akiuji HOSOKAWA to attack the Southern Dynasty forces, but this ends in failure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA accepted Takauji&apos;s request to send Akiuji HOSOKAWA to attack the Southern Dynasty forces, but it ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA accepted Takauji&apos;s request to send Akiuji HOSOKAWA to attack the Southern Court forces, but it ended in failure.</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>一方、高師直は翌1348年（正平 (日本)3年/貞和4年）の四條畷の戦いにおいて楠木正行ら南朝 (日本)（吉野朝廷）方を撃破し、更に勢いに乗じて南朝の本拠地吉野を陥落させ、南朝を賀名生（奈良県五條市）へ逃げ込ませた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Moronao destroyed the Southern Dynasty (Yoshino Court) forces led by Masatsura KUSUNOKI in the Battle of Shijonawate in 1348, and with the momentum, succeeded in attacking Yoshino, the main headquarters of the Southern Dynasty, leading to the escape of the Southern Dynasty to Gojo City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Moronao destroyed the Southern Dynasty (Yoshino Court) forces led by Masatsura KUSUNOKI in the Battle of Shijonawate in 1348, and with the momentum, succeeded in attacking Yoshino, the main headquarters of the Southern Dynasty, leading to the escape of the Southern Dynasty to Gojo City, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Ko no Moronao destroyed the Southern Court (Yoshino Court) forces led by Masatsura KUSUNOKI in the Battle of Shijonawate in 1348, and with the momentum, succeeded in attacking Yoshino, the main headquarters of the Southern Court, leading to the escape of the Southern Court to Ano (Gojo City, Nara Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Ko no補足南朝用語統一Ano補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この結果、幕府内における直義の発言力の低下と師直の台頭が生じ、両派の対立に一層の拍車がかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Tadayoshi&apos;s power decreased within the bakufu and Moronao&apos;s power increased, leading to further conflict between the two groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Tadayoshi&apos;s power decreased within the bakufu and Moronao&apos;s power increased, leading to further conflict between the two groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Tadayoshi&apos;s power decreased within the bakufu and Moronao&apos;s power increased, leading to further conflict between the two groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>直義の排除</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The elimination of Tadayoshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The elimination of Tadayoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The elimination of Tadayoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>翌1349年6月、上杉重能や畠山直宗、禅僧の妙吉らは直義に進言し、直義に将軍尊氏に対して高師直を讒言させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1349, Shigeyoshi UESUGI, Naomune HATAKEYAMA, and the Zen priest, Myokitsu advised Tadayoshi to slander KO no Moronao before the shogun Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1349, Shigeyoshi UESUGI, Naomune HATAKEYAMA, and the Zen priest, Myokitsu advised Tadayoshi to slander KO no Moronao before the shogun Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1349, Shigeyoshi UESUGI, Naomune HATAKEYAMA, and the Zen priest, Myokitsu advised Tadayoshi to slander KO no Moronao before the shogun Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>古典『太平記』によれば直義派による師直暗殺騒動も存在したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the classic, Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace), there was an attempt to assassinate Moronao by the Tadayoshi group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the classic, Taiheiki (The Record of the Great Peace), there was an attempt to assassinate Moronao by the Tadayoshi group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the classic, &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (The Record of the Great Peace), there was an attempt to assassinate Moronao by the Tadayoshi group.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>6月、師直は直義の要請で執事を解任される（後任は甥の高師世）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, Moronao was fired as steward by the request of Tadanao (his successor was his nephew, KO no Moroyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, Moronao was fired as steward by the request of Tadanao (his successor was his nephew, KO no Moroyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, Moronao was fired as steward by the request of Tadanao (his successor was his nephew, KO no Moroyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>直義は北朝の光厳天皇に師直追討の院宣を要請して師直を討とうとするが、8月12日、師直は河内から上洛した高師泰とともに手兵を集め、直義に対して武力による先制攻撃を行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi requests for an Imperial order to attack Moronao from Emperor Kogon to kill Moronao, but on August 12, Moronao gathers troops together with Moroyasu KO who came to the capital from Kawachi and make a preemptive strike against Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi requested an Imperial order to attack Moronao from Emperor Kogon to kill Moronao, but on August 12, Moronao gathered troops together with Moroyasu KO who came to the capital from Kawachi and made a preemptive strike against Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi requested an Imperial order to attack Moronao from Emperor Kogon of the Southern Court to kill Moronao, but on August 12, Moronao gathered troops together with Moroyasu KO who came to the capital from Kawachi and made a preemptive strike against Tadayoshi.</e>
<cmt>of the Sothren Court補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="25">
<j>尊氏の庶子で直義の猶子となり、4月に長門探題に任命されて備後国に滞在していた足利直冬は、京都での事件を知ると、養父直義に味方するために上洛しようとするが、師直は赤松則村（円心）らに命じて直冬の上洛を阻止し、尊氏に直冬追討を要請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, who was Takauji&apos;s bastard son and Tadayoshi&apos;s foster son who was staying in Bingo Province after being named the Nagato tandai (Shogunal deputies in Nagato) in April, heard about the events in Kyoto and tried to go to Kyoto to help his foster father Tadayoshi, but Moronao commanded Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) to stop Tadafuyu&apos;s movements towards Kyoto and asked Takauji to attack Tadafuyu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, who was Takauji&apos;s bastard son and Tadayoshi&apos;s foster son, who was staying in Bingo Province after being named the Nagato tandai (Shogunal deputies in Nagato) in April, heard about the events in Kyoto and tried to go to Kyoto to help his foster father Tadayoshi, but Moronao commanded Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) to stop Tadafuyu&apos;s movement toward Kyoto and asked Takauji to attack Tadafuyu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, who was Takauji&apos;s bastard son and Tadayoshi&apos;s foster son, who was staying in Bingo Province after being named the Nagato tandai (Shogunal deputies in Nagato) in April, heard about the events in Kyoto and tried to go to Kyoto to help his foster father Tadayoshi, but Moronao commanded Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) to stop Tadafuyu&apos;s movement toward Kyoto and asked Takauji to attack Tadafuyu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>直冬は九州に逃れ、少弐氏ら九州の諸勢力に迎えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadafuyu escaped to Kyushu and was welcomed by the various forces in Kyushu such as the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadafuyu escaped to Kyushu and was welcomed by the various forces there, such as the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadafuyu escaped to Kyushu and was welcomed by the various forces there, such as the Shoni clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>13日、直義は尊氏の邸に逃げ込むが、師直は大軍をもって尊氏邸を包囲する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 13th, Tadayoshi escaped into Takauji&apos;s quarters, but Moronao brought a large force and surrounded Takauji&apos;s quarters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 13th, Tadayoshi escaped into Takauji&apos;s quarters, but Moronao brought a large force and surrounded Takauji.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundancy</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the 13th, Tadayoshi escaped into Takauji&apos;s quarters, but Moronao brought a large force and surrounded Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>師直は重能・直宗の身柄引き渡しを要求する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moronao demands custody of Shigeyoshi and Naomune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moronao demands custody of Shigeyoshi and Naomune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moronao demands custody of Shigeyoshi and Naomune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>事件は禅僧夢窓疎石の仲介もあり、重能・直宗の配流、直義が出家し幕政から退くことを条件に、師直は包囲を解く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident was intervened by the Zen priest Muso Soseki, and under the conditions that Shigeyoshi and Naomune were exiled, Tadayoshi becomes a monk and retires from bakufu administration, Moronao releases his barricade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident was intervened into by the Zen priest Muso Soseki, under the condition that Shigeyoshi and Naomune were to be exiled, Tadayoshi became a monk and retired from the bakufu administration, Moronao removed his barricade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident was intervened into by the Zen priest Muso Soseki, under the condition that Shigeyoshi and Naomune were to be exiled, Tadayoshi became a monk and retired from the bakufu administration, Moronao removed his barricade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>直義が政務を退く代わりとして鎌倉に居た尊氏の嫡子足利義詮が上洛して次期将軍として政務を執ることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In place of Tadayoshi, who retired from governing, Takauji&apos;s legal son, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who lived in Kamakura came to Kyoto to become the next shogun and take up the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In place of Tadayoshi, who retired from governing, Takauji&apos;s legal son, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who lived in Kamakura came to Kyoto to become the next shogun and take up the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In place of Tadayoshi, who retired from governing, Takauji&apos;s legal son, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA who lived in Kamakura came to Kyoto to become the next shogun and take up the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>この事件は、直義の排除のため師直・尊氏の間で了解があったとする噂が存在し、現在でも積極的に意図されていたという考え方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident sparked rumors that said there was an understanding between Moronao and Takauji to eliminate Tadayoshi, and even to this day, there are theories that propose the incident was caused with intention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident sparked rumors that said there was an understanding between Moronao and Takauji to eliminate Tadayoshi, and even to this day, there are theories that propose the incident was caused with intention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident sparked rumors that said there was an understanding between Moronao and Takauji to eliminate Tadayoshi, and even to this day, there are theories that propose the incident was caused with intention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="32">
<j>11月に義詮が入京すると、12月に直義は出家して恵源と号する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira enters Kyoto in Novemeber and Tadayoshi becomes a monk in December and is called Egen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira entered Kyoto in Novemeber and Tadayoshi became a monk in December and is called Egen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira entered Kyoto in November and Tadayoshi became a monk in December and is called Egen.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、この月に上杉重能と畠山直宗が配流先で師直の配下に暗殺されたことから、両者の緊張は再び高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, during December, Shigeyoshi UESUGI and Naomune HATAKEYAMA were killed while under Moronao&apos;s custody, leading to tension between the two groups again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, during December, Shigeyoshi UESUGI and Naomune HATAKEYAMA were killed while under Moronao&apos;s custody, leading to tension between the two groups again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, during December, Shigeyoshi UESUGI and Naomune HATAKEYAMA were killed while under Moronao&apos;s custody, leading to tension between the two groups again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="34">
<j>高一族の滅亡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decline of the KO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decline of the KO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The decline of the KO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>翌1350年、北朝は元号を「観応」に改める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1350, the Northern Dynasty changed the era name to &quot;Kanno&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1350, the Northern Dynasty changed the era name to &quot;Kanno.&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1350, the Northern Court changed the era name to &apos;Kanno.&apos;</e>
<cmt>北朝用語統一&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>10月、尊氏は九州で勢力を拡大する直冬追討のために出陣すると、京都では直義が都を出奔する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, Takauji sets out with his forces to attack Tadafuyu in Kyushu, who was increasing his power, and meanwhile,Tadayoshi escapes Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, Takauji set out with his forces to attack Tadafuyu in Kyushu, who was increasing his power, and meanwhile,Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, Takauji set out with his forces to attack Tadafuyu in Kyushu, who was increasing his power, and meanwhile, Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>尊氏は進軍を続けるが、直義は畠山国清、桃井直常、石塔頼房、細川顕氏をはじめ、山名時氏、斯波高経らを味方に付け、関東では12月に上杉憲顕が高一族の高師冬を駆逐する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji continued to move his forces, and Tadayoshi gained the support of Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, Tadatsune MONONOI, Yorifusa ISHIDO, Tokiuji YAMANA, and Takatsune SHIBA, and in Kanto, Noriaki UESUGI chased away KO no Morofuyu of the KO clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji continued to move his forces, and Tadayoshi gained the support of Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, Tadatsune MONONOI, Yorifusa ISHIDO, Tokiuji YAMANA, and Takatsune SHIBA, and in Kanto, Noriaki UESUGI chased away KO no Morofuyu of the KO clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji continued to move his forces, and Tadayoshi gained the support of Kunikiyo HATAKEYAMA, Tadatsune MOMONOI, Yorifusa ISHIDO, Akiuji HOSOKAWA, Tokiuji YAMANA, and Takatsune SHIBA, and in Kanto, Noriaki UESUGI chased away KO no Morofuyu of the KO clan in December.</e>
<cmt>Akiuji HOSOKAWA補足in December補足人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>尊氏は備後から軍を返し、高兄弟も加わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji returned his forces from Bingo and the Ko brothers joined him.</e>
<cmt>軍を返し というフレーズの意味が汲み取りにくかったです</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji returned his forces from Bingo and the Ko brothers joined him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji returned his forces from Bingo and the Ko brothers joined him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>観応の擾乱のはじまりはこの時点に求められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered the start of the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is considered to be the start of the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is considered to be the start of the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>11月には直義は高兄弟の追討のために諸国の兵を募る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, Tadayoshi gathers troops from the various provinces to attack the Ko brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, Tadayoshi gathered troops from the various provinces to attack the Ko brothers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, Tadayoshi gathered troops from the various provinces to attack the Ko brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>光厳上皇による直義追討令が出ると、12月には直義は南朝に降る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Kogen gives the Imperial order to attack Tadayoshi, and in December, Tadayoshi goes to the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The retired Emperor Kogen gave the Imperial order to attack Tadayoshi, and in December, Tadayoshi went to the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Retired Emperor Kogen gave the Imperial order to attack Tadayoshi, and in December, Tadayoshi went to the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>1351年（正平6年/観応2年）1月、直義軍は義詮を京都から追い、北朝を確保する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1351, the Tadayoshi forces chase Yoshiakira from Kyoto and keeps the Northern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1351, the Tadayoshi forces chased Yoshiakira from Kyoto and preserved the Northern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1351, the Tadayoshi forces chased Yoshiakira from Kyoto and preserved the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>北朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>2月、尊氏は播磨国光明寺合戦や摂津国打出浜の戦いで直義に敗れ、師直・師泰兄弟の出家を条件に直義と和睦する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, Takuji loses to Tadayoshi in the Battle of Komyo-ji Temple (Harima Province) and the Battle of Uchidehama (Settsu Province), and reconciles with Tadayoshi under the condition that Moronao and Moroyasu brothers become monks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, Takuji lost to Tadayoshi at the Battle of Komyo-ji Temple (Harima Province) and the Battle of Uchidehama (Settsu Province), and reconciled with Tadayoshi under the condition that Moronao and Moroyasu brothers become monks.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, Takauji lost to Tadayoshi at the Battle of Komyo-ji Temple (Harima Province) and the Battle of Uchidehama (Settsu Province), and reconciled with Tadayoshi under the condition that Moronao and Moroyasu brothers become monks.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>高兄弟は摂津から京都への護送中に、待ち受けていた直義派の上杉能憲（師直に殺害された重能の養子）により、摂津の武庫川（兵庫県伊丹市）で一族とともに謀殺される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ko brothers were killed together with other family members by Yoshinori UESUGI (foster son of Shigeyoshi who was killed by Moronao) of the Tadayoshi group at Mukogawa River (Itami City, Hyogo Prefecture) in Settsu when they were on their way from Settu to Kyoto under guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ko brothers were killed together with other family members by Yoshinori UESUGI (foster son of Shigeyoshi who was killed by Moronao) of the Tadayoshi group at Mukogawa River (Itami City, Hyogo Prefecture) in Settsu when they were on their way from Settu to Kyoto under guard.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ko brothers were killed together with other family members by Yoshinori UESUGI (foster son of Shigeyoshi who was killed by Moronao) of the Tadayoshi group at Mukogawa River (Itami City, Hyogo Prefecture) in Settsu when they were on their way from Settsu to Kyoto under guard.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>直義は義詮の補佐として政務に復帰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi returns to the administration in a position to support Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi returned to the administration in a position to support Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi returned to the administration in a position to support Yoshiakira.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="46">
<j>直義の敗北と尊氏の南朝への降伏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The defeat of Tadayoshi and the surrender of Takauji to the Southern Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The defeat of Tadayoshi and the surrender of Takauji to the Southern Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The defeat of Tadayoshi and the surrender of Takauji to the Southern Court</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>幕府内部では高一族の滅亡後も直義派と反直義派との対立構造は存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the decline of the Ko clan, there was a conflict between the Tadayoshi group and the anti-Tadayoshi group within the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the decline of the Ko clan, there was conflict between the Tadayoshi group and the anti-Tadayoshi group within the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the decline of the Ko clan, there was conflict between the Tadayoshi group and the anti-Tadayoshi group within the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>佐々木道誉や赤松則祐らが南朝と通じて幕府に反すると、尊氏は近江へ佐々木、尊氏の子の義詮は赤松を討伐のために播磨へそれぞれ出兵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Doyo SASAKI and Norisuke AKAMATSU rebelled against the bakufu and joined the Southern Dynasty, and Takauji sets out to Omi to attach Sasaki, and Takauji&apos;s son, Yoshiakira sets out to Harima attach Akamatsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Doyo SASAKI and Norisuke AKAMATSU rebelled against the bakufu and joined the Southern Dynasty, and Takauji set out to Omi to attack Sasaki, and Takauji&apos;s son, Yoshiakira set out to Harima to attack Akamatsu.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Doyo SASAKI and Norisuke AKAMATSU rebelled against the bakufu and joined the Southern Court, and Takauji set out to Omi to attack Sasaki, and Takauji&apos;s son, Yoshiakira set out to Harima to attack Akamatsu.</e>
<cmt>南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>だが、尊氏・義詮らと道誉らは密約があり京都への挟撃を試みたともいわれ、直義は桃井、斯波、山名をはじめ自派の武将を伴って京都を脱出し、北陸地方・信濃国を経て鎌倉市へ至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Takauji and Yoshiakira had a secret treaty with Doyo and tried to pincer-attack Kyoto, so Tadayoshi escaped Kyoto via the Hokuriku region and Shinano Province to reach Kamakura City, together with his warriors such as Momonoi, Shiba, and Yamana,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Takauji and Yoshiakira had a secret treaty with Doyo and tried to pincer-attack Kyoto, so Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto via the Hokuriku region and Shinano Province to reach Kamakura City, together with his warriors such as Momonoi, Shiba, and Yamana,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Takauji and Yoshiakira had a secret treaty with Doyo and tried to pincer-attack Kyoto, so Tadayoshi escaped from Kyoto via the Hokuriku region and Shinano Province to reach Kamakura City, together with his warriors such as Momonoi, Shiba, and Yamana,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="50">
<j>尊氏は南朝とも交渉し、和議の提案と直義・足利直冬追討の綸旨を要請する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji negotiated with the Southern Dynasty and suggested peace talks and requested an order to attack Tadayoshi and Tadafuhu Ashikaga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji negotiated with the Southern Dynasty and suggested peace talks and requested an order to attack Tadayoshi and Tadafuhu Ashikaga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji negotiated with the Southern Court and suggested peace talks and requested an order to attack Tadayoshi and Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>人名修正南朝用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>南朝は、北朝が保持していた三種の神器（南朝は贋物であると主張）を渡し、政権を返上することなどを条件に和睦に応じ、10月には尊氏は南朝に降伏して綸旨を得る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Dynasty agreed to peace under conditions such as the return of the Three Sacred Treasures that the Northern Dynasty held (the Southern Dynasty claimed that they had fakes) and the administration, and in October, Takauji surrenders to the Southern Dynasty and receives the Imperial order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Dynasty agreed to peace under conditions such as the return of the Three Sacred Treasures that the Northern Dynasty held (the Southern Dynasty claimed that they had fakes in their possession) and the administration, and in October, Takauji surrendered to the Southern Dynasty and received the Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court agreed to peace under conditions such as the return of the Three Sacred Treasures that the Northern Court held (the Southern Court claimed that they had fakes in their possession) and the administration, and in October, Takauji surrendered to the Southern Court and received the Imperial order.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="52">
<j>尊氏は義詮を京に残して南朝との交渉を任せて直義追討のために出陣し、翌1352年（正平7年/観応3年）には直義を駿河国薩埵山（埵は漢字では土へんに「垂」、静岡県静岡市）、相模国早川尻（神奈川県小田原市）などの戦いで破って鎌倉に追い込み、直義を降伏させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji left Yoshiakira in Kyoto to be in charge of the negotiations with the Southern Dynasty, and took forces to attack Tadayoshi, and in 1352, he defeated Tadayoshi at battles in Mt.Satta, Suruga Province (Shizuoka City (Shizuoka Prefecture) and Hayakawariji, Sagami Province (Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture) and chased him into Kamakura, where Tadayoshi surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji left Yoshiakira in Kyoto to be in charge of the negotiations with the Southern Dynasty, and took forces to attack Tadayoshi, and in 1352, he defeated Tadayoshi at battles in Mt.Satta, Suruga Province (Shizuoka City (Shizuoka Prefecture) and Hayakawariji, Sagami Province (Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture) and chased him into Kamakura, where Tadayoshi surrendered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji left Yoshiakira in Kyoto to be in charge of the negotiations with the Southern Court, and took forces to attack Tadayoshi, and in 1352, he defeated Tadayoshi at battles in Mt. Satta, Suruga Province (Shizuoka City, Shizuoka Prefecture) and Hayakawariji, Sagami Province (Odawara City, Kanagawa Prefecture) and chased him into Kamakura, where Tadayoshi surrendered.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Courtスペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>鎌倉に幽閉された直義は2月に急死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayoshi was kept under arrest in Kamakura and died suddenly in February.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayoshi was kept under arrest in Kamakura and died suddenly in February.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayoshi was kept under arrest in Kamakura and died suddenly in February.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>『太平記』は尊氏による毒殺であると記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taiheiki describes the death as due to poisoning under orders of Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taiheiki describes the death as being due to poisoning under orders from Takauji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Taiheiki&quot; describes the death as being due to poisoning under orders from Takauji.</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="55">
<j>正平一統</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shohei Itto</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shohei Itto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shohei Itto</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>一方朝廷では、尊氏が南朝に降伏した事により北朝の崇光天皇や皇太子直仁親王は廃され、関白二条良基らも更迭される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the Imperial Court, the Northern Dynasty Emperor Suko and the Crown Prince Naohito were abolished and Kanpaku Yoshimoto NIJO lost their jobs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the Imperial Court, the Northern Dynasty Emperor Suko and the Crown Prince Naohito were abolished and Kanpaku Yoshimoto NIJO lost their jobs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the Imperial Court, with Takauji&apos;s surrender, the Northern Court Emperor Suko and the Crown Prince Naohito were abolished and Kanpaku Yoshimoto NIJO lost their jobs.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Courtwith Takauji&apos;s surrender補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また、年号も北朝の観応2年から南朝の「正平6年」に統一される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The era was unified from Kanno 2 of the Northern Dynasty to &quot;Shohei 6&quot; of the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The era was unified from Kanno 2 of the Northern Dynasty to &quot;Shohei 6&quot; of the Southern Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The era was unified from Kanno 2 of the Northern Court to &apos;Shohei 6&apos; of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>これを「正平一統」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called the &quot;Shohei Itto (Unification of Shohei)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called the &quot;Shohei Itto (Unification of Shohei).&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called the &apos;Shohei Itto&apos; (Unification of Shohei).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>南朝の勅使が入京して具体的な和睦案が協議された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial messenger from the southern Dynasty came to Kyoto and specific conditions for the peace treaty were discussed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial messenger from the southern Dynasty came to Kyoto and specific conditions for the peace treaty were discussed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial messenger from the Southern Court came to Kyoto and specific conditions for the peace treaty were discussed.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>南朝側は、北朝の意向により天台座主や寺社の要職に就いた者などを更迭して南朝方の人物を据えることや、建武の新政において公家や寺社に与えるため没収された地頭職を足利政権が旧主に返還した事の取り消しなどを求め、北朝方と対立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Dynasty confronted the Northern Dynasty by proposing to fire the people selected by the Northern Dynasty to become Tendaizasu (chief of Tendaishu) and important positions in temples and shrines and replace them with Southern Dynasty related people, and wanted the cancellation of the return by the Ashikaga administration of jito (land steward) positions that were taken away during the Kenmu Restoration to give to kuge and temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Dynasty confronted the Northern Dynasty by proposing to fire the people selected by the Northern Dynasty to become Tendaizasu (chief of Tendaishu) and important positions in temples and shrines and replace them with Southern Dynasty related people, and wanted the cancellation of the return by the Ashikaga administration of jito (land steward) positions that were taken away during the Kenmu Restoration to give to kuge and temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court confronted the Northern Court by proposing to fire the people selected by the Northern Court to become Tendaizasu (chief of Tendaishu) and important positions in temples and shrines and replace them with Southern Court related people, and wanted the cancellation of the return by the Ashikaga administration of jito (land steward) positions that were taken away during the Kenmu Restoration to give to kuge and temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>義詮は譲歩の確認のために尊氏と連絡し、万一の際の退路を確保するなど紛糾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira contacted Takauji to confirm the concessions and tried to keep a contingency escape route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira contacted Takauji to confirm the concessions and tried to keep a contingent escape route.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira contacted Takauji to confirm the concessions and tried to keep a contingent escape route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>正平一統が成立し、南朝の後村上天皇が帰京する噂が立つと、各地で南朝方の活動が活発化し、本拠を賀名生から河内国東条（河南町）、摂津国住吉（大阪市住吉区）まで移転する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shohei Itto was established and when rumors arose that Emperor Gomurakami was to return to Kyoto, Southern Dynasty supporters in various regions grew active and transferred the main headquarters from Ano to Tojo (Kanancho) Kawachi Province to Sumiyoshi Settsu Province (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shohei Itto was established and when rumors arose that Emperor Gomurakami was to return to Kyoto, Southern Dynasty supporters in various regions grew active and transferred the main headquarters from Ano to Tojo (Kanancho) Kawachi Province to Sumiyoshi Settsu Province (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shohei Itto was established and when rumors arose that Emperor Gomurakami was to return to Kyoto, Southern Court supporters in various regions grew active and transferred the main headquarters from Ano to Tojo (Kanancho) Kawachi Province to Sumiyoshi Settsu Province (Sumiyoshi Ward, Osaka City).</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="63">
<j>南朝方は北畠親房の指揮で、東西で呼応して京と鎌倉の同時奪還を企て、翌1352年2月には南朝は尊氏の征夷大将軍を解任し、代わって宗良親王を任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Dynasty under the lead of Chikafusa KITABATAKE planned to regain Kyoto and Kamakura together by calling for forces in both east and west Japan, and in February 1352, Takauji is relieved of his position as Seii Taishogun by the Southern Dynasty and Imperial Prince Muneyoshi was installed in his place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Dynasty under the leadership of Chikafusa KITABATAKE planned to regain Kyoto and Kamakura together by calling for forces in both eastern and western Japan, and in February 1352, Takauji is relieved of his position as Seii Taishogun by the Southern Dynasty and Imperial Prince Muneyoshi was installed in his place.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court under the leadership of Chikafusa KITABATAKE planned to regain Kyoto and Kamakura together by calling for forces in both eastern and western Japan, and in February 1352, Takauji is relieved of his position as Seii Taishogun by the Southern Court and Imperial Prince Muneyoshi was installed in his place.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>宗良親王を奉じた新田義興、新田義宗らが鎌倉を奪還し、直義を破ったばかりの尊氏は武蔵国へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshioki NITTA and Yoshimune NITTA supported Imperial Prince Muneyoshi and regained Kamakura, and Takauji, who had just defeated Tadayoshi, escaped to Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshioki NITTA and Yoshimune NITTA supported Imperial Prince Muneyoshi and regained Kamakura, and Takauji, who had just defeated Tadayoshi, escaped to Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshioki NITTA and Yoshimune NITTA supported Imperial Prince Muneyoshi and regained Kamakura, and Takauji, who had just defeated Tadayoshi, escaped to Musashi Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>南朝主力の楠木正儀や北畠顕信、千種顕経、直義派であった山名時氏などが京都を攻略し、義詮は近江へ逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main force behind the Southern Dynasty, Masanori KUSUNOKI, and Akinobu KITABATAKE, Akitsune CHIGUSA and Tokiuji YAMANA of the Tadayoshi group, attacked Kyoto and Yoshiakira escaped to Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main force behind the Southern Dynasty, Masanori KUSUNOKI, and Akinobu KITABATAKE, Akitsune CHIGUSA and Tokiuji YAMANA of the Tadayoshi group, attacked Kyoto and Yoshiakira escaped to Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main force behind the Southern Court, Masanori KUSUNOKI, and Akinobu KITABATAKE, Akitsune CHIGUSA and Tokiuji YAMANA of the Tadayoshi group, attacked Kyoto and Yoshiakira escaped to Omi.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この際に義詮は北朝の光厳天皇、光明天皇、崇光天皇、直仁親王を京都に取り残し、三上皇らは南朝方に確保され、賀名生へ連行される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he escaped, Yoshiakira left the Northern Dynasty Emperor Kogon, Emperor Komyo, Emperor Suko, and Imperial Prince Naohito in Kyoto, and they were taken into custody by the Southern Dynasty and sent to Ano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he escaped, Yoshiakira left the Northern Dynasty Emperor Kogon, Emperor Komyo, Emperor Suko, and Imperial Prince Naohito in Kyoto, and they were taken into custody by the Southern Dynasty and sent to Ano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he escaped, Yoshiakira left the Northern Court Emperor Kogon, Emperor Komyo, Emperor Suko, and Imperial Prince Naohito in Kyoto, and they were taken into custody by the Southern Court and sent to Ano.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="67">
<j>南朝方が東西で呼応して京と鎌倉を同時占拠すると、後村上天皇は賀名生から山城国男山（京都府八幡市の石清水八幡宮）へ至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Dynasty regained both Kyoto and Kamakura as a result of coordination between east and west Japan, and Emperor Gomurakami arrived in Otokoyama, Yamashiro Province (Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine in Yawata City, Kyoto Prefecture) from Ano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Dynasty regained both Kyoto and Kamakura as a result of coordination between eastern and western Japan, and Emperor Gomurakami arrived in Otokoyama, Yamashiro Province (Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine in Yawata City, Kyoto Prefecture) from Ano.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court regained both Kyoto and Kamakura as a result of coordination between eastern and western Japan, and Emperor Gomurakami arrived in Otokoyama, Yamashiro Province (Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine in Yawata City, Kyoto Prefecture) from Ano.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>近江へ逃れた義詮は正平一統を破棄、正平7年の年号を観応3年に戻し、協議された統一案も破棄されるが、一部は影響した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira, who had escaped to Omi, rescinds on the Shohei Itto and returns the era from Shohei 7 to Kanno 3, and ignored the unification plan that was discussed, but part of it affected him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira, who had escaped to Omi, rescinded on the Shohei Itto and returned to the way it was in the era from Shohei 7 to Kanno 3, and ignored the unification plan that was discussed, but part of it affected him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira, who had escaped to Omi, rescinded on the Shohei Itto and returned to the way it was in the era from Shohei 7 to Kanno 3, and ignored the unification plan that was discussed, but part of it affected him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>義詮は諸守護を動員し、美濃の土岐氏、四国の細川氏、播磨の赤松氏、近江の佐々木氏らの勢力を集め、直義派であった山名氏や斯波氏らの協力も得て、3月に京都を奪還、尊氏も新田勢を追い鎌倉を奪還している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira used the various shugo and gathered forces such as the Toki clan in Mino, Hosokawa clan in Shikoku, Akamatsu clan in Harima, Sasaki clan in Omi and with the cooperation of the Tadayoshi group Tamana clan and Shiba clan, they regained Kyoto in March and Takauji chased away the Nitta forces to regain Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira used the various shugo and gathered forces such as the Toki clan in Mino, Hosokawa clan in Shikoku, Akamatsu clan in Harima, Sasaki clan in Omi and with the cooperation of the Tadayoshi group Tamana clan and Shiba clan, they regained Kyoto in March and Takauji chased away the Nitta forces to regain Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira used the various shugo and gathered forces such as the Toki clan in Mino, Hosokawa clan in Shikoku, Akamatsu clan in Harima, Sasaki clan in Omi and with the cooperation of the Tadayoshi group Yamana clan and Shiba clan, they regained Kyoto in March and Takauji chased away the Nitta forces to regain Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="70">
<j>5月に後村上天皇は山城八幡から賀名生に逃れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, Emperor Gomurakami escaped from Yamashiro Yawata to Ano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, Emperor Gomurakami escaped from Yamashiro Yawata to Ano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, Emperor Gomurakami escaped from Yamashiro Yawata to Ano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>この際、四条隆資が戦死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO was killed in this skirmish.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takasuke SHIJO was killed in this skirmish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takasuke SHIJO was killed in this skirmish.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="72">
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Effects</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>南朝の延命</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The prolongation of the Southern Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The prolongation of the Southern Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The prolongation of the Southern Court</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>この乱により、足利尊氏・直義に分割されていた将軍の権力は尊氏のもとに一本化され、将軍の親裁権は強化されるが、高師直によって吉野を陥落させられ滅亡寸前にまで追い込まれた南朝に、直義・尊氏が交互に降るなど息を吹き返し延命したため、南北朝の動乱が長引いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this disturbance, the authority of the shogun that was divided between Takauji and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA was unified under Takauji and the power of the shogun was strengthened but the Southern Dynasty that was forced to the brink of elimination when KO no Moronao attacked Yoshino was prolonged when Tadayoshi and Takauji surrendered in turn, and led to the prolongation of the upheaval of the period of Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this disturbance, the authority of the shogun that was divided between Takauji and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA was unified under Takauji and the power of the shogun was strengthened but the Southern Dynasty that was forced to the brink of elimination when KO no Moronao attacked Yoshino, was prolonged when Tadayoshi and Takauji surrendered in turn, and led to the prolongation of the upheaval of the period of Southern and Northern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this disturbance, the authority of the shogun that was divided between Takauji and Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA was unified under Takauji and the power of the shogun was strengthened but the Southern Court that was forced to the brink of elimination when KO no Moronao attacked Yoshino, was prolonged when Tadayoshi and Takauji surrendered in turn, and led to the prolongation of the upheaval of the period of Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="75">
<j>尊氏が南朝に降ったときに南朝が要求した条件に、皇位は南朝に任せるという項目があったため、北朝の皇位の正統性が弱められる結果となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because one of the conditions that the Southern Dynasty demanded when Takauji surrendered was to unify the Imperial succession to the Southern Dynasty, the legitimacy of the Imperial succession of the Northern Dynasty was weakened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because one of the conditions that the Southern Dynasty demanded when Takauji surrendered was to unify Imperial succession to the Southern Dynasty, the legitimacy of the Imperial succession of the Northern Dynasty was weakened.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because one of the conditions that the Southern Court demanded when Takauji surrendered was to unify Imperial succession to the Southern Court, the legitimacy of the Imperial succession of the Northern Court was weakened.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>治天の君であった光厳上皇、天皇を退位した直後の崇光上皇、皇太子直仁親王が南朝に連れ去られ、南朝の後醍醐天皇が偽器であると主張していた北朝の三種の神器までもが南朝に接収されたため、北朝は治天・天皇・皇太子・神器不在の事態に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Chiten no kimi (the retired Emperor or the Cloistered Emperor who hold actual power of government) retired Emperor Kogon, the retired Emperor Suko who had just abdicated the throne and the Crown Prince Naohito were under custody of the Southern Dynasty and the Three Sacred Treasures of the Northern Dynasty that Emperor Godaigo of the Southern Dynasty claimed were fakes were also held by the Southern Dynasty, the Northern Dynasty was in the state of no Chiten, Emperor, Crown Prince or the Treasures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Chiten no kimi (the retired Emperor or the Cloistered Emperor who held actual power of government) retired, Emperor Kogon, the retired Emperor Suko, who had just abdicated the throne, and Crown Prince Naohito, were under custody of the Southern Dynasty and the Three Sacred Treasures of the Northern Dynasty that Emperor Godaigo of the Southern Dynasty claimed were fakes were also held by the Southern Dynasty, the Northern Dynasty was in a state of no Chiten, Emperor, Crown Prince, or the Treasures.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Chiten no kimi (the Retired Emperor or the Cloistered Emperor who held actual power of government) Retired Emperor Kogon, the Retired Emperor Suko, who had just abdicated the throne, and Crown Prince Naohito, were under custody of the Southern Court and the Three Sacred Treasures of the Northern Court that Emperor Godaigo of the Southern Court claimed were fakes were also held by the Southern Court, the Northern Court was in a state of no Chiten, Emperor, Crown Prince, or the Treasures.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>また、幕府にとっても、尊氏が征夷大将軍を解任されたため、幕府自体が法的根拠を失ってしまう状況になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Takauji was dismissed as Seii Taishogun, the bakufu itself also lost its legal foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Takauji was dismissed as Seii Taishogun, the bakufu itself also lost its legal foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Takauji was dismissed as Seii Taishogun, the bakufu itself also lost its legal foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>最終的な政治裁可を下しうる治天・天皇の不在がこのまま続けば、京都の諸勢力（公家・幕府・守護）らの政治執行がすべて遅滞することになってしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Chiten and Emperor, who make the final political decision, were absent, the political administration of the various forces in Kyoto (kuge, bakufu, shugo) was delayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Chiten and Emperor, who would make the final political decision, were absent, the political administration of the various forces in Kyoto (kuge, bakufu, shugo) was delayed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Chiten and Emperor, who would make the final political decision, were absent, the political administration of the various forces in Kyoto (kuge, bakufu, shugo) was delayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>ここに幕府・北朝側は深刻な政治的危機に直面することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This led to a serious political crisis for the bakufu/Northern Dynasty side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This led to a serious political crisis for the bakufu/Northern Dynasty side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This led to a serious political crisis for the bakufu/Northern Court side.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="80">
<j>事態を憂慮した二条良基は勧修寺経顕や尊氏と相計って、光厳・光明の実母西園寺寧子に治天の君となることを要請し、困難な折衝の上ようやく受諾を取り付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto NIJO was worried about the situation and in agreement with Tsuneaki KASHUJIand Takauji, he requested the biological mother of Kogon and Komyo, Neishi SAIONJI to become Chiten no kimi and after various obstacles were overcome, he gained acceptance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto NIJO was worried about the situation and in agreement with Tsuneaki KASHUJI and Takauji, he requested the biological mother of Kogon and Komyo, Neishi SAIONJI become Chiten no kimi and after various obstacles were overcome, he gained acceptance.</e>
<cmt>word spacing, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto NIJO was worried about the situation and in agreement with Tsuneaki KASHUJI and Takauji, he requested the biological mother of Kogon and Komyo, Neishi SAIONJI become Chiten no kimi and after various obstacles were overcome, he gained acceptance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>広義門院が伝国詔宣を行うことによって崇光弟の後光厳天皇即位が実現することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kogimon-in gave the Denkoku Shosen (announcement to the nation), Suko&apos;s brother, Emperor Gokogon was able to ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kogimon-in gave the Denkoku Shosen (announcement to the nation), Suko&apos;s brother, Emperor Gokogon was able to ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kogimon-in gave the Denkoku Shosen (announcement to the nation), Suko&apos;s brother, Emperor Gokogon was able to ascend to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>良基は神器なしの新天皇即位に躊躇する公家に対して「尊氏が剣（草薙剣）となり、良基が璽（八尺瓊勾玉）となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimoto said to the kuge who were reluctant about the ascension of a new emperor without the Sacred Treasures, &quot;Takauji will be the Kusanagi no tsurugi (sword) and Yoshimoto will be the ji (seal)&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimoto said to the kuge who were reluctant about the ascension of a new emperor without the Sacred Treasures, &quot;Takauji will be the Kusanagi no tsurugi&quot; (sword) &quot;and Yoshimoto will be the ji&quot; (seal).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimoto said to the kuge who were reluctant about the ascension of a new emperor without the Sacred Treasures, &apos;Takauji will be the Kusanagi no tsurugi (sword) and Yoshimoto will be the ji (seal).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>何ぞ不可ならん」と啖呵を切ったと言われている（『続本朝通鑑』）が、当時、即位に当たって神器の存在は必ずしも要件とはされておらず、治天による伝国詔宣により即位が可能であるとする観念が存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nothing is the matter&quot;(Zoku Honchotsugan (history book edited by Edo Bakufu) he is said to have openly said, but the existence of the Sacred Treasures was not mandatory for ascension and the Denkoku Shosen by the Chiten was thought to have been sufficient in those times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nothing is the matter&quot; (Zoku Honchotsugan (history book edited by the Edo Bakufu) he is said to have openly said, but the existence of the Sacred Treasures was not mandatory for ascension and the Denkoku Shosen by the Chiten was thought to have been sufficient in those times.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nothing is the matter&apos; (&quot;Zoku Honchotsugan&quot; (history book edited by the Edo bakufu) he is said to have openly said, but the existence of the Sacred Treasures was not mandatory for ascension and the Denkoku Shosen by the Chiten was thought to have been sufficient in those times.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="84">
<j>北朝内の皇統対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial conflict within the Northern Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial conflict within the Northern Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial conflict within the Northern Court</e>
<cmt>Northern Dynasty→Northern Court 用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>後光厳、後円融天皇、後小松天皇、称光天皇と4代にわたって後光厳系が皇位についた一方、兄筋の崇光上皇の子孫は嫡流から排されて世襲親王家である伏見宮家として存続し、北朝内部でも皇位継承をめぐる両系統間の確執があったとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 4 emperors of the Gokogon line, Emperors Gokogen, Koenyu, Gokomatsu, Shoko were on the throne, whereas the descendants of Emperor Suko who was the elder brother were eliminated from the succeeding line and existed as the hereditary Imperial Prince line, the Fushiminomiyake, and there is said to be a conflict between the two lines within the Northern Dynasty regarding the Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 4 emperors of the Gokogon line, Emperors Gokogen, Koenyu, Gokomatsu, Shoko were on the throne, whereas descendants of Emperor Suko who were the elder brothers, were eliminated from the succeeding line and existed as the hereditary Imperial Prince line, the Fushiminomiyake, and there is said to be a conflict between the two lines within the Northern Dynasty regarding Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 4 emperors of the Gokogon line, Emperors Gokogon, Koenyu, Gokomatsu, Shoko were on the throne, whereas descendants of Emperor Suko who were the elder brothers, were eliminated from the succeeding line and existed as the hereditary Imperial Prince line, the Fushiminomiya ke, and there is said to be a conflict between the two lines within the Northern Court regarding Imperial succession.</e>
<cmt>Dynasty→Court人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>結局、後光厳の系統は称光の代で途絶え、次の後花園天皇（崇光の曾孫）以降、皇位は崇光系が受け継ぐこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the Gokogon line ended with Shoko and the since the next emperor, Emperor Gohanazono (Suko&apos;s great-grandson), the Imperial line was continued on by the Suko line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the Gokogon line ended with Shoko and the next Emperor Gohanazono (Suko&apos;s great-grandson), continued on under the Suko line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the Gokogon line ended with Shoko and the next Emperor Gohanazono (Suko&apos;s great-grandson), continued on under the Suko line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), ロリ(id:613), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), ZZZ(id:9462), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Cave cattum(id:41235), Mishika(id:276), 地五郎(id:10835), でここ(id:9565), Rusk(id:9895), Yonoemon(id:55450), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 663highland(id:18755), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yosemite(id:5808), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>