<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>摂津源氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Settsu Genji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Settsu Genji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Settsu-Genji</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>摂津源氏(せっつげんじ)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Settsu Genji (a branch of the Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Settsu Genji (a branch of the Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Settsu-Genji (a branch of the Minamoto clan)</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>摂津源氏の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bloodline of the Settsu Genji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bloodline of the Settsu Genji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bloodline of the Settsu-Genji</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>源氏武士団を形成した源満仲の子の源頼光は、本拠地の摂津国川辺郡 (兵庫県)多田(現・兵庫県川西市多田)の地を相続し、大内守護(内裏警備、天皇護衛)の任に就いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu--the son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, founding father of the Minamoto clan warrior group--inherited the family&apos;s power base of Oita in Kawabe county of Settsu province (modern-day Oita in Kawanishi city of Hyogo Prefecture), and was appointed the Ouchi shugo (&quot;Protector of the Great Palace,&quot; in charge of guarding the Imperial Palace and the Emperor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu--the son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, founding father of the Minamoto clan warrior group--inherited the family&apos;s power base of Oita in Kawabe county of Settsu province (modern-day Oita in Kawanishi city of Hyogo Prefecture), and was appointed the Ouchi shugo (&quot;Protector of the Great Palace,&quot; in charge of guarding the Imperial Palace and the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu--the son of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, founding father of the Minamoto clan warrior group--inherited the family&apos;s power base of Tada in Kawabe County of Settsu Province (modern-day Tada in Kawanishi City of Hyogo Prefecture), and was appointed the Ouchi shugo (&quot;Protector of the Great Palace,&quot; in charge of guarding the Imperial Palace and the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Oita→Tada住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>摂津源氏は、もっぱら平安京で活動する武士であり、公家の日常に奉公する機会も多く、武はもとより文や和歌に長じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Settsu Genji were for a time the only warriors active in the Heian capital (today&apos;s Kyoto) and had ample opportunity to serve the nobility in their daily affairs, spurring the warriors to begin excelling more and more at literature and at composing waka poetry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Settsu Genji were for a time the only warriors active in the Heian capital (today&apos;s Kyoto) and had ample opportunity to serve the nobility in their daily affairs, spurring the warriors to begin excelling more and more at literature and at composing waka poetry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Settsu-Genji were for a time the only warriors active in the Heian capital (today&apos;s Kyoto) and had ample opportunity to serve the nobility in their daily affairs, spurring the warriors to begin excelling more and more at literature and at composing waka poetry.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>源頼光は、満仲伝来の本拠地を相続したが、その後武家源氏の主流は、頼光の弟の源頼信にはじまり東国へ勢力を扶植し、武家棟梁となった河内源氏のものとなり、子孫が繁栄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu inherited what had been the family&apos;s ancestral power base since Mitsunaka&apos;s time, soon afterwards the main line of the warrior Minamoto clan, and notably his own younger brother MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, transplanted much of their strength into eastern Japan, and formed into the Kawachi Genji, who became the preeminent among the warrior class, and whose descendants flourished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu inherited what had been the family&apos;s ancestral power base since Mitsunaka&apos;s time, soon afterwards the main line of the warrior Minamoto clan, and notably his own younger brother MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, transplanted much of their strength into eastern Japan, and formed into the Kawachi Genji, who became the preeminent among the warrior class, and whose descendants flourished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu inherited his family territory that had been passed down through generations since Mitsunaka, the principal members of the Minamoto clan, including Yorimitsu&apos;s younger brother MINAMOTO no Yorinobu, expanded their power in eastern Japan, marrying into the Kawachi-Genji clan, which served as the leader of all warriors in Japan, and thereby bringing prosperity to their descendants.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後の征夷大将軍は、源氏ではもっぱら河内源氏の流れから出ている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the later Sei-i taishogun (Shogun) came exclusively from the Kawachi Genji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the later Sei-i taishogun (Shogun) came exclusively from the Kawachi Genji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the later seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) came exclusively from the Kawachi-Genji.</e>
<cmt>Sei-i taishogun (Shogun)→seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;)ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>源頼政と源行綱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and MINAMOTO no Yukitsuna</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and MINAMOTO no Yukitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and MINAMOTO no Yukitsuna</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>摂津源氏で名の残る武士は、源頼光以外では、源仲政と、その子で、平治の乱の後、唯一生き残った源氏の長老の源頼政だろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu himself, the most famous warriors of the Settsu Genji included MINAMOTO no Nakamasa and his sons, as well as MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, the only senior member of the family to survive the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu himself, the most famous warriors of the Settsu Genji included MINAMOTO no Nakamasa and his sons, as well as MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, the only senior member of the family to survive the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu himself, the most famous warriors of the Settsu-Genji included MINAMOTO no Nakamasa and his sons, as well as MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, the only senior member of the family to survive the Heiji War.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>頼政は、摂津国の渡辺津(現・大阪市中央区)を本拠地とする滝口武者である嵯峨源氏の渡辺氏を郎党とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorimasa took as followers the Watanabe clan, who belonged to the Saga Genji--Takiguchi warriors--and whose stronghold was in Watanabetsu in Settsu province (in modern-day Chuo-ku (Central Ward) of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorimasa took as followers the Watanabe clan, who belonged to the Saga Genji--Takiguchi warriors--and whose stronghold was in Watanabetsu in Settsu province (in modern-day Chuo-ku (Central Ward) of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorimasa took as followers the Watanabe clan, who belonged to the Saga-Genji--Takiguchi warriors--and whose stronghold was in Watanabetsu in Settsu Province (in modern-day Chuo ward, Osaka City).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入スペル住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>彼は父の仲政と同じく馬場氏を号した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He, like his father Nakamasa, adopted the sobriquet &quot;Baba&quot; (Horse-Ground) clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He, like his father Nakamasa, adopted the sobriquet &quot;Baba&quot; (Horse-Ground) clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He, like his father Nakamasa, adopted the sobriquet Baba clan.</e>
<cmt>(Horse-Ground) 名前なので必要ないと思います。原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>「朝家の守護」と称された満仲、頼光の流れを汲む摂津源氏は、代々、大内守護(宮中護衛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each generation of the Settsu Genji--whose bloodline combined those of both Mitsunaka and Yorimitsu, who were called &quot;Protectors of the Imperial Family&quot;--was appointed Ouchi shugo (Protector of the Great Palace).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each generation of the Settsu Genji--whose bloodline combined those of both Mitsunaka and Yorimitsu, who were called &quot;Protectors of the Imperial Family&quot;--was appointed Ouchi shugo (Protector of the Great Palace).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each generation of the Settsu-Genji--whose bloodline combined those of both Mitsunaka and Yorimitsu, who were called &apos;Protectors of the Imperial Family&apos;--was appointed Ouchi shugo (Protector of the Great Palace).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>近衛部隊の前身のようなもの)の任に就いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(They were tasked with guarding the Imperial Court, and were a precursor of sorts to the later Imperial Guard Corps.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(They were tasked with guarding the Imperial Court, and were a precursor of sorts to the later Imperial Guard Corps.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(They were tasked with guarding the Imperial Court, and were a precursor of sorts to the later Imperial Guard Corps.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>多田を基盤とする系統で名前が残っているのは、鹿ケ谷の陰謀を密告したとされる多田行綱(源行綱)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One member of the Settsu Genji lineage, in their ancestral seat of Oita, gained particular notoriety: OITA Yukitsuna (MINAMOTO no Yukitsuna), who betrayed the Shishigatani conspiracy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One member of the Settsu Genji lineage, in their ancestral seat of Oita, gained particular notoriety: OITA Yukitsuna (MINAMOTO no Yukitsuna), who betrayed the Shishigatani conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One member of the Settsu-Genji lineage, in their ancestral seat of Tada, gained particular notoriety: Yukitsuna TADA (MINAMOTO no Yukitsuna), who betrayed the Shishigatani conspiracy.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入Oita→Tada</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>行綱は源平合戦では源義経軍の一翼の多田源氏棟梁として活躍。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Genpei War (the war between the Minamoto and the Taira clans), Yukitsuna was active as the leader of the Oita Genji, who formed a part of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Genpei War (the war between the Minamoto and the Taira clans), Yukitsuna was active as the leader of the Oita Genji, who formed a part of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Genpei War (the war between the Minamoto and the Taira clans), Yukitsuna was active as the leader of the Tada-Genji, who formed a part of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入Oita→Tada</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そのため、後に源頼朝から疎まれ、多田の所領を没収される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of his service with Yoshitsune, Yukitsuna was later shunned by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and his territory in Oita was eventually confiscated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of his service with Yoshitsune, Yukitsuna was later shunned by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and his territory in Oita was eventually confiscated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of his service with Yoshitsune, Yukitsuna was later shunned by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, and his territory in Tada was eventually confiscated.</e>
<cmt>Oita→Tada</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other notable details concerning the Settsu Genji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other notable details concerning the Settsu Genji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other notable details concerning the Settsu-Genji</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>兵庫県川西市にある満願寺(川西市)の境内に、源国房、源光国、源明国、源仲政、源国直、源行国、源国基ら摂津源氏の武将7人の供養塔がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the grounds of Manganji temple in Kawanishi city in Hyogo Prefecture, there is a memorial tower dedicated to seven warriors of the Settsu Genji: MINAMOTO no Kunifusa, MINAMOTO no Mitsukuni, MINAMOTO no Akikuni, MINAMOTO no Nakamasa, MINAMOTO no Kuninao, MINAMOTO no Yukikuni, and MINAMOTO no Kunimoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the grounds of Manganji temple in Kawanishi city in Hyogo Prefecture, there is a memorial tower dedicated to seven warriors of the Settsu Genji: MINAMOTO no Kunifusa, MINAMOTO no Mitsukuni, MINAMOTO no Akikuni, MINAMOTO no Nakamasa, MINAMOTO no Kuninao, MINAMOTO no Yukikuni, and MINAMOTO no Kunimoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the grounds of Mangan-ji Temple in Kawanishi City in Hyogo Prefecture, there is a memorial tower dedicated to seven warriors of the Settsu-Genji: MINAMOTO no Kunifusa, MINAMOTO no Mitsukuni, MINAMOTO no Akikuni, MINAMOTO no Nakamasa, MINAMOTO no Kuninao, MINAMOTO no Yukikuni, and MINAMOTO no Kunimoto.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>摂津源氏を源氏嫡流であるという見方に対して、「摂津源氏嫡流だの多田源氏嫡流だのの「歴代」を列挙する向きもあるが、源氏嫡流・摂津源氏嫡流・多田源氏嫡流などという概念は同時代には見られぬもの」とする批判がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some have criticized the viewpoint that the Settsu Genji are the primary and eldest lineage of the Minamoto, arguing that &quot;While it may be tempting to list successive generations as &quot;main lineage of the Settsu Genji&quot; or &quot;main lineage of the Oita Genji&quot;, no such conception of lineage for the Genji &quot;main&quot; line or the Settsu or Oita &quot;main&quot; lines really existed at that time.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some have criticized the viewpoint that the Settsu Genji are the primary and eldest lineage of the Minamoto, arguing that &quot;While it may be tempting to list successive generations as &quot;main lineage of the Settsu Genji&quot; or &quot;main lineage of the Oita Genji&quot;, no such conception of lineage for the Genji &quot;main&quot; line or the Settsu or Oita &quot;main&quot; lines really existed at that time.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some have criticized the viewpoint that the Settsu-Genji are the primary and eldest lineage of the Minamoto, arguing that &apos;While it may be tempting to list &apos;successive generations&apos; as main lineage of the Settsu-Genji or main lineage of the Tada-Genji, no such conception of lineage for the Genji main line or the Settsu or Tada main lines really existed at that time.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ハイフン挿入原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に原文に『』のない&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SuperTTS(id:221889), Izayohi(id:13095), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), やりたこ(id:113528), Amler(id:101250), Kusunose(id:5719), Andee(id:20421), 越中掾(id:149423), Junger(id:10282), 沢田(id:40580), 編集仁王(id:208160), 墨田真野(id:145448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>