<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>守護大名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>守護大名（しゅごだいみょう）は、軍事・警察権能だけでなく、経済的権能をも獲得し、一国内に領域的・一円的な支配を強化していった室町時代の守護を表す日本史上の概念。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shugo daimyo is a concept in Japanese history that refers to the shugo in the Muromachi period who acquired not only the function of the military and the law enforcement but also the economic power, and strengthened the territorial, pervasive control over a province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shugo daimyo is a concept in Japanese history that refers to the shugo of the Muromachi period, who acquired not only the function of the military and law enforcement but also the economic power, and strengthened the territorial, pervasive control over a province.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shugo daimyo is a concept in Japanese history that refers to the shugo of the Muromachi period, who acquired not only the function of the military and law enforcement but also the economic power, and strengthened the territorial, pervasive control over a province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>守護大名による領国支配の体制を守護領国制という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provincial system governed by the shugo daimyo is called the &apos;shugo-ryogoku system.&apos;</e>
<cmt>http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/守護領国制/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provincial system governed by the shugo daimyo is called the &apos;shugo-ryogoku system.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provincial system governed by the shugo daimyo is called the &apos;shugo-ryogoku system.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>15世紀後期～16世紀初頭ごろに一部は戦国大名となり、一部は没落していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late 15th to the early 16th century, some daimyo became the Sengoku daimyo (daimyo of the Sengoku, or &apos;Warring States&apos; period), and some other daimyo declined.</e>
<cmt>戦国大名: http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/534554/Sengoku-daimyo</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the period of the late fifteenth to early sixteenth century, some daimyo became Sengoku daimyo (daimyo of the Sengoku, or &apos;Warring States&apos; period) while other daimyo declined.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the period of the late fifteenth to early sixteenth century, some daimyo became Sengoku daimyo (daimyo of the Sengoku, or &apos;Warring States&apos; period) while other daimyo declined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>鎌倉時代における守護の権能は御成敗式目に規定があり、大犯三ヶ条の検断沙汰（御家人の義務である鎌倉・京都での大番役の催促、謀反人の捜索逮捕、殺害人の捜索逮捕）および大番役の指揮監督という軍事・警察面に限定され、国司の権限である国衙行政・国衙領支配に関与することは禁じられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The power of the shugo in the Kamakura period was prescribed by the Legal Code for the Warrior Class: their power was limited to the military and the law enforcement such as the &apos;Taibon-sankajo no kendan-sata&apos; (three official authorities given to the shugo over criminal cases: the prodding of lower-ranking vassals to fulfill their duty as obanyaku, i.e., security guard, in Kyoto and Kamakura, the search and arrest of rebels and murderers) and the direction and supervision of obanyaku, and the shugo was prohibited from participating in the administration of the kokuga and the kokuga&apos;s province, which the kokushi was authorized to perform.</e>
<cmt>御成敗式目: 英辞郎 on the WEB大番役: http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=大番役&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=1&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=02840602234000謀反人: 英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=国司&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=07478006377000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of the shugo during the Kamakura period was prescribed by the legal code for the warrior class: their power was limited to the military and law enforcement, such as the &apos;Taibon-sankajo no kendan-sata&apos; (three official authorities given to the shugo over criminal cases: the prodding of lower-ranking vassals to fulfill their duties as obanyaku, i.e., security guards, in Kyoto and Kamakura, the search and arrest of rebels and murderers) and the direction and supervision of obanyaku; the shugo was prohibited from participating in the administration of the kokuga and the kokuga&apos;s province, which the kokushi was authorized to perform.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The power of the shugo during the Kamakura period was prescribed by the legal code for the warrior class: their power was limited to the military and law enforcement, such as the &apos;Taibon-sankajo no kendan-sata&apos; (three official authorities given to the shugo over criminal cases: the prodding of lower-ranking vassals to fulfill their duties as obanyaku, i.e., security guards, in Kyoto and Kamakura, the search and arrest of rebels and murderers) and the direction and supervision of obanyaku; the shugo was prohibited from participating in the administration of the kokuga and the kokuga&apos;s province, which the kokushi was authorized to perform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>室町幕府が成立すると、鎌倉幕府の守護制度を継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shugo system of the Kamakura Shogunate was inherited when the Muromachi Shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shugo system of the Kamakura shogunate was inherited when the Muromachi shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shugo system of the Kamakura shogunate was inherited when the Muromachi shogunate was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当初、守護の職権については鎌倉期と同じく大犯三ヶ条の検断に限定されていたが、国内統治を一層安定させるため、1346年（貞和2）幕府は刈田狼藉の検断権と使節遵行権を新たに守護の職権へ加えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the power of the shugo was limited to the taibon-sankajo-no-kendan in the same way asthe Kamakura period, but in 1346, the Muromachi Shogunate gave the shugo the authority to judge the case of the &apos;karita-rozeki&apos; and the authority of the &apos;shisetsu-jungyo&apos; to administer the country more stably.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=刈田狼藉&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=04485803706200使節遵行: http://kotobank.jp/word/%E4%BD%BF%E7%AF%80%E9%81%B5%E8%A1%8C</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The power of the shugo was at first limited to the taibon-sankajo-no-kendan in the same way asthe Kamakura period, but in 1346 the Muromachi shogunate gave the shugo the authority to judge the case of the &apos;karita-rozeki&apos; and the authority of the &apos;shisetsu-jungyo&apos; to administer the country more stably.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the power of the shugo was limited to the taibon-sankajo-no-kendan, just as it was in the Kamakura period, but in 1346 the Muromachi shogunate gave the shugo the authority to judge the case of the karita-rozeki and the authority of the shisetsu-jungyo to administer the country more stably.</e>
<cmt>原文に「」のない&apos;　&apos;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>刈田狼藉とは土地の所有を主張するために田の稲を刈り取る実力行使であり、武士間の所領紛争に伴って発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The karita-rozeki was a physical act of harvesting rice in the paddy field in order to claim the ownership of the land, and occurred with the conflicts of land appropriation among samurais..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The karita-rozeki, an act of harvesting rice in the paddy field in order to claim the ownership of the land, occurred with the conflicts of land appropriation among samurai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The karita-rozeki, an act of harvesting rice in the paddy field in order to claim the ownership of the land, occurred with the conflicts of land appropriation among samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>使節遵行とは幕府の判決内容を現地で強制執行することである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shisetsu-jungyo was to enforce the shogunate&apos;s decision in the field.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shisetsu-jungyo was intended to enforce the shogunate&apos;s decision in the field.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shisetsu-jungyo was intended to enforce the shogunate&apos;s decision in the field.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらの検断権を獲得したことにより、守護は、国内の武士間の紛争へ介入する権利と、司法執行の権利の2つを獲得することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of obtaining these rights to judge criminal cases, the shugo had the two rights now: the right to intervene in the dispute between samurais in the province and the right to enforce the law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of obtaining the right of judgment over criminal cases, the shugo now had two: the right to intervene in the dispute between samurais in the province and the right to enforce the law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of obtaining the right of judgment over criminal cases, the shugo now had two rights: the right to intervene in the dispute between samurai in the province and the right to enforce the law.</e>
<cmt>rights を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、当初は現地の有力武士が任じられる事が多かった守護の人選も次第に足利将軍家の一族や譜代、功臣の世襲へと変更されていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the shugo, at first, were often selected from the powerful samurais in the local area, but the change was gradually made to select from the descents of the Ashikaga Shogun family, the Fudai (hereditary vassals), or the meritorious retainer.</e>
<cmt>譜代: http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761566679_16/japan.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, originally the shugo were often selected from the powerful samurais in the local area, but the change was gradually made to select from the descents of the Ashikaga shogun family, the Fudai (hereditary vassals) or the meritorious retainer.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, originally the shugo were often selected from the powerful samurais in the local area, but the change was gradually made to select from the descents of the Ashikaga shogun family, the Fudai (hereditary vassals) or the meritorious retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>1352年（文和元）、観応の擾乱における軍事兵粮の調達を目的に、国内の荘園・国衙領から年貢の半分を徴収することのできる半済の権利が守護に与えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1352, the shugo were given the right &apos;hanzei&apos; to collect half of the customs form the manor and the Kokuga&apos;s territory within the province in order to secure military provisions for the Kanno-no-Joran (turmoil of the Kanno).</e>
<cmt>半済: http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/159931/m0u/%E5%8D%8A%E6%B8%88/http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=観応の擾乱&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=04796703987200荘園: 英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=国衙領&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=1&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=07454006358200年貢: 英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1352, the shugo were given the right of &apos;hanzei&apos; to collect half the customs form the manor and the Kokuga&apos;s territory within the province, in order to secure military provisions for the Kanno-no-Joran (turmoil of the Kanno).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1352, the shugo were given the right of hanzei to collect half the customs from the manor and the Kokuga&apos;s territory within the province, in order to secure military provisions for the Kanno-no-Joran (turmoil of the Kanno).</e>
<cmt>原文に「」のない&apos;　&apos;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>当初、半済は戦乱の激しい3国（近江国・美濃国・尾張国）に限定して認められていたが、守護たちは半済の実施を幕府へ競って要望し、半済は次第に恒久化され、各地に拡がっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, the hanzei was granted only in the three provinces where fierce battles raged (Omi-no-kuni, Mino-no-kuni, and Owari-no-kuni), but the shugo competed to demand for the grant of the hanzei, and the right was gradually perpetuated, spreading all over.</e>
<cmt>http://kotobank.jp/word/美濃国http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/尾張国/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the hanzei was granted only in the three provinces where fierce battles had raged (Omi-no-kuni, Mino-no-kuni, and Owari-no-kuni), but the shugo competed to demand the granting of hanzei, and the right was gradually perpetuated, spreading throughout the land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the hanzei was granted only in the three provinces where fierce battles had raged (Omi Province, Mino Province, and Owari Provice), but the shugo competed to demand the granting of hanzei, and the right was gradually perpetuated, spreading throughout the land.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Omi-no-kuni, Mino-no-kuni, and Owari-no-kuni&quot;→&quot;Omi Province, Mino Province, and Owari Provice&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>1368年（応安元）に出された応安の半済令は、従来認められていた年貢の半分割だけでなく、土地自体の半分割をも認める内容であり、この後、守護による荘園・国衙領への侵出が著しくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hanzei decree of the Oan era issued in 1368 authorized the shugo to take not only half of the customs, which had been already granted, but also half of the land itself, and subsequently the shugo penetrated deep into the manor and the Kokuga&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hanzei decree of the Oan era issued in 1368 authorized the shugo to take not only half the customs, which had already been granted, but also half the land, and subsequently the shugo penetrated deep into the manor and the Kokuga&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hanzei decree of the Oan era issued in 1368 authorized the shugo to take not only half the customs, which had already been granted, but also half the land, and subsequently the shugo penetrated deep into the manor and the Kokuga&apos;s territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに、守護は荘園領主らと年貢納付の請け負い契約を結び、実質的に荘園への支配を強める守護請（しゅごうけ）も行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the shugo signed with lords of the manor a contract to manage the payment of the customs, and served as the shugo-uke who substantially had a stronger control over the manor.</e>
<cmt>荘園領主: 英辞郎 on the WEB守護請: http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the shugo signed, together with the manor lords, a contract to manage the payment of customs, and served as the shugo-uke, who had substantially greater control over the manor.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the shugo signed, together with the manor lords, a contract to manage the payment of customs, and served as the shugo-uke, who had substantially greater control over the manor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この守護請によって、守護は土地自体を支配する権利、すなわち下地進止権（したじしんしけん）を獲得していくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this shugo-uke, the shugo obtained the right to govern the land itself, i.e., the shitaji-shinshi-ken (the right to appropriate the land).</e>
<cmt>下地進止: http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this shugo-uke, the shugo obtained the right to govern the land itself, i.e., the shitaji-shinshi-ken (the right to appropriate the land).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this shugo-uke, the shugo obtained the right to govern the land itself, i.e., the shitaji-shinshi-ken (the right to appropriate the land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="16">
<j>また、朝廷や幕府が臨時的な事業（御所造営など）のため田の面積に応じて賦課した段銭や、家屋ごとに賦課した棟別銭の徴収は、守護が行うこととされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the shugo were granted to collect the tansen, or a tax imposed in proportion to the area by the Imperial court or the Shogunate for the contingent project, for example building the palace, and to collect the munebetsu-sen, or a tax imposed on each house.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=段銭&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=13619411762400http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=棟別銭&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=20968417969000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the shugo were granted the right to collect the tansen, a tax imposed in proportion to the area by the Imperial Court or the shogunate for the contingent project (for example, building the palace) and to collect the munebetsu-sen, a tax imposed on each house.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the shugo were granted the right to collect the tansen, a tax imposed in proportion to the area by the Imperial Court or the shogunate for the contingent project (for example, building the palace) and to collect the munebetsu-sen, a tax imposed on each house.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>守護はこの徴収権を利用して、独自に領国へ段銭・棟別銭を賦課・徴収し、経済的権能をますます強めていったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this right to collect tax, the shugo strengthened the economic power more and more by independently imposing and collecting the tansen and the munebetsu-sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this right to collect tax, the shugo continued to strengthen the economic power by independently imposing and collecting the tansen and munebetsu-sen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this right to collect tax, the shugo continued to strengthen the economic power by independently imposing and collecting the tansen and munebetsu-sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>守護は以上のように強化された権限を背景に、それまで国司が管轄していた国衙の組織を吸収し、国衙の在庁官人を被官（家臣）として組み込むと同時に、国衙領や在庁官人の所領を併合して、守護直轄の守護領（しゅごりょう）を形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of their enhanced powers described above, the shugo took over the organization governed by the kokushi, recruited the zaicho-kannin (kokuga&apos;s officer) in the kokuga as a vassa,l and at the same time, combined the kokuga&apos;s province with the zaicho-kannin&apos;s territory to form the shugo-ryo (shugo&apos;s province) directly governed by the shugo.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=国衙&amp;stype=0&amp;dtype=2在庁官人: http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=在庁官人&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=08296707098700</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the enhanced powers as described above, the shugo took over the organization governed by the kokushi and recruited the zaicho-kannin (kokuga&apos;s officer) in the kokuga as a vassal while at the same time combining the kokuga&apos;s province with the zaicho-kannin&apos;s territory to form the shugo-ryo (shugo&apos;s province) directly governed by the shugo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the enhanced powers as described above, the shugo took over the organization governed by the kokushi and recruited the zaicho-kannin (kokuga&apos;s officer) in the kokuga as a vassal while at the same time combining the kokuga&apos;s province with the zaicho-kannin&apos;s territory to form the shugo-ryo (shugo&apos;s province) directly governed by the shugo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="19">
<j>またこれと並行して、守護は強い経済力をもって、上記の在庁官人の他、国内の地頭・名主といった有力者（当時、国人と呼ばれた）をも被官（家臣）にしていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In parallel with these processes, the shugo, with their strong economy, recruited as a vassal even influential figures called kokujin at that time such as the jito (estate steward) and the myoshu (owner of the paddy field) in the province in addition to the zaicho-kannin mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>地頭: 英辞郎 on the WEBhttp://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=名主&amp;dtype=0&amp;stype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;ref=1&amp;index=20780717797500http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=国人&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=07485506384000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In parallel with these processes, the shugo, with their strong economy, recruited as vassals even influential figures called kokujin, such as the jito (estate steward) and the myoshu (owner of the paddy field) in the province, in addition to the zaicho-kannin mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In parallel with these processes, the shugo, with their strong economy, recruited as vassals even influential figures called kokujin, such as the jito (estate steward) and the myoshu (owner of the paddy field) in the province, in addition to the zaicho-kannin mentioned above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この動きを被官化というが、こうして守護は、土地の面でも人的面でも、国内に領域的かつ均一な影響力（一円支配）を強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This wholw process is called &apos;hikanka&apos; (被官化), and the shugo increased their equal, territorial influence (pervasive control) over the province.</e>
<cmt>被官化: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This entire process is called &apos;hikanka&apos; (被官化), and with it the shugo increased their equal, territorial influence (pervasive control) over the province.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This entire process is called &apos;hikanka&apos; (被官化), and with it the shugo increased their equal, territorial influence (pervasive control) over the province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>こうした室町期の守護のあり方は、軍事・警察的権能のみを有した鎌倉期守護のそれと大きく異なることから、室町期守護を指して守護大名と称して区別する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These functions of the shugo in the Muromachi period were considerably different from those in the Kamakura period, which were limited to the military and the law enforcement, and accordingly the shugo in the Muromachi period is called the shugo daimyo, distinguished from the shugo in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These functions of the shugo during the Muromachi period were considerably different from those of the Kamakura period, which were limited to the military and law enforcement; accordingly, the shugo of the Muromachi period is called the shugo daimyo, being distinguished from the shugo of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These functions of the shugo during the Muromachi period were considerably different from those of the Kamakura period, which were limited to the military and law enforcement; accordingly, the shugo of the Muromachi period is called the shugo daimyo, being distinguished from the shugo of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、守護大名による国内の支配体制を守護領国制という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the provincial system governed by the shugo daimyo is called the shugo-ryogoku system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the provincial system governed by the shugo daimyo is called the shugo-ryogoku system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the provincial system governed by the shugo daimyo is called the shugo-ryogoku system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただし、守護大名による領国支配は、後世の戦国領国制と比べると必ずしも徹底したものではなく、畿内を中心に、国人層が守護の被官となることを拒否した例も、実際には多く見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provincial control by the shugo daimyo, however, was not as complete as the one in the Sengoku-ryogoku system in the later period: in fact, there are many examples that the Kokujin refused to serve as a vassal of the shugo particularly in the Kinai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provincial control by the shugo daimyo, however, was not as complete as the one in the Sengoku-ryogoku system during the later period: in fact, there are many examples in which the Kokujin refused to serve as a vassal of the shugo, particularly in the Kinai.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provincial control by the shugo daimyo, however, was not as complete as the one in the Sengoku-ryogoku system during the later period: in fact, there are many examples in which the Kokujin refused to serve as a vassal of the shugo, particularly in the Kinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、幕府も荘園制度の解体や守護の権力強化は望ましいとは考えておらず、朝廷や寺社との対立をしてまで、有力守護大名に対して度々掣肘を加えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the shogunate did not think it appropriate to dismantle the manorial system or to strengthen the power of the shugo, and often disturbed powerful shugo daimyo despite the opposition of the Imperial court, temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>荘園制度: 英辞郎 on the WEB</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the shogunate did not think it was appropriate to dismantle the manorial system or strengthen the power of the shugo, and this often disturbed powerful shugo daimyo despite the opposition of the Imperial Court, temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the shogunate did not think it was appropriate to dismantle the manorial system or strengthen the power of the shugo, and this often disturbed powerful shugo daimyo despite the opposition of the Imperial Court, temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="25">
<j>室町中期までに、幕府における守護大名の権能は肥大化し、幕府はいわば守護大名の連合政権の様相を呈するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the mid Muromachi period, the system of the shugo daimyo in the shogunate was enlarged, and it was possible to describe the Muromachi Shogunate as a so-called coalition government of shugo daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the middle of the Muromachi period the system of the shugo daimyo in the shogunate was enlarged, and it was possible to describe the Muromachi shogunate as a so-called coalition government of shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the middle of the Muromachi period the system of the shugo daimyo in the shogunate was enlarged, and it was possible to describe the Muromachi shogunate as a so-called coalition government of shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>当時の有力な守護大名には、足利将軍家の一族である斯波氏・畠山氏・細川氏をはじめ、外様勢力である山名氏・大内氏・赤松氏など数ヶ国を支配する者がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Powerful shugo daimyo in those days include the tozama-seiryoku (forces of outside lords) such as the Yamana clan, the Ochi clan and the Akamatsu clan, as well as the clans of the Ashikaga Shogun family such as the Shiba clan, the Hatakeyama clan and the Hosokawa clan.</e>
<cmt>外様: http://encarta.msn.com/encyclopedia_761566679_16/japan.htmlhttp://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/斯波氏/http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/畠山氏/http://100.yahoo.co.jp/detail/山名氏/http://kotobank.jp/word/大内http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=赤松&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=00218200131300</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Powerful shugo daimyo in those days included the tozama-seiryoku (forces of outside lords) such as the Yamana, Ochi and Akamatsu clans, as well as the clans of the Ashikaga shogun family such as the Shiba, Hatakeyama and Hosokawa clans.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Powerful shugo daimyo in those days included the tozama-seiryoku (forces of outside lords) such as the Yamana, Ouchi and Akamatsu clans, as well as the clans of the Ashikaga shogun family such as the Shiba, Hatakeyama and Hosokawa clans.</e>
<cmt>Ochi→Ouchi に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これら有力守護は、幕府に出仕するため継続して在京することが多く、領国を離れる場合や多くの分国を抱える場合などに、守護の代官として国人や直属家臣の中から守護代を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These powerful shugo often resided in the capital for some duration to serve the shogunate, and for this reason, they appointed the shugo-dai (deputy shugo) from the kokujin and the direct vassals as a deputy of the shugo when they left the province or had many provinces.</e>
<cmt>守護代: The Cambridge History of Japan: Medieval Japan</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These powerful shugo often resided in the capital for some duration in order to serve the shogunate, and for that reason they appointed the shugo-dai (deputy shugo) from the kokujin and the direct vassals as deputies of the shugo when they left the province or had many provinces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These powerful shugo often resided in the capital for some duration in order to serve the shogunate, and for that reason they appointed the shugo-dai (deputy shugo) from the kokujin and the direct vassals as deputies of the shugo when they left the province or had many provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>さらに守護代も小守護代を置いて、二重三重の支配構造を形成していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even the shugo-dai placed the ko-shugo-dai (deputy of the shugo-dai), creating two to three layers of the governance structure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even the shugo-dai placed the ko-shugo-dai (deputy of the shugo-dai), creating a structure of governance having two or three layers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even the shugo-dai placed the ko-shugo-dai (deputy of the shugo-dai), creating a structure of governance having two or three layers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>応仁の乱の前後から、守護大名同士の紛争が目立って増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since around the Onin War (Onin-no-ran), conflicts between shugo daimyo increased in a striking manner.</e>
<cmt>応仁の乱: http://wsu.edu/~dee/TOKJAPAN/WARRING.HTM</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since approximately the time of the Onin War (Onin-no-ran), conflicts between shugo daimyo increased to a striking degree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since approximately the time of the Onin War (Onin-no-ran), conflicts between shugo daimyo increased to a striking degree.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>それに歩調を合わせるように、国人層の独立志向（国人一揆など）が顕著に現れるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In line with the increased conflicts, the Kokujin&apos;s aspirations for independence, for example the kokujin uprising (kokujin-ikki), became more apparent</e>
<cmt>国人一揆: The Cambridge History of Japan: Medieval Japan</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concurrent with the increased conflicts, the Kokujin&apos;s aspirations for independence, for example the kokujin uprising (kokujin-ikki), became more apparent</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concurrently with the increased conflicts, the Kokujin&apos;s aspirations for independence, as in the kokujin uprising (kokujin-ikki), became more apparent.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>これらの動きは、一方では守護大名の権威の低下を招いたが、また一方で守護大名による国人への支配強化へとつながっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the one hand, these movements undermined the authority of the shugo daimyo, but on the other hand, they tightened the control of the kokujin by the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On one hand, these movements undermined the authority of the shugo daimyo, but on the other hand they tightened the control of the kokujin by the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On one hand, these movements undermined the authority of the shugo daimyo, but on the other hand they tightened the control of the kokujin by the shugo daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そして、1493年（明応2）の明応の政変前後を契機として、低下した権威の復活に失敗した守護大名は、守護代・国人などにその地位を奪われて没落し、逆に国人支配の強化に成功した守護大名は、領国支配を一層強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting around the Meio-no-seihen (明応の政変) in 1493, the shugo daimyo who failed in regaining the authority were ousted from their positions, while those succeeded in tightening the control of the kokujin further strengthened the provincial control.</e>
<cmt>明応の政変: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting around the Meio-no-seihen (明応の政変) in 1493, the shugo daimyo that had failed to regain authority were ousted from their positions, while those that succeeded in tightening the control of the kokujin further strengthened the provincial control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting around the Meio-no-seihen (明応の政変) in 1493, the shugo daimyo that had failed to regain authority were ousted from their positions by shugo-dai and kokujin, while those that succeeded in tightening the control of the kokujin further strengthened the provincial control.</e>
<cmt>by shugo-dai and kokujin の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="33">
<j>こうして室町期の守護のうち領国支配の強化に成功した守護や、守護に取って代わった守護代・国人は、戦国大名へと変質・成長していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those shugo in the Muromachi period who succeeded in strengthening the control of the province, as wel as the shugo-dai and the kokujin who overthrew the shugo, were to evolve into the Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shugo in the Muromachi period that had succeeded in strengthening the control of the province, as well as the shugo-dai and the kokujin that had overthrown the shugo, gradually evolved into the Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shugo in the Muromachi period that had succeeded in strengthening the control of the province, as well as the shugo-dai and the kokujin that had overthrown the shugo, gradually evolved into the Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)は下位の者が上位者に取って代わる下克上の時代とされているが、実際にはかなりの守護大名が戦国大名への転身を遂げたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku period is said to have been the &apos;era of Gekokujo,&apos; in which the inferiors overthrew their superiors, but in fact, a considerable number of the shugo daimyo managed to turn into the Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sengoku period is said to have been the &apos;era of Gekokujo,&apos; in which the inferiors overthrew their superiors, but in fact a considerable number of shugo daimyo managed to become Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku period is said to have been the era of Gekokujo, in which the inferiors overthrew their superiors, but in fact a considerable number of shugo daimyo managed to become Sengoku daimyo.</e>
<cmt>原文に「」のない&apos;　&apos;を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>しかし、近世の大名として残存できた家は、上杉家、京極家、細川奥州家、和泉細川家、小笠原家、島津家、佐竹家、宗家のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only families that survived to remain as daimyo in the modern period, however, were as follows: the Uesugi family, the Kyogoku family, the Hosokawa-oshu family, the Izumi-Hosokawa family, the Ogasawara family, the Shimazu family, the Satake family, and the Soke family.</e>
<cmt>http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=上杉&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=01700901373300http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=京極&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=1&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=05458804571500http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=小笠原&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=02891302273700http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=島津&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=09777008369000http://dic.yahoo.co.jp/dsearch?enc=UTF-8&amp;p=佐竹&amp;dtype=0&amp;dname=0na&amp;stype=0&amp;pagenum=1&amp;index=08563707345000</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only families that survived to remain as daimyo in the modern period were as follows: the Uesugi, the Kyogoku, the Hosokawa-oshu, the Izumi-Hosokawa, the Ogasawara, the Shimazu, the Satake and the Soke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only families that survived to remain as daimyo in the modern period were as follows: the Uesugi, the Kyogoku, the Hosokawa-oshu, the Izumi-Hosokawa, the Ogasawara, the Shimazu, the Satake and the Soke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Doskoi 8(id:1070), Shimoxx(id:9332), Ittyon(id:1348), NoriBeat(id:2074), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>