<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>雑徭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>雑徭（ぞうよう、ざつよう）は、中国及び日本の律令制下での労役の形態を取る租税制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The zoyo was a tax system, in which taxes were paid in the form of labor, under the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in China and Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The zoyo tax system was one in which taxes were paid in the form of labor, under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in China and Japan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zoyo tax system was one in which taxes were paid in the form of labor, under the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) in China and Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>日本の雑徭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoyo in Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoyo in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoyo in Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>日本の雑徭（ぞうよう）は、中国の制度を元としているが、日本の国情に合わせて導入されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The zoyo in Japan was based on the Chinese system, and yet, it was introduced after being modified to adapt to the conditions of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The zoyo in Japan was based on the Chinese system, but it was introduced after being modified to meet the conditions of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zoyo in Japan was based on the Chinese system, but it was introduced after being modified to meet the conditions of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>地方において国司が徴発・編成し、治水灌漑工事をはじめとする各種インフラ整備や国衙等の修築などをさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kokushi (provincial governors) in local areas impressed and organized people to compel them to develop a range of infrastructure such as flood control work and irrigation construction and to renovate buildings such as the kokuga (provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kokushi (provincial governors) in local areas impressed and organized people so as to compel them to develop an infrastructure(such as flood control work and irrigation construction) and to renovate buildings such as the kokuga (provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kokushi (provincial governors) in local areas impressed and organized people so as to compel them to develop an infrastructure (such as flood control work and irrigation construction) and to renovate buildings such as the kokuga (provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その初見が692年（持統天皇6年）のため『飛鳥浄御原令』で制定されたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first zoyo is believed to have been established in the code &quot;Asuka-kiyomihara-ryo&quot; in 692.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first zoyo is believed to have been established in the &quot;Asuka-kiyomihara-ryo&quot; code of 692.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first zoyo is believed to have been established in the &quot;Asuka-kiyomihara-ryo&quot; code of 692.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>当初は正丁（21～60歳の男性）年間60日以下、次丁（正丁の障害者と老丁（61歳以上の男性））年間30日以下、中男（17～20歳の男性）年間15日以下を限度としたが、757年（天平宝字元年）に雑徭を半減する格式が出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, the maximum number of days per annum for the zoyo was less than or equal to sixty days for the seitei (male between the ages of 21 and 60), thirty days for the jitei (the seitei with disabilities and the rotei, or male over 60 years old), and fifteen days for the chunan (male between the ages of 17 and 20), but the kyakushiki code (code to amend and supplement the ritsuryo code) to reduce the zoyo by half was introduced in 757.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, the maximum number of days per annum for the zoyo was less than or equal to 60 for the seitei (a male between the ages of 21 and 60), 30 for the jitei (a seitei with disabilities) and the rotei (a male over age 60), and 15 days for the chunan (a male between the ages of 17 and 20), but the Kyakushiki code (a code to amend and supplement the Ritsuryo code) intended to reduce the zoyo by half was introduced in 757.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the maximum number of days per annum for the zoyo was less than or equal to 60 for the seitei (a male between the ages of 21 and 60), 30 for the jitei (a seitei with disabilities) and the rotei (a male over age 60), and 15 days for the chunan (a male between the ages of 17 and 20), but the Kyakushiki code (a code to amend and supplement the Ritsuryo code) intended to reduce the zoyo by half was introduced in 757.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>藤原仲麻呂の死後いったんは元に戻ったが、796年（延暦14年）に再度半減された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The maximum number of days was restored to the original one after FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s death, and yet again, was reduced by half in 796.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The maximum number of days was restored to the original amount after the death of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, but in 796 it was reduced by half.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The maximum number of days was restored to the original amount after the death of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, but in 796 it was reduced by half.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>雑徭の賦課は国司の権限であり、なかには私用で雑徭を課す国司もおり、公民の負担となり班田農民の没落・逃散を促したとする見解が通説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the kokushi&apos;s right to impose the zoyo, and among them, there were some kokushi who imposed the zoyo for personal use; it is commonly accepted that the zoyo became a burden to the komin (the registered people, especially farmers, under the ritsuryo system) and thus caused the handen farmers (farmers given by the government the handen, or the allotted land for farming) to decline and abandon the land to flee to a new domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the kokushi&apos;s right to impose the zoyo, and among the kokushi there was some who imposed the zoyo for personal use; it is commonly accepted that the zoyo became a burden to the komin (the registered people, especially farmers, under the Ritsuryo system) and thus caused the handen farmers (farmers whom the government had given the handen, or the allotted land for farming) to decline, abandon the land and flee to other domains.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the kokushi&apos;s right to impose the zoyo, and among the kokushi there was some who imposed the zoyo for personal use; it is commonly accepted that the zoyo became a burden to the komin (the registered people, especially farmers, under the Ritsuryo system) and thus caused the handen farmers (farmers whom the government had given the handen, or the allotted land for farming) to decline, abandon the land and flee to other domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>中国の雑徭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoyo (or zatsuyo) in China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoyo (or zatsuyo) in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoyo (or zatsuyo) in China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>中国の雑徭（ざつよう）は、北魏に始まり、唐で完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The zatsuyo in China was established in the Northern Wei Dynasty and was completed in the Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The zatsuyo in China was established in the Northern Wei dynasty and was completed during the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zatsuyo in China was established in the Northern Wei dynasty and was completed during the Tang dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>唐では地方官庁が徴発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tang Dynasty, the local governments impressed people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tang Dynasty, the local governments impressed people.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tang Dynasty, the local governments impressed people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>詳細については不明な点が多く、租庸調と並び基本的な税目とであったとする説と基本的な労役は租庸調とは別系統である差科（職役などが代表例）であるとする説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many details remain to be clarified, and there are two theories about the zatsuyo (zoyo): one is that the zatsuyo as well as the soyocho (a tax system under the kinden system, or equal-field system) was a basic tax; the other maintains that the labor to the government was basically provided in the form of the saka (allocated labor by rank, 差科), a major example of which was the shokueki (職役), or transporting of goods), a different tax system from the soyocho, but in Japan, the saka system, in which the ko (an administrative unit of a few families under the ritsuryo system) was classified by rank and the labor was allocated according to the rank, was not adopted and therefore the zoyo, free of rank, was mandated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many details remain to be clarified, and there are two theories about the zatsuyo (zoyo): one is that the zatsuyo as well as the soyocho (a tax system under the kinden system, or the equal-field system) was a basic tax; the other maintains that the labor to the government was basically provided in the form of the saka (labor allocated by rank, 差科), a major example of which was the shokueki (職役), or the transport of goods), being a different tax system from the soyocho.</e>
<cmt>grammar一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many details remain to be clarified, and there are two theories about the zatsuyo (zoyo): one is that the zatsuyo as well as the soyocho (a tax system under the kinden system, or the equal-field system) was a basic tax; the other maintains that the labor to the government was basically provided in the form of the saka (labor allocated by rank, 差科), a major example of which was the shokueki (職役), or the transport of goods), being a different tax system from the soyocho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかしながら、雑徭はその補完でしかない（日本は戸を等級で分けて等級ごとに負担する労役を定める差科制を採らなかった為に等級に依らない雑徭が義務化された）としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in Japan the saka system, in which the ko (an administrative unit of a few families under the Ritsuryo system) was classified by rank and the labor was allocated according to rank, was not adopted and therefore the zoyo, free of rank, was mandated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in Japan the saka system, in which the ko (an administrative unit of a few families under the Ritsuryo system) was classified by rank and the labor was allocated according to rank, was not adopted and therefore the zoyo, free of rank, was mandated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>またその負担についても義務であったとする説と、臨時的な税であり賦課されない場合もあったとする説に分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there is a controversy over the burden of the labor: one theory indicates that the burden was always mandatory, and the other claims that it was a provisional tax and was not always imposed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, there is a controversy regarding the burden of labor, in which one theory indicates that the burden was always mandatory and the other claims that it was a provisional tax that wasn&apos;t uniformly imposed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, there is a controversy regarding the burden of labor, in which one theory indicates that the burden was always mandatory and the other claims that it was a provisional tax that wasn&apos;t uniformly imposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>庸が年間20日の労役の義務であるのに対し40日の雑徭により庸が免除される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was possible to be exempted from the yo (a part of the soyocho), which mandated twenty days of labor a year, by substituting it with forty days of the zatsuyo; the zatsuyo had an aspect of substitute tax for the yo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was possible to be exempted from the yo (a part of the soyocho), which mandated 20 days of labor a year, by substituting it with 40 days of the zatsuyo; thus the zatsuyo had an aspect of substitute tax for the yo.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The yo was a part of the soyocho from which it was possible to be exempted; this annual mandatory 20 days of labor could be substituted with 40 days of the zatsuyo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。2文に分かれていますので、一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>庸の代替税の側面を持つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zatsuyo was effectively a substitute tax for the yo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Pieria(id:48925), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>