<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>任那日本府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Mimana Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimana Nihon-fu (Japanese government in Mimana)</e>
<cmt>英語の定訳はないようです。&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;という表記が多いです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimana Nihon-fu (Japanese government in Mimana)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>任那日本府（みまなのにほんふ、やまとのみこともち）とは、古代、朝鮮半島南部の任那にあったとされる倭国の統治機関である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Mimana Government is the governing institution of Wakoku (Japan) which is said to have been located in the southern area of Korean Peninsula in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mimana Nihon-fu or Yamato no Mikotomochi is the governing institution of Wakoku (Japan) which is said to have been located in Mimana in the southern area of the Korean Peninsula in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>一般的には「みまなにほんふ」と読むようです。（「の」は入らない）。Web上のwikipediaでもこの表記です。半島には通常定冠詞をつけると思います。&quot;in Mimana&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mimana Nihon-fu or Yamato no Mikotomochi is the governing institution of Wakoku (Japan) which is said to have been located in Mimana in the southern area of the Korean Peninsula in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>その実態については諸説あり、議論が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various theories about its actual status and discussions still continue to this day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various theories about its actual status and discussions still continue to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various theories about its actual status and discussions still continue to this day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』をはじめ、中国や朝鮮の史書でも朝鮮半島への倭国の進出を示す記事が存在すること、『広開土王碑』に倭が新羅や百済を臣民としたと記されていること、またいくつもの、日本列島独特の墓制である前方後円墳が朝鮮半島で発見され始めたこと、そして新羅・百済・伽耶の勢力圏内で日本産のヒスイ製勾玉が大量に出土（高句麗の旧領では稀）したこと等の史実より、倭国と深い関連を持つ何らかの集団（倭国から派遣された官吏や軍人、倭国に臣従した在地豪族など）が伽耶地域において一定の軍事的影響力および経済的利権を有していたことはほぼ確実視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is almost presumed from historical facts that some sort of group deeply related to Wakoku (such as government officials and military men dispatched by Wakoku or local powerful clans who served Wakoku) possessed certain military clout and economic interest in Gaya region; Wakoku&apos;s advance to the Korean Peninsula is recorded in history books of China and Korea as well as &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan); &quot;Gwanggaeto Stele&quot; tells that Wakoku subjugated Silla and Baekje as shinmin (subject); large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds, the institution of tombing peculiar to the Japanese archipelago, are starting to be discovered in Korean Peninsula; a massive amount of Japanese jade magadama (comma-shaped beads) have been excavated in the influence area of Silla, Baekje and Gaya (rare in the former territory of Goguryeo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is almost presumed from historical facts that some sort of group deeply related to Wakoku (such as government officials and military men dispatched by Wakoku or local powerful clans who served Wakoku) possessed certain military clout and economic interest in Gaya region (another name of Mimana); Wakoku&apos;s advance to the Korean Peninsula is recorded in history books of China and Korea as well as &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan); &quot;Gwanggaeto Stele&quot; tells that Wakoku subjugated Silla and Baekje; large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds, which are peculiar to the Japanese archipelago, are starting to be discovered in the Korean Peninsula; a massive amount of Japanese jade magadama (comma-shaped beads) have been excavated in the influence area of Silla, Baekje and Gaya (rare in the former territory of Goguryeo).</e>
<cmt>最初のセミコロンの前のスペースを削除しました。&quot;as shinmin (subject)&quot;は不要だと思います。&quot;the institution of tombing&quot;→tombは名詞なので、-ingの形をとりません。&quot;Gaya region&quot;→「伽耶」は初出で英語圏の人には馴染みがないと思うので、「任那の別名」であることを説明した方が分かりやすいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is almost presumed from historical facts that some sort of group deeply related to Wakoku (such as government officials and military men dispatched by Wakoku or local powerful clans who served Wakoku) possessed certain military clout and economic interest in Gaya region (another name of Mimana); Wakoku&apos;s advance to the Korean Peninsula is recorded in history books of China and Korea as well as &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan); &quot;Gwanggaeto Stele&quot; tells that Wakoku subjugated Silla and Baekje; large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds, which are peculiar to the Japanese archipelago, are starting to be discovered in the Korean Peninsula; a massive amount of Japanese jade magadama (comma-shaped beads) have been excavated in the influence area of Silla, Baekje and Gaya (rare in the former territory of Goguryeo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、倭国が当該地域に対して民政統治を行ったかどうかについては一定の見解がでていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But there is not yet an unified view whether Wakoku controlled the area by the civilian rule</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But there is not yet an unified view whether Wakoku controlled the area by civilian rule.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。&quot;the&quot;を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But there is not yet an unified view whether Wakoku controlled the area by civilian rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>なお、任那日本府の称は、国号の表記が日本と定まった後世に呼称されるようになったものであり、任那日本府が存在したとされる時代にあっては、倭府と称したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name, Japanese Mimana Government, came into use in later years after the country was officially named Japan and it was called Wafu (Japanese government) when the Japanese Mimana Government actually existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Mimana Nihon-fu came into use in later years after the country was officially named Nihon (Japan), but when it was actually existed, it was called Wafu (Wakoku government).</e>
<cmt>「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。「日本」→呼称の説明なので、&quot;Nihon&quot;とした方が良いと思います。同じく、「倭府」の説明も&quot;Wakoku government&quot;の方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Mimana Nihon-fu came into use in later years after the country was officially named Nihon (Japan), but when it was actually existed, it was called Wafu (Wakoku government).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>諸学説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various Theories</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>第二次大戦以前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the World War II</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the World War II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the World War II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>第二次世界大戦以前の日本における伽耶地方の研究については、当時の併合政策を正当化しようとする姿勢から、『日本書紀』に現れる任那日本府を倭国（大和政権）が朝鮮半島南部を支配するために設置した出先機関であるとする前提に立つものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the World War II, the study of Goya region in Japan stood on the premise that the Japanese Mimana Government, which appears in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, was the regional office established by Wakoku (Yamato Administration) to govern the southern area of Korean Peninsula, which would justify Japan&apos;s annexation policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the World War II, the study of Goya region in Japan stood on the premise that Mimana Nihon-fu, which appears in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, was the regional office established by Wakoku (Yamato Administration) to govern the southern area of the Korean Peninsula, which would justify Japan&apos;s annexation policy.</e>
<cmt>「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the World War II, the study of Goya region in Japan stood on the premise that Mimana Nihon-fu, which appears in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, was the regional office established by Wakoku (Yamato Administration) to govern the southern area of the Korean Peninsula, which would justify Japan&apos;s annexation policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>考古学的な研究についても、研究そのものに朝鮮人の参画が認められていなかったこともあり、まず任那日本府の解釈に沿って日本府を合理的に説明しようとする姿勢から抜け切ることができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese archaeological study also failed in the first place to completely get rid of the inclination to rationalize the existence of the Nihon-fu (Japanese government in Mimana) in accordance with the interpretation by the Japanese Mimana Government, partly because Koreans were prohibited from participating in the study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese archaeological study also failed in the first place to completely get rid of the inclination to rationalize the existence of Mimana Nihon-fu in accordance with such interpretaion, partly because Koreans were prohibited from participating in the study.</e>
<cmt>「上記のような任那日本府の解釈に沿って、任那日本府を説明しようとする姿勢」の意味だと思います。「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese archaeological study also failed in the first place to completely get rid of the inclination to rationalize the existence of Mimana Nihon-fu in accordance with such interpretaion, partly because Koreans were prohibited from participating in the study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのような解釈は明治期の那珂通世、菅政友らの研究から見られ、津田左右吉を経て戦後に末松保和『任那興亡史』において大成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such interpretation can be seen in the studies by Michiyo NAKA and Masatomo KAN in Meiji period, followed by Sokichi TSUDA and it was perfected in &quot;History of the Rise and Fall of Mimana&quot; by Yasukazu SUEMATSU after the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such interpretation can be seen in the studies by Michiyo NAKA and Masatomo KAN in the Meiji period, followed by Sokichi TSUDA and it was perfected in &quot;History of the Rise and Fall of Mimana&quot; by Yasukazu SUEMATSU after the war.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Meiji peiod&quot;→&quot;the Meiji period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such interpretation can be seen in the studies by Michiyo NAKA and Masatomo KAN in the Meiji period, followed by Sokichi TSUDA and it was perfected in &quot;History of the Rise and Fall of Mimana&quot; by Yasukazu SUEMATSU after the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>この時代の認識では、任那日本府の淵源を『日本書紀』神功紀にある「屯倉」に求め、任那日本府は伽耶地方＝任那地方を政治的軍事的に支配したとするものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period sought the origin of the Japanese Mimana Government in &apos;miyake&apos; (Imperial-controlled territory) which is recorded in the Jingu section of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and believed that the Japanese Mimana Government politically and militarily ruled the Gaya region = Mimana region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scholars of this period sought the origin of Mimana Nihon-fu in &apos;miyake&apos; (Imperial-controlled territory) which is recorded in the Jingu section of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and believed that Mimana Nihon-fu politically and militarily ruled the Gaya region, which was also called Mimana region.</e>
<cmt>主語を&quot;the scholars of this period&quot;に修正しました。「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。「=」を文章に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scholars of this period sought the origin of Mimana Nihon-fu in &apos;miyake&apos; (Imperial-controlled territory) which is recorded in the Jingu section of &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; and believed that Mimana Nihon-fu politically and militarily ruled the Gaya region, which was also called Mimana region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そのため三韓征伐のモデルとなった朝鮮半島への出兵を4世紀半ば（神功皇后49年（249年）を干支2巡繰り上げたものと見て369年と推定する）とし、以降、当地域は倭王の直轄地であったとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to make historical ends meet, the dispatch of troops to the Korean Peninsula, which served as the model of sankan-seibatsu (the conquest of three countries in old Korea), was said to have taken place in the mid fourth century (presumably to be 369 by advancing 249 by two rounds of the Oriental zodiac [120 years]) and this area was stated as the directly controlled land of the king of Wa (Japan) ever since.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to make historical ends meet, the dispatch of troops to the Korean Peninsula, which led to the legend of sankan-seibatsu (the conquest of three countries in old Korea), was said to have taken place in the mid fourth century (presumably in 369, calculated by adding two rounds of the Oriental zodiac [120 years] to the year of 249 as stated in Nihonshoki) and this area was considered as the directly controlled land of the king of Wa (Japan) ever since.</e>
<cmt>「三韓征伐のモデルとなった」→「三韓征伐伝説のモデルになった」「神功皇后49年（249年）」以下の文→「日本書紀に記載されている249年という年号に干支2巡を足して369年と推定する」として修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to make historical ends meet, the dispatch of troops to the Korean Peninsula, which led to the legend of sankan-seibatsu (the conquest of three countries in old Korea), was said to have taken place in the mid fourth century (presumably in 369, calculated by adding two rounds of the Oriental zodiac [120 years] to the year of 249 as stated in Nihonshoki) and this area was considered as the directly controlled land of the king of Wa (Japan) ever since.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、任那日本府は当初は臨時の軍事基地に過ぎなかったが、やがて常設の機関となったとみられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Japanese Mimana Government was thought to have been created as a mere temporary military base and eventually promoted to a permanent institution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Mimana Nihon-fu was thought to have been created as a mere temporary military base and eventually promoted to a permanent institution.</e>
<cmt>「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Mimana Nihon-fu was thought to have been created as a mere temporary military base and eventually promoted to a permanent institution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、高句麗や新羅が百済北部を侵すようになると、百済は執事の功績を賞賛し、大和に援軍を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Goguryeo began to invade Silla and the northern part of Baekje, so Baekje praised the great achievement of steward in order to ask Yamato for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Goguryeo began to invade Silla and the northern part of Baekje, so Baekje praised the great achievement of the official of Mimana Nihon-fu in order to ask Yamato for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>「執事」→ここでは「任那の執事（つかさ）」のこと。（http://www.loops.jp/~asukaclub/syoki/syoki104.html）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Goguryeo began to invade Silla and the northern part of Baekje, so Baekje praised the great achievement of the official of Mimana Nihon-fu in order to ask Yamato for reinforcement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>554年、百済が新羅に敗れて聖明王が殺され、562年には任那全土が新羅に奪われるに至り、日本府は滅亡したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 554, Baekje lost to Goguryeo and Shomyoo was killed and the whole Mimana was seized by Silla which meant the fall of Nihon-fu in 562.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 554, Baekje lost to Goguryeo and King Seong was killed and the whole Mimana was seized by Silla, which meant the fall of Mimana Nihon-fu in 562.</e>
<cmt>聖明王→King Seong「日本府」は「任那日本府」のこと。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 554, Baekje lost to Goguryeo and King Seong was killed and the whole Mimana was seized by Silla, which meant the fall of Mimana Nihon-fu in 562.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>戦後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>前述のような学説は皇国史観の強い影響下に成ったものとする考えから、その反動として戦後の研究では、日本の出先機関が存在したことを否定しようとする姿勢が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the World War II, the studies strongly attempted to deny the existence of a regional office of Japan in the Korean Peninsula on the rebound because the above-mentioned theory was thought to have been born under the strong influence of Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the World War II, the studies strongly attempted to deny the existence of a regional office of Japan in the Korean Peninsula on the rebound because the above-mentioned theory was thought to have been born under the strong influence of Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the World War II, the studies strongly attempted to deny the existence of a regional office of Japan in the Korean Peninsula on the rebound because the above-mentioned theory was thought to have been born under the strong influence of Kokoku Shikan (emperor-centered historiography which is based on state Shinto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>更に1960年代頃から朝鮮半島で広がった民族主義の影響もあり、特に朝鮮半島の研究者により、記紀に記されているヤマト朝廷の直接的な任那支配は誇張されたものだとの主張がなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, due to the influence of nationalism which spread in the Korean Peninsula from the 1960s, researchers, especially those in the Korean Peninsula, insisted that the records in Kiki (Kojiki [A Record of Ancient Matter] and Nihonshoki), which tell that Yamato Dynasty directly controlled the Mimana, were exaggerated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, due to the influence of nationalism which spread in the Korean Peninsula from the 1960s, researchers, especially those in the Korean Peninsula, insisted that the records in Kiki (Kojiki [A Record of Ancient Matter] and Nihonshoki), which say that Yamato Dynasty directly controlled the Mimana, were exaggerated.</e>
<cmt>&quot;tell&quot;は「伝える」意味では人を目的語にとります。ここは&quot;say&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, due to the influence of nationalism which spread in the Korean Peninsula from the 1960s, researchers, especially those in the Korean Peninsula, insisted that the records in Kiki (Kojiki [A Record of Ancient Matter] and Nihonshoki), which say that Yamato Dynasty directly controlled the Mimana, were exaggerated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>1970年代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the 1970s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the 1970s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the 1970s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>1970年代以降には洛東江流域の旧伽耶地域の発掘調査が飛躍的に進み、文献史料の少ない伽耶史を研究するための材料が豊富になってくるとともに、政治的欲求に基づく解釈から解放された議論が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the 1970s, the excavation and research of the former Gaya region in Rakuto river basin made a remarkable progress and discussions free from politically-biased interpretations came to prosper at the same time as the materials for the study of Gaya history enriched, which is poor in document historical materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the 1970s, the excavation and research of the former Gaya region in the Nakdong River basin made a remarkable progress, and discussions free from politically-biased interpretations came to prosper at the same time as more materials were discovered for the study of Gaya history, which was little documented.</e>
<cmt>洛東江→the Nakdong River後半部分を分かりやすく修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the 1970s, the excavation and research of the former Gaya region in the Nakdong River basin made a remarkable progress, and discussions free from politically-biased interpretations came to prosper at the same time as more materials were discovered for the study of Gaya history, which was little documented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この時期の日本での代表的論考は井上秀雄『任那日本府と倭』である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The argument and consideration of Japan at the time was led by &quot;Mimana Nihon-fu to Wa&quot; (Japanese Mimana Government and Japan) by Hideo INOUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The argument and consideration in Japan at the time were led by &quot;Mimana Nihon-fu to Wa&quot; (Japanese Mimana Government and Japan) by Hideo INOUE.</e>
<cmt>&quot;of Japan&quot;→&quot;in Japan&quot;に修正しました。&quot;was&quot;→&quot;were&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The argument and consideration in Japan at the time were led by &quot;Mimana Nihon-fu to Wa&quot; (Japanese Mimana Government and Japan) by Hideo INOUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="18">
<j>井上によると、任那日本府とは『日本書紀』が引用する『百済本紀』において見られる呼称であり、6世紀末の百済が高句麗・新羅に対抗するために倭国（ヤマト王権）を懐柔しようとして、『魏志』（『三国志 (歴史書)』）韓伝において朝鮮半島南部の諸国を表していた「倭」と、日本列島の倭人の政権とを結びつけて、ヤマト王権の勢力が早くから朝鮮半島南部に及んでいたかのような印象を与えるに過ぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to INOUE, the name of the Japanese Mimana Government can be found in &quot;History of Baekje&quot; quoted in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; which unintendedly gives the impression that the power of Yamato sovereignty extended to the southern area of Korean Peninsula early on, because &apos;Wa&apos;, the name used by Baekje to point the various districts in the southern area of Korean Peninsula mentioned in the account of Korea in &quot;Records of Wei&quot; (&quot;Sangokushi&quot; [Three Kingdom Saga]) to win the favor of Wakoku (Yamato sovereignty) to its side to compete with Goguryeo and Silla would appeal to the government of Wajin (Japanese people) in the Japanese archipelago.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Inoue, the name of Mimana Nihon-fu can be found in &quot;History of Baekje,&quot; which is quoted in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; and although the name of &apos;Wa&apos; (倭) originally meant the various districts in the southern area of the Korean Peninsula as mentioned in the account of Korea in &quot;Records of Wei&quot; (&quot;Sangokushi&quot; [Three Kingdoms Saga]), Baekje in the end of sixth century used the word as if it was related to the government of wajin (倭人, people of Wakoku) in the Japanese archipelago, trying to win their favor and support in order to compete with Goguryeo and Silla, which unintendedly gives the impression that the power of Yamato sovereignty extended to the southern area of the Korean Peninsula early on.</e>
<cmt>&quot;INOUE&quot;→頭文字のみ大文字に修正。「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正。「6世紀末の」→訳抜けです。「倭」と「倭人」を結びつけた、ということが分かりやすいように漢字を挿入しました。他、文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Inoue, the name of Mimana Nihon-fu can be found in &quot;History of Baekje,&quot; which is quoted in &quot;Nihonshoki,&quot; and although the name of &apos;Wa&apos; (倭) originally meant the various districts in the southern area of the Korean Peninsula as mentioned in the account of Korea in &quot;Records of Wei&quot; (&quot;Sangokushi&quot; [Three Kingdoms Saga]), Baekje in the end of sixth century used the word as if it was related to the government of wajin (倭人, people of Wakoku) in the Japanese archipelago, trying to win their favor and support in order to compete with Goguryeo and Silla, which unintendedly gives the impression that the power of Yamato sovereignty extended to the southern area of the Korean Peninsula early on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、実際の『百済本紀』の記述では、任那日本府とヤマト王権とは直接的には何の関係も持たないことが読み取れるという（→井上2004 pp.106-107.）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And he also says that it can be read from the actual description in &quot;History of Baekje&quot; that the Japanese Mimana Government had nothing to do with the Yamato sovereignty (=&gt; Inoue 2004 pp.106-107.).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And he also says that it can be read from the actual description in &quot;History of Baekje&quot; that Mimana Nihon-fu had nothing to do with the Yamato sovereignty (=&gt; Inoue 2004 pp.106-107.).</e>
<cmt>「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And he also says that it can be read from the actual description in &quot;History of Baekje&quot; that Mimana Nihon-fu had nothing to do with the Yamato sovereignty (=&gt; Inoue 2004 pp.106-107.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>つまり倭とは伽耶の別名とするものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is to say that Wa is another name of Gaya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is to say that Wa is another name of Gaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is to say that Wa is another name of Gaya.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>この説は、単なる伽耶地方の首長連合を後世に日本府と称したとするものであり架空説といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory is called fiction theory, which claims that a mere combination of chiefs in the Gaya Province was named Japanese Mimana Government by the later generations.</e>
<cmt>架空説の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory is called fiction theory, which claims that a mere combination of chiefs in the Gaya Province was named Mimana Nihon-fu by the later generations.</e>
<cmt>「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory is called fiction theory, which claims that a mere combination of chiefs in the Gaya Province was named Mimana Nihon-fu by the later generations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="22">
<j>これに対して吉田晶は、日本府の実体を半島の先進的な文物を入手するため設置された会議で、倭から派遣された卿、任那数ヶ国の君主を意味する旱岐層、大伽耶の大首長、安羅、多羅の次旱岐など現地の王や豪族、官人層により構成されたとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, YOSHIDA claimed that the true status of Nihon-fu was a committee established to gain access to the advanced culture and institutions of the Peninsula and was consisted of Kyo (lords) dispatched from Wa, Han gie, the monarch of the countries of Mimana, paramount chiefs of Dae Gaya, sub Han gie of Alla and Tara and other kings, local ruling families and government officials of Mimana.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Akira YOSHIDA claimed that the true status of Mimana Nihon-fu was a committee established to gain access to the advanced culture of the Peninsula and consisted of Kyo (lords) dispatched from Wa, local kings, powerful families and government officials, including Han gie who was the monarch of the countries of Mimana, paramount chiefs of Dae Gaya, sub Han gie of Alla and Tara.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Akira&quot;を挿入。「日本府」→任那日本府のこと。&quot;and institutions&quot;は不要なので削除。「旱岐」→「かんき」と読むようですが、訳文の&quot;Han gie&quot;の出典は不明です。訳はそのままにしてあります。「現地の王」以下は「旱岐層、大首長・・・」を指すと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Akira YOSHIDA claimed that the true status of Mimana Nihon-fu was a committee established to gain access to the advanced culture of the Peninsula and consisted of Kyo (lords) dispatched from Wa, local kings, powerful families and government officials, including Han gie who was the monarch of the countries of Mimana, paramount chiefs of Dae Gaya, sub Han gie of Alla and Tara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>なお、5世紀の倭王武が倭王と新羅・任那・加羅をはじめとする六ヶ国諸軍事の封号官職爵位を得ており、中華王朝から本拠のある日本列島の外部では君主としてではなく武官の地位のみ認められていたことから、日本府の役割を将軍府即ち軍事機関と捉えた坂元義種、山尾幸久等の説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory proposed by Yoshitane SAKAMOTO and Yukihisa YAMAO and others which treated the Japanese Mimana Government as Shogunfu (local government of shogun), namely military arm, because Waobu (the last king of ancient Japan) of fifth century was given a military rank, government post and title from six countries including king of Wa, Silla, Mimana and Kara which meant that he was not recognized as a monarch but as a mere militant outside the Japanese archipelago where he headquartered.</e>
<cmt>封号の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory proposed by Yoshitane SAKAMOTO, Yukihisa YAMAO and others, which treated Nihon Mimana-fu as a military institution, because King Bu of Wakoku in the fifth century was awarded by the Chinese dynasty the title of King of Wa, as well as a military rank and position for six countries including Silla, Mimana and Kara, which meant that he was not recognized as a monarch but as a mere military official outside his home, the Japanese archipelago.</e>
<cmt>「任那日本府」→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。「将軍府」→まだ5世紀なので、&quot;shogun&quot;という語は征夷大将軍を連想させるので使わない方が良いと思います。「倭王武」→&quot;King Bu of Wakoku&quot;に修正。武は、「倭の王」と、「6カ国の軍事の官職爵位」を中華王朝から認められていた。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory proposed by Yoshitane SAKAMOTO, Yukihisa YAMAO and others, which treated Nihon Mimana-fu as a military institution, because King Bu of Wakoku in the fifth century was awarded by the Chinese dynasty the title of King of Wa, as well as a military rank and position for six countries including Silla, Mimana and Kara, which meant that he was not recognized as a monarch but as a mere military official outside his home, the Japanese archipelago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>他に70年代から80年代の主な説に、倭国からの単なる使者とした説（請田正幸）、伽耶地方の首長連合による対倭国外交機関とする説（奥田尚）、百済による伽耶地方統治のための機関で倭系百済官人・倭系傭兵がいたとする説（金鉉球）などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other major theories in 1970s and 80s regarded Mimana as just an envoy from Wakoku (Japan) (Masayuki UKEDA), or as a diplomatic institution for Wakoku established by the combination of chiefs of Gaya region (Hisashi OKUDA), or as a governing institution of Gaya region set up by Baekje which employed Japanese Baekje officials and Japanese troops (Kim Hyun-koo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other major theories in the 1970s and 80s regarded Mimana Nihon-fu as just an envoy from Wakoku (Masayuki UKEDA), or as a diplomatic institution for Wakoku established by the combination of chiefs of Gaya region (Hisashi OKUDA), or as a governing institution for Gaya region set up by Baekje, which employed Japanese officials and troops there (Kim Hyun-koo).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Mimana&quot;→&quot;Mimana Nihon-fu&quot;に修正しました。&quot;Wakoku&quot;は既出なので説明不要。&quot;Japanese Baekje officials&quot;は分かりにくいので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other major theories in the 1970s and 80s regarded Mimana Nihon-fu as just an envoy from Wakoku (Masayuki UKEDA), or as a diplomatic institution for Wakoku established by the combination of chiefs of Gaya region (Hisashi OKUDA), or as a governing institution for Gaya region set up by Baekje, which employed Japanese officials and troops there (Kim Hyun-koo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>1990年代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since 1990s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the 1990s</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;を挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the 1990s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>1990年代になると伽耶研究の対象が従来の金官伽耶・任那加羅（いずれも金海地区）の倭との関係だけではなく、井上説を支持する田中俊明 (朝鮮史)の提唱になる大伽耶連盟の概念により、高霊地域の大伽耶を中心とする伽耶そのものの歴史研究に移行していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1990s, the study of Gaya targeted not only the relationship between Wa and Geumgwan Gaya/Mimana Gaya (both in Gimhae District) as in the past, but also the history of Gaya itself which centered Dae Gaya in Goryeong region, inspired by the concept of Dae Gaya confederacy proposed by Toshiaki TANAKA (Korean history) who supported INOUE&apos;s theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the 1990s, the study of Gaya targeted not only the relationship between Wa and Geumgwan Gaya or Mimana Gaya (in Gimhae District) as in the past, but also the history of Gaya itself, which centered Dae Gaya in Goryeong region, inspired by the concept of Dae Gaya confederacy proposed by Toshiaki TANAKA (Korean history) who supported Inoue&apos;s theory.</e>
<cmt>金官伽耶は任那加羅の別名のようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the 1990s, the study of Gaya targeted not only the relationship between Wa and Geumgwan Gaya or Mimana Gaya (in Gimhae District) as in the past, but also the history of Gaya itself, which centered Dae Gaya in Goryeong region, inspired by the concept of Dae Gaya confederacy proposed by Toshiaki TANAKA (Korean history) who supported Inoue&apos;s theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、1990年代後半からは主に考古学的側面から、卓淳（昌原）・安羅（咸安）などの諸地域の研究が推進される一方で、1983年に慶尚南道の松鶴洞一号墳（墳丘長66メートル）が前方後円墳であるとして紹介されて以来相次いだ朝鮮半島南西部での前方後円墳の発見これまでのところ全羅南道に11基、全羅北道に2基の前方後円墳が確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And, from the late 1990s, studies of 卓淳 (Changwon) and Alla (Haman) and other regions mainly from the archeological aspect were promoted and since the Songhakdong No. 1 tomb in Gyeongsang-namdo was announced as a large keyhole-shaped tomb mound in 1983, the same type of tombs were unearthed one after another in the southwest part of Korean Peninsula, totaling eleven in South Jeolla Province and two in North Jeolla Province so far.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And, from the late 1990s, studies of Tokujun (卓淳, in Changwon), Alla (in Haman) and other regions were promoted mainly from the archeological aspect and since the Songhakdong No. 1 tomb in Gyeongsangnam-do (66 meters in length) was announced as a large keyhole-shaped tomb mound in 1983, the same type of tombs have been unearthed one after another in the southwest part of the Korean Peninsula, totaling eleven in South Jeolla Province and two in North Jeolla Province so far.</e>
<cmt>「卓淳」は安羅と同じく伽耶諸国のひとつで、日本語では「とくじゅん」と読みます。現地語読みは不明です。昌原、咸安は地名。「慶尚南道」の区切りは&quot;Gyeongsangnam-do&quot;です。（http://english.gntour.com/）（墳丘長66メートル）→訳抜けです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And, from the late 1990s, studies of Tokujun (卓淳, in Changwon), Alla (in Haman) and other regions were promoted mainly from the archeological aspect and since the Songhakdong No. 1 tomb in Gyeongsangnam-do (66 meters in length) was announced as a large keyhole-shaped tomb mound in 1983, the same type of tombs have been unearthed one after another in the southwest part of the Korean Peninsula, totaling eleven in South Jeolla Province and two in North Jeolla Province so far.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また朝鮮半島の前方後円墳はいずれも5世紀後半から6世紀中葉という極めて限られた時期に成立したもので、百済が南遷する前は伽耶の勢力圏の最西部であった地域のみに存在し、円筒埴輪や南島産貝製品、内部をベンガラで塗った石室といった倭系遺物を伴うことが知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All the large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds found in the Korean Peninsula were built in a very limited period of time between late fifth century and mid sixth century, and especially those which were built before Baekje&apos;s shift to the south can be found only in the westernmost part of Gaya&apos;s sphere of influence and accompany Japanese relics, such as ento haniwa (cylindrical haniwa), shell objects made in south islands, and an rock chamber painted with bengara (iron oxide red pigment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All the large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds found in the Korean Peninsula were built in a very limited period of time between the late fifth century and mid sixth century, only in the area that used to be the westernmost part of Gaya&apos;s sphere of influence before Baekje moved to the south, and they are known for containing Japanese relics, such as ento haniwa (cylindrical haniwa), shell products made in south islands, and an rock chamber painted with bengara (iron oxide red pigment).</e>
<cmt>&quot;fifth century&quot;→&quot;the&quot;を挿入。訳文では、「前方後円墳のうち、特に百済が南遷する前に成立したものは」となりますが、ここでは「前方後円墳はいずれも、百済が南遷する前は」の意味です。&quot;shell object&quot;→&quot;shell products&quot;に修正。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All the large keyhole-shaped tomb mounds found in the Korean Peninsula were built in a very limited period of time between the late fifth century and mid sixth century, only in the area that used to be the westernmost part of Gaya&apos;s sphere of influence before Baekje moved to the south, and they are known for containing Japanese relics, such as ento haniwa (cylindrical haniwa), shell products made in south islands, and an rock chamber painted with bengara (iron oxide red pigment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>韓国報道などや新羅・百済・任那の勢力圏内で大量に出土（高句麗の旧領では稀）しているヒスイ製勾玉の原産地が糸魚川周辺に比定されている事などを踏まえ、一部地域への倭人の集住を認める論考が相次いで提出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A series of arguments and considerations admitting the collective habitation of Wajin (Japanese people) in certain areas within the spheres of influence of Silla, Baekje and Mimana appeared in light of the Korean media reports and the fact that the massive jade magadama (comma-shaped bead) found in the area (rare in the former territory of Goguryeo) have been identified as the products of the neighboring area of Itoi-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A series of arguments and considerations admitting the collective habitation of Wajin in certain areas within the spheres of influence of Silla, Baekje and Mimana appeared in light of the Korean media reports and the fact that the massive jade magadama found in the area (rare in the former territory of Goguryeo) had been identified as the products of the neighboring area of Itoi-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>「倭人」「勾玉」は既出なので説明不要。&quot;have been identified&quot;→&quot;had been identified&quot;に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A series of arguments and considerations admitting the collective habitation of Wajin in certain areas within the spheres of influence of Silla, Baekje and Mimana appeared in light of the Korean media reports and the fact that the massive jade magadama found in the area (rare in the former territory of Goguryeo) had been identified as the products of the neighboring area of Itoi-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>吉田孝によると、「任那」とは、高句麗・新羅に対抗するために百済・倭国と結んだ任那加羅（金官加羅）を盟主とする小国連合であり、いわゆる地名である伽耶地域とは必ずしも一致しない政治上の概念であり、任那が倭国の軍事力を勢力拡大に利用するために倭国に設置させた軍事を主とする外交機関を後世「任那日本府」と呼んだと主張し、百済に割譲した四県は倭人が移住した地域であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takashi YOSHIDA claims that &apos;Mimana&apos; was a combination of small countries led by Mimana Gaya (Geumgwan Gaya) which cooperated with Baekje and Wa to counter Goguryeo and Silla, a political concept which does not necessarily corresponds to Gaya region, and he insists that Mimana was a name given by the later generation to a diplomatic institution, mainly in charge of military affairs, set up by Wakoku under pressure from Baekje who intended to exploit the military power of Wakoku to expand its force, and also that the four prefectures ceded to Baekje were where Wajin emigrated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takashi YOSHIDA claims that &apos;Mimana&apos; was a combination of small countries led by Mimana Gaya (Geumgwan Gaya) which cooperated with Baekje and Wa to counter Goguryeo and Silla, and thus a political concept which does not necessarily corresponds to Gaya region, and Mimana, trying to use Wakoku&apos;s military power to expand its territory, led Wakoku into establishing a diplomatic institution mainly in charge of military affairs, which was later called &apos;Mimana Nihon-fu&apos;; the four prefectures of Mimana that Wakoku ceded to Baekje were the area where Wajin had immigrated.</e>
<cmt>倭国に外交機関を設置させたのは百済ではなく、任那。また、百済に四県を割譲したのは倭国（継体天皇のとき）。倭国の領土ではなかったが、倭人が移住した地域であった、という意味だと思います。（http://info.pref.fukui.jp/keitaidaio/achievement/index.html）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takashi YOSHIDA claims that &apos;Mimana&apos; was a combination of small countries led by Mimana Gaya (Geumgwan Gaya) which cooperated with Baekje and Wa to counter Goguryeo and Silla, and thus a political concept which does not necessarily corresponds to Gaya region, and Mimana, trying to use Wakoku&apos;s military power to expand its territory, led Wakoku into establishing a diplomatic institution mainly in charge of military affairs, which was later called &apos;Mimana Nihon-fu&apos;; the four prefectures of Mimana that Wakoku ceded to Baekje were the area where Wajin had immigrated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、532年の任那加羅（金官加羅）滅亡後は安羅に軍事機関を移したが、562年の大加羅の滅亡で拠点を失ったとしている（→吉田1997 pp.74-78.）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to YOSHIDA, the military institution was transferred to Alla after the fall of Mimana Gaya in 532 but it lost its base when Dae Gaya collapsed in 562 (=&gt;YOSHIDA 1997 pp.74-78.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Yoshida, the military institution was transferred to Alla after the fall of Mimana Gaya (Geumgwan Gaya) in 532, but it lost its base when Dae Gaya collapsed in 562 (=&gt;Yoshida 1997 pp.74-78.).</e>
<cmt>&quot;Yoshida&quot;を頭文字のみ大文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Yoshida, the military institution was transferred to Alla after the fall of Mimana Gaya (Geumgwan Gaya) in 532, but it lost its base when Dae Gaya collapsed in 562 (=&gt;Yoshida 1997 pp.74-78.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>吉田は一時期否定された4世紀の日本府について金官加羅の主導性を認めつつ倭国の軍事的外交機関として認めており、他の研究者と一線を画している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHIDA acknowledges the Nihon-fu of the fourth century as a military diplomatic institution as well as the leadership of Geumgwan Gaya in it, the opinion which was once denied, drawing a sharp contrast with other researchers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshida acknowledges that Mimana Nihon-fu in the fourth century was a military diplomatic institution though the leadership was held by Geumgwan Gaya, and by admitting this theory once denied, he draws a sharp contrast with other researchers.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Yoshida&quot;を頭文字のみ大文字に修正。日本府が軍事機関である、というのが一時期否定されていた説。加羅の主導性については否定されていなかった。分かりやすいように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshida acknowledges that Mimana Nihon-fu in the fourth century was a military diplomatic institution though the leadership was held by Geumgwan Gaya, and by admitting this theory once denied, he draws a sharp contrast with other researchers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="32">
<j>鬼頭清明は『加耶はなぜほろんだか』の中で、安羅の豪族が倭府と称し、伽耶地方や百済の政治決定に重要な関与をしていたことは認めたうえで、貢調徴取の機関でも直接支配の機関でもないとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyoaki KITO says in &quot;Gaya wa naze horonda ka&quot; (Why Gaya Collapsed) that a ruling family in Alla called itself Wafu and engaged itself considerably in the political decision making of Gaya region and Baekje, and denies its role as an institution to collect contributions or to implement an immediate dominance.</e>
<cmt>『加耶はなぜほろんだか』定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyoaki KITO says in &quot;Kaya wa naze horonda ka&quot; (Why Gaya Collapsed) that a ruling family of Alla called itself Wafu and engaged itself considerably in the political decision making of Gaya region and Baekje, but denies its role as an institution to collect contributions or to directly rule the area.</e>
<cmt>『加耶はなぜほろんだか』はローマ字表記のタイトルなので、&quot;Kaya&quot;に修正。他、文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyoaki KITO says in &quot;Kaya wa naze horonda ka&quot; (Why Gaya Collapsed) that a ruling family of Alla called itself Wafu and engaged itself considerably in the political decision making of Gaya region and Baekje, but denies its role as an institution to collect contributions or to directly rule the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>森公章によると、『日本書紀』を丁寧に読む限り言える点として、次のようなことが言えるとしている（森1998 pp.66-68.参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimiaki MORI points out that the followings can be said as far as carefully reading &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) (refer to MORI 1998 pp.66-68.).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimiyuki MORI points out that the followings can be said as far as carefully reading &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (refer to Mori 1998 pp.66-68.).</e>
<cmt>森公章は「きみゆき」です。（http://bunbun.toyo.ac.jp/shigaku/staff/mori.html）「日本書紀」は既出なので説明不要。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimiyuki MORI points out that the followings can be said as far as carefully reading &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (refer to Mori 1998 pp.66-68.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>確実な史料は、6世紀以降にしか登場しないこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reliable historical materials were created not until the sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">No reliable historical materials were created until the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>文法上の修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">No reliable historical materials were created until the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="35">
<j>所在地は安羅であること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was located in Alla.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was located in Alla.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was located in Alla.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="36">
<j>正式名は在安羅諸倭臣であること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its formal name was 在安羅諸倭臣 (Japanese retainers in Alla).</e>
<cmt>在安羅諸倭臣の定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its formal name was Ara ni Haberu Moromoro no Yamato no Maetsukimi (Yamato retainers in Alla).</e>
<cmt>「在安羅諸倭臣」→「あらにはべるもろもろのやまとのまへつきみ」（http://aizax.fc2-rentalserver.com/repo5/051075.html）「前つ君（まえつきみ）」は天皇に仕える人。（http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn2/207122/m0u/%E5%A4%A7%E5%A4%AB/）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its formal name was Ara ni Haberu Moromoro no Yamato no Maetsukimi (Yamato retainers in Alla).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>倭中央豪族、吉備臣などの倭地方豪族、伽耶系により構成され、実務は伽耶系が担っていたこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It consisted of the local ruling families in central and rural areas of Wa, like Kibi no omi, and Gaya people who handled the actual management.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It consisted of the powerful families from the capital of Wa, the families from rural areas of Wa, including Kibi no omi, and Gaya people who handled the actual management.</e>
<cmt>吉備臣は地方豪族に含まれるものとして、修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It consisted of the powerful families from the capital of Wa, the families from rural areas of Wa, including Kibi no omi, and Gaya people who handled the actual management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>倭本国との繋がりに乏しいこと</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It only had a poor relationship with the mainland Wa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It only had a poor relationship with the mainland Wa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It only had a poor relationship with the mainland Wa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>伽耶諸国と対等の関係にあり、協同で外交交渉を進めていること</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It stood on an equal footing with Gaya countries and pursued diplomatic negotiations with them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It stood on an equal footing with Gaya countries and pursued diplomatic negotiations in corperation with them.</e>
<cmt>&quot;with them&quot;だと、伽耶と交渉する意味に取れますが、「伽耶と協同して（高句麗や新羅と）交渉した」意味だと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It stood on an equal footing with Gaya countries and pursued diplomatic negotiations in corperation with them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="40">
<j>以上のように近年の任那日本府に関する言説は、倭人等の軍事的影響力や経済的利権の有無にではなく、その時期と組織の実体に移ってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As above-mentioned, the center of the current Japanese Mimana Government discourse is shifting from the presence or absence of the military clout and economic interest of Wajin, to its period of existence and the actual status of the organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As above mentioned, the subject of recent discussion on Mimana Nihon-fu is shifting from the presence or absence of the military clout and economic interest of Wajin, to its period of existence and the actual status of the organization.</e>
<cmt>&quot;discourse&quot;より&quot;discussion&quot;を使用した方が良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As above mentioned, the subject of recent discussion on Mimana Nihon-fu is shifting from the presence or absence of the military clout and economic interest of Wajin, to its period of existence and the actual status of the organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また韓国の考古学者の中にも、民族主義の影響を強く受けた従来の自国の研究者の学説を厳しく批判し、この時期の韓半島と日本列島の交流が極めて密接なものであったことを指摘する者が現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some South Korean archaeologists now sharply criticize conventional theories by Korean researchers strongly affected by nationalism and they point out that the interaction between the Korean Peninsula and the Japanese archipelago at the time was extremely inseparable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some South Korean archaeologists now sharply criticize conventional theories by Korean researchers strongly affected by nationalism and they point out that the interaction between the Korean Peninsula and the Japanese archipelago at the time was extremely inseparable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some South Korean archaeologists now sharply criticize conventional theories by Korean researchers strongly affected by nationalism and they point out that the interaction between the Korean Peninsula and the Japanese archipelago at the time was extremely inseparable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), KMT(id:1772), Elknz(id:265955), BlackPonix(id:20108), 経済準学士(id:22656), Texas588(id:207231), Akubim(id:145631), Race(id:131322), Law soma(id:45202), Nallimbot(id:230812), Bellcricket(id:37640), Kamakura(id:472), Peachkiller(id:99202), Suginamin(id:120015), 敷島健一(id:270317), Dr jimmy(id:111486), Dondokken(id:246411), Afaz(id:64776), 海衛士(id:19229), Abc root(id:219803), Mark-zero(id:48822), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>