<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>公文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumon (a local shoen official below the gesu in rank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumon (official document; letter of appointment; local shoen [manors in medieval Japan] official)</e>
<cmt>「公文」補足として主な意味を併記しました。「荘園」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumon (official document)</e>
<cmt>用語をひとつに変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>公文（くもん）とは、本来は律令制における公文書の総称であり、転じてこうした文書の取り扱う官吏の事も指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumon was originally a general term of official documents in the ritsuryo system, and derived from it, it also meant the government official who dealt with such monjo (written material).</e>
<cmt>「文書」は一般的な「ぶんしょ＝documents」としてではなく、C列定訳に従い「monjo」と英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumon was originally a general term for official documents in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), and derived from it, it also meant the government official who dealt with such documents.</e>
<cmt>of→for としました。「律令制」を補足しました。「文書」は &quot;documents&quot; で差し支えないと思いますので変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumon was originally a general term for official documents in the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), and derived from it, it also meant the government official who dealt with such documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後世においては公家や寺院、荘園でも重要文書やそれを扱う担当者の事を指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later generations, also at kuge (a court noble), temples and shoen (manors in medieval Japan), it meant the important monjo and the person in charge of dealing with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the later generations, kuge (a court noble), temples and shoen also used the term for important documents and the person in charge of dealing with it.</e>
<cmt>公家に at は不自然なので、削除して文を調整しました。「荘園」既出のため、補足を削除しました。monjo→documents としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the later generations, kuge (a court noble), temples and shoen also used the term for important documents and the person in charge of dealing with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、文書である公文の保管所や担当者の勤務場所を「公文所（くもんじょ）」と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the archive of kumon meaning monjo and the workplace of the person in charge is called kumonjo (administration office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the archive of kumon as documents and the workplace of the person in charge were called &apos;kumonjo&apos; (administration office).</e>
<cmt>meaning→as としました。monjo→documents としました。is→were としました。 &apos; &apos; を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the archive of kumon as documents and the workplace of the person in charge were called &apos;kumonjo&apos; (administration office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>律令制及び行政文書における公文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumon in the ritsuryo system and the gyosei monjo (administrative written material).</e>
<cmt>「行政文書」の定訳が見つからなかった為、「gyosei monjo (administrative written material）と英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumon in the ritsuryo system and Kumon as the administrative documents</e>
<cmt>Kumon as を追加しました。「行政文書」 administrative documents としました。見出しのため、ピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumon in the ritsuryo system and Kumon as the administrative documents</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>律令法においては「職制律」の疏において“公文謂在官文書”と定義され、また「公式令（くしきりょう）」と呼ばれる令が制定されて公文書の様式や手続が定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo law, the items on Shikisei-ritsu (Office Penal Laws) defined kumon as kan monjo (official written material), and the law called Kushiki-ryo (law on state documentary forms in the Yoro Code) was enacted to determine the form and the procedure of the official documents.</e>
<cmt>「官文書」の定訳がなかった為、を「kan monjo (official written material)」と英訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo law, the items on &apos;Shikisei-ritsu&apos; (Office Penal Laws) defined &quot;kumon as official documents,&quot; and the law called Kushiki-ryo (law on state documentary forms in the Yoro Code) was enacted to determine the form and the procedure of the official documents.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos;, &quot; &quot; を追加しました。「官文書」 official documents としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo law, the items on &apos;Shikisei-ritsu&apos; (Office Penal Laws) defined &quot;kumon as official documents,&quot; and the law called Kushiki-ryo (law on state documentary forms in the Yoro Code) was enacted to determine the form and the procedure of the official documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>朝廷においては、特に毎年一定の時期に各地の国司から提出される大計帳・正税帳・調帳・朝集帳を四度公文（しどのくもん/よどのくもん）と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Imperial Court, dai-keicho (the grand yearly tax registers), shozeicho (balance sheets of tax rice), chocho (list of choyo 〔tribute and labor〕) and choshucho (report of affairs of state) yearly submitted by Kokushi (provincial governors) in various places during some period of year were particularly called shidonokumon, and audited the figures in order to be able to reveal Kokushi&apos;s dishonesty and respected as basic information on administration and financial affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Imperial Court, dai-keicho (the grand yearly tax registers), shozeicho (balance sheets of tax rice), chocho (list of choyo [tribute and labor]) and choshucho (report of affairs of state) submitted by Kokushi (provincial governors) in various places at fixed times of the year were particularly called shidonokumon.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処〔 〕→[] としました。yearly を削除しました。（後出の year と重複するため）during some period of year→at fixed times of the year としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Imperial Court, dai-keicho (the grand yearly tax registers), shozeicho (balance sheets of tax rice), chocho (list of choyo [tribute and labor]) and choshucho (report of affairs of state) submitted by Kokushi (provincial governors) in various places at fixed times of the year were particularly called shidonokumon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>この数字を監査する事で国司の不正に対する監視を行うとともに、行政・財政の基本資料としても重要視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Court audited the figures in shidonokumon in order to reveal Kokushi&apos;s dishonesty, and respected them as basic information on administration and financial affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処主語を追加し、補足として in shidonokumon を追加しました。them を追加、be able to を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Court audited the figures in shidonokumon in order to reveal Kokushi&apos;s dishonesty, and treated them as important basic information on administration and financial affairs.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、国衙においてはこれらの文書を作成するために公文所が設置され、文筆や計算に通じた人物を国司・史生と言った在庁官人に任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in kokuga (provincial goverment offices), kumonjo was set up in order to create these monjo, and the figures who had skill in writing or calculation were appointed as zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) such as kokushi and shisho (people who performed miscellaneous duties about documents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in kokuga (provincial government offices), kumonjo was set up in order to produce these documents, and the figures who had skill in writing or calculation were appointed as zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) such as kokushi and shisho (people who performed miscellaneous duties about documents).</e>
<cmt>government スペル修正しました。create→produce としました。monjo→documents としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in kokuga (provincial government offices), kumonjo was set up in order to produce these documents, and the figures who had skill in writing or calculation were appointed as zaichokanjin (the local officials in Heian and Kamakura periods) such as kokushi and shisho (people who performed miscellaneous duties about documents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これを「公文目」・「公文史生」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called kumonmoku or kumonshisei.</e>
<cmt>「公文目」の読み方についてはインターネットでヒットしなかったので確認がとれていません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called &apos;kumonmoku&apos; or &apos;kumonshisei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos; を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called &apos;kumonmoku&apos; or &apos;kumonshisei.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>公家の政所や寺院の僧綱などにおいてもこれに倣った文書管理が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kuge&apos;s Mandokoro and sogo (office of monastic affairs) of temples also, the monjo management following this was done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The document management following this was also done in Kuge&apos;s Mandokoro (administrative board), sogo (office of monastic affairs) of temples, and so on.</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました。monjo→documentとしました。「政所」を補足しました。and so on を追加しました。（「など」訳漏れのため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The document management following this was also done in Kuge&apos;s Mandokoro (administrative board), sogo (office of monastic affairs) of temples, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>当初は「開闔（かいごう）」・「出納（しゅつのう）」・「預（あずかり）」などとも呼ばれていたが、次第に取扱う文書が多くなり訴訟なども担当するようになると、それらも「公文」と称せられる様になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, those were also called kaigo (post), shutsuno (receipts and expenditure) and azukari (an additional post to the chief of Naizenshi), but as the monjo to deal with were increasing and starting to include even lawsuits, all of those began to be called kumon uniformly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, those were also called &apos;kaigo&apos; (post), &apos;shutsuno&apos; (receipts and expenditure) and &apos;azukari&apos; (an additional post to the chief of Naizenshi), but as the documents to deal with increased and started to include even lawsuits, all of them began to be called kumon uniformly.</e>
<cmt>&apos; &apos; を追加しました。monjo→documents としました。were increasing→increased, starting→started としました。those→them としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning, those were also called &apos;kaigo&apos; (post), &apos;shutsuno&apos; (receipts and expenditure) and &apos;azukari&apos; (an additional post to the chief of Naizenshi), but as the documents to deal with increased and started to include even lawsuits, all of them began to be called kumon uniformly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、鎌倉幕府の引付の書記担当者も「公文」と呼ばれて所務沙汰の文書の受付などを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the person in charge of shoki (amanuensis) in the hikitsuke (judicial board) of Kamakura Bakufu was also called Kumon, and served as receptionist of the monjo of shomusata (trial dealing with land-related issues).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person in charge of shoki (amanuensis) in the hikitsuke (judicial board) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was also called &apos;Kumon,&apos; whose duties included acceptance of documents for shomusata (trial dealing with land-related issues).</e>
<cmt>Also 重複のため削除しました。「鎌倉幕府」用語統一に従い変更しました。 &apos; &apos; を追加しました。「受付」は受理のことと思いますので、receptionist→acceptance とし、前後を調整しました。the monjo of→documents for としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The person in charge of shoki (amanuensis) in the hikitsuke (judicial board) of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was also called &apos;Kumon,&apos; whose duties included acceptance of documents for shomusata (trial dealing with land-related issues).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>五山制度における公文（公帖）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumon (kojo) in the Five Mountain System</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumon (kojo) in the Five Mountain System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumon (kojo) in the Five Mountain System</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>また、足利将軍家が発給した五山十刹などの住持を任命（補任）する辞令を「公文」もしくは「公帖（こうじょう）」と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the letter of appointment issued by Ashikaga Shogun Family to appoint the chief priest of Gozan-Jissetsu was also called Kumon or Kojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The letter of appointment issued by Ashikaga Shogun Family to appoint the chief priest of Gozan-Jissetsu (five great Zen temples and ten important temples of Rinzai sect) was also called &apos;Kumon&apos; or &apos;Kojo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Also 重複のため削除しました。「五山十刹」を補足しました。 &apos; &apos; を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The letter of appointment issued by Ashikaga Shogun Family to appoint the chief priest of Gozan-Jissetsu (five great Zen temples and ten important temples of Rinzai sect) was also called &apos;Kumon&apos; or &apos;Kojo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>五山制度は鎌倉幕府にも存在しており公文（公帖）が出されていたが、同制度が整備されたのは、室町幕府初代征夷大将軍足利尊氏が禅宗保護に積極的であったことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Five Mountain System had already existed in Kamakura Bakufu with the issuance of kumon (kojo), and it was improved by Takauji ASHIKAGA, the first Seii Taishogun of Muromachi Bakufu, who was actively protecting the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Five Mountain System had already existed in the Kamakura bakufu with the issuance of kumon (kojo), and it was improved by Takauji ASHIKAGA, the first seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu, who was actively protecting the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt>「鎌倉幕府」「室町幕府」「征夷大将軍」用語統一に従い修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Five Mountain System had already existed in the Kamakura bakufu with the issuance of kumon (kojo), and it was improved by Takauji ASHIKAGA, the first seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of the Muromachi bakufu, who was actively protecting the Zen sect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>従って公文（公帖）は将軍直々の命令書である御教書もしくは御内書形式で発給されるのが通例であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, kumon (kojo) was usually issued in the form of Migyosho (a document for informing people of the decision of Third Rank or upper people) or Gonaisho (official document), which procedure was, at first, Shogun selects a nominee in reference to the Myobu (identification) submitted by representative Buddhist monks (Rokuon soroku and Inryoshiki (corresponding officer of Shogun and Soroku 〔highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect〕), then the Kumon Bugyo (magistrate) makes the text that Shogun later confirms, signs and seals to issue the representative Buddhist monks who hand it over to the nominee.</e>
<cmt>「将軍が内容を確認の上」の「内容」は、その前にある「本文」と同じものを指しているので、訳出しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, kumon (kojo) was usually issued in the form of Migyosho (a document for informing people of the decision of Third Rank or upper people) or Gonaisho (official document).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, kumon (kojo) was usually issued in the form of Migyosho (a document for informing people of the decision of Third Rank or upper people) or Gonaisho (official document).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>（手続としては、僧侶代表（鹿苑僧録・蔭涼職）から出された名簿を参考に将軍が選任し、将軍の指示に従って公文奉行が本文を執筆し、将軍が内容を確認の上で署名捺印して僧侶代表に発給してそれを被任命者に授与した）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(The procedure: at first, Shogun selects a nominee referring to the name list submitted by representative Buddhist monks: Rokuon soroku [highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect] and Inryoshiki [corresponding officer of Shogun and Soroku], then the Kumon Bugyo [magistrate] makes the text under Shogun&apos;s instruction, Shogun later confirms it, and signs and seals it to issue to the representative Buddhist monks who hand it over to the nominee).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処「名簿」は『みょうぶ』でなく『めいぼ』と解釈し、訳語変更しました。in reference to→referring to としました。「僧録」補足の位置を移動しました。under Shogun&apos;s instruction を追加し、後の文を微調整しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The procedure: at first, Shogun selects a nominee referring to the name list submitted by representative Buddhist monks: Rokuon soroku [highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect] and Inryoshiki [corresponding officer of Shogun and Soroku], then the Kumon Bugyo [magistrate] makes the text under Shogun&apos;s instruction, Shogun later confirms it, and signs and seals it to issue to the representative Buddhist monks who hand it over to the nominee).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、室町時代中期以後には実際には居住していない僧侶に対して名誉職の意味を持った住持職任命を目的とした公文（公帖）が発給される場合があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, from the middle of the Muromachi period, kumon (kojo) was sometimes issued for the purpose of appointing the monk who actually wasn&apos;t residing as Jujishoku (a resident head of the temple) that was considered as honorary position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, from the middle of the Muromachi period, kumon (kojo) was sometimes issued for the purpose of appointing the monk who did not live in the temple as Jujishoku (a resident head of the temple) that was considered as honorary position.</e>
<cmt>actually wasn&apos;t residing→ did not live in the temple としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, from the middle of the Muromachi period, kumon (kojo) was sometimes issued for the purpose of appointing the monk who did not live in the temple as Jujishoku (a resident head of the temple) that was considered as honorary position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これを「坐公文（いなりのくもん）」と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called &apos;inarinokumon.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called &apos;inarinokumon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>全角引用符を半角としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called &apos;inarinokumon.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>こうした公文（公帖）の発給のために献上された礼銭が室町幕府の重要な財政収入になったのみでなく、織田信長によって京都を追放された足利義昭の追放中の活動資金にもなったと言われている（「五山十刹」の住持の任免権は室町幕府ではなく、足利将軍個人にあると考えられていたため）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Reisen (honorarium) presented in exchange of kumon (kojo) is said to have been not only the important financial resource of Muromachi bakufu, but also the funds for enabling Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA banished from Kyoto by Nobunaga ODA to work underground (because the appointive power over the cheif priest of Gozan-Jissetsu was considered being in Ashikaga Shogun himself, not in Muromachi bakufu.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Reisen (honorarium) presented in exchange of kumon (kojo) is said to have been not only the important financial resource of the Muromachi bakufu, but also the funds for enabling Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA banished from Kyoto by Nobunaga ODA to work underground (because the appointive power over the chief priest of &apos;Gozan-Jissetsu&apos; was considered being in Ashikaga Shogun himself, not in Muromachi bakufu.)</e>
<cmt>the を追加しました。スペースを削除しました。&apos; &apos; を追加しました。chief スペル修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Reisen (honorarium) presented in exchange of kumon (kojo) is said to have been not only the important financial resource of the Muromachi bakufu, but also the funds for enabling Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA banished from Kyoto by Nobunaga ODA to work underground (because the appointive power over the chief priest of &apos;Gozan-Jissetsu&apos; was considered being in Ashikaga Shogun himself, not in Muromachi bakufu.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>なお、鎌倉五山などの関東の寺院に関する公文（公帖）は鎌倉府に発給権があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the issuing power over kumon (kojo) regarding temples such as Kamakura Gozan Temples in Kanto region was held by Kamakura Goverment, and as for the provincial temples, a record tells a local Shugo (provincial constable) issued on behalf of Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the issuing power over kumon (kojo) regarding temples in Kanto region, such as Kamakura Gozan Temples, was held by Kamakura Government, and as for the provincial temples, a record tells a local Shugo (provincial constable) issued on behalf of Shogun.</e>
<cmt>語順を変え、コンマを追加しました。Government スペル修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the authority to issue kumon (kojo) regarding temples in the Kanto region, such as the Kamakura Gozan Temples, was held by the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>地方の寺院については現地の守護が将軍の代理として発給した例も存在している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local Shugo (provincial constables) would sometimes issue kumon (kojo) for provincial temples on behalf of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>その後、足利義昭の出家による引退後は代わって豊臣政権や江戸幕府が公文（公帖）が発給している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, following Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos;s retirement to become a priest, the Toyotomi government, then the Edo bakufu handled the issuance of kumon (kojo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, following Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos;s retirement to become a priest, the Toyotomi government, then the Edo bakufu handled the issuance of kumon (kojo).</e>
<cmt>スペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, following Yoshiaki ASHIKAGA&apos;s retirement to become a priest, the Toyotomi government, then the Edo bakufu handled the issuance of kumon (kojo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>江戸幕府は五山十刹諸山之諸法度を出して蔭涼職を廃して鹿苑僧録に替わって金地院僧録を設置し、「秉払なしに公帖を発行してはならない」などの厳しい資格制限を付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu enforced the Gozan-Jissetsu Shozan no Shohatto (various laws put in force in Gozan-Jissetsu and Shozan 〔zen temples other than Gozan (five great zen temples) and Jissetsu (ten important temples of Rinzai sect)〕) to abolish the Inryoshiki (corresponding officer of Shogun and Soroku 〔highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect〕), and set up Konjin soroku (highest-ranking priest of the Gozan, the leader of the Zen sect) in place of Rokuon soroku, adding strict qualification restrictions such as &apos;No issuance of kojo without hinpotsu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu enforced the Gozan-Jissetsu Shozan no Shohatto (various laws put in force in Gozan-Jissetsu and Shozan [Zen temples other than Gozan-Jissetsu]) to abolish the Inryoshiki, and set up Konjin soroku in place of Rokuon soroku, adding strict qualification restrictions such as &apos;No issuance of kojo without hinpotsu (preaching by shuso [the leader of monks practicing asceticism] on behalf of Jujishoku).&apos;</e>
<cmt>「五山十刹」既出のため、「五山」と「十刹」の補足を削除しました。Zen 頭文字を大文字にしました。「蔭涼職」既出のため、補足を削除しました。「僧録」既出のため、補足を削除しました。「秉払」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu enforced the Gozan-Jissetsu Shozan no Shohatto (various laws put in force in Gozan-Jissetsu and Shozan [Zen temples other than Gozan-Jissetsu]) to abolish the Inryoshiki, and set up Konjin soroku in place of Rokuon soroku, adding strict qualification restrictions such as &apos;No issuance of kojo without hinpotsu (preaching by shuso [the leader of monks practicing asceticism] on behalf of Jujishoku).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>ただし、東福寺は九条家・一条家のいずれかが、天竜寺・大徳寺・南禅寺などは院宣や綸旨によって出される事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were some exceptions like, in Tofuku-ji Temple, the Kujo family or the Ichijo family was supposed to issue, and in Tenryu-ji Temple, Daitoku-ji Temple and Nanzen-ji Temple, Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) or Rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) was holding such issuing power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as exceptions, kumon (kojo) was sometimes issued to Tofuku-ji Temple by the Kujo family or the Ichijo family, and as Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) or Rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) it was issued to Tenryu-ji Temple, Daitoku-ji Temple, Nanzen-ji Temple and so on.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as exceptions, kumon (kojo) was sometimes issued to Tofuku-ji Temple by the Kujo family or the Ichijo family, and as Inzen (a decree from the retired Emperor) or Rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) it was issued to Tenryu-ji Temple, Daitoku-ji Temple, Nanzen-ji Temple and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>荘園における公文</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kumon in shoen (manor in medieval Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kumon in shoen</e>
<cmt>「荘園」既出のため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kumon in shoen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>荘園においては国衙や領家に対して提出する文書を作成する者を「公文」と呼んだが、後には文書を担当する者以外に対しても広く使われるようになり、荘園の下級荘官の役職として「公文」の呼称が用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In shoen, persons who made a text to submit to kokuga (provincial government office compounds) and ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor) had been called kumon, but this name later began to be also used for persons other than those in charge of writing and to be used as post name of low-ranking shokan of shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In shoen, persons who made a text to submit to kokuga and ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor) had been called &apos;kumon,&apos; but this name later began to be also used for persons other than those in charge of writing and &apos;kumon&apos; became a post name of low-ranking shokan (an officer governing shoen) of shoen.</e>
<cmt>「国衙」既出のため、補足を削除しました。 &apos; &apos; を追加しました。to be used as→&apos;kumon&apos; became a としました。「荘官」を補足しました。（用語検索より）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In shoen, persons who made a text to submit to kokuga and ryoke (virtual proprietor of manor) had been called &apos;kumon,&apos; but this name later began to be also used for persons other than those in charge of writing and &apos;kumon&apos; became a post name of low-ranking shokan (an officer governing shoen) of shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>本来は領家より派遣されるのが一般的であったが、後には現地の事情に通じた開発領主が任命され、給田と呼ばれる所領給与とともに子孫に継承されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, they were generally sent from ryoke, but some time later, kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) well-informed about the local situation began to be appointed, thus it was handed down to posterity along with kyuden meaning incomes from land taxes on shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, they were generally sent from ryoke, but some time later, kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) who were well-informed about the local situation began to be appointed, thus it was handed down to posterity along with kyuden meaning incomes from land taxes on shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt>who were を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning, they were generally sent from ryoke, but some time later, kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) who were well-informed about the local situation began to be appointed, thus it was handed down to posterity along with kyuden meaning incomes from land taxes on shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>彼らは現地の村々における責任者として荘園ならびにそこに住む百姓を監督する役目を担い、年貢・夫役などは彼らを通じて徴収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a responsible person of the village, they served as surveillance of shoen and peasants living in there, and nengu (annual tribute, land tax) and the compulsory service were provided through them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a responsible person of the village, they served as an overseer of shoen and peasants living in there, and nengu (annual tribute, land tax) and the compulsory service were paid through them.</e>
<cmt>変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a responsible person of the village, they served as a supervisor of shoen and peasants living in there, and nengu (annual tribute, land tax) and the compulsory service were paid through them.</e>
<cmt>overseer→supervisor</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>だが、領家・地頭・百姓間において対立が生じるとその間に挟まれて苦慮する立場でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the confrontation occurred between ryoke or jito (the leader of the group reciters) and peasants, they were put in the difficult position between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the confrontation occurred between ryoke or jito (manager and lord of manor) and peasants, they were put in the difficult position between them.</e>
<cmt>「地頭」の補足を修正しました。（『じとう』でなく『じがしら』の用語があてられていたため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the confrontation occurred between ryoke or jito (manager and lord of manor) and peasants, they were put in the difficult position between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>なお、検注に際して国衙側の公文が持つ土地台帳と荘園側の公文が持つ台帳を勘合する際の事務経費を公文勘料（くもんかんりょう）と呼び、検注時に農民に対して臨時に賦課されて、実際の経費及び実務に当たった荘園側の公文に対する得分（報酬）として宛がわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the clerical expense at kenchu (land survey) for reconciling the cadaster owned by kumon of kokuga and that of kumon of shoen was called kumon-kanryo, which was imposed to peasants as tax at the time of kenchu, in order to cover the actual expense and the reward to kumon of shoen who actually handled the practice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, kumon kanryo, the clerical expense at kenchu (land survey) for checking the cadaster owned by kumon of kokuga against that of kumon of shoen, was imposed on peasants as extra tax at the time of kenchu, in order to cover the actual expense and the reward to kumon of shoen who actually handled the practice.</e>
<cmt>語順を変えました。reconsiling～and→checking～against としました。to→on としました。extra を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, kumon kanryo, the clerical expense at kenchu (land survey) for checking the cadaster owned by kumon of kokuga against that of kumon of shoen, was imposed on peasants as extra tax at the time of kenchu, in order to cover the actual expense and the reward to kumon of shoen who actually handled the practice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 七之輔(id:55793), 三島平八(id:185773), ちょるや氏(id:88738), Shimoxx(id:9332), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>