<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宇治川の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Uji-gawa River</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Uji-gawa River</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Uji-gawa River</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>宇治川の戦い（うじがわのたたかい）は、平安時代末期の寿永3年（1184年）1月に源義仲と鎌倉の源頼朝から派遣された源範頼、源義経とで戦われた合戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Uji-gawa River was a battle in January 1184, at the end of Heian period, between MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune who were dispatched by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Uji-gawa River was a battle that took place in January 1184, at the end of Heian period, between MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune who were dispatched by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that took place&quot; added before &quot;in January&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Uji-gawa River was a battle that took place in January 1184, at the end of Heian period, between MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, and MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune who were dispatched by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>治承・寿永の乱の戦いの一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is one of the battles in the Jisho Juei Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s one of the battles in the Jisho Juei Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&apos;s&quot; replaces &quot;It is&quot; for ease of readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s one of the battles in the Jisho Juei Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Course</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Course</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Course</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>寿永2年（1183年）7月、信濃国で平家打倒の挙兵をした源義仲が数万騎を率いて入洛した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka who raised an army in Shinano Province to overturn the Taira family, led several tens of thousands of knights into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, who raised an army in Shinano Province to overturn the Taira family, led several tens of thousands of samurai into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>comma placed after &quot;Yoshinaka,&quot; and &quot;samurai&quot; replaces former wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, who raised an army in Shinano Province to overturn the Taira family, led several tens of thousands of samurai into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>義仲軍は京で乱暴狼藉を働き、やがて皇位継承を巡って後白河天皇とも対立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops brought violence and riots to Kyoto, and with time, was in conflict with Emperor Goshirakawa over succession to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops brought violence and riots to Kyoto, and with time, he was in conflict with Emperor Goshirakawa over succession to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>&quot;he&quot; added before &quot;was in conflict&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops brought violence and riots to Kyoto, and with time, he was in conflict with Emperor Goshirakawa over succession to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>9月、義仲軍は備前国水島の戦いで平家軍に大敗、後白河法皇は義仲を見放した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, Yoshinaka&apos;s troops was severely defeated by the troops of Taira family in the Battle of Mizushima in Bizen Province, and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa forsook him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, Yoshinaka&apos;s troops were severely defeated by the troops of the Taira family in the Battle of Mizushima in Bizen Province, and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa forsook him.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot; after &quot;troops replaced with &quot;were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, Yoshinaka&apos;s troops were severely defeated by the troops of the Taira family in the Battle of Mizushima in Bizen Province, and Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa forsook him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>10月、後白河法皇は鎌倉の源頼朝に東海道・東山道の支配を認める宣旨を下し、頼朝に接近する（寿永二年十月宣旨）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa sends an imperial letter to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo authorizing control over Tokaido and Tosando, and approaches Yoritomo (imperial letter of October, Juei 2).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa sent an imperial letter to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo authorizing control over Tokaido and Tosando, and their approaches Yoritomo (imperial letter of October, Juei 2).</e>
<cmt>&quot;sends&quot; replaced with &quot;sent&quot; and &quot;their&quot; inserted before &quot;approaches&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa sent an imperial letter to MINAMOTO no Yoritomo in Kamakura authorizing control over Tokaido and Tosando, and approaches Yoritomo (imperial letter of October, Juei 2).</e>
<cmt>in Kamakura補足their削除原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>11月、起死回生をはかった義仲は院御所の法住寺殿を攻撃、後白河法皇を幽閉して政権を掌握した（法住寺合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, Yoshinaka makes a revival by attacking the Hoju-ji Temple Palace, the residence of the retired Emperor, and confines the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa to gain power (the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November, Yoshinaka makes another attack on the Hoju-ji Temple Palace, the residence of the retired Emperor, and confines the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa to gain power (the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>&quot;makes another attack on&quot; placed before &quot;Hoju-ji Temple Palace&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November, Yoshinaka makes another attack on the Hoju-ji Temple Palace, the residence of the retired Emperor, and confines the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa to gain power (the Battle of Hoju-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>孤立を深める義仲は平家との和平を打診するが、拒絶される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka who became increasingly isolated attempts to make peace with the Taira family, but is rejected.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka, who became increasingly isolated, attempted to make peace with the Taira family, but was rejected.</e>
<cmt>tense corrected &quot;attempts&quot; changed to &quot;attempted,&quot; and &quot;is&quot; replaced with &quot;was&quot; before rejected.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka, who became increasingly isolated, attempted to make peace with the Taira family, but was rejected.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>12月、義仲は後白河法皇に強要して頼朝追討の院宣を発出させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, Yoshinaka forces Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa to issue a command from a retired Emperor for tracking down and killing Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Yoshinaka forced the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa to issue a command from a retired Emperor to track down and kill Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>tense changed to past tense for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Yoshinaka forced the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa to issue a command from a retired Emperor to track down and kill Yoritomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そして翌寿永3年（1184年）1月、義仲は征夷大将軍（または征東大将軍）に任命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1184, Yoshinaka was appointed Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) (or Seito Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1184, Yoshinaka was appointed Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) (or Seito Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1184, Yoshinaka was appointed Seii Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) (or Seito Taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the eastern barbarians&quot;)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1月20日、頼朝は近江にまで進出させていた範頼、義経に義仲追討を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20th, Yoritomo ordered Noriyori and Yoshitsune, whom he had moved to Omi, to track down and kill Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 20th, Yoritomo ordered Noriyori and Yoshitsune, whom he had moved to Omi, to track down and kill Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 20, Yoritomo ordered Noriyori and Yoshitsune, whom he had moved to Omi, to track down and kill Yoshinaka.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>入洛時には数万騎だった義仲軍は、水島の戦いの敗北と状況の悪化により脱落者が続出して千騎あまりに激減していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops, which numbered several tens of thousands of knights when they went into Kyoto, had decreased dramatically down to about one thousand knights, because of a stream of dropouts due to the defeat in the Battle of Mizushima and deteriorating situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops, that numbered several tens of thousands of samurai warriors when they went into Kyoto, had decreased dramatically down to about one thousand, because of the stream of dropouts due to the defeat at the Battle of Mizushima and the deteriorated situation.</e>
<cmt>tense changed to past tense for consistency and &quot;knights&quot; changed to &quot;samurai warriors&quot; and &quot;knights&quot; deleted after &quot;one thousand&quot; &quot;deteriorating&quot; changed to &quot;deteriorated&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops, that numbered several tens of thousands of samurai warriors when they went into Kyoto, had decreased dramatically down to about one thousand, because of the stream of dropouts due to the defeat at the Battle of Mizushima and the deteriorated situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>義仲は義仲四天王の今井兼平に500余騎を与えて瀬田 (滋賀県)を、根井行親、楯親忠には300余騎で宇治市を守らせ、義仲自身は100余騎で院御所を守護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka gave Kanehira IMAI, one of the big fours of Yoshinaka about 500 knights to guard Seta (Shiga Prefecture), about 300 knights to Yukichika NENOI and Chikatada TATE to guard Uji City, and Yoshinaka himself guarded the imperial palace with about 100 knights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka gave Kanehira IMAI, one of the big four of Yoshinaka, about 500 samurai to guard Seta (Shiga Prefecture), about 300 samurai to Yukichika NENOI and Chikatada TATE to guard Uji City, and Yoshinaka himself guarded the imperial palace with about 100 samurai.</e>
<cmt>&quot;fours&quot; changed to &quot;four&quot; and &quot;knights&quot; changed to &quot;samurai&quot; throughout the text.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka gave Kanehira IMAI, one of the big four of Yoshinaka, about 500 samurai to guard Seta (Shiga Prefecture), about 300 samurai to Yukichika NENOI and Chikatada TATE to guard Uji City, and Yoshinaka himself guarded the imperial palace with about 100 samurai.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>1月20日、範頼は大手軍3万騎で瀬田を、義経は搦手軍2万5千騎で宇治を攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20th, Noriyori attacked Seta with troops consisting of 30 thousand knights for an attack from the front side and Yoshitsune attacked Uji with backdoor troops of 25 thousand knights.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 20th, Noriyori attacked Seta with 30,000 samurai head-on and Yoshitsune attacked Uji from the rear with another 25,000.</e>
<cmt>terms rewritten, mix of numbers and written numbers changed to all numbers for consistency</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 20, Noriyori attacked Seta with 30,000 samurai head-on and Yoshitsune attacked Uji from the rear with another 25,000.</e>
<cmt>日付表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>義経軍は矢が降り注ぐ中を宇治川に乗り入れる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsune&apos;s troops enter the Uji-gawa River while being attacked by arrows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune&apos;s troops entered the Uji-gawa River under a shower of arrows.</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense, and &quot;under a shower of arrows&quot; replaces former text</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune&apos;s troops entered the Uji-gawa River under a shower of arrows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>佐々木高綱と梶原景季の「宇治川の先陣争い」はこのときのこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is where the &apos;Fight for the vanguard in Uji-gawa River&apos; between Takatsuna SASAKI and Kagesue KAJIWARA occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is where the &apos;Fight for the vanguard in Uji-gawa River&apos; between Takatsuna SASAKI and Kagesue KAJIWARA occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is where the &apos;Fight for the vanguard in Uji-gawa River&apos; between Takatsuna SASAKI and Kagesue KAJIWARA occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>根井行親、楯親忠は必死の防戦をするが、義経軍に宇治川を突破される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukichika NENOI and Chikatada TATE desperately fight a defensive battle, but Yoshitsune&apos;s troops manage to cross the Uji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukichika NENOI and Chikatada TATE desperately fought a defensive battle, but Yoshitsune&apos;s troops managed to cross the Uji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>corrected to past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukichika NENOI and Chikatada TATE desperately fought a defensive battle, but Yoshitsune&apos;s troops managed to cross the Uji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>義経軍は雪崩を打って京洛へ突入する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsune&apos;s troops surge into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune&apos;s troops surged into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>changed to past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune&apos;s troops surged into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>義仲が出陣し、義経軍と激戦となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka takes to the field and fights a fierce battle with Yoshitsune&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka fought a fierce battle with Yoshitsune&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;takes to the field&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka fought a fierce battle with Yoshitsune&apos;s troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>義仲は奮戦するが遂に敗れ、後白河法皇を連れて西国へ脱出すべく院御所へ向かう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka fights bravely, but is finally defeated, and heads to the imperial palace to escape to Kyushu with Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka fought bravely, but was finally defeated, and headed to the imperial palace to escape to Kyushu with the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>corrected to past tense</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka fought bravely, but was finally defeated, and headed to the imperial palace to escape to Kyushu with the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>義経は自ら数騎を率いて追撃、院御所門前で義仲を追い払い、後白河法皇の確保に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitsune personally leads several knights to chase him, drives away Yoshinaka in front of the gate of the imperial palace, and succeeds in securing Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitsune personally led several samurai warriors to chase and drive away Yoshinaka from the front gate of the imperial palace, and succeeded in securing the safety of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>terms changed, tense corrected, sentence shortened for clarity and ease of readability</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitsune personally led several samurai warriors to chase and drive away Yoshinaka from the front gate of the imperial palace, and succeeded in securing the safety of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後白河法皇を連れ出すことを断念した義仲は今井兼平と合流すべく瀬田へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Giving up on taking Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, Yoshinaka heads to Seta to join Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After giving up on taking the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, Yoshinaka headed to Seta to join Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt>tense corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After giving up on taking the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa, Yoshinaka headed to Seta to join Kanehira IMAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="23">
<j>瀬田で範頼軍と戦っていた今井兼平は宇治方面での敗報を知り退却、粟津で義仲との合流に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI, who has been fighting Noriyori&apos;s troops, retreats hearing the news of defeat in the Uji area, and successfully joins Yoshinaka in Awazu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanehira IMAI, who had been fighting Noriyori&apos;s troops, retreated, having heard about the defeat at Uji, and successfully joined Yoshinaka in Awazu.</e>
<cmt>tense corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanehira IMAI, who had been fighting Noriyori&apos;s troops at Seta, retreated, having heard about the defeat at Uji, and successfully joined Yoshinaka in Awazu.</e>
<cmt>at Seta補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>義仲は北陸道への脱出をはかるが、これへ範頼の大軍が襲いかかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka attempts to escape to Hokuriku-do (northern prefectures), but is attacked by Noriyori&apos;s vast army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka attempted to escape to Hokuriku-do (northern prefectures), but was attacked by Noriyori&apos;s enormous army.</e>
<cmt>tense corrected and change the term &quot;vast&quot; to &quot;enormous&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka attempted to escape to Hokuriku-do (northern prefectures), but was attacked by Noriyori&apos;s enormous army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>義仲軍は奮戦するが次々に討たれ、数騎にまで討ち減らされたところで、遂に義仲が顔面に矢を受けて討ち取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops fight bravely, but are killed one after another, and when they were down to the last few, Yoshinaka is killed by an arrow hitting his face.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops fought bravely, but were killed one after another, and when down to the last few, Yoshinaka was killed by an arrow striking deep into his face.</e>
<cmt>tense corrected and changed the latter part of the sentence to read &quot;deep into his face&quot; It would sound better if the exact location could be described such as &quot;between his eyes&quot; but lacking this detail I hope that face will suffice.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshinaka&apos;s troops fought bravely, but were killed one after another, and when down to the last few, Yoshinaka was killed by an arrow striking deep into his face.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>今井兼平も義仲を追って自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following Yoshinaka, Kanehira IMAI also took his own life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following Yoshinaka, Kanehira IMAI took his own life.</e>
<cmt>&quot;also&quot; deleted as Yoshinaka evidently did not take his own life.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Yoshinaka, Kanehira IMAI took his own life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 けふこえて(id:17107), BOTarate(id:185620), 桂鷺淵(id:151322), Kaba(id:17904), Reggaeman(id:6214), 味っ子(id:17086), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yanahan(id:2437), 越中掾(id:149423), Ash Crow(id:26765), Toki-ho(id:10691), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>