<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>季御読経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinomidokyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinomidokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinomidokyo (reading of the Great Perfection of Insight Sutra in spring and autumn)</e>
<cmt>補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>季御読経（きのみどきょう）は、平安時代に行われた宮中行事のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinomidokyo was one of the court functions performed in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinomidokyo was a court function performed during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;one of the&quot; to &quot;a&quot;; changed &quot;in&quot; to &quot;during&quot;; made &quot;period&quot; lowercase</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinomidokyo was a court function performed during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>奈良時代の和銅年間に始まったとする説もあるが、天平元年（729年）が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While it is believed by some that Kinomidokyo dates back to the Wado Era (from 708 to 715) of the Nara Period, it is generally agreed that it started in 729.</e>
<cmt>※文章の意味を考慮して「和銅年間」を残し、西暦を補足しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While some believe that Kinomidokyo dates back to the Wado Era (from 708 to 715) of the Nara period, it is generally agreed that it began in 729.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;started&quot; to &quot;began&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some believe that Kinomidokyo dates back to the Wado era (from 708 to 715) of the Nara period, it is generally agreed that it began in 729.</e>
<cmt>Era →era　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>季御読経は、春と秋に国家安泰を祈願して宮中に僧を招き、大般若経を転読する仏教法会である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinomidokyo was a Buddhist service in which monks were invited inside the Imperial Court, who selectively read Daihannyakyo (Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra) to pray for the peace and security of the nation in spring and fall.</e>
<cmt>※「大般若経」の訳語は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinomidokyo was a Buddhist service where monks were invited inside the Imperial Court in the spring and fall to selectively read Daihannyakyo (Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra) to pray for the peace and security of the nation.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinomidokyo was a Buddhist service where priests were invited inside the Imperial Court in the spring and fall to selectively read Daihannyakyo (Great Perfection of Wisdom Sutra) to pray for the peace and security of the nation.</e>
<cmt>monks →priests　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>通常4日ないし3日間の法会が開かれ、2日目に「引茶」という茶の接待が僧侶に対して行われ、3日目には僧侶同士の「論義」が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Usually, a hoe (Buddhist mass) was held for three or four days; On its second day, the monks were entertained with &apos;hikicha,&apos; tea served during service, and on its third, they had rounds of &apos;rongi&apos; (debate).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A hoe (Buddhist mass) was usually held for three or four days. On the second day, the monks were entertained by a tea service called &quot;hikicha,&quot; and on the third day rounds of debate were held called &quot;rongi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed semi-colon into a period; rearranged sentences and fixed grammar to read more naturally; made &quot;debate&quot; part of the sentence rather than in parenthesis</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A hoe (Buddhist mass) was usually held for three or four days; on the second day, the monks were entertained by a tea service called &apos;hikicha,&apos; and on the third day rounds of debate were held called &apos;rongi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし「引茶」と「論義」は原則春季のみであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But as a general rule, &apos;hikicha&apos; and &apos;rongi&apos; were only seen in spring.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a general rule, however, &quot;hikicha&quot; and &quot;rongi&quot; took place only in the spring.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a general rule, however, &apos;hikicha&apos; and &apos;rongi&apos; took place only in the spring.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>初日ないし最終日には法会と共に各寺院の得度を朝廷から賜る儀礼が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the first or final day of Kinomidokyo, a ritual was performed, along with a hoe, to enter the Buddhist priesthood of each temple through the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the first or final day of a Kinomidokyo, a ritual was performed through the Imperial Court, together with a hoe, for those entering into Buddhist priesthood at each temple.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the first or final day of a Kinomidokyo, a ritual was performed through the Imperial Court, together with a hoe, for those entering into Buddhist priesthood at each temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>宮中の公式行事として確立したのは貞観 (日本)元年（859年）であるが、この頃には「四季御読経」として年間を通じて催されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinomidokyo was established as an official function in the Imperial Court in 859, by which it had already been held as a &apos;Shikinomidokyo&apos; (Seasonal reading of the Great Perfection of Insight Sutra) throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>※「四季御読経」の訳語は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinomidokyo was established as an official function of the Imperial Court in 859, but by this time it had already been held as a &quot;Shikinomidokyo&quot; (Seasonal reading of the Great Perfection of Insight Sutra) throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;by which&quot; to &quot;but by this time&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinomidokyo was established as an official function of the Imperial Court in 859, but by this time it had already been held as a &apos;Shikinomidokyo&apos; (seasonal reading of the Great Perfection of Insight Sutra) throughout the year.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、元慶元年（877年）の陽成天皇の践祚より回数を減じて、春秋の季御読経に改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, it had been performed less frequently since Emperor Yozei took the throne in 877, and Kinomidokyo came to be performed only in spring and fall.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was performed less frequently later on due to Emperor Yozei taking the throne in 877, and Kinomidokyo came to be performed only during the spring and fall.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was performed less frequently later on due to Emperor Yozei taking the throne in 877, and Kinomidokyo came to be performed only during the spring and fall.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>参集する僧侶は60～100名前後に及び、御斎会、最勝講などの法会と比べても規模の大きいものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of monks who gathered at Kinomidokyo ranged from 60 to 100, whose scale was larger than such hoe as Gosaie (ritual for the Sutra of Golden Light performed at the Imperial Palace) and Saishoko (the annual five days of lectures on the Konkomyo-saishoo sutra).</e>
<cmt>※「御斎会」および「最勝講」の訳語は用語集から採用しています。※「季御読経」を訳出しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of monks who gathered at a Kinomidokyo ranged from sixty to one hundred. This was on a larger scale than other hoe, such as the Gosaie (Ritual for the Sutra of Golden Light performed at the Imperial Palace) and the Saishoko (The annual five days of lectures on the Konkomyo-saisho sutra).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;60 to 100&quot; to &quot;sixty to one hundred&quot;; split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of priests who gathered at a Kinomidokyo ranged from 60 to 100, and this was on a larger scale than other hoe, such as the Gosaie (ritual for the Sutra of Golden Light performed at the Imperial Palace) and the Saishoko (the annual five days of lectures on the Konkomyo-saisho sutra).</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、引茶の接待や、夜には参集した貴族に対して酒肴の接待があったことから、時代を経るにつれて仏教法会より饗応の宴としての派手さが目立つようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since gathering nobles were entertained with hikicha, and with food and drink at night, Kinomidokyo in later years attained extravagance as a wining and dining feast rather than a Buddhist service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, Kinomidokyo became an extravagant wining and dining feast rather than a Buddhist mass due to nobles gathering for hikicha service and then food and drink service at night.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Buddhist service&quot; to &quot;Buddhist mass&quot; to avoid overuse of the word &quot;service&quot;; rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, Kinomidokyo became an extravagant wining and dining feast rather than a Buddhist mass due to nobles gathering for hikicha service and then food and drink service at night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>10世紀頃には宮中行事とは別に太上天皇や東宮（皇太子）、皇后などの主催でも私的に季御読経が催されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aside from court functions, Kinomidokyo came to be held privately by daijo tenno (retired emperor), togu (crown prince) or kogo (empress) as as host by the tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the tenth century, aside from court functions, Kinomidokyo came to be held privately and hosted by the Daijo Tenno (Retired Emperor), the Togu (Crown Prince) or the Kogo (Empress).</e>
<cmt>moved &quot;by the tenth century&quot; to the beginning of the sentence; capitalized &quot;Daijo Tenno&quot; (Retired Emperor), &quot;Togu&quot; (Crown Prince) and &quot;Kogo&quot; (Princess); fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the tenth century, aside from court functions, Kinomidokyo came to be held privately and hosted by the Daijo Tenno (Retired Emperor), the Togu (Crown Prince) or the Kogo (Empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>延長 (元号)2年（924年）には藤原彰子が主催しているが、これは明らかに中宮の権力誇示を目的としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By 924, it was hosted by FUJIWARA no Shoshi, which was clearly intended as a display of the power of chugu (palace of the empress).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 924 it was hosted by FUJIWARA no Shoshi, which was clearly intended as a display of power for the Chugu (Palace of the Empress).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;By 924&quot; to &quot;In 924&quot;; capitalized &quot;Chugu&quot; (Palace of the Empress)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 924 it was hosted by FUJIWARA no Shoshi, which was clearly intended as a display of power for the Chugu (Palace of the Empress).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、摂関家でも嗜みとして催されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also held as part of accomplishments in families of regent to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The service was also held by regents and advisors of the Emperor as a token of accomplishment.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;The service&quot;; capitalized &quot;Emperor&quot;; changed &quot;as part of accomplishments&quot; to &quot;as a token of accomplishment&quot;; changed &quot;families of regent to the emperor&quot; to &quot;regents and advisors of the Emperor&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The service was also held by regents and advisors of the Emperor as a token of accomplishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし、藤原道長が政治の表舞台から外れると摂関家における季御読経の回数は減り、続く藤原頼通の時代にはほとんど行われなくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga stepped out from the political center stage, however, Kinomidokyo in families of regent to the emperor was held less frequently, and by the following era of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, it was not held any more.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga stepped out from the political center stage, however, Kinomidokyo by regents and advisors were held less frequently. By the following era of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, the service almost never held at all.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When FUJIWARA no Michinaga stepped out from the political center stage, however, Kinomidokyo by regents and advisors were held less frequently, and by the following era of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, the service almost never held at all.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>引茶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hikicha</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hikicha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hikicha</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>平安期における「茶」は唐より伝来された最新の文化で大変貴重であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cha&apos; (tea) in the Heian Period was one of the latest cultural trends that came from Tang and was very valuable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originating from Tang, &quot;Cha&quot; (tea) during the Heian period was one of the latest cultural trends and was very highly valued.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originating from Tang, &apos;Cha&apos; (tea) during the Heian period was one of the latest cultural trends and was very highly valued.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>そのため、宮中における茶の接待には準備も含めて莫大な手間と費用がかかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, it took enormous time and money to prepare for tea entertainment in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, it took enormous time and money to prepare tea services for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;For this reason&quot; to &quot;Consequently&quot;; changed &quot;tea entertainment&quot; to &quot;tea services&quot; for &quot;茶の接待&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, it took enormous time and money to prepare tea services for the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>引茶の飲茶法は、整然と並ぶ僧侶に対して、まず煎茶を注ぎ、甘葛、厚朴、生姜などの薬味を好みにより投じて供したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Manners of hikicha were as follows; first, sencha (green tea of middle grade) was served to monks who were standing in neat rows, and then such condiments as amazura (traditional sweetener commonly used in the past), koboku (skin of Magnolia obovata used for crude drugs) and ginger were added in to their taste.</e>
<cmt>※「甘葛」および「厚朴」の訳語は用語集から採用しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manners in which hikicha was served involved serving sencha (green tea of middle grade) to monks formed in an orderly line. Condiments would then be added, such as amazura (traditional sweetener commonly used in the past), koboku (skin of Magnolia obovata used for crude drugs) and ginger to suit individual tastes.</e>
<cmt>split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manners in which hikicha was served involved serving sencha (green tea of middle grade) to priests formed in an orderly line; condiments would then be added, such as amazura (traditional sweetener commonly used in the past), koboku (skin of Magnolia obovata used for crude drugs) and ginger to suit individual tastes.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>初め煎茶は遣唐使によりもたらされた貴重なものが用いられたが、9世紀後半には宮中の内裏茶園で栽培され、蔵人所の造茶使が製造を行っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, they used the valuable kind of sencha, introduced by Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), but by the late ninth century, zochashi (a person who manages tea garden) at Kurododokoro (the Chamberlain&apos;s Office) made tea, which was grown in the tea garden in the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>※「遣唐使」および「造茶使」の訳語は用語集から採用しています。※「蔵人所」の訳語が用語集に複数ありますので、確認が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After it was first introduced to Japan, a valuable kind of sencha was used that had been brought over by the Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), but by the late ninth century, the zochashi (a person who manages a tea garden) at the Kurododokoro (chamberlain&apos;s office) made tea from plants that had been grown in the tea garden of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more smoothly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After it was first introduced to Japan, a valuable kind of sencha was used that had been brought over by the Kento-shi (Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China), but by the late ninth century, the zochashi (a person who manages a tea garden) at the Kurodo-dokoro (chamberlain&apos;s office) made tea from plants that had been grown in the tea garden of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一し、Kurodo-dokoro とハイフンを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), MKT(id:6704), Point136(id:211299), Carkuni(id:79281), 蘭綾王(id:189560), 宝塚ファミリーランド(id:161197), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>