<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>朱雀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzaku, the Vermilion Bird</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzaku (the Vermilion Bird)</e>
<cmt>カッコを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzaku (the Vermilion Bird)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>朱雀（すざく・しゅじゃく、ピンイン）とは、中華人民共和国の伝説上の神獣（神鳥）で、四神（四獣・四象）・五行思想の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suzaku (also known as Shujaku, or in Pinyin) is one of the legendary divine beasts (a bird-god) of the People&apos;s Republic of China, and is one of the four gods (also known as the Four Beasts or the Four Phenomena) who rule over the four directions; he is also important in Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suzaku (also known as Shujaku, or in Pinyin) is one of the legendary divine beasts (God Bird) of the People&apos;s Republic of China, and is one of the four gods (also known as the Four Beasts or the Four Phenomena) who rule over the four directions; it is also important in the Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。「神鳥」については、&quot;God Bird&quot;の記述がウェブ上で多く見られましたのでそのようにしました。he→it と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suzaku (also known as Shujaku, or in Pinyin) is one of the legendary divine beasts (God Bird) of the People&apos;s Republic of China, and is one of the four gods (also known as the Four Beasts or the Four Phenomena) who rule over the four directions; it is also important in the Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>南方を守護する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He protects against threats from the south.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It protects against threats from the south.</e>
<cmt>He→It と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It protects against threats from the south.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>翼を広げた鳳凰状の鳥形で表される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He appears in the shape of a firebird with wings spread.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears in the shape of a firebird with wings spread.</e>
<cmt>He→It と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears in the shape of a firebird with wings spread.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>朱は赤であり、五行思想では南方の色とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Su&quot; from Suzaku means &quot;vermilion&quot; (that is, red), and so in Five Elements Theory the color of the southerly direction is red.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Su&quot; from Suzaku means &quot;vermilion&quot; (that is, red), and the color of the southern direction in the Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Su&quot; from Suzaku means &quot;vermilion&quot; (that is, red), and the color of the southern direction in the Five Elements Theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鳳凰、不死鳥と同一視されることがあり、インド神話に登場するガルダとの類似も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He is considered to be of the same type as the firebird and the phoenix, and some have pointed out similarities between him and Garuda, a bird-god who appears in Indian legends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to be of the same thing as the firebird and the phoenix, and some have pointed out the similarities between Suzaku and Garuda, a bird-god who appears in Indian legends.</e>
<cmt>He→It と修正しました。type→thing,him→Suzaku と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to be of the same thing as the firebird and the phoenix, and some have pointed out the similarities between Suzaku and Garuda, a bird-god who appears in Indian legends.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、朱雀は上に由来して寺社の縁起や地方の地誌等に私年号として散見される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the above-mentioned reasons, Suzaku also appears from time to time in the origin stories of temples and shrines, as well as in the private (non-official) era names listed in local gazeteers and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the above-mentioned reasons, Suzaku also appears from time to time in the origin stories of temples and shrines, as well as in the private (non-official) era names listed in the topographies and so forth.</e>
<cmt>the を補いました。local gazeteers→topographies と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the above-mentioned reasons, Suzaku also appears from time to time in the origin stories of temples and shrines, as well as in the private (non-official) era names listed in the topographies and so forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>私年号は逸年号とも呼ばれ、日本書紀に現れない年号をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such private, unofficial era names are also called itsunengo (era names that were actually used but were struck from the official histories), and refer to any era names that do not appear in the Nihon shoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such private, unofficial era names are also called itsunengo, and refer to any era names that do not appear in the Nihon shoki.</e>
<cmt>カッコ部分は文中で後述されており、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such private, unofficial era names are also called itsunengo, and refer to any era names that do not appear in the Nihon shoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>通説では朱鳥の別称、美称であるとされている（坂本太郎_(歴史学者)等の説）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the prevailing view, &quot;Suzaku&quot; is thought to be a pseudonym or eulogistic name for Shucho, which means &quot;red bird&quot; (this theory has been proposed by the historian Taro SAKAMOTO among others).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the prevailing view, &quot;Suzaku&quot; is thought to be a pseudonym or eulogistic name for Shucho (This theory has been proposed by the historian Taro SAKAMOTO among others.)</e>
<cmt>which means &quot;red bird&quot; という部分は確認ができないので削除しました。カッコ内、ピリオドの位置を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the prevailing view, &quot;Suzaku&quot; is thought to be a pseudonym or eulogistic name for Shucho (This theory has been proposed by the historian Taro SAKAMOTO among others.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>『続日本紀』神亀元年冬十月条（724年）にはこの記述が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In its winter entry for the tenth month of 724, the &quot;Shoku nihongi&quot; includes the following description: &quot;Beginning in the Hakuho (&quot;white firebird&quot; era) and continuing up until the Suzaku (vermilion bird era), the age was shrouded in darkness and distance, and it was very difficult to clarify our questioning.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its winter entry for the tenth month of 724, the &quot;Shoku nihongi&quot; includes the following description.</e>
<cmt>「冬十月条」の意味が明確ではありません。セルを分割し直しました。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its winter entry for the tenth month of 724, the &quot;Shoku nihongi&quot; includes the following description.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>「白鳳より以来、朱雀以前、年代玄遠にして、尋問明め難し。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Beginning in the Hakuho (&quot;white firebird&quot; era) and continuing up until the Suzaku (vermilion bird era), the age was shrouded in darkness and distance, and it was very difficult to clarify our questioning.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Beginning in the Hakuho (&quot;white firebird&quot; era) and continuing up until the Suzaku (vermilion bird era), the age was shrouded in darkness and distance, and it was very difficult to clarify our questioning.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>星空の朱雀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Suzaku constellation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Suzaku constellation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Suzaku constellation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>中国の星座である二十八宿（月の見かけ上の通り道である白道を28分したもの）は、四神の名によって7宿ずつ4つにまとめられ、それぞれが四神の姿をかたどるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 28 Moon Stations (or &quot;Mansions&quot;) of Chinese astrology (in which the moon&apos;s apparent course across the sky is split into 28 sections) are divided into four groups of seven stations, one group for each of the four directional gods, and each group was thought to model the appearance of its god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 28 constellations of Chinese astrology (in which the moon&apos;s apparent path across the sky is split into 28 sections) are divided into 4 groups of 7 constellations, 1 group for each of the 4 directional gods, and each group was thought to model the appearance of its god.</e>
<cmt>「28宿」については用語集を参照しましたが、ウェブ上にて&quot;28 constellations&quot;での記述が多く見られましたのでそのようにしました。moon&apos;s apparent course→moon&apos;s apparent path,four→4,seven stations→7 constellations,one→1 と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 28 constellations of Chinese astrology (in which the moon&apos;s apparent path across the sky is split into 28 sections) are divided into 4 groups of 7 constellations, 1 group for each of the 4 directional gods, and each group was thought to model the appearance of its god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>そのうちの1つ、南方朱雀に属する7宿のうち、中央の「星宿」は、西洋星座のうみへび座の心臓部に当たり、その中心は、うみへび座の主星アルファルドである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the seven moon stations grouped into the south, Suzaku&apos;s domain, the central station, called the &quot;star&quot; station, happens to be the heart of the Hydra constellation in Western astronomy; its central star is the principal star in the Hydra constellation, Alphard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the seven constellations grouped into the south, Suzaku&apos;s domain, the central constellation, called the &apos;Star&apos; is the heart of the Hydra constellation in Western astronomy; its central star is the principal star in the Hydra constellation, Alphard.</e>
<cmt>moon stations→constellations,station→constellation,star→Star,happen to be→is と修正しました。stationを削除しました。クォーツを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the seven constellations grouped into the south, Suzaku&apos;s domain, the central constellation, called the &apos;Star&apos; is the heart of the Hydra constellation in Western astronomy; its central star is the principal star in the Hydra constellation, Alphard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>「孤独な者」を意味する名をもつこの2等星は、明るい星の少ない中にあって目立つ星であり、「星」という宿名からもわかるように、中国の天文家にも、最も古くから知られてきた星の一つであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This second-magnitude star, whose name means &quot;solitary one,&quot; is in an area with few bright stars and thus seems to stand out; as can be inferred from their naming this station the &quot;star&quot; station, Chinese astronomers have known of this star since very ancient times, and indeed Alphard is one of the first stars to have been discovered by the Chinese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This second-magnitude star, whose name means &apos;the solitary one,&apos; is in an area with few bright stars and thus seems to stand out; as can be inferred from their naming this as &apos;Star&apos; constellation, Chinese astronomers have known of this star since very ancient times, and indeed Alphard is one of the first stars to have been discovered by the Chinese.</e>
<cmt>クォーツを修正しました。the を補いました。star→Star と修正し、文中ほどを文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This second-magnitude star, whose name means &apos;the solitary one,&apos; is in an area with few bright stars and thus seems to stand out; as can be inferred from their naming this as &apos;Star&apos; constellation, Chinese astronomers have known of this star since very ancient times, and indeed Alphard is one of the first stars to have been discovered by the Chinese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>このオレンジ色の星が、ライチョウなど羽色が橙色系の胸をもつ鳥とともに、「朱雀」という瑞鳥のイメージの成立に、何らかの形で関与している可能性もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This orange star, in addition to creating an image of the Ptarmigan or any other bird whose feathers are orange around the breast, specifically calls to mind the auspicious bird Suzaku; it is possible the star, then, may have influenced the Suzaku legend in some way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This orange colored star, in addition to creating an image of the Ptarmigan or any other birds whose feathers are orange around the breast, may also have possibly influenced the establishment of the image of this auspicious bird &apos;Suzaku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>colored を補いました。bird→birds と修正しました。クォーツを補いました。後半部分を文脈より修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This orange colored star, in addition to creating an image of the Ptarmigan or any other birds whose feathers are orange around the breast, may also have possibly influenced the establishment of the image of this auspicious bird &apos;Suzaku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>なお、同じ南方朱雀の「翼宿」は、朱雀の翼である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed, the &quot;Wing&quot; station, also in Suzaku&apos;s southerly group, represents Suzaku&apos;s wings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the &quot;Wings Manison,&quot; also in Suzaku&apos;s southerly group, represents Suzaku&apos;s wings.</e>
<cmt>Indeed→Furthermore と修正しました。「翼宿」は用語集を参照しましたが、ウェブ上で&quot;Wings Mansion&quot;での記述が多く見られるのでそのようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the &quot;Wings Manison,&quot; also in Suzaku&apos;s southerly group, represents Suzaku&apos;s wings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Novo(id:87875), GCN(id:268552), DragonBot(id:161936), Philolo(id:17346), 黄金もち(id:102311), Greenland4(id:114494), PipepBot(id:146181), Areiyo(id:27628), Su-no-G(id:52744), SpBot(id:209743), Janus01(id:69663), らりた(id:1327), Riku(id:16088), Whiz(id:15769), Mazbot(id:181195), 日陰のコスモス(id:3802), 十月之交(id:586), Chobot(id:20846), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Loveless(id:129239), 曼珠沙華(id:26417), Leo2006(id:48176), Mooning(id:68638), Izayohi(id:13095), U3002(id:66126), たね(id:10372), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Nallimbot(id:230812), Wilson Tam(id:17411), 怪盗蓬月(id:132496), Roots774(id:139464), Inukawa(id:842), Café au lait(id:30776), 彩華1226(id:64711), Tanuki Z(id:612), Yonoemon(id:55450), Vibakari(id:147034), Muro Bot(id:217619), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>