<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>寄人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriudo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriudo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>寄人（よりうど/よりゅうど）とは、平安時代以後中世にかけて用いられた一定の人々に対する呼称であるが、複数の意味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriudo/Yoryudo were a term used in the middle ages after the Heian period for calling certain people, but had multiple meanings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriudo/Yoryudo were terms used during the middle ages after the Heian period for certain people, but had multiple meanings.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriudo (Yoryudo) was a term used during the middle ages after the Heian period for certain people, but had multiple meanings.</e>
<cmt>yoriudo (yoryudo) としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>職制機関における寄人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriudo within a occupational institute</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriudo within an occupational institute</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriudo within an occupational institute</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>公家政権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuge (court nobles) Government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuge (court nobles) Government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuge (court nobles) government</e>
<cmt>小タイトルのため、小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>朝廷の官衙である和歌所・御書所・記録所・院文殿・後院などにおける職員を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indicates the staff that worked in Kanga (government office) of the imperial court such as Wakadokoro, Goshodokoro, Kirokujo (Land Record Office), Infumidono, Goin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indicates the staff that worked in Kanga (government office) of the imperial court such as Wakadokoro, Goshodokoro, Kirokujo (Land Record Office), Infumidono, Goin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates the staff that worked in Kanga (government office) of the Imperial Court such as Wakadokoro (office of waka), Goshodokoro (office to maintain books in the Imperial Court), Kirokujo (land record office), Infumidono (the retired emperor&apos;s documents bureau), Goin and so on.</e>
<cmt>役所の補足を一部追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>和歌所の場合は、召人（めしうど）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of Wakadokoro, they were also called Meshiudo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of Wakadokoro, they were also called Meshiudo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of Wakadokoro, they were also called meshiudo.</e>
<cmt>meshiudo 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>庶務・執務に精通した事務能力のある官人が選任された（和歌所の場合は、和歌の作成・選定能力がこれに替わる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Officials with administrative ability in general affairs and management were selected (in the case of Wakadokoro, ability to write and select waka poems was important).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Officials with administrative ability in general affairs and management were selected (in the case of Wakadokoro, ability to write and select waka poems was important).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Officials with administrative ability in general affairs and management were selected (in the case of Wakadokoro, ability to write and select waka poems was important).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>定員はおよそ10-20名で多くが他の官司からの出向・兼務で務めていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of personnel was about 10 to 20 and in many cases were sent or jointly appointed from other governmental offices.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of personnel was about ten to twenty and in many cases were sent or jointly appointed from other governmental offices.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of personnel was about 10 to 20 and in many cases were sent or jointly appointed from other governmental offices.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『類聚名物考』には、官司に「寄り合う人」を寄人と呼んだのが語源であると言われているが真偽は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ruijumeibutsuko (an encyclopedia compiled by Matsuake Yamaoka in the middle of Edo period) suggests that the origin of the word came from calling the people who &quot;came to gather&quot; at governmental offices as Yoriudo, but the actual origins are unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ruijumeibutsuko (an encyclopedia compiled by Matsuake Yamaoka during the middle of the Edo period) suggests that the origin of the word came from calling people who &quot;came to gather&quot; at governmental offices Yoriudo, but the actual origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ruiju meibutsu ko&quot; (an encyclopedia compiled by Matsuake YAMAOKA during the middle of the Edo period) suggests that the origin of the word came from calling people who &apos;came to gather&apos; at governmental offices yoriudo, but the actual origin is unknown.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>武家政権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military government</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military government</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>幕府の組織である公文所・政所・問注所・侍所に属する職員を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indicates the staff that worked at bakufu organizations such as Kumonjo (administration office), Mandokoro (Administrative Board), Monchujyo, the Office of Inquiry, and Samurai-dokoro (Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indicates the staff that worked at bakufu organizations such as Kumonjo (administration office), Mandokoro (Administrative Board), Monchujyo, the Office of Inquiry, and Samurai-dokoro (Board of Retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates the staff that worked at bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) organizations such as Kumonjo (administration office), Mandokoro (administrative board), Monchujo (court of justice), and Samuraidokoro (board of retainers).</e>
<cmt>役所の補足を一部追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>公人（くにん）とも呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also called Kunuin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also called Kunuin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also called kunin.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>書類の記録・作成の必要上、右筆などの経験者が任じられることもあり、執事・執事代・所司代・開闔などの幹部も寄人・公人から選ばれることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because it was necessary to record and prepare documents, experienced staff such as yuhitsu were appointed, and officers such as Shitsuji (steward), Shitsujidai (deputy steward), Shoshiidai and Kaigo were often selected from Yoriudo/Kunin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because it was necessary to record and prepare documents, experienced staff such as yuhitsu were appointed, and officers such as Shitsuji (steward), Shitsujidai (deputy steward), Shoshiidai and Kaigo were often selected from Yoriudo/Kunin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because it was necessary to record and prepare documents, experienced staff such as yuhitsu (amanuensis) were appointed, and officers such as Shitsuji (steward), Shitsujidai (deputy steward), Shoshiidai (representative of shoshi, a governor of the board of retainers) and Kaigo (assistant administrator) were often selected from yoriudo/kunin.</e>
<cmt>役職の補足を一部追加しました。yoriudo, kunin 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>民間における寄人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriudo among the public</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriudo among the public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriudo among the public</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>荘園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen (private manor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen (private manor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoen (private manor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>平安時代の荘園における特定の形態のもとで荘園領主（本家）の使役を受けた人々を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indicates the people who worked for the shoen landlord under a special agreement within the shoen during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indicates the people who worked for the shoen landlord under a special agreement within the shoen during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It indicates the people who worked for the shoen landlord (honke [the head family]) under a special agreement within the shoen during the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>本家　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>ただし、時期によってその意味合いは異なることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the meaning differed depending upon the time period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the meaning differed depending upon the time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the meaning differed depending upon the time period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>元は荘園に逃れてその隷属下に入って荘民化した浮浪・逃亡であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, it is thought to indicate the landless or exiles who escaped into shoen and became enslaved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, it was thought to indicate the landless or exiles who escaped into shoen and became enslaved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, it was thought to indicate the landless or exiles who escaped into shoen and became enslaved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>10世紀中頃より国衙から課される臨時雑役の賦課の免除を受けた荘民を指して寄人と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoriudo was used to indicated the shoen people who were exempt from temporary Zoyaku (odd-jobs task) taxed by the Kokuga from the middle of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoriudo was used to indicated the shoen people who were exempt from temporary Zoyaku (odd-jobs task) taxed by the Kokuga from the middle of the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoriudo was used to indicated the shomin (shoen people) who were exempt from temporary zoyaku (odd-jobs task) taxed by the Kokuga (provincial government offices) from the middle of the 10th century.</e>
<cmt>国衙　補足を追加しました。荘民　追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これに対して、対象にならなかった荘民は公領耕作者とともに公民と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen people who were not exempt and Koryo (public land) farmers were called Komin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen people who were not exempt and Koryo (public land) farmers were called Komin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shomin who were not exempt as well as koryo (public land) farmers were called komin (public people).</e>
<cmt>公民→public people と補足しました。（定訳不明です）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ところが、後に公民でありながら、臨時雑役免除の特権を持つ荘園の一部を耕作してそこに寄人として帰属して二重の隷属関係を持つことで、本来の耕作地を含めた臨時雑役の免除を図ろうとするものも現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in later years, some komin had a multiple vassal relationship by farming a part of a shoen that had temporary zoyaku exemption rights and belonged there as a Yoriudo as well and tried to get exempt from temporary zoyaku for their main farming lands as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in later years, some komin had a multiple vassal relationship by farming a part of a shoen that had temporary zoyaku exemption rights and belonged there as a Yoriudo as well and tried to be exempt from temporary zoyaku for their main farm lands as well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in later years, some komin had a multiple vassal relationship by farming a part of a shoen that had temporary zoyaku exemption rights and belonged there as a yoriudo as well and tried to be exempt from temporary zoyaku for their main farm lands as well.</e>
<cmt>yoriudo 小文字で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これに対して荘園領主もこれを受け入れて反対にこれを利用して彼らが本来耕していた耕作地（公領や他の荘園耕地）を自己に収めようとする者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some Shoen landowners accepted such people and used this to try and make the farming land (Koryo and other shoen farming lands) that they farmed as their own property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Shoen landowners accepted such people and used this to try and make the farm land (Koryo and other shoen farm lands) that they farmed their own property.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some shoen landowners accepted such people and used this to try and make the farm land (koryo and other shoen farm lands) that they farmed their own property.</e>
<cmt>shoen, koryo で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>こうした事態の放置は公領の減少のみならず、荘園間の境相論を引き起こす一因となったため、荘園整理令などで度々寄人を規制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This situation led to not only the reduction of Koryo but also a factor for boundary disputes between shoen and Yoriudo were regulated again and again by Manor Regulation Acts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This situation led to not only the reduction of Koryo but also became a factor for boundary disputes between shoen and Yoriudo that were regulated again and again by Manor Regulation Acts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This situation led to not only the reduction of koryo but also became a factor for boundary disputes between shoen, therefore yoriudo were regulated again and again by Manor Regulation Acts.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>11世紀中頃以後、不入の権 (日本)の拡大とともに一円支配が確立され、荘園内に居住するものは全て荘民として荘園領主に帰属されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the middle of the eleventh century, together with the expansion of Funyu rights, Ichien shihai (reigning of whole regions) became established and all those who lived within a shoen were under the rule of the shoen landowner as shoen people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the middle of the eleventh century, together with the expansion of Funyu rights, Ichien shihai (reigning of whole regions) became established and all those who lived within a shoen were under the rule of the shoen landowner as shoen people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the middle of the 11th century, together with the expansion of Funyu rights (Japan), Ichien shihai (reigning of whole regions) became established and all those who lived within a shoen were under the rule of the shoen landowner as shomin.</e>
<cmt>11th アラビア数字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>このため、荘園内に残されていた臨時雑役免除などを持たなかった公民と寄人の差は実質上消滅することになり、以後は荘民という語が用いられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the difference within the shoen between komin and Yoriudo such as whether they were exempt from temporary Zoyaku disappeared in actuality and the term Shomin (shoen person) was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the difference within the shoen between komin and Yoriudo such as whether they were exempt from temporary Zoyaku disappeared in actuality and the term Shomin (shoen person) was used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the difference within the shoen between komin and yoriudo such as whether they were exempt from temporary zoyaku disappeared in actuality and the term shomin was used subsequently.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>商工業者</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merchants and craftsmen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merchants and craftsmen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merchants and craftsmen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="20">
<j>また、荘園と同様に商工業者・職能人の間でも荘園の寄人のように特定の権門の隷属下に入ってその庇護を受けた者も寄人と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As with shoen, among merchants and craftsmen, people who belonged to a specific power structure and received protection were called Yoriudo, similar to the yoriudo of shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As with shoen, among merchants and craftsmen, people who belonged to a specific power structure and received protection were called Yoriudo, similar to the yoriudo of shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As with shoen, among merchants and craftsmen, people who belonged to a specific power structure and received protection were called yoriudo, similar to the yoriudo of shoen.</e>
<cmt>yoriudo 小文字で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>神人・供御人・散所雑色もその一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jinin (associates of Shinto shrines), Kugonin (purveyors to the imperial household), and Sanjozoshiki (low-level functionary) were one form of this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jinin (associates of Shinto shrines), Kugonin (purveyors to the imperial household), and Sanjozoshiki (low-level functionary) were examples of this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jinin (associates of Shinto shrines), Kugonin (purveyors to the imperial household), and Sanjozoshiki (low-level functionary) were examples of this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>その職業の性格上、その居住地とつながる権門以外の権門に属したり、複数の権門の寄人になる例もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the characteristics of their occupation, some would belong to a power structure other than that related with their living area or become Yoriudo of various power structures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the characteristics of their occupation, some would belong to a power structure other than that related with their living area or became Yoriudo of various power structures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the characteristics of their occupation, some would belong to a power structure other than that related with their living area or became yoriudo of various power structures.</e>
<cmt>yoriudo 小文字で統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>中世における座の形成にも寄人集団の関与が指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is suggested that the establishment of Za in the middle ages may also been influenced by Yoriudo groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is suggested that the establishment of Za in the middle ages may also been influenced by Yoriudo groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is suggested that the establishment of Za in the middle ages may also have been influenced by yoriudo groups.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>