<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>陶部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suebe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suebe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suebe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>陶部（すえべ・陶作部（すえつくりべ））とは、大化前代において須恵器の製造に携わった部。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suebe (or Suetsukuribe) was a group of people who were engaged in manufacturing Sueki (unglazed ware) before 645.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suebe (or Suetsukuribe) was a group of people who were engaged in manufacturing Sueki (unglazed ware) before Taika period.</e>
<cmt>・「大化の改新」ではなく元号の「大化」を指すと思われます：645→Taika period</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suebe (or Suetsukuribe) was a group of people who were engaged in manufacturing Sueki (unglazed ware) before Taika period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>須恵器及びその製造技法は古墳時代に朝鮮半島南部から伝えられたとされ、5世紀初めには茅渟県陶邑（現在の大阪府堺市中区 (堺市)・南区 (堺市)付近）などで大規模な須恵器の製造が行われて、陶部の形成が行われたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sueki and its producing technique are said to have been introduced from the Southern area of the Korean Peninsula in the Kofun period, and Suebe is considered to have been formed to manufacture Sueki in Suemura, Chinu Province (present-day near Naka Ward and Minami Ward, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture) in the beginning of the 5th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sueki and its producing technique are said to have been introduced from the Southern area of the Korean Peninsula in the Kofun period, and Suebe is considered to have been formed to manufacture Sueki on a large scale in Suemura, Chinu Province and other places (present-day near Naka Ward and Minami Ward, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture) in the beginning of the 5th century.</e>
<cmt>「大規模に」「など」を訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sueki and its producing technique are said to have been introduced from the Southern area of the Korean Peninsula in the Kofun period, and Suebe is considered to have been formed to manufacture Sueki on a large scale in Suemura, Chinu Province and other places (present-day near Naka Ward and Minami Ward, Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture) in the beginning of the 5th century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>『日本書紀』の垂仁天皇3年（紀元前27年）条には、近江国鏡村に日本に渡来した新羅の王子天日槍の従者であった陶人がいたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article of 27 B.C. in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), it says that in Kagami Village, Omi Province, there was a craftsman of Suebe who served the prince of Silla, Amenohiboko, who came to Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article of 27 B.C. in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), it says that in Kagami Village, Omi Province, there was a craftsman of Suebe who served the prince of Silla, Amenohiboko, who came to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article of 27 B.C. in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan), it says that in Kagami Village, Omi Province, there was a craftsman of Suebe who served the prince of Silla, Amenohiboko, who came to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、雄略天皇7年（463年）条には百済より陶部高貴ら工人が貢がれたことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the article of 463, it says that craftsmen including SUETSUKURI-no-Koki were presented as tributes from Baekje.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the article of 463, it says that craftsmen including SUETSUKURI-no-Koki were presented as tributes from Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the article of 463, it says that craftsmen including SUETSUKURI-no-Koki were presented as tributes from Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>これを直ちに事実とすることには問題があるものの、陶部の工人（陶人）が新羅や百済の出身を多く抱えていたことの反映とみる考え方がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this is not a certain fact but may reflect the fact that Suebe had a lot of craftsmen from Silla and Baekje.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This could not be soon regarded as a fact, but may be considered as a reflection of the fact that many of the Suebe craftsmen came from Silla and Baekje.</e>
<cmt>全体を改変しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This could not be soon regarded as a fact, but may be considered as a reflection of the fact that many of the Suebe craftsmen came from Silla and Baekje.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>ただし、陶部が属していた伴部は明らかではなく、律令制（少なくても養老律令）の下で特定の官司に所属した伴部・品部・雑戸になったことを示す記録も存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">t is unknown which official supervised Suebe and there is no document that recorded Suebe became Tomobe (administrative officials), Shinabe and Zakko (groups of technicians), who belonged to a specific government official, under the Ritsuryo system (especially, Yoro Ritsuryo Code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is unknown which official supervised Suebe and there is no record that shows Suebe became Tomobe (administrative officials), Shinabe and Zakko (groups of technicians), who belonged to a specific government official, under the Ritsuryo system (especially, Yoro Ritsuryo Code).</e>
<cmt>there is no document that recorded→there is no record that shows</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is unknown which official supervised Suebe and there is no record that shows Suebe became Tomobe (administrative officials), Shinabe and Zakko (groups of technicians), who belonged to a specific government official, under the Ritsuryo system (especially, Yoro Ritsuryo Code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このため、遅くても8世紀には陶部は解体して、民間の工人集団に吸収され、朝廷は調や正税交易などの方法で民間から須恵器などの土器類を調達するようになったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, Suebe was dissolved and its members were absorbed in a private group of craftsmen in the eighth century at the latest, and the Imperial Court was considered to have been given earth wares including Sueki from private sectors through tributes or exchanges with the rice tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, Suebe was dissolved and its members were absorbed in a private group of craftsmen in the eighth century at the latest, and the Imperial Court was considered to have been given earth wares including Sueki from private sectors through tributes or exchanges with the rice tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, Suebe was dissolved and its members were absorbed in a private group of craftsmen in the eighth century at the latest, and the Imperial Court was considered to have been given earth wares including Sueki from private sectors through tributes or exchanges with the rice tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>