<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>解 (公文書)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ge (Official Documents)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ge (Official Documents)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ge (Official Documents)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>解（げ）とは、律令制において下級の官司（被管）より上級の官司（所管）にあてて提出される公文書のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ge was an official document from a lower grade governmental official (hikan) to a higher grade official (shokan) in the ritsuryo sytem.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A &quot;ge&quot; was an official document submitted by a lower grade governmental official (hikan) to a higher grade official (shokan) in the ritsuryo sytem (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。律令制の説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A &quot;ge&quot; was an official document submitted by a lower grade governmental official (hikan) to a higher grade official (shokan) in the ritsuryo sytem (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>公式令 (律令法)にその書式が定められており、冒頭に「（下級官司）解申其事（げしもうすそのこと）」と記し、内容を記載後書止として、太政官充てであれば「謹解（つつしんでげす）」・それ以外の官司であれば「以解（もってげす）」と記してくくり、その後に年月日、上申者とその所属官司を構成する全員の官位姓名を記載することになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its form was ordained in Kushiki-ryo (ritsuryo law); It should begin with &quot;解申其事 (Geshi-mosu-tono-koto)&quot;, ending in &quot;謹解 (tsutsushinde gesu) if the document was to the Daijokan (Grand Council of State) or 以解 (motte-gesu) if it was to other officials after writing contents and under it the date, the name of the writer and ranks and names of all the members of his office should be written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its form was ordained in Kushiki-ryo (Ritsuryo law) which had to begin with &apos;(lower grade governmental official) 解申其事 (geshimosu sonokoto)&apos;, and after finishing the document, if the document was to Daijokan (Grand Council of State), it had to end with &apos;謹解 (tsutsushinde gesu)&apos;, or if the document was to other officials, it had to end with &apos;以解 (mottegesu)&apos;, and after the ending word, the date, the name of the writer and ranks and names of all the members of his office had to be written.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its form was ordained in Kushiki-ryo (Ritsuryo law) which had to begin with &apos;(lower grade governmental official) 解申其事 (geshimosu sonokoto)&apos;, and after finishing the document, if the document was to Daijokan (Grand Council of State), it had to end with &apos;謹解 (tsutsushinde gesu)&apos;, or if the document was to other officials, it had to end with &apos;以解 (mottegesu)&apos;, and after the ending word, the date, the name of the writer and ranks and names of all the members of his office had to be written.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>律令制においては官司の上下関係は明確であるため、解の提出先である上級官司は自ずから定まっており、差出所である下級官司の名称は記載されていても、宛所である上級官司は記載しないことになっていた（職 (律令制)・寮 (律令制)・司・郡→八省・国司→太政官）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because in the ritsuryo system the hierarchical relationship between government officials was so clear that the superior officers that lower officers reported to were fixed accordingly, therefore, in a ge the name of a reporter (lower officer) was written, while that of a receiver (superior officer) was not (Shoku [ritsuryo system]/Ryo [ritsuryo system]/Tsukasa/Gun.=&gt;Hassho/Kokushi=&gt;Dajokan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the hierarchical relationship among government officials was clearly defined in the ritsuryo system, the upper grade officials to whom lower grade officials had to submit ge were fixed accordingly, therefore, it was necessary to write the name of the reporter, lower grade official, while that of a receiver, higher grade official, was not written (Shoku [ritsuryo system]/Ryo [ritsuryo system]/Tsukasa/Gun=&gt;Hassho/Kokushi=&gt;Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>最後の括弧内の訳が不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the hierarchical relationship among government officials was clearly defined in the ritsuryo system, the upper grade officials to whom lower grade officials had to submit ge were fixed accordingly, therefore, it was necessary to write the name of the reporter, lower grade official, while that of a receiver, higher grade official, was not written (Shoku [ritsuryo system]/Ryo [ritsuryo system]/Tsukasa/Gun-&gt;Hassho/Kokushi-&gt;Dajokan).</e>
<cmt>記号調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、例外として神祇官と太政官の間では、神祇官が太政官側に解を出すことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as an exception, between the Jingikan (Department of Divinities) and the Daijokan (Grand Council of State), the Jingikan gave ge to the dajokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as an exception, when Jingikan (officer of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) was to submit ge, they had to present it to Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>スペースを半角に修正しました。原文にそって修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as an exception, when Jingikan (officer of the institution for dedicating to religious ceremony) was to submit ge, they had to present it to Daijokan (Grand Council of State).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、本来は令外官や寺社より太政官に上申する場合には牒が用いられ、個人が役所に出す文書には辞などが用いられていたが、後にはこれらの文書も一括して解として処理されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally when Ryoge no kan and temples and shrines submitted a report to the Dajokan, a 牒(cho) was used and when individuals did, a 辞 (ji) was used; In later years these monjo (written materials) were put together and dealt with as a 解 (ge).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally a cho (one of the styles of official documents in the ritsuryo system) was used for when Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) and temples and shrines submitted an official report to the Daijokan and a ji (an official document submitted to Guji [chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs] by the general public and lower grade officials) for individuals, however, in later years these monjo (written materials) were put together and dealt with as a ge.</e>
<cmt>（）で英文の説明を加え、原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally a cho (one of the styles of official documents in the ritsuryo system) was used for when Ryoge no kan (a post outside the original Ritsuryo code created by Imperial edicts) and temples and shrines submitted an official report to the Daijokan and a ji (an official document submitted to Guji [chief of those who serves shrine, controls festivals and general affairs] by the general public and lower grade officials) for individuals, however, in later years these monjo (written materials) were put together and dealt with as a ge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>更には民間も含めて下位者から上位者に出す文書は全て「解」と称されるようになるが、これは、律令制以前においては上申は全て口頭で申すことを原則としていたが、解の書式がその手続をそのまま文書化したための名残が反映されたものとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, including ordinary citizens, all monjo to be submitted from a person in lower rank to a person in higher rank came to be referred as &quot;ge&quot;; before the ritsuryo system all reports should be given orally, however, their procedures were taken place by a ge form, therefore it is said that calling all monjo &quot;ge&quot; was a reflection of such a change.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, including ordinary citizens, all monjo to be submitted from a person in lower rank to a person in higher rank came to be referred to as &apos;ge&apos;, which was because all reports had been given orally before the ritsuryo system, and calling all monjo ge has been said to be a reflection of the fact that the ge form put all the oral procedures of monjo in writing.</e>
<cmt>内容に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, all monjo to be submitted from a person with a lower rank (including ordinary citizens) to a person with a higher rank came to be referred to as &apos;ge,&apos; which was because all reports had been given orally before the ritsuryo system, and calling all monjo &quot;ge&quot; is said to be a reflection of the fact that the &quot;ge&quot; form put all the oral procedures for monjo in writing.</e>
<cmt>カンマの位置を調整原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Blue-comet(id:192801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>