<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>針博士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hari Hakase (Doctor of acupuncture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hari Hakase (Doctor of acupuncture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hari Hakase</e>
<cmt>タイトルのため、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>針博士（はりはかせ）は、宮内省典薬寮に属する職員の1つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hari Hakase is a member of Tenyakuryo (medical and pharmaceutical department) of Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hari Hakase is a member of Tenyakuryo (medical and pharmaceutical department) of the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hari hakase (Doctor of acupuncture) is a member of Tenyakuryo (medical and pharmaceutical department) of the Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>針博士　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>従七位下相当。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equivalent to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is equivalent to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is equivalent to Jushichiinoge (Junior Seventh Rank, Lower Grade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>定員1名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fixed number of seat was one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fixed number of seats was one.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fixed number of seats was one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>針生の教育と針師の監督を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hari Hakaser educated the students of acupuncture and supervised acupuncturists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hari Hakase educated the students of acupuncture and supervised acupuncturists.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hari hakase educated the students of acupuncture and supervised acupuncturists.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせ、hakase を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>針生（定員30名）は、針博士の下で基礎教養2年及び専門教育7年（実技及び専門書の講読）を受けた後、針博士による卒業・任官試験を受けて合格したものが針師として針治療の実務にあたる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the students of acupuncture (limited to 30 people) finished 2 year basic course and 7years professional training (skill practice and technical book reading) under a Hari Hakase, they took the final and commissioning exam held by their Hari Hakase and those who passed it started acupuncture treatment as acupuncturists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the students of acupuncture (limited to 30 people) finished a two year basic course and seven years of professional training (skill practice and technical book reading) under a Hari Hakase, they took the final and commissioning exam held by their Hari Hakase and those who passed it started acupuncture treatment as acupuncturists.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the students of acupuncture (limited to 30 people) finished a two year basic course and seven years of professional training (skill practice and technical book reading) under a Hari hakase, they took the final and commissioning exam held by their Hari Hakase and those who passed it started acupuncture treatment as acupuncturists.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせ、hakase を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>更にその中の優秀者から針博士は選任されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hari Hakase was selected from top performers among graduates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hari Hakase was selected from top performers among graduates.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hari hakase was selected from top performers among graduates.</e>
<cmt>他の記事と合わせ、hakase を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 新アルパカ(id:65850), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>