<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>猶子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushi (privately adopted child)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushi (privately adopted child)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushi (privately adopted child)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>猶子（ゆうし）とは、明治以前において存在した他人の子供を自分の子として親子関係を結ぶこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushi is a system existed prior to the Meiji period where parent-child relationship was privately contracted as if other person&apos;s child were a person&apos;s own child.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushi is a system that existed prior to the Meiji period to establish a parent-child relationship with a child who was not kin.</e>
<cmt>翻訳が原文と少し意味が離れていたためと自然な表現にするため、文章を1部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushi is a system that existed prior to the Meiji period to establish a parent-child relationship with a child who was not kin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ただし、養子縁組とは違い、契約関係によって成立し、子供の姓は変わらないなど親子関係の結びつきが弱く擬制的な側面（その子の後見人となる）が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However it was different from adoption; in Yushi system, the parent-child relationship was weak－the relation was made under a contract, and the surname of the child was not changed and the rest－with strong pseudo color (like becoming a godfather of the child).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike adoption, however, Yushi was based on a contract and had a weak connection, and a child&apos;s surname was not changed, so it was rather a fictitious parent-child relationship (in which a parent became guardian in many cases).</e>
<cmt>原文の語順と違って翻訳されているので、文を一部変更しました。擬制的の訳をpseudo color　→ fictitiousに変更、後見人をguardianに変更</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike adoption, however, Yushi was based on a contract and had a weak connection, and a child&apos;s surname was not changed, so it was rather a fictitious parent-child relationship (in which a parent became guardian in many cases).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>元は古代中国において兄弟の子を指したともいわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the word Yushi originally meant a child of siblings in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the word Yushi originally meant a child of siblings in the ancient China.</e>
<cmt>古代　訳抜けのためancientを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the word Yushi originally meant a child of siblings in the ancient China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>記録上に残る最も古いケースは源定が淳和天皇の猶子になったことであると言われているが、平安時代後期までは猶子と養子の違いは明確ではなかったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest case on the record was said to be that of MINAMOTO no Sadamu who became the Yusi of Emperor Junna, but till the late Heian period the difference between Yushi and adoption is believed to be not so clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest record of Yushi was allegedly the one of MINAMOTO no Sadamu who became the Yushi of Emperor Junna, but the difference between Yushi and Yoshi (adoption) is said to be not so clear until the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>英語表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest record of Yushi was allegedly the one of MINAMOTO no Sadamu who became the Yushi of Emperor Junna, but the difference between Yushi and Yoshi (adoption) is said to be not so clear until the late Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>貞観_(日本)14年10月10日_(旧暦)の右大臣藤原基経（藤原長良の子）の上表文に自分が叔父である故藤原良房（元摂政太政大臣）の猶子であったことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was written on a Johyobun (memorial to the Emperor), on November 18, 872, of FUJIWARA no Mototsune－who was then the Minister of the Right and a child of FURIWARA no Nagara－that he was the Yushi of late FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa (ex-Sessho Daijo daijin [ex-Regent and the Grand Minister]); Yoshifusa did not have other child and his privilege of Oni (an automatic promotion system in which an Imperial title are conferred) and the family property were inherited to Mototsune, therefore today this is regarded as not Yushi but an adoption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was written in a Johyobun (memorial to the Emperor) dated November 18, 872 of FUJIWARA no Mototsune, who was then the Minister of the Right and a child of FURIWARA no Nagara, that he was the Yushi of his uncle, late FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa (former Sessho Daijo daijin [Regent and the Grand Minister])</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処で文のセミコロン以下の文章を下のセルに移動しました。叔父である　訳抜けex → formerに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was written in a Johyobun (memorial to the Emperor) dated November 18, 872 of FUJIWARA no Mototsune, who was then the Minister of the Right and a child of FURIWARA no Nagara, that he was the Yushi of his uncle, late FUJIWARA no Yoshifusa (former Sessho Daijo daijin [Regent and the Grand Minister])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、良房に他に男子はなく、蔭位と家産は基経に継がれていることから今日では養子と解されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Yoshifusa did not have other son and the privilege of Oni (an automatic promotion system in which an Imperial title are conferred) and the family property were inherited by Mototsune, therefore today it is regarded as Yoshi (adoption), not Yushi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処（原文に「しかし」を追加しました）男子　childをsonに訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Yoshifusa did not have other son and the privilege of Oni (an automatic promotion system in which an Imperial title are conferred) and the family property were inherited by Mototsune, therefore today it is regarded as Yoshi (adoption), not Yushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、具平親王の子・源師房は源氏の姓のまま姉婿である関白藤原頼通の猶子になったが、当時の記録では「異姓の養子」（『小右記』）と書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And also, MINAMOTO no Morofusa (a child of Imperial Prince Tomohira) became the Yushi of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, who was the husband of his older sister and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) and never changed his surname, but according to a record of that time he was written as the `adopted child with different surname` (&quot;Shoyuki&quot;[the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, MINAMOTO no Morofusa (a child of Imperial Prince Tomohira) became the Yushi of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, who was the husband of his older sister and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) with his surname of Minamoto unchanged, but the record of that time described him as the &quot;adopted child with different surname&quot; (&quot;Shoyuki&quot;[the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke]).</e>
<cmt>he was writtenは不自然なため、described him as に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, MINAMOTO no Morofusa (a child of Imperial Prince Tomohira) became the Yushi of FUJIWARA no Yorimichi, who was the husband of his older sister and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) with his surname of Minamoto unchanged, but the record of that time described him as the &quot;adopted child with different surname&quot; (&quot;Shoyuki&quot;[the diary of FUJIWARA no Sanesuke]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、藤原邦綱の子の平清邦のように平清盛の猶子になってそのまま平氏に姓を改めた例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another case was TAIRA no Kiyokuni who was the child of FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna and became the Yushi of TAIRA no Kiyomori, then changed his surname to TAIRA as if it was the way things should be.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another case was TAIRA no Kiyokuni who was the child of FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, became the Yushi of TAIRA no Kiyomori, and then changed his surname to TAIRA.</e>
<cmt>as if it was the way things should beを削除しました（「そのまま」の直訳ですがこの場合は不要だと考えます）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another case was TAIRA no Kiyokuni who was the child of FUJIWARA no Kunitsuna, became the Yushi of TAIRA no Kiyomori, and then changed his surname to TAIRA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>鎌倉時代には養子との区別が明確化して武士や僧侶の間にも広まっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the difference between Yushi and an adopted child became clear and this practice was widely spread even among samurai and Buddhist monks; (however in later years there were some cases where a parent had no real child and Yushi became heir－but these are understood as exceptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura period, the difference between Yushi and an adopted child became clear and the practice was widely spread even among samurai and Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the difference between Yushi and an adopted child became clear and the practice was widely spread even among samurai and Buddhist monks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>（ただし、後世においても例外的に実子が無かった場合に猶子を相続人にする例も存在したが、これは特例として考えられる。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Though in later years there were some cases that a parent had no real child and Yushi became heir, they were regarded as exceptions.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Though in later years there were some cases that a parent had no real child and Yushi became heir, they were regarded as exceptions.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>猶子の目的としては、次の事などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The objects of Yushi were as the followings:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The objectives of Yushi were as the follows:</e>
<cmt>as the followings →　as the follows</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The objectives of Yushi were as the follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>1. 官位などの昇進上の便宜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Advantages in promotion such as Kani (official court rank)．</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1. Advantages in promotion such as Kani (official court rank)</e>
<cmt>原文に1.を追加しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1. Advantages in promotion such as Kani (official court rank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>2. 婚姻上の便宜</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">advantages in marriage</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">2. Advantages in marriage</e>
<cmt>原文に2.を追加しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">2. Advantages in marriage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>3. 他の氏族との関係強化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">strengthening of relationship with other clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">3. Strengthening of relationship with other clan</e>
<cmt>原文に3.を追加しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">3. Strengthening of relationship with other clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>1．の代表例としては、足利義満の猶子となった満済や皇位継承の箔付けのために後小松上皇の猶子となった伏見宮彦仁王（後花園天皇）、そして近衛前久の猶子として関白に就任した豊臣秀吉などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the typical cases of 1., the following cases－Mansai who became the Yushi of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, Prince Hikohito of Fushimi no miya (Emperor GoHanazono) who became the Yushi of the retired Emperor Gokomatsu in order to add dignity for his succession to the Imperial Throne, and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) as the Yushi of Sakihisa KONOE－can be pointed out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical examples of 1. include Mansai who became the Yushi of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, Prince Hikohito of Fushimi no miya (Emperor Gohanazono) who became the Yushi of the retired Emperor Gokomatsu in order to add dignity for his succession to the Imperial Throne, and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) as the Yushi of Sakihisa KONOE.</e>
<cmt>自然な文章にするために変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical examples of 1. include Mansai who became the Yushi of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, Prince Hikohito of Fushimi no miya (Emperor Gohanazono) who became the Yushi of the retired Emperor Gokomatsu in order to add dignity for his succession to the Imperial Throne, and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI who became Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor) as the Yushi of Sakihisa KONOE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="16">
<j>2．の代表例としては、藤原能信の猶子として後三条天皇に入内して白河天皇を生んだ藤原茂子や後白河法皇の猶子として高倉天皇に入内して安徳天皇を生んだ平徳子などが有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the typical cases of 2., the following cases－FUJIWARA no Moshi who became the Yushi of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu and married with Emperor Gosanjo to give birth to Emperor Shirakawa, and TAIRA no Tokuko who became the Yushi of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and married with Emperor Takakura to give birth to Emperor Antoku－were famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the typical examples of 2., FUJIWARA no Moshi who became the Yushi of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu and married with Emperor Gosanjo to give birth to Emperor Shirakawa, and TAIRA no Tokuko who became the Yushi of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and married with Emperor Takakura to give birth to Emperor Antoku are well-known.</e>
<cmt>自然な文章にするために変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the typical examples of 2., FUJIWARA no Moshi who became the Yushi of FUJIWARA no Yoshinobu and married with Emperor Gosanjo to give birth to Emperor Shirakawa, and TAIRA no Tokuko who became the Yushi of the Cloistered Emperor Goshirakawa and married with Emperor Takakura to give birth to Emperor Antoku are well-known.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="17">
<j>3．の代表例としては、小山政光の猶子となって同盟を結んだ宇都宮頼綱や羽柴（豊臣）秀吉の猶子となってその後見で家督を継いだ宇喜多秀家などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the typical cases of 3., the following cases －Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA who became the Yushi of Masamitsu OYAMA making an alliance with him, and Hideie UKITA who became the Yushi of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (TOYOTOMI) and succeeded the reigns of the UKITA clan under his guardian－ can be cited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical examples of 3. included Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA who became the Yushi of Masamitsu OYAMA and made an alliance with him, and Hideie UKITA who became the Yushi of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (TOYOTOMI) and succeeded the reigns of the UKITA clan under his guardian.</e>
<cmt>自然な文章にするために変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical examples of 3. included Yoritsuna UTSUNOMIYA who became the Yushi of Masamitsu OYAMA and made an alliance with him, and Hideie UKITA who became the Yushi of Hideyoshi HASHIBA (TOYOTOMI) and succeeded the reigns of the UKITA clan under his guardian.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="18">
<j>ただし、稀に不幸な結末を迎えた猶子関係も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there have been few rare parent-Yushi relationship which met with wretched endings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there have been few rare cases that Yushi relationship ended in tragedy.</e>
<cmt>which met with wretched endings　→　ended in tragedyに変更しました（自然な英語にするため）</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there have been few rare cases that Yushi relationship ended in tragedy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>兄藤原忠通の猶子になりながら保元の乱でその兄と争った藤原頼長、叔父源実朝の猶子になりながらその叔父を暗殺した公暁などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Yorinaga who became the Yushi of his older brother FUJIWARA no Tadamichi but fought with this very brother at Hogen War, and Kugyo who became the Yushi of his uncle, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, and assassinated that uncle were among the unfortunate ones.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga who became the Yushi of his older brother FUJIWARA no Tadamichi fought with his brother at Hogen War, and Kugyo who became the Yushi of his uncle, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, assassinated his uncle uncle.</e>
<cmt>翻訳文が主語が長すぎて文章のバランスがよくないので、文章を変更しました。などであるを訳出するためFor exampleを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga who became the Yushi of his older brother FUJIWARA no Tadamichi fought with his brother at Hogen War, and Kugyo who became the Yushi of his uncle, MINAMOTO no Sanetomo, assassinated his uncle uncle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Point136(id:211299), MBP(id:93853), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>