<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>横山城 (近江国)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokoyama-jo Castle (in Omi Province)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokoyama-jo Castle (in Omi Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokoyama-jo Castle (in Omi Province)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>横山城（よこやまじょう）は近江国坂田郡（滋賀県長浜市堀部町・石田町）にあった城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokoyama-jo Castle was located in Sakata-gun, Omi Province (presently Horibe and Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokoyama-jo Castle was located in Sakata-gun, Omi Province (the present-day Horibe and Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokoyama-jo Castle was located in Sakata County, Omi Province (the present-day Horibe and Ishida-cho, Nagahama City, Shiga Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>gun→county</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a castle located on a mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a castle situated on a mountain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a castle situated on a mountain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>元亀年間（1570年‐1573年）の織田信長と浅井長政の激しい戦いの拠点であり、信長の部将であった木下秀吉（のちの豊臣秀吉）が城番として守備していたことで知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is known as the base of the heavy battle between Nobunaga ODA and Nagamasa AZAI from 1570 to 1573 and the place where Hideyoshi KINOSHITA (future Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) defended as a guard when he was a head of Nobunaga&apos;s corp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is known as the base of heavy fighting between Nobunaga ODA and Nagamasa AZAI from 1570 to 1573 and the place where Hideyoshi KINOSHITA (the future Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) defended as a guard when he was the head of Nobunaga&apos;s corps.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is known as the base of heavy fighting between Nobunaga ODA and Nagamasa AZAI from 1570 to 1573 and the place where Hideyoshi KINOSHITA (the future Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) defended as a guard when he was the commander of Nobunaga&apos;s corps.</e>
<cmt>Nobunaga’s→Nobunaga&apos;shead→commander</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>横山城は近江北部の浅井郡と坂田郡とを分ける姉川の南岸の山の峰続きに永禄3年（1561年）、浅井長政が対六角氏用の防衛拠点として築城させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yokoyama-jo Castle was constructed on a ridge of the mountain chain on the south side of the Ane-gawa River running between Azai-gun and Sakata-gun by Nagamasa AZAI as a defence base against the Rokkaku clan in 1561.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yokoyama-jo Castle was constructed in 1561 on a ridge of the mountain chain on the south side of the Ane-gawa River running between Azai-gun and Sakata-gun by Nagamasa AZAI as a based of defense against the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yokoyama-jo Castle was constructed in 1561 on a ridge of the mountain chain on the south side of the Ane-gawa River running between Azai County and Sakata County by Nagamasa AZAI as a base of defense against the Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>gun→countyagainst の前のスペース短縮as a based→as a base</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>城主には一門の浅井井演を任命した｡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ihiro Azai from the clan was appointed as the lord of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ihiro Azai, from the clan, was appointed as the lord of the castle.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ihiro Azai, from the clan, was appointed as the lord of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>その後浅井氏は勢力を伸張して坂田郡から犬上郡まで勢力を広げるが、元亀元年（1570年）、織田信長と交戦状態になり、再び横山城の重要性が高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the Azai clan expanded its power from Sakata-gun to Inukami-gun, but in 1570 it started a war with Nobunaga ODA, by which the importance of Yokoyama-jo Castle rose again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, the Azai clan expanded its power from Sakata-gun to Inukami-gun, but in 1570 it started a war with Nobunaga ODA, by which the importance of Yokoyama-jo Castle emerged again.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, the Azai clan expanded its power from Sakata County to Inukami County, but in 1570 it started a war with Nobunaga ODA, by which the importance of Yokoyama-jo Castle emerged again.</e>
<cmt>gun→county</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>横山城は美濃国の関ヶ原（岐阜県関ケ原町）から浅井氏の本拠地である小谷城（滋賀県湖北町）の西側を通る北陸脇往還街道のすぐ脇に立地するうえに、小谷城から6-7kmほどの距離しかないため、織田信長は重要な前線基地として横山城の攻略を目指した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Yokoyama-jo Castle was located in Sekigahara of Mino Province (presently Sekigahara-cho in Gifu Prefecture) and near Hokuriku-wakiokan road running through the west side of the base of the Azai clan, Odani-jo Castle (in Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture) and located only 6-7km from Odani-jo Castle, Nobunaga ODA attempted to capture Yokoyama-jo Castle as an important front-line base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Yokoyama-jo Castle was located in Sekigahara of Mino Province (the present-day Sekigahara-cho, in Gifu Prefecture) and near the Hokuriku-wakiokan road running through the west side of the base of the Azai clan, Odani-jo Castle (in Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture), and located only six or seven kilometers from Odani-jo Castle, Nobunaga ODA attempted to capture Yokoyama-jo Castle as an important front-line base.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Yokoyama-jo Castle was located in Sekigahara of Mino Province (the present-day Sekigahara-cho, in Gifu Prefecture) and near the Hokuriku-wakiokan road running through the west side of the base of the Azai clan, Odani-jo Castle (in Kohoku-cho, Shiga Prefecture), and located only six or seven kilometers from Odani-jo Castle, Nobunaga ODA attempted to capture Yokoyama-jo Castle as an important front-line base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同6月28日 (旧暦)、姉川の戦いで浅井・朝倉連合軍を破った信長はすぐさま横山城の攻略に着手、時の城主三田村氏は降伏し、落城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 28 in the same year, soon after Nobunaga defeated the allied forces of Azai and Asakura at the Battle of Anegawa, he started to attack Yokoyama-jo Castle and forced the lord of the castle Mitamura clan to surrender.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 28 of the same year, soon after Nobunaga defeated the allied forces of Azai and Asakura at the Battle of Anegawa, he launched an attack on Yokoyama-jo Castle and forced the lord of the castle&apos;s Mitamura clan to surrender.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 28 (old calendar) of the same year, soon after Nobunaga defeated the allied forces of Azai and Asakura at the Battle of Anegawa, he launched an attack on Yokoyama-jo Castle and forced the lord of the castle&apos;s Mitamura clan to surrender.</e>
<cmt>（旧暦） 訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>信長は城番として木下秀吉を任命。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga appointed Hideyoshi KINOSHITA as the guard of the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga appointed Hideyoshi KINOSHITA as the guard of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga appointed Hideyoshi KINOSHITA as the guard of the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>秀吉はここを拠点として浅井氏攻略を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi was based in the castle and captured the AZAI clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi was based in the castle and captured the AZAI clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi was based in the castle and captured the AZAI clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>天正元年（1573年）9月に浅井氏が滅亡すると、秀吉は浅井郡・坂田郡の支配権を与えられ、本拠地として長浜城 (近江国)を築城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the AZAI clan was destroyed in September 1573, Hideyoshi who was given control of Azai-gun and Sakata-gun, built Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province as the base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the AZAI clan was destroyed in September 1573, Hideyoshi, who was given control of Azai-gun and Sakata-gun, built Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province as his base.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the AZAI clan was destroyed in October 1573, Hideyoshi, who was given control of Azai County and Sakata County, built Nagahama-jo Castle in Omi Province as his base.</e>
<cmt>September→Octobergun→County</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>これに前後して横山城は廃城となったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is assumed that Yokoyama-jo Castle fell into ruin around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is assumed that Yokoyama-jo Castle fell into ruin around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is assumed that Yokoyama-jo Castle fell into ruin around that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Chobot(id:20846), Im224(id:57113), ぱむ(id:24323), カテゴリ整理専用(id:146185), アセルス(id:87426), Uraios(id:72687), Aboshi(id:9318), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>