<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>塩谷氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIONOYA clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHIONOYA clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SHIONOYA clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>塩谷氏（しおのやし）は日本の氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIONOYA clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHIONOYA clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SHIONOYA clan is a Japanese clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>塩冶氏（えんやし）とは別である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ENYA clan is different from this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ENYA clan is distinct from it.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ENYA clan is distinct from it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>源姓塩谷氏（堀江氏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family (HORIE clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family (HORIE clan)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family (HORIE clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>源義親の子である塩谷頼純が大治 (日本)5年（1130年）頃、下野国塩谷郡に下り塩谷荘司として塩谷姓を創始したのがはじまりで、塩谷荘三十三郷三万八千町を支配。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 1130 Yorizumi SHIONOYA, a son of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, went down Shioya-gun, Shimotsuke Province, began to adopt the name SHIONOYA and governed SHIONOYA manor thirty-three go thirty-eight thousand cho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In or around 1130, Yorizumi SHIONOYA, a son of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, went down Shioya-gun, Shimotsuke Province, adopted the name SHIONOYA and governed SHIONOYA manor, with its thirty-three go thirty-eight thousand cho.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In or around 1130, Yorizumi SHIONOYA, a son of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, went down Shioya County, Shimotsuke Province, adopted the name SHIONOYA and governed SHIONOYA manor, with its thirty-three go thirty-eight thousand cho.</e>
<cmt>Shioya-gunをShioya Countyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>代々左衛門尉を名乗る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For generations they identified themselves as Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For generations they identified themselves as Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For generations they identified themselves as Saemon no jo (third-ranked officer of the Left Division of Outer Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>居城は堀江山城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle of a daimyo (feudal lord) was Horieyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horieyama-jo Castle was the castle of a daimyo (feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horieyama-jo Castle was the castle of a daimyo (feudal lord).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>御前原城とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some theory say that the castle was Gozenbara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some theories state that the castle was Gozenbara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some theories state that the castle was Gozenbara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>菩提寺は、奉り墓として寺山観音寺、埋め墓として六房寺の両墓制であったと言われているが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family temple was Terayama Kannonji Temple as a dedicated grave and was Rokubo-ji Temple as a buried grave, which was said to have been a double grave system, but was not sure.</e>
<cmt>「奉り墓」をdedicated grave、「埋め墓」を buried grave、「両墓制」をdouble grave systemとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family temple was Terayama Kannonji Temple as a dedicated grave and Rokubo-ji Temple as a buried grave; this was said to have been a double grave system, but that isn&apos;t certain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family temple was Terayama Kannonji Temple as a dedicated grave and Rokubo-ji Temple as a buried grave; this was said to have been a double grave system, but that isn&apos;t certain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、存在を裏付ける確実な史料類は存在しない（『ふるさと矢板のあゆみ』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are no historical material to surely back up the existence (&quot;Furusato Yaita no Ayumi&quot; (History of our hometown Yaita)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no historical material to verify the existence (&quot;Furusato Yaita no Ayumi (History of Our Hometown Yaita)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no historical material to verify the existence (&quot;Furusato Yaita no Ayumi&quot; (History of Our Hometown Yaita)).</e>
<cmt>()を&quot; &quot;の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>5代目塩谷朝義に子が無かったため、宇都宮業綱の次男塩谷朝業を養子に迎え家督を相続させ、源姓塩谷氏の時代は終焉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the fifth Tomoyoshi SHIONOYA had no child, he adopted Tomonari SHIONOYA, the second son of Naritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, made him succeed to the family and the period of SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the fifth Tomoyoshi SHIONOYA had no child, he adopted Tomonari SHIONOYA, the second son of Naritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, and had him succeed to the family, whereby the period of SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family ended.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the fifth Tomoyoshi SHIONOYA had no child, he adopted Tomonari SHIONOYA, the second son of Naritsuna UTSUNOMIYA, and had him succeed to the family, whereby the period of SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>藤姓塩谷氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>源姓塩谷氏の最後の当主・朝義の養子となった竹千代が元服して朝業と名乗り、家督を継いだことで藤姓塩谷氏の歴史が始まる（「秋田塩谷系譜」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takechiyo who was the last family head of SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family and was adopted by Tomoyoshi, went through genpuku (celebrate one&apos;s coming of age), identified himself as Tomonari and succeeded to the family, which started a history of the SHIONOYA family of the Fujiwara family (&quot;Family tree of Akita SHIONOYA family&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takechiyo, who was the last family head of SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family and was adopted by Tomoyoshi, went through genpuku (a celebration of one&apos;s coming of age), identified himself as Tomonari and succeeded to the family, which started a history of the SHIONOYA family of the Fujiwara family (&quot;Family Tree of the Akita SHIONOYA Family&quot;).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takechiyo, who was the last family head of SHIONOYA clan of the MINAMOTO family and was adopted by Tomoyoshi, went through genpuku (a celebration of one&apos;s coming of age), identified himself as Tomonari and succeeded to the family, which started a history of the SHIONOYA family of the Fujiwara family (&apos;Family Tree of the Akita SHIONOYA Family&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>朝業は婿として養子になったとも伝わる（「喜連川塩谷系譜」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonari is said to have been adopted as a husband (&quot;Family tree of Kitsuregawa SHIONOYA family&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonari is said to have been adopted as a husband (&quot;Family Tree of the Kitsuregawa SHIONOYA Family&quot;).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonari is said to have been adopted as a husband (&apos;Family Tree of the Kitsuregawa SHIONOYA Family&apos;).</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>藤姓とは、朝業の実家である宇都宮氏が藤原氏の出自であったためである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name FUJIWARA came from UTSUNOMIYA clan which was Tomonari&apos;s family home and originated from FUJIWARA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name FUJIWARA came from the UTSUNOMIYA clan, which was Tomonari&apos;s family home and had originated with the FUJIWARA clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name FUJIWARA came from the UTSUNOMIYA clan, which was Tomonari&apos;s family home and had originated with the FUJIWARA clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>朝業は、堀江山城の山続きの北側500mほどの山頂に新たに川崎城 (下野国)を築き居城とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomonari newly built Kawasaki-jo Castle (Shimotsuke Province) on the mountaintop which was about 500 meters north side along the mountainous line of Horieyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomonari built Kawasaki-jo Castle (Shimotsuke Province) on the mountaintop approximately 500 meters north along the mountainous line of Horieyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomonari built Kawasaki-jo Castle (Shimotsuke Province) on the mountaintop approximately 500 meters north along the mountainous line of Horieyama-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>菩提寺は長興寺 (栃木県矢板市)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family temple was Choko-ji Temple (Tochigi prefecture, Yaita city).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family temple was Choko-ji Temple (Tochigi Prefecture, Yaita City).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family temple was Choko-ji Temple (Tochigi Prefecture, Yaita City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>藤姓塩谷氏は、約260年～300年間に渡り続くが、応永30年（1423年）8月9日、塩谷教綱の時、鎌倉公方足利持氏と結び、宇都宮氏に謀反。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family lasted for about 260 to 300 years, but on August 9 in 1423 during the period of Noritsuna SHIONOYA, the family collaborated with Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo and raised a rebellion against UTSUNOMIYA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family lasted for approximately 260 to 300 years, but on August 9, 1423, during the period of Noritsuna SHIONOYA, the family collaborated with Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo, and raised a rebellion against the UTSUNOMIYA clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family lasted for approximately 260 to 300 years, but on September 22, 1423, during the period of Noritsuna SHIONOYA, the family collaborated with Mochiuji ASHIKAGA, Kamakura Kubo, and raised a rebellion against the UTSUNOMIYA clan.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>時の宇都宮当主、宇都宮持綱を自領の幸岡原に狩りに招いて殺害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They invited Mochitsuna UTSUNOMIYA, the family head of UTSUNOMIYA clan at that time, to hunting in Koka-hara plain of their own domain and killed him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They invited Mochitsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who was then the family head of the UTSUNOMIYA clan, to go hunting in the Koka-hara plain, in their own domain, and there they killed him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They invited Mochitsuna UTSUNOMIYA, who was then the family head of the UTSUNOMIYA clan, to go hunting in the Koka-hara plain, in their own domain, and there they killed him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この35年後の長禄2年（1458年）5月8日、今度は教綱が、和睦を口実に宇都宮城に招かれたところを殺害され、藤姓塩谷氏は衰退する（5月13日に宇都宮城からの帰りの氏家町で討たれたと記す文献もあり）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 8 in 1458, 35 years later, when Noritsuna was invited to Utsunomiya-jo Castle for the reconciliatory reason, he was killed and the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family headed for decline (there is also a document which says that he was killed in Ujiie-machi on his way back from Utsunomiya-jo Castle on May 13).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thirty-five years later, on May 8, 1458, when Noritsuna was invited to Utsunomiya-jo Castle under the pretense of reconciliation, he was killed, whereupon the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family entered a decline (there is also a document asserting that he was killed on May 13 in Ujiie-machi, on his way back from Utsunomiya-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thirty-five years later, on June 27, 1458, when Noritsuna was invited to Utsunomiya-jo Castle under the pretense of reconciliation, he was killed, whereupon the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family entered a decline (there is also a document asserting that he was killed on July 2 in Ujiie-machi, on his way back from Utsunomiya-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>教綱殺害により、藤姓塩谷氏時代が終焉するが、その経緯には2説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Noritsuna was killed, the period of the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family ended, but there are two theories concerning this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequent upon the death of Noritsuna, the period of the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family ended, but there are two theories concerning that.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequent upon the death of Noritsuna, the period of the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family ended, but there are two theories concerning that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>教綱の死で藤姓塩谷氏が断絶し、宇都宮正綱の四男塩谷孝綱が名跡を継いで宇都宮氏の影響下に入ったとする説（『下野国誌』所収「塩谷系図」）と、教綱の子に塩谷隆綱があって文明 (日本)10年（1478年）正月18日に塩谷弥五郎を養子に迎え家督を継がせたという説（「秋田塩谷系譜」）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says that by the death of Noritsuna, SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family ended and Takatsuna SHIONOYA, the fourth son of Masatsuna UTSUNOMIYA, succeeded to the family name and went under the influence of UTSUNOMIYA clan (&apos;family tree of the Shionoya family&apos; printed in &quot;Shimotsuke-kokushi&quot; (record of Shimotsuke Province)), and the other says that Norituna had a son called Takatsuna SHIONOYA and he adopted Yagoro SHIONOYA on January 18, 1478 and made Yagoro succeed to the family (&quot;family tree of Akita Shionoya family&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory states that with the death of Noritsuna the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family ended and Takatsuna SHIONOYA, the fourth son of Masatsuna UTSUNOMIYA, succeeded to the family name and came under the influence of the UTSUNOMIYA clan (&apos;Family Tree of the Shionoya Family&apos; printed in &quot;Shimotsuke-kokushi&quot; (the record of Shimotsuke Province)); the other states that Norituna had a son called Takatsuna SHIONOYA and that he adopted Yagoro SHIONOYA on January 18, 1478 and had Yagoro succeed to the family (&quot;Family Tree of the Akita Shionoya Family&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory states that with the death of Noritsuna the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family ended and Takatsuna SHIONOYA, the fourth son of Masatsuna UTSUNOMIYA, succeeded to the family name and came under the influence of the UTSUNOMIYA clan (&apos;Family Tree of the Shionoya Family&apos; printed in &quot;Shimotsuke-kokushi&quot; (the record of Shimotsuke Province)); the other states that Noritsuna had a son called Takatsuna SHIONOYA and that he adopted Yagoro SHIONOYA on March 1, 1478 and had Yagoro succeed to the family (&apos;Family Tree of the Akita Shionoya Family&apos;).</e>
<cmt>二番目のNoritsunaをNoritsunaに変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後者の説では、この養子関係に拠って宇都宮氏と塩谷氏は和睦したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the latter theory, UTSUNOMIYA clan and SHIONOYA clan reconciled by this adoptive tie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the latter theory, the UTSUNOMIYA and SHIONOYA clans reconciled through this adoptive tie.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the latter theory, the UTSUNOMIYA and SHIONOYA clans reconciled through this adoptive tie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>重興塩谷氏（再興塩谷氏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Juko SHIONOYA clan (Revived SHIONOYA clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Juko SHIONOYA clan (revived SHIONOYA clan)</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Juko SHIONOYA clan (revived SHIONOYA clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>孝綱は藤姓塩谷氏と同族の宇都宮氏嫡流の出身なので、藤姓であることには変わりないが（ただし孝綱の父の正綱は芳賀氏（清原氏）からの養子）、それ以前と区別して重興塩谷氏（再興塩谷氏）などと呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Takatsuna was from a direct descendant of UTSUNOMIYA clan, the same family as the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family, his name remained Fujiwara, but, to distinguish it from that of the former time, he was called Juko SHIONOYA clan (Revived SHIONOYA clan) and so on (however, Masatsuna, the father of Takatsuna, was an adopted person from HAGA clan (KIYOHARA clan)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because Takatsuna was from a direct descendant of the UTSUNOMIYA clan, the same family as the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family, his name remained Fujiwara, but to distinguish it from that of the former time he was called Juko SHIONOYA clan (revived SHIONOYA clan) and so on (however, Masatsuna, the father of Takatsuna, was an adopted person from the HAGA clan (KIYOHARA clan)).</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because Takatsuna was from a direct descendant of the UTSUNOMIYA clan, the same family as the SHIONOYA family of the FUJIWARA family, his name remained Fujiwara, but to distinguish it from that of the former time he was called Juko SHIONOYA clan (revived SHIONOYA clan) and so on (however, Masatsuna, the father of Takatsuna, was an adopted person from the HAGA clan (KIYOHARA clan)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>「秋田塩谷系譜」では、塩谷義孝と塩谷義綱の間に塩谷時綱、塩谷冬綱、塩谷通綱という3人の当主がいたとするが、史実と合わないため実在が疑わしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Family tree of Akita SHIONOYA family,&quot; there were the three family heads such as Tokitsuna SHIONOYA, Fuyutsuna SHIONOYA, Michitsuna SHIONOYA between Yoshitaka SHIONOYA and Yoshitsuna SHIONOYA, but it is contradictory to a historical fact and the existences are doubtful.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Family Tree of the Akita SHIONOYA Family,&quot; there were the three family heads--Tokitsuna SHIONOYA, Fuyutsuna SHIONOYA and Michitsuna SHIONOYA--between Yoshitaka SHIONOYA and Yoshitsuna SHIONOYA, but it is contradictory to a historical fact and the existence of such individuals is doubtful.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &apos;Family Tree of the Akita SHIONOYA Family,&apos; there were the three family heads--Tokitsuna SHIONOYA, Fuyutsuna SHIONOYA and Michitsuna SHIONOYA--between Yoshitaka SHIONOYA and Yoshitsuna SHIONOYA, but it is contradictory to a historical fact and the existence of such individuals is doubtful.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>但し、後世において、功績のあった塩谷氏の一族の者に当主の地位を追贈した可能性もあるので、完全に架空の存在であるとも言い切れない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, for the years to come, there was a possibility of giving the rank of family head to the members of SHIONOYA clan family who rendered distinguished service and thus it is impossible to say that they were completely fictitious characters.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in subsequent years there was the possibility of giving the rank of family head to the members of the SHIONOYA clan family who rendered distinguished service, and therefore it&apos;s impossible to say they were completely fictitious characters.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in subsequent years there was the possibility of giving the rank of family head to the members of the SHIONOYA clan family who rendered distinguished service, and therefore it&apos;s impossible to say they were completely fictitious characters.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また、塩谷義通については、義綱が家督を継いだのは天正2年（1574年）11月のことであり、義孝の死去から10年のブランクがあるため、正室の子である義綱が元服するまでの間、繋ぎ的に塩谷氏の当主であった可能性も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as for Yoshimichi SHIONOYA, it is pointed out that, as it was in November 1574 that Yoshitsuna succeeded to the family head and there were ten years blank after the death of Yoshitaka, until Yoshitsuna, a lawful wife&apos;s son, went through genpuku, possibly Yoshimichi might be the family head tentatively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for Yoshimichi SHIONOYA, it is pointed out that, as it was in November 1574 that Yoshitsuna succeeded to the position of family head and there was an unknown period of ten years after the death of Yoshitaka, until Yoshitsuna, a lawful wife&apos;s son, went through genpuku, possibly Yoshimichi might have been the family head on a tentative basis.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for Yoshimichi SHIONOYA, it is pointed out that, as it was in November 1574 that Yoshitsuna succeeded to the position of family head and there was an unknown period of ten years after the death of Yoshitaka, until Yoshitsuna, a lawful wife&apos;s son, went through genpuku, possibly Yoshimichi might have been the family head on a tentative basis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>一説では、時綱が義孝の弟で、結城晴朝と戦って討死した乙畑孫四郎こと塩谷義尾(没年が同じ永禄二年(1559年))、冬綱が孝信、通綱が義通とも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says that Tokitsuna was a younger brother of Yoshitaka and he was Yoshio SHIONOYA called Magoshito OTSUHATA, who fought with Harutomo YUKI and died (their year of death was in the same 1559), and Fuyutsuna was Takanobu, and Michitsuna was Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory states that Tokitsuna was a younger brother of Yoshitaka and was actually Yoshio SHIONOYA, called Magoshito OTSUHATA, who fought with Harutomo YUKI and died (they both died in 1559), and that Fuyutsuna was Takanobu and Michitsuna was Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory states that Tokitsuna was a younger brother of Yoshitaka and was actually Yoshio SHIONOYA, called Magoshito OTSUHATA, who fought with Harutomo YUKI and died (they both died in 1559), and that Fuyutsuna was Takanobu and Michitsuna was Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>塩谷氏は、重興塩谷氏の時代に入り、永禄7年（1564年）10月7日に、義孝が弟の塩谷孝信に殺害され川崎城を奪われて以降内紛が続き、天正18年（1590年）には、家臣の岡本正親に独立されるなど衰退していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for SHIONOYA clan, during the period of Juko SHIONOYA clan, Yoshitaka was killed by his younger brother Takanobu SHIONOYA, Kawasaki-jo Castle was taken over, after that internal troubles continued and in 1590 the retainer Masachika OKAMOTO became independent and so on and the clan declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the SHIONOYA clan, during the period of the Juko SHIONOYA clan Yoshitaka was killed by his younger brother Takanobu SHIONOYA, Kawasaki-jo Castle was overtaken, after which internal troubles continued, and in 1590 the retainer Masachika OKAMOTO became independent, etc., and the clan declined.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the SHIONOYA clan, during the period of the Juko SHIONOYA clan Yoshitaka was killed by his younger brother Takanobu SHIONOYA on November 20, 1564 and Kawasaki-jo Castle was overtaken, after which internal troubles continued, and in 1590 the retainer Masachika OKAMOTO became independent, etc., and the clan declined.</e>
<cmt>on November 20, 1564 and を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="27">
<j>そして、文禄4年（1595年）2月8日、塩谷義綱には豊臣秀吉により改易が言い渡される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on February 8 in 1595, Yoshitsuna SHIONOYA was ordered to change of rank by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 8 in 1595, Yoshitsuna SHIONOYA was ordered by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to accept a change of rank.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 18 in 1595, Yoshitsuna SHIONOYA was ordered by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI to accept &apos;kaieki&apos; sanction (sudden dismissal and deprivation of position, privileges and properties).</e>
<cmt>改易を用語統一に従い、変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>系譜に理由の記載は無いが、この2年後に本家である宇都宮氏も改易された事実とあわせて考えると、豊臣政権内の政争に巻き込まれたものと考えられているが定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is no description of the reason in the family tree, but two years later UTSUNOMIYA clan which was a head family was also ordered to change of rank, which suggests they were involved in political war in TOYOTOMI administration, but it is not clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is no description of the reason in the family tree, but two years later the UTSUNOMIYA clan, a head family, was also ordered to change rank, which suggests they were involved in political strife in the TOYOTOMI administration, but this isn&apos;t clear.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is no description of the reason in the family tree, but two years later the UTSUNOMIYA clan, a head family, was also ordered &apos;kaieki&apos;, which suggests they were involved in political strife in the TOYOTOMI administration, but this isn&apos;t clear.</e>
<cmt>to change rankを&apos;kaieki&apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、塩谷氏については、小田原の役の際、直接参陣しなかったために改易されたとする見解もあるが、義綱は、天正17年（1589年）6月29日に上洛して秀吉に恭順の意を表しており、小田原の陣では、名代として家臣の岡本正親を派遣していることから、この時に改易になったとは考え難い（『ふるさと矢板のあゆみ』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory says that SHIONOYA clan was ordered to change of rank because they did not directly join the Siege of Odawara, but Yoshitsuna went to the capital (Kyoto) on June 29 in 1589 to show reverence for Hideyoshi and in Siege of Odawara he sent his retainer Masachika OKAMOTO as a representative and thus it is not plausible that he was ordered to change of rank at that time (&quot;Furusato Yaita no Ayumi&quot; (History of our hometown Yaita)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory states that the SHIONOYA clan was ordered to change rank because they did not directly join the Siege of Odawara, but Yoshitsuna went to the capital (Kyoto) on June 29, 1589 to show reverence for Hideyoshi and, in the Siege of Odawara, he sent his retainer Masachika OKAMOTO as a representative; therefore, it isn&apos;t plausible that he was ordered to change rank at that time (&quot;Furusato Yaita no Ayumi (History of Our Hometown Yaita)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory states that the SHIONOYA clan was ordered &apos;kaieki&apos; because they did not directly join the Siege of Odawara, but Yoshitsuna went to the capital (Kyoto) on August 10, 1589 to show reverence for Hideyoshi and, in the Siege of Odawara, he sent his retainer Masachika OKAMOTO as a representative; therefore, it isn&apos;t plausible that he was ordered &apos;kaieki&apos; at that time (&quot;Furusato Yaita no Ayumi (History of Our Hometown Yaita)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>to change rankを&apos;kaieki&apos;に変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="30">
<j>文禄4年（1595年）に改易されたが、捨扶持として1000石が義綱に安堵された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1595 Yoshitsuna was ordered to change of rank, but he was recognized and guaranteed 1000 koku as Sutebuchi alms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1595, Yoshitsuna was ordered to change rank, but he was recognized and guaranteed 1000 koku as Sutebuchi alms.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1595, Yoshitsuna was ordered &apos;kaieki&apos;, but he was recognized and guaranteed 1000 koku as Sutebuchi alms.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし義綱はこれを捨て出奔し、義綱庶兄の義通が岡本正親の甥であり娘婿である関係からこの1000石を継いだという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yoshitsuna abandoned this and ran away, and Yoshimichi, his older brother by a concubine, succeeded to this 1000 koku because he was a cousin of Masachika OKAMOTO and his daughter&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yoshitsuna abandoned this and ran away, and Yoshimichi, his older brother by a concubine, succeeded to this 1000 koku because he was a cousin of Masachika OKAMOTO and his daughter&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yoshitsuna abandoned this and ran away, and Yoshimichi, his older brother by a concubine, succeeded to this 1000 koku because he was a cousin of Masachika OKAMOTO and his daughter&apos;s husband.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>そして義通の跡は次男・岡本保真が家督を継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the second son Yasumasa OKAMOTO took over the family head after Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second son, Yasumasa OKAMOTO, took over as family head after Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second son, Yasumasa OKAMOTO, took over as family head after Yoshimichi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、その保真は、正保元年（1644年）3月10日、甥の岡本義政の謀略により殺害（泉騒動）され、保真に男子が無かったため野州塩谷氏は断絶。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Yasumasa was killed by Yoshimasa OKAMOTO&apos;s conspiracy on March 10 in 1644 (Izumi-sodo riot) and Yasumasa had no son and thus Yashu SHIONOYA clan discontinued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Yasumasa was killed by Yoshimasa OKAMOTO&apos;s conspiracy on March 10, 1644 (Izumi-sodo riot) and Yasumasa had no son; consequently, the Yashu SHIONOYA clan was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Yasumasa was killed by Yoshimasa OKAMOTO&apos;s conspiracy on April 16, 1644 (Izumi-sodo riot) and Yasumasa had no son; consequently, the Yashu SHIONOYA clan was discontinued.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>重興塩谷氏の時代も終焉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period of Juko SHIONOYA clan also ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period of the Juko SHIONOYA clan also ended.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of the Juko SHIONOYA clan also ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>佐竹家臣時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SATAKE vassal period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The SATAKE vassal period</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The SATAKE vassal period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>義綱は、改易となった後、慶長2年（1597年）正月2日より常陸国の佐竹義宣 (右京大夫)に仕え、慶長7年（1602年）に佐竹氏が出羽国に転封となると、これに従い、出羽国平鹿郡横手に移り十二所城代を務め、子孫は、佐竹氏の家老職などを務める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshitsuna was ordered to change of rank, he served Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)) in Hitachi Province and when in 1602 SATAKE clan was ordered to change the territory in Dewa Province, he followed this and moved to Yokote, Hiraka-gun, Dewa Province and served as Jodai (the keeper of castle) of Junisho-jo Castle and his offsprings serves as Karo (chief retainer) of SATAKE clan and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshitsuna was ordered to change rank, he served Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)) in Hitachi Province and when, in 1602, the SATAKE clan was ordered to change its territory in Dewa Province, he followed this and moved to Yokote, Hiraka-gun, Dewa Province and served as Jodai (the keeper of the castle) of Junisho-jo Castle and his offsprings served as Karo (chief retainer) of the SATAKE clan and so on.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshitsuna was ordered &apos;kaieki&apos;, he served Yoshinobu SATAKE (Ukyo no daibu (Master of the Western Capital Offices)) in Hitachi Province from February 18, 1597 and when, in 1602, the SATAKE clan was ordered to change its territory in Dewa Province, he followed this and moved to Yokote, Hiraka County, Dewa Province and served as Jodai (the keeper of the castle) of Junisho-jo Castle and his offsprings served as Karo (chief retainer) of the SATAKE clan and so on.</e>
<cmt>to change rankを&apos;kaieki&apos;に変更しました。グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。gunをCountyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし、その最後の当主である塩谷温綱に子が無かったため、直系は明治時代に断絶する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the last family head Harutsuna SHIONOYA had no child and thus the direct line discontinued during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the last family head, Harutsuna SHIONOYA, had no child and thus the direct line discontinued during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the last family head, Harutsuna SHIONOYA, had no child and thus the direct line discontinued during the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>児玉党系塩谷氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KODAMA Party Line, SHIONOYA clan</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KODAMA Party Line, SHIONOYA clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>武蔵七党の一角を占める児玉党の本宗家3代目児玉家行（有道姓）の次男、児玉二郎家遠（後の塩谷家遠）が、武蔵国児玉郡大寄郷若泉庄の塩谷（現在の埼玉県本庄市児玉町塩谷）の地を父から与えられ、子孫が土着して名乗った事から始まる児玉党を構成する氏族。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KODAMA Jiro Ieto (later, Ieto SHIONOYA), the second son of Ieyuki KODAMA (Arimichi name) of the third generation of head family of KODAMA Party which occupied a part of the head family of Musashi-shichito Parties (seven parties of samurai in Musashi Province) was given SHIONOYA&apos;s land of Wakaizumi-sho, Oyose-go, Kodama-gun, Musashi Province (currently, Shioya, Kodama-cho, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) by his father and the offsprings were localized and identified themselves as KODAMA and made up KODAMA Party as a clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KODAMA Jiro Ieto (later, Ieto SHIONOYA), the second son of Ieyuki KODAMA (Arimichi name) of the third generation of the head family of the KODAMA Party, which occupied a part of the head family of the Musashi-shichito parties (seven parties of samurai in Musashi Province), was given SHIONOYA&apos;s land of Wakaizumi-sho, Oyose-go, Kodama-gun, Musashi Province (currently Shioya, Kodama-cho, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) by his father and the offspring were localized and identified themselves as KODAMA and made up the KODAMA Party as a clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KODAMA Jiro Ieto (later, Ieto SHIONOYA), the second son of Ieyuki KODAMA (Arimichi name) of the third generation of the head family of the KODAMA Party, which occupied a part of the head family of the Musashi-shichito parties (seven parties of samurai in Musashi Province), was given SHIONOYA&apos;s land of Wakaizumi-sho, Oyose-go, Kodama County, Musashi Province (currently Shioya, Kodama-cho, Honjo City, Saitama Prefecture) by his father and the offspring were localized and identified themselves as KODAMA and made up the KODAMA Party as a clan.</e>
<cmt>gunをCountyに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>従って、藤原氏とあるが本来の初姓は有道氏であり、12世紀中には塩谷を名乗っていたものと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the name was FUJIWARA, but originally the first name was ARIMICHI clan and during the twelfth century they identified themselves as SHIONOYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the name was FUJIWARA, but originally the first name was ARIMICHI clan; during the twelfth century, they identified themselves as SHIONOYA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the name was FUJIWARA, but originally the first family name was ARIMICHI clan; during the twelfth century, they identified themselves as SHIONOYA.</e>
<cmt>nameの前にfamilyを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>児玉党系塩谷氏の活躍については、『源平盛衰記』などの資料に見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The great success of KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan was described in the materials such as &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the MINAMOTO and the Taira clans) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The great success of the KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan was described in the materials such as &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the MINAMOTO and Taira Clans) and so on.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The great success of the KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan was described in the materials such as &quot;Genpei Seisui ki&quot; (Rise and Fall of the MINAMOTO and Taira Clans) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>『武蔵七党系図』では、嫡流を、家遠→塩谷経遠→塩谷経光（児玉二郎）としている（複数系図が存在している為、断定はできない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Family tree of the seven groups of samurai warriors in Musashi Province,&quot; the direct descendants were Ieto =&gt; Tsuneto SHIONOYA =&gt; Tsunemitsu SHIONOYA (Jiro KODAMA) (as several family trees existed, it cannot be said with certainty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Family Tree of the Seven Groups of Samurai Warriors in Musashi Province,&quot; the direct descendants were Ieto =&gt; Tsuneto SHIONOYA =&gt; Tsunemitsu SHIONOYA (Jiro KODAMA) (given that several family trees existed, it cannot be said with certainty).</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Family Tree of the Seven Groups of Samurai Warriors in Musashi Province,&quot; the direct descendants were Ieto =&gt; Tsuneto SHIONOYA =&gt; Tsunemitsu SHIONOYA (Jiro KODAMA) (given that several family trees existed, it cannot be said with certainty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>また、家遠の子、塩谷維弘は、一ノ谷の戦いに参戦し、奥州合戦にて戦死し、維弘の子、塩谷維盛とその子である塩谷維光は、共に建暦3年（1213年）5月2日の和田合戦時に討死にしたと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Ieto&apos;s son Korehiro SHIONOYA joined the Battle of Ichi no tani and killed in the Battle of Oshu and Korehiro&apos;s son, Koremori SHIONOYA and his son Koremitsu SHIONOYA were killed together in the Battle of WADA on May 2 in 1213.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieto&apos;s son Korehiro SHIONOYA joined the Battle of Ichi no tani and was killed in the Battle of Oshu, while Korehiro&apos;s son, Koremori SHIONOYA, and his son Koremitsu SHIONOYA were killed together in the Battle of WADA on May 2, 1213.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieto&apos;s son Korehiro SHIONOYA joined the Battle of Ichi no tani and was killed in the Battle of Oshu, while Korehiro&apos;s son, Koremori SHIONOYA, and his son Koremitsu SHIONOYA were killed together in the Battle of WADA on May 30, 1213.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="42">
<j>家遠の兄である庄家弘（児玉党本宗家4代目）は児玉郡の栗崎の地へ行き、庄氏を名乗り、弟の富田親家は富田の地へ土着して富田氏を名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieto&apos;s brother, Iehiro SHO (the fourth generation of the head family of the Kodama Party) went to Kurisaki in Kodama District and identified themselves as SHO clan and his younger brother Chikaie TOMIDA was localized in Tomida and identified him as TOMIDA clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieto&apos;s brother, Iehiro SHO (the fourth generation of the head family of the Kodama Party), went to Kurisaki in Kodama District and identified themselves as the SHO clan, while his younger brother Chikaie TOMIDA was localized in Tomida and identified himself as being of the TOMIDA clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieto&apos;s brother, Iehiro SHO (the fourth generation of the head family of the Kodama Party), went to Kurisaki in Kodama District and identified themselves as the SHO clan, while his younger brother Chikaie TOMIDA was localized in Tomida and identified himself as being of the TOMIDA clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>遵って、児玉党系塩谷氏は、庄氏・富田氏と同族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan was the same family group as SHO clan and TOMIDA clan.</e>
<cmt>「遵って」という言葉の意味が不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan was the same family group as the SHO and TOMIDA clans.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The KODAMA Party Line SHIONOYA clan was the same family group as the SHO and TOMIDA clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Hajimari(id:205606), Point136(id:211299), Kangoshiyouichi(id:100531), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Y mon(id:192749), KurmUmy(id:202680), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>