<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>武家領</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bukeryo (Lands of military family)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bukeryo (Lands of military families)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bukeryo (Lands of military families)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>武家領（ぶけりょう）とは、中世日本における武家の所領のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bukeryo was shoryo (individual holding) of military families in the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bukeryo was shoryo (individual holdings) of military families during the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bukeryo was shoryo (individual holdings) of military families during the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>武家領には一般的な武士が持つ所領から、武家の棟梁である伊勢平氏・河内源氏が武家公権に由来する所領まで存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bukeryo included from individual holdings owned by samurai (warrior) retainers to individual holdings owned by the Ise Heishi (a branch of the Taira clan) and the Kawachi Genji (a branch of the Minamoto family), each of which is a chief of the warrior houses, based on their military authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bukeryo included from individual holdings owned by samurai (warriors) retainers to individual holdings owned by the Ise Heishi (a branch of the Taira clan) and the Kawachi Genji (a branch of the Minamoto family), each a chief of the warrior houses, based on their military authority.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bukeryo included from individual holdings owned by samurai (warriors) retainers to individual holdings owned by the Ise Heishi (a branch of the Taira clan) and the Kawachi Genji (a branch of the Minamoto family), each a chief of the warrior houses, based on their military authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>元々中・下級の官人身分であった伊勢平氏や河内源氏をはじめとする地方の武士は自己の根拠地において荘園領主としての資格を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local samurai warriors including the Ise Heishi clan and the Kawachi Genji, both of which originated from middle and lower ranked officials, were qualified as shoen ryoshu (proprietary lord of manor) in their local power base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local samurai warriors including the Ise Heishi clan and the Kawachi Genji, both originating from middle and lower ranked officials, were qualified as shoen ryoshu (proprietary lord of manor) in their local power base.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local samurai warriors including the Ise Heishi clan and the Kawachi Genji, both originating from middle and lower ranked officials, were qualified as shoen ryoshu (proprietary lord of manor) in their local power base.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>その中でも伊勢平氏は平氏政権樹立の過程で各地の知行国や荘園を獲得して経済的基盤を形成し、最盛期には30ヶ国以上の知行国と500ヶ所以上の荘園を支配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, the Ise Heishi formed its economical foundation by receiving chigyokoku and shoen throughout Japan in the process of establishing the Taira administration, which culminated in ruling of 30 or more chigyokoku and 500 or more shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, the Ise Heishi formed its economic foundation by receiving chigyokoku and shoen throughout Japan in the process of establishing the Taira administration, which culminated in ruling of thirty or more chigyokoku and 500 or more shoen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, the Ise Heishi formed its economic foundation by receiving chigyokoku and shoen throughout Japan in the process of establishing the Taira administration, which culminated in ruling of thirty or more chigyokoku and 500 or more shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>河内源氏は鎌倉幕府樹立の過程で治承の戦いの際に恩賞などの形で獲得した旧伊勢平氏知行国のうち9ヶ国（下総国・上総国・武蔵国・相模国・伊豆国・越後国・信濃国・駿河国・豊後国）及び没官領となった500ヶ所以上の荘園を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kawachi Genji received nine provinces (Shimousa Province, Kazusa Province, Musashi Province, Sagami Province, Izu Province, Echigo Province, Shinano Province, Suruga Province, Bungo Province) among those which had been the Ise Heishi&apos;s chigyokoku, and 500 or more shoen, which had been mokkan ryo (confiscated lands) -- All of them were received as rewards in the Jisho no ran (Jisho civil war, 1180) in the process of establishing the Kamakura bakufu (military government of Kamakura.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kawachi Genji received nine provinces (Shimousa Province, Kazusa Province, Musashi Province, Sagami Province, Izu Province, Echigo Province, Shinano Province, Suruga Province, Bungo Province) among those that had been the Ise Heishi&apos;s chigyokoku, and 500 or more shoen, that had been mokkan ryo (confiscated lands) -- All of them were received as rewards in the Jisho no ran (Jisho civil war, 1180) in the process of establishing the Kamakura bakufu (military government of Kamakura.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kawachi Genji received nine provinces (Shimousa Province, Kazusa Province, Musashi Province, Sagami Province, Izu Province, Echigo Province, Shinano Province, Suruga Province, Bungo Province) among those that had been the Ise Heishi&apos;s chigyokoku, and 500 or more shoen, that had been mokkan ryo (confiscated lands) -- All of them were received as rewards in the Jisho no ran (Jisho civil war, 1180) in the process of establishing the Kamakura bakufu (military government of Kamakura).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>前者を関東御分国・後者を関東御領と呼び、一括して平家没官領とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former provinces were called Kanto gobunkoku (Kamakura bakufu&apos;s provincial jurisdiction) and the latter shoen were called Kanto goryo (Kamakura bakufu&apos;s private estates), both of which were also collectively called Heike mokkan ryo (lands confiscated from the Heike.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former provinces were called Kanto gobunkoku (Kamakura bakufu&apos;s provincial jurisdiction) and the latter shoen were called Kanto goryo (Kamakura bakufu&apos;s private estates), both of which were also collectively called Heike mokkan ryo (lands confiscated from the Heike.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former provinces were called Kanto gobunkoku (Kamakura bakufu&apos;s provincial jurisdiction) and the latter shoen were called Kanto goryo (Kamakura bakufu&apos;s private estates), both of which were also collectively called Heike mokkan ryo (lands confiscated from the Heike).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ここにおいて河内源氏の宗家当主である鎌倉殿は、当時の日本における屈指の荘園領主としての地位を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, Kamakura dono (Lord of Kamakura), who was the head of the head family of the Kawachi Genji, had attained the position of one of the greatest shoen ryoshu of Japan in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, Kamakura dono (Lord of Kamakura), who was the head of the head family of the Kawachi Genji, had attained the position of one of the greatest shoen ryoshu of Japan in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, Kamakura dono (Lord of Kamakura), who was the head of the head family of the Kawachi Genji, had attained the position of one of the greatest shoen ryoshu of Japan in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>こうした所領には御家人が守護・地頭として宛がわれてその軍事力を背景に強力な支配体制が構築された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To those shoryo, gokenin (personal retainers of the shogun) were appointed as shugo (protectors, or military governors) or jito (stewards), and a strong system of government was constructed based on their military forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To those shoryo, gokenin (personal retainers of the shogun) were appointed as shugo (protectors, or military governors) or jito (stewards), and a strong system of government was constructed based on their military forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To those shoryo, gokenin (personal retainers of the shogun) were appointed as shugo (protectors, or military governors) or jito (stewards), and a strong system of government was constructed based on their military forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この地位は河内源氏宗家断絶後も歴代征夷大将軍に継承され、承久の乱などの内乱や御家人の不祥事などで没収された所領や所職を接収して拡大していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after the whole family line of the Kawachi Genji was destroyed, the position was taken over by the successive seii taishogun (barbarian-subduing generalissimo), which expanded its power by taking over the shoryo and various shiki (the right to use land and to share in the products of the land) which were confiscated in disturbances such as the Jokyu no ran (Jokyu disturbance; 1221) and in times of crisis and rebellion of gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after the whole family line of the Kawachi Genji was destroyed, the position was taken over by the successive seii taishogun (barbarian-subduing generalissimo), which expanded its power by taking over the shoryo and various shiki (the right to use land and to share in the products of the land) which were confiscated in disturbances such as the Jokyu no ran (Jokyu disturbance; 1221) and in times of crisis and rebellion of gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after the whole family line of the Kawachi Genji was destroyed, the position was taken over by the successive seii taishogun (barbarian-subduing generalissimo), which expanded its power by taking over the shoryo and various shiki (the right to use land and to share in the products of the land) which were confiscated in disturbances such as the Jokyu no ran (Jokyu disturbance; 1221) and in times of crisis and rebellion of gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、その他の武士の所領も元は自己の荘園や公領の所職が主であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shoryo of the other bushi (samurai) also mainly originated in the various shiki of the own shoen and the koryo (public lands.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shoryo of the other bushi (samurai) also mainly originated in the various shiki of their own shoen and koryo (public lands.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shoryo of the other bushi (samurai) also mainly originated in the various shiki of their own shoen and koryo (public lands).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを括弧の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>彼らの多くは鎌倉幕府の守護や地頭になって獲得した軍事的・警察的権限を自己の所領にも展開し、他の所職を排除しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the gokenin applied the military and police powers, which they had obtained after becoming shugo or jito of the Kamakura bakufu, on their own shoryo to remove various kinds of shiki associated with their own shoryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the gokenin applied military and police powers, which they had obtained after becoming shugo or jito of the Kamakura bakufu, on their own shoryo to remove various kinds of shiki associated with their own shoryo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the gokenin applied military and police powers, which they had obtained after becoming shugo or jito of the Kamakura bakufu, on their own shoryo to remove various kinds of shiki associated with their own shoryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、その支配は荘園公領制の範疇におけるものであり、他の権門との協調を掲げる鎌倉幕府の所領よりも地方にある御家人の所領の方が武士による所領の独占的支配の傾向が早く出現するものの、この時代には上級の所職を占める公家・寺社や現地の国衙からの影響力を完全に排除するには至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rule of the gokenin remained subject to the shoen koryosei system; therefore, although samurai&apos;s monopolistic control of the shoryo was liable to appear earlier in the local shoryo of the gokenin than the shoryo of the Kamakura bakufu, which stated the policy of having gokenin in harmony with the other powerful houses, influences of the court nobles, temples, and shrines, which occupied higher various shiki, and the local kokuga cannot be completely removed in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rule of the gokenin remained subject to the shoen koryosei system; therefore, although samurai&apos;s monopolistic control of the shoryo was liable to appear earlier in the local shoryo of the gokenin than the shoryo of the Kamakura bakufu, which stated the policy of having gokenin in harmony with the other powerful houses, influences of the court nobles, temples, and shrines, which occupied higher various shiki, and the local kokuga cannot be completely removed iduring this period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rule of the gokenin remained subject to the shoen koryosei system; therefore, although samurai&apos;s monopolistic control of the shoryo was liable to appear earlier in the local shoryo of the gokenin than the shoryo of the Kamakura bakufu, which stated the policy of having gokenin in harmony with the other powerful houses, influences of the court nobles, temples, and shrines, which occupied higher various shiki, and the local kokuga cannot be completely removed during this period.</e>
<cmt>iduringをduringに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>これに対して一介の御家人から室町幕府を創設した足利氏の場合は、南北朝の内乱の中で敵から奪った所領の増加がある一方で恩賞や敵からの略奪による所領の喪失もあり、その御料所の規模は鎌倉幕府のそれよりも遥かに乏しかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Ashikaga clan, which raised from a mere gokenin to found the Muromachi bakufu, gained the shoryo by depriving the enemies of the shoryo in the Nanbokucho civil war, but lost their shoryo when their shoryo was taken as rewards to the others or was deprived by the enemies -- Consequently, its goryosho (shogunal domain) was far less than that of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Ashikaga clan, which raised from a mere gokenin to found the Muromachi bakufu, gained the shoryo by depriving the enemies of the shoryo during the Nanbokucho civil war, but lost their shoryo when their shoryo was taken as rewards to the others or was deprived by the enemies -- Consequently, its goryosho (shogunal domain) was far less than that of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Ashikaga clan, which raised from a mere gokenin to found the Muromachi bakufu, gained the shoryo by depriving the enemies of the shoryo during the Nanbokucho civil war, but lost their shoryo when their shoryo was taken as rewards to the others or was deprived by the enemies -- Consequently, its goryosho (shogunal domain) was far less than that of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが、長い内乱や半済令の影響で寺社本所領や公領の衰退が著しく、彼らが持っていた職は名目上のものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the influences of the long-lasting civil war and hanzeirei (half-tax decrees), Jisha honjoryo (lands of temples and nobles) and koryo were severely declined, and the shiki associated with the lands became in name only.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the influences of the long-lasting civil war and hanzeirei (half-tax decrees), Jisha honjoryo (lands of temples and nobles) and koryo were severely declined, and the shiki associated with the lands became in name only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the influences of the long-lasting civil war and hanzeirei (half-tax decrees), Jisha honjoryo (lands of temples and nobles) and koryo were severely declined, and the shiki associated with the lands became in name only.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この結果、守護大名をはじめとする各地の武士によって自己の所領の全一的支配が確立され、その影響は室町幕府の御料所にも及んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, each of the bushi throughout Japan including shugo daimyo (great feudal lord) established an integral rule over his own shoryo, which influenced the goryosho of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, each of the bushi throughout Japan including shugo daimyo (great feudal lord) established an integral rule over his own shoryo, which influenced the goryosho of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, each of the bushi throughout Japan including shugo daimyo (great feudal lord) established an integral rule over his own shoryo, which influenced the goryosho of the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ここにおいて名実ともに「武家領」が成立することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, &apos;bukeryo&apos; had been established both in name and in reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, &apos;bukeryo&apos; had been established both in name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, &apos;bukeryo&apos; had been established both in name and in reality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>この傾向は大名領国制への以降とともに日本全国規模で確立され、幕藩体制を経て明治の版籍奉還・秩禄処分まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This trend spread throughout Japan as the daimyo ryogokusei system (daimyo control over provinces) was introduced, and observed through bakuhan taisei (power structure of bakufu and daimyo domains) until hanseki hokan (surrender of the domain registers to the emperor) and chitsuroku shobun (abolish hereditary stipend) were carried out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This trend spread throughout Japan as the daimyo ryogokusei system (daimyo control over provinces) was introduced, and observed through bakuhan taisei (power structure of bakufu and daimyo domains) until hanseki hokan (surrender of the domain registers to the emperor) and chitsuroku shobun (abolish hereditary stipend) were carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This trend spread throughout Japan as the daimyo ryogokusei system (daimyo control over provinces) was introduced, and observed through bakuhan taisei (power structure of bakufu and daimyo domains) until hanseki hokan (surrender of the domain registers to the emperor) and chitsuroku shobun (abolish hereditary stipend) were carried out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nyao148(id:93723), 銅閣寺(id:252815), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>