<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>嫡流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chakuryu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chakuryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chakuryu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>嫡流（ちゃくりゅう）とは、氏族の直系の血筋のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chakuryu refers to the direct line of descent from a clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chakuryu refers to the direct line of descent from a clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chakuryu refers to the direct line of descent from a clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>主に惣領と正妻の間に生まれた長男、即ち嫡男により継承される血筋を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It mainly denotes the line of descent succeeded by the eldest son, or the chakunan (the eldest son and heir), of the soryo (head of a clan) and his legal wife.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It mainly denotes the line of descent succeeded by the eldest son, or the chakunan (the eldest son and heir), of the soryo (head of a clan) and his legal wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It mainly denotes the line of descent succeeded by the eldest son, or the chakunan (the eldest son and heir), of the soryo (head of a clan) and his legal wife.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>正嫡、直系、正系、嫡系ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called the seiteki (the eldest son of the legal wife), the chokkei (direct descent), the seikei (legitimate line), or the chakukei (嫡系).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the seiteki (the eldest son of the legal wife), the chokkei (direct descent), the seikei (legitimate line), or the chakukei (嫡系).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the seiteki (the eldest son of the legal wife), the chokkei (direct descent), the seikei (legitimate line), or the chakukei.</e>
<cmt>(嫡系)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>対義語は庶流という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The antonym of the word is the shoryu (line of a branch family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The antonym of the word is the shoryu (line of a branch family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The antonym of the word is the shoryu (line of a branch family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>敬って「御嫡々の家系」という場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chakuryu is also referred to as the &apos;gochakuchaku no kakei&apos; (御嫡々の家系) to pay more respect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chakuryu is also referred to as the &apos;gochakuchaku no kakei&apos; (御嫡々の家系) to pay more respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chakuryu is also referred to as the &apos;gochakuchaku no kakei&apos; to pay more respect.</e>
<cmt>(御嫡々の家系)削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>嫡流の家を宗家、嫡家、本家という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The chakuryu&apos;s family is called the soke (head family), the chakke (legitimate family), or the honke (main family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chakuryu&apos;s family is called the soke (head family), the chakke (legitimate family), or the honke (main family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chakuryu&apos;s family is called the soke (head family), the chakke (legitimate family), or the honke (main family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>嫡流とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What is the chakuryu?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What is chakuryu?</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What is chakuryu?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>氏族の血統が重んじられた古代・中世において、氏族の秩序は氏長者を中心に維持されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the ancient times and the medieval period when the blood line of a clan was highly regarded, the order within the clan was maintained mainly by the ujinochoja (head of a clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ancient times and during the medieval period when the blood line of a clan was highly regarded, the order within the clan was maintained mainly by the ujinochoja (head of a clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ancient times and during the medieval period when the blood line of a clan was highly regarded, the order within the clan was maintained mainly by the ujinochoja (head of a clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>中世一時的には氏長者の権威が低下する時期もあったものの、氏長者には氏爵といい、朝廷より一門に対する位階任官者推薦の特権が付与されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the authority of the ujinochoja temporarily declined during some times of the medieval period, the Imperial Court granted the ujinochoja the privilege of the ujinoshaku that allowed them to recommend candidates within their clans for the ikai (Court rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the authority of the ujinochoja sometimes temporarily declined during the medieval period, the Imperial Court granted the ujinochoja the privilege of ujinoshaku that allowed them to recommend candidates within their clans for the ikai (Court rank).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the authority of the ujinochoja sometimes temporarily declined during the medieval period, the Imperial Court granted the ujinochoja the privilege of ujinoshaku that allowed them to recommend candidates within their clans for the ikai (Court rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>こうした中で、氏長者の地位は、主に氏長者とその子孫により継承されたが、その継承方法には「氏的継承」と「嫡流継承」の二つの考え方があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the circumstances, the position of the ujinochoja was handed down from the ujinochoja to their descendants; there were two ideas of succession system, the &apos;clan succession&apos; and the &apos;chakuryu succession.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, the position of the ujinochoja was handed down from the ujinochoja to their descendants; there were two types of succession, the &apos;clan succession&apos; and the &apos;chakuryu succession.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the position of the ujinochoja was handed down from the ujinochoja to their descendants; there were two types of succession, the &apos;clan succession&apos; and the &apos;chakuryu succession.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>前者は古い形態の継承方法であり、一族中において最高位の地位にある者が氏長者の地位に就くという考え方であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former was an old succession system, whose basic idea was to let the person with the highest rank within a clan assume the position of the ujinochoja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former was an old succession system, where the basic idea was to let the person with the highest rank within a clan assume the position of ujinochoja.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former was an old succession system, where the basic idea was to let the person with the highest rank within a clan assume the position of ujinochoja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>律令法においては嫡男はあくまでも蔭位のための規則に過ぎず氏長者継承の条件としての意味は全くなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the ritsuryo code (criminal and administrative codes), being the chakunan was only a criterion for the oni (granting of the ikai to a son of a man with the Court rank), but never a requirement for the succession of the ujinochoja.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the ritsuryo code (criminal and administrative codes), being the chakunan was a criterion for the oni (granting of the ikai to a son of a man with Court rank), but never a requirement for the succession of ujinochoja.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the ritsuryo code (criminal and administrative codes), being the chakunan was a criterion for the oni (granting of the ikai to a son of a man with Court rank), but never a requirement for the succession of ujinochoja.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>逆に最高位の地位を占めるという要件を満たせば庶流でも氏長者に就く可能性もあったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even a clan member from a branch family, on the contrary, had a chance to be the ujinochoja as long as he held the highest rank..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoever, even a clan member from a branch family had a chance to become ujinochoja as long as he held the highest rank..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, even a clan member from a branch family had a chance to become ujinochoja as long as he held the highest rank.</e>
<cmt>スペルピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これに対して平安時代後期から登場したのが、正室を母とする嫡男によって代々継承されるという後者の存在である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the latter system, which came into existence in the late Heian period, let the chakunan of legal wives to take over the ujinochoja from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the latter system, which came into existence in the late Heian period, let chakunan of legal wives take over as ujinochoja from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the latter system, which came into existence in the late Heian period, let chakunan of legal wives take over as ujinochoja from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>これによって一族の財産や地位の分散を最小限に止め、血筋の尊貴さと正当性を有する嫡流は氏族の栄達を成し遂げ得る存在であり、庶流とも官位などの面で大きな差がつけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This minimized the risk of dispersing their fortunes and ranks; the chakuryu, who held the nobility and legitimacy of blood, were the ones that could advance the status of their clans and were greatly favored over the shoryu in terms of official ranks, for example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This minimized the risk of dispersing their fortunes and ranks; chakuryu, who held nobility and legitimacy of blood, were those who could advance the status of their clans and were greatly favored over the shoryu in terms of official ranks, for example.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This minimized the risk of dispersing their fortunes and ranks; chakuryu, who held nobility and legitimacy of blood, were those who could advance the status of their clans and were greatly favored over the shoryu in terms of official ranks, for example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、「氏的継承」が直ちに「嫡流継承」へと移行したわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is not to say, however, that the succession system momentarily changed from the &apos;clan succession&apos; to the &apos;chakuryu succession.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is not to say, however, that the succession system momentarily changed from &apos;clan succession&apos; to &apos;chakuryu succession.&apos;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is not to say, however, that the succession system momentarily changed from &apos;clan succession&apos; to &apos;chakuryu succession.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>所領の分散防止の観点から武士社会において先行して社会全般において「嫡流継承」の原理が完成するのは鎌倉時代後期に入ってからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;chakuryu succession&apos; started among the samurai society first in terms of preventing the shoryo (territory) from scattering, and it was not until the late Kamakura period that the basis of the system was realized by the whole society.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;chakuryu succession&apos; started among the samurai society first in terms of preventing the shoryo (territory) from being scattered, and it was not until the late Kamakura period that the basis of the system was realized by the whole society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;chakuryu succession&apos; started among the samurai society first in terms of preventing the shoryo (territory) from being scattered, and it was not until the late Kamakura period that the basis of the system was realized by the whole society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>特に公卿にあって内裏の差配を独占した藤原氏は、藤原道長の家系が摂政・関白の座を独占し続けることで摂関家としての地位を獲得し、嫡流の近衛家を筆頭とする、九条家、二条家、一条家、鷹司家の五摂家を形成するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fujiwara clan, Court nobles who monopolized the management of the dairi (Imperial Palace), assumed the position of the sekkan-ke (family line of regents and chief advisors to the Emperor) by letting the family lines of FUJIWARA no Michinaga monopolize the positions of Sessho (regent) and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), thus establishing the gosekke (the five sekkan-ke) of the Konoe family, the Kujo family, the Nijo family, the Ichijo family and the Takatsukasa family led by the Konoe family, the chakuryu of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Fujiwara clan, Court nobles who monopolized the management of the dairi (Imperial Palace), assumed the position of the sekkan-ke (family line of regents and chief advisors to the Emperor) by letting the family lines of FUJIWARA no Michinaga monopolize the positions of Sessho (regent) and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), thus establishing the gosekke (the five sekkan-ke) of the Konoe family, the Kujo family, the Nijo family, the Ichijo family, and the Takatsukasa family led by the Konoe family, the chakuryu of the clan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Fujiwara clan, Court nobles who monopolized the management of the dairi (Imperial Palace), assumed the position of the sekkan-ke (family line of regents and chief advisors to the Emperor) by letting the family lines of FUJIWARA no Michinaga monopolize the positions of Sessho (regent) and Kanpaku (chief adviser to the Emperor), thus establishing the gosekke (the five sekkan-ke) of the Konoe family, the Kujo family, the Nijo family, the Ichijo family, and the Takatsukasa family led by the Konoe family, the chakuryu of the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>ただし、古い氏族に由来する摂関家においても長く「氏的継承」と「嫡流継承」が混在し続ける事になり、ついに五摂家のうちの1つだけが嫡流の地位を占めるという事態は生じなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the &apos;clan succession&apos; and the &apos;chakuryu succession&apos; coexisted among the sekkan-ke originating from the old clan, preventing one family of the gosekke from monopolizing the position of the chakuryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, &apos;clan succession&apos; and &apos;chakuryu succession&apos; coexisted among the sekkan-ke originating from the old clan, preventing one family of the gosekke from monopolizing the position of chakuryu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, &apos;clan succession&apos; and &apos;chakuryu succession&apos; coexisted among the sekkan-ke originating from the old clan, preventing one family of the gosekke from monopolizing the position of chakuryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="20">
<j>一方の武家においては、武士の棟梁として台頭した河内源氏の流れを汲む源頼朝が源氏嫡流を称して、鎌倉幕府を開き、門葉という一族や有力御家人を中心とする武家政治の基礎を形成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the samurai class, on the other hand, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a descendant of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) who rose as the leader of samurai, called himself as the chakuryu of the Minamoto clan, established the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and established the basis of the samurai government mainly led by the monyo (clans basically connected by blood) of his clan members and prominent gokenin (shogun&apos;s vassals).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the samurai class, however, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a descendant of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) who rose as the leader of samurai, called himself chakuryu of the Minamoto clan, established the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and established the basis of samurai government mainly led by the monyo (clans basically connected by blood) of his clan members and prominent gokenin (shogun&apos;s vassals).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the samurai class, however, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, a descendant of the Kawachi-Genji (Minamoto clan) who rose as the leader of samurai, called himself chakuryu of the Minamoto clan, established the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and established the basis of samurai government mainly led by the monyo (clans basically connected by blood) of his clan members and prominent gokenin (shogun&apos;s vassals).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>同じ、源氏であって頼朝が、足利義兼や甲斐源氏などの一門を従え、従弟である源義仲や叔父　源義広 (志田三郎先生)、源行家、同族の源義重や佐竹昌義を圧倒し得たのも、源氏嫡流としての求心力によるところが大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mainly because of his uniting power as the chakuryu of the Minamoto clan, Yoritomo was able to preside over the descendants of the same Minamoto clan such as Yoshikane ASHIKAGA and the Kai-Genji and dominate his cousin MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, his uncles of MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (Master Saburo SHIDA) and MINAMOTO no Yukiie, and MINAMOTO no Yoshishige and Masayoshi SATAKE of the same clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mainly because of his uniting power as chakuryu of the Minamoto clan, Yoritomo was able to preside over the descendants of the same Minamoto clan such as Yoshikane ASHIKAGA and the Kai-Genji and dominate his cousin MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, his uncles of MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (Master Saburo SHIDA), and MINAMOTO no Yukiie, and MINAMOTO no Yoshishige, and Masayoshi SATAKE of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mainly because of his uniting power as chakuryu of the Minamoto clan, Yoritomo was able to preside over the descendants of the same Minamoto clan such as Yoshikane ASHIKAGA and the Kai-Genji and dominate his cousin MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka, his uncles of MINAMOTO no Yoshihiro (Master Saburo SHIDA), and MINAMOTO no Yukiie, and MINAMOTO no Yoshishige, and Masayoshi SATAKE of the same clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="22">
<j>同じく鎌倉幕府で政権を掌握した北条氏も一門で幕府の要職を独占したが、執権の職は数例を除いてそのほとんどが得宗により継承され、惣領たる地位を継ぐ嫡流の地位は非常に重んじられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo clan, who also held the reins of the Kamakura bakufu, dominated the important positions of the bakufu, and yet, the position of Shikken (Chief of Staff to the shogun) was succeeded mostly by the Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan) except for a few examples; the position of the chakuryu to succeed the position of the soryo was highly valued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo clan, who also held the reins of the Kamakura bakufu, dominated the important positions of the bakufu, and yet, the position of Shikken (Chief of Staff to the shogun) was succeeded mostly by the Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan) except for a few examples; the position of the chakuryu used to succeed the position of the soryo was highly valued.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo clan, who also held the reins of the Kamakura bakufu, dominated the important positions of the bakufu, and yet, the position of Shikken (Chief of Staff to the shogun) was succeeded mostly by the Tokuso (the patrimonial head of the main branch of the Hojo clan) except for a few examples; the position of the chakuryu used to succeed the position of the soryo was highly valued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>室町時代以降、武家においては次第に惣領制が強化されつつあり、嫡流の家系が宗家・本家を形成し、庶子家が次第に庶家として、宗家の家臣として編入される例もみられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Muromachi period, the soryo system (a system in which the shoryo of a clan were inherited by clan members but they and their shoryo were ruled by the soryo) was gradually enhanced; the family line of the chakuryu formed the soke and honke, and the shoshi-ke (families other than the chakuryu in a clan) as the shoke (branch families) were integrated into the soke as its vassals in some cases.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Muromachi period, the soryo system (a system in which the shoryo of a clan were inherited by clan members, but they and their shoryo were ruled by the soryo) was gradually enhanced; the family line of chakuryu formed the soke and honke, and the shoshi-ke (families other than the chakuryu in a clan) as shoke (branch families) were integrated as its vassals, in some cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar, redundancy, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Muromachi period, the soryo system (a system in which the shoryo of a clan were inherited by clan members, but they and their shoryo were ruled by the soryo) was gradually enhanced; the family line of chakuryu formed the soke and honke, and the shoshi-ke (families other than the chakuryu in a clan) as shoke (branch families) were integrated as its vassals, in some cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>しかし、庶流にも一定の独自性が担保され、嫡流からの自立を図ったり、公然と逆らう者もあった他、宗家の簒奪や打倒を図る者さえあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shoryu, however, were given a certain level of individuality and some of the shoryu attempted to be independent from or publicly opposed to the chakuryu; furthermore, there were even those who tried to usurp or overthrow the soke.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shoryu, however, were given a certain level of individuality and some shoryu attempted to be independent from or publicly opposed to the chakuryu; furthermore, there were even those who tried to usurp or overthrow the soke.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shoryu, however, were given a certain level of individuality and some shoryu attempted to be independent from or publicly opposed to the chakuryu; furthermore, there were even those who tried to usurp or overthrow the soke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>特に戦国時代 (日本)は室町幕府を開いた足利氏の嫡流　足利将軍家に対し、庶流の細川氏が管領として実権を奪ったり、出雲守護で嫡流であった京極氏は庶流の尼子氏に守護の地位を簒奪されるなど、血筋では地位や権力を担保し得ない実力本位の時代でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku period (period of warring states), in particular, was a time based on merit when bloodline did not guarantee the rank or the power; the Hosokawa clan, the shoryu, took the power as the kanrei (shogunal deputy) from the Ashikaga Shogun family, the chakuryu of the Ashikaga clan who established the Muromachi bakufu; and the Amago clan, the shoryu, usurped the position of Shugo (Provincial Constable) from the Kyogoku clan, Izumo Shugo and the chakuryu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sengoku period (period of warring states), in particular, was a time based on merit when bloodline did not guarantee rank or power; the Hosokawa clan, the shoryu, took power as the kanrei (shogunal deputy) from the Ashikaga Shogun family, the chakuryu of the Ashikaga clan who established the Muromachi bakufu; and the Amago clan, the shoryu, usurped the position of Shugo (Provincial Constable) from the Kyogoku clan, Izumo Shugo, and the chakuryu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku period (period of warring states), in particular, was a time based on merit when bloodline did not guarantee rank or power; the Hosokawa clan, the shoryu, took power as the kanrei (shogunal deputy) from the Ashikaga Shogun family, the chakuryu of the Ashikaga clan who established the Muromachi bakufu; and the Amago clan, the shoryu, usurped the position of Shugo (Provincial Constable) from the Kyogoku clan, Izumo Shugo, and the chakuryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、徳川家康が江戸幕府を開いた江戸時代以降、長幼の序を重んじる徳川将軍家により、嫡流の地位は徳川氏の政権下にあって再び重視されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Edo period when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established the Edo bakufu, however, the position of the chakuryu was emphasized again because the Tokugawa Shogun family highly valued the choyo no jo (Confucian teaching regarding the relationship between senior and junior).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Edo period when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established the Edo bakufu, however, the position of chakuryu was emphasized again because the Tokugawa Shogun family highly valued choyo no jo (Confucian teaching regarding the relationship between senior and junior).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Edo period when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established the Edo bakufu, however, the position of chakuryu was emphasized again because the Tokugawa Shogun family highly valued choyo no jo (Confucian teaching regarding the relationship between senior and junior).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>今日の日本では嫡流という価値観や概念は日常的なものとしては存在していないが、それでも本家や長男を中心に家の祭祀や家名存続を考える志向が強いといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The values and concept of the chakuryu no longer exist in the daily life in today&apos;s Japan, and yet there is a strong tendency to consider the family&apos;s religious services and the continuation of the family name mostly in terms of the honke and the eldest son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The values and concepts of chakuryu no longer exist in the daily life of today&apos;s Japan, and yet there is a strong tendency to consider the family&apos;s religious services and the continuation of the family name mostly in terms of honke and the eldest son.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The values and concepts of chakuryu no longer exist in the daily life of today&apos;s Japan, and yet there is a strong tendency to consider the family&apos;s religious services and the continuation of the family name mostly in terms of honke and the eldest son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ktmchi(id:113301), Andee(id:20421), 小者(id:172526), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>