<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>条坊制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jobosei (a city plan where streets were laidout in a grid pattern)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jobosei (a city plan where streets were laidout in a grid pattern)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jobosei (a city plan where streets were laidout in a grid pattern)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>条坊制（じょうぼうせい）とは、中国・朝鮮半島・日本の王城都市に見られる都市プランで、南北中央に朱雀大路を配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jobosei was the city plan seen in cities that contained the Emperor&apos;s palace in countries such as China, the Korean Penninsula, and Japan; furthermore, the Suzaku-oji Street was placed in the center of the city running from east to west.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jobosei was the city plan seen in cities that contained the Emperor&apos;s palace in countries such as China, the Korean Peninsula, and Japan; furthermore, the Suzaku-oji Street was placed in the center of the city running from east to west.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jobosei was the city plan seen in cities that contained the Emperor&apos;s palace in countries such as China, the Korean Peninsula, and Japan; furthermore, the Suzaku-oji Street was placed in the center of the city running from east to west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>南北の大路（条）と東西の大路（坊）を碁盤の目状に組み合わせた左右対称で方形の都市プランである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jobosei-type city was built in a symmetrical and square shape and streets were organized so that the Oji (jyo) streets that ran south to north and the Oji (bou) streets that ran east to west were arrenged in a grit pattern.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jobosei-type city was built in a symmetrical and square shape and streets were organized so that the Oji (jo) streets that ran south to north and the Oji (bo) streets that ran east to west were arranged in a grit pattern.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jobosei-type city was built in a symmetrical and square shape and streets were organized so that the Oji (jo) streets that ran south to north and the Oji (bo) streets that ran east to west were arranged in a grit pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>思想</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concept</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concept</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concept</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>儒教の教典『周礼』において、王城は次のようにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Scripture of Confucianism, &quot;Shurai,&quot; the capital was built &quot;in a square shape with the sides 36 km long and with each side having 3 gates.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Scripture of Confucianism, &quot;Shurai&quot; (Rites of Zhou) has descriptions about the capital where the emperor&apos;s palace is placed as follows.</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文・訳文を分割し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Scripture of Confucianism, &quot;Shurai&quot; (Rites of Zhou) has descriptions about the capital where the emperor&apos;s palace is placed as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>「一辺9里の正方形で、側面にはそれぞれ3つずつの門を開く。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the capital city, nine streets running east to west and nine streets running north to south were arranged in the grid pattern; moreover, the width of each street was set to be 9 times that of a rut (242.4cm).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The capital was built in a square shape with the sides 36 kilograms long and with each side having three gates.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文・訳文を分割しかっこ補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The capital was built in a square shape with the sides 36 kilograms long and with each side having three gates.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「城内には、南北と東西に9条ずつの街路を交差させ、幅は車のわだち（8尺）の9倍とする。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial palace was placed at the center of the city, a shrine (Sobyo) for the worship of ancestral spirits was placed to the east of the palace, and a shrine (Shashoku) for the worship of the gods to protect the land was placed to west of the palace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the capital city, nine streets running east to west and nine streets running north to south were arranged in the grid pattern; moreover, the width of each street was set to be nine times that of a rut (242.4 centimeters).&apos;</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文・訳文を分割しかっこ補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the capital city, nine streets running east to west and nine streets running north to south were arranged in the grid pattern; moreover, the width of each street was set to be nine times that of a rut (242.4 centimeters).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「中央に天子の宮、その東に祖先の霊を祀り（宗廟）、西に土地の神を祀る（社稷）。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court was placed in the front, located at the south side, and markets were placed in the back, located at the north side.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial palace was placed at the center of the city, a shrine (Sobyo) for the worship of ancestral spirits was placed to the east of the palace, and a shrine (Shashoku) for the worship of the gods to protect the land was placed to west of the palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文・訳文を分割しかっこ補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial palace was placed at the center of the city, a shrine (Sobyo) for the worship of ancestral spirits was placed to the east of the palace, and a shrine (Shashoku) for the worship of the gods to protect the land was placed to west of the palace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「前方、南には朝廷、後方、北には市場を置く。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>前文に付加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court was placed in the front, located at the south side, and markets were placed in the back, located at the north side.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ルールに従い、原文・訳文を分割しかっこ補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court was placed in the front, located at the south side, and markets were placed in the back, located at the north side.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>この思想を背景として、中国に条坊制の王城が発祥した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jobosei-type capital was developed in China based on this concept.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jobosei-type capital was developed in China based on this concept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jobosei-type capital was developed in China based on this concept.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その後、朝鮮半島や日本などへ周礼思想とともに条坊制が伝わり、これらの地域でも条坊制の王城が営まれるようになったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that Jobosei was later introduced to the Korean penninsula and Japan as the Shurai idea was spreading and Jaobosei-type capitals were being developed in these countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Jobosei was later introduced to the Korean peninsula and Japan as the Shurai idea was spreading and Jobosei-type capitals were being developed in these countries.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Jobosei was later introduced to the Korean peninsula and Japan as the Shurai idea was spreading and Jobosei-type capitals were being developed in these countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="10">
<j>各国の例</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Examples of Jobosei in each country</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Examples of Jobosei in each country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Examples of Jobosei in each country</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>中国では、風水説（四神相応）と並び首都建設の基本であったが、宋 (王朝)の時代に入ると条坊制に基づいた都はあまり作られなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joborei, as well as Fusui-setsu theory (Shijin-soo), was a basic idea of constructing capitals in China; however, construction of cities based on Jobosei became unpopular with the beginning the Sung Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jobosei, as well as Fusui-setsu (feng shui theory) (Shijin-soo [an ideal topography for the four Taoist gods, with a river in the east, a broad avenue in the west, a basin in the south, and a hill in the north]), was a basic idea of constructing capitals in China, however, construction of cities based on Jobosei became unpopular with the beginning the Sung Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt>スペル修正し、用語補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jobosei, as well as Fusui-setsu (feng shui theory) (Shijin-soo [an ideal topography for the four Taoist gods, with a river in the east, a broad avenue in the west, a basin in the south, and a hill in the north]), was a basic idea of constructing capitals in China, however, construction of cities based on Jobosei became unpopular with the beginning the Sung Dynasty period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>朝鮮半島では、7世紀後半頃新羅王京において採用されたといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Jobosei was applied in the capital city of Shiragi around the late 7th century in the Korean Penninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Jobosei was applied in the capital city of Silla around the late seventh century in the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Jobosei was applied in the capital city of Silla around the late seventh century in the Korean Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>日本における条坊制の都市には、都であった藤原京・平城京・長岡京・平安京、および、広い地方を統括した太宰府謎・矛盾・多賀城等がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jobosei-type cities in Japan included the Fujiwara Capital, the Heijo Capital, the Nagaoka Capital, the Heian Capital, the Dazaifu and the Taga-jyo Castle which controlled a broad area.</e>
<cmt>謎・矛盾ー意味が通じません。ウィキピーディアには、書かれていませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jobosei-type cities in Japan includes capital cities such as Fujiwara-kyo (the Fujiwara Palace; the ancient capital of Fujiwara), Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara), Nagaoka-kyo (the ancient capital of Nagaoka), and Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), and Dazaifu, Taga-jo Castle and others which controlled a broad area.</e>
<cmt>原文には 「太宰府謎・矛盾・多賀城等」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「大宰府・多賀城等」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jobosei-type cities in Japan includes capital cities such as Fujiwara-kyo (the Fujiwara Palace; the ancient capital of Fujiwara), Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara), Nagaoka-kyo (the ancient capital of Nagaoka), and Heian-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Kyoto), and Dazaifu, Taga-jo Castle and others which controlled a broad area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし、異民族の侵攻の恐れのある大陸においては、郭城（塀＝羅城をめぐらした城）であるが、島国である日本では城壁は作られず（大宰府には城壁があったとも考えられている)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, walls were not constructed around the capital cities in Japan because invasion by other races was not considered a threat because Japan was an island (Dazaifu might have been built with walls), although Rajo (a city surrounded by walls) was seen in the continent where invasion by different races was feared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, walls were not constructed around the capital cities in Japan because invasion by other races was not considered a threat because Japan was an island (Dazaifu might have been built with walls), although a castle with outer bailey (a capital surrounded by walls) was seen in the continent where invasion by different races was feared.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, walls were not constructed around the capital cities in Japan because invasion by other races was not considered a threat because Japan was an island (Dazaifu might have been built with walls), although a castle with outer bailey (a capital surrounded by walls) was seen in the continent where invasion by different races was feared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>平城京・平安京では都の入口を示す朱雀大路の門が羅城門と呼ばれるにとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only Rajyo-mon Gates seen in Heijyokyo and Heiankyo, ancient capitals of Japan in current Nara and Kyoto, respectively, were located at the Suzaku-Oji Street to indicate the entrance to the capital cities.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Rajo-mon Gates seen in Heijo-kyo and Heian-kyo, ancient capitals of Japan in current Nara and Kyoto, respectively, were located at the Suzaku-Oji Street to indicate the entrance to the capital cities.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Rajo-mon Gates seen in Heijo-kyo and Heian-kyo, ancient capitals of Japan in current Nara and Kyoto, respectively, were located at the Suzaku-Oji Street to indicate the entrance to the capital cities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 もね～るmoner(id:28477), Kurz(id:1601), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), Rusk(id:9895), けふこえて(id:17107), ゐ(id:795), Mixtures(id:29234), うぃき野郎(id:53567), Shimoxx(id:9332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>