<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山城屋事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamashiroya Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamashiroya Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamashiroya Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山城屋事件は1872年（明治5年）陸軍省の御用商人山城屋和助が陸軍省から無担保で借り受けた公金を返済できず自殺した事件。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamashiroya Incident is an incident that a government contractor of the Ministry of Army Wasuke YAMASHIROYA committed suicide when he was unable to repay the public money he borrowed from the Ministry without putting up collateral in 1872.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamashiroya Incident was an incident that Wasuke YAMASHIROYA, a government contractor for the Ministry of Army, committed suicide when he was unable to repay the public money he had borrowed from the Ministry without putting up collateral in 1872.</e>
<cmt>is→wasにしました。Wasuke YAMASHIROYAを肩書き(a government contractor･･･）の前にしました。Contractorの後のofをforにしました。Borrowed→had borrowedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamashiroya Incident was an incident that Wasuke YAMASHIROYA, a government contractor for the Ministry of Army, committed suicide when he was unable to repay the public money he had borrowed from the Ministry without collateral in 1872.</e>
<cmt>putting up を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>山城屋の借り出した公金は総額約65万円、当時の国家歳入の1%という途方もない額であった（藤村道生『山縣有朋』53ページによれば「歳入の12%」）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The public money YAMASHIROYA borrowed was 650,000 yen in total, which was an enormous amount of money equivalent to 1% of the annual national revenue at that time (according to the page 53 of &quot;Aritomo Yamagata&quot; written by Michio FUJIMURA, it was 12% of the national revenue).</e>
<cmt>・原文の「あった」と「藤村」の間に全く区切りがなかったため、「藤村」以降の文をカッコで閉じました。   ・本のタイトルである『山縣有朋』の「山縣」は小文字も含めて記述しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public money YAMASHIROYA had borrowed was approximately 650,000 yen in total, which was an enormous amount of money as much as 1% of the annual national revenue at that time (according to the page 53 of &quot;Aritomo Yamagata&quot; written by Michio FUJIMURA, it was 12% of the national revenue).</e>
<cmt>Borrowed→had borrowedにしました。650,000yenの前にApproximatelyを入れました。「1%という」は必ずしも「1%に等しい」わけではないと思われましたので、equivalent toをas much asとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public money YAMASHIROYA had borrowed was approximately 650,000 yen in total, which was an enormous amount of money as much as 1% of the annual national revenue at that time (according to the page 53 of &quot;Aritomo Yamagata&quot; written by Michio FUJIMURA, it was 12% of the national revenue).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>山城屋和助は長州人という縁故で兵部省御用商人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wasuke YAMASHIROYA became a government contractor of Hyobusho (Ministry of Military) taking advantage of his personal connection with people from Choshu, where he was also from.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wasuke YAMASHIROYA became a government contractor of Hyobusho (Ministry of Military) because he came from Choshu.</e>
<cmt>「taking advantage･･･」→「because he came from」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wasuke YAMASHIROYA became a government contractor of Hyobusho (Ministry of Military) because he came from Choshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>軍需品の納入などにたずさわっていたが、陸軍省の公金15万ドルを借用して生糸相場に手をだした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was engaged in delivery of military supplies but he borrowed 150,000 dollars of public money from the Ministry of Army and started to invest in silk market.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While he was engaged in delivery of military supplies, he borrowed 150,000 dollars of public money from the Ministry of Army and started to invest in silk market.</e>
<cmt>この場合の「が」は逆接の意味はないと思われましたので、whileにして冒頭に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While he was engaged in overseeing the delivery of military supplies, he borrowed 150,000 dollars of public money from the Ministry of the Army and started to invest in the silk market.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>この借金の背景には、陸軍省保管の現銀が価格低落を被っていたことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind the background of this borrowings, there was a fact that the price of silver coins kept by the Ministry of Army declined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background of this borrowings was the declined price of silver coins kept by the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>Behindを取って、The backgroundを主語にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background of this borrowings was the declined price of silver coins kept by the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>陸軍省は資金運用を理由として公金貸し付けを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ministry of Army lent the public money to him on grounds of fund management.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ministry of Army lent the public money to him on grounds of fund management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ministry of Army lent the public money to him on grounds of fund management.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>ところが、ヨーロッパでの生糸相場の暴落にあって投機は失敗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, his investment failed since the market price of silk in Europe plunged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, his investment ended in failure since the market price of silk in Europe plunged.</e>
<cmt>failed→ended in failureにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, his investment ended in failure since the market price of silk in Europe plunged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>山城屋は陸軍省から更に金を借り出し、フランスの商人と直接取引をしようとフランスに渡った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He borrowed more money from the Ministry of Army and went to France to deal directly with French merchants.</e>
<cmt>話の続きなので、「YAMASHIROYA」ではなく「he」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He borrowed more money from the Ministry of Army and went to France to deal directly with French merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He borrowed more money from the Ministry of Army and went to France to deal directly with French merchants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのうちに一人の日本人がフランスで豪遊しているという情報が、フランス駐在中弁務使鮫島尚信やイギリス駐在大弁務使寺島宗則の耳に入り、日本の外務省・副島外務卿に連絡が入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, a France-based middle commissioner Naonobu SAMEJIMA and an England-based major commissioner Munenori TERASHIMA heard the information that one Japanese was engaging in extravagances and reported to the Foreign Minister SOEJIMA in Japan.</e>
<cmt>重複を避けるため、「外務省」はあえて入れませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the meantime, a France-based middle commissioner Naonobu SAMEJIMA and an England-based major commissioner Munenori TERASHIMA heard a news that one Japanese was engaging in extravagances and this news was reported to the Foreign Minister SOEJIMA in Japan.</e>
<cmt>the information→a newsにしました。「and reported」の間に「this news was」を入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the meantime, a France-based middle commissioner Naonobu SAMEJIMA and an England-based major commissioner Munenori TERASHIMA heard a news that one Japanese was engaging in extravagances and this news was reported to the Foreign Minister SOEJIMA in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>このころ、山縣有朋は近衛都督として近衛兵を統括する立場にあったが、近衛兵内部の薩摩系軍人には長州人である山縣を近衛都督としていただくことを不服とする空気が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Aritomo YAMAGATA was supervising imperial guards as the commander, but there was a strong dissatisfaction among those guards from Satsuma against YAMAGATA since he was from Choshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, while Aritomo YAMAGATA was on the position of supervising imperial guards as the commander, there was a strong dissatisfaction among those guards from Satsuma against YAMAGATA, who was from Choshu.</e>
<cmt>「立場にあった」ので「on the position of」を挿入しました。「あったが」の「が」は逆接ではないと思われますので、but→whileにしArimotoの前に入れました。「since he was」を「, who was」にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, while Aritomo YAMAGATA was on the position of supervising imperial guards as the commander, there was a strong dissatisfaction among those guards from Satsuma against YAMAGATA, who was from Choshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そこに山城屋の一件を聞いた陸軍省会計監督・種田政明が密かに調査を始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the accounting manager of Ministry of Army Masaaki TANEDA heard the information of YAMASHIROYA and started investigation secretly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Masaaki TANEDA, the accounting manager of Ministry of Army, heard the news on YAMASHIROYA and started investigation secretly.</e>
<cmt>Masaaki TANEDAの肩書きを名前の後にしました。Information of→news onにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Masaaki TANEDA, the accounting manager of Ministry of Army, heard the news on YAMASHIROYA and started investigation secretly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>「一品の抵当もなしに」多額の陸軍省公金が貸し付けられていたことが発覚、桐野利秋ら薩摩藩系陸軍人の激しく追及するところとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that an enormous amount of public money was lent by the Ministry of Army was revealed and the military men from Satsuma including Toshiaki KIRINO grilled about it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that an enormous amount of public money was lent by the Ministry of Army was revealed and the military men from Satsuma including Toshiaki KIRINO investigated it thoroughly.</e>
<cmt>「一品の抵当もなしに」に対する訳がありません。grilled about it→investigated it thoroughlyにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the truth came out that such an enormous sum of public money had been lent, &apos;without any objection&apos;, by the Ministry of the Army, several army officers from Satsuma, including Toshiaki KIRINO, launched an investigation thoroughly.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>同年7月山縣は陸軍中将・近衛都督を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1871, YAMAGATA resigned as a lieutenant general and the commander of imperial guards.</e>
<cmt>「同年」とありますが、それ以前の文に関連する年号の記載がないため、いったい何年なのかわかりません。次の文が「翌1872年」で始まるので、一応1871年としておきましたが、調べてみるとこの年号の正確性は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1871, YAMAGATA resigned as a lieutenant general and the commander of imperial guards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1871, YAMAGATA resigned as a lieutenant general and the commander of imperial guards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>翌1872年（明治5年）、江藤新平率いる司法省による本格的な調査が始まろうとした同年11月、山城屋は山縣から至急の返済を求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1872, when the Ministry of Justice led by Shinpei ETO was about to start a serious investigation, YAMAGATA asked YAMASHIROYA to repay the money he owed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。　「同年11月」の後に、「山城屋は」を付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1872, when the Ministry of Justice led by Shinpei ETO was about to start a serious investigation, YAMAGATA asked YAMASHIROYA to repay the money he had borrowed.</e>
<cmt>owed→had borrowedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1872, when the Ministry of Justice led by Shinpei ETO was about to start a serious investigation, YAMAGATA asked YAMASHIROYA to repay the money he had borrowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>山城屋は公金返済が不可能であったため、陸軍省内部で割腹自殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since YAMASHIROYA was unable to repay the public money, he committed suicide through disembowelment inside the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since YAMASHIROYA was unable to repay the public money, he committed suicide through disembowelment inside the building of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>「陸軍省内部」というのは建物の中であることを言いたいと思われましたので、buildingを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since YAMASHIROYA was unable to repay the public money, he committed suicide through disembowelment inside the building of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その際、関係する帳簿と長州系軍人の借金証文類も焼き払われた為、事件の真相は解明されることなく、陸軍省会計監督長船越衛の処分をもって収束する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because all the relevant account books and debt bonds issued by military men from Choshu were burned away then, the truth of the incident was not clarified and the investigation ended with punishment of the accounting manager of the Ministry of Army Mamoru FUNAKOSHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because all the relevant account books and debt bonds issued by military men from Choshu were burned away then, the truth of the incident was not clarified and the investigation ended with punishment of the accounting manager of the Ministry of Army Mamoru FUNAKOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because all the relevant account books and debt bonds issued by military men from Choshu were burned away then, the truth of the incident was not clarified and the investigation ended with punishment of the accounting manager of the Ministry of Army Mamoru FUNAKOSHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="17">
<j>一説にはこう言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One theory is as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「一説には」がかかっている文章が非常に長かったので、わかりやすくするため分割しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One theory goes as follows.</e>
<cmt>is→goesにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One theory goes as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>徴兵令を推進する山縣とこれに反発する桐野を代表する薩摩系を中心とした保守的な軍人の対立があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a conflict between YAMAGATA who was promoting Conscription Ordinance and KIRINO who represented conservative military men mainly from Satsuma and was opposing YAMAGATA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a conflict between YAMAGATA who was promoting Conscription Ordinance and opposing military men from Satsuma represented by KIRINO.</e>
<cmt>「対立」は山縣対桐野になっていますが、桐野に対する修飾が長すぎるので、山縣対軍人として後半部分を書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a conflict between YAMAGATA who was promoting Conscription Ordinance and opposing military men from Satsuma represented by KIRINO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかも後者が山縣の抑制に期待をかけた西郷隆盛は、却って山縣を評価して弟の西郷従道とともに徴兵令の実施を支援した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, even though KIRINO was hoping Takamori SAIGO would play a major role to restrain YAMAGATA, SAIGO appreciated YAMAGATA on the contrary and supported him to enact Conscription Ordinance with his younger brother Tsugumichi SAIGO.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, KIRINO relied on Takamori SAIGO to play a major role in restraining YAMAGATA, but on the contrary SAIGO appreciated YAMAGATA and, together with his younger brother Tsugumichi SAIGO, supported him to enact Conscription Ordinance.</e>
<cmt>「was hoping･･･would」を「relied on･･･to」にし、その直後のtoをin　～ingにしました。「on the contrary」を「but on the contrary」にして文の継ぎ目に入れ、「even though」を取りました。「with･･･」を「together with」にして、動作「supported」の前に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, KIRINO relied on Takamori SAIGO to play a major role in restraining YAMAGATA, but on the contrary SAIGO appreciated YAMAGATA and, together with his younger brother Tsugumichi SAIGO, supported him to enact Conscription Ordinance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのことに対する（桐野の）山縣への嫉妬と敵意がこの事件の追及を強めた原因とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is ascribed as the cause that KIRINO intensified criticism against YAMAGATA pursuing the investigation of the case out of jealousy and hostility.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。主語がわかりにくいので、カッコ書きで（桐野の）と原文に加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KIRINO&apos;s jealousy and hostility against YAMAGATA was ascribed to the intensified pursuit of this incident.</e>
<cmt>訳文と原文の対応が難解であり、pursuingがどのように繋がってくるのかが分からなかったので、なるべく訳文の言葉を用いて書き直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KIRINO&apos;s jealousy and hostility against YAMAGATA was ascribed to the intensified pursuit of this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>事実、西郷は最後まで山縣の辞任には反対していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a matter of fact, SAIGO was opposing YAMAGATA&apos;s resignation until the last moment.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a matter of fact, SAIGO remained opposing YAMAGATA&apos;s resignation until the last moment.</e>
<cmt>wasをremainedにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a matter of fact, SAIGO remained opposing YAMAGATA&apos;s resignation until the last moment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>さらに、辞任後岩倉使節団の一員として洋行中の大久保利通に対して山縣を擁護出来なかったことを詫びる手紙を送っている（1872年8月12日付大久保宛西郷書簡）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, SAIGO sent a letter to Toshimichi OKUBO who was traveling as a member of Iwakura Mission to apologize that he could not protect YAMAGATA after he resigned (according to the letter from SAIGO to OKUBO written on August 12, 1872).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, SAIGO sent a letter to Toshimichi OKUBO who was traveling abroad as a member of Iwakura Mission to apologize that he could not protect YAMAGATA after his resignation (according to the letter from SAIGO to OKUBO written on August 12, 1872).</e>
<cmt>「洋行」なのでabroadを入れました。「after he resigned」→「after his resignation」としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, SAIGO sent a letter to Toshimichi OKUBO who was traveling abroad as a member of Iwakura Mission to apologize that he could not protect YAMAGATA after his resignation (according to the letter from SAIGO to OKUBO written on August 12, 1872).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>また、司法省の権限強化を目指した江藤新平の追及もこの事件に大きな影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the pursuit by Shinpei ETO who aimed strengthening of authority for the Ministry of Justice affected this incident greatly as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the pursuit by Shinpei ETO who aimed strengthening of authority for the Ministry of Justice also had a great influence on this incident.</e>
<cmt>「追求も」なので、alsoをhadの前に入れ、as wellを取りました。Affected greatly→had a great influence onにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the pursuit by Shinpei ETO who aimed strengthening of authority for the Ministry of Justice also had a great influence on this incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>江藤は、薩摩系軍人が山城屋の事務所封鎖を計画しているのを知ってこれを抑え、司法省が直接捜査に乗り出すよう指示を出している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finding out that military men from Satsuma was planning to close the office of YAMASHIROYA, ETO prevented them and ordered the Ministry of Justice to start an investigation directly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eto, finding out that military men from Satsuma had been planning to close the office of YAMASHIROYA, prevented them and ordered the Ministry of Justice to start an investigation directly.</e>
<cmt>Etoを冒頭に移動し、主語を明確にしました。Was planningをhad been planningにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eto, finding out that military men from Satsuma had been planning to close the office of YAMASHIROYA, prevented them and ordered the Ministry of Justice to start an investigation directly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>関連年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Relevant Timeline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relevant Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relevant Timeline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>1869年（明治2年）6月、山縣渡欧。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1869, YAMAGATA went to Europe.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1869, YAMAGATA went to Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1869, YAMAGATA went to Europe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="26">
<j>1870年（明治3年）8月、山縣帰国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1870, YAMAGATA returned home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1870, YAMAGATA returned home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1870, YAMAGATA returned home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>従五位兵部少輔となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He became Hyobu shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Military), which was Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He became Hyobu shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Military), which was Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He became Hyobu shoyu (junior assistant minister of the Ministry of Military), which was Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="28">
<j>1871年（明治4年）7月、山縣が兵部大輔となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1871, YAMAGATA became Hyobu taifu (the Commissioner of War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1871, YAMAGATA became Hyobu taifu (the Commissioner of War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1871, YAMAGATA became Hyobu taifu (the Commissioner of War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>1872年（明治5年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1,872</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1,872</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1,872</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="30">
<j>2月、兵部省改組・陸軍創設とともに山縣が陸軍大輔となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February, YAMAGATA became Taifu (vice-minister) of Ministry of Army along with the restructure of Hyobusho (ministry of military) and the establishment of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February, on the restructure of Hyobusho (ministry of military) and the establishment of Army, YAMAGATA became Taifu (vice-minister) of Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>along withをonにして冒頭に移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February, on the restructure of Hyobusho (ministry of military) and the establishment of Army, YAMAGATA became Taifu (vice-minister) of Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="31">
<j>3月、山縣が陸軍中将兼近衛都督となる（陸軍卿は任命されず）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, YAMAGATA became lieutenant general as well as the commander of the imperial guard (the post of the minister was vacant).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, YAMAGATA became lieutenant general as well as the commander of the imperial guard (the post of the minister was vacant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, YAMAGATA became lieutenant general as well as the commander of the imperial guard (the post of the minister was vacant).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>5月（旧暦4月）、江藤が初代の司法卿となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, ETO became the first minister of justice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, ETO became the first minister of justice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, ETO became the first minister of justice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>7月、山縣が山城屋事件に関する陸軍内部の追及を受けて陸軍中将・近衛都督を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July, YAMAGATA resigned as lieutenant general and the commander of the imperial guard in response to pursuit by the officials in the Army on Yamashiroya Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July, YAMAGATA resigned as lieutenant general and the commander of the imperial guard in response to pursuit by the officials in the Army on Yamashiroya Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, YAMAGATA resigned his posts as lieutenant general and commander of the imperial guard due to the ongoing internal investigation of the Yamashiroya Incident by army officers.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>西郷が陸軍元帥と近衛都督を引き受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">SAIGO took over the posts of the marshal and the commander of the imperial guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">SAIGO took over the posts of the marshal and the commander of the imperial guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">SAIGO took over the posts of the marshal and the commander of the imperial guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>11月29日、山城屋和助が陸軍省内で自殺。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 29, Wasuke YAMASHIROYA committed suicide inside the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 29, Wasuke YAMASHIROYA committed suicide inside the building of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>「陸軍省内」というのは建物の中であることを言いたいと思われましたので、buildingを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 29, Wasuke YAMASHIROYA committed suicide inside the building of the Ministry of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="36">
<j>1873年（明治6年-新暦）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1,873</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1,873</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1,873</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="37">
<j>1月10日、徴兵令の詔発布</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 10, Conscription Ordinance was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 10, Conscription Ordinance was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 10, Conscription Ordinance was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="38">
<j>4月、山縣が山城屋事件に関する司法省の追及を受けて陸軍大輔を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April, YAMAGATA resigned as vice-minister of Army in response to pursuit by the Ministry of Justice on Yamashiroya Incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April, YAMAGATA resigned as vice-minister of Army in response to pursuit by the Ministry of Justice on Yamashiroya Incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, YAMAGATA resigned as vice-minister of Army due to the ongoing internal investigation of the Yamashiroya Incident by Ministry of Justice.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その翌日、後藤、江藤、大木が参議となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the next day, GOTO, ETO and OKI became councilors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the next day, GOTO, ETO and OKI became councilors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the next day, GOTO, ETO and OKI became councilors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="40">
<j>6月、山縣が陸軍卿となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June, YAMAGATA became the Minister of Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June, YAMAGATA became the Minister of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June, YAMAGATA became the Minister of Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="41">
<j>10月、明治六年政変で江藤、副島らが参議を辞任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, ETO and SOEJIMA resigned as councilors due to Coups of 1873.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, ETO and SOEJIMA resigned as councilors due to Coups of 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, ETO and SOEJIMA resigned as councilors due to Coups of 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Proponent(id:1092), 経済準学士(id:22656), Nishi nishi(id:6874), Nonomura(id:72557), Sillago(id:187189), 彩華1226(id:64711), Hatsune(id:26654), Tsk(id:1153), あいまいみーまいん(id:202365), 玄史生(id:43670), Miya(id:1881), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), じゅらい(id:199203), R28Bot(id:177951), 海獺(id:153448), Korokoro(id:42329), Hdofc(id:175271), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>