<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>地租改正</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>地租改正（ちそかいせい）とは、に明治政府が行った租税制度改革である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land-tax reform refers to the tax system reform by Meiji Government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land-tax reform refers to the tax system reform conducted by the Meiji Government in 1873.</e>
<cmt>間違ってはいませんが、原文どおりに動詞を入れたほうが文として収まりがいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land-tax reform refers to the tax system reform conducted by the Meiji Government in 1873.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また、この改革により日本にはじめて土地に対する私的所有権が確立したことから、地租改正は土地制度改革としての側面を有している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And by this reform, private ownership of lands was firstly established in Japan and thus land-tax reform was also land system reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this reform the right of private ownership of land was established for the first time in Japan; for this reason this land-tax reform had the aspect of the land system reform.</e>
<cmt>一般の読者にとっては耳慣れない「firstly」をより一般的な「for the first time」に変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this reform the right of private ownership of land was established for the first time in Japan; for this reason this land-tax reform had the aspect of the land system reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>旧貢租・田租について</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Old koso (annual tax), denso (rice field tax).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Old koso (annual tax), denso (rice field tax).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Old koso (annual tax), denso (rice field tax).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>地租の由来は、大化の改新により成立した律令国家が、唐に倣って採用した租税制度である「租庸調」のうちの「租」にさかのぼる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of land-tax goes back to &apos;So&apos; of &apos;Soyocho system&apos; (a tax system, corvee), the tax system which the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, established through Taika no Kaishin (Great Reformation of the Taika Era) applied imitating Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of land-tax goes back to &apos;So&apos; of &apos;Soyocho system&apos; (a tax system, corvee), the tax system which the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, established through Taika no Kaishin (Great Reformation of the Taika Era) applied imitating Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of land-tax goes back to &apos;So&apos; of &apos;Soyocho system&apos; (a tax system, corvee), the tax system which the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes, established through Taika no Kaishin (Great Reformation of the Taika Era) applied imitating Tang Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>ここでいう租とは、田畑（口分田）の収益を課税物件とした租税である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So&apos; here is tax levied on profits of rice fields and vegetable fields (kubunden (the farm land given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here the meaning of &apos;So&apos; refers to the land tax levied on the yield of the fields (kubunden [rice fields given to each farmer in the Risuryo system) as the object of taxation.</e>
<cmt>「profits」はふさわしい訳語ではありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here the meaning of &apos;So&apos; refers to the land tax levied on the yield of the fields (kubunden [rice fields given to each farmer in the Risuryo system) as the object of taxation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治以前には田租（たそ）・貢租（こうそ）などと呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Meiji period it was called taso, koso and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Meiji period it was called taso, koso, and so on.</e>
<cmt>用語集には「Meiji period」と「the Meiji period」の両方が登録されていますが、通常は「the」が付きます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Meiji period it was called taso, koso, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>豊臣秀吉の行った太閤検地により、土地の生産力を石高（玄米の生産量）であらわし、その石高に応じて年貢を課すこととされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) production capacity of lands was indicated by (crop) yield (production volume of brown (unpolished) rice) and depending on the yield, nengu (land tax) was levied.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) production capacity of lands was indicated by (crop) yield (production volume of brown (unpolished) rice) and depending on the yield, nengu (land tax) was levied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI) production capacity of lands was indicated by (crop) yield (production volume of brown (unpolished) rice) and depending on the yield, nengu (land tax) was levied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、検地帳に土地の直接耕作者を登録し、その者を租税負担の責任者とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And on a cadastral register, direct cultivators on lands were registered and they were made to be persons in charge of tax burden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And on a cadastral register, direct cultivators on lands were registered and they were made to be persons in charge of tax burden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And on a cadastral register, direct cultivators on lands were registered and they were made to be persons in charge of tax burden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>地租は収穫量を今日でいう課税標準とし、直接に耕作者である百姓からその生産物をもって徴収された（物納）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The base of taxation of land-tax was crop yields and the yields were collected from the farmers, direct cultivators (payment in kind).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The base of taxation of land-tax was crop yields and the yields were collected from the farmers, direct cultivators (payment in kind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The base of taxation of land-tax was crop yields and the yields were collected from the farmers, direct cultivators (payment in kind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>なお、この納入は村請により村単位で一括して行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And this collection was done in a lump sum as a unit of village through the murauke system (village-wide, collective responsibility for tax payment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And this collection was done in a lump sum as a unit of village through the murauke system (village-wide, collective responsibility for tax payment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And this collection was done in a lump sum as a unit of village through the murauke system (village-wide, collective responsibility for tax payment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>地租改正の検討</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revision of land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Investigation into the land-tax reform</e>
<cmt>このセクションでは、廃藩置県が行われる前に抜本的な地租改正の実施を検討していた時期について書いているわけですから、「Revision」ふさわしくないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Investigation into the land-tax reform</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>明治初期から大蔵省や民部省では、全ての土地に賦課して一定の額を金納させる新しい税制である地租の導入が検討されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Meiji period Okura-sho (Ministry of the Treasury) and Minbusho (Ministry of Popular Affairs) tried to introduce the land-tax which was a new tax system where a certain amount of money was collected by levy on all lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the beginning of the Meiji period officials in the Okurasho (the Ministry of Finance) and the Minbusho (the Ministry of Civil Affairs) were investigating into the implementation of the new tax system in which all the land would be levied and in which the government would make people pay in cash a fixed amount of tax.</e>
<cmt>この文における大蔵省は明治時代から2000年まで存在した大蔵省のことですから、「the Ministry of Finance」となります。民部省も明治政府における民部省を指します。民部省の訳には「the Ministry of Civil Affairs」、「the Ministry of People&apos;s Affairs」、「Ministry of Popular Affairs」と複数用語集に登録されていますが、明治政府における民部省の訳は、「the Ministry of Civil Affairs」だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the beginning of the Meiji period officials in the Okurasho (the Ministry of Finance) and the Minbusho (the Ministry of Civil Affairs) were investigating into the implementation of the new tax system in which all the land would be levied and in which the government would make people pay in cash a fixed amount of tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、神田孝平も、に「田租改革建議」を提出して各藩ごとの税の不均衡を正して公正な税制にするための貢租改革が提案されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Takahira KANDA also suggested koso reform in order to make a fair tax system by correcting the disparity of taxes of each Domain, submitting &apos;Proposal for denso reform.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1870 Takahira KANDA also submitted &apos;A Proposal for Land-Tax Reform&apos;; in the proposal he suggested to correct inequality in taxes among domains and make a fair tax system.</e>
<cmt>原文には「各藩ごとの」とありますが、意味するところは藩によって税金の基準が違うという意味ですから、直訳は避けたほうがいいと思います。また、「land tax」 は「明治以前にはtaso (denso)や「koso」とも呼ばれていたと前のパラグラフで読者に説明していますから、ここでこれらの用語を使う必要はないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1870 Takahira KANDA also submitted &apos;A Proposal for Land-Tax Reform&apos;; in the proposal he suggested to correct inequality in taxes among domains and make a fair tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>だが、土地の賦課の是非は大名などの領主の権限と考えられていたこと、従来の検地に代わる大規模な測量の必要性があることから、政府内でも賛否両論があってまとまらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the pros and cons of land taxation was considered to be in the authority of landlords such as daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and so on and it was necessary to do a large-scale survey instead of traditional land survey, the proposal did not see the solution in the government because of discussion both for and against.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this proposal was not put into practice because there were arguments for and against within the government; the main reasons for the opposition lied in that at that time it was believed that the authority to impose land tax or not lied in the feudal lords such as daimyo and that it was necessary to conduct a large scale land survey replacing the existing nationwide land survey before getting into the land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>「代わる」の訳は「replacing」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this proposal was not put into practice because there were arguments for and against within the government; the main reasons for the opposition lied in that at that time it was believed that the authority to impose land tax or not lied in the feudal lords such as daimyo and that it was necessary to conduct a large scale land survey replacing the existing nationwide land survey before getting into the land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>だが、、に廃藩置県が行われると、日本からは領主が一掃される形となり、反対論の大きな理由が失われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was done in 1871 and landlords in Japan were cleared away and a big reason of objection disappeared.</e>
<cmt>「、、に」とありますが、廃藩置県なので、「１８７１年に」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was done in 1871 and landlords in Japan were cleared away and a big reason of objection disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was done in 1871 and landlords in Japan were cleared away and a big reason of objection disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>同年9月「地所売買放禁分一収税施設之儀正院伺」が大蔵省によって作成され、田畠永代売買禁止令の廃止とともに地租改正の実施が明治政府の方針として正式に決定されその準備が急がれたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September in the same year, &apos; &apos; was issued by Okura-sho and with the abolition of Ban on permanently purchasing rice fields and vegetable fields, the enforcement of land-tax revision was officially decided and was hurriedly prepared.</e>
<cmt>「地所売買放禁分一収税施設之儀正院伺」、不明のため、訳出不可でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the September of the same year the Ministry of Finance created the document titled &apos;To Seiin: On the matters of the abolition of the ban on trading and selling of farmland and establishing the tax collection system based on percentage&apos; and submitted it to Dajokan Seiin, the Main Office of the preconstitutional Meiji government that became the Cabinet later, for approval; subsequently the ban on trading and selling of farmland was abolished by the government and the implementation of the land-tax reform was officially concluded as the policy of the Meiji government and the governent quickly made preparation for the enforcement of the reform.</e>
<cmt>「大蔵省」は訳したほうがいいと思います。また、「地租改正」の訳が統一されていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the September of the same year the Ministry of Finance created the document titled &apos;To Seiin: On the matters of the abolition of the ban on trading and selling of farmland and establishing the tax collection system based on percentage&apos; and submitted it to Dajokan Seiin, the Main Office of the preconstitutional Meiji government that became the Cabinet later, for approval; subsequently the ban on trading and selling of farmland was abolished by the government and the implementation of the land-tax reform was officially concluded as the policy of the Meiji government and the governent quickly made preparation for the enforcement of the reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Process.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress</e>
<cmt>用語集には「Progress」と「Process」が両方登録されていますが、後続の文に「この地租改正は約7年にわたる大事業であった」と書いてありますから、「Progress」がより正確な訳だと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>7月28日に地租改正法（上諭と地代の3％を地租とする旨を記載した1ヶ条で構成）と具体的な規定を定めた地租改正条例などから成る太政官布告第272号が制定され、明治政府は翌年から地租改正に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dajokan fukoku (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) No. 272, which consists of law of land-tax reform (consisting of the one article describing the landlords&apos; order and land rent 3％) and regulation of land-tax reform which designates specific regulations and so on, was designated and Meiji government started land-tax reform from next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 28, 1873, the Meiji government promulgated the Ordinance of Dajokan No.272 which consisted of the Land Tax Reform Law (made up of an imperial edict and one article stating the land tax will be 3% of the cash value of the land) and the regulation of land-tax reform in which concrete rules were laid down; in the following year the government started the land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>「上諭」の訳が間違っています。なおウィキピデアの「地租改正」の項目をチェックしたところ、文のはじめの7月28日の前に1873年と書いてありましたので、写し漏れと解釈し、「1873」を訳文に入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 28, 1873, the Meiji government promulgated the Ordinance of Dajokan No.272 which consisted of the Land Tax Reform Law (made up of an imperial edict and one article stating the land tax will be 3% of the cash value of the land) and the regulation of land-tax reform in which concrete rules were laid down; in the following year the government started the land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>政府は当初、検地が農民からの反発を受けることを懸念し、農民からの自己申告主義を採った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first the government was afraid that land survey would receive the objection from farmers and thus applied farmers&apos; self-enumeration policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government initially ordered individual farmers to report details on their land because the government was concerned about farmers&apos; objection on the nationwide land survey.</e>
<cmt>耳慣れない「self-enumeration」のような語句は避けたほうがいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government initially ordered individual farmers to report details on their land because the government was concerned about farmers&apos; objection on the nationwide land survey.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>すなわち、農民自らが地押丈量を行い、面積・収量を算出し、地方庁は地方官心得書の検査例に基づいて点検し、これを経て地方庁が地券（改正地券）を発行するかたちをとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That is, farmers themselves did chioshi-joryo (measurement of land), calculated square footage and amount of crop and the intendance inspected according to examinations by chihokan (a local official) documents and through this the intendance issued the certificate of land title (revised one).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That is, the government adopted the method in which farmers to measure the plots of their land themselves, calculate their yield, and submit the results to local tax officials and the local officials were to examine the reports based on the previous examples described in the instruction book and upon the completion of this inspection, the local office was to issue the new land certificate.</e>
<cmt>主語は農民ではなく政府です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That is, the government adopted the method in which farmers to measure the plots of their land themselves, calculate their yield, and submit the results to local tax officials and the local officials were to examine the reports based on the previous examples described in the instruction book and upon the completion of this inspection, the local office was to issue the new land certificate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかしこの方法では、全国一律公平の租税を徴収する目的は達しがたく、また、の改租結果から、目標の租税額が確保できそうにないことが明らかとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was difficult for this method to reach the goal to collect uniform and fair taxes throughout the country and by the result of tax revision it becomes clear not to be able to secure the target amount of taxes.</e>
<cmt>「また、の」とありますが、単に「また、」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it became clear that it was difficult for the government to reach the goal of collecting land tax uniformly and fairly throughout the country and that the result of the land-tax reform of 1874 made the government know that it was difficult for the government to secure the amount of land tax it had aimed at.</e>
<cmt>時制に問題があります。また、ウィキペディアの「地租改正」をチェックすると、「また、」と「の」の間に「1874年」が入っていましたので、写し漏れと解釈し、「1874年」を入れて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it became clear that it was difficult for the government to reach the goal of collecting land tax uniformly and fairly throughout the country and that the result of the land-tax reform of 1874 made the government know that it was difficult for the government to secure the amount of land tax it had aimed at.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、政府高官間の政争の産物である「大蔵省分割問題」も影を落としていた（内務省_(日本)設置による測量機構と税額算定機構の分離）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, there was the influence of &apos;the problem of partitioning Okura-sho&apos; which was the product of political dispute among high government officials (separation of surveying system established by Ministry of Interior (Japan) and tax-calculating system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the problem of &apos;dividing the Ministry of Finance&apos; cast a shadow into the land-tax reform; that is, the organization responsible for the land survey and the organization responsible for calculating amount of tax were separated owing to the establishing of the Ministry of Home Affairs; this split was the product of the political dispute.</e>
<cmt>明治時代から終戦まであった「内務省」は「the Ministry of Home Affairs」です。 また「大蔵省」も訳したほうがいいと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the problem of &apos;dividing the Ministry of Finance&apos; cast a shadow into the land-tax reform; that is, the organization responsible for the land survey and the organization responsible for calculating amount of tax were separated owing to the establishing of the Ministry of Home Affairs; this split was the product of the political dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>このため政府は、、に内務省及び大蔵省の両省間に地租改正事務局を設置し、これを中心として改租を強力に進めるよう方針転換した（明治8年太政官達第38号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the government established a land-tax revision office between Ministry of Interior and Okura-sho (Ministry of the Treasury) and centering on this, changed the policy to strongly advance the tax reform (Dajokan tasshi (proclamation by the Grand Council of State) No. 38 in 1875).</e>
<cmt>「、、に」を訳出しないようにしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the government founded the Land Tax Bureau between the Ministry of Home Affairs and the Ministry of Finace in1875 and changed its policy to moving agressively for advancing the land-tax reform centering on the newly created Land Tax Reform Bureau (No. 32 of the Transmittal of Dajokan [Grand Council of State] of 1875).</e>
<cmt>「内務省」と「大蔵省」の訳が間違っています（この文章は明治時代の内務省と大蔵省について書いています。） また、ウィキペデアの「地租改正」をチェックすると、「このため政府は、」と「、」の間に「1875年」が入っていますので、写し漏れと解釈し、「1875年」を入れて訳しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the government founded the Land Tax Bureau between the Ministry of Home Affairs and the Ministry of Finace in1875 and changed its policy to moving agressively for advancing the land-tax reform centering on the newly created Land Tax Reform Bureau (No. 32 of the Transmittal of Dajokan [Grand Council of State] of 1875).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>このなかで、府県庁は地租改正事務局があらかじめ見当をつけた平均反収を絶対的な査定条件とし、申告額がこれに達しない場合は、農民が自らの労力と費用をかけて算定した地価を否定し強圧的に変更させたことから、伊勢暴動をはじめとした大規模な暴動が各地で頻発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these, prefectural governments made average tanshu (production per tan), which land-tax reform office previously figured out, absolute assessment condition and if the declared value did not reach this, the governments forcibly made the land price, which the farmers calculated with their labor and cost, changed and thus large-scale riots often happened in various areas, such as the Ise Revolt and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this aggressive approach, each prefectural government made the average yield per tan that the Land Tax Reform Bureau figured out beforehand be the absolute condition of assessment and in case the reported amount was under the average tan that the Land Tax Reform Bureau figured out, each prefecture denied the reported value of the land, of which farmers assessed with their own labor and expenses and made the value of the land change forcibly; for this reason, including the Ise Revolt large scale riots erupted frequently in various places.</e>
<cmt>原文の直訳の「Among these」が何を意味しているのか漠然としていて不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this aggressive approach, each prefectural government made the average yield per tan that the Land Tax Reform Bureau figured out beforehand be the absolute condition of assessment and in case the reported amount was under the average tan that the Land Tax Reform Bureau figured out, each prefecture denied the reported value of the land, of which farmers assessed with their own labor and expenses and made the value of the land change forcibly; for this reason, including the Ise Revolt large scale riots erupted frequently in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>（地租改正反対一揆）これをうけて政府は、1月に、地租を100分の3から100分の2.5に減額することを決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(The uprising for objection to land-tax reform) Because of this, in January the government decided to decrease the land-tax from 3 hundredth to 2.5 hundredth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Peasant revolts against the land-tax reform) In response to these revolts, the governments decided to lower the land-tax rate from 3 percent to 2.5 percent.</e>
<cmt>反対一揆は複数回起こっています。また「地租改正反対一揆」の訳が登録されている訳と違います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Peasant revolts against the land-tax reform) In response to these revolts, the governments decided to lower the land-tax rate from 3 percent to 2.5 percent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="26">
<j>その後政府の強硬姿勢は、頃まで続いたが、税収の見込みがつくようになると徐々に緩和されていき、に耕地宅地の改正作業が完了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the government&apos;s firm attitude continued, but with the prospect of tax revenue, the attitude was gradually eased and revision work of cultivated area and residential area were completed.</e>
<cmt>「頃まで」、「に」とありますが、不明のため訳出できませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hardline stance of the government continued through 1878; but the strict stance was gradually eased as the government was able to have the prospect of receiving revenue from tax and the work of reformation of arable land and the residential land was completed in 1880.</e>
<cmt>ウィキピデアの「地租改正」の項目をチェックすると、「強硬姿勢は、」と「頃まで」の間に「1878年」が入り、「緩和されていき、」と「に」の間に「1880年」が入っています。写し漏れと解釈し、「1878年」と「1880」を入れて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hardline stance of the government continued through 1878; but the strict stance was gradually eased as the government was able to have the prospect of receiving revenue from tax and the work of reformation of arable land and the residential land was completed in 1880.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この地租改正は約7年にわたる大事業であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The land-tax reform was a great undertaking which took about seven years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land-tax reform was a great undertaking which took about seven years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land-tax reform was a great undertaking which took about seven years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>旧貢租と新地租の違い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The difference between old koso and new land-tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Differences between the previous taxation and the new land-tax</e>
<cmt>違いは複数あります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Differences between the previous taxation and the new land-tax</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>前述のとおり、江戸時代までの貢租は米による物納制度であり、あくまで生産者が納税義務者であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned before, koso until Edo period was rice by the system of payment in kind and the producers were tax debtors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned before, koso until Edo period was rice by the system of payment in kind and the producers were tax debtors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned before, koso until Edo period was rice by the system of payment in kind and the producers were tax debtors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また、その制度は全国で統一したものではなく、地域毎に違いがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the systems were not unified across the country and differ depending on regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the tax system was not unified across the country and each region had a different tax system.</e>
<cmt>時制に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the tax system was not unified across the country and each region had a different tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>このような制度を、地租改正により、土地の価値に見合った金銭を所有者に納めさせる全国統一の課税制度に改めたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These systems were revised to nationally uniform tax levy system where landowners paid money according to the land value through land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These systems were revised to nationally uniform tax levy system where landowners paid money according to the land value through land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These systems were revised to nationally uniform tax levy system where landowners paid money according to the land value through land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="32">
<j>新地租の要点としては以下の点が挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The point of new land-tax were as follow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The points of the new land-tax were as follows.</e>
<cmt>要点は複数あります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The points of the new land-tax were as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="33">
<j>収穫量の代わりに、収穫力に応じて決められた地価を課税標準とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of crop yields, the land price was decided by crop yields power and was the tax levy standard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basis of taxation was not the actual crop yield but the cash value of the land based on harvest potential.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis of taxation was not the actual crop yield but the cash value of the land based on harvest potential.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="34">
<j>村単位とする賦課体系を廃して、個別の土地単位で賦課を行うこととした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Assessment system with a unit of village was abolished and with an individual land unit the assessment was done.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the new land-tax system, the system of imposing taxes on each village within the local community as a unit of taxation was abolished and the taxation was to be made to individual unit of land.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the new land-tax system, the system of imposing taxes on each village within the local community as a unit of taxation was abolished and the taxation was to be made to individual unit of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="35">
<j>従前は物納であったものを、金納とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Previously it had been by payment in kind, but it was by money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tax system of paying with crop yield was changed into the system o paying taxes in cash.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tax system of paying with crop yield was changed into the system o paying taxes in cash.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="36">
<j>税率を地価に対する一定率（3％：「旧来ノ歳入ヲ減ゼザルヲ目的」として算定）とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tax rate was decided to be a certain rate for the land value (3％: it was calculated in order not to decrease traditional income).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tax rate was calculated with a fixed rate to the value of the land; the rate was 3%; in deciding this percentage, the Meiji government figured out with &apos;the goal of receiving the tax revenue which was not below that of the Edo Shogunate received.&apos;</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tax rate was calculated with a fixed rate to the value of the land; the rate was 3%; in deciding this percentage, the Meiji government figured out with &apos;the goal of receiving the tax revenue which was not below that of the Edo Shogunate received.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="37">
<j>耕作者ではなく、地券の発行により確認された土地所有者（地主）を納税義務者とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of cultivators, by ensuring through the issuing of certificate of land title, the landowners (landlords) were made to be tax debtors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Instead of cultivators, by ensuring through the issuing of certificate of land title, the landowners (landlords) were made to be tax debtors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Instead of cultivators, by ensuring through the issuing of certificate of land title, the landowners (landlords) were made to be tax debtors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="38">
<j>制度を全国統一のものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system was made to be a nationally uniform one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system was made to be a nationally uniform one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system was made to be a nationally uniform one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="39">
<j>地租改正の影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>安定した税収の確保</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The securement of stable tax revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The securement of stable tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The securement of stable tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>税率を地価に対する一定率とすることにより、従前のように農作物の豊凶により税収が変動することなく、政府は安定した収入を確保することができるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By specifying a certain tax rate for land price, tax revenue did not fluctuate by the crop yields of agricultural crops like before and the government could secure stable tax revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By specifying a certain tax rate for land price, tax revenue did not fluctuate by the crop yields of agricultural crops like before and the government could secure stable tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By specifying a certain tax rate for land price, tax revenue did not fluctuate by the crop yields of agricultural crops like before and the government could secure stable tax revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>具体的には、農作物の価格変動リスクを、政府から農民へ転嫁したものといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specifically, the risk of price fluctuation of agricultural crops was passed on to farmers from the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To be more precise, it can be said that the risk of price fluctuation of agricultural crops was passed on to farmers from the government.</e>
<cmt>「ものといえる」が訳されていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To be more precise, it can be said that the risk of price fluctuation of agricultural crops was passed on to farmers from the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかも、「旧来の歳入を減じない」という方針によって3％という高額な税率が算定されたのである（なお、地租改正の推進派であった木戸孝允はこの高税率を聞くと、農民を幕藩体制よりも酷い状況に追い込むものだとして最後まで反対している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And by the policy of &apos;not decreasing traditional tax revenue,&apos; a high tax rate of 3％ was calculated (when Takayoshi KIDO, who was an advocate of land-tax reform, heard of this high tax rate, he objected to this until the last minute, saying that it forced farmers to harder situation than that of shogunate system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, by the policy of &apos;the tax revenue will be not be below that of the tax revenue that the Edo Shogunate received,&apos; the high tax rate of 3% was calculated; upon hearing this high tax rate, Takayoshi KIDO opposed the rate up to the last minute saying that the rate will drive the farmers into the more dire situation than they faced under the Edo Shogunate government; yet he belonged to people who promoted land-tax reform actively.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, by the policy of &apos;the tax revenue will be not be below that of the tax revenue that the Edo Shogunate received,&apos; the high tax rate of 3% was calculated; upon hearing this high tax rate, Takayoshi KIDO opposed the rate up to the last minute saying that the rate will drive the farmers into the more dire situation than they faced under the Edo Shogunate government; yet he belonged to people who promoted land-tax reform actively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="44">
<j>これは結果的には大多数の農民の負担を高めることにつながり、また土地の所有者がおらず納税が困難な入会地が事実上、政府に没収されたことなどから伊勢暴動、真壁暴動など一揆（地租改正反対一揆）が頻発し、自由民権運動へ影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This eventually led to the increase of burdens of majority of farmers and iriaichi (common land), where tax payment was difficult because there were no land owners, was virtually confiscated by the government and so on, and thus uprisings (against land-tax reform) such as the Ise Revolt, the Makabe Revolt and so on often happened, and this influenced Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In terms of the consequence, this high tax rate resulted in increasing the burden of majority of the farmers; therefore, peasant revolts against the land-tax reform erupted including the Ise Revolt, Makabe Revolt; the part of the reason these revolts occurred lied in that the government virtually confiscated common land (iriaichi) from which the government could not expect to receive taxes; these revolts gave influence to the Jiyu MInken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right).</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In terms of the consequence, this high tax rate resulted in increasing the burden of majority of the farmers; therefore, peasant revolts against the land-tax reform erupted including the Ise Revolt, Makabe Revolt; the part of the reason these revolts occurred lied in that the government virtually confiscated common land (iriaichi) from which the government could not expect to receive taxes; these revolts gave influence to the Jiyu MInken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>このため、士族反乱と農民一揆の結合を恐れた大久保利通の意見で、前述のとおり、に税率が2.5％に引き下げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, Toshimichi OKUBO, who was afraid of collusion of Shizoku no hanran (revolt by family or person with samurai ancestors) and farmers&apos; uprising, proposed a reduction of tax rate to 2.5％, as mentioned before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, the government lowered the tax rate from 3% to 2.5% as mentioned earlier and it was Toshimichi OKUBO who advanced his opinion on lowering the rate to the government because he was afraid of the collusion of the revolts of samurai or ancestors of samurai and peasants&apos; revolts.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, the government lowered the tax rate from 3% to 2.5% as mentioned earlier and it was Toshimichi OKUBO who advanced his opinion on lowering the rate to the government because he was afraid of the collusion of the revolts of samurai or ancestors of samurai and peasants&apos; revolts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="46">
<j>土地の私的所有の開始</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The beginning of private landownership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning of private landownership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning of private landownership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>地券の発行により、個人に対する土地の私的所有が認められることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By issuing of certificate of land title, private landownership for individuals was approved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The issuing of certificates of land titles led to recognition of private landownership.</e>
<cmt>「認められることとなった。」が訳されていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The issuing of certificates of land titles led to recognition of private landownership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この結果、土地は天皇のものであり、臣民は天皇または領主からその使用を許されているに過ぎないと考える公地公民制思想（王土王民説）や封建領主による領主権や村などの地域共同体による共同保有といった封建制度的な土地保有形態が完全に崩壊し、土地にも保有者個人の所有権が存在する事が初めて法的に認められることになり、土地が個人の財産として流通や担保の対象として扱われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the idea of complete state ownership of land and citizens, where lands belonged to the Emperor and the subjects were just allowed to use the lands by the Emperor or landlords, or feudalistic landownership form such as the feudal rights by suzerain or cooperative ownership by villages and so on, completely collapsed and the landownership of individual owners was legally admitted for the first time and the lands came to be treated as individual assets or objects of circulation or collateral.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the idea in that all land was under the sole ownership of the emperor and individuals were merely borrowing the land from the emperor or the idea in that feudal lords had the land ownership or the idea of cooperative ownership by local communities such as villages were completely collapsed; private land ownership by individuals was recognized legally for the first time in Japan; and land came to be treated as the objects of circulation or collateral as the property of individuals.</e>
<cmt>原文に「地主」 (landlords) は出てきません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the idea in that all land was under the sole ownership of the emperor and individuals were merely borrowing the land from the emperor or the idea in that feudal lords had the land ownership or the idea of cooperative ownership by local communities such as villages were completely collapsed; private land ownership by individuals was recognized legally for the first time in Japan; and land came to be treated as the objects of circulation or collateral as the property of individuals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その意味で、地租改正は日本における資本主義体制の確立を基礎づける重要な一歩であるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this sense, land-tax reform is said to have been an important first step for establishing the base of capitalistic system in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this sense, it can be said that land-tax reform is the first important step in establishing the foundation of capitalism system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>ここでは、「いわれている」ではなく、「いえる」ですから、著者の意見を述べています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this sense, it can be said that land-tax reform is the first important step in establishing the foundation of capitalism system in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="50">
<j>なお、地租改正に先立って、政府は、に田畑永代売買禁止令を解除して既に形骸化していた土地の売買禁止の合法化を行い、には地所質入書入規則及び動産不動産書入金穀貸借規則を定めて土地を担保とした貸借も合法化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And before land-tax reform, the government lifted denpata-eitai-baibai-kinshi-rei (a ban on buying and selling fields [of rice and other crops]), legalized the ban on buying and selling lands, which had already lost substance, and also legalized the borrowing and lending with lands as collateral, setting the regulations on pawing and listing real states and the regulations on listing money for rental of crops for movable assets and real estates.</e>
<cmt>「に田畑永代売買禁止令」の「に」、「には地所質入書入規則」の「には」を削除して訳出しました。また、「地所質入書入規則」、「動産不動産書入金穀貸借規則」、定訳不明でした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, before land-tax reform, the government legalized buying and selling of land by lifting the prohibition of sale and purchase of farming land which was already lacked in substance in 1872; in 1873 the government also legalized the borrowing and lending of money by using land as collateral by setting the regulations on pawing and listing real estates and regulations on listing movable property and real estate property for borrowing and lending of money and goods.</e>
<cmt>ウィキペデアの「地租改正」のページと照らし合わせたところ、「に」の前には「1872年」、「には」の前には「1873年」 が入っていましたので、これらの年数を入れて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, before land-tax reform, the government legalized buying and selling of land by lifting the prohibition of sale and purchase of farming land which was already lacked in substance in 1872; in 1873 the government also legalized the borrowing and lending of money by using land as collateral by setting the regulations on pawing and listing real estates and regulations on listing movable property and real estate property for borrowing and lending of money and goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="51">
<j>地主階級に対する参政権の付与</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enfranchisement for landowning class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enfranchisement for landowning class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enfranchisement for landowning class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>地主を納税義務者とすることで、従来の村請負制度が消滅することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By making landlords to be tax debtors, traditional village contract system disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By making landlords to be tax debtors, traditional village contract system disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By making landlords to be tax debtors, traditional village contract system disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>また、地主を納税義務者とすることは、彼らに参政権を付与することを意味し、地主階級に対して一定の政治的な力を与えることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making landlords to be tax debtors meant enfranchisement for them and the landowning class was given a certain political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making landowners pay tax meant giving them suffrage rights; accordingly, the landowning class was given a certain political power.</e>
<cmt>分詞構文の場合でも、「make」を能動態の使役動詞として使う場合は、原形不定詞となります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making landowners pay tax meant giving them suffrage rights; accordingly, the landowning class was given a certain political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="54">
<j>後に帝国議会が開かれた時に、当初衆議院の選挙権や貴族院_(日本)の多額納税議員の資格が与えられたのは、その多くがこうした地主層であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Imperial Diet was held later, at first election franchise for House of Representatives or entitlement of councilor of large taxpayer in House of Peers were given to many of such landlord class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Imperial Diet was held later, at first election franchise for House of Representatives or entitlement of councilor of large taxpayer in House of Peers were given to many of such landlord class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Imperial Diet was held later, at first election franchise for House of Representatives or entitlement of councilor of large taxpayer in House of Peers were given to many of such landlord class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="55">
<j>商業や流通に与える影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The influence of commerce and circulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence on commerce and distribution</e>
<cmt>意味は「influence of land-tax refrom on commerc and distribution」ですから、前置詞は「on」です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence on commerce and distribution</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>従来の藩が租税として集めた米をまとめて江戸や大坂の蔵屋敷を経由して同地の米問屋に売却するというこれまでの米の流通システムが崩壊して、個々の農民が地元の米商人などに直接米を換金してその代金を納め、地元の米商人が全国市場に米を売却するようになるなど、商業や流通に対する影響も大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The traditional circulation system of rice collapsed, where traditional clans collected rice as tax and sold to warehouse merchant of rice in the same place through Kurayashiki (Warehouse-residence) in Edo or Osaka, and individual farmers changed rice directly to money by the local rice merchants and so on and paid and the local rice merchants sold rice in the markets across the country and so on, which largely influenced commerce and circulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land-tax reform also had a large effect on Japanese commerce and distribution system; that is, prior to the reform rice collected as tax from various clans were sold and distributed by wholesale dealers in Edo or Osaka through storehouses of various clans in Edo or Osaka; the reform allowed farmers to change their rice to cash directly at local rice merchants, who sold rice to the market across the country; thus the previous distribution system collapsed.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land-tax reform also had a large effect on Japanese commerce and distribution system; that is, prior to the reform rice collected as tax from various clans were sold and distributed by wholesale dealers in Edo or Osaka through storehouses of various clans in Edo or Osaka; the reform allowed farmers to change their rice to cash directly at local rice merchants, who sold rice to the market across the country; thus the previous distribution system collapsed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="57">
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>地租改正は全ての土地に課税されるものとし、以前に認められていた恩賞や寺社領などに対する免税を否認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Land-tax reform levied all the lands and denied Onsho (reward grants) or tax exemption for territories of temples and shrines, which had been approved before.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Land-tax reform levied all the lands and denied Onsho (reward grants) or tax exemption for territories of temples and shrines, which had been approved before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Land-tax reform levied all the lands and denied Onsho (reward grants) or tax exemption for territories of temples and shrines, which had been approved before.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>これに先立って施行された解放令によって穢地の指定を外されていたかつての穢多非人の所有地も同様であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By Kaiho Rei (Emancipation Edict), which had been put in force before this, the lands of Eta (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (people whose work usually involved handling human bodies or animal carcasses)) and Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (often ex-convicts or vagrants)), whose land appointment was omitted, were also treated likewise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By Kaiho Rei (Emancipation Edict), which had been put in force before this, the lands of Eta (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (people whose work usually involved handling human bodies or animal carcasses)) and Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (often ex-convicts or vagrants)), whose land appointment was omitted, were also treated likewise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By Kaiho Rei (Emancipation Edict), which had been put in force before this, the lands of Eta (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (people whose work usually involved handling human bodies or animal carcasses)) and Hinin (one group comprising the lowest rank of Japan&apos;s Edo-period caste system (often ex-convicts or vagrants)), whose land appointment was omitted, were also treated likewise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、入会地なども同様に否定して国有地に編入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And iriaichi (common land) and so on were also denied and incorporated into national land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And iriaichi (common land) and so on were also denied and incorporated into national land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And iriaichi (common land) and so on were also denied and incorporated into national land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="61">
<j>また、欧米の農村社会の仕組みをそのまま日本に想定したために、不都合な例も発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And as the system of European agricultural village society was applied to Japan as it was and some inconvenient accidents also happened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, because the government assumed that there existed in Japan the same structure of farming society with those existed in Europe and America, undesirable outcomes came to exist, too.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, because the government assumed that there existed in Japan the same structure of farming society with those existed in Europe and America, undesirable outcomes came to exist, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>例えば、地租の算定における一般的な農家の経営の基準を商業生産的な家族経営による拡大再生産が行われている農家とし、また地主と小作人は自由契約による小作関係によって成立しており小作料の増減は地租の増減に対応することを前提として立法された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the standard of management of common farming household in calculation of land-tax was made to be a farming household in which expanded reproduction was done by family-run commercial production, and landlords and tenant farmers were linked by free contract tenant farming, and the increase and decrease of farm rent was legalized on the assumption that it corresponded to the increase and decrease of land-tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the standard of management of common farming household in calculation of land-tax was made to be a farming household in which expanded reproduction was done by family-run commercial production and that landlords and tenant farmers were linked by free contract tenant farming; and the increase and decrease of farm rent were legalized on the assumption that the increase and decrease of the rent corresponded to the increase and decrease of land-tax.</e>
<cmt>動詞が単数になっています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the standard of management of common farming household in calculation of land-tax was made to be a farming household in which expanded reproduction was done by family-run commercial production and that landlords and tenant farmers were linked by free contract tenant farming; and the increase and decrease of farm rent were legalized on the assumption that the increase and decrease of the rent corresponded to the increase and decrease of land-tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>これは実際には「生かさぬように殺さぬように」という発想で再生産が抑圧され、地主の地位が強力であった日本の農業社会の実態に合わず、また実際の地租算定においても生産経費を実際よりも低く見積もられたために、高率の税率も重なって地租が生産経費を圧迫し、小作料を跳ね上げる（当時の物価水準では収穫の1/3近くが地価の3％に相当し、更に地主が利潤を上乗せするために、結果的に小作料が上昇した）結果をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, this did not fit to actual agricultural society in Japan, where reproduction was suppressed with the idea that &apos;not to make them alive or dead&apos; and the status of landlords was strong, and also in actual calculation of land-tax, production expense was estimated to be lower than that of reality and with a high tax rate, land-tax oppressed the production expense and as a result heightened farm rent (in the price level in those days, nearly one thirds of crop yields corresponded to 3％ of land-tax and furthermore, landlords tacked on their profits and thus farm rent increased).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, this assumption proved to be incorrect in the Japanese agricultural society where the position of landowners were strong and reproduction was suppressed under the idea of &apos;let the farmers live only well enough to work but don&apos;t kill them&apos;; In addition, because the production expense was estimated lower than the expense required in the actual calculation of land-tax, together with high tax rate, land-tax put pressure on the production expense and as the result, the land-tax made the farm rent jump; (in the price level at the time, nearly the one third of the crop yield was equivalent to the 3% of the land price, and because the landowners added their profit on top of this, the farm rent increased as the result).</e>
<cmt>「生かさぬように殺さぬように」の訳が文法的に成り立っていません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, this assumption proved to be incorrect in the Japanese agricultural society where the position of landowners were strong and reproduction was suppressed under the idea of &apos;let the farmers live only well enough to work but don&apos;t kill them&apos;; In addition, because the production expense was estimated lower than the expense required in the actual calculation of land-tax, together with high tax rate, land-tax put pressure on the production expense and as the result, the land-tax made the farm rent jump; (in the price level at the time, nearly the one third of the crop yield was equivalent to the 3% of the land price, and because the landowners added their profit on top of this, the farm rent increased as the result).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="64">
<j>更に、法令などにおいて、政府自身が実は3％が高率であることを認めている部分がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, in the regulations and so on, the government itself actually admitted that 3％ was a high rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, in the regulations and so on, the government itself actually admitted that 3％ was a high rate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, in the regulations and so on, the government itself actually admitted that 3％ was a high rate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>現在の税率は印紙税・物品税などの商工業などからの収入が一定の軌道にのるまでの暫定的な税率で、将来はそこからの歳入と財政支出の抑制によって地租依存度を減少させて最終的には1％にまで引き下げると説明しているからである（地租改正条例第6条、地租条例で廃止）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Current tax rate is a tentative one until the revenue from trade and manufacture such as documentary stamp tax and commodity tax gets on track, and they explain that in the future the revenue from them and suppression of financial expenditure will decrease the dependency on land-tax and eventually lower it to 1％ (it was abolished by the regulation of land-tax reform No. 6, land-tax regulation).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government explained in writing that the current tax rate is a tentative one until the revenue from trade and manufacture such as documentary stamp tax and commodity tax gets on track and that in the future the tax rate will be lowered as the revenue from trade and manufacture increase and as the financial expenditure is restrained and that ultimately the government is planning to lower the tax rate to 1% (in the article 6 of the Regulation of land-tax reform [1873]; this article was abolished in the Regulation of land-tax, which was established later [1884]).</e>
<cmt>誤訳があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government explained in writing that the current tax rate is a tentative one until the revenue from trade and manufacture such as documentary stamp tax and commodity tax gets on track and that in the future the tax rate will be lowered as the revenue from trade and manufacture increase and as the financial expenditure is restrained and that ultimately the government is planning to lower the tax rate to 1% (in the article 6 of the Regulation of land-tax reform [1873]; this article was abolished in the Regulation of land-tax, which was established later [1884]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>だが、現実にはなかなか引き下げられなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However in reality, it was difficult to lower the rate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in reality, the government was not able to lower the tax rate so easily.</e>
<cmt>主語があいまいです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in reality, the government was not able to lower the tax rate so easily.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>ところが、後に地租改正条例に代わって制定された地租条例ではこの規定が削除されてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the land-tax regulation, which was designated instead of revised land-tax regulation, this rule was deleted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in the regulation of land-tax which was established later replacing the regulation of land-tax reform, the provision, in which the intention of lowering the tax rate was stated, had been deleted by the government.</e>
<cmt>「地租改正」の「改正」の訳が統一されておりません。またすぐ上の文の始まりが、「だが」で、この文のはじまりも「ところが」と同じ意味のことばですので、実質的な意味をとって訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in the regulation of land-tax which was established later replacing the regulation of land-tax reform, the provision, in which the intention of lowering the tax rate was stated, had been deleted by the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>このことが自由民権運動や初期帝国議会における激しい政府批判を招き、また地租に替わる財源として酒造税の相次ぐ増税の一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This invited a fierce criticism against the government in Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right) or the early Imperial Diet and let to the continued raise of brewery tax as financial resource instead of land-tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This deletion of the provision invited Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right) and fierce criticisms against the government in the initial Imperial Diet; in addition, it became a cause of a series of tax increase of brewery tax as the financial resource to replace land-tax.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This deletion of the provision invited Jiyu Minken Undo (Movement for Liberty and People&apos;s Right) and fierce criticisms against the government in the initial Imperial Diet; in addition, it became a cause of a series of tax increase of brewery tax as the financial resource to replace land-tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="69">
<j>地券の作成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making of certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making of certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making of certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>地租改正の際に行われた測量結果は地券に記され、この内容は地券台帳にまとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The result of measurement when in land-tax reform was described in certificate of land title and this content was summarized in the note of certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A result of the land surveys implemented by the land-tax reform was recorded on the certificate of land title and the content was recorded in a registry of certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A result of the land surveys implemented by the land-tax reform was recorded on the certificate of land title and the content was recorded in a registry of certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>地券は、土地所有を公証し、かつ納税義務者を表示するものとされ、また土地売買の法的手段であるとされたことから、土地の流通および土地金融はすべて地券により行われることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Certificate of land title notarized landownership and indicated tax debtors and was regarded as legal measures for selling and buying lands and thus circulation of lands and land finance were all done by certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Certificate of land title notarized landownership and indicated tax debtors and was regarded as legal measures for selling and buying lands and thus circulation of lands and land finance were all done by certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Certificate of land title notarized landownership and indicated tax debtors and was regarded as legal measures for selling and buying lands and thus circulation of lands and land finance were all done by certificate of land title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="72">
<j>の登記法成立後は、不動産登記登記簿が土地所有を公証するものとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the enactment of recording acts, immovable property registration notarized landownership.</e>
<cmt>「の登記法成立後」の「の」はなしとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Real Property Registration Act was enacted in 1885, the registry of real property became that which to notarize the land ownership.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。またウィキペディアの「地租改正」のページを参照すると、「の」前は「1885年」になっていましたので、この「1885年」を入れて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Real Property Registration Act was enacted in 1885, the registry of real property became that which to notarize the land ownership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="73">
<j>また、地券台帳自体も、に創設された土地台帳制度に引き継がれ、に事実上廃止されて、以後地租の収税はこの土地台帳によって行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the note of certificate of land title was succeeded to the established cadaster system and was virtually abolished and after that, collection of land-tax was done by this cadaster.</e>
<cmt>「に創設された」の「に」、「に事実上廃止されて」の「に」、ともになしとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the registry of certificate of land title itself was succeeded by cadaster system which was found in 1884; and in 1889 the registry system of certificate of the land title was virtually abolished; afterwards, collection of land-tax was carried out by this cadaster system.</e>
<cmt>ウィキピデアの「地租改正」のページを参照すると、最初の「に」の前には「1884年」が入り、次の「に」 の前には「1889年」が入っています。それで、この「1884年」と「1889年」を入れて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the registry of certificate of land title itself was succeeded by cadaster system which was found in 1884; and in 1889 the registry system of certificate of the land title was virtually abolished; afterwards, collection of land-tax was carried out by this cadaster system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="74">
<j>さらに土地台帳は登記簿と一元化されることで、に廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, cadaster was unified with registration and abolished.</e>
<cmt>「に廃止された」の「に」はなしとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the cadaster was to be unified with registry and came to be abolished in 1960.</e>
<cmt>ウィキピデアの「地租改正」のページを参照すると、「に廃止された」の前に「1960年」が入っています。それで「1960年」を入れて訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the cadaster was to be unified with registry and came to be abolished in 1960.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>このとき、土地台帳に記載されていた土地の表示に関する記載（所在、地番、地目、地積）が登記簿の表題部に移記された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, the description on the indication of lands listed on cadaster (address, lot number, land classification and acreage) was transferred to the title part of registration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, the description on the indication of lands listed on cadaster (address, lot number, land classification and acreage) was transferred to the title part of registry.</e>
<cmt>「登記簿」の訳は以下のサイトによると「registry」です。http://www.japaneselawtranslation.go.jp/law/detail/?ft=1&amp;re=01&amp;dn=1&amp;co=01&amp;ky=%E4%B8%8D%E5%8B%95%E7%94%A3%E7%99%BB%E8%A8%98%E6%B3%95&amp;page=1</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, the description on the indication of lands listed on cadaster (address, lot number, land classification and acreage) was transferred to the title part of registry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>したがって、現在の土地登記は、もとは地租改正時に作成された地券及び地券台帳にさかのぼるものであるといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, current land registration is said to have gone back to certificate of land title and the note of certificate of land title made when in land-tax reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it can be said that current registry of land goes back to the original certificate of land title and the registry of the certificate of land title created when land-tax reform was implemented.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it can be said that current registry of land goes back to the original certificate of land title and the registry of the certificate of land title created when land-tax reform was implemented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="77">
<j>しかしながら、地租改正当時の測量技術が未熟であったこと、時間と人員の制約から測量の専門家でない素人が測量にあたったこと、また税の軽減を図るために故意に過小に測量したことなどから、その内容は必ずしも正確なものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the contents were not precise because the technique of measurement was an unskilled one, amateurs, who were not measurement experts, did the measurement works because of constraints of time and human resource and they purposefully underestimated the lands in order to deduce the tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the details of survey at the time of land-tax reform were not necessarily accurate; it was because the survey technique used was primitive, people who were not the specialists for survey engaged in the task owning to the constraints of time and human resources, and there existed people who deliberately underestimated their land to deduce tax.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the details of survey at the time of land-tax reform were not necessarily accurate; it was because the survey technique used was primitive, people who were not the specialists for survey engaged in the task owning to the constraints of time and human resources, and there existed people who deliberately underestimated their land to deduce tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>このことが、現在の登記簿においても、登記簿と実際の地形や測量面積が一致しないこと（いわゆる「縄伸び」「縄縮み」）の原因となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This leads to disagreement between the registration and actual landform or measured square footage in current registration (so-called &apos;nawanobi,&apos; &apos;nawachijimi&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This inaccurate survey resulted in disagreement between the record in the registry and the actual topographical shape of the land or the surveyed area; (these inaccuracies are referred to &apos;nawa nobi&apos; (rope stretching) and &apos;nawa chijimi&apos; (rope shrinking).</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This inaccurate survey resulted in disagreement between the record in the registry and the actual topographical shape of the land or the surveyed area; (these inaccuracies are referred to &apos;nawa nobi&apos; (rope stretching) and &apos;nawa chijimi&apos; (rope shrinking).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="79">
<j>現在、正確な登記簿を作るべく地籍調査が全国的に進められている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At present, acreage survey was advanced across the country in order to make precise registration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Currently, nationwide land registry investigation is underway to create an accurate registry.</e>
<cmt>正確性に問題があります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Currently, nationwide land registry investigation is underway to create an accurate registry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Tomzo(id:16777), 水野白楓(id:22811), G.miyanomori(id:9984), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Osm8010(id:95471), Caren(id:44047), R463(id:150079), モにか(id:197445), Saisohn(id:62166), Taxidriver(id:85024), Avec(id:55682), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Shin-改(id:9914), Fromm(id:71291), Shimoxx(id:9332), Mbdnoob(id:108609), 宗治(id:111540), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>