<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>刈田狼藉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karita-rozeki (刈田狼藉, to harvest rice crop illegally)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karita-rozeki (刈田狼藉, to harvest rice crops illegally)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karita-rozeki</e>
<cmt>補足は削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>刈田狼藉（かりたろうぜき、かったろうぜき）は、中世日本において土地の知行などを主張するために田の稲を刈り取った実力行使をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karita-rozeki or Katta-rozeki means to harvest rice crop illegally in order to claim chigyo (the size of fiefs) to land in the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karita-rozeki or Katta-rozeki means to harvest rice crops illegally in order to claim chigyo (the size of fiefs) to land in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karita-rozeki or Katta-rozeki (刈田狼藉) means to harvest rice crops illegally in order to claim chigyo (tenure) to land# in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>苅田狼藉とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, karita-rozeki (苅田狼藉)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, karita-rozeki (苅田狼藉)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, karita-rozeki can be written in the following Chinese characters: (苅田狼藉)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>発現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Appearance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Appearance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Appearance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>中世日本の荘園公領制では、一つの土地に対して、複数の主体がそれぞれ各自の権利を有することが一般的だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the shoen koryo sei (social structure of the manorial public territory system) in medieval Japan, it was common for two or more parties to have an ownership to a piece of land.</e>
<cmt>荘園公領制は下記を参照しました。http://www.rekihaku.ac.jp/e_kenkyuu/report2001.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the shoen koryo sei (social structure of the manorial public territory system) in medieval Japan, it was common for two or more parties to have joint ownership to a piece of land.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the shoen koryo sei (social structure of the manorial public territory system) in medieval Japan, it was common for two or more parties to have joint ownership to a piece of land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ある土地からの収穫物またはその土地自体に対して、百姓・名主・荘官・地頭・領家・本家などといった多様な権利が重層的に存在していたのである（これを職の体系という）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Farmers, myoshu (owner of rice fields), shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)), jito (manager and lord of manor), ryoke (a lord of manor) and head family had their ownership to harvests generated from a certain piece of land or to a certain piece of land itself and these various ownerships were multilayered (this is called &quot;shiki no taikei (定訳不明, framework of tasks or authorities in specific functions of administration.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>職（Shiki)について下記参照しました。 http://eastasianstudies.research.yale.edu/japanworld/hamada.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Farmers, myoshu (owner of rice fields), shokan (an officer governing shoen or manor), jito (manager and lord of manor), ryoke (a lord of a manor) and head family had their ownership to harvests generated from a certain piece of land or to a certain piece of land itself and these various ownerships were multilayered (this is called &quot;shiki no taikei (定訳不明, framework of tasks or authorities in specific functions of administration.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Farmers, myoshu (owner of rice fields), shokan (an officer governing shoen or manor), jito (manager and lord of manor), ryoke (a lord of a manor) and head family had their ownership to harvests generated from a certain piece of land or to a certain piece of land itself and these various ownerships were multilayered (this is called &quot;shiki no taikei (定訳不明, framework of tasks or authorities in specific functions of administration.)&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>各権利主体は自らの権利の所在を自ら券契や安堵状などにより証明しなければならなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each entitled party had to prove the existence of their ownership by himself using kenkei (券契, 定訳不明) or a letter of ando (安堵状,定訳不明.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each entitled party had to prove the existence of their ownership by himself using kenkei (券契, 定訳不明) or a letter of ando (安堵状,定訳不明.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each entitled party had to prove the existence of their ownership by himself using kenkei (deed of title to one&apos;s property such as a land) or an andojo (a letter of certification of one&apos;s land).</e>
<cmt>券契→kenkei (deed of title to one&apos;s property such as a land)　（参考：http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/60365/m0u/%E5%88%B8%E5%A5%91/）　としました。安堵状→andojo (a letter of certification of one&apos;s land)　（参考：http://www.city.nasushiobara.lg.jp/icity/browser?ActionCode=content&amp;ContentID=1141983589569&amp;SiteID=0&amp;ParentGenre=1141120034307）　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのような不安定な権利関係にあって、所領をめぐる紛争は頻繁に発生していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Given those insecure multiple claims, there occurred many conflicts over territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Given such insecure multiple claims, there occurred many conflicts over territories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Given there were so many weak claims, naturally many territorial disputes arose.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>鎌倉時代初期ごろになると、所領に対する自らの知行権を主張するため、その所領の作物を強制的に刈り取る者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the early Kamakura Period, there appeared a person who reaped crop growing in a territory illegally for the purpose of claiming his ownership to the territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the early Kamakura Period, there appeared a person who illegally reaped crops growing in a territory for the purpose of claiming ownership to the territory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The early Kamakura period saw the appearance of the illegal reaping of crops to establish a claim to the ownership of the land.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これを当時、刈田・刈畠と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was called &quot;karita or karihata (reaping of crop)&quot; at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was called &quot;karita or karihata (reaping of crops)&quot; at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called &quot;karita&quot; or &quot;karihata&quot; (reaping of crops) at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura period</e>
<cmt>period　小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>刈田・刈畠行為をめぐる紛争は当初、所務沙汰（不動産に係る民事事件）として扱われていたが、時代が下るにつれ、刈田・刈畠行為が増加していくと、13世紀後期ごろには違法行為のニュアンスを含む「狼藉」、すなわち刈田狼藉と呼ばれるようになり、通常の所務沙汰とは別個の取扱いがなされ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially, karita or karihata related disputes were handled as shomusata (civil trial dealing with land-related issues), but the number of karita and karihata acts increased with the times, and around the late thirteenth century, such karita or karihata related disputes began to be called &apos;rozeki&apos; with the implication of illegal act, that is, karita-rozeki, and the handling of such disputes was separated from ordinary shomusata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially, karita or karihata related disputes were handled as shomusata (civil trials dealing with land-related issues), but the number of karita and karihata acts increased with the times, and around the late thirteenth century, such karita or karihata related disputes began to be called &apos;rozeki&apos; with the implication of illegal acts, that is, karita-rozeki, and the handling of such disputes was separated from ordinary shomusata.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, karita or karihata related disputes were handled as shomu-sata (civil trials dealing with land-related issues), but the number of karita and karihata acts increased with the times, and around the late thirteenth century, such karita or karihata related disputes began to be called &apos;rozeki&apos; with the implication of illegal acts, that is, karita-rozeki, and the handling of such disputes was separated from ordinary shomu-sata.</e>
<cmt>後に出てくる検断沙汰 (kendan-sata)の表記に合わせ、 shomu-sata としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1310年（延慶 (日本)3）からは鎌倉幕府によって検断沙汰（刑事事件）として扱われ、侍所および六波羅探題検断方の所管となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1310, such disputes were for the first time dealt with as kendan-sata (criminal case) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and was under the control of Samurai-dokoro (the board of retainers) and Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) Kendangata (criminal justice.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1310, such disputes were for the first time dealt with as kendan-sata (criminal cases) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and was under the control of Samurai-dokoro (the board of retainers) and Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) Kendangata (criminal justice).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1310, such disputes were for the first time dealt with as kendan-sata (criminal cases) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), and were under the control of Samurai-dokoro (the Board of Retainers) and Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto) Kendangata (criminal justice).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>実際に事案が発生した際は、侍所・六波羅の命を受けた当該国の守護が現地で紛争をおさめ、守護は経過を侍所などへ報告することとされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the event of the occurrence of a dispute, Shugo (provincial constable) of the state had to settle the dispute at the site under the direction of Samurai-dokoro or Rokuhara Tandai and report the result to Samurai-dokoro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the event of the occurrence of a dispute, Shugo (provincial constable) of the state had to settle the dispute at the site under the direction of Samurai-dokoro or Rokuhara Tandai and report the results to Samurai-dokoro.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the event of the occurrence of a dispute, shugo (provincial constable) of the state had to settle the dispute at the site under the direction of Samurai-dokoro or Rokuhara Tandai and report the results to Samurai-dokoro, etc.</e>
<cmt>など　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>ただし、刈田狼藉は即時、犯罪とされたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was not to say that karita-rozeki was determined to be a criminal immediately.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, karita-rozeki were immediately determined to be a criminals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, karita-rozeki was not immediately classified as a crime.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>裁判を経て刈田行為者の権利が認められれば、刈田行為は刈田狼藉として断罪されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the ownership claimed by a person who violated the karita was found right and acceptable in the court proceedings, his karita act did not constitute karita-rozeki and the person was not convicted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the ownership claimed by a person who violated the karita was found to be correct and acceptable in court proceedings, his karita act did not constitute karita-rozeki and the person was not convicted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the ownership claimed by a person who committed the karita was found to be correct and acceptable in court proceedings, his karita act did not constitute karita-rozeki and the person was not convicted.</e>
<cmt>committed としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>刈田行為は、検断沙汰に含まれる以前は当時の社会で広く受容されていた自力救済慣行の一つとして認識されていたものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before karita act became subject to kendan-sata, it looks to have been recognized as one of self-defense remedial practices which were widely accepted in the society of that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the karita act became subject to kendan-sata, it looks to have been recognized as one of self-defense remedial practices which were widely accepted in society at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the karita act became subject to kendan-sata, it looks to have been recognized as one of self-defense remedial practices which were widely accepted in society at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>室町期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muromachi Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>period　小文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>室町時代に入って間もなく1346年（貞和2）、室町幕府は守護による国内統治を安定させるため、刈田狼藉の検断権および使節遵行を守護へ付与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after the Muromachi Period began, in 1346, the Muromachi bakufu granted shugo (provincial constable) the power of kendan and shisetsu jungyo (process for implementing bakufu&apos;s decision on conflicts regarding property ownership) with an aim to stabilize the governing of the state by shugo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after the Muromachi Period began, in 1346, the Muromachi bakufu granted shugo (provincial constable) the power of kendan and shisetsu jungyo (process for implementing bakufu&apos;s decision on conflicts regarding property ownership) with the aim to stabilize the governing of the state by shugo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1346, soon after the Muromachi period began, the Muromachi bakufu, aiming to stabilize the governing of the state by shugo, granted them the power of kendan and shisetsu jungyo (the authority to implement the bakufu&apos;s judgments on property ownership disputes).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>鎌倉期守護は、侍所などの監督下で刈田狼藉の検断を実施してきたが、室町期守護は自らの権能として刈田狼藉の検断を実施することができるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo in the Kamakura Period was involved in kendan of karita-rozeki under the supervision of Samurai-dokoro (the board of retainers), but shugo in the Muromachi Period was able to be involved in kendan of karita-rozeki based on their own granted power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo in the Kamakura Period was involved in kendan of karita-rozeki under the supervision of Samurai-dokoro (the board of retainers), but shugo in the Muromachi Period was able to be involved in kendan of karita-rozeki based on their own granted power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While shugo in the Kamakura period were involved in the kendan (trials) of karita-rozeki under the supervision of Samurai-dokoro, shugo in the Muromachi period actually exercised their own authority when hearing karita-rozeki cases.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>刈田狼藉紛争とは、国内の武士・荘官などの間に起こった所領紛争に他ならず、刈田狼藉検断権を獲得したことによって、守護は国内の武士・荘官へ大きな影響を及ぼすことが可能となり、以後、室町期守護は国内武士・荘官の被官化を進めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Karita-rozeki disputes were just territory-related disputes occurring among warriors or shokan (an officer governing shoen (manor)) in a state, and after shugo acquired the karita-rozeki related kendan power, they were able to have significant influence on warriors and shokan of the state, and afterward, shugo in the Muromachi Period worked hard to strengthen hikan (low-level bureaucrat) for warriors and shokan of the state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Karita-rozeki disputes were just territory-related disputes occurring among warriors or shokan (an officer governing shoen or manor) in a state, and after shugo acquired the karita-rozeki related kendan power, they were able to have significant influence on warriors and shokan of the state, and afterward, shugo in the Muromachi Period worked hard to strengthen hikan (low-level bureaucrat) for warriors and shokan of the state.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karita-rozeki disputes were just territory-related disputes occurring among warriors or shokan in a state; after shugo acquired the karita-rozeki related kendan power, they were able to have significant influence on warriors and shokan of the state, and afterward, shugo in the Muromachi period worked hard to vassalize warriors and shokan of the state.</e>
<cmt>period　小文字にしました。&quot;shokan&quot; の補足を削除しました。被官化→vassalize としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この刈田狼藉検断権と使節遵行権の獲得は、室町期守護が守護大名へと成長し、国内に守護領国制を布くに至る重要な契機となったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The acquisition of the karita-rozeki kendan power and shisetsu jungyo power provided an important opportunity for shugo in the Muromachi Period to become shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and implement Shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a Shugo dominates a manor) in the state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The acquisition of the karita-rozeki kendan power and shisetsu jungyo power provided an important opportunity for shugo in the Muromachi Period to become shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and implement Shugo-ryogoku system (the system in which a Shugo dominates a manor) in the state.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The acquisition of the karita-rozeki kendan power and shisetsu jungyo power provided an important opportunity for shugo in the Muromachi period to become shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) and implement shugo-ryogoku system (the system in which a shugo dominates a manor) in the state.</e>
<cmt>period　小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>戦国期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sengoku period (period of warring states)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sengoku period (period of warring states)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sengoku period (period of warring states)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)にも刈田行為は行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were karita acts even in the Sengoku period (Japan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were karita acts even in the Sengoku period (Japan.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were karita acts even in the Sengoku period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>室町期守護は刈田狼藉を検断する立場だったが、戦国大名は自軍勢の兵粮とする目的で敵領田畠を刈田・刈畠することが少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo in the Muromachi Period was in a position to exercise kendan for karita-rozeki, and on the other hand, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period carried out a large number of karita and karihata acts in enemy&apos;s rice fields and other territories in order to secure provisions for their armies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo in the Muromachi Period was in a position to exercise kendan for karita-rozeki, and on the other hand, daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) in the Sengoku Period carried out a large number of karita and karihata acts in enemy&apos;s rice fields and other territories in order to secure provisions for their armies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While shugo in the Muromachi period were in a position to hold kendan for karita-rozeki, daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku period, in order to secure provisions for their armies, carried out many karita and karihata on enemy rice fields and other territories.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>またこの刈田行為には、敵側の収穫物を減少させる（奪う）という目的も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These karita acts were also meant to reduce (deprive) the harvest of crops on the side of enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These karita acts were also meant to reduce (deprive) the harvest of crops on the side of enemies.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karita (illegal harvesting) also deprived enemies of crops.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>太閤検地によって土地に対する重層的な権利関係が解消されると、刈田狼藉という行為も概念も次第に消失していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once multilayered relation of right was dissolved as a result of Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), both act of karita-rozeki and its concept gradually disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the multilayered relation of the right was dissolved as a result of Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), both acts of karita-rozeki and its concept gradually disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the multilayered relation of the rights to land were dissolved as a result of Taiko-kenchi (the land survey by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), both the act and concept of karita-rozeki gradually disappeared.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Oxhop(id:2551), Shimoxx(id:9332), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>