<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平氏政権</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taira clan administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira Clan Administration</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira Clan Administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平氏政権（へいしせいけん）は、平安時代末期（1160年代-1185年）に登場した平清盛を中心とする伊勢平氏による政権。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taira clan administration was the administration by the Ise Taira clan led by TAIRA no Kiyomori who lived in the late Heian Period (1160s to 1185)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan administration was the administration by the Ise Taira clan led by TAIRA no Kiyomori who lived in the late Heian Period (1160s to 1185)</e>
<cmt>冠詞を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan administration was the administration by the Ise-Taira clan led by TAIRA no Kiyomori who lived in the late Heian period (1160s to 1185).</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。-補足しました。ピリオド補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>清盛の館が京都六波羅にあったことから、六波羅政権ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Kiyomori&apos;s estate was located at Rokuhara in Kyoto, it is also called the Rokuhara administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Kiyomori&apos;s estate was located at Rokuhara in Kyoto, it is also called the Rokuhara administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Kiyomori&apos;s estate was located at Rokuhara in Kyoto, it is also called the Rokuhara administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>以前、学界では平氏政権を貴族政権的な性格が強いとする見解が主流であったが、1970年代・1980年代頃からは、平氏政権が地頭や国守護人を設置した事実に着目し、最初期の武家政権とする見解が非常に有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, many theories in the field considered the Taira clan administration as being a strongly aristocratic administration, but from around the 1970s and 1980s, a theory that the Taira clan administration was the first warrior class government by focusing on the fact that the Taira clan administration established Jito (local lord of a manor) and Province officers became extremely dominant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, many theories in the field considered the Taira clan administration as being a strongly aristocratic administration, but from around the 1970s and 1980s, the theory that the Taira clan administration was the first warrior class government which focussed on the fact that the Taira clan administration established Jito (local lord of a manor) and Province officers became dominant.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, many theories in the field considered the Taira clan administration as being a strongly aristocratic administration, but from around the 1970s and 1980s, the theory that the Taira clan administration was the first warrior class government which focussed on the fact that the Taira clan administration established Jito (local lord of a manor) and Province officers became dominant.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>平氏政権の成立時期については、仁安 (日本)2年（1167年）5月宣旨を画期とする見解と、治承三年の政変（1179年）の時点とする見解とが出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are two hypotheses on the establishment time of the Taira clan administration, one considering the May 1167 Imperial Order as the start and the other considering the Jisho sannen no seihen (coup d&apos;etat by TAIRA no Kiyomori in November 1179</e>
<cmt>November を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are two hypotheses on the date of the establishment of the Taira clan administration, one considering the May 1167 Imperial Order as the start and the other considering the Jisho sannen no seihen (coup d&apos;etat by TAIRA no Kiyomori in November 1179) as the start.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are two hypotheses on the date of the establishment of the Taira clan administration, one considering the May 1167 Imperial Order as the start and the other considering the Jisho sannen no seihen (coup d&apos;etat by TAIRA no Kiyomori in November 1179) as the start.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>前者の宣旨は平重盛へ東山・東海・山陽・南海諸道の治安警察権を委ねる内容であり、源頼朝による諸国の治安維持権を承認した建久2年（1191年）3月新制につながるものと評価されており、武家政権の性格を持つ平氏政権がこの宣旨によって成立したとする見方である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first hypothesis considers that the Imperial order allowed TAIRA no Shigemori the policing rights in Higashiyama, Tokai, Sanyo and various Nankai roads and is now considered to be related to the new system approved in March 1191that allowed MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to hold the policing rights of various provinces, and this order established the Taira clan administration as having characteristics of a warrior class administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first hypothesis considers that the Imperial order granted TAIRA no Shigemori the policing rights in Higashiyama, Tokai, Sanyo and various Nankai roads and is now considered to be related to the new system approved in March 1191 that allowed MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to hold the policing rights of various provinces, and this order established the Taira clan administration as having the characteristics of a warrior class administration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first hypothesis considers that the Imperial order granted TAIRA no Shigemori the policing rights in Higashiyama, Tokai, Sanyo and various Nankai roads and is now considered to be related to the new system approved in March 1191 that allowed MINAMOTO no Yoritomo to hold the policing rights of various provinces, and this order established the Taira clan administration as having the characteristics of a warrior class administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>一方、後者は、治承三年の政変の際に平氏勢力が従来の国家機構の支配権を掌握したことを重視している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the second hypothesis emphasizes the fact that the Taira forces grabbed hold of the control of conventional national organizations upon the coup d&apos;etat in 1179.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the second hypothesis emphasizes the fact that the Taira forces grabbed hold of the control of conventional national organizations upon the coup d&apos;etat in 1179.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the second hypothesis emphasizes the fact that the Taira forces grabbed hold of the control of conventional national organizations upon the coup d&apos;etat in 1179.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>一般的に平氏政権は12世紀中期から段階的に成立したのであり、仁安2年5月宣旨を大きな画期としつつ、治承三年の政変により平氏政権の成立が完了したものと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In general, the Taira clan administration was established in steps from the middle of the 11th century, and although the May 1167 Imperial Order was a major event, the coup d&apos;etat in 1179 is considered to be when the establishment of the Taira clan administration was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In general, the Taira clan administration was established in steps from the middle of the 11th century, and although the May 1167 Imperial Order was a major event, the coup d&apos;etat in 1179 is considered to indicate the completion of the establishment of the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In general, the Taira clan administration was established in steps from the middle of the 12th century, and although the May 1167 Imperial Order was a major event, the coup d&apos;etat in 1179 is considered to indicate the completion of the establishment of the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>12thに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pre-history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initial Period</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initial Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>平氏政権に至る基盤形成は、白河天皇期に遡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The foundation of the Taira clan administration began in the Emperor Shirakawa period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The foundation of the Taira clan administration began in the Emperor Shirakawa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The foundation of the Taira clan administration began in the Emperor Shirakawa period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>平正盛は、桓武平氏貞盛流の伊勢平氏に出自し、その父の正衡までは軍事貴族の中でもそれほど有力な一族ではなかったが、永長2年（1097年）伊賀国の所領を六条院（白河上皇の娘・郁芳門院の御堂）に寄進して鞆田荘を成立させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">TAIRA no Masamori was from the Sadamori branch of Kanmu Taira clan and his father Masahira was not such a powerful member among the warrior aristocracy, but donated his property in Iga Province to Rokujyo-in Temple (retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s daughter, Ikuhomonin&apos;s Mido, or enshrinement hall) and established Tomoda no sho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAIRA no Masamori was from the Sadamori branch of the Kanmu Taira clan and his father, Masahira, was not such a powerful member among the warrior aristocracy, but donated his property in Iga Province to the Rokujyo-in Temple (retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s daughter, Ikuhomonin&apos;s Mido, or enshrinement hall) and established Tomoda no sho.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAIRA no Masamori was from the Sadamori branch of the Kanmu-Taira clan and his father, Masahira, was not such a powerful member among the warrior aristocracy, but donated his property in Iga Province in 1097 to the Rokujyo-in Temple (Retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s daughter, Ikuhomonin no Mido) and established Tomoda no sho.</e>
<cmt>Retired 大文字にしました。-補足。名前なので、Ikuhomonin no Midoとしました。, or enshrinement hall 削除。年号を追加。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>正盛は預所となり、周辺の東大寺領も取り込んで立荘するなど、白河の政治権力を後ろ盾に東大寺や国衙の支配を除去して実質的な土地所有に成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori became the custodian of this shoen (private estate) and annexed the nearby Todai-ji Temple property, gaining actual land ownership by eliminating control by Todai-ji Temple and the Kokuga (provincial offices) with the backing of Shirakawa&apos;s political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori became the custodian of this shoen (private estate) and annexed the nearby Todai-ji Temple property, gaining actual land ownership by eliminating control by the Todai-ji Temple and the Kokuga (provincial offices) with the backing of Shirakawa&apos;s political power.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori became the custodian of this shoen (private estate) and annexed the nearby Todai-ji Temple property, gaining actual land ownership by eliminating control by the Todai-ji Temple and the Kokuga (provincial offices) with the backing of Shirakawa&apos;s political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>立荘の背景には、東大寺や国衙の支配と収奪を逃れようとする田堵農民層と、自らの所領の拡大・安定を狙った正盛の間に利害の一致があったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interests of the Tato (wealthy farmer) farmer class, who were controlled and deprived by the control of Toodai-ji Temple and Kokuga, and Masamori, who wished to enlarge and stabilize his property, coincided and led to the making of the shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interests of the Tato (wealthy farmer) farmer class, who were controlled and deprived of the control of the Todai-ji Temple and Kokuga, and Masamori, who wished to enlarge and stabilize his property, coincided and led to the creation of the shoen.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interests of the Tato (wealthy farmer) farmer class, who were controlled and deprived of the control of the Todai-ji Temple and Kokuga, and Masamori, who wished to enlarge and stabilize his property, coincided and led to the creation of the shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>正盛は自らに服従した田堵を郎等・家人にして、武士団を形成していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori made the Tato who followed him Roto (vassals) and Kenin (retainers) to produce a warrior group.</e>
<cmt>tato-&gt;有力農民の意</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori made the Tato who followed him into Roto (vassals) and Kenin (retainers) to produce a warrior group.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori made the Tato who followed him into Roto (vassals) and Kenin (retainers) to produce a warrior group.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>一方、白河上皇も権力維持のために、正盛の武力を必要としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Shirakawa required Masamori&apos;s armed forces to maintain his power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Shirakawa required Masamori&apos;s armed forces to maintain his power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Shirakawa required Masamori&apos;s armed forces to maintain his power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>当時の白河は院領が少なく、直属武力もほとんどなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Shirakawa owned little property as a retired Emperor and had almost no forces in his name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Shirakawa owned little property as a retired Emperor and had almost no forces in his name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Shirakawa owned little property as a Retired Emperor and had almost no forces in his name.</e>
<cmt>Retired 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>しかも、白河に対抗する勢力として、異母弟・輔仁親王や摂関家を始めとする伝統的貴族が存在し、田堵農民層を神人・寄人に組織して巨大化した寺社勢力の圧力も熾烈だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the forces against Shirakawa were strong, beginning with the traditional aristocracy such as his half-brother, Imperial Prince Sukehito, and the line of regents and advisers, along with the pressure from the growing religious groups that had organized the Tato farmer class into Jinin (temple followers) and Yoriudo (villeins).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the forces against Shirakawa were strong, beginning with the traditional aristocracy such as his half-brother, Imperial Prince Sukehito, and the line of regents and advisers, along with the pressure from the growing religious groups that had organized the Tato farmer class into Jinin (temple followers) and Yoriudo (villains).</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the forces against Shirakawa were strong, beginning with the traditional aristocracy such as his half-brother, Imperial Prince Sukehito, and the line of regents and advisers, along with the pressure from the growing religious groups that had organized the Tato farmer class into Jinin (temple followers) and Yoriudo (villains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これらの諸勢力を抑えて国政の主導権を確保するため、白河は自らの手足である院近臣や親衛隊ともいえる北面武士を、受領・太政官・兵衛府・衛門府などの公的機関に強引に送り込んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To suppress such opposition and maintain the initiative in national government, Shirakawa forcibly sent members of the Hokumen no bushi (northern guards), who were his close aids and royal guard, into official positions as Zuryo (career provincial officials), Daijokan (coucil of state), Hyoefu (military guards), and Emonfu (outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To suppress such opposition and maintain initiative in the national government, Shirakawa forcibly sent members of the Hokumen no bushi (northern guards), who were his close aids and royal guard, into official positions such as Zuryo (career provincial officials), Daijokan (coucil of state), Hyoefu (military guards), and Emonfu (outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To suppress such opposition and maintain initiative in the national government, Shirakawa forcibly sent members of the Hokumen no bushi (northern guards), who were his close aids and royal guard, into official positions such as Zuryo (career provincial officials), Daijokan (council of state), Hyoefu (military guards), and Emonfu (outer palace guards).</e>
<cmt>councilスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>このような情勢の中で北面武士になった正盛は、出雲国で源義親の濫行が起こると、嘉承2年（1107年）12月19日追討使に抜擢される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this situation, Masamori, who joined the Hokumen no bushi, was selected as Tsuitoshi (envoy to pursue and strike down) on December 19, 1107 in response to the wrongdoings of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this situation, Masamori, who had joined the Hokumen no bushi, was selected as Tsuitoshi (envoy to pursue and kill) on December 19, 1107 in response to the wrongdoings of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this situation, Masamori, who had joined the Hokumen no bushi, was selected as Tsuitoshi (envoy to pursue and kill) on February 9, 1108 in response to the wrongdoings of MINAMOTO no Yoshichika.</e>
<cmt>新暦に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>翌年正月には早くも義親の首を携えて華々しく凱旋し、白河は正盛を但馬守に任じた（ただし、その後も義親生存説が根強く残る）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the next month, he came back victoriously with Yoshichika&apos;s head and Shirakawa named Masamori as Tajima no kami (chief officer of Tajima Province)(However, a rumor that Yoshichika still lived persisted).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next month, he returned victoriously with Yoshichika&apos;s head, and Shirakawa named Masamori as Tajima no kami (chief officer of Tajima Province)(However, a rumor that Yoshichika still lived persisted).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next month, he returned victoriously with Yoshichika&apos;s head, and Shirakawa named Masamori as Tajima no kami (chief officer of Tajima Province) (However, a rumor that Yoshichika still lived persisted).</e>
<cmt>スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>これを契機に北面武士の規模は急激に膨張し、元永元年（1118年）延暦寺の強訴を防ぐため賀茂河原に派遣された部隊だけで「千余人」に達したという（『中右記』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this point onwards, the number of Hokumen no Bushi grew quickly and it was said that the number of troops sent to defent the Kamo Kawara from the monks of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1118 numbered &quot;one-thousand or so&quot;(&quot;Chuyuki&quot;(Diary of a court official)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this point onwards, the number of Hokumen no Bushi grew quickly and it was said that the number of troops sent to defend the Kamo Kawara from the monks of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1118 numbered &quot;around one-thousand or so&quot; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot;(Diary of a court official)).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this point onwards, the number of Hokumen no Bushi grew quickly and it was said that the number of troops sent to defend the Kamo Kawara from the monks of Enryaku-ji Temple in 1118 numbered &apos;around 1,000 or so&apos; (&quot;Chuyuki&quot; (Diary of a court official)).</e>
<cmt>原文に合せて “を&apos;に訂正しました。”を&quot;に訂正しました。1000 をアラビア数字に変更。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>正盛は主に、北面武士・検非違使・追討使といった国家権力の爪牙として活躍するが、各地の受領も歴任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori was mainly active as part of the military arm of the nation such as Hokumen no bushi, Kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura Periods), and Tsuitoshi, but also held positions as an officier at various provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori was mainly active as part of the military arm of the nation, such as Hokumen no bushi, Kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura Periods), and Tsuitoshi, but also held positions as an officier at various provinces.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori was mainly active as part of the military arm of the nation, such as Hokumen no bushi, Kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura periods), and Tsuitoshi, but also held positions as an officer at various provinces.</e>
<cmt>officer に訂正しました。period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>当時、国衙は在地領主・田堵農民層との闘争でその支配体制が危機に瀕していたため、武力による補強が求められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, military reinforcements were necessary because the organizational system of Kokuga was threatened by the conflict with local landowners and the Tato farmer class</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, military reinforcements were necessary because the organizational system of Kokuga was threatened by conflict between local landowners and the Tato farmer class.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, military reinforcements were necessary because the organizational system of Kokuga was threatened by conflict between local landowners and the Tato farmer class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="22">
<j>正盛の子・平忠盛も父の路線を継承して、院政の武力的主柱となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori&apos;s son, TAIRA no Tadamori kept his father&apos;s strategy and became the military mainstay of the government by cloistered emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori&apos;s son, TAIRA no Tadamori maintained his father&apos;s strategy and became the military mainstay of the government by cloistered emperors.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori&apos;s son, TAIRA no Tadamori maintained his father&apos;s strategy and became the military mainstay of the government by cloistered emperors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その役割は鳥羽天皇期となっても変化はなく、牛馬の管理・御幸の警護を行う院の武力組織の中核ともいえる院御厩（いんのみうまや）の預（あずかり）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His role did not change during Emperor Toba&apos;s rule, and became the In no miumaya no Azukari (Head Horseguard), which is the core position in In(cloister) military organization that was responsible for managing the horses and cattle and guarding the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His role did not change during Emperor Toba&apos;s rule, and became the In no miumaya no Azukari (Head Horseguard), which was the core position in the In (cloister) military organization that was responsible for managing the horses and cattle and guarding the emperor.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His role did not change during Emperor Toba&apos;s rule, and became the In no Miumaya no Azukari (Head Horse guard), which was the core position in the In (cloister) military organization that was responsible for managing the horses and cattle and guarding the emperor.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。Miumaya大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>鳥羽院政期になると荘園整理が全く実施されなくなったため、各地で荘園は爆発的に増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the government by the Cloistered Emperor Toba, shoen organization was not conducted., leading to an explosion in the number of shoens around the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the government by the Cloistered Emperor Toba, shoen organization was not conducted, leading to an explosion in the number of shoens around the nation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the government by the Cloistered Emperor Toba, shoen organization was not conducted, leading to an explosion in the number of shoens around the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>忠盛も受領として荘園の設立に関与し、院領荘園の管理も任されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadamori also was involved in making shoens as an officier and was also given managerial positions at the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s shoens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadamori was also involved as an officer in making shoens and held managerial positions at the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s shoens.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadamori was also involved as an officer in making shoens and held managerial positions at the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s shoens.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>肥前国神崎荘の預所となった忠盛は、大宰府の関与を排除して日宋貿易にも直接介入するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he became the Azukari dokoro of Kanzaki no sho (imperial estate) in the Hizen Province, he eliminated the influence of Dazaifu (under the ritsuryo system, governmental office with jurisdiction over Kyushu, Iki and Tsushima) and directly interfered with trade between Japan and Song.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he became the Azukari dokoro of Kanzaki no sho (imperial estate) in the Hizen Province, he eliminated the influence of Dazaifu (the governmental office with jurisdiction over Kyushu, Iki and Tsushima under the ritsuryo system) and became directly involved in trade between Japan and Song.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he became the Azukari dokoro of Kanzaki no sho (imperial estate) in the Hizen Province, he eliminated the influence of Dazaifu (the governmental office with jurisdiction over Kyushu, Iki and Tsushima under the ritsuryo system) and became directly involved in trade between Japan and Song.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="27">
<j>この頃、日宋貿易につながる海上交通ルート・瀬戸内海は、海賊の跋扈が大きな問題となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this period, the Seto Inland Sea, part of the the sea route in trade between Japan and Song, was infested with pirate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this period, the Seto Inland Sea, part of the the sea route in trade between Japan and Song, was infested with pirates.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this period, the Seto Inland Sea, part of the sea route in trade between Japan and Song, was infested with pirates.</e>
<cmt>余分なtheを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これらの海賊は、有力な在地領主、神人・供御人の特権を得た沿岸住民などが経済活動の合間に略奪しているケースが多く、国衙の力だけでは追討が困難だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These pirates were in most cases prominent local landowners or coastal residents with privileges as Jinin or Jugonin (purveyors to the imperial household) that were pirating when not conducting their usual commercial activities and were difficult to control with only the power held by the Kokuga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These pirates were in most cases prominent local landowners or coastal residents with privileges such as Jinin or Jugonin (purveyors to the imperial household) that were pirating when not conducting their usual commercial activities and were difficult to control with only the power held by the Kokuga.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These pirates were in most cases prominent local landowners or coastal residents with privileges such as Jinin or Jugonin (purveyors to the imperial household) that were pirating when not conducting their usual commercial activities and were difficult to control with only the power held by the Kokuga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>鎮圧するには強力な武士の棟梁を追討使にする他に手はなく、忠盛に白羽の矢が立てられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To control the situation necessitated nominating a leader of a strong bushi group as Tsuitoshi, and this led to the nomination of Masamori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To control the situation necessitated a leader of a strong bushi group as Tsuitoshi, and this led to the selection of Masamori.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To control the situation necessitated a leader of a strong bushi group as Tsuitoshi, and this led to the selection of Masamori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>忠盛は海賊追討に成功するが、降伏した海賊（在地領主）を自らの家人に組織化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masamori succeeded in subduing the pirates and organized the pirates that surrendered (local landowners) as his own Kenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masamori succeeded in subduing the pirates and organized the pirates that surrendered (local landowners) as his own Kenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masamori succeeded in subduing the pirates and organized the pirates that surrendered (local landowners) as his own Kenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>忠盛は他の院近臣受領と同じく院への経済奉仕に励む一方で、荘園の預所・受領・追討使の地位を利用して在地勢力を自らの私兵に編成するなど、武士団の増強も怠らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As with other close aides of the In and Zuryo, Masamori worked for the In&apos;s financial gain but also did not forget to strengthen the bushi group by using his position as the Azukaridokoro of shoen, Zuryo, Tsuitoshi to organize local forces into his private troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As with other close aides of the In and Zuryo, Masamori worked for the In&apos;s financial gain but also did not forget to strengthen the bushi group by using his positions as the Azukaridokoro of shoen, Zuryo, and Tsuitoshi to organize local forces into his private troops.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As with other In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier) and Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors), Masamori worked for the In&apos;s financial gain but also did not forget to strengthen the bushi group by using his positions as the Azukaridokoro of shoen, Zuryo, and Tsuitoshi to organize local forces into his private troops.</e>
<cmt>院近臣→In no Kinshin (the retired Emperor&apos;s courtier)受領→Zuryo (the head of the provincial governors)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これは院の権威のみを頼みとする通常の院近臣とは、決定的に異なる点だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the most different characteristic of his from the ordinary close aides of the In, who relied upon the authority of the In.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This characteristic differentiated him from the ordinary close aides of the In, who relied upon the authority of the In.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This characteristic differentiated him from the ordinary In no Kinshin, who relied upon the authority of the In.</e>
<cmt>In no Kinshin前出の為「In no Kinshin」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>仁平3年（1153年）忠盛が没したとき、藤原頼長は「数国の吏を経、富巨万を累ね、奴僕国に満ち、武威人にすぐ」（『宇槐記抄』）と評したが、これは平氏の実力の大きさを物語っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Tadamori died in 1153, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga said of him &apos;Governing several provinces, gaining riches, obtaining followers and full of military prowess&apos;(&quot;Ukaikisho&quot;), and this depicts the greatness of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Tadamori died in 1153, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga said of him &apos;he governed several provinces, gained riches, obtained followers and was full of military prowess&apos;(&quot;Ukaikisho&quot;), and this indicates the greatness of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Tadamori died in 1153, FUJIWARA no Yorinaga said of him &apos;he governed several provinces, gained riches, obtained followers and was full of military prowess&apos; (&quot;Ukaikisho&quot;), and this indicates the greatness of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>忠盛の築いた経済的・軍事的基盤は、子の平清盛に継承された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The financial and military foundation established by Tadamori was passed on to TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The financial and military foundation established by Tadamori was passed on to TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The financial and military foundation established by Tadamori was passed on to TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>形成期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Formative period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Formative period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Formative period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>保元元年（1156年）、治天の君及び摂関の座をめぐる対立が激化し、保元の乱が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict over the position of Chiten no kimi (supreme ruler) and Regent became intense and the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion) occurred in 1156.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict over the position of Chiten no kimi (supreme ruler) and Regent became intense and the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion) occurred in 1156.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict over the position of Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power) and Regent became intense and the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion) occurred in 1156.</e>
<cmt>治天の君→Chiten no kimi (the retired emperor in power)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この乱で清盛は後白河天皇に味方し、その武功により播磨国守となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori took Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s side in this uprising and was rewarded the post of Provincial constable of Harima for his efforts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori took Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s side in this uprising and was rewarded the post of Provincial constable of Harima for his efforts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori took Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s side in this uprising and was rewarded the post of Harima no kuni no kami (the governor of Harima Province) for his efforts.</e>
<cmt>播磨国守→Harima no kuni no kami (the governor of Harima Province)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その後、政治を主導する藤原信西と後白河院政派（藤原信頼・藤原成親・源師仲）・二条親政派（藤原経宗・藤原惟方）の対立が激しくなり、3年後の平治元年（1159年）に平治の乱が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the conflict between FUJIWARA no Shinzei, who led the government and the Goshirakawa cloister government group (FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, FUJIWARA no Narichika, MINAMOTO no Moronaka), and Nijo Shinsei (direct Imperial rule) group (FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, FUJIWARA no Korekata) intensified, with Heijo no ran (Heiji Rebellion) occurred three years later in 1159.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the conflict between FUJIWARA no Shinzei, who led the government and the Goshirakawa cloister government group (FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, FUJIWARA no Narichika, MINAMOTO no Moronaka), and Nijo Shinsei (direct Imperial rule) group (FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, FUJIWARA no Korekata) intensified, and the Heijo no ran (Heiji Rebellion) occurred three years later in 1159.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the conflict between FUJIWARA no Shinzei, who led the government and the Goshirakawa cloister government group (FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, FUJIWARA no Narichika, MINAMOTO no Moronaka), and Nijo Shinsei (direct Imperial rule) group (FUJIWARA no Tsunemune, FUJIWARA no Korekata) intensified, and the Heijo no ran (Heiji Rebellion) occurred three years later in 1159.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>信頼は源義朝を配下につけて、信西を自殺へ追い込むことに成功したが、二条親政派の裏切りと清盛の反撃に遭い、あえなく敗北し処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori gained MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a follower and succeeded in forcing Shinzei into suicide, but was defeated and executed when he was betrayed by the Nijo Shinsei group and counterattacked by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori gained MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a follower and succeeded in forcing Shinzei to commit suicide, but was miself defeated and executed when he was betrayed by the Nijo Shinsei group and counterattacked by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori gained MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo as a follower and succeeded in forcing Shinzei to commit suicide, but was himself defeated and executed when he was betrayed by the Nijo Shinsei group and counterattacked by Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>miselｆ→himselfに訂正しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>平治の乱後の永暦元年（1160年）、清盛は正三位参議に補任され、武士として初めて公卿（政治決定に参与する議政官）となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Heiji Rebellion, Kiyomori was given the post of Senior Third Rank councillor in 1160 and became the first bushi to become a court noble (a Giseikan (legislator) participating in political decisions)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Heiji Rebellion, Kiyomori was given the post of Senior Third Rank councillor in 1160 and became the first bushi to become a court noble (a Giseikan (legislator) participating in political decisions).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Heiji Rebellion, Kiyomori was given the post of Shosammi Sangi (Senior Third Rank, Royal Advisors) in 1160 and became the first bushi to become a court noble (a Giseikan (legislator) participating in political decisions).</e>
<cmt>正三位参議→Shosammi Sangi (Senior Third Rank, Royal Advisors)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>保元・平治両乱は政治抗争が武力で解決されることを示した歴史的な事件だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion) and Heiji no ran (Heiji Rebellion) were historical events that indicated that political conflict can be solved by military force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion) and Heiji no ran (Heiji Rebellion) were historical events that indicated that political conflict can be solved by military force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both the Hogen no ran (Hogen Rebellion) and Heiji no ran (Heiji Rebellion) were historical events that indicated that political conflict can be solved by military force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>乱後、後白河上皇と二条天皇の対立はしばらくの小康状態を経て再燃するが、武士で最大の実力者となっていた清盛は二条の乳父となり、室の平時子も乳母となったことで、天皇の後見役の地位を得て検非違使別当・中納言となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the rebellions, the conflict between the retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo seemed to slightly subside but then flared up again, with Kiyomori, who was the most powerful bushi at that time, gaining the position as the Emperor&apos;s regent by becoming godfather to Nijo and his wife, TAIRA no Tokiko, becoming godmother, and he also became Keibishi Betto (director) and Chunagon (middle councillor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the rebellions, the conflict between the retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo seemed to subside slightly but then flared up again, with Kiyomori, who was the most powerful bushi at that time, gaining the position of Emperor&apos;s regent by becoming godfather to Nijo while his wife, TAIRA no Tokiko, became godmother, and he also became Keibishi Betto (director) and Chunagon (middle councillor).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the rebellions, the conflict between the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo seemed to subside slightly but then flared up again, with Kiyomori, who was the most powerful bushi at that time, gaining the position of Emperor&apos;s regent by becoming godfather to Nijo while his wife, TAIRA no Tokiko, became godmother, and he also became Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) and Chunagon (vice-councilor of state).</e>
<cmt>Retired大文字にしました。検非違使別当→Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police)用語訂正&quot;middle councillor&quot;　-&gt; &quot;vice-councilor of state&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その一方で後白河院庁別当として後白河への奉仕も怠らず、両派の争いに巻き込まれないように細心の注意を払った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, he worked diligently for Goshirakawa as well as Betto of the Office of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa, and was careful not to become entangled into the conflict between the two groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, he worked diligently for Goshirakawa as well as Betto of the Office of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa, and was careful not to become entangled in the conflict between the two groups.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, he worked diligently for Goshirakawa as well as Betto of the Office of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa, and was careful not to become entangled in the conflict between the two groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>時子の妹・平滋子（建春門院）が後白河の皇子を出産すると、一門の時忠・教盛は立太子を画策して二条の逆鱗に触れて解官、後白河院政は停止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokiko&apos;s sister, TAIRA no Shigeko (Kenshunmon-in) gave birth to Goshirakawa&apos;s prince and when Tokitada and Norimori of the Taira clan tried to plan Rittaishi (investiture as Crown Prince) of the prince, they faced the anger of Nijo and were fired and Goshirakawa cloistered government was terminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokiko&apos;s sister, TAIRA no Shigeko (Kenshunmon-in) gave birth to Goshirakawa&apos;s prince and when Tokitada and Norimori of the Taira clan tried to plan Rittaishi (investiture as Crown Prince) of the prince, they faced the anger of Nijo and were fired and the Goshirakawa cloistered government was terminated.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokiko&apos;s sister, TAIRA no Shigeko (Kenshunmonin) gave birth to Goshirakawa&apos;s prince and when Tokitada and Norimori of the Taira clan tried to plan Rittaishi (investiture as Crown Prince) of the prince, they faced the anger of Nijo and were fired and the Goshirakawa cloistered government was terminated.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>ここに至り、清盛は院政派の反発を抑えるため皇居の警護体制を整えるなど、二条支持の姿勢を明確にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, Kiyomori organized the system for guarding the Imperial grounds to suppress rebellion by the cloistered government group, and therefore clarifying his position as supporting Nijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, Kiyomori organized the system for guarding the Imperial grounds to suppress rebellion by the cloistered government group, therefore clarifying his position as supporting Nijo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, Kiyomori organized the system for guarding the Imperial grounds to suppress rebellion by the cloistered government group, therefore clarifying his position as supporting Nijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>さらに関白藤原基実に娘の盛子を嫁入れし、摂関家にも接近する姿勢をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He further married his daughter Moriko to the Imperial Regent FUJIWARA no Motozane and tried to keep a close relationship with the line of regents and advisers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He further married his daughter Moriko to the Imperial Regent FUJIWARA no Motozane and tried to keep a close relationship with the line of regents and advisers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He further married his daughter Moriko to the Imperial Regent FUJIWARA no Motozane and tried to keep a close relationship with the line of regents and advisers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="46">
<j>永万元年（1165年）に二条天皇が死去した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Nijo died in 1165.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Nijo died in 1165.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Nijo died in 1165.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>前後して前関白藤原忠通（1164年死去）、太政大臣藤原伊通（1165年死去）、摂政藤原基実（1166年死去）など、政治の中心人物たちが相次いでこの世を去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around that time, several of the major political players died, such as former Imperial Regent FUJIWARA no Tadamichi(1164), Grand Minister of State FUJIWARA no Koremichi(1165) and Regent FUJIWARA no Motozane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around that time, several of the major political players died, such as former Imperial Regent FUJIWARA no Tadamichi (1164), Grand Minister of State FUJIWARA no Koremichi (1165) and Regent FUJIWARA no Motozane.</e>
<cmt>空白を調整しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around that time, several of the major political players died, such as former Imperial Regent FUJIWARA no Tadamichi (1164), Grand Minister of State FUJIWARA no Koremichi (1165) and Regent FUJIWARA no Motozane (1166).</e>
<cmt>(1166)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>清盛は院近臣の昇進の限界とされていた大納言となり女婿の基実を補佐していたが、基実が急死して後白河院政が復活すると「勲労久しく積もりて、社稷を安く全せり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori was Dainagon (Chief councilor of state), which was considered the highest position attainable by a close aide of the cloistered government, and supported his son-in-law Motozane, but when Motozane suddenly passed away, the Goshirakawa cloistered government was revived and &quot;His past achievements are many and the State is peaceful and settled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori was Dainagon (Chief councilor of state), which was considered the highest position attainable by a close aide of the cloistered government, and supported his son-in-law Motozane, but when Motozane suddenly passed away, the Goshirakawa cloistered government was revived and &quot;His past achievements are many and the State is peaceful and settled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori was Dainagon (Chief councilor of state), which was considered the highest position attainable by a close aide of the cloistered government, and supported his son-in-law Motozane, but when Motozane suddenly passed away, the Goshirakawa cloistered government was revived and &apos;His past achievements are many and the State is peaceful and settled.</e>
<cmt>“を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その功、古を振るにも比類少なければ、酬賞無くてやは有るべき」という理由で仁安元年（1166年）に内大臣へ昇進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This effort is unmatchable and should be rewarded&quot; was the reason why he was promoted to Nai-daijin (Minister of the Interior) in 1166.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This effort is unmatchable and should be rewarded&quot; was the reason why he was promoted to Nai-daijin (Minister of the Interior) in 1166.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This effort is unmatchable and should be rewarded&apos; was the reason why he was promoted to Nai-daijin (Minister of the Interior) in 1166.</e>
<cmt>“を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>大臣に昇進できたのは摂関家（中御門流・花山院流も含む）・村上源氏・閑院流に限られていて、清盛の昇進は未曾有のものだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only members of the line of regents (including the Naka no mikado branch, Kazan-in branch), Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan) and Kan-in branch were allowed to be promoted as Daijin (Minister) so Kiyomori&apos;s promotion was unheard of.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only members of the line of regents (including the Naka no mikado branch, Kazan-in branch), Murakami Genji (Minamoto clan) and Kan-in branch were allowed to be promoted to Daijin (Minister) so Kiyomori&apos;s promotion was unheard of.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only members of the line of regents (including the Naka no mikado branch, Kazanin branch), Murakami-Genji (Minamoto clan) and Kanin branch were allowed to be promoted to Daijin (Minister) so Kiyomori&apos;s promotion was unheard of.</e>
<cmt>-削除。-補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>なお翌年には太政大臣となるが、太政大臣はすでに実権のない名誉職となっていて、清盛は僅か3ヵ月で辞任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The next year, he became the Grand Minister of State, but this position was in name only and Kiyomori resigns after only 3 months at this post.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The next year, he became the Grand Minister of State, but this position was in name only and Kiyomori resigned after only 3 months in this post.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The next year, he became the Grand Minister of State, but this position was in name only and Kiyomori resigned after only 3 months in this post.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>この時期の清盛の出世について「当時の貴族社会の中では清盛を白河上皇の落胤とする説が信じられており、このことが清盛の異例の昇進に強く影響した」という説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the rapid progression of Kiyomori&apos;s career at this time, there is a hypothesis that &quot;many within the aristocracy believed the theory that Kiyomori was retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s illegitimate child and this led to his rapid promotion&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the rapid progression of Kiyomori&apos;s career at this time, there is a hypothesis that &quot;many within the aristocracy believed the theory that Kiyomori was retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s illegitimate child and this led to his rapid promotion&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the rapid progression of Kiyomori&apos;s career at this time, there is a hypothesis that &apos;many within the aristocracy believed the theory that Kiyomori was retired Emperor Shirakawa&apos;s illegitimate child and this led to his rapid promotion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>“を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>一方、橋本治はこれについて高倉天皇が立太子式を挙げた場所が藤原家の中でも最も格の高い邸宅であった東三条殿であったことに注目し、しかもこの東三条殿の当時の所有者が清盛の娘の盛子であった（藤原基実はこの立太子式の3ヶ月前に死去）ことが強く影響したという説を立てている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Osamu HASHIMOTO proposed a hypothesis that focused on the fact that Emperor Takakura held the ceremony for becoming Crown Prince was the Higashi Sanjo-den, the most noblest of all residences within the Fujiwara family, and that the owner of this residence was Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, Moriko (FUJIWARA no Motozane had died 3 months before the ceremony) could have strongly affected his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Osamu HASHIMOTO proposed an alternative hypothesis that focused on the fact that Emperor Takakura held the ceremony for becoming Crown Prince at the Higashi Sanjo-den, the noblest of all residences within the Fujiwara family, and that the owner of this residence was Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, Moriko (FUJIWARA no Motozane had died 3 months before the ceremony), who could have strongly affected his position.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Osamu HASHIMOTO proposed an alternative hypothesis that focused on the fact that Emperor Takakura held the ceremony for becoming Crown Prince at the Higashi Sanjo-den, the noblest of all residences within the Fujiwara family, and that the owner of this residence was Kiyomori&apos;s daughter, Moriko (FUJIWARA no Motozane had died 3 months before the ceremony), who could have strongly affected his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>橋本によれば、清盛はこの状況を奇貨として滋子の生んだ皇子の養母を「先の摂政の未亡人」である盛子に引き受けさせ、「東宮の養母の父親」である清盛が内大臣や太政大臣に出世する口実としたとされる（橋本200622-24）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Hashimoto, Kiyomori seized the chance by making Moriko (who was the widow of the former Regent) as foster mother of the prince that Shigeko gave birth, and therefore Kiyomori became the &quot;father of the foster mother of the Crown Prince&quot; and used this as a reason to be promoted as Nai-daijin and Daijyo-daijin(Hashimoto200622-24).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Hashimoto, Kiyomori seized the chance by making Moriko (who was the widow of the former Regent) the foster mother of the prince that Shigeko gave birth to, and therefore Kiyomori became the &quot;father of the foster mother of the Crown Prince&quot; and used this as a reason to promote him to Nai-daijin and Daijyo-daijin (Hashimoto200622-24).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Hashimoto, Kiyomori seized the chance by making Moriko (who was the widow of the former Regent) the foster mother of the prince that Shigeko gave birth to, and therefore Kiyomori became the &apos;father of the foster mother of the Crown Prince&apos; and used this as a reason to promote him to Nai-daijin and Daijyo-daijin (Hashimoto 200622-24).</e>
<cmt>“を&apos;に訂正しました。スペース補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>全盛期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peak</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peak</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peak</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="55">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）に滋子が出産した後白河の皇子が高倉天皇として即位した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1168, Goshirakawa&apos;s prince by Shigeko became Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1168, Goshirakawa&apos;s prince borne by Shigeko became Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1168, Goshirakawa&apos;s prince borne by Shigeko became Emperor Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>高倉の即位は、清盛だけでなく、安定した王統の確立を目指していた後白河も望んでいたものであり、後白河と清盛は利害をともにする関係にあったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakura&apos;s ascension was wished for by not only Kiyomori, but also Goshirakawa, who wanted to establish a stable Imperial line, and therefore the relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori may be considered to have common interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakura&apos;s ascension was wished for by not only Kiyomori, but also Goshirakawa, who wanted to establish a stable Imperial line, and therefore the relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori may be considered to have had common interests.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakura&apos;s ascension was wished for by not only Kiyomori, but also Goshirakawa, who wanted to establish a stable Imperial line, and therefore the relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori may be considered to have had common interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>この時期まで後白河と清盛の関係は良好であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori was good until this point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori was good until this point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori was good until this point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>清盛の家系は、代々院に仕えることで勢力を増してきたのであり、清盛も後白河の院司として精力的に貢献を重ねてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s family line had been followers of the cloistered government for generations and Kiyomori had been diligently contributing to Goshirakawa as his follower.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori&apos;s family line had been followers of the cloistered government for generations and Kiyomori had been diligently contributing to Goshirakawa as his follower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s family line had been followers of the cloistered government for generations and Kiyomori had been diligently contributing to Goshirakawa as his follower.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>応保2年（1162年）、後白河が日宋貿易の発展を目論んで摂津の大輪田泊を修築した際、清盛は隣接地の福原に日宋貿易の拠点として山荘を築いているが、このことは、後白河と清盛が共同して日宋貿易に取り組んでいたことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1162, Goshirakawa renovated Owada no tomari in Settsu with an eye on developing trade between Japan and Song, and Kiyomori built a mountain residence in the neighboring Fukuhara as a base for Japan-Song trade, showing that Goshirakwa and Kiyomori worked together to develop Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1162, Goshirakawa renovated Owada no tomari in Settsu with an eye on developing trade between Japan and Song, and Kiyomori built a mountain residence in the neighboring Fukuhara as a base for Japan-Song trade, showing that Goshirakwa and Kiyomori worked together to develop Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1162, Goshirakawa renovated Owada no tomari in Settsu with an eye on developing trade between Japan and Song, and Kiyomori built a mountain residence in the neighboring Fukuhara as a base for Japan-Song trade, showing that Goshirakwa and Kiyomori worked together to develop Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>清盛は、若い頃から西国の国司を歴任し、父から受け継いだ西国の平氏勢力をさらに強化していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori had taken positions as Kokushi (provincial governor) in Western Japan since he was young, and he further strengthened the influence of the Taira clan in the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori held the position of Kokushi (provincial governor) in Western Japan since he was young, and he further strengthened the influence of the Taira clan in the west.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori held the position of Kokushi (provincial governor) in Western Japan since he was young, and he further strengthened the influence of the Taira clan in the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>大宰大弐を務めた時は日宋貿易に深く関与し、安芸守・播磨守を務めた時は瀬戸内海の海賊を伊勢平氏勢力下の水軍に編成して瀬戸内海交通の支配を強めていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was deeply involved in Japan-Song trade when he was Dazai no daini (the next seat position of Dazaifu), and he organized the pirates in the Seto Inland Sea as a naval force under the Ise Heishi (Taira clan) when he was governor of the Aki and Harima provinces and strengthened his control over Seto Inland Sea transportation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was deeply involved in Japan-Song trade when he was Dazai no daini (the next seat position of Dazaifu), and he organized the pirates in the Seto Inland Sea as a naval force under the Ise Heishi (Taira clan) when he was governor of the Aki and Harima provinces and strengthened his control over Seto Inland Sea transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was deeply involved in Japan-Song trade when he was Dazai no daini (the next seat position of Dazaifu), and he organized the pirates in the Seto Inland Sea as a naval force under the Ise Heishi (Taira clan) when he was governor of the Aki and Harima Provinces and strengthened his control over Seto Inland Sea transportation.</e>
<cmt>Provinces大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>こうして涵養した実力を背景として、清盛は後白河と深く結びついていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With such a background of accumulating power, Kiyomori was deeply connected with Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With such a background of accumulating power, Kiyomori was deeply connected with Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With such a background of accumulating power, Kiyomori was deeply connected with Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="63">
<j>また、基実が死去した際、清盛は摂関家が蓄積してきた荘園群を基実の正室盛子＝清盛の娘に伝領させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, when Motozane died, Kiyomori had all of the shoen groups accumulated by the line of regents inherited by Motozane&apos;s official wife = Moriko, Kiyomori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, when Motozane died, Kiyomori had all of the shoen groups accumulated by the line of regents inherited by Motozane&apos;s official wife, Moriko, Kiyomori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, when Motozane died, Kiyomori had all of the shoen groups accumulated by the line of regents inherited by Motozane&apos;s official wife, Moriko, Kiyomori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>これにより清盛は厖大な摂関家領を自己の管理下へ置くことに成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori succeeded in taking control of the enormous property of the line of regents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori succeeded in taking control of the enormous property of the line of regents.</e>
<cmt>空白を調整しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori succeeded in taking control of the enormous property of the line of regents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>摂関家を嗣いだ藤原基房は伊勢平氏による押領だと非難したが、この事件は摂関家の威信の低下を如実に表しており、清盛一族は大きな経済基盤を獲得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Motofusa, who succeeded as family head of the line of regents, criticized this as usurping by the Ise Heishi but this incident clearly shows the decrease in authority of the line of regents and the Kiyomori family gained a substantial financial foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Motofusa, who succeeded FUJIWARA no Motozane as family head of the line of regents, criticized this as an usurping by the Ise Heishi but this incident clearly shows the decrease in authority of the line of regents and the Kiyomori family gained a substantial financial foundation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Motofusa, who succeeded FUJIWARA no Motozane as family head of the line of regents, criticized this as an usurping by the Ise-Heishi (Taira clan) but this incident clearly shows the decrease in authority of the line of regents and the Kiyomori family gained a substantial financial foundation.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除-補足。(Taira clan) 補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="66">
<j>以上に見るように、政治世界における武力が占める比重の増加、後白河と清盛の強い連携、後白河と滋子の関係、高倉の即位、清盛の大臣補任、日宋貿易や集積した所領（荘園）に基づく巨大な経済力、西国武士や瀬戸内海の水軍を中心とする軍事力などを背景として、1160年代後期に平氏政権が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown above, the Taira clan administration was established in the latter half of the 1160s due to increased influence of military force in the political scene, strong colloboration between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori, the relationship between Goshirakawa and Shigeko, Takakura&apos;s ascension, Kiyomori&apos;s support of the Daijin, substantial financial power based on Japan-Song trade and accumulated properties (shoen), and military power based on the western bushi and the Seto Inland Sea naval force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As shown above, the Taira clan administration was established in the latter half of the 1160s due to increased influence of military force in the political scene, strong colloboration between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori, the relationship between Goshirakawa and Shigeko, Takakura&apos;s ascension, Kiyomori&apos;s support of the Daijin, substantial financial power based on Japan-Song trade and accumulated properties (shoen), and military power based on the western bushi and the Seto Inland Sea naval force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As shown above, the Taira clan administration was established in the latter half of the 1160s due to increased influence of military force in the political scene, strong collaboration between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori, the relationship between Goshirakawa and Shigeko, Takakura&apos;s ascension, Kiyomori&apos;s support of the Daijin, substantial financial power based on Japan-Song trade and accumulated properties (shoen), and military power based on the western bushi and the Seto Inland Sea naval force.</e>
<cmt>collaboration スペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="67">
<j>この時期、後白河は院政の強化を図っており、清盛の子の平重盛に軍事警察権を委任し、東海道・東山道・山陽道・南海道の追討を担当させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, Goshirakawa was trying to strengthen the cloister government and gave Kiyomori&apos;s son, TAIRA no Shigemori the rights to the military and guards to police the Tokai-do, Tosan-do, Sanyo-do, and Nankai-do routes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, Goshirakawa was trying to strengthen the cloister government and gave Kiyomori&apos;s son, TAIRA no Shigemori the rights to the military and guards to police the Tokai-do, Tosan-do, Sanyo-do, and Nankai-do routes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, Goshirakawa was trying to strengthen the cloister government and gave Kiyomori&apos;s son, TAIRA no Shigemori the rights to the military and guards to police the Tokai-do, Tosan-do, Sanyo-do, and Nankai-do routes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また、内裏の警備のために諸国から武士を交替で上京させる内裏大番役の催促についても、清盛が担うようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori was in charge of making sure the Imperial Palace guard service, which required bushi from the provinces to travel to Kyoto for guard duty at the Imperial Palace in turns, ran smoothly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori was in charge of making sure the Imperial Palace guard service, which required bushi from the provinces to travel to Kyoto for guard duty at the Imperial Palace in alternation, ran smoothly.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori was in charge of making sure the Imperial Palace guard service, which required bushi from the provinces to travel to Kyoto for guard duty at the Imperial Palace in alternation, ran smoothly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>こうした動きは、院と深く連携して院政の軍事警察部門を担当することを平氏政権の基盤に置くものであり、その中心には重盛がいたが、その一方で清盛は、西国に築いた強固な経済・軍事・交通基盤によって院政とは独自の路線を志向するようになっていたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such actions required a close relationship with the retired Emperor and left the Taira clan administration with Shigemori at its center in charge of the military guard division of the cloister government, while on the other hand, Kiyomori is thought to have pursued a route independent of the retired Emperor and established a strong financial, military and transportation foundation in the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such actions required a close relationship with the retired Emperor and left the Taira clan administration, with Shigemori at its center, in charge of the military guard division of the cloister government, while on the other hand, Kiyomori is thought to have pursued a route independent of the retired Emperor and established strong financial, military and transportation foundations in the west.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such actions required a close relationship with the Retired Emperor and left the Taira clan administration, with Shigemori at its center, in charge of the military guard division of the cloister government, while on the other hand, Kiyomori is thought to have pursued a route independent of the Retired Emperor and established strong financial, military and transportation foundations in the west.</e>
<cmt>Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="70">
<j>仁安3年（1168年）に清盛は出家した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1168, Kiyomori became a monk.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1168, Kiyomori became a monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1168, Kiyomori became a monk.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>政界から引退して福原の山荘へ移り、日宋貿易および瀬戸内海交易に積極的に取り組み始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He retired from the political scene and moved to his mountain retreat in Fukuhara to start actively participating in Japan-Song trade and Seto Inland Sea trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He retired from the political scene and moved to his mountain retreat in Fukuhara to start actively participating in Japan-Song trade and Seto Inland Sea trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He retired from the political scene and moved to his mountain retreat in Fukuhara to start actively participating in Japan-Song trade and Seto Inland Sea trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>後白河も清盛の姿勢に理解を示し、嘉応元年（1169年）から安元3年（1177年）まで毎年のように福原の山荘へ赴いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa showed understanding towards Kiyomori&apos;s stance and visited the mountain retreat in Fukuhara every year from 1169 to 1177.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa showed understanding towards Kiyomori&apos;s stance and visited the mountain retreat in Fukuhara every year from 1169 to 1177.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa showed understanding towards Kiyomori&apos;s stance and visited the mountain retreat in Fukuhara every year from 1169 to 1177.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>嘉応2年（1170年）後白河は福原山荘にて宋人と対面しているが、これは宇多天皇の遺戒でタブーとされた行為であり、九条兼実は「我が朝、延喜以来未曾有の事なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1170, Goshirakawa met a person from Song at the Fukuhara mountain retreat, but this was an act that was considered taboo because of Emperor Uda&apos;swill and Kanezane Kujo wrote with astonishment, &apos;This is the most shocking event in Japan since Engi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1170, Goshirakawa met a person from Song at the Fukuhara mountain retreat, but this was an act that was considered taboo because of Emperor Uda&apos;s will and Kanezane Kujo wrote with astonishment, &quot;This is the most shocking event in Japan since Engi.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1170, Goshirakawa met a person from Song at the Fukuhara mountain retreat, but this was an act that was considered taboo because of Emperor Uda&apos;s will and Kanezane KUJO wrote with astonishment, &apos;This is the most shocking event in Japan since Engi era.</e>
<cmt>KUJO大文字にしました。原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Era補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>天魔の所為か」（『玉葉』）と驚愕している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Is it because of a demon?&apos;(&quot;Gyokuyo (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Is it because of a demon?&quot; (&quot;Gyokuyo (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)&quot;).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Is it because of a demon?&apos; (&quot;Gyokuyo&quot; (Diary of Kanezane KUJO)).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。&quot;の位置訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>同年に藤原秀衡が鎮守府将軍になるが、日宋貿易の輸出品である金の貢納と引き換えに任じられたと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same year, FUJIWARA no Hidehira became Chinjufu shogun (Commander-in-chief of the Defense of the North and the courtly title of the Fourth Rank) but was assumed to have received the position in exchange with donations of gold, which was an export good in Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same year, FUJIWARA no Hidehira became Chinjufu shogun (Commander-in-chief of the Defense of the North and the courtly title of the Fourth Rank) but was assumed to have received the position in exchange for donations of gold, which was an export in Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same year, FUJIWARA no Hidehira became Chinjufu shogun (Commander-in-chief of the Defense of the North and the courtly title of the Fourth Rank) but was assumed to have received the position in exchange for donations of gold, which was an export in Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これについても兼実は「夷狄（いてき）」の秀衡を任じたことは「乱世の基」であると非難しているが、これらの施策により日宋貿易は本格化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanezane also wrote regarding this and accused promoting the &apos;barbarian&apos; Hidehira was &apos;the cause of more troubled times&apos;, but these actions led to further developments in Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanezane also wrote regarding this and argued that promoting the &apos;barbarian&apos; Hidehira was &apos;the cause of more troubled times&apos;, but these actions led to further developments in Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanezane also wrote regarding this and argued that promoting the &apos;barbarian&apos; Hidehira was &apos;the cause of more troubled times,&apos; but these actions led to further developments in Japan-Song trade.</e>
<cmt>&apos;,を,&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="77">
<j>承安 (日本)元年（1171年）、清盛は娘の平徳子（建礼門院）を高倉天皇の中宮とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1171, Kiyomori had his daughter, TAIRA no Tokuko (Kenreimon-in) as Emperor Takakura&apos;s Chugu (Empress Consort).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1171, Kiyomori had his daughter, TAIRA no Tokuko (Kenreimon-in) appointed as Emperor Takakura&apos;s Chugu (Empress Consort).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1171, Kiyomori had his daughter, TAIRA no Tokuko (Kenreimonin) appointed as Emperor Takakura&apos;s Chugu (Empress Consort).</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>清盛一族と同様に、建春門院の兄・平時忠一族も栄達し、両平氏から全盛期には10数名の公卿、殿上人30数名を輩出するに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Together with Kiyomori&apos;s family, Kenshunmon-in&apos;s older brother, TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s family also was successful, and at its peak, there were more than 10 members from both Taira clans that were court nobles or officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Together with Kiyomori&apos;s family, Kenshunmon-in&apos;s older brother, TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s family was also successful, and at its peak, there were more than 10 members from both Taira clans that were court nobles or officials.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Together with Kiyomori&apos;s family, Kenshunmonin&apos;s older brother, TAIRA no Tokitada&apos;s family was also successful, and at its peak, there were more than 10 members of court nobles and more than 30 officials from both Taira clans.</e>
<cmt>内容を原文にあわせて変更しました。-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>『平家物語』によれば、時忠は「平家一門でない者は人ではない（この一門にあらざれば人非人たるべし）」と放言したと伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the Tale of Heike, Tokitada was quoted to have said &apos;Whoever is not a member of the Heike is a nobody&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the Tale of Heike, Tokitada was quoted to have said &apos;Anyone who is not a member of the Heike is a nobody&apos;.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Tale of Heike,&quot; Tokitada was quoted to have said &apos;Anyone who is not a member of the Heike is a nobody.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合せて&quot;を補足しました。&apos;.を.&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>動揺期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unrest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unrest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unrest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="80">
<j>ながらく続いた後白河と清盛の良好な関係は、安元2年（1176年）の建春門院の死によって大きな変化が生じ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The good relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori that had lasted for a while began to change greatly after Kenshunmon-in&apos;s death in 1176.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The good relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori that had lasted for a while began to change greatly after Kenshunmon-in&apos;s death in 1176.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The good relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori that had lasted for a while began to change greatly after Kenshunmonin&apos;s death in 1176.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>後白河の寵愛する建春門院は、後白河と清盛の関係をつなぐ重要な存在であったが、その死は、両者間に蓄積していた対立点を顕在化させることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenshunmon-in was deeply loved by Goshirakawa and was an important person in binding the relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori, but after her death, the conflicts that had accumulated between the two parties became apparent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenshunmon-in was deeply loved by Goshirakawa and was an important person in binding the relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori, but after her death, the conflicts that had accumulated between the two parties became apparent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenshunmonin was deeply loved by Goshirakawa and was an important person in binding the relationship between Goshirakawa and Kiyomori, but after her death, the conflicts that had accumulated between the two parties became apparent.</e>
<cmt>-削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="82">
<j>高倉天皇は成人して政治への関与を深めていたが、後白河も院政継続を望んでいたため、高倉を擁する平氏と後白河を擁する院近臣の間には人事を巡って鋭い対立が生じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Takakura had come of age and was interested in participating in politics, bur Goshirakawa wished for a continued cloistered government, leading to strong conflicts over promotions between the Taira clan who supported Takakura and the close aide that supported Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Takakura had come of age and was interested in participating in politics, but Goshirakawa wished for a continued cloistered government, which led to strong conflicts over promotions between the Taira clan who supported Takakura, and the close aides that supported Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Takakura had come of age and was interested in participating in politics, but Goshirakawa wished for a continued cloistered government, which led to strong conflicts over promotions between the Taira clan who supported Takakura, and the close aides that supported Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>院近臣の藤原定能・藤原光能が蔵人頭になったことに対抗して、平氏側からは重盛・宗盛がそれぞれ左大将・右大将になるなど、しばらくは膠着状態が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the cloistered government close aides, FUJIWARA no Sadayoshi and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi became Kurodo no to (Head of the Imperial Officers), in competition, Shigemori and Munemori from the Taira clan side became Sadaisho (leader of the left Imperial Guards) and Udaisho (leader of the right Imperial Guards), respectively, and a stalemate continued for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the cloistered government close aides, FUJIWARA no Sadayoshi and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi became Kurodo no to (Head of the Imperial Officers), in competition, Shigemori and Munemori from the Taira clan side became Sadaisho (leader of the left Imperial Guards) and Udaisho (leader of the right Imperial Guards) respectively, and a stalemate continued for a while.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the cloistered government close aides, FUJIWARA no Sadayoshi and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi became Kurodo no to (Head of the Imperial Officers), in competition, Shigemori and Munemori from the Taira clan side became Sadaisho (leader of the left Imperial Guards) and Udaisho (leader of the right Imperial Guards) respectively, and a stalemate continued for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>後白河は福原を訪れて平氏との関係修復を模索するが、ここに突然、新たな要素として延暦寺が登場する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa visited Fukuhara to try to find ways to recover the relationship with the Taira clan, but suddenly Enryaku-ji Temple becomes a new player in the game.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa visited Fukuhara to try to find ways to recover the relationship with the Taira clan, but suddenly the Enryaku-ji Temple became a new player in the game.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa visited Fukuhara to try to find ways to recover the relationship with the Taira clan, but suddenly the Enryaku-ji Temple became a new player in the game.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>加賀守・藤原師高の目代が白山の末寺を焼いたことが発端で、当初は目代と現地の寺社によるありふれた紛争にすぎなかったが、白山の本寺が延暦寺であり、師高の父が院近臣の西光だったため、中央に波及して延暦寺と院勢力との全面衝突に発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The beginning was an incident where Kaga no kami FUJIWARA no Morotaka burned a branch temple of Hakusan, and this was initially simply an ordinary conflict between the Mokudai (personal deputy of an absentee provincial governor) and local temple, but the main temple of Hakusan was Enryaku-ji Temple and because Morotaka;s father was the cloistered government aide Saiko, this led to a direct confrontation at the central government between Enryaku-ji Temple and cloistered government forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The beginning was an incident where Kaga no kami FUJIWARA no Morotaka burned a branch temple of Hakusan, and initially this was simply an ordinary conflict between the Mokudai (personal deputy of an absentee provincial governor) and the local temple, but the main temple of Hakusan was Enryaku-ji Temple and because Morotaka&apos;s father was the cloistered government aide Saiko, this led to a direct confrontation at the central government between the Enryaku-ji Temple and the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The beginning was an incident where Kaga no kami (the governer of Kaga Province) FUJIWARA no Morotaka burned a branch temple of Hakusan, and initially this was simply an ordinary conflict between the Mokudai (personal deputy of an absentee provincial governor) and the local temple, but the main temple of Hakusan was Enryaku-ji Temple and because Morotaka&apos;s father was the cloistered government aide Saiko, this led to a direct confrontation at the central government between the Enryaku-ji Temple and the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>加賀守→Kaga no kami (the governer of Kaga Province)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>この強訴では、重盛の兵が神輿を射るという失態を犯したことで延暦寺側に有利に事が運び、師高の配流で一旦は決着する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this direct petition, Shigemori&apos;s forces made a mistake when they shot an arrow at the portable shrine, which led to an advantage for the Enryaku-ji Temple side and was settled temporarily by Morotake&apos;s exile.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this direct petition, Shigemori&apos;s forces made a mistake when they shot an arrow at a portable shrine, which led to an advantage for the Enryaku-ji Temple side and was settled temporarily by Morotake&apos;s exile.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this direct petition, Shigemori&apos;s forces made a mistake when they shot an arrow at a portable shrine, which led to an advantage for the Enryaku-ji Temple side and was settled temporarily by Morotake&apos;s exile.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="87">
<j>安元3年（1177年）4月には、大内裏・大極殿・官庁の全てが全焼する大火が発生した（太郎焼亡）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1177, a great fire broke out and completely burned all of the Daidairi (Heian Imperial Palace), Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) and Kancho (government offices)(called &apos;Great Fire of Angen era&apos; or &apos;Taro(common name for a first son) Fire&apos;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1177, a great fire (called &apos;the Great Fire of the Angen era&apos; or &apos;Taro (a common name for a first son) Fire&apos;) broke out and completely burned the Daidairi (Heian Imperial Palace), Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) and Kancho (government offices).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1177, a great fire (called &apos;the Great Fire of the Angen era&apos; or &apos;Taro (a common name for a first son) Fire&apos;) broke out and completely burned the Daidairi (Heian Imperial Palace), Daigokuden (Council Hall in the Imperial Palace) and Kancho (government offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>この大火は後白河に非常に大きな衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This great fire was an enormous shock for Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This great fire was an enormous shock for Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This great fire was an enormous shock for Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>このような中で延暦寺への恨みを抱く西光は後白河に、天台座主・明雲が強訴の張本人であり処罰することを訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this situation, Saiko, who had a deep resentment towards Enryaku-ji Temple, demanded that Tendai Zasu (Chief Tendai Abbot) Myoun was the leader of the direct petition and asked Goshirakawa to punish him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this situation, Saiko, who had a deep resentment towards Enryaku-ji Temple, demanded that Tendai Zasu (Chief Tendai Abbot) Myoun was the leader of the direct petition and asked Goshirakawa to punish him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this situation, Saiko, who had a deep resentment towards Enryaku-ji Temple, demanded that Tendai Zasu (Chief Tendai Abbot) Myoun was the leader of the direct petition and asked Goshirakawa to punish him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>明雲は突如、座主を解任されて所領まで没収された上、伊豆に配流となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoun was suddenly forced to quit as Zasu, had his property taken away and was exiled to Izu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoun was suddenly forced to quit as Zasu, had his property taken away, and was exiled to Izu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoun was suddenly forced to quit as Zasu, had his property taken away, and was exiled to Izu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>激怒した延暦寺の大衆が明雲の身柄を奪回したため、ここに延暦寺と院勢力との抗争が再燃することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monks at Enryaku-ji Temple were angered and rescued Myoun, leading to a revival of hostilities between Enryaku-ji Temple and the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monks at the Enryaku-ji Temple were angered and rescued Myoun, leading to a revival of hostilities between the Enryaku-ji Temple and the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monks at the Enryaku-ji Temple were angered and rescued Myoun, leading to a revival of hostilities between the Enryaku-ji Temple and the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>後白河は清盛に延暦寺への攻撃を命じるが、清盛自身は攻撃に消極的であり、むしろ事態を悪化させた後白河や西光に憤りを抱いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa commanded Kiyomori to attack Enryaku-ji Temple, but Kiyomori himself was not motivated to attack and was rather angry at Goshirakwa and Saiko for making the situation worse.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa commanded Kiyomori to attack the Enryaku-ji Temple, but Kiyomori himself was not motivated to attack and instead was angry at Goshirakwa and Saiko for making the situation worse.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa commanded Kiyomori to attack the Enryaku-ji Temple, but Kiyomori himself was not motivated to attack and instead was angry at Goshirakwa and Saiko for making the situation worse.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>延暦寺攻撃直前の6月1日、多田行綱が京都郊外の鹿ヶ谷で成親、西光、俊寛ら院近臣が集まり平氏打倒の謀議をしていたと密告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately before the attack on Enryaku-ji Temple, Yukitsuna TADA informed on cloistered government aides, Narichika, Saiko, and Shunkan, claiming that they were gathered in Shishigatani in suburban Kyoto to discuss talks to topple the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately before the attack on the Enryaku-ji Temple, Yukitsuna TADA informed on cloistered government aides, Narichika, Saiko, and Shunkan, claiming that they had gathered in Shishigatani in suburban Kyoto to discuss toppling the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately before the attack on the Enryaku-ji Temple in June 1, Yukitsuna TADA informed on cloistered government aides, Narichika, Saiko, and Shunkan, claiming that they had gathered in Shishigatani in suburban Kyoto to discuss toppling the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>日付を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>清盛は関係者を速やかに斬罪や流罪などに処断した（鹿ヶ谷の陰謀）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori swiftly punished the related people by execution and exile (Shishigatani no Inbo (Shishigatani Conspiracy).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori swiftly punished the related people with execution and exile (Shishigatani no Inbo (the Shishigatani Conspiracy).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori swiftly punished the related people with execution and exile (Shishigatani no Inbo (the Shishigatani Conspiracy).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>陰謀が事実であったかは定かでないが、これにより清盛は延暦寺との望まぬ軍事衝突を回避することができ、後白河は多くの近臣を失い、政治発言権を著しく低下させてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clear whether there was an actual conspiracy, but Kiyomori was able to prevent a military confrontation with Enryaku-ji Temple that he did not want and Goshirakawa lost many close aides and political power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear whether there was an actual conspiracy, but Kiyomori was able to prevent a military confrontation with the Enryaku-ji Temple that he did not want and Goshirakawa lost many close aides and political power.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear whether there was an actual conspiracy, but Kiyomori was able to prevent a military confrontation with the Enryaku-ji Temple that he did not want and Goshirakawa lost many close aides and political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="96">
<j>清盛は、後白河との関係を放棄する一方で高倉天皇との関係を強化し、高倉もまた後白河院政からの独立を志向し、翌治承2年（1178年）、両者は連携して新制17条を発布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori dropped his relationship with Goshirakawa, and strengthened his ties with Emperor Takakura, and Takakura was interested in becoming independent of the Goshirakawa clostered government, leading to a joint issuance of the 17 New Rules in 1178.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori dropped his relationship with Goshirakawa, and strengthened his ties with Emperor Takakura, and Takakura was interested in becoming independent of the Goshirakawa clostered government, leading to a joint issuance of the 17 New Rules in 1178.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori dropped his relationship with Goshirakawa, and strengthened his ties with Emperor Takakura, and Takakura was interested in becoming independent of the Goshirakawa cloistered government, leading to a joint issuance of the 17 New Rules in 1178.</e>
<cmt>cloisteredスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>同年には中宮・徳子（清盛の娘）が高倉の皇子を出産し、皇子は生後1月で皇太子に立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1178, Shugu Tokuko (Kiyomori&apos;s daughter) gave birth to a prince of Emperor Takakura&apos;s and this prince was invested as Crown Prince when he was one month old.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1178, Shugu Tokuko (Kiyomori&apos;s daughter) gave birth to Emperor Takakura&apos;s son and this son was invested as Crown Prince when he was one month old.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1178, Chugu Tokuko (Kiyomori&apos;s daughter) gave birth to Emperor Takakura&apos;s son and this son was invested as Crown Prince when he was one month old.</e>
<cmt>Chuguに訂正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="98">
<j>治承3年（1179年）重盛と盛子が相次いで死去すると、後白河は関白基房と共謀し、清盛に無断で重盛の知行国（越前）と盛子の荘園を没収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1179, when Shigemori and Moriko died, Goshirakawa collaborated with Regent Motofusa to seize the province that Shigemori governed (Echizen) and Moriko&apos;s shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1179, when Shigemori and Moriko died, Goshirakawa collaborated with Regent Motofusa to seize the province that Shigemori governed (Echizen) and Moriko&apos;s shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1179, when Shigemori and Moriko died, Goshirakawa collaborated with Regent Motofusa to seize the province that Shigemori governed (Echizen) and Moriko&apos;s shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>特に盛子の所領は高倉が相伝することが決まっていたため、高倉・清盛側と後白河側の対立は悪化の一途をたどった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict between Takakura and Kiyomori&apos;s side with Goshirakawa&apos;s side worsened especially because Moriko&apos;s property was to be inherited by Takakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict between Takakura and Kiyomori&apos;s side with Goshirakawa&apos;s side worsened especially because Moriko&apos;s property was to be inherited by Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict between Takakura and Kiyomori&apos;s side with Goshirakawa&apos;s side worsened especially because Moriko&apos;s property was to be inherited by Takakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>11月14日清盛は福原から上京すると、関白・基房、権中納言・師家を手始めに、藤原師長以下39名（貴族8名、殿上人・受領・検非違使など31名）を解官、後白河も鳥羽殿へ幽閉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 14, Kiyomori arrived in Kyoto from Fukuhara and fired beginning with Regent Motofusa, Gonchunagon (head of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards) Moroie, and 39 other people starting with FUJIWARA no Moronaga (8 aristocrats, 31 court officers, province officers, Kenbiishi, etc.) and locked Goshirakawa up at the Toba residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 14, Kiyomori arrived in Kyoto from Fukuhara and fired, beginning with Regent Motofusa, Gonchunagon Moroie (head of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards), FUJIWARA no Moronaga and 39 other people (8 aristocrats, 31 court officers, province officers, Kenbiishi, etc.) and locked Goshirakawa up at the Toba residence.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 14, Kiyomori arrived in Kyoto from Fukuhara and fired, beginning with Regent Motofusa, Gonchunagon Moroie (head of the Left Division of the Outer Palace Guards), FUJIWARA no Moronaga and 39 other people (8 aristocrats, 31 court officers, province officers, Kenbiishi, etc.) and locked Goshirakawa up at the Toba residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>これは事実上、軍事力による朝廷の制圧であり後白河院政は完全に停止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was in actuality, suppression of the imperial Court by military power and the Goshirakawa cloistered government was completely terminated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was in actuality, suppression of the imperial Court by military power and the Goshirakawa cloistered government was completely terminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was in actuality, suppression of the imperial Court by military power and the Goshirakawa cloistered government was completely terminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>以後、平氏政権はますます軍事的な色彩を強めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this point onwards, the military color of the Taira clan administration becomes more prominent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this point onwards, the military color of the Taira clan administration became more prominent.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this point onwards, the military color of the Taira clan administration became more prominent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>この治承三年の政変をもって、武家政権としての平氏政権が初めて成立したとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &apos;Political Change in Jicho 3&apos; is considered by some as the initial establishment of the Taira clan administration as a bushi goevernment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &apos;Political Change in Jicho 3&apos; is considered by some as the initial establishment of the Taira clan administration as a bushi goevernment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Political Change in Jicho 3 (1179)&apos; is considered by some as the initial establishment of the Taira clan administration as a bushi government.</e>
<cmt>(1179)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>従前の高官に代わって平氏一族や親平氏的貴族が登用され、また知行国の大幅な入れ替えもあって中央・地方の両面において平氏一門を中心とする軍事的な支配体制が強化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Members of the Taira clan and pro-Taira aristocrats took the place of previous high officials and there was a massive exchange in province governors, leading to the strengthening of military control organization on the central and local level by the members of of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members of the Taira clan and pro-Taira aristocrats took the places of previous high officials and there was an extensive replacement of province governors, leading to the strengthening of military control organization on the central and local level by the members of of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members of the Taira clan and pro-Taira aristocrats took the places of previous high officials and there was an extensive replacement of province governors, leading to the strengthening of military control organization on the central and local level by the members of the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>余計なof削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="105">
<j>同年の平氏一門の知行国25か国、国守29か国にのぼり、伊勢平氏の勢力基盤の西国のみならず、東国にも平氏政権の勢力が及ぶこととなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, the 25 governing provinces and 29 provinces were with governors related to the Taira clan, leading to not only the west as the power base of Ise Taira clan (Heishi) but also the east began to feel the control of the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, the number of directly governed provinces reached 25 and the number of provinces with governors related to the Taira clan reached 29, which meant the the east as well as the west, the power base of Ise Taira clan (Heishi), began to feel the control of the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, the number of directly governed provinces reached 25 and the number of provinces with governors related to the Taira clan reached 29, which meant the east as well as the west, the power base of Ise Taira clan (Heishi), began to feel the control of the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>余計なthe削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>平氏の荘園は500余箇所だったとされているが、平氏は本家などといった最上位の領主として荘園を支配したのではなく、領家や預所といった職で荘園管理に当たっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the shoen of the Taira clan numbered over 500, but the Taira clan controlled these shoen not as the Honke (main house), which is the highest grade of owner), but worked for shoen management as the Ryoke (main proprietor) and Azukaridokoro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the shoen of the Taira clan numbered over 500, but the Taira clan controlled these shoen not as the Honke (main house), which is the highest grade of owner, but worked for shoen management as the Ryoke (main proprietor) and Azukari dokoro.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the shoen of the Taira clan numbered over 500, but the Taira clan controlled these shoen not as the Honke (main house), which is the highest grade of owner, but worked for shoen management as the Ryoke (main proprietor) and Azukari dokoro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>平氏政権は、各地の武士を系列化したり、家人の武士を各地へ派遣し、知行国においては国守護人、荘園においては地頭と呼ばれる職に任命して現地支配に当たらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan administration organized the local bushi and sent their retainers to provinces and assigned them as local custodians at provinces and Jito at shoens to facilitate local governance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan administration organized the local bushi and sent their retainers to provinces and assigned them as local custodians at provinces and Jito at shoens in order to facilitate local governance.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan administration organized the local bushi and sent their retainers to provinces and assigned them as local custodians at provinces and Jito at shoens in order to facilitate local governance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>ただし、こうした現地支配の形態は、関係史料が少ないため明らかでない部分もあるが、平氏支配地に一律で適用されたのではなく、武士による支配を模索する中で現れたに過ぎないとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the details of this system of local governance is not clear because there are few historical documents, and it is considered that it did not happen consistently throughout the area controlled by the Taira clan, but a transient phenomena while testing ways for bushi to govern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the details of this system of local governance are not clear because there are few historical documents, and it is considered that it did not happen consistently throughout the area controlled by the Taira clan, but was a transient phenomena while testing ways for bushi to govern.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the details of this system of local governance are not clear because there are few historical documents, and it is considered that it did not happen consistently throughout the area controlled by the Taira clan, but was a transient phenomena while testing ways for bushi to govern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>これは後の鎌倉幕府による本格的な武家政権支配と比較すると、御家人制度のように確立されたものでもなく未熟なものだったといえるが、武士を通じた支配ネットワークを構築したことは従前の貴族政権には見られない画期的なものとされ、ゆえに学界では発現期の武家政権であるとする評価が主流となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, compared to the more established samurai government control by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), it was an undeveloped system without an established lower-ranking vassal system, but was significant because it built a control network through bushi that was not seen in previous aristocratic governments, and therefore it is mainly considered in the academic field as a beginning form of samurai government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, compared to the more established samurai government control by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), it was an undeveloped system without an established lower-ranking vassal system, but was nonetheless significant because it built a control network through bushi that was not seen in previous aristocratic governments, and therefore in the academic field it is largely considered as a beginning form of samurai government.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, compared to the more established samurai government control by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), it was an undeveloped system without an established lower-ranking vassal system, but was nonetheless significant because it built a control network through bushi that was not seen in previous aristocratic governments, and therefore in the academic field it is largely considered as a beginning form of samurai government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>なお、平清盛が置いた国守護人・地頭は、鎌倉期におけるの守護・地頭の祖形だと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local custodians for the governor and Jito that TAIRA no Kiyomori established are considered as the prototype for Shugo and Jito in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The local custodians for the governor and Jito that TAIRA no Kiyomori established are considered as the prototypes of Shugo and Jito in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The local custodians for the governor and Jito that TAIRA no Kiyomori established are considered as the prototypes of Shugo and Jito in the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="111">
<j>治承4年（1180年）2月、3歳の安徳天皇が践祚し、高倉上皇は院政を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In February 1180, the 3-year-old Emperor Antoku ascended the throne and the retired Emperor Takakura started his cloistered government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In February 1180, the 3-year-old Emperor Antoku ascended the throne and the retired Emperor Takakura started his cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In February 1180, the three-year-old Emperor Antoku ascended the throne and the Retired Emperor Takakura started his cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>この時こそ清盛の平氏政権が最も強固な体制を築いた絶頂期であったが、しかし、平氏政権は後白河との良好な関係の上に形成されてきたのであり、前年のクーデターによって後白河との関係は解消されてしまっており、平氏政権の絶頂は極めて脆弱な基盤に載っていたといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period was the peak when the Taira clan administration built its strongest organization, but this was based on good relations with Goshirakawa, and since the relationship with Goshirakawa soured with the coup d&apos;etat the previous year, the peak of the Taira clan administration was on an extremely weak foundation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This period was the peak, when the Taira clan administration built its strongest organization, but this was based on good relations with Goshirakawa, and since the relationship with Goshirakawa had soured with the coup d&apos;etat the previous year, the peak of the Taira clan administration was on an extremely weak foundation.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This period was the peak, when the Taira clan administration built its strongest organization, but this was based on good relations with Goshirakawa, and since the relationship with Goshirakawa had soured with the coup d&apos;etat the previous year, the peak of the Taira clan administration was on an extremely weak foundation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>衰退・消滅期</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>（以後の経緯については、治承・寿永の乱も参照のこと。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(also refer to the article on &quot;Jisho and Juei no ran&quot; for further events)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(refer to the article on &quot;Jisho and Juei no ran&quot; for further events)</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(refer to the article on &quot;Jisho and Juei no ran&quot; for further events)</e>
<cmt>“を&quot;に訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="114">
<j>清盛は高倉院政の開始に当たって、高倉とともに安芸国厳島への社参を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Upon the start of Takakura&apos;s cloistered government, Kiyomori attended Takakura to give offerings at Itsukushima in the Aki Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Upon the start of Takakura&apos;s cloistered government, Kiyomori attended Takakura to give offerings at Itsukushima in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Upon the start of Takakura&apos;s cloistered government, Kiyomori attended Takakura to give offerings at Itsukushima in Aki Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>しかしこれは、代替わりに石清水八幡宮・賀茂神社へ社参するという慣例に反するものであり、園城寺・興福寺などは一斉に清盛へ反抗の姿勢を見せ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this was against tradition, which was to visit Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine and Kamo-jinja Shrine upon a change in emperor, leading to Onjo-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple simultaneously starting to rebel against Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But this was against tradition, which was to visit Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine and Kamo-jinja Shrine upon a change in emperor, leading to the Onjo-ji Temple and the Kofuku-ji Temple simultaneously starting to oppose Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But this was against tradition, which was to visit Iwashimizu Hachimangu Shrine and Kamo-jinja Shrine upon a change in emperor, leading to the Onjo-ji Temple and the Kofuku-ji Temple simultaneously starting to oppose Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>反清盛の気運が高まる中、治承4年（1180年）4月には以仁王（後白河の第2皇子）が平氏追討の令旨を発し、源頼政と結んで挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In April 1180, with the anti-Kiyomori movement, Prince Mochihito (Goshirakawa&apos;s second son) issued a call for attacking the Taira clan and collaborated with MINAMOTO no Yorimasa to raise forces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In April 1180, with the anti-Kiyomori movement, Prince Mochihito (Goshirakawa&apos;s second son) issued a call for attacking the Taira clan and collaborated with MINAMOTO no Yorimasa to raise forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April 1180, with the anti-Kiyomori movement, Prince Mochihito (Goshirakawa&apos;s second son) issued a call for attacking the Taira clan and collaborated with MINAMOTO no Yorimasa to raise forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>しかし清盛は迅速に対応し、平氏軍は以仁王と頼政をすぐに敗死へ追い込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kiyomori acted swiftly and the Taira troops won against Prince Mochihito and Yorimasa and they died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Kiyomori acted swiftly and the Taira troops were defeated, and Prince Mochihito and Yorimasa killed.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Kiyomori acted swiftly and the Taira troops were defeated, and Prince Mochihito and Yorimasa killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>しかし叛乱に興福寺や園城寺などの有力寺院が与したことから、清盛は平氏にとって地勢的に不利な京都からの遷都を目指して福原京福原行幸を決行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, major temples such as Kofuku-ji Temlpe and Onjo-ji Temple had participated in the rebellion, so Kiyomori decided to have the Emperor visit Fukuhara and aim for moving the capital from Kyoto, which was geographically at a disadvantage for the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, major temples such as the Kofuku-ji Temple and the Onjo-ji Temple had participated in the rebellion, so Kiyomori decided to have the Emperor visit Fukuhara with the aim of moving the capital from Kyoto, which would place the Taira clan at a geographic disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, major temples such as the Kofuku-ji Temple and the Onjo-ji Temple had participated in the rebellion, so Kiyomori decided to have the Emperor visit Fukuhara with the aim of moving the capital from Kyoto, which would place the Taira clan at a geographic disadvantage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="119">
<j>ところが高倉上皇が平安京を放棄しない意向を示すなど、この遷都計画は貴族らに極めて不評であり、朝廷内部に清盛への反感が募っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the retired Emperor Takakura indicated his wishes as to not wanting to leave Heian-kyo (ancient capital) and this move was also very unpopular with the aristocracy, leading to more animosity among the Imperial Court members against Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the retired Emperor Takakura indicated his desire to not leave Heian-kyo (the ancient capital) and this move was also very unpopular with the aristocracy, leading to more animosity among the Imperial Court members against Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the retired Emperor Takakura indicated his desire to not leave Heian-kyo (the ancient capital) and this move was also very unpopular with the aristocracy, leading to more animosity among the Imperial Court members against Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>さらに、以仁王の令旨を受けて、東国の源頼朝、源義仲、源信義（甲斐源氏）らが相次いで反平氏の兵を挙げ、さらに多田源氏、美濃源氏、近江源氏、河内の石川源氏、九州の菊池氏・紀伊熊野の湛増・土佐の源希義らも反平氏の行動を始めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, answering the call by Prince Mochihito, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, MINAMOTO no Nobuyoshi (Kai Genji (Minamoto clan)) of the east raised anti-Taira clan forces and also Tada-Genji (Minamoto clan), Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan), Omi-Genji (Minamoto clan), Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) of Kawachi, Kikuchi clan of Kyushu, Tanzo of Kumano in the Kii Province and MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi in Tosa started to rebel against the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, answering the call by Prince Mochihito, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, MINAMOTO no Nobuyoshi (Kai Genji (Minamoto clan)) of the east raised anti-Taira clan forces and also Tada-Genji (Minamoto clan), Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan), Omi-Genji (Minamoto clan), Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) of Kawachi, the Kikuchi clan of Kyushu, Tanzo of Kumano in Kii Province and MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi in Tosa started to rebel against the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, answering the call by Prince Mochihito, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, MINAMOTO no Yoshichika, MINAMOTO no Nobuyoshi (Kai Genji (Minamoto clan)) of the east raised anti-Taira clan forces and also Tada-Genji (Minamoto clan), Mino-Genji (Minamoto clan), Omi-Genji (Minamoto clan), Ishikawa-Genji (Minamoto clan) of Kawachi, the Kikuchi clan of Kyushu, Tanzo of Kumano in Kii Province and MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi in Tosa started to rebel against the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>こうした反平氏の動きの背景には、平氏が現地勢力を軽視して自らの家人や係累を優先して平氏知行国や平氏所領の支配に当たらせていたことへの反発があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The background for anti-Taira movements was because there was animosity towards the Taira clan, who gave precedence to their own vassals and related persons while preventing the local forces to rule Taira clan governed provinces and property.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background for anti-Taira movements was because there was animosity towards the Taira clan, who gave precedence to their own vassals and related persons while preventing local forces from ruling Taira clan governed provinces and property.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background for anti-Taira movements was because there was animosity towards the Taira clan, who gave precedence to their own vassals and related persons while preventing local forces from ruling Taira clan governed provinces and property.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>特にクーデターで国司が交代した上総・相模では、頼朝の下に武士たちが瞬く間に集結して一大勢力を形成しており、清盛は孫の平維盛に追討軍を率いさせたが、富士川の戦いであえなく敗走してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especiallly in Kazusa and Sagami, where the governor had just been changed after a coup d&apos;etat, many bushi gathered under Yoritomo very quickly and made one big force, which Kiyomori sent his grandson, TAIRA no Koremori to lead the attack force, but they lost at the Battle of Fuji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especiallly in Kazusa and Sagami, where the governor had just been changed after a coup d&apos;etat, many bushi gathered under Yoritomo very quickly and created one big force, which Kiyomori sent under his grandson, TAIRA no Koremori to lead the attack, but they lost at the Battle of Fuji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially in Kazusa and Sagami, where the governor had just been changed after a coup d&apos;etat, many bushi gathered under Yoritomo very quickly and created one big force, which Kiyomori sent under his grandson, TAIRA no Koremori to lead the attack, but they lost at the Battle of Fuji-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Especiallyスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="123">
<j>福原への行幸以降、貴族の不満も高まり、高倉上皇の健康が悪化していくなか、親清盛派の延暦寺（彼らは園城寺や興福寺と敵対関係にあったが、遷都には不満を抱いていた）などからの要望を契機として、福原行幸から半年後の11月、清盛は福原から京へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ever since the Imperial visit to Fukuhara, the dissatisfaction of the aristocrats grew and the retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s health deteriorated, using the request from Enryaku-ji Temple, who were pro-Kiyomori (they were enemies with Onjyo-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple but were not happy about the change in capital), as a reason, Kiyomori returned to Kyoto from Fukuhara in November, 6months after the imperial visit to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Imperial visit to Fukuhara, the dissatisfaction of the aristocrats continued to grow and the retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s health deteriorated, so using the request from the Enryaku-ji Temple, who were pro-Kiyomori (they were enemies with the Onjyo-ji Temple and the Kofuku-ji Temple but were not happy about the moving of the capital) as a reason, Kiyomori returned to Kyoto from Fukuhara in November, 6 months after the imperial visit to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Imperial visit to Fukuhara, the dissatisfaction of the aristocrats continued to grow and the Retired Emperor Takakura&apos;s health deteriorated, so using the request from the Enryaku-ji Temple, who were pro-Kiyomori (they were enemies with the Onjyo-ji Temple and the Kofuku-ji Temple but were not happy about the moving of the capital) as a reason, Kiyomori returned to Kyoto from Fukuhara in November, six months after the imperial visit to Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>Retiredに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>翌12月、園城寺・興福寺などが反平氏の挙兵を行ったため、清盛は断固とした態度で臨み、平知盛率いる軍は園城寺を焼き払い近江源氏を撃破、平重衡率いる軍も南都の諸寺を焼き払って荘園を没収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following December, Kiyomori took decisive action against anti-Taira forces raised by Onjyo-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple, with TAIRA no Tomomori burning down Onjyo-ji Temple and destroying the Omi Genji, and TAIRA no Shigehira&apos;s troop burned down various temples in the southern capital and took away their shoens.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following December, Kiyomori took decisive action against anti-Taira forces raised by the Onjyo-ji Temple and the Kofuku-ji Temple, with TAIRA no Tomomori burning down the Onjyo-ji Temple and destroying the Omi Genji, and TAIRA no Shigehira&apos;s troop burned down various temples in the southern capital and confiscated their shoens.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following December, Kiyomori took decisive action against anti-Taira forces raised by the Onjyo-ji Temple and the Kofuku-ji Temple, with TAIRA no Tomomori burning down the Onjyo-ji Temple and destroying the Omi-Genji, and TAIRA no Shigehira&apos;s troop burned down various temples in the southern capital and confiscated their shoens.</e>
<cmt>-補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>これにより畿内周辺の叛乱はひとまず沈静化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This quieted down the rebellions around Kinai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This quieted down the rebellions around Kinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This quieted down the rebellions around Kinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="126">
<j>治承5年（1181年）1月、高倉上皇が死去し、後白河院政が再開されたが、畿内に臨時の軍政を布くべしという高倉の遺志に基づいて、清盛は子の平宗盛を畿内周辺を直接管領する惣官に任じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1181, retired Emperor Takakura died and the Goshirakawa cloistered government was started again, and based on the wished of Takakura to establish a temporary military government in Kinai, Kiyomori named TAIRA no Munemasa as Sokan(a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai) to directly control the Kinai area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1181, retired Emperor Takakura died and the Goshirakawa cloistered government started again, and based on the wish of Takakura to establish a temporary military government in Kinai, Kiyomori named TAIRA no Munemasa as Sokan (a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai) to directly control the Kinai area.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1181, Retired Emperor Takakura died and the Goshirakawa cloistered government started again, and based on the wish of Takakura to establish a temporary military government in Kinai, Kiyomori named TAIRA no Munemasa as Sokan (a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai) to directly control the Kinai area.</e>
<cmt>Retiredに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>この惣官職は、畿内近国を軍事的に直轄支配することを目的に設置されたもので、平氏政権の武家政権としての性格を如実に表しており、平氏政権が本格的な武家政権へ成長していく可能性をここに見出しうると、学界では考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Sokan position was established to directly control the military aspects of Kinai and surroundings, clearly indicating the characteristics of the Taira clan administration as a bushi government and the academic field considers that it is possible to see this as a possibility for an established bushi government by the Taira clan administration to grow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Sokan position was established to directly control the military aspects of Kinai and its surroundings, clearly indicating the characteristics of the Taira clan administration as a bushi government and the academic field considers that it is possible to see this as a possibility for the bushi government established by the Taira clan administration to grow.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Sokan position was established to directly control the military aspects of Kinai and its surroundings, clearly indicating the characteristics of the Taira clan administration as a bushi government and the academic field considers that it is possible to see this as a possibility for the bushi government established by the Taira clan administration to grow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>清盛はこれにより京の富裕層から兵粮を徴収すると同時に、伊勢周辺の水軍に動員をかけて、反平氏勢力の追討に意欲を燃やしていたが、同年閏2月に熱病で急死し、平氏政権は大きな打撃を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori raised taxes from the wealthy class in Kyoto to feed the troops and at the same time, moved the naval forces around Ise, and was energetic about attacking the anti-Taira clan forces, but died suddenly from a febrile disease in leap month February of that year, which was a large blow for the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori raised taxes from the wealthy class in Kyoto to feed the troops and at the same time, moved the naval forces around Ise, and was energetic about attacking the anti-Taira clan forces, but died suddenly from a febrile disease in February of that year (a leap year), which was a large blow for the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori raised taxes from the wealthy class in Kyoto to feed the troops and at the same time, moved the naval forces around Ise, and was energetic about attacking the anti-Taira clan forces, but died suddenly from a febrile disease in February of that year (a leap year), which was a large blow for the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="129">
<j>清盛の死後、跡を継いだ宗盛は後白河との融和路線を採り、各地の叛乱も平氏の反撃と養和の大飢饉で小康状態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kiyomori&apos;s death, Munemori became the clan head and took a reconciliation stance with Goshirakawa, and there were less rebellions because of the counterattack by the Taira clan and the great famine of Youwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Kiyomori&apos;s death, Munemori became the clan head and took a reconcilitary stance with Goshirakawa, and there were less rebellions because of the counterattack by the Taira clan and the great famine of Youwa.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Kiyomori&apos;s death, Munemori became the clan head and took a reconciliatory stance with Goshirakawa, and there were less rebellions because of the counterattack by the Taira clan and the great famine of Youwa.</e>
<cmt>reconciliatory スペル訂正。養和の読みを「Yowa」に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>しかし、寿永2年（1183年）5月に源義仲の軍が北陸から一気に京へ進軍すると、義仲軍に主力を壊滅させられていた平氏は、ついに安徳天皇を伴って京を脱出し大宰府に下向するが、豊後の武士・緒方維栄に撃退され屋島にたどり着いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in May 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s troops swept into the Kyoto from Hokuriku, and the Taira clan, whose main forces were crushed by Yoshinaka&apos;s troops, finally decided to escape Kyoto and head towards Dazaifu accompanied by Emperor Antoku, but were repelled by Koreyoshi OGATA, a bushi of Bungo and landed on Yashima Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in May 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s troops swept into Kyoto from Hokuriku, and the Taira clan, whose main forces were crushed by Yoshinaka&apos;s troops, finally decided to escape Kyoto and headed towards Dazaifu accompanied by Emperor Antoku, but were repelled by Koreyoshi OGATA, a bushi of Bungo and landed on Yashima Island.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in May 1183, MINAMOTO no Yoshinaka&apos;s troops swept into Kyoto from Hokuriku, and the Taira clan, whose main forces were crushed by Yoshinaka&apos;s troops, finally decided to escape Kyoto and headed towards Dazaifu accompanied by Emperor Antoku, but were repelled by Koreyoshi OGATA, a bushi of Bungo and landed on Yashima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>この時点で平氏政権は、貴族社会に形成してきた基盤を捨て、西国の地方政権へと転落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, the Taira clan administration dropped its foundation established in the aristocracy and decayed into a local government of the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, the Taira clan administration abandonded its foundation established in the aristocracy and fell into being a local government of the west.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, the Taira clan administration abandoned its foundation established in the aristocracy and fell into being a local government of the west.</e>
<cmt>abandoned スペル訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>後白河は平氏と行動を共にせず、京に残って孫の後鳥羽天皇を即位させたが、これにより天皇が2人存在するという未曾有の事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshirakawa did not act together with the Taira clan, but stayed in Kyoto and made his grandson Emperor Gotoba, leading to unprecedented situation of two Emperors at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshirakawa did not act together with the Taira clan, but stayed in Kyoto and made his grandson Emperor Gotoba, leading to the unprecedented situation of two Emperors at the same time.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa did not act together with the Taira clan, but stayed in Kyoto and made his grandson Emperor Gotoba, leading to the unprecedented situation of two Emperors at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="133">
<j>平氏は、西国の勢力を再編成して軍の再建を進め、瀬戸内沿岸で義仲軍を徐々に押しやり、寿永3年（1184年）1月に義仲が頼朝政権軍（源範頼・源義経軍）に滅ぼされる頃には福原を回復するまでに至っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan reorganized the west forces and reestablished its troops, gradually pushing Yoshinaka away at the Setouchi seacoast, and by the time Yoshinaka is eliminated by the Yoritomo government troops (troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune) in January 1184, they had recovered Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan reorganized the west forces and reestablished its troops, gradually pushing Yoshinaka away at the Setouchi seacoast, and by the time Yoshinaka was eliminated by the Yoritomo government troops (troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune) in January 1184, they had recovered Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan reorganized the west forces and reestablished its troops, gradually pushing Yoshinaka away at the Setouchi seacoast, and by the time Yoshinaka was eliminated by the Yoritomo government troops (troops of MINAMOTO no Noriyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune) in January 1184, they had recovered Fukuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>平氏は、後白河の仲介による京への復帰を目指していたが、後白河にすれば平氏が政権に復帰することになれば再び院政停止・幽閉となる危険性があり、和平はありえなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan aimed for returning to Kyoto by the intermediation of Goshirakawa, but from Goshirakawa&apos;s point of view, having the Taira clan return to the administration had the possibility of termination of the cloistered government or even capture and so there was no chance for peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan aimed to return to Kyoto through the intermediation of Goshirakawa, but from Goshirakawa&apos;s point of view, having the Taira clan return to the administration had the possibility of termination of the cloistered government or even capture, and so there was no chance for peace.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan aimed to return to Kyoto through the intermediation of Goshirakawa, but from Goshirakawa&apos;s point of view, having the Taira clan return to the administration had the possibility of termination of the cloistered government or even capture, and so there was no chance for peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>平氏は半ば騙し討ちを受けた形で一ノ谷の戦いに敗北し、西下していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan was half betrayed and lost the Battle of Ichinotani and escaped westwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan was betrayed, lost the Battle of Ichinotani, and then escaped westwards.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan was betrayed, lost the Battle of Ichinotani, and then escaped westwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="136">
<j>その後、平氏は西国の諸勢力を組織して戦争に当たっていたが、元暦2年（1185年）3月、関門海峡での最終決戦（壇ノ浦の戦い）で源義経軍に敗れて滅亡し、平氏政権は名実ともに消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Taira clan organized the various forces of the west and continued to battle, but at the final pitched battle at the Kanmon Channel in March 1185, (Battle of Dannoura), they lost to MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s forces and the Taira clan administration ended in both name and reality.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Taira clan organized the various forces of the west and continued to battle, but at the final pitched battle at the Kanmon Channel in March 1185, (Battle of Dannoura), they lost to MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s forces and the Taira clan administration ended in both name and actuality.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Taira clan organized the various forces of the west and continued to battle, but at the final pitched battle at the Kanmon Channel in March 1185, (Battle of Dannoura), they lost to MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune&apos;s forces and the Taira clan administration ended in both name and actuality.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>意義と評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meaning and Evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meaning and Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meaning and Evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="137">
<j>平氏政権は、今日では日本史上初の武家政権と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan administration is no currently considered as the first bushi government in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan administration is currently considered as the first bushi government in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan administration is currently considered as the first bushi government in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="138">
<j>『平家物語』や『愚管抄』など同時代の文献は、平氏滅亡後に平氏政権に抑圧されてきた貴族社会や寺社層の視点で描かれてきたものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Documents written at the same time period such as &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; and &quot;Gukansho (Miscellany of Ignorant Views)&quot; are often written after the decline of the Taira clan and from the viewpoint of the aristocracy and temple classes that were suppressed under the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Documents written at the same time period such as &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; and &quot;Gukansho (Miscellany of Ignorant Views)&quot; are often written after the decline of the Taira clan and from the viewpoint of the aristocracy and temple classes that were suppressed under the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Documents written at the same time period such as &quot;The Tale of the Heike&quot; and &quot;Gukansho&quot; (Miscellany of Ignorant Views) are often written after the decline of the Taira clan and from the viewpoint of the aristocracy and temple classes that were suppressed under the Taira clan administration.</e>
<cmt>“を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>従って、後白河法皇が自己の政権維持のために平氏を利用して、高い官職を与え知行国を増やさせてきたという経緯や当時の社会問題に対する貴族社会の対応能力の無さという点には触れず、清盛と平氏一門がいかに専横を振るい、「驕れる者」であったかを強調している（だが、実際には少なくても治承3年以前における平氏の権力は後白河との強い関係の下で行使されたものが大半であり、その段階において清盛及び平氏一門が独裁的権力を有していたという具体的な事実は存在していない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, they do not mention that the retired Emperor Goshirakawa used the Taira clan to maintain his government by giving them high positions and increasing the number of provinces that they were custodians of, and the inability of the aristocracy at that time to deal with the social problems that they faced, but emphasized on the arrogant behavior of Kiyomori and the Taira clan members (whereas in reality, at least up to 1179, the authority of the Taira clan was mostly due to the strong relationship with Goshirakawa and there is no specific evidence that Kiyomori and the Taira clan members had any dictatorial powers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, they do not mention that the retired Emperor Goshirakawa used the Taira clan to maintain his government by giving them high positions and increasing the number of provinces that they were custodians of, and the inability of the aristocracy at that time to deal with the social problems that they faced, but instead emphasize the arrogant behavior of Kiyomori and the Taira clan members (whereas in reality, at least up to 1179, the authority of the Taira clan was mostly due to the strong relationship with Goshirakawa and there is no specific evidence that Kiyomori or the Taira clan members had any dictatorial powers).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, they do not mention that the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa used the Taira clan to maintain his government by giving them high positions and increasing the number of provinces that they were custodians of, and the inability of the aristocracy at that time to deal with the social problems that they faced, but instead emphasize the arrogant behavior of Kiyomori and the Taira clan members (whereas in reality, at least up to 1179, the authority of the Taira clan was mostly due to the strong relationship with Goshirakawa and there is no specific evidence that Kiyomori or the Taira clan members had any dictatorial powers).</e>
<cmt>Retired大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>そのため、以後の歴史書もこの歴史観に引きずられる形で「平氏政権観」を形成していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, later historical books were influenced by this historical view and established &apos;a view towards the Taira clan administration&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, later historical books were influenced by this historical view and established &apos;a view towards the Taira clan administration&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, later historical books were influenced by this historical view and established &apos;a view towards the Taira clan administration.&apos;</e>
<cmt>.を.&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="141">
<j>こうした背景を受けて以前の学界では、平氏政権が貴族社会の中で形成されたことに着目して、武家政権というよりも貴族政権として認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the past, the academic field focused on the fact that the Taira clan administration was developed under the aristocracy and it was recognized as an aristocratic government rather than a bushi one.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the past, the academic field focused on the fact that the Taira clan administration was developed under the aristocracy and it was recognized as an aristocratic government rather than a bushi one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the past, the academic field focused on the fact that the Taira clan administration was developed under the aristocracy and it was recognized as an aristocratic government rather than a bushi one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>貴族社会の官職に依存していること、院政と連携して政策推進を行っていたこと、などがその理由である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reasons for this was because they relied upon the positions within the aristocracy and governmental policies were collaborations with the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for this was because they relied upon the positions within the aristocracy, and governmental policies were in collaboration with the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for this was because they relied upon the positions within the aristocracy, and governmental policies were in collaboration with the cloistered government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>そのため、平氏政権は、武士に出自しながら旧来の支配勢力と同質化してしまったと批判されたのに対し、在地領主層＝武士階級から構成される鎌倉幕府は、旧来の支配階級を打倒した画期的・革新的な存在だとして、階級闘争史観などにより高く評価されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Taira clan administration was criticized as becoming one with the conventional control forces even though they were born as bushi, as regards to the Kamakura bakufu, which consists of local landowner class = bushi class, and was considered as a novel and significant existence by toppling the conventional control class and highly evaluated by views on the history of class conflict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Taira clan administration was criticized as becoming as one with the conventional control forces even though they were born as bushi, as regards to the Kamakura bakufu, which consisted of the local landowner class (bushi class), and was considered as a novel and significant existence due to their toppling of the conventional control class and was highly rated in the history of class conflict.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Taira clan administration was criticized as becoming as one with the conventional control forces even though they were born as bushi, as regards to the Kamakura bakufu, which consisted of the local landowner class (bushi class), and was considered as a novel and significant existence due to their toppling of the conventional control class and was highly rated in the history of class conflict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>こうした歴史像に基づく記述が、21世紀初頭まで一部の辞書などに残存していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such historical picture persisted in some dictionaries until the beginning of the 21 th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such a historical image remained in some dictionaries until the beginning of the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a historical image remained in some dictionaries until the beginning of the 21st century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="145">
<j>しかし、1970年代・1980年代頃から、史料に基づく実証的な研究が進んでいくと、平氏政権も鎌倉幕府に先立って武家政権的な性格を呈していたことが判明するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when empirical research based on historical documents became popular during the 1970s and 1980s, it was discovered that the Taira clan administration had bushi government-like characteristics before the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when empirical research based on historical documents became popular during the 1970s and 1980s, it was discovered that the Taira clan administration had bushi government-like characteristics before the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when empirical research based on historical documents became popular during the 1970s and 1980s, it was discovered that the Taira clan administration had bushi government-like characteristics before the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>史料によれば、平氏政権は支配地域の勢力を武士として系列化し、知行国・荘園に国守護人・地頭などといった従来あまり見られなかった職を置いて、半軍事的な支配を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to historical documents, the Taira clan administration organized the forces in its control area as bushi, and established positions such as Province bakufu office and Jito to their fiefdom and shoen, and developed a half-militaristic control</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to historical documents, the Taira clan administration organized the forces in areas under its control as bushi, and established positions such as Province bakufu officers and Jito in their fiefdom and shoen, and developed a semi-militaristic control.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to historical documents, the Taira clan administration organized the forces in areas under its control as bushi, and established positions such as Province bakufu officers and Jito in their fiefdom and shoen, and developed a semi-militaristic control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>関係史料が少ないため、平氏政権における国守護人・地頭の設置とそれに伴う支配の深化がどれほど進んでいたかは、必ずしも明らかとなっていないが、学界では、これら国守護人・地頭は、後の鎌倉幕府における守護・地頭の先駆的な存在だと考えるようになっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is not clear how large an influence the establishment by the Taira clan administration of Jito and Province officer and the control they exerted because there are few related hisotrical documents, but the academic field proposes that the Jito and Prvince officers were like a prototype for Shugo and Jito in the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is not clear how large an influence the establishment by the Taira clan administration of Jito and Province officers had, or the amount of control they exerted because there are few related hisotrical documents, but the academic field proposes that the Jito and Province officers were like a prototype for Shugo and Jito in the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is not clear how large an influence the establishment by the Taira clan administration of Jito and Province officers had, or the amount of control they exerted because there are few related historical documents, but the academic field proposes that the Jito and Province officers were like a prototype for Shugo and Jito in the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>historical スペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>また治承5年（1181年）に設置した畿内惣官職や諸道鎮撫使は、これもその職能の詳細は不明な点もあるが、数か国にわたる広い領域を軍事的に直轄支配するものと見られており、特に畿内惣官職は征夷大将軍と同様の性格を見出しうるとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although some points about the actual details of their work is unclear, Kinai Sokanshiki (a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai) and Shodo (various roads) chinbushi (one of the posts that were not originally specified in the Ritsuryo system) established in 1181, are considered to have directly ruled a wide area with several provinces regading military aspects and expecially Kinai Shokanshiki is proposed to have similar properties with Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some points about the actual details of their work are unclear, Kinai Sokanshiki (a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai) and Shodo (various roads) chinbushi (one of the posts that were not originally specified in the Ritsuryo system) which were established in 1181, are considered to have directly ruled a wide area with several provinces regarding military aspects and in particular Kinai Shokanshiki is proposed to have had similar properties to the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some points about the actual details of their work are unclear, Kinai Sokanshiki (a military position with power over the provinces of the Kinai) and Shodo (various roads) chinbushi (one of the posts that were not originally specified in the Ritsuryo system) which were established in 1181, are considered to have directly ruled a wide area with several provinces regarding military aspects and in particular Kinai Shokanshiki is proposed to have had similar properties to the Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>このように、平氏政権は従来の貴族政権と異なり、武力に大きな基盤を有していたことが明らかとなり、学界では日本最初の武家政権とするのが通説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why the Taira clan administration differs from pervious aristocrtic governments and it is clear that its main foundation was military power, and the academic field normally considers it the first bushi government inJapan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why the Taira clan administration differs from previous aristocratic governments and it is clear that its main foundation was military power, and the academic field normally considers it as the first bushi government in Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why the Taira clan administration differs from previous aristocratic governments and it is clear that its main foundation was military power, and the academic field normally considers it as the first bushi government in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>なお、元暦2年（1185年）滅亡することがなければ、平清盛の政権は鎌倉幕府とはまた違った、西国を中心とした独自の武家政権へ成長したのではないかとの可能性も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has been suggested that if it had not all ended in 1185, TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s government would have been different from the Kamakura bakufu, developing into an original bushi government with the west provinces as its center.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has been suggested that if it had not all ended in 1185, TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s government would have been different from the Kamakura bakufu, possibly developing into an original bushi government with the west provinces as its center.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has been suggested that if it had not all ended in 1185, TAIRA no Kiyomori&apos;s government would have been different from the Kamakura bakufu, possibly developing into an original bushi government with the west provinces as its center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="151">
<j>平氏政権は清盛という一個人に大きく依存しており、清盛の死から数年のうちに瓦解に至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan government relied heavily upon Kiyomori himself, and disintegrated within several years of his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan government relied heavily upon Kiyomori himself, and disintegrated within several years of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan government relied heavily upon Kiyomori himself, and disintegrated within several years of his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>また、前述したように、後白河との良好な関係に依存するところも大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned previously, it also relied heavily upon a good relationship with Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned previously, it also relied heavily upon a good relationship with Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned previously, it also relied heavily upon a good relationship with Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>院政期は律令制に代わり、院を頂点とした主従制的関係が形成され、官職や土地を恩給として臣下に与えて奉仕させるようになり、知行国・荘園制度が確立していった時期だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cloistered government took the place of the Ritsuryo system, developing lord-vassal relationships with the cloistered Emperor at the apex, and making subordinates work in exchange of positions and land as rewards, and was a period when the system of custodial provinces and shoen were established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cloistered government took the place of the Ritsuryo system, developing lord-vassal relationships with the cloistered Emperor at the apex, and making subordinates work in exchange for positions and land as rewards, and was a period when the system of custodial provinces and shoen were established.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cloistered government took the place of the Ritsuryo system, developing lord-vassal relationships with the cloistered Emperor at the apex, and making subordinates work in exchange for positions and land as rewards, and was a period when the system of custodial provinces and shoen were established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>保元の乱で摂関家が事実上壊滅し、平治の乱で源義朝などの有力武士が淘汰されると、平氏の勢力は他より突出することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The line of regents was destroyed in reality during the Hogen no ran, and major bushi such as MINMOTO no Yoshiaki were selected by Heiji no ran, making the Taira clan have more power than others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The line of regents was in actuality ended during the Hogen no ran, and major bushi such as MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki were selected during the Heiji no ran, giving the Taira clan have more power than others.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The line of regents was in actuality ended during the Hogen Rebellion, and major bushi such as MINAMOTO no Yoshiaki were selected during the Heiji Rebellion, giving the Taira clan have more power than others.</e>
<cmt>保元の乱→Hogen Rebellion、平治の乱→Heiji Rebellionとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="155">
<j>治承三年の政変により平氏政権は完成されたかに見えたが、それは平氏と反対勢力の全面衝突をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan administration seemed to have become complete by the Jisho sannen no seihen, but it only led to a head-to-head confrontation between the Taira clan and anti-Taira groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan administration seemed to have become complete by the Jisho sannen no seihen, but it only led to a head-to-head confrontation between the Taira clan and anti-Taira groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan administration seemed to have become complete by the Jisho sannen no seihen (Coup of the Third Year of Jisho), but it only led to a head-to-head confrontation between the Taira clan and anti-Taira groups.</e>
<cmt>「治承三年の政変」説明補足(Coup of the Third Year of Jisho)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>平氏の軍制の欠陥は、直属部隊が伊勢・伊賀の重代相伝の家人・「私郎従」と呼ばれる諸国の特定武士だけで、兵の大部分を公権力の発動によって動員する形態を採っていたことにある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The defect of the military organization of the Taira clan was that their direct troops consisted only of vassals from Ise and Iga and specific bushi from various provinces that were loyal for successive generations, and the majority of the troops were taken from official government calls to enlist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The defect of the military organization of the Taira clan was that their direct troops consisted only of vassals from Ise and Iga and specific bushi from various provinces that were loyal for successive generations, and the majority of the troops were taken from official government calls to enlist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The defect of the military organization of the Taira clan was that their direct troops consisted only of vassals from Ise and Iga and specific bushi from various provinces that were loyal for successive generations, and the majority of the troops were taken from official government calls to enlist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>都落ちして平氏追討宣旨が下された時点で、平氏に従う兵は僅かになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the point when the Taira clan escaped Kyoto and the Imperial call for attacking the Taira clan was issued, the number of troops that followed the Taira clan dwindled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the point when the Taira clan escaped Kyoto and the Imperial call for attacking the Taira clan was issued, the number of troops that followed the Taira clan had dwindled greatly.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the point when the Taira clan escaped Kyoto and the Imperial call for attacking the Taira clan was issued, the number of troops that followed the Taira clan had dwindled greatly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>安徳天皇を擁していてもその即位はクーデターによるものであり、平氏が自己の立場を正当化することは困難だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if they supported Emperor Antoku, his ascension was by a coup d&apos;etat and it was difficult for the Taira clan to keep credibility.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if they supported Emperor Antoku, his ascension was by a coup d&apos;etat and it was difficult for the Taira clan to maintain credibility.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if they supported Emperor Antoku, his ascension was by a coup d&apos;etat and it was difficult for the Taira clan to maintain credibility.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>平氏は成す術もなく敗北を繰り返し滅亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan could not do anything but lose again and again and eventually died out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan became unable to do anything but lose repeatedly and eventually died out.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan became unable to do anything but lose repeatedly and eventually died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>王朝政権の接収・大々的な外交の展開といった清盛の構想が実現したのは、平氏が滅亡してからおよそ200年後、足利義満の時代だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s plan to gain the court government and develop major trade and diplomacy was finally realized about 200 years after the Taira clan died out, during the period of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori&apos;s plan to create the court government and develop major trade and diplomacy was finally realized about 200 years after the Taira clan died out, during the period of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori&apos;s plan to create the court government and develop major trade and diplomacy was finally realized about 200 years after the Taira clan died out, during the period of Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 初瀬(id:74855), 森山弘一(id:28962), 経済準学士(id:22656), 松茸(id:27535), 水野白楓(id:22811), Greenleaf(id:126500), L III (N)(id:72793), Yanahan(id:2437), 葉月(id:25674), Ytp.rs(id:202698), 沢田(id:40580), 小者(id:172526), Tamachan21(id:34656), Kk8998982(id:43060), Ganman(id:96316), ゐ(id:795), 俊(id:14924), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 寂華(id:83725), Junger(id:10282), シェーラ(id:17988), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>