<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>筆子塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudekozuka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudekozuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudekozuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>筆子塚（ふでこづか）とは、江戸時代に庶民の教育機関であった寺子屋や家塾で、読書算や実務教育を教わった教え子が、師匠が死んだ際にその遺徳を偲んで、建てた墓である塚、または供養塔。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudekozuka is a mound or tower built either as a grave or as a monument in memory of a late teacher who taught at his home or at a terakoya (small private school) reading, arithmetic and other practical arts and sciences to the common people during the Edo Period, by his students who shared the cost of its construction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudekozuka is a mound or a memorial tower built by the students of terakoya (private elementary school) or kajuku (private school) which were educational institution for common people in the Edo period, to the memory of their late teacher who taught them reading, writing, arithmetic and other practical arts.</e>
<cmt>・訂正　分かりづらかったため、全体的に直しました。また、原文「自分たちで費用を出し合って」を分割し、・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudekozuka is a mound or a memorial tower built by the students of terakoya (private elementary school) or kajuku (private school) which were educational institution for common people in the Edo period, to the memory of their late teacher who taught them reading, writing, arithmetic and other practical arts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>筆子塚（ふでこづか）の費用は、教え子が自分たちで出し合った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cost of Fudekozuka was shared by the students</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処「自分たちで費用を出し合って」→「筆子塚（ふでこづか）の費用は、教え子が自分たちで出し合った。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cost of Fudekozuka was shared by the students</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>明治に入ってから建てられた例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some have been built even in Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are some instances built in Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are some instances built in Meiji Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>師匠塚・筆子塔・筆子碑という場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are those built as shisho-zuka, fudekoto or fudekohi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also referred as shisho-zuka, fudeko-to or fudeko-hi.</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also referred as shisho-zuka, fudeko-to or fudeko-hi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>寺子屋は、今日の小学校のように7～8歳前後で入学し、入学後3年から5年程度の間で読書算を習得させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Children were enrolled in terakoya at around age 7 or 8, similar to the enrollment age for elementary school today, and studied reading and arithmetic for 3 to 5 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Children were enrolled in terakoya at around their age of 7 or 8, as what elementary school is today, and learned reading and arithmetic for 3 to 5 years.</e>
<cmt>・訂正at around age 7 or 8,→at around their age of 7 or 8similar to the enrollment age for elementary school today, →as what elementary school is today,studied→learned</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Children were enrolled in terakoya at around their age of 7 or 8, as what elementary school is today, and learned reading and arithmetic for 3 to 5 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その生徒が「筆子」である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These students were called &quot;fudeko.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These students were called &quot;fudeko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These students were called &quot;fudeko.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これから、子どもがよく勉強するようにと、女子の名前としてこれが用いられた例も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this origin, the term was used in quite a few cases as name for a baby girl.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this origin, the term was often used as a name for girls.</e>
<cmt>in quite a few cases→often name for a baby girl→a name for girls</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this origin, the term was often used as a name for girls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸時代には、社会に出る前の準備教育を寺子屋で終える者が多かった為、寺子屋の師匠は筆子たちにとって生涯の師でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because many common people in the Edo Period studied at terakoya as preparations for gaining employment, teachers at these private schools were honored by their students as their masters and teachers of life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since many common people in the Edo Period studied at terakoya for the preparation of being a member of society, teacher of terakoya was regarded as their masters of life.</e>
<cmt>・訂正　全体的に直しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since many common people in the Edo Period studied at terakoya for the preparation of being a member of society, teacher of terakoya was regarded as their masters of life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「寺子屋」という呼称の通り、師匠がお寺の住職という例も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the name &quot;terakoya (temple room)&quot; suggests, many such teachers were Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the name &quot;terakoya (a room of temple)&quot; suggests, many teachers were Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt>・訂正temple room→a room of templesuch→削除</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the name &quot;terakoya (a room of temple)&quot; suggests, many teachers were Buddhist priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>関東地方などでは、筆子塚が各地に散らばって残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kanto region, there are many fudekozuka found in various parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kanto region, there are many fudekozuka found in various places.</e>
<cmt>・修正parts→places</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kanto region, there are many fudekozuka found in various places.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>特徴的な点は、墓石が全体として筆の穂先のような形をしている点である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A unique feature of the monument is that the tombstone is commonly shaped like the tip of a brush.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A unique feature of monuments is that tombstones are commonly shaped like the tip of a brush.</e>
<cmt>・修正the monument→monumentsthe tombstone is→tombstones are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A unique feature of monuments is that tombstones are commonly shaped like the tip of a brush.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>筆子が建立した物はこうした形という約束事もあったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shape is believed to be the protocol that the fudeko observed when building such a memorial for their teacher.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There seems some consensus to rule the shape of tombstone to be built by fudeko.</e>
<cmt>・訂正　分かりづらかったため、全体的に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There seems some consensus to rule the shape of tombstone to be built by fudeko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>又、「坂東の大学」と謳われた足利学校の歴代校長の墓石も、筆の穂先の形になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The tombstones for the schoolteachers who served as principals of Ashikaga Gakko, known as the &quot;university of the Bando region&quot; are also shaped like brush tips.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The tombstones of successive principals of Ashikaga school, known as the &quot;university of the Bando (old Kanto region),&quot; are also shaped like brush tips.</e>
<cmt>・訂正The tombstones for the schoolteachers who served as principals of Ashikaga Gakko, known as the &quot;university of the Bando region&quot;→The tombstones of successive principals of Ashikaga school, known as the &quot;university of the Bando (old Kanto region),</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The tombstones of successive principals of Ashikaga school, known as the &quot;university of the Bando (old Kanto region),&quot; are also shaped like brush tips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>筆塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudezuka</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudezuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudezuka</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>筆塚と呼ばれる物もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are also fudezuka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exists mounds called fudezuka.</e>
<cmt>誤訳のため訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exists mounds called fudezuka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>こちらは長年使って来た筆を供養して埋めた塚を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are mounds under which brushes that have been used for many years are buried as an expression of gratitude and prayer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudezuka is a mound in which brushes that have been used for many years were buried as an expression of gratitude</e>
<cmt>・訂正These are mounds under→Fudezuka is a mound inand prayer→削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudezuka is a mound in which brushes that have been used for many years were buried as an expression of gratitude</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mishika(id:276), Ons(id:21830), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>