<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元寇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genko (Mongol invasion)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genko (Mongol invasion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genko (Mongol invasion)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元寇（げんこう）とは、日本の鎌倉時代中期に、当時大陸を支配していたモンゴル帝国（元 (王朝)）及びその服属政権となった高麗王国によって2度にわたり行われた日本侵攻（遠征）の、日本側の呼称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genko is the Japanese name of two invasions (expeditions) that Japan suffered in the middle Kamakura period from the Mongol Empire (Yuan Dynasty), which was then dominant in the continent, and its subjected kingdom, the Kingdom of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genko is the Japanese name of two invasions (expeditions) that Japan suffered in the middle Kamakura period from the Mongol Empire (Yuan Dynasty), which was then dominant on the continent, and its subjected kingdom, the Kingdom of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genko is the Japanese name of two invasions (expeditions) that Japan suffered in the middle Kamakura period from the Mongol Empire (Yuan Dynasty), which was then dominant on the continent, and its subjected kingdom, the Kingdom of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>1度目を文永の役（ぶんえいのえき・1274年）、2度目を弘安の役（こうあんのえき・1281年）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first invasion is called Bunei no Eki (the Bunei War, 1274) and the second is called Koan no Eki (the Koan War, 1281).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first invasion is called Bunei no Eki (the Bunei War, 1274) and the second is called Koan no Eki (the Koan War, 1281).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first invasion is called Bunei no Eki (the Bunei War, 1274) and the second is called Koan no Eki (the Koan War, 1281).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>蒙古襲来とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also referred to as Moko Shurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also referred to as Moko Shurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also referred to as Moko Shurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>文中の（　）の年はユリウス暦、月日は西暦部分を除き全て和暦、宣明暦の長暦による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Years referred to in () is according to the Julian calendar, while all months and days, excluding years mentioned in the Western calendar, are according to the Japanese calendar calculated in a later era in accordance with the Senmyo calendar (Chinese luni-solar calendar employed in Japan).</e>
<cmt>「長暦」→遡って過去の暦日を復元したもの。（http://library.nao.ac.jp/kichou/open/003/index.html）&quot;calculated in a later era&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Years referred to in () are according to the Julian calendar, while all months and days, excluding years mentioned in the Western calendar, are according to the Japanese calendar calculated in a later era in accordance with the Senmyo calendar (Chinese luni-solar calendar employed in Japan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Years referred to in () are according to the Julian calendar, while all months and days, excluding years mentioned in the Western calendar, are according to the Japanese calendar calculated in a later era in accordance with the Senmyo calendar (Chinese luni-solar calendar employed in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>外交交渉から侵攻まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Diplomatic Negotiations to Invasion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Diplomatic Negotiations to Invasion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Diplomatic Negotiations to Invasion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>1260年にモンゴル帝国の第5代皇帝（ハーン、ハーン）に即位した後のいわゆる「元 (王朝)」（大元ウルス、大元朝、元朝）の皇帝クビライは、1268年（日本の文永5年・大元朝の至元 (元世祖)5年）に第2代皇帝オゴデイ以来の懸案であった南宋攻略を開始する一方、既に服属していた朝鮮半島の高麗を通じて、1266年に日本に初めて通交を求める使者を送ろうとしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kublai, who in 1260 became the fifth emperor (Khan) of the Mongol Empire that was later called &apos;Yuan&apos; (the Great Yuan Ulus, Great Yuan Dynasty or Yuan Dynasty), in 1266 planned to send the first envoys to establish diplomatic relations with Japan, through Goryeo in the Korean peninsula, which had already become its subject, while starting to conquer the Southern Sung Dynasty in 1268, which had been its long-standing aim since the reign of the second emperor Ogodei.</e>
<cmt>「元 (王朝)」→続く（）に「元朝」と出てくるので、（王朝）は訳出不要と判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kublai, who in 1260 became the fifth emperor (Khan) of the Mongol Empire that was later called &apos;Yuan&apos; (the Great Yuan Ulus, Great Yuan Dynasty or Yuan Dynasty), in 1266 planned to send the first envoys to establish diplomatic relations with Japan, through Goryeo in the Korean peninsula, which had already become its subject, while starting to conquer the Southern Sung Dynasty in 1268, which had been its long-standing aim since the reign of the second emperor Ogodei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kublai, who in 1260 became the fifth emperor (Khan) of the Mongol Empire that was later called &apos;Yuan&apos; (the Great Yuan Ulus, Great Yuan Dynasty or Yuan Dynasty), in 1266 planned to send the first envoys to establish diplomatic relations with Japan, through Goryeo in the Korean peninsula, which had already become its subject, while starting to conquer the Southern Sung Dynasty in 1268, which had been its long-standing aim since the reign of the second emperor Ogodei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>『元史日本伝』によるとこの使節を送るのは高麗人で元の官吏である趙彝の進言からとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Genshi Nihon Den&quot; (Japan in the History of the Yuan Dynasty), Goryeo was to send the envoys, in accordance with a proposal made by Cho-i, who was a government official of the Yuan Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>「趙彝」→英語名が不明なため、ローマ字表記です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Genshi Nihon Den&quot; (Japan in the History of the Yuan Dynasty), Goryeo was to send the envoys, in accordance with a proposal made by Cho-i, who was a government official of the Yuan Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Genshi Nihon Den&quot; (Japan in the History of the Yuan Dynasty), these envoys were going to be sent because of a proposal made by Cho-i who was from Goryeo and a government official of the Yuan Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>前後の文脈から、「高麗人で」は「趙彝」を修飾していると思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし高麗の宋君斐・金賛が案内する蒙古の使節ら（正使・黒的、副使・殷弘）は巨済島まで来て、航海の困難を理由に引き返し、クビライに対して日本への通使の不要を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Mongol envoys (chief envoy Kokuteki and vice-envoy Inko), guided by So Kunhi and Kinsan from Goryeo, returned due to the difficulty of the voyage after reaching Geoje Island, and explained Kublai that it was unnecessary to send envoys to Japan.</e>
<cmt>「宋君斐」「金賛」「黒的」「殷弘」→英語名が不明なため、ローマ字表記です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Mongol envoys (chief envoy Kokuteki and vice-envoy Inko), guided by So Kunhi and Kinsan from Goryeo, returned due to the difficulty of the voyage after reaching Geoje Island, and explained to Kublai that it was unnecessary to send envoys to Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Mongol envoys (chief envoy Kokuteki and vice-envoy Inko), guided by So Kunhi and Kinsan from Goryeo, returned due to the difficulty of the voyage after reaching Geoje Island, and explained to Kublai that it was unnecessary to send envoys to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>クビライは予め「風濤の険阻を以って辞となすなかれ」と日本側への国書の手交を厳命していたが、その「風濤の険阻」を理由に使者の両名は渡海もせず引き返してきたことに憤慨してこれを却下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kublai had ordered them strictly to deliver the imperial letter to Japan and &quot;not to give up for a reason attributable to bad weather,&quot; and thus, when both envoys returned without crossing the sea due to the reason of &apos;bad weather&apos;, he got upset and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kublai had ordered them strictly to deliver the imperial letter to Japan and &quot;not to give up for a reason attributable to bad weather,&quot; and thus, when both envoys returned without crossing the sea due to the reason of &apos;bad weather&apos;, he got upset and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kublai had ordered them strictly to deliver the imperial letter to Japan and &quot;not to give up for a reason attributable to bad weather,&quot; and thus, when both envoys returned without crossing the sea due to the reason of &apos;bad weather,&apos; he got upset and did not accept it.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そして再び高麗に命令し、使節として高麗国王元宗 (高麗王)の側近であった起居舎人・潘阜が派遣され、1268年正月に大宰府へと到着。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then ordered Goryeo again, and Hanpu, who was a secretary close to King Wonjong of Goryeo, was sent as envoy and reached Dazai-fu (local government office in Kyushu region) in January 1268.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「起居舎人」→日本の律令制では内記にあたる役職のようです。（http://www.sol.dti.ne.jp/~hiromi/kansei/r_namejckn.html） &quot;secretary&quot;と訳しました。「潘阜」→英語名が不明なため、ローマ字表記です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then ordered Goryeo again, and Hanpu, who was a secretary close to King Wonjong of Goryeo, was sent as envoy and reached Dazai-fu (local government office in the Kyushu region) in January 1268.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then ordered Goryeo again, and Hanpu, who was a secretary close to King Wonjong of Goryeo, was sent as envoy and reached Dazai-fu (local government office in the Kyushu region) in January 1268.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>大宰府の少弐資能（武藤資能）は蒙古国書（日本側では牒状と記録）と高麗王書状を受け取り、鎌倉幕府へ送達する（しかし、日本側からの返牒の気配がなかったためか、太宰府来着から七ヶ月後に潘阜は高麗へ帰還しており、高麗は同年10月には潘阜の遣使が不首尾に終わった旨を元朝宮廷側に潘阜ら自らが赴くなどして報告している）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sukeyoshi SHONI (Sukeyoshi MUTO) of Dazai-fu received the letter from the Mongol Empire (letter and records according to Japanese materials) and the one from the king of Goryeo, and sent them to the Kamakura shogunate (however, Hanpu returned to Goryeo seven months after his arrival at Dazai-fu, possibly because Japan showed no intention to reply, and in October of the same year, Goryeo reported the Yuan imperial court, by envoy Hanpu himself visiting there, that he had gained no fruit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sukeyoshi SHONI (Sukeyoshi MUTO) of Dazai-fu received the letter from the Mongol Empire (letter and records according to Japanese materials) and the one from the king of Goryeo, and sent them to the Kamakura shogunate (however, Hanpu returned to Goryeo seven months after his arrival at Dazai-fu, possibly because Japan showed no intention to reply, and in October of the same year, Goryeo reported to the Yuan imperial court, by envoy Hanpu himself visiting there, that he had gained no fruit).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukeyoshi SHONI (Sukeyoshi MUTO) of Dazai-fu received the letter from the Mongol Empire (letter and records according to Japanese materials) and the one from the king of Goryeo, and sent them to Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (however, Hanpu returned to Goryeo seven months after his arrival at Dazai-fu, possibly because Japan showed no intention to reply, and in October of the same year, Goryeo reported to the Yuan imperial court, by envoy Hanpu himself visiting there, that he had gained no fruit).</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>鎌倉幕府は5代執権北条時頼没後その嫡男北条時宗が若年のため傍系の6代北条長時、ついで7代北条政村が執政し、これを漸く成年に達した連署の北条時宗らが補佐する体制が敷かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura shogunate, after the death of the fifth regent Tokiyori HOJO, whose heir Tokimune HOJO was too young, Nagatoki HOJO from a branch line became the sixth regent, who was succeeded by the seventh regent Masamura HOJO, and then Tokimune HOJO finally reached the age of manhood and supported Masamura as rensho (assistant to regents).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura shogunate, after the death of the fifth regent Tokiyori HOJO, whose heir Tokimune HOJO was too young, Nagatoki HOJO from a branch line became the sixth regent, who was succeeded by the seventh regent Masamura HOJO, and then Tokimune HOJO finally reached the age of manhood and supported Masamura as rensho (assistant to regents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kamakura bakufu, after the death of the fifth regent Tokiyori HOJO, whose heir Tokimune HOJO was too young, Nagatoki HOJO from a branch line became the sixth regent, who was succeeded by the seventh regent Masamura HOJO, and then Tokimune HOJO finally reached the age of manhood and supported Masamura as rensho (assistant to regents).</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、この危機を前に1268年3月には時宗が8代執権に就任。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in this increasing threat, Tokimune assumed the position of the eighth regent in March 1268.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, facing this increasing threat, Tokimune assumed the position of the eighth regent in March 1268.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, facing this increasing threat, Tokimune assumed the position of the eighth regent in March 1268.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幕府では関東申次の西園寺実氏に託して蒙古国書を朝廷へ回送し、黙殺を決定させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate asked Saneuji SAIONJI, who was kanto moshitsugi (court-appointed liaison with the shogunate), to deliver the letter of the Mongol Empire to the Imperial Court, and led the court to the decision to ignore it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate asked Saneuji SAIONJI, who was kanto moshitsugi (court-appointed liaison with the shogunate), to deliver the letter from the Mongol Empire to the Imperial Court, and led the court to the decision to ignore it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu asked Saneuji SAIONJI, who was kanto moshitsugi (court-appointed liaison with bakufu), to deliver the letter from the Mongol Empire to the Imperial Court, and led the court to the decision to ignore it.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに幕府は後嵯峨上皇没の直後の二月騒動で時宗の庶兄北条時輔等を粛正し統制を強化、さらに諸国への異国警護、異国降伏の祈祷を行わせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate also purged Tokimune&apos;s older brother by a concubine, Tokisuke HOJO, and others, in order to strengthen its leadership, and in addition, it ordered various provinces to guard against foreign attacks and held prayer services for the surrender of foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate also purged Tokimune&apos;s older brother by a concubine, Tokisuke HOJO, and others, in order to strengthen its leadership, and in addition, ordered various provinces to guard against foreign attacks and held prayer services for the surrender of foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu also purged Tokimune&apos;s older brother by a concubine, Tokisuke HOJO, and others, in order to strengthen its leadership through Nigatsu-sodo (February rebellion) just after the death of the retired Emperor Gosaga, and in addition, ordered various provinces to guard against foreign attacks and held prayer services for the surrender of foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>term, 訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>宗教界にも影響を与え、日蓮は『立正安国論』を幕府に上程して国難を主張する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also influenced people of religion, and Nichiren submitted &quot;Rissho Ankoku Ron&quot; (Treatise for Spreading Peace Throughout the Country by Establishing the True Teaching) to the shogunate, insisting that it was a national crisis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also influenced people of religion, and Nichiren submitted &quot;Rissho Ankoku Ron&quot; (Treatise for Spreading Peace Throughout the Country by Establishing the True Teaching) to the shogunate, insisting that it was a national crisis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also influenced people of religion, and Nichiren submitted &quot;Rissho Ankoku Ron&quot; (Treatise for Spreading Peace Throughout the Country by Establishing the True Teaching) to bakufu, insisting that it was a national crisis.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>同年には再び知門下省事・申思佺、侍郎・陳子厚および潘阜ら高麗使臣が正使・黒的、副使・殷弘をともなって派遣され、第2回目の使節が日本へ上陸したが、これを黙殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Goryeo again sent envoys, including chancellor Shin Shisen, assistant chancellor Chin Shiko and Hanpu, accompanying chief envoy Kokuteki and vice-envoy Inko, but Japan ignored these second envoys who reached there.</e>
<cmt>「知門下省事」→高麗のchancellorの一人のようです。&quot;chancellor&quot;と訳しました。（http://www.dbpia.co.kr/view/ar_view.asp?arid=1013905）「侍郎」→次官職。&quot;assistant chancellor&quot;と訳しました。（デジタル大辞泉及びhttp://japan.donga.com/srv/service.php3?biid=2000111461430&amp;path_dir=20001114など参照）。「申思佺」「陳子厚」「潘阜」「黒的」「殷弘」→英語名が不明なため、ローマ字表記です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same year, Goryeo again sent envoys, including chancellor Shin Shisen, assistant chancellor Chin Shiko and Hanpu, accompanying chief envoy Kokuteki and vice-envoy Inko, but Japan ignored these second envoys who reached there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same year, vasslas from Goryeo were sent again, including chancellor Shin Shisen, assistant chancellor Chin Shiko and Hanpu, accompanying chief envoy Kokuteki and vice-envoy Inko, but Japan ignored these second envoys who reached there.</e>
<cmt>使節を派遣したのは元であり、元が高麗出身の家臣を派遣したと判断し、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかしながら、今度の使節は対馬に着いたのみで太宰府へは至らず、同島で住民らと諍いを起こし対馬島人の塔二郎と弥二郎という二名を捕らえて、これらとともに帰還した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these envoys did not reach Dazai-fu, only Tsushima Island, where they had a dispute with local people and captured two men in the island called Tojiro and Yajiro, and brought them home.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these envoys did not reach as far as Dazai-fu, only Tsushima Island, where they had a dispute with local people and captured two men on the island called Tojiro and Yajiro, and brought them home.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these envoys did not reach as far as Dazai-fu, only Tsushima Island, where they had a dispute with local people and captured two men on the island called Tojiro and Yajiro, and brought them home.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これを見た高麗に反乱を起していた三別抄から、共同で元に対抗する軍事的援助を求める使者が来訪したがこれも黙殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to it, Sambyeolcho, which had rose a rebellion against Goryeo, sent envoys to Japan to ask for military support and cooperation to fight against the Yuan Dynasty, but it was also ignored.</e>
<cmt>「来訪した」→「（日本に）来訪した」と補足して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to it, Sambyeolcho, which had risen in a rebellion against Goryeo, sent envoys to Japan to ask for military support and cooperation to fight against the Yuan Dynasty, but it was also ignored.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to it, Sambyeolcho, which had risen in a rebellion against Goryeo, sent envoys to Japan to ask for military support and cooperation to fight against the Yuan Dynasty, but it was also ignored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>1271年9月、元使の趙良弼らが元への服属を命じる国書を携えてきた際には、幕府はこれを朝廷に進上した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September 1271, when envoys from the Yuan Dynasty, including Chao Liang-pi, brought a letter ordering Japan to become its subject, the shogunate submitted it to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September 1271, when envoys from the Yuan Dynasty, including Chao Liang-pi, brought a letter ordering Japan to become its subject, the shogunate submitted it to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1271, when envoys from the Yuan Dynasty, including Chao Liang-pi, brought a letter ordering Japan to become its subject, bakufu submitted it to the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>朝廷は急いで伊勢に勅使を派遣し、神々に異国降伏を祈った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial Court hurriedly sent an envoy to Ise-jingu Shrine and held a prayer service for the surrender of foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>「伊勢」→伊勢神宮のことと思われます。伊勢だけでは不明瞭なため、&quot;Ise-jingu Shrine&quot;と補足して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial Court hurriedly sent an envoy to Ise-jingu Shrine and held a prayer service for the surrender of foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial Court hurriedly sent an envoy to Ise-jingu Shrine and held a prayer service for the surrender of foreign enemies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>朝廷内部では返事を出すかどうかで論争されたが、幕府が返事を出す事に反対した事、朝廷内でも「元の要求に屈するべきではない」という強硬論が強かった事から、朝廷・幕府ともに国書を黙殺する事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there was an argument in the Imperial Court over whether or not to reply, the shogunate opposed to reply, and the majority of the Imperial Court also had a strong attitude, insisting, &quot;we should not yield to the demand of the Yuan Dynasty,&quot; and thus, both the Imperial Court and shogunate decided to ignore the letter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there was an argument in the Imperial Court over whether or not to reply, the shogunate opposed replying, and the majority of the Imperial Court also had a strong attitude, insisting, &quot;we should not yield to the demand of the Yuan Dynasty,&quot; and thus, both the Imperial Court and shogunate decided to ignore the letter.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there was an argument in the Imperial Court over whether or not to reply, bakufu opposed replying, and the majority of the Imperial Court also had a strong attitude, insisting, &apos;we should not yield to the demand of the Yuan Dynasty,&apos; and thus, both the Imperial Court and bakufu decided to ignore the letter.</e>
<cmt>term, grammer</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>クビライはその後も何度か日本に使者を出したが全て無視され、最終的に武力侵攻を決定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kublai continued sending envoys to Japan several times after that, but Japan ignored all of them, and in the end, he decided a military invasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kublai continued sending envoys to Japan several times after that, but Japan ignored all of them, and in the end, he decided on a military invasion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kublai continued sending envoys to Japan several times after that, but Japan ignored all of them, and in the end, he decided on a military invasion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>『元史高麗伝』によると当初より3つの案が検討された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Genshi Korai Den&quot; (Goryeo in the History of the Yuan Dynasty), there were three plans in the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Genshi Korai Den&quot; (Goryeo in the History of the Yuan Dynasty), there were three plans in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Genshi Korai Den&quot; (Goryeo in the History of the Yuan Dynasty), there were three plans in the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="24">
<j>日本は島国で攻略が難しいので高麗に兵を置き国書により属国にする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Demanding Japan to become its subject, keeping soldiers in Goryeo, because Japan is an island country and difficult to conquer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Demanding Japan to become its subject, keeping soldiers in Goryeo, because Japan is an island country and difficult to conquer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Demanding Japan to become its subject by sovereign&apos;s message, keeping soldiers in Goryeo, because Japan is an island country and difficult to conquer.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>この案では損害もでず、また高麗の統治強化および南宋と日本の分断が可能。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This plan could strengthen its governing power in Goryeo and isolate the Southern Sung Dynasty and Japan from each other, without suffering any damage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This plan could strengthen its governing power in Goryeo and isolate the Southern Sung Dynasty and Japan from each other, without suffering any damage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This plan could strengthen its governing power in Goryeo and isolate the Southern Sung Dynasty and Japan from each other, without suffering any damage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="26">
<j>まず南宋を攻略し服属せしめた漢人を使って日本を攻略する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conquering the Southern Sung Dynasty firstly, and then Japan, employing the subjected people of Han.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conquering the Southern Sung Dynasty first, and then Japan, employing the subjected people of Han.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conquering the Southern Sung Dynasty first, and then Japan, employing the subjected people of Han.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この案は多数の兵力を準備でき蒙人高官が支持していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This plan would enable it to obtain a large number of soldiers and was supported by Mongol high officials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This plan would enable it to obtain a large number of soldiers and was supported by Mongol high officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This plan would enable it to obtain a large number of soldiers and was supported by Mongol high officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="28">
<j>高麗軍を使って東路より日本を攻略する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conquering Japan via the eastern route, by employing the Goryeo army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conquering Japan via the eastern route, by employing the Goryeo army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conquering Japan via the eastern route, by employing the Goryeo army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この案では兵力不足が懸念された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This plan might have the problem of soldier shortage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This plan might have a problem of a shortage of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This plan might have a problem of a shortage of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="30">
<j>『高麗史』及び『元史』によれば、高麗の（のちの忠烈王の）執拗な要請があり、蒙人の高官は兵力不足を懸念して南宋攻略を先にすべきと主張したが、高麗を経由する東路からの日本侵攻が決定されたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koraishi&quot; (The History of Goryeo) and &quot;Genshi&quot; (The History of the Yuan Dynasty), Mongol high officials were worried about soldier shortage and insisted on conquering the Southern Sung Dynasty firstly, but Goryeo (later King Chungnyeol) persistently requested them to invade Japan from the eastern route via Goryeo, and thus it was so decided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koraishi&quot; (The History of Goryeo) and &quot;Genshi&quot; (The History of the Yuan Dynasty), Mongol high officials were worried about soldier shortage and insisted on conquering the Southern Sung Dynasty first, but Goryeo (later King Chungnyeol) persistently requested them to invade Japan from the eastern route via Goryeo, and thus it was so decided.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Koraishi&quot; (The History of Goryeo) and &quot;Genshi&quot; (The History of the Yuan Dynasty), Mongol high officials were worried about soldier shortage and insisted on conquering the Southern Sung Dynasty first, but Goryeo (later King Chungnyeol) persistently requested them to invade Japan from the eastern route via Goryeo, and thus it was so decided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="31">
<j>クビライは高麗に命じて日本へ侵攻する艦船を作らせ、食糧などを供給した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kublai ordered Goryeo to construct ships to invade Japan, and supplied them with foods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kublai ordered Goryeo to construct ships to invade Japan, and supplied them with food.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kublai ordered Goryeo to construct ships to invade Japan, and supplied them with food.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この時の建造費は高麗が負担し、大小900艘と言われる船をわずか半年の突貫工事で完成させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goryeo bore the construction expenses and completed large and small ships, which are said to have been 900 in total, in a such short period of six months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goryeo bore the construction expenses and completed large and small ships, which are said to have been 900 in total, in a such short period of six months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goryeo bore the construction expenses and completed large and small ships, which are said to have been 900 in total, in a such short period of six months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これらの動向を察知していた鎌倉幕府は、1272年に異国警護番役を設置し、鎮西奉行であった少弐氏（武藤氏）や大友氏に対して指揮を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura shogunate, which had noticed these activities, created the position of Ikoku Keigo Banyaku (Foreign Enemy Defense) in 1272, and ordered the Shoni clan (Muto clan) serving as Chinzei Bugyo (Defense Commissioner of the West) and the Otomo clan to supervise it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura shogunate, which had noticed these activities, created the position of Ikoku Keigo Banyaku (Foreign Enemy Defense) in 1272, and ordered the Shoni clan (Muto clan) serving as Chinzei Bugyo (Defense Commissioner of the West) and the Otomo clan to supervise it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura bakufu, which had noticed these activities, created the position of Ikoku Keigo Banyaku (Foreign Enemy Defense) in 1272, and ordered the Shoni clan (Muto clan) serving as Chinzei Bugyo (Defense Commissioner of the West) and the Otomo clan to supervise it.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>元は1273年2月には南宋の襄陽を落とし、三別抄も平定する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuan Dynasty conquered Xiangyan in the Southern Sung Dynasty in February 1273, and also subdued Sambyeolcho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuan Dynasty conquered Xiangyan in the Southern Sung Dynasty in February 1273, and also subdued Sambyeolcho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuan Dynasty conquered Xiangyan in the Southern Sung Dynasty in February 1273, and also subdued Sambyeolcho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>文永の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bunei no Eki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bunei no Eki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bunei no Eki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="35">
<j>日本の文永11年・元の至元11年10月（1274年11月）に、忻都、金方慶らに率いられ、モンゴル人・漢人・女真人・高麗人など非戦闘員を含む3万人を乗せた船が朝鮮の月浦（合浦。現在の馬山）を出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November 1274, the ships departed from Gappo in the Korean peninsula (now Masan) with 30 thousand people on board, including non-soldiers, led by Xin Dou and Kim Bang-gyeong, consisting of people of Mongol, Han, Jurchen and Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>「月浦」→合浦とも書く。ここでは漢字の違いは訳出不要と思われます。また、英語名が不明なため、ローマ字表記です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1274, the ships departed from Gappo in the Korean peninsula (now Masan) with 30,000 people on board, including non-soldiers, led by Dou XIN and Bang-gyeong KIM, consisting of people of Mongol, Han, Jurchen, and Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1274, the ships departed from Gappo in the Korean peninsula (now Masan) with 30,000 people on board, including non-soldiers, led by Xin Dou, Kim Bang-gyeong and others, consisting of people of Mongol, Han, Jurchen, and Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ, term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="36">
<j>10月5日 (旧暦)に対馬、10月14日 (旧暦)に壱岐を襲撃し、平戸鷹島の松浦党の本拠を全滅させ、壱岐守護代の平景隆を自害に追い込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They attacked Tsushima on October 5 and Iki on October 14 (both dates according to old lunar calendar), completely destroying the headquarters of the Matsuura Party (group of local warriors based in Matsuura area) in Taka-shima Island, Hirado, and drove Shugodai (Deputy Military Governor) of Iki Province TAIRA no Kagetaka into committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>「松浦党」→松浦地方で活動していた集団。&quot;group of local warriors based in Matsuura area&quot;と説明を入れました。（http://www.city.sasebo.nagasaki.jp/rekisi/06/06_01.htm参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They attacked Tsushima on October 5 and Iki on October 14 (both dates according to old lunar calendar), completely destroying the headquarters of the Matsuura Party (group of local warriors based in Matsuura area) in Taka-shima Island, Hirado, and drove Shugodai (Deputy Military Governor) of Iki Province TAIRA no Kagetaka to committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They attacked Tsushima on October 5 and Iki on October 14 (both dates according to old lunar calendar), completely destroying the headquarters of the Matsuura Party (group of local warriors based in Matsuura area) in Taka-shima Island, Hirado, and drove Shugodai (Deputy Military Governor) of Iki Province TAIRA no Kagetaka to committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>さらに『新元史』によれば日蓮の書簡の記述に依るとして、この時民衆を殺戮し、生き残った者の手の平に穴を開け、そこに革紐を通して船壁に吊るし見せしめにしたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Shin Genshi&quot; (New History of the Yuan Dynasty), a letter of Nichiren describes that they then massacred people and made a hole in the palms of survivors to lace a leather cord through it, and hanged them on the ships&apos; walls as a warning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, according to &quot;Shin Genshi&quot; (New History of the Yuan Dynasty), a letter of Nichiren describes that they then massacred people and made a hole in the palms of survivors to lace a leather cord through it, and hung them on the ships&apos; sides as a warning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, according to &quot;Shin Genshi&quot; (New History of the Yuan Dynasty), a letter of Nichiren describes that they then massacred people and made a hole in the palms of survivors to lace a leather cord through it, and hung them on the ships&apos; sides as a warning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また高麗の将軍がこのときに捕虜とした子供男女200人を高麗王と王妃に献上したという記録が、高麗側に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Goryeo&apos;s records, a general from Goryeo then captured 200 children, including both boys and girls, and presented them to the king and queen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Goryeo&apos;s records, a general from Goryeo then captured 200 children, including both boys and girls, and presented them to the king and queen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Goryeo&apos;s records, a general from Goryeo then captured 200 children, including both boys and girls, and presented them to the king and queen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>壱岐の状況が博多に伝わり、京都や鎌倉へ向けての急報が発せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation of Iki was informed to Hakata, and then urgent messages were dispatched to Kyoto and Kamakura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation of Iki was informed to Hakata, and then urgent messages were dispatched to Kyoto and Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation of Iki was informed to Hakata, and then urgent messages were dispatched to Kyoto and Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>日本側は少弐氏や大友氏をはじめ九州の御家人を中心として大宰府に集結しつつあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, the shogunate&apos;s vassals were gathering in Dazai-fu, including the Shoni clan and Otomo clan, mainly those from Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, the shogunate&apos;s vassals were gathering in Dazai-fu, including the Shoni clan and Otomo clan, mainly those from Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate in the Kamakura and Muromachi through Edo periods) were gathering in Dazai-fu, including the Shoni clan and Otomo clan, mainly those from Kyushu region.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="41">
<j>元軍は10月19日 (旧暦)には博多湾に現れ、湾西端の今津に停泊し一部兵力を上陸させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuan army appeared in Hakata Bay on October 19 (according to old lunar calendar), and anchored ships at Imazu, located at the western edge of the bay, to disembark a part of its soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuan army appeared in Hakata Bay on October 19 (according to old lunar calendar), and anchored ships at Imazu, located at the western edge of the bay, to disembark some of its soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuan army appeared in Hakata Bay on October 19 (according to old lunar calendar), and anchored ships at Imazu, located at the western edge of the bay, to disembark some of its soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>10月20日 (旧暦)（太陽暦では11月25日）、船団は東に進み百道浜つづいて地行浜、長浜、那ノ津、須崎浜（博多）、東浜、箱崎浜に上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 20 (according to old lunar calendar, on November 25 according to solar calendar), the fleet moved towards the east, disembarking at Momochihama, and then at Jigyohama, Nagahama, Nanotsu, Suzakihama (Hakata), Higashihama and Hakozakihama.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 20 (according to old lunar calendar, on November 25 according to solar calendar), the fleet moved towards the east, disembarking at Momochihama, and then at Jigyohama, Nagahama, Nanotsu, Suzakihama (Hakata), Higashihama, and Hakozakihama.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 20 (according to old lunar calendar, on November 25 according to solar calendar), the fleet moved towards the east, disembarking at Momochihama, and then at Jigyohama, Nagahama, Nanotsu, Suzakihama (Hakata), Higashihama, and Hakozakihama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>博多湾西部から上陸した兵は、麁原（現在の祖原山）、別府に陣を構えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The soldiers having disembarked at the west part of Hakata Bay took a position in Sohara (now Mt. Sohara) and Beppu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The soldiers having disembarked at the western part of Hakata Bay took a position at Sohara (now Mt. Sohara) and Beppu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The soldiers having disembarked at the western part of Hakata Bay took a position at Sohara (now Mt. Sohara) and Beppu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="44">
<j>日本の武士は、当初は名乗りをあげての一騎打ちや、少人数での先駆けを試みたため一方的に損害を受けたが、昼頃には集団戦術に対応、また増援の到着により反撃に転じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese samurai, in the beginning, suffered damages unilaterally because they tried to fight one to one declaring their names, or lead an attack in a small group, but around noon they accommodated themselves to fighting with a large number of soldiers, and following the arrival of reinforcements, started to counterattack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese samurai, in the beginning, suffered damage unilaterally because they tried to fight one to one declaring their names, or led attacks in a small group, but around noon they organized themselves to fight with a large number of soldiers, and following the arrival of reinforcements, started to counterattack.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese samurai, in the beginning, suffered damage unilaterally because they tried to fight one to one declaring their names, or led attacks in a small group, but around noon they organized themselves to fight with a large number of soldiers, and following the arrival of reinforcements, started to counterattack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>『八幡愚童訓』（『八幡愚童訓』甲種本のひとつ）によると、百道浜より3キロ東の赤坂にて菊池武房らの軍勢230名ほどの騎馬が徒歩の部隊だった2千前後の元軍を撃破した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; (Tales of the God of War Told to the Simple) (one of so-called Koshu-type editions of &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot;), troops consisting of approximately 230 samurai on horseback, led by Takefusa KIKUCHI and others, defeated the Yuan army of about 2,000 foot soldiers, in Akasaka located three kilometers east of Momochihama.</e>
<cmt>「甲種本」→『八幡愚童訓』には内容の異なる甲種、乙種と呼ばれるタイプがあるそうです。&quot;so-called Koshu-type&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; (Tales of the God of War Told to the Simple) (one of so-called Koshu-type editions of &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot;), troops consisting of approximately 230 samurai on horseback, led by Takefusa KIKUCHI and others, defeated the Yuan army of about 2,000 foot soldiers, in Akasaka located three kilometers east of Momochihama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; (Tales of the God of War Told to the Simple) (one of so-called Koshu-type editions of &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot;), troops consisting of approximately 230 samurai on horseback, led by Takefusa KIKUCHI and others, defeated the Yuan army of about 2,000 foot soldiers, in Akasaka located three kilometers east of Momochihama.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>『蒙古襲来絵詞』によると竹崎季長が鳥飼潟から祖原へ追撃、上陸地点より500メートル付近まで押し返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Moko Shurai Ekotoba&quot; (Picture Scroll of the Mongol Invasion), Suenaga TAKEZAKI chased the enemy from Torikaigata to Sohara, and forced it back to the place about 500 meters from where they had disembarked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Moko Shurai Ekotoba&quot; (Picture Scroll of the Mongol Invasion), Suenaga TAKEZAKI chased the enemy from Torikaigata to Sohara, and forced it back to the place about 500 meters from where they had disembarked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Moko Shurai Ekotoba&quot; (Picture Scroll of the Mongol Invasion), Suenaga TAKEZAKI chased the enemy from Torikaigata to Sohara, and forced it back to the place about 500 meters from where they had disembarked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>さらに後続を待たず先駆けを試み窮地に陥ったところ白石通泰らが救援に駆けつけ矢戦となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He attacked further in front, without waiting other units to arrive, and when he fell into danger, Michiyasu SHIRAISHI came to rescue him, and then an arrow battle started.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He attacked further in front, without waiting for other units to arrive, and when he fell into danger, Michiyasu SHIRAISHI came to rescue him, and then an arrow battle started.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He attacked further in front, without waiting for other units to arrive, and when he fell into danger, Michiyasu SHIRAISHI and others came to rescue him, and then an arrow battle started.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="48">
<j>博多では海岸付近で激しい矢戦となり、日本軍は敗走したが殿軍の少弐景資が追撃してきた劉復亨を射倒すなどして、内陸への侵入を阻止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Hakata, they had a fierce arrow battle near the coast, and the Japanese army lost and withdrew, but prevented the enemy from entering into inland, by the rearguard unit led by Kagesuke SHONI shooting an arrow at Liu Fu-heng, who came in pursuit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Hakata, they had a fierce arrow battle near the coast, and the Japanese army lost and withdrew, but prevented the enemy from advancing inland, using the rearguard unit led by Kagesuke SHONI, shooting an arrow at Fu-heng LIU, who came in pursuit.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Hakata, they had a fierce arrow battle near the coast, and the Japanese army lost and withdrew, but prevented the enemy from advancing inland, using the rearguard unit led by Kagesuke SHONI, shooting an arrow at LIU Fu-heng, who came in pursuit.</e>
<cmt>grammer</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>『高麗史』によると、やがて日暮となり戦闘を解し、日本軍は大宰府に帰った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koraishi,&quot; it soon became dark and the battle ended, and the Japanese army returned to Dazai-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koraishi,&quot; it soon became dark and the battle ended, and the Japanese army returned to Dazai-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Koraishi,&quot; it soon became dark and the battle ended, and the Japanese army returned to Dazai-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>一方、元軍は博多を占拠したものの終日の激戦で矢が尽き、軍の編成が崩れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Yuan army occupied Hakata, but arrows run short due to the day-long fierce battles and the army became disorganized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the Yuan army occupied Hakata, but arrows ran short due to day-long fierce battles and the army became disorganized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Yuan army occupied Hakata, but arrows ran short due to day-long fierce battles and the army became disorganized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>このため、大宰府攻略をあきらめ、博多の市街に火をかけて焼き払い、撤退することにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It therefore gave up the conquest of Dazai-fu and decided to withdraw, leaving the city of Hakata in fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It therefore gave up the conquest of Dazai-fu and decided to withdraw, leaving the city of Hakata on fire.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It therefore gave up the conquest of Dazai-fu and decided to withdraw, leaving the city of Hakata on fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="52">
<j>『高麗史』金方慶伝によると、この夜に自陣に帰還した後の軍議と思われる部分が載っており、高麗軍の主将である金方慶と派遣軍総司令官である忽敦との間で、以下のようなやり取りがあったことが述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The records on Kim Bang-gyeong in &quot;Koraishi&quot; include descriptions that seem to be a part of the military meeting held on that night after returning to their position, saying that the following conversation was held between the head of the Goryeo army Kim Bang-gyeong and commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force Xin Dou.</e>
<cmt>「忽敦」→既出の忻都のことのようです。（岩波講座日本歴史：中世 [http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=Q8JHAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%E5%BF%BD%E6%95%A6&amp;dq=%E5%BF%BD%E6%95%A6&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=mbVcTNigI4bvcJvzgMsH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEoQ6AEwBg] など参照）。忻都と同じく&quot;Xin Dou&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The records on Bang-gyeong KIM in &quot;Koraishi&quot; include descriptions that seem to be part of the military meeting held on that night after returning to their position, saying that the following conversation was held between the head of the Goryeo army Bang-gyeong KIM and commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force Dou XIN.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The records on Bang-gyeong KIM in &quot;Koraishi&quot; include descriptions that seem to be part of the military meeting held on that night after returning to their position, saying that the following conversation was held between the head of the Goryeo army Bang-gyeong KIM and commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force Dou XIN.</e>
<cmt>grammer,term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="53">
<j>金方慶「兵法に『千里の県軍、その鋒当たるべからず』とあり、本国よりも遠く離れ敵地に入った軍は、却って志気が上がり戦闘能力が高まるものである。我が軍は少なしといえども既に敵地に入っている。我が軍は自ずから戦うことになるがこれは秦穆公の孟明の『焚船』や漢の韓信の『背水の陣』の故事に沿うものである。再度戦わせて頂きたい。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kim Bang-gyeong said, &quot;an art of war teaches us not to fight with an army that has come from far away. It means that entering into the enemy&apos;s territory, far away from home, rather raises the morale and fighting strength of the army. Our army is small, but already in the enemy&apos;s territory. Although we ourselves are to fight, it is in accordance with historical lessons such as &apos;burning his own ships to fight&apos; of Meng Ming, who served Duke Mu of Qin, and &apos;fighting with his back against the river&apos; of Han Xin, who served the Han Dynasty. Please let us fight again.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「秦穆公の孟明の『焚船』」→秦穆公に仕えた孟明が自軍の船を焼いて進軍した故事。（http://www.slideshare.net/gunyouak/16-3592537参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kim Bang-gyeong said, &quot;an art of war teaches us not to fight with an army that has come from far away. It means that entering into the enemy&apos;s territory, far away from home, rather raises the morale and fighting strength of the army. Our army is small, but already in the enemy&apos;s territory. Although we ourselves are to fight, it is in accordance with historical lessons such as &apos;burning his own ships to fight&apos; of Meng Ming, who served Duke Mu of Qin, and &apos;fighting with his back against the river&apos; of Han Xin, who served the Han Dynasty. Please let us fight again.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bang-gyeong KIM said, &quot;an art of war teaches us not to fight with an army that has come from far away. It means that entering into the enemy&apos;s territory, far away from home, rather raises the morale and fighting strength of the army. Our army is small, but already in the enemy&apos;s territory. Although we ourselves are to fight, it is in accordance with historical lessons such as &apos;burning his own ships to fight&apos; of Ming MENG, who served Duke Mu of Qin, and &apos;fighting with his back against the river&apos; of Xin HAN, who served the Han Dynasty. Please let us fight again.&quot;</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="54">
<j>忽敦　「孫子の兵法に『小敵の堅は、大敵の擒なり』とあって『孫子 (書物)』謀攻編「故善用兵者、屈人之兵、而非戰也。；拔人之城、而非攻也。；毀人之國、必以全爭于天下、故兵不頓、利可全、此謀攻之法也。故用兵之法、十則圍之、五則攻之、倍則分之、敵則能戰之、少則能守之、不若則能避之。故小敵之堅、大敵之擒也」、少数の兵が力量を顧みずに頑強に戦っても、多数の兵力の前には結局捕虜にしかならないものである。疲弊した兵士を用い、日増しに敵軍が増えている状況で相対させるのは、完璧な策とは言えない。撤退すべきである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Xin Dou said, &quot;the Art of War by Sun Tzu tells us that an obstinate attitude leads a small army to being captured by a large army. If the small army fiercely fights against the large army without considering the deference of their fighting strength, it will end up being captured. It is not a perfect plan to force tired soldiers to fight against the enemy who is increasing in number. We should withdraw.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「忽敦」→既出の忻都のことのようです。（岩波講座日本歴史：中世 [http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=Q8JHAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%E5%BF%BD%E6%95%A6&amp;dq=%E5%BF%BD%E6%95%A6&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=mbVcTNigI4bvcJvzgMsH&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=7&amp;ved=0CEoQ6AEwBg] など参照）。忻都と同じく&quot;Xin Dou&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Xin Dou said, &quot;the Art of War by Sun Tzu tells us that an obstinate attitude leads a small army to being captured by a large army. If the small army fiercely fights against the large army without considering the deference of their fighting strength, it will end up being captured. It is not a perfect plan to force tired soldiers to fight against the enemy that is increasing in number. We should withdraw.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dou XIN said, &quot;the Art of War by Tzu SUN tells us that an obstinate attitude leads a small army to being captured by a large army. If the small army fiercely fights against the large army without considering the deference of their fighting strength, it will end up being captured. It is not a perfect plan to force tired soldiers to fight against the enemy that is increasing in number. We should withdraw.&quot;</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="55">
<j>このような議論があり、また劉復亨が負傷したこともあって、軍は撤退することになったと言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army was said to have decided to withdraw as a result of the discussion held, and also due to the injury of Liu Fu-heng.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army was said to have decided to withdraw as a result of the discussion, and also due to the injury of Liu Fu-heng.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army was said to have decided to withdraw as a result of the discussion, and also due to the injury of Fu-heng LIU.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>しかしながら、後述のように文永の役での日本派遣軍の目的はもともと威力偵察の類いであり、このやり取りも当初からの撤退予定を見越したものではなかったか、という指摘もされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as explained later, there is an opinion that the purpose of the expeditionary force to Japan in Bunei no Eki was, from the beginning, a kind of reconnaissance of the fighting strength and this conversation also might have been held based on the withdrawal plan already made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as explained later, there is an opinion that the purpose of the expeditionary force to Japan in Bunei no Eki was, from the beginning, a kind of reconnaissance of the fighting strength and this conversation also might have been held based upon a withdrawal plan already made.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as explained later, there is an opinion that the purpose of the expeditionary force to Japan in Bunei no Eki was, from the beginning, a kind of reconnaissance of the fighting strength and this conversation also might have been held based upon a withdrawal plan already made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>当時の艦船では、博多‐高麗間の北上は南風の晴れた昼でなければ危険であり、この季節では天気待ちで1ヶ月掛かる事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the ships of that time, it was dangerous to voyage towards the north from Hakata to Goryeo except for a sunny day with south wind, and sometimes it took a month in this season waiting for a good weather.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the ships of that time, it was dangerous to voyage towards the north from Hakata to Goryeo except on a sunny day with south wind, and sometimes it took a month in this season waiting for a good weather.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the ships of that time, it was dangerous to voyage towards the north from Hakata to Goryeo except on a sunny day with south wind, and sometimes it took a month in this season waiting for a good weather.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="58">
<j>『八幡愚童訓』によると、この戦いの最中、鎌倉武士団が迎撃の拠点として加護を祈った筥崎宮から兵火によるものか出火し、社殿は焼け落ちたものの御神体その他は唐櫃に納めて運び出し、辛くも避難出来たという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun,&quot; in the middle of the battle, a fire started, probably from firearms, in Hakozaki-gu Shrine, where warriors of the Kamakura shogunate decided as their base for interception and prayed for the gods&apos; help, and it burned down the main building of the shrine, but they managed to save goshintai (object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a god) and other materials by carrying them out in a chest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun,&quot; in the middle of the battle, a fire started, probably from firearms, in Hakozaki-gu Shrine, where warriors of the Kamakura shogunate decided as their base for interception and prayed for the gods&apos; help, and it burned down the main building of the shrine, but they managed to save goshintai (object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a god) and other materials by carrying them out in a chest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun,&quot; in the middle of the battle, a fire started, probably from firearms, in Hakozaki-gu Shrine, where warriors of the Kamakura shogunate decided as their base for interception and prayed for the gods&apos; help, and it burned down the main building of the shrine, but they managed to save goshintai (object of worship believed to contain the spirit of a god) and other materials by carrying them out in a chest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>また夜中、炎上する筥崎宮より出た白装束の者30人ばかりが矢を射掛けたところ、元兵は恐怖し夜明けも待たず（朝鮮通信使のころでも夜間の玄界灘渡海は避けていた）我先にと抜錨し撤退は壊走となり玄界灘で遭難した、という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It further says that in the midnight, about 30 people in white came out from burning Hakozaki-gu Shrine and shot arrows at the Yuan soldiers, who were horrified and hurriedly withdrew in their ships without waiting for dawn, and in this chaotic flight, the ships are said to have wrecked in the Genkai-nada Sea (even Korean envoys in the Edo period avoided crossing the Genkai-nada Sea in the night).</e>
<cmt>「朝鮮通信使のころ」→起源は室町時代のようですが、一般的には江戸時代の朝鮮からの使節団を指すようです。&quot;Korean envoys in the Edo period&quot;と訳しました。（http://www.iwanami.co.jp/hensyu/sin/sin_kkn/kkn0709/sin_k375.htmlなど参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It further says that at the midnight, about thirty people in white came out from burning Hakozaki-gu Shrine and shot arrows at the Yuan soldiers, who were horrified and hurriedly withdrew in their ships without waiting for dawn, and in this chaotic flight, the ships are said to have wrecked in the Genkai-nada Sea (even Korean envoys in the Edo period avoided crossing the Genkai-nada Sea at the night).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It further says that at the midnight, about thirty people in white came out from burning Hakozaki-gu Shrine and shot arrows at the Yuan soldiers, who were horrified and hurriedly withdrew in their ships without waiting for dawn, and in this chaotic flight, the ships are said to have wrecked in the Genkai-nada Sea (even Korean envoys in the Edo period avoided crossing the Genkai-nada Sea at the night).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>ただし、この「白装束の者」たちは「白装束」という甚だしく「異形の者」たちであるため、鎌倉武士団その他の実際の軍勢では無く、「筥崎宮の八幡神による神威の顕現」の類いを描写したものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, these &apos;people in white&apos; are so &apos;uncanny&apos; that they are considered as a kind of &apos;manifestation of the power of the God of War in Hakozaki-gu Shrine&apos; and not the warriors of the Kamakura shogunate nor any other actual force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, these &apos;people in white&apos; are so &apos;uncanny&apos; that they are considered as a kind of &apos;manifestation of the power of the God of War in Hakozaki-gu Shrine&apos; and not the warriors of the Kamakura shogunate nor any other actual force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, these &apos;people in white&apos; are so &apos;uncanny&apos; that they are considered as a kind of &apos;manifestation of the power of the God of War in Hakozaki-gu Shrine&apos; and not the warriors of the Kamakura shogunate nor any other actual force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>『八幡愚童訓』や藤原兼仲（勘解由小路兼仲）の日記『勘仲記』の一写本によると、翌日、元の船団は姿を消しており、文永の役は終結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; and a copy of &quot;Kanchuki,&quot; the diary of FUJIWARA no Kanenaka (Kanenaka KADENOKOJI), the Yuan fleet disappeared on the following day and thus Bunei no Eki ended.</e>
<cmt>「藤原兼仲」→原文通り訳しましたが、『勘仲記』の作者は藤原ではなく「広橋兼仲」のようです。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E5%8B%98%E8%A7%A3%E7%94%B1%E5%B0%8F%E8%B7%AF%E5%85%BC%E4%BB%B2）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; and a copy of &quot;Kanchuki,&quot; the diary of FUJIWARA no Kanenaka (Kanenaka KADENOKOJI), the Yuan fleet disappeared on the following day and thus Bunei no Eki ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; and a copy of &quot;Kanchuki,&quot; the Diary of FUJIWARA no Kanenaka (Kanenaka KADENOKOJI), the Yuan fleet disappeared on the following day and thus Bunei no Eki ended.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>『元史』では「世祖本紀」や「日本伝」などにこの時の損耗については特に述べられていないが、『高麗史』、『高麗史節要』では夜中に大いに風雨があり、艦船が難破するなどして損害があり、十一月二十七日（12月26日）に合浦に帰還した際には、派遣軍の不還者は1万3500余人に登ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genshi&quot; do not particularly mention the damage suffered then in its &apos;Seiso Honki&apos; (Records on Kublai) and &apos;Nihon Den&apos; (Records on Japan), but &quot;Koraishi&quot; and &quot;Koraishi Setsuyo&quot; (Digested History of Goryeo) states that there was a storm in the midnight, which caused shipwreck and damage, and more than 13.5 thousand people of the expeditionary force did not return to Gappo on December 26.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genshi&quot; do not particularly mention the damage suffered then in its &apos;Seiso Honki&apos; (Records on Kublai) and &apos;Nihon Den&apos; (Records on Japan), but &quot;Koraishi&quot; and &quot;Koraishi Setsuyo&quot; (Digested History of Goryeo) states that there was a storm at midnight, which caused shipwreck and damage, and more than 13.5 thousand people of the expeditionary force did not return to Gappo on December 26.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Genshi&quot; do not particularly mention the damage suffered then in its &apos;Seiso Honki&apos; (Records on Kublai) and &apos;Nihon Den&apos; (Records on Japan), but &quot;Koraishi&quot; and &quot;Koraishi Setsuyo&quot; (Digested History of Goryeo) states that there was a storm at midnight, which caused shipwreck and damage, and more than 13.5 thousand people of the expeditionary force did not return to Gappo on December 26.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="63">
<j>定説では、日本の武士は名乗りを上げての一騎打ちしか戦い方を知らず一方的に敗退したが、幸運にも暴風雨、いわゆる神風が起きて、元の船団はその夜のうちに撤退したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The well accepted theory says that Japanese samurai easily lost, because the only fighting method they knew was one to one battle by declaring their names, but fortunately the Yuan fleet was forced to withdraw within that night by a storm, so-called Kamikaze (divine wind).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The well accepted theory says that Japanese samurai easily lost, because the only fighting method they knew was one to one battle by declaring their names, but fortunately the Yuan fleet was forced to withdraw within that night because of a storm, the so-called Kamikaze (divine wind).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The well accepted theory says that Japanese samurai easily lost, because the only fighting method they knew was one to one battle by declaring their names, but fortunately the Yuan fleet was forced to withdraw within that night because of a storm, the so-called Kamikaze (divine wind).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>しかし、これに関しては史料に矛盾する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it is inconsistent with historical records.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this is inconsistent with historical records.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this is inconsistent with historical records.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>詳しくは後述の元寇神風を参照。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For details, refer to Kamikaze of Genko described later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For details, refer to Kamikaze of Genko described later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For details, refer to Kamikaze of Genko described later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="66">
<j>元は撤退し、対南宋戦争が佳境に入ったことから、ひとまず主力は江南に向けられる事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuan army withdrew, and then the war with the Southern Sung Dynasty reached an important point so that its main forces were decided to be sent to the southern area of the Yangtze River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuan army withdrew, and then the war with the Southern Sung Dynasty reached an important phase so, it was decided to send its main forces to the southern area of the Yangtze River.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuan army withdrew, and then the war with the Southern Sung Dynasty reached an important phase so, it was decided to send its main forces to the southern area of the Yangtze River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="67">
<j>なお、文永の役は侵攻というより、威力偵察ではないのかとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Bunei no Eki would have been not an invasion but rather a reconnaissance in force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Bunei no Eki would not have been an invasion, but rather a reconnaissance in force.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Bunei no Eki would not have been an invasion, but rather a reconnaissance in force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>根拠として、本来モンゴル帝国の軍事行動では、事前に兵力100〜1万規模での敵地への威力偵察を数度段階的に行った後、本格的な侵攻を行う場合が多く、また『元史』「日本伝」には元軍の矢がすぐに尽きたという記述が見られることと、3万人程度（中には非戦闘員もいる）という少ない兵力からこの説も根強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This theory is persistent, based on the following facts; the army of the Mongol Empire in many cases performed several reconnaissances in a phased manner before a serious invasion, with the number of soldiers varying from a hundred to ten thousand; arrows run short soon in the Yuan army as described in &apos;Nihon Den&apos; of &quot;Genshi&quot;; and the number of soldiers was small, about thirty thousand (including non-soldiers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This theory is persistent, based upon the following facts; the army of the Mongol Empire in many cases performed several reconnaissances in a phased manner before a serious invasion, with a number of soldiers varying from a hundred to ten thousand; arrows run short soon in the Yuan army as described in &apos;Nihon Den&apos; of &quot;Genshi;&quot; and the number of soldiers was small, about thirty thousand (including non-soldiers).</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This theory is persistent, based upon the following facts; the army of the Mongol Empire in many cases performed several reconnaissances in a phased manner before a serious invasion, with a number of soldiers varying from a hundred to ten thousand; arrows run short soon in the Yuan army as described in &apos;Nihon Den&apos; of &quot;Genshi;&quot; and the number of soldiers was small, about thirty thousand (including non-soldiers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>『元史』「日本伝」は元側の記録であり、自分達で矢が尽きたと記録しているため信憑性は高いと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuan Dynasty itself recorded in &apos;Nihon Den&apos; of &quot;Genshi&quot; that arrows had run short, and therefore it is considered highly reliable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuan Dynasty itself recorded in &apos;Nihon Den&apos; of &quot;Genshi&quot; that arrows had run short, and therefore it is considered highly reliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuan Dynasty itself recorded in &apos;Nihon Den&apos; of &quot;Genshi&quot; that arrows had run short, and therefore it is considered highly reliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>本格的に侵攻し領土とする、または服属させるには、3万人程の人数で、当時の主力武器である弓の矢がすぐに尽きる程度の準備で来るとは考えにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is difficult to believe that it seriously tried to invade and conquer, or subject, with only about thirty thousand men and such a small number of arrows that run short soon, which was the main weapon of that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is difficult to believe that it seriously tried to invade and conquer, or subject, with only about thirty thousand men and such a small number of arrows that soon run short, which was the main weapon of that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is difficult to believe that it seriously tried to invade and conquer, or subject, with only about thirty thousand men and such a small number of arrows that soon run short, which was the main weapon of that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>元軍は大陸での野戦でも、騎馬兵の機動力を生かし、敵と一定の距離を保って馬上からの騎射で相手を損耗させる事を主な戦法の一つにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in an open battle in the continent, one of the main tactics of the Yuan army was to damage the enemy by shooting arrows on horseback, maintaining certain distance from it and taking advantage of the mobility of cavalry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in an open battle on the continent, one of the main tactics of the Yuan army was to damage the enemy by shooting arrows from horseback, maintaining certain distance from it and taking advantage of the mobility of the cavalry.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in an open battle on the continent, one of the main tactics of the Yuan army was to damage the enemy by shooting arrows from horseback, maintaining certain distance from it and taking advantage of the mobility of the cavalry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>弘安の役</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koan no Eki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koan no Eki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koan no Eki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="72">
<j>1275年（日本の建治元年・元の至元十二年）、クビライは再び礼部侍郎杜世忠を正使とする使者を日本に送る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1275, Kublai sent envoys again to Japan, with assistant minister of rites Du Shizhong as chief envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1275, Kublai sent envoys again to Japan, with assistant minister of rites Du Shizhong as chief envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1275, Kublai sent envoys again to Japan, with assistant minister of rites Shizhong DU as chief envoy.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>北条時宗は鎌倉の龍ノ口刑場（江ノ島付近）で杜世忠以下5名を斬首に処した（これは、使者が日本の国情を詳細に記録・偵察した、間諜（スパイ）としての性質を強く帯びていたためと言われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokimune HOJO executed Du Shizhong and other four men at Tatsunokuchi Execution Site (near Eno-shima Island) (it is said to have been because the envoys were almost spies in nature, recording and investigating the conditions of Japan in details).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokimune HOJO executed Du Shizhong and other four men at Tatsunokuchi Execution Site (near Eno-shima Island) (it is said to have been because the envoys were mostly spies in nature, recording and investigating the conditions of Japan in detail).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokimune HOJO executed Shizhong DU and other four men at Tatsunokuchi Execution Site (near Eno-shima Island) (it is said to have been because the envoys were mostly spies in nature, recording and investigating the conditions of Japan in detail).</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>1279年（日本の弘安二年・元の至元十六年）、元は江南軍司令官である南宋の旧臣范文虎の進言により、使者が殺されたことを知らないまま周福を正使とする使者を再度送ったが、大宰府にて全員斬首に処される（総計、5名という説が有力）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1279, without knowing the execution of the envoys, the Yuan Dynasty sent envoys again with Shufuku as their chief, in accordance with a proposal by Fan Wen-hu, who was the chief commander of the Southern Yangtze Army and used to be a vassal of the Southern Sung Dynasty, but all the envoys were executed in Dazai-fu (five in total according to the most accepted theory).</e>
<cmt>「周福」→英語名が不明なため、ローマ字表記です。「南宋の旧臣」→范文虎は南宋から帰順した元の武将です。「古くからの臣下」ではなく「昔は臣下だった」と解釈して訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1279, without knowing the execution of the envoys, the Yuan Dynasty sent envoys again with Shufuku as their chief, in accordance with a proposal by Fan Wen-hu, who was the chief commander of the Southern Yangtze Army and used to be a vassal of the Southern Sung Dynasty, but all the envoys were executed in Dazai-fu (five in total according to the most accepted theory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1279, without knowing the execution of the envoys, the Yuan Dynasty sent envoys again with Shufuku as their chief, in accordance with a proposal by Wen-hu FAN, who was the chief commander of the Southern Yangtze Army and used to be a vassal of the Southern Sung Dynasty, but all the envoys were executed in Dazai-fu (five in total according to the most accepted theory).</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>この年に南宋を完全征服した元は、日本との同盟や南宋への牽制の必要もなくなった（後項参照）うえ、クビライは逃げ出した水夫より使者の処刑の報を知り、特に、通常の使者よりも高位（礼部侍郎）であった杜世忠の処刑に腹を立て、日本への再度の侵攻を計画し、1280年には侵攻準備のため征東行省を設置している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conquest of the Southern Sung Dynasty in that year made it unnecessary for the Yuan Dynasty to align itself with Japan or warn against the Southern Sung Dynasty (refer to the relative paragraph described below), and further, Kublai got upset by the information brought by an escaped sailor of the execution of the envoys, particularly of Du Shizhong, who held a higher position (assistant minister of rites) than usual envoys, and consequently he planned to invade Japan again and in 1280 established Eastern Expedition Field Headquarters to prepare for the invasion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conquest of the Southern Sung Dynasty in that year made it unnecessary for the Yuan Dynasty to align itself with Japan or warn against the Southern Sung Dynasty (refer to the relative paragraph described below), and further, Kublai became upset by the information brought by an escaped sailor about the execution of the envoys, particularly of Du Shizhong, who held a higher position (assistant minister of rites) than usual envoys, and consequently he planned to invade Japan again and in 1280 established the Eastern Expedition Field Headquarters to prepare for the invasion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conquest of the Southern Sung Dynasty in that year made it unnecessary for the Yuan Dynasty to align itself with Japan or warn against the Southern Sung Dynasty (refer to the relative paragraph described below), and further, Kublai became upset by the information brought by an escaped sailor about the execution of the envoys, particularly of Shizhong DU, who held a higher position (assistant minister of rites) than usual envoys, and consequently he planned to invade Japan again and in 1280 established the Eastern Expedition Field Headquarters to prepare for the invasion.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>1281年（日本の弘安四年・元の至元十八年）、元・高麗軍を主力とした東路軍4万と、旧南宋軍を主力とした江南軍10万、計14万の軍が日本に向けて出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1281, the army of 140 thousand soldiers in total departed for Japan, consisting of the Eastern Route Army of 40 thousand soldiers mainly from the Yuan and Goryeo army and the Southern Yangtze Army of 100 thousand soldiers mainly from the former Southern Sung army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1281, an army of 140 thousand soldiers in total departed for Japan, consisting of the Eastern Route Army of 40,000 soldiers mainly from the Yuan and Goryeo army and the Southern Yangtze Army of 100,000 soldiers mainly from the former Southern Sung army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1281, an army of 140 thousand soldiers in total departed for Japan, consisting of the Eastern Route Army of 40,000 soldiers mainly from the Yuan and Goryeo army and the Southern Yangtze Army of 100,000 soldiers mainly from the former Southern Sung army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="77">
<j>しかし、日本側は既に防衛体制を整えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Japan had already prepared the defense system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Japan had already prepared defenses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Japan had already prepared defenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>博多沿岸に約20kmにも及ぶ防塁（元寇防塁）を築いてこれを迎えたのである（）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had built defense walls along Hakata Bay about 20 kilometers long to guard against the attack (Genko Borui).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It had built defense walls along Hakata Bay about twenty kilometers long to guard against the attack (Genko Borui).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It had built defense walls along Hakata Bay about twenty kilometers long to guard against the attack (Genko Borui).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>この防塁はもっとも頑強な部分で高さ3メートル、幅2メートル以上ともされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most strong part of these defense walls are said to have measured 3 meters high and more than 2 meters thick.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The strongest part of these defense walls is said to have measured three meters high and more than two meters thick.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The strongest part of these defense walls is said to have measured three meters high and more than two meters thick.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>いち早く到着した東路軍は防塁のない志賀島に上陸するが、日本軍の斬り込みを受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eastern Route Army arrived earlier and disembarked Shika-no-shima Island where there was no defense wall, but was attacked by the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eastern Route Army arrived earlier and disembarked Shika-no-shima Island where there was no defense wall, but they were attacked by the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eastern Route Army arrived earlier and disembarked Shika no shima Island where there was no defense wall, but they were attacked by the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>文永の役によって元軍の戦法を周知していた日本軍は優勢に戦い、元軍を海上に撤退させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army, having learned the Yuan army&apos;s tactics in Bunei no Eki, fought with advantage and forced the Yuan army to withdraw into the sea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army, having learned the Yuan army&apos;s tactics in Bunei no Eki, fought with advantage and forced the Yuan army to withdraw into the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army, having learned the Yuan army&apos;s tactics in Bunei no Eki, fought with advantage and forced the Yuan army to withdraw into the sea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>さらに小舟での襲撃などにより元軍を悩ませる武士も少なくなかった（一方で河野通有などのように石弓によって重傷を負った武士もいた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Yuan army was bothered by many samurai attacking in small boats (while some of them, like Michiari KONO, suffered severe injuries by stone arrows).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Yuan army was bothered by many samurai attacking in small boats (while some of them, like Michiari KONO, suffered severe injuries from stone arrowheads).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Yuan army was bothered by many samurai attacking in small boats (while some of them, like Michiari KONO, suffered severe injuries from stone arrowheads).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>江南軍は、総司令官右丞相阿刺罕が病気のため阿塔海に交代したこともあり、東路軍より遅れてやってきたが、両軍は、平戸鷹島付近にて合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Yangtze Army arrived later than the Eastern Route Army, for reasons including the substitution of commander-in-chief Arakan, who was the minister of the right and suffering a disease, by Atahai, and the both armies joined near Taka-shima Island, Hirado.</e>
<cmt>「阿刺罕」「阿塔海」→読みは「アラカン」「アタハイ」。英語名は不明のため、ローマ字表記です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Yangtze Army arrived later than the Eastern Route Army, for reasons including the substitution of commander-in-chief Arakan, who was the minister of the right and suffering from a disease, by Atahai, and the both armies joined near Taka-shima Island, Hirado.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Yangtze Army arrived later than the Eastern Route Army, for reasons including the substitution of commander-in-chief Arakan, who was the minister of the right and suffering from a disease, by Atahai, and the both armies joined near Taka-shima Island, Hirado.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>しかしここで暴風雨が襲来し、元の軍船は浮いているだけの状態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then a storm occurred and the Yuan fleet could do nothing but float.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then a storm occurred and the Yuan fleet could do nothing, but float.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then a storm occurred and the Yuan fleet could do nothing, but float.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>これを好機と見た武士らは元軍に襲いかかり、これを殲滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The samurai took this opportunity to attack the Yuan army and destroyed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The samurai took this opportunity to attack the Yuan army and destroyed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The samurai took this opportunity to attack the Yuan army and destroyed it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>辛うじて陸地にいた元軍兵士も、旧暦7月7日（ユリウス暦7月23日）の竹崎季長らによる鷹島奇襲などでほぼ消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most Yuan soldiers who had managed to disembark also perished by a surprise attack in Taka-shima Island by Suenaga TAKEZAKI and others on July 7 according to old lunar calendar (July 23 according to the Julian calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most Yuan soldiers who had managed to disembark also perished by a surprise attack on Taka-shima Island by Suenaga TAKEZAKI and others on July 7 according to old lunar calendar (July 23 according to the Julian calendar).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most Yuan soldiers who had managed to disembark also perished by a surprise attack on Taka-shima Island by Suenaga TAKEZAKI and others on July 7 according to old lunar calendar (July 23 according to the Julian calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>元軍で帰還できた兵士は、のちに解放された捕虜を含めて全体の1、2割だと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuan soldiers who could return home are said to be from 10 to 20% of the entire number, including captives who were released later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuan soldiers who were able to return home are said to be from ten to twenty percent of the total number, including captives who were released later.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuan soldiers who were able to return home are said to be from ten to twenty percent of the total number, including captives who were released later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>なお、日本軍は高麗人とモンゴル人、および漢人は捕虜として捕らえず殺害したが、交流のあった南宋人は捕虜として命を助け、大切に庇護したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army is said to have killed people of Goryeo, Mongol and Han, not trying to capture them, but saved people of the Southern Sung Dynasty, with which it had exchanges, and protected them with care.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army is said to have killed people of Goryeo, Mongol, and Han, not trying to capture them, but saved people of the Southern Sung Dynasty, with which it had exchanges, and protected them with care.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army is said to have killed people of Goryeo, Mongol, and Han, not trying to capture them, but saved people of the Southern Sung Dynasty, with which it had exchanges, and protected them with care.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>博多の唐人町は南宋人の街であるともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tojin-machi in Hakata is sometimes referred to as a town of people from the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tojin-machi in Hakata is sometimes referred to as a town of people from the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tojin-machi in Hakata is sometimes referred to as a town of people from the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>この戦いによって元軍の海軍戦力の3分の2以上が失われ、残った軍船も、相当数が破損された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this battle, more than two-third of the Yuan navy forces were lost, and a considerable number of the survived battleships were also destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this battle, more than two-thirds of the Yuan navy forces were lost, and a considerable number of the battleships were also destroyed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this battle, more than two-thirds of the Yuan navy forces were lost, and a considerable number of the battleships were also destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="91">
<j>なお、弘安の役における両軍の兵力は、元・高麗軍が約14万（東路軍4万、江南軍10万）、鎌倉軍が約4万だとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of soldiers who fought in Koan no Eki is said to have been about 140 thousand held by Yuan and Goryeo (40 thousand of the Eastern Route Army and 100 thousand of the Southern Yangtze Army) and about 40 thousand held by the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of soldiers who fought in Koan no Eki is said to have been about 140,000 held by Yuan and Goryeo (40,000 of the Eastern Route Army and 100,000 of the Southern Yangtze Army) and about 40,000 held by the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of soldiers who fought in Koan no Eki is said to have been about 140,000 held by Yuan and Goryeo (40,000 of the Eastern Route Army and 100,000 of the Southern Yangtze Army) and about 40,000 held by the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>日本の被害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damage inflicted on Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage inflicted on Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage inflicted on Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="92">
<j>「伏敵編」所取の「高祖遺文録」に次のように残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koso Ibun Roku&quot; (Record of the Writings Left Behind by the Founder) contained in &quot;Fukutekihen&quot; reads as follows.</e>
<cmt>文頭で’を入力すると正しく表示されないので、「」には&quot;&quot;を使いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koso Ibun Roku&quot; (Record of the Writings Left Behind by the Founder) contained in &quot;Fukutekihen&quot; reads as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koso Ibun Roku&apos; (Record of the Writings Left Behind by the Founder) contained in &apos;Fukutekihen&apos; reads as follows.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>この「遺文録』は、日蓮の遺文を集めた記事集である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This &quot;Koso Ibun Roku&quot; is a collection of the writings left behind by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>「遺文録』→前項の「高祖遺文録」のこと。&quot;Koso Ibun Roku&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This &quot;Koso Ibun Roku&quot; is a collection of the writings left behind by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This &apos;Koso Ibun Roku&apos; is a collection of the writings left behind by Nichiren.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="94">
<j>《去文永十一年（太歳甲戊）十月ニ、蒙古国ヨリ筑紫ニ寄セテ有シニ、対馬ノ者カタメテ有シ、総馬尉（そうまじょう）等逃ケレハ、百姓等ハ男ヲハ或八殺シ、或ハ生取（いけどり）ニシ、女ヲハ或ハ取集（とりあつめ）テ、手ヲトヲシテ船ニ結付（むすびつけ）或ハ生取ニス、一人モ助カル者ナシ、壱岐ニヨセテモ又如是（またかくのごとし）、》</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;In November 1274, the Mongol Empire attacked Tsukushi Province. People in Tsushima Island defended, but Sukekuni SO and others escaped. As for peasants, men were killed or captured. Women were gathered and hanged on the ships&apos; walls with their hands laced through, or captured. No one was saved. They also did the same in Iki Province.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「文永十一年（太歳甲戊）十月」→1274年11月「総馬尉」→宗助国のこと（通称が右馬允[うまのじょう]）。&quot;Sukekuni SO&quot;と訳しました。（http://books.google.co.jp/books?id=zWgxAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=%E7%B7%8F%E9%A6%AC%E5%B0%89&amp;dq=%E7%B7%8F%E9%A6%AC%E5%B0%89&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=0NxgTMClFYbyvQOAga29CQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAQ, http://d.hatena.ne.jp/Wallerstein/20060707など参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;In November 1274, the Mongol Empire attacked Tsukushi Province. People on Tsushima Island put up a defense, but Sukekuni SO and others escaped. As for the peasants, men were killed or captured. Women were gathered and hung on the ships&apos; sides with their hands laced through, or captured. No one was spared. They also did the same at Iki Province.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;In November 1274, the Mongol Empire attacked Tsukushi Province. People on Tsushima Island put up a defense, but Sukekuni SO and others escaped. As for the peasants, men were killed or captured. Women were gathered and hung on the ships&apos; sides with their hands laced through, or captured. No one was spared. They also did the same at Iki Province.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>「百姓」＝一般人は「男ヲハ或ハ殺シ、或ハ生取ニシ」ている状況とともに「女ヲハ或ハ取集テ、手ヲトヲシテ船ニ結付、或ハ生取ニス」 とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It states that as for &quot;peasants,&quot; which mean ordinary people, &quot;men were killed or captured&quot; and in addition, &quot;women were gathered and hanged on the ships&apos; walls with their hands laced through, or captured.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It states that as for &quot;peasants,&quot; meaning ordinary people, &quot;men were killed or captured&quot; and in addition, &quot;women were gathered and hung on the ships&apos; sides with their hands laced through, or were captured.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It states that as for &apos;peasants,&apos; meaning ordinary people, &apos;men were killed or captured&apos; and in addition, &apos;women were gathered and hung on the ships&apos; sides with their hands laced through, or were captured.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>そして、「男」と「女」に懸かるのであろうか、「一人モ助カル者ナシ」と書かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It then continues, &quot;no one was saved,&quot; which would mean both men and women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It then continues, &quot;no one was saved,&quot; which would mean neither men nor women.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It then continues, &apos;no one was saved,&apos; which would mean neither men nor women.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>壱岐でも、同様の残虐な仕打ちがなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar cruel acts were done also in Iki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar cruel acts were done also in Iki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar cruel acts were done also in Iki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>この史料を取めている「伏敵編」には、「按（あんずるに）」として、編者のコメントがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The editor of &apos;Fukutekihen,&apos; which contains this historical material, gives his comments as &quot;my opinion.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The editor of &apos;Fukutekihen,&apos; which contains this historical material, gives his comments as &quot;my opinion.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The editor of &apos;Fukutekihen,&apos; which contains this historical material, gives his comments as &apos;my opinion.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>ここでは、高麗の前身の国家である「百済」を引き合いに出し「手掌ヲ穿傷......」（手の平に穴をあけてそこへ縄を通す」の意）云々のやり方を、朝鮮半島において古来より続く伝統的行為としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He here explains that making a hole in palms to lace a rope through was a traditional act continuing from ancient times in the Korean peninsula, taking &apos;Baekje,&apos; which was the predecessor of Goryeo, for example.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He here explains that making a hole in the palms to lace a rope through was a traditional act continuing from ancient times in the Korean peninsula, taking &apos;Baekje,&apos; which was the predecessor of Goryeo, for example.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He here explains that making a hole in the palms to lace a rope through was a traditional act continuing from ancient times in the Korean peninsula, taking &apos;Baekje,&apos; which was the predecessor of Goryeo, for example.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>まさに、この残虐行為を証拠として高麗人の仕業、と編者は判断している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The editor concludes that this cruelty is the evidence of these acts having been done by people of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The editor concludes that this cruelty is the evidence of these acts having been committed by people of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The editor concludes that this cruelty is the evidence of these acts having been committed by people of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>日蓮は、対馬や壱岐、あるいは九州本土における惨劇を『高祖遺文録」の各個所で言及している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nichiren mentions the tragedies in Tsushima, Iki, or mainland Kyushu in various sections in &quot;Koso Ibun Roku.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nichiren mentions the tragedies in Tsushima, Iki, or mainland Kyushu in various sections in &quot;Koso Ibun Roku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nichiren mentions the tragedies in Tsushima, Iki, or mainland Kyushu in various sections in &quot;Koso Ibun Roku.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="102">
<j>『日蓮註画讃巻第五「蒙古來」篇』に「二島百姓等男はあるいは殺あるいは虜、女は一所に集め、手を徹、舷に結付虜の者は一人も害さざるなし。肥前国松浦党数百人伐虜さる。この国の百姓男女等、壱岐・対馬の如し。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Volume 5 &apos;Mongol Invasion&apos; of &quot;Nichiren Chugasan&quot; (Illustrated Biography of Nichiren) reads &quot;in Futajima, men were killed or captured. Women were gathered at one place and hanged on the ships&apos; walls with their hands laced through, and all captives suffered harm. In Bizen Province, several hundred people of the Matsuura Party were killed or captured. The people of this province, whether men or women, suffered the same as people in Iki and Tsushima.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Volume 5 &apos;Mongol Invasion&apos; of &quot;Nichiren Chugasan&quot; (Illustrated Biography of Nichiren) reads &quot;in Futajima, men were killed or captured. Women were gathered at one place and hung on the ships&apos; sides with their hands laced through, and all captives suffered harm. In Bizen Province, several hundred people of the Matsuura Party were killed or captured. The people of this province, whether men or women, suffered the same fate as the people in Iki and Tsushima.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Volume 5 &apos;Mongol Invasion&apos; of &quot;Nichiren Chugasan&quot; (Illustrated Biography of Nichiren) reads &apos;in Futajima, men were killed or captured. Women were gathered at one place and hung on the ships&apos; sides with their hands laced through, and all captives suffered harm. In Hizen Province, several hundred people of the Matsuura Party were killed or captured. The people of this province, whether men or women, suffered the same fate as the people in Iki and Tsushima.&apos;</e>
<cmt>spellingクォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>《皆人の当時の壱岐対馬の様にならせ給（たま）はん事思ひやり候へば涙も留まらず。》（「類纂高祖遺文録」、改題「類纂日蓮聖人遺文集平成版」）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;It brings me to tears to think that everyone may suffer the same as people in Iki and Tsushima of that time.&quot; (&apos;Ruisan Koso Ibun Roku&apos; [Collected Records of the Writings Left Behind by the Founder], whose revised title is &apos;Ruisan Nichiren Shonin Ibunshu Heiseiban&apos; [Collected Records of the Writings Left Behind by Saint Nichiren, Heisei Edition])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;It brings me to tears to think that everyone may suffer the same fate as the people in Iki and Tsushima at that time.&quot; (&apos;Ruisan Koso Ibun Roku&apos; [Collected Records of the Writings Left Behind by the Founder], whose revised title is &apos;Ruisan Nichiren Shonin Ibunshu Heiseiban&apos; [Collected Records of the Writings Left Behind by Saint Nichiren, Heisei Edition])</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;It brings me to tears to think that everyone may suffer the same fate as the people in Iki and Tsushima at that time.&quot; (&apos;Ruisan Koso Ibun Roku&apos; [Collected Records of the Writings Left Behind by the Founder], whose revised title is &apos;Ruisan Nichiren Shonin Ibunshu Heiseiban&apos; [Collected Records of the Writings Left Behind by Saint Nichiren, Heisei Edition])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="104">
<j>また他所で、《壱岐対馬九国の兵士並びに男女、多く或は殺され或は擒（と）られ或は海に入り或は崖より堕（お）ちし者幾千万と云ふ事なし。》（同右書）とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also states in another section, &quot;in Iki, Tsushima and nine provinces of Kyushu, numerous soldiers and people, whether men and women, were killed, captured, threw themselves into the sea, or fell off a cliff.&quot; (the same book as mentioned above)</e>
<cmt>「九国」→九州の９の国（筑前、築後、豊前、豊後、肥前、肥後、日向、大隅、薩摩）&quot;nine provinces of Kyushu&quot;と訳しました。「同右書」→前項の（）内の書物を同じ、と解釈し、&quot;the same book as mentioned above&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also states in another section, &quot;in Iki, Tsushima and the nine provinces of Kyushu, numerous soldiers and people, whether men or women, were killed, captured, threw themselves into the sea, or fell off a cliff.&quot; (the same book as mentioned above)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also states in another section, &quot;in Iki, Tsushima and the nine provinces of Kyushu, numerous soldiers and people, whether men or women, were killed, captured, threw themselves into the sea, or fell off a cliff&quot; (the same book as mentioned above).</e>
<cmt>periodクォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>なお、対馬→壱岐を侵した後、元艦船隊は鷹島へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yuan fleet that had invaded Tsushima and then Iki headed for Taka-shima Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yuan fleet that had invaded Tsushima and then Iki headed for Taka-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yuan fleet that had invaded Tsushima and then Iki headed for Taka-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>そして、上陸軍を揚げている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army disembarked there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army disembarked there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army disembarked there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>「八幡愚童記」（伏敵編」所収）に は、《同十六日、十七日平戸能古、鷹島辺（あたり）の男女多く捕（とらわ）らる。松浦党敗北す。》 とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hachiman Gudoki&quot; (another title of &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; and contained in &quot;Fukutekihen&quot;) reads, &quot;on the same day of 16th and 17th, many men and women were captured near Noko-no-shima Island in Hirado and Taka-shima Island. The Matsuura Party was defeated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「八幡愚童記」→既出の「八幡愚童訓」と同じだが、写本によって題名が異なるようです。&quot;another title of Hachiman Gudokun&quot;と説明を入れました。「能古」→能古島のこと。&quot;Noko-no-shima Island&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hachiman Gudoki&quot; (another title of &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; and contained in &quot;Fukutekihen&quot;) reads, &quot;on the same day of sixteenth and seventeenth, many men and women were captured near Noko-no-shima Island in Hirado and Taka-shima Island. The Matsuura Party was defeated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hachiman Gudoki&apos; (another title of &quot;Hachiman Gudokun&quot; and contained in &quot;Fukutekihen&quot;) reads, &quot;on the same day of sixteenth and seventeenth, many men and women were captured near Noko-no-shima Island in Hirado and Taka-shima Island. The Matsuura Party was defeated.&quot;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>「男女」が「捕らる」のだから、捕囚され強制連行されたことにほかならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Men and women were captured&quot; surely means that the enemy brought them home as captives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Men and women were captured&quot; surely means that the enemy brought them home as captives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Men and women were captured&quot; surely means that the enemy brought them home as captives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="109">
<j>その後の日本では、元寇の時、蒙古・高麗軍が日本を襲ったことを、「蒙古高句麗の鬼が来る」といって怖れたことから、転じて恐ろしいものの代表として子供の躾けなどで、「むくりこくり、鬼が来る」とおどす風習などとなり全国に広がった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Genko, Japanese people were scared by the attacks by the Mongol and Goryeo army, saying, &quot;moko kokuri no oni ga kuru&quot; (the devils of Mongol and Goryeo will come), which phrase later came to represent something scary, and thus a tradition spread to the whole country to scare children by saying &quot;mukuri kokuri, oni ga kuru&quot; to make them behave themselves.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of Genko, Japanese people were scared by the attacks of the Mongol and Goryeo army, saying, &quot;moko kokuri no oni ga kuru&quot; (the devils of the Mongol and Goryeo will come), which phrase later came to represent something scary, and thus a tradition spread to the whole country to scare children by saying &quot;mukuri kokuri, oni ga kuru&quot; to make them behave themselves.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of Genko, Japanese people were scared by the attacks of the Mongol and Goryeo army, saying, &apos;moko kokuri no oni ga kuru&apos; (the devils of the Mongol and Goryeo will come), which phrase later came to represent something scary, and thus a tradition spread to the whole country to scare children by saying &apos;mukuri kokuri, oni ga kuru&apos; to make them behave themselves.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>モッコの子守唄（青森県　木造町）のように「泣けば山がらモッコくるね、泣がねでねんねしな」などと、昔の蒙古襲来の怖さを子守唄にしたものなど、上記の残虐行為への恐怖を証明する民間伝承は全国に存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a lullaby called Mokko no Komoriuta (in Kizukuri-machi, Aomori Prefecture) with lyrics of &quot;if you cry, Mongols will come from a mountain, don&apos;t cry and sleep,&quot; representing the fear of the past Mongol invasion, and there are also other folk traditions across the country manifesting the fear of the cruel acts described above.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a lullaby called Mokko no Komoriuta (in Kizukuri-machi, Aomori Prefecture) with lyrics of &quot;if you cry, Mongols will come from a mountain, don&apos;t cry and sleep,&quot; representing the fear of the past Mongol invasion, and there are also other folk traditions across the country manifesting the fear of the cruel acts described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a lullaby called Mokko no Komoriuta (in Kizukuri-machi, Aomori Prefecture) with lyrics of &apos;if you cry, Mongols will come from a mountain, don&apos;t cry and sleep,&apos; representing the fear of the past Mongol invasion, and there are also other folk traditions across the country manifesting the fear of the cruel acts described above.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="111">
<j>また元寇への復讐の意味合いから倭寇の活動が活発化したきっかけとも言う説がある（詳細は倭寇を参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory that Genko provoked wako (Japanese pirates) to active operation in revenge (for details, refer to Wako).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory that Genko provoked wako (Japanese pirates) to active operation in revenge (for details, refer to Wako).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory that Genko provoked wako (Japanese pirates) to active operation in revenge (for details, refer to Wako).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="112">
<j>クビライは本格的に3度目の日本侵略を計画し、1287年に一旦解散した征東行省を再度開設し、高麗忠烈王が丞相に就任した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kublai seriously planned the third invasion of Japan and established again the Eastern Expedition Field Headquarters, which had been dissolved in 1287, appointing King Chungnyeol of Goryeo as minister.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kublai seriously planned the third invasion of Japan and established again the Eastern Expedition Field Headquarters, which had been dissolved in 1287, appointing King Chungnyeol of Goryeo as minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kublai seriously planned the third invasion of Japan and established again the Eastern Expedition Field Headquarters, which had been dissolved in 1287, appointing King Chungnyeol of Goryeo as minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>しかし、この時期に元の内部でも反乱が続き、日本へ軍が出せる状態ではなくなり、クビライの死と共に完全に頓挫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, successive occurrence of rebellions in the Yuan Dynasty during this period made it impossible to send an army to Japan, and following the death of Kublai, the plan was completely abandoned.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the successive occurrence of rebellions in the Yuan Dynasty during this period made it impossible to send an army to Japan, and following the death of Kublai, the plan was completely abandoned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the successive occurrence of rebellions in the Yuan Dynasty during this period made it impossible to send an army to Japan, and following the death of Kublai, the plan was completely abandoned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>なお、正安3年11月（1301年）に薩摩国甑島列島の沖に異国船が出現し、うち1隻から襲撃を受けている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, in November 1301, foreign ships appeared offshore near the Koshikijima Islands in Satsuma Province, and one of them made an attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in November 1301, foreign ships appeared offshore near the Koshikijima Islands in Satsuma Province, and one of them made an attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in November 1301, foreign ships appeared offshore near the Koshikijima Islands in Satsuma Province, and one of them made an attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>これについては、元の艦隊が偶発的に同地に辿り着いて上陸を試みたものと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are considered to have been the Yuan fleet that accidentally reached there and attempted to disembark.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are considered to have been the Yuan fleet that accidentally reached there and attempted to disembark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are considered to have been the Yuan fleet that accidentally reached there and attempted to disembark.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="116">
<j>文永の役後、幕府は博多湾の防備を強化しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Bunei no Eki, the shogunate intended to strengthen the defense of Hakata Bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Bunei no Eki, the shogunate intended to strengthen the defense of Hakata Bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Bunei no Eki, bakufu intended to strengthen the defense of Hakata Bay.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>しかしこの戦いで日本側が物質的に得たものは無く、見返りとしての恩賞は御家人たちの満足のいくものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Japan gained nothing materially out of this war, and the rewards granted to vassals did not satisfy them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Japan gained nothing materially out of this war, and the rewards granted to vassals did not satisfy them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Japan gained nothing materially out of this war, and the rewards granted to vassals did not satisfy them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>中には竹崎季長などのように鎌倉まで赴いて直接幕府へ訴え出て、恩賞を得るといったケースもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some vassals, like Suenaga TAKEZAKI, even went to Kamakura to make a direct appeal to the shogunate to obtain a reward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some vassals, like Suenaga TAKEZAKI, even went to Kamakura to make a direct appeal to the shogunate to obtain a reward.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some vassals, like Suenaga TAKEZAKI, even went to Kamakura to make a direct appeal to bakufu to obtain a reward.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="119">
<j>弘安の役後、幕府は元軍の再度の襲来に備えて御家人の統制を進めたが、文永の役に続き弘安の役においても十分な恩賞給与がなされなかったため、戦費で窮迫した御家人達は借金に苦しむようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Koan no Eki, in order to prepare for the next attack by the Yuan army, the shogunate tried to strengthen its control over vassals, but the vassals came to live in debts because they did not receive sufficient rewards in Koan no Eki as well as Bunei no Eki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Koan no Eki, in order to prepare for the next attack by the Yuan army, the shogunate tried to strengthen its control over the vassals, but the vassals came to live in debt because they did not receive sufficient rewards in Koan no Eki as well as Bunei no Eki.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Koan no Eki, in order to prepare for the next attack by the Yuan army, bakufu tried to strengthen its control over the vassals, but the vassals came to live in debt because they did not receive sufficient rewards in Koan no Eki as well as Bunei no Eki.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>幕府は徳政令を発布して御家人の困窮に対応しようとしたが、御家人の不満は完全には解消されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate issued a tokuseirei (debt cancellation order) to save the vassals from debts, but their frustration was not completely relieved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate issued a tokuseirei (debt cancellation order) to save the vassals from debt, but their frustration was not completely relieved.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakufu issued a tokuseirei (debt cancellation order) to save the vassals from debt, but their frustration was not completely relieved.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="121">
<j>一方、当時の日本に「元に勝ったのは、公家などの貴族たちが、勝利や平和についての歌を作って詠んだ、言霊の結果である」あるいは「僧侶や神官らの折伏（しゃくぶく）や祈祷による結果である」との認識が広く存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, people in Japan then commonly believed, &quot;what brought us the victory over the Yuan Dynasty was the power of language in poems created by nobles for victory and peace&quot; or &quot;it was shakubuku (to correct another&apos;s false views and awaken that person to the truth of Buddhism) and prayers performed by Buddhist and Shinto priests.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, people in Japan then commonly believed, &quot;what brought us the victory over the Yuan Dynasty was the power of language in poems created by nobles for victory and peace&quot; or &quot;it was shakubuku (to correct another&apos;s false views and awaken that person to the truth of Buddhism) and prayers performed by Buddhist and Shinto priests.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, people in Japan then commonly believed, &quot;what brought us the victory over the Yuan Dynasty was the power of language in poems created by nobles for victory and peace&quot; or &quot;it was shakubuku (to correct another&apos;s false views and awaken that person to the truth of Buddhism) and prayers performed by Buddhist and Shinto priests.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>実際に弘安4年から翌年にかけて九州の諸社及び伊勢神宮に対して「神領興行」と呼ばれる一種の徳政令が発布されて、幕府の安堵状が出されている御家人領も含めた全ての旧神領を神社へ返還するよう命じられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, from 1281 to the following year, a kind of tokuseirei called &apos;Shinryo Kyogo&apos; was issued for various shrines in Kyushu and Ise-jingu Shrine, ordering all land formerly owned by shrines, including the land granted to the shogunate&apos;s vassals by its official letter, to be returned to the shrines.</e>
<cmt>「弘安4年」→1281年</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, from 1281 to the following year, a kind of tokuseirei called &apos;Shinryo Kyogo&apos; was issued for various shrines in Kyushu and Ise-jingu Shrine, ordering all land formerly owned by shrines, including the land granted to the shogunate&apos;s vassals by its official letter, to be returned to the shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, from 1281 to the following year, a kind of Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) called &apos;Shinryo Kyogo&apos; was issued for various shrines in Kyushu and Ise-jingu Shrine, ordering all land formerly owned by shrines, including the land granted to bakufu&apos;s vassals by its official letter, to be returned to the shrines.</e>
<cmt>terms</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="123">
<j>当時の日本国内では、対元戦争を日本の神と元の神の争いと見る観念が広く共有されており、歌詠みや諸社による折伏・祈祷は日本の神の力を強めるものと認識されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan at that time, people had a common idea of seeing the war against the Yuan Dynasty as the war between the Japanese gods and Yuan gods, and believed that the power of the Japanese gods would be strengthened by creating poems and performing shakubuku and prayers in shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan at that time, people had a common idea of seeing the war against the Yuan Dynasty as the war between the Japanese gods and Yuan gods, and believed that the power of the Japanese gods would be strengthened by creating poems and performing shakubuku and prayers in shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan at that time, people had a common idea of seeing the war against the Yuan Dynasty as the war between the Japanese gods and Yuan gods, and believed that the power of the Japanese gods would be strengthened by creating poems and performing shakubuku and prayers in shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>これを天人相関思想というが、日本を救った暴風雨を神風と呼ぶこととなったのも、この天人相関思想に起因するという説が有力となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called Tenjin Sokan Shiso (Idea of Correlation between Heaven and Man), and according to a widely-accepted theory, this idea led people to call the storm that saved Japan Kamikaze.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called Tenjin Sokan Shiso (Idea of Correlation between Heaven and Man), and according to a widely-accepted theory, this idea led people to call the storm that saved Japan Kamikaze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called Tenjin Sokan Shiso (Idea of Correlation between Heaven and Man), and according to a widely-accepted theory, this idea led people to call the storm that saved Japan Kamikaze.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>また、神風によって日本が救われたという出来事は「神国思想」（＝日本は神国なのだから負けるはずがないという考え）を日本人に広く浸透させ、それが太平洋戦争末期の日本軍や国民思想の非合理性の温床となり、神風特別攻撃隊をはじめ数々の悲劇を生んだとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the event in which Kamikaze saved Japan led Japanese to widely believe in &quot;Shinkoku Shiso&quot; (the idea that Japan will never lose because it is the country protected by the gods), which became the grounds for the irrational idea held by the Japanese army and people at the end of the Pacific War, causing many tragedies, including Kamikaze Special Attack Unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the event in which Kamikaze saved Japan led Japanese to widely believe in &quot;Shinkoku Shiso&quot; (the idea that Japan will never lose because it is a country protected by the gods), which became the grounds for the irrational idea held by the Japanese army and people at the end of the Pacific War, causing many tragedies, including Kamikaze Special Attack Units.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the event in which Kamikaze saved Japan led Japanese to widely believe in &quot;Shinkoku Shiso&quot; (the idea that Japan will never lose because it is a country protected by the gods), which became the grounds for the irrational idea held by the Japanese army and people at the end of the Pacific War, causing many tragedies, including Kamikaze Special Attack Units.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="126">
<j>貨幣経済の浸透や百姓階層の分化とそれに伴う村落社会の形成といった13世紀半ばから進行していた日本社会の変動は、元寇の影響によってますます加速の度合いを強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changes in the Japanese society having been progressing since the middle 13th century, such as the development of monetary economy, hierarchization of peasant class and formation of rural communities, were further accelerated by the influence of Genko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in Japanese society having been progressing since the middle thirteenth century, such as the development of the monetary economy, hierarchization of the peasant class and formation of rural communities, were further accelerated by the influence of Genko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in Japanese society having been progressing since the middle thirteenth century, such as the development of the monetary economy, hierarchization of the peasant class and formation of rural communities, were further accelerated by the influence of Genko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>そして、御家人階層の没落傾向に対して新興階層である悪党の活動が活発化していき、この動きは鎌倉幕府滅亡へとつながっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The class of the shogunate&apos;s vassals began to fall, and on the contrary, a new class of villain emerged, and this change later led to the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The class of the shogunate&apos;s vassals began to fall, and to the contrary, a new class of villain emerged, and this change later led to the fall of the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The class of Gokenin began to fall, and to the contrary, a new class of Akuto (a villain in the medieval times) emerged, and this change later led to the fall of the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>terms</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>元寇の諸相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various Aspects of Genko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various Aspects of Genko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various Aspects of Genko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>日本侵略の理由</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reasons for the Invasion of Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Reasons for the Invasion of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Reasons for the Invasion of Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="128">
<j>文永の役の理由については南宋への牽制であり、少なくともクビライは最初から日本侵略を望んでいたわけではないと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for Bunei no Eki is considered to have been to warn against the Southern Sung Dynasty, and at least, in the beginning, Kublai did not desire to invade Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for Bunei no Eki is considered to have been to warn against the Southern Sung Dynasty, and at least, in the beginning, Kublai did not desire to invade Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for Bunei no Eki is considered to have been to warn against the Southern Sung Dynasty, and at least, in the beginning, Kublai did not desire to invade Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>また、短期間での帰還理由についても、自主的撤退とする説が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is also a theory that they voluntarily withdrew after a short period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is also a theory that they voluntarily withdrew after a short period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is also a theory that they voluntarily withdrew after a short period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="130">
<j>それは、日本側の対応を確認するため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose was to see how Japan would react.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose was to see how Japan would react.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose was to see how Japan would react.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>これは、軍事的に言えば「威力偵察」と呼ばれているものであり、ごく基本的な戦術のひとつである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called, in a military term, &apos;reconnaissance in force,&apos; which is one of very basic tactics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is called, in a military term, &apos;reconnaissance in force,&apos; which is one of the very basic tactics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is called, in a military term, &apos;reconnaissance in force,&apos; which is one of the very basic tactics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="132">
<j>ある程度の損害を与え、その後の交渉で日本に要求をのませるようにするため。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their aim was to damage Japan to some extent and force it to accept their demands in later negotiations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their aim was to damage Japan to some extent and force it to accept their demands in later negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their aim was to damage Japan to some extent and force it to accept their demands in later negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>これは、元がたびたび使っている戦法であり今回もそれに準じたものということである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is the tactic that the Yuan Dynasty often employed and this case seems to be in accordance with it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is a tactic that the Yuan Dynasty often employed and this case seems to be in accordance with it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is a tactic that the Yuan Dynasty often employed and this case seems to be in accordance with it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="134">
<j>これは、当時の元が日本に使者を送った理由や情勢を考えると、至極妥当だとする考えである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems to be very reasonable, taking into consideration the reason for Yuan&apos;s sending envoys to Japan then and its circumstances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems to be very reasonable, taking into consideration the reason for Yuan&apos;s sending envoys to Japan then and its circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems to be very reasonable, taking into consideration the reason for Yuan&apos;s sending envoys to Japan then and its circumstances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="135">
<j>威力偵察目的であったと言う傍証として、時の元の水軍には長期戦略に対する装備の用意はなく、そのため一日で矢を撃ち尽くして去っていったという、元側の記録が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A supporting evidence of the Yuan&apos;s purpose having been reconnaissance in force is a record in the Yuan Dynasty stating that the Yuan navy then had not prepared for a long battle so that it used all arrows within one day and left.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Supporting evidence of the Yuan&apos;s purpose having been reconnaissance in force is a record in the Yuan Dynasty stating that the Yuan navy then had not prepared for a long battle so that it used all their arrows within one day and left.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Supporting evidence of the Yuan&apos;s purpose having been reconnaissance in force is a record in the Yuan Dynasty stating that the Yuan navy then had not prepared for a long battle so that it used all their arrows within one day and left.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="136">
<j>一方で、南宋が滅んだ後の弘安の役については様々な説がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, there are various theories about Koan no Eki, which occurred after the fall of the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, there are various theories about Koan no Eki, which occurred after the fall of the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, there are various theories about Koan no Eki, which occurred after the fall of the Southern Sung Dynasty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="137">
<j>珍しいものとしては、南宋を降した後に旧南宋軍を日本攻撃にあたらせ、消耗させるためと言うものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unusual one says that the purpose was to weaken the former Southern Sung army, after its conquest, by forcing it to attack Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An unusual one says that the purpose was to weaken the former Southern Sung army, after its conquest, by forcing it to attack Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An unusual one says that the purpose was to weaken the former Southern Sung army, after its conquest, by forcing it to attack Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>旧南宋軍は被征服者のため元への忠誠心も全く無く、さらに元々南宋は金で兵士を募集する募兵という形をとっており、数は多いが所詮は寄せ集めであり、士気・忠誠心も低く、戦闘能力も高くなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former Southern Sung army had no loyalty to the Yuan Dynasty, because it was a conquered army, and furthermore, it had recruited soldiers through payment so that its soldiers were large in number but simple people who had low morale, loyalty and fighting strength.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former Southern Sung army had no loyalty to the Yuan Dynasty, because it was a conquered army, and furthermore, it had recruited soldiers through payment so that its soldiers were large in number but simple people who had low morale, loyalty, and fighting strength.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former Southern Sung army had no loyalty to the Yuan Dynasty, because it was a conquered army, and furthermore, it had recruited soldiers through payment so that its soldiers were large in number but simple people who had low morale, loyalty, and fighting strength.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>また軍を解散させると職を失った大量の兵士達が社会不安の要因となってしまうというものだが、征服した現地兵を次の戦争に投入することは元ではよく行われており、日本との戦いのときのみことさら強調すべきこととは考えにくい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that dissolving the army would cause social anxiety by producing numerous unemployed soldiers, but the Yuan Dynasty often sent local conquered soldiers to the next war and it could not be particularly emphasized only in the case of the war with Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that dissolving the army would cause social anxiety by producing numerous unemployed soldiers, but the Yuan Dynasty often sent local conquered soldiers to the next war and it could not be particularly emphasized only in the case of war with Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that dissolving the army would cause social anxiety by producing numerous unemployed soldiers, but the Yuan Dynasty often sent local conquered soldiers to the next war and it could not be particularly emphasized only in the case of war with Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="140">
<j>近年の調査では、博多湾の底で見つかった元の軍船から、農業用の鋤や鍬などが見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recent studies have found forks and spades used for farming in the Yuan&apos;s warship discovered in the bottom of Hakata Bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recent studies have found forks and spades used for farming in the Yuan&apos;s warship discovered at the bottom of Hakata Bay.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recent studies have found forks and spades used for farming in the Yuan&apos;s warship discovered at the bottom of Hakata Bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>『元史』日本伝　至元十八年正月条によると、クビライは遠征に先立って大都に遠征軍の指揮官である阿剌罕、范文虎、忻都、洪茶丘らを召集し勅を下している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihon Den of &quot;Genshi,&quot; in the article of January 1281, says that Kublai, before sending the expedition army, summoned the commanders such as Arakan, Fan Wen-hu, Xin Dou and Hong Da-gu, to Dadu and gave them an imperial order.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「至元十八年」→弘安の役の起きた年で、1281年。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihon Den of &quot;Genshi,&quot; in the article of January 1281, says that Kublai, before sending the expedition army, summoned his commanders such as Arakan, Fan Wen-hu, Xin Dou, and Hong Da-gu, to Dadu and gave them an imperial order.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Den of &quot;Genshi,&quot; in the article of January 1281, says that Kublai, before sending the expedition army, summoned his commanders such as Arakan, Wen-hu FAN, Dou XIN, and Da-gu HONG, to Dadu and gave them an imperial order.</e>
<cmt>names</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>そのなかで「朕、漢人の言に聞くに、『人の家、国を取るには百姓土地を得んと欲す。もし尽く百姓を殺さば徒に地を得るも何に用いん』」とも述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He then said, &quot;I have heard that people of Han say, &apos;to seize home and country of others, you need to obtain peasants and land. If you kill all peasants, for what use the land is obtained?&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then said, &quot;I have heard that people of Han say, &apos;to seize home and country of others, you need to obtain peasants and land. If you kill all the peasants, for what use is the land that is obtained?&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He then said, &quot;I have heard that people of Han say, &apos;to seize home and country of others, you need to obtain peasants and land. If you kill all the peasants, for what use is the land that is obtained?&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>このため、弘安の役で戦争に勝利した暁には屯田を目的として長期的な日本の占領・支配することを意図していたのではないかと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered, therefore, that he would have been thinking about a long-term occupation and ruling of Japan for the purpose of land cultivation after winning the war of Koan no Eki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered, therefore, that he would have been thinking about a long-term occupation and ruling of Japan for the purpose of land cultivation after winning the war of Koan no Eki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered, therefore, that he would have been thinking about a long-term occupation and ruling of Japan for the purpose of land cultivation after winning the war of Koan no Eki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>これをもって侵攻の意図と見る見解があり、14万人という過剰な人員のうち、旧南宋の兵員からなる江南軍10万人は軍隊兼移民団だったのでは、と言う見解も出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people consider that it indicates his intention of invasion, and out of 140 thousand soldiers, whose number was excessively large, 100 thousand soldiers of the Southern Yangtze Army, consisting of the former Southern Sung soldiers, would have been immigrants as well as soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people consider that it indicates his intention of invasion, and out of 140,000 soldiers, whose number was excessively large, 100,000 soldiers of the Southern Yangtze Army, consisting of the former Southern Sung soldiers, would have been immigrants as well as soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people consider that it indicates his intention of invasion, and out of 140,000 soldiers, whose number was excessively large, 100,000 soldiers of the Southern Yangtze Army, consisting of the former Southern Sung soldiers, would have been immigrants as well as soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>高麗の関与</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Involvement of Goryeo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Involvement of Goryeo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Involvement of Goryeo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="145">
<j>『高麗史』によると1272年に、高麗の王世子の諶（しん、後の忠烈王）が、元 (王朝)のクビライ皇帝に「惟んみるに、日本は未だに聖化を蒙らず。故に詔使を発し、軍容を継耀かし、戦艦兵糧まさに、須いる所あらん、もし此事を以って臣に委ねなば、勉めて心力を尽くして　小しく王師を助くるに庶幾（ちか）からん」と具申したとある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Koraishi,&quot; in 1272, Crown Prince Sim of Goryeo (later King Chungnyeol) told his opinion to the Emperor Kublai of the Yuan Dynasty, &quot;I think that Japan has not yet leant the virtues of the Emperor. Therefore, an imperial order should be issued to use the army, warships and provisions for this purpose. If you commission your vassals to do it, we will do our best to support the imperial army.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「聖化を蒙らず」→皇帝の徳を知らない、と解釈しました。（http://www.weblio.jp/content/%E8%81%96%E5%8C%96）「王師」→王の軍。官軍。（kotobank）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Koraishi,&quot; in 1272, Crown Prince Sim of Goryeo (later King Chungnyeol) gave his opinion to Emperor Kublai of the Yuan Dynasty, &quot;I think that Japan has not yet leant the virtues of the Emperor. Therefore, an imperial order should be issued to use the army, warships and provisions for this purpose. If you commission your vassals to do it, we will do our best to support the imperial army.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Koraishi,&quot; in 1272, Crown Prince Sim of Goryeo (later King Chungnyeol) gave his opinion to Emperor Kublai of the Yuan Dynasty, &quot;I think that Japan has not yet leant the virtues of the Emperor. Therefore, an imperial order should be issued to use the army, warships and provisions for this purpose. If you commission your vassals to do it, we will do our best to support the imperial army.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>また「元史」によると、元寇の発端は、高麗王の忠烈王が「元の皇帝に執拗に、東征して日本を属国にするよう勧めた」との記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Genshi&quot; states that Genko began with King Chungnyeol of Goryeo &quot;persistently recommending an expedition to the east to the Yuan&apos;s emperor in order to make Japan become its subject.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, &quot;Genshi&quot; states that Genko began with King Chungnyeol of Goryeo &quot;persistently recommending an expedition to the east to Yuan&apos;s emperor in order to force Japan to become its subject.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, &quot;Genshi&quot; states that Genko began with King Chungnyeol of Goryeo &quot;persistently recommending an expedition to the east to Yuan&apos;s emperor in order to force Japan to become its subject.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>これに対して忠烈王の発言の所以を高麗の国内事情に求める向きもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning it, some try to find the reason for King Chungnyeol&apos;s opinion in the internal conditions of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning this, some try to find the reason for King Chungnyeol&apos;s opinion in the internal conditions of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning this, some try to find the reason for King Chungnyeol&apos;s opinion in the internal conditions of Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>高麗はモンゴルの侵攻前は武臣が王を傀儡化して政権を執っており、王はモンゴルの兵力を借りることによって王権を奪い返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the invasion by Mongols, the king of Goryeo was a puppet ruler, with warrior vassals controlling the government, but the king regained the power by obtaining a support from the Mongol army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the invasion by the Mongols, the king of Goryeo was a puppet ruler, with warrior vassals controlling the government, but the king regained power by obtaining support from the Mongol army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the invasion by the Mongols, the king of Goryeo was a puppet ruler, with warrior vassals controlling the government, but the king regained power by obtaining support from the Mongol army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>それ以後、高麗王はほとんどモンゴルと一体化し、モンゴル名を貰い、モンゴル皇帝の娘を王妃にしモンゴル皇帝であるクビライ王家の娘婿（キュレゲン、グレゲン）となる姻族、「駙馬高麗国王家」となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, the king of Goryeo became almost a member of the Mongol Empire, having received a Mongol name and become a son-in-law of the Mongol imperial family of Kublai (kuregen or guregen) by marrying his daughter, and thus Goryeo became &apos;Mongol&apos;s son-in-law kingdom of Goryeo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「キュレゲン、グレゲン」→モンゴル語で娘婿の意。「駙馬高麗国王家」→駙馬は貴人の娘婿の意。（http://kotobank.jp/word/%E3%81%B5%E9%A6%AC）&quot;a Mongol&apos;s son-in-law kingdom of Goryeo&quot;と訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, the king of Goryeo became almost a member of the Mongol Empire, having received a Mongol name and become a son-in-law of the Mongol imperial family of Kublai (kuregen or guregen) by marrying his daughter, and thus Goryeo became &apos;Mongol&apos;s son-in-law kingdom of Goryeo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, the king of Goryeo became almost a member of the Mongol Empire, having received a Mongol name and become a son-in-law of the Mongol imperial family of Kublai (kuregen or guregen) by marrying his daughter, and thus Goryeo became &apos;Mongol&apos;s son-in-law kingdom of Goryeo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>これに反対する勢力は反乱を起こし、モンゴルにより鎮圧されるが、一部はなお激しい抵抗を続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People objecting it raised a rebellion, which was subdued by Mongol, but some of them still continued the fierce resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People objecting to it raised a rebellion, which was subdued by the Mongol, but some of them still continued fierce resistance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People objecting to it raised a rebellion, which was subdued by the Mongol, but some of them still continued fierce resistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>これが三別抄である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were called Sambyeolcho.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were called Sambyeolcho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were called Sambyeolcho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>忠烈王の発言は王権を保つためにクビライの意を迎えようとしたとする見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some consider that King Chungnyeol gave that opinion in order to preserve the power of the king, by attracting the intention of Kublai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some consider that King Chungnyeol gave that opinion in order to preserve the power of the king, by attracting the intention of Kublai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some consider that King Chungnyeol gave that opinion in order to preserve the power of the king, by attracting the intention of Kublai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>上述の3策のうち、高麗ルートを選ばせたのもモンゴル兵力が高麗から離れてしまうことを恐れたためとも考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the reason for recommending the route via Goryeo among the three plans described above might have been to prevent the Mongol army to leave Goryeo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the reason for recommending the route via Goryeo among the three plans described above might have been to prevent the Mongol army from leaving Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the reason for recommending the route via Goryeo among the three plans described above might have been to prevent the Mongol army from leaving Goryeo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>蒙古国書・元使殺害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Letter from the Mongol Empire and the Killing of the Yuan Envoys</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Letter from the Mongol Empire and the Killing of the Yuan Envoys</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Letter from the Mongol Empire and the Killing of the Yuan Envoys</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>元が最初に送った国書であるが、これに関しては東洋史学者は概ね他の歴代中国王朝の国書と比べて驚くほど低姿勢であると見ているのに対して、日本史学者は高圧的と見る傾向にあると言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the first letter sent by the Yuan Dynasty, most scholars of eastern history think that it is surprisingly polite compared to letters by other Chinese dynasties, but scholars of Japanese history are said to have a tendency to see it as authoritative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the first letter sent by the Yuan Dynasty, most scholars of eastern history think that it is surprisingly polite compared to letters by other Chinese dynasties, but scholars of Japanese history are said to have a tendency to see it as authoritative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the first letter sent by the Yuan Dynasty, most scholars of eastern history think that it is surprisingly polite compared to letters by other Chinese dynasties, but scholars of Japanese history are said to have a tendency to see it as authoritative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>蒙古皇帝国書を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Refer to Letter of the Mongol Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Refer to Letter of the Mongol Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Refer to Letter of the Mongol Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>ちなみに、北条時宗の反対で出される事はなかったものの、朝廷がクビライに出そうとした返書は「日本は天照大神以来の神国であって、外国に臣従する謂れはない」とするかなり過激な内容だったとも伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the reply that the Japanese Imperial Court intended to give, though it was not given because Tokimune HOJO opposed to it, is said to have contained rather aggressive phrases, saying &quot;Japan is a country protected by the gods, originating from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and thus there is no reason to obey a foreign country.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the reply that the Japanese Imperial Court intended to give, though it was not given because Tokimune HOJO opposed to it, is said to have contained rather aggressive phrases, saying &quot;Japan is a country protected by the gods, originating from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and thus there is no reason to obey a foreign country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the reply that the Japanese Imperial Court intended to give, though it was not given because Tokimune HOJO opposed to it, is said to have contained rather aggressive phrases, saying &quot;Japan is a country protected by the gods, originating from Amaterasu Omikami (the Sun Goddess), and thus there is no reason to obey a foreign country.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="157">
<j>また使者に対する殺害に関して、彼らがスパイ行為を行っていたためと言う見解がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the killing of the envoys, some consider that the reason was because they were acting as spies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the killing of the envoys, some consider that the reason was because they were acting as spies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the killing of the envoys, some consider that the reason was because they were acting as spies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>文永の役以前の使者の行動はかなり自由で、道中では色々な情報を集めることができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before Bunei no Eki, envoys were rather free and could gather various information during their trip.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before Bunei no Eki, envoys were rather free and could gather various information during their trips.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before Bunei no Eki, envoys were rather free and could gather various information during their trips.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>そのため、使者による間諜行為がおこなわれたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It seems to have led the envoys to spy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems to have led the envoys to spy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems to have led the envoys to spy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>『八幡大菩薩愚童訓』には「夜々ニ筑紫之地ヲ見廻、船戦之場懸足逃道ニ至マテ、差図ヲ書」とあり、『元史』趙良弼伝にも「使日本趙良弼、至太宰府而還、具以日本君臣爵号、州郡名数、風俗土宜来上」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu Gudokun&quot; (another title of Hachiman Gudokun) reads, &quot;they looked around Chikushi Province in the night and wrote instructions about the place for naval battle, position and the way to escape&quot; and in addition, the records on Chao Liang-pi in &quot;Genshi&quot; also says, &quot;envoy to Japan Chao Liang-pi reached Dazai-fu and returned with detailed information about Japanese titles granted to vassals, the number and names of provinces, customs and products.&quot;</e>
<cmt>『八幡大菩薩愚童訓』→既出の「八幡愚童訓」のこと。写本によって題名が異なるようです。&quot;another title of Hachiman Gudokun&quot;と説明を入れました。「使日本趙良弼、至太宰府而還、具以日本君臣爵号、州郡名数、風俗土宜来上」→遣日本使趙良弼が大宰府から帰来し、具（つぶ）さに日本の君臣の爵号や州郡の名数・風俗・土宜（特産物）をもってきた。（http://www015.upp.so-net.ne.jp/gofukakusa/ryo-susumu-mokoshurai-05.htmなど参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu Gudokun&quot; (another title of Hachiman Gudokun) reads, &quot;they looked around Chikushi Province in the night and wrote instructions about the place for naval battle, position and the way to escape&quot; and in addition, the records on Chao Liang-pi in &quot;Genshi&quot; also says, &quot;envoy to Japan Chao Liang-pi reached Dazai-fu and returned with detailed information about Japanese titles granted to vassals, the number and names of provinces, customs and products.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Hachiman Daibosatsu Gudokun&quot; (another title of Hachiman Gudokun) reads, &quot;they looked around Chikushi Province in the night and wrote instructions about the place for naval battle, position and the way to escape&quot; and in addition, the records on Liang-pi CHAO in &quot;Genshi&quot; also says, &quot;envoy to Japan Liang-pi CHAO reached Dazai-fu and returned with detailed information about Japanese titles granted to vassals, the number and names of provinces, customs and products.&quot;</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>こういった間諜行為が考慮されてか、文永の役以降は使者を斬るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Bunei no Eki, Japan killed envoys, probably being afraid of such spying.</e>
<cmt>主語として「日本（Japan）」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Bunei no Eki, Japan killed envoys, probably being afraid of such spying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Bunei no Eki, Japan killed envoys, probably being afraid of such spying.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>また、武家政権である鎌倉幕府の性格からの武断的措置であるとする解釈や、対外危機を意識させ防戦体制を整える上での決定的措置であるとする考え方などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some also consider that the decision was made, trying to solve the problem by force of arms, taking into consideration the nature of the Kamakura shogunate as a military government, or trying to prepare the defense system by alerting its people about a threat from foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some also consider that a decision was made, trying to solve the problem by force of arms, taking into consideration the nature of the Kamakura shogunate as a military government, or trying to prepare the defense system by alerting its people about a threat from foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some also consider that a decision was made, trying to solve the problem by force of arms, taking into consideration the nature of Kamakura bakufu as a military government, or trying to prepare the defense system by alerting its people about a threat from foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="163">
<j>元使殺害の評価については賛否両論がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are both arguments for and against the killing of the Yuan envoys.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are both arguments for and against the killing of the Yuan envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are both arguments for and against the killing of the Yuan envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>同時代では日蓮が批判し、後世の評価では2回目の日本侵攻の口実になった暴挙であると評価する論者と、元の2回目の対日侵攻には影響を与えなかった、あるいは国難に対しては手本にするべき好例であると肯定的に評価する『大日本史』や、頼山陽らがいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time it occurred, it was criticized by Nichiren, and in a later era, there are both arguments for and against; some criticize it as a reckless act that gave the enemy a reason for the second invasion of Japan, and others affirm it, including Sanyo RAI and &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan), which states that it did not affect the Yuan&apos;s second invasion of Japan and is a good example to be followed when tackling a crisis of the nation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time it occurred, it was criticized by Nichiren, and in a later era, there were both arguments for and against; some criticized it as a reckless act that gave the enemy a reason for the second invasion of Japan, and others affirm it, including Sanyo RAI and &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan), which states that it did not influence the Yuan&apos;s second invasion of Japan and is a good example to be followed when tackling a crisis of the nation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time it occurred, it was criticized by Nichiren, and in a later era, there were both arguments for and against; some criticized it as a reckless act that gave the enemy a reason for the second invasion of Japan, and others affirm it, including Sanyo RAI and &quot;Dainihonshi&quot; (Great History of Japan), which states that it did not influence the Yuan&apos;s second invasion of Japan and is a good example to be followed when tackling a crisis of the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>神風</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamikaze</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamikaze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamikaze</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="165">
<j>文永の役における蒙古軍の撤退に関して、日本側の史料には一夜明けると蒙古船が消失していた事実が記されているのみとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerning the withdrawal of the Mongol army, Japanese historical materials only state the fact that the Mongol fleet disappeared in the next morning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerning the withdrawal of the Mongol army, Japanese historical materials only state the fact that the Mongol fleet disappeared the next morning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerning the withdrawal of the Mongol army, Japanese historical materials only state the fact that the Mongol fleet disappeared the next morning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>公家の広橋兼仲の日記『勘仲記』には、伝聞として逆風が吹いたことを記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kanchuki,&quot; the diary of noble Kanenaka HIROHASHI, reads that people then said that the upwind had blown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kanchuki,&quot; the diary of noble Kanenaka HIROHASHI, reads that people then said that the upwind had blown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Kanchuki,&quot; the Diary of noble Kanenaka HIROHASHI, reads that people then said that the upwind had blown.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>高麗の史料、『高麗史』などには、撤退途中に風雨が起きて多数が座礁した事が記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The historical materials of Goryeo, including &quot;Koraishi,&quot; says that a storm occurred during their withdrawal and stranded many ships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The historical materials of Goryeo, including &quot;Koraishi,&quot; says that a storm occurred during their withdrawal and stranded many ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The historical materials of Goryeo, including &quot;Koraishi,&quot; says that a storm occurred during their withdrawal and stranded many ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>しかし日本側の史料にその記載が無い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Japanese materials lack such descriptions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Japanese materials lack such descriptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Japanese materials lack such descriptions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>気象学的には過去の統計に台風の渡来記録が無いことから、台風以外の気象現象という見解もとられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to meteorology, there is no statistical record of the past that a typhoon came then, and therefore, some consider that it was a weather phenomenon other than a typhoon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to meteorology, there is no statistical record of the past that a typhoon came then, and therefore, some consider that it was a weather phenomenon other than a typhoon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to meteorology, there is no statistical record of the past that a typhoon came then, and therefore, some consider that it was a weather phenomenon other than a typhoon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>文永の役に関しては、台風の可能性はほぼなかったと、今日では見なす者が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, most people think that it is unlikely to have been a typhoon in relation to Bunei no Eki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, most people think that it is unlikely to have been a typhoon in relation to Bunei no Eki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, most people think that it is unlikely to have been a typhoon in relation to Bunei no Eki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="171">
<j>弘安の役においても、当時の日本が知り得なかった江南軍壊滅の理由を台風や熱帯低気圧の影響としながらも、博多沖の東路軍は、それとは違った理由で壊滅したという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also in Koan no Eki, what had destroyed the Southern Yangtze Army, which Japan could not know then, is said to have been a typhoon or tropical cyclone, but there is a theory that the Eastern Route Army staying offshore near Hakata perished due to a different reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also in Koan no Eki, what had destroyed the Southern Yangtze Army, which Japan could not know then, is said to have been a typhoon or tropical cyclone, but there is a theory that the Eastern Route Army staying offshore near Hakata perished due to a different reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also in Koan no Eki, what had destroyed the Southern Yangtze Army, which Japan could not know then, is said to have been a typhoon or tropical cyclone, but there is a theory that the Eastern Route Army staying offshore near Hakata perished due to a different reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="172">
<j>文永の役については現在では壊滅的な被害があったかについても含め多くの疑問が持たれているが、弘安四年七月三十日から翌閏七月一日（1281年8月15日 - 8月16日）にかけては京都でも激しい風雨に見舞われたことが日記類などの記録にあるため、弘安の役での東路・江南両軍の壊滅の原因は台風であるとの説は現在でも有力視されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nowadays, there are many doubts about Bunei no Eki, including whether there was any serious damage, but what destroyed the both armies of Eastern Route and Southern Yangtze in Koan no Eki is still now widely considered to have been a typhoon, because there are diaries and records stating that even Kyoto had a furious storm from August 15, 1281 to August 16.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nowadays, there are many doubts about Bunei no Eki, including whether there was any serious damage, but what destroyed both armies of the Eastern Route and Southern Yangtze in Koan no Eki is still now widely considered to have been a typhoon, because there are diaries and records stating that even Kyoto had a furious storm from August 15, 1281 to August 16.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nowadays, there are many doubts about Bunei no Eki, including whether there was any serious damage, but what destroyed both armies of the Eastern Route and Southern Yangtze in Koan no Eki is still now widely considered to have been a typhoon, because there are diaries and records stating that even Kyoto had a furious storm from August 15, 1281 to August 16.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="173">
<j>なお、軍歌の「元寇 (軍歌)」の歌詞にも『弘安四年夏の頃』という一節があるが、文永の役に関しては何も触れてはいない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A military song called &apos;Genko&apos; contains the lyric of &quot;in the summer of the fourth year of Koan (1281)&quot; but does not mention Bunei no Eki at all.</e>
<cmt>「弘安四年」→1281年</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A military song called &apos;Genko&apos; contains the lyric of &quot;in the summer of the fourth year of Koan (1281)&quot; but does not mention Bunei no Eki at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A military song called &apos;Genko&apos; contains the lyric of &quot;in the summer of the fourth year of Koan (1281)&quot; but does not mention Bunei no Eki at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>軍事面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Military Aspect</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Military Aspect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Military Aspect</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="174">
<j>かつては元軍の集団戦術、いわゆる組織戦闘に対して、当時の日本側は一騎打ちを基本とした戦い方をしていたと言われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It used to be said that Japan at that time fought basically by means of one-to-one battle against the Yuan army which fought in organized groups.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It used to be said that Japan at that time fought basically by means of one-to-one battle against the Yuan army which fought in organized groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It used to be said that Japan at that time fought basically by means of one-to-one battle against the Yuan army which fought in organized groups.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>また元軍は毒矢・てつはう（鉄火砲）など、日本側が装備しない武器を活用したことにより、各地で日本軍は圧倒されたと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the Yuan army fought far better, by using weapons that the Japanese army did not have, such as poison arrows and guns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the Yuan army fought far better, by using weapons that the Japanese army did not have, such as poison arrows and guns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the Yuan army fought far better, by using weapons that the Japanese army did not have, such as poison arrows and guns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>しかし、現在の研究では双方共に被害を出していることが判明していることから、日本側もある程度まとまった兵力を投入できた局面などでは、一方的に圧倒されたわけではないケースもあったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, present studies have confirmed that both parties suffered damage, and therefore, it would have been cases in which Japan could employ a fairly large number of warriors and fought well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, present studies have confirmed that both parties suffered damage, and therefore, there would have been cases in which Japan could employ a fairly large number of warriors and fought well.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, present studies have confirmed that both parties suffered damage, and therefore, there would have been cases in which Japan could employ a fairly large number of warriors and fought well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="177">
<j>日本側の弘安の役での戦術や対策としては、下記があげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan employed the following tactics and measures in Koan no Eki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan employed the following tactics and measures in Koan no Eki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan employed the following tactics and measures in Koan no Eki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="178">
<j>先述の防塁に楯を用いた防御。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Defense using the defense walls mentioned earlier and shields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Defense using the defense walls mentioned earlier and shields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Defense using the defense walls mentioned earlier and shields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>鎌倉期でいう「城郭を構える」と呼ばれる行為に類するものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered to have been a kind of act called &apos;building castle walls&apos; in the Kamakura period (which means preparing for a battle).</e>
<cmt>「城郭を構える」→臨戦態勢をとること、と解釈し、説明を入れました。（http://www.kashiwashobo.co.jp/new_web/column/rensai/r07-01.html参照）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered to have been a kind of act called &apos;building castle walls&apos; in the Kamakura period (which meant preparing for a battle).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered to have been a kind of act called &apos;building castle walls&apos; in the Kamakura period (which meant preparing for a battle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="180">
<j>夜間、日本側からの小舟に分乗して、元船を奇襲。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Surprise attacks in the night against the Yuan ships, departing from Japan in small boats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Surprise attacks in the night against the Yuan ships, departing from Japan in small boats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Surprise attacks in the night against the Yuan ships, departing from Japan in small boats.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>鎌倉幕府法では禁圧対象となっている「夜討ち」と呼ばれる行為だが、弘安の役では幕府側が積極的に活用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was called &apos;attack in the night&apos; and prohibited under the laws of the Kamakura shogunate, but in Koan no Eki, the shogunate proactively used this method.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was called &apos;attack in the night&apos; and prohibited under the laws of the Kamakura shogunate, but in Koan no Eki, the shogunate proactively used this method.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was called &apos;attack in the night&apos; and prohibited under the laws of Kamakura bakufu, but in Koan no Eki, bakufu proactively used this method.</e>
<cmt>term</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>狭い船内での斬り合いでは、日本の武士の方に分があったと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that Japanese samurai had an advantage in the battles in narrow spaces inside the ships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that Japanese samurai had an advantage in the battles in narrow spaces inside the ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that Japanese samurai had an advantage in the battles in narrow spaces inside the ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="183">
<j>合流するはずだった江南軍は、総司令官の交替と多人数による混乱により統率が取れず、東路軍との合流が1ケ月半ほど遅れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Yangtze Army, which was to join the Eastern Route Army, was delayed about one and a half months because the army was disorganized due to the substitution of commander-in-chief and confusion caused by a large number of soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Yangtze Army, which was to join the Eastern Route Army, was delayed about one and a half months because the army was disorganized due to the substitution of the commander-in-chief and confusion caused by a large number of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Yangtze Army, which was to join the Eastern Route Army, was delayed about one and a half months because the army was disorganized due to the substitution of the commander-in-chief and confusion caused by a large number of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="184">
<j>一方、東路軍は度重なる日本軍のコマンド作戦により、博多沖の海上で釘付け状態となり、やがて食料や水不足と発生した疫病により「兵糧攻め」と同じ状態になって疲弊していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Eastern Route Army was forced to stay in the sea near Hakata by successive attacks by Japanese commandoes, and soon became exhausted by the situation that would &apos;drive them into starvation,&apos; due to the shortage of foods and water as well as an epidemic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Eastern Route Army was forced to stay at sea near Hakata by successive attacks by Japanese commandoes, and soon became exhausted by the situation that would &apos;drive them into starvation,&apos; due to the shortage of food and water as well as an epidemic.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Eastern Route Army was forced to stay at sea near Hakata by successive attacks by Japanese commandoes, and soon became exhausted by the situation that would &apos;drive them into starvation,&apos; due to the shortage of food and water as well as an epidemic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="185">
<j>江南軍が遅れて出発したが、そのために台風時期と重なり、合流前にほぼ壊滅状態。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The later departure of the Southern Yangtze Army coincided with the period of typhoon attacks, and the army was almost destroyed before it joined the other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The later departure of the Southern Yangtze Army coincided with the period of typhoon attacks, and the army was almost destroyed before it joined the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The later departure of the Southern Yangtze Army coincided with the period of typhoon attacks, and the army was almost destroyed before it joined the other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>博多沖の東路軍も時間差で、同じ台風ないしは熱帯低気圧によって壊滅したと見なされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eastern Route Army is also considered to have perished shortly after that, due to the same typhoon or tropical cyclone.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eastern Route Army is also considered to have perished shortly after that, due to the same typhoon or tropical cyclone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eastern Route Army is also considered to have perished shortly after that, due to the same typhoon or tropical cyclone.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="187">
<j>その他、敗因はさまざまに語られるが、上記のとおり重複する点も含めて、日本軍が元軍の上陸前に船や陸上から攻撃を与えたことも要因の一つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although various other reasons are considered to have led to the defeat, one of the reasons was the fact that the Japanese army attacked the Yuan army in boats or on shore, before it disembarked, including the attacks described above.</e>
<cmt>「上記のとおり重複する点も含めて」→上記で既に述べたことを含めて、と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although various other reasons are considered to have led to the defeat, one of the reasons was the fact that the Japanese army attacked the Yuan army in boats or on shore, before it disembarked, including the attacks described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although various other reasons are considered to have led to the defeat, one of the reasons was the fact that the Japanese army attacked the Yuan army in boats or on shore, before it disembarked, including the attacks described above.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>遊牧民族であるモンゴル人は船上の戦法を心得ておらず、モンゴル軍が有効に活用し、連戦連勝を重ねてきた得意の騎馬隊を上陸戦のため使うことができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Mongols were nomadic people, they were not familiar with a battle in ships, and also could not use their specialty cavalry, which they had been using well to achieve successive victories, in the battle to reach the shore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Mongols were a nomadic people, they were not familiar with conducting battle in ships, and also could not use their cavalry, which they had been using well to achieve successive victories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Mongols were a nomadic people, they were not familiar with conducting battle in ships, and also could not use their cavalry, which they had been using well to achieve successive victories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>また、暴風雨によって多くの船がもろくも沈んだ理由として、船を服属させた高麗人や越人（ベトナム人）に作らせたことにあるとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that the fact that their ships had been made by people of subjected countries, such as Goryeo and Vietnam, was one of the reasons why many ships were so easily destroyed by the storm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that the fact that their ships had been made by people of subjected countries, such as Goryeo and Vietnam, was one of the reasons why many ships were so easily destroyed by the storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that the fact that their ships had been made by people of subjected countries, such as Goryeo and Vietnam, was one of the reasons why many ships were so easily destroyed by the storm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>彼らはすでにモンゴル人支配の不満を募らせており、輸送船の造船は急務でもあり、突貫工事的に手抜きによって建造されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were already frustrated at the dominance of Mongols, and because the construction of the transport ships was an urgent mission, they cut corners to complete it early.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were already frustrated at the dominance of Mongols, and because constructing transport ships was an urgent mission, they cut corners to complete it early.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were already frustrated at the dominance of Mongols, and because constructing transport ships was an urgent mission, they cut corners to complete it early.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>また、兵士も占領した高麗人や漢民族を徴用した多民族軍であったため、士気が低かったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army also seems to have had low morale because it consisted of various ethnic groups, including people of Goryeo and Han who had been conquered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army also seems to have had a low morale because it consisted of various ethnic groups, including people of Goryeo and Han who had been conquered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army also seems to have had a low morale because it consisted of various ethnic groups, including people of Goryeo and Han who had been conquered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>江南軍のほとんどが嘗ての南宋の兵であり、放っておけば社会不安の要因となる彼らを厄介払いする目的もあったと言われる杉山正明の一連の著作、『中国史3』P449など（山川出版社）（それを裏付けるように、モンゴルの司令官たちが乗った船は一隻も沈んでおらず、江南軍に従軍した兵士達の墓も旧南宋の領内では確認されていない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to a series of books written by Masaaki SUGIYAMA and page 449 of &quot;Chugokushi 3&quot; (The History of China, Volume 3) (published by Yamakawa Shuppansha) says that a purpose for organizing the most of the Southern Yangtze Army with soldiers from the former Southern Sung Dynasty was to get rid of them, who would cause social anxiety if left alone (in fact, to support it, no ship in which Mongol commanders were on board sank, and the tombs of the soldiers joined in the Southern Yangtze Army have not been found in the former territory of the Southern Sung Dynasty).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to a series of books written by Masaaki SUGIYAMA and page 449 of &quot;Chugokushi 3&quot; (The History of China, Volume 3) (published by Yamakawa Shuppansha) says that a purpose for organizing most of the Southern Yangtze Army with soldiers from the former Southern Sung Dynasty was to get rid of them, and they would cause social anxiety if left alone (in fact, to support this idea, no ship in which Mongol commanders were on board sank, and tombs of the soldiers joined in the Southern Yangtze Army have not been found in the former territory of the Southern Sung Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to a series of books written by Masaaki SUGIYAMA and page 449 of &quot;Chugokushi 3&quot; (The History of China, Volume 3) (published by Yamakawa Shuppansha) says that a purpose for organizing most of the Southern Yangtze Army with soldiers from the former Southern Sung Dynasty was to get rid of them, and they would cause social anxiety if left alone (in fact, to support this idea, no ship in which Mongol commanders were on board sank, and tombs of the soldiers joined in the Southern Yangtze Army have not been found in the former territory of the Southern Sung Dynasty).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>また、『高麗史』金方慶伝によると、高麗は軍船を建造するのに「蛮様」（南宋様式）の船にしたのでは建設費がかさみ期限には間に合わないので、高麗様式の船を造船したとされており、軍船の準備が整っているので日本を征服しましょうとの忠烈王によるクビライへの進言は実態とまったく異なることであったことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the records on Kim Bang-gyeong in &quot;Koraishi&quot; says that Goryeo constructed the warships in Goryeo style, because constructing them in Southern Sung style was too expensive and would not be completed in time, and the situation was totally different from the suggestion by King Chungnyeol, who told Kublai that the warships were ready to conquest Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the records on Kim Bang-gyeong in &quot;Koraishi&quot; says that Goryeo constructed the warships in Goryeo style, because constructing them in Southern Sung style was too expensive and would not be completed in time, and the situation was totally different from that suggested by King Chungnyeol, who told Kublai that the warships were ready to conquer Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the records on Bang-gyeong KIM in &quot;Koraishi&quot; says that Goryeo constructed the warships in Goryeo style, because constructing them in Southern Sung style was too expensive and would not be completed in time, and the situation was totally different from that suggested by King Chungnyeol, who told Kublai that the warships were ready to conquer Japan.</e>
<cmt>name</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Taka 470(id:239005), 田英(id:85936), クレパスしんちゃん(id:241543), 冬月(id:30384), Trudi3194(id:283128), 937(id:48634), Shizhao(id:1325), 経済準学士(id:22656), 22010515528(id:43149), Lupinoid(id:68), Kkkr27(id:104426), かわはぎ(id:150392), Mercurius(id:57130), Andee(id:20421), Hokahoka(id:37244), Hootaataa(id:199570), Greenland4(id:114494), でここ(id:9565), Pontafon(id:33761), Commonsenses(id:11185), らりた(id:1327), Jugger90(id:17088), Diabah(id:12574), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Knua(id:66861), 今門裕樹(id:107091), Lulusuke(id:44392), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), 麦塚ほとり(id:54917), Sumaru(id:20609), ArthurBot(id:265089), Moltke(id:17553), Shn(id:4425), ちちぶ(id:184715), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Nallimbot(id:230812), Takezaki(id:133200), 深紫(id:24031), Edoo(id:59461), Miita(id:30561), Yourroads(id:214607), Histwr(id:15646), Fryed-peach(id:63402), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Nidarin(id:6420), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Chlewbot(id:33904), けんち(id:5147), Ptbotgourou(id:229657), Nsq(id:54991), Junger(id:10282), JAnDbot(id:66507), Straysheep(id:42448), MIsogi(id:20599), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 味っ子(id:17086), Kotoito(id:21045), WR(id:4432), Tyoron(id:207233), 踊奉行(id:194325), Uraios(id:72687), Askken(id:83502), Snow steed(id:9428), Bandalgom(id:31841), A6M4(id:14155), Nevylax(id:38464), Real Madrid(id:27490), Hamilton(id:6033), Poo-T(id:10118), FUBUKI(id:181308), Rei-bot(id:94097), Loveless(id:129239), Yosemite(id:5808), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Ranbus(id:152482), Oyoyoyo(id:196287), るるちゃん52(id:19533), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), Race(id:131322), Web.dweller(id:153933), Wilson Tam(id:17411), Cave cattum(id:41235), Haydar(id:56911), Shinkansen(id:13703), Aboshi(id:9318), Kamitani(id:30757), Kebosebo(id:203944), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Sarumann(id:56190), VolkovBot(id:105371), YurikBot(id:18605), Oomen(id:15158), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), 暇編集(id:222403), SieBot(id:126695), 「あなたには関係ない」(id:49400), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>