<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>賜田</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiden (Farmland given by Emperor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiden</e>
<cmt>（）内は後列に解説があるので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>賜田（しでん）は、日本の律令制において、勅（天皇の命令）によって個人へ支給された田地をいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiden is the farmland given by emperors through issuing Shochoku (an imperial edict) to individuals under the rules set in the Ritsuryo Code of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiden is the farmland given by emperors through issuing Shochoku (an imperial edict) to individuals under the rules set in the Ritsuryo Code of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiden is the farmland given by emperors through issuing Shochoku (an imperial edict) to individuals under the rules set in the Ritsuryo Code of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>現存する養老律令の田令第12条（賜田条）では、「特別の勅命によって個人へ賜与する田地を賜田という」と定めている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the existing code book of Yoro Ritsuryo Denryo (the law about providing farmland) article No. 12 defines that &quot;the farmland given to individuals by a special Chokumei (an imperial edict) is called shiden.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing Denryo code (the law about providing farmland) article No. 12 in Yoro Ritsuryo defines that &apos;the farmland given to individuals by a special Chokumei (an imperial edict) is called shiden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・全体を改変しました（主節と従属節が不明瞭なため）・引用符</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing Denryo code (the law about providing farmland) article No. 12 in Yoro Ritsuryo defines that &apos;the farmland given to individuals by a special Chokumei (an imperial edict) is called shiden.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この賜田条の規定により、天皇が自分の意思に基づいて、ある者へ田地を支給する道が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By defining the rule of shiden in the code, emperors could intentionally provide farmland to a particular individual.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By defining the rule of shiden in the code, emperors could intentionally provide farmland to a particular individual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By defining the rule of shiden in the code, emperors could intentionally provide farmland to a particular individual.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>賜田の支給という行為を通じて、天皇は特定の人物へ影響を及ぼすことも可能だったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This rule indicates that an emperor could have the influence on a particular person through his act of providing farmland.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This rule indicates that an emperor could have the influence on a particular person through his act of providing farmland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This rule indicates that an emperor could have the influence on a particular person through his act of providing farmland.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>賜田が支給されていたのは、主に有力貴族層だったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is considered that the provision of shiden was mostly made to a dominant nobility class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that shiden was maily provided to a dominant nobility class.</e>
<cmt>the provision of shiden was mostly made to a dominant nobility class→shiden was maily provided to a dominant nobility class</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that shiden was maily provided to a dominant nobility class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>なお、賜田は、田租の賦課対象の輸租田（ゆそでん）とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shiden was categorized as &quot;輸租田&quot; (&quot;Yusoden,&quot; rice field subject to taxation) the objects for imposing &quot;田租.&quot; (&quot;denso,&quot; rice field tax)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shiden was categorized as 輸租田 (Yusoden, or rice fields subject to taxation) for which 田租 (denso, or rice field tax) was imposed.</e>
<cmt>・仕様にしたがって引用符などを調整・文を改変</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shiden was categorized as 輸租田 (Yusoden, or rice fields subject to taxation) for which 田租 (denso, or rice field tax) was imposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、賜田を支給された者が官位を解免されたときは、位田や職分田だけでなく賜田も収公される規定となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the rule defined that not only &quot;位田&quot; (&quot;iden,&quot; fields given based on the court rank) and &quot;職分田&quot; (&quot;shokubunden,&quot; fields allotted for administrating and managing) but also shiden was also officially seized when an official was dismissed from his court rank in any reason.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the rule defined that not only 位田 (iden, or fields given based on the court rank) and 職分田 (shokubunden, or fields allotted for administrating and managing) but also shiden was also officially seized when an official who had been provided shiden was dismissed from his court rank in any reason.</e>
<cmt>・仕様にしたがって引用符などを調整・「賜田を支給された」を訳出しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the rule defined that not only 位田 (iden, or fields given based on the court rank) and 職分田 (shokubunden, or fields allotted for administrating and managing) but also shiden was also officially seized when an official who had been provided shiden was dismissed from his court rank in any reason.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>奈良時代には、おそらく既に耕地化された田地が支給されていたが、平安時代に入ると荒廃地・空閑地が賜与される事例が増えていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During Nara period, most of the shiden provided to individuals was cultivated agricultural land, but in Heian period, the number of cases increased that provided shiden was a ruined, empty land.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Nara period, the provided shiden was already cultivated before provision, but in Heian period, the cases increased that the provided shiden was ruined, empty land.</e>
<cmt>全体を改変しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Nara period, the provided shiden was already cultivated before provision, but in Heian period, the cases increased that the provided shiden was ruined, empty land.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>荒廃地・空閑地が支給されたのは、墾田を促す意味も含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The provision of ruined or empty land as shiden also meant that such land was required to be newly cultivated by the hand of shiden receiver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The provision of ruined or empty land as shiden also meant that such land was required to be newly cultivated by the hand of shiden receiver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The provision of ruined or empty land as shiden also meant that such land was required to be newly cultivated by the hand of shiden receiver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また、本人一代限り（相続は認めない）として賜与された一身田も、賜田の範疇に含まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;一身田&quot; (&quot;Isshinden,&quot; a farmland given for his lifetime without the permission of inheritance) was also included as part of shiden.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">一身田 (Isshinden, or a farmland given for his lifetime without the permission of inheritance) was also included as part of shiden.</e>
<cmt>・仕様にしたがって引用符などを調整しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">一身田 (Isshinden, or a farmland given for his lifetime without the permission of inheritance) was also included as part of shiden.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>三重県津市に現存する一身田の地名は、賜田としての一身田の痕跡と考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The existing name of Isshinden in Tsu City, Mie Prefecture, is considered to be the trace of shiden given as an Isshinden in those days.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The existing name of Isshinden in Tsu City, Mie Prefecture, is considered to be the trace of shiden given as an Isshinden in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The existing name of Isshinden in Tsu City, Mie Prefecture, is considered to be the trace of shiden given as an Isshinden in those days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>