<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>東京時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Jidai (Tokyo Period)</e>
<cmt>日本語読み＋英語表記としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Jidai (Tokyo Period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>東京時代（とうきょうじだい）とは、日本の歴史における時代区分のうちで、江戸幕府が崩壊して明治維新が開始された1868年以後についての呼称として考え出された概念の一つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokyo period is a notion devised as a way to refer to the period after 1868, when the Edo bakufu collapsed and the Meiji restoration was started, within the framework of periodization of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokyo period is a notion devised as a way to refer to the period after 1868, when the Edo bakufu collapsed and the Meiji restoration was started, within the framework of periodization of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokyo period is a notion devised as a way to refer to the period after 1868, when the Edo bakufu collapsed and the Meiji restoration was started, within the framework of periodization of Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>現在、日本においては明治維新以後の時代区分を明治時代・大正時代・昭和時代・平成時代と元号を冠して用いるのが一般的であるが、日本の歴史における時代区分において明治維新以前には鎌倉時代・江戸時代などといった政治の中心地から取られて呼称が用いられている（弥生時代、戦国時代 (日本)のようにその中心地が確定できない時代を除く）が通例なのに明治以後は元号で分けるのはおかしいという意見がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, the history after the Meiji restoration is generally periodized with the use of gengo (era name), such as the Meiji period, Taisho period, Showa period and Heisei period, but the history before the Meiji restoration is normally periodized with the use of names of political centers, such as the Kamakura period and Edo period (except for periods for which the political center cannot be ascertained including the Yayoi period and Sengoku period); some point out that it is unnatural to periodize only the history after the Meiji restoration with the use of gengo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the history after the Meiji restoration is generally periodized with the use of gengo (name for an emperor&apos;s period of reign), such as the Meiji period, Taisho period, Showa period and Heisei period, but the history before the Meiji restoration is normally periodized with the use of names of political centers, such as the Kamakura period and Edo period (except for the periods for which the political center cannot be ascertained, such as the Yayoi period and Sengoku period); thus there comes up a view that calling the periods after the Meiji restoration with their gengo is inappropriate.</e>
<cmt>元号の意味がわからないと、次の地名による時代区分との差異が読めないので、元号に name for an emperor&apos;s period of reignと入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the history after the Meiji restoration is generally periodized with the use of gengo (name for an emperor&apos;s period of reign), such as the Meiji period, Taisho period, Showa period and Heisei period, but the history before the Meiji restoration is normally periodized with the use of names of political centers, such as the Kamakura period and Edo period (except for the periods for which the political center cannot be ascertained, such as the Yayoi period and Sengoku period); thus there comes up a view that calling the periods after the Meiji restoration with their gengo is inappropriate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>その意見に基づけば、明治維新以後は政治の中心が東京にあったのであるから、「東京時代」として一括されるべきではないかというのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They think that the period after the Meiji restoration should be collectively referred to as the &quot;Tokyo period&quot; because the political center has lain in Tokyo since then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that viewpoint, the period of time after the Meiji restoration should be collectively referred to as the &quot;Tokyo period&quot; because the political center has existed in Tokyo since the restoration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that viewpoint, the period of time after the Meiji restoration should be collectively referred to as the &quot;Tokyo period&quot; because the political center has existed in Tokyo since the restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、東京時代と言っても大日本帝国憲法下と日本国憲法下では政治体制に大きな違いがある事や、100年以上前と現在を一括した呼称となるだけに違和感を抱かれる事が多いのか、一部の本で近現代（近代と現代）の日本を指す呼称として用いられるケースもあるものの、一般においては全く使われていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Tokyo period&quot; is not generally used at all, except being used in some books as naming of modern and contemporary Japan, because the political systems under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and those under the Constitution of Japan were quite different and because it may seem strange to use the same naming for the period of nearly a hundred years ago and the present day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the term &quot;Tokyo period&quot; is not used in general, except in some books that use the term to refer to modern or contemporary Japan, probably because there is a big difference in political systems between Japan under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and Japan under the present Constitution of Japan, and because it may seem unnatural to call a period that stretches beyond 100 years with the same name.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the term &quot;Tokyo period&quot; is not used in general, except in some books that use the term to refer to modern or contemporary Japan, probably because there is a big difference in political systems between Japan under the Constitution of the Empire of Japan and Japan under the present Constitution of Japan, and because it may seem unnatural to call a period that stretches beyond 100 years with the same name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="5">
<j>こうした時代区分法は、現在から過去の歴史を区分して用いられる方法である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This periodization is a method to divide the present day and the past history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the periodization is a method to distinguish the present day from the past.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the periodization is a method to distinguish the present day from the past.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>だが、時代の変遷により、将来的に現在の時代区分の枠組みが変化する可能性は否定出来ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it cannot be denied that the present framework of periodization may change in the future according to changing times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it cannot be denied that the present framework of periodization may change in the future according to changing times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it cannot be denied that the present framework of periodization may change in the future according to changing times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>例えば将来的に東京からの首都移転が行われた場合、東京の改称が行われた場合などに、それ以前と以後を区別する必要性から、明治以後の歴史の一括表現としてこの言葉が用いられる可能性があると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, if the capital is relocated from Tokyo or if Tokyo is renamed, the term &quot;Tokyo period&quot; may be used for collectively referring to the period since the Meiji era in order to distinguish the times before and after such relocation or rename.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, if the capital is relocated from Tokyo or if Tokyo is renamed, the term &quot;Tokyo period&quot; may be used for collectively referring to the period since the Meiji era in order to distinguish the times before and after such relocation or rename.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, if the capital is relocated from Tokyo or if Tokyo is renamed, the term &quot;Tokyo period&quot; may be used for collectively referring to the period since the Meiji era in order to distinguish the times before and after such relocation or rename.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tiyoringo(id:70026), Point136(id:211299), Damdamdamd(id:109603), Nevylax(id:38464), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>