<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>明治十四年の政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>明治十四年の政変（めいじじゅうよねんのせいへん）は、1881年（明治14年）自由民権運動の流れの中、憲法制定論議が高まり、政府内でも君主大権を残すビスマルク憲法かイギリス型の議院内閣制の憲法とするかで争われ、前者を支持する伊藤博文が、後者を支持する大隈重信を政府から追放した政治事件をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881) is a politically-motivated incident, which occurred during movement of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights and dispute regarding creation of a constitution in government, especially between Hirobumi ITO, who recommended Bismarck&apos;s constitution, which preserves the royal prerogative and Shigenobu OKUMA, who recommended constitution from England, which has parliamentary system of government, as a result of the incident Shigenobu Okuma was banned from government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881) is a politically-motivated incident, which occurred during movement of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights and dispute regarding creation of a constitution in government, especially between Hirobumi ITO, who recommended Bismarck&apos;s constitution, which preserves the royal prerogative and Shigenobu OKUMA, who recommended constitution from England, which has parliamentary system of government, as a result of the incident in which Shigenobu OKUMA was banned from government.</e>
<cmt>・incidentの後は関係代名詞が必要です。・指示に従って、Shigenobu Okumaは名字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen (the failed Meiji-14 coup of 1881) is a politically-motivated incident, which occurred during movement of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights and dispute regarding creation of a constitution in government, especially between Hirobumi ITO, who recommended Bismarck&apos;s constitution, which preserves the royal prerogative and Shigenobu OKUMA, who recommended constitution from England, which has parliamentary system of government, as a result of the incident in which Shigenobu OKUMA was banned from government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>この事件により後に制定される大日本帝国憲法は君主大権を残すドイツ憲法を範とされることが決まったといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident resulted in later formulation of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan, which modeled after the Constitution of the German Empire, which preserves the royal prerogative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident resulted in later formulation of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan, which modeled after the Constitution of the German Empire, which preserves the royal prerogative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident resulted in later formulation of the Constitution of the Empire of Japan, which modeled after the Constitution of the German Empire, which preserves the royal prerogative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>立憲体制の導入を巡る議論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dispute regarding introduction of constitutional government system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dispute regarding introduction of constitutional government system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dispute regarding introduction of constitutional government system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>大久保利通亡き後、明治政府はいつ立憲体制に移行するかという疑問が持ち上がっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Toshimichi OKUBO, there was a dispute among the government regarding transitional period to constitutional government system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Toshimichi OKUBO, there was a dispute among the government regarding transitional period to constitutional government system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Toshimichi OKUBO, there was a dispute among the government regarding transitional period to constitutional government system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そのような状況下で、消極論者の右大臣岩倉具視を擁しながら、漸進的な伊藤博文・井上馨（長州閥）とやや急進的な大隈重信（参議・大蔵卿・肥前藩出身）を中心に運営されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the condition, the dispute regarding introduction of constitutional government system was led by Tomomi IWAKIRA, Minister of the Right, was in a passive attitude, Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, aimed gradual introduction (Choshu clique), and Shigenobu OKUMA (Sangi, Okura-kyo (Minister of the Treasury), from Hizen Domain), aimed earlier introduction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the condition, the dispute regarding introduction of constitutional government system was led by Tomomi IWAKURA, Minister of the Right, who was in a passive attitude, Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, who aimed gradual introduction (Choshu clique), and Shigenobu OKUMA (Sangi, Okura-kyo [Minister of the Treasury], from Hizen Domain), who aimed earlier introduction.</e>
<cmt>・IWAKIRAはIWAKURAのスペルミスです。・それぞれの修飾節で関係代名詞が抜けています。・指示に従って、括弧の中の括弧は[]としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the condition, the dispute regarding introduction of constitutional government system was led by Tomomi IWAKURA, Minister of the Right, who was in a passive attitude, Hirobumi ITO and Kaoru INOUE, who aimed gradual introduction (Choshu clique), and Shigenobu OKUMA (Sangi, Okura-kyo [Minister of the Treasury], from Hizen Domain), who aimed earlier introduction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大隈重信は政府内にあって、大隈財政（西南戦争後の財政赤字を外債によって克服しようと考えていた）を巡って松方正義らと対立していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the government, Shigenobu OKUMA was opposed to Masayoshi MATSUKATA, regarding his financial policy (After the Seinan War, OKUMA aimed to overcome financial deficit by foreign debt).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the government, Shigenobu OKUMA was opposed to Masayoshi MATSUKATA, regarding his financial policy (After the Seinan War, OKUMA aimed to overcome financial deficit by foreign debt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the government, Shigenobu OKUMA was opposed to Masayoshi MATSUKATA, regarding his financial policy (After the Seinan War, OKUMA aimed to overcome financial deficit by foreign debt).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>更に宮中にいた保守的な宮内省官僚も「天皇親政」を要求して政治への介入工作を行うなど、政情は不安定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, conservative bureaucracy required &quot;direct rule by the emperor&quot; and stepped in government, at that time political situation was unstable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, conservative Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) bureaucrats required &quot;direct rule by the emperor&quot; and intervened in the government, at that time political situation was unstable.</e>
<cmt>・官僚はbureaucratです。・ここではgovernmentは定冠詞が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, conservative Kunaisho (Ministry of the Sovereign&apos;s Household) bureaucrats required &quot;direct rule by the emperor&quot; and intervened in the government, at that time political situation was unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1880年に入ると、立憲体制に消極的であった岩倉も自由民権運動への対応から、参議や諸卿から今後の立憲体制導入の手法について意見を求めることにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1880, IWAKURA, who was in a passive attitude to constitutional government started to request opinions from Sangi (councilor) and ministers to deal the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1880, Iwakura, who was in a passive attitude to constitutional government started to request opinions from Sangi (councilor) and ministers to deal with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement.</e>
<cmt>・IWAKURAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・dealはdeal withが適切と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1880, Iwakura, who was in a passive attitude to constitutional government started to request opinions from Sangi (councilor) and ministers to deal with the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>伊藤は同年暮れに意見書を提出し、漸進的な改革と上院設置のための華族制度改革を提議した（後者は公家出身の岩倉が嫌う点であるが、伊藤は敢えて提出したのである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ITO submitted written opinion and proposed gradual reform and reform of new peerage system to set up a upper house (IWAKIRA, who was from court noble family disliked the latter opinion but ITO submitted this daringly).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ito submitted written opinion and proposed gradual reform and reform of new peerage system to set up a upper house (IWAKIRA, who was from court noble family disliked the latter opinion but ITO submitted this daringly).</e>
<cmt>・ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ito submitted written opinion and proposed gradual reform and reform of new peerage system to set up a upper house (IWAKIRA, who was from court noble family disliked the latter opinion but ITO submitted this daringly).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>ただし、どこの国の制度を参考にするかは明らかにしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, ITO didn&apos;t mention from which country he will have a model of the system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ito didn&apos;t mention from which country he will have a model of the system.</e>
<cmt>・ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ito didn&apos;t mention from which country he will have a model of the system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>伊藤に相前後して参議らから次々に意見書が出され、様々な意見が出される中で1人大隈だけが意見書の提出を先延ばしにしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before and after ITO&apos;s submission, opinions were proposed by Sangi but only OKUMA postponed submission of his opinion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before and after Ito&apos;s submission, opinions were proposed by Sangi but only Okuma postponed submission of his opinion.</e>
<cmt>・ITOとOKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before and after Ito&apos;s submission, opinions were proposed by Sangi but only Okuma postponed submission of his opinion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>1881年3月、漸く大隈が左大臣（岩倉からみて上位）の有栖川宮熾仁親王に対して「密奏」という形で意見書を提出、その中でイギリス流の立憲君主制国家を標榜し、早期の憲法公布と国会の2年後開設を主張したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1881, finally OKUMA secretly submitted opinions to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, Minister of the left (higher rank than IWAKURA), recommended constitutional monarchy from England and insisted earlier issue of constitution and establishment of the National Diet two years later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1881, finally Okuma secretly submitted opinions to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, Minister of the left (higher rank than Iwakura), recommended constitutional monarchy from England and insisted on earlier issue of constitution and establishment of the National Diet in two years.</e>
<cmt>・OKUMAおよびIWAKURAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・insistの後はonが適切です。・two years laterは意味が変わってくるので、in two yearsとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1881, finally Okuma secretly submitted opinions to Imperial Prince Arisugawanomiya Taruhito, Minister of the left (higher rank than Iwakura), recommended constitutional monarchy from England and insisted on earlier issue of constitution and establishment of the National Diet in two years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>5月に内容を知った岩倉はその内容とともに自分を無視して熾仁親王に極秘裏に意見書を出した経緯に激怒、太政官大書記官の井上毅に意見を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May IWAKURA came to know the contents of the proposal and got very angry about the contents and the fact that OKUMA ignored IWAKURA and submitted the written proposal to Imperial Prince Taruhito, then IWAKURA consulted with Kowashi INOUE.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May, Iwakura came to know the contents of the proposal, got very angry about the contents and the fact that Okuma ignored Iwakura, and submitted the written proposal to Imperial Prince Taruhito, and then Iwakura consulted with Kowashi INOUE.</e>
<cmt>・OKUMAとIWAKURAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・文頭の前置詞句の後は、読みやすさのためコンマを入れました。・then Iwakuraの前にはandが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May, Iwakura came to know the contents of the proposal, got very angry about the contents and the fact that Okuma ignored Iwakura, and submitted the written proposal to Imperial Prince Taruhito, and then Iwakura consulted with Kowashi INOUE.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>井上毅は大隈案と福澤諭吉の民権論（『民情一新』）との類似点を指摘して、一刻も早い対抗策を出す事を提言した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kowashi INOUE pointed out the similarities between OKUMA&apos;s proposal and Minken-ron (&quot;Minjo-isshin&quot;) and recommended to propose a counter plan as soon as possible, then INOUE made a proposal that a state system modeled after the Kingdom of Prussia that established German Empire and had the royal prerogative has was appropriate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kowashi INOUE pointed out the similarities between Okuma&apos;s proposal and Minken-ron (democratic right theory) (&quot;Minjo-isshin&quot; [The transition of people&apos;s way of thinking]) by Yukichi FUKUZAWA and recommended to propose a counter plan as soon as possible.</e>
<cmt>・OKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・民情一新→Minjo-isshin (The transition of people&apos;s way of thinking)と仮訳を当てました。定訳不明です。・「福澤諭吉」が訳漏れです。・has wasのhasを削除しました。・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kowashi INOUE pointed out the similarities between Okuma&apos;s proposal and Minken-ron (democratic right theory) (&quot;Minjo-isshin&quot; [The transition of people&apos;s way of thinking]) by Yukichi FUKUZAWA and recommended to propose a counter plan as soon as possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>岩倉の命令を受けた井上はドイツ帝国を樹立したプロシア王国式に倣った君権主義国家が妥当とする意見書を作成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue made a proposal that a state system modeled after the Kingdom of Prussia, which established German Empire and had the royal prerogative, was appropriate.</e>
<cmt>・that establishedは非制限用法が適切と思われますので修正しました。・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue made a proposal that a state system modeled after the Kingdom of Prussia, which established German Empire and had the royal prerogative, was appropriate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>だが、大隈の密奏も岩倉・井上毅の意見書も他の政府首脳には詳細が明かされなかったために、伊藤がこの事情を知ったのは6月末であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, because the details of the secret proposal made by OKUMA and the written opinions by IWAKURA and INOUE were not notified to government leaders, ITO finally came to know the situation at the end of June.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, because the details of the secret proposal made by Okuma and the written opinions by Iwakura and Inoue were not disclosed to government leaders, Ito finally came to know the situation at the end of June.</e>
<cmt>・ITO、IWAKURA、INOUE、OKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・notifiedはこの形では目的語が不適切ですので、disclosedに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, because the details of the secret proposal made by Okuma and the written opinions by Iwakura and Inoue were not disclosed to government leaders, Ito finally came to know the situation at the end of June.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、伊藤は大隈に対してのみではなく、岩倉・井上毅が勝手にプロシア式の導入を進めようとしていた事に対しても激怒して、説明に来た井上毅を罵倒した（6月30日）上で太政大臣三条実美に辞意を伝えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ITO got very angry not only at OKUMA but also the fact that IWAKURA and INOUE planned to introduce Prussia style secretly, so he took down Kowashi INOUE when INOUE came to visit him to explain (on June 30) and told his resignation to Sanetomi SANJO, Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ito got very angry not only at Okuma but also the fact that Iwakura and Inoue planned to introduce Prussia style secretly, so he took down Kowashi INOUE when Inoue came to visit him to explain (on June 30) and told his own resignation to Sanetomi SANJO, Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt>・ITO、OKUMA、IWAKURA、INOUEは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・his resignationだと誰かわかりづらいため、ownを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ito got very angry not only at Okuma but also the fact that Iwakura and Inoue planned to introduce Prussia style secretly, so he took down Kowashi INOUE when Inoue came to visit him to explain (on June 30) and told his own resignation to Sanetomi SANJO, Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>岩倉は伊藤に辞意の翻意を求め、井上毅も国家基盤を安定させてからイギリス流の議院内閣制に移行する方法もあるとして、自説への賛同を求めたが、伊藤はイギリス式かプロシア式かは今決める事ではないとして、岩倉が唱える「大隈追放」にも否定的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IWAKURA asked ITO not to resign and INOUE recommended the plan to switch to parliamentary Cabinet system from England after stabilizing state infrastructure, however ITO didn&apos;t made a decision on England style or Prussia style and agreed with banishment of OKUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura asked Ito not to resign and Kowashi INOUE recommended and asked for the approval of the plan to switch to parliamentary Cabinet system from England after stabilizing state infrastructure; however, Ito didn&apos;t made a decision on whether to adopt England style or Prussia style and did not agree with banishment of Okuma, either.</e>
<cmt>・IWAKURA、ITOおよびOKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・howeverは接続詞ではないため、直前にセミコロンを追加しました。・訳漏れです。・誤訳があります。（agreedと訳されていますが、「否定的」なので逆です。）・decision on England style or Prussia styleは不自然な表現ですので、whether to adoptを挿入しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura asked Ito not to resign and Kowashi INOUE recommended and asked for the approval of the plan to switch to parliamentary Cabinet system from England after stabilizing state infrastructure; however, Ito didn&apos;t made a decision on whether to adopt England style or Prussia style and did not agree with banishment of Okuma, either.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この間にも井上毅が伊藤の盟友・井上馨（当初は将来的な議院内閣制導入を唱えていた）を自派に引き入れ、伊藤が薩摩藩藩閥と結んでまず憲法制定・議会開催時期の決定することを求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this time, Kowashi INOUE convinced Kaoru INOUE, a sworn allies of ITO (INOUE thought of introduction of parliamentary Cabinet system in future) and asked ITO to cooperate with Satsuma domain clique and decide on establishment of a constitution and the time of opening a parliament.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this time, Kowashi INOUE convinced Kaoru INOUE, a sworn ally of Ito (Inoue thought of introduction of parliamentary Cabinet system in future), and asked Ito to cooperate with Satsuma domain clique and decide on establishment of a constitution and the time of opening a parliament.</e>
<cmt>・a sworn allies→a sworn allyです。・ITOとINOUE（二つ目）は名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・括弧の後に挿入句を閉じるコンマが必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this time, Kowashi INOUE convinced Kaoru INOUE, a sworn ally of Ito (Inoue thought of introduction of parliamentary Cabinet system in future), and asked Ito to cooperate with Satsuma domain clique and decide on establishment of a constitution and the time of opening a parliament.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>明治十四年の政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji juyonen no seihen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji juyonen no seihen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>一方、自由民権運動は3月に起きたロシア帝国のアレクサンドル2世暗殺事件の影響で過激な論調が現れるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, among the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, radical opinions were expressed after assassination of Alexander II of the Russia Empire on March.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, radical opinions were expressed after assassination of Alexander II of the Russia Empire in March.</e>
<cmt>・on March→in Marchが正です。・on the other handの後のamongは「運動の中で」の意味なのでinが適切と思われます。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, radical opinions were expressed after assassination of Alexander II of the Russia Empire in March.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そんな折の7月末に「東京横浜毎日新聞」及び「郵便報知新聞」のスクープにより、開拓使長官の黒田清隆が同郷の政商五代友厚に格安の金額で官有物払下げを行うことが明るみに出た（開拓使官有物払下げ事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end of July, Yokohama Mainichi Shinbun (Yokohama Daily Newspaper) and Yubin Hochi Shinbun(Post Dispatch Newspaper) got a scoop that Kiyotaka KURODA, chief of Hokkaido Development Commissioner was planning to sell government owned facilities and equipments to Tomoatsu GODAI who was from the same village at a very cheap price(開拓使官有物払下げ事件), then criticism towards government became stronger and the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement was pumped up.</e>
<cmt>※開拓使官有物払下げ事件：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of July, Tokyo Yokohama Mainichi Shinbun (Tokyo Yokohama Daily Newspaper) and Yubin Hochi Shinbun (Post Dispatch Newspaper) got a scoop that Kiyotaka KURODA, chief of Hokkaido Development Commissioner, was planning to sell government owned facilities and equipment to Tomoatsu GODAI, who was from the same village, at very cheap prices (Kaitakushi Kanyubutsu Haraisage Jiken [Incident of Development Commissioner&apos;s Selling of Government-Owned Facilities and Equipment]).</e>
<cmt>・括弧内の不要なスペースを削除しました。・文頭の句には前置詞が必要ですので追加しました。・訳漏れです（東京横浜毎日新聞）。・commissionerの後には挿入句を閉じるコンマが必要です。・equipmentは不可算名詞です。・GODAIの後は非制限用法が適切なのでコンマが必要です。同様にvillageの後もコンマが必要です。・値段はそれぞれの物によって異なるはずですので複数形が適切と思われます。・開拓使官有物払下げ事件→Kaitakushi Kanyubutsu Haraisage Jiken (Incident of Development Commissioner&apos;s Selling of Government-Owned Facilities and Equipment) [読み方・定訳不明です]・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of July, Tokyo Yokohama Mainichi Shinbun (Tokyo Yokohama Daily Newspaper) and Yubin Hochi Shinbun (Post Dispatch Newspaper) got a scoop that Kiyotaka KURODA, chief of Hokkaido Development Commissioner, was planning to sell government owned facilities and equipment to Tomoatsu GODAI, who was from the same village, at very cheap prices (Kaitakushi Kanyubutsu Haraisage Jiken [Incident of Development Commissioner&apos;s Selling of Government-Owned Facilities and Equipment]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>そうすると、政府への強い批判が起こり自由民権運動が一層の盛り上がりを見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, criticism towards the government became stronger and the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement was pumped up.</e>
<cmt>・governmentは定冠詞が必要です。・一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, criticism towards the government became stronger and the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement was pumped up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>更に大蔵省内の大隈派が黒田の払い下げ内容が不当に廉価であるとして中止を公然と主張したことから、伊藤が大隈派の「利敵行為」に激怒して一転して「大隈追放」に賛成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, political faction of OKUMA at the Okura-sho (Ministry of the Treasury) criticized KURODA regarding the cheap sales price and called for stop of the sale, ITO got very angry because he considered this as contributions to enemies, ITO completely changed his opinion and agreed on banishment of OKUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, political faction of Okuma at the Okura-sho (Ministry of the Treasury) criticized Kuroda regarding the cheap sales prices and called for stop of the sales publicly; hence, Ito got very angry because he considered this as contributions to enemies and completely changed his opinion, agreeing with the banishment of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>・OKUMA、KURODA、ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・priceは複数あると思われますので複数にしました。・saleも同様に複数にしました。・訳漏れです（「公然と」）。・複数の文が不完全につながっていたため、修正しました。合わせて表現も若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, political faction of Okuma at the Okura-sho (Ministry of the Treasury) criticized Kuroda regarding the cheap sales prices and called for stop of the sales publicly; hence, Ito got very angry because he considered this as contributions to enemies and completely changed his opinion, agreeing with the banishment of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>8月31日、政府は大隈と民権陣営が結託した上での陰謀と断じて大隈の追放を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 31, the government determined that OKUMA and supporters of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement cooperated on the dark plot and decided banishment of OKUMA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 31, the government determined that Okuma and supporters of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement cooperated on the dark plot, and thus decided the banishment of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>・OKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・現状ではdecidedの主語が誤読されるため、表現を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 31, the government determined that Okuma and supporters of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement cooperated on the dark plot, and thus decided the banishment of Okuma.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>政府内で払下げに反対していた大隈の処分と反政府運動の鉾先を収めるため、岩倉具視（ただし岩倉は7月から10月まで休養を取って有馬温泉に行っていたので現在では岩倉の関与を否定し、伊藤が主な計画者とする説が有力。）、参議伊藤博文、井上毅らは協議を行い、明治天皇の行幸に大隈が同行している間に大隈の罷免、払下げ中止、10年後の国会開設などの方針を決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding punishment of OKUMA who was against the sale in government and cooling down the movement against government, Tomomi IWAKURA (However, IWAKURA was on vacation in Arima-onsen (hot spring) from July to October, today there is doubt about involvement of IWAKURA and ITO is considered as a main plotter), Hirobumi ITO, a Sangi and Kowashi INOUE discussed about dismissal of OKUMA, stop of the sales of government owned facilities and equipments and establishment of the National Diet after 10 years during OKUMA was away for a trip with Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the punishment of Okuma, who was against the sale in government, and cooling down the movement against the government, Tomomi IWAKURA (However, because Iwakura was on vacation in Arima-onsen (hot spring) from July to October, today there is doubt about involvement of Iwakura, and Ito is considered as a main plotter), Hirobumi ITO, a Sangi, and Kowashi INOUE discussed about dismissal of Okuma, stop of the sales of government owned facilities and equipment and establishment of the National Diet after 10 years while Okuma was away for a trip with Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>・punishmentの前に定冠詞が必要です。・OKUMA、IWAKURA、ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・who was against～governmentは非制限用法なので、前後にコンマを入れました。・governmentには定冠詞が必要です。・括弧内のHoweverは接続詞ではないため、後にbecauseを入れました。・a Sangiの後にはコンマが必要です。・duringはこのようには使えませんのでwhileにしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the punishment of Okuma, who was against the sale in government, and cooling down the movement against the government, Tomomi IWAKURA (However, because Iwakura was on vacation in Arima-onsen (hot spring) from July to October, today there is doubt about involvement of Iwakura, and Ito is considered as a main plotter), Hirobumi ITO, a Sangi, and Kowashi INOUE discussed about dismissal of Okuma, stop of the sales of government owned facilities and equipment and establishment of the National Diet after 10 years while Okuma was away for a trip with Emperor Meiji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>天皇が行幸から帰京した10月11日に御前会議の裁許を得て、翌日国会開設の詔勅などが公表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 11, after Emperor came back from gyoko (imperial visit), a permission of conference in the presence of the emperor was given and the Imperial Edict for Establishing a Diet was disclosed in public on the next day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 11, after Emperor came back from gyoko (imperial visit), a permission of conference in the presence of the emperor was given and the Imperial Edict for Establishing a Diet was disclosed in public on the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 11, after Emperor came back from gyoko (imperial visit), a permission of conference in the presence of the emperor was given and the Imperial Edict for Establishing a Diet was disclosed in public on the next day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>なお、この際に以下のような政府首脳間の合意が為された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt>※意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。　「建国の本各源流を殊にす。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On this occasion, the following agreement was made among government leaders.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On this occasion, the following agreement was made among government leaders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>「建国の本各源流を殊にす。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">建国の本各源流を殊にす。&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処※意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。　「建国の本各源流を殊にす。」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">建国の本各源流を殊にす。&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>「彼れを以て此れに移すべからず。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">彼れを以て此れに移すべからず。&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処※意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。「彼れを以て此れに移すべからず」</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">彼れを以て此れに移すべからず。&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>結果として自由民権運動や大隈の唱えるフランス流やイギリス流を否定したものの、岩倉らの進めようとしたプロシア流についても一旦は白紙撤回されることとなった（勿論、これによってプロシア（ドイツ）流論者の政府内での立場が強化されたのは事実であるが）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The agreement among government leaders was made, as a result, the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement and France style and England style which recommended by OKUMA were rejected but also Prussia style which recommended by IWAKURA was called of (as a result, people advocated Prussia (Germany) style strengthened their position).</e>
<cmt>※意味解釈が困難なため訳出できず。　彼れを以て此れに移すべからず」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, France style and England style, which were recommended by Okuma, were rejected but also Prussia style, which was recommended by Iwakura, was rejected (as a result, people who advocated Prussia (Germany) style strengthened their position).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処・分割したため文頭を一部削除しました。・France styleの前のandは不要です。・which recommended～Okumaは非制限用法のため前後にコンマを入れました。・OKUMA、IWAKURAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・which recommendedは動詞が自動詞ではないため、which was/were recommendedが正です。・called ofは意味が不明なので、rejectedとしました。・people advocatedは関係代名詞が必要です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement, France style and England style, which were recommended by Okuma, were rejected but also Prussia style, which was recommended by Iwakura, was rejected (as a result, people who advocated Prussia (Germany) style strengthened their position).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="30">
<j>野に下った大隈は10年後の国会開設に備え、翌1882年3月には小野梓とともに立憲改進党を結成、また10月、東京専門学校（現・早稲田大学）を早稲田に開設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKUMA left the government and started preparation for establishment of the National Diet 10 years later, in March 1882 next year, he set up the Constitutional Progressive Party with Azusa ONO and established Tokyo Senmon Gakko (present-day Waseda University) in Waseda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okuma left the government and started preparation for establishment of the National Diet, which had been targeted at 10 years later, and in March 1882, the next year, he set up the Constitutional Progressive Party with Azusa ONO and established Tokyo Senmon Gakko (present-day Waseda University) in Waseda.</e>
<cmt>・OKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・10 years laterは誤訳です。表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okuma left the government and started preparation for establishment of the National Diet, which had been targeted at 10 years later, and in March 1882, the next year, he set up the Constitutional Progressive Party with Azusa ONO and established Tokyo Senmon Gakko (present-day Waseda University) in Waseda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>一方、既にプロシア式の憲法導入に積極的であった岩倉や井上毅と違い、政変後の伊藤個人は立憲体制導入の決意は固めていたものの、どの形態を採るかについてはまだ確信は得ていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, unlike IWAKURA and INOUE who advocated introduction of Prussia style constitution, even ITO had decided on introduction of constitutional government system, but he was still thinking about the style of the system even after the Meiji juyonen no seihen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, unlike Iwakura and Inoue, who advocated introduction of Prussia style constitution, even Ito had decided on introduction of constitutional government system, but he was still thinking about the style of the system even after the Meiji juyonen no seihen.</e>
<cmt>・IWAKURA、ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, unlike Iwakura and Inoue, who advocated introduction of Prussia style constitution, even Ito had decided on introduction of constitutional government system, but he was still thinking about the style of the system even after the Meiji juyonen no seihen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>また、華族制度改革や将来の内閣_(日本)制度導入を巡って、岩倉との間に見解の相違があることも明らかになってきた（岩倉は華族に維新の功臣が加えられることや既存の律令制・太政官制度に基づいた大臣制が廃止されることで、公家出身の自分が政府の中枢から排除されることを警戒していた）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there was conflict of views between IWAKURA and ITO regarding reform of the peerage system and introduction of cabinet (Japan) system in future (IWAKURA worried about adding new meritorious retainers during the Meiji Restoration to the peerage and abolishment of institution of ministers based on existing the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code) and Dajokan (Great Council of State) system, because he thought he would be excluded from the center of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there was conflict of views between Iwakura and Ito regarding reform of the peerage system and introduction of cabinet (Japan) system in future (Iwakura worried about adding new meritorious retainers during the Meiji Restoration to the peerage and abolishment of institution of ministers based on existing the ritsuryo system [a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code] and Dajokan [Great Council of State] system, because he thought he would be excluded from the center of the government.)</e>
<cmt>・IWAKURA、ITOおよびOKUMAは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・括弧の中の括弧は指示に従って[]としました。・閉じ括弧がありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there was conflict of views between Iwakura and Ito regarding reform of the peerage system and introduction of cabinet (Japan) system in future (Iwakura worried about adding new meritorious retainers during the Meiji Restoration to the peerage and abolishment of institution of ministers based on existing the ritsuryo system [a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code] and Dajokan [Great Council of State] system, because he thought he would be excluded from the center of the government.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>このため、1882年伊藤はドイツ（プロシア）の憲法事情を研究するという名目でドイツを訪問した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore ITO went to Germany in 1882 to study constitution of Germany (Prussia), but it was not because of IWAKURA&apos;s recommendation, ITO thought the supporters of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement would study about England and France style, so he just chose what the supporter don&apos;t study (according to letters for Kencho SUEMATSU).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore Ito went to Germany in 1882 to study the circumstances around the constitution of Germany (Prussia).</e>
<cmt>・ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・一原文一訳文例外対処・「憲法事情」が訳出されていないため、表現を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore Ito went to Germany in 1882 to study the circumstances around the constitution of Germany (Prussia).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし、あくまでも岩倉の意に沿ったというだけではなく、単にイギリスやフランスの事は自由民権派の人達が研究するだろうから、彼らが研究しないドイツを選んだ（末松謙澄充ての書簡など）という選択に過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was not because of Iwakura&apos;s recommendation; instead, Ito thought that the supporters of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement would study about England and France styles, so he just chose what those supporter don&apos;t study (according to letters for Kencho SUEMATSU).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文例外対処・分割に伴って、文頭の表現を修正しました。・文のつなぎ方が不完全なため修正しました。・England and France styleは複数なのでstylesとしました。・the supportersは明確にするためthose supportersとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was not because of Iwakura&apos;s recommendation; instead, Ito thought that the supporters of the Freedom and People&apos;s Rights Movement would study about England and France styles, so he just chose what those supporter don&apos;t study (according to letters for Kencho SUEMATSU).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>伊藤がプロシア式の憲法導入の決意を固めたのは、現地で指導を受けたロレンツ・フォン・シュタインの助言（シュタイン自身はドイツの立憲体制を批判してドイツを追われた学者であったが、日本の国情を研究した上でむしろ日本の方がドイツ本国以上にプロシア式の条件に符合していると説いた）によるものであるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ITO decided on introduction of Prussia style constitution because of advise by Lorenz von Stein who lectured ITO in Germany (Stein was opposed to the constitutional government system in Germany and was exiled from Germany, but after he studied about Japan, he realized that the Prussia style constitutional government system would be more appropriate for Japan than Germany).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ito decided on introduction of Prussia style constitution because of advice by Lorenz von Stein, who lectured Ito in Germany (Stein was opposed to the constitutional government system in Germany and was exiled from Germany, but after he studied about Japan, he realized that the Prussia style constitutional government system would be more appropriate for Japan than for Germany).</e>
<cmt>・ITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・adviseは動詞なのでadviceとしました。・who lectured～は非制限用法であるべきなので、直前にコンマを入れました。・than Germanyは比較対象が不明確な表現なので、than for Germanyとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ito decided on introduction of Prussia style constitution because of advice by Lorenz von Stein, who lectured Ito in Germany (Stein was opposed to the constitutional government system in Germany and was exiled from Germany, but after he studied about Japan, he realized that the Prussia style constitutional government system would be more appropriate for Japan than for Germany).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>伊藤は1883年に岩倉の死に合わせるかのようにして帰国して、本格的な憲法制定作業に取り掛かることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IWAKURA died in 1883, ITO came back to Japan as if he was waiting for the right time, then he started to work on creation of a constitution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwakura died in 1883, and Ito came back to Japan as if he was waiting for this, and then he started to work on creation of a constitution.</e>
<cmt>・接続詞を入れました。・IWAKURAとITOは名字だけですので、指示に従って、頭文字だけ大文字にしました。・the right timeは「岩倉の死」のことであるべきなので、thisに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwakura died in 1883, and Ito came back to Japan as if he was waiting for this, and then he started to work on creation of a constitution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 EULE(id:74209), Straysheep(id:42448), 明治(id:110234), Rambler(id:59491), 水野白楓(id:22811), 小太刀(id:18154), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>