<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>近江令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi-Ryo (Omi Administrative Code)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>近江令（おうみりょう）は、日本の飛鳥時代（天智天皇の治世）に制定されたとされる法令体系。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi-Ryo is a legal system, believed to be enacted in the Asuka Period (during the reign of the Emperor Tenchi) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi-Ryo is a legal system, believed to have been enacted in the Asuka Period (during the reign of the Emperor Tenchi) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>過去の出来事についてなので、時制を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi-Ryo is a legal system, believed to have been enacted in the Asuka Period (during the reign of the Emperor Tenchi) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>全22巻。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a 22-volume series.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a 22-volume series.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a 22-volume series.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>古代日本政府による最初の律令法に位置づけられるが、原本は現存せず、存在を裏付ける史料にとぼしいことから、存在説と非存在説の間で激しい論争が続いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the first Ritsuryo code by the ancient Japanese government but because there is no original book remaining, and no historical sources which can confirm the existence of the code, there have been fierce debates about its existence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the first Ritsuryo code by the ancient Japanese government but because there is neither the original book remaining nor historical sources which confirm the existence of the code, there have been fierce debates about its existence.</e>
<cmt>Neither-norを使ったほうが良いと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the first Ritsuryo code by the ancient Japanese government but because there is neither the original book remaining nor historical sources which confirm the existence of the code, there have been fierce debates about its existence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>両説とも、律が制定されなかったという点では、ほぼ見解が一致している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most people on both sides agree, however, that the code had not been enacted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most people on both sides agree, however, that the Ritsu part (the penal cord) was not enacted in this cord.</e>
<cmt>律は「律令cord」の一部なので、この点に関し訳出に誤りがあると思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most people on both sides agree, however, that the Ritsu part (the penal cord) was not enacted in this cord.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>存在説と非存在説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Did it exist or not?</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Did it exist or not?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Did it exist or not?</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>存在説の根拠は、下記の2つの記事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grounds for believing in its existence are in the two references below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The grounds for believing in its existence are in the two references below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The grounds for believing in its existence are in the two references below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「天智天皇の命令により藤原鎌足が天智元年（668年）に律令を編纂した」（『藤氏家伝』大織冠伝）及び「天智元年に令22巻を制定した。これが『近江朝廷之令』である」（『弘仁格式』序）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Firstly, &quot;By the order of the Emperor Tenchi, FUJIWARA no Kamatari compiled a Ritsuryo code in 668&quot; in the Taishokukanden (story of Kamatari) in the &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; (Biographies of the Fujiwara clan); and secondly &quot;A 22-volume series code was enacted in 668. It is &apos;Omi-chotei-no-ryo&apos; (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court)&quot; in the introduction of the &quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; (compilation of rules, regulations, and precedents).</e>
<cmt>『弘仁格式』はhttp://books.google.co.nz/books?id=nCJwEDzyxNgC&amp;pg=PA215&amp;lpg=PA215&amp;dq=Konin+Kyakushiki&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=O68YRbCzFL&amp;sig=hbCvk35PfxRL3agymGVXfoDvPAE&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=JJUjTPqwF9yAnAfDp4QB&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;ved=0CBYQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Konin%20Kyakushiki&amp;f=falseには&quot;amendments to penal and administrative law&quot;となっています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Firstly, the description in Taishokukanden (the story of Kamatari) in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; (Biographies of the Fujiwara clan): &quot;By the order of the Emperor Tenchi, FUJIWARA no Kamatari compiled a Ritsuryo code in 668&quot;; and secondly, the description in the introduction of &quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; (compilation of rules, regulations, and precedents): &quot;A 22-volume series code was enacted in 668. It is &apos;Omi-chotei-no-ryo&apos; (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court).&quot;</e>
<cmt>不必要なtheを省きました。The description in..を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Firstly, the description in Taishokukanden (the story of Kamatari) in &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; (Biographies of the Fujiwara clan): &apos;By the order of the Emperor Tenchi, FUJIWARA no Kamatari compiled a Ritsuryo code in 668&apos;; and secondly, the description in the introduction of &quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; (compilation of rules, regulations, and precedents): &apos;A 22-volume series code was enacted in 668. It is &quot;Omi-chotei-no-ryo&quot; (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court)&apos;.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーション調整</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当時は天智天皇のもとで政治体制の近代化が進められ、中国の諸制度の積極的な導入が行われており、その根幹となる律令（近江令）が当然に定められたはずと見るのが存在説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who believe that the code did exist consider that modernization of the government, promoted at that time under the Emperor Tenchi, by actively introducing rules and systems from China, would have required a Ritsuryo code (Omi-Ryo) to have been enacted as the basis of this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who believe that the code did exist consider that modernization of the government, which had been promoted at that time under the Emperor Tenchi through active introduction of rules and systems from China, would have required a Ritsuryo code (Omi-Ryo) to be enacted as the basis of it.</e>
<cmt>分かりやすいよう、文中半の表現を少し変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who believe that the code did exist consider that modernization of the government, which had been promoted at that time under the Emperor Tenchi through active introduction of rules and systems from China, would have required a Ritsuryo code (Omi-Ryo) to be enacted as the basis of it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>存在説の立場では、近江令は律令制導入へ至る先駆的かつ重要な法令であり、後の飛鳥浄御原令や大宝律令へ影響を与えたとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the believers, Omi-Ryo was a pioneering and important legal code toward the introduction of the Ritsuryo system, which had a great impact on Asukakiyomihararyo (the legal code of the Japanese ancient state of Asuka) and Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) later on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the believers, Omi-Ryo was a pioneering and important legal code toward the introduction of the Ritsuryo system, which had a great impact on Asukakiyomihararyo (the legal code of the Japanese ancient state of Asuka) and Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the believers, Omi-Ryo was a pioneering and important legal code toward the introduction of the Ritsuryo system, which had a great impact on Asukakiyomihararyo (the legal code of the Japanese ancient state of Asuka) and Taiho Ritsuryo (Taiho Code) later on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし、『藤氏家伝』も『弘仁格式』も後世（8～9世紀）に編纂されたものであり、正史の『日本書紀』には近江令制定の記事はない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, both &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; and &quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; were compiled later on (between the eighth and the ninth century) and there is no mention of the &quot;Omi-Ryo&quot; in the official history book the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>ninth</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, both &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; and &quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; were the documents compiled later (between the eighth and the ninth century) and there is no mention of the &quot;Omi-Ryo&quot; in the official history book &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>Theを除きました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, both &quot;Toshi Kaden&quot; and &quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; were the documents compiled later (between the eighth and the ninth century) and there is no mention of the &quot;Omi-Ryo&quot; in the official history book &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかし、天智9年(670年)条「朝庭の礼儀と行路の相避ることを宣う」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yet, in the Article of the year 670 of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, it states &quot;Pronounce the rules and rites of the court and how to properly meet or depart from people met on the road.&quot;</e>
<cmt>この「朝庭の礼儀と行路の相避ることを宣う」の解釈に自信がありません。でも、http://nihonshoki.wikidot.com/scroll-27-tenjiには&quot;On the 14th day, there was a pronouncement about the rules and rites of the court and how to properly meet or depart from people met on the road.&quot;とあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yet, in the Article of the year 670 of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, it states &quot;… pronounced the rules and rites of the court and how to properly meet or depart from people met on the road.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「」内は主語抜けの記述だと思いますが、この場合の主語が何になるか分かりませんので…としておきました（天智天皇かとも思いますが）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yet, in the Article of the year 670 of the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot;, it states &quot;The rules and rites of the court and how to properly meet or depart from people met on the road are pronounced.&quot;</e>
<cmt>主語が不明なため、受け身にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは令とともに礼を撰述させたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This means that the Emperor Tenchi ordered the writing of the code to include reference to courtesy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This means that the Emperor Tenchi ordered the writing of the code to include reference to courtesy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This means that the Emperor Tenchi ordered the writing of the code to include reference to courtesy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>天智10年(671年)に「冠位・法度の事を宣い行い給う」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; in 671 it also says &quot;Promise to do something about the current official ranking system and hatto (law and measurement).&quot;</e>
<cmt>「冠位・法度の事を宣い行い給う」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The article of the year 671 also describes &quot;… pronounced on and enacted kani (office and rank) and hatto (law and measurement).&quot;</e>
<cmt>上記と同様、主語が何になるか分かりませんので…としておきました（天智天皇かとも思いますが）。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The article of the year 671 also describes &quot;kani (office and rank) and hatto (law and measurement) are pronounced and enacted.&quot;</e>
<cmt>主語が不明なため、受け身にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、『弘仁格式』は、天智天皇系の皇統を重視した記述となっているため、天智天皇の業績をより大きく評価したものであると理解できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; wrote mainly about the imperial line of the Emperor Tenchi, so it is understood that the contents were to greatly exaggerate the Emperor&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; wrote mainly about the imperial line derived from the Emperor Tenchi, so it is understood that the contents were to greatly exaggerate the Emperor&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>こうした方がわかりやすいと思いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Konin Kyakushiki&quot; wrote mainly about the imperial line derived from the Emperor Tenchi, so it is understood that the contents were to greatly exaggerate the Emperor&apos;s achievements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これが非存在説の根拠である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These are the reasons that some people think the Omi-Ryo did not exist.</e>
<cmt>「これ」は「上記」＝複数と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are the reasons that some people think the Omi-Ryo did not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are the reasons that some people think the Omi-Ryo did not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>ただし、非存在説はいくつかの立場に分かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there are several different views for the non-existent theory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there are several different views about the non-existent theory.</e>
<cmt>前置詞を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there are several different views about the non-existent theory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>まったく令は存在しなかったとする説、天智期に制定された諸法令を総称して、後代に近江令と呼んだとする説、完全ではないがある程度の令が編纂されたとする説、ほぼ完全な形に近い令が編纂されたが施行は一部にとどまったとする説、などである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While some believe that the Omi-Ryo did not exist at all, others believe that all the laws and legislation enacted during the reign of the Emperor Tenchi were later called Omi-Ryo collectively; that the code was partially written but not completed, or that it was almost completed but only a part of it was executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While some believe that the Omi-Ryo did not exist at all, others believe that all the laws and legislation enacted during the reign of the Emperor Tenchi were later called Omi-Ryo collectively; that the code was partially written but not completed, or that it was almost completed but only a part of it was executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While some believe that the Omi-Ryo did not exist at all, others believe that all the laws and legislation enacted during the reign of the Emperor Tenchi were later called Omi-Ryo collectively; that the code was partially written but not completed, or that it was almost completed but only a part of it was executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>非存在説の主張は、律令制構築への動きについて、天智天皇よりも天武天皇の影響力の大きさを重視する傾向が強い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who do not believe in its existence tend to insist that the Emperor Tenmu had more impact on the process of constructing the Ritsuryo system than the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who do not believe in its existence tend to insist that the Emperor Tenmu had more impact on the process of constructing the Ritsuryo system than the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who do not believe in its existence tend to insist that the Emperor Tenmu had more impact on the process of constructing the Ritsuryo system than the Emperor Tenchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>近江朝廷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi Chotei (Omi Court)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi Chotei (Omi Court)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi Chotei (Omi Court)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>667年に天智天皇（当時中大兄皇子）は宮都を飛鳥から近江大津（近江宮）へ遷し、668年には即位し、新たな政治体制を発足させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the year 667, the Emperor Tenchi (then &quot;Naka no Oe no Oji&quot;, Prince Naka no Oe) moved the imperial capital from Asuka to Otsu in the Omi Province (Omi no miya), and took over the throne in 668 to start a new government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the year 667, the Emperor Tenchi (then &quot;Naka no Oe no Oji&quot;, Prince Naka no Oe) moved the imperial capital from Asuka to Otsu in the Omi Province (Omi no miya), and took over the throne in 668 to start a new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the year 667, the Emperor Tenchi (then &quot;Naka no Oe no Oji&quot;, Prince Naka no Oe) moved the imperial capital from Asuka to Otsu in the Omi Province (Omi no miya), and took over the throne in 668 to start a new government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この政治体制を近江朝廷（おうみちょうてい）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This new government was called &quot;Omi Chotei.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This new government was called &quot;Omi Chotei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This new government was called &quot;Omi Chotei.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>近江朝廷が668年に制定した法令なので『近江朝廷之令』または『近江令』と呼ばれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law was enacted by the Omi Chotei in 668, and is therefore called &quot;Omi-chotei-no-ryo&quot; (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court) or &quot;Omi-Ryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law was enacted by the Omi Chotei in 668, and is therefore called &quot;Omi-chotei-no-ryo&quot; (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court) or &quot;Omi-Ryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law was enacted by the Omi Chotei in 668, and is therefore called &quot;Omi-chotei-no-ryo&quot; (The Administrative Code of the Omi Court) or &quot;Omi-Ryo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="21">
<j>天智10年(671年)、大友皇子を太政大臣、蘇我赤兄・中臣金を左右大臣、蘇我果安以下三人を御史大夫とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 671, the Emperor made Otomo no Oji (Prince Otomo) the Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister), SOGA no Akane and NAKATOMI no Kane as the Sayu-daijin (Ministers of the Left and the Right) and three more including SOGA no Hatayasu as Gyoshi Taifu (Chiefs controlling the officials).</e>
<cmt>左右大臣と御史大夫は単数でいいか不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 671, the Emperor appointed Otomo no Oji (Prince Otomo) the Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister), SOGA no Akane and NAKATOMI no Kane as the Sayu-daijin (Ministers of the Left and the Right) and three more including SOGA no Hatayasu as Gyoshi Taifu (Chiefs controlling the officials).</e>
<cmt>asを使っているので、動詞をappointに変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 671, the Emperor appointed Otomo no Oji (Prince Otomo) Daijo-daijin (Grand Minister), SOGA no Akane and NAKATOMI no Kane as Sayu-daijin (Ministers of the Left and the Right) and three more including SOGA no Hatayasu as Gyoshi Taifu (Chiefs controlling the officials).</e>
<cmt>the を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これが近江令の官制である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the government system for the Omi-Ryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the government system made under the Omi-Ryo.</e>
<cmt>原文をこのように解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the government system established under the Omi-Ryo.</e>
<cmt>made→established</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>新しく太政大臣を置いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor created a new position of the Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor created a new position of the Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor created a new position of the Daijo-daijin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>御史大夫は、新しい官名で、後の納言の前身で、大化前代以来、大臣・大連の下にあった国政参議官、大夫の制を官制化したもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Gyoshi taifu was also a new official position, which was later changed to Nagon (councilor) and it was to make the system of Kokusei sangi kan (government councilor) and Daibu (master), which had been under Daijin (minister) and Omuraji (military chief) since before the Taika Reform, to the new government-regulated system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gyoshi Taifu was also a new official position, which was later changed to Nagon (councilor), and was to transform the system of Kokusei sangi kan (government councilor) and Daibu (master), which had been under Daijin (minister) and Omuraji (military chief) since before the Taika Reform, into the new government-regulated system.</e>
<cmt>単語の使用を少し(transformなど)変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gyoshi Taifu was also a new official position, which was later changed to Nagon (councilor), and was to transform the system of Kokusei sangi kan (government councilor) and Daibu (master), which had been under Daijin (minister) and Omuraji (military chief) since before the Taika Reform, into the new government-regulated system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="25">
<j>なお、近江朝廷が滅亡した672年（壬申の乱）に近江令が廃止されたとする意見がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is an opinion that Omi-Ryo was abolished when Omi Court was destroyed in 672 (in the Jinshin War).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is an opinion that Omi-Ryo was abolished when Omi Court was destroyed in 672 (in the Jinshin War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is an opinion that Omi-Ryo was abolished when Omi Court was destroyed in 672 (in the Jinshin War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shimoxx(id:9332), アスカ(id:9205), Yas(id:739), BAKU(id:55205), ごまふあざ(id:36855), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>