<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>侍</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>侍（さむらい）は、古代から中世にかけての日本における官人の身分呼称、あるいはそこから発展的に生じた武士の別名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Samurai&quot; is the positional title for officials in Japan from the ancient to middle ages, or the alternative name for &quot;bushi&quot; that was derived from the first meaning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Samurai&quot; is the positional title for officials in Japan from the ancient to middle ages, and an alternative name for &quot;bushi&quot; that was derived from the first meaning.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Samurai&quot; is the positional title for officials in Japan from the ancient to middle ages, and an alternative name for &quot;bushi&quot; (warrior) that was derived from the first meaning.</e>
<cmt>「”」→「&quot;」「&quot;bushi&quot;」→「&quot;bushi&quot;(warrior)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「伺候する」「従う」を意味する「さぶらう」に由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is derived from &quot;saburau&quot;, which means &quot;to attend&quot; or &quot;to follow&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is derived from &quot;saburau&quot;, which means &quot;to attend&quot; or &quot;to follow&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is derived from &quot;saburau&quot;, which means &quot;to attend&quot; or &quot;to follow&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「”」→「&quot;」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>成立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>元来は有力貴族や諸大夫に仕える位階六位どまりの下級技能官人層（侍品さむらいほん）を指すが、次第にその中でも武芸を職能とする技能官人である武士を指すことが多くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, this was the term for the class of low-ranking technical palace officials up to the sixth rank who worked for significant aristocracy and shodabu (ranking officials of fourth or fifth rank), but eventually was used to define the bushi, who were technical palace officials with military skills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, this was a term for the class of low-ranking technical palace officials up to the sixth rank who worked for aristocracy and shodabu (ranking officials of fourth or fifth rank), but eventually was used to define the bushi, who were technical palace officials with military skills.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, this was a term for the class of low-ranking technical palace officials up to the sixth rank who worked for aristocracy and Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo), but eventually was used to define the bushi, who were technical palace officials with military skills.</e>
<cmt>「shodabu (ranking officials of fourth or fifth rank)」→「Shodaibu (aristocracy lower than Kugyo)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>初期の武士身分は諸大夫身分の軍事貴族と、侍身分の一般武士のふたつの階層から構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position of bushi originally had two classes, the militaristic aristocracy with the position of shodaibu, and the ordinary bushi with the position of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position of bushi originally had two classes, the militaristic aristocracy with the position of shodaibu, and the ordinary bushi with the position of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position of bushi originally had two classes, the militaristic aristocracy with the position of shodaibu, and the ordinary bushi with the position of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>時代が下って武士階層の裾野が広がり、侍身分より下の地侍なども武士の扱いを受けるようになると、侍は上層の武士を指すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As time past, the range of bushi class was enlarged and jizamurai with positions lower than samurai where also considered as bushi and samurai began to indicate the upper class bushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As time passed, the range of bushi class was expanded and jizamurai with positions lower than samurai were also considered bushi while the term samurai began to indicate upper class bushi.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As time passed, the range of bushi class was expanded and jizamurai (local samurai) with positions lower than samurai were also considered bushi while the term samurai began to indicate upper class bushi.</e>
<cmt>「jizamurai」→「jizamurai (local samurai)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>たとえば、17世紀初頭に刊行された『日葡辞書』では、BuxiやMononofuはそれぞれ「武人」「軍人」という訳語が与えられているのに対して、Saburaiは「貴人、または尊敬すべき人」と訳されていることからも、侍が武士階層の中でも特別な存在であったことは窺えよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, the Vocabvlario da Lingoa de Iapam(Nipojisho, Japanese-Portuguese Dictionary) gave the meaning of the terms &quot;Buxi&quot; and &quot;Mononofu&quot; as &quot;bujin&quot; and, &quot;gunjin&quot;, respectively. However, &quot;Saburai&quot; was translated as &quot;a nobleman or person to be respected&quot;, suggesting that samurai were special people within the bushi class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, the Vocabvlario da Lingoa de Iapam(Nipojisho, Japanese-Portuguese Dictionary) gave the meaning of the terms &quot;Buxi&quot; and &quot;Mononofu&quot; as &quot;bujin&quot; and, &quot;gunjin&quot;, respectively. However, &quot;Saburai&quot; was translated as &quot;a nobleman or person to be respected&quot;, suggesting that samurai were special people within the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, &quot;the Vocabvlario da Lingoa de Iapam&quot; (Nipojisho, Japanese-Portuguese Dictionary), published in early seventeen century, gave the meaning of the terms Buxi and Mononofu as &apos;bujin&apos; (warrior) and &apos;gunjin&apos; (military man), respectively, however, Saburai was translated as &apos;a nobleman or person to be respected&apos;, suggesting that samurai were special people within the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>書名に「&quot;」をつけ、「, published in early seventeen century,」を追加し、「“」→「&quot;」「. However,」→「, however,」「&apos;bujin&apos;」→「&apos;bujin&apos; (warrior)」「&apos;gunjin&apos;」→「 &apos;gunjin&apos; (military man)」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>ちなみに、ここで言う上層とは、厳密には発生期の武士と同様に、騎馬戦闘の権利資格を有する階層の武士を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Strictly speaking, upper class bushi indicates the class of bushi who had the right to fight on horseback, which has been the definition of bushi since the beginning of the bushi class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Strictly speaking, upper class bushi indicates the class of bushi who had the right to fight on horseback, which had been used to define bushi since the beginning of the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Strictly speaking, upper class bushi indicates the class of bushi who had the right to fight on horseback, which had been used to define bushi since the beginning of the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>語源</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Origin of a Word</e>
<cmt>訳出しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>「サムライ」は16世紀になって登場した比較的新しい語形であり、鎌倉時代から室町時代にかけては「サブライ」、平安時代には「サブラヒ」とそれぞれ発音されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Samurai&quot; is a fairly recent pronunciation that arose in the 16th century, and it was pronounced &quot;saburai&quot; from the Kamakura to Muromachi Periods and &quot;saburahi&quot; in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Samurai&quot; is a fairly recent pronunciation that arose in the 16th century, and it was pronounced &quot;saburai&quot; from the Kamakura to Muromachi Periods and &quot;saburahi&quot; in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Samurai&quot; is a fairly recent pronunciation that arose in the sixteenth century; before that, it was pronounced &quot;saburai&quot; from the Kamakura period to the Muromachi period and &quot;saburahi&quot; in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>「サブラヒ」は動詞「サブラフ」の連用形が名詞化したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Saburahi&quot; is the conjunctive form of the verb, &quot;mandafu&quot; used as a noun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Saburahi&quot; is the conjunctive form of the verb, &quot;mandafu&quot; used as a noun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Saburahi&quot; is the conjunctive form of the verb &quot;saburafu&quot; (meaning to serve a higher-ranking person), and it can also be used as a noun.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>以下、「サブラフ」の語史について述べれば、まず奈良時代には「サモラフ」という語形で登場しており、これが遡り得る最も古い語形であるであると考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next is a short history of the word, &quot;mandafu&quot;. It first is found in the form &quot;samorahu&quot; in the Nara Period, and this is the oldest form that can be found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next is a short history of the word, &quot;mandafu&quot;. It first is found in the form &quot;samorahu&quot; in the Nara Period, and is the oldest form that can be found.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a brief history of the word &quot;saburafu&quot;. The oldest form of this word to have been found is &quot;samorafu&quot;, which made its appearance in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「サモラフ」は動詞「モラフ（候）」に語調を整える接頭語「サ」が接続したもので、「モラフ」は動詞「モル（窺・守）」に存在・継続の意の助動詞（動詞性接尾語ともいう）「フ」が接続して生まれた語であると推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Samorahu&quot; consists of the verb &quot;morahu (wait)&quot; with the prefix &quot;sa&quot; to fix the rhythm of the word. &quot;Morahu&quot; is thought to come from the verb &quot;moru (lookout, guard) and the verb suffix &quot;hu&quot; to add the meaning of existence or continuance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Samorahu&quot; consists of the verb &quot;morahu (wait)&quot; with the prefix &quot;sa&quot; to fix the rhythm of the word. &quot;Morahu&quot; is thought to come from the verb &quot;moru (lookout, guard) and the verb suffix &quot;hu&quot; to add the meaning of existence or continuance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Samorafu&quot; is a combination of the verb &quot;morafu&quot; (meaning wait) and the prefix &quot;sa&quot;, which was added to fix the rhythm of the word, and the verb &quot;morafu&quot; is thought to have come from the verb &quot;moru&quot; (meaning lookout, guard) and the suffix &quot;fu&quot;, which was added to include the nuance of &quot;existence&quot; or &quot;continuance&quot;.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その語構成からも窺えるように、「サモラフ」の原義は相手の様子をじっと窺うという意味であったが、奈良時代には既に貴人の傍らに控えて様子を窺いつつその命令が下るのを待つという意味でも使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As suggested from the word composition, the original meaning of &quot;samorahu&quot; had implications of carefully watching the opponent&apos;s actions. It was already used in the Nara Period to indicate waiting close to a nobleman on the look out and waiting until there was a command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As suggested from the word composition, the original meaning of &quot;samorahu&quot; had implications of carefully watching the opponent&apos;s actions. It was already used in the Nara Period to indicate waiting close to a nobleman on the look out and waiting until there was a command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As its roots suggest, the word &quot;samorafu&quot; originally conveyed the meaning of carefully watching an opponent&apos;s actions; in fact, it was already used in the Nara period to communicate the idea of waiting close by to a nobleman on the lookout while awaiting instructions.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>この「サモラフ」が平安時代に母音交替を起こしていったん「サムラフ」となり、更に子音交替を起こした結果「サブラフ」という語形が誕生したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a vowel exchange in the Heian Period that changed &quot;Samorahu&quot; to &quot;Samurahu&quot;, and a further consonant change led to the word form, &quot;mandafu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A vowel was replaced in the Heian Period that changed &quot;Samorahu&quot; to &quot;Samurahu&quot;, and a further consonant change led to the word form, &quot;mandafu&quot;.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A vowel was replaced in the Heian period that changed &quot;Samorahu&quot; to &quot;Samurahu,&quot; and a further consonant change led to the word form, &quot;mandafu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「”」→「&quot;」「Period」→「period」とし、「,」「.」の位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「サブラフ」は「侍」の訓としても使用されていることからもわかるように、平安時代にはもっぱら貴人の側にお仕えするという意味で使用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;mandafu&quot; was used to read the character &quot;侍&quot;, indicating that it was used as a word to indicate service to a nobleman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;mandafu&quot; was used to read the character &quot;侍&quot;, indicating that it was used as a word to indicate service to a nobleman.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;mandafu&quot; was used to read the character &quot;侍,&quot; indicating that it was used as a word to indicate service to a nobleman.</e>
<cmt>「”」→「&quot;」とし「,」の位置を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「侍」という漢字には、元来 「貴族のそばで仕えて仕事をする」という意味があるが、武士に類する武芸を家芸とする技能官人を意味するのは日本だけである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kanji &quot;侍&quot;, originally meant &quot;to work and serve a aristocrat at hand&quot;, but only in Japan is the word used to define the technical palace officials with military skills who belong to the bushi class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kanji &quot;侍&quot;, originally meant &quot;to work and serve a aristocrat at hand&quot;, but only in Japan is the word used to define the technical palace officials with military skills who belong to the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kanji (Chinese character) &quot;侍&quot; originally meant &quot;to be on hand to work for and serve an aristocrat,&quot; and only in Japan is the word used to refer to ginou kanjin (culturally and academically accomplished palace officials) with military skills who belonged to the bushi class.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>さてその「サブラフ」の連用形から平安時代に「サブラヒ」という名詞が生まれたわけであるが、その原義は「主君の側近くで面倒を見ること、またその人」で、後に朝廷に仕える官人でありながら同時に上級貴族に伺候した中下級の技能官人層を指すようになり、そこからそうした技能官人の一角を構成した「武士」を指すようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conjunctive form of &quot;mandafu&quot; became &quot;saburahi&quot; in the Heian Period, and the original meaning is &quot;a person who takes care and serves a lord by his side, or the act&quot;. This eventually indicated the technical palace officials of low to middle rank who served upper class aristocrats while serving the Imperial Court, and from this meaning, it became to indicate only one type of technical palace official, the &quot;bushi&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conjunctive form of &quot;mandafu&quot; became &quot;saburahi&quot; in the Heian Period, and the original meaning is &quot;a person who takes care and serves a lord by his side, or the act&quot;. This eventually indicated the technical palace officials of low to middle rank who served upper class aristocrats while serving the Imperial Court, and from this meaning, it came to indicate only one type of technical palace official, the &quot;bushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conjunctive form of &quot;saburafu&quot; became &quot;saburahi&quot; in the Heian period, and while this originally meant &quot;a person who is on hand to take care of and serve his/her lord&quot; (or the act of doing so), it later came to mean ginou kanjin of low to middle rank who served upper class aristocrats at the Imperial Court, before finally coming to indicate only one type of ginou kanjin: the &quot;bushi.&quot;</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>つまり、最初は武士のみならず、明法家などの他の中下級技能官人も「侍」とされたのであり、そこに武人を意味する要素はなかったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, &quot;samurai&quot; originally included not only &quot;bushi&quot; but also other low to middle ranking technical palace officials such as myobouka, and there was no particular implication of military men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, &quot;samurai&quot; originally included not only &quot;bushi&quot; but also other low to middle ranking technical palace officials such as myobouka, and there was no particular implication of military men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the word &quot;saburafu&quot; originally included the nuance of not only &quot;bushi&quot; but also other low- to middle-ranking ginou kanjin such as myoboke (legal experts), so it did not have the connotation of warrior or soldier.</e>
<cmt>FBに従って修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>前述したように、「サブラヒ」はその後「サブライ」→「サムライ」と語形変化を遂げていったが、地位に関係なく武士全般をこの種の語で呼ぶようになったのは、江戸時代近くからであり、それまでは貴族や将軍などの家臣である上級武士に限定されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As mentioned before, &quot;saburahi&quot; changed to &quot;saburai&quot; and then &quot;samurai&quot;, but this word was used to indicate bushi in general regardless of position from around the Edo Period, but until then, it was only used to indicate the aristocrats or higher-ranking bushi who were the vassals of the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As mentioned before, &quot;saburahi&quot; changed to &quot;saburai&quot; and then &quot;samurai,&quot; but this word was used to indicate bushi in general regardless of position from around the Edo Period, but until then, it was only used to indicate the aristocrats or higher-ranking bushi who were the vassals of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As mentioned before, &quot;saburahi&quot; changed to &quot;saburai&quot; and then &quot;samurai,&quot; but this word was used to indicate bushi in general regardless of position from around the Edo period, but until then, it was only used to indicate the aristocrats or higher-ranking bushi who were the vassals of the shogun.</e>
<cmt>「”」→「&quot;」「Period」→「period」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Avanzare(id:34657), KUROSAWA(id:46472), Bakkai(id:7233), Nana11(id:49980), HassY(id:4166), Ojigiri(id:329), Eskimbot(id:29676), Poporonbomber(id:8192), Halfd(id:145364), BAKU(id:55205), GIL.(id:2207), Yosri(id:9357), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Niboshi(id:46978), Qurren(id:20140), Akaniji(id:229701), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 水野白楓(id:22811), R-pro(id:7329), Tekken(id:546), Tanke(id:47583), Rusk(id:9895), SuisuiBot(id:10165), Sin19830503(id:86812), 健ちゃん(id:60346), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), 海衛士(id:19229), Ponsaku(id:31417), Safkan(id:423), Dump(id:26383), ウミユスリカ(id:9504), Pankepanke(id:71471), Suisui(id:69), Nerv4(id:38341), Binh Giang(id:79801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>