<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本統治時代 (台湾)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Period of Japanese rule (Taiwan)</e>
<cmt>日本統治時代→period of Japanese rule（Japan&apos;s rule よりJapanese ruleのほうが使用例が多いためこちらの表記にしました）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Period of Japanese rule (Taiwan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Period of Japanese rule (Taiwan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>台湾の日本統治時代（にっぽんとうちじだい）は、日清戦争の敗戦に伴い清朝が台湾を大日本帝国に割譲した1895年（明治28年）4月17日から、第二次世界大戦後の1945年（昭和1945年）10月25日、中華民国統治下に置かれるまでの植民地支配の約50年間を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period of Japanese rule of Taiwan refers to approximately 50 years of Taiwan governed by Japan as colony, from April 17, 1895 when the Qing dynasty ceded Taiwan to the Imperial Japan due to the defeat of the Sino-Japanese War to October 25, 1945 when Taiwan was put under the rule of the Republic of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period of Japanese rule of Taiwan refers to approximately fifty years that Taiwan was governed by Japan as colony, from April 17, 1895 when the Qing dynasty ceded Taiwan to Imperial Japan due to the defeat of the Sino-Japanese War to October 25, 1945 when Taiwan was put under the rule of the Republic of China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period of Japanese rule of Taiwan refers to approximately fifty years during which time Taiwan was governed by Japan as colony from April 17, 1895 when the Qing dynasty ceded Taiwan to Imperial Japan due to the defeat of the Sino-Japanese War to October 25, 1945 when Taiwan was put under the rule of the Republic of China.</e>
<cmt>fifty years の意味をより明確にするために that ではなく during which time としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、台湾では政治的立場や、歴史認識に対する観点の相違などによって、日本統治時代をそれぞれ日本時代、日治時代、日據時代、日本統治時期あるいは日本殖民時期と呼称しているが、日據時代と表記する場合については日本統治時代に対し批判的な意味合いがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Taiwan, the period of Japanese rule is called by different names such as &quot;日本時代&quot;,&quot;日治時代&quot;,&quot;日據時代&quot;,&quot;日本統治時期&quot; or &quot;日本殖民時期&quot;, depending on the political positions or historic perspectives, and &quot;日據時代&quot; implies a criticism of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Taiwan, the period of Japanese rule is called by different names such as &quot;日本時代&quot;,&quot;日治時代&quot;,&quot;日據時代&quot;,&quot;日本統治時期&quot; or &quot;日本殖民時期&quot;, depending upon the political positions or historic perspectives, and &quot;日據時代&quot; implies a criticism of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Taiwan, the period of Japanese rule is called by different names such as &quot;日本時代&quot;,&quot;日治時代&quot;,&quot;日據時代&quot;,&quot;日本統治時期&quot; or &quot;日本殖民時期&quot;, depending upon the political positions or historic perspectives, and &quot;日據時代&quot; implies a criticism of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>統治初期の政策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Policies in the early period of Japanese rule</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Policies during the early period of Japanese rule</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Policies during the early period of Japanese rule</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>日本統治の初期段階は1895年5月から1915年の西来庵事件までを第1期と区分することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early stage of Japanese rule is classified as the first phase between May 1895 and the Silaian Incident in 1915.</e>
<cmt>西来庵事件→Silaian Incident</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The early stage of Japanese rule is classified as the first phase between May 1895 and the Silaian Incident in 1915.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period between May 1895 and the Silaian Incident in 1915 is classified as the first phase of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>「初期段階」と「第一期」を両立させようとして、無理が生じています。ここの文意は「1895年・・・事件までを日本統治の初期段階と区分される」もしくは「1895年・・・事件までを日本統治の第一期と区分」と思われます。後ほど「第二期」の記述があるので、後者に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>この時期、台湾総督府は軍事行動を全面に出した強硬な統治政策を打ち出し、台湾居民の抵抗運動を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period the Taiwan Sotoku-fu (Government-General) took a hard-line policy backed up by the military force, which caused resistance movements among the people in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period the Taiwan Sotoku-fu (Government-General) took a hard-line policy backed up by military force, which caused the growth of resistant movements among the people in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period the Taiwan Sotoku-fu (Government-General) took a hard-line policy backed up by military force, which caused the growth of resistant movements among the people in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>それらは武力行使による犠牲者を生み出した他、内外の世論の関心を惹起し、1897年の帝国議会では台湾を1億元でフランスに売却すべきという「台湾売却論」まで登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such policy with use of force created victims as well as caused interest in and outside of Japan, so the 1897 session of the Imperial Diet debated whether it should sell Taiwan to France at 100 million yuan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such policy with use of force created victims as well as causing interest in and outside of Japan, so the 1897 session of the Imperial Diet debated whether it should sell Taiwan to France for 100 million yuan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such policy with use of force created victims as well as caused public interest in and outside of Japan, so the 1897 session of the Imperial Diet debated whether Japan should sell Taiwan to France for 100 million yuan.</e>
<cmt>・as well as の後は翻訳に従いました。・「世論の関心」は意味を明確にするため、publicを加えました。・「フランスに売却する」のは日本なので、it を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>こうした情況の中台湾総督には中将以上の武官が就任し台湾の統治を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these circumstances, the post of Governor-General of Taiwan was held by military officers ranking Chujo (Middle Captain) or higher to govern Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under these circumstances, the post of Governor-General of Taiwan was held by military officers ranking Chujo (Middle Captain) or higher to govern Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under these circumstances, the post of Governor-General of Taiwan was held by military officers ranking Chujo (Middle Captain) or higher to govern Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1898年、児玉源太郎が第4代台湾総督として就任すると、内務省 (日本)の官僚として活躍していた後藤新平を民政長官に抜擢し、台湾の硬軟双方を折衷した政策で台湾統治を進めていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gentaro KODAMA, who assumed the fourth Governor-General in 1898, promoted Shinpei GOTO, a bureaucrat of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (in Japan) as Chief of Home Affairs, taking the carrot and stick approach toward governance of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>児玉源太郎→Gentaro KODAMA民政長官→Chief of Home Affairs 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gentaro KODAMA, who assumed the fourth Governor-General in 1898, promoted Shinpei GOTO, a bureaucrat of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (in Japan) as Chief of Home Affairs, taking the carrot and stick approach toward governance of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gentaro KODAMA, who assumed the fourth Governor-General in 1898, promoted Shinpei GOTO, a bureaucrat of the prewar Ministry of Home Affairs (in Japan) as Chief of Home Affairs, taking the carrot and stick approach toward the governance of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>governance の前に定冠詞を付けました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また1902年末に抗日運動を制圧した後は、台湾総督府は日本の内地法を超越した存在として、特別統治主義が採用されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After anti-Japanese movement was put down in the end of 1902, Taiwan Sotoku-fu became an entity not subject to the Japanese law and the special governance approach was adopted.</e>
<cmt>特別統治主義　special governace approach定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the anti-Japanese movement was put down at the end of 1902, Taiwan Sotoku-fu became an entity not subject to Japanese law and the special governance approach was adopted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the anti-Japanese movement was put down at the end of 1902, the Sotoku-fu became an entity not subject to Japanese law and the special governance approach was adopted.</e>
<cmt>先に台湾総督府を説明しているので、the Sotoku-fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本統治初期は台湾統治に2種類の方針が存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early period of Japanese rule, there were two kinds of approaches to rule Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early period of Japanese rule, there were two types of approaches to rule Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early period of Japanese rule, there were two types of approaches to rule Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>第1が後藤新平などに代表される特別統治主義である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One is the special governance approach represented by Shinpei GOTO and others.</e>
<cmt>特別統治主義　special governace approach定訳不明です</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One is the special governance approach represented by Shinpei GOTO and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One is the special governance approach represented by Shinpei GOTO and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>当時ドイツ帝国の科学的植民地主義に傾倒していた後藤は生物学の観点から植民地の同化は困難であり、英国政府の植民地政策を採用し、日本内地の外に存在する植民地として内地法を適用せず、独立した特殊な方式により統治するというものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goto, who was inclined to the scientific imperialism of Germany, claimed that it was difficult to assimilate the natives of the colonies from a biological viewpoint and that Japan should follow the British colonial policies; the colony outside Japan should not be subject to the Japanese law and should be governed under the special approach independent from Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goto, who was inclined towards scientific imperialism of Germany, claimed that it was difficult to assimilate the natives of colonies from a biological viewpoint and that Japan should follow the British colonial policies; the colony outside Japan should not be subject to Japanese law and should be governed under a special approach independent from Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goto, who was inclined towards scientific imperialism of Germany, claimed that it was difficult to assimilate the natives of colonies from a biological viewpoint and that Japan should follow the British colonial policies; the colony outside Japan should not be subject to Japanese law and should be governed under a special approach independent from Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後藤は台湾の社会風俗などの調査を行い、その結果をもとに政策を立案、生物学的原則を確立すると同時に、漸次同化の方法を模索するという統治方針であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goto conducted researches on the Taiwanese society and customs and formulated the governance policy based on the research results to establish the biological principles as well as to seek eventual assimilation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goto conducted researche on Taiwanese society and customs and formulated the governance policy based upon research results to establish biological principles as well as to seek eventual assimilation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goto conducted research on Taiwanese society and customs and formulated the governance policy based upon research results to establish biological principles as well as to seek eventual assimilation.</e>
<cmt>reserche となっていたので修正しましたが、単数形で用いられることが多いので単数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>これに対し原敬などは『内地延長主義』を提唱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The opposing view was held by Takashi HARA, who advocated &quot;inland extensionism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>内地延長主義→mainland extensionalism 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The opposing view was held by Takashi HARA, who advocated &quot;inland extensionism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The opposing view was held by Takashi HARA, who advocated &quot;inland territorial expansionism.&quot;</e>
<cmt>「内地延長主義」は定訳を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>フランスの植民地思想に影響を受けた原は、人種・文化が類似する台湾は日本と同化することが可能であるとし、台湾を内地の一部とし、内地法を適用させるというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hara, who was influenced by French colonialism, claimed that it was possible to assimilate Taiwan to Japan as Taiwanese were similar enough to Japanese in race and culture, and that Japan should treat Taiwan as a part of Japan and apply the Japanese law to Taiwan..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hara, who was influenced by French colonialism, claimed that it was possible to assimilate Taiwan to Japan as Taiwanese were similar enough to Japanese in race and culture, and that Japan should treat Taiwan as a part of Japan and apply the Japanese law to Taiwan..</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hara, who was influenced by French colonialism, claimed that it was possible to assimilate Taiwan to Japan as Taiwanese were similar enough to Japanese in race and culture, and that Japan should treat Taiwan as a part of Japan and apply the Japanese law to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドが2つ打たれていました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>1898年から1906年にかけて民政長官を務めた後藤新平は自らの特別統治主義に基づいた台湾政策を実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpei GOTO, who served Chief of Home Affairs from 1898 to 1906, introduced the governing policy of Taiwan based on his own special governance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpei GOTO, who served Chief of Home Affairs from 1898 to 1906, introduced the governing policy of Taiwan based upon his own special governance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpei GOTO, who served as Chief of Home Affairs from 1898 to 1906, introduced the governing policy of Taiwan based upon his own special governance.</e>
<cmt>served as と修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>この期間内、台湾総督は六三法により「特別立法権」が授権され、立法、行政、司法、軍事を中央集権化した存在となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period, the Governor-General was authorized &quot;special legislative power&quot; in accordance with the Law No. 63, and had the centralized authority with administrative, legislative, judicial and military powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period, the Governor-General was authorized &quot;special legislative power&quot; in accordance with Law No. 63, and had centralized authority with administrative, legislative, judicia,l and military powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period, the Governor-General of Taiwan was authorized &apos;special legislative power&apos; in accordance with the Law No. 63, and had the centralized authority with administrative, legislative, judicial and military powers.</e>
<cmt>・the Governor-General of Taiwan としました。・ダブルコーテーションをシングルにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>これらの強力な統治権は台湾での抗日運動を鎮圧し、台湾の社会と治安の安定に寄与している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such strong ruling power contributed to the suppression of anti-Japanese movement and thus to the stability and safety of the Taiwanese society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such strong ruling power contributed to the suppression of any anti-Japanese movements and thus contibuted to the stability and safety of the Taiwanese society.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such strong ruling power contributed to the suppression of any anti-Japanese movements and thus contributed to the stability and safety of the Taiwanese society.</e>
<cmt>スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>また特筆すべき政策としてはアヘン対策がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The measure to be especially noted was the measures against opium.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The measures to be especially noted were measures against opium.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The measures to be especially noted were measures against opium.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを詰めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>流行していた阿片を撲滅すべく、阿片吸引を免許制とし、また阿片を専売制にして段階的に税を上げ、また新規の阿片免許を発行しないことで阿片を追放することにも成功した（阿片漸禁策）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to exterminate opium prevailing at that time, the government introduced the licensing system for smoking opium and monopoly of opium to gradually increase tax and stopped to issue new license for opium, thus succeeding to expel opium from Taiwan (Policy to phase out opium).</e>
<cmt>（阿片漸禁政策）が下のセルになっていたので移動しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to eliminate opium that was prevailing at that time, the government introduced a licensing system for smoking opium and a monopoly of opium to gradually increase the tax and to stop the issue of new licenses for opium, thus succeeding to get rid of opium from Taiwan (Policy to phase out opium).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to eliminate opium that was prevailing at that time, the government introduced a licensing system for smoking opium and a monopoly of opium to gradually increase the tax and to stop the issue of new licenses for opium, thus succeeding to get rid of opium from Taiwan (Policy to phase out opium).</e>
<cmt>最後の箇所のスペースが余分だったので詰めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そのため現在の台湾の教育・民生・軍事・経済の基盤は当時の日本によって建設されたものが基礎となっていると主張する意見（李登輝など）と、近代化の中の日本の役割を過大評価することは植民地統治の正当化と反発する意見、台湾は日本への農作物供給地として農業を中心に発展させられたため工業発展に遅れたと主張する意見、日本商人の搾取によって富が奪われたとする意見（図解台湾史、台湾歴史図説）も提示されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are different opinions about the ruling of Japan as follows; one opinion is that the infrastructure of Taiwan, such as education, people&apos;s livelihood, military and economy, was based on the one built by Japan at that time (Teng-hui LEE and others) and the other opposing opinions are that an overstimating the role of Japan in the modernization leads to a justification of colonial ruling, Japan imposed an agriculture-centered policy to make Taiwan as a supply source of agricultural products to Japan, resulting in the delay of industrial development and the wealth of Taiwan was deprived by Japanese merchants Taiwan (Illustrated History of Taiwan, Illustration of Taiwanese History)</e>
<cmt>(阿片漸禁策）は文章の意味から考えて前のパラグラフにあるほうが自然だと思ったため移動済みです。「～に成功した（阿片漸禁策）。」図解台湾史 Illustrated History of Taiwan台湾歴史図説 Illustration of Taiwanese History定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there are different opinions about the ruling byJapan as follows; one opinion is that the infrastructure of Taiwan, such as education, people&apos;s livelihood, military and economy, was based upon one built by Japan at that time (Teng-hui LEE and others) and other opposing opinions are that overstimating the role of Japan in modernization leads to a justification for colonial rule, Japan imposed an agriculture-centered policy to make Taiwan a supply source of agricultural products to Japan, resulting in delaying industrial development and the wealth of Taiwan was deprived by Japanese merchants Taiwan (Illustrated History of Taiwan, Illustration of Taiwanese History)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there are different opinions about the ruling by Japan as follows; one opinion is that the infrastructure of Taiwan, such as education, people&apos;s livelihood, military and economy, was based upon one built by Japan at that time (Teng-hui LEE and others) and other opposing opinions are that overestimating the role of Japan in modernization leads to a justification for colonial rule, Japan imposed an agriculture-centered policy to make Taiwan a supply source of agricultural products to Japan and it resulted in delaying industrial development and the wealth of Taiwan was deprived by Japanese merchants Taiwan (Illustrated History of Taiwan, Illustration of Taiwanese History).</e>
<cmt>・about the ruling by Japanの中のスペースが設けられていない箇所にスペースを設けました。・overstimating のスペルミスを修正しました。・「工業発展に遅れた」の箇所ですが、翻訳、チェックに従うと「日本が工業発展を遅らせた」ことになりますが、「日本の農業中心政策」が「工業発展を遅らせた」のが正当なのでそのように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>内地延長主義時期（1915年-1937年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inland Extensionalism period (1915-1937)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inland Extensionalism period (1915-1937)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inland territorial expansionism period (1915-1937)</e>
<cmt>用語集に従いました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>日本統治の第2期は西来庵事件の1915年から1937年の盧溝橋事件であり、国際情勢の変化、特に第一次世界大戦の結果、西洋諸国の植民地統治の権威が失墜し、民族主義が高揚した時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second phase of Japanese ruling was from the Silaian Incident in 1915 to the Marco Polo Bridge Incident in 1937, during which the authority of colonialism by the Western countries fell and the nationalism emerged due to the change of the world situation, especially after the First World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The second phase of Japanese rule was from the Silaian Incident in 1915 to the Marco Polo Bridge Incident in 1937, during which the authority of colonialism by the Western countries fell and nationalism emerged due to the change of the world situation, especially after the First World War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The second phase of Japanese rule was from 1915 when the Silaian Incident broke out to 1937 when the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred, during which time the authority of colonialism by the Western countries fell and nationalism emerged due to the change of the world situation, especially after World War I.</e>
<cmt>・during which を during which time とし、意味を明確にしました。・原文は「第２期は1915年から1937年の期間」となっているので修正しました。・「第一次世界大戦」は用語統一リストの「第二次・・・」に従いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>民主と自由の思想による民族自決が世界の潮流となり、1918年1月にアメリカ合衆国大統領ウッドロウ・ウィルソンが提唱する民族自決の原則と、ウラジーミル・レーニンの提唱した植民地革命論は世界の植民地に大きな影響を与えるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The self-determination based on democracy and freedom became a mainstream of the world, and the principle of self-determination advocated by Woodrow Wilson and the colonial revolutionism by Vladimir Lenin had a great influence on the colonies in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Self-determination based upon democracy and freedom became a mainstream of the world, and the principle of self-determination advocated by Woodrow Wilson and the colonial revolutionism by Vladimir Lenin had a great influence on colonies in the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Self-determination based upon democracy and freedom became a mainstream of the world, and the principle of self-determination advocated by Woodrow Wilson and the colonial revolutionism by Vladimir Lenin had a great influence on colonies in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>このような国際情勢の変化の中、日本による台湾統治政策も変化していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such changing world affairs, the Japanese governance policy of Taiwan was also changing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such changing world affairs, the Japanese governance policy of Taiwan was also changing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such changing world affairs, the Japanese governance policy of Taiwan was also changing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>1910年代、日本の国内政治で新しい潮流が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910s, the new stream of politics was born in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 1910s, a new stream of politics was born in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 1910s, a new stream of politics was born in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>それは藩閥政治に反対し政党政治を実現しようという大正デモクラシーであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the Taisho Democracy which objected the domain dominated politics and tried to realize the party politics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was Taisho Democracy which objected to domain dominated politics and tried to realize party politics.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Taisho Democracy which objected to domain dominated politics and tried to realize party politics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>その政治環境の中、1919年に台湾総督に就任した田健治郎は初めての文官総統である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In such political environment, Kenjiro DEN was appointed to the first civilian Governor-General of Taiwan in 1919.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文例外対応田健治郎　Kenjiro DEN</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In such political environment, Kenjiro DEN was appointed to the first civilian Governor-General of Taiwan in 1919.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In such political environment, Kenjiro DEN was appointed as the first civilian Governor-General of Taiwan in 1919.</e>
<cmt>appointed as としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>田は赴任する前に当時首相であった原敬と協議し、台湾での同化政策の推進が基本方針と確認され、就任した10月にその方針が発表された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prior to his departure, Den conferred with then-Prime Minister Takashi HARA, where both men agreed to pursue an assimilation approach in Taiwan as principle policy, and formally announced the new policy in October of the year he assumed the position.</e>
<cmt>一文一訳文例外対応</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prior to his departure, Den conferred with then-Prime Minister Takashi HARA, where both men agreed to pursue an assimilation approach in Taiwan as a principle policy, and formally announced the new policy in October of the year he assumed the position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prior to his departure, Den conferred with then-Prime Minister Takashi HARA, with whom he agreed to pursue an assimilation approach in Taiwan as a principle policy, and formally announced the new policy in October of the year when he assumed the position.</e>
<cmt>具体的な場所が明示されていないので where は使えないと判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>田は同化政策とは内地延長主義であり、台湾民衆を完全な日本国民とし、皇室に忠誠な国民とするための教化と国家国民としての観念を涵養するものと述べている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Den stated that an assimilation policy was the mainland extensionalism and that the Taiwanese would be educated to understand their role and responsibilities as Japanese subjects loyal to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Den stated that an assimilation policy was mainland extensionalism and that the Taiwanese would be educated to understand their role and responsibilities as Japanese subjects loyal to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Den stated that an assimilation policy was inland territorial expansionism and that the Taiwanese would be educated to understand their role and responsibilities as Japanese subjects loyal to the Imperial family.</e>
<cmt>「内地延長主義」は定訳を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>その後20年にわたり台湾総督は同化政策を推進し、具体的な政策としては地方自治を拡大するための総督府評議会の設置、日台共学制度及び共婚法の公布、笞刑の撤廃、日本語学習の整備などその同化を促進し、台湾人への差別を減少させるための政策を実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Governor-General of Taiwan promoted the assimilation policy for the next 20 years, which included an establishment of an elected advisory committee to expand autonomy, an introduction of non-segregation to educational institutions, an issuance of the intermarriage act, a demolishment of caning as criminal punishment, an encouragement of the study of the Japanese language in order to promote assimilation as well as to decrease the discrimination on Taiwanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Governor-General of Taiwan promoted the assimilation policy for the next twenty years, which included an establishment of an elected advisory committee to expand autonomy, the introduction of non-segregation to educational institutions, an issuance of the intermarriage act, a demolishment of caning as criminal punishment, encouraging the study of the Japanese language in order to promote assimilation as well as to decrease discrimination of Taiwanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Governor-General of Taiwan promoted the assimilation policy for the next twenty years, policy which included an establishment of an elected advisory committee to expand autonomy, the introduction of non-segregation to educational institutions, an issuance of the intermarriage act, a demolishment of flogging as criminal punishment, encouraging the study of the Japanese language in order to promote assimilation as well as to decrease discrimination of Taiwanese.</e>
<cmt>・which の指す内容を明確にしました。・「笞刑」の訳に caning を当てていますが、これは「杖で打つ」の意なので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また後藤新平の消極的な政策を改め、鉄道や水利事業などへの積極的な関与を行い、同化政策は具体的に推進されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The government changed the hands-off approach taken by Shinpei GOTO and actively involved in railway and water systems and promoted the assimilation policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The government changed the hands-off approach taken by Shinpei GOTO and actively introduced railway and water systems and promoted assimilation policies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The government changed the hands-off approach taken by Shinpei GOTO and actively introduced railway and water systems and promoted assimilation policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>この時期に勃興した台湾の社会史としては1914年、台中霧峰の著名な土着地主資産家である林献堂は来台した板垣退助と協力し在台日本人と同等の権利を求める台湾同化会を設立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a notable event in the social history in Taiwan, Xiantang LIN, who was born into a renowned wealthy family in Wufong, Taichung, founded the Taiwan Dokakai (Taiwan Assimilation Society) in collaboration with Taisuke ITAGAKI visiting Taiwan, to demand the same right with the Japanese resident in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味が不明瞭です「この時期に勃興した台湾の社会史としては」→「この時期に注目すべき社会史の事象として」と訳しました。台湾同化会　定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a notable event in the social history of Taiwan, Xiantang LIN, who was born into a renowned wealthy family in Wufong, Taichung, founded Taiwan Dokakai (Taiwan Assimilation Society) in collaboration with Taisuke ITAGAKI visiting Taiwan, to demand the same right with the Japanese residents in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a notable event in the social history of Taiwan, Xiantang LIN, who was born into a renowned wealthy family in Wufong, Taichung, founded Taiwan Dokakai (Taiwan Assimilation Society) in collaboration with Taisuke ITAGAKI visiting Taiwan, to demand the same right with the Japanese residents in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、板垣が台湾を離れるとまもなく台湾総督府により解散させられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, soon after Itagaki left Taiwan, the Taiwan Dokakai was disbanded by Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, soon after Itagaki left Taiwan, Taiwan Dokakai was disbanded by Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, soon after Itagaki left Taiwan, Taiwan Dokakai was disbanded by the Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>the Sotoku-fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="33">
<j>その後、台湾総督府の中央集権的な特権を認めた六三法の撤廃を求めて啓発会が結成され、その解散後は新民会が結成される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that the Keihatsukai (Enlightenment Society) was founded aiming at repealing the Law No. 63 that allowed the centralized privileged of Taiwan Sotoku-fu, followed by Shinminkai (New People &apos;s Society) formed after the Keihatsukai was disbanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that the Keihatsukai (The Enlightenment Society) was founded aiming at repealing Law No. 63 that allowed the centralized privileged of Taiwan Sotoku-fu, followed by Shinminkai (New People &apos;s Society) formed after the Keihatsukai was disbanded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that the Keihatsukai (The Enlightenment Society) was founded aiming at repealing Law No. 63 that allowed the centralized privileged of the Sotoku-fu, followed by Shinminkai (New People &apos;s Society) formed after the Keihatsukai was disbanded.</e>
<cmt>the Sotoku-fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>しかし知識人階級から六三法撤廃は台湾の特殊性の否定であるとの批判が出ると、台湾に議会設置を求める台湾議会設置請願運動が開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the intellectuals criticized this movement, saying that repealing of Law No. 63 means the denial of the special character of Taiwan, the new movement was initiated to call for the establishment of a parliament in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, intellectuals criticized this movement, saying that repealing Law No. 63 meant the denial of the special character of Taiwan, the new movement was initiated to call for the establishment of a parliament in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when intellectuals criticized this movement, saying that repealing Law No. 63 meant the denial of the special character of Taiwan, the new movement was initiated to call for the establishment of a parliament in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>時系列を明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>1921年、第一回台湾議会設置請願書を大日本帝国議会に提出すると、以降13年15回にわたって継続的に行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1921, the first petition to establish the Taiwan parliament was submitted to the Imperial Diet of Japan, which continued for the next 13 years in total of 15 times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1921, the first petition to establish a Taiwan parliament was submitted to the Imperial Diet of Japan, which continued for the next thirteen years for a total of fifteen times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1921, the first petition to establish a Taiwan parliament was submitted to the Imperial Diet of Japan and the deliberations on its establishment continued for the next thirteen years for a total of fifteen times.</e>
<cmt>訳文では which が何を指すのか不明確です。「台湾議会設置に関する審議が行われた」の意になるよう修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="36">
<j>1921年には台湾文化の涵養を目的として、林献堂を総理とした台湾文化協会が設立される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1921, the Taiwan Cultural Association was organized with Lin Xiaotang as president, aiming at developing the Taiwanese culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1921, the Taiwan Cultural Association was organized with Lin Xiaotang as president, aiming at developing Taiwanese culture.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1921, the Taiwan Cultural Association was organized with Xiantang LIN as president, aiming at developing Taiwanese culture.</e>
<cmt>「林献堂」の英語表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>台湾文化協会は各地で講演会や映画上映などを行い大衆啓蒙運動を展開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taiwan Cultural Association developed the enlightening movement for public by organizing lectures or showing movies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taiwan Cultural Association developed the enlightening movement for the public by organizing lectures or showing movies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taiwan Cultural Association developed the enlightening movement for the public by organizing lectures or showing movies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>しかし1927年、左派が協会の主導権を握ると右派の離脱を惹起し、台湾における社会運動は分裂することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1927, however, the left wing took control of the association and the right wing to withdraw from the association, resulting in the split of the social movement in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1927, however, the left wing took control of the association and the right wing to withdraw from the association, resulting in a split of the social movement in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1927, however, the left wing took control of the association and the right wing withdrew from the association, which incident resulted in a split of the social movement in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・the right wing の一節が文法的に成立していないので修正しました。・訳文では resulting の主語が不明確なので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>台湾文化協会は事実上台湾共産党の支配下に入り、台湾共産党が一斉検挙されると同時に台湾文化協会も崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taiwan Cultural Association became virtually under the control of Taiwanese Communist Party, and it fell apart at the same time with the arrest of the Taiwanese Communist Party members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taiwan Cultural Association came virtually under the control of the Taiwanese Communist Party, and it fell apart at the same time with the arrest of the Taiwanese Communist Party members.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taiwan Cultural Association came virtually under the control of the Taiwanese Communist Party and fell apart at the same time with the arrest of the Taiwanese Communist Party members.</e>
<cmt>fell の主語は「台湾文化協会」なのでわざわざ it で言い換える必要はないと判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="40">
<j>離脱した右派は、その後台湾民衆党を結成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The right wing, who left the Taiwan Cultural Association, later formed the Taiwan People&apos;s party.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right wing, who left the Taiwan Cultural Association, later formed the Taiwan People&apos;s party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right wing, who left the Taiwan Cultural Association, later formed the Taiwan People&apos;s Party.</e>
<cmt>partyを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、台湾民衆党も蒋渭水により左傾化すると右派は台湾の地方自治実現を単一目標に挙げる地方自治連盟を結成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, when the Taiwan People&apos;s Party also became radical initiated by Weishui JIANG, the right wing formed the Taiwanese Federation for Local Autonomy with autonomy in Taiwan as a single goal.</e>
<cmt>蒋渭水 Weishui JIANG</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when the Taiwan People&apos;s Party also became radical initiated by Weishui JIANG, the right wing formed the Taiwanese Federation for Local Autonomy with autonomy in Taiwan as a single goal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when the Taiwan People&apos;s Party also became radical initiated by Weishui JIANG, the right wing formed the Taiwanese Federation for Local Autonomy with the establishment of local autonomy in Taiwan as a single goal.</e>
<cmt>「台湾の地方自治実現」をより明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>1937年、日本統治期最後の政治団体である地方自治連盟が解散に追い込まれ、「台湾人」による政治運動は終わりを告げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When in 1937, the Federation for Local Autonomy, which was the last political organization during the period of Japanese rule, was forced to shut down, which marked the end of political movement by &quot;Taiwanese.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When in 1937, the Federation for Local Autonomy, which was the last political organization during the period of Japanese rule, was forced to shut down, which marked the end of political movements by &quot;Taiwanese.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When in 1937, the Taiwanese Federation for Local Autonomy, which was the last political organization during the period of Japanese rule, was forced to shut down, which incident marked the end of political movements by &apos;Taiwanese.&apos;</e>
<cmt>・「地方自治連盟」は直前の表現に合わせました。・ダブルコーテーションをシングルに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>皇民化運動（1937年-1945年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kominka (Subjects of the Emperor) movement (1937 - 1945)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kominka (Subjects of the Emperor) movement (1937 - 1945)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kominka (Subjects of the Emperor) movement (1937 - 1945)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="43">
<j>1937年に盧溝橋事件が発生すると日本の戦争推進のための資源供給基地として台湾が重要視されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred in 1937, Taiwan was regarded important as a resource supply base for Japan to develop the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred in 1937, Taiwan was regarded important as a resource supply base for Japan to develop the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Marco Polo Bridge Incident occurred in 1937, Taiwan was regarded as an important resource supply base for Japan to develop the war.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>台湾における国民意識の向上が課題となった総督府により皇民化政策が推し進められることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu needed to improve the Taiwanese awareness as the Japanese, it started to promote the kominka (subjects of the emperor) policy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotoku-fu needed to improve Taiwanese awareness as the Japanese, it started to promote the kominka (subjects of the emperor) policy</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the Sotoku-fu needed to improve Taiwanese awareness as the Japanese, it started to promote the kominka (subjects of the emperor) policy.</e>
<cmt>・因果関係を明確化しました。・ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>皇民化運動は国語運動、改姓名、志願兵制度、宗教・社会風俗改革の4点からなる、台湾人の日本人化運動である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kominka movement was the forced transformation of the Taiwanese into loyal subjects of the emperor, consisting of the four major campaigns: the encouragement of speaking Japanese, the change of the names to the Japanese names, the military volunteer system and the religious, social and life style reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kominka movement was the forced transformation of the Taiwanese into loyal subjects of the emperor, consisting of the four major campaigns: the encouragement to speak Japanese, the change of names to Japanese names, the military volunteer system and the religious, social and life style reforms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kominka movement was the forced transformation of the Taiwanese into loyal subjects of the emperor, consisting of the four major campaigns: the encouragement to speak Japanese, the change of names to Japanese names, the military volunteer system and the religious, social and life style reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その背景には長引く戦争の結果、日本の人的資源が枯渇し、植民地に頼らざるをえなくなったという事情があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The background of this movement was that the prolonged war caused the Japanese human resources to be exhausted and that Japan had no choice but to rely on the colonies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The background of this movement was that a prolonged war caused the Japanese human resources to be exhausted and that Japan had no choice but to rely on the colonies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The background of this movement was that a prolonged war caused the Japanese human resources to be exhausted and that Japan had no choice but to rely on the colonies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>国語運動は日本語使用を徹底化する運動で、各地に日本語講習所が設けられ、日本語家庭が奨励された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kokugo (literally national language) movement was a thorough movement to make the Taiwanese use Japanese, in which the Japanese language schools were established throughout Taiwan and the the Japanese speaking home was encouraged.</e>
<cmt>日本語家庭　Japanese speaking home 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kokugo (literally national language) movement was a thorough movement to make the Taiwanese use Japanese, whereby Japanese language schools were established throughout Taiwan and a Japanese speaking home was encouraged.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kokugo (literally national language) movement was a thorough movement to make the Taiwanese use Japanese, whereby Japanese language schools were established throughout Taiwan and a Japanese speaking home was encouraged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>日本語家庭とは家庭においても日本語が使われるというもので、国語運動の最終目標でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese speaking home, in which family members spoke Japanese even at home, was the ultimate goal of the kokugo movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Japanese speaking home, in which family members spoke Japanese even at home, was the ultimate goal of the kokugo movement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Japanese speaking home, in which family members spoke Japanese even at home, was the ultimate goal of the kokugo movement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>その過程で台湾語・客家語・原住民語の使用は抑圧・禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the process, the use of Taiwanese, Hakka and aboriginal languages were discouraged or prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the process, the use of Taiwanese, Hakka and aboriginal languages was discouraged or prohibited.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the process, the use of Taiwanese, Hakka and aboriginal languages was discouraged or prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="50">
<j>改姓名は強制されなかったが、日本式姓名を持つことは社会的上昇に有利なこともあり、多くの台湾人が改姓名を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the change of family names was not forced, many Taiwanese changed their family names as it was advantageous in enhancing social status.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the change of family names was not forced, many Taiwanese changed their family names as it was advantageous to enhance social status.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the change of family names was not forced, many Taiwanese changed their family names as it was advantageous to enhance social status.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="51">
<j>日本は中国と戦争を行っていたことから、台湾の漢民族を兵士として採用することには反対が多かったが、兵力不足からやむをえず志願兵制、そして1945年からは徴兵制が施行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Japan was fighting war with China, many objected to accept the Taiwanese of Han race as soldiers, but the shortage of soldiers made the government to introduce volunteer soldier system and then draft system in 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Japan was fighting a war with China, many objected to accept the Taiwanese of the Han race as soldiers, but the shortage of soldiers caused the government to introduce the volunteer soldier system and then the draft system in 1945.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Japan was fighting a war with China, many objected to accept the Taiwanese of the Han race as soldiers, but the shortage of soldiers caused the government to introduce the volunteer soldier system and then the draft system in 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>およそ21万人（軍属を含む）が戦争に参加し、3万人が死亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Almost 210,000 people (including civilian war workers) participated in war, of them 30,000 people died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Almost 210,000 people (including civilian war workers) participated in the war, of them 30,000 people died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Almost 210,000 people (including civilian war workers) participated in the war, of them 30,000 people died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>また台湾の宗教や風俗は日本風なものに「改良」された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the religion and life style of Taiwan was &quot;improved&quot; into the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the religion and life style of Taiwan was &quot;improved&quot; to the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the religion and life style of Taiwan was &apos;improved&apos; to the Japanese style.</e>
<cmt>ダブルコーテーションをシングルにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>寺廟は取り壊されたり、神社に改築された（寺廟整理）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Temples and monasteries were destroyed or converted into the Shinto shrines (rearranging temples and monasteries)</e>
<cmt>寺廟整理 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Temples and monasteries were destroyed or converted into the Shinto shrines (rearranging temples and monasteries)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Temples and mausoleums were destroyed or converted into the Shinto shrines (rearranging temples and mausoleums).</e>
<cmt>・「廟」の訳を修正しました。・ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>中華風の結婚や葬式は日本風な神前結婚や寺葬に改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chinese marriages and funerals were forced to change to the Japanese Shinto style marriage or temple funerals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinese marriages and funerals were forced to change to the Japanese Shinto style of marriage or temple funerals.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinese marriages and funerals were forced to change to the Japanese Shinto style of marriage or temple funerals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="56">
<j>1937年の10月1日には台北時間・西部標準時（UTC+8）が廃止され、東京時間・日本標準時（UTC+9）に統一された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 1, 1937, the Taipei time/Western standard time (UTC +3) was abolished and unified to Tokyo time/Japan standard time (UTC +9).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 1, 1937, the Taipei time/Western standard time (UTC +3) was abolished and unified to Tokyo time/Japan standard time (UTC +9).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 1, 1937, the Taipei time/Western standard time (UTC +8) was abolished and unified to Tokyo time/Japan standard time (UTC +9).</e>
<cmt>UTC+8 とすべきを+3 となっていたので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>（1945年9月元に復帰）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(It was revived in September 1945).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(It was revived in September 1945).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(The original standard time was revived in September 1945).</e>
<cmt>訳文では it の内容が不明確なので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="58">
<j>これらの運動は短期的であったこともあり、台湾社会に根付くことはなかったが、台湾が香港やシンガポールなど、日本の支配を受けたが皇民化運動が徹底されなかった他の華人社会に比べて日本的であるという理由の一つの説明にはなるだろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These movements were short term and failed to take root in Taiwan, but it would be one of the reasons that, compared with the other Chinese societies such as Hong Kong or Singapore which were controlled by Japan but was not subjected to the thorough kominka movement, Taiwanese were more Japanized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These movements were short term and failed to take root in Taiwan, but it would be one of the reasons that, compared with the other Chinese societies such as Hong Kong or Singapore controlled by Japan, but were not subjected to the thorough kominka movement, Taiwanese were more Japanized.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These movements were short term and failed to take root in Taiwan, but this would be one of the reasons that the Taiwanese society was more Japanized than other Chinese societies such as Hong Kong or Singapore controlled by Japan, but not subject to the thorough kominka movement.</e>
<cmt>・文法を修正しました。・it would be… としていますが、この it は前文を指していると思われるので、this としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>敗戦と中華民国の接収</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Defeat and seizure by the Republic of China</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Defeat and seizure by the Republic of China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s defeat and the Republic of China&apos;s seizure of Taiwan</e>
<cmt>意味を明確にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="59">
<j>1945年8月15日、日本は終戦の詔書を発表し太平洋戦争が終結し、台湾は中華民国による接収が行われることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 15, 1945 the Pacific war ended with Japan issuing the imperial rescript on the termination of the war, as a result of which Taiwan was to be seized by the Republic of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 15, 1945 the Pacific war ended with Japan issuing the imperial rescript on the termination of the war, as a result of which Taiwan was to be seized by the Republic of China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 15, 1945 the Pacific War ended with Japan issuing the imperial rescript on the termination of the war and Taiwan was to be seized by the Republic of China.</e>
<cmt>・warを大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>同年8月29日、国民政府主席の蒋介石は陳儀を台湾省行政長官に任命、9月1日には重慶市にて台湾行政長官公署及び台湾警備総部が設置され、陳儀は台湾警備司令を兼任することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 29 of the same year, Kai Shek CHIANG, the head of the nationalist government, appointed Chen Yi as governor of Taiwan province, and with the establishment of Taiwan Security Bureau on September 1, Chen served concurrently as Commander of Taiwan Security.</e>
<cmt>台湾警備総部 定訳不明陳儀 Yi CHEN</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 29 of the same year, Kai Shek CHIANG, the head of the nationalist government, appointed Chen Yi as governor of Taiwan province, and with the establishment of Taiwan Security Bureau on September 1, Chen served concurrently as Commander of Taiwan Security.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 29 of the same year, Kai Shek CHIANG, the head of the nationalist government, appointed Yi CHEN as governor of Taiwan province, and with the establishment of Taiwan Security Bureau on September 1, Chen served concurrently as Commander of Taiwan Security.</e>
<cmt>「陳儀」を表記のルールに従って記載しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>そして10月5日、台湾省行政長官公署前進指揮所が台北に設置されると、接收要員は10月5日から10月24日にかけて上海市、重慶市から台湾に移動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then on October 5, the front commander office of Taiwan provincial administration office was established, and the personnel for seizure moved to Taiwan from Shianhai and Chongqing from 5 to 24 October.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then on October 5, the front commander office of Taiwan provincial administration office was established, and the personnel for seizure moved to Taiwan from Shianhai and Chongqing from 5 to 24 October.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then on October 5, the front commander office of Taiwan provincial administration office was established, and the personnel for seizure moved to Taiwan from Shanghai and Chongqing from October 5 to October 24.</e>
<cmt>上海のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>1945年10月25日、中国戦区台湾省の降伏式典が午前10時に台北公会堂で行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 10 o&apos;clock in the morning of October 25, 1945, the ceremony of the surrender of Japan to Taiwan Province, China wartime administrative region, was held at the Taipei City Hall.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 10 o&apos;clock in the morning of October 25, 1945, the ceremony of the surrender of Japan to Taiwan Province, China wartime administrative region, was held at Taipei City Hall.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 10 o&apos;clock in the morning of October 25, 1945, the ceremony of the surrender of Japan to Taiwan Province, China wartime administrative region, was held at Taipei City Hall.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを詰めました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>日本側は台湾総督安藤利吉が、中華民国側は陳儀がそれぞれ全権として出席し降伏文書に署名され、台湾省行政長官公署が正式に台湾統治に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rikichi ANDO, governor-general of Taiwan and Chen Yi were present representing Japan and China, respectively, and signed a surrender instrument, after which Taiwan province administrative office officially started to work on the control of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>安藤利吉　Rikichi ANDO一原文一訳文例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rikichi ANDO, governor-general of Taiwan and Chen Yi were present representing Japan and China, respectively, and signed a surrender instrument, after which Taiwan province administrative office officially started to work on the control of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rikichi ANDO, then Governor-General of Taiwan and Yi CHEN were present representing Japan and China, respectively, and signed a surrender instrument, after which Taiwan province administrative office officially started to work on the control of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>「台湾総督」と「陳儀」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>公署は旧台北市役所（現在の中華民国行政院）に設置され、国民政府代表の陳儀、葛敬恩、柯遠芬、黄朝琴、游弥堅、宋斐如、李万居の他、台湾住民代表として林献堂、陳炘、林茂生、日本側代表として安藤利吉及び諫山春樹が参加し、ここに日本による台湾統治は終焉を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The administrative office was established in the former Taipei municipal office (today&apos;s Executive Yuan of the Republic of China) and with Yi CHEN, Jing-en GE, Yuan-fen KE, Chao-qin HUANG, Mi-jian YOU, Fei-ju SUNG and Wan-ju LI representing the National government, Xiaotang LIN, Xin CHEN and Mao-sheng LIN and Rikichi ANDO and Haruki ISAYAMA representing Japan, the ruling of Taiwan by Japan ended.</e>
<cmt>諌山春樹　Haruki ISAYAMA中国人名の表記はプログレッシブ中国語辞典の表記によります。一部下記サイトを参照しました。www.lse.ac.uk/collections/taiwanProgramme/TCP1Fleischauer.pdfwww.cwcmf.org.tw/download/2009/0907-end.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The administrative office was established in the former Taipei municipal office (today&apos;s Executive Yuan of the Republic of China) and with Yi CHEN, Jing-en GE, Yuan-fen KE, Chao-qin HUANG, Mi-jian YOU, Fei-ju SUNG and Wan-ju LI representing the National government, Xiaotang LIN, Xin CHEN and Mao-sheng LIN and Rikichi ANDO and Haruki ISAYAMA representing Japan, the ruling of Taiwan by Japan ended.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The administrative office was established in the former Taipei municipal office (today&apos;s Executive Yuan of the Republic of China) and with Yi CHEN, Jing-en GE, Yuan-fen KE, Chao-qin HUANG, Mi-jian YOU, Fei-ju SUNG and Wan-ju LI representing the National government, Xiantang LIN, Xin CHEN and Mao-sheng LIN on behalf of the residents of Taiwan and Rikichi ANDO and Haruki ISAYAMA representing Japan, the ruling of Taiwan by Japan ended.</e>
<cmt>・「台湾住民代表」が訳漏れでしたので訳を入れました。・「林献堂」のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>行政機構</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Administrative body</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Administrative body</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Administrative body</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>台湾総督府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotoku-fu of Taiwan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotoku-fu of Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotoku-fu of Taiwan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="65">
<j>台湾総督府は日本統治時代の最高統治機関であり、その長官が台湾総督である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taiwan Sotoku-fu was the highest governing authority in Taiwan during the period of Japanese rule, and it was headed by a Governor General of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taiwan Sotoku-fu was the highest governing authority in Taiwan during the period of Japanese rule, and it was headed by a Governor General of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taiwan Sotoku-fu was the highest governing authority in Taiwan during the period of Japanese rule, and it was headed by a Governor-General of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>他の箇所ではGovernor-General となっているので、この表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>総督の組織は中央集権式に特徴があり、台湾総督により行政、立法、司法、軍事が総覧され専制的な統治権が施行されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu was characterized by the highly centralized system with the Governor-General wielding supreme executive, legislative and judicial power, effectively making the government a dictatorship.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotoku-fu was characterized by the highly centralized system with the Governor-General wielding supreme executive, legislative and judicial power, effectively making the government a dictatorship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu, characterized by the highly centralized system with the Governor-General wielding supreme executive, legislative, judicial and military power, governed Taiwan dictatorially.</e>
<cmt>・「軍事」が訳漏れになっていたので訳を入れました。・表現を若干修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>台湾総督府の設立当初は民政、陸軍、海軍の3局が設置されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In its earliest incarnation, the Sotoku-fu of Taiwan was composed of three bureaus: Home Affairs, Army and Navy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In its earliest incarnation, the Sotoku-fu of Taiwan was composed of three bureaus: Home Affairs, Army, and Navy.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In its early days, the Sotoku-fu was composed of three bureaus: Home Affairs, Army, and Navy.</e>
<cmt>・incarnation は大げさと判断しました。・単にthe Sotoku-fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>民政局には内務、殖産、財務、学務の4部が設置されたほか、台湾民主国の活動が行われた期間に高島鞆之助が副総督として任命されたケースもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Home Affairs Bureau was further divided into four offices: Internal Affairs, Agriculture, Finance and Education, and Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA was appointed as vice governor during the short-lived Republic of Formosa existed on Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>高島鞆之助　Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Home Affairs Bureau was further divided into four offices: Internal Affairs, Agriculture, Finance and Education, and Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA was appointed as vice governor during the short-lived Republic of Formosa existed on Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Home Affairs Bureau was further divided into four offices: Internal Affairs, Agriculture, Finance and Education, and Tomonosuke TAKASHIMA was appointed as Vice Governor-General when the Republic of Formosa existed on Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>副総督は総督の英語表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>1896年、陸海軍両局が統合され軍務局に、また民政局より総務、法務、通信の各局が分離し7局体制が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1896, the army and navy bureaus were merged to form the Military Affairs Bureau, and the General Affairs, Judicial and Communication Bureaus were separated from the Home Affairs Bureau, resulting in the seven-bureau system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1896, the army and navy bureaus were merged to form the Military Affairs Bureau, and the General Affairs, Judicial and Communication Bureaus were separated from the Home Affairs Bureau, resulting in the seven-bureau system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1896, the army and navy bureaus were merged to form the Military Affairs Bureau, and the General Affairs, Judicial and Communication Bureaus were separated from the Home Affairs Bureau, which separation resulted in the establishment of the seven-bureau system.</e>
<cmt>resulting の主語が不明確だったので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>その後1898年、1901年、1919年の3回にわたる総督府官制変更の際にも組織形態は維持されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the system of the Sotoku-fu was changed three times in 1898, 1901 and 1919, but the organizational structure was maintained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the system of the Sotoku-fu was changed three times in 1898, 1901, and 1919, but the organizational structure was maintained.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the system of the Sotoku-fu was changed three times in 1898, 1901, and 1919, but the organizational structure was maintained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>総督</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Governors-General</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governors-General</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Governors-General</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>1896年に施行された台湾ニ施行スヘキ法令ニ関スル法律明治29年法律第63号（六三法）及び1906年に公布された台湾ニ施行スヘキ法令ニ関スル法律明治39年法律第31号（三一法）或いは1921年の台湾ニ施行スヘキ法令ニ関スル法律大正10年法律第3号（法三号）により台湾に委任立法制度が施行され、総督府はその中央機関と位置づけられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law relating to laws and ordinances to be enforced in Taiwan (Law No.63) enacted in 1986, the law relating to laws and ordinances to be enforced in Taiwan (Law No. 39) issued in 1906 and the amendment of the law relating to laws and ordinances be enforced in Taiwan (Law No. 3) in 1921, enforced the delegated legislation in Taiwan, and the Sotoku-fu was positioned as central authority.</e>
<cmt>法律名は直訳すると不自然なため説明的な訳にしました。委任立法　delegated legislatiion</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law relating to laws and ordinances to be enforced in Taiwan (Law No.63) enacted in 1986, the law relating to laws and ordinances to be enforced in Taiwan (Law No. 39) issued in 1906 and the amendment of the law relating to laws and ordinances be enforced in Taiwan (Law No. 3) in 1921, enforced delegated legislation in Taiwan, and the Sotoku-fu was positioned as the central authority.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law relating to laws and ordinances to be enforced in Taiwan (Law No. 63) enacted in 1896, the amended law (Law No. 31) in 1906 and the third amended law (Law No. 3) in 1921, enforced delegated legislation in Taiwan, and the Sotoku-fu was positioned as the central authority.</e>
<cmt>数値の修正と表現を簡略にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>一般の政策決定は総督府内部の官僚により法律が策定された後、台湾総督府による総督府令の形式により発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The decision of general governmental policies was issued by the Sotoku-fu in the form of an edict of the Sotoku-fu after the government bureaucrat formulated laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The decision of general governmental policies was issued by the Sotoku-fu in the form of an edict of the Sotoku-fu after the government bureaucrat formulated laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">General governmental policies were issued by the Sotoku-fu in the form of an edict of the Sotoku-fu after the Sotoku-fu bureaucrats formulated laws and ordinances.</e>
<cmt>「政策決定」が施行されるのではなく、「政策」が施行されるので、そのように修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また専売制などの導入など一部の内容は日本政府との事前協議及び国会の承認を必要とした内容もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of the policies such as an introduction of monopoly required the conference with the Japanese government in advance and the authorization by the Diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of the policies such as the introduction of monopoly required a conference with the Japanese government in advance and authorization by the Diet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of the policies such as the introduction of monopoly required a conference with the Japanese government in advance and authorization by the Diet.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを詰めました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="74">
<j>1895年から1945年の期間中、日本は19代の台湾総督を任命している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During 1985 to 1945, 19 governors-general of Taiwan were appointed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During 1985 to 1945, 19 governors-general of Taiwan were appointed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During 1895 to 1945, 19 governors-general of Taiwan were appointed.</e>
<cmt>数値を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>その出身より前期武官総督期、文官総督期、後期武官総督期に分類することができ、各総督の平均在任期間は2年半である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The period can be divided based on the background of the Governor-General: the early period of military governor-general, the period of civilian governor-general and the later period of military governor-general, and the tenure of each was two years and a half on average.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The period can be divided based on the background of the Governor-General: the early period of military governor-general, the period of civilian governor-general and the later period of military governor-general, and the tenure of each was two years and a half on average.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The period can be divided based on the background of the Governor-General: the early period of military governor-general, the period of civilian governor-general and the later period of military governor-general, and the tenure of each was two years and a half on average.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="76">
<j>前期武官総督期の総督は樺山資紀、桂太郎、乃木希典、兒玉源太郎、佐久間左馬太、安東貞美、明石元二郎である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Governors-General from the early military period included Sukenori KABAYAMA, Taro KATSURA, Maresuke NOGI, Gentaro KODAMA, Samata SAKUMA, Sadami ANDO and Motojiro AKASHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governors-General from the early military period included Sukenori KABAYAMA, Taro KATSURA, Maresuke NOGI, Gentaro KODAMA, Samata SAKUMA, Sadami ANDO and Motojiro AKASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Governors-General in the early days included Sukenori KABAYAMA, Taro KATSURA, Maresuke NOGI, Gentaro KODAMA, Samata SAKUMA, Sadami ANDO and Motojiro AKASHI.</e>
<cmt>「前期武官総督期」は単に「初期の時代」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>この中で安東貞美と明石元二郎は台湾人の権益を保護する政策を実施し、明石はその死後台湾に墓地が建立されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, Sadami ANDO and Motojiro AKASHI carried out the policies to protect Taiwanese interests, and AKASHI was buried in Taiwan after his death.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, Sadami ANDO and Motojiro AKASHI carried out the policies to protect Taiwanese interests, and AKASHI was buried in Taiwan after his death.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, Sadami ANDO and Motojiro AKASHI carried out the policies to protect Taiwanese interests, and Akashi was buried in Taiwan after his death.</e>
<cmt>最後のAKASHIを通常表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="78">
<j>文官総督時代は大正デモクラシーの時期とほぼ一致し、日本の政党の推薦を受け赴任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The civilian period occurred at roughly the same time as the Taisho Democracy, and they were nominated by the political parties in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The civilian period occurred at roughly the same time as the Taisho Democracy, and they were nominated by political parties in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The civilian period occurred at roughly the same time as the Taisho Democracy, and the Governors-General during this period were nominated by political parties in Japan.</e>
<cmt>意味を明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>1919年から1937年までに田健治郎、内田嘉吉、伊沢多喜男、上山満之進、川村竹治、石塚英藏、太田政弘、南弘、中川健蔵が就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The governors-general appointed from 1919 to 1937 included Kenjiro DEN, Kakichi UCHIDA, Takio IZAWA, Mitsunoshin KAMIYAMA, Eizo Ishizuka, Masahiro OTA, Hiroshi MINAMI and Kenzo NAKAGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The governors-general appointed from 1919 to 1937 included Kenjiro DEN, Kakichi UCHIDA, Takio IZAWA, Mitsunoshin KAMIYAMA, Eizo Ishizuka, Masahiro OTA, Hiroshi MINAMI and Kenzo NAKAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Governors-General appointed from 1919 to 1937 included Kenjiro DEN, Kakichi UCHIDA, Takio IZAWA, Mitsunoshin KAMIYAMA, Eizo ISHIZUKA, Masahiro OTA, Hiroshi MINAMI and Kenzo NAKAGAWA.</e>
<cmt>表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>また台湾の統治方式を抗日運動の鎮圧から経済建設による社会安定に転換した時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During their tenures, the government changed their governance policy from the suppression of anti-Japanese movement to the establishment of the stable society by developing economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During their tenures, the government changed their governance policy from the suppression of anti-Japanese movement to the establishment of a stable society by developing the economy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During their tenures, the government changed their governance policy from the suppression of anti-Japanese movement to the establishment of a stable society by developing the economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="81">
<j>1937年に日華事変が勃発し台湾の軍事的価値が高まると、再び武官が台湾総督に任命されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1937 the Japan-China war broke out and the military importance of Taiwan heightened, so military officers were again appointed to the governor-general.</e>
<cmt>日華事変　Japan-China war</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1937 the Japan-China war broke out and the military importance of Taiwan heightened, so military officers were again appointed to the governor-general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1937 the Japan-China war broke out and the military importance of Taiwan heightened, so military officers were again appointed to the post.</e>
<cmt>表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>この時期の総督は小林躋造、長谷川清、安藤利吉であり、戦争遂行のための軍事需要への対応と軍事基地化がその政策の中心であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Governors-general during this period included Seizo KOBAYASHI, Kiyoshi HASEGAWA and Rikichi ANDO, and their policies primarily focused on meeting the military demand to support the Japanese war efforts and making Taiwan into the military base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Governors-general during this period included Seizo KOBAYASHI, Kiyoshi HASEGAWA, and Rikichi ANDO, and their policies primarily focused on meeting the military demand to support the Japanese war efforts, making Taiwan into the military base.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Governors-General during this period included Seizo KOBAYASHI, Kiyoshi HASEGAWA, and Rikichi ANDO, and their policies primarily focused on meeting the military demand to support the Japanese war efforts, making Taiwan into the military base.</e>
<cmt>General としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>また最後の総督である安藤は、戦後戦犯とみなされ拘束され、1946年に上海において自殺している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ando, the last Governor-General, was arrested as war criminal after the war and killed himself in Shanghai in 1946.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ando, the last Governor-General, was arrested as war criminal after the war and killed himself in Shanghai in 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ando, the last Governor-General, was arrested as war criminal after the war and killed himself in Shanghai in 1946.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>総務長官</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chief of Home Affairs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chief of Home Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chief of Home Affairs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="84">
<j>台湾総督府初期は民政局長官（1895年 - 1896年）、民政局長（1896年 - 1898年）、民政長官（1898年 - 1919年）と称され、1919年8月20日に総務長官と改称された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early days of Taiwan Sotoku-fu, the chief of Home affairs was called as 民生局長官 (1985-1896), 民生局長 (1986-1898) and 民生長官 (1898-1919), respectively, and finally changed to the Chief of Home Affairs on August 20, 1919.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early days of Taiwan Sotoku-fu, the chief of Home affairs was called as 民生局長官 (1985-1896), 民生局長 (1986-1898) and 民生長官 (1898-1919), respectively, and finally changed to the Chief of Home Affairs on August 20, 1919.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early days of Taiwan Sotoku-fu, the Chief of Home Affairs was referred to as 民生局長官 (1895-1896), 民生局長 (1896-1898), 民生長官 (1898-1919) and 総務長官 after August 20, 1919.</e>
<cmt>・日本語表記を使っているので、統一しました。・数値を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>総務長官は台湾総督の姿勢を輔弼すると共に、台湾総督府の各政策の実務を担当した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chief of Home Affairs assisted the Governor General as well as was responsible for the actual implementation of each policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chief of Home Affairs assisted the Governor General as well and was responsible for the actual implementation of each policy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chief of Home Affairs assisted the Governor-General and was responsible for the actual implementation of each policy formulated by the Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>・台湾総督の表記を修正しました。・意味を明確にしました。・as well は削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="86">
<j>台湾総務長官は、前身である民政長官などを含め水野遵、曽根静夫、後藤新平、祝辰巳、大島久満次、宮尾舜治、内田嘉吉、下村宏、賀来佐賀太郎、後藤文夫、河原田稼吉、人見次郎、高橋守雄、木下信、平塚広義、森岡二郎、斎藤樹、成田一郎が就任している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chief of Home Affairs, including the formerly named Director of the Home Affairs Bureau, included Takashi MIZUNO, Shizuo SONE, Shinpei GOTO, Tatsumi IO, Kumaji OSHIMA, Shunji MIYAO, Kakichi UCHIDA, Hiroshi SHIMOMURA, Sagataro KAKU, Fumio GOTO, Kakichi KAWARADA, Jiro HITOMI, Morio TAKAHASHI, Shin KINOSHITA, Hiroyoshi HIRATSUKA, Jiro MORIOKA, Itsuki SAITO and Ichiro NARIA.</e>
<cmt>人名はすべて講談社デジタル版日本人名大辞典+Plusによります</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chief of Home Affairs, including the formerly named Director of the Home Affairs Bureau, included Takashi MIZUNO, Shizuo SONE, Shinpei GOTO, Tatsumi IO, Kumaji OSHIMA, Shunji MIYAO, Kakichi UCHIDA, Hiroshi SHIMOMURA, Sagataro KAKU, Fumio GOTO, Kakichi KAWARADA, Jiro HITOMI, Morio TAKAHASHI, Shin KINOSHITA, Hiroyoshi HIRATSUKA, Jiro MORIOKA, Itsuki SAITO, and Ichiro NARIA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive Chief of Home Affairs and its forerunners such as Director of the Home Affairs Bureau (民政長官) included Takashi MIZUNO, Shizuo SONE, Shinpei GOTO, Tatsumi IO, Kumaji OSHIMA, Shunji MIYAO, Kakichi UCHIDA, Hiroshi SHIMOMURA, Sagataro KAKU, Fumio GOTO, Kakichi KAWARADA, Jiro HITOMI, Morio TAKAHASHI, Shin KINOSHITA, Hiroyoshi HIRATSUKA, Jiro MORIOKA, Itsuki SAITO and Ichiro NARITA.</e>
<cmt>・「民政長官」の英訳は唐突なので日本語表記を補足しました。・「成田一郎」のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>その中で顕著な活動をした人物に後藤新平があげられ、日本統治時代の台湾経済の基礎を築いた人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among them, Shinpei GOTO was a person with the most notable achievement, who built the foundation of the Taiwanese economy under the Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, Shinpei GOTO was a person with the most notable achievements, who built the foundation of the Taiwanese economy under Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, Shinpei GOTO, who built the foundation of the Taiwanese economy under Japanese rule, was a person with the most notable achievements.</e>
<cmt>文法的な理由により、順序を入れ替えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>その他官庁</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other administrative divisions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other administrative divisions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other administrative divisions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="88">
<j>総督及び総務長官以外に総督官房、警務局、農務局、財務局、文教局、鉱工局、外事部、法務部などが設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the Governor-General and the Chief of Home Affairs, there were the secretarial office of the governor general, departments of law enforcement, agriculture, finance, education, mining, external affairs, and judicial affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides the Governor-General and the Chief of Home Affairs, there were the secretarial office of the governor general, departments of law enforcement, agriculture, finance, education, mining, external affairs, and judicial affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides the Governor-General and the Chief of Home Affairs, there were the secretarial office of the governor general, departments of law enforcement, agriculture, finance, education, mining, external affairs, and judicial affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="89">
<j>これら行政機関以外に法院、刑務支所、少年教護院、警察官訓練所、交通局、港務局、専売局、台北帝国大学、各直属学校、農林業試験所などの司法、教育関係の部署を擁していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other governmental bodies included judicial and educational department such as courts, corrections, orphanages, police academies, transportation, port authority, monopoly bureaus, Taihoku Imperial University, schools of all levels, agricultural and forestry research stations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other governmental bodies included judicial and educational departments such as courts, corrections, orphanages, police academies, transportation, port authority, monopoly bureaus, Taihoku Imperial University, schools of all levels, agricultural and forestry research stations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other governmental bodies included judicial and educational departments such as courts, corrections, orphanages, police academies, transportation, port authority, monopoly bureaus, Taihoku Imperial University, schools of all levels, agricultural and forestry research stations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>地方行政区域</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local administrative regions</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local administrative regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local administrative regions</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="90">
<j>中央行政機構以外に、内政統治を行うための行政区域が設置され、日本統治の50年間に10回もの改変が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the central administrative bodies, the administrative regions were established for local governance, during 50 years under the Japanese rule they were changed as many as 10 times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the central administrative bodies, the administrative regions were established for local governance, during fifty years under Japanese rule they were changed as many as ten times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the central administrative bodies, the administrative regions were established for local governance and during fifty years under Japanese rule, they were changed as many as ten times.</e>
<cmt>接続詞を加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>1895年、台湾統治に着手した日本は台北、台湾、台南の3県と澎湖庁を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895 Japan started the ruling of Taiwan and set up three prefectures of Taihoku, Taiwan and Tainan and Hoko County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895 Japan started ruling Taiwan and set up three prefectures of Taihoku, Taiwan, and Tainan and Hoko County.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895 Japan started ruling Taiwan and set up three prefectures of Taihoku, Taiwan, and Tainan and Hoko-cho.</e>
<cmt>澎湖庁の表記を直後のそれに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>その後組織可変が頻繁に行われ、1920年に実施した台北州、新竹州、台中州、台南州、高雄州、台東庁、花蓮港庁および澎湖庁（1926年高雄州より離脱）の日本統治時代の台湾行政区分設置と、その下に置かれた市・街・庄（高砂族の集落には社が置かれた）の地方行政区域で最終的な地方行政区域が確定することとなた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the frequent structural changes, the administrative divisions of Taiwan were confirmed as follows: the administrative regions consisting of Taihoku-shu, Shinchiku-shu, Taichu-shu, Tainan-shu and Takao-shu and Taito-cho, Karenko-cho and and Hoko-cho (independent from Takao-cho in 1926) and Karenko-cho, established in 1920 during the period of the Japanese rule and the local administrative regions of shi (city), machi (town) and sho (village) (&quot;sha&quot; for the Takasago Tribe settlement) under them.</e>
<cmt>台北州などの地名は日本国内の地域として扱っているため日本語表記しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the frequent structural changes, the administrative divisions of Taiwan were confirmed as follows: the administrative regions consisting of Taihoku-shu, Shinchiku-shu, Taichu-shu, Tainan-shu and Takao-shu and Taito-cho, Karenko-cho and and Hoko-cho (independent from Takao-cho in 1926) and Karenko-cho, established in 1920 during the period of the Japanese rule and the local administrative regions of shi (city), machi (town) and sho (village) (&quot;sha&quot; for the Takasago Tribe settlement) under them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the frequent structural changes, the administrative divisions of Taiwan were confirmed as follows: the administrative regions consisting of Taihoku-shu, Shinchiku-shu, Taichu-shu, Tainan-shu and Takao-shu and Taito-cho, Karenko-cho and and Hoko-cho (independent from Takao-shu in 1926) were established in 1920 with the local administrative regions of shi (city), machi (town) and sho (village) (&quot;sha&quot; for the Takasago Tribe settlement) under each administrative region.</e>
<cmt>・括弧内のTakao-cho を Takao-shu に修正しました。・「日本統治時代の・・」は既知事項なので削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>この時の行政区域はその後の国民政府による台湾行政区域決定にも影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The administrative regions established at this time influenced the Nationalist Government to determine Taiwan administrative regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The administrative regions established at this time influenced the Nationalist Government to determine Taiwan administrative regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The administrative regions established at this time influenced the Nationalist Government when it determined Taiwan administrative regions.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>なお、5州3庁は内地の都道府県に、市・街・庄および社は内地の市町村にそれぞれ相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Five shu and three cho were equivalent to prefectures in the mainland Japan, and shi, machi, sho and sha were equivalent to city, town and villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Five shu and three cho were equivalent to prefectures in the mainland Japan, and shi, machi, sho and sha were equivalent to city, town and villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Five shu and three cho were equivalent to prefectures in the mainland Japan, and shi, machi, sho and sha were equivalent to cities, towns and villages.</e>
<cmt>city, town を複数形しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>また1920年の行政区域設定の際には、打狗を高雄市、錫口を松山区 (台北市)、枋橋を板橋市、阿公店を岡山鎮、媽宮を馬公市としたような日本的地名等への改称が行われ、改称された地名は現在でも数多く使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In establishing the administrative regions in 1920, the names were changed to the Japanese names in some places, such as 打狗 to 高雄市、錫口 to 松山区 (台北市)、枋橋 to 板橋市、阿公店 to 岡山鎮、媽宮 to 馬公市, and these names are still used even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In establishing the administrative regions in 1920, the names were changed to Japanese names in some places, such as 打狗 to 高雄市、錫口 to 松山区 (台北市)、枋橋 to 板橋市、阿公店 to 岡山鎮、媽宮 to 馬公市, and these names are still used even today.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In establishing the administrative regions in 1920, the original names were changed to Japanese names in some places, such as 打狗 to 高雄市、錫口 to 松山区 (台北市)、枋橋 to 板橋市、阿公店 to 岡山鎮、媽宮 to 馬公市, and these names are still used even today.</e>
<cmt>意味を明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>抗日運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anti-Japan movement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anti-Japan movement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anti-Japan movement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>台湾民主国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Republic of Formosa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Republic of Formosa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Republic of Formosa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>1895年に日清戦争の敗北が決定的になった清朝は、戦争の早期講和を目指して同年4月17日に日本と下関条約を締結し、その際に日本が求めた台湾地域（台湾島と澎湖諸島）の割譲を承認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing dynasty China, which defeat was inevitable in the Sino Japanese war in 1895, aimed at an early peace pact and signed the Treaty of Shimonoseki with Japan on April 17 of the same year, in which it agreed to cede the Taiwan region (the island of Taiwan and Penghu archipelago) as Japan demanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing dynasty China, of which the defeat was inevitable in the Sino Japanese war in 1895, aimed at an early peace pact and signed the Treaty of Shimonoseki with Japan on April 17 of the same year, in which it agreed to cede the Taiwan region (the island of Taiwan and Penghu archipelago) as Japan demanded.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing dynasty, of which the defeat was inevitable in the Sino-Japanese War in 1895, aimed at an early peace pact and signed the Treaty of Shimonoseki with Japan on April 17 of the same year, in which it agreed to cede the Taiwan region (the island of Taiwan and Penghu archipelago) as Japan demanded.</e>
<cmt>・China は削除しました。・「日清戦争」の表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="97">
<j>しかし台湾に住む清朝の役人と中国系移民の一部が清朝の判断に反発して同年5月25日「台湾民主国」を建国、丘逢甲を義勇軍の指揮官とし日本の接収に抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some officials of the Qing dynasty as well as the Chinese immigrants living in Taiwan repelled the decision by the Qing dynasty and proclaimed the establishment of the Republic of Formosa on May 25 of the same year to resist the seizure by Japan with the volunteer army led by Feng-chia CHIU.</e>
<cmt>台湾民主国　Republic of Formosa丘逢甲 Feng-chia CHIU</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some officials of the Qing dynasty as well as Chinese immigrants living in Taiwan repelled the decision by the Qing dynasty and proclaimed the establishment of the Republic of Formosa on May 25 of the same year to resist the seizure by Japan with the volunteer army led by Feng-chia CHIU.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some officials of the Qing dynasty as well as Chinese immigrants living in Taiwan repelled the decision by the Qing dynasty and proclaimed the establishment of the Republic of Formosa on May 25 of the same year to resist the seizure by Japan with the volunteer army led by Feng-chia CHIU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>しかし日本軍が台北への進軍を開始すると、傭兵を主体として組織された台湾民主国軍は間もなく瓦解、台南では劉永福が軍民を指揮、また各地の民衆も義勇軍を組織して抵抗を継続した.</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Japanese army started advance to Taipei, the military force of the Republic of Formosa, which was mainly composed of mercenaries, fell apart soon, but they continued the resistance with Yung-fu LIU commanding military and private soldiers in Tainan and voluntary armies formed in various places in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Japanese army started their advance to Taipei, the military force of the Republic of Formosa, which was mainly composed of mercenaries, fell apart soon, but they continued the resistance with Yung-fu LIU commanding military and private soldiers in Tainan and voluntary armies formed in various places in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Japanese army started their advance to Taipei, the military force of the Republic of Formosa, which was mainly composed of mercenaries, fell apart soon, while, in Tainan, Yung-fu LIU commanded military and private soldiers and voluntary armies were formed in various places throughout Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>they は文法上直前の傭兵を指すことになり、辻褄が合わないので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>しかし日本軍が台北への進軍を開始すると、傭兵を主体として組織された台湾民主国軍は間もなく瓦解、台南では劉永福が軍民を指揮、また各地の民衆も義勇軍を組織して抵抗を継続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Japanese army started to advance to Taipei, the military force of the Republic of Formosa, which was mainly composed of mercenaries, became soon to fall apart, but they continued the resistance with Yung-fu LIU commanding military and private soldiers in Tainan and voluntary armies formed in various places in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Japanese army started to advance to Taipei, the military force of the Republic of Formosa, which was mainly composed of mercenaries, became soon to fall apart, but they continued the resistance with Yung-fu LIU commanding military and private soldiers in Tainan and voluntary armies formed in various places in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Japanese army started their advance to Taipei, the military force of the Republic of Formosa, which was mainly composed of mercenaries, fell apart soon, while, in Tainan, Yung-fu LIU commanded military and private soldiers and voluntary armies were formed in various places throughout Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>they は文法上直前の傭兵を指すことになり、辻褄が合わないので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>しかし、同年6月下旬、日本軍が南下、圧倒的な兵力・武器の差の前に敗退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the Japanese army further advanced southward, they were defeated by the overwhelming military force and weapons of the Japanese army in the late June of the same year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as the Japanese army further advanced southward, the Taiwan forces were defeated by the overwhelming military force and weapons of the Japanese army in the late June of the same year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as the Japanese army further advanced southward, the Taiwan forces were defeated by the overwhelming military force and weapons of the Japanese army in the late June of the same year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>10月下旬に劉永福が大陸に逃亡、日本軍が台南を占領したことで台湾民主国は崩壊した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of October, Yung-fu LIU fled to the continent and the Japanese army occupied Taiwan, which marked the collapse of the Republic of Formosa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of October, Yung-fu LIU fled to the continent and the Japanese army occupied Taiwan, which marked the collapse of the Republic of Formosa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of October, Yung-fu LIU fled to the continent and the Japanese army occupied Tainan, which events marked the collapse of the Republic of Formosa.</e>
<cmt>・意味を明確にしました。・訳文では「台湾を占領」になっているので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>台湾軍民で戦死又は殺害された者は14,000人（『台湾史小事典』）に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people, both military and civilian, killed in the war amounted to 14,000 (Taiwan History Dictionary).</e>
<cmt>台湾史小事典　定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people, both military and civilian, killed in the war amounted to 14,000 (Taiwan History Dictionary).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people, whether military or civilian, killed in the war amounted to 14,000 in numbers (Taiwan History Dictionary).</e>
<cmt>「民間人、軍人を問わず」の意に解釈すべきと判断しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>抗日運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anti-Japan movement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anti-Japan movement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anti-Japan movement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="103">
<j>台湾民主国の崩壊後、台湾総督樺山資紀は1895年11月8日に東京の大本営に対し台湾全島の鎮圧を報告、日本による台湾統治が開始された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the collapse of the Republic of Formosa, Sukenori Kabayama, the governor-general of Taiwan, reported the suppression of the entire Taiwan to the headquarters in Tokyo, which marked the start of the Japanese rule of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the collapse of the Republic of Formosa, Sukenori Kabayama, the governor-general of Taiwan, reported the suppression of the entire Taiwan to the headquarters in Tokyo, which marked the start of the Japanese rule of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the collapse of the Republic of Formosa, Sukenori KABAYAMA, then-Governor-General of Taiwan, reported the suppression of the entire Taiwan to the Imperial headquarters in Tokyo in November 8, 1895 and the Japanese rule of Taiwan started.</e>
<cmt>・人名の表記・日付の漏れ・「大本営」は定訳を採用しました。・表現を若干修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>しかし12月には台湾北部で清朝の郷勇が台湾民主国の延長としての抗日運動を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, however, the anti-Japanese movements led by the volunteer forces of the Qing dynasty started in the northern Taiwan, which was an extension of the armed resistance of the Republic of Formosa.</e>
<cmt>郷勇（ごうゆう）→volunteer forces</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, however, the anti-Japanese movements led by the volunteer forces of the Qing dynasty started in northern Taiwan, which was an extension of the armed resistance of the Republic of Formosa.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, however, the anti-Japanese movements led by the volunteer forces of the Qing dynasty started in northern Taiwan in the form of an extension of the armed resistance of the Republic of Formosa.</e>
<cmt>which の指す内容が不明確なので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>1902年になると漢人による抗日運動は制圧され、民間が所有する武器は没収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1902, the anti-Japanese movements by Han Chinese were put down and the weapons owned by civilian were confiscated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1902, the anti-Japanese movements by the Han Chinese were put down and the weapons owned by civilians were confiscated.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1902, the anti-Japanese movements by the Han Chinese were put down and the weapons owned by civilians were confiscated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>これらの抗日運動で戦死又は逮捕殺害された者は1万人余り（図解台湾史）との説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one research, the the number of the people killed at war or killed after arrested was approximately 10,000 (Illustrated History of Taiwan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one bit of research, the number of people killed in the war or killed after arrested was approximately 10,000 (Illustrated History of Taiwan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one bit of research, the number of people killed in the war or killed after arrested was approximately 10,000 (Illustrated History of Taiwan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>この時期の総統である児玉源太郎は鎮圧を前面に出した高圧的な統治と、民生政策を充実させる硬軟折衷政策を実施し、一般民衆は抗日活動を傍観するに留まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gentaro KODAMA, who was Governor-General then, used the dual policy of the active suppression and the improvement of public livelihood, so most of the people in Taiwan chose to watch and wait attitude for these anti-Japanese movements.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gentaro KODAMA, who was Governor-General then, used the dual policy of the active suppression and the improvement of public livelihood, so most of the people in Taiwan chose the watch and wait attitude for these anti-Japanese movements.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gentaro KODAMA, who was Governor-General then, used the dual policy of the active suppression and the improvement of public livelihood, so most of the people in Taiwan chose the watch and wait attitude for these anti-Japanese movements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>日本統治前期の抗日活動は台湾を制圧し清朝への帰属を目指すものであり、台湾人としての民族自覚より清朝との関係の中で発生した武装闘争であると言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anti-Japanese movement in the early days of the Japanese rule aimed at gaining control of Taiwan and coming under the jurisdiction of the Qing dynasty, which could be regarded as the armed resistance occurred in the connection with the Qing dynasty rather than the one happened due to the heightened nationalism.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anti-Japanese movement in the early days of the Japanese rule aimed at gaining control of Taiwan and coming under the jurisdiction of the Qing dynasty, which could be regarded as the armed resistance occurred in the connection with the Qing dynasty rather than the one happened due to heightened nationalism.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anti-Japanese movement in the early days of the Japanese rule aimed at gaining control of Taiwan and coming under the jurisdiction of the Qing dynasty and it could be regarded as the armed resistance occurred in the connection with the Qing dynasty rather than the one happened due to heightened nationalism.</e>
<cmt>which の内容が不明確なので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="109">
<j>一旦は平定された抗日武装運動であるが、1907年に北埔事件が発生すると1915年の西来庵事件までの間に13件の抗日武装運動が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the armed resistance against Japan was suppressed, a total of 13 armed resistances occurred from the Beipu Incident in 1907 to the Xilaian Incident in 1907.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though armed resistance against Japan was suppressed, a total of thirteen armed resistance attempts occurred from the Beipu Incident in 1907 to the Xilaian Incident in 1907.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though armed resistance against Japan was suppressed, a total of thirteen armed resistance attempts occurred from the Beipu Incident in 1907 to the Xilaian Incident in 1915.</e>
<cmt>数値を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>規模としては最後の西来庵事件以外は小規模、または蜂起以前に逮捕されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These uprisings were relatively small in scale except for the last Xilaian Incident and conspirators were arrested before the planned uprisings could even take place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These uprisings were relatively small in scale except for the last Xilaian Incident and conspirators were arrested before the planned uprisings could even take place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These uprisings were relatively small in scale except for the last Xilaian Incident and conspirators were arrested before the planned uprisings could even take place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>そのうち11件は1911年の辛亥革命の後に発生し、そのうち辛亥革命の影響を強く受けた抗日運動もあり、4件の事件では中国に帰属すると宣言している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of which, eleven uprisings occurred after the Xinhai Revolution in 1911, and some of the anti-Japanese movements were strongly influenced by the Xinhai Revolution with four incidents declaring to belong to China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of which, eleven uprisings occurred after the Xinhai Revolution in 1911, and some of the anti-Japanese movements were strongly influenced by the Xinhai Revolution with four incidents declaring to belong to China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of them, eleven uprisings occurred after the Xinhai Revolution in 1911, and some anti-Japanese movements were strongly influenced by the Revolution and four of them declared that Taiwan would belong to China.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>また自ら皇帝を称するなど台湾王朝の建国を目指したものが6件あった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Six uprisings took place aiming at establishing the Taiwan dynasty with the conspirators calling themselves as emperors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Six uprisings took place aiming at establishing a Taiwan dynasty with the conspirators calling themselves emperors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Six uprisings aimed at establishing a Taiwan dynasty with the conspirators calling themselves emperors.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡潔にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>霧社事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wushe Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wushe Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wushe Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="113">
<j>後期の抗日運動の中で大規模なものとして霧社事件がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wushe Incident was one of the biggest and last anti-Japanese movement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wushe Incident was one of the biggest and last anti-Japanese movements.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wushe Incident was one of the biggest anti-Japanese movements in the late stage.</e>
<cmt>訳文では「大規模で最後の抗日運動の一つ」となっており、文意と異なるので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>これは1930年10月27日に台中州能高郡霧社（現在の南投県仁愛郷）でサイディック族の大頭目莫那魯道が6部落の300余人の族人を率いた反日武装事件であり、小学校で開催されていた運動会会場に乱入し日本人約140人を殺害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 27, 1930, the chief of the Seediq Rudao MONA assembled a group of more than 300 people from six villages, and assaulted the athletic festival held at an elementary school to kill about 140 Japanese in Wuche, Nantou County, Taichung prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Seediq姓名　順序不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 27, 1930, the chief of the Seediq Rudao MONA assembled a group of more than 300 people from six villages, and assaulted the athletic festival held at an elementary school to kill about 140 Japanese in Wuche, Nantou County, Taichung prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 27, 1930, a group of more than 300 people from six villages, led by the Seediq Rudao MONA, assaulted the athletic festival held at an elementary school to kill about 140 Japanese in Wuche, 能高郡, Taichung Prefecture (present-day Ren-ai, Nantou County).</e>
<cmt>・訳文では会場に乱入したのは大頭目になっていますが、彼と彼の率いたグループが乱入したのでそのように修正しました。・「現在の・・・」が抜けていました。・訳文では「能高郡」を Nantou County としていますが、誤りと思われます。「能高郡」の読みは確認できなかったので日本語表記のままとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>事件発生後総督府は原住民への討伐を決定、軍隊出動による討伐作戦を2ヶ月にわたって展開し、対立部族の協力も得た鎮圧作戦の結果700人ほどの抗日サイディック族が死亡もしくは自殺、500人ほどが投降した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu decided to retaliate the tribe after the Incident and developed the subjugation campaign with the use of the military force as well as the cooperation with the rival tribes, resulting in 700 Seediq killed in fighting or committed suicide and 500 people surrendered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotoku-fu decided to retaliate against the tribe after the Incident and developed a subjugation campaign with the use of the military force as well as cooperation with the rival tribes, resulting in 700 Seediq killed in fighting or committed suicides and 500 people surrendered.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu decided to retaliate against the tribe after the Incident and developed a subjugation campaign using the military force in cooperation with the rival tribes for two months, as a result of which military campaign 700 Seediq were killed in fighting or committed suicides and 500 people surrendered.</e>
<cmt>・「２ヶ月」が漏れていました。・訳文に従うと cooperation がどこにつながっていくのかが分かりません。With the use of cooperation の意かと思われますが、こういった表現は聞いたことがないので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>その後生き残った約300人は川中島に移され、霧社タイヤル族は消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 300 survivors were forced to relocate to Chingliu (Kawanakajima) Village, which marked the end of the Wushe-atayal</e>
<cmt>川中島　Chingliu village</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 300 survivors were forced to relocate to Chingliu (Kawanakajima) Village, which marked the end of the Wushe-atayal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 300 survivors were forced to relocate to Chingliu (Kawanakajima) Village, which event marked the end of the Wushe Atayal.</e>
<cmt>・ピリオドを入れました。・意味を明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>経済</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Economy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Economy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Economy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="117">
<j>日本統治時代の台湾は植民地型経済構造であり、総論的には台湾の資源と労働力を日本内地の発展のために利用していたと言える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The economy of Taiwan under Japanese rule was a colonial economy, which can be summarized that Japan used the resources and labors of Taiwan for the domestic development of the mainland Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The economy of Taiwan under Japanese rule was a colonial economy, which can be summarized that Japan used the resources and labors of Taiwan for the domestic development of mainland Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The economy of Taiwan under Japanese rule was a colonial economy, which means that Japan used the resources and labors of Taiwan for the domestic development of mainland Japan.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>この経済構造は児玉源太郎総督の時代に基礎が築かれ、太平洋戦争により最盛期を迎えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This economic structure was started by Governor General Gentaro KODAMA and reached its peak due to the Pacific war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This economic structure was started by Governor General Gentaro KODAMA and reached its peak due to the Pacific war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This economic structure, founded by then Governor-General Gentaro KODAMA, reached its peak due to the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>この台湾経済をその内容により分類するとすれば、1920年までの糖業を主軸とする期間、1920年から1930年代にかけての蓬莱米の生産を主軸とする期間、そして1930年代以降にそれまでの工業を内地、農業を台湾としていた分業論を改め、軍需に対応すべく台湾の工業化が展開された3時期に区分することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taiwanese economy was classified by content into three: pre-1920 period of sugar industry, rice cultivation between 1920s to 1930s and post-1930 period of industrialization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taiwanese economy was classified by content into three: pre-1920 periods of sugar industry, rice cultivation between 1920s to 1930s and a post-1930 period of industrialization.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taiwanese economy was classified by its features into three periods: before 1920 when sugar industry was main, from the 1920s to the 1930s during which time Horai rice cultivation was spotlighted and after the 1930s when an international division of labor between mainland Japan focusing on industry and Taiwan on agriculture discontinued and Taiwan&apos;s industrialization was promoted to meet military demand.</e>
<cmt>かなり訳漏れがあったので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="120">
<j>これらは重点産業こそ異なれ、経済発展の目標は農産物或いは工業製品の生産工場に拠り日本国内の需要を満たすことにあったが、日本からの大量資本投下は台湾経済の発展と社会インフラ整備を支援し、戦後の台湾経済にも大きな影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the primary industry differs in each period, the primary goal throughout the entire time was to meet the domestic demand in Japan by increasing the production of agricultural and industrial products, so Japan invested a large amount of money to support the development of Taiwan&apos;s economy and social infrastructure and it influenced the post-war economy of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>生産工場に拠り　生産工場により</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the primary industry differed in each period, the primary goal throughout the entire time was to meet the domestic demand in Japan by increasing the production of agricultural and industrial products, so Japan invested a large amount of money to support the development of Taiwan&apos;s economy and social infrastructure and it influenced the post-war economy of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the primary industry differed in each period, the primary goal throughout the entire time was to meet the domestic demand in Japan by increasing the production of agricultural and industrial products, while Japan&apos;s massive investment, which supported the development of Taiwan&apos;s economy and social infrastructure, influenced the post-war economy of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・前半と後半の文言は so ではつなげられないと判断しました。・後半部は修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>糖業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sugar industry</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sugar industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sugar industry</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>台湾の糖業は日本資本の大規模資本投下によりそれまでの零細な生産体制から工場による大量生産へと転換した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sugar industry in Taiwan, which scale was very small in production, was changed to factory mass production due to a large scale investment by the Japanese capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sugar industry in Taiwan, of which the scale was very small in production, was changed to factory mass production due to large scale investment by the Japanese capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sugar industry in Taiwan, of which the scale was very small in production, was changed to factory mass production due to large scale investment by the Japanese capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>台湾総督府も糖業の発展のために高い含糖量の蔗種導入を図るとともに、製糖方法の改善を推奨するなどの政策を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The office of the Governor-General promoted the policies for developing the sugar industry in Taiwan, by introducing the species with high sugar content or improving the method of making sugar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The office of the Governor-General promoted the policies for developing the sugar industry in Taiwan, by introducing a species with high sugar content or improving the method of making sugar.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu promoted the development of the sugar industry in Taiwan by introducing sugarcane with high sugar content as well as improving the method of producing sugar.</e>
<cmt>・蔗種は「サトウキビ」としました。・単にthe Sotoku-fuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>また製糖業者保護のために「原料採集区域制度」を導入、甘蔗農家は付近の製糖工場への作物納入が義務付けられ、またその価格は工場側が決定するというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also introduced the &quot;raw material collection area system&quot; to protect the sugar manufacturers, in which the sugarcane farmers were required to supply their products to the sugar manufacturing factories in their neighbourhood at the price determined by the factories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also introduced the &quot;raw material collection area system&quot; to protect the sugar manufacturers, in which the sugarcane farmers were required to supply their products to the sugar manufacturing factories in their neighbourhood at a price determined by the factories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also introduced the &apos;raw material collection area system&apos; to protect the sugar manufacturers, system in which the sugarcane farmers were required to supply their products to the sugar manufacturing factories in their neighborhood at a price determined by them.</e>
<cmt>・ダブルコーテーションをシングルに変更しました。・表現を修正しました。・neighborhoodと米式にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="124">
<j>このような保護政策の下、日本の財閥も台湾糖業への投資を行い製糖が次々に設立され、台湾の伝統的な糖業は大きな打撃を受け、また甘蔗農家の収入が抑圧される事態が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under these protection policies, the Japanese Zaibatsu began investing in the sugar manufacturing industry and setting up sugar manufacturing factories, which was a blow to the traditional sugar manufacturing in Taiwan as well as suppressed the income of the sugar cane farmers.</e>
<cmt>製糖　→　製糖工場</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under these protection policies, the Japanese Zaibatsu began investing in the sugar manufacturing industry and setting up sugar manufacturing factories, which was a blow to the traditional sugar manufacturing in Taiwan as well as suppressed the income of the sugar cane farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under these protection policies, the Japanese Zaibatsu (company syndicate) began investing in the sugar manufacturing industry and setting up sugar manufacturing factories, which situation was a blow to the traditional sugar manufacturing in Taiwan and suppressed the income of the sugarcane farmers.</e>
<cmt>・「財閥」は補足説明を加えました。・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>金融</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Finance</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Finance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Finance</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="125">
<j>1895年5月、日本軍が台湾に進駐すると、9月には大阪中立銀行が基隆市に「大阪中立銀行基隆出張所」を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the cession of Taiwan by the Japanese army in May 1895, Osaka Churitsu Bank opened &quot;Keelung Branch Office of Osaka Churitsu Bank&quot; in Keelung City in September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the cession of Taiwan by the Japanese army in May 1895, Osaka Churitsu Bank opened &quot;Keelung Branch Office of the Osaka Churitsu Bank&quot; in Keelung City in September.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the cession of Taiwan by the Japanese army in May 1895, Osaka Churitsu Bank opened &apos;Keelung Branch Office of the Osaka Churitsu Bank&apos; in Keelung City in September.</e>
<cmt>ダブルコーテンションをシングルにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>1896年6月、台湾総督樺山資紀は大阪中立銀行在台分行の設立を認可し、台湾における最初の銀行の設立となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1896, Sukenori KABAYAMA, the governor-general of Taiwan, authorized the establishment of a branch bank of Osaka Churitsu Bank in Taiwan, which was the first bank in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>大阪中立銀行　Osaka Churitsu Bank 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1896, Sukenori KABAYAMA, the governor-general of Taiwan, authorized the establishment of a branch bank of Osaka Churitsu Bank in Taiwan, which was the first bank in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1896, Sukenori KABAYAMA, then Governor-General of Taiwan, authorized the establishment of the branch, which was the first bank in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・直前の出張所の設立を認可したことと思われるので、the branch としました。・「当時の台湾総督」としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="127">
<j>1897年3月、帝国議会で台湾銀行法が通過、11月に台湾銀行創立委員会が組織され台湾銀行の開設準備が着手された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1897, the Bank of Taiwan Act was passed in the Imperial Diet, and in November the committee of establishing Bank of Taiwan was organized to prepare for the opening of Bank of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1897, the Bank of Taiwan Act was passed in the Imperial Diet, and in November the committee of establishing Bank of Taiwan was organized to prepare for the opening of Bank of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1897, the Bank of Taiwan Act was passed in the Imperial Diet, and in November the committee of establishing Bank of Taiwan was organized to prepare for the opening of Bank of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>1899年3月、台湾銀行法が改正され、日本政府は100万元を限度額に台湾銀行株式の取得を認可した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1899, the Bank of Taiwan Act was amended, and the Japanese government authorized to acquire the shares of Bank of Taiwan with the limit of one million yuan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1899, the Bank of Taiwan Act was amended, and the Japanese government authorized to acquire the shares of Bank of Taiwan with the limit of one million yuan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1899, the Bank of Taiwan Act was amended, and the Japanese government authorized to acquire the shares of Bank of Taiwan with the limit of one million yuan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>同年6月に「株式会社台湾銀行」が設立され、9月26日より営業開始となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June of the same year &quot;Bank of Taiwan Corporation&quot; was established, which began operation on September 26.</e>
<cmt>株式会社台湾銀行　定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June of the same year &quot;Bank of Taiwan Corporation&quot; was established, which began operations on September 26.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June of the same year &apos;Bank of Taiwan Corporation&apos; was established and began operations on September 26.</e>
<cmt>・ダブルコーテーションをシングルにしました。・which が指すものが位置的に遠いので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>日本統治期間中、台湾銀行は台湾総督府の委託を受け台湾での貨幣台湾銀行券を発行していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of Japanese rule, Bank of Taiwan was responsible for issuing Bank of Taiwan notes, currency used in Taiwan, entrusted by the Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of Japanese rule, the Bank of Taiwan was responsible for issuing Bank of Taiwan notes, currency used in Taiwan, entrusted by the Taiwan Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of Japanese rule, the Bank of Taiwan, on the Taiwan Sotoku-fu&apos;s request, issued Bank of Taiwan notes, currency used in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>訳文ではentrustedがどこにつながるのかが不鮮明なので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>台湾銀行の本部は台北に置かれたが、頭取は東京に駐在し、株式総会も東京で開催されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The headquarter of the Bank of Taiwan was in Taipei, but the head of the Bank was resident in Tokyo, and the shareholders&apos; meeting was also held in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headquarter of the Bank of Taiwan was in Taipei, but the head of the Bank was resident in Tokyo, and the shareholders&apos; meeting was also held in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headquarter of the Bank of Taiwan was in Taipei, but the head of the Bank was resident in Tokyo, and the shareholders&apos; meeting was also held in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>この台湾銀行を通して日本資本が大量に台湾に投下され、台湾の資本主義が発達したと共に、更に台湾より中国や東南アジアへの資金が投資されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through the Bank of Taiwan, a large amount of Japanese capitals was put in Taiwan, which contributed to the development of the capitalism in Taiwan, and further investment in China and the Southeast Asian countries from Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through the Bank of Taiwan, a large amount of Japanese capital was put into Taiwan, which contributed to the development of capitalism in Taiwan, and further investment in China and the Southeast Asian countries from Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through the Bank of Taiwan, a large amount of Japanese capital was put into Taiwan, which economic policy contributed to the development of capitalism in Taiwan, and further investment in China and the Southeast Asian countries from Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>whichの指す内容を明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="133">
<j>台湾銀行以外に、台湾総督府は台湾金融の安定化を図るために彰化銀行、嘉義銀行、台湾商工銀行、新高銀行、華南銀行、日本勧業銀行などを設立し、また特別法を制定し、信用組合、無尽、金融講、信託会社なども設立され台湾経済の発展に寄与させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Bank of Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu allowed the establishment of the Shoka Bank, Kayoshi Bank, Bank of Taiwan of Commerce, Niitaka Bank, Bank of Hunan and the Nihon Kangyo Bank, and it also enacted a special act to establish credit associations, trust companies, mutual loan associations, savings and credit associations to contribute to the economic development in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to Bank of Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu allowed the establishment of the Shoka Bank, Kayoshi Bank, Bank of Taiwan of Commerce, Niitaka Bank, Bank of Hunan and the Nihon Kangyo Bank, and it also enacted a special act to establish credit associations, trust companies, mutual loan associations, savings and credit associations to contribute to the economic development in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to Bank of Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu allowed the establishment of the Shoka Bank, Kayoshi Bank, Bank of Taiwan of Commerce, Niitaka Bank, Bank of Hunan and the Nihon Kangyo Bank, and it also enacted a special act to establish credit associations, trust companies, mutual loan associations, savings and credit associations to contribute to the economic development in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>専売制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monopoly system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monopoly system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monopoly system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="134">
<j>日本統治初期、台湾の財政は日本本国からの補助に依拠しており、当時の日本政府において大きな財政的負担となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early times of the Japanese rule, the finance of Taiwan was dependent on the grant from Japan, which was a significant financial burden for the government of Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early times of the Japanese rule, the finance of Taiwan was dependent upon a grant from Japan, which was a significant financial burden for the government of Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early times of the Japanese rule, the finance of Taiwan was dependent upon a grant from Japan, which situation was a significant financial burden for the government of Japan at that time.</e>
<cmt>whichの指す内容を明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>第4代台湾総督の児玉源太郎は、民政長官の後藤新平と共に『財政20年計画』を策定、20年以内に補助金を減額し台湾の財政独立を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fourth Governor-General of Taiwan, Gentaro KODAMA, made the 20-year financial plan with the Chief of Home Affairs Shinpei GOTO, aiming at decreasing the grant and making Taiwan financially independent within 20 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fourth Governor-General of Taiwan, Gentaro KODAMA, made the twenty year financial plan with the Chief of Home Affairs Shinpei GOTO, aiming at decreasing the grant and making Taiwan financially independent within twenty years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fourth Governor-General of Taiwan, Gentaro KODAMA, made the twenty year financial plan with the Chief of Home Affairs Shinpei GOTO, aiming at decreasing the grant and making Taiwan financially independent within twenty years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>1904年に日露戦争が勃発すると、その戦費捻出のために日本の国庫が枯渇、台湾は計画を前倒して財政独立を実現する必要性に迫られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1904 the Russo-Japan war broke out, which required war expenditure and caused the national treasury to dry up, so Taiwan was forced to realize the financial independence by accelerating the implementation of the plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1904 the Russo-Japan war broke out, which required war expenditure and caused the national treasury to dry up, so Taiwan was forced to realize financial independence by accelerating the implementation of the plan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Russo-Japan war, which broke out in 1904, required war expenditure and caused the national treasury to dry up, so Taiwan was forced to realize financial independence by accelerating the implementation of the plan.</e>
<cmt>whichの指す内容が不明確だったので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="137">
<j>具体的な施策として総督府は地籍整理、公債発行、統一貨幣と度量衡の制定以外に、多くの産業インフラの整備を行うと共に、専売制度と地方税制の改革による財政の建て直しを図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The measures taken by the Sotoku-fu included the land registry readjustment, issuing of public bond, formulation of standard currency and weights and measures systems as well as the financial reforms by introducing monopoly system and local tax system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The measures taken by the Sotoku-fu included the land registry readjustment, issuing of public bonds, formulation of standard currency and weights and measures systems as well as financial reforms by introducing monopoly system and local tax system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The measures taken by the Sotoku-fu included the land registry readjustment, issuing of public bonds, formulation of standard currency and weights and measures systems as well as financial reforms by introducing monopoly system and local tax system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>専売制度の対象となったのは阿片、タバコ（参照台湾総督府専売局松山煙草工場）、樟脳、アルコール、塩及び度量衡であり、専売政策は総督府の歳入の増大以外に、これらの産業の過当競争を防ぎ、また対象品目の輸入規制を行うことで台湾内部での自給自足を実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The monopoly included opium, tobacco (refer to the section of Songshan Tobacco Factory established by Taiwan Sotoku-fu Monopoly Bureau), camphor, salt and weights and measurement, and the monopoly policy contributed to an increase of the revenue as well as the realization of self sufficiency by preventing excessive competition and controlling the imports of these items.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The monopoly included opium, tobacco (refer to the section of Songshan Tobacco Factory established by Taiwan Sotoku-fu Monopoly Bureau), camphor, salt and weights and measurement, and the monopoly policy contributed to an increase of the revenue as well as the realization of self sufficiency by preventing excessive competition and controlling the imports of these items.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The monopoly system applied to opium, tobacco (refer to the section of Songshan Tobacco Factory established by Taiwan Sotoku-fu Monopoly Bureau), camphor, alcohol, salt and weights and measurement, and the monopoly policy contributed to an increase of the revenue as well as the realization of self sufficiency in Taiwan by preventing excessive competition in the field of each item and controlling the imports of these items.</e>
<cmt>「アルコール」の訳漏れと表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>教育</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="139">
<j>台湾で抗日武力闘争が発生していた時期、総督府は武力による鎮圧以外にその統治体制を確立し、教育の普及による撫民政策をあわせて実施した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the armed anti-Japanese movement was taking place in Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu tried to establish the ruling system other than suppression by armed forces and it implemented the policy to pacify the Taiwanese people through the spread of education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the armed anti-Japanese movement that was taking place in Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu tried to establish a ruling system other than suppression by armed forces and it implemented the policy to pacify the Taiwanese people through the spread of education.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the armed anti-Japanese movement that was taking place in Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu tried to establish a ruling system other than suppression by armed forces and it implemented the policy to pacify the Taiwanese people through the spread of education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>台湾人を学校教育を通じて日本に同化させようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It tried to assimilate the Taiwanese into Japan through school education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It tried to assimilate the Taiwanese into Japan through school education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It tried to assimilate the Taiwanese into Japan through school education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>初等中等教育機関は当初、台湾人と日本人を対象としたものが別個に存在し、試験制度でも日本人が有利な制度であったが、統治が進むにつれ次第にその差異は縮小していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the primary and secondary schools were initially separated for Taiwanese and Japanese and the Japanese received a privileged treatment in examination, the difference was gradually becoming smaller as the Japanese rule progressed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though primary and secondary schools were initially separated for Taiwanese and Japanese and the Japanese received a privileged treatment in examination, the difference was gradually becoming smaller as the Japanese rule progressed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though elementary and secondary schools were initially separated for Taiwanese and Japanese and the Japanese received a privileged treatment in examination, the difference was gradually becoming smaller as the Japanese rule progressed.</e>
<cmt>「初等教育」は定訳ではelementaryを使っているので、こちらを採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>台湾に教育制度を普及させた日本の政策は現在の台湾の教育水準の高さに一定の影響を与えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japan&apos;s policy to spread the educational system influenced the high educational standard of today&apos;s Taiwan to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s policy to spread the education system influenced the high educational standard of today&apos;s Taiwan to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s policy to spread the education system influenced the high educational standard of today&apos;s Taiwan to a certain extent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>初等中等教育</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Elementary and primary education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elementary and primary education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elementary and secondary education</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="143">
<j>1895年7月14日、台湾総督府は初代学務部長に伊沢修二を任命し台湾における教育政策を担当させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 14, 1895, Taiwan Sotoku-fu appointed Shuji ISAWA as the first Education Minister responsible for the educational policy in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 14, 1895, Taiwan Sotoku-fu appointed Shuji ISAWA as the first Education Minister responsible for the educational policy in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 14, 1895, the Sotoku-fu appointed Shuji IZAWA as the first chief of Education Bureau responsible for the educational policy in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・「伊沢」は「いさわ」「いざわ」両方の読みが紹介されていますが、定訳に従いました。・「台湾総督府」は何度も出てきているので、theとしました。・「学務部」は後にでてくる訳語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>伊沢は日本内地でも実現していなかった義務教育の採用を上申し、総督府もその提言を受け入れて同年、台北市芝山岩に最初の近代教育を行う小学校（現在の台北市士林国小）を設置、義務教育の実験校とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Izawa proposed to implement compulsory education in Taiwan, which had not been implemented even in Japan, and the Sotoku-fu accepted his proposal and established a primary school in Zhishanyan, Taipei (today&apos;s Shilin elementary school in Taipei) as an experimental school for compulsory education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Izawa proposed to implement compulsory education in Taiwan, which had not been implemented even in Japan, and the Sotoku-fu accepted his proposal and established a primary school in Zhishanyan, Taipei (today&apos;s Shilin elementary school in Taipei) as an experimental school for compulsory education.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Izawa proposed to implement compulsory education in Taiwan, which had not been implemented even in Japan, and the Sotoku-fu accepted his proposal and established an elementary school in Zhishanyan, Taipei (today&apos;s Shilin elementary school in Taipei) as an experimental school for compulsory education.</e>
<cmt>小学校はelementary schoolに統一しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>その後六氏先生事件なども発生したが、総督府は教育政策を推進し、翌年台湾全域に国語伝習所を設置するなどの教育機関の拡充に努めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Zhishanyan Incident happened, in which six teachers were killed by guerrillas, the Sotoku-fu promoted the education policy to improve the educational institution by establishing the Japanese language study school throughout Taiwan next year.</e>
<cmt>六氏先生事件→Zhishanyan Incident</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the Zhishanyan Incident happened, in which six teachers were killed by guerrillas, the Sotoku-fu promoted the education policy to improve the educational institution by establishing the Japanese language study school throughout Taiwan the next year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the Zhishanyan Incident happened, in which six teachers were killed by guerrillas, the Sotoku-fu promoted the education policy to improve the educational institution by establishing the Japanese language study school throughout Taiwan the next year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>1898年、国語伝習所は公学校に昇格している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1898 Japanese language schools were upgraded to public schools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1898 Japanese language schools were upgraded to public schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1898 Japanese language schools were upgraded to public schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="147">
<j>当初、台湾の初等中等教育制度は台湾人と日本人を対象とするものが別個に存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially the primary and secondary educational system was separate for Taiwanese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially the primary and secondary educational systems were separate for Taiwanese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially, the elementary and secondary educational systems were separate for Taiwanese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt>・Initiallyの後にコンマを加えました。・primaryをelementaryにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>内地人(日本人)の初等中等教育は、内地に適用されるのと同じ教育法令に基づいて設置される旧制小学校および旧制中学校、本島人(台湾人)のそれは、台湾教育令に基づいて設置される公学校および高等普通学校によってそれぞれ担われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The elementary and primary education for the mainlanders (Japanese) was charged by the elementary and primary schools under the old system of education in accordance with the same Act of Education with the one enforced in Japan, while the one for Taiwanese was kogakko (public schools) and higher primary schools in accordance with the Act of Taiwanese Education.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Elementary and primary education for the mainlanders (Japanese) was charged by the elementary and primary schools under the old system of education in accordance with the same Act of Education with the one enforced in Japan, while the one for Taiwanese was kogakko (public schools) and higher primary schools in accordance with the Act of Taiwanese Education.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Elementary and secondary education for the mainlanders (Japanese) was charged by the elementary and secondary schools under the old system of education in accordance with the same Act of Education with the one enforced in Japan, while the one for Taiwanese was charged by kogakko (public schools) and higher elementary schools in accordance with the Act of Taiwanese Education.</e>
<cmt>・secondaryとすべき箇所をprimaryとしているので修正しました。・語句を付け加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="149">
<j>しかし1929年になると台湾教育令を改正し、中等教育については高等普通学校が廃止、中学校に一本化され、台湾人と日本人の共学制が採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1929, however, the Act of Taiwanese Education was amended, which discontinued higher primary school to unify into junior high school in the secondary education and employed the desegregated school system for Taiwanese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1929, however, the Act of Taiwanese Education was amended, which discontinued higher primary school to unify into junior high school in secondary education and employed a desegregated school system for Taiwanese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1929, however, the Act of Taiwanese Education was amended, which amendment integrated higher elementary school into junior high school and employed a desegregated school system for Taiwanese and Japanese.</e>
<cmt>・「一本化」という表現に「廃止」も含まれているので、そのように処理しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>同時に初等教育においても「内地人」、「本島人」という民族による区分が廃止され「日本語を常用する児童」が小学校に、「日本語を常用しない児童」が公学校に入学することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the segregation by ethnicity &quot;Naichi jin&quot; and &quot;Honto jin&quot; was discontinued in primary education system, and the children who always used Japanese attended elementary schools and those who did not always use Japanese attended Kogakko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, segregation by ethnicity &quot;Naichi jin&quot; and &quot;Honto jin&quot; was discontinued in the primary education system, and the children who always used Japanese attended elementary schools and those who did not always use Japanese attended Kogakko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, segregation by ethnicity &apos;Naichi jin&apos; and &apos;Honto jin&apos; was discontinued in the elementary education system, and the children who always used Japanese attended elementary schools and those who did not always use Japanese attended Kogakko.</e>
<cmt>・ダブルコーテーションをシングルにしました。・primaryをelementaryに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="151">
<j>1941年3月、台湾教育令は再度改正が行われ、小學校、蕃人公学校と公学校を統合し国民学校（一部は蕃童教育所として統一された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March 1941, the Act of Taiwanese Education was amended again, which unified Banjin Kogakko (public schools for Taiwanese aboriginal people) and Kogakko into Kokumin gakko (partially the aboriginal school).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March 1941, the Act of Taiwanese Education was amended again, which unified Banjin Kogakko (public schools for Taiwanese aboriginal people) and Kogakko into Kokumin gakko (partially the aboriginal school).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March 1941, the Act of Taiwanese Education was amended again, which amendment integrated Banjin Kogakko (public schools for Taiwanese aboriginal people) and Kogakko into Kokumin gakko and some schools were re-established as the ones for aboriginal children.</e>
<cmt>「一部は蕃童教育所として・・」の訳文はよく分からなかったので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>これにより台湾の教育制度は完全に統一され、特殊な台湾原住民を対象とする教育以外、中央或いは地方財政で学校が運営され8歳以上14歳未満の学童に対し6年制の義務教育が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the education system in Taiwan was finally unified, when all schools (except for a few aboriginal education) were public schools operated by central and local budget, with six year compulsory for children aged from 8 to 14 (not included)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the education system in Taiwan was finally unified, when all schools (except for a few aboriginal education) were public schools operated by central and local budget, with six year compulsory for children aged from 8 to 14 (not included)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the education system in Taiwan was finally unified and all schools (except for a few aboriginal education) were operated by central and local budget with six year compulsory education introduced for children aged from 8 to 13.</e>
<cmt>・Thenとwhenの使い方が不自然だったので、修正しました。・14歳未満なので13としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="153">
<j>台湾人の就学率は当初緩慢な増加であったが、義務教育制度が施行されると急速に上昇、1944年の台湾では国民学校が944校設置され、就学児童数は876,000人（女子を含む）、台湾人児童の就学率は71.17%、日本人児童では90%を越える世界でも高い就学率を実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though initial enrollment rate for Taiwanese children was slow to increase, it showed a sharp increase with the compulsory education system; by 1944 there were 944 primary schools in Taiwan with total enrollment rates of 71.17% for Taiwanese children, over 90% for the Japanese children in Taiwan, realizing the high enrollment rate in Asia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the initial enrollment rate for Taiwanese children was slow to increase, it showed a sharp increase with the compulsory education system; by 1944 there were 944 primary schools in Taiwan with total enrollment rates of 71.17% for Taiwanese children, over 90% for the Japanese children in Taiwan, realizing the high enrollment rate in Asia.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the initial enrollment rate for Taiwanese children was slow to increase, it showed a sharp increase with the implementation of the compulsory education system; In 1944, there were 944 elementary schools in Taiwan with 876,000 children (including girls) enrolled and the enrollment rates of Taiwanese children and the Japanese children in Taiwan were 71.17% and 90% respectively, which figures indicated the high enrollment rate in the world.</e>
<cmt>・876,000の訳漏れがあったので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>高等教育</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higher education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higher education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higher education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="154">
<j>日本統治期間中、台湾における高等教育は当初は日本人を対象とし、台湾人が高等教育を受ける機会は限定されたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Japanese rule, the higher education in Taiwan was initially for the Japanese only, so the Taiwanese had a limited chance of attending higher educational institution.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under Japanese rule, higher education in Taiwan was initially for Japanese only, so the Taiwanese had a limited chance of attending a higher educational institution.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under Japanese rule, higher education in Taiwan was initially for Japanese only, so the Taiwanese had a limited chance of attending a higher educational institution.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>職業教育</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Vocational education</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Vocational education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Vocational education</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="155">
<j>職業教育では総督府は当初農試験講習生制度を設立し台湾の産業発展に寄与する人材育成に着手した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For vocational education, the Sotoku-fu established the agricultural examination trainee system to educate the person who could contribute to the development of the farming in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For vocational education, the Sotoku-fu established the agricultural examination trainee system to educate persons who could contribute to the development of farming in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For vocational education, the Sotoku-fu established the agricultural examination trainee system to educate persons who could contribute to the development of farming in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>その後糖業講習所た学務部付属工業講習所など就学期間を半年から2年とする教育機関を設立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later the Sotoku-fu established the educational institutions with six months to two years schooling,such as school for sugar production or industrial learning schools attached to the Sotoku-fu Education Bureau.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later the Sotoku-fu established educational institutions with six months to two years schooling,such as school for sugar production or industrial learning schools attached to the Sotoku-fu Education Bureau.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later the Sotoku-fu established educational institutions with six months to two years schooling, such as schools for sugar production or industrial learning schools attached to the Sotoku-fu Education Bureau.</e>
<cmt>・コンマの直後にスペースを設けました。・「糖業講習所」は複数としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>その後台湾各地に中学校が設立されるようになると、総督府は技術人材の育成を目的とした職業教育の充実を目標とし、1922年の台湾教育令改正の差異に、職業学校として農業、工業、商業学校を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After primary schools were established at various places in Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu set the target to make more fulfilling vocational education to produce technical experts, and the amended part of the Act of Taiwanese Education in 1922 stipulated agricultural, industrial and commercial schools as vocational school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After primary schools were established at various places in Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu set the target to make more fulfilling vocational education to produce technical experts, and the amended part of the Act of Taiwanese Education in 1922 stipulated agricultural, industrial, and commercial schools as vocational schools.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After elementary schools were established at various places in Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu set the target to make more fulfilling vocational education to produce technical experts, and the amended Act of Taiwanese Education in 1922 stipulated agricultural, industrial, and commercial schools as vocational schools.</e>
<cmt>・primaryをelementaryに変更しました。・amended part of→amended ACT</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>これらの実業学校は当初2年制であったが、太平洋戦争勃発後は4年に修業期限が延長され、台湾における技術人員の育成が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially these vocational schools were two year schooling, but extended to four years after the Pacific war broke out to educate technical experts in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially these vocational schools were two years, but extended to four years after the Pacific war broke out to educate technical experts in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially these vocational schools were two years, but extended to four years after the Pacific War broke out to educate technical experts in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>warはWarとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>交通</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Transportation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="159">
<j>総督府は台湾の近代化のために都市整備と交通改善を実施している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Office of the Governor-General also placed a strong emphasis on modernization of Taiwan&apos;s urban infrastructure and transportation system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Office of the Governor-General also placed a strong emphasis on modernization of Taiwan&apos;s urban infrastructure and transportation system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu also placed a strong emphasis on the modernization of Taiwan&apos;s urban infrastructure and transportation system.</e>
<cmt>「総督府」はこれまでの表記に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>その中で台湾の鉄道が最重要政策とされ、また一定規模を有する道路建設も重要項目として整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railways was the most important policy, and to a lesser extent highways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railway was the most important policy, and to a lesser extent highways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railway was the most important policy, and to a lesser extent highways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>交通の改善により台湾の人口は1895年の260万人から1945年の650万人に増加し、台湾の南北を連絡する交通網は台湾社会の大動脈として現在も利用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the development of transportation in Taiwan, the population increased 2.6 million people in 1895 to 6.5 million in 1945, the transportation network linking the west and north is still used now as the main artery in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to the development of transportation in Taiwan, the population increased 2.6 million people in 1895 to 6.5 million in 1945, the transportation network linking the west and north is still used now as the main artery in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to the development of transportation in Taiwan, the population increased from 2.6 million people in 1895 to 6.5 million in 1945 and the transportation network linking the west and north is still used now as the main artery in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>前置詞を付け加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>鉄道</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Railways</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Railway</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="162">
<j>1899年11月8日、台湾の鉄道を管轄した鉄道部（台湾総督府鉄道）が総督府内に設立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Railway Ministry (the Sotoku-fu Railway) was established within the Sotoku-fu to manage the railway in Taiwan on November 8, 1899.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Railway Ministry (the Sotoku-fu Railway) was established within the Sotoku-fu to manage the railway in Taiwan on November 8, 1899.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Railway Ministry (the Sotoku-fu Railway) was established within the Sotoku-fu to manage the railway in Taiwan on November 8, 1899.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>成立後総督府は台湾での鉄道建設を積極的に推進し、1908年には台湾南北を縦貫する西部幹線を完成させるなど、それまで数日を必要とした移動を1日で移動できる空間革命となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the establishment, the Sotoku-fu actively promoted the railway construction in Taiwan, and completed the Western line, linking the north and west, reducing the travel time from several days to a single day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the establishment, the Sotoku-fu actively promoted railway construction in Taiwan, and completed the Western line, linking the north and west, reducing the travel time from several days to a single day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the establishment, the Sotoku-fu actively promoted railway construction in Taiwan, and completed the western line in 1908, which, linking the north and west, reduced the travel time from several days to a single day.</e>
<cmt>・Westernと大文字にする必要はないと判断しました。・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="164">
<j>鉄道部はその後も鉄道整備を推進し淡水線 (台湾鉄路管理局)、宜蘭線、屏東線、東港線などを建設すると共に、私鉄路線であった台東南線（現台東線の一部）、平渓線を買収した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Railway Ministry continued to develop railway system, constructing the Tnasui Line, Giran Line, Heito Line and Toko Line as well as purchasing the Taitong southern line (currently a part of Taitong Line) and Ping Hsi Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Railway Ministry continued to develop the railway system, constructing the Tnasui Line, Giran Line, Heito Line, and Toko Line as well as purchasing the Taitong southern line (currently a part of Taitong Line) and Ping Hsi Line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Railway Ministry continued to develop the railway system, constructing the Tnasui Line (Taiwan Railroad Administration), Giran Line, Heito Line, and Toko Line as well as purchasing the Taitong Southern Line (currently a part of Taitong Line) and Ping Hsi Line.</e>
<cmt>・最初の括弧内の訳漏れがありましたので訳を入れました。・「台東南線」も大文字としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>このほか林田山、八仙山、太平山、阿里山森林鉄道などの森林鉄道の整備も進められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Sotoku-fu developed the forest railways such as Lin tian shan, Ba hsien shan the Alishan Forest railway</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Sotoku-fu developed the forest railways such as Lin tian shan, Ba hsien shan the Alishan Forest railway</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Sotoku-fu developed the forest railways such as Lin tian shan, Ba hsien shan, and Alishan Forest railways.</e>
<cmt>太平山と阿里山の間にandを入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="166">
<j>このほか総督府は北廻線、南廻線、中央山脈横断線などの調査も行ったが、これらの新規路線は太平洋戦争の激化により計画にとどまっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the Sotoku-fu conducted research for North Link Line, South Link Line and the line through the mountains of central Taiwan, which were never realized due to the outbreak of the Second World War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the Sotoku-fu conducted research for North Link Line, South Link Line and the line through the mountains of central Taiwan, which were never realized due to the outbreak of the Second World War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the Sotoku-fu conducted research for the north link line, the south link line and the line through the mountains of central Taiwan but they were not established due to the outbreak of the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>・路線名は固有名詞ではないと思われるので、小文字にしました。・「太平洋戦争」は修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>また民間企業による鉄道建設も進み、糖業鉄道、塩業鉄道、鉱業鉄道などが軽便鉄道として台湾各地を網羅し台湾における交通の要となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The private railways were also constructed, such as the Taiwan Sugar Railways, Salt Railways, Mining Railways, which extended throughout Taiwan vital to transportation in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The private railways were also constructed, such as the Taiwan Sugar Railways, Salt Railways, Mining Railways, which extended throughout Taiwan vital to transportation in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The private railways were also constructed and the Taiwan Sugar Railways, Salt Railways, Mining Railways, as light railways, extended throughout Taiwan, playing the vital role for the transportation in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・語句のつなげ方がよくないように思えたので修正しました。・「軽便鉄道」が訳漏れでしたので訳を入れました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="168">
<j>国民政府により台湾の資源を収奪した植民地時代として否定的な評価が行われるが、鉄道に関して確実に戦後の台湾経済の発展に大きな影響を与えた遺産となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The National Government made the negative evaluation on Japan&apos;s colonial rule as depriving Taiwanese of their resources, but the railways are undoubtedly the heritage that contributed greatly to the post-war economic development in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The National Government made a negative evaluation on Japan&apos;s colonial rule as depriving Taiwanese of their resources, but the railways are undoubtedly the heritage that contributed greatly to post-war economic development in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The National Government made a negative evaluation on Japan&apos;s colonial rule as depriving Taiwanese of their resources, but the railways are undoubtedly the heritage that contributed greatly to post-war economic development in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>現在台湾の鉄道輸送に対する依存度は低下したが、しかし鉄道網の日本統治時代の鉄道路線をそのまま踏襲し、重要な輸送手段の一つとして使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the dependence on rail transportation is lower in Taiwan today, the railway lines built during the period of Japanese rule remained as they were and are used as one of the important transportation means.</e>
<cmt>鉄道網の（日本統治時代の）鉄道路線は単語の重複に近いので、鉄道網を省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though dependence upon rail transportation is lower in Taiwan today, the railway lines built during the period of Japanese rule remained as they were and are used as one of the important means of transportation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though dependence upon rail transportation is lower in Taiwan today, the railway lines built during the period of Japanese rule remained as they were and are used as one of the important means of transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>道路</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Highways</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Highways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Highways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="170">
<j>鉄道の整備に比べ、日本統治時代の道路建設は積極的なものでなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to the development of the railway system, the highway system saw much less attention during the period of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to the development of the railway system, the highway system saw much less attention during the period of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to the development of the railway system, the development of the highway system attracted much less attention during the period of Japanese rule.</e>
<cmt>表現をより明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>濁水渓や下淡水渓（現・高屏渓）など比較的川幅の広い河川への橋脚整備が未整備であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bridges over the wide rivers such as Cho shui River and Xia tamsui River (today Kaoping River) were being underdeveloped.</e>
<cmt>濁水渓→Cho shui River高屏渓→Kaoping River下淡水渓→Xia tamsui River</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bridges over wide rivers such as the Cho shui River and Xia tamsui River (today Kaoping River) were underdeveloped.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bridges over wide rivers such as the Cho shui River and Xia tamsui River (today Kaoping River) were underdeveloped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>しかし日本統治時代後半になると道路網の整備も一定の成果があると、鉄道と自動車輸送の競争が生じ多くの軽便鉄道がバス輸送に代替された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The later days of the Japanese rule, the development of highways was achieved to a certain extent, achievement, causing the competition between railroad and motor transportation and replacing light railway service with bus service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The later days of Japanese rule, the development of highways was achieved to a certain extent, achievement, causing competition between the railroad and motor transportation and replacing light railway service with bus service.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toward the later days of Japanese rule, the development of highways caused competition between the railroad and motor transportation and many light railway lines were replaced with bus service.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>このバス輸送に対し鉄道部は鉄道との平行バス路線を買収するなど対策を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ministry of railway took measures by purchasing the bus service running in parallel to the railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ministry of the railway took measures by purchasing the bus service running in parallel to the railways.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ministry of the railway took measures by purchasing the bus service running in parallel to the railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="174">
<j>また市内交通では「乗合自動車」が設置され、鉄道駅を中心に放射状のバス路線が整備されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the urban transportation, &quot;bus&quot; service was available, with the bus routes centering on local railway stations.</e>
<cmt>乗り合い自動車→bus</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for urban transportation, &quot;bus&quot; service was available, with the bus routes centering on local railway stations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for urban transportation, &apos;noriai jidosha&apos; (a type of bus) service was available, with the bus routes centering on local railway stations.</e>
<cmt>ここまでバスに関する記述がなされているのに、この箇所だけ&quot;bus&quot;とすると不自然なので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="28">
<tit>
<j>港湾</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Port authority</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Port authority</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Port authority</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="175">
<j>台湾の海運業の改善と、日本の南方進出のための中継港湾基地として総督府は基隆港、高雄港の築港を行い、大型船の利用が可能な近代的港湾施設が整備された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu constructed the various in Keeling and Kaohsiung for improving Taiwanese maritime industry and as a transit base for Japan&apos;s operation to the south, thus developing the modern port facilities that were accessible by large vessels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotoku-fu constructed various in Keeling and Kaohsiung for improving Taiwanese maritime industry and as a transit base for Japan&apos;s operation to the south, thus developing modern port facilities that were accessible by large vessels.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu constructed Keeling and Kaohsiung Ports for improving Taiwanese maritime industry as well as for making them the transit bases for Japan&apos;s operation to the south, thus developing modern port facilities that were accessible by large vessels.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>そのほか台湾東部や離島との海上交通の整備の一環として花蓮港や馬公港などもこの時代に整備されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makung Harbour and Hualien harbour were developed at that time as a part of maritime transportation system to service the eastern part of Taiwan and islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makung Harbour and Hualien harbour were developed at that time as a part of the maritime transportation system to service the eastern part of Taiwan and the islands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makung Harbor and Hualien Harbor were developed at that time as a part of the maritime transportation service for the eastern part of Taiwan and the islands.</e>
<cmt>・Harbourは両方とも大文字にし、米式にしました。・後半若干変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="29">
<tit>
<j>水利事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Water works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water supply</e>
<cmt>用語集に従いました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="177">
<j>日本統治時代、台湾の主要産業は農業であり、水利施設の拡充は台湾経済発展に重要な地位を占めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main industry of Taiwan under Japanese rule was agriculture, so the fulfilment of water facilities was an important to develop the Taiwanese economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The main industry of Taiwan under Japanese rule was agriculture, so the fulfilment of water facilities was important in order to develop the Taiwanese economy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The main industry of Taiwan under Japanese rule was agriculture, so the fulfillment of water facilities was important in order to develop the Taiwanese economy.</e>
<cmt>fulfilmentのスペル修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>もう業方面では地籍登録事業により台湾の耕地面積を確定させた後、水利事業の整備を推進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For agricultural development, the government confirmed the farming area by land registry system and then set on the development of water works.</e>
<cmt>もう業　明らかに農業の間違いだと判断しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For agricultural development, the government confirmed the farming area by the land registry system and then set on the development of water works.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For agricultural development, the Stoke-fu confirmed the farming area by the land registry system and then set on the development of water supply.</e>
<cmt>・主語を「総督府」としました。・「水利」は用語集に従いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="179">
<j>1901年、総督府は『台湾公共規則』を公布、以前からの水利施設を回収すると共に、新たに近代的な水利施設を建設することをその方針とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sotoku-fu issued the &quot;Taiwan Public Rules&quot; in 1901, and repaired the old water facilities and constructed the modern new water facilities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sotoku-fu issued the &quot;Taiwan Public Rules&quot; in 1901, and repaired the old water facilities and constructed the modern new water facilities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu issued the &quot;Taiwan Public Rules&quot; in 1901, by which the old water facilities were replaced with the modern water facilities.</e>
<cmt>文法的に成立していないので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>これら水利事業の整備は台湾の農業に大きな影響を与え、農民の収入を増加させるとともに、総督府の農業関連歳入の増加を実現している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of the water facilities influenced the agriculture in Taiwan, increasing the income for farmers as well as the agriculture-related revenue for the Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The development of water facilities influenced agriculture in Taiwan, increasing the income for farmers as well as agriculture-related revenue for the Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The development of water facilities influenced agriculture in Taiwan, increasing the income for farmers as well as agriculture-related revenue for the Sotoku-fu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="30">
<tit>
<j>嘉南大圳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chianan Canal</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chianan Canal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chianan Canal</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="181">
<j>台湾南部に広がる嘉南平原は大河川が存在しない上に降水量が乏しい地域であり、秋から冬にかけては荒涼とした荒野になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chianan Plains in the southern part of Taiwan was a barren territory, especially in the autumn and winter, as it had no major rivers and little rain,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chianan Plains in the southern part of Taiwan was a barren territory, especially during the autumn and winter, as it had no major rivers and little rain,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chianan Plain in the southern part of Taiwan was a barren territory, especially during the autumn and winter, as it had no major rivers and little rain.</e>
<cmt>・平原を複数にする必要はないと判断しました。・ピリオドの代わりにコンマが打たれていました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>総督府技師の八田与一は10年の歳月を費やし、当時東南アジアで最大となる烏山頭ダムを完成させると、1920年には嘉南大圳建設に着工、1934年に主要部分が完成すると嘉南平原への水利実現に伴い、台湾耕地面積の14%にも及ぶ広大な装置を創出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoichi HATTA, a civil engineer of the Sotoku-fu, spent 10 years to complete Ushantou dam, the largest in the south east Asia at that time, and started the construction of Chianan Canal in 1920, and, with the completion of the major part in 1934, it became a huge water supply facility to supply water to the Chianan Plains, which covered as many as 14% of the total farming area in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoichi HATTA, a civil engineer of the Sotoku-fu, spent ten years to complete the Ushantou dam, the largest in the south east Asia at that time, and started the construction of Chianan Canal in 1920, and, with the completion of the major part in 1934, it became a huge water supply facility to supply water to the Chianan Plains, which covered as much as 14% of the total farming area in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoichi HATTA, a civil engineer of the Sotoku-fu, spent ten years to complete the Ushantou dam, the largest in the south east Asia at that time, and started the construction of Chianan Canal in 1920, and, with the completion of the major part in 1934, it became a huge water supply facility to supply water to the Chianan Plain, which covered as much as 14% of the total farming area in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>Plainsを単数にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="31">
<tit>
<j>発電事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Power plants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Power plants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Power plants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="183">
<j>台湾での工業化を推進するために整備が進められた台湾での本格的な発電事業は、1903年2月12日に土倉龍次郎により台北電気株式会社の設立に始まる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of power plants in Taiwan was started with the establishment of Taipei Electric Company by Ryujiro DOKURA on February 2, 1903.</e>
<cmt>土倉龍次郎→Ｒｙｕｊｉｒｏ DOKURA読みを確認できませんでしたが、彼が育成した品種がドクラス・スカーレットというのでdokuraだと判断しました。台北電気株式会社 Taipei Electric Company 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The development of power plants in Taiwan was started with the establishment of Taipei Electric Company by Ryujiro DOKURA on February 2, 1903.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The development of power plants in Taiwan started with the establishment of Taipei Electric Company by Ryujiro DOKURA on February 12, 1903.</e>
<cmt>・was started のwasを削除しました。・日付を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>深坑郷を流れる淡水河の支流である南勢溪を利用した水力発電所を建設し、台北市への電力供給を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It constructed a hydraulic power plant, which used Nanshi River, a branch river of Danshui River running in Shenkeng Township to start power supply to Taipei City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It constructed a hydraulic power plant, which used the Nanshi River, a branch river of the Danshui River running in Shenkeng Township to start a power supply to Taipei City.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He constructed a hydraulic power plant, which used the Nanshi River, a branch river of the Danshui River running in Shenkeng Township to start a power supply to Taipei City.</e>
<cmt>文脈から主語は土倉龍次郎なので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>その後台湾の近代化を推進する総督府は官営の発電所として台北電気作業所及び亀山水力発電所を1905年には台北に、翌年には基隆への電力供給を開始している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu, which was promoting the modernization of Taiwan, established Taipei Electric Works and Kueishan Hydraulic Power Plant in Taipei in 1905, and started power supply to Keeling th following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sotoku-fu, which was promoting the modernization of Taiwan, established Taipei Electric Works and Kueishan Hydraulic Power Plant in Taipei in 1905, and started the power supply to Keeling the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sotoku-fu, which was promoting the modernization of Taiwan, established Taipei Electric Works and Kueishan Hydraulic Power Plant in Taipei in 1905, and started the power supply to Keeling the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>その後1909年に新店渓の小粗坑発電所、高雄県美濃鎮の竹子門発電所、1911年には台湾中部の后里発電所などが次々と建設された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently the Xiaotzukeng Power Plant and Jhuzihment Power Plant were constructed in 1909, and Chiahui Power Plant in 1911.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently the Xiaotzukeng and Jhuzihment Power Plants were constructed in 1909, and Chiahui Power Plant in 1911.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently the Xiaotzukeng Power Plant in the Xindian River and the Jhuzihment Power Plant in Meinong Township, Kaohsiung County were constructed in 1909, and the Chiahui Power Plant in the middle of Taiwan in 1911.</e>
<cmt>幾つか訳漏れがあったので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="187">
<j>1919年、台湾総督明石元二郎は各公営・民営発電所による台湾電力株式会社を設立、より大規模な水力発電所の計画を立案し、当時アジア最大の発電所建設のための調査が着手された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1919, Motojiro AKASHI, Governor-General of Taiwan, established Taiwan Power Plant Company by consolidating public and private power plants, planned larger scale hydraulic power plants and started the research for the construction of Asia&apos;s largest power plant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1919, Motojiro AKASHI, Governor-General of Taiwan, established The Taiwan Power Plant Company by consolidating public and private power plants, planned larger scale hydraulic power plants and started the research for the construction of Asia&apos;s largest power plant.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1919, Motojiro AKASHI, then Governor-General of Taiwan, established the Taiwan Power Plant Company by consolidating public and private power plants, planned the construction of larger scale hydraulic power plants and started the research for the construction of Asia&apos;s largest power plant.</e>
<cmt>表現をより明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>その結果日月潭が建設予定地に選定され、日月潭と門牌潭に落差320mの水力発電所建設が着工された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Sun Moon Lake was chosen as the construction site, the construction of hydraulic power plant was started, which had a drop of 320 m between Sun Moon Lake and Menpai Lake.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Sun Moon Lake was chosen as the construction site, the construction of the hydraulic power plant was started, which had a drop of 320 m between Sun Moon Lake and Menpai Lake.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Sun Moon Lake was chosen as the construction site and the construction of the hydraulic power plant, which had a drop of 320 m between Sun Moon Lake and Menpai Lake, started.</e>
<cmt>順序を入れ替えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>この建設のために西部幹線二八水駅（現・二水駅）より工事作業地区までの鉄道を敷設し物資の輸送を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the construction, the railroad was laid from Erbashui Station (today Ershuei Station) on the Western Line to the construction site to transport materials.</e>
<cmt>二八水駅　Erbashui Station （確認できなかったため発音表記しました）ニ水駅 Ershui Station （Taiwan Railways Administration のHPより）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For construction, the railroad was laid from Erbashui Station (today Ershuei Station) on the Western Line to the construction site to transport materials.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For construction, the railroad was laid from Erbashui Station (today Ershuei Station) on the Western Line to the construction site to transport materials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>これが現在の集集線の前身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the predecessor of the Jiji Line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the predecessor of the Jiji Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the predecessor of the Jiji Line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>工事は第1次世界大戦後の恐慌の影響を受けるなどあったが、1934年に日月潭第一発電所が完成、台湾の工業化の基礎となる電力供給が実現した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though the construction was influenced by the economic depression after the First World War, the First Power Station in Sun Moon Lake was completed in 1934, which enabled the power supply to support the foundation for industrialization in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though the construction was influenced by the economic depression after the First World War, the First Power Station in Sun Moon Lake was completed in 1934, which enabled the power supply to support the foundation for industrialization in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though the construction was influenced by the economic depression after World War Ⅰ, the First Power Station in Sun Moon Lake was completed in 1934, enabling the power supply to support the foundation for industrialization in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・関係代名詞がない方が意味が明確になると判断しました。・「第一次世界大戦」は用語集に従いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>その後増加する電力需要に対応するため、1935年に日月潭第二発電所、1941年には万大発電所の建設が開始されたが、太平洋戦争中のアメリカ軍の空襲にで被害を受け工事が中断した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to meet the increasing demand for power, the constructions of the Second Power Plant in Sun Moon Lake and the Wanda power plant were started in 1935 and 1941, respectively, which constructions were suspended as they were bombed and damaged by the US air force during the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>万大発電所→Wanda Power Plant日月譚観光局ＨＰによる</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to meet the increasing demand for power, construction of the Second Power Plant in Sun Moon Lake and the Wanda power plant was started in 1935 and 1941, respectively, but construction was suspended while being bombed and damaged by the US air force during the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to meet the increasing demand for power, construction of the Second Power Plant in Sun Moon Lake and the Wanda Power Plant started in 1935 and 1941, respectively, but construction was suspended while being bombed and damaged by the US air force during the Pacific War.</e>
<cmt>「万大発電所」も大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="32">
<tit>
<j>社会改善事業</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Social improvement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Social improvement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Social improvement</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="33">
<tit>
<j>阿片対策</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Control measures on opium</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Control measures on opium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Control measures on opium</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="193">
<j>1895年に日本による台湾統治が開始されると当初阿片吸引は禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shortly after the start of Japanese rule of Taiwan in 1895, opium was banned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly after the start of Japanese rule of Taiwan in 1895, opium was banned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly after the start of Japanese rule of Taiwan in 1895, opium was banned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>しかし阿片吸引人口が多く、急進的な禁止政策は社会不安を招くとし、即時禁止政策を漸禁政策へと転換させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, due to the pervasiveness of opium addiction the complete prohibition might cause social stability, so the government changed the initial hard line policy to ban opium immediately to phase-out policy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, due to the pervasiveness of opium addiction complete prohibition might cause social stability, so the government changed the initial hard line policy to ban opium immediately to a phase-out policy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, due to the pervasiveness of opium addiction complete prohibition might cause social stability, so the government changed the initial hard line policy to ban opium immediately to a phase-out policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>1897年1月21日、総督府により『台湾阿片令』が公布されると、総督府は阿片を専売対象品目とし民間の販売を禁止し、また習慣的な吸引者には一代限定の吸引免許を発行し、新規免許の発行を行わないことで時間をかけた阿片撲滅を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 21, 1897, the Sotoku-fu issued the Taiwan Opium Edict mandating a government monopoly of opium trade and prohibiting private sales of opium, and issuing the permits to opium addicts which allowed permit holders to smoke opium for their lifetime only and discontinuing to issue new permits, with the ultimate goal of eliminating opium with time.</e>
<cmt>台湾阿片令→Taiwan Opium Edict 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 21, 1897, the Sotoku-fu issued the Taiwan Opium Edict mandating a government monopoly of opium trade and prohibiting private sales of opium, and issued permits to opium addicts which allowed permit holders to smoke opium for their lifetime only and discontinuing the issue of new permits, with the ultimate goal of eliminating opium over time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 21, 1897, the Sotoku-fu issued the Taiwan Opium Edict mandating a government monopoly of opium trade and prohibiting private sales of opium, and allowed opium addicts to smoke opium for their lifetime by issuing opium smoking permits without producing new permits to eliminate opium over time.</e>
<cmt>関係代名詞whichの指す内容が位置的に遠いのと、discontinuingの主語が不鮮明なので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>1900年の調査では阿片吸引者は169,064名（総人口の6.3%）であったものが、1921年には45,832人（1.3%）とその政策の効果が現れている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The policy proved to be effective because the number of opium addicts in Taiwan was 169,064 (6.3% of the total population) in the 1900 survey and 45,832 (1.3%) in 1921.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The policy proved to be effective because the number of opium addicts in Taiwan was 169,064 (6.3% of the total population) in the 1900 survey and 45,832 (1.3%) in 1921.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The policy proved to be effective because the number of opium addicts in Taiwan was 169,064 (6.3% of the total population) in the 1900 survey and 45,832 (1.3%) in 1921.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>また財政的にも阿片専売による多額の歳入があり、台湾経済の自立にも寄与する政策であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, it was financially beneficial to the independence of Taiwanese economy as the monopoly sales of opium generated substantial amount of revenue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, it was financially beneficial to the independence of The Taiwanese economy as the monopoly sales of opium generated a substantial amount of revenue.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, it was financially beneficial to the independence of the Taiwanese economy as the monopoly sales of opium generated a substantial amount of revenue.</e>
<cmt>The Taiwanese economyの定冠詞を小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="34">
<tit>
<j>公共衛生</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Public health</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Public health</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Public health</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="198">
<j>日本が台湾に進駐した初期において、日本軍は伝染病などにより多くの戦病死者を出した経験から総督府が台湾の公共衛生改善を重要政策として位置づけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early years of Japanese occupation of Taiwan, the Government-General put the improvement of public health in Taiwan as an important policy because the Japanese army suffered from many deaths caused by infectious decease at war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early years of Japanese occupation of Taiwan, the Government-General put the improvement of public health in Taiwan as an important policy because the Japanese army suffered from many deaths caused by infectious diseases in war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early years of Japanese occupation of Taiwan, the Sotoku-fu put the improvement of public health in Taiwan as an important policy because the Japanese army suffered from many deaths caused by infectious diseases in war.</e>
<cmt>「総督府」は従来通りの表記としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>当初総督府は各地に衛生所を設置し、日本から招聘した医師による伝染病の発生を抑止する政策を採用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially the Sotoku-fu established public clinics throughout Taiwan and brought in doctors from Japan to halt the spread of infectious decease.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially the Sotoku-fu established public clinics throughout Taiwan and brought in doctors from Japan to halt the spread of infectious diseases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially the Sotoku-fu established public clinics throughout Taiwan and brought in doctors from Japan to halt the spread of infectious diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>大規模病院こそ建設されなかったが、衛生所を中心とする医療体制によりマラリア、結核、ペストを減少させ、この医療体系は1980年代まで継承されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The public health system was dominated primarily by small local clinics rather than large hospitals, which was successful in decreasing malaria, plague and tuberculosis and remained in Taiwan until the 1980s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public health system was dominated primarily by small local clinics rather than large hospitals, that were successful in decreasing malaria, plague, and tuberculosis and remained in Taiwan until the 1980s.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public health system was dominated primarily by small local clinics rather than large hospitals, which policy was successful in decreasing malaria, plague, and tuberculosis and continued in Taiwan until the 1980s.</e>
<cmt>関係代名詞のthatをこのような用法で用いることは文法的にできないので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="201">
<j>設備方面ではイギリス人ウィリアム・バードンにより台湾の上下水道が設計されたほか、道路改善、秋の強制清掃、家屋の換気奨励、伝染病患者の強制隔離、予防注射の実施など公共衛生改善のための政策が数多く採用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for public health facility in Taiwan, in addition to the water and sewage system designed by a British engineer William Burdon, many policies were adopted to improve public health, such as improvement of streets, compulsory cleaning in the autumn, encouragement of ventilation in houses, quarantine of the patients with infectious diseases.</e>
<cmt>ウィリアム・バードン　William Burdon 確認ができなかったため一般的な氏名のスペルを使用しました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for public health facilities in Taiwan, in addition to the water and sewage system designed by a British engineer William Burdon, many policies were adopted to improve public health, such as the improvement of streets, compulsory cleaning in the autumn, encouragement of ventilation in houses, quarantine of the patients with infectious diseases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for public health facilities in Taiwan, in addition to the water and sewage system designed by a British engineer William Burdon, many policies were adopted to improve public health, such as the improvement of streets, compulsory cleaning in the autumn, encouragement of ventilation in houses, quarantine of the patients with infectious diseases.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを詰めました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="202">
<j>また学校教育や警察機構を通じた台湾人の衛生概念改善行動もあり、一般市民の衛生概念も着実に改善を見ることができ、また台北帝国大学内に熱帯医学研究所を設置し、医療従事者の育成と台湾の衛生改善のための研究が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The activities were developed through school education or policy for improving public health awareness of Taiwanese, resulting in a steady improvement of public health awareness of the public, and a tropical research center was established attached to the Taihoku Imperial University to educate healthcare professionals and research for the public health improvement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Activities were developed through school education or policy for improving public health awareness of Taiwanese, resulting in a steady improvement of public health awareness of the public, and a tropical research center was established attached to the Taihoku Imperial University to educate healthcare professionals and research for the public health improvement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Activities were developed through school education or policy for improving public health awareness of Taiwanese, resulting in a steady improvement of public health awareness of the public, and a research center for tropical medicine was established attached to the Taihoku Imperial University to educate healthcare professionals and research for the public health improvement.</e>
<cmt>「熱帯医学研究所」をより正確に訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="35">
<tit>
<j>歴史的評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historic evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historic evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historic evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="36">
<tit>
<j>日本統治の功罪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merits and demertis of Japanese ruling</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merits and demertis of Japanese ruling</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merits and demerits of Japanese ruling</e>
<cmt>demertisのスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="203">
<j>鉱山の開発や鉄道の建設、衛生環境の改善や、農林水産業の近代化などで台湾の生活水準は向上し、農工業の生産も増大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of mines, construction of railways and improvement of public health, modernization of agriculture, forestry and fisheries industries contributed to a higher living standard of Taiwan as well as an increase of agricultural and industrial productions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The development of mines, construction of railways and improvement of public health, modernization of agriculture, forestry and fisheries industries contributed to a higher living standard of Taiwan as well as an increase of agricultural and industrial production.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The development of mines, construction of railways and improvement of public health, modernization of agriculture, forestry and fisheries industries contributed to a higher living standard of Taiwan as well as an increase of agricultural and industrial production.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>戦争になると台湾の豊富な食料物資が内地への供給に貢献したほか、高雄市には飛行基地が建設され、徴兵制度が敷かれるなど、日本人と同様に台湾人も兵士や労働力として活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Once the war broke out, the rich food resources in Taiwan became an useful source of supply to Japan and an air base was constructed in Kaohsiung and, with draft system enforced in Taiwan, Taiwanese also contributed as the labor or soldiers like Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Once the war broke out, the rich food resources in Taiwan became a useful source of supply to Japan and an air base was constructed in Kaohsiung and, with the draft system enforced in Taiwan, Taiwanese also contributed as labor or soldiers like Japanese.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Once the war broke out, the rich food resources in Taiwan became a useful source of supply to Japan and an air base was constructed in Kaohsiung and, with the draft system enforced in Taiwan, Taiwanese were also employed as labor force or soldiers like Japanese.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>1945年には選挙法が改正され、台湾から国会議員が選出される道も開かれたが、敗戦により実現はされなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1945, the electoral law was amended, which enabled to elect the Diet members from Taiwan, but it was never realized due to the defeat of the Japan&apos;s defeat in the war.</e>
<cmt>敗戦により→Japan&apos;sを加えました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1945, the electoral law was amended, which enabled the election of Diet members from Taiwan, but it was never realized due to the defeat of the Japan in the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1945, the electoral law was amended, enabling the election of Diet members from Taiwan, but it was never realized due to the defeat of the Japan in the war.</e>
<cmt>whichの指す内容が位置的に離れているので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>また満州国の経営や中国との折衝で台湾人が登用されるケースも多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many Taiwanese were recruited for the management of Manchukuo or the negotiation with China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many Taiwanese were recruited for the management of Manchukuo or negotiations with China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many Taiwanese were recruited for the management of Manchukuo or negotiations with China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="207">
<j>しかし台湾人の登用はあくまで日本人の補助としての存在であり、多くの有形・無形の差別があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the recruitment of Taiwanese was only for assisting Japanese, and they suffered from discrimination, tangible and intangible, in many cases.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the recruitment of Taiwanese was only for assisting Japanese, and they suffered from discrimination, tangible, and intangible, in many cases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the recruitment of Taiwanese was only for assisting Japanese, and they suffered from discrimination, tangible, and intangible, in many cases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>例えば初等教育においては日本人の通う小学校と、現地人の公学校は明確に区別された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In elementary education, for example, elementary schools for Japanese and local people were clearly segregated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In elementary education, for example, elementary schools for Japanese and local people were clearly segregated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In elementary education, for example, elementary schools for Japanese and local children were clearly segregated.</e>
<cmt>peopleをchildrenとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>そして高等教育機関進学や官吏登用では制度的に差別された上、日本人の間には台湾人に対する差別意識も存在しており、それを解消すべく戦時中には皇民化政策により日本人との同化が義務化されるなどの政策が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The systematic discrimination existed in the admission to higher educational institutions or entering government service and Japanese had a sense of discrimination against Taiwanese, so the government conducted the kominka policy to oblige them to assimilate to Japanese during the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Systematic discrimination existed in the admission to higher educational institutions or entering government service and Japanese had a sense of discrimination against Taiwanese, so the government conducted the kominka policy to oblige them to assimilate to Japanese during the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Systematic discrimination existed in the admission to higher educational institutions or for governmental employment and Japanese had a sense of discrimination against Taiwanese, so the government conducted the kominka policy to oblige them to assimilate to Japanese during the war.</e>
<cmt>「官吏登用」は別の表現を使いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="210">
<j>また、当時理蕃政策と称された台湾原住民に対する統治政策では、原住民の教育水準に一定程度の向上を見ることができ、法的には日本人や中国語系住民とほぼ同等の権利の保障が認められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The management policy of the aborigines in Taiwan so called &quot;riban seisaku&quot; (aboriginal management policy) contributed to the improvement of the educational level to some extent, and they were legally given almost the same right with the Japanese or Chinese people.</e>
<cmt>理蕃政策→riban seisaku (aboriginal management policy) 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The management policy of the aborigines in Taiwan so called &quot;riban seisaku&quot; (aboriginal management policy) contributed to the improvement of the educational level to some extent, and they were legally given almost the same rights as the Japanese or Chinese people.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The management policy of the aborigines in Taiwan so called &quot;riban seisaku&quot; (aboriginal management policy) contributed to the improvement of the educational level among them to some extent, and they were legally given almost the same rights as the Japanese or Chinese people.</e>
<cmt>意味をより明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>しかし現実には社会的な差別は根強く残存していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reality, however, was that there existed a deep-rooted discrimination in the society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reality, however, was that there existed a deep-rooted discrimination in the society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reality, however, was that there existed a deep-rooted discrimination in the society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="212">
<j>更にこうした差別や、経済的・政治的格差に対する反発から、植民地統治に反抗する武力蜂起も数多く起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These discriminations as well as economic and political gaps caused many armed uprisings to occur against the colonial rule by Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This discrimination as well as economic and political gaps caused many armed uprisings to occur against colonial rule by Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This discrimination as well as economic and political gaps caused many armed uprisings to occur against colonial rule by Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>こうした武力蜂起は日本警察や軍隊により悉く鎮圧され蜂起に参加した者の多くは逮捕、もしくは殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The armed uprisings were all suppressed by the Japanese police or army, and many participants in these uprisings were arrested or killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The armed uprisings were all suppressed by the Japanese police or army, and many participants in these uprisings were arrested or killed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The armed uprisings were all suppressed by the Japanese police or army, and many participants in these uprisings were arrested or killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>特に、日本統治時代最大規模の武力蜂起である霧社事件の際は、鎮圧への毒ガス使用が検討された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially at the time of Wushe Incident, the largest scale armed uprising under the Japanese rule, the use of poison gas was considered to put down it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially at the time of Wushe Incident, the largest scale armed uprising under the Japanese rule, the use of poison gas was considered to put it down.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially at the time of Wushe Incident, the largest scale armed uprising under the Japanese rule, the use of poison gas was considered to put it down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>また、蜂起した原住民部族に対する出草（首狩り、理蕃政策の一環として法律で規制されていた風習）が、鎮圧に協力した部族に許可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The headhunting of rebeling tribes called shusso (a practice of headhunting which was legally permitted as a part of the riban seisaku) was admitted for the tribes cooperating the suppression of rebellions.</e>
<cmt>出草→shusso, headhunting</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The headhunting of rebeling tribes called shusso (a practice of headhunting which was legally permitted as a part of the riban seisaku) was admitted for the tribes cooperating in the suppression of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The headhunting of rebelling tribes called shusso (a practice of headhunting which was legally permitted as a part of the riban seisaku) was admitted for the tribes cooperating in the suppression of rebellion.</e>
<cmt>rebelingのスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>このため、事件前に1400人だった霧社地区の人口は、事件後300人にまで減少し、消滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this, the population in Wushe region decreased from 1,400 before the incident to 300 after the incident, which caused the tribe to extinct.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this, the population in the Wushe region decreased from 1,400 before the incident to 300 after the incident, which caused the tribe to become extinct.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this, the population in the Wushe region decreased from 1,400 before the incident to 300 after the incident and the tribe became extinct.</e>
<cmt>whichの指す内容が不鮮明なので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="217">
<j>1942年には台湾で陸軍特別志願兵制度が始まり、1944年には徴兵制も実施され、それに伴い、台湾からも衆議院を選出できるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The volunteer soldier recruiting system started in 1942 and the army draft system started in 1944, in line with which Taiwan could have had the election of the Diet members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The volunteer soldier recruiting system started in 1942 and the army draft system started in 1944, in line with which Taiwan could have had elections of Diet members.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The volunteer soldier recruiting system and the army draft system started in 1942 and 1944 respectively, in line with which incidents House of Representative members were selected from Taiwan as well.</e>
<cmt>表現を簡略化し、より明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>約20万人余りの台湾人日本兵（軍属を含む）が日本軍で服務し、約3.3万人が戦死または行方不明となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Approximately 200,000 Taiwanese soldiers (including civilian military workers) served the Japanese army, of whom approximately 33,000 people died or were missing at the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Approximately 200,000 Taiwanese soldiers (including civilian military workers) served the Japanese army, of whom approximately 33,000 people died or were missing in the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Approximately 200,000 Taiwanese soldiers (including civilian military workers) served the Japanese army and approximately 33,000 people of them died or were missing in the war.</e>
<cmt>whomの指す内容が位置的に遠いので、修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>先住民族からなる高砂義勇隊は南方戦線で大きな活躍を見せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takasago Volunteer Army consisted of the aborigines were very brave in the Southern battle line.</e>
<cmt>高砂義勇軍 Takasago Volunteer Army 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Takasago Volunteer Army consisting of aborigines were very brave in the Southern battle line.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Takasago Volunteer Army consisting of aborigines were very brave in the Southern battle line.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>しかし日本は国交が無いことなどを理由に補償を拒み、戦後40年以上経った1987年に、漸く一律200万円の弔慰金が支払われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Japanese government refused to pay the compensation on the basis that there was no diplomatic relations, and finally paid uniform choikin (condolence money) of two million yen per person in 1987, forty years after the end of war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Japanese government refused to pay compensation on the basis that there were no diplomatic relations, and finally paid uniform choikin (condolence money) of two million yen per person in 1987, forty years after the end of the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Japanese government refused to pay compensation on the basis that there were no diplomatic relations between Japan and Taiwan, and finally paid uniform choikin (condolence money) of two million yen per person in 1987, more than forty years after the end of the war.</e>
<cmt>表現をより明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>しかし毎月30万円の遺族年金が支払われている日本人兵士に対し、日本国民を離脱した台湾人兵士にはそれ以上の支払いはなく、批判する声もある（高金素梅など）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the Japanese soldiers have received 300,000 yen monthly pension, the Taiwanese soldiers who had renounced Japanese nationality received nothing except for choikin, which some people have been criticizing (Sumei GAOJIN).</e>
<cmt>高金素梅→Sumei GAOJIN</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Japanese soldiers have received a 300,000 yen monthly pension, the Taiwanese soldiers who had renounced Japanese nationality received nothing except for choikin, which some people have been criticizing (Sumei GAOJIN).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Japanese soldiers have received a 300,000 yen monthly pension, the Taiwanese soldiers who had renounced Japanese nationality received nothing except for choikin, of which fact some people including Sumei GAOJIN have been criticizing.</e>
<cmt>表現をより明確にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="222">
<j>また日本ではインフラ確立など、植民地統治のプラス面が評価されがちだが、それに対し結局は台湾人でなく日本人の利益を第一義に考えての投資、優遇された日本人商人による搾取、日本の食糧庫・南進基地に位置づけられ、工業化が遅れたなどの批判もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese tended to mention the positive side of the colonial ruling such as establishing the infrastructure, on the other hand some criticized the investment was done for the benefit of Japanese, not Taiwanese, the deprivement by the privileged Japanese merchants, delayed industrialization as Taiwan was regarded as the source of food or base.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese tended to mention the positive side of the colonial ruling such as establishing the infrastructure, on the other hand some criticized the investment was done for the benefit of Japanese, not Taiwanese, the deprivement by the privileged Japanese merchants, delayed industrialization as Taiwan was regarded as a source of food or a base.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese tended to mention the positive side of the colonial ruling such as establishing the infrastructure, on the other hand, some mentioned the investment that was allegedly done for the benefit of Japanese, not Taiwanese, the exploitation by the privileged Japanese merchants, delayed industrialization as a result of Taiwan being positioned as a source of food or a base for southward advancement.</e>
<cmt>・表現をより明確にしました。・deprivementという単語はないので、別の単語を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="37">
<tit>
<j>戦後の評価</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Post-war public evaluation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Post-war public evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Post-war public evaluation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="223">
<j>台湾では戦後、国共内戦に破れ遷台した中国国民党が、それまで台湾に住む本省人を弾圧（白色テロ、1947年に発生した二・二八事件はその最大規模のものである。）、大陸反攻を国是とし軍事を優先とした政策を実施したため、台湾のインフラ整備は後回しにされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the postwar Taiwan, the Kuomintang Party, which was defeated by communist forces in the Chinese civil war and moved to Taiwan, suppressed the native-born Taiwanese who had been living in Taiwan before the Kuomintang related immigration wave (the White Terror and the 228 incident in 1947 were the largest scale suppression) and developed the military-first policy with the national credo of &quot;counterattack the mainland&quot;, as a result the development of the infrastructure in Taiwan was put on the back-burner.</e>
<cmt>一つの文章が２つのセルに分かれていたので一文に修正しました。本省人→native-born Taiwanese; someone whose ancestors had lived in Taiwan before the Kuomintang related immigration wave (tangorin.com) 説明的な意味で原文にない&quot;before the Kuomintang related immigration wave&quot;を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In postwar Taiwan, the Kuomintang Party, which was defeated by communist forces in the Chinese civil war and moved to Taiwan, suppressed the native-born Taiwanese who had been living in Taiwan before the Kuomintang related immigration wave (the White Terror and the 228 incident in 1947 was the largest scale suppression) and developed the military-first policy with the national credo of &quot;counterattack the mainland,&quot; as a result the development of the infrastructure in Taiwan was put on the back-burner.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In postwar Taiwan, the Kuomintang Party, which was defeated by communist forces in the Chinese civil war and moved to Taiwan, suppressed the native-born Taiwanese who had been living in Taiwan before the Kuomintang related immigration wave (the White Terror and the 228 incident in 1947 was the largest scale suppression) and developed the military-first policy with the national credo of &quot;counterattack the mainland,&quot; and as a result, the development of the infrastructure in Taiwan was put on the back-burner.</e>
<cmt>・余分なスペースを詰めました。・内容を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>このため一部の本省人は「犬（煩いかわりに役には立つ）の代わりに豚（食べるばかりで役たたず）が来た」（狗走豬擱來）と大陸からやってきた人間を揶揄し、日本の統治時代を部分的・相対的に肯定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some native-born Taiwanese made a mockery of the people from the mainland China and affirmed partially and relatively the Japanese ruling, saying &quot;dogs (annoying but useful) left and pigs (which did nothing but eat) came&quot; (狗走猪擱來).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some native-born Taiwanese made a mockery of the people from mainland China and affirmed partially and relatively the Japanese ruling, saying &quot;dogs (annoying but useful) left and pigs (which did nothing but eat) came&quot; (狗走猪擱來).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some native-born Taiwanese made a mockery of the people from mainland China and affirmed partially and relatively the Japanese ruling, saying, &quot;dogs (annoying but useful = Japanese) left and pigs (which did nothing but eat = mainland Chinese) came&quot; (狗走猪擱來).</e>
<cmt>表現を補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="225">
<j>前総統の李登輝は国民党の独裁政治を廃し台湾内での民主化を導いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teng-hui LEE, the former chairman, stopped the dictatorship of the Kuomingtang Party and promoted the democratic reforms in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>李登輝→Teng-hui LEE (表記がいくつかありますが、CNNの表記を使用しました）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teng-hui LEE, the former chairman, stopped the dictatorship of the Kuomingtang Party and promoted democratic reforms in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teng-hui LEE, the former President of the Republic of China, stopped the dictatorship of the Kuomintang Party and promoted democratic reforms in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>・「総統」は「中華民国の総統」なので修正しました。・「国民党」のスペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>李登輝の時代に監修された台湾の歴史教科書「認識台湾（歴史編）」では、従来地方史として軽視されていた台湾史を本国史として扱い、特に日本の統治時代を重点的に論じたが、この認識台湾は陳水扁の民進党政権時代に公教育から撤廃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history textbook compiled during Teng-hui LEE&apos;s tenure titled &quot;認識台湾(歴史編)&quot; (Perception of Taiwan [History]) treated the history of Taiwan as national history, which had been neglected as regional history, and focused on the period of Japanese rule, but the use of &quot;認識台湾&quot; in the public education discontinued during the period of the Democratic Progress Party government led by Shui-bian CHEN.</e>
<cmt>認識台湾（歴史編）→Perception of Taiwan (History) 定訳不明です認識台湾は～撤廃された→使われなくなったという意味で&quot;the use of&quot; を挿入しました。陳水扁→Shui-bian CHEN</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history textbook compiled during Teng-hui LEE&apos;s tenure titled &quot;認識台湾(歴史編)&quot; (Perception of Taiwan [History]) treated the history of Taiwan as national history, which had been neglected as regional history, and focused on the period of Japanese rule, but the use of &quot;認識台湾&quot; in the public education discontinued during the period of the Democratic Progress Party government led by Shui-bian CHEN.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history textbook compiled during Teng-hui LEE&apos;s tenure titled &apos;認識台湾 (歴史編)&apos; (Perception of Taiwan [History]) treated the history of Taiwan, which had been neglected as regional history, as national history, and focused on the period of Japanese rule, but the Democratic Progress Party government led by Shui-bian CHEN stopped adopting the textbook in the public education.</e>
<cmt>・ダブルコーテーションをシングルにしました。・表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="227">
<j>総統引退後の李登輝は台湾の中華民国（中国）からの独立を訴えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Teng-hui LEE appealed the Taiwan&apos;s independence from the Republic of China (China) after retiring from the chairman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Teng-hui LEE appealed for Taiwan&apos;s independence from the Republic of China (China) after retiring from being chairmanp.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Teng-hui LEE appealed for Taiwan&apos;s independence from the Republic of China (China) after having retired from presidency.</e>
<cmt>表現を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>その中で国民党批判と共に日本の統治政策を再評価を訴えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his appealing he criticized the Kuomintang and re-evaluated the Japan&apos;s governance policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In his appeal he criticized the Kuomintang and re-evaluated Japan&apos;s governance policies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In his appeal he criticized the Kuomintang Party and re-evaluated Japan&apos;s governance policies.</e>
<cmt>Kuomintang Partyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="229">
<j>一方で国民党や親民党は李登輝の日本評価を売国的であると批判し、日本統治時代についても日本による搾取に過ぎなかったと位置付けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the Kuomintang Party and the People First Party criticized Teng-hui LEE&apos;s evaluation on Japan as quislingism and positioned the period of Japanese rule as the one being exploited by Japan.</e>
<cmt>親民党→People First Party</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the Kuomintang Party and the People First Party criticized Teng-hui LEE&apos;s evaluation of Japan as quislingism and positioned the period of Japanese rule as one being exploited by Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the Kuomintang Party and the People First Party criticized Teng-hui LEE&apos;s evaluation of Japan as quislingism and positioned the period of Japanese rule as one being exploited by Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>また民主進歩党では日本統治に対して同情的ではあるが、植民地主義は現代において認められないとの立場を表明しており、日本統治を評価しつつも、その根底に存在した植民地主義を批判する立場を取っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Democratic Progressive Party was more sympathetic toward the Japanese rule but made it clear that the colonialism was not accepted today, so it valued the Japanese rule to some extent but took a stance to criticize the colonialism based on which Japan ruled Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>民主進歩党→Democratic Progressive Party</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Democratic Progressive Party was more sympathetic toward Japanese rule but made it clear that colonialism was not accepted today, so it valued the Japanese rule to some extent, but took a stance to criticize the colonialism based upon which Japan ruled Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Democratic Progressive Party is more sympathetic toward Japanese rule but makes it clear that colonialism was not accepted today, so it values the Japanese rule to some extent, but takes a stance to criticize the colonialism based upon which Japan ruled Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>時制を現在にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="231">
<j>日本統治時代の台湾での評価は朝鮮に比べて肯定的であり、特に日本時代に育った層は、その時代を懐かしみ、評価する者も多く、そのような声を載せた著書も数多く出版されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The public evaluation of the Japanese rule is more positive in Taiwan than in Korea, and many people, especially those who were grown up under the Japanese rule, longed for the days of the Japanese rule and valued it, and there have been many books carrying such voices too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The public evaluation of the Japanese rule is more positive in Taiwan than in Korea, and many people, especially those who grew up under Japanese rule, longed for the days of the Japanese rule and valued it, and there have been many books carrying such voices too.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The public evaluation of the Japanese rule is more positive in Taiwan than in Korea, and many people, especially those who grew up under Japanese rule, long for the days of the Japanese rule and value it, and there have been many books carrying such voices too.</e>
<cmt>時制を現在にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>その影響もあり台湾人は日本には好意的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore Taiwanese are friendly to Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore Taiwanese are friendly to Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore Taiwanese are friendly to Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Cck1988(id:242533), Los688(id:12316), Nnh(id:474), Shizhao(id:1325), Hhaithait(id:37092), 経済準学士(id:22656), 22010515528(id:43149), Lichenes(id:22557), Rename1014b(id:53199), Kamakura(id:472), Tribot(id:186681), Petz(id:95202), Naigai(id:288953), ぱろれろ(id:179604), Redpepper(id:58488), ПФК ЦСКА София(id:81859), PPP(id:22924), RON ST(id:156891), IwaimBot(id:190695), Amikake3(id:89826), Bow(id:16755), 十詩子(id:58571), Lemon pie(id:66842), BoB774(id:148281), いろはにほへと(id:89648), Carbuncle(id:346), Nallimbot(id:230812), Redtea(id:237140), 李小明(id:174463), Sh(id:2707), 李李(id:23108), Necromania2(id:58921), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ＮｉＫｅ(id:7512), Mine-Kansai(id:2080), Balmung0731-AWB(id:223943), 蔭人(id:80171), 立志堂(id:132177), TT(id:46431), ドラムスコ(id:40234), Straysheep(id:42448), 鉞(id:5476), Uaa(id:136371), Honeplus(id:35348), Charlesy(id:137799), Kumatora(id:16941), Esistdas(id:59219), Sgi1962(id:80778), Yytm2002(id:1723), Johncapistrano(id:969), Jossi(id:73665), Kurz(id:1601), Bandalgom(id:31841), Dondokken(id:246411), Real Madrid(id:27490), Kone(id:377), スミス16号(id:189050), Tsubame-ex(id:53988), Koika(id:16738), Yauchi(id:115025), Bankokuya(id:91191), あばさー(id:95106), Goronyan(id:192030), Hokuhoku(id:144300), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), Race(id:131322), Clarin(id:60278), Threetrees(id:188577), Yonoemon(id:55450), Suzuki jinro(id:180764), Ponsaku(id:31417), M at m(id:34756), Corwin(id:973), ちゃねらー(id:56717), Lincun(id:22742), Trek011(id:7105), Ssudo2002(id:22689), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>