<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>大河内氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ookouchi clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ookouchi Clan</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okochi Clan</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>大河内氏（おおこうちし）は、清和源氏、摂津源氏の一族で、源頼政の孫、顕綱（あきつな）が三河国額田郡大河内郷（愛知県岡崎市大平町字大河内・注、異説あり。洞町等）に移り住み、大河内氏を称したことを始まりとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ookouchi clan is part of the Seiwa Genji clan and Settsu Genji clan, and is said to have been established when Akitsuna, the grandson of Yorimasa MINAMOTO, moved to Ookouchikyo, Nukatagun in the Mikawa Province (now thought to be Aza-Ookouchi, Ohiracho, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture but different opinions exist.) and called himself Ookouchi.</e>
<cmt>洞町等が大河内に続くのか不明。括弧内で原文が分割されていますが、訳文では一つのセルに挿入。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ookouchi clan is part of the Seiwa Genji and Settsu Genji clans, and is said to have been established when Akitsuna, the grandson of Yorimasa MINAMOTO, moved to Ookouchikyo, Nukatagun in Mikawa Province (which some have asserted to be the present-day Aza-Ookouchi, Ohiracho, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) and called himself Ookouchi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Okochi clan is part of the Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan) and Settsu-Genji (Minamoto clan), and is said to have been established when Akitsuna, the grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, moved to Okochi-go, Nukata County in Mikawa Province (which some have asserted to be the present-day Aza-Okochi, Ohira-cho, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture) and called himself Okochi.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi(Minamoto clan) 追記して clans 削除Genji→-GenjiYorimasa MINAMOTO→MINAMOTO no Yorimasagun→CountyMikawa の前のスペース短縮Ohiracho→Ohira-choOkochikyo→Okochi-go</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>顕綱の父は源兼綱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitsuna&apos;s father was MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitsuna&apos;s father was MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitsuna&apos;s father was MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>しかし、大河内氏の初期段階の動向・系図には不明な点が多く、顕綱も信頼性のある資料に見えていないことから仮冒であるとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the activities and the family tree of the clan in its early period are imprecise, and the name of Akitsuna does not appear in any reliable source, so there is a view that the said origin is only an assumption.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the clan&apos;s activity and family tree aren&apos;t clearly defined, and the name &quot;Akitsuna&quot; doesn&apos;t appear in any reliable source, so to some the stated origin is only an assumption.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the clan&apos;s activity and family tree aren&apos;t clearly defined, and the name &quot;Akitsuna&quot; doesn&apos;t appear in any reliable source, so to some the stated origin is only an assumption.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>松平正綱の代に、徳川氏一族の河内源氏で新田氏流とされる長沢松平家の養子となり、それ以後は大河内松平家と言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA became an adopted son of Nagasawa Matsudaira family, which was said to be the Nitta clan branch of the Kawachi Genji clan which belonged to the House of Tokugawa, and since then the clan is known as the Ookouchi Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA became an adopted son of the Nagasawa Matsudaira family, which was said to be the Nitta clan branch of the Kawachi Genji clan, which in turn belonged to the House of Tokugawa; since then, the clan has been known as the Ookouchi Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA became an adopted son of the Nagasawa Matsudaira family, which was said to be the Nitta clan branch of the Kawachi Genji (Minamoto clan), which in turn belonged to the House of Tokugawa; since then, the clan has been known as the Okochi Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>clan→(Minamoto clan)Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代は大名や旗本であり、知恵伊豆と称される老中松平信綱などを輩出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period the family members held the ranks of daimyo (Japanese territorial lord) or hatamoto (samurai in the direct service of Tokugawa family), and produced prominent characters such as Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, a roju (Elder) with a nickname of &quot;the wisdom of Izu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period the family members held the ranks of daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) or hatamoto (samurai in the direct service of Tokugawa family), and produced prominent characters such as Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, a roju (elder) whose nickname mean &quot;The Wisdom of Izu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period the family members held the ranks of daimyo (Japanese territorial lords) or hatamoto (samurai in the direct service of Tokugawa family), and produced prominent characters such as Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, a roju (elder) whose nickname meant &quot;The Wisdom of Izu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>mean→meant</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>明治に入り、大河内姓に復する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan restored the name of Ookouchi in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Meiji period, the clan restored the Ookouchi name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Meiji period, the clan restored the Okochi name.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>長沢松平家に養子になる前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family history before Masatsuna was adopted by the Nagasawa Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family history before Masatsuna was adopted by the Nagasawa Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family history before Masatsuna was adopted by the Nagasawa Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="7">
<j>以仁王の乱（治承4年（1180年））で、祖父源頼政と父源兼綱を討たれた源顕綱は母と共に三河国額田郡大河内郷（現在の東名高速道路の岡崎インターチェンジの辺り）に落ちた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitsuna MINAMOTO, who lost both his grandfather, MINAMOTO no Yorimasa, and father, MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna in the Mochihitoo Rebellion of 1180, fled to Ookouchikyo, Nukatagun in Mikawa Prefecture (now near the Okazaki interchange of the Tomei Highway) with his mother.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitsuna MINAMOTO, who lost his grandfather MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and father MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna in the Mochihitoo Rebellion of 1180, fled to Ookouchikyo, Nukatagun, in Mikawa Prefecture (now near the Okazaki interchange of the Tomei Highway) with his mother.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">MINAMOTO no Akitsuna, who lost his grandfather MINAMOTO no Yorimasa and father MINAMOTO no Kanetsuna in the War of Prince Mochihito of 1180, fled to Okochi-go, Nukata County, in Mikawa Province (now near the Okazaki interchange of the Tomei Highway) with his mother.</e>
<cmt>源顕綱の表現を訂正Mochihitoo Rebellion→War of Prince MochihitoOkochikyo→Okochi-gogun→CountyPrefecture→Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>後に足利義氏 (足利家3代目当主)（文治5年（1189年）～建長6年（1255年））が承久の乱（承久3年（1221年））の戦功により鎌倉幕府の命で守護職として三河国に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (1189 to 1255), the third head of the Ashikaga family, was later appointed the Military Governor of the Mikawa prefecture by the Kamakura Shogunate as a reward for his contributions during the Jokyu Rebellion of 1221.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (1189 - 1255), the third head of the Ashikaga family, was later appointed to serve as the military governor of Mikawa Prefecture by the Kamakura shogunate as a reward for his contributions during the Jokyu Rebellion of 1221.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA (1189 - 1255), the third head of the Ashikaga family, was later appointed to serve as the military governor of Mikawa Province by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as a reward for his contributions during the Jokyu War of 1221.</e>
<cmt>Prefecture→Provinceshogunate→bakufuRebellion→War</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>顕綱は年下の足利義氏の傘下に家臣として入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akitsuna joined the service of Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, who was Akitsuna&apos;s junior in age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akitsuna joined the service of Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, who was Akitsuna&apos;s junior in age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akitsuna joined the service of Yoshiuji ASHIKAGA, who was Akitsuna&apos;s junior in age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>この源顕綱が初代大河内顕綱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Akitsuna MINAMOTO is the first Akitsuna OOKOUCHI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Akitsuna MINAMOTO is the first Akitsuna OOKOUCHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This MINAMOTO no Akitsuna is the first Akitsuna OKOCHI.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi源顕綱の表現を訂正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その子、大河内政綱（政顕）は足利泰氏の臣下となったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His son, Masatsuna (Masaaki) OOKOUCHI, is said to have been retained by Yasuuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His son, Masatsuna (Masaaki) OOKOUCHI, is said to have been retained by Yasuuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His son, Masatsuna (Masaaki) OKOCHI, is said to have been retained by Yasuuji ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>その後、大河内家は足利一門の血統の吉良氏の家老となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, the Ookouchi family held the post of minister of the Kira family, who are part of the Ashikaga family tree.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, the Ookouchi family held the post of minister of the Kira family, which was part of the Ashikaga family tree.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, the Okochi family held the post of chief retainer of the Kira family, which was part of the Ashikaga family tree.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochiminister→chief retainer</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>幡豆郡の寺津城(西尾市寺津町）を拠点とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They operated from the Teratsu Castle in Hazunokori area (now Teratsucho town in Nishio city).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It operated from Teratsu Castle in the Hazunokori area (now Teratsucho Town, Nishio City).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It operated from Teratsu-jo Castle in the Hazunokori area (now Teratsu-cho Town, Nishio City).</e>
<cmt>Teratsu→Teratsu-joTeratsucho→Teratsu-cho</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>大河内氏の正紋から臥蝶城とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle is also called Fusecho Castle because of the design of the formal crest of the Ookouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The castle is also called Fusecho Castle due to the design of the formal crest that represented the Ookouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The castle is also called Fusecho-jo Castle due to the design of the formal crest that represented the Okochi clan.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→OkochiFusecho→Fusecho-jo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>吉良氏の所領である遠江国引馬荘（静岡県浜松市）の代官となった一流がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A branch of the family came to take the post of daikan (regional administrator) of the Hikumaso in the Totoumi Prefecture (now Hamamatsu City of the Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A branch of the family came to take the post of daikan (regional administrator) of the Hikumaso, in Totoumi Prefecture (now Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A branch of the family came to take the post of daikan (regional administrator) of the Hikumaso, in Totoumi Province (now Hamamatsu City, Shizuoka Prefecture) which was the territory of the Kira clan.</e>
<cmt>Prefecture→Province「吉良氏の所領である」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大河内貞綱は斯波氏と結び今川氏に執拗に抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sadatsuna OOKOUCHI joined hands with the Shiba clan and determinedly fought against the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳分例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sadatsuna OOKOUCHI joined hands with the Shiba clan and determinedly fought against the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sadatsuna OKOCHI joined hands with the Shiba clan and determinedly fought against the Imagawa clan.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>12代金兵衛秀綱（天文15年（1546年） - 元和 (日本)4年（1618年）9月13日 (旧暦)）の代になって徳川家康に属し、秀綱は慶長年間に鹿沼市で代官をつとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 12th generation, Kinbei Hidetsuna (1546 to September 13, 1618) was retained by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became daikan of Kanuma City during the Keicho years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The twelfth generation, Kinbei Hidetsuna (1546 to September 13, 1618) was retained by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became the daikan of Kanuma City during the Keicho years.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 12th generation, Kinbei Hidetsuna (1546 to September 13, 1618 [old calendar]) was retained by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA and became the daikan (local governor) of Kanuma City during the Keicho years.</e>
<cmt>数字表記変更[old calendar]　追記代官の説明補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>近世以前に分かれた一族の別系に、代々「大河内善兵衛」を称した旗本があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the members of the family branch that split before the modern times, there was a family of hatamoto who used the name &quot;Zenbei Ookouchi&quot; down the generation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the members of the family branch that split prior to the modern times, there was a family of hatamoto that passed the name &quot;Zenbei Ookouchi&quot; down through the generations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the members of the family branch that split prior to the modern times, there was a family of hatamoto that passed the name &apos;Zenbei OKOCHI&apos; down through the generations.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>長沢松平家に養子になって以後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Family history after being adopted by the Nagasawa Matsudaira family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Family history after adoption by the Nagasawa Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Family history after adoption by the Nagasawa Matsudaira family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>天正15年（1587年）、徳川家康により、大河内秀綱の二男松平正綱が長沢松平家庶流の松平正次の養子となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1587, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA arranged Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA, the second son of Hidetsuna OOKOUCHI, to become a adopted son of Masatsugu MATSUDAIRA, who belonged to the Nagasawa Matsudaira family group.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1587, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA arranged for Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA, the second son of Hidetsuna OOKOUCHI, to become an adopted son of Masatsugu MATSUDAIRA, who belonged to the Nagasawa Matsudaira family group.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1587, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA arranged for Masatsuna MATSUDAIRA, the second son of Hidetsuna OKOCHI, to become an adopted son of Masatsugu MATSUDAIRA, who belonged to the Nagasawa Matsudaira family group.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>旗本として出世の後、元和 (日本)3年（1617年）に相模国玉縄藩2万2000石の大名となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masatsuna rose in ranks as hatamoto then became daimyo of the Tamatsuna domain in the Sagami Prefecture with 22,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masatsuna rose through the ranks as hatamoto and eventually became the daimyo of the Tamatsuna domain in Sagami Prefecture, with 22,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masatsuna rose through the ranks as hatamoto and eventually became the daimyo of the Tamatsuna domain in Sagami Province, with 22,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>Prefecture→Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このため大河内一族は松平氏を称することが許され大河内松平家と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is why the Ookouchi family is allowed to use the name of Matsudaira, and the family is called Ookouchi Matsudaira.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is why the Ookouchi family is allowed to use the Matsudaira name and is therefore called Ookouchi Matsudaira.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is why the Okochi family is allowed to use the Matsudaira name and is therefore called Okochi Matsudaira.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>江戸時代は、大名の家が三家有った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, there were three daimyos in the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, there were three daimyo in the family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, there were three daimyo in the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>松平伊豆守という名は、大河内氏の一分家の大名が代々名乗った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A daimyo in one of the Ookouchi family branches used the name Matsudaira Izunokami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A daimyo in one of the Ookouchi family branches used the name &quot;Matsudaira Izunokami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A daimyo in one of the Okochi family branches used the name &quot;Matsudaira Izunokami.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>武蔵国忍藩（埼玉県行田市）そして川越藩主（同県川越市）であり智慧伊豆と謳われる松平信綱は大河内氏である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, who was the lord of Oshi domain in the Musashi Prefecture (Gyoda City, Saitama Prefecture) and of Kawagoe domain (Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture), and was revered as the &quot;wisdom of Izu&quot; was a member of the Ookouchi clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, who was the lord of the Oshi domain in Musashi Prefecture (Gyoda City, Saitama Prefecture) and of the Kawagoe domain (Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture), and who was revered as the &quot;Wisdom of Izu,&quot; was a member of the Ookouchi clan.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobutsuna MATSUDAIRA, who was the lord of the Oshi domain in Musashi Prrovince (Gyoda City, Saitama Prefecture) and of the Kawagoe domain (Kawagoe City, Saitama Prefecture), and who was revered as the &quot;Wisdom of Izu,&quot; was a member of the Okochi clan.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→OkochiPrefecture→Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>明治以後は旗本の家も大河内氏に戻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Meiji period, families who were hatamoto also reverted to the name of Ookouchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Meiji period, families that were hatamoto also reverted to the Ookouchi name.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Meiji period, families that were hatamoto also reverted to the Okochi name.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>大名の三家は、爵位を下され、子爵となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The three daimyo families were given peerage and became viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The three daimyo families were given peerage and became viscounts.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The three daimyo families were given peerage and became viscounts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>末裔には理化学研究所の所長も務めた物理学者の大河内正敏がいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decendents include Masatoshi OOKOUCHI, a physicist, who was the Director of the Science and Chemistry Institute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decendents include Masatoshi OOKOUCHI, a physicist who was the director of the Science and Chemistry Institute.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decendents include Masatoshi OKOCHI, a physicist who was the director of the Science and Chemistry Institute.</e>
<cmt>Ookochi→Okochi</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>紋所</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the family crest</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family crest</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family crest</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="28">
<j>家紋は、正紋が臥蝶に十六菊（ふせちょうにじゅうろくきく）（通称、伊豆蝶）、替紋が三ツ扇（みつおうぎ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formal crest is a butterfly with 16 chrysanthemums (commonly called Izu butterfly) and the alternative crest is three fans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formal crest is a butterfly with 16 chrysanthemums (commonly called an Izu butterfly), and the alternative crest is three fans.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formal crest is a butterfly with 16 chrysanthemums (commonly called an Izu butterfly), and the alternative crest is three fans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>また、分家の上野国高崎藩（群馬県高崎市）の家系の替紋は高崎扇と呼ばれ、この形を基盤に高崎市立の高崎経済大学の高崎経済大学学章ができた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The alternative crest of one of the branches, in Takasaki Domain, Ueno Prefecture (Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture) is called Takasaki fan, and the school crest of the Takasaki Economic University, which is a public university run by Takasaki City, was created out of this crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The alternative crest of one of the branches, in the Takasaki domain, Ueno Prefecture (Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture), is called Takasaki fan, and the school crest of Takasaki Economics University, which is a public university run by Takasaki City, was created from this crest.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The alternative crest of one of the branches, in the Takasaki domain, Kozuke Province (Takasaki City, Gunma Prefecture), is called Takasaki-ogi crest, and the school crest of Takasaki Economics University, which is a public university run by Takasaki City, was created from this crest.</e>
<cmt>上野国の読み方訂正Takasaki fan→ Takasaki-ogi crest</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Gimbrow(id:65660), やりたこ(id:113528), Cprobot(id:97843), 松茸(id:27535), ふぉるて(id:85845), しまながし(id:90740), BAKU(id:55205), 総州之毛豆(id:26880), GAVVA(id:47103), 小者(id:172526), Masyu(id:31065), 墓石と鉄塔(id:18104), Yonoemon(id:55450), Nalc(id:139567), 編集仁王(id:208160), ウィキ豊(id:82961), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>