<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>成功 (任官)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jougou (government posting)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jougou (government posting)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogo</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので補足を削除し表記を変えました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>成功(じょうごう)とは、朝廷の公事・行事及び殿舎の営繕、寺社の堂塔修造費用など本来、朝廷の公費で負担すべきところを、任官希望者を募り任料を納めさせるか、または自己負担でそれぞれの事業の功を成らせて、見返りに官職に叙任するという売官制度の一種である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jougou is a form of a cash-for-government posts system whereby those aspiring for a government post would either directly pay to gain an appointment or pay the expenses of public functions or events of the Imperial Court, building or repairing of the main residence, or repairing of holy towers (sympolizing the tomb of Buddha) in temples and shrines, which should be paid from the coffers of the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jougou was a system by which those aspiring to a government post would either pay directly to gain an appointment, or pay for expenses that would otherwise have had to be paid from the coffers of the Imperial Court, such as those incurred in carrying out public functions or events for the Imperial Court, building or repairing the palace, or repairing the buildings and pagodas of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>It is always useful if the translator provides the reader with extra information, but I think &quot;holy towers (symbolizing the tomb of Buddha) in temples and shrines&quot; goes a little beyond what is necessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jogo was a system by which those aspiring to a government post would either pay directly to gain an appointment, or pay for expenses that would otherwise have had to be paid from the coffers of the Imperial Court, such as those incurred in carrying out public functions or events for the Imperial Court, building or repairing the palace, or repairing the buildings and pagodas of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>律令においては、無官の者は散位寮、勲等を有する者は軍団 (古代日本)に勤仕することとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statute at the time required that those without a government post must serve in the San-ino-ryo (a department for those with ranks but without a government post) while those with an order of merit to serve in the military.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statute at the time required that those without a government post must serve in the San-ino-ryo (a department for those who held ranks but were not assigned government posts) while requiring those with an order of merit to serve in the military.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statute at the time required that those without a government post must serve in the Sani no ryo (a department for those who held ranks but were not assigned government posts) while requiring those with an order of merit to serve in the military.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>但し、これらの任務には定員が定められるようになり、次第に定員外の者については銭を納めて労にかえることが許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, once the capacities for the department and the military were determined, those beyond the capacity were gradually allowed to replace labor for money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, once the capacities for the department and the military were determined, those beyond the capacity were gradually allowed to replace labor with money.</e>
<cmt>preposition</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, once the capacities for the department and the military were determined, those beyond the capacity were gradually allowed to replace labor with money.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>これが、続労銭という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such monetary contribution was called Zokurosen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such monetary contribution was called Zokurosen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was called Zokurosen.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>こうした習慣は南北朝時代 (日本)まで続いたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system is believed to have continued until the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system is believed to have continued until the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system is believed to have continued until the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Freedonian(id:110955), Shimoxx(id:9332), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>