<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>若江八人衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakae Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>若江八人衆（わかえはちにんしゅう）は豊臣秀次の精鋭家臣団の通称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu is a popular term for the group of elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakae Hachinin-shu is a popular term for the group of elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu is a popular term for the group of elite retainers of Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>後に石田三成に仕えたものが多く、その多くが忠誠を誓い、関ヶ原の戦いで奮戦し、ほとんどが戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of those who belonged to Wakae Hachinin-shu later served Mitsunari ISHII, and they pledged their loyalty to their master and fought in the Battle of Sekigahara, as a result of which most of them died.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of those who belonged to Wakae Hachinin-shu later served Mitsunari ISHII, and they pledged their loyalty to their master and fought in the Battle of Sekigahara, as a result of which most of them died.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of those who belonged to Wakae Hachinin-shu later served Mitsunari ISHIDA, and they pledged their loyalty to their master and fought in the Battle of Sekigahara, as a result of which most of them died.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>経歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>出自</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>多くの武将は三好康長に仕えていた家臣であるが、豊臣秀吉が人選して甥で後継者候補の豊臣秀次の配下にしたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although most of members of Wakae Hachinin-shu were originally military commanders who served Yasunaga MIYOSHI as his retainers, they came to serve Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, who was a prospective successor of Hideyoshi, personally chosen by Hideyoshi himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although most of members of Wakae Hachinin-shu were originally military commanders who served Yasunaga MIYOSHI as his retainers, they came to serve Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, who was a prospective successor of Hideyoshi, personally chosen by Hideyoshi himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although most of members of Wakae Hachinin-shu were originally military commanders who served Yasunaga MIYOSHI as his retainers, they came to serve Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI, who was a prospective successor of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI, personally chosen by Hideyoshi himself.</e>
<cmt>人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>八人衆は秀次をよく補佐し、各地を転戦しつつ武名をあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu supported Hidetsugu with professionalism, and they fought in many places and distinguished themselves as military commanders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wakae Hachinin-shu supported Hidetsugu with professionalism, and they fought in many places and distinguished themselves as military commanders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wakae Hachinin-shu supported Hidetsugu with professionalism, and they fought in many places and distinguished themselves as military commanders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>転機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A Turning Point</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Turning Point</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A turning point</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし文禄2年（1593年）に秀吉に嫡男・豊臣秀頼が生まれると事態は急変し、関白の地位に就いていた秀次の立場は微妙になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the situation changed completely as a result of the birth of Hideyoshi&apos;s son, Hideyori in 1593, and the status of Hidetsugu as Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor) became insecure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the situation changed completely as a result of the birth of Hideyoshi&apos;s son, Hideyori in 1593, and the status of Hidetsugu as Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor) became insecure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the situation changed completely as a result of the birth of Hideyoshi&apos;s son, Hideyori in 1593, and the status of Hidetsugu as Kanpaku (the chief adviser to the Emperor) became insecure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>秀次は将来に不安を抱き、京都などで辻斬り（一般人を殺傷する事件、盲目の人間を故なく殺害したとされる）などを起こし「殺生関白」という悪名を広めたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidetsugu, who was frightened for his own future, caused the incidents of tsujikiri (killing ordinary people in the street to test a new sword; it is said that he killed a blind person without a reason) in Kyoto and other places, and the incidents labeled him as &quot;Sessho Kanpaku&quot; (Killer-Kanpaku).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidetsugu, who was frightened for his own future, caused incidents of tsujikiri (killing ordinary people in the street to test a new sword; it is said that he killed a blind person without a reason) in Kyoto and other places, and the incidents labeled him as &quot;Sessho Kanpaku&quot; (Killer-Kanpaku).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidetsugu, who was frightened for his own future, caused incidents of tsujikiri (killing ordinary people in the street to test a new sword; it is said that he killed a blind person without a reason) in Kyoto and other places, and the incidents labeled him as &apos;Sessho Kanpaku&apos; (Killer-Kanpaku).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>様々な陰謀説が議論されており実情は不明である（豊臣秀次参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The truth of the fact, however, is not known as there were various conspiracy theories (refer to the section on Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The truth of the fact, however, is not known as there were various conspiracy theories (refer to the section on Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The truth of the fact, however, is not known as there were various conspiracy theories (refer to the section on Hidetsugu TOYOTOMI).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>このころ秀吉は秀次の処分を考え始めたとされ、その直後に秀次の謀反の噂が広まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that Hideyoshi started to consider the punishment for Hidetsugu around this time, and the rumor about Hidetsugu as a rebel was starting to be spread after this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that Hideyoshi started to consider punishment for Hidetsugu around this time, and the rumor about Hidetsugu as a rebel started to spread after this.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that Hideyoshi started to consider punishment for Hidetsugu around this time, and the rumor about Hidetsugu as a rebel started to spread after this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>秀次の補佐役を任されていた前野長康は秀次のために奔走する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagayasu MAENO, who was given a role as an assistant of Hidetsugu, worked hard in order to save Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagayasu MAENO, who was given a role as an assistant of Hidetsugu, worked hard in order to save Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagayasu MAENO, who was given a role as an assistant of Hidetsugu, worked hard in order to save Hidetsugu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>特に石田三成は秀次助命のために奔走し、秀吉に「秀次公は無実であること」（武宗記）を直訴した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA, in particular, tried everything to save the life of Hidetsugu, and pleaded the &quot;innocence of the lord Hidetsugu&quot; (according to &quot;Buso-ki&quot;) directly to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari ISHIDA, in particular, tried everything to save the life of Hidetsugu, and pleaded the &quot;innocence of the lord Hidetsugu&quot; (according to &quot;Buso-ki&quot;) directly to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA, in particular, tried everything to save the life of Hidetsugu, and pleaded the &apos;innocence of the lord Hidetsugu&apos; (according to &quot;Buso-ki&quot;) directly to Hideyoshi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし秀吉は元々秀次の処分を考えていた事もあって、高野山へ追放にした上、切腹させてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi, however, had already decided on the ultimate retribution for Hidetsugu, and he expelled Hidetsugu to Koya-san Mountain, and forced him to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi, however, had already decided on the ultimate retribution for Hidetsugu, and he expelled Hidetsugu to Koya-san Mountain, and forced him to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi, however, had already decided on the ultimate retribution for Hidetsugu, and he expelled Hidetsugu to Mt. Koya, and forced him to commit seppuku (suicide by disembowelment).</e>
<cmt>用語統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>再起</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Return to the Fore</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Return to the Fore</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Return to the fore</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>秀次の豊臣家が断絶したため、若江八人衆を含め、多くの武将が連座し浪人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the family line of the Toyotomi family became extinct, many military commanders, including Wakae Hachinin-shu became ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the family line of the Toyotomi family became extinct, many military commanders, including Wakae Hachinin-shu became ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Hidetsugu&apos;s family line of the Toyotomi family became extinct, many military commanders, including Wakae Hachinin-shu became ronin (masterless samurai).</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>石田三成は無実であった秀次家臣団を哀れみ、また、浪人増加による社会不安を防ぐため、多くの秀次家臣団を石田氏に受け入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA, who felt the need to prevent the social instability that may result from the increasing number of ronin, took pity on the former vassals of Hidetsugu and accepted them into the Ishida clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsunari ISHIDA, who felt the need to prevent the social instability that may result from the increasing number of ronin, took pity on the former vassals of Hidetsugu and accepted them into the Ishida clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsunari ISHIDA, who felt the need to prevent the social instability that may result from the increasing number of ronin, took pity on the former vassals of Hidetsugu and accepted them into the Ishida clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>また、若江八人衆も秀次助命のため最後まで奔走した三成に感謝し、慶長5年（1600年）の勃発した関ヶ原の戦いでは石田三成軍の本陣を死守する獅子奮迅の戦いをしている（ただし、藤堂玄蕃は従兄弟の藤堂高虎に仕え、安井喜内は浅野幸長に仕えるなど、必ずしも全員が三成に尽くしたわけではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members of Wakae Hachinin-shu were also grateful for Mitsunari who tried his best to save Hidetsugu&apos;s life, and in return, they fought to protect the army headquarter of Mitsunari ISHIDA during the Battle of Sekigahara, which started in 1600(However, not all the members served Mitsunari, as there were exceptions such as Yoshimasa TODO who served his cousin Takatora TODO and Kinai YASUI who served Yoshinaga ASANO).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members of Wakae Hachinin-shu were also grateful for Mitsunari who tried his best to save Hidetsugu&apos;s life, and in return, they fought to protect the army headquarters of Mitsunari ISHIDA during the Battle of Sekigahara, which started in 1600 (However, not all the members served Mitsunari, as there were exceptions such as Yoshimasa TODO who served his cousin Takatora TODO and Kinai YASUI who served Yoshinaga ASANO).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members of Wakae Hachinin-shu were also grateful for Mitsunari who tried his best to save Hidetsugu&apos;s life, and in return, they fought to protect the army headquarters of Mitsunari ISHIDA during the Battle of Sekigahara, which started in 1600 (However, not all the members served Mitsunari, as there were exceptions such as Yoshimasa TODO who served his cousin Takatora TODO and Kinai YASUI who served Yoshinaga ASANO).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>関ヶ原の戦いでの戦歴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War Careers at the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War Careers during the Battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War careers during the battle of Sekigahara</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="15">
<j>大場土佐（石田隊右翼を守備し奮戦する。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosa OBA (he protected and fought for the right wing of the Ishida squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosa OBA (he protected and fought for the right wing of the Ishida squad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosa OBA (he protected and fought for the right wing of the Ishida squad.)</e>
<cmt>)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>（戦後は生き残って蜂須賀至鎮に仕えた）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He survived the Battle of Sekigahara, after which he served Yoshishige HACHISUKA.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He survived the Battle of Sekigahara, after which he served Yoshishige HACHISUKA.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(He survived the Battle of Sekigahara, after which he served Yoshishige HACHISUKA.)</e>
<cmt>(補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>大山伯耆（石田隊先鋒として奮戦、討死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoki OYAMA (he fought for the superhead convoy of the Ishida squad, and died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoki OYAMA (he fought for the superhead convoy of the Ishida squad, and died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoki OYAMA (He fought for the spearhead convoy of the Ishida squad, and died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>高野越中（関ヶ原では石田隊で奮戦して生き残り、戦後は浅野幸長に仕えた）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ecchu TAKANO (he fought for the Ishida squad and survived the Battle, and later served Yukinaga ASANO.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ecchu TAKANO (he fought for the Ishida squad and survived the Battle, and later served Yukinaga ASANO.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ecchu TAKANO (He fought for the Ishida squad and survived the Battle, and later served Yukinaga ASANO.)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>藤堂玄蕃（東軍・藤堂隊先鋒として奮戦、討死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimasa TODO (he fought for the east army, and the superhead convoy of the Todo squad, and died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimasa TODO (he fought for the east army, and the superhead convoy of the Todo squad, and died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimasa TODO (He fought for the east army, and the spearhead convoy of the Todo squad, and died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>前野忠康（前野忠康）（石田隊先鋒として奮戦、嫡男とともに討死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadayasu MAENO (he fought for the superhead convoy of the Ishida squad, and died during the battle, together with his son.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadayasu MAENO (he fought for the superhead convoy of the Ishida squad, and died during the battle, together with his son.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadayasu MAENO (He fought for the spearhead convoy of the Ishida squad, and died during the battle, together with his son.)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>牧野成里（石田隊後方を守備、戦後は生き残って徳川氏の旗本となる）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigesato MAKINO (he protected and fought as the rearguard of the Ishida squad, and survived the Battle, after which became hatamoto (direct retainers) of the Tokugawa clan.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigesato MAKINO (he protected and fought as the rearguard of the Ishida squad, and survived the Battle, after which he became hatamoto (direct retainer) of the Tokugawa clan.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigesato MAKINO (He protected and fought as the rearguard of the Ishida squad, and survived the Battle, after which he became hatamoto (direct retainer) of the Tokugawa clan.)</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>森九兵衛（石田隊先鋒として前方柵を防衛、奮戦し討死）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuhee Mori (he fought for the superhead convoy of the Ishida squad and protected the front line and exalted, but died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuhee Mori (he fought for the superhead convoy of the Ishida squad and protected the front line and exalted, but died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuhee MORI (He fought for the spearhead convoy of the Ishida squad and protected the front line and exalted, but died during the battle.)</e>
<cmt>スペル人名修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>安井喜内（秀次没後は浅野幸長に仕え、大坂の役では徳川方として参加）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinai YASUI (After the death of Hidetsugu, he served Yukinaga ASANO, and at the Siege of Osaka, he joined the army of Tokugawa.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinai YASUI (After the death of Hidetsugu, he served Yukinaga ASANO, and at the Siege of Osaka, he joined the army of Tokugawa.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinai YASUI (After the death of Hidetsugu, he served Yukinaga ASANO, and at the Siege of Osaka, he joined the army of Tokugawa.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>異説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heresy</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heresy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heresy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>若江「八人衆」ではなく、若江七人衆であるという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a different opinion that it was in fact Wakae Shichinin-shu (seven elite retainers of Wakae), and not Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a difference of opinion that it was in fact Wakae Shichinin-shu (seven elite retainers of Wakae), and not Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a difference of opinion that it was in fact Wakae Shichinin-shu (seven elite retainers of Wakae), and not Hachinin-shu (eight elite retainers).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>また、構成員の中には秀次の近侍として仕えた富田高定（前田利長に仕えて、関ヶ原で北陸にて戦死）を含める場合もあるなど、史料によっては八人ではなく七人ともされ、さらにメンバーも変わることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other case, Takasada TOMITA, who served Hidetsugu closely, is included as a member, and depending on the historical documents, the number of the members is seven, and not eight, and there is a case in which even the consisting members themselves are different.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In another case, Takasada TOMITA, who served Hidetsugu closely, was included as a member, and depending upon the historical documents, the number of the members were seven, and not eight, and there was a case in which even the members themselves were different.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In another case, Takasada TOMITA, who served Hidetsugu closely, later served Toshinaga MAEDA and died during the Battle of Sekigahara, was included as a member, and depending upon the historical documents, the number of the members were seven, and not eight, and there was a case in which even the members themselves were different.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), ドルチェット(id:46458), Kuro-hato(id:34041), Moltke(id:17553), 水野白楓(id:22811), Point136(id:211299), Ko1(id:27076), こぶまき(id:38278), Sea of Japan(id:3230), 百人(id:16483), Bue(id:237847), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>