<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>年爵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nenshaku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nenshaku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nenshaku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>年爵（ねんしゃく）とは、日本の古代・中世前期において、治天の君及び三宮（太皇太后、皇太后、皇后）が保有していた叙位権を指す用語。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Nenshaku means the right to confer a court rank on a person that was granted to chiten no kimi (the retired Emperor in power) and sangu (the Three Empresses : Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager and Empress) in Japan&apos;s ancient/early medieval period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Nenshaku means the right to confer a court rank on a person that was granted to chiten no kimi (the retired Emperor in power) and sangu (the Three Empresses : Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager and Empress) in Japan&apos;s ancient/early medieval period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Nenshaku means the right to confer a court rank on a person that was granted to chiten no kimi (the Retired Emperor in power) and sangu (the Three Empresses : Great Empress Dowager, Empress Dowager and Empress) in Japan&apos;s ancient/early medieval period.</e>
<cmt>the Retired Emperorとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>毎年、治天ないし三宮に1人分の叙爵権を付与し、治天及び三宮は叙爵希望者より叙料を納めさせることで、従五位に叙爵させることができるとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each of chiten and sangu was given every year the right to confer a court rank on one person and allowed to confer the Junior Fifth Rank on one of applicants in return for the payment of joryo (a fee for attaining a court rank).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each of the chiten and sangu was given every year the right to confer a court rank on one person and allowed to confer the Junior Fifth Rank on one of the applicants in return for a payment of joryo (a fee for attaining a court rank).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each of the chiten and sangu was given every year the right to confer a court rank on one person and allowed to confer the Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank) on one of the applicants in return for a payment of joryo (a fee for attaining a court rank).</e>
<cmt>Junior Fifth Rank→Jugoi (Junior Fifth Rank)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>当該制度は平安時代初期にはじまり、次第に年爵の特典は女院や准后にも与えられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system started in the early Heian period and later, the privilege of nenshaku was also granted to nyoin (close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparative standing) and jugo (honorable rank next to the three empresses).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system started in the early Heian period and later, the privilege of nenshaku was also granted to nyoin (close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparative standing) and jugo (honorable rank next to the three empresses).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system started in the early Heian period and later, the privilege of nenshaku was also granted to nyoin (close female relatives of the Emperor or a woman of comparative standing) and jugo (honorable rank next to the three empresses).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>寺社や宮司に対して叙料を納めさせる代わりに叙爵する栄爵と同じく売位によるものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system was originally the sale of court rank, like the system of eishaku under which temples/shrines and guji (chief of those who serves shrine) were conferred court ranks in return for the payment of joryo..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system was originally the sale of court rank, like the system of eishaku under which temples/shrines and guji (chief of those who serves shrine) were conferred court ranks in return for a payment of joryo.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system was originally the sale of court rank, like the system of eishaku under which temples/shrines and guji (chief of those who serves shrine) were conferred court ranks in return for a payment of joryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、平安時代末期から鎌倉時代にかけて年爵による昇叙（加階）が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end Heian period and the Kamakura period, however, shojo (promotion) (kakai (promotion)) using nenshaku system became popular.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of the Heian period and the Kamakura period however, shojo (promotion) (kakai (promotion)) using the nenshaku system became popular.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of the Heian period and the Kamakura period however, shojo (promotion) (kakai (promotion)) using the nenshaku system became popular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Shimoxx(id:9332), 水野白楓(id:22811), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>