<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平治の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>平治の乱（へいじのらん）は平安時代の平治元年12月9日 (旧暦)（1159年1月19日）より発生した、院の近臣らの対立により起きた政変である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heiji Rebellion (Heiji no ran), which began on January 19, 1159 (the ninth day of the second month of Heiji 1 according to the old lunisolar calendar) was a coup d&apos;etat that occurred because of antagonism among the close vassals of the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heiji Rebellion (Heiji no ran), which began on January 19, 1159 (the ninth day of the second month of Heiji 1 according to the old lunisolar calendar) was a coup d&apos;etat that occurred because of antagonism among the close vassals of the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heiji Rebellion (Heiji no ran), which began on January 19, 1159 in Heian period, was a coup d&apos;etat that occurred because of antagonism among the close vassals of the retired emperor.</e>
<cmt>旧暦の表記は不要と考え、削除しました。in Heian period,補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>文中の（）の年はユリウス暦、月日は西暦部分を除き全て和暦、宣明暦の長暦による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note: all subsequent years given are according to the Julian calendar, while except for a few dates also given according to the Western calendar, all months and days are given under the Japanese calendar--specifically, the long version of the (originally Chinese) Senmyoreki calendar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Note: all subsequent years given are according to the Julian calendar, while except for a few dates also given according to the Western calendar, all months and days are given under the Japanese calendar--specifically, the long version of the (originally Chinese) Senmyoreki calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Note: all subsequent years given are according to the Julian calendar, while except for a few dates also given according to the Western calendar, all months and days are given under the Japanese calendar--specifically, the long version of the (originally Chinese) Senmyoreki calendar.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress of the Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress of the Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress of the Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>信西の執政</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei&apos;s (that is, FUJIWARA no Michinori) administration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei&apos;s (that is, FUJIWARA no Michinori) administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei&apos;s (that is, FUJIWARA no Michinori) administration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>保元元年（1156年）の保元の乱に勝利した後白河天皇は、同年閏9月に『保元新制』と呼ばれる代替わり新制を発令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Shirakawa, who had emerged victorious from the Hogen Rebellion that occurred in 1156 (the first year of the Hogen era), proclaimed the creation of a new government, called the Hogen shinsei (new governmment of Hogen), in the intercalary ninth month of 1156 as part of the switch to a new era name (that is, Hogen).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Shirakawa, who had emerged victorious from the Hogen Rebellion that occurred in 1156 (the first year of the Hogen era), proclaimed the creation of a new government, called the Hogen shinsei (new governmment of Hogen), in the intercalary ninth month of 1156 as part of the switch to a new era name (that is, Hogen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Goshirakawa, who had emerged victorious from the Hogen Rebellion that occurred in 1156, proclaimed the creation of a new government, called the &quot;Hogen shinsei&quot; (new government of Hogen), in the intercalary ninth month of 1156 as part of the switch to a new era name, Hogen.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。governmentスペル訂正しました。原文の『』に合わせて&quot; &quot;補足しました。旧暦補足は不要と考え、削除しました。(that is,)削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「九州の地は一人の有なり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The lands of the entire realm belong to one man--the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;The lands of the entire realm belong to one man--the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lands of the entire realm belong to one man, the emperor.</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除、, 補足しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>王命の外、何ぞ私威を施さん。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There shall be no granting of private dominion over land apart from an imperial order.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There shall be no granting of private dominion over land apart from an imperial order.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There shall be no granting of private dominion over land apart from an imperial order.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>」と王土思想を強く宣言したこの新制は、荘園整理令を主たる内容としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Forcefully proclaiming a renewed monarchic ideology with these words, the new government began land reform that was substantively concerned with the Shoen chorirei, their order to reform the shoen (private estate) system of land ownership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Forcefully proclaiming a renewed monarchic ideology with these words, the new government began land reform that was substantively concerned with the Shoen chorirei, their order to reform the shoen (private estate) system of land ownership.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Forcefully proclaiming a renewed monarchic ideology with these words, the new government began land reform that was substantively concerned with the Shoen seirirei, their order to reform the shoen (private estate) system of land ownership.</e>
<cmt>荘園整理令→Shoen seirirei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>鳥羽院政期は全国に多くの荘園が形成され、各地で国務の遂行をめぐって紛争が起きていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was under the administration of Retired Emperor Toba that many of the shoen took shape throughout the country, and disputes quickly started to spring up all over the place concerning the carrying out of state business vis-à-vis the shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was under the administration of Retired Emperor Toba that many of the shoen took shape throughout the country, and disputes quickly started to spring up all over the place concerning the carrying out of state business vis-à-vis the shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was under the administration of Retired Emperor Toba that many of the shoen took shape throughout the country, and disputes quickly started to spring up all over the place concerning the carrying out of state business vis-à-vis the shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>この荘園整理令はその混乱を収拾して、全国の荘園・国衙領を天皇の統治下に置くことを意図したものであり、荘園公領制の成立への大きな契機となった新制と評価されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Shoen chorirei (order to reform the shoen system) sought to end the chaos that had begun during Emperor Toba&apos;s time; it was intended to bring all the shoen and kokugaryo (public territories) under the Emperor&apos;s direct rule, and the new system it introduced is considered to have generated significant momentum towards the establishment of the Shoen koryosei (shoen and duchy system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Shoen chorirei (order to reform the shoen system) sought to end the chaos that had begun during Emperor Toba&apos;s time; it was intended to bring all the shoen and kokugaryo (public territories) under the Emperor&apos;s direct rule, and the new system it introduced is considered to have generated significant momentum towards the establishment of the Shoen koryosei (shoen and duchy system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Shoen seirirei (order to reform the shoen system) sought to end the chaos that had begun during Emperor Toba&apos;s time; it was intended to bring all the shoen and kokugaryo (public territories) under the Emperor&apos;s direct rule, and the new system it introduced is considered to have generated significant momentum towards the establishment of the Shoen koryosei (shoen and duchy system).</e>
<cmt>荘園整理令→Shoen seirirei に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>その国政改革を立案・推進したのが、後白河の側近である藤原通憲（信西）であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The architect and driving force of these political reforms was Go-Shirakawa&apos;s right-hand man, FUJIWARA no Mochinori (generally known as Shinzei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The architect and driving force of these political reforms was Go-Shirakawa&apos;s right-hand man, FUJIWARA no Mochinori (generally known as Shinzei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The architect and driving force of these political reforms was Goshirakawa&apos;s right-hand man, FUJIWARA no Michinori (generally known as Shinzei).</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。Michinoriスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>信西は改革実現のために、記録所を設置する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to ensure his reforms would come to fruition, Shinzei created the Kirokusho (Records Office for Shoen Land Deeds).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to ensure his reforms would come to fruition, Shinzei created the Kirokusho (Records Office for Shoen Land Deeds).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to ensure his reforms would come to fruition, Shinzei created the Kirokusho (Records Office for Shoen Land Deeds).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>長官である上卿には大納言・三条公教が就任、実務を担当する弁官からは右中弁・藤原惟方、左少弁・源雅頼、右少弁・藤原俊憲（信西の嫡子）が起用され、その下で21人の寄人が荘園領主から提出された文書の審査、本所間の争論の裁判にあたった（後白河が「暗主」であるという信西の言葉は、この記録所の寄人だった清原頼業が九条兼実に後年語ったものである）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dainagon (Major Counselor) Kiminori SANJO was appointed the highest lord (i.e., the head) of the Records Office, while the officials actually responsible for running the office day to day, the controllers and so forth, included FUJIWARA no Korekata, appointed as Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right), MINAMOTO no Masayori as Sashoben (Lesser Controller of the Left), and FUJIWARA no Toshinori (Shinzei&apos;s own son and heir) as Ushoben (Lesser Controller of the Right); under these officials, twenty-one Yoriudo (clerks) worked, inspecting the land deed documents submitted to the office from the shoen owners and judging disputed cases of ownership at the office (Shinzei&apos;s infamous comment that Go-Shirakawa was a &quot;foolish (unenlightened) ruler&quot; was actually first mentioned by one of these Yoriudo, KIYOHARA no Yorinari, who repeated it years later to Kanezane KUJO.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dainagon (Major Counselor) Kiminori SANJO was appointed the highest lord (i.e., the head) of the Records Office, while the officials actually responsible for running the office day to day, the controllers and so forth, included FUJIWARA no Korekata, appointed as Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right), MINAMOTO no Masayori as Sashoben (Lesser Controller of the Left), and FUJIWARA no Toshinori (Shinzei&apos;s own son and heir) as Ushoben (Lesser Controller of the Right); under these officials, twenty-one Yoriudo (clerks) worked, inspecting the land deed documents submitted to the office from the shoen owners and judging disputed cases of ownership at the office (Shinzei&apos;s infamous comment that Go-Shirakawa was a &quot;foolish (unenlightened) ruler&quot; was actually first mentioned by one of these Yoriudo, KIYOHARA no Yorinari, who repeated it years later to Kanezane KUJO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dainagon (chief councilor of state) Kiminori SANJO was appointed the highest lord of the Records Office, while the officials in fact responsible for running the office day to day, the controllers and so forth, included FUJIWARA no Korekata, appointed as Uchuben (Middle Controller of the Right), MINAMOTO no Masayori as Sashoben (third-ranked officer of the left), and FUJIWARA no Toshinori (Shinzei&apos;s own son and heir) as Ushoben (third-ranked officer of the right); under these officials, 21 Yoriudo (clerks) worked, inspecting the land deed documents submitted to the office from the shoen owners and judging disputed cases of ownership at the office (Shinzei&apos;s infamous comment that Goshirakawa was a &apos;foolish (unenlightened) ruler&apos; was actually first mentioned by one of these Yoriudo, KIYOHARA no Yorinari, who repeated it years later to Kanezane KUJO).</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。大納言→Dainagon (chief councilor of state)(i.e., the head)不要と考え削除しました。左少弁の説明を(third-ranked officer of the left)に訂正しました。右少弁の説明を(third-ranked officer of the right)に訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。)補足。&quot;actually&quot; -&gt; &quot;in fact&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに内裏の復興にも着手して、保元2年（1157年）10月に再建した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, Shinzei launched an effort to restore the Imperial Palace; restorations were completed in the tenth month of 1157 (Hogen 2).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Shinzei launched an effort to restore the Imperial Palace; restorations were completed in the tenth month of 1157 (Hogen 2).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Shinzei launched an effort to restore the Imperial Palace; restorations were completed in October, 1157.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。the tenth monthをOctoberに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>その直後にも新たに新制30ヶ条を出し、公事・行事の整備、官人の綱紀粛正に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the palace restoration, Shinzei produced a list of 30 new provisions of the new administration, and poured his efforts into tightening discipline both among government officials and in the provision and maintenance for political operations and events of the court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the palace restoration, Shinzei produced a list of 30 new provisions of the new administration, and poured his efforts into tightening discipline both among government officials and in the provision and maintenance for political operations and events of the court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the palace restoration, Shinzei produced a list of 30 new provisions of the new administration, and poured his efforts into tightening discipline both among government officials and in the provision and maintenance for political operations and events of the court.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>この過程で信西とその一族の台頭は目覚ましく、高階重仲の女を母とする俊憲・藤原貞憲は弁官として父と共に実務を担当する一方で、藤原朝子（後白河の乳母）を母とする藤原成憲・藤原脩憲はそれぞれ遠江・美濃の受領となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this process Shinzei and the head of his family (the Fujiwara) each rose to remarkable prominence, and both Toshinori and his brother FUJIWARA no Sadanori--their mother being the daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka--worked as Controllers with their father (Shinzei) at running the Records Office, while FUJIWARA no Shigenori and FUJIWARA no Naganori, both the children of FUJIWARA no Asako (Go-Shirakawa&apos;s wet nurse), were awarded control over Toto&apos;umi and Mino provinces, respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this process Shinzei and the head of his family (the Fujiwara) each rose to remarkable prominence, and both Toshinori and his brother FUJIWARA no Sadanori--their mother being the daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka--worked as Controllers with their father (Shinzei) at running the Records Office, while FUJIWARA no Shigenori and FUJIWARA no Naganori, both the children of FUJIWARA no Asako (Go-Shirakawa&apos;s wet nurse), were awarded control over Toto&apos;umi and Mino provinces, respectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this process Shinzei and the his family (the Fujiwara) each rose to remarkable prominence; FUJIWARA no Toshinori and Sadanori (sons of Shinzei and their mother was the daughter of TAKASHINA no Shigenaka) worked as Controllers with their father at running the Records Office, while FUJIWARA no Shigenori and Naganori (sons of Shinzei and their mother was FUJIWARA no Asako, who was also known as Emperor Goshirakawa&apos;s wet nurse) were awarded control over Totomi and Mino Provinces, respectively.</e>
<cmt>head of削除しました。スペース削除。文章訂正しました。遠江→Totomi に訂正しました。Provinces大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>信西自身は、保元の乱で敗死した藤原頼長の所領を没収して後院領に組み込み、自らはその預所になるなど経済基盤の確保にも余念がなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei himself confiscated the lands owned by FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, who perished in the Hogen Rebellion, and nominally added these estates to the land already prescribed for the Emperor&apos;s use after he abdicated the throne, yet in reality devoted his undivided attention to making those lands into a buffer to guarantee his own financial footing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei himself confiscated the lands owned by FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, who perished in the Hogen Rebellion, and nominally added these estates to the land already prescribed for the Emperor&apos;s use after he abdicated the throne, yet in reality devoted his undivided attention to making those lands into a buffer to guarantee his own financial footing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei himself confiscated the lands owned by FUJIWARA no Yorinaga, who perished in the Hogen Rebellion, and nominally added these estates to the land already prescribed for the Emperor&apos;s use after he abdicated the throne, yet in reality devoted his undivided attention to making those lands into a buffer to guarantee his own financial footing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>平氏一門の台頭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rise of the Heike (the Taira clan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rise of the Heike (the Taira clan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rise of the Taira clan</e>
<cmt>訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>国政改革推進のため、信西は平清盛を厚遇する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to ensure he could continue to make progress with his political reforms, Shinzei befriended TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to ensure he could continue to make progress with his political reforms, Shinzei befriended TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to ensure he could continue to make progress with his political reforms, Shinzei befriended TAIRA no Kiyomori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>平氏一門は保元の乱の結果、清盛が播磨守、平頼盛が安芸守、平教盛が淡路守、平経盛が常陸介となり兄弟で四ヶ国の受領を占めるなど、その実力は無視できないものがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The end result of the Hogen Rebellion was favorable to the Taira clan, with Kiyomori made governor of Harima province and TAIRA no Yorimori governor of Aki, TAIRA no Norimori governor of Awaji, and TAIRA no Tsunemori Suke (deputy governor) of Hitachi; the Taira&apos;s power and influence, what with a single set of brothers now controlling four provinces, could no longer be ignored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The end result of the Hogen Rebellion was favorable to the Taira clan, with Kiyomori made governor of Harima province and TAIRA no Yorimori governor of Aki, TAIRA no Norimori governor of Awaji, and TAIRA no Tsunemori Suke (deputy governor) of Hitachi; the Taira&apos;s power and influence, what with a single set of brothers now controlling four provinces, could no longer be ignored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The end result of the Hogen Rebellion was favorable to the Taira clan, with Kiyomori made governor of Harima Province and TAIRA no Yorimori governor of Aki Province, TAIRA no Norimori governor of Awaji Province, and TAIRA no Tsunemori assistant governor of Hitachi Province; the Taira&apos;s power and influence, what with a single set of brothers now controlling four provinces, could no longer be ignored.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。Province補足しました。Assistant Governor of Hitachi Provinceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また、荘園整理、荘官・百姓の取り締まり、神人・悪僧の統制、戦乱で荒廃した京都の治安維持のためにも、平氏の武力は不可欠だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Taira&apos;s military strength was indispensable in supervising the shoen reforms as well as shoen officials and commoners, and controlling members of the clergy and evil monks alike, not to mention for keeping the peace in Kyoto, in ruins from the recent wars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the Taira&apos;s military strength was indispensable in supervising the shoen reforms as well as shoen officials and commoners, and controlling members of the clergy and evil monks alike, not to mention for keeping the peace in Kyoto, in ruins from the recent wars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Taira&apos;s military strength was indispensable in supervising the shoen reforms as well as shoen officials and commoners, and controlling members of the clergy and evil monks alike, not to mention for keeping the peace in Kyoto, in ruins from the recent wars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>大和守に平基盛が任じられたのも、平氏に対する期待の現われといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the appointing of TAIRA no Motomori as governor of Yamato province is an expression of the hopes placed in the Taira clan to achieve a balance of power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the appointing of TAIRA no Motomori as governor of Yamato province is an expression of the hopes placed in the Taira clan to achieve a balance of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the appointing of TAIRA no Motomori as governor of Yamato Province is an expression of the hopes placed in the Taira clan to achieve a balance of power.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>大和は興福寺の所領が充満していて、これまで国検をしようとしても神人・悪僧の抵抗によりことごとく失敗に終わっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato was riddled with territories under the control of Kofukuji temple, and up until that point in time all attempts by the central government to conduct inspections (land surveys, etc.) of the province had run into stiff opposition from the clergy and from evil monks, and each and every attempt had failed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato was riddled with territories under the control of Kofukuji temple, and up until that point in time all attempts by the central government to conduct inspections (land surveys, etc.) of the province had run into stiff opposition from the clergy and from evil monks, and each and every attempt had failed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato was riddled with territories under the control of Kofuku-ji Temple, and up until that point in time all attempts by the central government to conduct inspections (land surveys, etc.) of the province had run into stiff opposition from the clergy and from evil monks, and each and every attempt had failed.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足。Temple大文字にしました。スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>清盛は武力を背景に国検を断行する一方、寺院勢力の特権もある程度は認めるなど柔軟な対応で、大和の知行国支配を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Kiyomori, backed by his military might, did conduct a decisive inspection, he also engaged in softer diplomatic measures, as when he acknowledged that temples did have a certain degree of influence and therefore special privileges, and in this way managed to carry out a survey of the enfiefed lands in Yamato that were under state control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Kiyomori, backed by his military might, did conduct a decisive inspection, he also engaged in softer diplomatic measures, as when he acknowledged that temples did have a certain degree of influence and therefore special privileges, and in this way managed to carry out a survey of the enfiefed lands in Yamato that were under state control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Kiyomori, backed by his military might, did conduct a decisive inspection, he also engaged in softer diplomatic measures, as when he acknowledged that temples did have a certain degree of influence and therefore special privileges, and in this way managed to carry out a survey of the chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) in Yamato that were under state control.</e>
<cmt>知行国→chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>さらに清盛は大宰大弐に就任することで日宋貿易に深く関与することになり、経済的実力を高めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And through his position as second-in-command (Daini) of Dazaifu (an important outpost in Kyushu), Kiyomori also became a major participant in the Japanese trade with Song China, and thus increased the economic might of the Taira as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And through his position as second-in-command (Daini) of Dazaifu (an important outpost in Kyushu), Kiyomori also became a major participant in the Japanese trade with Song China, and thus increased the economic might of the Taira as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And through his position as second-in-command (Daini) of Dazaifu (an important outpost in Kyushu), Kiyomori also became a major participant in the Japanese trade with Song China, and thus increased the economic might of the Taira as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>信西は、自らの子・成憲と清盛の女（後の花山院兼雅室）の婚姻によって平氏一門との提携を世間に示し、改革は順調に進行するかに見えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei arranged a marriage between his own son Narinori and Kiyomori&apos;s daughter (who later became the wife of Kanemasa KAZANIN), thereby showing society the strong partnership between his own family and the Taira clan,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei arranged a marriage between his own son Narinori and Kiyomori&apos;s daughter (who later became the wife of Kanemasa KAZANIN), thereby showing society the strong partnership between his own family and the Taira clan,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei arranged a marriage between his own son Narinori and Kiyomori&apos;s daughter (who later became the wife of Kanemasa KAZANIN), thereby showing society the strong partnership between his own family and the Taira clan,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>二条親政派の攻勢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The faction supporting direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo strikes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The faction supporting direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo strikes</e>
<cmt>wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The faction supporting direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo strikes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="25">
<j>しかし、ここにもう一つ無視できない政治勢力が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point in time there was, however, one more political colossus that could not be ignored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point in time there was, however, one more political colossus that could not be ignored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point in time there was, however, one more political colossus that could not be ignored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>美福門院を中心に東宮・守仁の擁立を図るグループ（二条親政派）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was the group (the faction in support of direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo), centered around Bifukumon&apos;in (that is, FUJIWARA no Nariko), that planned to back then-crown prince Morihito (later Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the group (the faction in support of direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo), centered around Bifukumon&apos;in (that is, FUJIWARA no Nariko), that planned to back then-crown prince Morihito (later Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the group (the faction in support of direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo), centered around Bifukumonin (that is, FUJIWARA no Nariko), that planned to back then-crown prince Morihito (later Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>美福門院は、鳥羽法皇から荘園の大半を相続して最大の荘園領主となっており、その意向を無視することはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bifukumon&apos;in had inherited from cloistered emperor Toba the lion&apos;s share of his shoen, making her a major landholder of the day and rendering Shinzei&apos;s ideas on shoen too threatening to ignore.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bifukumon&apos;in had inherited from cloistered emperor Toba the lion&apos;s share of his shoen, making her a major landholder of the day and rendering Shinzei&apos;s ideas on shoen too threatening to ignore.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bifukumonin had inherited from Cloistered Emperor Toba the most share of his shoen, making her a major landholder of the day and rendering Shinzei&apos;s ideas on shoen too threatening to ignore.</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。Cloistered Emperor大文字にしました。Lions→most</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>美福門院はかねてからの念願であった、自らの養子・守仁の即位を信西に要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bifukumon&apos;in decided to demand of Shinzei what she had long desired: that her adopted son, Morihito, be raised to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bifukumon&apos;in decided to demand of Shinzei what she had long desired: that her adopted son, Morihito, be raised to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bifukumonin decided to demand of Shinzei what she had long desired: that her adopted son, Morihito, be raised to the imperial throne.</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>もともと後白河の即位は守仁即位までの中継ぎとして実現したものであり、信西も美福門院の要求を拒むことはできず、保元3年（1158年）8月「仏と仏との評定」（『兵範記』）、すなわち信西と美福門院の協議により後白河天皇は守仁親王に譲位した（二条天皇）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Go-Shirakawa&apos;s own enthronement had occurred with the understanding that Morihito would succeed him to the throne, Shinzei dared not refuse Bifukumon&apos;in&apos;s request, and so in the eighth month of 1158 (Hogen 3), in what is known in the &apos;Heihanki&apos; as &quot;a Buddha&apos;s joint decision with another Buddha,&quot; or in other words a negotiation between the two powerful figures, Shinzei and Bifukumon&apos;in, in which it was decided for Go-Shirakawa to abdicate in favor of prince Morihito (who became Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Go-Shirakawa&apos;s own enthronement had occurred with the understanding that Morihito would succeed him to the throne, Shinzei dared not refuse Bifukumon&apos;in&apos;s request, and so in the eighth month of 1158 (Hogen 3), in what is known in the &apos;Heihanki&apos; as &quot;a Buddha&apos;s joint decision with another Buddha,&quot; or in other words a negotiation between the two powerful figures, Shinzei and Bifukumon&apos;in, in which it was decided for Go-Shirakawa to abdicate in favor of prince Morihito (who became Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Goshirakawa&apos;s own enthronement had occurred with the understanding that Morihito would succeed him to the throne, Shinzei dared not refuse Bifukumonin&apos;s request, and so in August, 1158, in what is known in the &quot;Heihanki&quot; as &apos;a Buddha&apos;s joint decision with another Buddha,&apos; or in other words a negotiation between the two powerful figures, Shinzei and Bifukumonin, in which it was decided for Goshirakawa to abdicate in favor of Imperial Prince Morihito (who became Emperor Nijo).</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。Bifukumoninに訂正しました。新暦のみにしました。原文の『』に合わせて&apos;を&quot;に訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Imperial Princeに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ここに、後白河院政派と二条親政派の対立が始まることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was at this point that animosity was born between the faction supporting Go-Shirakawa&apos;s insei (government in retirement) and the faction for direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was at this point that animosity was born between the faction supporting Go-Shirakawa&apos;s insei (government in retirement) and the faction for direct imperial rule by Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was at this point that animosity was born between the faction supporting Goshirakawa&apos;s insei (cloister government) and the faction for direct Imperial rule by Emperor Nijo.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。院政→(cloister government)の説明に訂正しました。Imperial 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>二条親政派は藤原経宗（二条天皇の伯父）・藤原惟方（二条天皇の乳兄弟、記録所の弁官の一人）が中心となり、美福門院の支援を背景に後白河の政治活動を抑圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principal figures of the Nijo faction were FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (Emperor Nijo&apos;s uncle) and FUJIWARA no Korekata (Nijo&apos;s &quot;milk brother,&quot; meaning they were both essentially raised by the same wet nurse), one of the controllers at the Records Office, and with the continued financial backing and aid of Bifukumon&apos;in, they worked to limit Go-Shirakawa&apos;s political activities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principal figures of the Nijo faction were FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (Emperor Nijo&apos;s uncle) and FUJIWARA no Korekata (Nijo&apos;s &quot;milk brother,&quot; meaning they were both essentially raised by the same wet nurse), one of the controllers at the Records Office, and with the continued financial backing and aid of Bifukumon&apos;in, they worked to limit Go-Shirakawa&apos;s political activities.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principal figures of the Nijo faction were FUJIWARA no Tsunemune (Emperor Nijo&apos;s uncle) and FUJIWARA no Korekata (Nijo&apos;s foster brother, meaning they were both essentially raised by the same wet nurse), one of the controllers at the Records Office, and with the continued financial backing and aid of Bifukumonin, they worked to limit Goshirakawa&apos;s political activities.</e>
<cmt>乳兄弟→foster brother としました。Bifukumoninに訂正しました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これに対して後白河は近衛天皇急死により突然皇位を継いだこともあり、頼れるのは信西のみで状況は不利だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Go-Shirakawa himself had hastily been raised to the throne upon the sudden death of Emperor Konoe, so he was at a distinct disadvantage against the Nijo faction, and the only one he could rely upon was Shinzei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Go-Shirakawa himself had hastily been raised to the throne upon the sudden death of Emperor Konoe, so he was at a distinct disadvantage against the Nijo faction, and the only one he could rely upon was Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Goshirakawa himself had hastily been raised to the throne upon the sudden death of Emperor Konoe, so he was at a distinct disadvantage against the Nijo faction, and the only one he could rely upon was Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>後白河にとっては、自らの院政を支える近臣の育成が急務となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For Go-Shirakawa, cultivating close retainers that would support his insei (government in retirement) was an urgent priority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For Go-Shirakawa, cultivating close retainers that would support his insei (government in retirement) was an urgent priority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For Goshirakawa, cultivating close retainers that would support his insei (cloister government) was an urgent priority.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。院政→(cloister government)の説明に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>信頼の登場</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori arrives on the scene</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori arrives on the scene</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori arrives on the scene</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="34">
<j>そこで後白河は、武蔵守・藤原信頼を抜擢する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this climate, Go-Shirakawa selected FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, governor of Musashi province, to promote and groom as a retainer.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this climate, Go-Shirakawa selected FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, governor of Musashi province, to promote and groom as a retainer.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this climate, Goshirakawa selected FUJIWARA no Nobuyori, governor of Musashi Province, to promote and groom as a retainer.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>信頼は保元2年（1157年）3月に右近権中将になると、10月に蔵人頭、翌年2月に参議・皇后宮権亮、8月に中納言、11月に検非違使別当と急速に昇進する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori, after being made Ukon gonchujo (deputy lieutenant of the Guards of the Inner Right) in the third month of 1157 (Hogen 2), he embarked on a meteoric rise, being promoted to Kuroudo no To (Chief of the Palace Storehouses) in the tenth month, and then in 1158 was named Sangi (Director of Palace Affairs) and Kogogu gon no suke (Deputy Director of the Empress&apos;s Palace) in the second month, then Chunagon (Middle Counselor) in the eighth month, and finally Inspector-General (Kebi&apos;ishi no betto) in the eleventh month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori, after being made Ukon gonchujo (deputy lieutenant of the Guards of the Inner Right) in the third month of 1157 (Hogen 2), he embarked on a meteoric rise, being promoted to Kuroudo no To (Chief of the Palace Storehouses) in the tenth month, and then in 1158 was named Sangi (Director of Palace Affairs) and Kogogu gon no suke (Deputy Director of the Empress&apos;s Palace) in the second month, then Chunagon (Middle Counselor) in the eighth month, and finally Inspector-General (Kebi&apos;ishi no betto) in the eleventh month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori, after being made Ukon no gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards) in March, 1157, he embarked on a meteoric rise, being promoted to Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain) in October, and then in 1158 was named Sangi (councillor) and Kogo no miya gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Empress&apos;s Household) in February, then Chunagon (vice-councilor of state) in August, and finally Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police) in November.</e>
<cmt>右近権中将→Ukon no gon no chujo (Provisional Middle Captain of the Right Division of Inner Palace Guards)新暦の表記にしました。蔵人頭→Kurodo no to (Head Chamberlain)参議→Sangi (councillor)皇后宮権亮→Kogo no miya gon no suke (Provisional Assistant Master of the Empress&apos;s Household)中納言→Chunagon (vice-councilor of state)検非違使別当→Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>もともと信頼の一門は武蔵国・陸奥国を知行国としており、両国と深いつながりを持つ源義朝と連携していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori&apos;s branch of the Fujiwara clan had long controlled the provinces of Musashi and Hitachi through their fiefs there, and had a friendly relationship with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, who had strong ties to both provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori&apos;s branch of the Fujiwara clan had long controlled the provinces of Musashi and Hitachi through their fiefs there, and had a friendly relationship with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, who had strong ties to both provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori&apos;s branch of the Fujiwara clan had long controlled the provinces of Musashi and Hitachi through their fiefs there, and had a friendly relationship with MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo, who had strong ties to both provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>久寿2年（1155年）8月に源義平（義朝の長男）が叔父の源義賢を滅ぼした武蔵国大蔵館合戦においても、武蔵守であった信頼の支援があったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, it is suspected that the summer, 1155 (eighth month of Kuju 2) battle of Okura Warehouse in Musashi province, in which MINAMOTO no Yoshihira (Yoshitomo&apos;s eldest son) destroyed his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshikata, occurred with the approval and support of Nobuyori, the governor of Musashi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, it is suspected that the summer, 1155 (eighth month of Kuju 2) battle of Okura Warehouse in Musashi province, in which MINAMOTO no Yoshihira (Yoshitomo&apos;s eldest son) destroyed his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshikata, occurred with the approval and support of Nobuyori, the governor of Musashi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, it is suspected that the summer, in August, 1155, battle of Okura Warehouse in Musashi Province, in which MINAMOTO no Yoshihira (Yoshitomo&apos;s eldest son) destroyed his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshikata, occurred with the approval and support of Nobuyori, the governor of Musashi.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>保元3年（1158年）8月に後白河院庁が開設されると、信頼は院の軍馬を管理する厩別当に就任する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Go-Shirakawa opened his Office of Retired Government (In no Cho) in the eighth month of 1158 (Hogen 3), he appointed Nobuyori the Commander of his Imperial Stables, in charge of all Go-Shirakawa&apos;s own horses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Go-Shirakawa opened his Office of Retired Government (In no Cho) in the eighth month of 1158 (Hogen 3), he appointed Nobuyori the Commander of his Imperial Stables, in charge of all Go-Shirakawa&apos;s own horses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Goshirakawa opened his Office of Retired Government (In no Cho) in August, 1158, he appointed Nobuyori the Commander of his Imperial Stables, in charge of all Goshirakawa&apos;s own horses.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>義朝は宮中の軍馬を管理する左馬頭であり、両者の同盟関係はさらに強固となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that point Yoshitomo was Commander of the Imperial Stables of the Left, in charge of all the horses at the imperial palace, and the two of them only grew closer through their similar appointments.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point Yoshitomo was Commander of the Imperial Stables of the Left, in charge of all the horses at the imperial palace, and the two of them only grew closer through their similar appointments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point Yoshitomo was Commander of the Imperial Stables of the Left, in charge of all the horses at the imperial palace, and the two of them only grew closer through their similar appointments.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>義朝の武力という切り札を得た信頼は、自らの妹と摂関家の嫡子・藤原基実の婚姻も実現させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having obtained the ultimate trump card, Yoshitomo&apos;s military might, Nobuyori was able to marry his younger sister to FUJIWARA no Motozane, an heir in the Fujiwara branch of regents and advisors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having obtained the ultimate trump card, Yoshitomo&apos;s military might, Nobuyori was able to marry his younger sister to FUJIWARA no Motozane, an heir in the Fujiwara branch of regents and advisors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having obtained the ultimate trump card, Yoshitomo&apos;s military might, Nobuyori was able to marry his younger sister to FUJIWARA no Motozane, an heir in the Fujiwara branch of regents and advisors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>摂関家は保元の乱によって藤原忠実の知行国・頼長の所領が没収された上に、家人として荘園管理の武力を担っていた源為義が処刑されたことで各地の荘園で紛争が激化するなど、その勢力を大きく後退させていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This branch of regents and advisors had suffered the confiscation of FUJIWARA no Tadazane&apos;s enfiefed province as well as Yorinaga&apos;s territories due to the Hogen Rebellion, and worse yet the execution of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, a retainer on whose military strength they had increasingly come to rely to manage their shoen properties; as a result, their power had greatly waned, as evidenced by the disputes over ownership of their lands escalating all over the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This branch of regents and advisors had suffered the confiscation of FUJIWARA no Tadazane&apos;s enfiefed province as well as Yorinaga&apos;s territories due to the Hogen Rebellion, and worse yet the execution of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, a retainer on whose military strength they had increasingly come to rely to manage their shoen properties; as a result, their power had greatly waned, as evidenced by the disputes over ownership of their lands escalating all over the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This branch of regents and advisors had suffered the confiscation of FUJIWARA no Tadazane&apos;s chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) as well as Yorinaga&apos;s territories due to the Hogen Rebellion, and worse yet the execution of MINAMOTO no Tameyoshi, a retainer on whose military strength they had increasingly come to rely to manage their shoen properties; as a result, their power had greatly waned, as evidenced by the disputes over ownership of their lands escalating all over the country.</e>
<cmt>知行国→chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>混乱の収拾のためには代替の武力が必要であり、義朝と密接なつながりのある信頼との提携もやむを得ないことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to bring the chaos under control, they needed a new source of military might, making their cooperation with Nobuyori, who had a secret alliance with Yoshitomo, something they dared not jeopardize.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to bring the chaos under control, they needed a new source of military might, making their cooperation with Nobuyori, who had a secret alliance with Yoshitomo, something they dared not jeopardize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to bring the chaos under control, they needed a new source of military might, making their cooperation with Nobuyori, who had a secret alliance with Yoshitomo, something they dared not jeopardize.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>後白河の近臣としては他にも、藤原成親（藤原家成の三男）や源師仲が加わり院政派の陣容も整えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Shirakawa&apos;s other close vassals included FUJIWARA no Narichika (FUJIWARA no Ienari&apos;s third son) and MINAMOTO no Moronaka, who joined the Insei (government in retirement) faction and began making military preparations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Shirakawa&apos;s other close vassals included FUJIWARA no Narichika (FUJIWARA no Ienari&apos;s third son) and MINAMOTO no Moronaka, who joined the Insei (government in retirement) faction and began making military preparations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa&apos;s other close vassals included FUJIWARA no Narichika (FUJIWARA no Ienari&apos;s third son) and MINAMOTO no Moronaka, who joined the Insei (cloister government) faction and began making military preparations.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。院政→(cloister government)の説明に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>反信西派の形成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anti-Shinzei faction emerges</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anti-Shinzei faction emerges</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anti-Shinzei faction emerges</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="44">
<j>ここに、信西一門・二条親政派・後白河院政派・平氏一門というグループがそれぞれ形成されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By this point, four distinct groups had taken shape: Shinzei&apos;s branch of the Fujiwara clan, the Nijo faction, Go-Shirakawa&apos;s Insei faction, and the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this point, four distinct groups had taken shape: Shinzei&apos;s branch of the Fujiwara clan, the Nijo faction, Go-Shirakawa&apos;s Insei faction, and the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this point, four distinct groups had taken shape: Shinzei&apos;s branch of the Fujiwara clan, the Nijo faction, Goshirakawa&apos;s Insei faction, and the Taira clan.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>『平治物語』では信頼が近衛大将を希望して、信西が断ったために確執が生まれたとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji) claims that Nobuyori wished to be appointed Konoe Daisho (Commander of the Palace Guards), and that discord arose between them when Shinzei refused his request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji) claims that Nobuyori wished to be appointed Konoe Daisho (Commander of the Palace Guards), and that discord arose between them when Shinzei refused his request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Heiji) claims that Nobuyori wished to be appointed Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards), and that discord arose between them when Shinzei refused his request.</e>
<cmt>近衛大将→Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>しかし『愚管抄』にはその話は見えず、大将に任じられるのは院近臣の身分では常識的に無理なことから事実かどうかは疑わしい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But no trace of this version of events can be found in the &quot;Gukansho&quot; and indeed, given the fact that close retainers of the retired emperor did not normally have the authority to appoint Commanders, it is doubtful whether this episode really occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But no trace of this version of events can be found in the &quot;Gukansho&quot; and indeed, given the fact that close retainers of the retired emperor did not normally have the authority to appoint Commanders, it is doubtful whether this episode really occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But no trace of this version of events can be found in the &quot;Gukansho&quot; and indeed, given the fact that close retainers of the retired emperor did not normally have the authority to appoint Commanders, it is doubtful whether this episode really occurred.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>信西一門の政治主導に対する反発が、平治の乱勃発の最大の原因と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The backlash generated by the political initiatives Shinzei and his family were launching is considered to be the biggest cause of the outbreak of the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The backlash generated by the political initiatives Shinzei and his family were launching is considered to be the biggest cause of the outbreak of the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The backlash generated by the political initiatives Shinzei and his family were launching is considered to be the biggest cause of the outbreak of the Heiji Rebellion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>二条親政派と後白河院政派は互いに激しく対立していたが、信西の排除という点では意見が一致し、信西打倒の機会を伺っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nijo direct rule faction and the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction, despite being pitted in an increasingly harsh antagonism, had one goal in common--eliminating Shinzei--and so they searched for opportunities to strike him down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nijo direct rule faction and the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction, despite being pitted in an increasingly harsh antagonism, had one goal in common--eliminating Shinzei--and so they searched for opportunities to strike him down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nijo direct rule faction and the Goshirakawa Insei faction, despite being pitted in an increasingly harsh antagonism, had one goal in common, eliminating Shinzei, and so they searched for opportunities to strike him down.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。ハイフンを, に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>一方、清盛は自らの娘を信西の子・成憲に嫁がせていたが、信頼の嫡子・藤原信親にも娘（後の藤原隆房室）を嫁がせるなど、両派の対立では中立的立場にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori, on the other hand, had married one of his own daughters to Narinori, Shinzei&apos;s son, yet also married off another daughter (who would later become FUJIWARA no Takafusa&apos;s wife) to FUJIWARA no Nobuchika, Nobuyori&apos;s son and heir, and took other steps to avoid the conflict between the two factions and achieve a neutral position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori, on the other hand, had married one of his own daughters to Narinori, Shinzei&apos;s son, yet also married off another daughter (who would later become FUJIWARA no Takafusa&apos;s wife) to FUJIWARA no Nobuchika, Nobuyori&apos;s son and heir, and took other steps to avoid the conflict between the two factions and achieve a neutral position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori, on the other hand, had married one of his own daughters to Narinori, Shinzei&apos;s son, yet also married off another daughter (who would later become FUJIWARA no Takafusa&apos;s wife) to FUJIWARA no Nobuchika, Nobuyori&apos;s son and heir, and took other steps to avoid the conflict between the two factions and achieve a neutral position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>平治元年（1159年）12月、清盛が熊野参詣に赴き京都に軍事的空白が生まれた隙をついて、反信西派はクーデターを起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the twelfth month of 1159 (the first year of the Heiji era), the anti-Shinzei faction took advantage of the sudden vacuum in military forces in the capital created by Kiyomori&apos;s departure on a pilgrimage to Kumano to launch a coup d&apos;etat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the twelfth month of 1159 (the first year of the Heiji era), the anti-Shinzei faction took advantage of the sudden vacuum in military forces in the capital created by Kiyomori&apos;s departure on a pilgrimage to Kumano to launch a coup d&apos;etat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January, 1160, the anti-Shinzei faction took advantage of the sudden vacuum in military forces in the capital created by Kiyomori&apos;s departure on a pilgrimage to Kumano to launch a coup d&apos;etat.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>三条殿襲撃</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The attack on the Sanjo palace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The attack on the Sanjo palace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The attack on the Sanjo Palace</e>
<cmt>Palace大文字にしました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="51">
<j>12月9日深夜、藤原信頼・源義朝の軍勢は院御所・三条殿を襲撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the ninth day of the twelfth month, the forces of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo carried out a raid on the palace at Sanjo (Third Avenue), an old palace of the retired emperor&apos;s (Go-Shirakawa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the ninth day of the twelfth month, the forces of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo carried out a raid on the palace at Sanjo (Third Avenue), an old palace of the retired emperor&apos;s (Go-Shirakawa).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 26, 1160, the forces of FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo carried out a raid on the Sanjo Palace, an old palace of the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。the Sanjo Palaceとしました。the Retired Emperor Goshirakawa としました。&apos;s削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>後白河上皇・上西門院（後白河の同母姉）の身柄を確保すると、三条殿に火をかけて逃げる者には容赦なく矢を射掛けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After capturing and securing retired emperor Go-Shirakawa and Josaimon&apos;in (his biological sister), they torched Sanjo palace and unleashed a relentless barrage of arrows against those who tried to flee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After capturing and securing retired emperor Go-Shirakawa and Josaimon&apos;in (his biological sister), they torched Sanjo palace and unleashed a relentless barrage of arrows against those who tried to flee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After capturing and securing Retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Josaimonin (his biological sister), they torched Sanjo Palace and unleashed a relentless barrage of arrows against those who tried to flee.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor 大文字にしました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。Josaimoninとしました。the Sanjo Palaceとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>警備にあたっていた大江家仲・平康忠、一般官人や女房などが犠牲となるが、信西一門はすでに逃亡していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ienaka OE and TAIRA no Yasutada, who were in charged of the palace defence, gave up their lives along with many lesser officials and ladies in waiting, but Shinzei and his family had already escaped.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ienaka OE and TAIRA no Yasutada, who were in charged of the palace defence, gave up their lives along with many lesser officials and ladies in waiting, but Shinzei and his family had already escaped.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ienaka OE and TAIRA no Yasutada, who were in charged of the palace defense, gave up their lives along with many lesser officials and ladies in waiting, but Shinzei and his family had already escaped.</e>
<cmt>defenseを使いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>信頼・義朝は上皇と上西門院を内裏内の一本御書所に移して軟禁状態にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori and Yoshitomo brought the retired emperor and his sister Josaimon&apos;in to the Ippon gosho dokoro (the Ippon gosho hall) inside the main imperial palace complex and kept them there under house arrest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori and Yoshitomo brought the retired emperor and his sister Josaimon&apos;in to the Ippon gosho dokoro (the Ippon gosho hall) inside the main imperial palace complex and kept them there under house arrest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori and Yoshitomo brought the retired emperor and his sister Josaimonin to the Ippon-goshodokoro (Ippon-gosho hall) inside the main imperial palace complex and kept them there under house arrest.</e>
<cmt>Josaimoninとしました。Ippon-goshodokoro (Ippon-gosho hall)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>上皇を乗せる車は源師仲が用意し、源重成・源光基・源季実が護送した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The carriage in which the retired emperor was forced to ride was prepared by MINAMOTO no Moronaka, and he traveled escorted by MINAMOTO no Shigenari, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto, and MINAMOTO no Suezane.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The carriage in which the retired emperor was forced to ride was prepared by MINAMOTO no Moronaka, and he traveled escorted by MINAMOTO no Shigenari, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto, and MINAMOTO no Suezane.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The carriage in which the Retired Emperor was forced to ride was prepared by MINAMOTO no Moronaka, and he traveled escorted by MINAMOTO no Shigenari, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto, and MINAMOTO no Suezane.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor 大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>このうち、源光基は美福門院の家人・源光保の甥であり、京都の治安を預かる検非違使別当は藤原惟方であることから、クーデターには二条親政派の同意もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among these conspirators, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto was the nephew of MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, who was a retainer of Bifukumon&apos;in, and this, coupled with the fact that the Kebi&apos;ishi Betto (Inspector-General), whose duty was to preserve the peace in Kyoto, was FUJIWARA no Korekata, also a Nijo faction member, indicates that the Nijo faction had at least tacitly agreed to and supported the coup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among these conspirators, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto was the nephew of MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, who was a retainer of Bifukumon&apos;in, and this, coupled with the fact that the Kebi&apos;ishi Betto (Inspector-General), whose duty was to preserve the peace in Kyoto, was FUJIWARA no Korekata, also a Nijo faction member, indicates that the Nijo faction had at least tacitly agreed to and supported the coup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among these conspirators, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto was the nephew of MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu, who was a retainer of Bifukumonin, and this, coupled with the fact that the Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police), whose duty was to preserve the peace in Kyoto, was FUJIWARA no Korekata, also a Nijo faction member, indicates that the Nijo faction had at least tacitly agreed to and supported the coup.</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。検非違使別当→Kebiishi no betto (Superintendent of the Imperial Police)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>翌10日には、信西の子息（俊憲・貞憲・成憲・脩憲）が逮捕され全員の配流が決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following day, the tenth, four of Shinzei&apos;s sons (Toshinori, Sadanori, Narinori, and Naganori) were arrested, and the conspirators decided to exile all four of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the following day, the tenth, four of Shinzei&apos;s sons (Toshinori, Sadanori, Narinori, and Naganori) were arrested, and the conspirators decided to exile all four of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the following day, 27, four of Shinzei&apos;s sons (Toshinori, Sadanori, Narinori, and Naganori) were arrested, and the conspirators decided to exile all four of them.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>山城国田原に逃れた信西は源光保の追撃を振り切れず、郎等の藤原師光（西光）らに命じて自らを地中に埋めさせて自害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinzei, who had fled to Tawara in Yamashiro province, found himself unable to shake off MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu&apos;s pursuit, so he ordered FUJIWARA no Morimitsu (also known as Saiko) and his other retainers to bury him in the earth, thereby committing suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinzei, who had fled to Tawara in Yamashiro province, found himself unable to shake off MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu&apos;s pursuit, so he ordered FUJIWARA no Morimitsu (also known as Saiko) and his other retainers to bury him in the earth, thereby committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinzei, who had fled to Tawara in Yamashiro Province, found himself unable to shake off MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu&apos;s pursuit, so he ordered FUJIWARA no Morimitsu (also known as Saiko) and his other retainers to bury him in the earth, thereby committing suicide.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>光保は信西の首を切って京都に戻り、首は大路を渡され獄門に晒された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuyasu cut off Shinzei&apos;s head and returned to Kyoto, where the head was processed down the main streets of the capital before being exposed on the city&apos;s prison gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuyasu cut off Shinzei&apos;s head and returned to Kyoto, where the head was processed down the main streets of the capital before being exposed on the city&apos;s prison gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuyasu cut off Shinzei&apos;s head and returned to Kyoto, where the head was processed down the main streets of the capital before being exposed on the city&apos;s prison gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="60">
<j>信西が自害した14日、内裏に二条天皇・後白河上皇を確保して政権を掌握した信頼は、臨時除目を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the fourteenth, when Shinzei committed suicide, Nobuyori, having secured the persons of both Emperor Nijo and retired emperor Go-Shirakawa inside the palace and seized political power, next convened a Rinji jimoku (special promotions session).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the fourteenth, when Shinzei committed suicide, Nobuyori, having secured the persons of both Emperor Nijo and retired emperor Go-Shirakawa inside the palace and seized political power, next convened a Rinji jimoku (special promotions session).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By January 31, when Shinzei committed suicide, Nobuyori, having secured the persons of both Emperor Nijo and Retired Emperor Goshirakawa inside the palace and seized political power, next convened a Rinji jimoku (special promotions session).</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。Retired Emperor 大文字にしました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>この除目で源義朝は播磨守、嫡子・源頼朝は右兵衛権佐となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this session, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was made the governor of Harima while his son and heir, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, was appointed U&apos;hyoe gonza (Assistant Commander of the Right Guard).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this session, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was made the governor of Harima while his son and heir, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, was appointed U&apos;hyoe gonza (Assistant Commander of the Right Guard).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this session, MINAMOTO no Yoshitomo was made the governor of Harima while his son and heir, MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, was appointed Uhyoe no Gon no suke (provisional assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards).</e>
<cmt>右兵衛権佐→Uhyoe no Gon no suke (provisional assistant captain of the Right Division of Middle Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>『平治物語』は信頼が近衛大将になったとするが、『愚管抄』にその話は見えない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; Nobuyori did become the Konoe Daisho (Commander of the Palace Guard), but no trace of this event is recorded in the &quot;Gukansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; Nobuyori did become the Konoe Daisho (Commander of the Palace Guard), but no trace of this event is recorded in the &quot;Gukansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; Nobuyori did become Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards), but no trace of this event is recorded in the &quot;Gukansho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>近衛大将→Konoe no daisho (Major Captain of the Palace Guards)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>藤原伊通はこの除目について「人を多く殺した者が官位を得るなら、なぜ三条殿の井戸に官位をやらないのか」と皮肉ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Koremichi had the following cynical comment on this promotion session: &quot;If killing many people is the key to winning promotions in rank, why then was the well at Sanjo palace not promoted?&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Koremichi had the following cynical comment on this promotion session: &quot;If killing many people is the key to winning promotions in rank, why then was the well at Sanjo palace not promoted?&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Koremichi had the following cynical comment on this promotion session: &apos;If killing many people is the key to winning promotions in rank, why then was the well at Sanjo Palace not promoted?&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。Palace大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>信頼の政権奪取には大半の貴族が反感を抱いていたが、二条親政派も義朝の武力を背景とした信頼の独断専行を見て、密かに離反の機会を伺っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears that most noblemen bore Nobuyori ill will for his usurpation of political power, but given the circumstances--he had the backing of the Nijo direct rule faction as well as Yoshitomo&apos;s military forces--all the disaffected could do was search in secret for opportunities to show their displeasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that most noblemen bore Nobuyori ill will for his usurpation of political power, but given the circumstances--he had the backing of the Nijo direct rule faction as well as Yoshitomo&apos;s military forces--all the disaffected could do was search in secret for opportunities to show their displeasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that most noblemen bore Nobuyori ill will for his usurpation of political power, but given the circumstances--he had the backing of the Nijo direct rule faction as well as Yoshitomo&apos;s military forces--all the disaffected could do was search in secret for opportunities to show their displeasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>その最中、東国より兵を率いて馳せ上った源義平は直ちに清盛の帰路を討ち取るよう主張したが、信頼はその必要はないと退けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the midst of these proceedings, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, who had raised an army out in the eastern provinces and hastily made his way to the capital, strongly advocated that he prepare to kill or capture Kiyomori while he was still on his way back to the capital, but Nobuyori refused, declaring there was no need for such measures.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the midst of these proceedings, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, who had raised an army out in the eastern provinces and hastily made his way to the capital, strongly advocated that he prepare to kill or capture Kiyomori while he was still on his way back to the capital, but Nobuyori refused, declaring there was no need for such measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the midst of these proceedings, MINAMOTO no Yoshihira, who had raised an army out in the eastern provinces and hastily made his way to the capital, strongly advocated that he prepare to kill or capture Kiyomori while he was still on his way back to the capital, but Nobuyori refused, declaring there was no need for such measures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>信頼にしてみれば嫡男・信親と清盛の女の婚姻関係により、清盛も自らの協力者になると見込んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Nobuyori&apos;s perspective, Kiyomori remained a potential ally who might cooperate, given their marriage ties--Nobuyori&apos;s son and heir Nobuchika was married to Kiyomori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Nobuyori&apos;s perspective, Kiyomori remained a potential ally who might cooperate, given their marriage ties--Nobuyori&apos;s son and heir Nobuchika was married to Kiyomori&apos;s daughter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Nobuyori&apos;s perspective, Kiyomori remained a potential ally who might cooperate, given their marriage ties (Nobuyori&apos;s son and heir Nobuchika was married to Kiyomori&apos;s daughter).</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除。括弧書きにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>二条天皇の六波羅行幸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Nijo pays a state visit to Rokuhara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Nijo pays a state visit to Rokuhara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Nijo pays a state visit to Rokuhara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>清盛は、紀伊国で京都の異変を知った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori was in Kii province when he heard of the political disaster that had occurred in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori was in Kii province when he heard of the political disaster that had occurred in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori was in Kii Province when he heard of the political disaster that had occurred in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>動転した清盛は九州へ落ち延びることも考えるが、紀伊の武士・湯浅宗重や熊野別当・湛快の協力により、17日帰京する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Stunned by the turn of events, Kiyomori considered slipping off to safety in Kyushu, but finally decided to march on the capital with the combined strength and cooperation of the warriors of Kii and the forces of Muneshige YUASA as well as the Betto (Chief) and Tankai of Kumano, setting out for Kyoto on the seventeenth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Stunned by the turn of events, Kiyomori considered slipping off to safety in Kyushu, but finally decided to march on the capital with the combined strength and cooperation of the warriors of Kii and the forces of Muneshige YUASA as well as the Betto (Chief) and Tankai of Kumano, setting out for Kyoto on the seventeenth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Stunned by the turn of events, Kiyomori considered slipping off to safety in Kyushu, but finally decided to march on the capital with the combined strength and cooperation of the warrior of Kii, Muneshige YUASA as well as Tankai of Kumano Betto (Chief), setting out for Kyoto on February 3.</e>
<cmt>warrior of Kii, Muneshige YUASA as well as Tankai of Kumano Betto (Chief)に訂正しました。新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>帰京までに、伊藤景綱・館貞保などの伊賀・伊勢の郎等が合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the time he reached the capital, several retainers from Iga and Ise provinces, including Kagetsuna ITO and Sadayasu TACHI, had joined their forces to his.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the time he reached the capital, several retainers from Iga and Ise provinces, including Kagetsuna ITO and Sadayasu TACHI, had joined their forces to his.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the time he reached the capital, several retainers from Iga and Ise Provinces, including Kagetsuna ITO and Sadayasu TACHI, had joined their forces to his.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>一方、義朝はクーデターのため隠密裏に少人数の軍勢を集めたに過ぎず、合戦を想定していなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo, on the other hand, had assembled only a handful of warriors, never expecting to fight a battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo, on the other hand, had assembled only a handful of warriors, never expecting to fight a battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo, on the other hand, had assembled only a handful of warriors, never expecting to fight a battle.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>京都の軍事バランスは大きく変化し、信頼の優位は揺らぐことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military balance of power in Kyoto having shifted so greatly, Nobuyori&apos;s predominance was also shaken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military balance of power in Kyoto having shifted so greatly, Nobuyori&apos;s predominance was also shaken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military balance of power in Kyoto having shifted so greatly, Nobuyori&apos;s predominance was also shaken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>信西と親しかった内大臣・三条公教は信頼の専横に憤りを抱き、二条親政派の経宗・惟方に接触を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiminori SANJO, the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), had been close with Shinzei, and was enraged at Nobuyori&apos;s tyranny, so he contacted Tsunemune and Korekata of the Nijo direct rule faction to plot his overthrow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiminori SANJO, the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), had been close with Shinzei, and was enraged at Nobuyori&apos;s tyranny, so he contacted Tsunemune and Korekata of the Nijo direct rule faction to plot his overthrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiminori SANJO, the Naidaijin (Minister of the Center), had been close with Shinzei, and was enraged at Nobuyori&apos;s tyranny, so he contacted Tsunemune and Korekata of the Nijo direct rule faction to plot his overthrow.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>二条親政派にすれば信西打倒を果たしたことにより、信頼ら後白河院政派は用済みとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To the Nijo faction, now that Shinzei had been eliminated, they no longer had any use for Nobuyori and others of the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To the Nijo faction, now that Shinzei had been eliminated, they no longer had any use for Nobuyori and others of the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To the Nijo faction, now that Shinzei had been eliminated, they no longer had any use for Nobuyori and others of the Goshirakawa Insei faction.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>公教と惟方により二条天皇の六波羅行幸の計画が練られ、藤原尹明（信西の従兄弟・惟方の義兄弟）が密命を帯びて内裏に参入する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A plan to spirit Emperor Nijo away by having him make a visit to Rokuhara was perfected thanks to Kiminori and Korekata, while FUJIWARA no Tadaaki (Shinzei&apos;s cousin and Korekata&apos;s brother-in-law, also known as Masaaki) paid a visit to the Imperial palace bearing a secret order.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A plan to spirit Emperor Nijo away by having him make a visit to Rokuhara was perfected thanks to Kiminori and Korekata, while FUJIWARA no Tadaaki (Shinzei&apos;s cousin and Korekata&apos;s brother-in-law, also known as Masaaki) paid a visit to the Imperial palace bearing a secret order.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A plan to spirit Emperor Nijo away by having him make a visit to Rokuhara was perfected thanks to Kiminori and Korekata, while FUJIWARA no Tadaaki (Shinzei&apos;s cousin and Korekata&apos;s brother-in-law, also known as Masaaki) paid a visit to the Imperial Palace bearing a secret order.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。Palace大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>25日早朝、清盛は信頼に名簿を提出して恭順の意を示し、婿に迎えていた信親を送り返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early in the morning of the twenty-fifth, Kiyomori submitted a register of names to Nobuyori, tantamount to a pledge of allegiance, and also returned Nobuchika, who had come to him as a son-in-law, unharmed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early in the morning of the twenty-fifth, Kiyomori submitted a register of names to Nobuyori, tantamount to a pledge of allegiance, and also returned Nobuchika, who had come to him as a son-in-law, unharmed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early in the morning of February 11, Kiyomori submitted a register of names to Nobuyori, tantamount to a pledge of allegiance, and also returned Nobuchika, who had come to him as a son-in-law, unharmed.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>信頼は清盛が味方についたことを喜ぶが、義朝は信親を警護していた清盛の郎等（難波経房・館貞保・平盛信・伊藤景綱）が「一人当千」の武者であることから危惧を抱いたという（『古事談』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that although Nobuyori was delighted to have secured Kiyomori as an ally, Yoshitomo, who noticed that the retainers of Kiyomori (NANIWA no Tsunefusa, Sadafusa TACHI, TAIRA no Morinobu, and Kagetsuna ITO) sent to escort Nobuchika back were all renowned &quot;warriors worth a thousand,&quot; meaning each one of them was rumored to be the match of a thousand regular soldiers, which caused him to feel misgivings (as recorded in the &quot;Kojidan,&quot; &quot;Old Setsuwa Tales&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that although Nobuyori was delighted to have secured Kiyomori as an ally, Yoshitomo, who noticed that the retainers of Kiyomori (NANIWA no Tsunefusa, Sadafusa TACHI, TAIRA no Morinobu, and Kagetsuna ITO) sent to escort Nobuchika back were all renowned &quot;warriors worth a thousand,&quot; meaning each one of them was rumored to be the match of a thousand regular soldiers, which caused him to feel misgivings (as recorded in the &quot;Kojidan,&quot; &quot;Old Setsuwa Tales&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that although Nobuyori was delighted to have secured Kiyomori as an ally, Yoshitomo, who noticed that the retainers of Kiyomori (NANIWA no Tsunefusa, Sadafusa TACHI, TAIRA no Morinobu, and Kagetsuna ITO) sent to escort Nobuchika back were all renowned &apos;warriors worth a thousand,&apos; meaning each one of them was rumored to be the match of a thousand regular soldiers, which caused him to feel misgivings (as recorded in the &quot;Kojidan,&quot; Old Setsuwa Tales).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。文献の説明の&quot; &quot;削除。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="77">
<j>25日夜、惟方が後白河のもとを訪れて二条天皇の脱出計画を知らせると、後白河はすぐに仁和寺に脱出した（『愚管抄』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The night of the twenty-fifth, after Korekata came to Go-Shirakawa and informed him of the plan to rescue Emperor Nijo and take him away from Nobuyori, Go-Shirakawa immediately made his escape to Ninnaji temple (according to the &quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The night of the twenty-fifth, after Korekata came to Go-Shirakawa and informed him of the plan to rescue Emperor Nijo and take him away from Nobuyori, Go-Shirakawa immediately made his escape to Ninnaji temple (according to the &quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The night of the February 11, after Korekata came to Goshirakawa and informed him of the plan to rescue Emperor Nijo and take him away from Nobuyori, Goshirakawa immediately made his escape to Ninna-ji Temple (according to the &quot;Gukansho&quot;).</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。ハイフン補足、Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>日付が変わって26日丑刻（午前2時）、大宮二条で火災が起こり武士が気を取られた隙に、尹明は二条天皇を女房車に乗せ内裏を出て、六波羅の清盛邸に入った（二条天皇の六波羅行幸）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the twenty-fifth faded into the twenty-sixth, at around the hour of the Ox (about 2 AM), a fire was set in Omiya Nijo palace, and taking advantage of the soldiers&apos; distraction, Tadaaki hid Emperor Nijo in a carriage restricted to ladies and drove away, soon entering Kiyomori&apos;s mansion at Rokuhara (this being Emperor Nijo&apos;s aforementioned Imperial visit to Rokuhara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the twenty-fifth faded into the twenty-sixth, at around the hour of the Ox (about 2 AM), a fire was set in Omiya Nijo palace, and taking advantage of the soldiers&apos; distraction, Tadaaki hid Emperor Nijo in a carriage restricted to ladies and drove away, soon entering Kiyomori&apos;s mansion at Rokuhara (this being Emperor Nijo&apos;s aforementioned Imperial visit to Rokuhara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As February 11 faded into 12, at around the hour of the Ox (about 2 AM), a fire was set in Omiya Nijo Palace, and taking advantage of the soldiers&apos; distraction, Tadaaki hid Emperor Nijo in a carriage restricted to ladies and drove away, soon entering Kiyomori&apos;s mansion at Rokuhara (this being Emperor Nijo&apos;s aforementioned Imperial visit to Rokuhara).</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。Palace大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>なお『平治物語』では、内裏を出る際に警護の武士が怪しんで中を覗くが、17歳の天皇を女房と見誤ったとする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And according to the &quot;Heiji monogatari,&quot; as they left the palace grounds some of the guardsmen found them suspicious and searched the carriage, but mistook the seventeen-year-old Emperor for a lady in waiting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And according to the &quot;Heiji monogatari,&quot; as they left the palace grounds some of the guardsmen found them suspicious and searched the carriage, but mistook the seventeen-year-old Emperor for a lady in waiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And according to the &quot;Heiji monogatari,&quot; as they left the palace grounds some of the guardsmen found them suspicious and searched the carriage, but mistook the seventeen-year-old Emperor for a lady in waiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>惟方の弟藤原成頼がこれを触れて回ったことで、上皇・女院・公卿・諸大夫も六波羅に集結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korekata&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Nariyori, spread the news of the Emperor&apos;s successful escape around, which led the retired emperor, his empress, the nobles of the court, and various high ministers and stewards all to assemble at Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korekata&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Nariyori, spread the news of the Emperor&apos;s successful escape around, which led the retired emperor, his empress, the nobles of the court, and various high ministers and stewards all to assemble at Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korekata&apos;s younger brother, FUJIWARA no Nariyori, spread the news of the Emperor&apos;s successful escape around, which led the retired emperor, his empress, the nobles of the court, and various high ministers and stewards all to assemble at Rokuhara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>信頼と提携関係にあった摂関家の藤原忠通・基実父子も参入したことで、清盛は一気に官軍としての体裁を整えるに至り、信頼・義朝の追討宣旨が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even FUJIWARA no Tadamichi and his son Motozane, both of the elite Fujiwara branch that produced regents and advisors and with whom Nobuyori had been close, joined the counter-rebellion at Rokuhara, meaning that Kiyomori had achieved, in a stroke, total legitimacy for his army, and soon his forces received an imperial order to hunt down and destroy Nobuyori and Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even FUJIWARA no Tadamichi and his son Motozane, both of the elite Fujiwara branch that produced regents and advisors and with whom Nobuyori had been close, joined the counter-rebellion at Rokuhara, meaning that Kiyomori had achieved, in a stroke, total legitimacy for his army, and soon his forces received an imperial order to hunt down and destroy Nobuyori and Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even FUJIWARA no Tadamichi and his son Motozane, both of the elite Fujiwara branch that produced regents and advisors and with whom Nobuyori had been close, joined the counter-rebellion at Rokuhara, meaning that Kiyomori had achieved, in a stroke, total legitimacy for his army, and soon his forces received an imperial order to hunt down and destroy Nobuyori and Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>26日早朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The early morning of the twenty-sixth</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The early morning of the twenty-sixth</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The early morning of February 12</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="83">
<j>天皇・上皇の脱出を知った後白河院政派は激しく動揺し、義朝は信頼を「日本第一の不覚人」と罵倒したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Members of the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction were greatly stunned to learn of the escape of the Emperor and retired emperor, and Yoshitomo is said to have lambasted Nobuyori as &quot;the biggest fool in all Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members of the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction were greatly stunned to learn of the escape of the Emperor and retired emperor, and Yoshitomo is said to have lambasted Nobuyori as &quot;the biggest fool in all Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members of the Goshirakawa Insei faction were greatly stunned to learn of the escape of the Emperor and Retired Emperor, and Yoshitomo is said to have lambasted Nobuyori as &apos;the biggest fool in all Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。Retired Emperor 大文字にしました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>信頼・成親は義朝とともに武装して出陣するが、源師仲は保身のため三種の神器の一つである内侍所（神鏡）を持ち出して逃亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobuyori and Narichika joined Yoshitomo in taking up arms and marching out to battle, but MINAMOTO no Moronaka, in order to save his own life, took one of the three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the sacred Mirror, and fled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobuyori and Narichika joined Yoshitomo in taking up arms and marching out to battle, but MINAMOTO no Moronaka, in order to save his own life, took one of the three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the sacred Mirror, and fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobuyori and Narichika joined Yoshitomo in taking up arms and marching out to battle, but MINAMOTO no Moronaka, in order to save his own life, took one of the three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the sacred Mirror, and fled.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>合戦の経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The progress of the battle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The progress of the battle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The progress of the battle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="85">
<j>義朝側の戦力は、三条殿襲撃に参加した源重成・源光基・源季実、信西を追捕した源光保などの同盟軍、子息の義平・源朝長・頼朝、叔父・源義隆、信濃源氏・平賀義信などの一族、鎌田正家・後藤実基・佐々木秀義などの郎等により形成され、義朝の勢力基盤である関東からは、三浦義澄・上総介広常・山内首藤氏などが参戦したに過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The warriors fighting on Yoshitomo&apos;s side included MINAMOTO no Shigenari, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto, and MINAMOTO no Hidezane, all of whom had taken part in the raid on the Sanjo palace, and MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and others who had tracked down and captured Shinzei, as well as Yoshitomo&apos;s sons Yoshihira, Tomonaga, and Yoritomo and his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka and Yoshinobu HIRAGA and others of the Shinano branch of the Minamoto clan, and his army took shape around his retainers, including Masaie KAMATA, Sanemoto GOTO, and Hideyoshi SASAKI; yet from the Kanto, the source of Yoshitomo&apos;s power, only a handful, including Yoshizumi MIURA, Hidetsune KAZUSANOSUKE (TAIRA no Hidetsune), and some warriors of the Yamanouchi-sudo clan were present to fight with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The warriors fighting on Yoshitomo&apos;s side included MINAMOTO no Shigenari, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto, and MINAMOTO no Hidezane, all of whom had taken part in the raid on the Sanjo palace, and MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and others who had tracked down and captured Shinzei, as well as Yoshitomo&apos;s sons Yoshihira, Tomonaga, and Yoritomo and his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka and Yoshinobu HIRAGA and others of the Shinano branch of the Minamoto clan, and his army took shape around his retainers, including Masaie KAMATA, Sanemoto GOTO, and Hideyoshi SASAKI; yet from the Kanto, the source of Yoshitomo&apos;s power, only a handful, including Yoshizumi MIURA, Hidetsune KAZUSANOSUKE (TAIRA no Hidetsune), and some warriors of the Yamanouchi-sudo clan were present to fight with him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The warriors fighting on Yoshitomo&apos;s side included MINAMOTO no Shigenari, MINAMOTO no Mitsumoto, and MINAMOTO no Hidezane, all of whom had taken part in the raid on the Sanjo Palace, and MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and others who had tracked down and captured Shinzei, as well as Yoshitomo&apos;s sons Yoshihira, Tomonaga, and Yoritomo and his uncle MINAMOTO no Yoshitaka and Yoshinobu HIRAGA and others of the Shinano branch of the Minamoto clan, and his army took shape around his retainers, including Masaie KAMATA, Sanemoto GOTO, and Hideyoshi SASAKI; yet from the Kanto, the source of Yoshitomo&apos;s power, only a handful, including Yoshizumi MIURA, Hidetsune KAZUSANOSUKE (TAIRA no Hidetsune), and some warriors of the Yamanouchi-Sudo clan were present to fight with him.</e>
<cmt>Palace大文字にしました。Sudo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>三浦義澄は義平の叔父、上総介広常は義朝を養君として擁立していた上総氏の嫡子、山内首藤氏は源氏譜代の家人であり、いずれも義朝と個人的に深い関係を有する武士である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshizumi MIURA was Yoshihira&apos;s uncle while Hidetsune KAZUSANOSUKE was the heir of the Kazusa clan, who backed Yoshitomo, having adopted him as their liege lord, and the Yamanouchi-sudo clan had been vassals of the Minamoto for many generations, meaning that all of these warriors had close personal relationships with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshizumi MIURA was Yoshihira&apos;s uncle while Hidetsune KAZUSANOSUKE was the heir of the Kazusa clan, who backed Yoshitomo, having adopted him as their liege lord, and the Yamanouchi-sudo clan had been vassals of the Minamoto for many generations, meaning that all of these warriors had close personal relationships with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshizumi MIURA was Yoshihira&apos;s uncle while Hidetsune KAZUSANOSUKE was the heir of the Kazusa clan, who backed Yoshitomo, having adopted him as their liege lord, and the Yamanouchi-Sudo clan had been vassals of the Minamoto for many generations, meaning that all of these warriors had close personal relationships with Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除。Sudo大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>保元の乱では国家による公的な動員だったのに対して今回はクーデターのための隠密裏の召集であり、義朝が組織できたのは私的武力に限られ兵力は僅少だったと推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whereas the mobilization during the Hogen Rebellion had been public, sanctioned by the state, this time the order to muster had to be given in the utmost secrecy due to the coup, and so Yoshitomo was only able to assemble what soldiers he had immediately around him; it is conjectured that his army, in the end, numbered very few indeed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whereas the mobilization during the Hogen Rebellion had been public, sanctioned by the state, this time the order to muster had to be given in the utmost secrecy due to the coup, and so Yoshitomo was only able to assemble what soldiers he had immediately around him; it is conjectured that his army, in the end, numbered very few indeed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whereas the mobilization during the Hogen Rebellion had been public, sanctioned by the state, this time the order to muster had to be given in the utmost secrecy due to the coup, and so Yoshitomo was only able to assemble what soldiers he had immediately around him; it is conjectured that his army, in the end, numbered very few indeed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="88">
<j>清盛は内裏が戦場となるのを防ぐために六波羅に敵を引き寄せる作戦を立て、嫡男平重盛と弟・頼盛が出陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kiyomori, in order to avoid turning the imperial palace into a battlefield, lauunched a strategy to lure his enemies to Rokuhara, and his eldest son and heir, TAIRA no Shigemori, as well as Kiyomori&apos;s younger brother, Yorimori, also fought in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kiyomori, in order to avoid turning the imperial palace into a battlefield, lauunched a strategy to lure his enemies to Rokuhara, and his eldest son and heir, TAIRA no Shigemori, as well as Kiyomori&apos;s younger brother, Yorimori, also fought in the battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kiyomori, in order to avoid turning the imperial palace into a battlefield, launched a strategy to lure his enemies to Rokuhara, and his eldest son and heir, TAIRA no Shigemori, as well as Kiyomori&apos;s younger brother, Yorimori, also fought in the battle.</e>
<cmt>launchedスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>『平治物語』では重盛と義平が待賢門で一騎打ちを繰り広げ、御所の右近の橘・左近の桜の間を7度も義平が重盛を追い回した、頼盛が退却中に敵に追いつかれそうになり重代の名刀「抜丸」で辛くも撃退した、というエピソードが出てくるがこれらは話を盛り上げるための創作と思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; describes a scene in which Shigemori and Yoshihira fought in single combat at the Taikenmon gate, Yoshihira driving Shigemori back seven times in an area of the palace between the tachibana on the right and the cherry tree on the left, and meanwhile, Yorimori was staging a fighting withdrawal, but when he came under danger of being overrun by his foes he furiously struck all around him with &quot;Nukimaru,&quot; his famous and ancient sword; needless to say, this episode is considered to be a literary embellishment to create a stirring climactic scene.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; describes a scene in which Shigemori and Yoshihira fought in single combat at the Taikenmon gate, Yoshihira driving Shigemori back seven times in an area of the palace between the tachibana on the right and the cherry tree on the left, and meanwhile, Yorimori was staging a fighting withdrawal, but when he came under danger of being overrun by his foes he furiously struck all around him with &quot;Nukimaru,&quot; his famous and ancient sword; needless to say, this episode is considered to be a literary embellishment to create a stirring climactic scene.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; describes a scene in which Shigemori and Yoshihira fought in single combat at the Taikenmon gate, Yoshihira driving Shigemori back seven times in an area of the palace between the tachibana on the right and the cherry tree on the left, and meanwhile, Yorimori was staging a fighting withdrawal, but when he came under danger of being overrun by his foes he furiously struck all around him with &apos;Nukimaru,&apos; his famous and ancient sword; needless to say, this episode is considered to be a literary embellishment to create a stirring climactic scene.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>このとき陽明門を警護していた源光保、光基は門の守りを放棄して寝返るが、光保は美福門院の家人で政治的には二条親政派であり、信西打倒のため義朝に協力していたに過ぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and Mitsumoto, who were charged with guarding the Yomeimon gate, abandoned their posts at the gate and switched sides, but after all, Mitsuyasu was a retainer to Bifukumon&apos;in and thus politically a member of the Nijo direct rule faction, and had merely temporarily collaborated with Yoshitomo to strike down Shinzei, not entered a permanent alliance with him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and Mitsumoto, who were charged with guarding the Yomeimon gate, abandoned their posts at the gate and switched sides, but after all, Mitsuyasu was a retainer to Bifukumon&apos;in and thus politically a member of the Nijo direct rule faction, and had merely temporarily collaborated with Yoshitomo to strike down Shinzei, and had not entered a permanent alliance with him.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and Mitsumoto, who were charged with guarding the Yomeimon gate, abandoned their posts at the gate and switched sides, but after all, Mitsuyasu was a retainer to Bifukumonin and thus politically a member of the Nijo direct rule faction, and had merely temporarily collaborated with Yoshitomo to strike down Shinzei, and had not entered a permanent alliance with him.</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>平氏軍は予定通り退却し、義朝は決死の覚悟で六波羅に迫るが六条河原であえなく敗退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira army began to withdraw, as planned, and although Yoshitomo prepared himself to die and charged after them towards Rokuhara, his force was soundly defeated at the Rokujo-gawara riverbed and forced to retreat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira army began to withdraw, as planned, and although Yoshitomo prepared himself to die and charged after them towards Rokuhara, his force was soundly defeated at the Rokujo-gawara riverbed and forced to retreat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira army began to withdraw, as planned, and although Yoshitomo prepared himself to die and charged after them towards Rokuhara, his force was soundly defeated at the Rokujo-gawara riverbed and forced to retreat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>『平治物語』は源頼政が味方につかなかったとするが、もともと頼政も美福門院の家人であり義朝に従属する立場ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; claims Yoshitomo had been unable to get and keep MINAMOTO no Yorimasa as an ally, but in fact Yorimasa was a retainer of Bifukumon&apos;in and had been from the start, meaning he had never truly been a follower of Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; claims Yoshitomo had been unable to get and keep MINAMOTO no Yorimasa as an ally, but in fact Yorimasa was a retainer of Bifukumon&apos;in and had been from the start, meaning he had never truly been a follower of Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; claims Yoshitomo had been unable to get and keep MINAMOTO no Yorimasa as an ally, but in fact Yorimasa was a retainer of Bifukumonin and had been from the start, meaning he had never truly been a follower of Yoshitomo.</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>義朝は平氏軍と頼政軍の攻撃を受け、山内首藤俊通・片桐景重らが必死の防戦をする間に戦場から脱出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshitomo&apos;s army came under the joint attack of the Taira forces as well as Yorimasa&apos;s army, Toshimichi YAMANOUCHI-SUDO and Kageshige KATAGIRI, among others, fought a delaying action to the death, and taking full advantage of the time they had bought him, Yoshitomo slipped away from the battlefield.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshitomo&apos;s army came under the joint attack of the Taira forces as well as Yorimasa&apos;s army, Toshimichi YAMANOUCHI-SUDO and Kageshige KATAGIRI, among others, fought a delaying action to the death, and taking full advantage of the time they had bought him, Yoshitomo slipped away from the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshitomo&apos;s army came under the joint attack of the Taira forces as well as Yorimasa&apos;s army, Toshimichi YAMANOUCHI-SUDO and Kageshige KATAGIRI, among others, fought a delaying action to the death, and taking full advantage of the time they had bought him, Yoshitomo slipped away from the battlefield.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>後白河院政派の壊滅</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The annihilation of the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The annihilation of the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The annihilation of the Goshirakawa Insei faction</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="94">
<j>藤原信頼・成親は仁和寺の覚性法親王のもとへ出頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and Narichika fled to Ninnaji temple to wait upon Prince Kakusho, a priest there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and Narichika fled to Ninnaji temple to wait upon Prince Kakusho, a priest there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">FUJIWARA no Nobuyori and Narichika fled to Ninna-ji Temple to wait upon Cloistered Imperial Prince Kakusho.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン補足、Temple大文字にしました。法親王→Cloistered Imperial Prince, a priest there削除。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>清盛の前に引き出された信頼は自己弁護をするが、信西殺害・三条殿襲撃の首謀者であり最後まで武装して参戦していたことから、戦闘員とみなされ処刑された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When he was hauled before Kiyomori, Nobuyori did try to justify his actions, but given that he was the ringleader in the death of Shinzei and the assault on Sanjoden palace, and had taken up arms and fought in the battle right up until the very moment of defeat, he was judged an enemy of war and executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When he was hauled before Kiyomori, Nobuyori did try to justify his actions, but given that he was the ringleader in the death of Shinzei and the assault on Sanjoden palace, and had taken up arms and fought in the battle right up until the very moment of defeat, he was judged an enemy of war and executed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When he was hauled before Kiyomori, Nobuyori did try to justify his actions, but given that he was the ringleader in the death of Shinzei and the assault on Sanjo Palace, and had taken up arms and fought in the battle right up until the very moment of defeat, he was judged an enemy of war and executed.</e>
<cmt>Sanjoden palace→Sanjo Palaceに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>成親は重盛室の兄という理由で、特別に助命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narichika, owing to the fact that he was the brother of Shigemori&apos;s wife, was specially granted clemency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narichika, owing to the fact that he was the brother of Shigemori&apos;s wife, was specially granted clemency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narichika, owing to the fact that he was the brother of Shigemori&apos;s wife, was specially granted clemency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>逃亡していた師仲は、神鏡を手土産に六波羅に出頭するが処罰は厳しく、下野国への配流が決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moronaka, who had fled, returned and brought the Sacred Mirror back to Rokuhara as a gift, yet his punishment remained severe--he was exiled to Shimotsuke province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moronaka, who had fled, returned and brought the Sacred Mirror back to Rokuhara as a gift, yet his punishment remained severe--he was exiled to Shimotsuke province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moronaka, who had fled, returned and brought the Sacred Mirror back to Rokuhara as a gift, yet his punishment remained severe; he was exiled to Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除、;補足Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="98">
<j>義朝は東国への脱出を図るが途中で頼朝とはぐれ、朝長・義隆を失い、12月29日尾張国内海荘司・長田忠致の邸にたどり着いたところを鎌田正家とともに殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshitomo was planning to escape to safety in the Kanto, but along the way got separated from Yoritomo and lost Yorinaga and Yoshitaka as well, until at last, on the 29th day of the twelfth month, just as he arrived at the residence of Tadamune OSADA, he and his companion Masaie KANATA were slain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshitomo was planning to escape to safety in the Kanto, but along the way got separated from Yoritomo and lost Yorinaga and Yoshitaka as well, until at last, on the 29th day of the twelfth month, just as he arrived at the residence of Tadamune OSADA, he and his companion Masaie KANATA were slain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshitomo was planning to escape to safety in the Kanto, but along the way got separated from Yoritomo and lost Yorinaga and Yoshitaka as well, until at last, on February 15, just as he arrived at the residence of Tadamune OSADA, he and his companion Masaie KANATA were slain.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>義朝と正家の首は、正月9日京都で獄門に晒された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The heads of Yoshitomo and Masaie were put on display at the prison gate in Kyoto on the ninth day of the first month of the new year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The heads of Yoshitomo and Masaie were put on display at the prison gate in Kyoto on the ninth day of the first month of the new year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The heads of Yoshitomo and Masaie were put on display at the prison gate in Kyoto on February 24, 1160.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>義平は18日難波経房の郎等・橘俊綱に捕らえられ、21日六条河原で処刑。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihira was captured by TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna, a retainer of Tsunefusa NANBA, on the 18th, and executed at the Rokujo gawara riverbed three days later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihira was captured by TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna, a retainer of Tsunefusa NANBA, on the 18th, and executed at the Rokujo gawara riverbed three days later.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihira was captured by TACHIBANA no Toshitsuna, a retainer of Tsunefusa NANBA, on March 4, and executed at the Rokujo gawara riverbed on March 7.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>頼朝も2月9日平頼盛の郎等・平宗清に捕まりやはり処刑されるところを、清盛の継母・池禅尼の嘆願で助命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the ninth day of the second month, Yoritomo also was captured, by TAIRA no Munekiyo, a retainer of TAIRA no Yorimori, and just when his execution seemed certain, Kiyomori&apos;s stepmother Ike no zenni intervened, successfully pleading for his life to be spared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the ninth day of the second month, Yoritomo also was captured, by TAIRA no Munekiyo, a retainer of TAIRA no Yorimori, and just when his execution seemed certain, Kiyomori&apos;s stepmother Ike no zenni intervened, successfully pleading for his life to be spared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 25, Yoritomo also was captured, by TAIRA no Munekiyo, a retainer of TAIRA no Yorimori, and just when his execution seemed certain, Kiyomori&apos;s stepmother Ike no zenni intervened, successfully pleading for his life to be spared.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>この背景には頼朝が上西門院の蔵人をつとめていたため、上西門院とその近臣・熱田大宮司家が待賢門院（後白河上皇・上西門院の母）近臣家出身の池禅尼に働きかけた可能性が考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a tentative explanation for why she intervened, Yoritomo had served Empress Dowager Josaimon&apos;in as a kuraudo (storehouse attendant), and it is considered possible that he worked directly for Ike no zenni--who was of a family, the Atsuta Daiguji, that was a vassal of Empress Dowager Taikenmon&apos;in (the mother of both retired emperor Go-Shirakawa and Josaimon&apos;in, meaning her family had also served their lady&apos;s daughter, Josaimon&apos;in)--while serving there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a tentative explanation for why she intervened, Yoritomo had served Empress Dowager Josaimon&apos;in as a kuraudo (storehouse attendant), and it is considered possible that he worked directly for Ike no zenni--who was of a family, the Atsuta Daiguji, that was a vassal of Empress Dowager Taikenmon&apos;in (the mother of both retired emperor Go-Shirakawa and Josaimon&apos;in, meaning her family had also served their lady&apos;s daughter, Josaimon&apos;in)--while serving there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a tentative explanation for why she intervened, Yoritomo had served Empress Dowager Josaimonin as a Kurodo (Chamberlain), and it is considered possible that he worked directly for Ike no zenni, who belonged a family of Atsuta Daiguji, that was a vassal of Empress Dowager Taikenmonin (the mother of both retired emperor Goshirakawa and Josaimonin, meaning her family had also served their lady&apos;s daughter, Josaimonin), while serving there.</e>
<cmt>Josaimoninに訂正しました。蔵人→Kurodo (Chamberlain)ハイフン削除。,補足who belonged a family of Atsuta Daigujiに訂正しました。Taikenmoninに訂正しました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>義朝と行動を共にした源重成・季実も滅亡の運命を辿り、ここに後白河院政派は事実上壊滅することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Orders to eliminate MINAMOTO no Shigenari and Hidezane, who had acted in tandem with Yoshitomo, followed in due course, and with their deaths, the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction had effectively been destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Orders to eliminate MINAMOTO no Shigenari and Hidezane, who had acted in tandem with Yoshitomo, followed in due course, and with their deaths, the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction had effectively been destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Orders to eliminate MINAMOTO no Shigenari and Hidezane, who had acted in tandem with Yoshitomo, followed in due course, and with their deaths, the Goshirakawa Insei faction had effectively been destroyed.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>経宗・惟方の失脚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune and Korekata&apos;s fall from grace</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune and Korekata&apos;s fall from grace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune and Korekata&apos;s fall from grace</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>合戦の終息した12月29日恩賞の除目があり、頼盛が尾張守、重盛が伊予守、宗盛が遠江守、教盛が越中守、経盛が伊賀守にそれぞれ任じられ、平氏一門の知行国は乱の前の5ヶ国から7ヶ国に増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A session granting awards was held on the 29th day of the twelfth month, just after the battle ended; at this session, Yorimori was made governor of Owari province, Shigemori of Iyo province, Munemori of Totomi province, Norimori of Ecchu province, and Tsunemori of Iga province, meaning that following the battle, the Taira&apos;s control over provinces through enfiefment increased from five provinces to seven.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A session granting awards was held on the 29th day of the twelfth month, just after the battle ended; at this session, Yorimori was made governor of Owari province, Shigemori of Iyo province, Munemori of Totomi province, Norimori of Ecchu province, and Tsunemori of Iga province, meaning that following the battle, the Taira&apos;s control over provinces through enfiefment increased from five provinces to seven.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A session granting awards was held on February 15, just after the battle ended; at this session, Yorimori was made governor of Owari Province, Shigemori of Iyo Province, Munemori of Totomi Province, Norimori of Ecchu Province, and Tsunemori of Iga Province, meaning that following the battle, the Taira&apos;s control over chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) increased from five provinces to seven.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。Province大文字にしました。知行国→chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>同日二条天皇は美福門院の八条殿に行幸し、清盛が警護した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The same day, Emperor Nijo paid a state visit to Bifukumon&apos;in at Hachijoden palace, with Kiyomori serving as his escort.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The same day, Emperor Nijo paid a state visit to Bifukumon&apos;in at Hachijoden palace, with Kiyomori serving as his escort.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The same day, Emperor Nijo paid a state visit to Bifukumonin at Hachijoden Palace, with Kiyomori serving as his escort.</e>
<cmt>Bifukumoninに訂正しました。Palace大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>翌永暦元年（1160年）正月に天皇は近衛天皇の皇后だった藤原多子を入内させ、自らの権威の安定につとめた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following year, in the first month of 1160 (the first year of the Enryaku era), Emperor Nijo welcomed FUJIWARA no Masaruko, the former empress of Emperor Konoe, into his court, and worked at stabilizing his own power and influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following year, in the first month of 1160 (the first year of the Enryaku era), Emperor Nijo welcomed FUJIWARA no Masaruko, the former empress of Emperor Konoe, into his court, and worked at stabilizing his own power and influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following year, in February, 1160, Emperor Nijo welcomed FUJIWARA no Masaruko, the former empress of Emperor Konoe, into his court, and worked at stabilizing his own power and influence.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>実権を握った二条親政派の経宗・惟方は、後白河上皇への圧迫を強めることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsunemune and Korekata, members of the Nijo direct rule faction who held true power, increased their pressure on retired emperor Go-Shirakawa to fall into line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsunemune and Korekata, members of the Nijo direct rule faction who held the true power, increased their pressure on retired emperor Go-Shirakawa to fall into line.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; added</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsunemune and Korekata, members of the Nijo direct rule faction who held the true power, increased their pressure on retired emperor Goshirakawa to fall into line.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>正月6日上皇が八条堀河の藤原顕長邸に御幸して桟敷で八条大路を見物していたところ、堀河にあった材木を外から打ちつけ視界を遮るという嫌がらせを行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the sixth day of the first month, Go-Shirakawa went on an imperial visit to FUJIWARA no Akinaga&apos;s residence in the Horikawa area of Hachijo (Eighth Avenue), but as he was sightseeing from a box set up alongside the Hachijo thoroughfare, he suffered harrassment in the form of some trees that were sent crashing down from outside the box to obstruct his view.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the sixth day of the first month, Go-Shirakawa went on an imperial visit to FUJIWARA no Akinaga&apos;s residence in the Horikawa area of Hachijo (Eighth Avenue), but as he was sightseeing from a box set up alongside the Hachijo thoroughfare, he suffered harrassment in the form of some trees that were sent crashing down from outside the box to obstruct his view.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 21, Goshirakawa went on an imperial visit to FUJIWARA no Akinaga&apos;s residence in the Horikawa area of Hachijo (Eighth Avenue), but as he was sightseeing from a box set up alongside the Hachijo thoroughfare, he suffered harassment in the form of some trees that were sent crashing down from outside the box to obstruct his view.</e>
<cmt>harassmentスペル訂正しました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>上皇は激怒して清盛に経宗・惟方の逮捕を命じ、2月20日清盛の郎等・源為長が二人の身柄を拘束、上皇の眼前に引き据て拷問にかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Go-Shirakawa flew into a rage and ordered Kiyomori to arrest Tsunemune and Korekata, so on the 20th day of the second month, one of Kiyomori&apos;s retainers, MINAMOTO no Tamenaga, captured the two of them, dragged them before Go-Shirakawa and had them tortured.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Go-Shirakawa flew into a rage and ordered Kiyomori to arrest Tsunemune and Korekata, so on the 20th day of the second month, one of Kiyomori&apos;s retainers, MINAMOTO no Tamenaga, captured the two of them, dragged them before Go-Shirakawa and had them tortured.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshirakawa flew into a rage and ordered Kiyomori to arrest Tsunemune and Korekata, so on April 5, one of Kiyomori&apos;s retainers, MINAMOTO no Tamenaga, captured the two of them, dragged them before Goshirakawa and had them tortured.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。新暦の表記にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>貴族への拷問は免除されるのが慣例であり、上皇の二人に対する憎しみの深さを現わしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an established precedent exempting members of the nobility from torture, so their fate helps to show just how deeply Go-Shirakawa must have hated them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an established precedent exempting members of the nobility from torture, so their fate helps to show just how deeply Go-Shirakawa must have hated them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an established precedent exempting members of the nobility from torture, so their fate helps to show just how deeply Goshirakawa must have hated them.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>経宗・惟方の失脚の理由としては、信西殺害の共犯者としての責任を追及されたことによるものと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reason for Tsunemune and Korekata&apos;s downfall is thought to be the fruits of the investigation into their guilt for colluding in the death of Shinzei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reason for Tsunemune and Korekata&apos;s downfall is thought to be the fruits of the investigation into their guilt for colluding in the death of Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reason for Tsunemune and Korekata&apos;s downfall is thought to be the fruits of the investigation into their guilt for colluding in the death of Shinzei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="112">
<j>2月22日信西の子息が帰京を許され、入れ替わりに3月11日経宗が阿波国、惟方が長門国に配流された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the 22nd day of the second month, Shinzei&apos;s son was allowed to return to the capital, while by contrast, on the eleventh day of the third month, Tsunemune was exiled to Awa province and Korekata to Nagato province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the 22nd day of the second month, Shinzei&apos;s son was allowed to return to the capital, while by contrast, on the eleventh day of the third month, Tsunemune was exiled to Awa province and Korekata to Nagato province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 7, Shinzei&apos;s son was allowed to return to the capital, while by contrast, on April 26, Tsunemune was exiled to Awa Province and Korekata to Nagato Province.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>同日、師仲・頼朝・源希義（頼朝の同母弟）もそれぞれ配流先に下っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That same day, the destinations to which Moronaka, Yoritomo, and MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi (Yoritomo&apos;s younger brother by the same mother) were to be exiled were announced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That same day, the destinations to which Moronaka, Yoritomo, and MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi (Yoritomo&apos;s younger brother by the same mother) were to be exiled were announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That same day, the destinations to which Moronaka, Yoritomo, and MINAMOTO no Mareyoshi (Yoritomo&apos;s younger brother by the same mother) were to be exiled were announced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>6月には信西の首をとった源光保と子の源光宗が謀反の疑いで薩摩国に配流され、14日殺害された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the sixth month, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and his son Mitsumune, who had taken Shinzei&apos;s head, were exiled to Satsuma province on suspicion of plotting against the government, and were killed on the fourteenth day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the sixth month, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and his son Mitsumune, who had taken Shinzei&apos;s head, were exiled to Satsuma province on suspicion of plotting against the government, and were killed on the fourteenth day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July, MINAMOTO no Mitsuyasu and his son Mitsumune, who had taken Shinzei&apos;s head, were exiled to Satsuma Province on suspicion of plotting against the government, and were killed on the fourteenth day.</e>
<cmt>新暦の表記にしました。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>信西打倒に関わった者は、後白河院政派・二条親政派を問わず政界から一掃された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All those who had participated in Shinzei&apos;s overthrow and demise, regardless of whether they belonged to the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction or the Nijo direct rule faction, had now been annihilated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All those who had participated in Shinzei&apos;s overthrow and demise, regardless of whether they belonged to the Go-Shirakawa Insei faction or the Nijo direct rule faction, had now been annihilated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All those who had participated in Shinzei&apos;s overthrow and demise, regardless of whether they belonged to the Goshirakawa Insei faction or the Nijo direct rule faction, had now been annihilated.</e>
<cmt>天皇の名前表記訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>その後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The aftermath of the rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The aftermath of the rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The aftermath of the rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="116">
<j>後白河上皇と二条天皇の対立は双方の有力な廷臣が共倒れになったため小康状態となり、「院・内、申シ合ツツ同ジ御心ニテ」（『愚管抄』）とあるように二頭政治が行われたが、乱勝利の最大の貢献者である清盛はどちらの派にも組することなく慎重に行動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflict between retired emperor Go-Shirakawa and Emperor Nijo, which had resulted in the mutual destruction of many of their most capable courtiers, now entered a lull, and indeed, the government became something of a diumvirate between the two of them (as written in the &apos;Gukansho,&apos; &quot;Now the retired emperor and the Emperor spoke in harmony, and were of one mind&quot;), but as for Kiyomori, who had made the single greatest contribution to the current half-victory for each of them, he continued to act prudently, not joining either faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflict between retired emperor Go-Shirakawa and Emperor Nijo, which had resulted in the mutual destruction of many of their most capable courtiers, now entered a lull, and indeed, the government became something of a diumvirate between the two of them (as written in the &apos;Gukansho,&apos; &quot;Now the retired emperor and the Emperor spoke in harmony, and were of one mind&quot;), but as for Kiyomori, who had made the single greatest contribution to the current half-victory for each of them, he continued to act prudently, not joining either faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflict between Retired Emperor Goshirakawa and Emperor Nijo, which had resulted in the mutual destruction of many of their most capable courtiers, now entered a lull, and indeed, the government became something of a duumvirate between the two of them (as written in the &quot;Gukansho,&quot; &apos;Now the Retired Emperor and the Emperor spoke in harmony, and were of one mind&apos;), but as for Kiyomori, who had made the single greatest contribution to the current half-victory for each of them, he continued to act prudently, not joining either faction.</e>
<cmt>Retired Emperor大文字にしました。天皇の名前表記訂正しました。duumvirateスペル訂正しました。原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。原文の『』に合わせて&apos;を&quot;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>平氏一門は院庁別当・左馬寮・内蔵寮などの要職を占め、政治への影響力を増大させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira family took charge of several important offices, including the posts of Incho betto (Chief of the Incho (government of the retired emperor)), Sama no ryo (Commander of the Left Horse), and Uchikura no ryo (Chief of the Palace Storehouses), thereby greatly increasing their political influence over the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira family took charge of several important offices, including the posts of Incho betto (Chief of the Incho (government of the retired emperor)), Sama no ryo (Commander of the Left Horse), and Uchikura no ryo (Chief of the Palace Storehouses), thereby greatly increasing their political influence over the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira family took charge of several important offices, including the posts of Innocho Betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office), Samaryo (Left Division of Bureau of Horses), and Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses), thereby greatly increasing their political influence over the government.</e>
<cmt>院庁別当→Innocho Betto (chief administrator of the Retired Emperor&apos;s Office)左馬寮→Samaryo (Left Division of Bureau of Horses)内蔵寮→Kuraryo (Bureau of Palace Storehouses)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>平氏の知行国も平家貞が筑後守、藤原能盛が壱岐守・安芸守、源為長が紀伊守となるなど、一門だけでなく郎等にも及びその経済基盤も他から抜きん出たものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the power of the Taira clan was even greater still when one factors in the economic base they had to draw upon over and above the ample resources of the immediate family, the enfiefed provinces they controlled indirectly through their retainers, including TAIRA no Iesada&apos;s appointment as governor of Chikugo province, FUJIWARA no Yoshimori as governor of both Iki and Aki, and MINAMOTO no Tamenaga as governor of Iyo province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the power of the Taira clan was even greater still when one factors in the economic base they had to draw upon over and above the ample resources of the immediate family, the enfiefed provinces they controlled indirectly through their retainers, including TAIRA no Iesada&apos;s appointment as governor of Chikugo province, FUJIWARA no Yoshimori as governor of both Iki and Aki, and MINAMOTO no Tamenaga as governor of Iyo province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the power of the Taira clan was even greater still when one factors in the economic base they had to draw upon over and above the ample resources of the immediate family, the chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom) they controlled indirectly through their retainers, including TAIRA no Iesada&apos;s appointment as governor of Chikugo Province, FUJIWARA no Yoshimori as governor of both Iki and Aki, and MINAMOTO no Tamenaga as governor of Iyo Province.</e>
<cmt>知行国→chigyo-koku (provincial fiefdom)としました。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>さらに多くの軍事貴族が戦乱で淘汰されたため、京都の治安維持・地方反乱の鎮圧・荘園の管理の役割も平氏の独占するところとなり、国家的な軍事・警察権も事実上掌握した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the ranks of the nobility involved in military affairs had been greatly thinned by the recents wars and rebellions, which allowed the Taira clan to achieve a monopoly over the vital roles of preserving the peace in Kyoto, suppressing revolts in the provinces, and protecting and managing the shoen (private estates), and they also held de facto power as the sole police authorities throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the ranks of the nobility involved in military affairs had been greatly thinned by the recents wars and rebellions, which allowed the Taira clan to achieve a monopoly over the vital roles of preserving the peace in Kyoto, suppressing revolts in the provinces, and protecting and managing the shoen (private estates), and they also held de facto power as the sole police authorities throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the ranks of the nobility involved in military affairs had been greatly thinned by the recent wars and rebellions, which allowed the Taira clan to achieve a monopoly over the vital roles of preserving the peace in Kyoto, suppressing revolts in the provinces, and protecting and managing the shoen (private estates), and they also held de facto power as the sole police authorities throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>recent、s削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>清盛はその経済力・軍事力を背景に朝廷における武家の地位を確立して、永暦元年（1160年）、参議に任命され、武士で初めて公卿（議政官）の地位に就いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the weight of the Taira&apos;s great economic and military might behind him, Kiyomori firmly established the (high) position of the warrior clans at court; in 1160 (Enryaku 1) he was named Sangi (Director of Palace Affairs), marking the first time a warrior had been raised to such a high and lordly (Giseikan) rank at court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the weight of the Taira&apos;s great economic and military might behind him, Kiyomori firmly established the (high) position of the warrior clans at court; in 1160 (Enryaku 1) he was named Sangi (Director of Palace Affairs), marking the first time a warrior had been raised to such a high and lordly (Giseikan) rank at court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the weight of the Taira&apos;s great economic and military might behind him, Kiyomori firmly established the (high) position of the warrior clans at court; in 1160 he was named Sangi (councillor), marking the first time a warrior had been raised to such a high and lordly (Giseikan) rank at court.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除。Sangi (councillor)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>やがて一門からも公卿・殿上人が輩出し、平氏政権を形成していったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long his branch of the Taira clan produced great numbers of high-ranking noblemen and courtiers, and the political power of the Taira took definite form.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long his branch of the Taira clan produced great numbers of high-ranking noblemen and courtiers, and the political power of the Taira took definite form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long his branch of the Taira clan produced great numbers of high-ranking noblemen and courtiers, and the political power of the Taira took definite form.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="122">
<j>文学作品</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literary works on the Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literary works on the Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literary works on the Heiji Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>平治の乱を題材にした文学に『平治物語』がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; is a literary work that takes the Heiji Rebellion as its topic.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; is a literary work that takes the Heiji Rebellion as its topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Heiji monogatari&quot; is a literary work that takes the Heiji Rebellion as its topic.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>同書は作者不明で全3巻の軍記物語であり、平治物語を題材に絵巻物の「平治物語絵巻」が描かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This work is a war chronicle totaling three volumes, whose author or authors remain unknown; an emaki (hand scroll) called &quot;Heiji monogatari emaki,&quot; which takes the Heiji monogatari itself as its subject, was also created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This work is a war chronicle totaling three volumes, whose author or authors remain unknown; an emaki (hand scroll) called &quot;Heiji monogatari emaki,&quot; which takes the Heiji monogatari itself as its subject, was also created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This work is a war chronicle totaling three volumes, whose author or authors remain unknown; an emaki (hand scroll) called &apos;Heiji monogatari emaki,&apos; which takes the Heiji monogatari itself as its subject, was also created.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Shishin(id:22312), Ignis(id:28979), Reggaeman(id:6214), 水野白楓(id:22811), 味っ子(id:17086), Andee(id:20421), Mintleaf(id:2216), Ash Crow(id:26765), 沢田(id:40580), Greenland4(id:114494), 小者(id:172526), Kamitani(id:30757), MDR-SK(id:192066), でここ(id:9565), Rusk(id:9895), 氷鷺(id:73707), SilvonenBot(id:190970), NoriBeat(id:2074), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Hamilton(id:6033), NPD(id:58640), 日本一弱い男(id:92046), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), Wybot(id:81801), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>