<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>局部磨製石斧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokubumasei-sekifu (edge-ground stone axe)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyokubumasei-sekifu (edge-ground stone axe)</e>
<cmt>日本語（英語）の併記にしてあります。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokubumasei-sekifu (edge-ground stone axe)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>局部磨製石斧（きょくぶませいせきふ）とは、いまより約3万年前の後期旧石器時代初頭に登場した、刃先に磨きをかけた石斧のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokubumasei-sekifu is a edge-ground stone axe which emerged in the early upper Palaeolithic Period about 30 thousand years ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyokubumasei-sekifu is a edge-ground stone axe which appeared in the early upper Paleolithic period about 30 thousand years ago.</e>
<cmt>用語を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokubumasei-sekifu is a edge-ground stone axe which appeared in the early upper Paleolithic period about 30 thousand years ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大形獣の狩猟や解体、木の伐採や切断、土掘りなど多目的に用いられたと推定される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is presumed to have been used for multipurpose such as for hunting and demising large-sized animals, felling and cutting trees, and digging.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought to have been used for multiple purposes such as for hunting and demising large-sized animals, felling and cutting trees, and digging.</e>
<cmt>用語を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought to have been used for multiple purposes such as for hunting and demising large-sized animals, felling and cutting trees, and digging.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>石材は、黒曜石、頁岩、チャート、讃岐岩、輝石などを利用している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obsidian, shale, chert, sanukite, pyroxene and so on were used for stone materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such stone materials as obsidian, shale, chart, sanukite, and pyroxene were used.</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such stone materials as obsidian, shale, chart, sanukite, and pyroxene were used.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>この年代は、現在のところ日本出土のものが世界最古とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ones unearthed in Japan are considered to be the oldest among those of this age in the world at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The artifacts from Japan are considered to be the oldest ones in the world among the artifacts of this age unearthed so far.</e>
<cmt>構文を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The artifacts from Japan are considered to be the oldest ones in the world among the artifacts of this age unearthed so far.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>1949年の岩宿遺跡が初出で、このときは旧石器存否論争、無土器新石器説、中石器時代説を引き起こし、石器資料そのものに関しては摩耗論争さえ巻き起こっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyokubumasei-sekifu first appeared in 1949 when they were unearthed at Iwajuku Archeological Site, which caused a dispute over the existence of palaeolith, the theory of Neolithic Period without usage of pottery, the theory of Mesolithic Period and even a dispute over the tools&apos; being abraded or not.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The artifacts of Kyokubumasei-sekifu were unearthed in 1949 for the fist time from Iwajuku Archeological Site, and this finding opened the debate not only on the existence of Paleolithic with the publication of the non-pottery Neolithic period theory and the Mesolithic period theory but also on the possible abrasion of the tools, even questioning the reliability of the lithic materials unearthed.</e>
<cmt>構文、用語を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyokubumasei-sekifu were first discovered in 1949 when they were unearthed at the Iwajuku Archeological Site, and this finding sparked a controversy over whether the Paleolithic Period had in fact existed, which in turn resulted in the development of the theory that pottery had not been used in the Neolithic Period and the theory of the Mesolithic Period; there was even a dispute as to whether the abrasion of the stone tools was genuine.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その後、日本では北海道を除く、関東・中部地方を中心に100箇所から650本ほどの出土がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, about 650 of them were unearthed at100 sites around Kanto and Chubu region in Japan outside of Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, about 650 of the artifacts were unearthed at 100 sites in Kanto and Chubu regions and others except Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>「北海道を除く」の表現などを変えました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, about 650 of the artifacts were unearthed at 100 sites in Kanto and Chubu regions and other areas except Hokkaido.</e>
<cmt>others →other areas</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>手斧が大部分を占め、木材加工よりも骨の粉砕や皮なめしなどに使用された可能性が高い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of them were hand axes and it is highly possible that they were used for smashing bones and tanning rather than wood processing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of them were hand axes and it is highly possible that they were used for smashing bones and tanning rather than wood processing.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of them were hand axes and it is highly possible that they were used for smashing bones and tanning rather than wood processing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>野尻湖周辺遺跡群から250点あまり出土している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 250 of them have been unearthed from the remains near lake Nojiri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 250 of them have been unearthed from the remains near Lake Nojiri.</e>
<cmt>250 →250 of them</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 250 of them have been unearthed from the remains near Lake Nojiri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本以外ではオーストリアのヴォレンドルフ遺跡出土の約2万5000年前の全面磨製石斧があるのみで、他にロシアのコスチョンキ（約1万4000年前）、アフォントヴァゴラ（約2万年前）、オーストラリアのナワモイン（約2万1500年前）、マランガンガー（約2万9000年前）からの報告がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The only example of this outside Japan is blade stone axes of 25 thousand years ago unearthed from remains of ヴォレンドルフ in Australia, and there are several other reports on this from コスチョンキ (about 14 thousand years ago) and アフォントヴァゴラ (about 20 thousand years ago) in Russia, ナワモイン (about 21 thousand 5 hundred years ago) and マランガンガー (about 29 thousand years ago) in Australia.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明「ヴォレンドルフ」「コスチョンキ」「アフォントヴァゴラ」「ナワモイン」「マランガンガー」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The only example outside Japan is the blade stone axe of 25,000 years ago unearthed from Vollendorf (ヴォレンドルフ) site in Australia, although there are some reports on the unearthed axes from Kostenki (about 14,000 years ago) and Afontova Gora (about 20,000 years ago) in Russia, ナワモイン (about 21,500 years ago) and Malanganger (about 29,000 years ago) in Australia.</e>
<cmt>「ヴォレンドルフ」→定訳不明：Vollendorf (ヴォレンドルフ)「コスチョンキ」→Kostenki 「アフォントヴァゴラ」→Afontova Gora「ナワモイン」→定訳不明：ナワモイン「マランガンガー」→Malanganger</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The only example outside Japan is the blade stone axe of 25,000 years ago unearthed from Vollendorf site in Australia, although there are some reports on the unearthed axes from Kostenki (about 14,000 years ago) and Afontova Gora (about 20,000 years ago) in Russia, Nawamoyn (about 21,500 years ago) and Malanganger (about 29,000 years ago) in Australia.</e>
<cmt>ナワモイン→Nawamoyn参照：http://www.library.uq.edu.au/ojs/index.php/qar/article/viewFile/265/309オーストラリアのヴォレンドルフのスペルが不明です（Vollendorf としています）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>コスチョンキ出土資料は製作時に磨いたのか使用痕によるものなのかをめぐって日本国内でも論争が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a dispute in Japan as well whether the materials unearthed from コスチョンキ was formed by rubbing in the process of production or trace of use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The artifacts unearthed in Kostenki arose an academic discussion also in Japan on whether the shape of the artifacts was deliberately formed by grinding in the production process or it was an abrasion as a result of use.</e>
<cmt>用語･表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The artifacts unearthed in Kostenki caused a debate in Japan as well as to whether the shape of the artifacts had been deliberately formed by grinding in a production process or it was a result of abrasion caused by use.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>アフォントヴァゴラの資料は表面採集資料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The materials of アフォントヴァゴラ is the ones collected from the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The materials from Afontova Gora are those collected from the surface of the ground.</e>
<cmt>用語を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The materials from Afontova Gora are those collected from the surface of the ground.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>オーストラリアの2例は溝部をもつ例として報告されているが、石器実測図からは研磨部分を読み取ることは難しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two examples of Australia were reported as the ones with groove portion but it is difficult to read the ground parts from the survey map of the stone tools.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the two examples of Australia were reported to have a grooved part, although it is difficult to identify the ground parts from the measurement chart of the stone tools.</e>
<cmt>実測図：measurement chartとしました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the two examples found in Australia were reported to have grooves, it is difficult to identify the ground facets from the measurement chart of the stone tools.</e>
<cmt>２つ目のalthough を削除しました。ground parts→ground facets原文に合わせて修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>とくに海外について、今後の資料の増加とデータの充実が求められる石器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">More materials and plentiful data on this stone tools, especially the ones of overseas are necessary in the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">More examples and the enhanced data of this stone tool, especially those of overseas are needed for the future studies.</e>
<cmt>用語を若干変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">More examples and the enhanced data of this stone tool, especially those of overseas are needed for the future studies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), Godaigo(id:133481), 建長(id:119884), Greenland4(id:114494), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>