<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>ぼう示</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>牓示（ぼうじ）とは、所領などの土地の四至あるいは境界のうち重要な地点に立てた掲示のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term &quot;Boji&quot; means a notice which was put up at shishi (northern, southern, eastern and western boundary) of the territory or the important positions of boundary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term &quot;Boji&quot; means a notice put up at shishi (northern, southern, eastern and western boundary) of aterritory or the important positions of a boundary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term &quot;Boji&quot; means a notice put up at shishi (northern, southern, eastern and western boundary) of a territory or the important positions of a boundary.</e>
<cmt>aとterritoryの間にスペースを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>寺社の境内の境界や一円支配が確立した荘園の排他的権利の及ぶ範囲を示す境界線として立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was put up in order to show a boundary of the precincts of temples/shrines or that of the land where shoen (manor), which accomplished ichienshihai (complete rule over the land), could exert its exclusive right.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was put up in order to show a boundary of the precincts of temples/shrines or that of the land where shoen (manor), which accomplished ichienshihai (complete rule over the land), could exert its exclusive right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was put up in order to show a boundary of the precincts of temples/shrines or that of the land where shoen (manor), which accomplished ichienshihai (complete rule over the land), could exert its exclusive right.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>牓示は自然物（岩や立木など）がその役目を果たすこともあったが、通常は木や石で作られた柱が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under normal circumstances, poles made of wood or stone were put up as boji though natural objects (rocks or trees) sometimes played a role of boji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under normal circumstances, poles made of wood or stone were put up as boji though natural objects (rocks or trees) sometimes played the role of boji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under normal circumstances, poles made of wood or stone were put up as boji though natural objects (rocks or trees) sometimes played the role of boji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>荘園の認定時に荘園領主の使者や荘官、朝廷の使者、国衙の役人が立ちあって立てられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When shoen was acknowledged, boji was put up in the presence of the envoy of the lord of shoen, the envoy of the Imperial Court and the official of kokuga (provincial government).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a shoen was acknowledged, boji was put up in the presence of the envoy of the lord of a shoen, an envoy of the Imperial Court and an official from the kokuga (provincial government).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a shoen was acknowledged, boji was put up in the presence of the envoy of the lord of a shoen, an envoy of the Imperial Court and an official from the kokuga (provincial government).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>牓示は境界を明確にして境相論を防止する意味があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Boji was put up in order to clarify a boundary so that a boundary dispute could be prevented.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Boji was put up in order to clarify a boundary so that a boundary dispute could be prevented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Boji was put up in order to clarify a boundary so that a boundary dispute could be prevented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、国司の交替による方針変更や境相論の相手側の工作によって引き抜かれる場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was sometimes pulled out due to the policy change arising from the change of kokushi (provincial governor) or backroom maneuver by the counterparty of boundary dispute.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it was sometimes pulled out due to the policy change arising from the change of kokushi (provincial governor) or a backroom maneuver by a counterparty of boundary dispute.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it was sometimes pulled out due to the policy change arising from the change of kokushi (provincial governor) or a backroom maneuver by a counterparty of boundary dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>中世において朝廷の権威が物理的な強制力を持つものではなかったために牓示の権威が絶対性を持つものではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the authority of the Imperial Court was not backed by coercive power in the medieval times, the authority of boji was not absolute.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the authority of the Imperial Court was not backed by coercive power during medieval times, the authority of boji was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the authority of the Imperial Court was not backed by coercive power during medieval times, the authority of boji was not absolute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そのため、荘園領主・荘官などは荘園図などを作成して合わせて証拠とする必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the lord or administrator of shoen was required to prepare a manorial map and use it as an evidence together with boji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the lord or administrator of shoen was required to prepare a manorial map and use it as evidence along with boji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the lord or administrator of shoen was required to prepare a manorial map and use it as evidence along with boji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mugu-shisai(id:190501), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>