<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>山国隊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamagunitai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamagunitai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamagunitai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>山国隊（やまぐにたい）は、幕末期に丹波国桑田郡山国郷（現京都市右京区京北町）で結成された農兵隊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamagunitai (the Yamaguni Corps or Troop) was an armed force of farmers that was formed during the Bakumatsu period (a fifteen-year period, from 1853-1868, that saw the demise of the Tokugawa bakufu) in the hamlet of Yamaguni in Kuwata county of Tanba province (the modern-day town of Keihoku, Ukyo ward in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamagunitai (the Yamaguni Corps or Troop) was an armed force of farmers that was formed during the Bakumatsu period (a fifteen-year period, from 1853-1868, that saw the demise of the Tokugawa bakufu) in the hamlet of Yamaguni in Kuwata county of Tanba province (the modern-day town of Keihoku, Ukyo ward in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamagunitai (the Yamaguni Corps or Troop) was an armed force of farmers that was formed during the Bakumatsu period (a fifteen-year period, from 1853-1868, that saw the demise of the Tokugawa bakufu) in the hamlet of Yamaguni in Kuwata county of Tanba Province (the modern-day Keihoku-cho, Ukyo Ward, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>スペル住所表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>因幡鳥取藩に付属し官軍に加わって戊辰戦争を戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were associated with Inaba and Tottori domains, and fought as part of the loyalist forces in the Boshin war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were associated with Inaba and Tottori domains, and fought as part of the loyalist forces in the Boshin war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were associated with Inaba and Tottori domains, and fought as part of the loyalist forces in the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>京都時代祭行列で維新勤王隊列の鼓笛隊としても知られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are also known for their role as flute- and drum-players as part of the imperial loyalist troop in the procession of the Kyoto Jidai Matsuri (the Festival of the Ages in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are also known for their role as flute- and drum-players as part of the imperial loyalist troop in the procession of the Kyoto Jidai Matsuri (the Festival of the Ages in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are also known for their role as flute- and drum-players as part of the imperial loyalist troop in the procession of the Kyoto Jidai Matsuri (the Festival of the Ages in Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>山国隊はフランス式教練を受け、銃の射撃精度は山村の猟で慣らしていたため非常に優れていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamagunitai had received training in French-style military drilling, and were extremely skilled at marksmanship with guns thanks to their long familiarity from hunting excursions in their mountain villages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamagunitai had received training in French-style military drilling, and were extremely skilled at marksmanship with guns thanks to their long familiarity from hunting excursions in their mountain villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamagunitai had received training in French-style military drilling, and were extremely skilled at marksmanship with guns thanks to their long familiarity from hunting excursions in their mountain villages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また関東を行軍中、彼らの熊毛の陣笠姿を見て河童隊と呼んだ人がいたというエピソードがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, while marching to the Kanto, the distinctive appearance of their bearskin military caps led some to begin calling them the Kappa Corps (kappa were mythical water goblins with distinctive heads).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, while marching to the Kanto, the distinctive appearance of their bearskin military caps led some to begin calling them the Kappa Corps (kappa were mythical water goblins with distinctive heads).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, while marching to the Kanto, the distinctive appearance of their bearskin military caps led some to begin calling them the Kappa Corps (kappa were mythical water goblins with distinctive heads).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>沿革</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of the corps</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of the corps</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of the corps</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>結成</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their formation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their formation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>平安京造都の木材を供給した伝承をもつ山国郷は古くより皇室との関係が深く、山国一円は太閤検地まで禁裏直轄の荘園であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamaguni hamlet, which local legend has it supplied the timber to construct Heian Kyo (ancient Kyoto), had from ancient times possessed deep ties to the imperial house, and the whole area of Yamaguni was actually a shoen (private estate) under the direct control of the imperial house up until the time of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s nationwide land survey in 1582.</e>
<cmt>Giving the fact of the land survey without supplying the date is not helpful to those unfamiliar with Japanese history, so I&apos;ve supplied the date as well.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamaguni hamlet, which local legend has it supplied the timber to construct Heian Kyo (ancient Kyoto), had from ancient times possessed deep ties to the imperial house, and the whole area of Yamaguni was actually a shoen (private estate) under the direct control of the imperial house up until the time of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s nationwide land survey in 1582.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamaguni hamlet, which local legend has it supplied the timber to construct Heian Kyo (ancient Kyoto), had from ancient times possessed deep ties to the imperial house, and the whole area of Yamaguni was in fact a shoen (private estate) under the direct control of the imperial house up until the time of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s nationwide land survey.</e>
<cmt>原文に忠実にするため、年号を削除しました。&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし幕末には禁裏御料は郷内の半分ほどで、村々の所領関係が異なることは、山国の諸村が一体となり山国神社の宮座を堅持していく上で問題も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But by the Bakumatsu period (1853-1868), the remaining territory controlled by the imperial house was about half of the interior of the region, and territorial relations among the villages had changed; the various villages in Yamaguni had joined together as organized parishioners of the same local shrine, the Yamaguni Jinja, and the new balance of power led to many conflicts over land control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But by the Bakumatsu period (1853-1868), the remaining territory controlled by the imperial house was about half of the interior of the region, and territorial relations among the villages had changed; the various villages in Yamaguni had joined together as organized parishioners of the same local shrine, the Yamaguni Jinja, and the new balance of power led to many conflicts over land control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But by the Bakumatsu period (1853-1868), the remaining territory controlled by the imperial house was about half of the interior of the region, and territorial relations among the villages had changed; the various villages in Yamaguni had joined together as organized parishioners of the same local shrine, the Yamaguni-jinja Shrine, and the new balance of power led to many conflicts over land control.</e>
<cmt>神社表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>そこで名主仲間（宮座仲間）は、かつての荘園「山国庄」の時代と同様に天皇から正式に官位を授かることなどで地域の一円禁裏御料化を目指し、宮座の結束強化をはかっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this point the council of village headmen (who were also comrades from the shrine organization) began to set their sights on the entire region remaining under the control of the imperial house, arguing that, much like during the days the area was a shoen, &quot;Yamaguni estate,&quot; they had received an official position and rank from the emperor and should have control over the whole area, thereby aiming to fortify the unity of the shrine organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this point the council of village headmen (who were also comrades from the shrine organization) began to set their sights on the entire region remaining under the control of the imperial house, arguing that, much like during the days the area was a shoen, &quot;Yamaguni estate,&quot; they had received an official position and rank from the emperor and should have control over the whole area, thereby aiming to fortify the unity of the shrine organization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this point the council of village headmen (who were also comrades from the shrine organization) began to set their sights on the entire region remaining under the control of the imperial house, arguing that, much like during the days the area was a shoen, &apos;Yamaguni estate,&apos; they had received an official position and rank from the emperor and should have control over the whole area, thereby aiming to fortify the unity of the shrine organization.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>このような状況のなか、慶応4年(1868年)1月3日に鳥羽・伏見の戦いが始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in the midst of these developments, on January 3, 1868, that countrywide tensions broke out into open conflict in the battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>I added &quot;countrywide tensions&quot; because to the non-specialist it would be hard to understand why fighting began at this point, or who was doing the fighting, for that matter.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in the midst of these developments, on January 3, 1868, that countrywide tensions broke out into open conflict in the battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in the midst of these developments, on January 27, 1868, that countrywide tensions broke out into open conflict in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>間もなく山陰道鎮撫総督西園寺公望から丹波に王政復古(日本)の募兵があり、前年末頃から御所警備などの勤王奉仕策を練っていた山国では、平安時代以来の皇室との関係と郷中復古（禁裏御料回復）の願いから、直ちにこれに応じて自弁による農兵隊が結成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soon after, imperial loyalist (anti-bakufu) troops recruited by Kinmochi SAIONJI, the general placed in charge of pacifying the Sanindo highway and the surrounding area, appeared in Tanba province, and in Yamaguni, whose inhabitants had been training to serve the imperial cause, for example by standing guard at the imperial palace in Kyoto, since the end of the previous year (1867), they were also hoping for a restoration of their own hamlet along with a resumption of the ties with the imperial house they had held since the Heian period, desires which quickly prompted them to form, at their own expense, a fighting force of farmers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after, imperial loyalist (anti-bakufu) troops recruited by Kinmochi SAIONJI, the general placed in charge of pacifying the Sanindo highway and the surrounding area, appeared in Tanba province, and in Yamaguni, whose inhabitants had been training to serve the imperial cause, for example by standing guard at the imperial palace in Kyoto, since the end of the previous year (1867), they were also hoping for a restoration of their own hamlet along with a resumption of the ties with the imperial house they had held since the Heian period, desires which quickly prompted them to form, at their own expense, a fighting force of farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after, imperial loyalist (anti-bakufu) troops recruited by Kinmochi SAIONJI, the general placed in charge of pacifying the Sanindo highway and the surrounding area, appeared in Tanba Province, and in Yamaguni, whose inhabitants had been training to serve the imperial cause, for example by standing guard at the imperial palace in Kyoto, since the end of the previous year (1867), they were also hoping for a restoration of their own hamlet along with a resumption of the ties with the imperial house they had held since the Heian period, desires which quickly prompted them to form, at their own expense, a fighting force of farmers.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>農兵隊には荘園時代の古例により四沙汰人を置き、第一陣「西軍」・第二陣「東軍」の2軍が目的別に編成され、両軍が慶応4年1月11日山国神社に集結し出陣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This peasant army had four commanding officers, in accordance with the ancient precedent from back in the days where the region was a shoen (private estate), and was split into two companies, the Western and Eastern Companies, which were composed with different goals in mind; both companies assembled and were formed on January 11, 1868 at Yamaguni shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This peasant army had four commanding officers, in accordance with the ancient precedent from back in the days where the region was a shoen (private estate), and was split into two companies, the Western and Eastern Companies, which were composed with different goals in mind; both companies assembled and were formed on January 11, 1868 at Yamaguni shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This peasant army had four commanding officers, in accordance with the ancient precedent from back in the days where the region was a shoen (private estate), and was split into two companies, the Western and Eastern Companies, which were composed with different goals in mind; both companies assembled and were formed on February 4, 1868 at Yamaguni Shrine.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="12">
<j>西軍 （隊士64人客士12人、沙汰人：水口備前守・藤野近江守）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Western Company (with 64 regular soldiers and 12 auxiliaries, commanded by Mr. MIZOGUCHI, the governor of Bizen province, Mr. FUJINO, the governor of Omi province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Western Company (with 64 regular soldiers and 12 auxiliaries, commanded by Mr. MIZOGUCHI, the governor of Bizen province, Mr. FUJINO, the governor of Omi province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Western Company (with 64 regular soldiers and 12 auxiliaries, commanded by Mr. Mizoguchi, the governor of Bizen Province, Mr. Fujino, the governor of Omi Province.</e>
<cmt>人名表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>山陰道の西園寺との合流を目指したが、道中でこの方面が既に平定されていたことが判明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Western Company intended to join forces with Saionji on the Sanindo highway, but along the way they decided that Saionji had already effectively suppressed the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Western Company intended to join forces with Saionji on the Sanindo highway, but along the way they decided that Saionji had already effectively suppressed the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Western Company intended to join forces with Saionji on the Sanindo highway, but along the way they decided that Saionji had already effectively suppressed the area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし鳥取藩の伊王野治郎左衛門（後の久美浜県知事）の仲介もあって、岩倉具視から鳥取藩に付属し「山国隊」と称するようにとの指示を受けることができ、山国隊が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Jirozaemon IONO of Tottori domain (who later became prefectural governor of Kumihama Pref.) intervened in their support as well, and Tonomi IWAKUNI officially linked them to Tottori domain and gave them instructions to begin calling themselves the &quot;Yamagunitai&quot; (Yamaguni army); with this, the Yamagunitai was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Jirozaemon IONO of Tottori domain (who later became prefectural governor of Kumihama Pref.) intervened in their support as well, and Tonomi IWAKUNI officially linked them to Tottori domain and gave them instructions to begin calling themselves the &quot;Yamagunitai&quot; (Yamaguni army); with this, the Yamagunitai was born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Jirozaemon IONO of Tottori Domain (who later became prefectural governor of Kumihama Prefecture) intervened in their support as well, and Tonomi IWAKURA officially linked them to Tottori Domain and gave them instructions to begin calling themselves the &apos;Yamagunitai&apos; (Yamaguni army); with this, the Yamagunitai was born.</e>
<cmt>スペル人名スペル&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>東軍 （隊士27人、沙汰人：鳥居河内守・河原林大和守）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eastern Company (27 regular soldiers commanded by Mr. TORII, governor of Kawachi province, and Mr. KAWARABAYASHI, governor of Yamato province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eastern Company (27 regular soldiers commanded by Mr. TORII, governor of Kawachi province, and Mr. KAWARABAYASHI, governor of Yamato province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eastern Company (27 regular soldiers commanded by Mr. Torii, governor of Kawachi Province, and Mr. Kawarabayashi, governor of Yamato Province).</e>
<cmt>人名表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>大坂の征討大将軍仁和寺宮の陣に合流を目指したが上手くいかず、更に「親兵組」と称し御親兵として御所警衛にあたることに拘ったが最後まで不調のまま終った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Eastern Company aimed to join forces with the army of Prince Niwajinomiya, the Seito Taishogun (the supreme commander temporarily appointed to destroy the shogunate), at Osaka, but their attempts to do so did not succeed; moreover, they acquired the nickname the &quot;Shinpeigumi&quot; (Company of Imperial Soldiers) and tried to attain the role of guarding the palace as imperial guardsmen, but the fighting ended before they ever organized themselves into an effective unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Eastern Company aimed to join forces with the army of Prince Niwajinomiya, the Seito Taishogun (the supreme commander temporarily appointed to destroy the shogunate), at Osaka, but their attempts to do so did not succeed; moreover, they acquired the nickname the &quot;Shinpeigumi&quot; (Company of Imperial Soldiers) and tried to attain the role of guarding the palace as imperial guardsmen, but the fighting ended before they ever organized themselves into an effective unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Eastern Company aimed to join forces with the army of Prince Ninnajinomiya, the Seito Taishogun (the supreme commander temporarily appointed to destroy the shogunate), at Osaka, but their attempts to do so did not succeed; moreover, they acquired the nickname the &apos;Shinpeigumi&apos; (Company of Imperial Soldiers) and tried to attain the role of guarding the palace as imperial guardsmen, but the fighting ended before they ever organized themselves into an effective unit.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;人名スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>京都出陣と東征</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army&apos;s departs Kyoto for the east</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army&apos;s departs Kyoto for the east</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army&apos;s departs Kyoto for the east</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>東征大総督有栖川宮熾仁親王の京都出陣に伴い、山国隊に1小隊東征の指令が下った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Following imperial prince Taruhito ARISUGAWA, who was Tosei Daisotoku (Great Leader Who Journeys East), who led his army out of Kyoto, one small company from the Yamagunitai received orders to accompany the prince eastwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Following imperial prince Taruhito ARISUGAWA, who was Tosei Daisotoku (Great Leader Who Journeys East), who led his army out of Kyoto, one small company from the Yamagunitai received orders to accompany the prince eastwards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following Imperial Prince Taruhito ARISUGAWA, who was Tosei Daisotoku (great leader who journeys east), who led his army out of Kyoto, one small company from the Yamagunitai received orders to accompany the prince eastwards.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>慶応4年2月13日、山国隊の1個小隊（隊士28人客士2人）が東山道軍の鳥取藩部隊に加わり、「十三番隊」として京都を出発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 13, 1868, this small company of the Yamagunitai (comprised of 28 regulars and 2 auxiliaries) added their own force to the Tottori domain regiment of the Tosando (highway) army, becoming the &quot;Thirteenth Company,&quot; and departed Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 13, 1868, this small company of the Yamagunitai (comprised of 28 regulars and 2 auxiliaries) added their own force to the Tottori domain regiment of the Tosando (highway) army, becoming the &quot;Thirteenth Company,&quot; and departed Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 6, 1868, this small company of the Yamagunitai (comprised of 28 regulars and 2 auxiliaries) added their own force to the Tottori domain regiment of the Tosando (highway) army, becoming the &apos;Thirteenth Company,&apos; and departed Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>残りの隊士は京都で御所警備などにあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remaining soldiers stayed behind in Kyoto, performing guard duty for the palace and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The remaining soldiers stayed behind in Kyoto, performing guard duty for the palace and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The remaining soldiers stayed behind in Kyoto, performing guard duty for the palace and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="20">
<j>（東征の詳細は年表を参照。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(For more on the journey east, consult the chronology below.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For more on the journey east, consult the chronology below.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For more on the journey east, consult the chronology below.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>山国凱旋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their triumphal return to Yamaguni</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their triumphant return to Yamaguni</e>
<cmt>Edited for spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their triumphant return to Yamaguni</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>明治2年2月18日、山国隊は大勢の見物人・出迎えのなか、鼓笛を奏して京都から山国への凱旋を果たし山国神社を参拝した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 18 of 1869 (the second year of the Meiji era), the Yamagunitai was met by a tremendous crowd of onlookers as they marched, playing flutes and drums, from Kyoto to Yamaguni in a triumphal return, paying homage at Yamaguni Jinja (shrine).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 18 of 1869 (the second year of the Meiji era), the Yamagunitai was met by a tremendous crowd of onlookers as they marched, playing flutes and drums, from Kyoto to Yamaguni in a triumphant return, paying homage at Yamaguni Jinja (shrine).</e>
<cmt>Edited for spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 30, 1869, the Yamagunitai was met by a tremendous crowd of onlookers as they marched, playing flutes and drums, from Kyoto to Yamaguni in a triumphant return, paying homage at Yamaguni-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に旧暦削除神社表記</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>2月25日には死者の慰霊祭を行ない、辻村に招魂場（今の山国護国神社）を設けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 25 a memorial service was held for those soldiers who had died in battle, and founded a shrine, Shokonjo (today&apos;s Yamaguni gokoku jinja), in Tsuji village.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 25 a memorial service was held for those soldiers who had died in battle, and founded a shrine, Shokonjo (today&apos;s Yamaguni gokoku jinja), in Tsuji village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 6, a memorial service was held for those soldiers who had died in battle, and founded a shrine, Shokonjo (today&apos;s Yamaguni gokoku-jinja Shrine), in Tsuji village.</e>
<cmt>神社表記グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="23">
<j>最終的に山国隊はその活躍とともに、戦死4人（行方不明1人含）、病死3人という多大な犠牲を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, the Yamagunitai suffered four war dead (including one who was never located afterwards) and three deaths to illness during the course of their activities, a steep sacrifice considering their total numbers.</e>
<cmt>I felt compelled to qualify the term &quot;gisei&quot; with some explanation; this sort of phrase is very offputting in English without some sort of justification.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the Yamagunitai suffered four war dead (including one who was never located afterwards) and three deaths to illness during the course of their activities, a steep sacrifice considering their total numbers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the Yamagunitai suffered four war dead (including one who was never located afterwards) and three deaths to illness during the course of their activities, a steep sacrifice considering their total numbers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また新兵組とともに軍費自弁のためにできた膨大な借金は名主仲間共有の山林を売り払うなどして賄われ、肝心の宮座は維新後間もなく消滅してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But much like the Shinpeigumi, they were left with enormous debts because they were shouldering the financial burden of their wartime activities themselves, so although the council of village headsmen managed to cover their expenses by selling the lumber and other things they owned jointly as villages, this led to the shrine organization--the heart and soul of the troop--quickly ceasing to exist soon after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But much like the Shinpeigumi, they were left with enormous debts because they were shouldering the financial burden of their wartime activities themselves, so although the council of village headsmen managed to cover their expenses by selling the lumber and other things they owned jointly as villages, this led to the shrine organization--the heart and soul of the troop--quickly ceasing to exist soon after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But much like the Shinpeigumi, they were left with enormous debts because they were shouldering the financial burden of their wartime activities themselves, so although the council of village headsmen managed to cover their expenses by selling the lumber and other things they owned jointly as villages, this led to the shrine organization--the heart and soul of the troop--quickly ceasing to exist soon after the Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>しかしこれ以来山国隊は郷土の誇りとされ、山国神社の還幸祭と京都時代祭では山国隊姿の行進を見ることができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But thereafter, the Yamagunitai became a source of local pride, which is why figures representing the Yamagunitai can still be seen in the processions for the Yamaguni shrine Kankosai (festival of re-enshrinement) and in the Kyoto Jidais Matsuri (Kyoto&apos;s Festival of the Ages).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But thereafter, the Yamagunitai became a source of local pride, which is why figures representing the Yamagunitai can still be seen in the processions for the Yamaguni shrine Kankosai (festival of re-enshrinement) and in the Kyoto Jidais Matsuri (Kyoto&apos;s Festival of the Ages).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But thereafter, the Yamagunitai became a source of local pride, which is why figures representing the Yamagunitai can still be seen in the processions for the Yamaguni Shrine Kankosai (festival of re-enshrinement) and in the Kyoto Jidai Matsuri (Kyoto&apos;s Festival of the Ages).</e>
<cmt>神社表記スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronology</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="26">
<j>慶応4年（明治元年）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1868 (the first year of the Meiji era)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1868 (the first year of the Meiji era)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1868 (the first year of the Meiji era)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>1月18日　岩倉具視の指示で山国隊が誕生。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">January 18: acting under the instructions of Tomomi IWAKURA, the Yamagunitai is formed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">January 18: acting under the instructions of Tomomi IWAKURA, the Yamagunitai is formed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">February 11: acting under the instructions of Tomomi IWAKURA, the Yamagunitai is formed.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="28">
<j>2月13日　山国隊1個小隊が京都を出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 13: one small company from the Yamagunitai joins the army marching east from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 13: one small company from the Yamagunitai joins the army marching east from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 6: one small company from the Yamagunitai joins the army marching east from Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>2月15日　補充6人が合流。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 15: they are joined by six new recruits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 15: they are joined by six new recruits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 8: they are joined by six new recruits.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>隊士34人となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This brings the total strength of the force to 34.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This brings the total strength of the force to 34.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This brings the total strength of the force to 34.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>2月20日　美濃大垣で戦場に臨む決意を示す血判書を作成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">February 20: after witnessing the battlefield at Ogaki in Mino province, the troop members sign a pledge of perseverence in blood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">February 20: after witnessing the battlefield at Ogaki in Mino province, the troop members sign a pledge of perseverence in blood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 13: after witnessing the battlefield at Ogaki in Mino Province, the troop members sign a pledge of perseverance in blood.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>3月3日　鳥取藩内参謀の河田左久馬が山国隊隊長を兼務。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 3: Sakuma KAWATA, of the general administrative staff of Tottori domain, takes over the leadership of the Yamagunitai in addition to his other duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 3: Sakuma KAWATA, of the general administrative staff of Tottori domain, takes over the leadership of the Yamagunitai in addition to his other duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 26: Sakuma KAWATA, of the general administrative staff of Tottori Domain, takes over the leadership of the Yamagunitai in addition to his other duties.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="33">
<j>3月6日　甲州勝沼の戦いに加戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 6: the troop takes part in the battle of Katsunuma in Kai province (Yamanashi Pref. today).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 6: the troop takes part in the battle of Katsunuma in Kai province (Yamanashi Pref. today).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March 29: the troop takes part in the battle of Katsunuma in Kai Province (Yamanashi Pref. today).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="34">
<j>3月9日　ゲベール銃に換えてミニエー銃を付与される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 9: the troop&apos;s outdated Gewehr guns are replaced by the newer Minié rifles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 9: the troop&apos;s outdated Gewehr guns are replaced by the newer Minié rifles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 1: the troop&apos;s outdated Gewehr guns are replaced by the newer Minié rifles.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="35">
<j>3月19日　江戸入り。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 19: the troop enters Edo (modern-day Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 19: the troop enters Edo (modern-day Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 11: the troop enters Edo (modern-day Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="36">
<j>3月24日　隊士に「魁」(さきがけ)の文字を冠した熊毛の陣笠配布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March 24: new bearskin caps with the character &quot;sakigake&quot; (&quot;leading the charge&quot;) emblazoned on them are distributed to the troop&apos;s soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March 24: new bearskin caps with the character &quot;sakigake&quot; (&quot;leading the charge&quot;) emblazoned on them are distributed to the troop&apos;s soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 16: new bearskin caps with the character &apos;sakigake&apos; (leading the charge) emblazoned on them are distributed to the troop&apos;s soldiers.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="37">
<j>4月22日　野州安塚の戦いで激戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 22: they are caught in fierce fighting during the battle of Yasuzuka in Shimotsuke province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 22: they are caught in fierce fighting during the battle of Yasuzuka in Shimotsuke province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 14: they are caught in fierce fighting during the battle of Yasuzuka in Shimotsuke Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>戦死2人 負傷5人 行方不明1人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Two of their number are killed in battle, while five are wounded and one vanishes without a trace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Two of their number are killed in battle, while five are wounded and one vanishes without a trace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Two of their number are killed in battle, while five are wounded and one vanishes without a trace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>閏4月25日　江戸に凱旋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The intercalary 25th day of April: they make a triumphal return to Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The intercalary 25th day of April: they make a triumphal return to Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 17: they make a triumphal return to Edo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>錦の御旗の警衛を任される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are entrusted with the honor of guarding the brocaded Imperial standard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are entrusted with the honor of guarding the brocaded Imperial standard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are entrusted with the honor of guarding the brocaded Imperial standard.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>5月15日　上野戦争で彰義隊と交戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 15: the troop clashes with the Shogitai (a pro-bakufu force) during the battle of Ueno.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 15: the troop clashes with the Shogitai (a pro-bakufu force) during the battle of Ueno.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 4: the troop clashes with the Shogitai (a pro-bakufu force) during the Battle of Ueno.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>戦死1人 負傷4人</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One soldier is killed and four wounded in the fighting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One soldier is killed and four wounded in the fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One soldier is killed and four wounded in the fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="43">
<j>6月28日　隊士9人が隊長と奥州へ向け江戸を出陣。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 28: nine of the troop&apos;s regulars accompany the troop commander as he departs from Edo for the front in Mutsu province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 28: nine of the troop&apos;s regulars accompany the troop commander as he departs from Edo for the front in Mutsu province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 16: nine of the troop&apos;s regulars accompany the troop commander as he departs from Edo for the front in Mutsu province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="44">
<j>7月3日　常陸平潟に上陸。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 3: this force lands in Hirakata in Hitachi province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 3: this force lands in Hirakata in Hitachi province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 20: this force lands in Hirakata in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="45">
<j>8月7日　相馬中村城に入城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 7: they occupy Soma-nakamura castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 7: they occupy Soma-nakamura castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 22: they occupy Soma-nakamura-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に城表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="46">
<j>9月12日　隊士3人が隊長と残り、6人は東京（江戸）に帰営。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 12: three of the troop&apos;s soldiers remain behind with the commander, while six return to duty in the newly renamed Tokyo (formerly Edo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 12: three of the troop&apos;s soldiers remain behind with the commander, while six return to duty in the newly renamed Tokyo (formerly Edo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">October 27: three of the troop&apos;s soldiers remain behind with the commander, while six return to duty in the newly renamed Tokyo (formerly Edo).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="47">
<j>9月21日　亘理城に入城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 21: their force occupies Watari castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 21: their force occupies Watari castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 5: their force occupies Watari-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に城表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="48">
<j>10月1日　仙台城に入城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 1: they occupy Sendai castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 1: they occupy Sendai castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">November 14: they occupy Sendai-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に城表記</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="49">
<j>10月21日　隊士3人が隊長と東京に帰営。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">October 21: the three soldiers and the commander return to military duty in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">October 21: the three soldiers and the commander return to military duty in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 4: the three soldiers and the commander return to military duty in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="50">
<j>11月5日　有栖川宮の凱旋に随伴して東京出発。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 5: as participants in Prince Arisugawanomiya&apos;s planned triumphal entry (into Kyoto), they depart from Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 5: as participants in Prince Arisugawanomiya&apos;s planned triumphal entry (into Kyoto), they depart from Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">December 18: as participants in Prince Arisugawanomiya&apos;s planned triumphal entry (into Kyoto), they depart from Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>（錦旗警衛）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Their function during the procession was to guard the gold-brocaded imperial flag.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Their function during the procession was to guard the gold-brocaded imperial flag.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Their function during the procession was to guard the gold-brocaded imperial flag.)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="52">
<j>11月25日　有栖川宮とともに京都凱旋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">November 25: they, together with Prince Arisugawannomiya, have a triumphal entry into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">November 25: they, together with Prince Arisugawannomiya, have a triumphal entry into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">January 7, 1869: they, together with Prince Arisugawanomiya, have a triumphal entry into Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリ暦にスペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>帰洛。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They return to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>（錦旗警衛）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Their function during this procession was to guard the gold-brocaded imperial flag.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Their function during this procession was to guard the gold-brocaded imperial flag.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Their function during this procession was to guard the gold-brocaded imperial flag.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), 玄史生(id:43670), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>