<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>質取行為</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shichitorikoi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichitorikoi (Action of demanding compensation)</e>
<cmt>（）で英語での説明を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichitorikoi (Action of demanding compensation)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>質取行為（しちとりこうい）とは、中世日本において、別の地域に住む債務者から弁済を受けられなかった債権者が、債務者と同一の地域に住む第三者（債務者との面識の有無は問わず）の身柄あるいは財物を債務の賠償として私的に差し押さえる行為。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Middle Ages in Japan Shichitorikoi was an action of a creditor, who could not receive compensation from a debtor living in a different region, arresting a third person who lived in the same region as the creditor (whether the person is acquainted with the debtor or not) and privately confiscating his/her properties as compensation for the debt.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the medieval Japan, Shichitorikoi was an action of a creditor, who could not receive compensation from a debtor living in a different region, to capture a third person who lived in the same region as the creditor (regardless of whether the person is acquainted with the debtor or not) or to privately confiscate the person&apos;s properties as compensation for the debt.</e>
<cmt>文法を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the medieval Japan, Shichitorikoi was an action of a creditor, who could not receive compensation from a debtor living in a different region, to capture a third person who lived in the same region as the creditor (regardless of whether the person is acquainted with the debtor or not) or to privately confiscate the person&apos;s properties as compensation for the debt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>また訴訟の当事者が係争相手と同一の地域に住む第三者に対して行われる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes the accuser (creditor) sued a third person who lived in the same region as the accused (debtor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes the accuser (creditor) sued a third person who lived in the same region as the accused (debtor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes the accuser (creditor) sued a third person who lived in the same region as the accused (debtor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>この場合、対象とした「地域」によって呼び方が異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this case, different terms were used depending on where it took place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this case, Shichitorikoi was called differently depending on the subject &apos;area&apos;.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this case, Shichitorikoi was called differently depending on the subject &apos;area&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>同一の令制国居住者を対象とする質取行為→国質（くにじち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of shichitori targeting a resident living in the same ryoseikoku (province) =&gt; kunijichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same ryoseikoku (province) =&gt; kunijichi</e>
<cmt>The act of shichitori→Shichitorikoiに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same ryoseikoku (province) =&gt; kunijichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>同一の荘園居住者を対象とする質取行為→荘質（しょうじち・庄質）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of shichitori targeting a resident living in the same shoen (private estate) =&gt; shojichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same shoen (private estate) =&gt; shojichi</e>
<cmt>The act of shichitori→Shichitorikoiに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same shoen (private estate) =&gt; shojichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>同一の郷居住者を対象とする質取行為→郷質（ごうじち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of shichitori targeting a resident living in the same village =&gt; gojichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same go (an administrative unit of provincial land) =&gt; gojichi</e>
<cmt>The act of shichitori→Shichitorikoiに変更しました。郷をvillageと訳すと後列の訳と同じになってしまうため、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same go (an administrative unit of provincial land) =&gt; gojichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>同一の村居住者を対象とする質取行為→村質（むらじち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of shichitori targeting a resident living in the same village =&gt; murajichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same village =&gt; murajichi</e>
<cmt>The act of shichitori→Shichitorikoiに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same village =&gt; murajichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同一の所（都市・町・所領・座）居住者を対象とする質取行為→所質（ところじち）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act of shichitori targeting a resident living in the same place (city/town/shoryo [territory]/za [trade guild]) =&gt; tokorojichi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same place (city/town/shoryo [territory]/za [trade guild]) =&gt; tokorojichi</e>
<cmt>The act of shichitori→Shichitorikoiに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shichitorikoi targeting a resident living in the same place (city/town/shoryo [territory]/za [trade guild]) =&gt; tokorojichi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>これらの行為は対象とする地域の範疇を異にするだけで内容的にはほぼ同一の行為である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These acts were different only in the regional category, but almost the same in their contents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These acts only differed in the regional categories, and the contents were almost the same.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These acts only differed in the regional categories, and the contents were almost the same.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>これは氏族社会における血縁関係者に課された集団責任・連帯責任が、氏族社会の崩壊と地縁による社会形成に伴って転換されて慣習法化されたものであると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is said to have been due to group responsibility/collective responsibility imposed on people with blood relationship in a clan society that changed into a common law accompanied by the collapse of a clan society and social shaping by territorial connections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This has been said to be the group responsibility/collective responsibility imposed on people in a blood relationship in a clan society, that changed into a common law, following the collapse of a clan society and social shaping by territorial connections.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This has been said to be the group responsibility/collective responsibility imposed on people in a blood relationship in a clan society, that changed into a common law, following the collapse of a clan society and social shaping by territorial connections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これは当時の人々が人間は居住する地域によって生かされて生涯を送るという認識を持っていたことと関係しているとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that this was related to the cognition of people then that they would spend their lifetime, supported by their residence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that this was related to the cognition of people then that they would spend their whole lifetime where they lived with the supports from their place of residence.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that this was related to the cognition of people then that they would spend their whole lifetime where they lived with the supports from their place of residence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>特に守護領国制や郷村制の形成が進んだ南北朝時代_(日本)以後によく見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was often seen in and after the Nanbokucho (Northern and Southern Dynasties) period (Japan) with the advanced formation of the Shugo-ryogoku system and the goson-sei (system of coalitions of villages).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was often seen in and after the period of the Northern and Southern Courts when the formation of the Shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a Shugo dominates a manor) and the goson-sei (system of coalitions of villages) advanced.</e>
<cmt>南北朝時代を用語統一リストに従い訂正しました。守護領国制の英文の説明を加えました。以下文章も原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was often seen in and after the period of the Northern and Southern Courts when the formation of the Shugo-ryogoku system (the system that a Shugo dominates a manor) and the goson-sei (system of coalitions of villages) advanced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>また、郷村制が発達した東国では郷質が、郷村制が発達せず商業・交通が盛んであった西国では所質が多かったと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that gojichi was more frequent in the Togoku (eastern Japan) where goson-sei was developed, while tokorojichi was more frequent in the Saigoku (western Japan) where business/transportation developed instead the goson-sei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that gojichi was more frequent in the Togoku (eastern Japan) where goson-sei was developed, while tokorojichi was more frequent in the Saigoku (western Japan) where business/transportation developed rather than the goson-sei.</e>
<cmt>instead→rather thanに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that gojichi was more frequent in the Togoku (eastern Japan) where goson-sei was developed, while tokorojichi was more frequent in the Saigoku (western Japan) where business/transportation developed rather than the goson-sei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>なお、問題の行為が殺人であったりした場合には仇討・復讐の一環として下手人の代わりに質取対象者の生命を差し押さえて没収する行為も「質取行為」として正当なものとされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even in the case of murder, as part adauchi (revenge including killing)/fukushu (revenge) the act of shichitori of arresting or killing a person for shichitori, instead of a murderer, was justified.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even in the case of murder, seizing and taking a debtor&apos;s life instead of a murderer&apos;s as a part of adauchi (revenge including killing)/fukushu (revenge) was justified as a way of Shichitorikoi.</e>
<cmt>Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even in the case of murder, seizing and taking a debtor&apos;s life instead of a murderer&apos;s as a part of adauchi (revenge including killing)/fukushu (revenge) was justified as a way of Shichitorikoi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="15">
<j>室町幕府や戦国大名なども市場や道路などのいわゆる「アジール」的な場所での質取行為は禁止したものの、前述の地縁に関する認識の存在と慣習法としての一般認識の存在、他に債務者に対して債務返済への心理的圧力としてある程度までは有効性があったことから、規制は行われても禁止にまで踏み切った法は存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu and warring lords banned shichitori acts in so-called sanctuary-like places such as markets and streets, which had some effectiveness to restrict the existence of the above-mentioned cognition of territorial connection, the existence of general cognition as a common law and to give some mental pressure to the creditor asking the debtor to pay the debt, however, there was no law to ban the acts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) banned Shichitorikoi in so-called sanctuary-like places such as markets and streets, there were only restrictions and was no law to ban the actions because Shichitorikoi was effective as the existence of the above-mentioned cognition of the group responsibility in a local community and the general cognition as a common law and mental pressure on the debtor to pay for his or her debt.</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストに沿うよう単語を修正しました。原文に沿うよう修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period) banned Shichitorikoi in so-called sanctuary-like places such as markets and streets, there were only restrictions and was no law to ban the actions because Shichitorikoi was effective as the existence of the above-mentioned cognition of the group responsibility in a local community and the general cognition as a common law and mental pressure on the debtor to pay for his or her debt.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸幕府が全国支配を確立して、幕府による法の支配が確立されるまでこうした慣習は存在していたとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the Edo bakufu established the system to rule the whole Japan under law, such a custom is estimated to have existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was recognized that these customs had existed until the Edo bakufu established the system and law to rule the whole Japan.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was recognized that these customs had existed until the Edo bakufu established the system and law to rule the whole Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Londonbashi(id:19027), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>