<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鉄道国有法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Railway Nationalization Act</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Railway Nationalization Act</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Railway Nationalization Act</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鉄道国有法（てつどうこくゆうほう；明治39年3月31日法律第17号）は、全国的な鉄道網を内閣鉄道院に一元化するため、私鉄を国有化することを定めた日本の法律である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Railway Nationalization Act (the 17th Law issued on March 31 1906) is a Japanese law to nationalize private railroads in order to unify the nation-wide networks of railroads under the Tetsudoin (Railway Bureau) in the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Railway Nationalization Act (the 17th Law issued on March 31, 1906) is a Japanese law to nationalize private railways in order to unify the nation-wide networks of railways under the Tetsudoin (Railway Bureau) in the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>March 31 1906→コンマを追加しました。この列以降訳分の中にrailway(英)とrailroad(米)が混在しています。米語表記で統一という規則ですが、テーマタイトルを調べると日本では&quot;The Railway Nationalization Act&quot;が通例のようであり、ＪＲもJapan RailwaysとあるようにRailwayを使用している事から、こちらで統一する方がよろしいかと思います。どちらにせよ、同じテーマの中で英語と米語が混在している現状況はおかしいので、以降の列もrailwayで修正をかけています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Railway Nationalization Act (the 17th Law issued on March 31, 1906) is a Japanese law to nationalize private railways in order to unify the nation-wide networks of railways under the Tetsudoin (Railway Bureau) in the Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>1906年（明治39年）3月31日公布、1920年（大正9年）8月5日改正。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The law was issued on March 31, 1906 and revised on August 5, 1920.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The law was issued on March 31, 1906 and revised on August 5, 1920.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The law was issued on March 31, 1906 and revised on August 5, 1920.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1987年（昭和62年）4月1日、日本国有鉄道改革法等施行法（昭和61年法律第93号）第110条の規定により廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was abolished on April 1, 1987 by the provision no.110 of Enforcement Law of Japanese National Railways Reform Act (Law no.93 issued in 1986).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was abolished on April 1, 1987 by the provision no.110 of Enforcement Law of Japanese National Railways Reform Act (Law no.93 issued in 1986).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was abolished on April 1, 1987 by the provision no.110 of Enforcement Law of Japanese National Railways Reform Act (Law no.93 issued in 1986).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>これにより、1906年から翌年の1907年（明治40年）にかけて、下記の17社の2,812.0マイル（約4,500km）が買収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railroad networks of 17 railroad companies mentioned below, which were as long as 2812 miles (about 4500km), were acquired over the period from 1906 to 1907 by the nationalization act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railway networks of 17 railway companies mentioned below, which were as long as 2812 miles (about 4500km), were acquired over the period from 1906 to 1907 by the nationalization act.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。as 2812余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railway networks of 17 railway companies mentioned below, which were as long as 2812 miles (about 4500km), were acquired over the period from 1906 to 1907 by the nationalization act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>買収前には1,600哩（約2,600km）に過ぎなかった官設鉄道は、4,400哩（約7100km）と3倍に増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The networks of Japanese Imperial Government Rail away, which had been only 1600 miles (about 2600 km) before the acquisition, tripled to 4400 miles (about 7100 km).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The networks of Japanese Imperial Government Railway, which had been only 1600 miles (about 2600 km) before the acquisition, tripled to 4400 miles (about 7100 km).</e>
<cmt>Rail away→Railwayのスペルミスだと思われます。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The networks of Japanese Imperial Government Railway, which had been only 1600 miles (about 2600 km) before the acquisition, tripled to 4400 miles (about 7100 km).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>私鉄は地域輸送のみに限定されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The activities of private railroad companies were limited to only local transportation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The activities of private railway companies were limited to only local transportation.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The activities of private railway companies were limited to only local transportation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="7">
<j>鉄道国有論の展開</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of the theory to nationalize the railroads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The development of the theory to nationalize the railways</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The development of the theory to nationalize the railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>日本の鉄道は創業以来、官設官営を基本方針とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic railroad policy in Japan was, from the beginning, to build and administer it by the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic railway policy in Japan was, from the beginning, to build and administer it by the government.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic railway policy in Japan was, from the beginning, to build and administer it by the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これは、草創期の日本の鉄道行政を頂点に立って牽引した井上勝が、熱心な鉄道国有論者であったことが大きい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The policy was largely due to the fact that Masaru INOUE, who was the leader and the driving force of railroad administration in Japan, was an ardent advocate of railroad nationalization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The policy was largely due to the fact that Masaru INOUE, who was the leader and the driving force of railway administration in Japan, was an ardent advocate of railway nationalization.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The policy was largely due to the fact that Masaru INOUE, who was the leader and the driving force of railway administration in Japan, was an ardent advocate of railway nationalization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>しかしながら、政府財政の窮乏により鉄道をすべて官設官営で建設運営することはかなわず、やむなく民営鉄道に幹線鉄道建設の一部を委ねざるを得ないことになってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the financial drought the government was not able to build and administer all the railroads, and the government ended up being obliged to leave a part of building main railroads to private railroad companies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the financial drought, the government was not able to build and administer all the railways, and the government ended up being obliged to leave a part of building main railways to private railway companies.</e>
<cmt>droughtの後にコンマを追加しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the financial drought, the government was not able to build and administer all the railways, and the government ended up being obliged to leave a part of building main railways to private railway companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そのため、井上は機会あるごとに、自説の鉄道国有論と私設鉄道買収を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the fact, Inoue took every chance to insist on his claim to nationalize the railroads and acquire the private railroad companies.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the fact, Inoue took every chance to insist on his claim to nationalize the railways and acquire the private railway companies.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the fact, Inoue took every chance to insist on his claim to nationalize the railways and acquire the private railway companies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>鉄道国有化法案も再三国会に提出されたが、井上が退官する1893年（明治26年）までにそれが可決されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the bill to nationalize the railroads was repeatedly submitted to the Diet, it did not go through the Diet until Inoue retired.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the bill to nationalize the railways was repeatedly submitted to the Diet, it did not go through the Diet until Inoue&apos;s retirement in 1893.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。年号の部分が訳漏れです、追加に伴いretiredの箇所も変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the bill to nationalize the railways was repeatedly submitted to the Diet, it did not go through the Diet until Inoue&apos;s retirement in 1893.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="13">
<j>政府の財政を窮乏させる原因となったのは、西南戦争による過大な戦費の支出であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the vast war spending of Seinan War that aggravated the government&apos;s finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the vast war spending of Seinan War that aggravated the government&apos;s finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the vast war spending of Seinan War that aggravated the government&apos;s finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これにより、鉄道建設のための予算がなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the war spending, the government ran out of the budget to build railroads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the war spending, the government ran out of the budget to build railways.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the war spending, the government ran out of the budget to build railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>それまでに完成していた京浜間、京阪神間鉄道を民間に売却して、その代金により新線建設を行なおうという案まで出たほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It went so far that the idea came up that Keihin (Tokyo and Yokohama) and Keihanshin railroads completed by then would be sold to the private sectors and with money obtained by selling the lines, the new lines would be built.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It went so far that the idea came up that Keihin (Tokyo and Yokohama) and Keihanshin railways completed by then would be sold to the private sectors and with money obtained by selling the lines, the new lines would be built.</e>
<cmt>Yokohama) andの間のスペースを削除しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It went so far that the idea came up that Keihin (Tokyo and Yokohama) and Keihanshin railways completed by then would be sold to the private sectors and with money obtained by selling the lines, the new lines would be built.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>鉄道網速成の方針と財政窮乏のジレンマが、幹線鉄道建設の一部を民間に委ねる方針転換をさせることになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dilemma between the policy of building the networks of railroads quickly and the financial drought made the government change its policy and leave a part of the building main railroads to private sectors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dilemma between the policy of building the networks of railways quickly and the financial drought made the government change its policy and leave a part of the building main railways to private sectors.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dilemma between the policy of building the networks of railways quickly and the financial drought made the government change its policy and leave a part of the building main railways to private sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>こうして1881年（明治14年）、日本初の私設鉄道、日本鉄道が設立されたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how Nippon Railway, the first private railroad company in Japan, was established in 1881.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how Nippon Railway, the first private railway company in Japan, was established in 1881.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how Nippon Railway, the first private railway company in Japan, was established in 1881.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>井上は1883年（明治16年）、工部卿宛てに意見書「私設鉄道に関する論旨」を提出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inoue submitted a written opinion entitled &apos;An opinion on building private railways&apos; to Construction Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inoue submitted a written opinion entitled &apos;An opinion on building private railways&apos; to Construction Minister in 1883.</e>
<cmt>年号訳漏れです。追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inoue submitted a written opinion entitled &apos;An opinion on building private railways&apos; to Construction Minister in 1883.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>この中で、鉄道の用途は国道と同様であって、これを民営に委ねるべきでないことを原則とすると自説を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the written opinion Inouye claimed that in principle railroads should not be left to the private sectors because the purpose of the railroads use was the same with one of National Route.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the written opinion, Inoue claimed that in principle railways should not be left to the private sectors because the purpose of the railways use was the same with one of National Route.</e>
<cmt>opinionの後にコンマを追加しました。Inouyeの名前がスペルミスです。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the written opinion, Inoue claimed that in principle railways should not be left to the private sectors because the purpose of the railways use was the same with one of National Route.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>民営に委ねた場合に発生する、無用の競争や改良努力の怠慢など8項目の弊害をあげた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He pointed out the eight adverse effects including the unnecessary competition and the neglect of improvement efforts that may occur when it was left to the private sectors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He pointed out the eight adverse effects including the unnecessary competition and the neglect of improvement efforts that may occur when it was left to the private sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He pointed out the eight adverse effects including the unnecessary competition and the neglect of improvement efforts that may occur when it was left to the private sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="21">
<j>一方で、政府の手厚い保護を受けていたとはいえ、日本鉄道が好調な決算を発表すると、各地で私設鉄道設立ブームが起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, even though Nippon Railway had received a careful protection from the government, the boom to build private railroads started across Japan when Nippon Railway announced its positive financial statements.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, even though Nippon Railway had received a careful protection from the government, the boom to build private railways started across Japan when Nippon Railway announced its positive financial statements.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, even though Nippon Railway had received a careful protection from the government, the boom to build private railways started across Japan when Nippon Railway announced its positive financial statements.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>1884年（明治17年）南海電気鉄道や、1887年（明治20年）の伊予鉄道を皮切りに、両毛線、山陽鉄道、水戸線（初代）、九州鉄道、関西鉄道（初代）などが認可された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting with Nankai Electric Railway in 1884 and Iyo Railway in 1887, Mito Line, Sanyo Railway Company, Mito Line (the first), Kyushu Railway and Kansai Railway were approved.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting with Nankai Electric Railway in 1884 and Iyo Railway in 1887, Ryomo Line, Sanyo Railway Company, Mito Line (the first), Kyushu Railway and Kansai Railway (the first) were approved.</e>
<cmt>Mito Lineが二つあり、両毛線が訳漏れです。関西鉄道の括弧内も訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with Nankai Electric Railway in 1884 and Iyo Railway in 1887, Ryomo Line, Sanyo Railway Company, Mito Line (the first), Kyushu Railway and Kansai Railway (the first) were approved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>それまでの官設官営の原則が崩れて、日本の幹線鉄道は、官設・私設の両方により建設されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principle of construction and administration of railroads by the government collapsed, and main railroads in Japan came to be built both by the government and by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principle of construction and administration of railways by the government collapsed, and main railways in Japan came to be built both by the government and by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principle of construction and administration of railways by the government collapsed, and main railways in Japan came to be built both by the government and by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>だが、中には無謀な計画や投資を誘発したものもあり、それは1890年（明治23年）の経済恐慌となってはね返った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some of the projects induced reckless plans and investments, which resulted in the economic crisis in 1980.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some of the projects induced reckless plans and investments, which resulted in the economic crisis in 1980.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some of the projects induced reckless plans and investments, which resulted in the economic crisis in 1980.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>建設工事の停滞や株式払込みの遅滞、既設私設鉄道の経営の悪化を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, such projects caused stagnation in construction, the delay of paid-in capital and deteriorating management of existing private railroads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, such projects caused stagnation in construction, the delay of paid-in capital and deteriorating management of existing private railways.</e>
<cmt>existing privateの間のスペースを削除しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, such projects caused stagnation in construction, the delay of paid-in capital and deteriorating management of existing private railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="26">
<j>状況は間もなく回復したが、このような状況の中で、1891年（明治24年）、井上は「鉄道政略に関する議」を上申した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation picked up soon, and under such circumstances Inoue submitted &apos;The opinion on the policies of railways&apos; to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation improved soon, and under such circumstances, Inoue submitted &apos;The opinion on the policies of railways&apos; to the government in 1891.</e>
<cmt>picked upは口語的なのでimprovedに変更しました。circumstancesのあとにコンマを追加しました。年号が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation improved soon, and under such circumstances, Inoue submitted &apos;The opinion on the policies of railways&apos; to the government in 1891.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>この上申書では、従来からの鉄道国有論に加えて既設私設鉄道の買収を前面に押し出しており、そのためには私設鉄道買収法の制定が必要であると説いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the written opinion he stressed the importance of acquisition of existing private railroads in addition to his theory of nationalization of railroads and insisted, for the purpose, that it was necessary to enact the law to acquire private railroads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the written opinion, he stressed the importance of acquisition of existing private railways in addition to his theory of nationalization of railways and insisted, for the purpose, that it was necessary to enact the law to acquire private railways.</e>
<cmt>opinionの後にコンマを追加しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the written opinion, he stressed the importance of acquisition of existing private railways in addition to his theory of nationalization of railways and insisted, for the purpose, that it was necessary to enact the law to acquire private railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="28">
<j>この上申書を契機として、政府は再三、鉄道公債法と私設鉄道買収法を帝国議会に提出したが、いずれも可決されなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, the government repeatedly submitted the bill of railroad public ponds and acquisition of private railways to the Diet, but every time the bill was not passed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking this opportunity, the government repeatedly submitted the bill of railway public ponds and acquisition of private railways to the Diet, but every time the bill was not passed.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking this opportunity, the government repeatedly submitted the bill of railway public ponds and acquisition of private railways to the Diet, but every time the bill was not passed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>1892年（明治25年）に、買収法案に大幅な修正を加えた鉄道敷設法が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1892 The Railway Construction Act, in which great amendment was added to the bill of acquisition, was enacted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1892, the Railway Construction Act, in which great amendment was added to the bill of acquisition, was enacted.</e>
<cmt>年号の後にコンマを追加しました。Theを小文字に修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1892, the Railway Construction Act, in which great amendment was added to the bill of acquisition, was enacted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>しかしそれは、予定線建設のために必要がある場合のみ、私設鉄道の買収ができ、さらに議会の協賛を必要とするものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to the act, the acquisition of private railroad was possible only when acquisition was necessary for the construction of planned lines, and in order to do so the support from the Diet was necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the act, the acquisition of private railway was possible only when acquisition was necessary for the construction of planned lines, and the support from the Diet was necessary.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。in order to do so文脈から見て不要だと思うので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the act, the acquisition of private railway was possible only when acquisition was necessary for the construction of planned lines, and the support from the Diet was necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>将来の国有化の可能性をにおわせながら、実際は予定線の民間による建設を容認するなどとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hinting the possibility of nationalization in the future, actually the act allowed the construction of planned lines by private sectors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hinting the possibility of nationalization in the future, in fact, the act allowed the construction of planned lines by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>actually口語的なのでin factに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hinting the possibility of nationalization in the future, in fact, the act allowed the construction of planned lines by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>議会を構成する私設鉄道の株主でもある華族や資本家、地主たちによって完全に骨抜きにされてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The act was watered down completely because the Diet was composed of the peerage, capitalists and land owners who were also the shareholders of private railroads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The act was watered down completely because the Diet was composed of the peerages, capitalists, and land owners who were also the shareholders of private railways.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。文章の整合性を取るためpeerageを複数形に修正しました。capitalistsの後にコンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The act was watered down completely because the Diet was composed of the peerages, capitalists, and land owners who were also the shareholders of private railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>これに憤慨した井上は翌年、退官することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being outraged by this, Inoue retired the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being outraged by this, Inoue retired the following year.</e>
<cmt>翌年という意味でのnext yearは誤訳です。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being outraged by this, Inoue retired the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="34">
<j>井上の鉄道国有論に対抗して鉄道民営論を唱えたのは、渋沢栄一や田口卯吉、中上川彦次郎、三井財閥や三菱財閥などの財界の有力者たちであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Against Inoue&apos;s theory of nationalization of railroad, the powerful persons in Mitsui and Mitsubishi-zaibatsu including Eichi SHIBUSAWA, Ukichi TAGUCHI and Hikojiro NAKAMIGAWA advocated the theory of railway management by private sectors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against Inoue&apos;s theory of nationalization of railway, the powerful businessmen in Mitsui and Mitsubishi-zaibatsu (company syndicate) including Eichi SHIBUSAWA, Ukichi TAGUCHI, and Hikojiro NAKAMIGAWA advocated the theory of railway management by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。Persons→具体的に人物像が分かるようにbusinessmenに変更しました。Zaibatsuだけでは英文として意味不足なので(company syndicate)を追加しました。TAGUCHIの後にコンマを追加しました。advocated theの間のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against Inoue&apos;s theory of nationalization of railway, the powerful businessmen in Mitsui and Mitsubishi-zaibatsu (company syndicate) including Eichi SHIBUSAWA, Ukichi TAGUCHI, and Hikojiro NAKAMIGAWA advocated the theory of railway management by private sectors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>彼らは資本主義の発展にともなって鉄道経営が大きな利益をもたらすとともに、産業支配と鉄道支配との間に密接な関連性があることをよく認識していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were well aware that railway management would bring a huge profit along with the development of capitalism and there is close relationship between the control of industries and the control of railroads.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were well aware that railway management would bring a huge profit along with the development of capitalism and there is close relationship between the control of industries and the control of railways.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were well aware that railway management would bring a huge profit along with the development of capitalism and there is close relationship between the control of industries and the control of railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>渋沢らが関わる東京経済学協会が1891年に発表した「鉄道調査報告書」に掲載された佐分利一嗣の論文では、鉄道国有化論に対する反証を一々あげて論じ、「将来の鉄道は、私設民営たるべし」という結論を導いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In his thesis run in the &apos;The investigative report on railways&apos; published by the Tokyo Economic Association, Kazuchika SABURI refuted every point of the theory of railroad nationalization by indicating the proof of it, and concluded &apos;The railroads in the future should be built and administered by private sectors.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In their thesis run in the &apos;The investigative report on railways&apos; published by the Tokyo Economic Association in 1891, Kazuchika SABURI refuted every point of the theory of railway nationalization by indicating the proof of it, and concluded &apos;The railways in the future should be built and administered by private sectors&apos;.</e>
<cmt>his→前列からの流れを見ると文法ミスです。年号が訳漏れです。railroad→railwayに修正しました。最後のピリオドの位置が不適切です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In their thesis run in the &apos;The investigative report on railways&apos; published by the Tokyo Economic Association in 1891, Kazuchika SABURI refuted every point of the theory of railway nationalization by indicating the proof of it, and concluded &apos;The railways in the future should be built and administered by private sectors&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>続いて渋沢らは、1894年（明治27年）に官設鉄道払下計画を立案し、一挙に彼らの理想とする鉄道民営の実現を図ったが、日清戦争の勃発にともない、計画は頓挫している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this, the powerful persons including Shibusawa planned the disposal by the government of Japanese Imperial Government Railway and tried to realize the railroad management by the private sectors in one stroke, but the plan came to a deadlock with the outbreak of Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this, the powerful businessmen including Shibusawa planned the disposal by the government of Japanese Imperial Government Railway in 1894 and tried to realize the railway management by the private sectors in one stroke, but the plan came to a deadlock with the outbreak of Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>persons→businessmenに変更しました。年号が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this, the powerful businessmen including Shibusawa planned the disposal by the government of Japanese Imperial Government Railway in 1894 and tried to realize the railway management by the private sectors in one stroke, but the plan came to a deadlock with the outbreak of Sino-Japanese War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="38">
<j>その後、鉄道国有化が政治課題となるのは、1899年（明治32年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, it was in 1899 that the railroad nationalization became a political agenda.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, it was in 1899 that the railway nationalization became a political agenda.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, it was in 1899 that the railway nationalization became a political agenda.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>衆議院に「鉄道国有に関する建議案」が提出、可決され、調査期間として首相直属の鉄道国有調査会が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bill of proposal on railroad nationalization&apos; was submitted to the House of Representatives and passed, and the Committee on railroad nationalization that directly reported to the Prime Minister was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bill of proposal on railway nationalization&apos; was submitted to the House of Representatives and passed, and the Committee on railway nationalization under the direct control of the Prime Minister was established.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。that directly reported to→文章を簡潔にするため変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bill of proposal on railway nationalization&apos; was submitted to the House of Representatives and passed, and the Committee on railway nationalization under the direct control of the Prime Minister was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その報告に基づき、翌年鉄道国有法案および私設鉄道買収法案が帝国議会に提出されたが、これも議決されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the report by the committee, the next year the bills of railroad nationalization and acquisition of private railroads were submitted to the Imperial Diet, but the bills did not go through the Diet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the report by the committee, the following year, the bills of railway nationalization and acquisition of private railways were submitted to the Imperial Diet, but the bills did not go through the Diet.</e>
<cmt>翌年という意味でのnext yearは誤訳です。修正しました。yearの後にコンマを追加しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the report by the committee, the following year, the bills of railway nationalization and acquisition of private railways were submitted to the Imperial Diet, but the bills did not go through the Diet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="41">
<j>しかし、この頃には、日清戦争後の三国干渉によって対ロシア戦を意識しだした軍部も、鉄道国有問題を第一義とするようになっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the military that began to be aware of the war against Russia with the Triple Intervention after the Sino-Japanese War came to consider the issue of railroad nationalization as the most imminent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the military that began to be aware of the war against Russia with the Triple Intervention after the Sino-Japanese War came to consider the issue of railway nationalization as the primary purpose.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。imminentにmostを修飾する事はできません。文法ミスです。the primary purposeに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the military that began to be aware of the war against Russia with the Triple Intervention after the Sino-Japanese War came to consider the issue of railway nationalization as the primary purpose.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>鉄道が民営であることの軍事的に不利な理由は、私鉄の場合、株式会社であるから、経営状態を詳しく株主に報告しなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disadvantaged point of railroad management by private sector was that in the case of the private railroads, being the joint-stock companies, they must report their managing status in detail to the shareholders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disadvantaged point of railway management by private sector was that in the case of the private railways, being the joint-stock companies, they must report their managing status in detail to the shareholders.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disadvantaged point of railway management by private sector was that in the case of the private railways, being the joint-stock companies, they must report their managing status in detail to the shareholders.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし、その株主の中には外国人投資家もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But, among the shareholders there were some foreign investors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But, among the shareholders there were some foreign investors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But, among the shareholders there were some foreign investors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>そのため、彼らに経営状況を教える時には、軍事輸送用の臨時列車を走らせることまでも公開する必要に迫られる可能性があり、同時に軍事機密が外国に漏洩される恐れもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, when the companies told the foreign investors their managing status, the companies needed to tell them so far as to the information on running the extra trains for military transportation, and at the same time there was a fear that military secrets would leak to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, when the companies told the foreign investors their managing status, the companies needed to tell them so far as to the information on running the extra trains for military transportation, and at the same time there was a fear that military secrets would leak to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, when the companies told the foreign investors their managing status, the companies needed to tell them so far as to the information on running the extra trains for military transportation, and at the same time there was a fear that military secrets would leak to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>加えて、外国人投資家に株を買い占められた時、それが敵国の資本家なら軍事輸送を拒否される恐れすらあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, there was even a fear that when the stocks were bought up by foreign investors, military transportation might be refused if the investors were the ones from enemy country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, there was even a fear that when the stocks were bought up by foreign investors, military transportation might be refused if the investors were the ones from enemy country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, there was even a fear that when the stocks were bought up by foreign investors, military transportation might be refused if the investors were the ones from enemy country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>軍事的理由以外にも、日露戦争後は、主要産業を独占化しつつあった財閥が、物流の大動脈である鉄道の意義を高く評価するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides military reasons, Zaibatsu (company syndicate) that were monopolizing the key industries after Russo-Japanese War came to think highly of the significance of railroads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides military reasons, Zaibatsu that were monopolizing the key industries after Russo-Japanese War came to think highly of the significance of railways.</e>
<cmt>Zaibatsu (company syndicate)はぜんれにて既出事項なのでカッコ内を削除しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides military reasons, Zaibatsu that were monopolizing the key industries after Russo-Japanese War came to think highly of the significance of railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>主要幹線が多数の私設鉄道によって分割保有されていることが、諸外国との競争上、非常な不利であると認識されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Zaibatsu came to recognize that the fact of main railroads being divided and held separately by private railroads was so disadvantageous in terms of the competition with foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Zaibatsu came to recognize that the fact of main railways being divided and held separately by private railways was so disadvantageous in terms of the competition with foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Zaibatsu came to recognize that the fact of main railways being divided and held separately by private railways was so disadvantageous in terms of the competition with foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="48">
<j>そして1906年、紆余曲折を経た鉄道国有法案は、第1次西園寺内閣によって第22帝国議会に提出される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in 1906, after twists and turns, the bill of Railway Nationalization Act was submitted to the 22nd Imperial Diet by the First Saionji Cabinet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in 1906, after twists and turns, the bill of Railway Nationalization Act was submitted to the 22nd Imperial Diet by the First Saionji Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in 1906, after twists and turns, the bill of Railway Nationalization Act was submitted to the 22nd Imperial Diet by the First Saionji Cabinet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>渋沢栄一に加えて井上馨や加藤高明、高橋是清も反対論を唱えて衆議院を説得しようとしたために政府は彼らの説得に苦慮したが、同年3月16日に賛成243・反対109で可決された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With not only Eichi SHIBUSAWA but Koru INOUE, Takaaki KATO and Korekiyo TAKAHASHI opposing the bill and trying to persuade the Diet, the government had trouble dissuading them, but on March 16 in the same year the bill was approved with 243 in favor and 109 opposed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With not only Eichi SHIBUSAWA but also Kaoru INOUE, Takaaki KATO, and Korekiyo TAKAHASHI opposing the bill and trying to persuade the Diet, the government had trouble dissuading them, but on March 16 in the same year, the bill was approved with 243 in favor and 109 opposed.</e>
<cmt>口語体を避けるため、alsoを追加しました。Koru→Kaoruのスペルミスです。KATOの後にコンマを追加しました。the same yearの後にコンマ追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With not only Eichi SHIBUSAWA but also Kaoru INOUE, Takaaki KATO, and Korekiyo TAKAHASHI opposing the bill and trying to persuade the Diet, the government had trouble dissuading them, but on March 16 in the same year, the bill was approved with 243 in favor and 109 opposed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>貴族院_(日本)では曾我祐準（日本鉄道社長）や仙石貢（九州鉄道社長）が反対論を唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the House of Peers, Sukenori SOGA (the president of Nippon Railway) and Mitsugi SENGOKU (the president of Kyushu Railway) opposed to the bill.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the House of Peers, Sukenori SOGA (the president of Nippon Railway) and Mitsugi SENGOKU (the president of Kyushu Railway) opposed to the bill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the House of Peers, Sukenori SOGA (the president of Nippon Railway) and Mitsugi SENGOKU (the president of Kyushu Railway) opposed to the bill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>だが、研究会_(貴族院)の指導者三島弥太郎の工作によって3月25日に修正付きで可決された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But by the maneuvering of Yataro MISHIMA, the leader of a study group (in the House of Peers), the bill was approved with amendments on March 25.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But by the maneuvering of Yataro MISHIMA, the leader of a study group (in the House of Peers), the bill was approved with amendments on March 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But by the maneuvering of Yataro MISHIMA, the leader of a study group (in the House of Peers), the bill was approved with amendments on March 25.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>本来は両院協議会が開催される予定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally a joint committee of both Houses was going to be held.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, a joint committee of both Houses was going to be held.</e>
<cmt>originallyの後にコンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, a joint committee of both Houses was going to be held.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>だが、西園寺が総裁である立憲政友会が会期末であることを理由に全く同一の修正案を可決したために、同一の法案が成立したとみなされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, since Rikken Seiyukai Party whose president was Saionji passed the amended bill with completely same contents on the grounds that it was the end of the Diet session, the same bill was recognized to be passed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since Rikken Seiyukai Party (a political party organized by Hirobumi ITO) whose president was Saionji passed the amended bill with completely same contents because it was the end of the Diet session, the same bill was recognized to be passed.</e>
<cmt>Rikken Seiyukai Party→英文として理解できないので(a political party organized by Hirobumi ITO)を追加しました。on the grounds that→長いのでbecauseに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since Rikken Seiyukai Party (a political party organized by Hirobumi ITO) whose president was Saionji passed the amended bill with completely same contents because it was the end of the Diet session, the same bill was recognized to be passed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>これにより、井上の悲願であった鉄道国有化は漸く実現し、17私鉄が国有化されることとなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the passage of the bill, railroad nationalization was realized at last and 17 private railroads were going to be nationalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the passage of the bill, railway nationalization which had been a long-cherished wish of Inoue was realized at last and 17 private railways were going to be nationalized.</e>
<cmt>原文の「井上の悲願であった」の箇所が訳漏れです。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the passage of the bill, railway nationalization which had been a long-cherished wish of Inoue was realized at last and 17 private railways were going to be nationalized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="55">
<j>この時提出された法案の原案は、17私鉄の他に15私鉄を加えた32私鉄を買収するものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original draft of the bill submitted at this time was to acquire 32 private railroads including 15 private railroads, besides the original 17 private railroads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original draft of the bill submitted at this time was to acquire 32 private railways including 15 private railways, besides the original 17 private railways</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original draft of the bill submitted at this time was to acquire 32 private railways including 15 private railways, besides the original 17 private railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これは、閣議において17私鉄を買収するという原原案に15私鉄を加えたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The draft was to include the acquisition of 15 private railroads besides 17 private railroads that had been to be acquired in the first draft.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The draft was to include the acquisition of 15 private railways besides 17 private railways that had been to be acquired in the first draft.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The draft was to include the acquisition of 15 private railways besides 17 private railways that had been to be acquired in the first draft.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>衆議院は通過したものの、貴族院 (日本)で修正され、原原案の17私鉄買収に戻った経緯がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bill was passed in the House of Representatives but was amended and changed in the House of Peers to the original plan to acquire 17 private railroads.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bill was passed in the House of Representatives but was amended and changed in the House of Peers to the original plan to acquire 17 private railways.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bill was passed in the House of Representatives but was amended and changed in the House of Peers to the original plan to acquire 17 private railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>追加の15私鉄は、次のとおりであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The additional 15 private railroads are as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The additional 15 private railways were as follows.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。are→文法ミスです。修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The additional 15 private railways were as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="59">
<j>川越鉄道、成田線（初代）、東武鉄道、秩父鉄道、伊豆箱根鉄道駿豆線、水郡線（2代）、中越鉄道、豊川鉄道、名鉄尾西線、近江鉄道、南海本線、南海高野線、大阪鉄道 (2代目)、中国鉄道、博多湾鉄道汽船</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kawagoe Railway, Narita Line (the first), Tobu Railway Co., Ltd., Chichibu-Railway, Izu Hakone railway Sunzu Line, Suigun Line (the second), Chuetsu Railway, Toyokawa Railway, Meitetsu Bisai Line, Ohmi Railway Corporation, Nankai Main Line, Nankai Takano Route, Osaka Railway (the second), Chugoku Railway, Hakata Bay Railway Kisen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kawagoe Railway, Narita Line (the first), Tobu Railway Co., Ltd., Chichibu-Railway, Sunzu Line of Izu Hakone Railway, Suigun Line (the second), Chuetsu Railway, Toyokawa Railway, Meitetsu Bisai Line, Omi Railway Corporation, Nankai Main Line, Nankai Takano Route, Osaka Railway (the second), Chugoku Railway, Hakata Bay Railway Kisen</e>
<cmt>伊豆箱根鉄道駿豆線→修正しています。Ohmi→Ohは使用不可です。Omiに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kawagoe Railway, Narita Line (the first), Tobu Railway Co., Ltd., Chichibu-Railway, Sunzu Line of Izu Hakone Railway, Suigun Line (the second), Chuetsu Railway, Toyokawa Railway, Meitetsu Bisai Line, Omi Railway Corporation, Nankai Main Line, Nankai Takano Route, Osaka Railway (the second), Chugoku Railway, Hakata Bay Railway Kisen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>被買収私鉄の一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The list of acquired private railroads</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lists of acquired private railways</e>
<cmt>list複数形に修正しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lists of acquired private railways</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>その後の動き</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later movement</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later movements</e>
<cmt>movement複数形に修正しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later movements</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="60">
<j>1906年5月、私鉄買収の準備を行なう臨時鉄道国有準備局が、逓信大臣の管下に設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May, 1906 the Temporary Preparation Bureau for Railroad Nationalization was established under the control of the Communication Minister.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1906, the Temporary Preparation Bureau for Railway Nationalization was established under the control of the Communication Minister.</e>
<cmt>May, 1906→コンマの位置を修正しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1906, the Temporary Preparation Bureau for Railway Nationalization was established under the control of the Communication Minister.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>同局は、買収完了後もしばらくの間存続し、廃止されたのは鉄道院発足後の1909年（明治42年）7月末である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bureau existed for a while after completion of the acquisition, and was abolished in 1909 after the inauguration of Tetsudoin (Railway Bureau).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bureau existed for a while after completion of the acquisition, and was abolished at the end of July in 1909 after the inauguration of Tetsudoin.</e>
<cmt>原文、「7月末」の箇所が訳漏れです。(Railway Bureau)は前列にて既出なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bureau existed for a while after completion of the acquisition, and was abolished at the end of July in 1909 after the inauguration of Tetsudoin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="62">
<j>私鉄の買収により、官設鉄道の現業部門である鉄道作業局の規模は一気に膨れあがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the acquisition of private railroads, the scale of the Imperial Government Railway, the fieldwork agency of government railroads, swelled enormously in a short period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the acquisition of private railways, the scale of the Imperial Government Railway, the fieldwork agency of government railways, swelled enormously in a short period.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the acquisition of private railways, the scale of the Imperial Government Railway, the fieldwork agency of government railways, swelled enormously in a short period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>私鉄から引き継がれた鉄道路線の延長は4,550km、未開業線292km、機関車1,118両、客車3,101両、貨車20,850両であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The succeeded length of the private railroads was 4550 km, unopened line 292 km with 1118 locomotives, 3101 passenger carriages and 20850 freight cars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The succeeded length of the private railways was 4550 km, unopened line 292 km with 1118 locomotives, 3101 passenger carriages, and 20850 freight cars.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。carriagesのあとにコンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The succeeded length of the private railways was 4550 km, unopened line 292 km with 1118 locomotives, 3101 passenger carriages, and 20850 freight cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>それまで官設鉄道が保有していた路線延長2,525km、機関車769両、客車1,832両、貨車10,821両を大きく上回っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those figures far exceeded the ones Japanese Imperial Government Railway had possessed with 2525 km in length of the railroad, 1832 passenger carriages and 10821 freight cars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those figures far exceeded the ones Japanese Imperial Government Railway had possessed with 2525 km in length of the railway, 769 locomotives, 1832 passenger carriages, and 10821 freight cars.</e>
<cmt>carriagesのあとにコンマを追加しました。原文「機関車769両」の箇所が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those figures far exceeded the ones Japanese Imperial Government Railway had possessed with 2525 km in length of the railway, 769 locomotives, 1832 passenger carriages, and 10821 freight cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>それらの受入れのため、1907年4月1日に鉄道作業局を帝国鉄道庁に改編した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to accommodate them, on Aril 1, 1907 the Imperial Government Railway was reorganized to the Imperial Railway Agency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to accommodate them, on Aril 1, 1907 the Imperial Government Railway was reorganized to the Imperial Railway Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to accommodate them, on Aril 1, 1907 the Imperial Government Railway was reorganized to the Imperial Railway Agency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="66">
<j>帝国鉄道庁では、各私鉄から引き継いだ膨大な人員を糾合したため、ポストの重複などによって余剰人員を抱えることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Imperial Government Railway employed the vast number of employees that it had succeeded from the private railways, it ended up holding redundant workers because of position overlapping etc.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Imperial Government Railway employed the vast number of employees that it had succeeded from the private railways, it ended up holding redundant workers because of position overlapping etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Imperial Government Railway employed the vast number of employees that it had succeeded from the private railways, it ended up holding redundant workers because of position overlapping etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>その一方で、私鉄の監督、許認可を行なっていた逓信省鉄道局においても、業務が激減する事態が生じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the Railway Agency of Ministry of Communication that was in charge of approval and license on private railways, the business reduced greatly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the Railway Agency of Ministry of Communication that was in charge of approval and license on private railways, the business reduced greatly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the Railway Agency of Ministry of Communication that was in charge of approval and license on private railways, the business reduced greatly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>そのため、両者を統合再編して体制の簡素化を図ることとなり、1908年（明治41年）12月5日鉄道院が発足した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, in order to streamline both agencies by integration and reorganization, Tetsudoin (Railway Bureau) was established on December 5, 1908.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, in order to streamline both agencies by integration and reorganization, Tetsudoin was established on December 5, 1908.</e>
<cmt>(Railway Bureau)は前列にて既出なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, in order to streamline both agencies by integration and reorganization, Tetsudoin was established on December 5, 1908.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>この際、鉄道院は逓信大臣の管轄から離れて、新たに総裁を置き、内閣の直轄となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From this moment the bureau was put out of control of Communication Minister and put under the direct control of the Cabinet with new position of president set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From this moment, the bureau was put out of control of Communication Minister and put under the direct control of the Cabinet with new position of president set up.</e>
<cmt>momentのあとにコンマを加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From this moment, the bureau was put out of control of Communication Minister and put under the direct control of the Cabinet with new position of president set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="70">
<j>各私鉄から引き継がれた雑多な車両は、国有化後もしばらくの間、私鉄時代の形式番号のまま使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The various kinds of train cars that were succeeded from the private railways were used in the same model number as they had been used in private railways.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The various kinds of train cars that were succeeded from the private railways were used in the same model number as they had been used in private railways.</e>
<cmt>same modelの間のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The various kinds of train cars that were succeeded from the private railways were used in the same model number as they had been used in private railways.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>旧鉄道作業局の車両を含めて、新たな形式番号体系が制定されるのは、買収開始から実に3年後の1909年のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was in 1909 well after three years since the acquisition had started that, including the model number of train cars that had been used in the former Imperial Government Railway of Japan, the new model numbers were set up.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was in 1909 well after three years since the acquisition had started that, including the model number of train cars that had been used in the former Imperial Government Railway of Japan, the new model numbers were set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was in 1909 well after three years since the acquisition had started that, including the model number of train cars that had been used in the former Imperial Government Railway of Japan, the new model numbers were set up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>蒸気機関車だけに限定しても、タンク機関車103形式、テンダー機関車84形式、あわせて187形式に及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Looking at only steam locomotives, there were as many as 187 forms, combined with 103 forms of tank locomotive and 84 forms of tender locomotive.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Looking at only steam locomotives, there were as many as 187 forms, combined with 103 forms of tank locomotive and 84 forms of tender locomotive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Looking at only steam locomotives, there were as many as 187 forms, combined with 103 forms of tank locomotive and 84 forms of tender locomotive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>客車、貨車を含めると、実に膨大な作業であったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be assumed that the number of the forms was really enormous including the number of passenger and freight cars.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be assumed that the number of the forms was enormous including the number of passenger and freight cars.</e>
<cmt>reallyは口語的なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be assumed that the number of the forms was enormous including the number of passenger and freight cars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>この時制定された蒸気機関車の形式番号体系は、1928年（昭和3年）に新たな体系が制定された後も併存し、現在に至るまで踏襲されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The form of steam locomotive set up at this time existed together even after the new form was set up in 1928 and the form has been used until now.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The form of steam locomotive set up at this time existed together even after the new form was set up in 1928 and the form has been used until now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The form of steam locomotive set up at this time existed together even after the new form was set up in 1928 and the form has been used until now.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="75">
<j>鉄道院発足直後の1910年（明治43年）は、1両の機関車も製造されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1910, right after the inauguration of the Tetsudoin (Railway Bureau), not a single locomotive was produced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1910, right after the inauguration of the Tetsudoin, not a single locomotive was produced.</e>
<cmt>(Railway Bureau)は前列にて既出なので削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1910, right after the inauguration of the Tetsudoin, not a single locomotive was produced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>これは一気に膨れあがった雑多な形式を抱え、それらの今後の処遇や、輸送計画を練るのに手一杯で、機関車の新製にまで手が回らなかった結果ではないかと想像されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is imagined that this is because the bureau was so tied up with dealing with the existing locomotives in various forms that swelled in a short period that it was not able to create new locomotive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is imagined that this is because the bureau was so tied up with dealing with the existing locomotives in various forms that swelled in a short period that it was not able to create new locomotive.</e>
<cmt>in variousの間のスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is imagined that this is because the bureau was so tied up with dealing with the existing locomotives in various forms that swelled in a short period that it was not able to create new locomotive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>その後は、各車種にわたって標準型車両が制定され、雑多な少数形式の淘汰が推進されていくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, standard train cars in each form of car was set up, and assorted small number of train cars began to be culled out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, standard train cars in each form of car were set up, and assorted small number of train cars began to be culled out.</e>
<cmt>was文法ミスです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, standard train cars in each form of car were set up, and assorted small number of train cars began to be culled out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="78">
<j>また、鉄道国有法公布後、今度は新たな私鉄の出願がほとんど無くなるという事態になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And after the Railway Nationalization Act was issued, few new applications for new private railroad were turned in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And after the Railway Nationalization Act was issued, few new applications for new private railway were turned in.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And after the Railway Nationalization Act was issued, few new applications for new private railway were turned in.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>これは、私鉄を監督する法律である私設鉄道法の条件が厳しいという背景もあったが、地域開発の観点から見ると問題があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is partly because the conditions of the Private Railroad Law that supervised the private railroads were strict.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is partly because the conditions of the Private Railway Law that supervised the private railways were strict, however, there were some problems in terms of local development.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処とありますが、特に分ける必要もないと判断し一文に統合しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is partly because the conditions of the Private Railway Law that supervised the private railways were strict, however, there were some problems in terms of local development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>そのため、1910年（明治43年）に鉄道開業に関する条文を相当簡略化した軽便鉄道法を制定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to solve this problem, the provisions concerning railroad establishment were simplified, and Light Railway Law was issued in 1910.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to solve this problem, the provisions concerning railway establishment were simplified, and Light Railway Law was issued in 1910.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to solve this problem, the provisions concerning railway establishment were simplified, and Light Railway Law was issued in 1910.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>その後、私設鉄道法に基づく私鉄の出願が全く無くなったため、1919年（大正8年）には軽便鉄道法と私設鉄道法を廃止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, as no applications based on Private Railway Act were turned in, the Light Railway Act and Private Railway Act were abolished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, as no applications based on Private Railway Act were turned in, the Light Railway Act and Private Railway Act were abolished in 1919.</e>
<cmt>年号が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, as no applications based on Private Railway Act were turned in, the Light Railway Act and Private Railway Act were abolished in 1919.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>新たに地方鉄道法を制定、私鉄の監督はこの法に基づいて行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Local Railways Act was established, the supervision of private railroads were conducted based on this law.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Local Railways Act was established, the supervision of private railways were conducted based on this law.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Local Railways Act was established, the supervision of private railways were conducted based on this law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="83">
<j>またこれとは別に、路面電車と同じ軌道法に準拠した郊外鉄道の敷設を目論む者も現れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to this movement, some business persons aimed at establishing suburban railroad system based on the Tramways Act which was applied for streetcar system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to this movement, some business persons aimed at establishing suburban railway system based on the Tramways Act which was applied for streetcar system.</e>
<cmt>railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to this movement, some business persons aimed at establishing suburban railway system based on the Tramways Act which was applied for streetcar system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>米国で当時流行していたインターアーバンを真似たものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This system followed the example of the inter-urban which was popular in the United States at that time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system followed the example of the inter-urban which was popular in the United States at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system followed the example of the inter-urban which was popular in the United States at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>1905年（明治38年）の阪神電気鉄道開業以後、全国に広まっていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The railroad system began to spread throughout Japan since the inauguration of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The railway system began to spread throughout Japan since the inauguration of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. in 1905.</e>
<cmt>年号が訳漏れです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The railway system began to spread throughout Japan since the inauguration of Hanshin Electric Railway Co., Ltd. in 1905.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>その中には、阪鶴鉄道の幹部が設立した箕面有馬電気軌道（後の阪急電鉄）のように、鉄道国有法によって会社を手放した資本家が出資を行ったものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of such systems, like Mino-Arima Electric Tramline (later Hanyu Railway) established by the executives of Hankaku Railway, were invested by the capitalists that gave up their business by the Railway Nationalization Act.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of such systems, like Mino-Arima Electric Tramline (later Hankyu Railway) established by the executives of Hankaku Railway, were invested by the capitalists that gave up their business by the Railway Nationalization Act.</e>
<cmt>Hanyu→スペルミスです。Railway) establishedの間のスペース削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of such systems, like Mino-Arima Electric Tramline (later Hankyu Railway) established by the executives of Hankaku Railway, were invested by the capitalists that gave up their business by the Railway Nationalization Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="87">
<j>1987年の国鉄分割民営化により、国有化された鉄道は結局80年ほどして民営に戻ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After all, after about 80 years the management of the nationalized railroad ended up returning to private sectors by the division and privatization of JNR in 1987.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After all, after about 80 years the management of the nationalized railway ended up returning to private sectors by the division and privatization of Japanese National Railways in 1987.</e>
<cmt>JNR→前列に特に子の言葉を説明したものがないのでJapanese National Railwaysに修正しました。railroad→railwayに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After all, after about 80 years the management of the nationalized railway ended up returning to private sectors by the division and privatization of Japanese National Railways in 1987.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tam0031(id:165560), Nnh(id:474), Carbuncle(id:346), Lonin(id:44716), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cozy(id:132), Krp(id:15909), Maxima m(id:28947), March(id:9468), Shinkansen(id:13703), Desktoptetsu(id:339), Rusk(id:9895), ビリリー・G(id:33421), Kone(id:377), ペトチザン(id:19878), 210.(id:9838), Sekicho(id:1578), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>