<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>物売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri, Street Vendor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monouri</e>
<cmt>次のパラグラフで説明があるので、ここでは説明を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monouri</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>物売り（ものうり）とは路上で移動しながら、主に鳴り物や独特の売り声を発しながら呼び込みをして食事を提供したり、物品などを販売、修理や古物や廃品の買取や交換をする者。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri is a street vendor who sells foods or goods, serves as a repairman, buys old things or wastes, or exchanges these things for some goods, traveling by attracting people with musical instruments and distinctive call.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monouri is a street vendor who sells foods or goods, serves as a repairman, buys old things or wastes, or exchanges these things for some goods, traveling by attracting people with musical instruments and distinctive calls.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monouri is a street vendor who sells foods or goods, serves as a repairman, buys old things or wastes, or exchanges these things for some goods, traveling by attracting people with musical instruments and distinctive calls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「引き売り」・「引売り」ともいうが「物売りの声」・「引き売りの声」という言葉が一般的に馴染深い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Hikiuri,&apos; but the words &apos;Monouri no koe&apos; and &apos;Hikiuri no koe&apos;, meaning vender&apos;s call, are more familiar to the Japanese.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;Hikiuri,&apos; but the words &apos;Monouri no koe&apos; and &apos;Hikiuri no koe&apos;, meaning vender&apos;s call, are more familiar to the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Hikiuri,&apos; but the words &apos;Monouri no koe&apos; and &apos;Hikiuri no koe&apos;, meaning vender&apos;s call, are more familiar to the Japanese.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>屋台や行商や街商と重複する部分もあるが、行商は固定客に対しての訪問販売が主であり、街商は市や縁日で一所（ひとつところ）で留まって商売する事や物売りが必ずしも屋台ではなかった事から区別する事が出来る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri partly overlaps with food stalls, peddlers, and street vendors, but differs from them in that monouri does not necessarily uses the food stall, that the traveling salesmen mainly sells goods to fixed customers by door-to-door sales, and that street vendors do their businesses by occupying their places in bazaar or small-town festivals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monouri partly overlaps with food stalls, peddlers, and stallholders, but differs from them in that monouri does not necessarily use the food stall, that peddlers mainly sell goods to fixed customers by door-to-door sales, and that street vendors do their businesses by occupying their places in bazaar or small-town festivals.</e>
<cmt>街商の訳を単語リストに揃えました。行商の訳が同列内で違っていましたので揃えました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monouri partly overlaps with food stalls, peddlers, and stallholders, but differs from them in that monouri does not necessarily use the food stall, that peddlers mainly sell goods to fixed customers by door-to-door sales, and that street vendors do their businesses by occupying their places in bazaar or small-town festivals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸時代から盛んになり「棒手振」・「棒手売」（ぼてふり）と呼ばれていて日用品の食材から生活必需品まで衣食住に係わる全てのものが売られており幕府の許認可を受け鑑札を持った物だけが営業できた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri became popular during the Edo period as nicknamed &apos;botefuri&apos; and dealt with almost anything that has to do with food, clothing, and house, ranging from everyday foods to necessities of life; only those licensed by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) were allowed to do their businesses as monouri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Monouri became popular during the Edo period as nicknamed &apos;botefuri&apos; and dealt with almost anything that has to do with food, clothing, and housing, ranging from everyday foods to necessities of life; only those licensed by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) were allowed to do their businesses as monouri.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Monouri became popular during the Edo period as nicknamed &apos;botefuri&apos; and dealt with almost anything that has to do with food, clothing, and housing, ranging from everyday foods to necessities of life; only those licensed by the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) were allowed to do their businesses as monouri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これに違反すれば厳しい処罰があったが、生活困窮者や弱者の就業を目的とした幕府の政策でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu severely punished monouri who violated the license, and also treated monouri as measures for providing jobs to the poor and the weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu severely punished monouri who violated the license, and also treated monouri as measures for providing jobs to the poor and the weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu severely punished monouri who violated the license, and also treated monouri as measures for providing jobs to the poor and the weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>季節物の販売も多く、蓮の葉商いの傾向も強いが市や祭事の門前町などの街商は場所代や既得権が必要であったが、棒手振は歩き売りという形を取っていたのが街商などとの差異であり、また季節物ではない代表的なものとして、夜鳴き蕎麦屋や鮨屋などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Monouri sell a lot of seasonal goods like the street vendors, some of which were specialized in those trades, but differ from them in that the street vendors do their businesses in bazaar, festivals, or in temple towns by paying for their places and the right for carry on their businesses whereas monouri do their businesses by slowly cruising the neighborhood; on the other hand, some of monouri like Yonaki-soba and Sushiya sell items nothing to do with the season.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Botefuri sold a lot of seasonal goods, so-called Hasunohaakinai (trade of lotus leaves, which means a dealing with seasonal goods), by slowly cruising the neighborhood, which differed from stallholders who did their businesses in bazaar, festivals, or in temple towns by paying for their places and for the right to carry on their businesses; and also, some of monouri like Yonaki-soba vendors (merchants vending soba at night) and Sushi vendors sold items nothing to do with the season.</e>
<cmt>時制を修正しました。棒手振を主語にしました。余分な説明を削除し、不足していた説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Botefuri sold a lot of seasonal goods, so-called Hasunohaakinai (trade of lotus leaves, which means a dealing with seasonal goods), by slowly cruising the neighborhood, which differed from stallholders who did their businesses in bazaar, festivals, or in temple towns by paying for their places and for the right to carry on their businesses; and also, some of monouri like Yonaki-soba vendors (merchants vending soba at night) and Sushi vendors sold items nothing to do with the season.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>当時は大八車（リヤカー）ではなく主に道具や商品や食材の入った箱や笊（ざる）、籠（かご）や桶（おけ）などを両天秤にして天秤棒を担いで売り歩いたので棒手振と呼ばれていたが、道具や品物の入った箱を片方の肩で担いで売り歩く者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days, most of monouri cruised streets for selling goods by carrying tools and foods not on a large cart but in a pair of boxes, bamboo sieves, baskets, or tubs on a pole, which was the origin of their nickname &apos;botefuri,&apos; and some of monouri sold goods by carrying tools and goods in a box on a shoulder.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, most of monouri cruised streets for selling goods by carrying tools and foods not on a large cart but in a pair of boxes, bamboo sieves, baskets, or tubs on both sides of a pole, which was the origin of their nickname &apos;botefuri&apos; (&apos;bo&apos; is a pole, &apos;te&apos; is a hand, and &apos;furi&apos; is to swing), and some of monouri sold goods by carrying tools and goods in a box on a shoulder.</e>
<cmt>天秤の説明を補いました。棒手振りの説明を補いましたが、少々助長ですのでご検討ください。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, most of monouri cruised streets for selling goods by carrying tools and foods not on a large cart but in a pair of boxes, bamboo sieves, baskets, or tubs on both sides of a pole, which was the origin of their nickname &apos;botefuri&apos; (&apos;bo&apos; is a pole, &apos;te&apos; is a hand, and &apos;furi&apos; is to swing), and some of monouri sold goods by carrying tools and goods in a box on a shoulder.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸時代にはその場で調理する屋台だけでなく、調理済みの天ぷら（てんぷら）、鰻（うなぎ）の蒲焼などを木箱に入れ、物売りが売り歩いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, food stalls cooked foods in front of the customers and sold them, and monouri sold processed foods like fried fish and broiled eel by carrying them in a wooden box.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, food stalls cooked foods in front of customers and sold them, and monouri sold processed foods like fried fish and broiled eel by carrying them in a wooden box.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, food stalls cooked foods in front of customers and sold them, and monouri sold processed foods like fried fish and broiled eel by carrying them in a wooden box.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>近年では自転車やリヤカーをもとに形だけではなく設備も充実させ、煮炊きが出来る（ただし江戸時代から屋台では煮炊きの設備を備えていた）物売りも増え、昭和初期から昭和40年代まで品を替え（鮨や蕎麦は廃れおでん売りや菓子パン売りなどが盛んになった）世間で一般的に見られたが、江戸時代から変わらず続いた豆腐売りや納豆売りや金魚売りなども含め、今ではほとんど見る事はなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These past few years, more and more number of monouri not only advanced in appearance but were equipped with cooking facilities on their bicycles or trailers towed by bicycles (though, monouri were already equipped with cooking facilities during the Edo period,) and from the beginning to the 40s of the Showa period (1926 - 1974,) monouri changed their items and became widely seen here and there in Japan (Japanese style hodgepodge and sweets bread replaced sushi and soba); at present, monouri including those once sold bean curds, fermented beans, and goldfish are fading out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In recent years, more and more monouri not only advanced in appearance but also got equipped with enhanced cooking facilities on their bicycles or trailers towed by bicycles (though, monouri were already equipped with cooking facilities during the Edo period,) and from around 1926 to 1974, monouri were widely seen here and there in Japan by changing their items (Japanese style hotchpotch and sweets bread replaced sushi and soba); at present, however, monouri including those who sell tofu (bean curd), natto (fermented soybeans), and goldfish, the items which were already sold in the Edo period, are fading out.</e>
<cmt>「近年」の訳を修正しました。和暦を西暦に直しました。「おでん」の訳をイギリス英語からアメリカ英語のつづりに修正しました。文法の修正と、不足していた訳を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In recent years, more and more monouri not only advanced in appearance but also got equipped with enhanced cooking facilities on their bicycles or trailers towed by bicycles (though, monouri were already equipped with cooking facilities during the Edo period,) and from around 1926 to 1974, monouri were widely seen here and there in Japan by changing their items (Japanese style hotchpotch and sweets bread replaced sushi and soba); at present, however, monouri including those who sell tofu (bean curd), natto (fermented soybeans), and goldfish, the items which were already sold in the Edo period, are fading out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>しかし現在では自動車に設備を載せ決まった場所（就労者は多いが外食産業や商店の無い所など）で食事や弁当やパンなどを調理、販売をしているものも見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These days, however, there are businesses serving foods, selling box lunch, bread, and the like by cooking them in front of the customers on the equipped automobiles at the fixed places where a lot of workers are being around but few restaurants and food shops are in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These days, however, there are businesses serving foods, selling box lunch, bread, and the like by cooking them in front of customers on the equipped automobiles at the fixed places where a lot of workers are being around but few restaurants and food shops are in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These days, however, there are businesses serving foods, selling box lunch, bread, and the like by cooking them in front of customers on the equipped automobiles at the fixed places where a lot of workers are being around but few restaurants and food shops are in the neighborhood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また高齢化社会に伴い利潤のみならず地域振興や福祉目的を持って幾つかの小さな企業が、物売りとして豆腐などの大豆食品を呼び込みのラッパを使うなど、昔ながらの形態で販売を始めている地域も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Japanese society is aging, several small businesses have launched traditional style monouri using a whistle for attracting customers for selling tofu curds and processed-soybean products in some regions not only for aiming at the pursuit of profits but also the promotion of regional development and welfare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Japanese society is aging, several small businesses have launched traditional style monouri using a whistle for attracting customers for selling tofu curds and processed-soybean products in some regions not only for the pursuit of profits but also for the promotion of regional development and welfare.</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Japanese society is aging, several small businesses have launched traditional style monouri using a whistle for attracting customers for selling tofu curds and processed-soybean products in some regions not only for the pursuit of profits but also for the promotion of regional development and welfare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="13">
<j>物売りの種類と売り声や鳴り物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Variations of call and musical instrument used by monouri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Variations of goods old by monouri and their calls and musical instruments</e>
<cmt>自然な訳になるように修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Variations of goods old by monouri and their calls and musical instruments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>食事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foods</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foods</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>鮨屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sushiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sushi vendors</e>
<cmt>「屋」をvendorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sushi vendors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>---江戸前寿司の始まりは、物売りや屋台であったので今でも名残として立ち食いの鮨屋も東京を中心にみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since edomae-zushi originated from monouri and food stalls, still the original style can be seen in some sushi restaurants around Tokyo as their stand-and-eat bars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since edomae-zushi (hand-rolled sushi) originated from monouri and food stalls, still the original style can be seen in some sushi restaurants around Tokyo as their stand-and-eat bars.</e>
<cmt>江戸前寿司の説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since edomae-zushi (hand-rolled sushi) originated from monouri and food stalls, still the original style can be seen in some sushi restaurants around Tokyo as their stand-and-eat bars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>夜鳴き蕎麦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonaki-soba</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonaki-soba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonaki-soba</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>---呼子といわれる笛を吹いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They blew a whistle called Yobuko.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They blew a whistle called Yobuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They blew a whistle called Yobuko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>宵に笛を吹きながら商売したので「夜鳴き蕎麦」とよばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As they served boiled buckwheat noodles in the evening by blowing a whistle, they were called &apos;Yonaki soba&apos; (lit. evening vendor of noodles.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As they served boiled buckwheat noodles in the evening by blowing a whistle, they were called &apos;Yonaki (night cry) soba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「夜泣き蕎麦」の訳は上記で出てきましたので、「夜泣き」の説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As they served boiled buckwheat noodles in the evening by blowing a whistle, they were called &apos;Yonaki (night cry) soba.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>日本蕎麦はなくなり中華蕎麦（ラーメン）になり、笛もチャルメラという物に変わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their items were changed from Japanese buckwheat noodles to Chinese noodles called larmen and a flute called charumera replaced the whistle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their items were changed from Japanese buckwheat noodles to Chinese noodles called ramen and a flute called charumera replaced the whistle.</e>
<cmt>ラーメンのスペルを変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their items were changed from Japanese buckwheat noodles to Chinese noodles called ramen and a flute called charumera replaced the whistle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="21">
<j>ウナギ売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unagi-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unagi (eel) vendors</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unagi (eel) vendors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>---江戸時代当初は生をその場で捌いて客に渡したが、その後蒲焼にした物を売ったり、その場で調理するものもあらわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, the eel vendor, in the their early period, cut open and cleaned the raw eel in front of the customers and sold it, and later, some of them began to sell broiled eel or cook the eel in front of the customers and sold it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, eel vendors, in their early period, cut open and cleaned raw eels in front of customers and sold them, and later, some of them began to sell broiled eels or cook eels in front of customers and sold them.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, eel vendors, in their early period, cut open and cleaned raw eels in front of customers and sold them, and later, some of them began to sell broiled eels or cook eels in front of customers and sold them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>割り箸は鰻屋の発案で引き割り箸といった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The disposable wooden chopsticks were devised by the eel vendor and called hikiwaribashi in those days instead of waribashi at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disposable wooden chopsticks were devised by eel vendors and called hikiwaribashi in those days instead of waribashi at present.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disposable wooden chopsticks were devised by eel vendors and called hikiwaribashi in those days instead of waribashi at present.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="24">
<j>賄い屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Makanaiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Makanai (meal) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Makanai (meal) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>---江戸は女性の比率が二割といわれ独身の男性が非常に多く、宮使いで制約の多かった下級武士の専門の弁当屋として成り立っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that female accounted for only 20 percent and unmarried males occupied large part of the population of Edo city; in those circumstances, makanaiya was a paying business as box lunch shops with lower-ranking samurai, who served as the government officials under many restrictions, as customers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that female accounted for only 20 percent and unmarried males occupied large part of the population of Edo city; in those circumstances, makanai vendors sold box lunches to lower-ranking samurai, who served as the government officials under many restrictions.</e>
<cmt>paying businessは不適切だと思いましたので削除しました。自然な文章になるように修正をしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that female accounted for only 20 percent and unmarried males occupied large part of the population of Edo city; in those circumstances, makanai vendors sold box lunches to lower-ranking samurai, who served as the government officials under many restrictions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="26">
<j>おでん売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oden-uri (Japanese style hodgepodge vendor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oden-uri (Japanese style hotchpotch vendor)</e>
<cmt>「おでん」の訳をイギリス英語からアメリカ英語のつづりに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oden-uri (Japanese style hotchpotch vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>---昭和40年代まで日本各地にみられ、晩のおかずに主婦が鍋を持って買いに来たり、子どもがおやつとして買っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the 40s of Showa period (1974), oden-uri was popular with housewives who brought their pots to buy oden for dinner and with children who buy it for their afternoon snacks.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until about 1974, oden-uri was popular with housewives who brought their pots to buy oden for dinner and with children who buy it for their afternoon snacks.</e>
<cmt>和暦を西暦に直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until about 1974, oden-uri was popular with housewives who brought their pots to buy oden for dinner and with children who buy it for their afternoon snacks.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="28">
<j>菓子</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confectionery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confectionery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confectionery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>飴売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ame-uri (candy vendor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ame-uri (candy vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ame-uri (candy vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>---多種多様な飴売りが存在し競争も激しかった為、今の出店や夜店の的屋の元になる、くじ形式や余興や口上などで趣向を凝らしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various types of candy vendors competed fiercely; some sold candy by using lotteries, some attracted the customers with their entertainments, and some sold candies by delivering sales pitch, from all of which street stalls and night stalls called tekiya derived later.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various types of candy vendors competed so fiercely that some sold candies by using lotteries, some attracted customers with entertainments, and some sold candies by delivering sales pitch, from which derived mountebanks called tekiya in present street stalls and night stalls.</e>
<cmt>的屋の解釈に誤解がありましたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various types of candy vendors competed so fiercely that some sold candies by using lotteries, some attracted customers with entertainments, and some sold candies by delivering sales pitch, from which derived mountebanks called tekiya in present street stalls and night stalls.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>鼈甲飴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bekkoame</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bekkoame candy</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bekkoame candy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>---練る飴細工も有名だが、鼈甲飴も溶かした飴を型などに流し込み、様々な形を平面的に作り上げて、売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Comparable to popular Amezaiku, which was candy craft made from taffy, Bekkoame was made by molding melted candy into various flat shapes and sold it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Comparable to popular Amezaiku, which was candy craft made from taffy, Bekkoame candy was made by molding melted candy into various flat shapes and sold.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。鼈甲飴にcandyを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Comparable to popular Amezaiku, which was candy craft made from taffy, Bekkoame candy was made by molding melted candy into various flat shapes and sold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="33">
<j>飴細工</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amezaiku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amezaiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amezaiku</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>---鋏（はさみ）や指先を使い飴を練って三次元的な立体造形の飴を作って売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor created sculptures out of taffy with his hands and scissors and sold them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors created three dimensional sculptures out of taffy with his hands and scissors and sold them.</e>
<cmt>「三次元的な」の訳を補いました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors created three dimensional sculptures out of taffy with his hands and scissors and sold them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>詳しくは飴細工を参照の事。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Amezaiku.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For further details, see &apos;Amezaiku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Amezaiku.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="36">
<j>揚げ団子売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agedango-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agedango (deep-fried dumpling) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agedango (deep-fried dumpling) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>---昭和初期ごろまで見られ、小麦粉を甘く味付けして中華菓子の様にその場で揚げて、主に子ども向けに売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agedango vendor, which were seen until the early Showa period, were deep-frying sweetened flour dumplings at the stall and sold them mainly to children.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agedango vendors, who were seen until the early Showa period, cooled deep-fried sweetened flour dumplings at the stall and sold them mainly to children.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agedango vendors, who were seen until the early Showa period, cooled deep-fried sweetened flour dumplings at the stall and sold them mainly to children.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="38">
<j>菓子パン売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kashipan-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kashipan (sweet bread) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kashipan (sweet bread) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>---手に持ったベルを鳴らしながら呼び込みをした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor attracted the customers with his calls and sounds of bell in hand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors attracted customers with his calls and sounds of bell in hand.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors attracted customers with his calls and sounds of bell in hand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>リヤカーの上にガラスケースの棚を作り商品を並べて売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold sweet bread displayed in a glass case on his two-wheeled street vendor cart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors sold sweet bread displayed in a glass case on his two-wheeled street vendor cart.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors sold sweet bread displayed in a glass case on his two-wheeled street vendor cart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="41">
<j>焼芋屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yakiimoya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yakiimo (baked sweet potato) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yakiimo (baked sweet potato) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>---「やきいもーやきいもー栗よりうまい十三里ー」栗より美味い十三里と言う文言は「栗」を九里と「より」を四里とを足して焼き芋のことを十三里というなぞかけ言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold baked sweet potatoes by shouting &apos;Sweet Potatoes! Sweet Potatoes! It&apos;s 13 miles, 4 miles more delicious than 9 miles!&apos;, which is wordplay meaning that sweet potatoes are more delicious (&apos;more&apos; is synonym of &apos;4 Japanese miles&apos;) than chestnuts (synonym of &apos;9 miles&apos;.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors sold baked sweet potatoes by shouting &apos;Sweet Potatoes! Sweet Potatoes! It&apos;s 13 ri (old Japanese unit of distance), 4 ri more delicious than 9 ri!,&apos; which is a wordplay meaning that sweet potatoes are more delicious (&apos;more&apos; is synonym of &apos;4 ri&apos;) than chestnuts (synonym of &apos;9 ri&apos;.)</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。里をmileからriに変え、説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors sold baked sweet potatoes by shouting &apos;Sweet Potatoes! Sweet Potatoes! It&apos;s 13 ri (old Japanese unit of distance), 4 ri more delicious than 9 ri!,&apos; which is a wordplay meaning that sweet potatoes are more delicious (&apos;more&apos; is synonym of &apos;4 ri&apos;) than chestnuts (synonym of &apos;9 ri&apos;.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="43">
<j>食材</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Foodstuffs</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Foodstuffs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Foodstuffs</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>蜆浅蜊売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shijimi asari-uri (Clam vendor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shijimi asari-uri (Clam vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shijimi asari-uri (Clam vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>---「しじみーあさりー」この他にも蛤や赤貝なども専門で売られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor usually sold corbicula and short-neck clam by shouting &apos;Corbicula! Short-neck clam!&apos;, but some of them specialized in other clams like cherry stone clam or ark shell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendor usually sold corbicula and short-neck clam by shouting &apos;Corbicula! Short-neck clam!&apos;, but some of them specialized in other clams like cherry stone clam or ark shell.</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendor usually sold corbicula and short-neck clam by shouting &apos;Corbicula! Short-neck clam!&apos;, but some of them specialized in other clams like cherry stone clam or ark shell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="46">
<j>鰯売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iwashi-uri (Sardine vendor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iwashi-uri (Sardine vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iwashi-uri (Sardine vendor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>---売り声「いわしこーいわしこー」「いわし」は真鰯で「しこ」はカタクチイワシのことで獲れたてを海浜近郊で売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor was called sardine vendor but it sold fresh anchovy in towns neighboring the seashore by shouting &apos;Anchovy! Anchovy!&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors sold fresh sardine and anchovy in towns neighboring the seashore by shouting &apos;Sardine and Anchovy! Sardine and Anchovy!&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。解釈に誤解がありましたので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors sold fresh sardine and anchovy in towns neighboring the seashore by shouting &apos;Sardine and Anchovy! Sardine and Anchovy!&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>魚は他にも、鯨、初鰹、烏賊、白魚、秋刀魚、鯵など旬の物も売られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold other fishes in season including whale meat, bonito, cuttlefish, whitebait, saury, and horse mackerel.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendor sold other fishes in season including whale meat, the season&apos;s first bonito, cuttlefish, whitebait, saury, and horse mackerel.</e>
<cmt>初鰹の訳を単語リストに揃えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendor sold other fishes in season including whale meat, the season&apos;s first bonito, cuttlefish, whitebait, saury, and horse mackerel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="49">
<j>納豆売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Natto-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Natto vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Natto vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>---売り声「なっとー、なっとなっとうー、なっと」江戸時代から続いていたが近年では主に自転車に品物を積み販売していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold fermented soybeans from the Edo period by shouting &apos;Natto! Natto!&apos;, recently mostly with a bicycle carrying the goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors sold fermented soybeans from the Edo period by shouting &apos;Natto! Natto!,&apos; and recently they carried the products mainly on a bicycle.</e>
<cmt>言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors sold fermented soybeans from the Edo period by shouting &apos;Natto! Natto!,&apos; and recently they carried the products mainly on a bicycle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>江戸では上記の蜆浅蜊売りとともにポピュラーな存在で､「納豆と蜆に朝寝起こされる」などという川柳も残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo period, Natto-uri was popular with the clam vendor so that the vendors were the subjects of satirical short poem &apos;Natto vendor and Clam vendor alarmed me when I was sleeping in.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, Natto vendors were popular along with the clam vendors so that there remains a satirical short poem, &apos;Natto and Clam wake me up in the morning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>川柳の部分の訳を変更しました。ご検討ください。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, Natto vendors were popular along with the clam vendors so that there remains a satirical short poem, &apos;Natto and Clam wake me up in the morning.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="52">
<j>豆腐売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tofu-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tofu vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tofu vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>---ラッパを使い「とーふー」と聞こえる様に吹いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold bean-curds with distinguished notes of pipe that sounded like shouting &apos;Tofu!&apos; (bean-curd.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendor sold bean-curds with distinguished notes of pipe that sounded like shouting &apos;Tofu!&apos; (bean-curd.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendor sold bean-curds with distinguished notes of pipe that sounded like shouting &apos;Tofu!&apos; (bean-curd.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>行商の色合いが強い地域もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some regions, tofu vendor was much more like itinerant vendor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some regions, tofu vendors were much more like peddlers.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。行商の訳を前述のpeddlerに揃えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some regions, tofu vendors were much more like peddlers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="55">
<j>青果など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fruits and vegetables</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fruits and vegetables</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fruits and vegetables</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>---蜜柑、西瓜や大根、蕪（かぶ）、ヤマノイモ、生姜など野菜や果物を季節ごとに販売していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were vendors selling fruits and vegetables in season like mandarin orange, watermelon, radish, turnip, yam, and ginger.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were vendors selling fruits and vegetables in season like mandarin orange, watermelon, radish, turnip, yam, and ginger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were vendors selling fruits and vegetables in season like mandarin orange, watermelon, radish, turnip, yam, and ginger.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="57">
<j>生活用品の修理、販売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Repair and selling of daily commodities</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Repair and sales of daily commodities</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Repair and sales of daily commodities</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>定斎屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josaiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josaiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josaiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>---昭和30年頃まで存在したといわれ、江戸時代の物売りそのままの装束で半纏（はんてん）を身にまとい、天秤棒で薬箱を両端に掛け担いで漢方薬を売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Josaiya was around until 1955, selling Chinese herbal drugs by carrying them in a pair of medicine chests on a pole; the vendor wore a traditional jacket as monouri did during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Josai vendors were around until 1955, selling Chinese herbal drugs by carrying them in a pair of medicine chests on a pole and they wore the same hanten (a short coat originally for craftsmen worn over a kimono) as monouri in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>半纏の訳を単語リストに揃えました。言い回しを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Josai vendors were around until 1955, selling Chinese herbal drugs by carrying them in a pair of medicine chests on a pole and they wore the same hanten (a short coat originally for craftsmen worn over a kimono) as monouri in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また力強く一定の調子で歩いた為、薬箱と金具や天秤棒のぶつかり合う音が独特の音となり近隣に知らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josaiya walked strongly at a pace so that the medicine chests, their metal parts, and the pole were knocked against each other to make distinguished noises, by which the neighbors were aware of the vendor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josai vendors walked strongly at a pace so that the metal parts of their medicine chests and the pole knocked against each other to make distinguished noises, by which the neighbors were aware of the vendor.</e>
<cmt>自然な文章になるように語順を修正しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josai vendors walked strongly at a pace so that the metal parts of their medicine chests and the pole knocked against each other to make distinguished noises, by which the neighbors were aware of the vendor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="61">
<j>羅宇屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rauya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rau (bamboo stem of tobacco pipe) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rau (bamboo stem of tobacco pipe) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>---煙管の羅宇と呼ばれる部分のヤニとりや交換をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor cleaned out the resin from the bamboo stem of a Japanese long thin pipe, or exchanged the parts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors cleaned out resin from the bamboo stem of a Japanese long thin tobacco pipe or exchanged the parts.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors cleaned out resin from the bamboo stem of a Japanese long thin tobacco pipe or exchanged the parts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>小型のボイラーを積みその蒸気で掃除をし、また蒸気の出口に羅宇を被せ蒸気機関車の警笛の様に「ぴー」という音を出して知らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor loaded a small boiler for cleaning the pipe; the sounds like the steam locomotive whistles from the bamboo stem put on the steam rising from the exhaust vent of the boiler signaled the presence of rauya.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors loaded a small boiler to clean pipes with its steam and put the rau on top of the steam exhaust vent of the boiler to make a sound like the steam locomotive whistles to signal their presence.</e>
<cmt>自然な文章になるように語順を修正しました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors loaded a small boiler to clean pipes with its steam and put the rau on top of the steam exhaust vent of the boiler to make a sound like the steam locomotive whistles to signal their presence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>詳しくは煙管を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Kiseru.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For further details, see &apos;Kiseru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Kiseru.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="65">
<j>竿竹売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saodake-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saodake (bamboo pole) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saodake (bamboo pole) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>---売り声「さおやーさおだけー」本のタイトルにもなり注目を集めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor&apos;s call &apos;Saoya--, Saodake--&apos; (bamboo pole) recently became the book title and attracted the people&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendor&apos;s call &apos;Saoya--, Saodake--&apos; recently became the book title and attracted the people&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>タイトルで竿竹の説明をしましたので、この列では削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendor&apos;s call &apos;Saoya--, Saodake--&apos; recently became the book title and attracted the people&apos;s attention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="67">
<j>鋳掛屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikakeya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikakeya (a craftsman who fixes the metal pans or pots)</e>
<cmt>単語リストに揃えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikakeya (a craftsman who fixes the metal pans or pots)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>---金属製の鍋や釜の修理販売をしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold metal pots and pans and also repaired them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors sold metal pots and pans and also repaired them.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors sold metal pots and pans and also repaired them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>詳しくは鋳掛屋を参照のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Ikakeya.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For further details, see &apos;Ikakeya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For further details, see &apos;Ikakeya.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="70">
<j>金魚売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kingyo-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kingyo (goldfish) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kingyo (goldfish) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>---売り声「きんぎょーえー、きんぎょー」金魚とともにガラスの金魚鉢も売っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor sold goldfish and glass fish bowls by attracting the customers with the call &apos;Goldfish! Goldfish!&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors sold goldfish and glass fish bowls by attracting customers with the call &apos;Goldfish! Goldfish!&apos;</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors sold goldfish and glass fish bowls by attracting customers with the call &apos;Goldfish! Goldfish!&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>ちなみに江戸時代の金魚鉢は吊り下げ式で軒下などに吊るして下から観賞していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, people in the Edo period hung the glass fish bowl from the eaves and looked up the goldfish from below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, people in the Edo period hung the glass fish bowl from the eaves and looked up the goldfish from below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, people in the Edo period hung the glass fish bowl from the eaves and looked up the goldfish from below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="73">
<j>風鈴売り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furin-uri</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furin (wind chime) vendor</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furin (wind chime) vendor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>---風鈴の音色が呼び込みになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wind bell vendor attracted the customers with the sounds of the bells.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wind chime vendors attracted customers with the sound of the bells.</e>
<cmt>風鈴の訳を単語リストに揃えました。文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wind chime vendors attracted customers with the sound of the bells.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="75">
<j>買取</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Purchase</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Purchase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Purchase</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>古紙,古着,金物,番傘,屎尿,樽,桶,糠など様々で,江戸時代は最近の研究では,全ての時代の世界の中でも高い水準でのリサイクル社会であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor purchased wide variety of things including used paper, used clothes, metal utensils and fittings, coarse oil-paper umbrellas, human waste, used barrels, used wash tubs, and rice bran; according to a recent study, Japan was one of the most advanced society in recycling throughout the history in the whole world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors purchased wide variety of things including used papers, used clothes, metal utensils and fittings, coarse oil-paper umbrellas, human waste, used barrels, used wash tubs, and rice bran; according to a recent study, Japan was one of the most advanced society in recycling throughout the history of the whole world.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。文頭の「---」が数式になってしまうため、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors purchased wide variety of things including used papers, used clothes, metal utensils and fittings, coarse oil-paper umbrellas, human waste, used barrels, used wash tubs, and rice bran; according to a recent study, Japan was one of the most advanced society in recycling throughout the history of the whole world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="77">
<j>落ち買い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ochi-gai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ochi-gai (buyer of fallen hairs)</e>
<cmt>タイトルも意味が分かるように説明を補いました。落ち買いの定訳は不明です。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ochi-gai (buyer of fallen hairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>「おちゃない おちゃない」という呼び込みの声で抜け落ちた髪の毛を買い取っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vendor purchased lost hair by shouting &apos;Ochanai? Ochanai?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vendors purchased fallen hairs by shouting &apos;Ochanai? Ochanai?&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。「抜け落ちた髪の毛」の訳をfallen hairに修正しました。文頭の「---」が数式になってしまうため、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vendors purchased fallen hairs by shouting &apos;Ochanai? Ochanai?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>京都では女性の専業であり、髪文字屋（「かもじや」と読み、付け毛製作販売業）に買い取った髪の毛を卸していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Kyoto, the vendor was specialized to female and sold the purchased hair wholesale to a hairpiece maker and seller.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyoto, ochi-gai was exclusively women&apos;s work and they sold the purchased hairs wholesale to wig makers and sellers.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyoto, ochi-gai was exclusively women&apos;s work and they sold the purchased hairs wholesale to wig makers and sellers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>「落ちていないか」が「おちない」から「おちゃない」に変化したといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the call changed from &apos;Ochite inai ka?&apos; (Are there hair fallen?) to &apos;Ochanai? Ochanai?&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the call changed from &apos;Ochite inai ka?&apos; (Are there hair fallen?) to &apos;Ochanai? Ochanai?&apos;</e>
<cmt>余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the call changed from &apos;Ochite inai ka?&apos; (Are there hair fallen?) to &apos;Ochanai? Ochanai?&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Point136(id:211299), BoB774(id:148281), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), OSGS(id:102369), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>