<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>沢柳事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sawayanagi incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sawayanagi incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sawayanagi incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>沢柳事件（さわやなぎじけん）は、1913年から翌1914年にかけて京都帝国大学（現京都大学）で起こった、総長（学長）と学部教授会との間の内紛事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sawayanagi incident was an internal conflict occurred at Kyoto Imperial University (current Kyoto University) from 1913 to 1914 in which the president of university confronted with faculty councils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sawayanagi incident was an internal conflict that occurred at Kyoto Imperial University (current Kyoto University) from 1913 to 1914 in which the president of the university confronted the faculty council.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sawayanagi incident was an internal conflict that occurred at Kyoto Imperial University (current Kyoto University) from 1913 to 1914 in which the president of the university confronted the faculty council.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「京大事件」とも呼ばれ、大学における教授会自治を確立させるきっかけとなった事件として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Kyodai incident&quot; and a well-known incident that led to the establishment of faculty council autonomy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the &quot;Kyodai incident&quot; and a well-known incident that led to the establishment of faculty council autonomy.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the &quot;Kyodai incident&quot; and a well-known incident that led to the establishment of faculty council autonomy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>1913年7月、文部省の任命で就任して2ヵ月になったばかりの澤柳政太郎京都帝国大学総長は、教学の刷新を標榜して7教授（医科大学1名、理工科大学5名、文科大学1名）に辞表を提出させ8月に免官を発令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1913, the president of Kyoto Imperial University Masataro SAWAYANAGI, who was appointed by the Ministry of Education two months before, ordered seven professors (one for medical school, five for science and engineering school, one for literature school) to submit resignation letter calling for the renovation of education, and dismissed them in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1913, the president of Kyoto Imperial University Masataro SAWAYANAGI, who was appointed by the Ministry of Education two months before, ordered seven professors (one for the medical school, five for the science and engineering school, and one for the literature school) to submit resignation letters because they called for the education reform, and dismissed them in August.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1913, the president of Kyoto Imperial University Masataro SAWAYANAGI, who was appointed by the Ministry of Education two months before, ordered seven professors (one for the medical school, five for the science and engineering school, and one for the literature school) to submit resignation letters because they called for the education reform, and dismissed them in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このなかには、かねてから学内自治を主張していた谷本富文科大学（現・京大文学部）教授（教育学）が含まれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomeri TANIMOTO, a professor of literature school (current literature department of Kyoto University) (pedagogy) who had been advocating university autonomy for some time, was one of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomeri TANIMOTO, a professor of the literature school (current literature department of Kyoto University) (pedagogy) who had been advocating university autonomy for some time, was one of them.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomeri TANIMOTO, a professor of the literature school (current literature department of Kyoto University) (pedagogy) who had been advocating university autonomy for some time, was one of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>7教授罷免に際して京都帝大法科大学（現・京大法学部）の教授・助教授たちは仁保亀松学長（現在の学部長）を中心に結束し、教授の人事権は教授会にありと主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When they learned the dismissal of seven professors, professors/assistant professors of law school of Kyoto Imperial University (current law department of Kyoto University) stood together with the principlal of school (current dean) Kamematsu NIHO being in the center, arguing that the authority over the personal issues of professors should belong to faculty councils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When they learned of the dismissal of seven professors, professors/assistant professors of the law school of Kyoto Imperial University (current law department of Kyoto University) stood together with the principal of the school, (current dean) Kamematsu NIHO being in the center, arguing that authority over personal issues of professors should belong to faculty councils.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When they learned of the dismissal of seven professors, professors/assistant professors of the law school of Kyoto Imperial University (current law department of Kyoto University) stood together with the principal of the school, (current dean) Kamematsu NIHO being in the center, arguing that authority over personal issues of professors should belong to faculty councils.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>これに対し沢柳総長は、教授の地位を保つのはその実であって制度的保障はなく、また現行制度においても教授の任免に教授会の同意は必要でないと反論した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The president of university Sawayanagi countered their argument saying that the position of professor should be maintained by ones ability, rather than by the system, and that the approval of faculty council is not required for reshuffling professors even under existing system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The president of the university, Sawayanagi, countered their argument saying that the positions of professors should be maintained by ones ability, rather than by the system, and that the approval of the faculty council is not required for reshuffling professors even under the existing system.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The president of the university, Sawayanagi, countered their argument saying that the positions of professors should be maintained by ones ability, rather than by the system, and that the approval of the faculty council is not required for reshuffling professors even under the existing system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>総長と法科の対立は激化し、翌1914年1月になって法科教授・助教授は抗議の連帯辞職を敢行し、学生たちも教官を支持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With confrontation intensified between the president and the law school, professors/assistant professors of law school jointly resigned from their posts in January 1914, and students also supported them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When confrontation intensified between the president and the law school, professors/assistant professors of the law school jointly resigned from their posts in January 1914, and students also supported them.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When confrontation intensified between the president and the law school, professors/assistant professors of the law school jointly resigned from their posts in January 1914, and students also supported them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>東京帝国大学法科の首脳は京大法科を支持、当時の奥田義夫文部大臣も「教授ノ任免ニ付テハ総長カ職権ノ運用上教授会ト協定スルハ差支ナク且ツ妥当ナリ」と京大法科を支持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The head of the law school of Tokyo Imperial University supported the law school of Kyoto Imperial University, and then Minister for Education Yoshio OKUDA also supported the law school of Kyoto Imperial University by saying &quot;in the case of the appointment and dismissal of professors, it is all right and appropriate for the president to conclude the agreement with faculty councils&quot;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The head of the law school of Tokyo Imperial University supported the law school of Kyoto Imperial University, and then Minister for Education Yoshio OKUDA also supported the law school of Kyoto Imperial University by saying &quot;in the case of the appointment and dismissal of professors, it is all right and appropriate for the president to conclude the agreement with faculty councils.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The head of the law school of Tokyo Imperial University supported the law school of Kyoto Imperial University, and then Minister for Education Yoshio OKUDA also supported the law school of Kyoto Imperial University by saying &quot;in the case of the appointment and dismissal of professors, it is all right and appropriate for the president to conclude the agreement with faculty councils.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>その結果、教官たちは辞表を撤回した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, professors etc. withdrew their resignation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, professors etc. withdrew their resignation.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, professors etc. withdrew their resignation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>このため同年4月、進退窮まった沢柳総長は辞職に追い込まれた（後任総長は山川健次郎東京帝大総長が兼任した）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under such circumstances, president of university Sawayanagi was driven into a corner and was forced to resign from his post in April of the same year (Kenjiro YAMAKAWA, the president of Tokyo Imperial University, was concurrently appointed as a successor).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under such circumstances, the president of the university, Sawayanagi, was driven into a corner and was forced to resign from his post in April of the same year (Kenjiro YAMAKAWA, the president of Tokyo Imperial University, was concurrently appointed as a successor).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under such circumstances, the president of the university, Sawayanagi, was driven into a corner and was forced to resign from his post in April of the same year (Kenjiro YAMAKAWA, the president of Tokyo Imperial University, was concurrently appointed as a successor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>意義</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Significance of the incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Significance of the incident</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Significance of the incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>教官の人事権を事実上教授会が掌握するという慣行を文相が承認したことで、学問の自由大学の自治は大きく前進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the Minister for Education approved a practice under which fuculty councils held the essential authority over personell issues of professors, academic freedom as well as university autonomy became solid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the Minister for Education approved a practice under which faculty councils held essential authority over personnel issues of professors, academic freedom as well as university autonomy became solid.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the Minister for Education approved a practice under which faculty councils held essential authority over personnel issues of professors, academic freedom as well as university autonomy became solid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>また京大では沢柳総長辞任の1年後、荒木寅三郎医学部教授を総長として選出、以降総長の学内選出が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One year after the resignation of Sawayanagi, Torasaburo ARAKI, a professor f Medical Department, was selected as the president of Kyoto Imperial University, and since then successive presidents were selected from among professors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One year after the resignation of Sawayanagi, Torasaburo ARAKI, a professor of the Medical Department, was selected as the president of Kyoto Imperial University, and since then successive presidents were selected from among professors.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One year after the resignation of Sawayanagi, Torasaburo ARAKI, a professor of the Medical Department, was selected as the president of Kyoto Imperial University, and since then successive presidents were selected from among professors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>沢柳事件の経緯と結末により「大学自治の本山」とみなされた京大は、1930年代以降、戦時体制のもとで大学への統制を進めようとする勢力からは敵視されるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyoto Imperial Univesity, which was regarded as &quot;the center of university autonomy&quot; thanks to the development and conclusion of Sawayanagi incident, came to be regarded as an enemy by people who intended to place universities under government&apos;s control under the wartime regime in 1930&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyoto Imperial University, which was regarded as &quot;the center of university autonomy&quot; thanks to the development and conclusion of the Sawayanagi incident, came to be regarded as an enemy by people who intended to place universities under the government&apos;s control under the wartime regime in 1930&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyoto Imperial University, which was regarded as &quot;the center of university autonomy&quot; thanks to the development and conclusion of the Sawayanagi incident, came to be regarded as an enemy by people who intended to place universities under the government&apos;s control under the wartime regime in 1930&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>スペース</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>こうしたことが、滝川事件に見られる教授会自治への攻撃につながったとする見解もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say that the above led to the attack on the autonomy of faculty council, which was seen in Takigawa incident.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say that the above led to the attack on the autonomy of faculty council, which was seen in the Takigawa incident.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say that the above led to the attack on the autonomy of faculty council, which was seen in the Takigawa incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>