<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>青苗簿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seibyobo (the register of standing crops)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seibyobo (the register of standing crops)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seibyobo (the register of standing crops)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>青苗簿（せいびょうぼ）とは、律令制において実際の田地の耕作状況を記した帳簿のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seibyobo (the register of standing crops) refers to an account book recording the actual conditions of cultivation of rice field in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seibyobo (the register of standing crops) refers to an account book recording the actual conditions of cultivation of rice field in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seibyobo (the register of standing crops) refers to an account book recording the actual conditions of cultivation of rice field in the Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>律令制においては、農民に口分田が与えられていたが、実際には逃亡などで耕作されない土地や逆に定まった耕作者が元からおらず賃租が行われている土地も存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system, kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) was given to each farmer, but in fact, there also existed lands which were not cultivated due to runaway and so on, or on which chinso (land taxes under the Ritsuryo system) was imposed by reason that there were no specific cultivators from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Ritsuryo system, kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) was given to each farmer, but in fact, there also existed lands which were not cultivated due to escape of farmers and so on, or on the contrary, on which chinso (land taxes under the Ritsuryo system) was imposed despite there were no specific cultivators from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>わかりやすくするために、runaway ⇒　escape of farmers　に訂正しました。 また、逆に（on the contrary)の役を加え、自然な流れにするために、by reason that を　despiteに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Ritsuryo system, kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system) was given to each farmer, but in fact, there also existed lands which were not cultivated due to escape of farmers and so on, or on the contrary, on which chinso (land taxes under the Ritsuryo system) was imposed despite there were no specific cultivators from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そのため、税収見込みの計算や災害時の課役免除の実施のために実際の耕作状況を把握する必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it was necessary to grasp the actual conditions of cultivation in order to calculate anticipated tax yields, and to implement an exemption from distribution of assignments when a disaster occurred.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it was necessary to grasp the actual conditions of cultivation in order to calculate anticipated tax yields, and to implement an exemption from distribution of assignments at the time of disaster.</e>
<cmt>災害時を簡潔に、at the time of disaster に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it was necessary to grasp the actual conditions of cultivation in order to calculate anticipated tax yields, and to implement an exemption from distribution of assignments at the time of disaster.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そのために作られたのが、青苗簿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What was created for the above purpose was seibyobo (the register of standing crops).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What was created for the above purpose was seibyobo.</e>
<cmt>(the register of standing crops)　一度出てきているので、削除しても良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What was created for the above purpose was seibyobo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>日本では養老元年（717年）に青苗簿式が制定され、諸国に青苗簿を作成させ、口分田や賃租に出された田地、乗田などについて調査が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan, seibyobo-shiki (codes and regulations on seibyobo (the register of standing crops)) was established in 717, each province was ordered to create seibyobo (the register of standing crops), and surveys on kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system), rice fields provided for chinso, joden (surplus fields) and so on came to be conducted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan, seibyobo-shiki (codes and regulations on seibyobo) was established in 717, each province was ordered to create seibyobo, and surveys on kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system), rice fields provided for chinso, joden (surplus fields) and so on came to be conducted.</e>
<cmt>(the register of standing crops)　一度出てきているので、削除しても良いと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan, seibyobo-shiki (codes and regulations on seibyobo) was established in 717, each province was ordered to create seibyobo, and surveys on kubunden (rice fields given to each farmer in the Ritsuryo system), rice fields provided for chinso, joden (surplus fields) and so on came to be conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>