<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>能勢氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Nose clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Nose clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the Nose clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>能勢氏（のせし）は、摂津国（北摂地方）の大身領主。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nose clan was a taishin ryoshu (noble land owner) in Settsu Province (Hokusetsu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nose clan was a taishin ryoshu (noble land owner) in Settsu Province (Hokusetsu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nose clan was a taishin ryoshu (noble land owner) in Settsu Province (Hokusetsu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>清和源氏源頼光流を称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They claimed that they followed MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They claimed to have followed MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They claimed to have followed MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu line of Seiwa-Genji (Minamoto clan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>「能瀬」・「野瀬」・「能世」など複数の表記が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nose&apos; is written in several patterns of kanji such as &apos;能瀬,&apos; &apos;野瀬,&apos; &apos;能世&apos; and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nose&apos; is written in several patterns of kanji such as &apos;能瀬,&apos; &apos;野瀬,&apos; &apos;能世.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nose&apos; is written in several patterns of kanji such as &apos;能瀬,&apos; &apos;野瀬,&apos; &apos;能世.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&apos;能世.の後に&apos;を付加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>家紋は切竹矢筈十字、獅子牡丹など。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their family crest has several designs such as &apos;kiritake yahazu juji (cross of bamboo and nock), Sishi-Botan (lion and peony) and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their family crest has several designs such as &apos;kiritake yahazu juji (cross of bamboo and nock), Sishi-Botan (lion and peony).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their family crest has several designs such as &apos;kiritake yahazu juji (cross of bamboo and nock), Shishi-Botan (lion and peony).</e>
<cmt>SishiをShishiに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>発祥</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Origin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>能勢氏は摂津源氏の流れを汲む一族で、源頼光の玄孫・源国基を祖とするが、多田源氏の惣領であった源頼盛の三男・能瀬高頼の後裔であるともいう（『尊卑分脈』の記述によると国基の後裔は田尻、高頼の後裔は倉垣を本拠としていたものと推察される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nose clan follows Settsu Genji having MINAMOTO no Kunimoto, a great-great-grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu as their ancestor, while they are said to have been the descendant of Takayori NOSE, the third son of MINAMOTO no Yorimori, who was the successor of Tada-Genji (according to the description from &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku,&quot; Kunimoto&apos;s descendants were based in Tajiri and Takayori&apos;s were in Kuragaki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nose clan follows Settsu Genji having MINAMOTO no Kunimoto, a great-great-grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu as their ancestor, while they are said to have been the descendant of Takayori NOSE, the third son of MINAMOTO no Yorimori, the successor of Tada-Genji (according to the description from &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku,&quot; Kunimoto&apos;s descendants were based in Tajiri and Takayori&apos;s were in Kuragaki).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nose clan follows Settsu Genji having MINAMOTO no Kunimoto, a great-great-grandson of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu as their ancestor, while they are said to have been the descendant of Takayori NOSE, the third son of MINAMOTO no Yorimori, the successor of Tada-Genji (according to the description from &quot;Sonpi Bunmyaku,&quot; Kunimoto&apos;s descendants were based in Tajiri and Takayori&apos;s were in Kuragaki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>源満仲以来の本拠地である多田に隣接する能勢地方は古くから源氏一族とも関係の深い土地であったと考えられ、能勢氏や地元の伝承などによると源頼光の長子・源頼国が最初に入部し開発したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lying next to Tada, which was the home to the Minamoto clan since the time of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, Nose region is considered to have been closely related to the Minamoto clan and according to the local and the Nose clan&apos;s tradition, MINAMOTO no Yorikuni, the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, first entered this place and exploited it</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lying next to Tada, which was the home to the Minamoto clan since the time of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, the Nose region is considered to have been closely related to the Minamoto clan and according to the local and the Nose clan&apos;s tradition, MINAMOTO no Yorikuni, the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, first entered this place and exploited it</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lying next to Tada, which was the home to the Minamoto clan since the time of MINAMOTO no Mitsunaka, the Nose region is considered to have been closely related to the Minamoto clan and according to the local and the Nose clan&apos;s tradition, MINAMOTO no Yorikuni, the eldest son of MINAMOTO no Yorimitsu, first entered this place and exploited it</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかし、現在のところ頼国と能勢を関連付ける史料は確認されておらず、能勢氏の直接の祖とされる国基は平安時代後期から末期にかけての人物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, no historical material that associates Yorikuni with Nose has been found by now, so Kunimoto, who is said to be the direct ancestor of the Nose clan, was a figure who lived from the late to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, no historical material that associates Yorikuni with Nose has been found by now, so Kunimoto, who is said to be the direct ancestor of the Nose clan, was a figure who lived from the late to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, no historical material that associates Yorikuni with Nose has been found by now, so Kunimoto, who is said to be the direct ancestor of the Nose clan, was a figure who lived from the late to the end of the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>しかし太田亮は摂津源氏は仮冒で古代能勢郡領家の後裔としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Akira OTA had it that they had only assumed the name of Settsu Genji and that they had been the descendant of the lord of the manor in Nose District in ancient times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Akira OTA stated they only assumed the name of Settsu Genji and had actually been the descendant of the lord of the manor in Nose District in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Akira OTA stated they only assumed the name of Settsu Genji and had actually been the descendant of the lord of the manor in Nose District in ancient times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>高頼の子孫とする系図は裏付けがなく、国基の系統も所伝や系譜が諸説ありはっきりしていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family tree saying that the Nose clan is the descendant of Takayori NOSE is not corroborated or the lineage of MINAMOTO no Kunimoto is not clear because it has other family trees and traditions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family tree showing that the Nose clan is a descendant of Takayori NOSE is not corroborated or the lineage of MINAMOTO no Kunimoto is not clear because it has other family trees and traditions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family tree showing that the Nose clan is a descendant of Takayori NOSE is not corroborated or the lineage of MINAMOTO no Kunimoto is not clear because it has other family trees and traditions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉・南北朝時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nose clan in the period of the Kamakura and Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nose clan during the Kamakura and Northern and Southern Courts period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nose clan during the Kamakura and Northern and Southern Courts period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>鎌倉時代に入ると国基の後裔は幕府の御家人となり、『吾妻鏡』建久6年（1195年）3月10日 (旧暦)条にある将軍家東大寺供養に随行する兵の中に「野瀬判官代」とその同族「安房判官代」の名がみえている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura period, the descendants of Kunimoto became gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) and on the entry dated April 28, 1195 of &quot;Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East),&quot; the names of &apos;Nose hogandai&apos; and his cognate, &apos;Awa hogandai&apos; are listed among soldiers who accompanied the group on a trip to memorial service for Shogun family at Todai-ji temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Kamakura period, descendants of Kunimoto became gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) and on an entry dated April 28, 1195 of &quot;Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East),&quot; the names of &apos;Nose hogandai&apos; and his cognate, &apos;Awa hogandai&apos; are listed among soldiers who accompanied the group on a trip to memorial service for Shogun family at Todai-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Kamakura period, descendants of Kunimoto became gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) and on an entry dated April 28, 1195 of &quot;Azuma Kagami (The Mirror of the East),&quot; the names of &apos;Nose hogandai&apos; and his cognate, &apos;Awa hogandai&apos; are listed among soldiers who accompanied the group on a trip to memorial service for Shogun family at Todai-ji temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>そして、承久の乱では摂津守護大内惟信や同族の多田基綱のほか畿内の武士の多くが京方に属して敗れたが、能勢氏は幕府方に属したとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in the Jokyu war while many of samurais in Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) such as Korenobu OUCHI, the shugo of Settsu Province and his cognate Mototsuna TADA and so on joined the army of Kyoto side and were defeated, the Nose clan are said to have been on the part of Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then in the Jokyu war while many samurais in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) such as Korenobu OUCHI, the shugo of Settsu Province and his cognate Mototsuna TADA joined the army on the Kyoto side and were defeated, the Nose clan are said to have been on the side of theShogunate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then in the Jokyu war while many samurais in the Kinai region (provinces surrounding Kyoto and Nara) such as Korenobu OUCHI, the shugo of Settsu Province and his cognate Mototsuna TADA joined the army on the Kyoto side and were defeated, the Nose clan are said to have been on the side of the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>theとShogunateの間にスペースを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="12">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)には北朝 (日本)方として戦ったともされるが、南朝 (日本)方の武将であった多田頼貞の系譜を引くとも伝え明確でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they were said to fight on the side of the Northern Court, but that is not clear because they were said to belong to the genealogy of Yorisada TADA, who was a busho (Japanese military commander) on the Southern side (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they were said to fight on the side of the Northern Court, but that is not clear because they were said to belong to the genealogy of Yorisada TADA, who was a busho (Japanese military commander) on the Southern side (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they were said to fight on the side of the Northern Court, but that is not clear because they were said to belong to the genealogy of Yorisada TADA, who was a busho (Japanese military commander) on the Southern side (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>後醍醐天皇の忠臣であった多田頼貞は、建武の新政で摂津能勢郷の目代となり足利尊氏離反後には南朝方として各地を転戦したが劣勢により備前国で自害し、その子能勢頼仲の代で尊氏に仕えたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yorisada TADA, a loyal subject to Emperor Godaigo became mokudai (deputy provincial governor) in Settsu Nose village and after Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s estrangement, he moved from place to place to fight on the side of the Southern Court but killed himself in Bizen Province when his army got inferior, and after that, his son Yorinaka NOSE served Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yorisada TADA, a loyal subject to Emperor Godaigo became mokudai (deputy provincial governor) in Settsu Nose village and after Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s estrangement, he moved from place to place to fight on the side of the Southern Court, but killed himself in Bizen Province when his army was in an inferior position, and after that, his son Yorinaka NOSE served Takauji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yorisada TADA, a loyal subject to Emperor Godaigo became mokudai (deputy provincial governor) in Settsu Nose village and after Takauji ASHIKAGA&apos;s estrangement, he moved from place to place to fight on the side of the Southern Court, but killed himself in Bizen Province when his army was in an inferior position, and after that, his son Yorinaka NOSE served Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>室町・戦国時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">the Muromachi and the Sengoku (civil war) period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">the Muromachi and Sengoku (civil war) period</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">the Muromachi and Sengoku (civil war) period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="14">
<j>室町時代には幕府の奉公衆（番衆）に加えられ直参の御家人となり、摂津の有力国人へと成長する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Muromachi period being enrolled on the hokoshu (or banshu; the shogunal military guard), the Nose clan became gokenin (an immediate vassal of the shogunate) and grew into a powerful local lord in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Muromachi period being enrolled on the hokoshu (or banshu; the shogunal military guard), the Nose clan became gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) and grew into a powerful local lord in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Muromachi period being enrolled on the hokoshu (or banshu; the shogunal military guard), the Nose clan became gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) and grew into a powerful local lord in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また、摂津守護細川氏（京兆家）の被官としても行動し、応仁の乱では細川勝元に与し東軍として戦っており、能勢頼弘とその子能勢頼満が討死している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, they acted as vassals of the Hosokawa clan (Keicho family), Settsu no kami and when they fought against the East squad on the side of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA in the Onin War, Yorihiro NOSE and his son Yorimitsu NOSE were killed in it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, they acted as vassals of the Hosokawa clan (Keicho family), Settsu no kami and when they fought against the East squad on the side of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA in the Onin War, Yorihiro NOSE and his son Yorimitsu NOSE were killed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, they acted as vassals of the Hosokawa clan (Keicho family), Settsu no kami and when they fought against the East squad on the side of Katsumoto HOSOKAWA in the Onin War, Yorihiro NOSE and his son Yorimitsu NOSE were killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>戦国時代 (日本)となると、能勢の丸山城 (摂津国能勢郡)を本拠に芥川山城や山城国の今里城なども居城としてその勢力を拡げる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period (Japan), based at Maruyama-jo Castle in Nose (Nose-gun, Settsu Province), they extended power making Akutagawa-yama Castle, Imasato-jo Castle and so on their own.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Sengoku period (Japan), based at Maruyama-jo Castle in Nose (Nose-gun, Settsu Province), they extended power making Akutagawa-yama Castle, Imasato-jo Castle on their own.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Sengoku period (Japan), based at Maruyama-jo Castle in Nose (Nose-gun, Settsu Province), they extended power making Akutagawa-yama Castle, Imasato-jo Castle on their own.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>しかし、将軍家の近習であった経緯から織田信長には非協力的であったとされ、天正10年（1582年）の本能寺の変では能勢頼次が明智光秀方に加勢し、豊臣秀吉によって光秀が滅ぼされると頼次は能勢を追われ先祖多田頼貞に縁のある備前に潜伏したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, they are said to have taken the noncooperative stance toward Nobunaga ODA because they were attendants to Shogun, so at the Honnoji Incident in 1582 Yoritsugu NOSE supported Mitsuhide AKECHI and after Mitsuhide was destroyed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI Yoritsugu was forced from Nose and kept hidden in Bizen Province, which was associated with his ancestor Yorisada TADA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, they are said to have taken anoncooperative stance toward Nobunaga ODA because they were attendants to the Shogun, so at the Honnoji Incident in 1582 Yoritsugu NOSE supported Mitsuhide AKECHI and after Mitsuhide was destroyed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI Yoritsugu was forced from Nose and hid in Bizen Province, which was associated with his ancestor Yorisada TADA.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, they are said to have taken a no cooperative stance toward Nobunaga ODA because they were attendants to the Shogun, so at the Honnoji Incident in 1582 Yoritsugu NOSE supported Mitsuhide AKECHI and after Mitsuhide was destroyed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI Yoritsugu was forced from Nose and hid in Bizen Province, which was associated with his ancestor Yorisada TADA.</e>
<cmt>anoncooperativeを a　no cooperativeに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その後、能勢の地は秀吉に降伏した島津氏に在京賄料として与えられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, as the traveling and living cost in Kyoto the land of Nose was given to the Shimazu clan, who had surrendered to Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>定訳不明「在京賄料」territory given to daimyo as their traveling and living cost in Kyoto としました</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, for traveling and living cost in Kyoto the land of Nose was given to the Shimazu clan, who had surrendered to Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, for traveling and living cost in Kyoto the land of Nose was given to the Shimazu clan, who had surrendered to Hideyoshi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="19">
<j>秀吉の没後、能勢氏の伝承によると長年雌伏していた頼次は弟である東寺の僧金剛院 (僧)を介して徳川家康に召し出されたとされ、慶長4年（1599年）に能勢氏を小規模ながら再興する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died, according to the tradition of the Nose clan, Yoritsugu, who had hidden himself for a long time, is said to have been called by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA through his younger brother Priest Kongo-in at To-ji Temple, and small scale as it was he revived the Nose clan in 1599.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Hideyoshi died, according to the tradition of the Nose clan, Yoritsugu, who had hidden himself for a long time, is said to have been called by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA through his younger brother Priest Kongo-in at To-ji Temple, and small scale as it was, he revived the Nose clan in 1599.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Hideyoshi died, according to the tradition of the Nose clan, Yoritsugu, who had hidden himself for a long time, is said to have been called by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA through his younger brother Priest Kongo-in at To-ji Temple, and small scale as it was, he revived the Nose clan in 1599.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>そして、翌年の関ヶ原の戦いでは東軍として戦い、戦後西軍に属した島津氏より召し上げた能勢の所領5千4百石を与えられ旧領を回復することの成功した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in the Battle of Sekigahara, which took place the next year (1600), he fought on the side of the East Squad and after the battle he successfully regained his former territory when he was given the land of 5400 koku in Nose which was seized from the Shimazu clan, who had been on the side of the West Squad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then during the Battle of Sekigahara, which took place the following year (1600), he fought on the side of the East Squad and after the battle he successfully regained his former territory when he was given the land totaling 5400 koku in Nose which was seized from the Shimazu clan, who had been on the side of the West Squad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then during the Battle of Sekigahara, which took place the following year (1600), he fought on the side of the East Squad and after the battle he successfully regained his former territory when he was given the land totaling 5400 koku in Nose which was seized from the Shimazu clan, who had been on the side of the West Squad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>江戸時代以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>江戸時代に入ると頼次は旗本として家康に仕え、子孫は数家に分かれそれぞれ旗本家として存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period Yoritsugu served Ieyasu as hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), and his descendants branched into several families, each of which continued as hatamoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period Yoritsugu served Ieyasu as hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), and his descendants branched into several families, each continuing as hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period Yoritsugu served Ieyasu as hatamoto (direct retainers of the bakufu), and his descendants branched into several families, each continuing as hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>また、能勢の領地は累代の居城であった丸山城を廃して地黄陣屋を置き幕末に至るまで統治した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Maruyama-jo Castle, which had been a residential castle for the Nose clan for generations, was replaced with Jio jinya (residence for small clans) in the territory in Nose, which kept ruled by the Nose clan until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, Maruyama-jo Castle, that had been a residential castle for the Nose clan for generations, was replaced with Jio jinya (residence for small clans) in the territory in Nose, which continued to be ruled by the Nose clan until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, Maruyama-jo Castle, that had been a residential castle for the Nose clan for generations, was replaced with Jio jinya (residence for small clans) in the territory in Nose, which continued to be ruled by the Nose clan until the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>その知行は江戸時代を通して加増され、幕末には庶家を含め14家、総知行高は1万3千石を超えていたとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their chigyo (enfeoffment) was increased during the Edo period and in the end of the Edo period total Chigyo fief amount of 14 cognate families was said be more than 13000 koku including those of branch families.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their chigyo (enfeoffment) was increased during the Edo period and at the end of the Edo period total Chigyo fief amount of fourteen cognate families was said to be more than 13,000 koku including branch families.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their chigyo (enfeoffment) was increased during the Edo period and at the end of the Edo period total Chigyo fief amount of fourteen cognate families was said to be more than 13,000 koku including branch families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>現在、能勢氏の菩提寺である清普寺の境内に一族の墓所がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a graveyard of the Nose family in the precincts of Seifu-ji Temple, which is their family temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a graveyard for the Nose family in the precincts of Seifu-ji Temple, which is their family temple.</e>
<cmt>graammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a graveyard for the Nose family in the precincts of Seifu-ji Temple, which is their family temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 SuperTTS(id:221889), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>