<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>会合衆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Egoshu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Egoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Egoshu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>会合衆（えごうしゅう、かいごうしゅう）とは、室町時代から安土桃山時代の都市で自治の指導的役割を果たした評定組織またはその組織の構成員。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Egoshu (wealthy marchants who led self-governing organizations in cities from the Muromachi to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period)(会合衆)are consultative organizations or the term refers to the members of this organization which possessed a leading role in the self-government of cities from the Muromachi to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Egoshu (wealthy marchants who led self-governing organizations in cities from the Muromachi to the Azuchi-Momoyama Period)(会合衆)are consultating organizations or the term refers to the members of this organization which possessed a leading role in the self-government of cities from the Muromachi to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Egoshu (or Kaigoshu) (wealthy merchants who led self-governing organizations in cities from the Muromachi to the Azuchi-Momoyama period) are consultation organizations, or is a term that refers to the members of this organization which possessed a leading role in the self-government of cities from the Muromachi to the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>period を小文字にしました。文法、スペルを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>とくに堺市におけるものが有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially the one in Sakai City is famous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially the one in Sakai City is famous.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The example in Sakai City is especially famous.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>同じ時期に山田 (伊勢市)（伊勢国）、大湊 (伊勢市)（伊勢）、博多、酒田市などの都市にも類似した組織が見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around the same time, similar organizations were seen in cities such as Yamada (Ise City, Ise Province), Ominato (Ise City, Ise), Hakata or Sakata City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around the same time, similar organizations were seen in cities such as Yamada (Ise City, Ise Province), Ominato (Ise City, Ise), Hakata or Sakata City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around the same time, similar organizations were seen in cities such as Yamada (Ise City) (Ise Province), Ominato (Ise City) (Ise Province), Hakata or Sakata City.</e>
<cmt>大湊も　Ise Province としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outline</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outline</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>他の記事と統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>会合衆の名前の由来は、寺の集会（しゅうえ）にあったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Egoshu owes its name to Shue (gathering) at a temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Egoshu owes its name to Shue (gathering) at a temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Egoshu owes its name to Shue (gathering) at a temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>会合衆は、堺の有徳者（有力商人）で構成され、能登屋や臙脂屋（べにや）などの有力商人がその任にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Egoshu comprised good livers (influential merchants) in Sakai, and influential merchants such as Notoya and Beniya served as Egoshu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Egoshu comprised the affluent (influential merchants) in Sakai, and influential merchants such as Notoya and Beniya served as Egoshu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Egoshu comprised the affluent (influential merchants) in Sakai, and influential merchants such as Notoya and Beniya served as Egoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>堺で会合衆の名が初見されるのは季弘大叔の『蔗軒日録』で、1484年（文明16年）8月1日に三村社（開口神社）の祭礼で頭を務めたのが「会合衆内、カスエ（材木商・三宅主計）、イスミ（和泉）屋両人」と記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the &quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot; by Daishuku KIKO it is written that the name of Egoshu was first mentioned in Sakai, and it is written that &quot;both, the Kasueya (lumber dealer, Kazue MIYAKE) and the Isumiya (Izumiya) from among Egoshu members&quot; led the festival at Mimura-sha Shrine (Aguchi-jinja Shrine) on August 1st in 1484.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the &quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot; by Daishuku KIKO it is written that the name of Egoshu was first mentioned in Sakai, and it is written that &quot;both, the Kasueya (lumber dealer, Kazue MIYAKE) and the Isumiya (Izumiya) from among Egoshu members&quot; led the festival at Mimura-sha Shrine (Aguchi-jinja Shrine) on August 1st in 1484.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Egoshu first appears in Sakai City, in the &quot;Shaken nichiroku,&quot; a diary written by a Zen priest, Daishuku KIKO. It records that on August 1 in 1484, both the Kasueya (timber merchant, Kazue MIYAKE) and the Isumiya (Izumiya) from among the Egoshu members led the festival at Mimura-sha Shrine (Aguchi-jinja Shrine).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>会合衆の数は36人とされるが、文明 (日本)年間は10人と見える（『蔗軒日録』）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the number of Egoshu members was 36, but there were ten during the Bunmei era (&quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the number of Egoshu members was 36, but there were ten during the Bunmei era (&quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the number of Egoshu members was thirty-six, but there were ten during the Bunmei era (Japan) (&quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot;).</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、納屋衆（倉庫業）として10人が訴訟を評定した（『糸乱記』）とする資料もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, some accounts say that ten members as nayashu (warehousing business) were consulting on court cases (&quot;Shiranki&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some accounts say that ten members as nayashu (warehousing business) were consulting on court cases (&quot;Shiranki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some accounts say that ten members as nayashu (warehousing business) were consulting on court cases (&quot;Shiranki&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これらのことから、36人の会合衆の中でもとりわけ有力な者が10人の納屋衆であるとする向きが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore it is often said that the ten Nayashu were especially powerful among the 36 Egoshu members.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore it is often said that the ten Nayashu were especially powerful among the 36 Egoshu members.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore it is often said that the ten nayashu were especially powerful among the thirty-six Egoshu members.</e>
<cmt>数字をスペルアウトしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>堺は摂津国の堺荘と和泉国の堺南荘に分かれていたが、会合衆が集まる会所それぞれにあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai was divided into the Sakaisho region of Settsu Province and the Sakaiminamisho region of Izumi Province, and there were meeting places for Egoshu members in both regions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai was divided into the Sakaisho region of Settsu Province and the Sakaiminamisho region of Izumi Province, and there were meeting places for Egoshu members in both regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai was divided into the Sakaisho region of Settsu Province and the Sakaiminamisho region of Izumi Province, and there were meeting places for Egoshu members in both regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>堺荘では「北庄経堂」（『蔗軒日録』）とあるが場所は不明である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sakaisho region it was called &quot;Hokusho Kyodo&quot; (according to the &quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot;), but the location is unknown.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Sakaisho region it was called &quot;Hokusho Kyodo&quot; (according to the &quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot;), but the location is unknown.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Sakaisho region it was called &apos;Hokusho Kyodo&apos; (according to the &quot;Shaken nichiroku&quot;), but the location is unknown.</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>堺南荘の会所は、発掘調査などで開口神社境内の念仏寺（廃寺）にあったと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The meeting place of the Sakaiminamisho region has been determined through excavations etc. and is assumed to have been at Nenbutsu-ji Temple (abolished temple) on the precincts of Aguchi-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meeting place of the Sakaiminamisho region has been determined through excavations etc. and is assumed to have been at the Nenbutsu-ji Temple (abolished temple) on the precincts of Aguchi-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meeting place of the Sakaiminamisho region has been determined through excavations etc. and is assumed to have been at the Nenbutsu-ji Temple (abolished temple) on the precincts of Aguchi-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>類似制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar systems</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar systems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar systems</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>同じころ、伊勢の山田には年寄による自治制度（山田三方）があったほか、伊勢の大湊にも会合衆による自治組織が、また博多は12人の年行司が町を治め、庄内酒田には町政を取り仕切った三十六人衆がいるなど、それぞれの都市に応じた制度で自治が行われた</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same period there was a self-government system led by elders in Yamada in Ise (Yamadasanpo), and a self-government organisation of Egoshu in Ominato in Ise, while in Hakata 12 Nengyoji were ruling the city and in Shonai Sakata the Sanju-roku-nin shu (36 members) were in control of town administration, which means there existed self-government systems that were suited to the respective cities.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same period there was a self-government system led by elders in Yamada in Ise (Yamadasanpo), and a self-government organisation of Egoshu in Ominato in Ise, while in Hakata 12 Nengyoji were ruling the city and in Shonai Sakata the Sanju-roku-nin shu (36 members) were in control of town administration, which means there existed self-government systems that were suited to the respective cities.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same period, the elders of Yamada in Ise, headed a self-government system called &quot;Yamadasanpo,&quot; a form of self-government was also found in Egoshu in Ominato, Ise, while in Hakata, twelve Nengyoji (town officials) were administering the city, and in Shonai Sakata the Sanju-roku-nin shu with thirty-six members were in control of town administration; all these are examples of self-government that was suited to their respective cities.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づき修正しました。#削除しました。余分なスペース削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Sralin(id:15915), Mnd(id:15140), Oxhop(id:2551), Straysheep(id:42448), Miyuki Meinaka(id:251638), S kitahashi(id:10307), トホホ川(id:50502), Komura Jutaro(id:35057), BAKU(id:55205), ブレイズマン(id:183852), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>