<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>丹後王国論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango okoku ron (the theory of the Tango Kingdom)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango okoku ron (the theory of the Tango Kingdom)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango okoku ron (the theory of the Tango Kingdom)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>丹後王国論（たんごおうこくろん）は、門脇禎二が古墳時代に丹後地方（今の京都府京丹後市辺り）を中心に、ヤマト王権などと並び独立性をもって存在したとされる勢力『丹後王国』があったと提唱したもの（丹後国は後年に丹波国から分国したものであるため『丹波王国』とも称される）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tango okoku ron is a theory in which Teiji KADOWAKI asserted an existence of &quot;Tango Kingdom&quot; in and around Tango region (present Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture) in Kofun period (tumulus period), which is believed to have been independent and rivaled Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) (It is also referred to as &quot;Tanba Kingdom&quot; because Tango Province was divided from Tanba Province later).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tango okoku ron is a theory in which Teiji KADOWAKI asserted an existence of &quot;Tango Kingdom&quot; in and around Tango region (present Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture) during the Kofun period (tumulus period), which is believed to have been independent and rivaled Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) (It is also referred to as &quot;Tanba Kingdom&quot; because Tango Province was divided from Tanba Province later).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tango okoku ron is a theory in which Teiji KADOWAKI asserted an existence of &quot;Tango Kingdom&quot; in and around Tango region (present Tango City, Kyoto Prefecture) during the Kofun period (tumulus period), which is believed to have been independent and rivaled Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) (It is also referred to as &quot;Tanba Kingdom&quot; because Tango Province was divided from Tanba Province later).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>門脇禎二によれば、『丹後王国』は4世紀中・末期頃から5世紀が最盛期。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to Teiji KADOWAKI, the peak of &quot;Tango Kingdom&quot; was the mid to late fourth century to the fifth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to Teiji KADOWAKI, the peak of &quot;Tango Kingdom&quot; was the mid to late fourth century to the fifth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to Teiji KADOWAKI, the peak of &quot;Tango Kingdom&quot; was the mid to late fourth century to the fifth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>6世紀中頃ヤマトの出雲征討に伴いヤマト王権の支配下に入っていったと想定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He assumes that the kingdom went under control of Yamato sovereignty along with the conquest of Izumo by Yamato in the mid sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He assumes that the kingdom came under control of Yamato sovereignty along with the conquest of Izumo by Yamato in the mid sixth century.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He assumes that the kingdom came under control of Yamato sovereignty along with the conquest of Izumo by Yamato in the mid sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>丹後地方は大型古墳が集中（網野銚子山古墳、神明山古墳、蛭子山古墳など）していることや、近年の発掘調査などから、古代に独自の勢力が存在していたと想定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that an independent power existed in Tango region in ancient times because large tumulus center there (Aminochoshiyama Burial Mound, Shinmeiyama-kofun Tumulus, Ebisuyama-kofun Tumulus, and the like), as well as from the recent excavations and researches.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that an independent power existed in Tango region in ancient times due to a large tumulus center found there (Aminochoshiyama Burial Mound, Shinmeiyama-kofun Tumulus, Ebisuyama-kofun Tumulus, and the like), as well as recent excavations and researches.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that an independent power existed in Tango region in ancient times due to a large tumulus center found there (Aminochoshiyama Burial Mound, Shinmeiyama-kofun Tumulus, Ebisuyama-kofun Tumulus, and the like), as well as recent excavations and researches.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 まったけ(id:130042), 横浜大塚(id:107010), Ganman(id:96316), BAKU(id:55205), Kalz(id:92749), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>