<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>百万塔陀羅尼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakuman-to Pagoda Dhahran</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakumanto Darani (The one million pagodas and Dharani prayers)</e>
<cmt>タイトルを一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakumanto Darani (The one million pagodas and Dharani prayers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>百万塔 陀羅尼（ひゃくまんとう だらに）とは、日本の奈良時代に、鎮護国家と滅罪を祈願するために、100万の小塔に陀羅尼を納めて、仏教寺院に奉納された陀羅尼である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakuman-to Pagoda Dharani (one million pagoda dharani) are the collection of Dharanis that have been dedicated to Buddhist temples by way of being placed in one million mini pagodas during the Nara Period for the protection of the nation as well as for repentance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakumanto Darani is the collection of Dharanis that was dedicated to Buddhist temples by way of being placed in one million mini pagodas during the Nara period for the protection of the nation as well as for repentance.</e>
<cmt>have been→ was に変更しました。Period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakumanto Darani is the collection of Dharanis that was dedicated to Buddhist temples by way of being placed in one million mini pagodas during the Nara period for the protection of the nation as well as for repentance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>塔は百万塔と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tower is called Hyakuman-to Tower (One million pagodas).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pagoda is called Hyakumanto (one million pagodas).</e>
<cmt>tower →pagoda としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pagoda is called Hyakumanto (one million pagodas).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>The を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>天平宝字8年（764年）に藤原仲麻呂の乱を平定した称徳天皇は、戦死した将兵の菩提を弔うと共に、鎮護国家を祈念するために、6年の歳月を掛けて宝亀元年（770年）に『無垢浄光大陀羅尼経』に基づいて、陀羅尼を100万巻印刷した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 764, Emperor Shotoku who brought an end to the FUJIWARA no Nakamaro&apos;s war, spent six years to print one million scrolls of Dharanis based on the &quot;Pure Light Great Dharani Sutras &quot;in 770 for the purpose of mourning for the souls of departed warriors who were killed in action as well to pray for the protection of the nation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Empress Shotoku, who had brought an end to the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro in 764, printed one million scrolls of Dharanis based on the &quot;Pure Light Great Dharani Sutras&quot; in 770, which took six years, for the purpose of mourning for the souls of departed warriors who were killed in action as well to pray for the protection of the nation.</e>
<cmt>女帝であったようですので、Empress Shotoku としました。一部翻訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Empress Shotoku, who had brought an end to the Rebellion of FUJIWARA no Nakamaro in 764, printed one million scrolls of Dharanis based on the &quot;Pure Light Great Dharani Sutras&quot; in 770, which took six years, for the purpose of mourning for the souls of departed warriors who were killed in action as well to pray for the protection of the nation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>そして小型の塔に納めて10万基ずつ大安寺・元興寺・法隆寺・東大寺・西大寺 (奈良市)・興福寺・薬師寺・四天王寺・川原寺・崇福寺 (大津市)の10大寺に奉納した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scrolls were placed in mini pagodas, and pagodas containing 100,000 scrolls each were dedicated to Daian-ji Temple; Gango-ji Temple; Horyu-ji Temple; Todai-ji Temple; Saidai-ji Temple; Kofuku-ji Temple; Yakushi-ji Temple; Shitenno-ji Temple; Kawahara-dera Temple; and Sufuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scrolls were placed in mini pagodas, and pagodas containing 100,000 scrolls each were dedicated to Daian-ji Temple; Gango-ji Temple; Horyu-ji Temple; Todai-ji Temple; Saidai-ji Temple; Kofuku-ji Temple; Yakushi-ji Temple; Shitenno-ji Temple; Kawahara-dera Temple; and Sufuku-ji Temple (Otsu City).</e>
<cmt>大津市　追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scrolls were placed in mini pagodas, and pagodas containing 100,000 scrolls each were dedicated to Daian-ji Temple; Gango-ji Temple; Horyu-ji Temple; Todai-ji Temple; Saidai-ji Temple; Kofuku-ji Temple; Yakushi-ji Temple; Shitenno-ji Temple; Kawahara-dera Temple; and Sufuku-ji Temple (Otsu City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>これらの塔はそのほとんどが火災で焼失、或いは散逸し、2005年現在、法隆寺に4万数千基が残っているほかは、博物館や個人に数基所蔵されているのみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of these pagodas have either been burnt in fires or have been scattered and lost; as of 2005, apart from the 40,00-odd scrolls remaining in Horyu-ji Temple, several of them are either kept in museums or are privately owned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of these pagodas have either been burnt in fires or have been scattered and lost; as of 2005, except for the 40,000-odd scrolls remaining in Horyu-ji Temple, only several of them are either kept in museums or are privately owned.</e>
<cmt>数字を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of these pagodas have either been burnt in fires or have been scattered and lost; as of 2005, except for the 40,000-odd scrolls remaining in Horyu-ji Temple, only several of them are either kept in museums or are privately owned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>陀羅尼を版（木製か金属製かは不明）に凸状に彫り、その上に幅4.5cm、長さ15cm～50cmの虫食い防止のために黄檗で染められた紙を載せて印刷した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By convexly carving the Dharanis on a plate (whether the plate was of wood or metal is unclear), they were printed by casting a paper dyed from a Phellodendron amurense tree on top with a width of 4.5cm and a length extending from 15-50cm to prevent vermiculation.</e>
<cmt>Phellodendron amurenseは仮訳です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By convexly carving the Dharanis on a plate (whether the plate was of wood or metal is unclear), they were printed by casting a paper dyed from a Phellodendron amurense tree on top with a width of 4.5 cm and a length extending from 15 - 50 cm to prevent vermiculation.</e>
<cmt>単位の前にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By convexly carving the Dharanis on a plate (whether the plate was of wood or metal is unclear), they were printed by casting a paper dyed from a Phellodendron amurense tree on top with a width of 4.5 cm and a length extending from 15 - 50 cm to prevent vermiculation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、紙を下にして捺印方式で印刷したという説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is a theory purporting that it was printed by the sealing method by putting the paper underneath.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is a theory purporting that it was printed by the sealing method by putting the paper underneath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is a theory purporting that it was printed by the sealing method by putting the paper underneath.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>因みに、2005年現在、確認出来る世界最古の印刷物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As of 2005, it is said to be the oldest verifiable printed material in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As of 2005, it is said to be the oldest verifiable printed material in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As of 2005, it is said to be the oldest verifiable printed material in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>陀羅尼を納める塔は、小さな三重の塔で、中国より伝来したロクロを使用した木製で、白い染料が塗布されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The mini pagodas where the Dharanis are placed are made up of small triple pagodas that are of a wooden make by using the traditional Chinese potter&apos;s wheel painted white.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The mini pagodas where the Dharanis are placed are made up of small triple pagodas that are of a wooden make by using the traditional Chinese potter&apos;s wheel painted white.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The mini pagodas where the Dharanis are placed are made up of small triple pagodas that are of a wooden make by using the traditional Chinese potter&apos;s wheel painted white.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Mnd(id:15140), TEX(id:27502), ReijiYamashina(id:29567), Nakadati(id:26815), Kstigarbha(id:13376), Wolfgang3264(id:84392), Point136(id:211299), MsOka(id:149781), Kzhr(id:131), SieBot(id:126695), Rita(id:19950), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>