<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>三田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>三田藩（さんだはん）は摂津国有馬郡三田（現・兵庫県三田市）周辺を領有した藩。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanda Domain was the ruler of Mita Arima County, Settsu Province and the area around it (modern days Sanda City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanda Domain was the ruler of Sanda, Arima County, Settsu Province and the area around it (modern days Sanda City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。Sanda と読みを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanda Domain was the ruler of Sanda, Arima County, Settsu Province and the area around it (modern days Sanda City, Hyogo Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>藩庁は当初、三田城のち三田陣屋。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They changed government building Sanda-jo Castle (initial government building) to Mita jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their government building was initially Sanda-jo Castle but was later chanted to Sanda jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt>Sanda と読みを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their government building was initially Sanda-jo Castle but was later chanted to Sanda jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>略史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Brief history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Brief history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三田藩の成立過程</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The course of Sanda Domain&apos;s establishment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The course of Sanda Domain&apos;s establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The course of Sanda Domain&apos;s establishment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代以前の三田は金心寺と三輪神社の門前町を中心に多くの荘園ができていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Kamakura period, Mita had many Shoens (manors in medieval Japan) in which centered a Monzen-machi (a temple town) of 金心寺 and Miwa Shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　 金心寺 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Kamakura period, many shoens (manors in medieval Japan) were developed in Sanda centering around the monzen-machi (a temple town) of Konshin-ji Temple and Miwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>金心寺　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Kamakura period, many shoens (manors in medieval Japan) were developed in Sanda centering around the monzen-machi (a temple town) of Konshin-ji Temple and Miwa-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>地頭である豪族が桑原城、貴志城、大原城などの小さな山城を築いて統治していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jigashira (the leader of the group reciters) who was also called Gozoku (a local ruling family) governed Mita constructing small size of Yamashiros (castles built on the top of mountains or halfway up the mountains for defensive reasons) like Kuwabara-jo Castle, Kishi-jo castle and Ohara-jo castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The gozoku (a local ruling family) who worked as jito (manager and lord of manor) governed Sanda by constructing small Yamashiros (castles built on the top of mountains or halfway up the mountains for defensive reasons) such as Kuwabara-jo Castle, Kishi-jo Castle and Ohara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Castle を大文字にしました。Jigashira→ Jito としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The gozoku (a local ruling family) who worked as jito (manager and lord of manor) governed Sanda by constructing small Yamashiros (castles built on the top of mountains or halfway up the mountains for defensive reasons) such as Kuwabara-jo Castle, Kishi-jo Castle and Ohara-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>室町時代に荘園公領制が消滅すると城下町としての性格を強め三田藩が成立していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After shoen koryo sei disappeared in the Muromachi period, Sanda Domain was formed as a castle town.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) disappeared in the Muromachi period, Sanda Domain was formed as a castle town.</e>
<cmt>荘園公領制 補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After shoen koryo sei (the system of public lands and private estates) disappeared in the Muromachi period, Sanda Domain was formed as a castle town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>1361年（康安元年）　播磨国守護だった赤松則村（円心）の四男・赤松氏範が有馬郡を領有し三田城（車瀬城）を築城。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1361 Ujinori AKAMATSU, the forth son of Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) who was the Governor of Harima Province, became the ruler of Arima County and construct Sanda-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1361 Ujinori AKAMATSU, the forth son of Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) who was the Governor of Harima Province, became the ruler of Arima County and constructed Sanda-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>constructed としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1361 Ujinori AKAMATSU, the forth son of Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) who was the Governor of Harima Province, became the ruler of Arima County and constructed Sanda-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>1386年（至徳3年） 南北朝の争いで赤松一門が足利軍に組する中、氏範だけは南朝方に付いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1386 in the disturbance of Northern and Southern Dynasties, although Akamatsu family took the side of Ashikaga army Ujinori was the only one took Southern Dynasties.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1386 in the disturbance of Northern and Southern Courts, although Akamatsu family took the side of Ashikaga army, only Ujinori was on the side of Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>dynasties →courts としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1386 in the disturbance of Northern and Southern Courts, although Akamatsu family took the side of Ashikaga army, only Ujinori was on the side of Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>幕府派遣の討伐軍に攻められ自害。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujinori committed suicide having an attack made by a punitive force dispatched from bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujinori committed suicide after having been attacked by a punitive force dispatched from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>having been attacked としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujinori committed suicide after having been attacked by a punitive force dispatched from the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>1409年（応永16年）　氏範の兄である赤松則祐の五男・有馬義祐が有馬郡を領有し摂津有馬氏を名乗るようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1409 Yoshisuke ARIMA the fifth son of Norisuke AKAMATSU who was Ujinori&apos;s old brother became the ruler of Arima County calling himself the Settsu Arima clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1409 Yoshisuke ARIMA, the fifth son of Norisuke AKAMATSU who was Ujinori&apos;s older brother, became the ruler of Arima County and started calling himself the Settsu Arima clan.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1409 Yoshisuke ARIMA, the fifth son of Norisuke AKAMATSU who was Ujinori&apos;s older brother, became the ruler of Arima County and started calling himself the Settsu Arima clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="12">
<j>1575年（天正3年） 織田信長の「天下布武」の下、摂津国を平定した荒木村重が、織田陣営の丹波国攻略の要として家臣の安都部弥市郎を荒木重堅と改名させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1575 Murashige ARAKI who had suppressed Settsu Province under the banner of Nobunaga ODA&apos;s &quot;Tenka-fubu&quot; (a slogan that means that the samurai governs the whole world) changed 安都部弥市郎&apos;s name to 荒木重堅 as Oda camp&apos;s point of the conquering of Tamba region.</e>
<cmt>安都部弥市郎 荒木重堅　読み方不明　一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1575 Murashige ARAKI who had suppressed Settsu Province under the banner of Nobunaga ODA&apos;s &apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; (a slogan that means that the samurai governs the whole world) had his vassal change his name from Yaichiro ATOBE to Shigekata ARAKI as the pivot of Oda camp in conquering Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>人名の読みを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1575 Murashige ARAKI who had suppressed Settsu Province under the banner of Nobunaga ODA&apos;s &apos;Tenka-fubu&apos; (a slogan that means that the samurai governs the whole world) had his vassal change his name from Yaichiro ATOBE to Shigekata ARAKI as the pivot of Oda camp in conquering Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>三田城に入城させ1万石の城下町として整備していく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Murashige ARAKI allocated 荒木重堅 to Sanda-jo Castle having him built a castle town of Ten thousand koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>荒木重堅 読み方不明　一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Murashige ARAKI had Shigekata ARAKI move into Sanda-jo Castle and build a castle town of 10,000 koku (an unit of assessed crop yields of the land [1 koku: about 180 liter], which was also used to express the size of the land).</e>
<cmt>人名の読みを追加しました。石（koku)　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Murashige ARAKI had Shigekata ARAKI move into Sanda-jo Castle and build a castle town of 10,000 koku (an unit of assessed crop yields of the land [1 koku: about 180 liter], which was also used to express the size of the land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>1582年（天正10年） 荒木村重が謀反を起こし織田信長に討たれたことで重堅は三田城を開城、代わって信長の家臣であった山崎片家（堅家）が近江国山崎城より三田に入封、2万3千石の領主となり三田に藩が成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1582 with Murashige ARAKI killed by Nobunaga ODA due to the rebellion he rose, 重堅 surrendered Sanda-jo Castle to the enemy letting Kataie YAMAZAKI from Yamazaki-jo Castle in Omi province the vassal of Nobunaga take the place of 重堅 to be a feudal lord of Sanda with twenty three thousand koku crop yields.</e>
<cmt>重堅 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1582 with Murashige ARAKI killed by Nobunaga ODA due to the rebellion he rose, Shigekata surrendered Sanda-jo Castle to the Oda side; subsequently, Kataie YAMAZAKI, a vassal of Nobunaga who was from Yamazaki-jo Castle in Omi Province, entered Sanda to be the feudal lord with 23,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1582 with Murashige ARAKI killed by Nobunaga ODA due to the rebellion he rose, Shigekata surrendered Sanda-jo Castle to the Oda side; subsequently, Kataie YAMAZAKI, a vassal of Nobunaga who was from Yamazaki-jo Castle in Omi Province, entered Sanda to be the feudal lord with 23,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="15">
<j>1601年（慶長6年） 山崎家盛は関ヶ原合戦で西軍に仕え敗戦、因幡国若桜藩に転封となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1601 Iemori YAMAZAKI was forced to changed his territory to 若桜藩 in Inaba Province due to the defeat at the Battle of Sekigahara having taken the side of Sei-Gun.</e>
<cmt>若桜藩 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1601 Iemori YAMAZAKI was forced to change his territory to Wakasa Domain in Inaba Province due to the defeat at the Battle of Sekigahara having taken the side of the West camp.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1601 Iemori YAMAZAKI was forced to change his territory to Wakasa Domain in Inaba Province due to the defeat at the Battle of Sekigahara having taken the side of the West camp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>代わって摂津有馬氏の出で東軍の武将であった有馬則頼が遠江国横須賀藩から2万石で入封。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To taking the place of Iemori YAMAZAKI, Noriyori ARIMA of Yokosuka clan in Totomi Province who belong to the Settsu Arima clan and was also a busho (Japanese military commander) of To-Gun (the &apos;eastern&apos; army) entered into Sanda-jo Castle as a feudal lord with twenty thousand koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To take the place of Iemori YAMAZAKI, Noriyori ARIMA of Yokosuka Domain in Totomi Province who was originally from Settsu Arima clan and was also a busho (Japanese military commander) of the East camp entered into Sanda-jo Castle as a feudal lord with 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To take the place of Iemori YAMAZAKI, Noriyori ARIMA of Yokosuka Domain in Totomi Province who was originally from Settsu Arima clan and was also a busho (Japanese military commander) of the East camp entered into Sanda-jo Castle as a feudal lord with 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="17">
<j>1602年（慶長7年） 有馬則頼が没すると丹波国福知山藩6万石を所領していた嫡男の有馬豊氏が家督を継ぎ、三田藩2万石を併合し福知山藩8万石の所領となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1602 after the death of Noriyori ARIMA, Toyouji ARIMA the eldest legitimate son and also the ruler of Fukuchiyama Domain in Tango Province with sixty thousand koku became the successor to Arima Clan annexing Sanda Domain of twenty thousand koku to Fukuchiyama Domain, as a result the total number of Fukuchiyama Domain&apos;s koku became eighty thousand koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1602 after the death of Noriyori ARIMA, Toyouji ARIMA, the eldest legitimate son and also the ruler of Fukuchiyama Domain in Tango Province with 60,000 koku, became the successor and annexed Sanda Domain of 20,000 koku to Fukuchiyama Domain, making the total crop yield of Fukuchiyama Domain 80,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1602 after the death of Noriyori ARIMA, Toyouji ARIMA, the eldest legitimate son and also the ruler of Fukuchiyama Domain in Tango Province with 60,000 koku, became the successor and annexed Sanda Domain of 20,000 koku to Fukuchiyama Domain, making the total crop yield of Fukuchiyama Domain 80,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>これにより三田藩は一旦廃藩となり三田城（車瀬城）も破却される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, Sanda Domain was once abolished and at the same time Sanda-jo Castle (車瀬城) was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>（車瀬城） 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, Sanda Domain was once abolished and at the same time Sanda-jo Castle (Kurumase-jo Castle) was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>くるませじょう　と読みを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, Sanda Domain was once abolished and at the same time Sanda-jo Castle (Kurumase-jo Castle) was destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="19">
<j>1620年（元和6年）　福知山藩主の有馬豊氏は大坂の役の武功により20万石の大名となり筑後国久留米藩に移封。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1620 with highly evaluated distinguished service at Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka), Toyouji ARIMA the lord of Fukuchiyama Domain was changed his territory to Kurume Domain with twenty thousand koku as the local lord in Chikugo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1620 with highly evaluated and distinguished service at the Siege of Osaka, Toyouji ARIMA, the lord of Fukuchiyama Domain, became a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) with 200,000 koku and was transferred to Kurume Domain in Chikugo Province.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1620 with highly evaluated and distinguished service at the Siege of Osaka, Toyouji ARIMA, the lord of Fukuchiyama Domain, became a daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) with 200,000 koku and was transferred to Kurume Domain in Chikugo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="20">
<j>1626年（寛永3年）　出羽国上山藩から松平重直が3万石で三田に入封し三田藩は復活する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1626 At the same time that Shigenao MATSUDAIRA entered into Sanda from Kaminoyama Domain in Dewa Province receiving thirty thousands koku, Sanda Domain was restored.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1626, after Shigenao MATSUDAIRA entered into Sanda from Kaminoyama Domain in Dewa Province receiving 30,000 koku, Sanda Domain was restored.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1626, after Shigenao MATSUDAIRA entered into Sanda from Kaminoyama Domain in Dewa Province receiving 30,000 koku, Sanda Domain was restored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="21">
<j>1633年（寛永10年） 志摩国鳥羽藩の九鬼氏の家督争いを理由に、幕府は九鬼氏の5万6千石を分割し、九鬼久隆を3万6千石で三田藩に、九鬼隆季を2万石で丹波国綾部藩に移封。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1633 The Kuki family&apos;s territory of fifty six thousand was divided by Bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) for the reason of succession dispute changing Hisataka KUKI&apos;s territory to Sanda Domain with thirty six thousands koku and Takasue KUKI&apos;s territory to Ayabe Domain in Tanba Province with twenty thousand koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1633, the bakufu divided Kuki clan&apos;s territory of 56,000 koku into two for the reason of succession dispute, in which Hisataka KUKI&apos;s territory was changed to Sanda Domain with 36,000 koku and Takasue KUKI&apos;s territory was transferred to Ayabe Domain in Tanba Province with 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1633, the bakufu divided Kuki clan&apos;s territory of 56,000 koku into two for the reason of succession dispute, in which Hisataka KUKI&apos;s territory was changed to Sanda Domain with 36,000 koku and Takasue KUKI&apos;s territory was transferred to Ayabe Domain in Tanba Province with 20,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>これにより松平重直は豊後国高田藩 (豊後国)（竜王藩）に転封となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, Shigenao MATSUDAIRA&apos;s territory was relocated to Takada Domain in Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, Shigenao MATSUDAIRA&apos;s territory was relocated to Takada Domain (Ryuo Province) in Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>竜王藩　を追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, Shigenao MATSUDAIRA&apos;s territory was relocated to Takada Domain (Ryuo Province) in Bungo Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="23">
<j>九鬼氏三田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The KUKI family Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuki clan of Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt>clan としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuki clan of Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>九鬼氏は藤原北家熊野別当の末裔で紀伊国牟婁郡（現在の三重県尾鷲市）で起こり、志摩国鳥羽藩（三重県鳥羽市）を拠点に九鬼水軍を統率し秀吉の九州攻めや朝鮮出兵で水軍総督を務めた大名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The KUKI family was a Japanese feudal lord descended from Kumano betto (title of an official who administered the shrines at Kumano) of FUJIWARA Hokke (one of the four FUJIWARA family lines) originating in Muro County, Ki Province (modern day Owase City, Mie Prefecture) and was the leader of Kuki Suigun navy whose strategic point in Toba domain in Shima Province (the old name for Toba City, Mie Prefecture) acting as the general leader of Suigun navy in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Kyushu and Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kuki clan was a daimyo descended from Kumano betto (title of an official who administered the shrines at Kumano) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan originating in Muro County, Kii Province (modern day Owase City, Mie Prefecture), and was the leader of Kuki Suigun navy whose strategic point was located in Toba Domain in Shima Province (present-day Toba City, Mie Prefecture) acting as the general leader of Suigun navy in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Kyushu and the dispatch of troops to Korea.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kuki clan was a daimyo descended from Kumano betto (title of an official who administered the shrines at Kumano) of the Northern House of the Fujiwara clan originating in Muro County, Kii Province (modern day Owase City, Mie Prefecture), and was the leader of Kuki Suigun navy whose strategic point was located in Toba Domain in Shima Province (present-day Toba City, Mie Prefecture) acting as the general leader of Suigun navy in Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion of Kyushu and the dispatch of troops to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>九鬼守隆の死後、五男の九鬼久隆と三男の九鬼隆季との間に家督争いが起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Moritaka KUKI&apos;s death, Hisataka KUKI the fifth son and Takasue KUKI the third son had a succession dispute among them.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Moritaka KUKI&apos;s death, Hisataka KUKI, the fifth son, and Takasue KUKI, the third son, had a succession dispute within the family.</e>
<cmt>カンマを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Moritaka KUKI&apos;s death, Hisataka KUKI, the fifth son, and Takasue KUKI, the third son, had a succession dispute within the family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>水軍力を恐れた徳川家光はこの家督争いを理由に九鬼氏の石高5万6千石を分割、内陸の三田と綾部に移封させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iemitsu TOKUGAWA who had a fear of Kuki&apos;s Suigun navy power divided the Kuki family&apos;s total yield of fifty six thousand and the Kuki&apos;s territory into inland area Sanda and Ayabe for the reason of the succession dispute.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, who had a fear of Kuki&apos;s Suigun navy power, divided the Kuki family&apos;s total yield of 56,000 koku and relocated their territories to Sanda and Ayabe, both of which were inland areas, for the reason of the succession dispute.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, who had a fear of Kuki&apos;s Suigun navy power, divided the Kuki family&apos;s total yield of 56,000 koku and relocated their territories to Sanda and Ayabe, both of which were inland areas, for the reason of the succession dispute.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>これにより九鬼氏は鳥羽の地と水軍を失う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this, KUKI family lost the territory in Toba and Suigun navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this, Kuki clan lost the territory in Toba and Suigun navy.</e>
<cmt>clan としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this, Kuki clan lost the territory in Toba and Suigun navy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>宗家を三田に移し廃藩置県までの約240年間、三田藩を統治することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, after moved their head family to Sanda the KUKI family ruled Sanda Domain for approximately two hundred forty years until Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After moving their head family to Sanda, the Kuki family ruled Sanda Domain for approximately 240 years until Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After moving their head family to Sanda, the Kuki family ruled Sanda Domain for approximately 240 years until Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="29">
<j>居城は三田城で、現在の有馬高校校舎敷地（三田城跡）に二の丸・御茶屋・武器庫・煙硝蔵などを設け、現在の三田小学校敷地に御館が築かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The castle of the lord was Sanda-jo Castle with Ninomaru (second bailey), Ochaya (rest house), Arms store house and 煙硝蔵 built in premises of today&apos;s Arima High School campus (the site of Sanda-jo Castle) and Otate built in the premises of existing Sanda Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>煙硝蔵 読み方訳不明　御館　訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The residence of the lord was Sanda-jo Castle with ninomaru (second bailey), ochaya (rest house), arms store house and ammunition storage built in premises of today&apos;s Arima High School campus (the site of Sanda-jo Castle) and mitachi (feudal lord&apos;s office) built in the premises of existing Sanda Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。御館→Mitachi (feudal lord&apos;s office)　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The residence of the lord was Sanda-jo Castle with ninomaru (second bailey), ochaya (rest house), arms store house and ammunition storage built in premises of today&apos;s Arima High School campus (the site of Sanda-jo Castle) and mitachi (feudal lord&apos;s office) built in the premises of existing Sanda Elementary School.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>御館は、御広間・御小書院・御大書院・御居間・台所・御局・御守殿などから構成されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Otate was composed of hiroma (a hall), kojoin, daishoin, ima (a living room), daidokoro (a kitchen), mitsubone (room for dignified lady) and goshuden (room for legal wife) and so on.</e>
<cmt>御館　小書院　大書院　訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitachi was composed of onhiroma (a hall), gokoshoin (small study), godaishoin (large study), ima (a living room), daidokoro (a kitchen), mitsubone (room for dignified lady) and goshuden (room for legal wife) and so on.</e>
<cmt>御館→Mitachi としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitachi was composed of onhiroma (a hall), gokoshoin (small study), godaishoin (large study), ima (a living room), daidokoro (a kitchen), mitsubone (room for dignified lady) and goshuden (room for legal wife) and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>現在陣屋跡には水堀が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mizubori (water-filled moat) still remains in the site of jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mizubori (water-filled moat) still remains in the site of jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mizubori (water-filled moat) still remains in the site of jinya (regional government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>御下屋敷表門（黒門）の部材が金心寺の門に使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some components of the front gate (kuro-mon gate) of shimo-yashiki (One of the residences granted to daimyou) are used for the gate of 金心寺.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処 金心寺 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some components of the front gate (kuro-mon gate) of shimo-yashiki (one of the residences granted to daimyo) are used for the gate of Konshin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Konshin-ji Temple としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some components of the front gate (kuro-mon gate) of shimo-yashiki (one of the residences granted to daimyo) are used for the gate of Konshin-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="33">
<j>九鬼氏は石高にそぐわない多くの家臣団を召し抱えていたため、財政は入封早々より行き詰まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time KUKi family enterd into Sanda, they had financial affairs due to an excess vassals over their crop yields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soon after Kuki clan entered Sanda, they began to face financial difficulty due to an excess number of vassals over their crop yields.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soon after Kuki clan entered Sanda, they began to face financial difficulty due to an excess number of vassals over their crop yields.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="34">
<j>2代九鬼隆昌の時代に藩の機構が整えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the period of Takamasa the second of KUKI family, the domain&apos;s organization was arranged.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the era of Takamasa KUKI, the second of head of the family, the domain&apos;s organization was arranged.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the era of Takamasa KUKI, the second of head of the family, the domain&apos;s organization was arranged.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>7代九鬼隆由は寛保2年（1742年）藩校「国光館」を開いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1742 Takayori the seventh KUKI founded a hanko (a domain school) named &apos;国光館&apos;.</e>
<cmt>「国光館」 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1742, Takayori KUKI the seventh founded a hanko (a domain school) named &apos;Kokkokan&apos; (国光館).</e>
<cmt>国光館→Kokkokan と読むのではないかと推測し、漢字も追記しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1742, Takayori KUKI the seventh founded a hanko (a domain school) named &apos;Kokkokan&apos; (国光館).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>8代九鬼隆邑の安永9年（1780年）には増税により一揆が起こり、城下の商家数件が打ち壊しに遭った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1780 in the period of Takamura the eighth, an uprising broke out due to tax increase leaving several mercantile houses broken by Uchikowashi (it refers to an act where people destroyed residences of privileged merchants or officials who were involved in misgovernment).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1780 in the era of Takamura KUKI the eighth, an uprising broke out due to a tax increase, and several mercantile houses in the castle town were torn down by Uchikowashi (an act where people destroyed residences of privileged merchants or officials who were involved in misgovernment).</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1780 in the era of Takamura KUKI the eighth, an uprising broke out due to a tax increase, and several mercantile houses in the castle town were torn down by Uchikowashi (an act where people destroyed residences of privileged merchants or officials who were involved in misgovernment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="37">
<j>特筆すべきは10代藩主九鬼隆国である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takakuni KUKI the tenth lord of domain was worthy of mention.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takakuni KUKI, the tenth lord of the domain, was worthy of mention.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takakuni KUKI, the tenth lord of the domain, was worthy of mention.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>文化 (元号)年間（1804年 - 1817年）に江戸城神田橋御門・常盤橋御門番を務めた功績により、天保10年（1839年）に城主大名に引き上げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1839 Takakuni KUKI was promoted to Joshu Daimyo (daimyo who is allowed to live in a castle) by his distinguished service as a gatekeeper at Kanda-bridge and Tokiwa-bridge of Edo Castle from 1894 to 1817.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1839 he was promoted to Joshu daimyo (daimyo who is allowed to live in a castle) by his distinguished service as a gatekeeper at Kanda-bashi Bridge and Tokiwa-bashi Bridge of Edo-jo Castle during the Bunka era (1894 to 1817).</e>
<cmt>神田橋→Kanda-bashi Bridge としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1839 he was promoted to Joshu daimyo (daimyo who is allowed to live in a castle) by his distinguished service as a gatekeeper at Kanda-bashi Bridge and Tokiwa-bashi Bridge of Edo-jo Castle during the Bunka era (1894 to 1817).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>好学の名君であり文政元年（1818年）藩校である「国光館」を新たに「造士館」として発展させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1818 Takakuni KUKi the wise ruler developed the hanko (a domain school) &apos;国光館&apos; further as a new school named Zoshikan school.</e>
<cmt>「国光館」 読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He was a wise ruler who loved learning, and in 1818 he developed the hanko &apos;Kokkokan&apos; further into a new school named &apos;Zoshikan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He was a wise ruler who loved learning, and in 1818 he developed the hanko &apos;Kokkokan&apos; further into a new school named &apos;Zoshikan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>また洋学にも関心を示し、幕末に向け三田藩の近代化を推進する素地を開いた中興の祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was a restorer who established groundwork for promoting westernization of Sanda Domain as preparation for the end of Edo Period showing interest in Western studies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also showed interest in Western studies, and was a restorer who established groundwork for promoting westernization of Sanda Domain as preparation for the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also showed interest in Western studies, and was a restorer who established groundwork for promoting westernization of Sanda Domain as preparation for the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="41">
<j>最後の13代九鬼隆義は藩政改革を行い、軍隊を洋式に改めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takayoshi The last thirteenth KUKI changed the system of thier army to western style by conducting reformation of domain duties.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takayoshi KUKI, the 13th and the last head, changed the system of their army to western style by conducting reformation of domain duties.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takayoshi KUKI, the 13th and the last head, changed the system of their army to western style by conducting reformation of domain duties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>慶応3年（1867年）藩論が倒幕に統一され、鳥羽伏見の戦いにおいても洋式軍隊を率い官軍方として参戦した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1867 after the opinion of people in the domain was integrated into overthrowing the Shogunate, Takayoshi KUKI took the side of Imperial army commanding western style army at the Battle of Toba and Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1867 after the opinion of people in the domain was integrated into that of overthrowing the bakufu, Takayoshi KUKI took the side of Imperial army commanding western style army at the Battle of Toba and Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1867 after the opinion of people in the domain was integrated into that of overthrowing the bakufu, Takayoshi KUKI took the side of Imperial army commanding western style army at the Battle of Toba and Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="43">
<j>また、明治維新が起こると、近代港として神戸港が整備されると知るや、幕末から明治維新の混乱による財政の立て直しと廃藩置県で困窮する三田藩士を救うべく、藩士の白洲退蔵（白洲次郎の祖父）、小寺泰次郎らとともに「志摩三商会」という神戸初の輸入商社を設立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Meiji restoration occurred, with receiving the information about improvement of Kobe Port, he founded the first Kobe import business nemed [Shima San Shokai] with Taizo SHIRASU (grandfather of Jiro SHIRASU) and Taijiro KODERA to set the finances crisis caused by confusion around the end of Edo Period to the Meiji restoration in order and help feudal retainer of Sanda domain in need of finance aid.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, after the Meiji Restoration and upon receiving the information that the Kobe Port would be improved as one of the modern ports, he founded the first import business in Kobe named &apos;Shima San Shokai&apos; with domain&apos;s retainers Taizo SHIRASU (grandfather of Jiro SHIRASU) and Taijiro KODERA to save the domain&apos;s finance crisis caused by the confusion from the end of Edo period to the Meiji Restoration and to help the feudal retainers of Sanda Domain who had been reduced to poverty due to Haihan-chiken.</e>
<cmt>Restoration 大文字にしました。Period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, after the Meiji Restoration and upon receiving the information that the Kobe Port would be improved as one of the modern ports, he founded the first import business in Kobe named &apos;Shima San Shokai&apos; with domain&apos;s retainers Taizo SHIRASU (grandfather of Jiro SHIRASU) and Taijiro KODERA to save the domain&apos;s finance crisis caused by the confusion from the end of Edo period to the Meiji Restoration and to help the feudal retainers of Sanda Domain who had been reduced to poverty due to Haihan-chiken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>これが成功を収め不動産や金融業に乗り出し、現在の元町 (神戸市)、三宮といった神戸港周辺の都市開発や神戸女学院の前身である女子寄宿学校・神戸ホームの創立に関わるなど、神戸の街づくりに多大な影響を及ぼしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this success, he expanded his business into real estate, financial business and at the same time was involved in urban development around Kobe Port such as Moto Machi (Kobe City), San no miya and foundation of Kobe home the lodge school for female which was previously Kobe jogakuin exercising a major influence on Kobe&apos;s development plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this success, he expanded his business into real estate, financial business and at the same time was involved in urban development around Kobe Port such as Moto-machi (Kobe City) and Sannomiya, and foundation of Kobe Home, the boarding school for female students which was a predecessor of Kobe College (Kobe Jogakuin), exercising a major influence on Kobe&apos;s development.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this success, he expanded his business into real estate, financial business and at the same time was involved in urban development around Kobe Port such as Moto-machi (Kobe City) and Sannomiya, and foundation of Kobe Home, the boarding school for female students which was a predecessor of Kobe College (Kobe Jogakuin), exercising a major influence on Kobe&apos;s development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="45">
<j>明治4年（1871年）廃藩置県により三田県となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871 Sanda Domain was changed its name to Sanda Prefecture due to Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, Sanda Domain was changed its name to Sanda Prefecture due to Haihan-chiken.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, Sanda Domain was changed its name to Sanda Prefecture due to Haihan-chiken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>その後、兵庫県に編入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanda Prefecture was incorporated into Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was then incorporated into Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を一部変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was then incorporated into Hyogo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="47">
<j>藩主家は明治17年（1884年）子爵となり華族に列した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1884 the family of lord of Sanda domain was raised to the peerage as viscount.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1884 the family of lord of Sanda Domain was raised to the peerage as viscount.</e>
<cmt>Domain 大文字にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1884 the family of lord of Sanda Domain was raised to the peerage as viscount.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 エグゼビア(id:172680), ドルチェット(id:46458), 赤井彗星(id:18381), Monado(id:53906), クモハモハ大王(id:185685), Blowback(id:173308), Reggaeman(id:6214), Tiyoringo(id:70026), Point136(id:211299), かもめ(id:36246), Kamuin(id:5241), Roga246(id:53246), Jade0416(id:104181), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>