<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>焙烙火矢</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horokuhiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horokuhiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horokuhiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>焙烙火矢（ほうろくひや）は、戦国時代 (日本)の日本で考案、使用されていた兵器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horokuhiya is a weapon invented and used in Japan in the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horokuhiya was a weapon invented and used in Japan during the Sengoku Period (Period of Warring States).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horokuhiya was a weapon invented and used in Japan during the Sengoku period (period of warring states) (Japan).</e>
<cmt>period 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>なお、現在世間一般で言われている焙烙火矢は焙烙玉（後述）のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Horokuhiya that is generally recognized now is Horokudama (described below).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horokuhiya is generally recognized today as the weapon called Horokudama (described below).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horokuhiya is generally recognized today as the weapon called Horokudama (described below).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>焙烙玉の導火線に火を点けて、火縄銃の30匁筒など大筒に詰めて放ち、敵兵の殺傷を主目的とした兵器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is weapon to light a fuse of Horokudama, put it into big guns like 112g matchlock gun and fire to wound and kill enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A Horokudama was a weapon designed to wound and kill enemies by lighting its fuse, putting it into a large gun, such as the 112g matchlock, and firing it off.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A Horokudama was a weapon designed to wound and kill enemies by lighting its fuse, putting it into a large gun, such as the 112-gram matchlock, and firing it off.</e>
<cmt>30匁筒→112-gram matchlock　としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>付随して周辺の木造部分へ引火することもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly surrounding wood works caught fire sometimes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, wood surrounding the weapon often caught on fire.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Accordingly&quot; to &quot;Incidentally&quot;;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, wood surrounding the weapon often caught on fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>現代でいう焼夷弾に似た兵器であるが、爆発力や容器の破片での殺傷が主目的で、炎での攻撃は威力が低かったと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is similar to modern incendiary bomb, but the main purpose was its explosion power and to wound and kill enemies by its broken pieces of container, so the fire itself was likely to be no powerful attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was similar to a modern incendiary bomb, but its main purpose was to have explosive power to wound and kill enemies with broken fragments of its container, so the fire itself was not likely a very powerful attack.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was similar to a modern incendiary bomb, but its main purpose was to have explosive power to wound and kill enemies with broken fragments of its container, so the fire itself was not likely a very powerful attack.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>雑賀衆が船上などで用いていた事で有名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is famous that Saikashu (a group of soldiers from Saika in Wakayama) used it on board.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Saikashu (a group of soldiers from Saika in Wakayama) are famous for using it on board a ship.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;a ship&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Saikashu (a group of soldiers from Saika in Wakayama) are famous for using it on board a ship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>焙烙玉とは、料理器具である焙烙、ないしはそれに似た陶器に火薬を入れ、導火線に火を点けて敵方に投げ込む兵器。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Horakudama is a weapon made by putting powder in Horaku which is a kitchenware, or in a similar earthenware to light and throw into enemies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horokudama is a weapon created by putting gun powder in a piece of kitchenware called a Horoku or similar earthenware, lighting it and throwing it at enemies.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Horaku&quot; to &quot;Horoku&quot; for &quot;焙烙&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horokudama is a weapon created by putting gun powder in a piece of kitchenware called a Horoku or similar earthenware, lighting its fuse and throwing it at enemies.</e>
<cmt>導火線　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>手で直接投げたり縄を付けて遠心力で投げたりする手榴弾の様な物。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is something like a grenade to throw directly by hand or with rope using centrifugal force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is similar to a grenade, thrown directly by hand or sometimes with a rope using centrifugal force.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is similar to a grenade, thrown directly by hand or sometimes with a rope using centrifugal force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="9">
<j>こちらは雑賀衆の他に村上水軍、乃美水軍(浦水軍)、児玉水軍などの瀬戸内水軍も使用していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides Saikashu, the groups of pirates in Setouchi such as Mirakami suigun, Nomi suigun (Ura suigun), Kodama suigun also used it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the Saikashu, groups of pirates in Setouchi, such as Mirakami suigun, Nomi suigun (Ura suigun) and Kodama suigun also made use of Horokudama.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;it&quot; to &quot;horokudama&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the Saikashu, Setouchi navies, such as Murakami navy, Nomi navy (Ura navy) and Kodama navy also made use of Horokudama.</e>
<cmt>村上水軍、以下をXX navyとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="10">
<j>これらの兵器に対抗する為に織田信長が九鬼嘉隆に命じて鉄甲船を開発させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To compete against those weapons, Nobunaga ODA ordered Yoshitaka KUKI to develop Tekkosen (armoured ship with steel).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to compete against these weapons, Nobunaga ODA ordered Yoshitaka KUKI to develop Tekkosen (armored steel ships).</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;armoured&quot; to &quot;armored&quot; because I&apos;m an American＾＾; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to compete against these weapons, Nobunaga ODA ordered Yoshitaka KUKI to develop Tekkosen (armored steel ships).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="11">
<j>また、黒色火薬の火力を推進力として利用した原始的なロケットのような兵器を指して言う場合もあり、その中には標的に着弾した時に焼き払ったり爆発するように燃焼物や火薬を仕込むものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also sometimes indicates weapons like primitive rocket that used black fire powder as the driving force and some of them were loaded burning materials and powder to burn down their targets or explode when it land in the target.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Horokuhiya also indicate other similar weapons, such as primitive rockets that used gun powder for propulsion and were sometimes loaded with burning materials and gun powder to burn down targets or explode on impact.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;Horokuhiya&quot;; fixed grammar and word selection to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Horokuhiya also indicate other similar weapons, such as primitive rockets that used black gunpowder for propulsion and were sometimes loaded with burning materials and gun powder to burn down targets or explode on impact.</e>
<cmt>black を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>こうした兵器は、おそらくは中国の神火飛鴉などの同様のロケット型の兵器（火箭）を糸口にして作成されたと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those weapons were probably created by clues from the rocket shaped weapons in China (Kasen) such as Shinkahia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These weapons were likely created by clues from rocket-shaped weapons from China (Kasen), such as Shinkahia.</e>
<cmt>added hyphen in &quot;rocket-shaped&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These weapons were likely created by clues from rocket-shaped weapons from China (Kasen), such as Shinkahia (a missile disguised as a bird).</e>
<cmt>神火飛鴉　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>西洋諸国のように大形の大砲を製造できるほどにまだ鋳造技術が優れていなかった当時の東アジアでは、こうしたロケット型の兵器が攻城戦や海戦で比較的多く導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East Asia at the time didn&apos;t have superior casting technology yet like Western countries, therefore large cannons were unable to be produced and relatively-numerous rocket-shaped weapons were introduced in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time, East Asia had not yet created superior metal casting technology similar to Western countries. This meant that large cannons were unable to be produced and relatively numerous rocket-shaped weapons were introduced in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;metal&quot; before &quot;casting techology&quot; for better clarity; split into two sentences for easier reading; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time, East Asia had not yet created superior metal casting technology similar to Western countries, which meant that large cannons were unable to be produced and relatively numerous rocket-shaped weapons were introduced in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt>一文につなげました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>そもそも、建築物や軍船のほとんどが木製だったため、衝突力を主な攻撃力とする大砲よりも燃焼力、爆発力を利用した攻撃が有効だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because most of the buildings and warships were of wood at that time, an attack using burning power and explosion power was more effective than a cannon which used colliding force to attack.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Attacks using explosive force and burning power were more effective than cannons that used colliding force since most of the buildings and warships during this time were made of wood.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Attacks using explosive force and burning power were more effective than cannons that used colliding force since most of the buildings and warships during this time were made of wood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>こうした理由から攻城戦や水上戦で防御施設や船を焼き払うことができるために重要な戦力となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was therefore an important war potential to burn down defence facilities and ships in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there was significant military potential in burning down defense facilities and ships in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;important war potential&quot; to &quot;significant military potential&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there was significant military potential in such weapons as it could burn down defense facilities and ships in siege warfare and naval battles.</e>
<cmt>一部翻訳を補足しました</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>焙烙火矢、焙烙玉が使用されたとする戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battles in which Horakuhiya and Horakudama were used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battles in which Horakuhiya and Horakudama were used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battles in which Horakuhiya and Horakudama were used</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="16">
<j>厳島の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle of Itsukushima Island</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Itsukushima Island</e>
<cmt>these titles seem to deserve capitalization, so I made them so</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Itsuku-shima Island</e>
<cmt>Itsuku-shima としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>第一次木津川口の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first battle of Kizugawaguchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The First Battle of Kizugawaguchi</e>
<cmt>these titles seem to deserve capitalization, so I made them so</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The First Battle of Kizugawaguchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>第二次木津川口の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The second battle of Kizugawaguchi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Second Battle of Kizugawaguchi</e>
<cmt>these titles seem to deserve capitalization, so I made them so</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Second Battle of Kizugawaguchi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大塩平八郎の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heihachiro Oshio War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heihachiro Oshio War</e>
<cmt>these titles seem to deserve capitalization, so I made them so</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Rebellion of Heihachiro OSHIO</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 BuxWV(id:169145), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Young-G(id:153839), Judointel(id:160133), 水野白楓(id:22811), 白鉢巻(id:250052), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>