<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>段銭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tansen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tansen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tansen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>段銭（たんせん）とは日本の中世における税の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tansen was a form of tax in Japan&apos;si Middle Ages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tansen was a form of tax in Japan&apos;s Middle Ages.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tansen was a form of tax in Japan&apos;s Middle Ages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>仁治2年(1241年)に鎌倉幕府が課した例が初出といわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was adopted for the first time in 1241 by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was adopted for the first time in 1241 by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was adopted for the first time in 1241 by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>国家的行事や寺社の造営など、臨時の支出が必要な時に地域を限定(多くは国ごと)し、臨時に課する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was a temporary tax imposed on specific regions (usually by provinces) to fund national events or construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was a temporary tax imposed on specific regions (usually by provinces) to fund national events or construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was a temporary tax imposed on specific regions (usually by provinces) to fund national events or construction of shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>銭納が原則で、「田畑一反あたり何文」という形で課せられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The principle was to pay in cash, and the amount was calculated in ratio to the size of farming or rice fields.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The principle was to pay in cash, and the amount was calculated in proportion to the scale of farming or the size of rice fields.</e>
<cmt>rewording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The principle was to pay in cash, and the amount was calculated in proportion to &apos;the scale of farming or the size of rice fields.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>大田文に記載されている公田の数量に応じて課税する段銭を公田段銭（こうでんだんせん）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kodendansen (public tansen) was tansen imposed on the basis of the number of public fields recorded in the Otabumi (state land register).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kodendansen (public tansen) was tansen imposed on the basis of the number of public fields recorded in the Otabumi (state land register).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kodendansen (public tansen) was tansen imposed on the basis of the number of public fields recorded in the Otabumi (state land register).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>室町時代になると度々課せられるようになり、次第に恒常的税に変貌する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Muromachi Period, this tax was imposed so often that it gradually transpired into a permanent tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Muromachi Period, this tax was imposed so often that it gradually transpired into a permanent tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Muromachi period, this tax was imposed so often that it gradually transpired into a permanent tax.</e>
<cmt>表記を半角に変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>段銭が賦課された国には幕府から奉行が派遣されて徴収にあたるのが原則であるが、守護に代行させて徴収させる場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A magistrate would generally be sent by the bakufu to the tax-imposed province for tax collection but sometimes the bakufu would have a provincial governor act on its behalf.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A magistrate would generally be sent by the bakufu to the tax-imposed province for tax collection, but sometimes the bakufu would have a provincial governor act on its behalf.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A magistrate would generally be sent by the bakufu to the tax-imposed province for tax collection, but sometimes the bakufu would have a provincial governor act on its behalf.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、奉行や守護による徴収の場合、実際には彼らが算定した賦課額に上乗せをした金額を徴収して差額を得る場合もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes a magistrate or a provincial governor would add a top-up above the tax they calculated and put the difference in their pockets.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes a magistrate or a provincial governor would add a top-up above the tax they calculated and put the difference in their pockets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes a magistrate or a provincial governor would add a top-up above the tax they calculated and put the difference in their pockets.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>そのため、公家や寺院、奉公衆・奉行衆などの室町幕府官僚集団などは、段銭免除や京都の幕府倉奉行への直接納付（京済・直進）の特権を幕府から得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This encouraged the court nobles, shrines and temples and the bureaucratic groupings in the Muromachi bakufu, such as Hokoshu and Hogyoshu, to acquire the privilege from the bakufu either to be exempted from tansen or to pay directly to the bakufu&apos;s magistrate in Kyoto who was in charge of monetary and rice payment to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This encouraged the court nobles, shrines and temples, and the bureaucratic groupings in the Muromachi bakufu, such as Hokoshu and Hogyoshu, to acquire the privilege from the bakufu either to be exempted from tansen or to pay directly to the bakufu&apos;s magistrate in Kyoto, who was in charge of monetary and rice payment to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This encouraged the court nobles, shrines and temples, and the bureaucratic groupings in the Muromachi bakufu, such as hokoshu (a military post in Muromachi Shogunate) and bugyoshu (group of magistrates), to acquire the privilege from the bakufu either to be exempted from tansen or to pay directly to the bakufu&apos;s magistrate in Kyoto, who was in charge of monetary and rice payment to the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="10">
<j>また、守護や荘園領主なども私段銭と呼ばれる私的な段銭を徴収するようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, provincial governors and owners of manors began collecting shitansen, which was private tansen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, provincial governors and owners of manors began collecting shitansen, which was private tansen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, provincial governors and owners of manors began collecting shitansen, which was private tansen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>各領主は段銭帳を作成し、領内で賦課する段銭の基礎資料や記録とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Landlords kept tansen register and used it as the reference for collecting tansen and a record of tax collection in their estate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Landlords kept tansen registers and used them as references for collecting tansen and records of tax collection in their estate.</e>
<cmt>plural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Landlords kept tansen registers and used them as references for collecting tansen and records of tax collection in their estate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>後に私段銭は守護大名・戦国大名による領主的な賦課へと転換していくことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shitansen developed into a form of feudal landlord-tax imposed by provincial governors and daimyos (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shitansen developed into a form of feudal landlord-tax imposed by provincial governors and daimyos (Japanese territorial lords) in the Sengoku Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shitansen developed into a form of feudal landlord-tax imposed by provincial governors and Sengoku daimyo (Japanese territorial lord in the Sengoku period).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Nalc(id:139567), 伏儀(id:142093), 水野白楓(id:22811), 怪蘇(id:45514), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>