<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>飛鳥京</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka-kyo Or Asuka no Miyako (the Capital of Asuka)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asuka-kyo (the Capital of Asuka)</e>
<cmt>タイトルなので、一般的な読みを採用しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asuka-kyo (the Capital of Asuka)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>飛鳥京 (あすかきょう、あすかのみやこ) は現在の奈良県高市郡明日香村一帯にあったと想定される古代都市の、主に飛鳥時代のものを指し示す名称。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka-kyo or Asuka no miyako (the capital of Asuka) is the name of the ancient capital believed to be existed in the general area covering present-day Asuka-mura Takaichi-gun, Nara Prefecture; it refers to the part of the capital which was built primarily in the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asuka-kyo (also known as Asuka no Miyako [the capital of Asuka]) is the name of the ancient capital mainly in the Asuka period, which is believed to be existed in the general area covering present-day Asuka Village, Takaichi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asuka-kyo (also known as Asuka no Miyako [the capital of Asuka]) is the name of the ancient capital mainly in the Asuka period, which is believed to be existed in the general area covering present-day Asuka Village, Takaichi County, Nara Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>飛鳥時代の多くの期間は、この地域に天皇（大王 (ヤマト王権)）の宮が置かれており、今日的にいえば日本の首都であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the most part of the Asuka period, Emperor, okimi (great king), of Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) had a palace in the area and Asuka-kyo was the capital of Japan in today&apos;s language.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the most part of the Asuka period, the emperor (or okimi [great king]) of Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) had a palace in the area, that is, Asuka-kyo was what is now called the capital of Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the most part of the Asuka period, the emperor (or okimi [great king]) of Yamato sovereignty (the ancient Japan sovereignty) had a palace in the area, that is, Asuka-kyo was what is now called the capital of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>そのことを示して飛鳥「京」という名称が用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the word &quot;kyo&quot; (capital) is included in the name Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the word &quot;kyo&quot; (capital) is included in the name Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the word &quot;kyo&quot; (capital) is included in the name Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>後の時代の藤原京 (や平城京等) のように全体的に計画されて作られたものだとは考えられておらず、また、発掘調査など考古学的な成果においても全体像を明らかにするにいたっていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is agreed that Asuka-kyo didn&apos;t have an overall city plan unlike Fujiwara-kyo (the Imperial capital of Japan for sixteen years between 694 and 710) or Heijo-kyo (the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara) build in the later periods; in addition, the result of archaeological studies such as the data collected in excavation is not yet enough to form a comprehensive view of Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike later Fujiwara-kyo (the Imperial capital of Japan for 16 years between 694 and 710; or Heijo-kyo [the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara]), it is agreed that Asuka-kyo didn&apos;t have an overall city plan, in addition, the result of archaeological studies such as the data collected in excavation is not yet enough to form a comprehensive view of the Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike later Fujiwara-kyo (the Imperial capital of Japan for 16 years between 694 and 710; or Heijo-kyo [the ancient capital of Japan in current Nara]), it is agreed that Asuka-kyo didn&apos;t have an overall city plan, in addition, the result of archaeological studies such as the data collected in excavation is not yet enough to form a comprehensive view of the Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのため、地理的な範囲など「飛鳥京」が指し示すものの実態は必ずしも明確ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, what Asuka-kyo actually refers to, including the geographical area, is not strictly defined.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, what &apos;Asuka-kyo&apos; actually refers to, including the geographical area, is not strictly defined.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, what &apos;Asuka-kyo&apos; actually refers to, including the geographical area, is not strictly defined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのためか、歴史学や考古学的な文脈においても、飛鳥時代あたりの飛鳥を指すのに「飛鳥京」という名称が必ずしも使われているわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of the ambiguity of the term, the name &quot;Asuka-kyo&quot; is not always used to mean the Asuka area in the Asuka period in historical and archaeological contexts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Maybe because of the ambiguity of the term, the name &apos;Asuka-kyo&apos; is not always used to mean the Asuka area in the Asuka period in historical and archaeological contexts.</e>
<cmt>用語、クォーテーションを変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Maybe because of the ambiguity of the term, the name &apos;Asuka-kyo&apos; is not always used to mean the Asuka area in the Asuka period in historical and archaeological contexts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このような点については藤原京以降の「...京」と呼ばれるものとは対照的といえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this regard, &quot;Asuka-kyo&quot; is not like other cities with names ending with &quot;kyo&quot; established after Fujiwara-kyo; the area of Fujiwara-kyo was defined in the plan whereas that of &quot;Asuka-kyo&quot; was not defined in any plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this regard, it is not like other places with names ending with &apos;kyo&apos; established in and after Fujiwara-kyo.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this regard, it is not like other places with names ending with &apos;kyo&apos; established in and after Fujiwara-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ただし、飛鳥の街に対して「京」の字を使った表記は近年になって作り出されたわけではなく、古くは日本書紀においても「倭京」や「古京」と表記される例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Using the letter &quot;京&quot; (kyo) in the word for the city of Asuka did not start in recent years; examples are found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) and &quot;倭京&quot; and &quot;古京&quot; are used to describe &quot;Asuka-kyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The expression for the city of Asuka using the character &apos;京&apos; (kyo) did not create in recent years, but found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) such as &apos;倭京&apos; (literally, Japanese capital) and &apos;古京&apos; (literally, ancient capital).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The expression for the city of Asuka using the character &apos;京&apos; (kyo) did not create in recent years, but found in &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) such as &apos;倭京&apos; (literally, Japanese capital) and &apos;古京&apos; (literally, ancient capital).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>遺跡との関連においては、明日香村に飛鳥京跡と呼ばれる遺跡があるが、飛鳥京跡が文字通り飛鳥京の遺跡と考えられるものと等しいわけではないことに注意が必要である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In relation to ruins, there is the ruin called Asukakyo Site in Asuka-mura; however, it must be noted that Asukakyo Site should not literally be thought as the ruins of Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It requires attention that the ruins found in Asuka Village called the site of Asuka-kyo is not literally considered as the ruin of the Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It requires attention that the ruins found in Asuka Village called the site of Asuka-kyo is not literally considered as the ruin of the Asuka-kyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>明日香村には飛鳥京を構成していたものだと考えられる遺跡は多数ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are many ruins thought to be parts of the Asuka-kyo in Asuka-mura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are many ruins thought to be parts of the Asuka-kyo in Asuka Village.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are many ruins thought to be parts of the Asuka-kyo in Asuka Village.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>それらは、島庄遺跡、石神遺跡、水落遺跡 など遺跡の存在地の字 (あざ、大字の場合も小字の場合も) を冠するもの、雷丘東方遺跡、甘樫丘東麓遺跡 など遺跡の存在地を他の地理的名称から示したもの、川原寺跡、飛鳥寺跡 など建造物に由来するもの、飛鳥池遺跡、飛鳥京跡苑池遺構 など遺跡の機能や形状を示したものなどがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimasho Site, Ishigami Site, and Mizuochi Site derived their names from the names of sites&apos; locations (large or small administrative units of villages), Ikazuchi no Oka Toho Site and Amakashi no Oka Toroku Site derived their names from the references to their geographical locations, Kawahara-dera Temple Site and Asuka-dera Temple Site derived their names from the architectural structures on their sites, and Asukaike Ruins and Asukakyo-enchi Site derived their names from functions or forms of their ancient structural remnants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among them, there are ruins derived from their names from the names of sites&apos; locations (large or small administrative units of villages) such as Shimasho Site, Ishigami Site, and Mizuochi Site, those from the references to their geographical locations such as Ikazuchi no Oka Toho Site and Amakashi no Oka Toroku Site, those from the architectural structures on their sites such as Kawahara-dera Temple Site and Asuka-dera Temple Site, and those from functions or forms of their ancient structural remnants such as Asukaike Ruins and Asukakyo-ato Enchi Site.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among them, there are ruins derived from their names from the names of sites&apos; locations (large or small administrative units of villages) such as Shimasho Site, Ishigami Site, and Mizuochi Site, those from the references to their geographical locations such as Ikazuchi no Oka Toho Site and Amakashi no Oka Toroku Site, those from the architectural structures on their sites such as Kawahara-dera Temple Site and Asuka-dera Temple Site, and those from functions or forms of their ancient structural remnants such as Asukaike Ruins and Asukakyo-ato Enchi Site.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>命名には特に規則性は無いようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were no special rules for naming these sites.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It seems no special rules are found for naming these sites.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It seems no special rules are found for naming these sites.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ゴンボ(id:22207), Ｋ－２１(id:102707), ロロ(id:104252), Arisis0215(id:113505), TEy(id:32722), BAKU(id:55205), Iunewruueruyuyr(id:126521), 彩華1226(id:64711), Reedo(id:155043), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>