<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>領家</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoke (a lord of the manor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoke (a lord of the manor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoke</e>
<cmt>トピックタイトルなので、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>領家（りょうけ）は、日本の荘園において、荘園を開発した開発領主（かいほつりょうしゅ）から寄進を受けた荘園領主である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoke is a term used in the context of Japanese shoen (manor in medieval Japan) to represent a lord of the manor, or shoen, donated by Kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoke is a term used in the context of Japanese shoen (manor in medieval Japan) to represent a lord of the manor, or shoen, donated by Kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoke is a term used in the context of Japanese shoen (manor in medieval Japan) to represent a lord of the shoen, donated by Kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land).</e>
<cmt>用語表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>中央の有力貴族や有力寺社が荘園寄進を受けて領家となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Powerful central nobility, temples, and shrines that were donated shoen became ryoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Powerful central nobility, temples, and shrines that were donated shoen became ryoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Powerful central nobility, temples, and shrines that were donated shoen became ryoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>平安時代中葉の10世紀後期から11世紀の頃、地方の有力農民である田堵（たと）による田地開発とその私有地化が活発化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the mid Heian period, from the late 10th century to the 11th century, farmlands development and their privatization by Tato, local powerful farmers, had been accelerated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the mid-Heian period, from the late 10th century to the 11th century, farmland development and their privatization by Tato, local powerful farmers, had been accelerated.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the mid-Heian period, from the late 10th century to the 11th century, farmland development and their privatization by Tato, local powerful farmers, had been accelerated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>このような開発田地の所有者を開発領主という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The owners of those developed farmlands were called Kaihatsu-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The owners of those developed farmlands were called Kaihatsu-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The owners of those developed farmlands were called Kaihatsu-ryoshu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>しかし、その土地所有は法的根拠に欠け、国衙に収公される可能性も高く、非常に不安定なものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, their status of land possession actually lacked the legal foundation and was therefore quite unstable, with high possibility of confiscation of their lands by kokuga (provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, their status of land possession actually lacked legal foundation and was therefore quite unstable, with a high possibility of confiscation of their lands by kokuga (provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, their status of land possession actually lacked legal foundation and was therefore quite unstable, with a high possibility of confiscation of their lands by kokuga (provincial government offices).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そのため、開発領主の多くは、中央の有力貴族や有力寺社へ荘園を寄進することで、荘園の支配権・管理権を確保するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, many of Kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to retain their dominion and the right to manage shoen by donating their shoen to the powerful central nobility, temples, and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, many Kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to retain their dominion and the right to manage shoen by donating their shoen to the powerful central nobility, temples, and shrines.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, many Kaihatsu-ryoshu tried to retain their dominion and the right to manage shoen by donating their shoen to the powerful central nobility, temples, and shrines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このとき、寄進を受けた者が領家である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who were donated shoen in this situation were called ryoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who were donated shoen in this situation were called ryoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who were donated shoen in this situation were called ryoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>当時、天皇の代替わりの際に「新政」として荘園整理令が出されたり、また、国衙が荘園を認めずに国衙領へ編入しようとすることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, Manor Regulation Acts were often ordered by a &apos;new government&apos; upon the change of the emperors, and also in many cases, kokuga did not authorize the ownership of shoen and incorporated them into Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, Manor Regulation Acts were often ordered by a &apos;new government&apos; upon the change of the emperors, and also in many cases, kokuga did not authorize the ownership of shoen and incorporated them into Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, Manor Regulation Acts were often ordered by a &apos;new government&apos; upon the change of the emperors, and also in many cases, kokuga did not authorize the ownership of shoen and incorporated them into Kokugaryo (territories governed by provincial government office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>領家の権威だけでは荘園の所有が維持できないケースも見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sometimes, the authorities of ryoke alone were not enough to maintain their possession of shoen.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sometimes, the authority of ryoke alone was not enough to maintain their possession of shoen.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sometimes, the authority of ryoke alone was not enough to maintain their possession of shoen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>そこで、より権威のある皇族や摂関家へ領家から荘園寄進が行われることがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To cope with these situations, some ryoke would donate their shoen to more authoritative bodies like the Imperial family or Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To cope with this situation, some ryoke would donate their shoen to more authoritative bodies like the Imperial family or Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To cope with this situation, some ryoke would donate their shoen to more authoritative bodies like the Imperial family or Sekkan-ke (the families which produced regents).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>これらの最上位の荘園領主を本家（ほんけ）という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The lord of the manor on the top of this hierarchy was called honke (head family).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The lord of the manor on the top of this hierarchy was called honke (head family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The lord of the manor on the top of this hierarchy was called honke (head family).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>本家・領家のうち、荘園の実効支配権を持つ者を本所（ほんじょ）と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Specifically, the honke loads of the manor who had effective dominion of shoen were called Honjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Specifically, the honke lords of the manor who had effective dominion of shoen were called Honjo.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Specifically, the honke and ryoke who had effective dominion of shoen were called Honjo.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>本所が、荘園に係る権利・利益の一部を他の貴族へ付与し、その貴族を領家ということもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In some cases, other nobilities who were granted part of the rights and profits of honjo regarding shoen were called ryoke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In some cases, other nobilities who were granted part of the rights and profits of honjo regarding shoen were called ryoke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In some cases, other nobility who were granted part of the rights and profits of honjo regarding shoen were called ryoke.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>領家は、開発領主を現地管理者として荘官に任命した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoke appointed kaihatsu-ryoshu as shokan (an officer governing shoen) to play a role of local managers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoke appointed kaihatsu-ryoshu as shokan (an officer governing shoen) to play the role of local managers.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoke appointed Kaihatsu-ryoshu as shokan (an officer governing shoen) to play the role of local managers.</e>
<cmt>前出用語に合わせました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>領家は荘官を通じて、荘園からの収穫を年貢として徴収したり、荘園内の百姓（荘民）に労役を課したり（公事）して、自らの収入とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Through those shokan, ryoke collected harvests from their shoen as nengu (land tax), and imposed labor service (kuji (public duties)) on the shomin (farmers living in their manor), taking those taxes as their own revenue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through those shokan, ryoke collected harvests from their shoen as nengu (land tax), and imposed labor service (kuji (public duties)) on the shomin (farmers living in their manor), taking those taxes as their own revenue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through those shokan, ryoke collected harvests from their shoen as nengu (land tax), and imposed labor service (kuji [public duties]) on the shomin (farmers living in their manor), taking those taxes as their own revenue.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>本家がある場合は、その収入の一部を本家へ納入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If they had honke, they delivered some of the revenue to their honke.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If they had honke, they delivered some of the revenue to their honke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If they had honke, they delivered some of the revenue to their honke.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>領家はほとんどの場合、中央に在していたため、現地で紛争が発生した時は、その対応を荘官へ任せたり、御使（おんし）という使者を派遣して対応させることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since ryoke mostly resided in the central areas, when disputes or troubles erupted in local areas, ryoke usually had shokan deal with them, or dispatched an envoy called onshi to solve the situation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since ryoke mostly resided in the central areas, when disputes or trouble erupted in local areas, ryoke usually had shokan deal with them, or dispatched an envoy called onshi to solve the situation.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since ryoke mostly resided in the central areas, when disputes or trouble erupted in local areas, ryoke usually had shokan deal with them, or dispatched an envoy called onshi to solve the situation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>時代が下ると、荘官の武士化が始まり、鎌倉時代には荘官が鎌倉幕府から地頭に任じられる例も見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later eras, Bushika (classification where shokan became a samurai) began to be seen, and in some cases in the Kamakura period, some shokan were even appointed as jito (manager and lord of manor) by Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later eras, Bushika (classification where shokan became a samurai) began to be seen, and in some cases in the Kamakura period, some shokan were even appointed as jito (manager and lord of manor) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later eras, shokan began to work like samurai, and in some cases in the Kamakura period, some shokan were even appointed as jito (manager and lord of manor) by the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>武士化した荘官は、次第に領家を軽視するようになり、領家の支配権は蚕食されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gradually, those armed shokan had come to disregard ryoke, encroaching their dominion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gradually, these armed shokan had come to disregard ryoke, encroaching their dominion.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gradually, these armed shokan had come to disregard ryoke, encroaching their dominion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>室町時代に入ると、守護に直接、荘園からの年貢徴収を認める半済が行われるようになり、領家の権益はさらに奪われていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the beginning of the Muromachi period, the introduction of hanzei system (the system where the Muromachi bakufu allowed military governors or Shugo to collect half of the taxes from manors and demesnes as military fund) further encroached ryoke&apos;s vested interests.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the beginning of the Muromachi period, the introduction of the hanzei system (the system where the Muromachi bakufu allowed military governors or Shugo to collect half of the taxes from manors and demesnes as military funds) further encroached on ryoke&apos;s vested interests.</e>
<cmt>slight modification</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the beginning of the Muromachi period, the introduction of the hanzei system (the system where the Muromachi bakufu allowed military governors or Shugo to collect half of the taxes from manors and demesnes as military funds) further encroached on ryoke&apos;s vested interests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>最終的には、太閤検地に伴う荘園の解体により領家という地位も消滅したことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eventually, shoen were demised by taiko kenchi (the cadastral surveys conducted by Hideyoshi), leading to extinction of the position of ryoke as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eventually, shoen were demised by taiko kenchi (the cadastral surveys conducted by Hideyoshi), leading to extinction of the position of ryoke as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eventually, shoen were demised by taiko kenchi (the cadastral surveys conducted by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI), leading to extinction of the position of ryoke as well.</e>
<cmt>用語補足を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Shimoxx(id:9332), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>