<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>不輸の権 (日本)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) (Japan)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) (Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyu no ken (Japan)</e>
<cmt>タイトルですので、補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>不輸の権（ふゆのけん）とは、荘園が国家への租税の一部またはすべてが免除される権利。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was the right of shoen to be exempted from all or part of the land tax to be paid to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was the right of shoen to be exempted from all or part of the land tax to be paid to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was the right of shoen (manor in medieval Japan) to be exempted from all or part of the land tax to be paid to the government.</e>
<cmt>荘園　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本においては、10世紀ころ、摂関政治のもとで官省符荘をもって成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Japan it was established in the form of Kanshofu so (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) around the tenth century under regency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Japan it was established in the form of Kanshofu so (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs) around the tenth century under regency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Japan it was established in the form of Kanshofu sho (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both Dajokan [the Council of State] and Minbusho [the Ministry of Popular Affairs]) around the tenth century under regency.</e>
<cmt>官省符荘→Kanshohu sho と読みを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>官省符荘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanshofu so (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanshofu so (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanshofu sho</e>
<cmt>官省符荘→Kanshohu sho と読みを変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>上級の官庁から下級の官庁へと下す文書を「符」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A document that was passed from superior authority to lower authority was called &apos;Fu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A document that was passed from superior authority to lower authority was called &apos;Fu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A document that was passed from superior authority to lower authority was called &apos;Fu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>しかし、荘園の寄進を受けて本家や領家となった大貴族（権門勢家）・大寺社などの荘園領主はみずからの政治権力を行使した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, having been donated shoen, major aristocrats (the great and powerful) and major temples became Honke (the owner of the highest-graded patches of land under the stratified land ruling) or ryoke (lords of the manors), and they exercised their political power as the lords of manors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, having been donated shoen, major aristocrats (the great and powerful) and major temples became Honke (the owner of the highest-grade patches of land under the stratified land ruling) or ryoke (lords of the manors), and they exercised their political power as the lords of manors.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, having been donated shoen, major aristocrats (the great and powerful) and major temples became honke (the owner of the highest-grade patches of land under the stratified land ruling) or ryoke (lords of the manors), and they exercised their political power as the lords of shoen.</e>
<cmt>honke 小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そして、太政官の発する太政官符や太政官の指令に基づいて民部省が発する民部省符によって、租税の徴収権を国家より公認された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the state granted them the right to collect surtax, based on the Dajokan (Grand Council of State) fu (tally) and the Minbusho fu issued by the Ministry of Popular Affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the state granted them the right to collect surtax, based on the Dajokan (Grand Council of State) fu (tally) and the Minbusho fu issued by the Ministry of Popular Affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the state granted them the right to collect surtax by issuing the Dajokanpu (the official documents of the Dajokan) issued by Dajokan or Minbushofu (the official documents of the Minbusho) issued by Minbusho.</e>
<cmt>太政官符、民部省符　補足を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>その免田（荘田）の年貢や公事を自己の収入とし、国家に対しては租税の一部またはすべてが免除された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The nengu (annual tribute, land tax) on the tax-exempt rice fields and kuji (public duties) were the sources of their incomes, and they were exempted from all or part of the land tax to be paid to the state.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The nengu (annual tribute, land tax) on tax-exempt rice fields and kuji (public duties) were the sources of their incomes, and they were exempted from all or part of the land tax to be paid to the state.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The nengu (annual tribute, land tax) on tax-exempt rice fields and kuji (public duties) were the sources of their incomes, and they were exempted from all or part of the land tax to be paid to the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>このような荘園を「官省符荘」と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen like this was called &apos;Kanshofu so&apos; (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen like these were called &apos;Kanshofu so&apos; (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoen like these were called &apos;Kanshofu sho.&apos;</e>
<cmt>官省符荘→Kanshohu sho と読みを変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>国免荘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokumen sho (a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in bempo or binko system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokumen sho (a shoen allowed exemption from so or other tribute in a bempo or binko system)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokumen sho (provincially exempted shoen)</e>
<cmt>補足を変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>不輸の権は官省符荘をもって成立したが、のちに地方における国司の権限が強大となると、しばしば自分自身や、縁故のある貴族・寺社に対し、国司による認可（国司免判）が認められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was established in the form of Kanshofu so (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs), as Kokushi (provincial governors) came to have more authority later on, they were often allowed to grant authorization (remission of Tax by kokushi) to themselves, as well as connected aristocrats, shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was established in the form of Kanshofu so (a shoen enjoying immunity from taxation by virtue of having official documents from both the Council of State and the Ministry of Popular Affairs), as Kokushi (provincial governors) came to have more authority later on, they were often allowed to grant authorization (remission of Tax by kokushi) to themselves, as well as connected aristocrats, shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Fuyu no ken was established in the form of Kanshofu sho, as kokushi (provincial governors) came to have more authority later on, they were often allowed to grant authorization (remission of tax by kokushi) to themselves, as well as connected aristocrats, shrines and temples.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>このような荘園を「国司免判の荘」略して「国免荘」と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen like this was called &apos;Kokushi menban no so&apos; (So of remission of tax by kokushi,&apos; or &apos;Kokumen so&apos; in short.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen like these were called &apos;Kokushi menban no so&apos; (So of remission of tax by kokushi,&apos; or &apos;Kokumen so&apos; in short.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoen like these were called &apos;Kokushi menban no sho&apos; (sho of remission of tax by kokushi), or &apos;Kokumen sho&apos; in short.</e>
<cmt>国免荘→kokumen sho としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ただし、国免荘で不輸の権が保障されるのは国司の任期中に限られていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was guaranteed for Kokumen sho only during the kokushi&apos;s term.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was guaranteed for Kokumen sho only during the kokushi&apos;s term.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Fuyu no ken was guaranteed for Kokumen sho only during the kokushi&apos;s term.</e>
<cmt>既出単語の補足を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>国免荘における不輸の権は、国司辞任後の生活にそなえたものであり、多くは任期の末期に生じたが、次期の国司によって収公されることが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was for kokushi to prepare for the life after retirement, the right was exercised more towards the end of his term, but in many cases what he had gained was confiscated by the incoming kokushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Fuyu no ken (the right of tax exemption) was for kokushi to prepare for life after retirement, the right was exercised more towards the end of his term, but in many cases what he had gained was confiscated by the incoming kokushi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Fuyu no ken was for kokushi to prepare for life after retirement, the right was exercised more towards the end of his term, but in many cases what he had gained was confiscated by the incoming kokushi.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>荘園内での開発が進展するにともない、不輸の範囲や対象をめぐる開発領主と国司の対立がはげしくなると、荘園領主の権威を利用して国司の使者の立ち入りを認めない不入の権 (日本)を得る荘園が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the progress of developments in shoen, the conflict between kaihatsu-ryoshu (local notables who actually developed the land) and kokushi intensified over the scope and the target of Fuyu (tax exemption), and more and more shoen acquired Funyu no ken (the right to keep the tax agents from entering the property) so that they could take advantage of the authority of kokushi to refuse the entry by kokushi&apos;s envoy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the progress of developments in shoen, conflict between kaihatsu-ryoshu (local nobles who actually developed the land) and kokushi intensified over the scope and the target of Fuyu (tax exemption), and more and more shoen acquired Funyu no ken (the right to keep the tax agents from entering their property) so they could take advantage of refusing the entry by kokushi&apos;s envoy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the progress of developments in shoen, conflict between kaihatsu-ryoshu (local nobles who actually developed the land) and kokushi intensified over the scope and the target of Fuyu (tax exemption), and more and more shoen acquired Funyu no ken (the right to keep the tax agents from entering their property) so they could take advantage of refusing the entry by kokushi&apos;s envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして、両特権の拡大によって、荘園における土地・人民の私的支配はいっそう強まり、荘園を整理しようとする国司と荘園領主とのあいだでも対立が深まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, due to the expansion of the two privileges, private dominance of land and people in shoen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, due to the expansion of the two privileges, private dominance of land and people in shoen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, due to the expansion of the two privileges, private dominance of land and people in shoen further grew, and the confrontation between kokushi who tried to reorganize shoen and lords of shoen intensified.</e>
<cmt>翻訳を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>こうして、紛争は日本各地で多発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, many disputes occurred in various parts of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, many disputes occurred in various parts of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, many disputes occurred in various parts of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>地方豪族や有力農民のなかには自らの勢力を維持・拡大するため、また、農民の反抗を防止して土地・人民を確保するために武装する者が少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quite a few powerful local clans and influential peasants armed themselves to maintain and enlarge their power, and to secure the land and people by preventing defiance by the peasants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quite a few powerful local clans and influential peasants armed themselves to maintain and enlarge their power, and to secure the land and people by preventing defiance by the peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quite a few powerful local clans and influential peasants armed themselves to maintain and enlarge their power, and to secure the land and people by preventing defiance by the peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また、紛争鎮圧のために政府から押領使や追捕使として派遣された中級・下級の貴族のなかにも武士として現地に留まる者があらわれ、やがて軍事的ネットワークが各地に形成されていくのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, some middle-level and lower-level aristocrats that the government had dispatched as Oryoshi or Tsuibushi (envoys to pursue and capture) to suppress disputes remained in the locality, and before long military networks were formed around the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, some middle-level and lower-level aristocrats that the government had dispatched as Oryoshi or Tsuibushi (envoys to pursue and capture) to suppress disputes remained in the locality, and before long military networks were formed around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, some middle-level and lower-level aristocrats that the government had dispatched as Oryoshi or Tsuibushi (envoys to pursue and capture) to suppress disputes remained in the locality, and before long military networks were formed around the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Greenland4(id:114494), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>