<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>藩札</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hansatsu (a Han Bill)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hansatsu (a Han Bill)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hansatsu (a Han Bill)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>藩札（はんさつ）は、江戸時代に各藩が独自に領内に発行した紙幣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A han bill was a bill issued by respective domains for use within their territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A han bill was paper currency issued by each domain for use within their respective territories.</e>
<cmt>Clarified what kind of bill.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A han bill was paper currency issued by each domain for use within their respective territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>最初の藩札は、福井藩が寛文元年（1661年）に発行したものであると言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first han bill is said to have been issued by the Fukui Domain in 1661.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first han bill is said to have been issued by Fukui Domain in 1661.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first han bill is said to have been issued by Fukui Domain in 1661.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>それ以前に伊勢国や大和国で私札の発行が見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before han bills were issued, private bills were issued in Ise Province and Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before han bills were issued, private bills were issued in Ise Province and Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before han bills were issued, private bills were issued in Ise Province and Yamato Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>現存する日本最古の紙幣ともいわれる山田羽書（1610年）もこれに属する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamada Hagaki (issued in 1610), which is said to be the oldest existing bill in Japan, was also a private bill.</e>
<cmt>Yamada Hagaki:http://www.imes.boj.or.jp/cm/pdffiles/kahei20_53.pdf一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamada Hagaki (issued in 1610), which is said to be the oldest existing bill in Japan, was also a private bill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamada Hagaki (issued in 1610), which is said to be the oldest existing bill in Japan, was also a private bill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当時は貨幣鋳造技術が未発達であり、土木工事などの賃金の支払いで小額貨幣が大量に必要になったときに、これらの私札が発行されたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, coin-cast technologies were not well- developed, so private bills are assumed to have been issued when a large amount of fractional coins were needed for purposes such as payment of workers on construction projects.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, coin-casting technology was not well-developed, so private bills are assumed to have been issued when a large amount of low denomination coins were needed for purposes such as payment of workers on construction projects.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, coin-casting technology was not well-developed, so private bills are assumed to have been issued when a large amount of low denomination coins were needed for purposes such as payment of workers on construction projects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>これらの私札が藩札への発行へとつながったと見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Private bills eventually led to the creation of han bills.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Private bills eventually led to the creation of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Private bills eventually led to the creation of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>その後、特に銀遣い経済地域である西国の諸大名を中心として、多くの藩が藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, han bills were issued by many domains, mainly territorial lords in Saigoku (the western part of Japan) where silver coins were commonly circulated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, han bills were issued by many domains, mainly territorial lords in Saigoku (the western part of Japan) where silver coins were commonly circulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, han bills were issued by many domains, mainly territorial lords in Saigoku (the western part of Japan) where silver coins were commonly circulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>藩札発行の目的は、自領内の貨幣の不足を補い、通貨量の調整機能を担わせることであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purposes of issuing han bills were to supplement coins in times of shortages and to adjust the amount of coins in circulation within their territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purposes of issuing han bills were to supplement coins in times of shortages and to adjust the amount of coins in circulation within territories.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purposes of issuing han bills were to supplement coins in times of shortages and to adjust the amount of coins in circulation within territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>それには十分な正貨準備が不可欠であったが、実際には、藩札発行で得られる実通貨の納庫を目論み、これによって藩の財政難の解消を試みる場合がしばしばあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For those purposes, preparing sufficient coins was necessary, but keeping those exchanged coins within their domains were still important, as each domain tried to save as much coins as possible to improve their financial situation within their domains.</e>
<cmt>原文の意味が、前文とつながっていません。前文では、貨幣の不足を補うことが目的とされているにもかかわらず、当文では、「それには（その目的のためには）十分な正貨準備が不可欠であった・・・」とされています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For those purposes, preparing sufficient coins was necessary, but keeping those exchanged coins within their domains were still important, as each domain tried to save as many coins as possible to improve their financial situation within their domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such issuance was supposed to be based on a sufficient amount of standard coins retained by the domain, but actually, in most cases, domains tried to collect as many circulating coins as possible in exchange for issued han bills for the purpose of improving their financial situation.</e>
<cmt>「本来であれば藩札発行には裏付けとなる正貨の存在が必要なはずだが、実際には、市中から通貨を回収して藩の資金に充てるために藩札が発行された」という内容であると解釈して修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>藩札の流通は、藩が独自の流通規則を定め、藩札以外の貨幣の流通を禁じた藩もあったが、藩札と幕府貨幣の両方の流通を認めた藩も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each domain regulated the circulation of currency independently; some domains forbade the circulation of other currencies, but many domains allowed the circulation of both han bills and the currency issued by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each domain regulated the circulation of currency independently; some domains forbade the circulation of other currencies, but many domains allowed the circulation of both han bills and the currency issued by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each domain regulated the circulation of currency independently; some domains forbade the circulation of other currencies, but many domains allowed the circulation of both han bills and the currency issued by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>藩札の運用が行き詰った場合に、藩札の兌換を巡る取り付け騒ぎや一揆、打ちこわしも発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When domains had difficulty managing han bills, panics, uprisings and destructive urban riots broke out over the exchange of han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When domains had difficulty managing han bills, panics, uprisings and destructive urban riots broke out over the exchange of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When domains had difficulty managing han bills, panics, uprisings and destructive urban riots broke out over the exchange of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>藩札は藩の取り潰しがあれば紙くずになるリスクも存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Han bills always had the risk of forfeiture whenever domains were disbanded.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Han bills always had the risk of forfeiture whenever domains were broken up.</e>
<cmt>Wording - disbanding a domain sounds unnatural.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Han bills always had the risk of forfeiture whenever domains were broken up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>藩の財政状況が悪化すれば藩札の信用力も落ちる結果につながる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The credibility of han bills was also at risk whenever economies worsened.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The credibility of han bills was also at risk whenever economies worsened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The credibility of han bills was also at risk whenever the financial situation of the domain worsened.</e>
<cmt>「経済が」ではなく「藩の財政状況が」です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>藩札は表書きの金銀などの兌換保証が前提であったが、実際には、藩にそれだけの正貨が用意できたところは少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although han bills carried a face value, which was promised to be exchangeable for gold or silver coins, few domains could prepare enough coins to honar that promise.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although han bills carried a face value, and were promised to be exchangeable for gold or silver coins, few domains could prepare enough coins to honor that promise.</e>
<cmt>Wording/ spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although han bills carried a face value, and were promised to be exchangeable for gold or silver coins, few domains could prepare enough coins to honor that promise.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>初期のころは、藩自身が藩札会所などを設けて藩札の発行を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early on, han bills were issued at a hansatsu-kaisho (exchanger for han bills).</e>
<cmt>藩札会所:定訳不明一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early on, the domain&apos;s themselves established hansatsu-kaisho (exchanger of han bills) to issue han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording, some information missing in original translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early on, domains themselves established hansatsu-kaisho (exchanger of han bills) to issue han bills.</e>
<cmt>所有格にする意味がありません。特定の藩ではないので無冠詞複数が妥当です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>その後、領地内外の富裕な商人が藩札の札元となり発行を行い、その商人の信用によって藩札が流通した側面もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, they were distributed through credible merchants who were prominent in the distribution of han bills.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, they were issued through wealthy merchants who were prominent in the distribution of han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, they were issued through wealthy merchants who were prominent in the distribution of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>畿内近国においては、幕府領、諸藩領、旗本領などがモザイク状に入り組んでいたために、他領地との取引が諸領の経済活動に占める割合は非常に大きかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were many territories within the Kinai-Kingoku area (the shogunate, domains and hatamoto [direct retainers of the shogunate]), so the percentage of trading within the domains was high.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were many territories within the Kinai-Kingoku area (the shogunate, domains and hatamoto [direct retainers of the shogunate]), so a high percentage of trading was conducted within these domains.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were many territories within the Kinai-Kingoku area (the shogunate, domains and hatamoto [direct retainers of the shogunate]), so a high percentage of trading was conducted within these domains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>また江戸時代後期以降は幕府の意図的な銀単位通貨流通量抑制政策のために手形や藩札による取引も盛んであったため、藩札が発行した藩の思惑に反して藩領を超えた比較的広い範囲にまで流通していた場合も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the late Edo period, trading with the tegata (drafts) or han bills were active due to a policy intentionally issued by the shogunate to control the amount of silver coins in circulation, so han bills were sometimes extensively circulated over the domains against expectations of the domains who issued those han bills.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処銀単位通貨流通量抑制政策: 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the late Edo period, trading with tegata (drafts) or han bills was active due to a policy issued by the shogunate to control the amount of silver coins in circulation, so han bills were sometimes extensively circulated outside the issuing domain, against the expectations of the domains who had issued those han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the late Edo period, trading with tegata (drafts) or han bills was active due to a policy adopted by the shogunate to control the amount of silver coins in circulation, so han bills were sometimes extensively circulated outside the issuing domain, against the expectations of the domains who had issued those han bills.</e>
<cmt>「政策を発行する」では不自然です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>近隣の藩で藩札が発行された場合、領内の良貨（幕府貨幣）が悪貨（近隣の藩が発行した信用の裏付けの弱い紙幣）に取って代わられる、言い換えれば良貨を近隣他領に吸い上げられることは自領の経済活動に悪影響が及ぶ可能性があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">If neighboring domains issued han bills, there was a possibility that good currency (coins issued by the shogunate) was exchanged for bad currency (bills issued by neighboring domains which had low credibility) and which could affect the economy of the domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">If neighboring domains issued han bills, there was a possibility that good currency (coins issued by the shogunate) was exchanged for bad currency (bills issued by neighboring domains which had low credibility), which could affect the economy of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">If neighboring domains issued han bills, there was a possibility that good currency (coins issued by the shogunate) was exchanged for bad currency (bills issued by neighboring domains which had low credibility), which could affect the economy of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>それを防ぐための自衛策として、小藩や旗本領、関東諸藩の飛び地領などでも独自の紙幣を発行せざるを得なくなる場合も少なくなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To prevent that, they had to issue their own han bills in the detached territories of small domains, hatamoto and various domains in the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To prevent that, the detached territories of small domains, hatamoto and various domains in the Kanto region had to issue their own han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To prevent that, the detached territories of small domains, hatamoto and various domains in the Kanto region had to issue their own han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="22">
<j>明治4年（1871年）に明治政府が藩札の発行状況を調べたところ、全国の藩の約8割に当たる244藩、14の代官所、9の旗本領が紙幣の発行を行っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Meiji government researched the issue status of han bills in 1871, they found that 244 domains (80 percent of all domains), 14 magistrate&apos;s offices, and 9 hatamoto issued han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Meiji government researched the issue status of han bills in 1871, they found that 244 domains (80 percent of all domains), 14 magistrate&apos;s offices, and 9 hatamoto issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Meiji government researched the issue status of han bills in 1871, they found that 244 domains (80 percent of all domains), 14 magistrate&apos;s offices, and 9 hatamoto issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>明治政府は同年の廃藩置県の機に藩札回収令を発布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji government issued the Order of Withdrawing Han Bills when Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was introduced in 1871.</e>
<cmt>藩札回収令：定訳不明一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji government issued the Order of Withdrawing Han Bills when Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was introduced in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji government issued the Order of Withdrawing Han Bills when Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) was introduced in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>その後、各藩札の正貨との実交換相場による藩札回収を始めたが、処理を完了したのは明治12年（1879年）6月であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the government started to withdraw han bills in exchange for coins at actual rate after issuing the order, they only completed withdrawing in June 1879.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the government started to withdraw han bills in exchange for coins at the actual rate after issuing the order, they only completed withdrawing in June 1879.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the government started to withdraw han bills in exchange for coins at the actual rate after issuing the order, they only completed withdrawing in June 1879.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>廃藩置県後、新通貨が整備されて普及するまでは、太政官札・民部省札などといった藩札類似の政府発行紙幣、旧幕府領に設置された府県のいくつかが発行した札、新政府が各地の商業中心地に開設させた為替会社や通商会社が発行した札などと並び、藩札に円銭厘の単位を示した大蔵省印が加印された藩札が、新貨交換比率が設定された寛永通寶銭などの銭貨と共に使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to Daijokan bills and Minbusho bills (bills issued by the governamet akin to han bills), bills issued by prefectures placed in the old shogunate&apos;s territories, and bills issued by exchange companies and commerce companies (companies established in the heart of commerce in various places by the government), han bills with a stamp of the Ministry of Finance showing yen, sen, and ri (unit of old currency), and coins set up new exchange rate, such as Kanei Tsuho, were also circulated until new currency was spread and circulated after Haihan-chiken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Haihan-chiken (the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), and until the new currency had spread and circulated, the government issued the following: Daijokan bills and Minbusho bills (bills issued by the government akin to han bills); bills issued by prefectures placed in the old shogunate&apos;s territories; bills issued by exchange companies and commerce companies (companies established in the heart of commerce in various places by the government); han bills with a stamp of the Ministry of Finance showing yen, sen, and ri (units of old currency); and coins with a newly established exchange rate, such as Kanei Tsuho.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Haihan-chiken (the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures), and until the new currency had spread and circulated, the government issued the following: Daijokan bills and Minbusho bills (bills issued by the government akin to han bills); bills issued by prefectures placed in the old shogunate&apos;s territories; bills issued by exchange companies and commerce companies (companies established in the heart of commerce in various places by the government); han bills with a stamp of the Ministry of Finance showing yen, sen, and ri (units of old currency); and coins with a newly established exchange rate, such as Kanei Tsuho.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>藩札の種類</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Types of Han Bills</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Types of Han Bills</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Types of Han Bills</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>藩札は、和紙に木版刷りが基本であったが、手書き墨書の札も少なくない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Han bills were generally woodblock-printed, but some were hand-written with ink.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Han bills were generally woodblock-printed, but some were hand-written with ink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Han bills were generally woodblock-printed, but some were hand-written with ink.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>仙台藩により天明4年（1784年）に発行された仙台通宝のように貨幣形式のものも広義の藩札に含める場合がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Tsuho, which was a coin issued by the Sendai Domain in 1784, was also sometimes broadly referred to as a han bill.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Tsuho, which was a coin issued by Sendai Domain in 1784, was also broadly referred to as a han bill.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Tsuho, which was a coin issued by Sendai Domain in 1784, was also broadly referred to as a han bill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="29">
<j>藩札用紙は流通上の利便性のため、耐用年数を上げるために小型で丈夫な厚手の和紙であるケースが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In most cases, strong small thick Japanese paper was used for han bills to make them easy to carry and durable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In most cases, strong, small and thick Japanese paper was used for han bills to make them easy to carry and durable.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In most cases, strong, small and thick Japanese paper was used for han bills to make them easy to carry and durable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>すかしや着色紙、隠し文字などの偽造防止などを取り入れたものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Watermarks, colored paper and secret marks were used in some han bills to prevent counterfeiting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Watermarks, colored paper and secret marks were used in some han bills to prevent counterfeiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Watermarks, colored paper and secret marks were used in some han bills to prevent counterfeiting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>各藩は偽造防止のために藩札用紙の確保には神経を使った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each domain was very careful in securing paper for han bills to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each domain was very careful in securing paper for han bills to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each domain was very careful in securing paper for han bills to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>摂津国有馬郡名塩村（現・兵庫県西宮市）で作られた和紙は、雁皮に特殊な土を漉き込むことによって虫食いの害を防ぐことができるため、全国的に普及した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese paper made in Najio-mura, Arima-gun, Settsu Province (Nishinomiya City, Hyogo Prefecture) was spread nationwide because it was made with special soil and fibers taken from the bark of a clove-like bush to prevent bug bites.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese paper made in Najio-mura, Arima-gun, Settsu Province (Nishinomiya City, Hyogo Prefecture) was used nationwide because it was made with special soil and fibers taken from the bark of a clove-like bush to prevent it being eaten by bugs.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese paper made in Najio-mura, Arima-gun, Settsu Province (Nishinomiya City, Hyogo Prefecture) was used nationwide because it was made with special soil and fibers taken from the bark of a clove-like bush to prevent it being eaten by bugs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="33">
<j>藩札は兌換保証の紙幣であり、藩札の交換対象となる物とその量が藩札に明示されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Han bills were promised to be exchangeable and the things exchangeable with the amount were clearly stated on han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Han bills were guaranteed as exchangeable, and the items exchangeable and the amount were clearly stated the bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Han bills were guaranteed as exchangeable, and the kind and amount of commodities to be exchanged were clearly stated on the bills.</e>
<cmt>「その量」「藩札に」の訳し方が不正確です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>一般には、札使いは銀遣い経済地域である西日本において特に盛んであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Generally, han bills were circulated especially in the western part of Japan where silver coins were also commonly circulated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Han bills were especially common in the western part of Japan where silver coins were also circulated.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Although it follows the original Japanese, generally and especially make no sense used together like this.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Han bills were especially common in the western part of Japan where silver coins were also circulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>藩札は、丁銀との兌換の銀札が最も多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most han bills were ginsatsu (bills exchangeable for silver coins).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most han bills were ginsatsu (bills exchangeable for silver coins).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most han bills were ginsatsu (bills exchangeable for silver coins).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>同じく貨幣との兌換の藩札としては、金札、銭札があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to han bills exchangeable for silver coins, there were kinsatsu (han bills exchangeable for gold coins) and zenisatsu (han bills exchangeable for copper coins).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other han bills exchangeable for coins included kinsatsu (exchangeable for gold coins) and zenisatsu (exchangeable for copper coins).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other han bills exchangeable for coins included kinsatsu (exchangeable for gold coins) and zenisatsu (exchangeable for copper coins).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="37">
<j>藩札には貨幣ではなく物品との兌換を明示した預り手形（現在の商品券に相当）形式のものもあり、この種のものでは米札が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some han bills were used as a form of azukari-tegata (equivalent to a current gift certificate) marked for an exchange in a commodity, mostly rice, instead of coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some han bills were used as a form of azukari-tegata (equivalent to a modern gift certificate) marked for exchange with a commodity, mostly rice, instead of coins.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some han bills were used as a form of azukari-tegata (equivalent to a modern gift certificate) marked for exchange with a commodity, mostly rice, instead of coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>特殊な例として、傘札、轆轤札、糸札、するめ札や昆布札などもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular cases, there were han bills exchangeable for umbrellas, pottery wheels, threads, dried cuttlefish or dried kelp.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular cases, there were han bills exchangeable for umbrellas, pottery wheels, threads, dried cuttlefish or dried kelp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular cases, there were han bills exchangeable for umbrellas, pottery wheels, threads, dried cuttlefish or dried kelp.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>また、振り手形（現在の小切手に相当）の形式で、発行藩及び取引先両替商の信用の元で不特定多数に流通できるよう藩札用の小型で厚手の和紙で作製したものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, some han bills were used as a form of furi-tegata (equivalent to a current cheque), which were made from small thick Japanese paper to be circulated among the general public under the credibility of issuers (domains) or money-exchangers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, some han bills were used as a form of furi-tegata (equivalent to a modern cheque), which were made from small thick Japanese paper to be circulated among the general public under the credibility of issuers (domains) or money-exchangers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, some han bills were used as a form of furi-tegata (equivalent to a modern cheque), which were made from small thick Japanese paper to be circulated among the general public under the credibility of issuers (domains) or money-exchangers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="40">
<j>藩領内の特産品の専売制を推進するため、これら専売品の買上げに藩札を使用した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to develop monopolization of local products in the domains, there was a case that only the use of han bills were allowed to buy such products.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to develop monopolization of local products in the domains, there is a case where such products could only be bought with han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to develop monopolization of local products in the domains, there is a case where such products could only be bought with han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>家臣の倹約を目的として、藩士間の贈答用に用いることを義務付けられた、本来の贈答品の購入費用からすれば比較的低額の兌換紙幣（音物札）を発行した藩もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For use only in purchasing presents for other feudal retainers of the same domain, some domains issued exchangeable bills (Inmotsusatsu) that can be used to purchase presents at a reduced price for their vassals to save money.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some domains issued exchangeable bills (Inmotsusatsu) that could be used to purchase presents for their vassals at a reduced price so as to save money; they were for use only in purchasing presents for other feudal retainers of the same domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some domains issued exchangeable bills (Inmotsusatsu) which their retainers were forced to use in purchasing presents for their colleague retainers, whose face value was very small compared with the price of presents the retainers had customarily bought, for the purpose of making the retainers save money.</e>
<cmt>日本文の内容が英文に適切に反映されていません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="42">
<j>明治初年に政府は銀通貨の通用を停止したため、それ以降、新貨幣制度が開始され藩札の発行が禁止される明治4年までに発行された藩札は、金単位あるいは銭単位の額面である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the government forbade silver coins to circulate in 1868, han bills were only issued with values of gold or copper until 1871 when han bills were eventually out of circulation due to arriving of the new currency system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the government banned the circulation of silver coins in 1868, han bills were only issued with values in gold or copper until 1871, when han bills were eventually taken out of circulation due to the arrival of the new currency system.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the government banned the circulation of silver coins in 1868, han bills were only issued with values in gold or copper until 1871, when han bills were eventually taken out of circulation due to the arrival of the new currency system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>銀単位の藩札を大量に発行していた西日本諸藩及び東日本諸藩の西日本の飛地領では、それらの旧札の額面部分に金単位または銭単位の加印を施して再発行させた例も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many domains that issued ginsatsu in western Japan and their detached territories in eastern Japan reissued han bills with a stamp of the value of gold or copper.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many domains that issued ginsatsu in western Japan and their detached territories in eastern Japan reissued han bills stamped with the gold or copper value.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many domains that issued ginsatsu in western Japan and their detached territories in eastern Japan reissued han bills stamped with the gold or copper value.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="44">
<j>幕府の対応</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Response from the Shogunate</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Response from the Shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Response from the Shogunate</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>幕府の藩札の対応は二転三転している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The response regarding han bills from the shogunate changed repeatedly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate&apos;s response regarding han bills changed repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate&apos;s response regarding han bills changed repeatedly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>宝永2年（1705年）に藩札の調査が行われ、それを受けて幕府発行の貨幣の流通が滞るとして宝永4年（1707年）、すべての藩札の使用が禁止された（宝永の札遣い停止令）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the investigation of han bills in 1705, the shogunate prohibited the use of han bills in 1707 because han bills stopped coins issued by the shogunate from circulation (the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era).</e>
<cmt>宝永の札遣い停止令：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After an investigation of han bills in 1705, the shogunate prohibited their use in 1707 because han bills prevented the circulation of coins issued by the shogunate (the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After an investigation of han bills in 1705, the shogunate prohibited their use in 1707 because han bills prevented the circulation of coins issued by the shogunate (the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>実際には、幕府の行っていた貨幣改鋳の妨げになるとの思惑であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the actual reason was that han bills would interrupt the Currency Reform conducted by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the actual reason was that han bills would interrupt the Currency Reform conducted by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the actual reason was that han bills would interrupt the Currency Reform conducted by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="48">
<j>享保15年（1730年）に領国の石高が20万石以上であれば通用期間25年、20万石以下であれば通用期間15年などの条件付きで藩札の発行が再解禁された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1730, the shogunate again allowed domains to issue han bills with conditions; large domains (200,000 koku and above) could issue han bills valid for 25 years, and small domains (less than 200,000 koku) for 15 years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1730, the shogunate again allowed domains to issue han bills with conditions; large domains producing 200,000 koku (approximately 36 million liters of crop yield) and above could issue han bills valid for 25 years, and small domains (less than 200,000 koku) for 15 years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1730, the shogunate again allowed domains to issue han bills with conditions; large domains producing 200,000 koku (approximately 36 million liters of crop yield) and above could issue han bills valid for 25 years, and small domains (less than 200,000 koku) for 15 years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>この背景には、享保の改革で下落した米の価格があり、諸藩の財政を救済する目的であったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the purpose of this change was to improve the financial affairs of each domain affected by the price of rice dropped down because of the Kyoho Reforms (reforms made in the Kyoho era of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the purpose of this change was to improve the financial affairs of each domain, which were affected by the falling price of rice that resulted from the Kyoho Reforms (reforms made in the Kyoho era of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the purpose of this change was to improve the financial affairs of each domain, which were affected by the falling price of rice that resulted from the Kyoho Reforms (reforms made in the Kyoho era of the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>しかし宝暦9年（1759年）には新規の藩札発行が禁止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1759, new han bills were prohibited from being issued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1759, the issuing of new han bills was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1759, the issuing of new han bills was prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>その後、銀札以外の藩札の流通に制限が加えれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, restrictions of circulation were added to han bills except for ginsatsu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, restrictions were placed on the circulation of han bills, except for ginsatsu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, restrictions were placed on the circulation of han bills, except for ginsatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>このような幕府の藩札の取り締まりにも関わらず、財政難に苦しむ諸藩は幕府に無断で発行を続けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Despite the restrictions by the shogunate, domains with financial difficulties continued to issue han bills without permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Despite the shogunate&apos;s restrictions, domains with financial difficulties continued to issue han bills without permission.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Despite the shogunate&apos;s restrictions, domains with financial difficulties continued to issue han bills without permission.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="53">
<j>幕府自体は、貨幣流通にこだわり続けたが、幕末の慶応3年（1867年）に江戸横浜通用札、江戸および関八州通用札、兵庫開港札の三種類の金札紙幣を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate kept trying to circulate coins, but in 1867, at the end of the Edo period, they finally issued three kinds of kinsatsu such as the Edo Yokohama Tsuyo-satsu, the Edo and Kanhassyu Tsuyo-satsu and the Hyogokaiko-satsu.</e>
<cmt>江戸横浜通用札:Shogunate Note for Yedo &amp; Yokohamahttp://www.imes.boj.or.jp/cm/pdffiles/kahei20_53.pdf上記の日本銀行金融研究所のHPでは江戸横浜通用札のみしか掲載されていません。その他の二種類の紙幣の定訳が不明のため、定訳を使用せず訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate kept trying to circulate coins, but in 1867, at the end of the Edo period, they finally issued three kinds of kinsatsu such as the Edo Yokohama Tsuyo-satsu, the Edo and Kanhassyu Tsuyo-satsu and the Hyogokaiko-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate kept trying to circulate coins, but in 1867, at the end of the Edo period, they finally issued three kinds of kinsatsu such as the Edo Yokohama Tsuyo-satsu, the Edo and Kanhassyu Tsuyo-satsu and the Hyogokaiko-satsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="54">
<j>各藩の状況（東北地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Tohoku Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in each domain (Tohoku region)</e>
<cmt>Matched established style. Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in each domain (Tohoku region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>弘前藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hirosaki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hirosaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hirosaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>宝暦の飢饉で疲弊した陸奥国弘前藩の財政を立て直すため、勘定奉行の乳井貢が宝暦6年（1756年）に導入したのが標符という藩札類似のものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsugi NYUI, the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), introduced a hyofu, which was similar to a han bill, in 1756 to rebuild the economy of the Hirosaki Domain of Mutsu Province battered by the Horeki Famine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsugi NYUI, the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), introduced a hyofu, which was similar to a han bill, in 1756 to rebuild the economy of Hirosaki Domain in Mutsu Province, which had been battered by the Horeki Famine.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsugi NYUI, the kanjo bugyo (commissioner of finance), introduced a hyofu, which was similar to a han bill, in 1756 to rebuild the economy of Hirosaki Domain in Mutsu Province, which had been battered by the Horeki Famine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>藩札と異なり標符は、通帳のようになっており商取引が書き込む形式となっている特徴があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The hyofu was used differently from han bills; it was akin to a bankbook, and business transactions were recorded on it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The hyofu was used differently from han bills; it was similar to a bankbook, and business transactions were recorded on it.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The hyofu was used differently from han bills; it was similar to a bankbook, and business transactions were recorded on it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="58">
<j>商人は一家一業を原則とし、全ての商品と蓄えられた米や金銀を半ば強制的に藩に納めさせ、改めて標符と商品を下付した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Each merchant was only allowed to run one business and was forced to give all the products and saved rice, gold and silver to the domain first, then later, a hyofu and products were granted by the domain to the merchant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Each merchant was only allowed to run one business and was forced to give all his products and savings of rice, gold and silver to the domain first, then later, a hyofu and products were granted to the merchant by the domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Each merchant was only allowed to run one business and was forced to give all his products and savings of rice, gold and silver to the domain first, then later, a hyofu and products were granted to the merchant by the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>商人はすべての商いを標符で決算され、利益の一割を商人の取り分として残りは藩に納めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Merchants did all the business using hyofu and could keep 10 percent of the profit, but they had to give the rest to the domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Merchants conducted all business using the hyofu and could keep 10 percent of the profit, but they had to give the rest to the domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Merchants conducted all business using the hyofu and could keep 10 percent of the profit, but they had to give the rest to the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、藩の家臣は禄高に応じた銀の額の標符が渡され、買い物毎に商人がその標符に取引を書き込む形式を取った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, vassals were given a hyofu with the amount of silver coins depending on their stipends, and merchants filled business records on it whenever they made a purchase.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, vassals were given a hyofu with the amount of silver coins depending on their stipends, and merchants wrote business records on it whenever they made a purchase.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, vassals were given a hyofu with the amount of silver coins depending on their stipends, and merchants wrote business records on it whenever they made a purchase.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="61">
<j>標符はあまりにも急進的な試みであったため、2年足らずで廃止、乳井貢も失脚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because introducing hyofu was such a radical approach, it was abolished in less than two years and as a result, Mitsugi NYUI also lost his position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because introducing hyofu was too radical, it was abolished less than two years later and as a result, Mitsugi NYUI lost his position.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because introducing hyofu was too radical, it was abolished less than two years later and as a result, Mitsugi NYUI lost his position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="62">
<j>久保田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kubota Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kubota Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kubota Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>宝暦3年（1753年）から宝暦4年（1754年）、出羽国久保田藩は凶作に見舞われ、幕府に願い出て藩札を銀札1匁につき銭70文の相場で発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From 1753 to 1754, the Kubota Domain of Dewa Province suffered from famine, so they issued a ginsatsu carrying the value of one monme (an old currency unit in Japan) of silver coins in one mon (an old currency unit in Japan) of copper coins with permission of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From 1753 to 1754, the Kubota Domain of Dewa Province suffered from famine, so with permission from the shogunate they issued a ginsatsu with the value of one monme (an old currency unit in Japan) of silver coins as seventy mon (an old currency unit in Japan) of copper coins with permission of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>I don&apos;t understand translation 1 as it states one mon instead of 70 mon in the original.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From 1753 to 1754, Kubota Domain of Dewa Province suffered from famine, so with permission from the shogunate they issued a ginsatsu with the value of one monme (an old currency unit in Japan) of silver coins as seventy mon (an old currency unit in Japan) of copper coins with permission of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>他の箇所では藩名を無冠詞で表記していますので統一します。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>当初10匁、5匁、3匁、2匁、1匁の5種類だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the beginning, there were five kinds of han bills: a ten-monme-bill, a five-monme-bill, a three-monme-bill, a two-monme-bill and a one-monme-bill.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the beginning, there were han bills with denominations of ten, five, three, two and one monme.</e>
<cmt>Trans 1 very hard to read with so much repetition and so many hyphens.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the beginning, there were han bills with denominations of ten, five, three, two and one monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>その後、3分、2分の藩札も発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, a three-bu-bill and a two-bu-bill were also issued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, three and two bu (another old currency unit in Japan) bills were also issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, three and two bu (another old currency unit in Japan) bills were also issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>当初は順調であったが、凶作による米の値上がりを見込んで商人らが米を隠匿するなどして藩札による買い上げを拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although han bills worked well at first, merchants expected the price of rice to go up because of famine, so they refused to sell with han bills by concealing rice.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although han bills worked well at first, merchants expected the price of rice to go up because of famine, so they concealed rice and refused to trade it for han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although han bills worked well at first, merchants expected the price of rice to go up because of famine, so they concealed rice and refused to trade it for han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>また藩は凶作のため正貨で米を買い集めなければならなくなり、兌換の資金が流出してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain also had to buy rice with normally coins reserved for exchanges of han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of the poor harvest the domain also had to buy rice with coins normally reserved for exchanges of han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of the poor harvest the domain also had to buy rice with coins normally reserved for exchanges of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>混乱のうちに宝暦7年（1757年）に藩札は廃止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During social unrest, han bills were abolished in 1757.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amid social unrest, han bills were abolished in 1757.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amid social unrest, han bills were abolished in 1757.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="69">
<j>失敗の責任が問われ、家老や銀札奉行などが切腹や蟄居など重い処分が下された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people such as the karo (chief retainer) and the ginsatsu bugyo (commissioner of the ginsatsu) were held accountable for the failure and were sentenced to seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) or chikkyo (being confined to home).</e>
<cmt>銀札奉行：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people such as the karo (chief retainer) and the ginsatsu bugyo (commissioner of the ginsatsu) were held accountable for the failure and were sentenced to seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) or chikkyo (being confined to home).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people such as the karo (chief retainer) and the ginsatsu bugyo (commissioner of the ginsatsu) were held accountable for the failure and were sentenced to seppuku (suicide by disembowelment) or chikkyo (being confined to home).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また藩主よりの中下層の藩士が連座についたが、佐竹一族や古くからの家臣は加増されるなど派閥争いの様相も垣間見えた(佐竹騒動)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the feudal retainers in the middle lower class close to the lord were implicated, there were special favors given to the Satake family and old vassals by issuing them more stipends (the Satake disturbance).</e>
<cmt>加増は、禄高や領地を増やすことを意味するようなので、禄高が増やされたと解釈し訳しています。http://kotobank.jp/word/加増</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the feudal retainers in the middle lower class close to the lord were implicated, there were special favors given to the Satake family and old vassals by issuing them more stipends (the Satake disturbance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the feudal retainers in the middle lower class close to the lord were implicated, there were special favors given to the Satake family and old vassals by issuing them more stipends (the Satake disturbance).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>仙台藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>陸奥国仙台藩では幕府の許可を得て、藩内流通限定とした天明の大飢饉への救済を名目とした仙台通宝が天明4年（1784年）11月より作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sendai Domain of Mutsu Province issued Sendai Tsuho for use within the domain for the purpose of improving the financial situation affected by the Tenmei Famine with the shogunate&apos;s permission.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the shogunate&apos;s permission, Sendai Domain of Mutsu Province issued Sendai Tsuho for use within the domain in order to improve the financial situation affected by the Tenmei Famine.</e>
<cmt>Wording (explanation of Tsuho follows)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the shogunate&apos;s permission, in December 1784 or January 1785, Sendai Domain of Mutsu Province started to issue Sendai Tsuho for use within the domain in order to improve the financial situation affected by the Tenmei Famine.</e>
<cmt>年号の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>江戸時代の地方貨としては初めての物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Tsuho was the first provincial coin in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Tsuho was the first provincial coin in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Tsuho was the first provincial coin in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>仙台通宝は当時藩内経済の要衝であった石巻の鋳銭場で作られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sendai Tsuho was made at a coin-cast mint in Ishinomaki City, which was the financial point of the domain at that time.</e>
<cmt>鋳銭場:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sendai Tsuho was made at an Isenba (coin-casting mint) in Ishinomaki City, which was the financial center of the domain at that time.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sendai Tsuho was made at an Isenba (coin-casting mint) in Ishinomaki City, which was the financial center of the domain at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>「鋳銭場」の地名は現在の石巻市中心部に残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The coin-cast mint is now called &apos;Isenba&apos; located in the heart of Ishinomaki City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area where the mint stood in the heart of Ishinomaki City still retains the name &apos;Isenba&apos;.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area where the mint stood in the heart of Ishinomaki City still retains the name &apos;Isenba&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>また、同時期に紙幣としての藩札も発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Han bills were also issued at that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Han bills were also issued at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Han bills were also issued as paper currency at the same time.</e>
<cmt>「紙幣としての」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>藩札は、貞享・宝永・天明・升屋札・両替所札などがあげられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Issued han bills included Jokyo bills, Hoei bills, Tenmei bills, Masuya bills Ryogaejo bills.</e>
<cmt>両替所札:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Issued han bills included Jokyo, Hoei, Tenmei, Masuya and Ryogaejo bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Issued han bills included Jokyo, Hoei, Tenmei, Masuya and Ryogaejo bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>会津藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aizu Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>陸奥国会津藩では、藩財政窮乏の打開と藩士救済を目的として、元締役 長井九八郎の意見具申を容れる形で元禄13年（1700年）に金札、翌年には銭札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Aizu Domain of Mutsu Province issued a kinsatsu in 1700 and a zenisatsu in the following year accepting the opinions of Kyuhachiro NAGAI, the manager, to overcome financial difficulties and to save feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>元締役 : 定訳不明長井九八郎:http://www.jlogos.com/webtoktai/index.html?jid=10912322</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu Domain of Mutsu Province accepted the opinions of Kyuhachiro NAGAI, the manager, and issued a kinsatsu in 1700 and a zenisatsu in the following year in order to overcome financial difficulties and to help feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu Domain of Mutsu Province accepted the opinions of Kyuhachiro NAGAI, the manager, and issued a kinsatsu in 1700 and a zenisatsu in the following year in order to overcome financial difficulties and to help feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>しかし、町方、村方には受け入れられず、元禄16年（1703年）までに金札、銭札共に通用を停止した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, people in towns and villages did not accept those bills, so both of the kinsatsu and zenisatsu were suspended of circulation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, people in towns and villages did not accept those bills, so circulation of both the kinsatsu and zenisatsu was suspended.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, people in towns and villages did not accept those bills, so circulation of both the kinsatsu and zenisatsu was suspended before 1703.</e>
<cmt>年号の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>その一方で、、播磨国に飛地領を有する同藩は、播磨国加東郡小澤村の辻氏の引請による銀札を江戸末期頃に発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the domain had a detached territory in Harima Province and they also issued a ginsatsu guaranteed by the Tsuji clan of Ozawa-mura, Kato-gun, Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>原文に「、」が二つあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the domain, which had a detached territory in Harima Province, also issued a ginsatsu guaranteed by the Tsuji clan of Ozawa-mura, Kato-gun, Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the domain, which had a detached territory in Harima Province, also issued a ginsatsu guaranteed by the Tsuji clan of Ozawa-mura, Kato-gun, Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>他に会津藩発行の貨幣としては、寛永通寶、天保通寶の密鋳銭、会津銀判などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Aizu Domain also issued coins including the Kanei Tsuho, the Micchusen of Tenpo Tsuho and the Aizu Ginban.</e>
<cmt>密鋳銭 : 定訳不明会津銀判 : 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aizu Domain also issued coins including the Kanei Tsuho, the Micchusen of Tenpo Tsuho and the Aizu Ginban.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aizu Domain also issued coins including the Kanei Tsuho, the Micchusen of Tenpo Tsuho and the Aizu Ginban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="81">
<j>各藩の状況（関東地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Kanto Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in each domain (Kanto region)</e>
<cmt>Matched established style. Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in each domain (Kanto region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>岡部藩（半原藩）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okabe Domain (Hanbara Domain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okabe Domain (Hanbara Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okabe Domain (Hanbara Domain)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="82">
<j>武蔵国岡部藩（のち三河国半原藩）では、摂津国の飛地領で、大坂堂嶋御用場の出入り両替商加嶋屋熊七、天王寺屋彦十郎が引請人となった銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Okabe Domain of Musashi Province (later Hanbara Domain of Mikawa Province) issued a ginsatsu guaranteed by Kumashichi KASHIMAYA and Hikojyuro Tennojiya, the money exchangers who had business with Osaka Dojima Goyoba, in the detached territory of Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>加嶋屋熊七：読み方不明天王寺屋彦十郎：読み方不明大坂堂嶋御用場：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okabe Domain of Musashi Province (later Hanbara Domain of Mikawa Province) issued a ginsatsu guaranteed by Kumashichi KASHIMAYA and Hikojyuro Tennojiya, the money exchangers who had business with Osaka Dojima Goyoba, in the detached territory of Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Ideally Dojima Goyoba needs an explanation, perhaps business center? I was unable to find a translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okabe Domain of Musashi Province (later Hanbara Domain of Mikawa Province) issued a ginsatsu guaranteed by Kumashichi KASHIMAYA and Hikojuro Tennojiya, the money exchangers who had business with Osaka Dojima Goyoba, in the detached territory of Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>「じゅ」のローマ字表記を訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>摂津国の豊嶋郡、能勢郡、川辺郡、有馬郡に散在する同藩の領地を中心とした地域で通用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginsatsu was mainly circulated in the domain&apos;s territories located in Teshima-gun, Nose-gun, Kawabe-gun, and Arima-gun in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>豊嶋郡：http://jisho.dnuts.jp/word/豊嶋郡</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginsatsu was mainly circulated in the domain&apos;s territories located in Teshima-gun, Nose-gun, Kawabe-gun, and Arima-gun in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginsatsu was mainly circulated in the domain&apos;s territories located in Teshima-gun, Nose-gun, Kawabe-gun, and Arima-gun in Settsu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="84">
<j>安政4年（1857年）、飛地陣屋である桜井谷陣屋の役人の不正が発端となり、抜本的な財政改革を要求する騒動が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fraud by an officer of Sakuraidani jinya (a regional government office) caused a commotion asking for a drastical financial reform in 1857.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1857, fraud committed by an officer of Sakuraidani jinya (a regional government office of a detached land) caused a commotion and demands for drastic financial reform.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1857, fraud committed by an officer of Sakuraidani jinya (a regional government office of a detached land) caused a commotion and demands for drastic financial reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>近隣の麻田藩では大坂商人で西本願寺家臣の石田敬起（大根屋小右衛門）による改革で藩札は農民側の管理に委ねられて適切に運用されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the neaby Asada Domain, a reform was conducted by Takaoki ISHIDA (Koemon DAIKONYA), the vassal of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and as a result their han bills were managed and circulated properly by peasants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処石田敬起：http://tois.nichibun.ac.jp/hsis/heian-jinbutsushi/Tanzaku/index/index.s0.html大根屋小右衛門:http://www.city.kaizuka.lg.jp/ikkrwebBrowse/material/files/group/52/temp33.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In nearby Asada Domain, a reform was conducted by Takaoki ISHIDA (Koemon DAIKONYA), the vassal of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and as a result their han bills were managed and circulated properly by peasants.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In nearby Asada Domain, a reform was conducted by Takaoki ISHIDA (Koemon DAIKONYA), the vassal of Nishi Hongan-ji Temple, and as a result their han bills were managed and circulated properly by peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>そのため、麻田藩に倣った改革が岡部藩の領民から要求された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, people in the Okabe Domain asked for a reform following the example of the Asada Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, people in Okabe Domain demanded reform following the example of Asada Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, people in Okabe Domain demanded reform following the example of Asada Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>その結果、藩札は大坂の両替商の関与を断たれ、桜井谷陣屋の米奉行が発行し、豊嶋郡の領内有力農民が銀穀方として運用する形態が幕末まで続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the currency exchangers in Osaka ceased supporting the domain&apos;s han bills, so their han bills were issued by a kome bugyo (commissioner of rice) of Sakuraidani jinya and were circulated by influential peasants in the territory of Teshima-gun as ginkokukata until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>銀穀方：締約不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the currency exchangers in Osaka stopped supporting the domain&apos;s han bills, so their han bills were issued by a kome bugyo (commissioner of rice) of Sakuraidani jinya and were circulated as &apos;ginkokukata&apos; by influential peasants in the territory of Teshima-gun until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the currency exchangers in Osaka stopped supporting the domain&apos;s han bills, so their han bills were issued by a kome bugyo (commissioner of rice) of Sakuraidani jinya and were circulated as &apos;ginkokukata&apos; by influential peasants in the territory of Teshima-gun until the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="88">
<j>各藩の状況（中部地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Chubu Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in Each Domain (Chubu Region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Chubu Region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>浜松藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hamamatsu Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hamamatsu Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hamamatsu Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="89">
<j>遠江国浜松藩では、飛地領を有する播磨国東部の加東郡・美嚢郡で安政3年（1856年）頃、銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hamamatsu Domain of Totomi Province issued a ginsatsu in their detached territories of Kato-gun and Mino-gun located in the eastern part of Harima Province in roughly 1856.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hamamatsu Domain of Totomi Province issued a ginsatsu in their detached territories of Kato-gun and Mino-gun located in the eastern part of Harima Province in roughly 1856.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hamamatsu Domain of Totomi Province issued a ginsatsu in their detached territories of Kato-gun and Mino-gun located in the eastern part of Harima Province in roughly 1856.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>札面には、偽造防止のためオランダ語の単語（Voordeelig；お互いの利益のために）が描かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dutch word (Voordeelig；for mutual profit) was written on the face of the ginsatsu to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dutch word Voordeelig (for mutual profit) was written on the face of the ginsatsu to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dutch word Voordeelig (for mutual profit) was written on the face of the ginsatsu to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>額面は銀五匁、一匁、三分、二分であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The face values of silver coins were five monme, one monme, three bu and two bu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The face values of silver coins were five monme, one monme, three bu and two bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The face values of silver coins were five monme, one monme, three bu and two bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="92">
<j>各藩の状況（近畿地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Kinki Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in each domain (Kinki region)</e>
<cmt>Matched established style. Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in each domain (Kinki region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>狭山藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sayama Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="93">
<j>河内国狭山藩では、天保6年（1835年）に銀札、翌7年（1836年）に銭札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sayama Domain of Kawachi Province issued a ginsatsu in 1835, and a zenisatsu in 1836.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sayama Domain of Kawachi Province issued a ginsatsu in 1835, and a zenisatsu in 1836.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sayama Domain of Kawachi Province issued a ginsatsu in 1835, and a zenisatsu in 1836.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>銀札の引替所は池尻村の小谷六左衛門方であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginsatsu was exchanged at the residence of Rokuzaemon KOTANI in Ikejiri-mura.</e>
<cmt>小谷六左衛門：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The residence of Rokuzaemon KOTANI in Ikejiri-mura acted as the currency exchange office for ginsatsu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The residence of Rokuzaemon KOTANI in Ikejiri-mura acted as the currency exchange office for ginsatsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>丹南藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tannan Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tannan Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tannan Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="95">
<j>河内国丹南藩からは、文政4（1821年）に米の価格を銀単位で表示（「米弐升代銀壱匁」など）した米銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tannan Domain of Kawachi Province issued a kome-ginsatsu with the price of rice in silver coins (e.g. &apos;two sho [unit of volume] of rice for one monme in silver coins&apos;) in 1821.</e>
<cmt>米銀札：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tannan Domain of Kawachi Province issued a kome-ginsatsu with the price of rice in silver coins (e.g. &apos;two sho [unit of volume] of rice for one monme in silver coins&apos;) in 1821.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tannan Domain of Kawachi Province issued a kome-ginsatsu with the price of rice in silver coins (e.g. &apos;two sho [unit of volume] of rice for one monme in silver coins&apos;) in 1821.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>その他、明治期には、丹南引替役所から銭札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The zenisatsu was also issued at the Tannan currency exchange place in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>引替役所：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The zenisatsu was also issued at the Tannan currency exchange office in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The zenisatsu was also issued at the Tannan currency exchange office in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>岸和田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kishiwada Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishiwada Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishiwada Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="97">
<j>和泉国岸和田藩では、延宝4（1676年）から藩札（銀札）を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kishiwada Domain of Izumi Province issued a han bill (ginsatsu) in 1676.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kishiwada Domain of Izumi Province issued a han bill (ginsatsu) in 1676.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kishiwada Domain of Izumi Province issued a han bill (ginsatsu) in 1676.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>当初よりさまざまな引請人の銀札が発行されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various guarantors guaranteed the ginsatsu after its issuance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various guarantors guaranteed the ginsatsu after it was issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various guarantors guaranteed the ginsatsu after it was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>このことから、札遣いが盛んだったことがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This proved that the bills were well circulated within the domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This proved that the bills were well circulated within the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This proved that the bills were well circulated within the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>享保15年（1730年）の札遣い再開からは、領内の泉佐野の廻船問屋で加賀国の銭屋五兵衛と並び称された豪商の食野（めしの）家などの引請による銀札が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since han bills were again allowed to be issued in 1730, a ginsatsu guaranteed by wealthy merchants, such as the Meshino family who were a kaisen donya (wholesaler in port) in Izumisano located in the territory and was also known as well as Gohei ZENIYA of Kaga Province, was issued.</e>
<cmt>銭屋五兵衛：http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/銭屋五兵衛</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since issuing of han bills was again permitted in 1730, a ginsatsu guaranteed by wealthy merchants located in the territory, such as the Meshino family who were a kaisen donya (wholesaler in port) in Izumisano, as well as Gohei ZENIYA of Kaga Province, was issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Please check I have understood this sentence correctly.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since issuing of han bills was again permitted in 1730, a ginsatsu guaranteed by wealthy merchants located in the territory, such as the Meshino family, who were a kaisen donya (wholesaler in port) in Izumisano no less famous than Gohei ZENIYA of Kaga Province, was issued.</e>
<cmt>「と並び称された」の訳出が不適切です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>なお、岸和田藩は食野家から多額の借財を抱えており、藩財政は同家の強い影響下にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Kishiwada Domain had large amounts of borrowed properties from the Meshino family, so the finance of the domain was under strong influence of the family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Kishiwada Domain had a large amount of debt with the Meshino family, so the family had a strong influence over the finances of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Borrowed properties sounds quite unnatural to me.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Kishiwada Domain had a large amount of debt with the Meshino family, so the family had a strong influence over the finances of the domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>伯太藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakata Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakata Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakata Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="102">
<j>和泉国伯太藩からは、宝暦5年（1755年）に領内の黒鳥村の黒川武左衛門が札元となって発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hakata Domain issued a han bill guaranteed by Buzaemon KUROKAWA of Kurodori-mura in 1755.</e>
<cmt>黒川武左衛門：読み方不明黒鳥村：読み方不明和泉市に黒鳥（くろどり）町があるため、Kurodori-muraとしています。http://yubin.senmon.net/5940022.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakata Domain of Izumi Province issued a han bill guaranteed by Buzaemon KUROKAWA of Kurodori-mura in 1755.</e>
<cmt>Added Izumi Province.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakata Domain of Izumi Province issued a han bill guaranteed by Buzaemon KUROKAWA of Kurodori-mura in 1755.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>その他、仲村吉次郎、大植清左衛門が札元となった銀札が現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A ginsatsu guaranteed by Kichijiro NAKAMURA and Seizaemon OUE still remain.</e>
<cmt>仲村吉次郎：読み方不明大植清左衛門：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A ginsatsu guaranteed by Kichijiro NAKAMURA and Seizaemon OUE still remains.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A ginsatsu guaranteed by Kichijiro NAKAMURA and Seizaemon OUE still remains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>明治期には、銭札が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A zenisatsu was issued in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A zenisatsu was issued in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A zenisatsu was issued in the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>麻田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asada Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asada Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asada Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="105">
<j>摂津国麻田藩は1万石程度の小藩としては例外的に、かなり早期の延宝5年（1677年）3月から藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Asada Domain of Settsu Province issued han bills in March of 1677, which was exceptionally early for a small domain holding about 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asada Domain of Settsu Province issued han bills in March 1677, which was exceptionally early for a small domain of about 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asada Domain of Settsu Province issued han bills in March 1677, which was exceptionally early for a small domain of about 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>これは、麻田藩領の多くが経済の中心地であった大阪に程近い摂津国豊島郡 (摂津国)（豊嶋郷）、川辺郡 (兵庫県)（高平郷）にあったことによるものと考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This might have been because most of the territories of the Asada Domain were located in Toshima-gun (Toshimago) and Kawabe-gun (Takahirago) in Settsu Province close to Osaka, which was the center of finance.</e>
<cmt>原文に、(摂津国)と（兵庫県）が記載されていますが、HPには、記載されていないため省略してあります。 http://ja.wikipedia.org/wiki/藩札#.E9.BA.BB.E7.94.B0.E8.97.A9豊嶋郷：読み方不明高平郷：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This might have been because most of the territories of Asada Domain were located in Toshima-gun (Toshimago) and Kawabe-gun (Takahirago) in Settsu Province close to Osaka, which was the center of finance.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This might have been because most of the territories of Asada Domain were located in Toshima-gun (Toshimago) and Kawabe-gun (Takahirago) in Settsu Province close to Osaka, which was the center of finance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>幕命により宝永4年（1707年）に一旦は発行を中止したが、その後、幕許を得て宝暦3年（1753年）7月に再度発行し、明治維新後まで継続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the order of the shogunate, the domain once stopped issuing han bills; later, they again issued the han bill with the permission of the shogunate in July 1753 and continued until after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to an order from the shogunate, the domain once stopped issuing han bills; later, they again issued the han bill with the permission of the shogunate in July 1753 and continued until after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to an order from the shogunate, the domain once stopped issuing han bills; later, they again issued the han bill with the permission of the shogunate in July 1753 and continued until after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>なお、麻田藩は備中国にも飛地領を有し、同地でも藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Asada Domain issued han bills in the detached territory of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Asada Domain issued han bills in the detached territory of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Asada Domain issued han bills in the detached territory of Bicchu Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>尼崎藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amagasaki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="109">
<j>摂津国尼崎藩は、経済活動の盛んな西宮、兵庫津を領し、更に大坂、伊丹に囲まれるという地理的条件のため、早期に藩札が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amagasaki Domain of Settsu Province had territories in Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu where business was active, and were also surrounded by Osaka and Itami allowing the domain to issue han bills early.</e>
<cmt>兵庫津:http://www.city.kobe.lg.jp/culture/leisure/history/kindai/shousai/012.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki Domain of Settsu Province had territories in Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu where business was active, and were also surrounded by Osaka and Itami allowing the domain to issue han bills early.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki Domain of Settsu Province had territories in Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu where business was active, and were also surrounded by Osaka and Itami allowing the domain to issue han bills early.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>尼崎藩札として確実なものは油屋庄右衛門を札元とした寛文10年（1670年）発行の札がはじめである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first recognized han bill issued by the Amagasaki Domain was the one guaranteed by Shoemon ABURAYA in 1670.</e>
<cmt>油屋庄右衛門：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first recognized han bill issued by Amagasaki Domain was guaranteed by Shoemon ABURAYA in 1670.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first recognized han bill issued by Amagasaki Domain was guaranteed by Shoemon ABURAYA in 1670.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>宝永の札遣い停止令を経て、享保15年（1730年）に西宮の町人を札元に登用した銀札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era, the domain issued han bills guaranteed by the townspeople of Nishinomiya in 1730.</e>
<cmt>宝永の札遣い停止令：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era lapsed, the domain issued han bills guaranteed by the townspeople of Nishinomiya in 1730.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era lapsed, the domain issued han bills guaranteed by the townspeople of Nishinomiya in 1730.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>尼崎藩での銀札の引き請けは、家屋敷・田畑を抵当に多額の資金を無利子で得るという形式をとっていたため希望者が多く、札元は数十人に上った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Amagasaki Domain allowed guarantors of ginsatsu to borrow a large amount of money without any interest by mortgaging their houses and fields, so many people applied and there were dozens of guarantors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amagasaki Domain allowed guarantors of ginsatsu to borrow a large amount of money without any interest by mortgaging their houses and fields, so many people applied and there were dozens of guarantors.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amagasaki Domain allowed guarantors of ginsatsu to borrow a large amount of money without any interest by mortgaging their houses and fields, so many people applied and there were dozens of guarantors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="113">
<j>明和6年（1769年）に尼崎藩の経済の根幹であった西宮と兵庫津を含めた灘筋の村々が幕府領として上知された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1769, villages in Nadasuji including Nishinomiya and Hogotsu (the essential business areas of the Amagasaki Domain) were confiscated as territories of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1769, villages in Nadasuji including Nishinomiya and Hogotsu (the essential business areas of Amagasaki Domain) were confiscated as territories of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Wording. Althought I can&apos;t find a better one, I&apos;m not sure &apos;confiscated&apos; is the best possible translation here, as row 176 explains that villages were exchanged.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1769, villages in Nadasuji including Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu (the essential business areas of Amagasaki Domain) were confiscated as territories of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>ミススペリング修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>藩財政に対する不安から藩札流通にも多大な影響が見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Concerns regarding the economy of the domain strongly affected the circulation of han bills.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Concerns regarding the economy of the domain strongly affected the circulation of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Concerns regarding the economy of the domain strongly affected the circulation of han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>このため、庄屋層に管理を託していた旧札を回収して、新引替人による統一的な新札発行に切り替えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this, old bills managed by village headmen were collected and unified new bills were issued by new currency exchangers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this, old bills managed by village headmen were collected and unified new bills were issued by new currency exchangers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, old bills managed by village headmen were collected and unified new bills were issued by new currency exchangers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>文政元年（1818年）には引き替えは泉屋利兵衛、樋口屋十郎右衛門、尼崎引替役所の3か所となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1818, han bills could be exchanged by Rihe IZUMIYA, Zyuroemon HINOKUCHIYA and the Amagasaki Exchange Office.</e>
<cmt>泉屋利兵衛：http://www.archives.city.amagasaki.hyogo.jp/apedia/index.php?key=%C0%F4%B2%B0%CD%F8%CA%BC%B1%D2&amp;redirect=no樋口屋十郎右衛門：http://www.archives.city.amagasaki.hyogo.jp/apedia/m/index.php?key=%94%F3%8C%FB%89%AE%8F%5C%98Y%89E%89q%96%E5&amp;redirect=no尼崎引替役所：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1818, han bills could be exchanged by Rihe IZUMIYA, Zyuroemon HINOKUCHIYA and the Amagasaki Exchange Office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1818, han bills could be exchanged by Rihe IZUMIYA, Zyuroemon HINOKUCHIYA and the Amagasaki Exchange Office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>しかしその後も数度新・旧札の切り替えが行われ、札元も入れ替わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, han bills were changed repeatedly and guarantors also changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, han bills were changed repeatedly and guarantors also changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, han bills were changed repeatedly and guarantors also changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="118">
<j>明治初期には銀札は銭札に切り替えられ、金札も併せて発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, the ginsatsu was changed to the zenisatsu, and the kinsatsu was added.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early Meiji period, the ginsatsu was replaced by the zenisatsu, and in addition the kinsatsu was issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early Meiji period, the ginsatsu was replaced by the zenisatsu, and in addition the kinsatsu was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>明治新政府回収の際の引替率は、金札1両は1円、銭札五百文は4銭、百文は8厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the new Meiji government collected han bills, one ryo (unit of weight) of kinsatsu was exchanged for 1 yen, 500 mon of zenisatsu for 4 sen, and 100 mon of zenisatsu for 8 ri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the new Meiji government collected han bills, one ryo (unit of weight) of kinsatsu was exchanged for 1 yen, 500 mon of zenisatsu for 4 sen, and 100 mon of zenisatsu for 8 ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the new Meiji government collected han bills, one ryo (currency unit only used for gold coins) of kinsatsu was exchanged for 1 yen, 500 mon of zenisatsu for 4 sen, and 100 mon of zenisatsu for 8 ri.</e>
<cmt>この「両」は質量の単位ではありません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="120">
<j>また尼崎藩では、明和6年の西宮、兵庫津をはじめとする灘目筋村々の上知に伴って与えられた播磨国の飛地領においても、赤穂郡上郡村及び多可郡中安田村に置かれた会所で藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Amagasaki Domain issued han bills at a kaisho (exchanger) in Kamigori-mura, Ako-gun and Nakayasuta-mura, Taka-gun in their detached territory in Harima Province, which was given by the shogunate in exchange for villages including Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu in Nadamesuji in 1769.</e>
<cmt>上郡村：http://canpal.net/library/municipality_history/hyogo_history.pdf中安田村：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Amagasaki Domain issued han bills at a kaisho (exchanger) in Kamigori-mura, Ako-gun and Nakayasuta-mura, Taka-gun in their detached territory in Harima Province, which was given by the shogunate in exchange for villages including Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu in Nadamesuji in 1769.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Amagasaki Domain issued han bills at a kaisho (exchanger) in Kamigori-mura, Ako-gun and Nakayasuta-mura, Taka-gun in their detached territory in Harima Province, which was given by the shogunate in exchange for villages including Nishinomiya and Hyogotsu in Nadamesuji in 1769.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>三田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanda Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="121">
<j>摂津国三田藩は近隣の尼崎藩、麻田藩などと同様にかなり早期の、元禄13年（1700年）から藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1700, the Sanda Domain of Settsu Province issued han bills as early as the Amagasaki Domain and the nearby Asada Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1700, Sanda Domain of Settsu Province issued han bills as early as Amagasaki Domain and nearby Asada Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1700, Sanda Domain of Settsu Province issued han bills as early as Amagasaki Domain and nearby Asada Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>宝永の札遣い停止令を経て、元文5年（1740年）に、藩財政窮乏の緩和、藩経済の発展に対応した通貨量増大などを目的として藩札の発行を再開した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era, the domain again issued han bills to improve the economy and to increase the amount of currencies for economic growth in 1740.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era lapsed, in 1740 the domain again issued han bills to ease financial poverty and to increase the amount of currency for economic growth.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the order for the suspension of bills in the Hoei era lapsed, in 1740 the domain again issued han bills to ease financial poverty and to increase the amount of currency for economic growth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="123">
<j>三田藩が陣屋を置いた三田町は、周辺の摂津・播磨内陸部の国境地帯が幕府領、小藩領、関東諸藩の飛地領、旗本領等の錯綜地であったこともあり、商業の一大中心地として栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mita-cho, where a jinya from the Sanda Domain was located, was flourished as the center of commerce because it was close to the border area between Settsu Province and Harima Province (where many territories of the shogunate, small domains, domains in Kanto region, and hatamoto were located).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mita-cho, where a jinya from Sanda Domain was located, flourished as the center of commerce because it was close to the border between Settsu Province and Harima Province (where many territories of the shogunate, small domains, domains in Kanto region, and hatamoto were located).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mita-cho, where Sanda Domain established its jinya, flourished as the center of commerce because it was close to the border between Settsu Province and Harima Province (where many territories of the shogunate, small domains, detached areas of domains in Kanto region, and hatamoto were located).</e>
<cmt>「三田藩が陣屋を置いた」の訳出が不適切です。また「飛地領」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>また、酒造好適米の生産地である播磨国東部から酒造の一大中心地である摂津国武庫郡西宮町への陸路による輸送の重要な中継点であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, it was located on an important ground transportation route for rice from the eastern Harima Province, where good rice for brewing sake were grown, to Nishinomiya-cho, Muko-gun, Settsu Province, where was the center of brewing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, it was located on an important ground transportation route for rice running from eastern Harima Province, where good rice for brewing sake was grown, to Nishinomiya-cho, Muko-gun, Settsu Province, which was the center of brewing.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, it was located on an important ground transportation route for rice running from eastern Harima Province, where good rice for brewing sake was grown, to Nishinomiya-cho, Muko-gun, Settsu Province, which was the center of brewing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>後に西宮町を含む灘地方（摂津国西部沿岸地域）における酒造業の飛躍的発展に伴って、三田藩領及び周辺の米も酒米として利用されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the sake brewing industry was later developed remarkably in the Nada area (a coast area in the western part of Settsu Province), rice grown in the territory of the Sanda Domain and its surroundings were also used for brewing sake.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the sake brewing industry later developed rapidly in the Nada area (a coastal area in the western part of Settsu Province), rice grown in the territory of Sanda Domain and its surroundings was also used for brewing sake.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the sake brewing industry later developed rapidly in the Nada area (a coastal area in the western part of Settsu Province), rice grown in the territory of Sanda Domain and its surroundings was also used for brewing sake.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>三田藩が藩領外の商人に対しても自藩領内での藩札の使用を義務付けていたこともあり、摂津国西部から播磨国東部にかけてのかなり広い地域で同藩の札は流通した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Sanda Domain obliged outside merchants to use han bills issued by the domain within their territories, han bills were extensively circulated between the western part of Settsu Province and the eastern part of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Sanda Domain obliged outside merchants to use han bills issued by the domain within their territories, han bills were extensively circulated from the western part of Settsu Province and the eastern part of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Sanda Domain obliged outside merchants to use han bills issued by the domain within their territories, han bills were extensively circulated from the western part of Settsu Province and the eastern part of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="127">
<j>三田藩では領内のみならず、領外の多くの有力商人・農民をも自藩札の引請人としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influential merchants and peasants both inside and outside of the Sanda Domain guaranteed these han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influential merchants and peasants both inside and outside of Sanda Domain guaranteed these han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influential merchants and peasants both inside and outside of Sanda Domain guaranteed these han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>ただし、三田藩本領、摂津国灘地域、播磨国東部地方では発行された札の図柄が異なっており、必ずしも相互の地域で一元的に流通していたわけではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, han bills issued in the main territory of the Sanda Domain, Nada area of Settsu Province, and the eastern area of Harima Province had different designs, so bills were not always circulated in all areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, han bills issued in the main territory of Sanda Domain, the Nada area of Settsu Province, and the eastern area of Harima Province had different designs, so bills were not always circulated in all areas.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, han bills issued in the main territory of Sanda Domain, the Nada area of Settsu Province, and the eastern area of Harima Province had different designs, so bills were not always circulated in an integrated fashion in all areas.</e>
<cmt>「一元的に」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="129">
<j>なお、三田藩は丹波国氷上郡にも飛地領を有し、同地でも藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sand Domain also issued han bills in their territory in Hikami-gun, Tanba Province</e>
<cmt>氷上郡：http://www.hyogo-c.ed.jp/~rekihaku-bo/historystation/exhibit-meihin/meihin20.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanda Domain also issued han bills in their territory in Hikami-gun, Tanba Province</e>
<cmt>Wording/typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanda Domain also issued han bills in their territory in Hikami-gun, Tanba Province.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド漏れを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>高槻藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takatsuki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takatsuki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takatsuki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="130">
<j>摂津国高槻藩では、財政基盤が脆弱で、国産品の専売制も困難であったため、借入、頼母子講、御用金といった起債の形で財政難の対策としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the financial foundations of the Takatsuki Domain of Settsu Province were weak (they also had difficulties to monopolize local products), they floated loans by borrowing money and using Tanomoshi-ko (beneficial association) and goyokin (the money the shogunate charged temporarily on farmers and merchants) to solve their financial difficulties.</e>
<cmt>原文に「対策としており」とありますが、「対策をしており」だと思います。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the financial foundations of Takatsuki Domain of Settsu Province were weak (they also had difficulties monopolizing local products), they floated loans by borrowing money and using Tanomoshi-ko (beneficial association) and goyokin (the money the shogunate temporarily charged farmers and merchants) to solve their financial difficulties.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the financial foundations of Takatsuki Domain of Settsu Province were weak (they also had difficulties monopolizing local products), they floated loans by borrowing money and using Tanomoshi-ko (beneficial association) and goyokin (the money the shogunate temporarily charged farmers and merchants) to solve their financial difficulties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>周辺の藩のような藩札の積極的な発行は明治元年（1868年）～2年（1869年）まで待たねばならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain could not issue han bills actively akin to other domains until 1868 to 1869.</e>
<cmt>原文に、「待たねばならない」とありますが、「待たねばならなかった」の方が良いと思います。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain could not issue han bills actively like other domains until 1868 or 1869.</e>
<cmt>I understand that these two years given represent uncertainty over the specific year.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain could not issue han bills actively like other domains until 1868 or 1869.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>江戸期には、倹約を目的として、家中の贈答用に発行された銀札の音物（いんもつ）札のみが発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An inmotsusatsu (it was also a ginsatsu) was only issued for the purpose of thrift in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period an inmotsusatsu (a kind of ginsatsu) was issued for the purpose of thrift.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, only an inmotsusatsu (a kind of ginsatsu) to be used to purchase presents for family members was issued, for the purpose of thrift.</e>
<cmt>「家中の贈答用に発行された」「のみ」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>音物札はあらゆる贈答の機会に使用することが義務付けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inmotsusatsu were obliged for use when purchasing presents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inmotsusatsu could only be used when purchasing presents.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was mandatory to use an inmotsusatsu whenever a present was purchased.</e>
<cmt>日本文の内容と合いません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>交付の際に額面の2％の手数料が必要であったが、正銀への交換は無料であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although two percent of the face value was charged as a service fee to issue the inmotsusatsu, it could be exchanged for silver coins for free.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although two percent of the face value was charged as a service fee to issue the inmotsusatsu, it could be exchanged for silver coins for free.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although two percent of the face value was charged as a service fee to issue the inmotsusatsu, it could be exchanged for silver coins for free.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>明石藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akashi Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akashi Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akashi Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="135">
<j>播磨国明石藩札は畿内近国の諸藩からは少し遅れ、寛延3年（1750年）11月より、この時点で藩主であった松平氏（親藩、越前松平家庶流）によって発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Matsudaira clan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives and a branch family of the Echizen Matsudaira family), the lord of the Akashi Domain of Harima Province, issued han bills later than other domains in the Kinai-Kingoku area in 1750.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Matsudaira clan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives and a branch family of the Echizen Matsudaira family), feudal lords of Akashi Domain in Harima Province, issued han bills later than other domains in the Kinai-Kingoku area in 1750.</e>
<cmt>I assume 松平氏 refers the whole clan being feudal lords.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Matsudaira clan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives and a branch family of the Echizen Matsudaira family), the feudal lord of Akashi Domain in Harima Province of the time, issued han bills in November, 1750, a little later than other domains in the Kinai-Kingoku area.</e>
<cmt>「少し」「11月」「この時点で」の訳漏れを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>このとき発行された札は五拾匁、拾匁、壱匁、三分、弐分の銀札であり、藩の勘定奉行管轄の銀会所が取り扱った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, 500 monme, 100 monme, 3 bu and 2 bu of ginsatsu were issued and were managed by a gin-kaisho (exchanger for ginsatsu) under the jurisdiction of a kanjo bugyo of the domain.</e>
<cmt>銀会所:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, ginsatsu with values of 500 monme, 100 monme, 3 bu and 2 bu were issued, and these were managed by a gin-kaisho (exchanger for ginsatsu) under the jurisdiction of a kanjo bugyo of the domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, ginsatsu with values of 50 monme, 10 monme, 3 bu and 2 bu were issued, and these were managed by a gin-kaisho (exchanger for ginsatsu) under the jurisdiction of a kanjo bugyo of the domain.</e>
<cmt>数字の表記ミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="137">
<j>明治維新後、廃藩置県によって明石藩が明石県を経て飾磨県となった明治5年（1872年）4月から明治6年（1873年）12月までの間、新通貨に引き替えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, between April 1872 and December 1873, when the Akashi Domain became Shikama Prefecture from Akashi Prefecture as a result of Haihan-chiken, han bills were exchanged to the new currency.</e>
<cmt>飾磨県：http://www.city.shiso.lg.jp/kids/history/index.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, when Akashi Domain became part of Shikama Prefecture from Akashi Prefecture as a result of Haihan-chiken, from April 1872 to December 1873 han bills were exchanged to the new currency.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During a period from April 1872 to December 1873, during which Akashi Domain became Akashi Prefecture and then a part of Shikama Prefecture as a result of Haihan-chiken after the Meiji Restoration, han bills were exchanged to the new currency.</e>
<cmt>日本文の内容が正確に反映されていません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>引替率は、拾匁札は3銭9厘、壱匁札は4厘、弐分札は1厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A 100-monme-bill was exchanged for 3 sen 9 ri, a 1-monme-bill for 4 ri, and a 2-bu-bill for 1 ri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A 100 monme bill was exchanged for 3 sen 9 ri, a 1 monme bill for 4 ri, and a 2 bu bill for 1 ri.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A 10 monme bill was exchanged for 3 sen 9 ri, a 1 monme bill for 4 ri, and a 2 bu bill for 1 ri.</e>
<cmt>数字の表記ミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="139">
<j>また美作国の飛地領においても、小原村の引替会所で藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, han bills were issued by a hikikae-kaisho (exchanger) in Ohara-mura, their detached territory in Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>引替会所：定訳不明小原村：読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, han bills were issued by a hikikae-kaisho (exchanger) in Ohara-mura, in their detached territory in Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, han bills were issued by a hikikae-kaisho (exchanger) in Ohara-mura, in their detached territory of Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>前置詞ミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>赤穂藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ako Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ako Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ako Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>元禄赤穂事件の際に、家老の大石良雄がすぐさま藩札を額面の6割交換という高い率の銀正貨で回収し、城下の混乱を抑えた話はつとに有名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was well known that Yoshio OISHI, the chief retainer, collected han bills in exchange for silver coins at a high rate (60 percent of the face values) and controlled social unrest when the Genroku Ako Incident happened.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was well known that Yoshio OISHI, the chief retainer, collected han bills in exchange for silver coins at a high rate (60 percent of the face values) and controlled social unrest when the Genroku Ako incident happened.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was well known that Yoshio OISHI, the chief retainer, collected han bills in exchange for silver coins at a high rate (60 percent of the face values) and controlled social unrest when the Genroku Ako incident happened.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>播磨国赤穂藩の藩札は延宝8年（1680年）に初めて発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ako Domain of Harima Province first issued han bills in 1680.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ako Domain of Harima Province first issued han bills in 1680.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ako Domain of Harima Province first issued han bills in 1680.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>領内の通用を藩札のみに限り、正貨の流通を禁じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain prohibited coins and only allowed han bills to be circulated.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain prohibited coins and only allowed han bills to be circulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain prohibited coins and only allowed han bills to be circulated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>この時の交換比率は大きな問題であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exchange rate was a big issue.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The exchange rate was a big issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The exchange rate was a big issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>また、赤穂藩は塩の生産と専売により財務的に耐えられた点もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The production and monopoly of salt supported the Ako Domain financially.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The production and monopoly of salt supported Ako Domain financially.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The production and monopoly of salt supported Ako Domain financially.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>浅野統治時代の赤穂藩の藩札はことのとき、ほとんど回収されてしまったため、現在は数枚が残る程度で、古銭としては高額で取引されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since most of the han bills issued under Asano rule were collected, only a few bills now exist and are traded at high price.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since most of the han bills issued under Asano rule were collected, only a few bills now exist and are traded at a high price.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since most of the han bills issued under Asano rule were collected on this occasion, only a few bills now exist and are traded at a high price.</e>
<cmt>「このとき」（原文は「ことのとき」となっていますが誤記と判断されます）の訳漏れを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="146">
<j>なお、後に赤穂に入封した永井氏、森氏もまた藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nagai clan and the Mori clan, who later entered the Ako Domain, also issued han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nagai clan and the Mori clan, who later entered Ako Domain, also issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nagai clan and the Mori clan, who later entered Ako Domain, also issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="147">
<j>永井氏の札は3年余りとごく短期間の統治のためもあり、現存札は確認されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Nagai clan only ruled the domain for three years, there is no existing bill issued by them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Nagai clan only ruled the domain for three years, no bills issued by them remain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Nagai clan only ruled the domain for three years, no bills issued by them remain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>森氏の札は長期にわたって発行されたため、多様な札が残っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, various bills issued by the Mori clan still exist because they were issued for a longer time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, various bills issued by the Mori clan still exist because they were issued for a longer time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, various bills issued by the Mori clan still exist because they were issued for a longer time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>赤穂藩は領地が山に囲まれた地形のため、領外との取引を行う商人などを除き、領内での藩札の専一流通が確実に行われていたことは多くの史料によって確認されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many historical articles state that people except for merchants who had business with outsiders surely used only han bills within the territory because mountains surrounded the territory of the Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many historical articles state it is certain that people, except for merchants who had business with outsiders, used only han bills within the territory because mountains surrounded the territory of Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many historical articles state it is certain that people, except for merchants who had business with outsiders, used only han bills within the territory because mountains surrounded the territory of Ako Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>名目上、藩札の専一流通を規定した藩は数多いが、赤穂藩ほど徹底していた例は稀である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although many domains only allowed their han bills to be circulated within the territories, few of them could thoroughly do it in the same way as the Ako Domain did.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although many domains only allowed their han bills to be circulated within the territories, few of them could do this as thoroughly as Ako Domain did.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although many domains only allowed their han bills to be circulated within the territories, few of them could do this as thoroughly as Ako Domain did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>安志藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Anji Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anji Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anji Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="151">
<j>播磨国安志藩は、近隣の大藩である姫路藩が文政3年（1820年）に札使いを再開したことに影響を受け、文政5年（1822年）に幕許を受けて銭札（銭匁札）を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Anji Domain of Harima Province issued zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) with permission of the shogunate in 1822 under the influence of the Himeji Domain, the large domain nearby, when they resumed issuing bills in 1820.</e>
<cmt>銭匁札：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Anji Domain of Harima Province issued zenimonmesatsu (a kind of zenisatsu) with permission of the shogunate in 1822 under the influence of Himeji Domain, the large domain nearby, when they resumed issuing bills in 1820.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Anji Domain of Harima Province issued zenimonmesatsu (a kind of zenisatsu) with permission of the shogunate in 1822 under the influence of Himeji Domain, the large domain nearby, which resumed issuing bills in 1820.</e>
<cmt>この文ではresumedの主語が安志藩か姫路藩か分かりにくいのでwhichを用いた方が適切です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>額面は十匁、五匁、一匁、三分、二分であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The face values were 10 monme, 1 monme, 3 bu, 2 bu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The face values were 10 monme, 1 monme, 3 bu, and 2 bu.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The face values were 10 monme, 5 monme, 1 monme, 3 bu, and 2 bu.</e>
<cmt>「五匁」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>後に同額面の銀札を併せて発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ginsatsu with the same values were later issued.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ginsatsu with the same values were later issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ginsatsu with the same values were later issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>同藩では、溜池普請、洪水被害を受けた村々への救済が藩札によって行われたことが史料に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historical data states that the domain used han bills for the construction of irrigation ponds and for saving villages that suffered from floods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical data states that the domain used han bills for the construction of irrigation ponds and for saving villages that suffered from floods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical data states that the domain used han bills for the construction of irrigation ponds and for saving villages that suffered from floods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>同藩が発行した特殊な藩札として、額面が郷人足一人、半人の郷人足札、三百目から二十目までの銀建ての高額面の札である銀方札座札がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for particular han bills, the domain issued goninsokusatsu with face values of one coolie and a half coolie, and ginhousatsuzasatsu exchangeable for large amounts of silver coins (from 20 me [unit of old currency] to 300 me).</e>
<cmt>郷人足：定訳不明銀方札座札:定訳不明、読み方不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for particular han bills, the domain issued goninsokusatsu with face values of one laborer and a half laborer, and ginhousatsuzasatsu exchangeable for large amounts of silver coins (from 20 me [unit of old currency] to 300 me).</e>
<cmt>coolie&apos; is meaningless to me, so changed this to laborer.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for special han bills, the domain issued goninsokusatsu with face values of one laborer and a half laborer, and ginhousatsuzasatsu exchangeable for large amounts of silver coins (from 20 me [unit of old currency] to 300 me).</e>
<cmt>「特殊な」はspecialの方が適切だと思われます。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>明治4年（1871年）より新通貨に引き替えられた際の引替率は、銀十匁札は1銭、銭十匁札は9厘、壱匁札は銀札、銭札共に1厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for the new currency, 10 monme of ginsatsu was exchanged for 1 sen, 10 monme of zenisatsu for 9 ri, and both 1 monme of ginsatsu and 1 monme of zenisatsu for 1 ri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for the new currency, 10 monme of ginsatsu was exchanged for 1 sen, 10 monme of zenisatsu for 9 ri, and both 1 monme of ginsatsu and 1 monme of zenisatsu for 1 ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for the new currency, 10 monme of ginsatsu was exchanged for 1 sen, 10 monme of zenisatsu for 9 ri, and both 1 monme of ginsatsu and 1 monme of zenisatsu for 1 ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>小野藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ono Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ono Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ono Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="157">
<j>播磨国小野藩では江戸大火による上屋敷の類焼、地震被害等で財政が逼迫し、安政3年（1856年）より、銀札として五文目（匁）、一文目、二分、一分の4種を引替会所が発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Ono Domain of Harima Province financially suffered from the fire that burned down houses in Edo, and an earthquake, a hikikae-kaisho issued four kinds of ginsatsu with the value of five monme, one monme, two bu, and one bu.</e>
<cmt>引替会所：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Ono Domain of Harima Province financially suffered from both the fire that burned down houses in Edo and an earthquake, a hikikae-kaisho issued four kinds of ginsatsu with the value of five monme, one monme, two bu, and one bu.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Ono Domain of Harima Province financially suffered from both the fire that burned down houses in Edo and an earthquake, a hikikae-kaisho issued four kinds of ginsatsu with the value of five monme, one monme, two bu, and one bu in 1856.</e>
<cmt>年号の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>また明治維新後、銭札として一貫文、五百文の2種を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, 2 kinds of zenisatsu carrying the value of 1 kanmon and 500 mon were also issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, 2 kinds of zenisatsu carrying the values of 1 kanmon and 500 mon were also issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, two kinds of zenisatsu carrying the values of 1 kanmon and 500 mon were also issued.</e>
<cmt>数字を英語表記に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>銭札には偽造防止のため神代文字が描かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient Japanese Characters were written on zenisatsu to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient Japanese Characters were written on zenisatsu to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient Japanese Characters were written on zenisatsu to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>明治4年より新通貨に引き替えられた際の引替率は、五匁札は1銭3厘、壱匁札は3厘、弐分札は2厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for the new currency, a five-monme-bill was exchanged for one sen three ri, a one-monme-bill for three ri, and a two-bu-bill for two ri.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for the new currency, a five monme bill was exchanged for one sen three ri, a one monme bill for three ri, and a two bu bill for two ri.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for the new currency, a five monme bill was exchanged for one sen three ri, a one monme bill for three ri, and a two bu bill for two ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>龍野藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tatsuno Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tatsuno Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tatsuno Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>播磨国龍野藩では、最も古いものとしては文化2年（1805年）8月発行の銭札が現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest han bill issued by the Tatsuno Domain of Harima Province in August 1805 still exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest han bill issued by Tatsuno Domain of Harima Province in August 1805 still exists.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest han bill issued by Tatsuno Domain of Harima Province in August 1805 still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>文化15年（1818年）には引請人を掛屋の茂右衛門と丈左衛門とし、城下の立町に引替所を置いて藩札の取り扱い業務を行わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1818, han bills were guaranteed by Moemon and Jozaemon, the kakeya (a financial agent of the warehouse), and were also managed by a currency exchanger placed in Tate-machi near the castle.</e>
<cmt>丈左衛門：読み方不明掛屋:http://books.google.com/books?id=6YMfh3s4-gAC&amp;pg=PA30&amp;lpg=PA30&amp;dq=Edo+kakeya&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=dwNYEJlX3j&amp;sig=PbqBL_FRtr8A82vMyF4hoT3_DT0&amp;hl=ja&amp;ei=SNteTI3KAYT58Abcv6S1DQ&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CDoQ6AEwCDgU#v=onepage&amp;q=kakeya&amp;f=false</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1818, han bills were guaranteed by Moemon and Jozaemon, the kakeya (a financial agent of the warehouse), and were also managed by a currency exchanger placed in Tate-machi near the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1818, han bills were guaranteed by Moemon and Jozaemon, the kakeya (a financial agent of the warehouse), and were also managed by a currency exchanger placed in Tate-machi near the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>のち、安政3年（1856年）8月には俵屋・大川屋の引請の札、半田屋・栄屋の引請の札が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1856, han bills guaranteed by Tawaraya and Okawaya, and Handaya and Sakaeya were also issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1856, han bills guaranteed by Tawaraya and Okawaya, and by Handaya and Sakaeya were also issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1856, han bills guaranteed by Tawaraya and Okawaya, and by Handaya and Sakaeya were also issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>林田藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hayashida Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hayashida Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hayashida Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="164">
<j>播磨国林田藩では、近隣の大藩姫路藩の札遣いとほぼ同時期の文政2年（1819年）11月より藩札（銀札及び銭匁札）を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November of 1819, the Hayashida Domain of Harima Province issued han bills (ginsatsu and zenimonmesatsu) almost at the same time as the Himeji Domain nearby.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1819, Hayashida Domain of Harima Province issued han bills (ginsatsu and zenimonmesatsu) almost at the same time as nearby Himeji Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1819, Hayashida Domain of Harima Province issued han bills (ginsatsu and zenimonmesatsu) almost at the same time as Himeji Domain, a large domain nearby.</e>
<cmt>「大藩」の訳漏れを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>額面は、銭匁札では、銭10匁、5匁、1匁、5分、3分、2分、5厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The face values of the zenimonmesatsu were 10 monme, 5 monem, 1 monme, 5 bu, 3 bu, 2 bu, and 5 ri of copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The face values of the zenimonmesatsu were 10 monme, 5 monme, 1 monme, 5 bu, 3 bu, 2 bu, and 5 ri of copper coins.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The face values of the zenimonmesatsu were 10 monme, 5 monme, 1 monme, 5 bu, 3 bu, 2 bu, and 5 ri of copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>明治元年（1868年）に銀遣いが新政府により禁止されると、多くの西国他藩と同様に両・分・朱を額面とした金札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the new government prohibited the use of silver coins in 1868, the domain issued kinsatsu with the face value of ryo, bu and syu (unit of old currency) the same as many domains in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the new government prohibited the use of silver coins in 1868, the domain issued kinsatsu with face values of ryo, bu and syu (units of old currency), the same as many domains in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the new government prohibited the use of silver coins in 1868, the domain issued kinsatsu with face values in ryo, bu and syu (units of old currency), the same as many domains in Saigoku.</e>
<cmt>「額面を量・分・朱で表記した」の意ですから前置詞はinが相当です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>姫路藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himeji Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himeji Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himeji Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="167">
<j>播磨国姫路藩は同国の中核を担う典型的な領国型の領地を有しており、幕府領、小藩領、旗本領などが入り組んでいる周辺の地域経済にまで大きな影響力を有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Himeji Domain of Harima Province owned a territory in the core area of the province influencing the economy of the territories of the shogunate, small domains and hatamoto located in their surrounding area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himeji Domain of Harima Province owned a territory in the core area of the province influencing the economy of the territories of the shogunate, small domains and hatamoto located in their surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himeji Domain of Harima Province owned a typical ryokoku (daimyos&apos; own territory)-style land in the core area of the Province, having a major influence even on the economy of the surrounding area which was a labyrinthian mixture of the territories of the shogunate, small domains and hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>日本文の内容が適切に表現されていません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>姫路藩が領地を有していた播磨平野は綿作の好適地であり、木綿の専売で大きな実績を上げていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Harima Plain owned by the Himeji Domain was an ideal place for cotton, so they earned money by monopolizing cotton.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harima Plain, owned by Himeji Domain, was an ideal place to produce cotton, so they earned money by monopolizing cotton.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harima Plain, owned by Himeji Domain, was an ideal place to produce cotton, so they earned money by monopolizing cotton.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>姫路藩は文政3年（1820年）、姫路城下の綿町に切手会所を開設し、掛屋、用達に藩札の取り扱いを命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain opened a kitte-kaisyo (exchanger for kitte) in Wata-machi near Himeji-jo Castle in 1820, and ordered a kakeya and a yotashi (merchant who assisted officials) to manage han bills.</e>
<cmt>綿町：http://yubin.senmon.net/search/?q=姫路市%2067009切手会所：定訳不明用達：http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/srch/jn/用達/m0u/https://kb.osu.edu/dspace/bitstream/1811/669/1/v9n1Yonemoto.pdf</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain opened a kitte-kaisyo (exchanger of kitte [merchandising certificates]) in Wata-machi near Himeji-jo Castle in 1820, and ordered a kakeya and a yotashi (merchant who assisted officials) to manage han bills.</e>
<cmt>Translated kitte as merchandising certificates. Unable to access webpage referenced in column E.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain opened a kitte-kaisyo (exchanger of kitte [merchandising certificates]) in Wata-machi near Himeji-jo Castle in 1820, and ordered a kakeya and a yotashi (merchant who assisted officials) to manage han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>翌年3月には木綿の専売を取り仕切る綿町国産会所を開設し、後に切手会所を国産会所に併設した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March of 1821, a Wata-machi kokusan-kaisho (domestic exchanger), who managed the monopolization of cotton, was opened, and a kitte-kaisho was later built next to it.</e>
<cmt>国産会所：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March of 1821, a Wata-machi kokusan-kaisho (domestic exchanger), who managed the monopolization of cotton, was opened, and a kitte-kaisho was later built next to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March of 1821, a Wata-machi kokusan-kaisho (domestic exchanger), who managed the monopolization of cotton, was opened, and a kitte-kaisho was later built next to it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="171">
<j>国産会所では木綿手形形式の藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The kokusan-kaisho issued a momen-tegata as a han bill.</e>
<cmt>木綿手形：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The kokusan-kaisho issued a momen-tegata (a draft made of cotton) as a han bill.</e>
<cmt>Added explanation of momen-tegata.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The kokusan-kaisho issued a momen-tegata (a draft made of cotton) as a han bill.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>藩は木綿手形形式の藩札で木綿を生産者から買い取り、買い取った木綿を大坂などで売却して正貨に換えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain bought cotton from producers using momen-tegata and exchanged the cotton for coins outside of the domain, such as Osaka.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain bought cotton from producers using momen-tegata and exchanged the cotton for coins outside of the domain, in places such as Osaka.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain bought cotton from producers using momen-tegata and exchanged the cotton for coins outside of the domain, in places such as Osaka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>その後、生産者が所有する藩札の正貨への兌換を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, they exchanged the momen-tegata owned by the producers to coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, they accepted the momen-tegata owned by the producers and gave coins in exchange.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, they accepted the momen-tegata owned by the producers and gave coins in exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>兌換用の正貨確保の確実さから、姫路藩の木綿手形は高い信用を付与された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The momen-tegata of the Himeji Domain had high credibility because they could steadily secure coins for exchange.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The momen-tegata of Himeji Domain had high credibility because they could steadily secure coins for exchange.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The momen-tegata of Himeji Domain had high credibility because they could steadily secure coins for exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="175">
<j>その他姫路藩では、藩士の慶弔用の贈答品として用いる鯣札や昆布札も発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the Himeji Domain issued han bills exchangeable for dried cuttlefish or dried kelp for use in purchasing congratulatory or condolence presents for feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the Himeji Domain issued han bills exchangeable for dried cuttlefish or dried kelp for use in purchasing congratulatory or condolence presents for feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the Himeji Domain issued han bills exchangeable for dried cuttlefish or dried kelp for use as congratulatory or condolence presents for feudal retainers.</e>
<cmt>「贈答品として用いる」の訳出が不適切です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>福本藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukumoto Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukumoto Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukumoto Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="176">
<j>播磨国福本藩は鳥取藩の支藩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukumoto Domain was a branch domain of the Tottori Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukumoto Domain of Harima Province was a branch domain of Tottori Domain.</e>
<cmt>Added Harima Province to translation.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukumoto Domain of Harima Province was a branch domain of Tottori Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>江戸時代中期以降は、慶応4年（1868年）に鳥取藩より蔵米を支給されて石高が1万石を越えて再度立藩するまで、交代寄合の旗本であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Fukumoto Domain was a hatamoto ranked as a kotaiyoriai (a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period) after the middle of the Edo period, until 1868, when they again established the domain because their yield reached over 10,000 koku after the Tottori Domain gave them kuramai (rice preserved in a depository by Edo Shogunate and domains).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukumoto Domain was a hatamoto ranked as a kotaiyoriai (a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period) from the middle of the Edo period, until 1868, when it was again established as a domain because their yield reached over 10,000 koku after Tottori Domain gave them kuramai (rice preserved in a depository by Edo Shogunate and domains).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukumoto Domain was a hatamoto ranked as a kotaiyoriai (a family status of samurai warriors in the Edo period) from the middle of the Edo period, until 1868, when it was again established as a domain because their yield reached over 10,000 koku after Tottori Domain gave them kuramai (rice preserved in a depository by Edo Shogunate and domains).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>領地は市川流域の神東郡・神西郡北部にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their territories were located in the Ichi-kawa river basin in the northern part of Jinto-gun and Jinsai-gun.</e>
<cmt>神東郡・神西郡:http://www.geocities.jp/hosinoufo3/harima.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their territories were located in the Ichi-kawa river basin in the northern part of Jinto-gun and Jinsai-gun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their territories were located in the Ichi-kawa river basin in the northern part of Jinto-gun and Jinsai-gun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>両郡の南部は姫路藩領であったが、北部は同藩及び分家の旗本2家の領地で占められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the southern part of both Jinto-gun and Jinsai-gun were owned by the Himeji Domain, the northern part was owned by the Fukumoto Domain and the two families of hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the southern part of both Jinto-gun and Jinsai-gun were owned by Himeji Domain, the northern part was owned by Fukumoto Domain and two families of the hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the southern part of both Jinto-gun and Jinsai-gun were owned by Himeji Domain, the northern part was owned by Fukumoto Domain and its two branch families which were hatamoto.</e>
<cmt>「分家」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>陣屋を置いていた福本村及び隣村の粟賀村は同地域の政治経済の中心地であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukumoto-mura, where the jinya was located, and Awaga-mura next to it were the political and economic center of the region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukumoto-mura, where the jinya was located, and neighboring Awaga-mura were the political and economic center of the region.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukumoto-mura, where the jinya was located, and neighboring Awaga-mura were the political and economic center of the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="181">
<j>同藩では、交代寄合であった文政5年（1822年）より立藩後の明治初年にかけて、銀札及び銭札（銭匁札）を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain issued ginsatsu and zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) between 1822 (when it was a hatamoto) and 1868 (after the domain was established).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain issued ginsatsu and zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) between 1822 (when it was a hatamoto) and 1868 (after the domain was established).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain issued ginsatsu and zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) between 1822 (when it was a hatamoto) and 1868 (after the domain was established).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>切手引替所は福本村に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An exchanger for kitte was placed in Fukumoto-mura.</e>
<cmt>切手引替所:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An exchanger for kitte was established in Fukumoto-mura.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An exchanger for kitte was established in Fukumoto-mura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>三日月藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikazuki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikazuki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikazuki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="183">
<j>播磨国三日月藩は、美作国に近い佐用郡を中心に所領を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mikazuki Domain had territories mainly in Sayo-gun close to Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>佐用郡：http://www.city.shinagawa.tokyo.jp/hp/page000008600/hpg000008538.htm</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territories of Mikazuki Domain centered around Sayo-gun, near Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The territories of Mikazuki Domain of Harima Province were centered around Sayo-gun, near Mimasaka Province.</e>
<cmt>「播磨国」の訳漏れです。またbe動詞が必要です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>三日月藩札として現存最古のものは、文化14年（1817年）に発行した手書き墨書の銭札（銭匁札）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest existing han bill of the Mikazuki Domain was a zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) with ink writings issued in 1817.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest existing han bill of Mikazuki Domain was a zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) with ink writing issued in 1817.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest existing han bill of Mikazuki Domain was a zenisatsu (zenimonmesatsu) handwritten in ink, which was issued in 1817.</e>
<cmt>「手書き墨書」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>その他、領内の鉱山で通用させた札、三日月藩勘定場発行の人馬駄賃預切手、町会所、生産所、産物会所などが発行した札、明治元年（1868年）に商法方や金方が発行した札など、多種類の札が現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, various kinds of bills, such as the bills circulated at the mine in the territory, jinbadachin azukari-kitte issued by the kanjoba of the Mikazuki Domain, bills issued by a machi-kaisyo, a seisan-kaisyo and a sanbutsu-kaisho, and those issued by a shohokata and a kinkata in 1868, still exist.</e>
<cmt>勘定場:定訳不明人馬駄賃預切手:定訳不明、読み方不明町会所、生産所、産物会所：定訳不明商法方、金方：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, various kinds of bills, such as the bills circulated at the mine in the territory, jinbadachin azukari-kitte issued by the kanjoba of the Mikazuki Domain, bills issued by a machi-kaisyo, a seisan-kaisyo and a sanbutsu-kaisho, and those issued by a shohokata and a kinkata in 1868, still exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, various kinds of bills, such as the bills circulated at the mine in the territory, jinbadachin azukari-kitte issued by the kanjoba of the Mikazuki Domain, bills issued by a machi-kaisyo, a seisan-kaisyo and a sanbutsu-kaisho, and those issued by a shohokata and a kinkata in 1868, still exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>三草藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mikusa Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikusa Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikusa Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="186">
<j>播磨国三草藩は1万石の小藩である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Mikusa Domain was a small domain holding 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mikusa Domain was a small domain holding 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mikusa Domain of Harima Province was a small domain holding 10,000 koku.</e>
<cmt>「播磨国」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>領内の村々は特産品が乏しく、また藩主が江戸在府で領内統治も幕府の統制力が強かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The villages in the domain did not have enough local products, and the lord of the domain was in Edo, so the domain was under strong control of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The villages in the domain did not have enough local products, and the lord of the domain was in Edo, so the domain was under strong control of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The villages in the domain did not have enough local products, and the lord of the domain was in Edo, so the domain was under strong control of the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>そのため、札遣いの盛んな播磨にありながら、藩札の発行は幕末の安政4年（1857年）とかなり遅い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to the circumstance, although the domain was located in Harima Province, where han bills were well circulated, they eventually issued han bills in 1857 at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to these circumstances, although the domain was located in Harima Province, where han bills were well circulated, they did not issue han bills until 1857, at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to these circumstances, although the domain was located in Harima Province, where han bills were well circulated, they did not issue han bills until 1857, at the end of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>このとき、銀札として五匁、一匁、三分、二分と、銭札（いわゆる銭匁札）として五匁、一匁、三分、二分、一分の札が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, five monme, one monme, three bu and two bu of ginsatsu, and five monme, one monme, three bu, two bu and one bu of zenisatsu (also known as zenimonmesatsu) were issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, five monme, one monme, three bu and two bu ginsatsu, and five monme, one monme, three bu, two bu and one bu zenisatsu (also known as zenimonmesatsu) were issued.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, five monme, one monme, three bu and two bu ginsatsu, and five monme, one monme, three bu, two bu and one bu zenisatsu (also known as zenimonmesatsu) were issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>発行高はあわせて980貫目であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The total amount of issuance was 980 kanme (unit of weight).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The amount issued totalled 980 kanme (unit of weight).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The amount issued totalled 980 kanme (unit of weight).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="191">
<j>この後に公式の藩札摺り立ては行われていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, han bills were no longer officially printed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, han bills were no longer officially printed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, han bills were no longer officially printed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>これらの札は明治3年（1870年）の引き揚げまで通用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those bills were circulated until they were withdrawn in 1870.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those bills were circulated until they were withdrawn in 1870.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those bills were circulated until they were withdrawn in 1870.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>発行高が少なく、他藩と比べて迅速に引き揚げが行われたため、大蔵省の円・銭・厘の単位の加印が押された札は発行されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the amount of han bills was law and the domain withdrew han bills earlier than other domains, there was no han bill with yen, sen and ri stamped on it by the Ministry of Finance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the amount of han bills issued was determined by the law and the domain withdrew han bills earlier than other domains, there were no han bills stamped by the Ministry of Finance with the denominations in yen, sen or ri.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the amount of han bills issued was small and the domain withdrew han bills earlier than other domains, there were no han bills stamped by the Ministry of Finance with the denominations in yen, sen or ri.</e>
<cmt>「発行高が少ない」の訳出が不適切です。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>山崎藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamasaki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamasaki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamazaki Domain</e>
<cmt>一つの文章内では読み方を統一すべきです。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="194">
<j>播磨国山崎藩は播磨国北部の山がちの地域である宍粟（しそう）郡に所領を有した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamazaki Domain of Harima Province had their territory in Shiso-gun in a mountainous area located in the northern part of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The territory of Yamazaki Domain of Harima Province was located in Shiso-gun, in a mountainous area in the northern part of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The territory of Yamazaki Domain of Harima Province was located in Shiso-gun, in a mountainous area in the northern part of Harima Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>山崎藩では文政元年（1818年）5月より藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamazaki Domain issued han bills from May of 1818.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamazaki Domain issued han bills from May 1818.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamazaki Domain issued han bills from May 1818.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>その後もさまざまな引請人の札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The domain continued issuing han bills guaranteed by various guarantors.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The domain continued issuing han bills guaranteed by various guarantors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The domain continued issuing han bills guaranteed by various guarantors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>そのうちいくつかの札では、偽造防止のために図柄の中に微小文字（「シソウツウヨウ」など）を隠し文字として入れたものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some of those bills had micro-sized letters (e.g. &apos;shisotsuyo&apos; [for Shiso-gun]) in the designs as secret letters to prevent forgery.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some of those bills had hidden microscopic letters in the designs to prevent forgery, such as &apos;shisotsuyo&apos; (for Shiso-gun).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some of those bills had hidden microscopic letters in the designs to prevent forgery, such as &apos;shisotsuyo&apos; (circulated only in Shiso-gun).</e>
<cmt>「シソウツウヨウ」は「宍粟通用」だと考えられますので、for Shiso-gunのみでは不十分です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>領内には鉄山があり、鉄山勘定場からも藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an iron mine in the territory, and Tetsuyama-kanjoba also issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>鉄山勘定場：定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an iron mine in the territory, and Tetsuyama-kanjoba (cashier&apos;s office of the iron mine) also issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>Added explanation for kanjoba</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an iron mine in the territory, and Tetsuyama-kanjoba (cashier&apos;s office of the iron mine) also issued han bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="199">
<j>各藩の状況（中国地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Chugoku Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in each domain (Chugoku region)</e>
<cmt>Matched established style. Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in each domain (Chugoku region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>備中松山藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicchu-matsuyama Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bicchu-matsuyama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bicchu-matsuyama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="200">
<j>備中国備中松山藩は、元禄年間に当時の藩主であった安藤氏が発行し、次の領主であった石川氏もこれに倣った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ando clan, who was the lord of the Bicchu-matsuyama Domain of Bicchu Province during the Genroku era, issued han bills, and the Ishikawa clan, the next lord, continued issuing them afterwards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ando clan, who where the lords of Bicchu-matsuyama Domain of Bicchu Province during the Genroku era, issued han bills, and the Ishikawa clan, the next lords, continued issuing them afterwards.</e>
<cmt>Please confirm if the whole clan or just one member were feudal lords.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ando clan, which was the lord of Bicchu-matsuyama Domain of Bicchu Province during the Genroku era, issued han bills, and the Ishikawa clan, the next lords, continued issuing them afterwards.</e>
<cmt>who whereでは意味が通じません。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>延享元年（1744年）に新たに板倉氏が入封すると、直ちに五匁、一匁の銀札を発行したが、国内の荒廃などによって表高5万石に対して実収2万石しかなかった同藩財政は逼迫した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a five-monme and a one-monme ginsatsu were issued as soon as the Itakura clan entered the domain in 1744, the territory was devastated and the economy became tight because they only had 20,000 koku in spite of their 50,000 koku of omote-daka (face value of kokudaka assessed by the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a five monme and a one monme ginsatsu were issued as soon as the Itakura clan entered the domain in 1744, the territory was devastated and the economy became tight because they actually had only 20,000 koku in spite of their 50,000 koku of omote-daka (face value of koku assessed by the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a five monme and a one monme ginsatsu were issued as soon as the Itakura clan entered the domain in 1744, the territory was devastated and the economy became tight because they actually had only 20,000 koku in spite of their 50,000 koku of omote-daka (face value of koku assessed by the shogunate).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>天保年間には準備金が底を尽きた上に更に大量の五匁札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After their reserve fund was all used in the Tenpo era, they additionally issued a large number of five-monme- bills.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After their reserve fund was all used up in the Tenpo era, they issued an additional large number of five monme bills.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After their reserve fund was all used up in the Tenpo era, they issued an additional large number of five monme bills.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>このため、藩札の価値は大暴落して財政を却って悪化させる原因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, the value of the han bills dropped greatly and it worsened the economy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the value of the han bills dropped greatly and caused the economy to worsen.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the value of the han bills dropped greatly and caused the economy to worsen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="204">
<j>これに対して藩執政に就任した山田方谷は敢えて藩札の廃止と3年間に限って額面価格での引き取りを行う事を表明した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokoku YAMADA appointed as the consul daringly decided to abolish han bills and exchange them for the face value for a duration of three years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokoku YAMADA, who was appointed as the consul, daringly decided to abolish han bills and exchange them for the face value for a duration of three years.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokoku YAMADA, who was appointed as the consul, daringly decided to abolish han bills and exchange them for the face value only for a duration of three years.</e>
<cmt>「に限って」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>その結果藩札481貫110匁（金換算8,019両）が回収され、未発行分の230貫190匁（同3,836両）と合わせた合計711貫300匁（同11,855両、当時の藩財政の約1/6相当にあたる）が、方谷の命令によって嘉永5年（1852年）9月5日_(旧暦)領内の高梁川にある近似川原（ちかのりがわら）に集められた藩士・領民の目前で焼却処分された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, 481 kan and 110 monme (8,019 ryo of gold) of the han bills collected and 230 kan and 190 monme (3.836 ryo of gold) of unissued han bills (711 kan and 300 monme [11,855 ryo of gold, one sixth of their fund] in total) were burned in front of feudal retainers and the people of the domain at Chikanorigawara beside Takahashi-gawa River by the order of Hokoku on September 5, 1852 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, 481 kan and 110 monme (8,019 ryo of gold) of the han bills collected and 230 kan and 190 monme (3.836 ryo of gold) of unissued han bills (711 kan and 300 monme [11,855 ryo of gold, one sixth of their fund] in total) were burned in front of feudal retainers and the people of the domain at Chikanorigawara beside Takahashi-gawa River by the order of Hokoku on September 5, 1852 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, 481 kan and 110 monme (8,019 ryo of gold) of the han bills collected and 230 kan and 190 monme (3.836 ryo of gold) of unissued han bills (711 kan and 300 monme [11,855 ryo of gold, one sixth of their fund] in total) were burned in front of feudal retainers and the people of the domain at Chikanorigawara beside Takahashi-gawa River by the order of Hokoku on September 5, 1852 (old lunar calendar).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>その後方谷は五匁、十匁、百匁からなる「永銭」と呼ばれる額面の新しい藩札を発行した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Hokoku issued han bills called &apos;eisen&apos; carrying the value of 5 monme, 10 monme and 100 monme.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Hokoku issued han bills called &apos;eisen&apos; carrying the values of 5 monme, 10 monme and 100 monme.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Hokoku issued han bills called &apos;eisen&apos; carrying the values of 5 monme, 10 monme and 100 monme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>そして、準備金が不正に流用される事の無い様に厳しい管理下に置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their reserve fund was also strictly managed not to be used fraudulently.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their reserve fund was also strictly managed so as not to be used fraudulently.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their reserve fund was also strictly managed so as not to be used fraudulently.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>そのため、藩札の信用は回復される一方、その準備金の適切な投資・貸し出しによって裏打ちされた殖産興業は成功を収めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the credibility of han bills were restored, the industry of local productions with proper investment and loan of reserve fund became successful.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the credibility of han bills was restored, the industry of local productions became successful backed by proper investment and loans.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The credibility of han bills was restored, and the industry of local productions became successful backed by proper investment and loans of the reserve fund.</e>
<cmt>文の前半－後半は原因－理由の関係ではないので接続詞asは不適切です。また「その準備金の」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>その結果、10万両と言われた藩の借財は数年で完済されて、藩札も額面以上の信用を得るという好循環を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, their 100,000 ryo of debt was paid off in a few years, and han bills gained more than the face values of credibility.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, their 100,000 ryo debt was paid off in a few years, and han bills gained credibility raising their value above the face values.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the domain paid off their debts, which were reputed to be as much as 100,000 ryo, in several years, and their han bills gained high credibility above the face values, creating a virtuous cycle.</e>
<cmt>日本文の内容が十分に表現されていません。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>備後福山藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bingo-fukuyama Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bingo-fukuyama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bingo-fukuyama Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="210">
<j>備後国備後福山藩では、通説よりも早い寛永7年（1630年）に、当時の藩主であった水野勝成が領内の殖産興業のために領内の両替商を発行元に藩札を発行したとの記述が地元の書籍にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The local book states that Katsunari MIZUNO, who was the lord of the Bingo-fukuyama Domain of Bingo Province at tha time, introduced han bills issued by currency exchangers in the domain in 1630 (earlier than common belief).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A local book states that Katsunari MIZUNO, who was the lord of Bingo-fukuyama Domain in Bingo Province at that time, introduced han bills issued by currency exchangers in the domain in 1630 (earlier than common belief).</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A local book states that Katsunari MIZUNO, who was the lord of Bingo-fukuyama Domain of Bingo Province at that time, introduced han bills issued by currency exchangers in the domain in 1630 (earlier than common belief) for the purpose of promoting the industry in the domain.</e>
<cmt>「領内の殖産興業のため」の訳漏れです。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>事実であれば通説よりも早い発行であるが、水野氏備後福山藩・結城藩水野家が廃絶する前に正貨である銀貨との兌換が行われ、ほぼ全てが回収されたとあり、伝来するものがなく確認できない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if the common belief was correct, there is no proof of that because almost all of the han bills were collected and were exchanged for silver coins before the Mizuno clan of the Bingo-fukuyama Domain and the Mizuno family of the Yuki Domain were ended.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if the common belief was correct, there is no proof of that because almost all of the han bills were collected and exchanged for silver coins before the Mizuno clan of Bingo-fukuyama Domain and the Mizuno family of Yuki Domain died out.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if the common belief was correct, there is no proof of that because almost all of the han bills were collected and exchanged for silver coins before the Mizuno clan of Bingo-fukuyama Domain and the Mizuno family of Yuki Domain died out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>ただし、その当時発行したと思われる藩札とおぼしき紙片もあるが、虫食いや磨耗が激しく真贋の鑑別が困難である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although a piece of paper, which may be a han bill issued at tha time, still exists, it is difficult to determine if it is a han bill because of bug bites and damages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although a piece of paper, which may be a han bill issued at that time, still exists, it is difficult to determine if it is a han bill because of bug bites and damages.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although a piece of paper, which may be a han bill issued at that time, still exists, it is difficult to determine if it is a han bill because of bug bites and damages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="213">
<j>そのため備後福山藩が発行したのが確実な藩札は享保15年（1730年）に発行したものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the recognized han bill issued by the Bingo-fukuyama Domain is the one issued in 1730.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the han bill issued by Bingo-fukuyama Domain in 1730 is the only recognized one.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the han bill issued by Bingo-fukuyama Domain in 1730 is the only recognized one.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="214">
<j>各藩の状況（四国地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Shikoku Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in each domain (Shikoku region)</e>
<cmt>Matched established style. Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in each domain (Shikoku region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>徳島藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokushima Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokushima Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokushima Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="215">
<j>徳島藩は阿波国及び家臣で洲本城主の稲田氏が統治する淡路国を領有していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokushima Domain owned Awa Province and Awaji Province, which was ruled by the Inada clan (who was the vassal of the domain and was also the lord of Sumoto-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokushima Domain owned Awa Province and Awaji Province, which was ruled by the Inada clan (who were the vassals of the domain and also the lords of Sumoto-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokushima Domain owned Awa Province and Awaji Province, which was ruled by the Inada clan (who were the vassals of the domain and also the lords of Sumoto-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>徳島藩の銀札及び銭札は阿波国及び淡路国の両国で通用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ginsatsu and the zenisatsu issued by the Tokushima Domain were circulated in both Awa Province and Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ginsatsu and the zenisatsu issued by Tokushima Domain were circulated in both Awa Province and Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ginsatsu and the zenisatsu issued by Tokushima Domain were circulated in both Awa Province and Awaji Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>古いものでは、延宝8年（1680年）の年号が書かれた銀札が現存している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An old ginsatsu with the year of 1680 written on it still exists.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An old ginsatsu with the year of 1680 written on it still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An old ginsatsu with the year of 1680 written on it still exists.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>のち、幕府による札遣い禁止を経て、明治期まで札遣いが続けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the suspension of bills by the shogunate, han bills were again circulated until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the shogunate&apos;s suspension of bills finished, han bills were again circulated until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the shogunate&apos;s suspension of bills finished, han bills were again circulated until the Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>明治4年（1871年）より新通貨に引き替えられた際の引替率は、一匁札及び百文札はは8厘、三分札及び弐分札は2厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for new currency, a 1-monme-bill and a 100-mon-bill were exchanged for an 8 ri, and 3-bu-bill and a 2-bu-bill for 2 ri.</e>
<cmt>原文で「は」が連続しています。「百文札はは8厘」</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for new currency, 1 monme and 100 mon bills were exchanged for 8 ri, and 3 bu and 2 bu bills for 2 ri.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1871, when bills were exchanged for new currency, 1 monme and 100 mon bills were exchanged for 8 ri, and 3 bu and 2 bu bills for 2 ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="220">
<j>その他、洲本銀札場から銀一貫目から十匁までの高額面の銀札が発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, ginsatsu carrying high values (from 10 monme to 1 kanme of silver coins) were issued from Sumoto ginsatsu place.</e>
<cmt>銀札場:定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, ginsatsu carrying high values (from 10 monme to 1 kanme of silver coins) were issued at Sumoto ginsatsu place.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, ginsatsu carrying high values (from 10 monme to 1 kanme of silver coins) were issued at Sumoto ginsatsu place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="221">
<j>各藩の状況（九州地方）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Situations in Each Domain (Kyushu Region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Situations in each domain (Kyushu region)</e>
<cmt>Matched established style. Fragment in par section.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Situations in each domain (Kyushu region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>秋月藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Akizuki Domain</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akizuki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akizuki Domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="222">
<j>筑前国秋月藩は幕府から独立した藩として公認されてはいたが、福岡藩の分家として立藩した支藩である関係で、軍事・財政面で相互援助が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Akizuki Domain of Chikuzen Province was officialy approved as an independent domain from the shogunate, the domain and the Fukuoka Domain were supported each other in military and financial affairs because they were established as a branch domain of the Fukuoka Domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Akizuki Domain of Chikuzen Province was officially approved as independent from the shogunate, but it was established as a branch domain of the Fukuoka Domain, so those two domains supported each other in military and financial affairs.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Akizuki Domain of Chikuzen Province was officially approved as independent from the shogunate, but it was established as a branch domain of the Fukuoka Domain, so those two domains supported each other in military and financial affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>このため、藩札も相互に領内流通を認めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, han bills were allowed to be circulated in both territories.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, circulation of han bills was permitted in both territories.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, circulation of han bills was permitted in both territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>秋月藩の藩札発行は、福岡藩で発行された翌年の元禄17年（1704年）からであるが、各藩に下された札遣い停止の幕命により、わずか4年で回収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Akizuki Domain issued han bills a year after the Fukuoka domain did in 1704, their han bills were withdrawn after only four years due to the order for suspension of bills by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Akizuki Domain issued han bills a year after Fukuoka domain did in 1704, their han bills were withdrawn after only four years due to the order for suspension of bills by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Akizuki Domain issued han bills in 1704, a year after issuance in Fukuoka domain, their han bills were withdrawn after only four years due to the order for suspension of bills by the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>元禄17年に藩札を発行したのは福岡藩ではなく秋月藩である。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>しかし、幕許によって藩札発行が認められた享保15年（1730年）には早くも藩札の発行を再開している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the shogunate allowed domains to reissue han bills in 1730, domains soon resumed issuing han bills.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, domains resumed issuing han bulls as soon as the shogunate allowed it in 1730.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, domains resumed issuing han bulls as soon as the shogunate allowed it in 1730.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>明治維新後、新通貨に引き替えられた際の引替率は、五匁札は4銭2厘、壱匁札は8厘、弐分札は2厘であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, bills were exchanged for the new currency, a five-monme-bill was exchanged for four sen two ri, a one-monme-bill for eight ri, and a two-bu-bill for two ri.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji Restoration, bills were exchanged for the new currency; a five monme bill was exchanged for four sen two ri, a one monme bill for eight ri, and a two bu bill for two ri.</e>
<cmt>Matched established style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji Restoration, bills were exchanged for the new currency; a five monme bill was exchanged for four sen two ri, a one monme bill for eight ri, and a two bu bill for two ri.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>これは、福岡藩よりも高い相場であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exchange rate was higher than the rate in Fukuoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This exchange rate was higher than that in Fukuoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>Wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This exchange rate was higher than that in Fukuoka Domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), As6022014(id:214263), 橄欖岩(id:24996), Nevylax(id:38464), 二八(id:10408), 水野白楓(id:22811), Shotetsu(id:10171), 松茸(id:27535), D.h(id:79056), Ruikon(id:204937), Im224(id:57113), ASAMA501(id:91947), Yosemite(id:5808), Carpkazu(id:27566), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>