<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>輩行名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haikomei (name for men that represents the order of his birth)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haikomei (name for men representing the order of their birth)</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haikomei (name for men representing the order of their birth)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>輩行名（はいこうめい）は、主に日本における男性の名前の種類のひとつ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haikomei is one of the types of names for men in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A haikomei is a type of name for men used mostly in Japan.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;mostly&quot; for &quot;主に&quot;; fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A haikomei is a type of name for men used mostly in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>輩行の仮名（はいこうのけみょう）、輩行仮名（はいこうけみょう）と言うこともある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;haiko no kemyo&quot; or&quot; haiko kemyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haikomei has also been called &quot;haiko no kemyo&quot; and &quot;haiko kemyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;Haikomei&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haikomei has also been called &quot;haiko no kemyo&quot; and &quot;haiko kemyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸時代以前は、仮名 (通称)(けみょう)の一種であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the Edo period, it was a kind of kemyo (assumed name).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the Edo period, it was a kind of kemyo (assumed name).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the Edo period, it was a kind of kemyo (assumed name).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>輩行名とは</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meaning of Haikomei:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The meaning of Haikomei</e>
<cmt>eliminated colon and changed to read more like a title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The meaning of Haikomei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「輩行」とは「一族のうち同世代の者」という意味で、通常は兄弟のことを言う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Haiko&quot; means &quot;people of the same generation within a family&quot;, typically brothers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Haiko&quot; carries the meaning of &quot;people of the same generation within a family,&quot; typically in the case of brothers.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Haiko&quot; carries the meaning of &quot;people of the same generation within a family,&quot; typically in the case of brothers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>輩行名は「輩行」のうちの序列（＝出生順）を表すもので、太郎、次郎、三郎・・・といった名のことであり、今日でも日本人の名前としても広く用いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haikomei represents the seniority in the &quot;Haiko&quot; (birth order), which are names like Taro, Jiro, Saburo and so on, and they are widely used as given names today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haikomei represents the seniority in the &quot;Haiko&quot; (birth order) in names such as Taro, Jiro and Saburo, and they are widely used as given names today.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haikomei represents the seniority in the &quot;Haiko&quot; (birth order) in names such as Taro, Jiro and Saburo, and they are widely used as given names today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、「太郎、次郎・・・」の前に一字をつける場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Often one character is added in front of the names &quot;Taro, Jiro&quot; and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One character is often added in front of the names, such as the &quot;太&quot; (ta) of &quot;太郎&quot; (Taro) or the &quot;次&quot; of (ji) of &quot;次郎&quot; (Jiro).</e>
<cmt>added kanji to help illustrate the description</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Often one character is added in front of the names, &quot;Taro, Jiro&quot; and so forth.</e>
<cmt>意味が変わってしまうので（太郎の太、のことではなく、「○太郎」などのことだと考えられます）、元の訳に戻し、同格のカンマを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>これら太郎、次郎といった名乗りのはじまりは、遠く嵯峨天皇の時代に遡る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of such names as Taro and Jiro goes way back to the time of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of such names as Taro and Jiro goes all the way back to the time of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>added &quot;all the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of such names as Taro and Jiro goes all the way back to the time of Emperor Saga.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>嵯峨天皇が第一皇子以下に対して太郎、次郎、三郎といった幼名を授けたことから、時代を追うにつれ一般に広まるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Emperor Saga gave the childhood name Taro to the first prince, Jiro to the second prince, Saburo to the third prince and so forth, these names spread to the commoners over time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Emperor Saga gave the childhood name Taro to the first prince, Jiro to the second prince, Saburo to the third prince and so forth, these names spread to the general populace over time.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;commoners&quot; to &quot;general populace&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Emperor Saga gave the childhood name Taro to the first prince, Jiro to the second prince, Saburo to the third prince and so forth, these names spread to the general populace over time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>とりわけ武士としては、源頼義の嫡男源義家と名乗り弟もそれぞれ源義綱、源義光等と名乗っているように平安時代には既に武士階級に広まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Particularly Haikomei spread to the samurai (warriors) class already in the Heian period as seen in the example of the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi took the name MINAMOTO no Yoshiie, his younger brothers MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna and MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the samurai (warrior) class in particular, Haikomei had already spread in the Heian period, as seen by examples such as the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi taking the name MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and his younger brothers taking the names MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna and MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the samurai (warrior) class in particular, Haikomei had already spread in the Heian period, as seen by examples such as the legitimate son of MINAMOTO no Yoriyoshi taking the name MINAMOTO no Yoshiie and his younger brothers taking the names MINAMOTO no Yoshitsuna and MINAMOTO no Yoshimitsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>太郎、次郎の名乗りは時代が下った後も武士階級、町人階級問わず広く用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Names such as Taro and Jiro were widely used during the passage of time both in the samurai class and the merchant class</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over time, names such as Taro and Jiro were widely used in both the samurai and merchant classes.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over time, names such as Taro and Jiro were widely used in both the samurai and merchant classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>武士階級が仮名なのに対して、諱を持たぬ町人の場合は正真正銘の本名として用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the samurai class these names were assumed names while in the merchant class they were real names because merchants did not have imina (personal name).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haikomei used by the samurai class were assumed names, while in the merchant class they were real names due to merchants not having an imina (personal name).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haikomei used by the samurai class were assumed names, while in the merchant class they were real names due to merchants not having an imina (personal name).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>なお、太郎、次郎・・・という名は必ずしも出生順と一致せず、例えば宇喜多秀家は次男であるが「八郎」であったり、茶屋四郎次郎のように代々襲名される場合もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Names such as Taro and Jiro don&apos;t always correspond with the birth order and, for example, although Hideie UKITA was the second son, his childhood name was &quot;Hachiro&quot;(which means the eighth son), and sometimes the predecessor&apos;s name was handed down like the case of Shirojiro CHAYA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Names such as Taro and Jiro do no always correspond to the order in which they are born. For example, although Hideie UKITA was a second son, his childhood name was &quot;Hachiro&quot; (meaning the &quot;eighth&quot; son), and in other cases, a predecessor&apos;s name was handed down, as seen in the case of Shirojiro CHAYA.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Names such as Taro and Jiro do no always correspond to the order in which they are born. For example, although Hideie UKITA was a second son, his childhood name was &quot;Hachiro&quot; (meaning the &quot;eighth&quot; son), and in other cases, a predecessor&apos;s name was handed down, as seen in the case of Shirojiro CHAYA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>（ちなみに「四郎次郎」は「四郎の次男」の意味である。)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(In fact, &quot;Shirojiro&quot; means &quot;the second son of Shiro.&quot;)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(In fact, &quot;Shirojiro&quot; means &quot;the second son of Shiro.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(In fact, &quot;Shirojiro&quot; means &quot;the second son of Shiro.&quot;)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 日陰猫Joga(id:9749), 海衛士(id:19229), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>