<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二十五三昧会</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijugozanmaie</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijugozanmaie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijugozanmaie</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二十五三昧会（にじゅうござんまいえ）とは、平安時代に結成された念仏結社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijugozanmaie was a Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) association established in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijugozanmaie was a Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) association established in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijugozanmaie was a Nenbutsu (Buddhist invocation) association established in the Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>986年（寛和2年）に比叡山内延暦寺横川にあった首楞厳院で、25人の僧が結集して結成された念仏結社である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was a Nenbutsu association established in 986 by 25 monks who gathered at Shuryogonin in Enryaku-ji Temple, Yokawa within Mt. Hie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was a Nenbutsu association established in 986 by 25 monks who gathered at Shuryogonin in Enryaku-ji Temple, Yokawa within Mt. Hie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was a Nenbutsu association established in 986 by 25 monks who gathered at Shuryogonin in Enryaku-ji Temple, Yokawa within Mt. Hie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この結社の性格は、極楽往生を希求する念仏結社であり、月の15日ごとに僧衆25名が集結して念仏を誦し、極楽往生を願った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic of this association was that it was a Nenbutsu association that wished for gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) and on the fifteenth of each month, 25 monks would gather to chant Nenbutsu and wish for gokuraku ojo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristic of this association was that it was a Nenbutsu association that wished for gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) and on the fifteenth of each month, 25 monks would gather to chant Nenbutsu and wish for gokuraku ojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic of this association was that it was a Nenbutsu association that wished for gokuraku ojo (peaceful death) and on the fifteenth of each month, 25 monks would gather to chant Nenbutsu and wish for gokuraku ojo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>彼等の「発願文」に、善友の契りを結び、臨終の際には相互に扶助して念仏することを記していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Hotsugan bun (vow)&quot; states that they agree to a bond of friendship, promise to help each other upon death and chant Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Hotsugan bun&quot; (vow) states that they agree to a bond of friendship, promise to help each other upon death and chant Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>moved quotation mark</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Hotsugan bun&apos; (vow) states that they agree to a bond of friendship, promise to help each other upon death and chant Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>『日本往生極楽記』の撰者でもある慶滋保胤が起草した「二十五三昧起請」には、</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who was also the editor of &quot;Nihon ojo gokurakuki&quot; (Japanese records of birth into the Pure Land), drafted the &quot;Nijugozanmai kisho&quot; which stated:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who was also the editor of &quot;Nihon ojo gokurakuki&quot; (Japanese records of birth into the Pure Land), drafted the &quot;Nijugozanmai kisho&quot; which stated:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">YOSHISHIGE no Yasutane, who was also the editor of &quot;Nihon ojo gokurakuki&quot; (Japanese records of birth into the Pure Land), drafted the &apos;Nijugozanmai kisho&apos; which stated:</e>
<cmt>シングルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>毎月十五日に念仏三昧を修すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the fifteenth of each month, nenbutsu-zammai (mental absorption in the nenbutsu) should be chanted</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the fifteenth of each month, nenbutsu-zammai (mental absorption in the nenbutsu) should be chanted.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the fifteenth of each month, nenbutsu-zammai (mental absorption in the nenbutsu) should be chanted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="7">
<j>光明真言を誦して、土砂加持を修すること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Komyo shingon (Mantra of Light) should be chanted and Dosha kaji (incantation) conducted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Komyo shingon (Mantra of Light) should be chanted and Dosha kaji (incantation) conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Komyo shingon (Mantra of Light) should be chanted and Dosha kaji (incantation) conducted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="8">
<j>結衆は規律を厳守し、叛いた者は脱退させて、代わりの者を補充する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Members should strictly adhere to rules and non-adherents will be expelled and new members recruited instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Members should strictly adhere to rules and non-adherents will be expelled and new members recruited instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Members should strictly adhere to rules and non-adherents will be expelled and new members recruited instead.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="9">
<j>別所に阿弥陀如来を奉安した往生院を建立し、病んだ結衆はそこに移す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An Ojoin celebrating Amida Nyorai will be established in a Bessho(remote religious facilities from main temple facilities) and sick members will be transferred there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An Ojoin celebrating Amida Nyorai will be established in a Bessho (remote religious facilities from main temple facilities) and sick members will be transferred there.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An Ojo-in Temple celebrating Amida Nyorai will be established in a Bessho (remote religious facilities from main temple facilities) and sick members will be transferred there.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="10">
<j>病んだ結衆を往生院に移した時は、二人一組となって昼夜の別なく従い、一人が看病、一人が念仏を担当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a sick member is transferred to the Ojoin, a pair will stay with the sick member day and night, with one caring for the sick, while the other chants Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a sick member is transferred to the Ojoin, a pair will stay with the sick member day and night, with one caring for the sick, while the other chants Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a sick member is transferred to the Ojo-in Temple, a pair will stay with the sick member day and night, with one caring for the sick, while the other chants Nenbutsu.</e>
<cmt>用語集に統一</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="11">
<j>花台廟と名づけた結衆の墓地を定め、春秋2回、集まって念仏会を修する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The members&apos; tomb will be called Kadaibyo and members will gather for a Nenbutsu meeting will be held twice a year in spring and autumn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The members&apos; tomb will be called Kadaibyo and members will gather for a Nenbutsu meeting twice a year in spring and autumn.</e>
<cmt>deleted “will be held”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The members&apos; tomb will be called Kadaibyo and members will gather for a Nenbutsu meeting twice a year in spring and autumn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="12">
<j>ひたすら西方極楽浄土を念じ、極楽往生を念ずる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land (of Amida Buddha)) should be meditated about with mental absorption and gokuraku ojo should be wished for.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land) should be meditated on with mental absorption and gokuraku ojo should be wished for.</e>
<cmt>nested parentheses; spacing; prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (The West Pure Land) should be meditated on with mental absorption and gokuraku ojo should be wished for.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="13">
<j>結衆に欠員が出ても、残った結衆が修善によって、先に往生した結衆との縁を保たなければならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if there are absent members, the members that are left must keep the en(ties) with the pre-deceased member by Shuzen(restoration).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if there are absent members, the members that are left must keep ties with deceased members by Shuzen (restoration).</e>
<cmt>spacing; deleted “pre-”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if there are absent members, the members that are left must keep ties with deceased members by Shuzen (restoration).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="14">
<j>という結社の決まりが述べられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the rules of the association.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These are the rules of the association.</e>
<cmt>as-&gt;these are</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These are the rules of the association.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="15">
<j>二十五三昧会の成立には、964年（応和4年）に大学寮の学生らが比叡山の僧らと結集した結社である勧学会の影響が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Th influence of &quot;Kangaku-e&quot;(assembly to encourage learning), an association established by Daigakuryo students and monks from Mt. Hie in 964 are seen in the establishment of Nijugozanmaie.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The influence of &quot;Kangaku-e&quot; (assembly to encourage learning), an association established by Daigakuryo students and monks from Mt. Hie in 964, are seen in the establishment of Nijugozanmaie.</e>
<cmt>spelling; spacing; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The influence of &quot;Kangaku-e&quot; (assembly to encourage learning), an association established by Daigakuryo students and monks from Mt. Hie in 964, are seen in the establishment of Nijugozanmaie.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>但し、勧学会の場合は、念仏結社的な性格も有してはいたが、『法華経』を読誦し、作詩も行なうサロン的傾向の強い集団であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Kangaku-e had aspects of Nenbutsu association but the group also had an aspect of a salon where &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra (the Lotus Sutra)&quot; was chanted and poems were written.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, although Kangaku-e resembled a Nenbutsu association, the group also had an aspect of a salon where &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Lotus Sutra) was chanted and poems were written.</e>
<cmt>had aspects of-&gt;resembled; punctuation; moved quotation mark</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, although Kangaku-e resembled a Nenbutsu association, the group also had an aspect of a salon where &quot;Hoke-kyo Sutra&quot; (the Lotus Sutra) was chanted and poems were written.</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォート</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nsq(id:54991), Chi-Ham(id:143515), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>