<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日本美術史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon Bijutsu-Shi&quot; (Japanese Art History)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon Bijutsu-Shi&quot; (Japanese Art History)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihon Bijutsu-Shi (Japanese Art History)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>日本美術史（にほんびじゅつし）とは、日本の美術の流れ、様式の変遷、各時代の代表的な作品や作家の研究、相互の影響関係、作品や作家を生んだ時代背景（政治、経済、信仰、風俗、社会、文学などとの関連）などについて述べたもの、またはそうした分野を研究する学問のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nihon bijutsu-shi&quot; refers to the chronological explanation - or the academic field - of the Japanese art history, such as the trend of Japanese art, the transition of its style, the research of the representative works and artists in each period, their mutual influence, and the historical background of the works and artists - that is, the works&apos; and artists&apos; relation with the Japanese politics, economy, religion, customs, society, literature and others.</e>
<cmt>・「概論」で「美術」という日本語そのものに焦点が当てられているので、ここでも「日本美術史」につきローマ字表記を記しておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nihon bijutsu-shi&quot; refers to the chronological explanation - or the academic field - of Japanese art history, such as the trend of Japanese art, the transition of its style, the research of the representative works and artists in each period, their mutual influence, and the historical background of the works and artists - that is, the works&apos; and artists&apos; relation with Japanese politics, economy, religion, customs, society, literature and others.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nihon bijutsu-shi&quot; refers to the chronological explanation - or the academic field - of Japanese art history, such as the trend of Japanese art, the transition of its style, the research of the representative works and artists in each period, their mutual influence, and the historical background of the works and artists - that is, the works&apos; and artists&apos; relation with Japanese politics, economy, religion, customs, society, literature and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>本項では日本美術史の概観を述べるにとどめ、各時代の美術についてはそれぞれ別項目を設けて詳説する（予定）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the summary of the Japanese art history is explained in this section, and the detail about art works in each period will be explained in other sections.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only the summary of Japanese art history is explained in this section, and the detail about art works in each period will be explained in other sections.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only the summary of Japanese art history is explained in this section, and the detail about art works in each period will be explained in other sections.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>「日本美術史」の始まり</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beginning of Japanese art history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beginning of Japanese art history</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beginning of Japanese art history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>「美術」という日本語の単語は西洋語からの翻訳語であり、1873年（明治6年）、当時の日本政府がウィーン万国博覧会へ参加するに当たり、出品する品物の区分名称として、ドイツ語のKunstgewerbeの訳語として「美術」を採用したのが初出と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese word &quot;bijutsu&quot; is the translation from the Western word that means &quot;art,&quot; and in A.D. 1873, the then Japanese government participated in Vienna International Exhibition, and used for the first time &quot;bijutsu&quot; as the translation of the German word &quot;Kunstgewerbe&quot; in order to distinguish Japanese exhibits from others, they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese word &quot;bijutsu&quot; is the translation of the Western word that means &quot;art,&quot; and in A.D. 1873, the then Japanese government participated in the Vienna International Exhibition, and used for the first time &quot;bijutsu&quot; as the translation of the German word &quot;Kunstgewerbe&quot; in order to distinguish Japanese exhibits from others, they say.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese word &apos;bijutsu&apos; is the translation of the Western word that means &apos;art,&apos; and in A.D. 1873, the then Japanese government participated in the Vienna International Exhibition, and used for the first time &apos;bijutsu&apos; as the translation of the German word &apos;Kunstgewerbe&apos; in order to distinguish Japanese exhibits from others, they say.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>もっとも、この当時の「美術」には詩や音楽なども含まれ、現代日本語の「芸術」に近い語義であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, &quot;bijutsu&quot; included poetry, music, and others, so it was almost synonymous with &quot;geijutsu&quot; (today&apos;s Japanese word that means art and other artistic skills).</e>
<cmt>・原文からは、「美術」と「芸術」とは訳し分ける必要があるように思われます。よって前者を&quot;art&quot; 後者を&quot;art and other artistic skills&quot; としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, &quot;bijutsu&quot; included poetry, music, and others, so it was almost synonymous with &quot;geijutsu&quot; (today&apos;s Japanese word that means art and other artistic skills).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, &apos;bijutsu&apos; included poetry, music, and others, so it was almost synonymous with &apos;geijutsu&apos; (today&apos;s Japanese word that means art and other artistic skills).</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>「美術」という単語自体が明治時代案出の訳語であり、西洋の概念を日本に当てはめたものであった以上、「日本美術」あるいは「日本美術史」という概念もそれ以前の時代には存在しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only in the Meiji period that the word &quot;bijutsu&quot; itself was devised as the Japanese equivalent of the Western concept of &quot;art,&quot; so the word &quot;Nihon bijutsu&quot; (Japanese art) or &quot;Nihon bijutsu-shi&quot; (Japanese art history) had not been seen until then.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was only in the Meiji period that the word &quot;bijutsu&quot; itself was devised as the Japanese equivalent of the Western concept of &quot;art,&quot; so the word &quot;Nihon bijutsu&quot; (Japanese art) or &quot;Nihon bijutsu-shi&quot; (Japanese art history) had not been seen until then.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was only in the Meiji period that the word &apos;bijutsu&apos; itself was devised as the Japanese equivalent of the Western concept of &apos;art,&apos; so the word &apos;Nihon bijutsu&apos; (Japanese art) or &apos;Nihon bijutsu-shi&apos; (Japanese art history) had not been seen until then.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>「美術館」「美術家」「美術史」などの語も当然明治時代以降に使用されるようになったものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, it was only in the Meiji period that the Japanese words related to &quot;bijutsu,&quot; such as &quot;bijutsu-kan&quot; (an art museum), &quot;bijutsu-ka&quot; (an artist), and &quot;bijutsu-shi&quot; (art history), began to be used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, it was only in the Meiji period that the Japanese words related to &quot;bijutsu,&quot; such as &quot;bijutsu-kan&quot; (an art museum), &quot;bijutsu-ka&quot; (an artist), and &quot;bijutsu-shi&quot; (art history), began to be used.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, it was only in the Meiji period that the Japanese words related to &apos;bijutsu,&apos; such as &apos;bijutsu-kan&apos; (an art museum), &apos;bijutsu-ka&apos; (an artist), and &apos;bijutsu-shi&apos; (art history), began to be used.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>「美術館」という名称は1877年（明治10年）に東京・上野で開催された第1回内国勧業博覧会の陳列館の名称として使用されたのが初出である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bijutsu-kan&quot; was used as the word to mean an art exhibition building for the first time in 1877, when the First National Industrial Exhibition was held in Ueno, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bijutsu-kan&quot; was used as the word to mean an art exhibition building for the first time in 1877, when the First National Industrial Exhibition was held in Ueno, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bijutsu-kan&apos; was used as the word to mean an art exhibition building for the first time in 1877, when the First National Industrial Exhibition was held in Ueno, Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>1889年（明治22年）に開校した東京美術学校（現・東京芸術大学美術学部）では「美学及び美術史」が開講され、この頃から「美術史」の語は現代と同様の意味で使用されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokyo Fine Arts School (today&apos;s fine arts faculty of Tokyo University of the Arts), which started in 1889, opened the course of aesthetics and art history, and around then the word of art history began to be used in the similar meaning to today&apos;s.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokyo Fine Arts School (today&apos;s fine arts faculty of Tokyo University of the Arts), which started in 1889, opened the course of aesthetics and art history, and around then the word of art history began to be used with a similar meaning to today&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokyo Fine Arts School (today&apos;s fine arts faculty of Tokyo University of the Arts), which started in 1889, opened the course of aesthetics and art history, and around then the word of art history began to be used with a similar meaning to today&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>1900年（明治33年）には日本初の美術史本と目される『稿本日本帝国美術略史』が刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1900, the book with the title &quot;The original draft of the brief history of the Japanese art&quot; was published, which is deemed the first book written on art history in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1900, the book with the title &quot;The original draft of the brief history of Japanese art&quot; was published, which is deemed the first book written on art history in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1900, the book with the title &quot;The original draft of the brief history of Japanese art&quot; was published, which is deemed the first book written on art history in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日本美術史の扱う範囲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Range that Japanese art history covers</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Range that Japanese art history covers</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Range that Japanese art history covers</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>日本列島の地域で制作・享受された美術をその範囲とすると考えるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geographically speaking, it is common that the arts produced or enjoyed on the Japanese archipelago are regarded as the objects which the Japanese art history covers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geographically speaking, it is common that the arts produced or enjoyed on the Japanese archipelago are regarded as the objects which Japanese art history covers.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geographically speaking, it is common that the arts produced or enjoyed on the Japanese archipelago are regarded as the objects which Japanese art history covers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>おもに北海道に住み、特有の文化をもつアイヌの人々の美術や、現代の沖縄県にあたる琉球の美術については、いわゆる日本美術史とは別の文脈で論じられることがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The history of art in Ainu tribe, which inhabits mainly in Hokkaido Prefecture and has the culture of its own, is sometimes discussed separately from what is called Japanese art history, and this is the same as the history of the art in Ryukyu (today&apos;s Okinawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The history of art in the Ainu tribe, which inhabits mainly Hokkaido Prefecture and has a culture of its own, is sometimes discussed separately from what is called Japanese art history, and this is the same as the history of the art from Ryukyu (today&apos;s Okinawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The history of art in the Ainu tribe, which inhabits mainly Hokkaido Prefecture and has a culture of its own, is sometimes discussed separately from what is called Japanese art history, and this is the same as the history of the art from Ryukyu (today&apos;s Okinawa Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>もっとも、20世紀以降の美術については、作者がもっぱら海外で制作していたり、国境を越えて幅広く活動していることが多く、上記の考え方は必ずしも妥当しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the above-mentioned idea about the geographical range does not always apply to the art from the 20th century, because many Japanese artists have come to produce their arts only in foreign countries or make their activities worldwide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the above-mentioned idea about the geographical range does not always apply to the art from the 20th century, because many Japanese artists have come to produce their arts only in foreign countries or make their activities worldwide.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the above-mentioned idea about the geographical range does not always apply to the art from the 20th century, because many Japanese artists have come to produce their arts only in foreign countries or make their activities worldwide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>次に、ジャンルの面でどこまでを「美術史」で扱うかという点であるが、日本美術においては、絵画、彫刻と並んで工芸品の占める位置が非常に大きく、金工、漆工、染織、陶磁などの分野を抜きにして美術史を語ることは妥当でない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, when it comes to the genre of the art history, handicrafts, as well as paintings and sculptures, occupy a large part in Japanese art, so the art history cannot be discussed without touching on the fields of metal work, lacquer work, dyeing and weaving work, ceramic ware, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, when it comes to the genre of the art history, handicrafts, as well as paintings and sculptures, occupy a large part in Japanese art, so art history cannot be discussed without touching on the fields of metal work, lacquer work, dyeing and weaving work, ceramic ware, and so on.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, when it comes to the genre of the art history, handicrafts, as well as paintings and sculptures, occupy a large part in Japanese art, so art history cannot be discussed without touching on the fields of metal work, lacquer work, dyeing and weaving work, ceramic ware, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>刀剣・武具も日本美術の伝統を考えるうえで軽視できない存在であり、「武士の魂」と称され神聖視されている刀剣はその外装や小道具のみならず、刀身自体が美的鑑賞の対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Swords and arms cannot be disdained in the tradition of Japanese art, and especially swords have been sanctified as the soul of samurai, so that the exterior ornament, the attached tools, and the blade itself become appreciated as the symbol of beauty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Swords and arms cannot be disdained in the tradition of Japanese art, and especially swords have been sanctified as the soul of samurai, so that the exterior ornament, the attached tools, and the blade itself become appreciated as a symbol of beauty.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Swords and arms cannot be disdained in the tradition of Japanese art, and especially swords have been sanctified as the soul of samurai, so that the exterior ornament, the attached tools, and the blade itself become appreciated as a symbol of beauty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>中国の場合と同様、「書」も重要なジャンルであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similar to the case in China, calligraphy occupied an important genre in the Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similar to the case in China, calligraphy occupied an important genre in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similar to the case in China, calligraphy occupied an important genre in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「詩書画三絶」という言葉が示すように、水墨画などでは1つの作品に詩、書、絵画が表わされ、これらは不可分のものとして鑑賞された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Calligraphy forms a harmonious whole with poetry and painting in, for example, &quot;suibokuga&quot; (a monochrome painting in India ink), so these three have been appreciated as the inseparable art, and this is symbolized by the existence of the phrase &quot;The Three Perfections: Calligraphy, Poetry and Painting.&quot;</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Calligraphy forms a harmonious whole with poetry and painting in, for example, &quot;suibokuga&quot; (a monochrome painting in India ink), so these three have been appreciated as an inseparable art, and this is symbolized by the existence of the phrase &quot;The Three Perfections: Calligraphy, Poetry and Painting.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Calligraphy forms a harmonious whole with poetry and painting in, for example, &quot;suibokuga&quot; (a monochrome painting in India ink), so these three have been appreciated as an inseparable art, and this is symbolized by the existence of the phrase &apos;The Three Perfections: Calligraphy, Poetry and Painting.&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>このほか、「日本美術史」という場合には、建築や庭園についても併せて論じるのが一般的である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, the history of architecture and Japanese garden is commonly included in the Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, the history of architecture and Japanese garden is commonly included in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, the history of architecture and Japanese garden is commonly included in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="18">
<j>なお、近代以降については、写真、グラフィックアートなど、現代（第二次世界大戦以降）においては（日本に限った現象ではないが）、パフォーマンス、ハプニング、ビデオアート、ランドアート、コンセプチュアル・アートなど、さまざまな表現形態が「美術」の文脈で語られ、「美術」とそうでないものとの差異は次第にあいまいになってきている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, various styles of expression have come to be included in &quot;art&quot; - from the modern age, photographs, graphic arts, and others, and in the present age (after World War Ⅱ), performing arts, happenings, video art, land art, and conceptual art, which are seen in other countries as well - so that the boundary between &quot;art&quot; and others gradually becomes ambiguous.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, various styles of expression have come to be included in &quot;art&quot; - from the modern age, photographs, graphic arts, and others, and in the present age (after World War Ⅱ), performing arts, happenings, video art, land art, and conceptual art, which are seen in other countries as well - so that the boundary between &quot;art&quot; and others gradually becomes ambiguous.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, various styles of expression have come to be included in &apos;art&apos; - from the modern age, photographs, graphic arts, and others, and in the present age (after World War Ⅱ), performing arts, happenings, video art, land art, and conceptual art, which are seen in other countries as well - so that the boundary between &apos;art&apos; and others gradually becomes ambiguous.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>日本美術の位置付けと特色</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Position and characteristics of Japanese art</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Position and characteristics of Japanese art</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Position and characteristics of Japanese art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>日本の美術は、古代以来、中国・朝鮮半島からの影響が大きいが、平安時代の国風文化をはじめ、日本独自の展開も見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese art has been greatly influenced by Chinese and Korean art since ancient times, but it also developed the culture of its own, including &quot;Kokufu Bunka&quot; (Japan&apos;s original national culture) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese art has been greatly influenced by Chinese and Korean art since ancient times, but it also developed a culture of its own, including &quot;Kokufu Bunka&quot; (Japan&apos;s original national culture) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese art has been greatly influenced by Chinese and Korean art since ancient times, but it also developed a culture of its own, including Kokufu Bunka (Japan&apos;s original national culture) in the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>近世初期に宣教師らが日本を訪れ、一部に西洋美術が知られるようになったが、その影響は局所的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At an early stage of the early modern ages, Christian missionaries came over to Japan, and Western art became known to some Japanese at that time, but its influence on Japanese art was quite limited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At an early stage of the early modern ages, Christian missionaries came over to Japan, and Western art became known to some Japanese at that time, but its influence on Japanese art was quite limited.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At an early stage of the early modern ages, Christian missionaries came over to Japan, and Western art became known to some Japanese at that time, but its influence on Japanese art was quite limited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>ただし、江戸時代の美術にオランダ絵画の影響を指摘する研究者もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, some scholars point out that Japanese art in the Edo period was influenced by Dutch paintings.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, some scholars point out that Japanese art in the Edo period was influenced by Dutch paintings.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, some scholars point out that Japanese art in the Edo period was influenced by Dutch paintings.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>明治時代になると、西洋化近代化が国家目標になり、美術分野でもお雇い外国人による指導が行われ、芸術の本場と考えられたフランスへ留学する者もいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Japanese government set the national goal on westernization and modernization, and therefore, also in the art field, hired foreigners taught Japanese, and since France was deemed the home of art, some Japanese went there for study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, the Japanese government set a national goal of westernization and modernization, and therefore, also in the art field, hired foreigners taught Japanese, and since France was deemed the home of art, some Japanese went there for study.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Japanese government set a national goal of westernization and modernization, and therefore, also in the art field, hired foreigners taught Japanese, and since France was deemed the home of art, some Japanese went there for study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>洋画の技法が習得される一方、伝統への志向が生れ「日本画」が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some learned the technique of the Western-style painting, and others became tradition-oriented, which gave birth to the Japanese-style painting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some learned the technique of Western-style painting, and others became tradition-oriented, which gave birth to Japanese-style painting.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some learned the technique of Western-style painting, and others became tradition-oriented, which gave birth to Japanese-style painting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一方、海外において日本美術の装飾性が注目され、ジャポニズムがブームとなり、印象派やアール・ヌーボーへの刺激を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, in foreign countries, Japanese art attracted people&apos;s attention to its decorativess, originated the boom of Japonisme (in English, Japanism), and gave artistic stimulation to the impressionists and Art Nouveau.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in foreign countries, Japanese art attracted people&apos;s attention to its decorativeness, originated the boom of Japonisme (in English, Japanism), and gave artistic stimulation to the impressionists and Art Nouveau.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in foreign countries, Japanese art attracted people&apos;s attention to its decorativeness, originated the boom of Japonisme (in English, Japanism), and gave artistic stimulation to the impressionists and Art Nouveau.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>日本美術は、広い視野で見れば、アジア美術の一環であり、インド、中国を含む仏教圏の美術と見なすこともできる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From a broader perspective, Japanese art is deemed a part of Asian art, and it can also be deemed a part of the art of Buddhist countries, which includes India and China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From a broader perspective, Japanese art is deemed a part of Asian art, and it can also be deemed a part of the art of Buddhist countries, which includes India and China.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From a broader perspective, Japanese art is deemed a part of Asian art, and it can also be deemed a part of the art of Buddhist countries, which includes India and China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>日本の美術は、縄文時代を例外として、常に外国（近世以前はおもに中国、近代以降はおもに西洋）の影響を強く受けつつ、独自の様式を発達させてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese art has developed its peculiar style always - except for the Jomon period - under the great influence of other countries - mainly that of China before the early modern ages, and that of Western countries after the modern age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese art has developed its peculiar style always - except for the Jomon period - under the great influence of other countries - mainly that of China before the early modern ages, and that of Western countries after the modern age.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese art has developed its peculiar style always - except for the Jomon period - under the great influence of other countries - mainly that of China before the early modern ages, and that of Western countries after the modern age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>日本美術の流れを理解するには、常に中国や朝鮮半島の美術史と対比して考えねばならず、日本の美術が日本人のみの手によって自律的に発達したものと考えることは誤りである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in order to understand the trend of Japanese art, it should always be compared with the art history of China and Korea, and if you think Japanese developed their art all by themselves, it is wrong.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in order to understand the trend of Japanese art, it should always be compared with the art history of China and Korea, and if you think Japanese developed their art all by themselves, it is wrong.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in order to understand the trend of Japanese art, it should always be compared with the art history of China and Korea, and if you think Japanese developed their art all by themselves, it is wrong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>だが、日本美術を中国美術の亜流と見なすことも同様に誤りといえよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, if you regard Japanese art as the poor imitation of Chinese art, it might be wrong as well.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, if you regard Japanese art as a poor imitation of Chinese art, it might be wrong as well.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, if you regard Japanese art as a poor imitation of Chinese art, it might be wrong as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>欧米の大美術館の多くに日本美術ギャラリーがあり、「日本美術」は独自の様式をもった美術として認識されていることがわかる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many European and American art museums have the Japanese art gallery, and this shows they recognize Japanese art as the art with its unique style.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many European and American art museums have a Japanese art gallery, and this shows they recognize Japanese art as an art with its own unique style.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many European and American art museums have a Japanese art gallery, and this shows they recognize Japanese art as an art with its own unique style.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>ただし、ニューヨークのメトロポリタン美術館やロンドンの大英博物館の日本ギャラリーは、中国美術やエジプト美術のギャラリーに比べて規模も小さく、開設時期も比較的新しいということは事実である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is true, however, that the Japanese art gallery of the Metropolitan Museum in New York and that of the British Museum in London are both smaller and newer than their Chinese and Egyptian art galleries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is true, however, that the Japanese art gallery of the Metropolitan Museum in New York and that of the British Museum in London are both smaller and newer than their Chinese and Egyptian art galleries.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is true, however, that the Japanese art gallery of the Metropolitan Museum in New York and that of the British Museum in London are both smaller and newer than their Chinese and Egyptian art galleries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="31">
<j>以下、主に絵画・彫刻・工芸・建築の各分野について記述する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the explanation mainly for the painting, sculpture, handicraft, and architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is a description focusing on painting, sculpture, handicraft, and architecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a description focusing on painting, sculpture, handicraft, and architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="32">
<j>先史時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prehistoric age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prehistoric age</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prehistoric age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>縄文時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jomon period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomon period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomon period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="34">
<j>日本列島にも旧石器文化が存在したことは、岩宿遺跡（群馬県）をはじめ、各地での発掘調査の結果から明らかとなっているが、日本の旧石器文化の遺物には造形芸術と呼ぶべきものはほとんど存在しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Excavation and research in many places, including Iwajuku Archaeological Site (in Gunma Prefecture), revealed that there had once existed the Paleolithic culture on the Japanese archipelago, but things that can be said art and design have rarely been found in the relics of the Paleolithic culture.</e>
<cmt>・「遺跡」の訳はHPにより異なりますが、このファイルでは以下全て&quot;archaeological site&quot; で統一しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Excavation and research in many places, including the Iwajuku Archaeological Site (in Gunma Prefecture), revealed that there had once existed a Paleolithic culture on the Japanese archipelago, but things that can be called art and design have rarely been found in the relics of the Paleolithic culture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Excavation and research in many places, including the Iwajuku Archaeological Site (in Gunma Prefecture), revealed that there had once existed a Paleolithic culture on the Japanese archipelago, but things that can be called art and design have rarely been found in the relics of the Paleolithic culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>現代人の考える「美術」に該当する遺物が出現するのは新石器文化に相当する縄文時代からである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is from the sites in (and after) this Jomon period, which falls under the Neolithic culture, that the relics people of today regard as &quot;art&quot; can be found.</e>
<cmt>・原文は多少舌足らずなので、末尾の「縄文時代」のあとに「以降の遺跡」と補って英訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is from the sites in (and after) this Jomon period, which falls under the Neolithic culture, that the relics people of today regard as &quot;art&quot; can be found.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is from the sites in (and after) this Jomon period, which falls under the Neolithic culture, that the relics people of today regard as &apos;art&apos; can be found.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>縄文時代は日本列島の美術が外部からの影響や情報にさらされず、独自の発展をとげた唯一の時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jomon period was the only period that the Japanese art developed by itself without the influence and the information from abroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jomon period was the only period that Japanese art developed by itself without the influence and information from abroad.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jomon period was the only period that Japanese art developed by itself without the influence and information from abroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>この時代、人々はおもに狩猟、漁労、採集によって生活していたが、三内丸山遺跡（青森県）などの発掘調査結果によると、この時代すでに栽培が行われ、人々は豊かな食生活をしていたことが明らかになり、時代観も変わりつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this period, people made their living mainly with hunting, fishing, and herborizing, but the excavation and research in some places, such as Sannai-Maruyama Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), revealed that people had already begun cultivating and had enjoyed plentiful diets, so our perspective on this period is changing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this period, people made their living mainly with hunting, fishing, and gathering, but the excavation and research in some places, such as the Sannai-Maruyama Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), revealed that people had already begun cultivating and had enjoyed plentiful diets, so our perspective on this period is changing.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this period, people made their living mainly with hunting, fishing, and gathering, but the excavation and research in some places, such as the Sannai-Maruyama Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), revealed that people had already begun cultivating and had enjoyed plentiful diets, so our perspective on this period is changing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>縄文時代は出土する土器の様式編年から草創期、早期、前期、中期、後期、晩期の6期に区分されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jomon period is classified, according to the style of the excavated pottery, into six stages, that is, the initial stage, the pre-early stage, the early stage, the middle stage, the late stage, and the final stage.</e>
<cmt>・「土器」の訳は色々ありますが、このファイルでは抽象的・集合的なそれを表す時は&quot;pottery&quot;（不可算名詞） とし、数えられる個々の土器を指す時は&quot;earthen vessel&quot; としています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jomon period is classified, according to the style of the excavated pottery, into six stages, that is, the initial stage, the pre-early stage, the early stage, the middle stage, the late stage, and the final stage.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jomon period is classified, according to the style of the excavated pottery, into six stages, that is, the initial stage, the pre-early stage, the early stage, the middle stage, the late stage, and the final stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>草創期の土器は、放射性炭素年代測定で今から約16,500年前（暦年較正年代法による。従来の放射性炭素測定年代では約13,000年前から。）にさかのぼるとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The carbon dating with the calibration method shows that the initial stage&apos;s pottery dates back to about 16,500 years ago - with the conventional uncalibrated method, it dates back to about 13,000 years ago.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The carbon dating with calibration method shows that the initial stage&apos;s pottery dates back to about 16,500 years ago - with the conventional uncalibrated method, it dates back to about 13,000 years ago.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The carbon dating with calibration method shows that the initial stage&apos;s pottery dates back to about 16,500 years ago - with the conventional uncalibrated method, it dates back to about 13,000 years ago.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>その年代については議論が存在するが、現在のところ、これは世界規模で見ても最古の土器ということになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whichever method is right, the initial stage&apos;s pottery is the oldest of all ever found in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whichever method is right, the initial stage&apos;s pottery is the oldest of all ever found in the world.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whichever method is right, the initial stage&apos;s pottery is the oldest of all ever found in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="41">
<j>木製品、繊維などの有機物は土中で遺存しにくいため、この時代の出土遺物は土製品、石製品、骨角製品が中心となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Organic matter, such as woodenware and fiber, deteriorates easily in the soil, so the excavated relics of this period are mainly occupied with clay artifacts, stone objects, and bone and antler objects.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Organic matter, such as wooden ware and fiber, deteriorates easily in soil, so the excavated relics of this period are mainly occupied with clay artifacts, stone objects, and bone and antler objects.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Organic matter, such as wooden ware and fiber, deteriorates easily in soil, so the excavated relics of this period are mainly occupied with clay artifacts, stone objects, and bone and antler objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>このうち、時代の変遷をもっともよく示す遺物が土器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, the pottery shows the transition of historical stages more vividly than anything else.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, the pottery shows the transition of historical stages more vividly than anything else.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, the pottery shows the transition of historical stages more vividly than anything else.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>土器は時代や地域によって様式にかなりの相違があり、多くの形式に区分されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The pottery varies significantly in style depending on when it was made and where it was found, and it is classified into many types.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The pottery varies significantly in style depending on when it was made and where it was found, and it is classified into many types.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The pottery varies significantly in style depending on when it was made and where it was found, and it is classified into many types.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>全般的な特色として言えることは、いわゆる縄文（縄紋とも書く）をはじめとした各種文様で器面を加飾し、全体に装飾過剰の気味があることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the whole, it can be said characteristic of this period&apos;s pottery that the surface is covered with such various patterns, including what is called &quot;jomon&quot; (a straw-rope pattern, or a cord mark), that the pottery smacks of being too much decorative.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the whole, it can be said that a characteristic of this period&apos;s pottery is that the surface was covered with such various patterns, including what is called &quot;jomon&quot; (a straw-rope pattern, or a cord mark), that the pottery can be considered being too decorative.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the whole, it can be said that a characteristic of this period&apos;s pottery is that the surface was covered with such various patterns, including what is called &quot;jomon&quot; (a straw-rope pattern, or a cord mark), that the pottery can be considered being too decorative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>縄文は、棒に撚り紐をさまざまな形に巻き付けた施文具を焼成前の器面に押し当て、ころがすことによって生ずるもので、紐の巻き付け方によってさまざまな文様が生まれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the firing of the pottery, jomon was engraved by pushing a tool - a stick with a twisted thread, and there were varieties of twisting - against the pottery&apos;s surface and by rolling the tool on it, and various patterns appeared depending on how the thread was twisted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before the firing of the pottery, jomon was engraved by pushing a tool - a stick with a twisted thread, and there were varieties of twisting - against the pottery&apos;s surface and by rolling the tool on it, and various patterns appeared depending on how the thread was twisted.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before the firing of the pottery, jomon was engraved by pushing a tool - a stick with a twisted thread, and there were varieties of twisting - against the pottery&apos;s surface and by rolling the tool on it, and various patterns appeared depending on how the thread was twisted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>このほか、竹管、貝殻などを施文具とした文様、粘土紐の貼り付け、刻線などさまざまな手段を用いて器面装飾が施されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, on the surface of the pottery are seen various kinds of decoration, such as the pattern engraved with some tool (a bamboo tube, a seashell, or the like), the clay string attachment, and engraved lines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, on the surface of the pottery are seen various kinds of decoration, such as a pattern engraved with some tool (a bamboo tube, a seashell, or the like), the clay string attachment, and engraved lines.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, on the surface of the pottery are seen various kinds of decoration, such as a pattern engraved with some tool (a bamboo tube, a seashell, or the like), the clay string attachment, and engraved lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>草創期の土器は、豆粒文、爪型文などと称される素朴な装飾を施したものが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of the initial stage&apos;s earthen vessel have simple decorations, such as &quot;toryumon&quot; (bean applique design) and &quot;tsumegatamon&quot; (fingernail-like design).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of the initial stage&apos;s earthen vessels have simple decorations, such as &quot;toryumon&quot; (bean shaped design) and &quot;tsumegatamon&quot; (fingernail-like design).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of the initial stage&apos;s earthen vessels have simple decorations, such as &quot;toryumon&quot; (bean shaped design) and &quot;tsumegatamon&quot; (fingernail-like design).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>中期は縄文時代特有の造形がピークに達する時期で、土器、土偶ともに装飾過多とも思えるほどのダイナミックな造形が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The art and design unique to the Jomon period reached its peak in its middle stage, when the earthen vessel, as well as the earthen figurine, became so dynamic in its design as to look too decorative.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The art and design unique to the Jomon period reached its peak in its middle stage, when the earthen vessels, as well as earthen figurines, became so dynamic in its design as to look too decorative.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The art and design unique to the Jomon period reached its peak in its middle stage, when the earthen vessels, as well as earthen figurines, became so dynamic in its design as to look too decorative.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>中部地方の勝坂式土器、新潟県で出土する馬高式土器などがその代表的なものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical examples are &quot;Katsusaka-shiki doki&quot; (the Katsusaka-type earthen vessel) excavated in Chubu region, and &quot;Umataka-shiki doki&quot; (the Umataka-type earthen vessel) excavated in Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical examples are &quot;Katsusaka-shiki doki&quot; (the Katsusaka-type earthen vessel) excavated in the Chubu region, and &quot;Umataka-shiki doki&quot; (the Umataka-type earthen vessel) excavated in Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical examples are Katsusaka-shiki doki (the Katsusaka-type earthen vessel) excavated in the Chubu region, and Umataka-shiki doki (the Umataka-type earthen vessel) excavated in Niigata Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>特に後者はいわゆる火焔式土器と称されるもので、口縁部には鶏冠ないし王冠を思わせる複雑な形状の装飾を付し、器面にも粘土紐の貼り付けで複雑な文様を表わしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of the two, the latter is what is called &quot;kaen-shiki doki&quot; (the flame-shaped earthen vessel), and an elaborate decoration like a cockscomb (or a crown) was put on the rim, and clay strings were attached to the vessel&apos;s surface for showing the elaborate pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of the two, the latter is what is called &quot;kaen-shiki doki&quot; (the flame-shaped earthen vessel), and an elaborate decoration like a cockscomb (or a crown) was put on the rim, and clay strings were attached to the vessel&apos;s surface for showing an elaborate pattern.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of the two, the latter is what is called &quot;kaen-shiki doki&quot; (the flame-shaped earthen vessel), and an elaborate decoration like a cockscomb (or a crown) was put on the rim, and clay strings were attached to the vessel&apos;s surface for showing an elaborate pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>後期から晩期にかけては、施した縄文の一部を磨り消して平滑にし、「地」と「文様」の区別を鮮明にした「磨消縄文」が現われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the late to the final stage of the period, the technique of &quot;surikeshi-jomon&quot; (cord mark erasing) appeared, with which part of the engraved &quot;jomon&quot; (cord mark) was erased for setting off the remaining jomon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the late to the final stage of the period, the technique of &quot;surikeshi-jomon&quot; (cord mark erasing) appeared, with which part of the engraved &quot;jomon&quot; (cord mark) was erased for setting off the remaining jomon.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the late to the final stage of the period, the technique of &quot;surikeshi-jomon&quot; (cord mark erasing) appeared, with which part of the engraved &quot;jomon&quot; (cord mark) was erased for setting off the remaining jomon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>器形や装飾も中期の呪術的で装飾過剰なものから次第に洗練されたものになり、製作者の美意識の変化がうかがわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In these stages, the shape and the decoration of the earthen vessel gradually became more sophisticated than the shamanistic, too decorative ones in the middle stage, and this suggests that the vessel-maker&apos;s sense of beauty changed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In these stages, the shape and the decoration of the earthen vessel gradually became more sophisticated than the shamanistic, too decorative ones in the middle stage, and this suggests that the vessel-maker&apos;s sense of beauty changed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these stages, the shape and the decoration of the earthen vessel gradually became more sophisticated than the shamanistic, too decorative ones in the middle stage, and this suggests that the vessel-maker&apos;s sense of beauty changed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>晩期の土器は用途に応じて器種・器形も変化に富み、現代の急須と同形の土器などもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the final stage, the type and shape of the earthen vessel became full of variety as its use became varied, so there also appeared the earthen vessel that has the same shape as today&apos;s teapot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the final stage, the type and shape of the earthen vessel became full of variety as its use became varied, so there also appeared a earthen vessel that has the same shape as today&apos;s teapot.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the final stage, the type and shape of the earthen vessel became full of variety as its use became varied, so there also appeared a earthen vessel that has the same shape as today&apos;s teapot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="54">
<j>土偶もこの時期に特有の遺物である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earthen figurines were also the relic unique to this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earthen figurines were also relics unique to this period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earthen figurines were also relics unique to this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>ハート形土偶、ミミズク形土偶、遮光器形土偶などと通称されるさまざまな形態のものがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist earthen figurines of various shapes, including those commonly known as the heart-shaped figurine, the horned-owl-like figurine, and the goggle-eyed figurine.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist earthen figurines of various shapes, including those commonly known as the heart-shaped figurine, the horned-owl-like figurine, and the goggle-eyed figurine.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist earthen figurines of various shapes, including those commonly known as the heart-shaped figurine, the horned-owl-like figurine, and the goggle-eyed figurine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>現実の人体の比例とは全く異った姿に表わされ、かろうじて人物像と認識できる段階までデフォルメされたものが多く、独特の造形感覚で作られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were made with an unique sense of design, so they cut a completely unpropotionate figure to the real human body, in other words, they were deformed so much as to be barely recognizable as a human-like figure.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were made with an unique sense of design, so they cut a figure of the real human body completely out of proportion, in other words, they were deformed so much as to be barely recognizable as a human-like figure.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were made with an unique sense of design, so they cut a figure of the real human body completely out of proportion, in other words, they were deformed so much as to be barely recognizable as a human-like figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>さまざまな呪術的意図をもって製作されたものと思われるが、妊娠した女性を表現した土偶などは豊穣祈願の意図をもって作られたものであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They seem to have been made with various shamanistic purposes, and the earthen figurine in the shape of a pregnant woman, for example, seems to have been made with the purpose of praying for the rich harvest of grain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They seem to have been made with various shamanistic purposes, and the earthen figurine in the shape of a pregnant woman, for example, seems to have been made with the purpose of praying for the rich harvest of grain.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They seem to have been made with various shamanistic purposes, and the earthen figurine in the shape of a pregnant woman, for example, seems to have been made with the purpose of praying for the rich harvest of grain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="58">
<j>縄文式土器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jomon-shiki doki&quot; (Cord-marked pottery)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jomon-shiki doki&quot; (Cord-marked pottery)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomon-shiki doki (Cord-marked pottery)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>笹山遺跡（新潟県）出土品（十日町市所有）－いわゆる火焔形土器など57点が国宝に指定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earthen vessels excavated at Sasayama Archaeological Site (in Niigata Prefecture) and owned by Tokamachi City : 57 pieces of earthen vessel, including what is called &quot;kaen-gata doki&quot; (the flame-shaped earthen vessel), were designated as the national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earthen vessels excavated at Sasayama Archaeological Site (in Niigata Prefecture) and owned by Tokamachi City : 57 pieces of earthen vessel, including what is called &quot;kaen-gata doki&quot; (the flame-shaped earthen vessel), were designated as national treasures.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earthen vessels excavated at Sasayama Archaeological Site (in Niigata Prefecture) and owned by Tokamachi City: 57 pieces of earthen vessel, including what is called &quot;kaen-gata doki&quot; (the flame-shaped earthen vessel), were designated as national treasures.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="60">
<j>土偶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Earthen figurine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Earthen figurine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Earthen figurine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>長野県棚畑遺跡出土土偶（茅野市所有）通称「縄文のビーナス」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The earthen figurine excavated at Tanabatake Archaeological Site in Nagano Prefecture (owned by Chino City) : commonly known as &quot;Jomon Venus&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earthen figurine excavated at Tanabatake Archaeological Site in Nagano Prefecture (owned by Chino City) : commonly known as &quot;Jomon Venus&quot;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earthen figurine excavated at Tanabatake Archaeological Site in Nagano Prefecture (owned by Chino City): commonly known as &apos;Jomon Venus&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>著名な遺跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known archaeological sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known archaeological sites</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known archaeological sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>三内丸山遺跡（青森県）、是川遺跡（青森県）、夏島貝塚（神奈川県）、鳥浜貝塚（福井県）など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sannai-Maruyama Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), Korekawa Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), Natsushima Shell-Midden (in Kanagawa Prefecture), Torihama Shell-Midden (in Fukui Prefecture), and so on</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sannai-Maruyama Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), Korekawa Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), Natsushima Shell-Midden (in Kanagawa Prefecture), Torihama Shell-Midden (in Fukui Prefecture), and so on</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sannai-Maruyama Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), Korekawa Archaeological Site (in Aomori Prefecture), Natsushima Shell-Midden (in Kanagawa Prefecture), Torihama Shell-Midden (in Fukui Prefecture), and so on</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="64">
<j>弥生時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yayoi period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yayoi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>初期農耕文化の時代であり、おおよそ紀元前3世紀から紀元後3世紀頃までの期間を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yayoi period falls under the age of the early agrarian culture, and ranged from about the third century B.C. to about the third century A.D.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yayoi period falls under the age of the early agrarian culture, and ranged from about the third century B.C. to about the third century A.D.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yayoi period falls under the age of the early agrarian culture, and ranged from about the third century B.C. to about the third century A.D.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>ただし、北九州から出土する最初期の土器を炭素14による年代測定法で調査したところ、紀元前8～9世紀という値が出たとの報告もあり、弥生時代の始期を5世紀ほどさかのぼらせるべきだとの主張もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some argue that the Yayoi period should date from five-century-earlier point, based on a carbon-14 dating report that the earliest earthen vessel of this period had been made in the eighth or ninth century B.C.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some argue that the Yayoi period should date from a point five centuries earlier, based on a carbon-14 dating report that the earliest earthen vessel of this period had been made in the eighth or ninth century B.C.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some argue that the Yayoi period should date from a point five centuries earlier, based on a carbon-14 dating report that the earliest earthen vessel of this period excavated in Kitakyushu had been made in the eighth or ninth century B.C.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>前代との大きな相違は、日本列島の文化が外来の文化や技術の影響を受けるようになったことであり、稲作農耕と金属器が中国大陸からもたらされ、文化は新たな時代に入った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What differed greatly from the last period was that the Japanese culture became influenced by foreign culture and technology, and the rice growing and the metal artifact, both from China, led the Japanese culture to a new age.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What differed greatly from the previous period was that Japanese culture became influenced by foreign culture and technology, and rice growing and metal artifacts, both from China, led Japanese culture to a new age.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What differed greatly from the previous period was that Japanese culture became influenced by foreign culture and technology, and rice growing and metal artifacts, both from China, led Japanese culture to a new age.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>文明の進化に伴い、支配者と被支配者が分化したのもこの時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also in this period that the ruler and the ruled diverged as the civilization evolved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also in this period that rulers and the ruled diverged as the civilization evolved.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also in this period that rulers and the ruled diverged as the civilization evolved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>日本列島はいまだ先史時代であり、この時代の歴史は同時代の中国の史書によって間接的に知るほかない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan was still in the prehistoric age at that time, so we can but know about the Japanese history of this period indirectly from the contemporary Chinese history book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan was still in the prehistoric age at that time, so we can only know about the Japanese history of this period indirectly from the contemporary Chinese history books.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan was still in the prehistoric age at that time, so we can only know about the Japanese history of this period indirectly from the contemporary Chinese history books.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>この時代の土器は、前時代のものに比して器形も洗練され、装飾も控えめな弥生式土器となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Compared to the last period&apos;s pottery, this period&apos;s (called &quot;Yayoi-shiki doki&quot; [Yayoi pottery]) became sophisticated in shape and moderate in decoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Compared to the previous period&apos;s pottery, this period&apos;s (called &quot;Yayoi-shiki doki&quot; [Yayoi pottery]) became sophisticated in shape and moderate in decoration.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Compared to the previous period&apos;s pottery, this period&apos;s (called &quot;Yayoi-shiki doki&quot; [Yayoi pottery]) became sophisticated in shape and moderate in decoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>1万年以上続いた縄文時代に比して、弥生時代は期間的には数百年にすぎないが、出土品の形式編年から前期・中期・後期に分けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to the Jomon period, which lasted ten millennia and more years, the Yayoi period lasted only several hundred years, and the Yayoi period is classified, according to the style of the excavated articles, into three stages, that is, the early stage, the middle stage, and the late stage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to the Jomon period, which lasted more than ten millennia, the Yayoi period lasted only several hundred years, and the Yayoi period is classified, according to the style of the excavated articles, into three stages, that is, the early stage, the middle stage, and the late stage.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to the Jomon period, which lasted more than ten millennia, the Yayoi period lasted only several hundred years, and the Yayoi period is classified, according to the style of the excavated articles, into three stages, that is, the early stage, the middle stage, and the late stage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="72">
<j>この時代の土器は1874年（明治17年）に帝国大学（現・東京大学）の隣地の向ヶ岡弥生町（現・東京都文京区弥生）から出土した壷形土器が学史的には最初の出土例とされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all earthen vessels of this period, the crock-shaped vessel, excavated in Mukaigaoka-Yayoi-cho (the present Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis) next to the Tokyo Imperial University (today&apos;s Tokyo University), was found for the first time in the history of Japanese archaeology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all earthen vessels of this period, the crock-shaped vessel, excavated in Mukaigaoka-Yayoi-cho (the present Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis) next to Tokyo Imperial University (today&apos;s Tokyo University), was found for the first time in the history of Japanese archeology</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all earthen vessels of this period, the crock-shaped vessel, excavated in Mukaigaoka-Yayoi-cho (the present Yayoi, Bunkyo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis) next to Tokyo Imperial University (today&apos;s Tokyo University) in 1874, was found for the first time in the history of Japanese archeology.</e>
<cmt>年号補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>出土地名をとって「弥生式土器」の名称が定着し、それが時代名ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Yayoi,&quot; which came from the excavation site, took root as the name of the pottery and became the period&apos;s name, too.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Yayoi,&quot; which came from the excavation site, took root as the name of the pottery and became the period&apos;s name, too.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Yayoi,&quot; which came from the excavation site, took root as the name of the pottery and became the period&apos;s name, too.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>弥生式土器は地理的に中国大陸や朝鮮半島に近い北部九州で最初に出現したもので、他の地方でも縄文式土器に代わって製作されるようになり、北海道を除く日本全国に分布している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yayoi pottery was made at first in the northern part of Kyushu region, which is situated near to China and the Korean Peninsula, and then the Yayoi pottery began to replace the Jomon pottery in other regions as well, so the excavation site of the Yayoi pottery ranges nationwide except for Hokkaido Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yayoi pottery was made at first in the northern part of the Kyushu region, which is situated close to China and the Korean Peninsula, and then Yayoi pottery began to replace Jomon pottery in other regions as well, so the excavation site of the Yayoi pottery ranges nationwide except for Hokkaido Island.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yayoi pottery was made at first in the northern part of the Kyushu region, which is situated close to China and the Korean Peninsula, and then Yayoi pottery began to replace Jomon pottery in other regions as well, so the excavation site of the Yayoi pottery ranges nationwide except for Hokkaido Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>縄文式土器に見られた過剰な装飾は影をひそめ、弥生式土器は器形、文様ともに温和で洗練されたものが多く見られるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jomon pottery was sometimes too much decorative, whereas the Yayoi pottery was mostly moderate and sophisticated in both shape and pattern.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jomon pottery was sometimes too decorative, whereas Yayoi pottery was mostly moderate and sophisticated in both shape and pattern.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jomon pottery was sometimes too decorative, whereas Yayoi pottery was mostly moderate and sophisticated in both shape and pattern.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>土器の中には口縁部に人面を表わしたものもあるが、一般にこの時代には具象的な人物表現はまれで、前代に盛んに作られた土偶もこの時代にはほとんど姿を消している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some earthen vessels were engraved with the human face at their rim, but in general, the figurative expression of human is rare during this period, and the earthen figurine enthusiastically made in the former period was almost gone in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some earthen vessels were engraved with a human face on their rim, but in general, the figurative expression of a human is rare during this period, and the earthen figurines enthusiastically made in the former period was almost gone in this period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some earthen vessels were engraved with a human face on their rim, but in general, the figurative expression of a human is rare during this period, and the earthen figurines enthusiastically made in the former period was almost gone in this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>土器以外の出土品としては青銅器、鉄器などの金属器、石製品、骨角製品、貝製品などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides the pottery, there exist other excavated articles as well, such as the metal artifact (the bronzeware, ironware, and others), the stone object, the bone and antler object, and the shell object.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides pottery, there exist other excavated articles as well, such as metal artifacts (bronze ware, ironware, and others), stone objects, bone and antler objects, and shell objects.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides pottery, there exist other excavated articles as well, such as metal artifacts (bronze ware, ironware, and others), stone objects, bone and antler objects, and shell objects.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>青銅器には銅剣、銅鉾、銅戈（どうか）、銅鐸、銅鏡などがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the category of bronzeware, there were bronze sword, bronze pike, bronze dagger-axe, bronze bell, bronze mirror, and so on.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the category of bronze ware, there were bronze swords, bronze pikes, bronze dagger-axes, bronze bells, bronze mirrors, and so on.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the category of bronze ware, there were bronze swords, bronze pikes, bronze dagger-axes, bronze bells, bronze mirrors, and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>このうち、時代を象徴する代表的遺物と目されるのは銅鐸であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all, the most symbolic, typical bronzeware of the period is supposed to be the bronze bell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all, the most symbolic, typical bronze ware of the period is supposed to be the bronze bell.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all, the most symbolic, typical bronze ware of the period is supposed to be the bronze bell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>銅鐸は後世の釣鐘を扁平に圧しつぶしたような器形で、その祖形は朝鮮半島にあったと推定されるが、日本で独自に発達をとげた銅器である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze bell is in the shape of a flattened-out-temple-bell (temple bell itself appeared in later days in Japan), and the bronze bell is supposed to have had its prototype in the Korean Peninsula, but it developed uniquely in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze bell is in the shape of a flattened-out-temple-bell (temple bell itself appeared later in Japan), and the bronze bell is supposed to have had its prototype in the Korean Peninsula, but it developed uniquely in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze bell is in the shape of a flattened-out-temple-bell (temple bell itself appeared later in Japan), and the bronze bell is supposed to have had its prototype in the Korean Peninsula, but it developed uniquely in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>内部に舌（ぜつ）をもつ個体があることから、その原型は打ち鳴らす楽器であったと思われるが、次第に形式化し、祭器となったものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some bronze bells have a reed inside, so the prototype seems to have been a kind of wind instrument, but the bell seems to have gradually lost its use as a musical instrument and to have become an implement for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>・原文の「打ち鳴らす楽器」は打楽器を指しているようにも思えます。しかし、同じく原文にある「舌（reed)」が「管楽器等の発音源となる竹や金属でできた薄片のこと」で、「空気を送り込み振動させて音を出す」（国語辞典）のだとすると、上の表現も「管楽器の一種」という意味ではないかと思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some bronze bells have a reed inside, so the prototype seems to have been a kind of wind instrument, but the bell seems to have gradually lost its use as a musical instrument and to have become an implement for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some bronze bells have a reed inside, so the prototype seems to have been a kind of wind instrument, but the bell seems to have gradually lost its use as a musical instrument and to have become an implement for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>基本的形状はどの個体も同様だが、大きさや表面の装飾にはバラエティがあり、表面に素朴な絵画表現の見られるものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every bell is similar in its basic shape, while the size and the surface decoration varies, and some bells have a simple drawing on the surface.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every bell is similar in its basic shape, while the size and surface decoration varies, and some bells have a simple drawing on the surface.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every bell is similar in its basic shape, while the size and surface decoration varies, and some bells have a simple drawing on the surface.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>製作当初は金色に輝き、所有者の富と威厳を誇示する役割があったものと想像される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bell is imagined to have given off a gold radiance at first, and to have flaunted the owner&apos;s wealth and dignity with the radiance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bell is imagined to have given off a gold radiance at first, and to have flaunted the owner&apos;s wealth and dignity with the radiance.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bell is imagined to have given off a gold radiance at first, and to have flaunted the owner&apos;s wealth and dignity with the radiance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>銅剣等も武器としての本来の用途から離れ、祭器化したものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other bronzeware, including the bronze sword, seems to have lost its original use as a weapon and to have become an implement for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other bronze ware, including the bronze sword, seems to have lost its original use as a weapon and to have become an implement for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other bronze ware, including the bronze sword, seems to have lost its original use as a weapon and to have become an implement for Shinto rituals.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="85">
<j>弥生式土器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yayoi pottery</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yayoi pottery</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yayoi pottery</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>銅鐸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze bell</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze bell</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze bell</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>伝・香川県出土銅鐸（東京国立博物館、国宝）、神戸市桜ヶ丘出土銅鐸（神戸市博物館、国宝）などが著名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist some well-known bronze bells, such as the bronze bell that is said to have been excavated in Kagawa Prefecture - this is owned by Tokyo National Museum, and is designated as the national treasure - and the bronze bell that was excavated in Sakuragaoka, Kobe City - this is owned by Kobe City Museum, and is also designated as the national treasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist some well-known bronze bells, such as the bronze bell that is said to have been excavated in Kagawa Prefecture - this is owned by the Tokyo National Museum, and is designated as a national treasure - and the bronze bell that was excavated in Sakuragaoka, Kobe City - this is owned by the Kobe City Museum, and is also designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist some well-known bronze bells, such as the bronze bell that is said to have been excavated in Kagawa Prefecture - this is owned by the Tokyo National Museum, and is designated as a national treasure - and the bronze bell that was excavated in Sakuragaoka, Kobe City - this is owned by the Kobe City Museum, and is also designated as a national treasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="88">
<j>著名な遺跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Well-known archaeological sites</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Well-known archaeological sites</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Well-known archaeological sites</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>登呂遺跡（静岡県）、唐古遺跡（奈良県）、荒神谷遺跡（島根県）、吉野ヶ里遺跡（佐賀県）など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toro Archaeological Site (in Sizuoka Prefecture), Karako Archaeological Site (in Nara Prefecture), Kojindani Archaeological Site (in Shimane Prefecture), Yoshinogari Archaeological Site (in Saga Prefecture), and so on</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toro Archaeological Site (in Sizuoka Prefecture), Karako Archaeological Site (in Nara Prefecture), Kojindani Archaeological Site (in Shimane Prefecture), Yoshinogari Archaeological Site (in Saga Prefecture), and so on</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toro Archaeological Site (in Shizuoka Prefecture), Karako Archaeological Site (in Nara Prefecture), Kojindani Archaeological Site (in Shimane Prefecture), Yoshinogari Archaeological Site (in Saga Prefecture), and so on</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>古墳時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kofun period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kofun period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kofun period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="91">
<j>おおよそ3世紀後半から6世紀半ば頃までの期間を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Roughly speaking, the Kofun period refers to the time that ranged from the later third century to the middle of the sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Roughly speaking, the Kofun period refers to the time that ranged from the later third century to the middle of the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Roughly speaking, the Kofun period refers to the time that ranged from the later third century to the middle of the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>多数の小国家に分かれていた日本には、この頃から強大な権力をもった王権が成立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan had been divided into small states, but around this period, powerful royal authority was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan had been divided into small states, but around this period, a powerful royal authority was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan had been divided into small states, but around this period, a powerful royal authority was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>この時代を代表する遺物は、時代の名称にもなっている古墳、そのなかでも前方後円墳である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The typical relic of this period is &quot;kofun&quot; (mounded tomb) - the period&apos;s name also comes from this -, particularly &quot;zenpo-koen-fun&quot; (keyhole-shaped mounded tomb).</e>
<cmt>・「古墳」の訳は色々考えられますが、以下基本的には&quot;mounded tomb&quot;で統一しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The typical relic of this period is &quot;kofun&quot; (mounded tomb) - the period&apos;s name also comes from this - particularly &quot;zenpo-koen-fun&quot; (keyhole-shaped mounded tomb).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The typical relic of this period is &quot;kofun&quot; (mounded tomb) - the period&apos;s name also comes from this - particularly &quot;zenpo-koen-fun&quot; (keyhole-shaped mounded tomb).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>すでに弥生時代から西日本を中心に墳丘墓が営まれていたが、3世紀後半頃から大和盆地を中心に前方後円墳と称される日本独特の形式の大規模な墳墓が営まれるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Burial mounds had been already constructed in the Yayoi period mainly in Western Japan, and from around the later third century, what is called zenpo-koen-fun -- a large-scale tomb peculiar to Japan -- began to be constructed mainly in the Yamato Basin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Burial mounds had already been constructed in the Yayoi period mainly in Western Japan, and from around the later third century, what is called zenpo-koen-fun -- a large-scale tomb peculiar to Japan -- began to be constructed mainly in the Yamato Basin.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Burial mounds had already been constructed in the Yayoi period mainly in Western Japan, and from around the later third century, what is called zenpo-koen-fun -- a large-scale tomb peculiar to Japan -- began to be constructed mainly in the Yamato Basin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>奈良県桜井市の箸墓（はしはか）古墳は最初期の古墳と言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hashihaka Mounded Tomb in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, is said to have been the earliest example of kofun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hashihaka Mounded Tomb in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, is said to have been the earliest example of kofun.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hashihaka Mounded Tomb in Sakurai City, Nara Prefecture, is said to have been the earliest example of kofun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>こうした大規模な土木工事が可能になったということは、技術の発達とともに、多くの労働力を使えるだけの権力をもち、広範囲に支配を広げた王権の成立を意味する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fact that such large-scale public works were possible implies the development of the works skills and the establishment of the royal authority which had not only the power to mobilize the large workforce but also the control over the wide-ranging area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that such large-scale public works were possible implies the development of work skills and the establishment of the royal authority which not only had the power to mobilize a large workforce but also the control over a wide-ranging area.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that such large-scale public works were possible implies the development of work skills and the establishment of the royal authority which not only had the power to mobilize a large workforce but also the control over a wide-ranging area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>5世紀には大阪平野を中心にさらに大規模な前方後円墳が営まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the fifth century, some zenpo-koen-fun, much larger than before, were constructed mainly in Osaka Plain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the fifth century, some zenpo-koen-fun, much larger than before, were constructed mainly in the Osaka Plain.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the fifth century, some zenpo-koen-fun, much larger than before, were constructed mainly in the Osaka Plain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>大阪府堺市の大仙古墳（伝・仁徳天皇陵）はその典型的な例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the typical example is Daisen Mounded Tomb in Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture, which is supposed to be the Mausoleum of Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And a typical example is the Daisen Mounded Tomb in Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture, which is supposed to be the Mausoleum of Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And a typical example is the Daisen Mounded Tomb in Sakai City, Osaka Prefecture, which is supposed to be the Mausoleum of Emperor Nintoku.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>古墳は７世紀に入っても築造され、地方によっては8世紀まで造られているが、仏教公伝の年とされる538年頃を境に、それ以後を飛鳥時代、以前を古墳時代と呼んでいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mounded tombs were still constructed in the seventh century - in some local provinces, even until the eighth century -, however, with the year A.D. 538 (around when Buddhism was introduced into Japan, they say) being the boundary, we Japanese call the time before the year the Kofun period, and call the time after the year the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mounded tombs were still constructed in the seventh century - in some local provinces, even until the eighth century - however, with the year 538 (around when Buddhism was introduced into Japan, they say) being the boundary, the period before this year is called the Kofun period, and the time after this is called the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mounded tombs were still constructed in the seventh century - in some local provinces, even until the eighth century - however, with the year 538 (around when Buddhism was introduced into Japan, they say) being the boundary, the period before this year is called the Kofun period, and the time after this is called the Asuka period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="100">
<j>この時代の出土品には馬具、刀装具などの精巧な金属製品があり、その他土器・土製品、石製品、玉類、刀剣などが多く出土する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period&apos;s excavated articles, there are elaborate metal goods, including harness and accouterments, and besides, there are many excavations as well, such as earthen vessels, clay artifacts, stone objects, gems, and swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this period&apos;s excavated articles, there are elaborate metal goods, including harness and accouterments, in addition, there were many other itmes as well, such as earthen vessels, clay artifacts, stone objects, gems, and swords.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period&apos;s excavated articles, there are elaborate metal goods, including harness and accouterments, in addition, there were many other items as well, such as earthen vessels, clay artifacts, stone objects, gems, and swords.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>そのなかで、この時代を特徴づける出土品は埴輪であろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of all, the typical excavated article of this period must be &quot;haniwa.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of all, the most characteristic excavated article of this period must be the &quot;haniwa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of all, the most characteristic excavated article of this period must be the &quot;haniwa.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>埴輪は古墳の墳丘の周囲に立てられた素焼きの土製品で、具象的な形体を表わさない円筒埴輪から始まり、やがて鳥形埴輪が登場、鳥以外の動物埴輪、人物埴輪がこれに続く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Haniwa&quot; is an unglazed clay artifact arranged around the mounded tomb, and at first, non-figurative cylinder haniwa appeared, and before long, bird-shaped haniwa appeared, and then, animal-shaped haniwa -- other than bird-shaped haniwa -- and human-shaped haniwa followed it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Haniwa&quot; is an unglazed clay artifact arranged around the mounded tomb, and at first, non-figurative cylindrical haniwa appeared, and before long, bird-shaped haniwa appeared, and then, animal-shaped haniwa (other than bird-shaped ones), and human-shaped haniwa followed that.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Haniwa&quot; is an unglazed clay artifact arranged around the mounded tomb, and at first, non-figurative cylindrical haniwa appeared, and before long, bird-shaped haniwa appeared, and then, animal-shaped haniwa (other than bird-shaped ones), and human-shaped haniwa followed that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>動物埴輪には犬、猪、牛、鶏、馬具を付けた馬などの出土例があり、人物埴輪には甲冑を付けた武人像、巫女、農民などさまざまな階層や立場の人物が表現されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the category of animal-shaped haniwa, there are the haniwa of dog, white whiskered boar (Japanese wild boar), cow, chicken, horse in harness, and others, and in the category of human-shaped haniwa, there are the haniwa of warrior in armor, sorceress, farmer, and other people of various classes and positions.</e>
<cmt>・日本にいる「猪」は研究社・和英大辞典によれば、&quot;wild boar&quot; ではなく&quot;white whiskered boar&quot; です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the category of animal-shaped haniwa, there are the haniwa of dogs, white whiskered boars (Japanese wild boar), cows, chickens, horses in harnesses, and others, and in the category of human-shaped haniwa, there are the haniwa of warriors in armor, sorceresses, farmers, and other people of various classes and positions.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the category of animal-shaped haniwa, there are the haniwa of dogs, white whiskered boars (Japanese wild boar), cows, chickens, horses in harnesses, and others, and in the category of human-shaped haniwa, there are the haniwa of warriors in armor, sorceresses, farmers, and other people of various classes and positions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>これらは、製法上の制約から、形体は単純で、人物の顔貌表現は横長の穴を開けることによって両眼と口を表現したものがほとんどである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The limitation on the manufacturing process made these haniwas&apos; shape simple, and the face (eyes and a mouth) of the human-shaped haniwa was mostly depicted by making three horizontal slits.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The limitation on the manufacturing process made the shape of these haniwa simple, and the face (eyes and a mouth) of the human-shaped haniwa was mostly depicted by making three horizontal slits.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The limitation on the manufacturing process made the shape of these haniwa simple, and the face (eyes and a mouth) of the human-shaped haniwa was mostly depicted by making three horizontal slits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>素朴な表現と単純な技法ながら、人物の表情を巧みにとらえ、芸術的に高く評価される作品が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The works are simple in their expression and skill, but nevertheless, they captured people&apos;s facial expressions in a dexterous way, so many of them are highly evaluated as art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The works are simple in their expression and skill, but nevertheless, they captured people&apos;s facial expressions in a dexterous way, so many of them are highly evaluated as art.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The works are simple in their expression and skill, but nevertheless, they captured people&apos;s facial expressions in a dexterous way, so many of them are highly evaluated as art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>武人埴輪の中には、当時の刀剣や甲冑を忠実に表現した入念作もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some haniwa of the warrior in armor are elaborate works, in which the sword and armor at that time were depicted faithfully.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some haniwa of warriors in armor are elaborate works, in which the sword and armor at that time were depicted faithfully.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some haniwa of warriors in armor are elaborate works, in which the sword and armor at that time were depicted faithfully.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>埴輪は、当時の人々の服装、髪型、化粧など生活の実態を具体的に知ることのできる視覚情報を提供してくれるという点でも、学術的に貴重な資料である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haniwa is academically precious, partly because it provides us with the visual information, from which we can know vividly about people&apos;s daily life in those days, such as clothes, hairstyle, and makeup.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haniwa is academically precious, partly because it provides us with visual information, from which we can know vividly about people&apos;s daily life in those days, such as clothes, hairstyle, and makeup.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haniwa is academically precious, partly because it provides us with visual information, from which we can know vividly about people&apos;s daily life in those days, such as clothes, hairstyle, and makeup.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="108">
<j>埴輪</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haniwa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haniwa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haniwa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>武装男子埴輪（群馬県太田市出土、国宝）、「踊る男女の埴輪」（埼玉県出土）などが著名。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist some well-known haniwa, such as Man In Armor Haniwa (excavated in Ota City, Gunma Prefecture, and designated as the national treasure), and Haniwa Of Dancing Man and Woman (excavated in Saitama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist some well-known haniwa, such as the Man In Armor Haniwa (excavated in Ota City, Gunma Prefecture, and designated as a national treasure), and the Haniwa Of the Dancing Man and Woman (excavated in Saitama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist some well-known haniwa, such as the Man In Armor Haniwa (excavated in Ota City, Gunma Prefecture, and designated as a national treasure), and the Haniwa of the Dancing Man and Woman (excavated in Saitama Prefecture).</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="110">
<j>古墳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mounded tomb</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mounded tomb</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mounded tomb</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>前方後円墳</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zenpo-koen-fun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zenpo-koen-fun</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenpo-koen-fun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>大仙古墳（伝・仁徳天皇陵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daisen Mounded Tomb : supposed to be the Mausoleum of Emperor Nintoku</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daisen Mounded Tomb : supposed to be the Mausoleum of Emperor Nintoku</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daisen Mounded Tomb: supposed to be the Mausoleum of Emperor Nintoku</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="113">
<j>古代・中古</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient and medieval ages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient and medieval ages</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient and medieval ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>飛鳥時代（飛鳥文化）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asuka period (Asuka culture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asuka period (Asuka culture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asuka period (Asuka culture)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="115">
<j>美術史上の飛鳥時代は、6世紀半ば、日本へ仏教が公式に伝来した時期から、7世紀後半の天智天皇の治世あたりまでを指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the Asuka period ranged from the middle of the sixth century, when Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan, to the later seventh century, around when Japan was under the Emperor Tenchi&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the perspective of art history, the Asuka period ranged from the middle of the sixth century, when Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan, to the later seventh century, around when Japan was under the Emperor Tenchi&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the Asuka period ranged from the middle of the sixth century, when Buddhism was officially introduced into Japan, to the later seventh century, around when Japan was under the Emperor Tenchi&apos;s reign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>この時代に入っても古墳の造営は引き続き行われているが、一応、仏教公伝の時期をもって古墳時代と区切っている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mounded tombs were continued to be constructed in this period, but anyway, we Japanese put an end to the Kofun period with the official introduction of Buddhism into Japan being the boundary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mounded tombs continued to be constructed in this period, but the Kofun period ended with the official introduction of Buddhism into Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mounded tombs continued to be constructed in this period, but the Kofun period ended with the official introduction of Buddhism into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>飛鳥時代の終期については、政治史上の区分では710年の平城遷都の年とするのが通常である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the perspective of political history, the Asuka period is commonly said to have ended in A.D. 710 (the year of national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the perspective of political history, the Asuka period is commonly said to have ended in A.D. 710 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the perspective of political history, the Asuka period is commonly said to have ended in A.D. 710 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>美術史上の区分でも710年までを飛鳥時代とする場合もあるが、法隆寺が火災で炎上した（『日本書紀』による）670年、ないし天武天皇即位の673年あたりを始期として、以後平城遷都までの期間は「白鳳時代」または「奈良時代前期」として別の時代と見るのが通例となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even from the perspective of art history, the period until A.D. 710 is occasionally deemed the Asuka period, but commonly, the period until 710 from 670 (the year &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan] says Horyu-ji Temple burned down) -- or from around 673 (the year Emperor Tenmu ascended to the throne) -- is deemed another period (called the Hakuho period, or the Nara period&apos;s former half).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even from the perspective of art history, the period until 710 is occasionally deemed the Asuka period, but commonly, the period until 710 from 670 (the year &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; [Chronicles of Japan] says Horyu-ji Temple burned down) -- or from around 673 (the year Emperor Tenmu ascended to the throne) -- is deemed another period (called the Hakuho period, or the Nara period&apos;s earlier half).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even from the perspective of art history, the period until 710 is occasionally deemed the Asuka period, but commonly, the period until 710 from 670 (the year &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) says Horyu-ji Temple burned down) -- or from around 673 (the year Emperor Tenmu ascended to the throne) -- is deemed another period (called the Hakuho period, or the Nara period&apos;s earlier half).</e>
<cmt>カッコ修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="119">
<j>この時代は、日本が初めて外来の宗教である仏教を受け入れ、その後の文化の下地をつくったという点で重要な時期である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period is significant, because Japan then accepted Buddhism - the first religion from abroad - and by that means laid the foundation of its culture after that.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This period is significant, because Japan accepted Buddhism then - the first religion from abroad - and by that means laid the foundation of its culture after that.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This period is significant, because Japan accepted Buddhism then - the first religion from abroad - and by that means laid the foundation of its culture after that.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>仏教が百済経由で日本へ公式にもたらされた（仏教公伝）時期については、公式の史書である『日本書紀』には552年、『上宮聖徳法王帝説』や『元興寺縁起』には538年とあるが、今日では後者の538年を仏教公伝の年とするのが定説である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The exact year of official introduction of Buddhism via Paekche (an ancient Korean kingdom) into Japan is argued between the A.D. 552-theory (backed up by the official Japanese history book Nihonshoki) and the A.D. 538-theory (backed up by &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; [Biography of Prince Shotoku] and &quot;Gango-ji Engi&quot; [History of the Gango-ji Temple]), and today, the established theory is the latter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The exact year of official introduction of Buddhism via Paekche (an ancient Korean kingdom) into Japan is argued between the A.D. 552-theory (backed up by the official Japanese history book Nihonshoki) and the A.D. 538-theory (backed up by &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; [Biography of Prince Shotoku] and &quot;Gango-ji Engi&quot; [History of the Gango-ji Temple]), and today, the established theory is the latter.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The exact year of official introduction of Buddhism via Paekche (an ancient Korean kingdom) into Japan is argued between the A.D. 552-theory (backed up by the official Japanese history book Nihonshoki) and the A.D. 538-theory (backed up by &quot;Jogu Shotoku Hooteisetsu&quot; (Biography of Prince Shotoku) and &quot;Gango-ji Engi&quot; (History of the Gango-ji Temple)), and today, the established theory is the latter.</e>
<cmt>カッコ修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>仏教の受容をめぐっては有力氏族である蘇我氏（崇仏派）と物部氏（排仏派）の間に対立があり、ついには武力抗争に突入するが、結果は崇仏派の蘇我氏が勝利した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Over the introduction of Buddhism, a conflict between the two influential clans, the Soga clan (pro-Buddhist) and the Mononobe clan (anti-Buddhist), escalated into an armed struggle, and it ended in the pro-Buddhist Soga clan&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Over the introduction of Buddhism, a conflict between the two influential clans, the Soga clan (pro-Buddhist) and the Mononobe clan (anti-Buddhist), escalated into an armed struggle, and it ended in the pro-Buddhist Soga clan&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Over the introduction of Buddhism, a conflict between the two influential clans, the Soga clan (pro-Buddhist) and the Mononobe clan (anti-Buddhist), escalated into an armed struggle, and it ended in the pro-Buddhist Soga clan&apos;s victory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>6世紀末には日本最初の本格的仏教寺院である法興寺（飛鳥寺）の建設が蘇我氏によって始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end of the sixth century, the Soga clan started to construct Hoko-ji Temple (or called Asuka-dera Temple), which was the first full-scale Buddhist Temple in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end of the sixth century, the Soga clan started to construct Hoko-ji Temple (also called Asuka-dera Temple), which was the first full-scale Buddhist Temple in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end of the sixth century, the Soga clan started to construct Hoko-ji Temple (also called Asuka-dera Temple), which was the first full-scale Buddhist Temple in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="123">
<j>用明天皇の皇子である厩戸皇子（聖徳太子の名で広く知られる）は、仏教に深く帰依し、6世紀末に四天王寺、7世紀初めに法隆寺を建立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Yomei&apos;s son Prince Umayado, commonly known as Prince Shotoku, became a devout believer in Buddhism, so he constructed Shitenno-ji Temple in the end of the sixth century, and Horyu-ji Temple in the early seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Yomei&apos;s son Prince Umayado, commonly known as Prince Shotoku, became a devout believer in Buddhism, so he constructed Shitenno-ji Temple in the end of the sixth century, and Horyu-ji Temple in the early seventh century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Yomei&apos;s son Prince Umayado, commonly known as Prince Shotoku, became a devout believer in Buddhism, so he constructed Shitenno-ji Temple in the end of the sixth century, and Horyu-ji Temple in the early seventh century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>聖徳太子は日本における仏教興隆の祖として神格化され、日本の仏教寺院では宗派を問わず崇拝の対象となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Shotoku is now deified as the person who laid the foundation of the development of Buddhism in Japan, so he is worshipped in every Buddhist temple in Japan regardless of its sect and school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Shotoku is now deified as the person who laid the foundation of the development of Buddhism in Japan, so he is worshiped in every Buddhist temple in Japan regardless of its sect and school.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Shotoku is now deified as the person who laid the foundation of the development of Buddhism in Japan, so he is worshiped in every Buddhist temple in Japan regardless of its sect and school.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>法隆寺の西院伽藍は現存する世界最古の木造建築として著名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Saiin Garan&quot; (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple is famous as the oldest wooden construction of all existent in the world.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Saiin Garan&quot; (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple is famous as the oldest wooden construction of all existing in the world.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiin Garan (Western Precinct) of Horyu-ji Temple is famous as the oldest wooden construction of all existing in the world.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="126">
<j>だが、『日本書紀』によれば、法隆寺は670年に一度焼亡しており、現存する同寺の伽藍はその後（7世紀末頃）の再建であることは発掘調査の結果等からも定説となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to Nihonshoki, Horyu-ji Temple burned down in A.D. 670 and the existent Saiin Garan was reconstructed later (around the end of the seventh century), and this depiction is now widely accepted, partly because the excavation and research proved the truth of the depiction.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to Nihonshoki, Horyu-ji Temple burned down in A.D. 670 and the existing Saiin Garan was reconstructed later (around the end of the seventh century), and this depiction is now widely accepted, partly because the excavation and research proved the truth of the depiction.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to Nihonshoki, Horyu-ji Temple burned down in A.D. 670 and the existing Saiin Garan was reconstructed later (around the end of the seventh century), and this depiction is now widely accepted, partly because the excavation and research proved the truth of the depiction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="127">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>・具体的彫刻名につき、下記HPを参照しています。（その左上の検索欄に「釈迦三尊像」等と入力すると、関連するHPが幾つか出てきます。以下、仏教美術関係については全て下記HPを参照しています。）[http://www.onmarkproductions.com/html/terminology.shtml]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>銅造釈迦三尊像（法隆寺金堂、止利作）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze Shaka triad statue : enshrined in &quot;Kondo&quot; (Main Hall) of Horyu-ji Temple, and made by Tori Busshi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze Shaka triad statue : enshrined in the &quot;Kondo&quot; (Main Hall) of Horyu-ji Temple, and made by Tori Busshi</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze Shaka triad statue: enshrined in the Kondo (Main Hall) of Horyu-ji Temple, and made by Tori Busshi</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="129">
<j>木造観音菩薩立像（法隆寺、百済観音）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of &quot;Kannon Bosatsu&quot; (the Budhisattva of Mercy) : enshrined at Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; (Paekche Kannon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden standing statue of &quot;Kannon Bosatsu&quot; (the Budhisattva of Mercy) : enshrined at Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; (Paekche Kannon)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu (the Budhisattva of Mercy): enshrined at Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Kudara Kannon&quot; (Paekche Kannon)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>木造観音菩薩立像（法隆寺夢殿、救世観音）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu : enshrined in &quot;Yumedono&quot; (literally, Hall of Dreams) of Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Guze Kannon&quot; (literally, Salvation Kannon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu : enshrined in &quot;Yumedono&quot; (literally, Hall of Dreams) of Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Guze Kannon&quot; (literally, Salvation Kannon)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu: enshrined in Yumedono (literally, Hall of Dreams) of Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Guze Kannon&quot; (literally, Salvation Kannon)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>木造弥勒菩薩半跏思惟像（広隆寺、半島からの渡来像とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden &quot;hanka shiyuizo&quot; (seated statue half-inclined in meditation) of &quot;Miroku Bosatsu&quot; (the Bodhisattva of the Present) : enshrined in Koryu-ji Temple, and - some people say - introduced from Korean Peninsula</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden &quot;hanka shiyuizo&quot; (seated statue half-inclined in meditation) of &quot;Miroku Bosatsu&quot; (the Bodhisattva of the Present) : enshrined in Koryu-ji Temple, and - some people say - introduced from the Korean Peninsula</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden hanka shiyuizo (seated statue half-inclined in meditation) of Miroku Bosatsu (the Bodhisattva of the Present): enshrined in Koryu-ji Temple, and - some people say - introduced from the Korean Peninsula</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="133">
<j>玉虫厨子（法隆寺）、天寿国繍帳（中宮寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tamamushi no zushi&quot; (The Beetle Wing Shrine) owned by Horyu-ji Temple/&quot;Tenjukoku-shucho&quot; (Embroidery of Long Life in Heaven) owned by Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Tamamushi no zushi&quot; (The Beetle Wing Shrine) owned by Horyu-ji Temple/&quot;Tenjukoku-shucho&quot; (Embroidery of Long Life in Heaven) owned by Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamamushi no zushi (The Beetle Wing Shrine) owned by Horyu-ji Temple/Tenjukoku-shucho (Embroidery of Long Life in Heaven) owned by Chugu-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>当代の遺品なし（法隆寺西院伽藍は飛鳥時代様式だが7世紀後半の再建）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nonexistent : Saiin Garan of Horyu-ji Temple has the style of the Asuka period, but it was reconstructed in the later seventh century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nonexistent : Saiin Garan of Horyu-ji Temple has the style of the Asuka period, but it was reconstructed in the later seventh century.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nonexistent: Saiin Garan of Horyu-ji Temple has the style of the Asuka period, but it was reconstructed in the later seventh century.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="136">
<j>奈良時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nara period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nara period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nara period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="137">
<j>美術史上の区分では、法隆寺が焼亡した670年、ないし天武天皇即位の年である673年から、794年の平安遷都までを奈良時代とすることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the Nara period is commonly thought to have ranged from A.D. 670 (the year Horyu-ji Temple burned down) - or from A.D. 673 (the year Emperor Tenmu ascended to the throne) - to A.D. 794 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heian-kyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the perspective of art history, the Nara period is commonly thought to have ranged from A.D. 670 (the year Horyu-ji Temple burned down) - or from A.D. 673 (the year Emperor Tenmu ascended to the throne) - to A.D. 794 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heian-kyo).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the Nara period is commonly thought to have ranged from A.D. 670 (the year Horyu-ji Temple burned down) - or from A.D. 673 (the year Emperor Tenmu ascended to the throne) - to A.D. 794 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heian-kyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>この場合、平城遷都の710年を境として、それ以前を奈良時代前期（または白鳳時代）、以後を奈良時代後期（または天平時代）と称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Provided we follow this theory, the time before A.D. 710 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo) is called the Nara period&apos;s former half (or the Hakuho period), and the time after the year is called the Nara period&apos;s latter half (or the Tenpyo period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Provided we follow this theory, the time before A.D. 710 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo) is called the Nara period&apos;s earlier half (or the Hakuho period), and the time after then is called the Nara period&apos;s latter half (or the Tenpyo period).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Provided we follow this theory, the time before A.D. 710 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo) is called the Nara period&apos;s earlier half (or the Hakuho period), and the time after then is called the Nara period&apos;s latter half (or the Tenpyo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>時代の終期については、長岡遷都の年である784年とする見方もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people say this period ended in A.D. 784 (the year of the national capital transfer to Nagaoka-kyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some people say this period ended in A.D. 784 (the year of the national capital transfer to Nagaoka-kyo).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some people say this period ended in A.D. 784 (the year of the national capital transfer to Nagaoka-kyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="140">
<j>710年の平城遷都に際し、当時飛鳥にあった法興寺（元興寺）、大官大寺（大安寺）、薬師寺、厩坂寺（興福寺）などの寺院はこぞって新京へ移転した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the occasion of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo in 710, the temples located in Asuka, such as Hoko-ji Temple (also called Gango-ji Temple), Daikandai-ji Temple (also called Daian-ji Temple), Yakushi-ji Temple, and Umaya-zaka-dera Temple, all together transferred to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the occasion of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo in 710, the temples located in Asuka, such as Hoko-ji Temple (also called Gango-ji Temple), Daikandai-ji Temple (also called Daian-ji Temple), Yakushi-ji Temple, and Umaya-zaka-dera Temple, all together transferred to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the occasion of the national capital transfer to Heijo-kyo in 710, the temples located in Asuka, such as Hoko-ji Temple (also called Gango-ji Temple), Daikandai-ji Temple (also called Daian-ji Temple), Yakushi-ji Temple, and Umaya-zaka-dera Temple (also called Kofuku-ji Temple), all together transferred to Heijo-kyo.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>また、新京には東大寺、西大寺 (奈良市)、唐招提寺などが新たに建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in Heijo-kyo, some temples, such as Todai-ji Temple, Saidai-ji Temple, and Toshodai-ji Temple, were newly constructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in Heijo-kyo, some temples, such as Todai-ji Temple, Saidai-ji Temple, and Toshodai-ji Temple, were newly constructed.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in Heijo-kyo, some temples, such as Todai-ji Temple, Saidai-ji Temple, and Toshodai-ji Temple, were newly constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>時の政権は仏教を厚く保護し、寺院の造営、仏像の造立、経典の書写などは国家の事業として実施された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The regime at that time protected Buddhism substantially, and implemented the Buddhism-related work, such as construction of temples, making Buddhist statues, and transcription of sutras, as the national project.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The regime at that time protected Buddhism substantially, and implemented the Buddhism-related work, such as construction of temples, making Buddhist statues, and transcription of sutras, as a national project.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The regime at that time protected Buddhism substantially, and implemented the Buddhism-related work, such as construction of temples, making Buddhist statues, and transcription of sutras, as a national project.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>中でも聖武天皇は仏教に深く帰依し、東大寺に大仏を造立し、また各国に国分寺・国分尼寺を建立することを命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, Emperor Shomu became a devout believer in Buddhism, so he ordered to construct the Great Buddha in Todai-ji Temple, and to construct provincial monasteries and nunneries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, Emperor Shomu became a devout believer in Buddhism, so he ordered to construct the Great Buddha in Todai-ji Temple, and construction of provincial monasteries and nunneries.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, Emperor Shomu became a devout believer in Buddhism, so he ordered to construct the Great Buddha in Todai-ji Temple, and construction of provincial monasteries and nunneries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>平城京に都があった時代の文化は、年号から「天平文化」と呼ばれ、国際色豊かな仏教文化が栄えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The culture of this period, whose national capital was Heijo-kyo, was called Tenpyo culture after the imperial era, and it saw the prosperity of Buddhist culture with a highly cosmopolitan character.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The culture of this period, whose national capital was Heijo-kyo, was called Tenpyo culture after the imperial era, and it saw the prosperity of Buddhist culture with a highly cosmopolitan character.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The culture of this period, whose national capital was Heijo-kyo, was called Tenpyo culture after the imperial era, and it saw the prosperity of Buddhist culture with a highly cosmopolitan character.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>東大寺の倉庫であった正倉院の宝物は聖武天皇の遺愛品を中心とする8世紀美術の宝庫で、日本製品とともに唐からの舶載品を数多く所蔵する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoso-in Treasure Repository (formerly, the storehouse affiliated to Todai-ji Temple) is literally the treasury of the eighth century&apos;s art - this art is mainly occupied with the articles tresured by the late Emperor Shomu -, so Shoso-in owns many goods from Tang-dynasty China as well as Japanese goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoso-in Treasure Repository (formerly, the storehouse affiliated to Todai-ji Temple) is literally the treasury of the eighth century&apos;s art - this art is mainly occupied with the articles treasured by the late Emperor Shomu - so Shoso-in owns many goods from Tang-dynasty China as well as Japanese goods.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoso-in Treasure Repository (formerly, the storehouse affiliated to Todai-ji Temple) is literally the treasury of the eighth century&apos;s art - this art is mainly occupied with the articles treasured by the late Emperor Shomu - so Shoso-in owns many goods from Tang-dynasty China as well as Japanese goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>天平時代は華やかな時代というイメージがあるが、一方で天災、凶作、権力者同士の抗争などが相次ぐ不安定な時代でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Tenpyo period has the image of the flourishing period, but it was also the period of uncertainty, when many troubles, such as natural calamities, crop failures, and conflicts between influential court nobles, happened one after another.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Tenpyo period has the image of a flourishing period, but it was also the period of uncertainty, when many troubles, such as natural calamities, crop failures, and conflicts between influential court nobles, happened one after another.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Tenpyo period has the image of a flourishing period, but it was also the period of uncertainty, when many troubles, such as natural calamities, crop failures, and conflicts between influential court nobles, happened one after another.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="147">
<j>白鳳文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hakuho culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hakuho culture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hakuho culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>法隆寺金堂壁画（1949年焼損）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Wall Paintings in Horyu-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo (burnt down in 1949)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Wall Paintings in Horyu-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo (burnt down in 1949)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Wall Paintings in Horyu-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo (burnt down in 1949)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>銅造聖観音立像（薬師寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze standing statue of &quot;Sho-Kannon&quot; (another name for &quot;Guze Kannon&quot;) : enshrined in Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze standing statue of &quot;Sho-Kannon&quot; (another name for &quot;Guze Kannon&quot;) : enshrined in Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze standing statue of Sho-Kannon (another name for Guze Kannon): enshrined in Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>銅造観音菩薩立像（法隆寺、夢違観音像）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu : enshrined in Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Yume-Chigai Kannon&quot; (literally, Dream-Changing Kannon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu : enshrined in Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Yume-Chigai Kannon&quot; (literally, Dream-Changing Kannon)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze standing statue of Kannon Bosatsu: enshrined in Horyu-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Yume-Chigai Kannon&quot; (literally, Dream-Changing Kannon)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>弥勒仏坐像（当麻寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sitting statue of &quot;Miroku Butsu&quot; (literally, Future Buddha) : enshrined in Taima-dera Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The sitting statue of &quot;Miroku Butsu&quot; (literally, Future Buddha) : enshrined in Taima-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The sitting statue of Miroku Butsu (literally, Future Buddha): enshrined in Taima-dera Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>銅造仏頭（興福寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bronze Head of Buddha : enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bronze Head of Buddha : enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bronze Head of Buddha: enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>銅造釈迦如来倚像（深大寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze &quot;izo&quot; (statue that is seated on a stool or pedestal usually with both legs pendent) of &quot;Shaka Nyorai&quot; (the Historical Buddha) : enshrined in Jindai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze &quot;izo&quot; (statue that is seated on a stool or pedestal usually with both legs pendent) of &quot;Shaka Nyorai&quot; (the Historical Buddha) : enshrined in Jindai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze izo (statue that is seated on a stool or pedestal usually with both legs pendent) of Shaka Nyorai (the Historical Buddha): enshrined in Jindai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>銅造釈迦如来坐像（蟹満寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bronze seated statue of Shaka Nyorai : enshrined in Kaniman-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bronze seated statue of Shaka Nyorai : enshrined in Kaniman-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bronze seated statue of Shaka Nyorai: enshrined in Kaniman-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>木造菩薩半跏像（中宮寺、伝・如意輪観音）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden &quot;Bosatsu hankazo&quot; (seated statue of Bodhisattva half-inclined in meditation) : This is enshrined in Chugu-ji Temple, and the temple says it is &quot;Nyoirin Kannon&quot; (Omnipotent God [or Goddess] of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>原文にある「伝」とは「寺の言い伝えるところでは」の意味です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden &quot;Bosatsu hankazo&quot; (seated statue of Bodhisattva half-inclined in meditation) : This is enshrined in Chugu-ji Temple, and the temple says it is &quot;Nyoirin Kannon&quot; (Omnipotent God [or Goddess] of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden Bosatsu hankazo (seated statue of Bodhisattva half-inclined in meditation): This is enshrined in Chugu-ji Temple, and the temple says it is &quot;Nyoirin Kannon&quot; (Omnipotent God (or Goddess) of Mercy).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>法隆寺西院伽藍、法起寺三重塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saiin Garan of Horyu-ji Temple/Three-storey Pagoda of Hokki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saiin Garan of Horyu-ji Temple/Three-story Pagoda of Hokki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saiin Garan of Horyu-ji Temple/Three-story Pagoda of Hokki-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="160">
<j>天平文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpyo culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenpyo culture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpyo culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>絵因果経（東京芸術大学、上品蓮台寺、醍醐寺、出光美術館ほか）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;E Ingakyo&quot; (Illustrated Sutra of Cause and Effect) : owned by each of some institutions, such as Tokyo University of Arts, Jobonrendai-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, and Idemitsu Museum of Arts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;E Ingakyo&quot; (Illustrated Sutra of Cause and Effect) : owned by some institutions, such as the Tokyo University of Arts, Jobonrendai-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, and Idemitsu Museum of Arts</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">E Ingakyo (Illustrated Sutra of Cause and Effect): owned by some institutions, such as the Tokyo University of Arts, Jobonrendai-ji Temple, Daigo-ji Temple, and Idemitsu Museum of Arts</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>吉祥天像（薬師寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of &quot;Kisshoten&quot; (Goddess of Beauty, Luck, Prosperity, and Merit) : owned by Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of &quot;Kisshoten&quot; (Goddess of Beauty, Luck, Prosperity, and Merit) : owned by Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Kisshoten (Goddess of Beauty, Luck, Prosperity, and Merit): owned by Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>聖徳太子像（御物）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of Prince Shotoku : imperial property</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of Prince Shotoku : imperial property</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Prince Shotoku: imperial property</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>盧舎那仏像（東大寺、奈良の大仏）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of &quot;Rushanabutsu&quot; (Deity Coming From The Sun) : enshrined in Todai-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Nara no Daibutsu&quot; (Great Buddha in Nara)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of &quot;Rushanabutsu&quot; (Deity Coming From The Sun) : enshrined in Todai-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Nara no Daibutsu&quot; (Great Buddha in Nara)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of Rushanabutsu (Deity Coming From The Sun): enshrined in Todai-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Nara no Daibutsu&quot; (Great Buddha in Nara)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>乾漆八部衆像（興福寺、8体のうち阿修羅が著名）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dry lacquer statues of Eight Guardians : enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple, and the statue of &quot;Ashura&quot; (Bellicose Demon) is most famous of the eight</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dry lacquer statues of Eight Guardians : enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple, and the statue of &quot;Ashura&quot; (Bellicose Demon) is most famous of the eight</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dry lacquer statues of Eight Guardians: enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple, and the statue of Ashura (Bellicose Demon) is most famous of the eight</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>乾漆十大弟子像（興福寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dry lacquer statues of Ten Great Disciples : enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dry lacquer statues of Ten Great Disciples : enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dry lacquer statues of Ten Great Disciples: enshrined in Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>乾漆不空羂索観音立像、塑造日光・月光菩薩立像ほか東大寺法華堂（三月堂）・戒壇院諸仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Todai-ji Temple&apos;s statues enshrined in its Hokke-do Hall (also called Sangatsu-do Hall) and Kaidan-in Hall : the dry lacquer standing statue of &quot;Fukukenjaku Kannon&quot; (literally, Never-Empty Lasso Kannon), the standing statue of &quot;Nikko Bosatsu&quot; (Sunlight Bodhisattva), the standing statue of &quot;Gakko Bosatsu&quot; (Moonlight Bodhisattva), and so on</e>
<cmt>・やや長いので、コロンで区切りました（具体的な仏像名をコロンの後に紹介しています。）</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Todai-ji Temple&apos;s statues enshrined in its Hokke-do Hall (also called Sangatsu-do Hall) and Kaidan-in Hall : the dry lacquer standing statue of &quot;Fukukenjaku Kannon&quot; (literally, Never-Empty Lasso Kannon), the standing statue of &quot;Nikko Bosatsu&quot; (Sunlight Bodhisattva), the standing statue of &quot;Gakko Bosatsu&quot; (Moonlight Bodhisattva), and so on</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Todai-ji Temple&apos;s statues enshrined in its Hokke-do Hall (also called Sangatsu-do Hall) and Kaidan-in Hall: the dry lacquer standing statue of Fukukenjaku Kannon (literally, Never-Empty Lasso Kannon), the standing statue of Nikko Bosatsu (Sunlight Bodhisattva), the standing statue of Gakko Bosatsu (Moonlight Bodhisattva), and so on</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>唐招提寺金堂・講堂諸仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Toshodai-ji Temple&apos;s statues enshrined in its Kondo and &quot;Kodo&quot; (Lecture Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Toshodai-ji Temple&apos;s statues enshrined in its Kondo and &quot;Kodo&quot; (Lecture Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Toshodai-ji Temple&apos;s statues enshrined in its Kondo and Kodo (Lecture Hall)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>乾漆鑑真和上坐像（唐招提寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dry lacquer seated statue of the Buddhist Master &quot;Ganjin&quot; (in Chinese pinyin, Jianzhen) : enshrined in Toshodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dry lacquer seated statue of the Buddhist Master &quot;Ganjin&quot; (in Chinese pinyin, Jianzhen) : enshrined in Toshodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dry lacquer seated statue of the Buddhist Master Ganjin (in Chinese pinyin, Jianzhen): enshrined in Toshodai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="172">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>正倉院宝物（金工、漆工、楽器、染織、三彩陶器、刀剣など各種。渡来品を多く含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The treasure stored in Shoso-in Treasure Repository : There exist various kinds of treasure, including the articles from abroad, such as metal works, lacquer works, musical instruments, dyeing and weaving works, three-color-glazed earthen vessels, and swords.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The treasure stored in Shoso-in Treasure Repository : There exist various kinds of treasure, including the articles from abroad, such as metal works, lacquer works, musical instruments, dyeing and weaving works, three-color-glazed earthen vessels, and swords.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The treasure stored in Shoso-in Treasure Repository: There exist various kinds of treasure, including the articles from abroad, such as metal works, lacquer works, musical instruments, dyeing and weaving works, three-color-glazed earthen vessels, and swords.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="174">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>東大寺法華堂（三月堂）、正倉院宝庫</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokke-do Hall (also called Sangatsu-do Hall) in Todai-ji Temple/the treasury of Shoso-in Treasure Repository</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokke-do Hall (also called Sangatsu-do Hall) in Todai-ji Temple/the treasury of Shoso-in Treasure Repository</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokke-do Hall (also called Sangatsu-do Hall) in Todai-ji Temple/the treasury of Shoso-in Treasure Repository</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="176">
<j>唐招提寺金堂、講堂、経蔵、宝蔵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshodai-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo, Kodo, &quot;Kyozo&quot; (Sutra Repository), and &quot;Hozo&quot; (Treasure House)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshodai-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo, Kodo, &quot;Kyozo&quot; (Sutra Repository), and &quot;Hozo&quot; (Treasure House)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshodai-ji Temple&apos;s Kondo, Kodo, Kyozo (Sutra Repository), and Hozo (Treasure House)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="177">
<j>平安時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="178">
<j>平安遷都の794年から1185年頃まで、9世紀から12世紀に至る約4世紀にわたる時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heian period ranged over about four centuries from A.D. 794 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heian-kyo) to around A.D. 1185.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Heian period ranged over about four centuries from A.D. 794 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heian-kyo) to around A.D. 1185.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Heian period ranged over about four centuries from A.D. 794 (the year of the national capital transfer to Heian-kyo) to around A.D. 1185.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="179">
<j>美術史では、遣唐使が廃止された894年あたりを境にして、以前を平安時代前期、以後を平安時代後期（藤原時代）と呼ぶことが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Commonly, from the perspective of art history, the term until around A.D. 894 (the year that the dispatch of the Japanese envoy to Tang-dynasty China was ended) is called the Heian period&apos;s former half, and the term after the year is called the Heian period&apos;s latter half (or the Fujiwara period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Commonly, from the perspective of art history, the term until around A.D. 894 (the year that the dispatch of the Japanese envoy to Tang-dynasty China was ended) is called the Heian period&apos;s former half, and the term after the year is called the Heian period&apos;s latter half (or the Fujiwara period).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Commonly, from the perspective of art history, the term until around A.D. 894 (the year that the dispatch of the Japanese envoy to Tang-dynasty China was ended) is called the Heian period&apos;s former half, and the term after the year is called the Heian period&apos;s latter half (or the Fujiwara period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="180">
<j>特に彫刻史の方面では平安時代前期を貞観（じょうがん）時代または弘仁時代と呼ぶこともあったが、特定の元号で平安時代前期を代表させることにはあまり意味がないことから、今日ではこれらの呼称はあまり用いられていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially from the perspective of sculpture art history, the Heian period&apos;s former half was occasionally called the Jogan period (or the Konin period), but it does not make sense to use these specific imperial eras&apos; names (Jogan and Konin) as the symbol of the Heian period&apos;s former half, so today these names are not used so often.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Especially from the perspective of sculpture art history, the Heian period&apos;s former half was occasionally called the Jogan period (or the Konin period), but it does not make sense to use these specific imperial eras&apos; names (Jogan and Konin) as the symbol of the Heian period&apos;s former half, so today these names are not used so often.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Especially from the perspective of sculpture art history, the Heian period&apos;s former half was occasionally called the Jogan period (or the Konin period), but it does not make sense to use these specific imperial eras&apos; names (Jogan and Konin) as the symbol of the Heian period&apos;s former half, so today these names are not used so often.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="181">
<j>平安時代前期には空海、最澄が相次いで唐に渡航し、密教が日本に伝えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period&apos;s former half, Priest Kukai and Saicho went to Tang-dynasty China one after another, and they brought back Esoteric Buddhism into Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period&apos;s former half, Priest Kukai and Saicho went to Tang-dynasty China one after another, and they brought back Esoteric Buddhism into Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period&apos;s former half, Priest Kukai and Saicho went to Tang-dynasty China one after another, and they brought back Esoteric Buddhism into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>空海、最澄らが伝えた仏教思想や文物は美術の面でも大きな影響をもたらし、密教曼荼羅や、奈良時代には見られなかった本格的密教彫像がつくられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Buddhist thought and culture, introduced by Kukai, Saicho, and others, had a great influence on Japanese art, so the Mandala of Esoteric Buddhism, and the full-blown Esoteric Buddhism statues, which could not be seen in the Nara period, were made in this period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Buddhist thought and culture, introduced by Kukai, Saicho, and others, had a great influence on Japanese art, so the Mandala of Esoteric Buddhism, and the full-blown Esoteric Buddhism statues, which could not be seen in the Nara period, were made in this period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Buddhist thought and culture, introduced by Kukai, Saicho, and others, had a great influence on Japanese art, so the Mandala of Esoteric Buddhism, and the full-blown Esoteric Buddhism statues, which could not be seen in the Nara period, were made in this period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>日本の文化は常に中国大陸および朝鮮半島を主とする外来文化の影響を受け、仏教が文化全般に多大な影響を与えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese culture had been always influenced by foreign culture - mainly by that of China and Korea - and Buddhism introduced from them greatly influenced the whole Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese culture had been always influenced by foreign culture - mainly by that of China and Korea - and Buddhism introduced from them greatly influenced the whole of Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese culture had been always influenced by foreign culture - mainly by that of China and Korea - and Buddhism introduced from them greatly influenced the whole of Japanese culture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>それは平安時代も例外ではないが、この時代は、受容した外来文化が和風化し、文化のさまざまな面で「和様」が成立した時代としてとらえられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Heian period is no exception, but this period is deemed to have been the time that the accepted foreign culture became Japanised and the Japanese style was established in various fields of its culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Heian period is no exception, but this period is deemed to have been the time that the accepted foreign culture became Japanised and the Japanese style was established in various fields of its culture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Heian period is no exception, but this period is deemed to have been the time that the accepted foreign culture became Japanized and the Japanese style was established in various fields of its culture.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>遣唐使が中止された9世紀末以降、文化の和風化が進展し、漢字を元にして日本固有の文字である仮名が考案され、和歌や『源氏物語』に代表される物語文学が盛んになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the dispatch of the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China was ended in the end of the ninth century, the Japanization of the culture advanced, so &quot;kana&quot; (syllables peculiar to Japan) based on Chinese characters was created, and kana helped the spread of &quot;waka&quot; (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and narrative literature exemplified by &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the dispatch of the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China was ended in the end of the ninth century, the Japanization of the culture advanced, so &quot;kana&quot; (syllables peculiar to Japan) based on Chinese characters was created, and kana helped the spread of &quot;waka&quot; (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and narrative literature exemplified by &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the dispatch of the Japanese envoy to Tang Dynasty China was ended in the end of the ninth century, the Japanization of the culture advanced, so &quot;kana&quot; (syllables peculiar to Japan) based on Chinese characters was created, and kana helped the spread of &quot;waka&quot; (a traditional Japanese poem of thirty-one syllables) and narrative literature exemplified by &quot;Genji Monogatari&quot; (The Tale of Genji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>これらの文学は、絵画や書道作品のテーマとなり、工芸品のデザインにも大いに影響している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such works of literature not only became the theme of paintings and works of calligraphy but also influenced greatly the design of handicrafts.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such works of literature not only became the theme of paintings and works of calligraphy but also influenced greatly the design of handicrafts.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such works of literature not only became the theme of paintings and works of calligraphy but also influenced greatly the design of handicrafts.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="187">
<j>また、仏像、絵画、書道、寺院建築など、造形芸術の各方面で和様が確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the Japanese style was established in every field of art and design, such as the Buddhist statue, the painting, the calligraphy, and the temple architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the Japanese style was established in every field of art and design, such as Buddhist statues, painting, calligraphy, and temple architecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the Japanese style was established in every field of art and design, such as Buddhist statues, painting, calligraphy, and temple architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>平安時代後期には源信_(僧侶)（恵心僧都）の『往生要集』などの影響で浄土教信仰が盛んとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the later Heian period, Priest Genshin (also called Eshin Sozu) wrote &quot;Ojoyoshu&quot; (The Essentials of Salvation), and this helped the spread of the faith in &quot;Jodo Sect&quot; (the Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the later Heian period, Priest Genshin (also called Eshin Sozu) wrote &quot;Ojoyoshu&quot; (The Essentials of Salvation), and this helped the spread of the faith in &quot;Jodo Sect&quot; (the Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the later Heian period, Priest Genshin (also called Eshin Sozu) wrote &quot;Ojoyoshu&quot; (The Essentials of Salvation), and this helped the spread of the faith in Jodo Sect (the Pure Land Sect of Buddhism).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>また、1052年を「末法」の年と信じる末法思想（「末法」の年以後、釈迦の唱えた正しい仏法が行われなくなると信じられた）が流布した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And &quot;Mappo-shiso&quot; (the end-of-the-world belief) became rampant, which made people in those days believe that A.D. 1052 was the first year of &quot;Mappo&quot; (Age of the Final Dharma) and that thereafter the Buddhist law taught by Shaka would be neglected.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And &quot;Mappo-shiso&quot; (the end-of-the-world belief) became rampant, which made people in those days believe that A.D. 1052 was the first year of &quot;Mappo&quot; (Age of the Final Dharma) and that thereafter the Buddhist law taught by Shaka would be neglected.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And &apos;Mappo-shiso&apos; (the end-of-the-world belief) became rampant, which made people in those days believe that A.D. 1052 was the first year of &apos;Mappo&apos; (Age of the Final Dharma) and that thereafter the Buddhist law taught by Shaka would be neglected.</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>このため、貴族らは西方極楽浄土への往生を願い、各地に阿弥陀如来像を安置する阿弥陀堂や浄土式庭園が造られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, wishing for their rebirth in &quot;Saiho Gokuraku Jodo&quot; (the West Pure Land, which refers to the Buddhist paradise), court nobles constructed &quot;Amida-do halls&quot; (temple halls that have an enshrined image of &apos;Amida Nyorai&apos; [Buddha of Limitless Light and Life]) and Jodo-Sect-style gardens in some places.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, wishing for their rebirth in &quot;Saiho Gokuraku Jodo&quot; (the West Pure Land, which refers to the Buddhist paradise), court nobles constructed &quot;Amida-do halls&quot; (temple halls that have an enshrined image of &apos;Amida Nyorai&apos; [Buddha of Limitless Light and Life]) and Jodo-Sect-style gardens in some places.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, wishing for their rebirth in Saiho Gokuraku Jodo (the West Pure Land, which refers to the Buddhist paradise), court nobles constructed Amida-do halls (temple halls that have an enshrined image of Amida Nyorai (Buddha of Limitless Light and Life)) and Jodo-Sect-style gardens in some places.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="191">
<j>平安前期（弘仁時代・貞観時代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian period&apos;s former half (once called the Konin period, or the Jogan period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian period&apos;s former half (once called the Konin period, or the Jogan period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian period&apos;s former half (once called the Konin period, or the Jogan period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="192">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>両界曼荼羅（東寺、伝・真言院曼荼羅）（「西院曼荼羅」とも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryokai Mandala&quot; (Mandalas of the two Realms) : enshrimned in To-ji Temple, and is called &quot;Den Shingon-in Mandala&quot; (the Mandalas attributed to Priest Kukai), or &quot;Saiin Mandala&quot; (the Mandalas stored in &apos;Sai-in&apos; [Miei-do Hall])</e>
<cmt>・「伝真言院曼陀羅」は曼荼羅の名称です。その意味については「（真言宗の開祖である）空海の作と伝えられる曼荼羅」と解しています。　　これと「西院曼荼羅」の意味（西院[御影堂]に伝わる曼荼羅）につき下記HPを参照しました。　[http://bany.bz/qukai/entry_44420.php] [http://www.toji.or.jp/2009_autumn.shtml]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryokai Mandala&quot; (Mandalas of the two Realms) : enshrined in To-ji Temple, and is called &quot;Den Shingon-in Mandala&quot; (the Mandalas attributed to Priest Kukai), or &quot;Saiin Mandala&quot; (the Mandalas stored in &apos;Sai-in&apos; [Miei-do Hall])</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryokai Mandala (Mandalas of the two Realms): enshrined in To-ji Temple, and is called Den Shingon-in Mandala (the Mandalas attributed to Priest Kukai), or Saiin Mandala (the Mandalas stored in Sai-in (Miei-do Hall))</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>不動明王像（園城寺、黄不動）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of &quot;Fudo-Myoo&quot; (the Wrathful Lord) : enshrined in Enjo-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Ki Fudo&quot; (Yellow-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of &quot;Fudo-Myoo&quot; (the Wrathful Lord) : enshrined in Enjo-ji Temple, and commonly called &quot;Ki Fudo&quot; (Yellow-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Fudo-Myoo (the Wrathful Lord): enshrined in Enjo-ji Temple, and commonly called Ki Fudo (Yellow-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="195">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>木造薬師如来立像（神護寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of &quot;Yakushi Nyorai&quot; (Medicine Buddha) : enshrined in Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden standing statue of &quot;Yakushi Nyorai&quot; (Medicine Buddha) : enshrined in Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden standing statue of Yakushi Nyorai (Medicine Buddha): enshrined in Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>木造薬師如来坐像（新薬師寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden seated statue of Yakushi Nyorai : enshrined in Shin-Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden seated statue of Yakushi Nyorai : enshrined in Shin-Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden seated statue of Yakushi Nyorai: enshrined in Shin-Yakushi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>東寺講堂諸仏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statues in Kodo of To-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statues in Kodo of To-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statues in Kodo of To-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="199">
<j>木造如意輪観音坐像（観心寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden seated statue of Nyoirin Kannon : enshrined in Kanshin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden seated statue of Nyoirin Kannon : enshrined in Kanshin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden seated statue of Nyoirin Kannon: enshrined in Kanshin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="200">
<j>木造八幡三神像（東寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The wooden statues of Three &quot;Hachiman&quot; (Gods of Archery and War) : enshrined in To-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The wooden statues of Three &quot;Hachiman&quot; (Gods of Archery and War) : enshrined in To-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The wooden statues of Three Hachiman (Gods of Archery and War): enshrined in To-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>室生寺五重塔、金堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muroo-ji Temple&apos;s Five-storey Pagoda, and its Kondo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muroo-ji Temple&apos;s Five-storey Pagoda, and its Kondo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muroo-ji Temple&apos;s Five-storey Pagoda, and its Kondo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="203">
<j>平安後期（藤原時代）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heian period&apos;s latter half (also called the Fujiwara period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heian period&apos;s latter half (also called the Fujiwara period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heian period&apos;s latter half (also called the Fujiwara period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="204">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>仏画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>阿弥陀聖衆来迎図（高野山有志八幡講）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of Amida Nyorai accompanied by his heavenly retinue bodhisattvas and other heavenly beings : owned by &quot;Koyasan Yushi Hachiman-ko&quot; (the voluntary organization of temples on Mt. Koya, which worship Hachiman)</e>
<cmt>・「高野山有志八幡講」については下記HPを参照の上、「八幡神を崇拝する、高野山の寺社からなる有志的組織」と訳しました。[http://www.reihokan.or.jp/yomoyama/various/culture/yushi/hachiman_01.htm]</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of Amida Nyorai accompanied by his heavenly retinue bodhisattvas and other heavenly beings : owned by &quot;Koyasan Yushi Hachiman-ko&quot; (the voluntary organization of temples on Mt. Koya, which worship Hachiman)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Amida Nyorai accompanied by his heavenly retinue bodhisattvas and other heavenly beings: owned by Koyasan Yushi Hachiman-ko (the voluntary organization of temples on Mt. Koya, which worship Hachiman)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>普賢菩薩像（東京国立博物館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of &quot;Fugen Bosatsu&quot; (Bodhisattva of Practice) : owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of &quot;Fugen Bosatsu&quot; (Bodhisattva of Practice) : owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Fugen Bosatsu (Bodhisattva of Practice): owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="208">
<j>不動明王二童子像（青蓮院、青不動）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of Fudo-Myoo and his two attendant boys : enshrined in Shoren-in Temple, and commonly called &quot;Ao Fudo&quot; (Blue-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of Fudo-Myoo and his two attendant boys : enshrined in Shoren-in Temple, and commonly called &quot;Ao Fudo&quot; (Blue-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Fudo-Myoo and his two attendant boys: enshrined in Shoren-in Temple, and commonly called &quot;Ao Fudo&quot; (Blue-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>不動明王二童子像（高野山明王院、赤不動）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of Fudo-Myoo and his two attendant boys : enshrined in Myoo-in temple on Mt. Koya, and commonly called &quot;Aka Fudo&quot; (Red-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of Fudo-Myoo and his two attendant boys : enshrined in Myoo-in temple on Mt. Koya, and commonly called &quot;Aka Fudo&quot; (Red-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Fudo-Myoo and his two attendant boys: enshrined in Myoo-in temple on Mt. Koya, and commonly called &quot;Aka Fudo&quot; (Red-Colored Lord)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>五大力菩薩像（高野山有志八幡講）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The painting of Five Forceful Bodhisattvas : owned by Koyasan Yushi Hachiman-ko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The painting of Five Forceful Bodhisattvas : owned by Koyasan Yushi Hachiman-ko</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The painting of Five Forceful Bodhisattvas: owned by Koyasan Yushi Hachiman-ko</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>絵巻物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Emakimono&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls)</e>
<cmt>・｢絵巻物」については以下 &quot;illustrated handscroll&quot; の訳で統一しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Emakimono&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono (Illustrated handscrolls)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>源氏物語絵巻（徳川美術館、五島美術館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Genji) : owned by the Tokugawa Art Museum and the Gotoh Art Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Genji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Genji) : owned by the Tokugawa Art Museum and the Gotoh Art Museum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genji Monogatari Emaki (The illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Genji): owned by the Tokugawa Art Museum and the Gotoh Art Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="213">
<j>鳥獣人物戯画（高山寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Choju-jinbutsu-giga&quot; (The illustrated handscrolls of frolicking animals and humans) : owned by Kozan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Choju-jinbutsu-giga&quot; (The illustrated handscrolls of frolicking animals and humans) : owned by Kozan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Choju-jinbutsu-giga (The illustrated handscrolls of frolicking animals and humans): owned by Kozan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>信貴山縁起絵巻（朝護孫子寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shigisan Engi-emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of Legends of Mt. Shigi) : owned by Chogosonshi-ji temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shigisan Engi-emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of Legends of Mt. Shigi) : owned by Chogosonshi-ji temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigisan Engi-emaki (The illustrated handscroll of Legends of Mt. Shigi): owned by Chogosonshi-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>伴大納言絵詞（出光美術館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bandainagon Ekotoba&quot; (The illustrated handscrolls about Conspiracy of Ote-mon gate) : owned by Idemitsu Museum of Arts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bandainagon Ekotoba&quot; (The illustrated handscrolls about Conspiracy of Ote-mon gate) : owned by Idemitsu Museum of Arts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bandainagon Ekotoba (The illustrated handscrolls about Conspiracy of Ote-mon gate): owned by Idemitsu Museum of Arts</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="216">
<j>粉河寺縁起絵巻（粉河寺、京都国立博物館寄託）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kokawadera Engi-emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of Legends of Kokawa-dera Temple) : owned by Kokawa-dera Temple, and deposited in Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kokawadera Engi-emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of Legends of Kokawa-dera Temple) : owned by Kokawa-dera Temple, and deposited in Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokawadera Engi-emaki (The illustrated handscroll of Legends of Kokawa-dera Temple): owned by Kokawa-dera Temple, and deposited in Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>地獄草紙（東京国立博物館、奈良国立博物館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jigoku zoshi&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the Hell) : owned by Tokyo National Museum and Nara National Museum each</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jigoku zoshi&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the Hell) : owned by Tokyo National Museum and Nara National Museum each</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jigoku zoshi (The illustrated handscroll of the Hell): owned by Tokyo National Museum and Nara National Museum each</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>装飾経</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Decorative sutras</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Decorative sutras</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Decorative sutras</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>平家納経（厳島神社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heike-nokyo&quot; (the sutras dedicated by the Taira family) : enshrined in Itsukushima-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heike-nokyo&quot; (the sutras dedicated by the Taira family) : enshrined in Itsukushima-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heike-nokyo (the sutras dedicated by the Taira family): enshrined in Itsukushima-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>扇面法華経冊子（四天王寺、東京国立博物館ほか）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi&quot; (Lotus Sutra Booklet on a Fan) : owned by each of some institutions, including Shitenno-ji Temple and Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi&quot; (Lotus Sutra Booklet on a Fan) : owned by some institutions, including Shitenno-ji Temple and Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senmen Hokkekyo Sasshi (Lotus Sutra Booklet on a Fan): owned by some institutions, including Shitenno-ji Temple and Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>阿弥陀如来坐像（平等院鳳凰堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seated statue of Amida Nyorai : enshrined in &quot;Hoo-do Hall&quot; (the Phoenix Pavilion) of Byodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seated statue of Amida Nyorai : enshrined in &quot;Hoo-do Hall&quot; (the Phoenix Pavilion) of Byodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Amida Nyorai: enshrined in Hoo-do Hall (the Phoenix Pavilion) of Byodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>一字金輪坐像（中尊寺ほか17箇院）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The seated statue of &quot;Ichiji Kinrin&quot; (literally, the deity of One-Syllable Gold Wheel) : enshrined in Chuson-ji Temple and other 17 temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The seated statue of &quot;Ichiji Kinrin&quot; (literally, the deity of One-Syllable Gold Wheel) : enshrined in Chuson-ji Temple and 17 other temples</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The seated statue of Ichiji Kinrin (literally, the deity of One-Syllable Gold Wheel): enshrined in Chuson-ji Temple and 17 other temples</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="224">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>片輪車螺鈿蒔絵手箱（東京国立博物館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Katawaguruma Raden Makie Tebako&quot; (Toiletry Case with Cart Wheels in Stream) : owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Katawaguruma Raden Makie Tebako&quot; (Toiletry Case with Cart Wheels in Stream) : owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katawaguruma Raden Makie Tebako (Toiletry Case with Cart Wheels in Stream): owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>平等院鳳凰堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoo-do Hall of Bodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoo-do Hall of Bodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoo-do Hall of Byodo-in Temple</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="228">
<j>中尊寺金色堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Konjiki-do Hall&quot; (Golden Hall) of Chuson-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Konjiki-do Hall&quot; (Golden Hall) of Chuson-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Konjiki-do Hall (Golden Hall) of Chuson-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>一乗寺三重塔</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Three-storey Pagoda of Ichijo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Three-storey Pagoda of Ichijo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Three-storey Pagoda of Ichijo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="230">
<j>庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gardens</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gardens</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gardens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>浄土式庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jodo-sect-style gardens</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jodo-sect-style gardens</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo-sect-style gardens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>平等院庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Byodo-in Temple Garden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Byodo-in Temple Garden</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Byodo-in Temple Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>浄瑠璃寺庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Joruri-ji Temple Garden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Joruri-ji Temple Garden</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joruri-ji Temple Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="234">
<j>毛越寺庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Motsu-ji Temple Garden</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Motsu-ji Temple Garden</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Motsu-ji Temple Garden</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="235">
<j>中世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Middle age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Middle age</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Middle age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="236">
<j>鎌倉時代・南北朝時代 (日本)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamakura period/Northern and Southern Courts period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamakura period/Northern and Southern Courts period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura period/Northern and Southern Courts period (Japan)</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="237">
<j>平氏滅亡の年であり、源頼朝によって全国に守護地頭が設置された1185年を鎌倉時代の始期とすることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura period is commonly thought to have begun in A.D. 1185, when the Taira family fell and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo dipatched &quot;Shugo and Jito&quot; (military governors and estate stewards) all over Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura period is commonly thought to have begun in A.D. 1185, when the Taira family fell and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo dispatched &quot;Shugo and Jito&quot; (military governors and estate stewards) all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamakura period is commonly thought to have begun in A.D. 1185, when the Taira family fell and MINAMOTO no Yoritomo dispatched Shugo and Jito (military governors and estate stewards) all over Japan.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="238">
<j>1180年には平重衡による南都焼き討ちで奈良（南都）の2大仏教勢力であった東大寺と興福寺が炎上したが、このことは美術史上、象徴的な事件であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In A.D. 1180, Todai-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple (the two Buddhist powerhouses in &quot;Nanto&quot; [the southern capital, which refers to Nara]), were burned down in &quot;Nanto Yakiuchi&quot; (Burning of Nanto) by TAIRA no Shigehira, and this was a symbolic incident in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In A.D. 1180, Todai-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple (the two Buddhist powerhouses in &quot;Nanto&quot; [the southern capital, which refers to Nara]), were burned down in &quot;Nanto Yakiuchi&quot; (Burning of Nanto) by TAIRA no Shigehira, and this was a symbolic incident in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In A.D. 1180, Todai-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple (the two Buddhist powerhouses in Nanto (the southern capital, which refers to Nara)), were burned down in Nanto Yakiuchi (Burning of Nanto) by TAIRA no Shigehira, and this was a symbolic incident in Japanese art history.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="239">
<j>焼失した東大寺の大仏と大仏殿、興福寺の堂宇や仏像はただちに再建計画が進められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Immediately after the incident, the reconstruction project was launched for the Great Buddha and its hall of Todai-ji Temple, and for the temple buildings and Buddhist statues of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Immediately after the incident, the reconstruction project was launched for the Great Buddha and its hall of Todai-ji Temple, and for the temple buildings and Buddhist statues of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Immediately after the incident, the reconstruction project was launched for the Great Buddha and its hall of Todai-ji Temple, and for the temple buildings and Buddhist statues of Kofuku-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="240">
<j>大仏と大仏殿の再建担当者に任じられたのは渡宋経験のある俊乗坊重源（しゅんじょうぼうちょうげん）であり、彼によって宋から伝来の新建築様式の大仏様が導入された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was the priest Chogen who was appointed chief of the reconstruction of the Great Buddha and its hall, and Chogen (also called Shunjo-bo) once had been to Sung-dynasty China, so he newly applied &quot;Daibutsu-yo&quot; (the Buddhist architecture), which originated from Sung-dynasty China, to the hall.</e>
<cmt>・一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was the priest Chogen who was appointed chief of the reconstruction of the Great Buddha and its hall, and Chogen (also called Shunjo-bo) once had been to Sung-dynasty China, so he newly applied &quot;Daibutsu-yo&quot; (the Buddhist architecture), which originated from Sung-dynasty China, to the hall.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was the priest Chogen who was appointed chief of the reconstruction of the Great Buddha and its hall, and Chogen (also called Shunjo-bo) once had been to Sung-dynasty China, so he newly applied Daibutsu-yo (the Buddhist architecture), which originated from Sung-dynasty China, to the hall.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="241">
<j>また、東大寺や興福寺の仏像再興には、康慶、運慶、快慶ら慶派を中心とする仏師が登用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in the reconstruction of statues in Todai-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple, &quot;busshi&quot; (sculptors of Buddhist statues) from Kei school (a school of sculptors at that time), such as Kokei, Unkei, and Kaikei, played the major role.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in the reconstruction of statues in Todai-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple, &quot;busshi&quot; (sculptors of Buddhist statues) from the Kei school (a school of sculptors at that time), such as Kokei, Unkei, and Kaikei, played a major role.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in the reconstruction of statues in Todai-ji Temple and Kofuku-ji Temple, busshi (sculptors of Buddhist statues) from the Kei school (a school of sculptors at that time), such as Kokei, Unkei, and Kaikei, played a major role.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="242">
<j>この時代の前期には引き続き院政が行われていたものの、政治・文化の中心は次第に鎌倉へ移っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the former half of the Kamalura period, the nominal rule of the cloistered emperor still continued in Kyoto, but Kamakura gradually replaced Kyoto as the center stage of Japanese politics and culture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the former half of the Kamalura period, the nominal rule of the cloistered emperor still continued in Kyoto, but Kamakura gradually replaced Kyoto as the center stage of Japanese politics and culture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the former half of the Kamakura period, the nominal rule of the cloistered emperor still continued in Kyoto, but Kamakura gradually replaced Kyoto as the center stage of Japanese politics and culture.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>平氏は華麗な「平家納経」を残したことでもわかるように、一面で貴族文化に憧れをもっていたが、代わって政権をとった源氏は純然たる武家であり、美術の主要な享受者も前時代の貴族から武士へと移っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Taira clan adored the aristocratic culture, which is symbolized by the gorgeous Heike-nokyo, while the Minamoto clan, which replaced the Taira clan as the political power, was the genuine samurai family, so samurai gradually replaced court nobles as the major beneficiaries of the art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Taira clan adored the aristocratic culture, which is symbolized by the gorgeous Heike-nokyo, while the Minamoto clan, which replaced the Taira clan as the political power, was a genuine samurai family, so samurai gradually replaced court nobles as the major beneficiaries of art.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Taira clan adored the aristocratic culture, which is symbolized by the gorgeous Heike-nokyo, while the Minamoto clan, which replaced the Taira clan as the political power, was a genuine samurai family, so samurai gradually replaced court nobles as the major beneficiaries of art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="244">
<j>この時代には栄西、道元らの入宋僧によって日本にも本格的な禅宗が伝わり、比叡山などの旧仏教の圧迫を受けつつも、徐々に勢力を伸ばしていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period, the full-blown Zen sect of Buddhism was introduced into Japan by Eisai, Dogen, and other priests who went to Sung-dynasty China, and the sect gradually increased its influence in spite of the pressure from the old Buddhist powerhouses, such as Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this period, the full-blown Zen sect of Buddhism was introduced into Japan by Eisai, Dogen, and other priests who went to Sung-dynasty China, and the sect gradually increased its influence in spite of the pressure from the old Buddhist powerhouses, such as Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period, the full-blown Zen sect of Buddhism was introduced into Japan by Eisai, Dogen, and other priests who went to Sung-dynasty China, and the sect gradually increased its influence in spite of the pressure from the old Buddhist powerhouses, such as Enryaku-ji Temple on Mt. Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>13世紀に京都の建仁寺建立を皮切りに、鎌倉にも建長寺、円覚寺などの本格的な禅寺が建立された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 13th century, with Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto as the start, full-blown &quot;Zen temples&quot; (temples that belong to the Zen sect), such as Kencho-ji Temple and Enkaku-ji Temple, were constructed in Kamakura as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 13th century, with Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto as the start, full-blown &quot;Zen temples&quot; (temples that belong to the Zen sect), such as Kencho-ji Temple and Enkaku-ji Temple, were constructed in Kamakura as well.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 13th century, with Kennin-ji Temple in Kyoto as the start, full-blown Zen temples (temples that belong to the Zen sect), such as Kencho-ji Temple and Enkaku-ji Temple, were constructed in Kamakura as well.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="246">
<j>南北朝時代は美術史的には過渡期ととらえられ、鎌倉時代に含めて論じられることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts is deemed the transitional period, so its art is commonly mentioned in the art of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the perspective of art history, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts is deemed the transitional period, so its art is commonly mentioned in the art of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the period of the Northern and Southern Courts is deemed the transitional period, so its art is commonly mentioned in the art of the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>ただし、刀剣武具の分野に関しては、長大な大太刀の流行など、明らかな「南北朝時代様式」があり、鎌倉時代とは別の時代とされることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the field of swords and arms, there obviously existed the style peculiar to this period, which is exemplified by the long Japanese sword - popular in this period - so that this period is commonly distinguished from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the field of swords and arms, there obviously existed a style specific to this period, which is exemplified by the long Japanese sword - popular in this period - so that this period is commonly distinguished from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the field of swords and arms, there obviously existed a style specific to this period, which is exemplified by the long Japanese sword - popular in this period - so that this period is commonly distinguished from the Kamakura period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="40">
<sen id="248">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>似絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nise-e&quot; (Realistic portraiture of courtiers and warriors)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nise-e&quot; (Realistic portraits of courtiers and warriors)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nise-e (Realistic portraits of courtiers and warriors)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>伝・源頼朝像・平重盛像・藤原光能像（神護寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The portraits that are supposed to be MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, TAIRA no Shigemori, and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi : owned by Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Portraits that are supposed to be MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, TAIRA no Shigemori, and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi : owned by Jingo-ji Temple.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Portraits that are supposed to be MINAMOTO no Yoritomo, TAIRA no Shigemori, and FUJIWARA no Mitsuyoshi: owned by Jingo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除ピリオド削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>絵巻物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emakimono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emakimono</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emakimono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="252">
<j>合戦絵巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kassen emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscroll of battles)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kassen emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscroll of battles)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kassen emaki (Illustrated handscroll of battles)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>平治物語絵巻（東京国立博物館、静嘉堂、ボストン美術館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Heiji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Heiji) : owned by Tokyo National Museum, Seikado Bunko Art Museum, and Boston Museum of Fine Arts each</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Heiji Monogatari Emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Heiji) : owned by Tokyo National Museum, Seikado Bunko Art Museum, and Boston Museum of Fine Arts each</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heiji Monogatari Emaki (The illustrated handscroll of the Tale of Heiji): owned by Tokyo National Museum, Seikado Bunko Art Museum, and Boston Museum of Fine Arts each</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="254">
<j>文学絵巻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bungaku emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscroll of literature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bungaku emaki&quot; (Illustrated handscroll of literature)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bungaku emaki (Illustrated handscroll of literature)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>佐竹本三十六歌仙絵巻（諸家分蔵）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Satake version of the illustrated handscroll of thirty-six immortal poets : owned dividedly by some families</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Satake version of the illustrated handscroll of thirty-six immortal poets : separately owned by some families</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Satake version of the illustrated handscroll of thirty-six immortal poets: separately owned by some families</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>社寺縁起</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shaji engi&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls of temples and shrines)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shaji engi&quot; (Illustrated handscrolls of temples and shrines)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaji engi (Illustrated handscrolls of temples and shrines)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>北野天神縁起絵巻（北野天満宮）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kitano Tenjin Engi Emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the history of Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine) : owned by Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kitano Tenjin Engi Emaki&quot; (The illustrated handscroll of the history of Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine) : owned by Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitano Tenjin Engi Emaki (The illustrated handscroll of the history of Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine): owned by Kitano Tenman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>高僧伝絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Koso den-e&quot; (Illustrated biography of high rank priest)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Koso den-e&quot; (Illustrated biography of high rank priest)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koso den-e (Illustrated biography of high rank priest)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="259">
<j>一遍上人絵伝（歓喜光寺・清浄光寺共有）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ippen Shonin Eden&quot; (The pictorial biography of the monk Ippen) : shared between Kankiko-ji Temple and Shojoko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ippen Shonin Eden&quot; (The pictorial biography of the monk Ippen) : shared between Kankiko-ji Temple and Shojoko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ippen Shonin Eden (The pictorial biography of the monk Ippen): shared between Kankiko-ji Temple and Shojoko-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>垂迹画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Suijaku-ga&quot; (Painting based on the theory of Buddhist and Shinto unity)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Suijaku-ga&quot; (Painting based on the theory of Buddhist and Shinto unity)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suijaku-ga (Painting based on the theory of Buddhist and Shinto unity)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>康慶 : 不空羂索観音像（興福寺南円堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokei : The statue of Fukukenjaku Kannon enshrined in Nanen-do Hall of Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokei : The statue of Fukukenjaku Kannon enshrined in Nanen-do Hall of Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokei: The statue of Fukukenjaku Kannon enshrined in Nanen-do Hall of Kofuku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>運慶 : 弥勒仏像、無著・世親像（興福寺北円堂） 大日如来像（円成寺多宝塔）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unkei : The statue of Miroku Butsu, the statues of Muchaku and Seshin - these three are enshrined in Hokuen-do Hall of Kofuku-ji Temple - and the statue of &quot;Dainichi Nyorai&quot; (Cosmic Buddha) enshrined in &quot;Tahoto pagoda&quot; (the multi-treasure pagoda) of Enjo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unkei : The statue of Miroku Butsu, the statues of Muchaku and Seshin - these three are enshrined in Hokuen-do Hall of Kofuku-ji Temple - and the statue of &quot;Dainichi Nyorai&quot; (Cosmic Buddha) enshrined in &quot;Tahoto pagoda&quot; (the multi-treasure pagoda) of Enjo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unkei: The statue of Miroku Butsu, the statues of Muchaku and Seshin - these three are enshrined in Hokuen-do Hall of Kofuku-ji Temple - and the statue of Dainichi Nyorai (Cosmic Buddha) enshrined in Tahoto pagoda (the multi-treasure pagoda) of Enjo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>快慶 : 僧形八幡像（東大寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaikei : The statue of &quot;Sogyo Hachiman&quot; (Hachiman in guise of a Buddhist priest) : enshrined in Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaikei : The statue of &quot;Sogyo Hachiman&quot; (Hachiman in guise of a Buddhist priest) : enshrined in Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaikei: The statue of Sogyo Hachiman (Hachiman in guise of a Buddhist priest): enshrined in Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="265">
<j>湛慶 : 千手観音像（妙法院蓮華王院＝三十三間堂）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tankei : The statue of &quot;Senju Kannon&quot; (Thousand Armed Goddess of Mercy) enshrined in Renge O-in (also known as Sanjusangen-do Hall) of Myoho-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tankei : The statue of &quot;Senju Kannon&quot; (Thousand Armed Goddess of Mercy) enshrined in Renge O-in (also known as Sanjusangen-do Hall) of Myoho-in Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tankei: The statue of Senju Kannon (Thousand Armed Goddess of Mercy) enshrined in Renge O-in (also known as Sanjusangen-do Hall) of Myoho-in Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>金剛力士像（東大寺南大門、運慶、快慶他作）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The statue of &quot;Kongo Rikishi&quot; (Benevolent Kings) : placed at &quot;Nandai-mon gate&quot; (the Great South Gate) of Todai-ji Temple, and carved by Unkei, Kaikei, and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The statue of &quot;Kongo Rikishi&quot; (Benevolent Kings) : placed at &quot;Nandai-mon gate&quot; (the Great South Gate) of Todai-ji Temple, and carved by Unkei, Kaikei, and others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The statue of Kongo Rikishi (Benevolent Kings): placed at Nandai-mon gate (the Great South Gate) of Todai-ji Temple, and carved by Unkei, Kaikei, and others</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="267">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>陶磁器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceramic ware</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceramic ware</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceramic ware</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>漆工</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lacquer work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lacquer work</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lacquer work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>金工</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Metal work</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Metal work</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Metal work</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="272">
<j>和様</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>大仏様（天竺様）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daibutsu-yo (also called &quot;Tenjiku-yo&quot; [Indian-style])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daibutsu-yo (also called &quot;Tenjiku-yo&quot; [Indian-style])</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daibutsu-yo (also called &quot;Tenjiku-yo&quot; (Indian-style))</e>
<cmt>カッコ修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>東大寺南大門</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nandai-mon gate of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nandai-mon gate of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nandai-mon gate of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>浄土寺 (小野市)浄土堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Jodo-do Hall&quot; (The Pure Land Hall) of Jodo-ji Temple in Ono City</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Jodo-do Hall&quot; (The Pure Land Hall) of Jodo-ji Temple in Ono City</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jodo-do Hall (The Pure Land Hall) of Jodo-ji Temple in Ono City</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="276">
<j>禅宗様（唐様）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Zenshu-yo&quot; (Zen-sect-style) [also called &apos;Kara-yo&apos; (Chinese-style)]</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Zenshu-yo&quot; (Zen-sect-style) [also called &apos;Kara-yo&apos; (Chinese-style)]</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zenshu-yo (Zen-sect-style) (also called &apos;Kara-yo&apos; (Chinese-style))</e>
<cmt>カッコ修正&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="277">
<j>功山寺仏殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Buddha Hall of Kozan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Buddha Hall of Kozan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Buddha Hall of Kozan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="278">
<j>善福院釈迦堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shaka-do Hall of Zenpuku-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shaka-do Hall of Zenpuku-in Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shaka-do Hall of Zenpuku-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="41">
<sen id="279">
<j>室町時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muromachi period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muromachi period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="42">
<sen id="280">
<j>南北朝分裂の時代を経て、室町幕府3代将軍足利義満の時代、1392年にようやく南北両朝は合一し、文化の中心は再び京都へ戻った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the period of separation, the Northern and Southern Courts were at last unified in A.D. 1392, when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA reigned Muromachi &quot;bakufu&quot; (Japanese feudal regime) as the third shogun, and the center stage of Japanese culture returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the period of separation, the Northern and Southern Courts were at last unified in A.D. 1392, when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA reigned over the Muromachi &quot;bakufu&quot; (Japanese feudal regime) as the third shogun, and the center stage of Japanese culture returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the period of separation, the Northern and Southern Courts were at last unified in A.D. 1392, when Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA reigned over the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) as the third shogun, and the center stage of Japanese culture returned to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>用語統一&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="281">
<j>義満は京都の北山に山荘を営み（後の鹿苑寺＝金閣寺）、この時代の文化を北山文化と呼ぶことがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On &quot;Kitayama&quot; (the Northern Hills) of Kyoto, Yoshimitsu constructed a villa, which in later days began to be called Rokuon-ji Temple (more commonly, Kinkaku-ji Temple), so the culture around then is occasionally called Kitayama culture after the location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On &quot;Kitayama&quot; (the Northern Hills) of Kyoto, Yoshimitsu constructed a villa, which was later called Rokuon-ji Temple (more commonly, Kinkaku-ji Temple), so the culture around then is occasionally called Kitayama culture after the location.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Kitayama (the Northern Hills) of Kyoto, Yoshimitsu constructed a villa, which was later called Rokuon-ji Temple (more commonly, Kinkaku-ji Temple), so the culture around then is occasionally called Kitayama culture after the location.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>8代将軍の足利義政は為政者としての務めを怠り、茶道、書道、唐物（中国渡来の文物）愛玩などの趣味にふけっていたが、そのため文化の振興には大いに貢献した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA made light of his duty as a politician, and indulged in his hobbies, such as Japanese tea ceremony, calligraphy, and &quot;kara-mono&quot; (things imported from China), and ironically, he contributed to the advancement of the culture to a great extent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA made light of his duty as a politician, and indulged in his hobbies, such as Japanese tea ceremony, calligraphy, and &quot;kara-mono&quot; (things imported from China), and ironically, he contributed to the advancement of the culture to a great extent.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth shogun Yoshimasa ASHIKAGA made light of his duty as a politician, and indulged in his hobbies, such as Japanese tea ceremony, calligraphy, and kara-mono (things imported from China), and ironically, he contributed to the advancement of the culture to a great extent.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>彼の山荘（後の慈照寺＝銀閣寺）が東山にあったことから、その時代の文化を東山文化と称することがある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On &quot;Higashiyama&quot; (Mt. Higashi), he constructed a villa, which in later days began to be called Jisho-ji Temple (more commonly, Ginkaku-ji Temple), so the culture around then is occasionally called Higashiyama culture after the location.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On &quot;Higashiyama&quot; (Mt. Higashi), he constructed a villa, which later came to be called Jisho-ji Temple (more commonly, Ginkaku-ji Temple), so the culture around then is occasionally called Higashiyama culture after the location.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On Higashiyama (Mt. Higashi), he constructed a villa, which later came to be called Jisho-ji Temple (more commonly, Ginkaku-ji Temple), so the culture around then is occasionally called Higashiyama culture after the location.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>義政の東山山荘は、後の書院造の原型であり、日本の伝統的住宅建築のルーツとなるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">His villa on Higashiyama is the prototype of the later days&apos; &quot;Shoin-zukuri style&quot; (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a &apos;tokonoma&apos; [alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed]) - in short, it is the origin of the traditional style of Japanese architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">His villa on Higashiyama is the prototype of the &quot;Shoin-zukuri style&quot; (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a &apos;tokonoma&apos; [alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed]) which came later - in short, it is the origin of the traditional style of Japanese architecture.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">His villa on Higashiyama is the prototype of the Shoin-zukuri style (a traditional Japanese style of residential architecture that includes a &apos;tokonoma&apos; (alcove in a traditional Japanese room where art or flowers are displayed)) which came later - in short, it is the origin of the traditional style of Japanese architecture.</e>
<cmt>カッコ修正&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="285">
<j>歴代の足利将軍は禅宗に帰依し、これを保護したため、京都を中心に禅宗寺院が隆盛し、そこから造園、文学、茶道など、さまざまな文化が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Successive shoguns of Muromachi bakufu devoutly believed in and patronized Zen sect of Buddhism, so Zen-sect-style temples were constructed one after another mainly in Kyoto, and these temples became the stage of various kinds of culture, such as landscape gardening, literature, and Japanese tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Successive shoguns of the Muromachi bakufu devoutly believed in and patronized the Zen sect of Buddhism, so Zen-sect-style temples were constructed one after another mainly in Kyoto, and these temples became the stage of various kinds of culture, such as landscape gardening, literature, and Japanese tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Successive shoguns of the Muromachi bakufu devoutly believed in and patronized the Zen sect of Buddhism, so Zen-sect-style temples were constructed one after another mainly in Kyoto, and these temples became the stage of various kinds of culture, such as landscape gardening, literature, and Japanese tea ceremony.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="286">
<j>能もこの時代に観阿弥・世阿弥により完成されたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And it was also in this period that &quot;Noh&quot; (the Japanese traditional dance-drama in mask) was perfected by Kanami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And it was also in this period that &quot;Noh&quot; (the Japanese traditional dance-drama in mask) was perfected by Kanami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And it was also in this period that Noh (the Japanese traditional dance-drama in mask) was perfected by Kanami and Zeami.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="43">
<sen id="287">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>頂相</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chinzo&quot; (Portrait of a Zen monk)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chinzo&quot; (Portrait of a Zen monk)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinzo (Portrait of a Zen monk)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>大燈国師像（大徳寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The portrait of &quot;Daito Kokushi&quot; (national Buddhist master Daito) : enshrined in Daitoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The portrait of &quot;Daito Kokushi&quot; (national Buddhist master Daito) : enshrined in Daitoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The portrait of Daito Kokushi (national Buddhist master Daito): enshrined in Daitoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>水墨画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suibokuga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suibokuga</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suibokuga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="291">
<j>如拙：『瓢鮎図』--詩画軸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Josetsu : &quot;Hyotan-zu&quot; (The painting of catching Japanese catfish with bottle gourd), which is &quot;Shigajiku&quot; (the hanging scroll with Chinese poetry)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Josetsu : &quot;Hyotan-zu&quot; (The painting of catching Japanese catfish with bottle gourd), which is &quot;Shigajiku&quot; (a hanging scroll with Chinese poetry)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Josetsu: &quot;Hyotan-zu&quot; (The painting of catching Japanese catfish with bottle gourd), which is Shigajiku (a hanging scroll with Chinese poetry)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>雪舟：「山水長巻」「秋冬山水図」「破墨山水図」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sesshu : &quot;Sansui-Chokan&quot; (Long Scroll of Landscapes), &quot;Shuto-Sansui-zu&quot; (Landscapes of Autumn and Winter), and &quot;Haboku-Sansui-zu&quot; (Landscapes painted with splashed-ink technique)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sesshu : &quot;Sansui-Chokan&quot; (Long Scroll of Landscapes), &quot;Shuto-Sansui-zu&quot; (Landscapes of Autumn and Winter), and &quot;Haboku-Sansui-zu&quot; (Landscapes painted with splashed-ink technique)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sesshu: &apos;Sansui-Chokan&apos; (Long Scroll of Landscapes), &apos;Shuto-Sansui-zu&apos; (Landscapes of Autumn and Winter), and &apos;Haboku-Sansui-zu&apos; (Landscapes painted with splashed-ink technique)</e>
<cmt>&quot;→&apos;スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="294">
<j>陶磁器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceramic ware</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceramic ware</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceramic ware</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="44">
<sen id="295">
<j>北山文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kitayama culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kitayama culture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kitayama culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="296">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Construction</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Construction</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Construction</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>鹿苑寺（金閣寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuon-ji Temple (or Kinkaku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuon-ji Temple (or Kinkaku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuon-ji Temple (or Kinkaku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="45">
<sen id="298">
<j>東山文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Higashiyama culture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Higashiyama culture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Higashiyama culture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="300">
<j>書院造</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoin-zukuri style</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoin-zukuri style</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoin-zukuri style</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>慈照寺（銀閣寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jisho-ji Temple (or Ginkaku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jisho-ji Temple (or Ginkaku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jisho-ji Temple (or Ginkaku-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="302">
<j>庭園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gardens</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gardens</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gardens</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>枯山水　竜安寺石庭など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Karesansui&quot; (Garden of hill-and-stream landscape without water) : e.g. the rock garden of Ryoan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Karesansui&quot; (Garden of hill-and-stream landscape without water) : e.g. the rock garden of Ryoan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Karesansui (Garden of hill-and-stream landscape without water): e.g. the rock garden of Ryoan-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="46">
<sen id="304">
<j>近世</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Early modern ages</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Early modern ages</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Early modern ages</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>桃山時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momoyama period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momoyama period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momoyama period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="47">
<sen id="306">
<j>室町幕府が滅亡した1573年から、徳川政権が確立するまでの時代を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Momoyama period refers to the period that ranged from when Muromachi bakufu fell in A.D. 1573, to when Tokugawa bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Momoyama period refers to the period that ranged from when the Muromachi bakufu fell in A.D. 1573, to when the Tokugawa bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Momoyama period refers to the period that ranged from when the Muromachi bakufu fell in A.D. 1573, to when the Tokugawa bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="307">
<j>美術史上の区分では、豊臣家が滅亡した1615年までを桃山時代とすることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the Momoyama period is commonly deemed to have lasted until A.D. 1615, when the Toyotomi family fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the perspective of art history, the Momoyama period is commonly deemed to have lasted until A.D. 1615, when the Toyotomi family fell.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the perspective of art history, the Momoyama period is commonly deemed to have lasted until A.D. 1615, when the Toyotomi family fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>半世紀に満たない短い期間であるが、美術史上は特に絵画と建築において特記される時代である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lasting for less than half a century, the Momoyama period is noteworthy in art history, especially in the fields of painting and architecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lasting for less than half a century, the Momoyama period is noteworthy in art history, especially in the fields of painting and architecture.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lasting for less than half a century, the Momoyama period is noteworthy in art history, especially in the fields of painting and architecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>城郭建築が発達し、権力のシンボル的な天守閣が築かれ、御殿は華麗な障壁画で装飾された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period saw the development of the castle architecture, so feudal lords constructed &quot;tenshukaku&quot; (the keep or tower) as the symbol of their power, and &quot;goten&quot; (the palace) was decorated with gorgeous &quot;shoheki-ga&quot; (paintings on wall, &apos;byobu&apos; [folding screen], and &apos;fusuma&apos; [sliding door]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This period saw the development of castle architecture, so feudal lords constructed &quot;tenshukaku&quot; (the keep or tower) as the symbol of their power, and &quot;goten&quot; (the palace) was decorated with gorgeous &quot;shoheki-ga&quot; (paintings on walls, &apos;byobu&apos; [folding screen], and &apos;fusuma&apos; [sliding door]).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This period saw the development of castle architecture, so feudal lords constructed tenshukaku (the keep or tower) as the symbol of their power, and goten (the palace) was decorated with gorgeous shoheki-ga (paintings on walls, byobu (folding screen), and fusuma (sliding door)).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除カッコ修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>室町時代に始まった茶の湯は千利休によって大成され、前時代の書院の茶から、草庵の茶、わび茶という独特の美意識が形成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chanoyu&quot; (The tea ceremony), which started in the Muromachi period, was perfected in this period by SEN no Rikyu, who transformed the tea ceremony fitting for Shoin-zukuri architecture into that fitting for the thatched hut, in other words, &quot;wabicha&quot; (the tea ceremony accompanied by &apos;wabi&apos; [an unique aesthetic sense that finds surpassing beauty and deep significance in what is humble or commonplace and appears natural or artless]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chanoyu&quot; (tea ceremony), which started in the Muromachi period, was perfected in this period by SEN no Rikyu, who transformed the tea ceremony fitting for Shoin-zukuri architecture into that fitting for a thatched hut, in other words, &quot;wabicha&quot; (the tea ceremony accompanied by &apos;wabi&apos; [an unique aesthetic sense that finds surpassing beauty and deep significance in what is humble or commonplace and appears natural or artless]).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chanoyu (tea ceremony), which started in the Muromachi period, was perfected in this period by SEN no Rikyu, who transformed the tea ceremony fitting for Shoin-zukuri architecture into that fitting for a thatched hut, in other words, wabicha (the tea ceremony accompanied by wabi (an unique aesthetic sense that finds surpassing beauty and deep significance in what is humble or commonplace and appears natural or artless)).</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除カッコ修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="48">
<sen id="311">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>金碧障壁画・風俗画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kinpeki-shoheki-ga&quot; (Shoheki-ga using gold-foil-pressed paper)/&quot;Fuzoku-ga&quot; (Genre painting)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kinpeki-shoheki-ga&quot; (Shoheki-ga using gold-foil-pressed paper)/&quot;Fuzoku-ga&quot; (Genre painting)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinpeki-shoheki-ga (Shoheki-ga using gold-foil-pressed paper)/Fuzoku-ga (Genre painting)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>狩野派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kano school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kano school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kano school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>狩野永徳：『唐獅子図屏風』（宮内庁）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Eitoku KANO : &quot;Karajishi-zu byobu&quot; (The huge folding screen of Chinese lions) in the custody of the Imperial Household Agency</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Eitoku KANO : &quot;Karajishi-zu byobu&quot; (The huge folding screen of Chinese lions) in the custody of the Imperial Household Agency</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Eitoku KANO: &quot;Karajishi-zu byobu&quot; (The huge folding screen of Chinese lions) in the custody of the Imperial Household Agency</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="315">
<j>狩野山楽：『牡丹図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanraku KANO : &quot;Botan-zu&quot; (The painting of peonies)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanraku KANO : &quot;Botan-zu&quot; (The painting of peonies)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanraku KANO: &quot;Botan-zu&quot; (The painting of peonies)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="316">
<j>長谷川等伯：『松林図屏風』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tohaku HASEGAWA : &quot;Shorin-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen of Pine Trees)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tohaku HASEGAWA : &quot;Shorin-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen of Pine Trees)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tohaku HASEGAWA: &quot;Shorin-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen of Pine Trees)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="317">
<j>狩野長信：『花下遊楽図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naganobu KANO : &quot;Kaka-Yuraku-zu&quot; (Merrymaking Under the Cherry Blossoms)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naganobu KANO : &quot;Kaka-Yuraku-zu&quot; (Merrymaking Under the Cherry Blossoms)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naganobu KANO: &quot;Kaka-Yuraku-zu&quot; (Merrymaking Under the Cherry Blossoms)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="318">
<j>狩野秀頼：『高雄観風図屏風』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyori KANO : &quot;Takao Kanpu-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen of Viewing Maple Trees in Takao)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyori KANO : &quot;Takao Kanpu-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen of Viewing Maple Trees in Takao)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyori KANO: &quot;Takao Kanpu-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen of Viewing Maple Trees in Takao)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="319">
<j>『南蛮屏風』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Nanban byobu&quot; (The folding screen of South European Visitors To Japan)</e>
<cmt>・「南蛮屏風」の定訳は見つからず、翻訳者が創作で英訳を付しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Nanban byobu&quot; (The folding screen of South European Visitors To Japan)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Nanban byobu&quot; (The folding screen of South European Visitors To Japan)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="320">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="321">
<j>城郭建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Castle architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Castle architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Castle architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="322">
<j>『姫路城』（天守閣）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Himeji-jo Castle : the keep</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Himeji-jo Castle : the keep</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Himeji-jo Castle: the keep</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="323">
<j>『二条城』（書院造）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nijo-jo Castle : the Shoin-zukuri style architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nijo-jo Castle : the Shoin-zukuri style architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nijo-jo Castle: the Shoin-zukuri style architecture</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="324">
<j>『西本願寺』書院・飛雲閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishi-Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s Shoin-zukuri style architecture and Hiun-kaku Pavilion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishi-Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s Shoin-zukuri style architecture and Hiun-kaku Pavilion</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishi-Hongan-ji Temple&apos;s Shoin-zukuri style architecture and Hiun-kaku Pavilion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="325">
<j>茶道--千利休</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tea ceremony : perfected by SEN no Rikyu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tea ceremony : perfected by SEN no Rikyu</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tea ceremony: perfected by SEN no Rikyu</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="326">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handifacts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handifacts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicrafts</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="327">
<j>茶器</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Chaki&quot; (Tea utensils)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Chaki&quot; (Tea utensils)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chaki (Tea utensils)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="328">
<j>志野茶碗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shino-jawan&quot; (Shino teabowl)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shino-jawan&quot; (Shino tea bowl)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shino-jawan (Shino tea bowl)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="329">
<j>楽茶碗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Raku-jawan&quot; (Raku teabowl)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Raku-jawan&quot; (Raku tea bowl)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Raku-jawan (Raku tea bowl)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="330">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="331">
<j>如庵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Joan&quot; (a teahouse in Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Joan&quot; (a teahouse in Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Joan (a teahouse in Aichi Prefecture)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="332">
<j>妙喜庵茶室</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Myoki-an Temple&apos;s teahouse</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Myoki-an Temple&apos;s teahouse</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Myoki-an Temple&apos;s teahouse</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="49">
<sen id="333">
<j>江戸時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="50">
<sen id="334">
<j>徳川家康が征夷大将軍に任ぜられたのは1603年だが、美術史上の区分では、大坂の役で豊臣氏が滅亡し、江戸幕府の支配体制が確立した1615年を桃山時代と江戸時代の区切りとすることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though it was in A.D. 1603 when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed &quot;seii taishogun&quot; (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians), the boundary between the Momoyama period and the Edo period is commonly thought to have been in A.D. 1615, when the Toyotomi clan fell in &quot;Osaka no Eki&quot; (The Siege of Osaka) and the ruling system of the Edo bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though it was in A.D. 1603 when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed &quot;seii taishogun&quot; (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians), the boundary between the Momoyama period and the Edo period is commonly thought to have been in A.D. 1615, when the Toyotomi clan fell in &quot;Osaka no Eki&quot; (The Siege of Osaka) and the ruling system of the Edo bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though it was in A.D. 1603 when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed seii taishogun (literally, great general who subdues the barbarians), the boundary between the Momoyama period and the Edo period is commonly thought to have been in A.D. 1615, when the Toyotomi clan fell in Osaka no Eki (The Siege of Osaka) and the ruling system of the Edo bakufu was established.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="335">
<j>この時代の美術は多様化し、その性格を一言で言い表わすことは困難であるが、古代・中世の美術が宗教（仏教）中心であったのに比べ、著しく世俗化の傾向が強まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This period&apos;s art was so diversified as to be difficult to define its character in a word, but it could be said to become extremely popularized, compared with the art of ancient and middle ages, which was mainly occupied with religious (Buddhist) art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This period&apos;s art was so diversified as to be difficult to define its character in a word, but it could be said to become extremely popularized, compared with the art of the ancient and middle ages, which was mainly occupied with religious (Buddhist) art.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This period&apos;s art was so diversified as to be difficult to define its character in a word, but it could be said to become extremely popularized, compared with the art of the ancient and middle ages, which was mainly occupied with religious (Buddhist) art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="336">
<j>この時代は世情が一応安定し、2世紀以上にわたって大きな戦乱もなく、庶民の生活レベルも、それ以前の時代に比較すれば向上していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this period, the Japanese society was more or less stable because there was no big disturbance of war for more than two centuries, and the ordinary people&apos;s living standard was improved from that of the former periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this period, the Japanese society was more or less stable because there was no big disturbance of war for more than two centuries, and the ordinary people&apos;s living standard was improved from that of the former periods.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this period, the Japanese society was more or less stable because there was no big disturbance of war for more than two centuries, and the ordinary people&apos;s living standard was improved from that of the former periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="337">
<j>そのため、美術の享受者層も増大し、寺社、公家、武家などに加え、裕福な町人層が有力なパトロンとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the stratum of the art beneficiaries became wider, in other words, the rich merchant class entered the art community - almost occupied by temples, shrines, court nobles, and samurai until then - as the powerful patron.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the stratum of the art beneficiaries became wider, in other words, the rich merchant class entered the art community - almost occupied by temples, shrines, court nobles, and samurai until then - as a powerful patron.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the stratum of the art beneficiaries became wider, in other words, the rich merchant class entered the art community - almost occupied by temples, shrines, court nobles, and samurai until then - as a powerful patron.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="338">
<j>さらには、同じ作品を複数生産できる版画という方式の流布により、浮世絵のような町人の手に届く芸術が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the spread of the reproducible method of &quot;hanga&quot; (wood printing) gave birth to the new art, including &quot;ukiyoe&quot; (Japanese woodblock prints), which was within reach of the merchant.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the spread of the mass production method of &quot;hanga&quot; (wood printing) gave birth to a new art, including &quot;ukiyoe&quot; (Japanese woodblock prints), which was within reach of the merchant.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the spread of the mass production method of hanga (wood printing) gave birth to a new art, including ukiyoe (Japanese woodblock prints), which was within reach of the merchant.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="339">
<j>文化の中心は上方（京都・大阪）と江戸に二分される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The center stages of the culture were &quot;Kamigata&quot; (Kyoto and Osaka area) and Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The center stages of the culture were &quot;Kamigata&quot; (Kyoto and Osaka area) and Edo.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The center stages of the culture were Kamigata (Kyoto and Osaka area) and Edo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="340">
<j>幕府開設当初、江戸の地はひなびた場所であり、上方が文化の先進地域であったが、やがて諸国の人材が集まる江戸に美術の担い手が集まるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Edo bakufu was founded, Edo was just a rural area, while Kamigata was the cultural frontline, but before long, Edo began to attract artists, because Edo became the mecca of local talents in other fields as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Edo bakufu was founded, Edo was just a rural area, while Kamigata was the cultural front line, but before long, Edo began to attract artists, because Edo became the mecca of local talents in other fields as well.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Edo bakufu was founded, Edo was just a rural area, while Kamigata was the cultural front line, but before long, Edo began to attract artists, because Edo became the mecca of local talents in other fields as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="341">
<j>各地方においても陶磁、漆工芸など独自の工芸品が生産されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Local domains began to produce their own handicrafts, such as ceramic ware and lacquer works.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Local domains began to produce their own handicrafts, such as ceramic ware and lacquer works.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Local domains began to produce their own handicrafts, such as ceramic ware and lacquer works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="51">
<sen id="342">
<j>寛永文化（前期）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanei culture (in the early stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanei culture (in the early stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanei culture (in the early stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="343">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="344">
<j>御用絵師</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Goyo-eshi&quot; (Purveying painter to the regime)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Goyo-eshi&quot; (Purveying painter to the regime)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goyo-eshi (Purveying painter to the regime)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="345">
<j>狩野派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kano school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kano school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kano school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="346">
<j>狩野探幽：『探幽縮図』（京都国立博物館ほか）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tanyu KANO : &quot;Tanyu shukuzu&quot; (reduced-size copies made by Tanyu) owned by Kyoto National Museum and others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tanyu KANO : &quot;Tanyu shukuzu&quot; (reduced-size copies made by Tanyu) owned by Kyoto National Museum and others</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tanyu KANO: &quot;Tanyu shukuzu&quot; (reduced-size copies made by Tanyu) owned by Kyoto National Museum and others</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="347">
<j>狩野山雪：『雪汀水禽図』（京都国立博物館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sansetsu NANO : &quot;Settei-Suikin-zu&quot; (Waterfowl by Snowy Shore) owned by Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sansetsu NANO : &quot;Settei-Suikin-zu&quot; (Waterfowl by Snowy Shore) owned by Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sansetsu NANO: &quot;Settei-Suikin-zu&quot; (Waterfowl by Snowy Shore) owned by Kyoto National Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="348">
<j>土佐派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tosa school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tosa school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tosa school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="349">
<j>土佐光起：『三十六歌仙図屏風』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuoki TOSA : The folding screen of Thirty-six Immortal Poets</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuoki TOSA : The folding screen of Thirty-six Immortal Poets</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuoki TOSA: &quot;The folding screen of Thirty-six Immortal Poets&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="350">
<j>住吉派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sumiyoshi school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sumiyoshi school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sumiyoshi school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="351">
<j>住吉如慶：『源氏物語画帖』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jokei SUMIYOSHI : Tale of Genji Album</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jokei SUMIYOSHI : Tale of Genji Album</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jokei SUMIYOSHI: &quot;Tale of Genji Album&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="352">
<j>風俗画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fuzoku-ga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fuzoku-ga</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fuzoku-ga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="353">
<j>岩佐又兵衛：『三十六歌仙図額』--浮世絵の開祖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Matabei IWASA : The maker of the Portraits of Thirty-six Immortal Poets, and the founder of ukiyoe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Matabei IWASA : The maker of the Portraits of Thirty-six Immortal Poets, and the founder of ukiyoe</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Matabei IWASA: The maker of &quot;the Portraits of Thirty-six Immortal Poets,&quot; and the founder of ukiyoe</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="354">
<j>絵画・工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Painting and artifact</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Painting and artifact</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Painting and artifact</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="355">
<j>琳派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rin school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rin school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rin school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="356">
<j>本阿弥光悦：『舟橋蒔絵硯箱』（東京国立博物館）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koetsu HONAMI : &quot;Funabashi Makie Suzuribako&quot; (Writing Box with Pontoon Bridge) owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koetsu HONAMI : &quot;Funabashi Makie Suzuribako&quot; (Writing Box with Pontoon Bridge) owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koetsu HONAMI: &quot;Funabashi Makie Suzuribako&quot; (Writing Box with Pontoon Bridge) owned by Tokyo National Museum</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="357">
<j>俵屋宗達：『風神雷神図屏風』（建仁寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotatsu TAWARAYA : &quot;Fujin Raijin-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screens of Wind God and Thunder God) owned by Kennin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotatsu TAWARAYA : &quot;Fujin Raijin-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screens of Wind God and Thunder God) owned by Kennin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotatsu TAWARAYA: &quot;Fujin Raijin-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screens of Wind God and Thunder God) owned by Kennin-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="358">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="359">
<j>日光東照宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nikko Tosho-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nikko Tosho-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nikko Tosho-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="360">
<j>桂離宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katsura Imperial Villa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katsura Imperial Villa</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katsura Imperial Villa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="361">
<j>知恩院三門・本堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chion-in Temple&apos;s San-mon Gate and &quot;Hon-do Hall&quot; (Main Hall)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chion-in Temple&apos;s San-mon Gate and &quot;Hon-do Hall&quot; (Main Hall)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chion-in Temple&apos;s San-mon Gate and Hon-do Hall (Main Hall)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="52">
<sen id="362">
<j>元禄文化（中期）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genroku culture (in the middle stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genroku culture (in the middle stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genroku culture (in the middle stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="363">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="364">
<j>文人画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literati paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literati paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literati paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="365">
<j>祇園南海</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nankai GION</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nankai GION</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nankai GION</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="366">
<j>柳沢淇園</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kien YANAGISAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kien YANAGISAWA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kien YANAGISAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="367">
<j>彭城百川</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hyakusen SAKAKI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hyakusen SAKAKI</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hyakusen SAKAKI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="368">
<j>版画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanga</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="369">
<j>浮世絵--錦絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukiyoe (&quot;Nishikie&quot; [Colored woodblock print])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukiyoe (&quot;Nishikie&quot; [Colored woodblock print])</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukiyoe (Nishikie (Colored woodblock print))</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除カッコ修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="370">
<j>菱川師宣：『見返り美人図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moronobu HISHIKAWA : Looking Back Beauty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moronobu HISHIKAWA : Looking Back Beauty</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moronobu HISHIKAWA: &quot;Looking Back Beauty&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="371">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="372">
<j>円空：『聖観音菩薩像』（清峯寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enku : Sho-Kannon Bosatsu-zo enshrined in Seiho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enku : Sho-Kannon Bosatsu-zo enshrined in Seiho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enku: &quot;Sho-Kannon Bosatsu-zo&quot; enshrined in Seiho-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="373">
<j>絵画・工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings and artifacts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings and artifacts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings and artifacts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="374">
<j>琳派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rin school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rin school</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rin school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="375">
<j>尾形光琳：『紅白梅図屏風』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korin OGATA : &quot;Kohakubai-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of Red and White Plum Blossoms)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Korin OGATA : &quot;Kohakubai-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of Red and White Plum Blossoms)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Korin OGATA: &quot;Kohakubai-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of Red and White Plum Blossoms)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="376">
<j>酒井抱一：『風雨草花図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoitsu SAKAI : &quot;Fuu-u Soka-zu&quot; (Grasses and Flowers in the Wind and Rain)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoitsu SAKAI : &quot;Fuu-u Soka-zu&quot; (Grasses and Flowers in the Wind and Rain)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoitsu SAKAI: &quot;Fuu-u Soka-zu&quot; (Grasses and Flowers in the Wind and Rain)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="377">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Artifacts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Artifacts</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Artifacts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="378">
<j>野々村仁清--色絵陶器--京焼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninsei NONOMURA : The maker of &quot;iro-e toki&quot; (painted earthen vessel) called &quot;Kyoyaki&quot; (Kyoto-style ceramic art)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninsei NONOMURA : The maker of &quot;iro-e toki&quot; (painted earthen vessel) called &quot;Kyoyaki&quot; (Kyoto-style ceramic art)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninsei NONOMURA: The maker of iro-e toki (painted earthen vessel) called &quot;Kyoyaki&quot; (Kyoto-style ceramic art)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="379">
<j>酒井田柿右衛門--色絵磁器--有田焼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kakiemon SAKAIDA : The maker of iro-e toki called &quot;Aritayaki&quot; (Arita-style ceramic art)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kakiemon SAKAIDA : The maker of iro-e toki called &quot;Aritayaki&quot; (Arita-style ceramic art)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kakiemon SAKAIDA: The maker of iro-e toki called &quot;Aritayaki&quot; (Arita-style ceramic art)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="380">
<j>建築</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Architecture</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Architecture</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="381">
<j>東大寺金堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kon-do Hall of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kon-do Hall of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kon-do Hall of Todai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="53">
<sen id="382">
<j>化政文化（後期）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kasei culture (in the later stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kasei culture (in the later stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kasei culture (in the later stage of the Edo period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="54">
<sen id="383">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="384">
<j>文人画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Literati painting</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Literati painting</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Literati painting</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="385">
<j>与謝蕪村：『鳶烏図』--俳画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buson YOSA : The painting of crows and a black kite, which falls under &quot;haiga&quot; (simple paintings that accompany and interact with the 17 syllable poetic verse called haiku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buson YOSA : The painting of crows and a black kite, which falls under &quot;haiga&quot; (simple paintings that accompany and interact with the 17 syllable poetic verse called haiku)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buson YOSA: &quot;The painting of crows and a black kite,&quot; which falls under haiga (simple paintings that accompany and interact with the 17 syllable poetic verse called haiku)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="386">
<j>池大雅：『楼閣山水図屏風』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">IKE no Taiga : &quot;Rokaku Sansui-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen with a painting of a palace and landscape)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">IKE no Taiga : &quot;Rokaku Sansui-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen with a painting of a palace and landscape)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">IKE no Taiga: &quot;Rokaku Sansui-zu byobu&quot; (The folding screen with a painting of a palace and landscape)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="387">
<j>谷文晁：『公余探勝図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buncho TANI : &quot;Koyo Tansho-zu&quot; (The paintings of scenic spots, made during the break of his public service)</e>
<cmt>・「公余探勝図」の定訳は見つからなかったので、翻訳者が創作で英訳を付しています（その中身は「公務の合間に描いた景勝地」です）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buncho TANI : &quot;Koyo Tansho-zu&quot; (The paintings of scenic spots, made during the break of his public service)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buncho TANI: &quot;Koyo Tansho-zu&quot; (The paintings of scenic spots, made during the break of his public service)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="388">
<j>渡辺崋山：『鷹見泉石像』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE : &quot;Takami Senseki-zo&quot; (Portrait of Senseki Takami)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazan WATANABE : &quot;Takami Senseki-zo&quot; (Portrait of Senseki Takami)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazan WATANABE: &quot;Takami Senseki-zo&quot; (Portrait of Senseki Takami)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="389">
<j>曾我蕭白：『寒山拾得図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shohaku SOGA : &quot;Kanzan Jittoku-zu&quot; (The paintings of Kanzan and Jittoku)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shohaku SOGA : &quot;Kanzan Jittoku-zu&quot; (The paintings of Kanzan and Jittoku)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shohaku SOGA: &quot;Kanzan Jittoku-zu&quot; (The paintings of Kanzan and Jittoku)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="390">
<j>宮本武蔵：『布袋見闘鶏図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Musashi MIYAMOTO : &quot;Hotei Ken Tokei-zu&quot; (Hotei Watching a Cockfight)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Musashi MIYAMOTO : &quot;Hotei Ken Tokei-zu&quot; (Hotei Watching a Cockfight)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Musashi MIYAMOTO: &quot;Hotei Ken Tokei-zu&quot; (Hotei Watching a Cockfight)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="391">
<j>写生画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Shasei-ga&quot; (Realistic sketches of nature)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shasei-ga&quot; (Realistic sketches of nature)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shasei-ga (Realistic sketches of nature)</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="392">
<j>円山応挙：『雪松図屏風』--円山派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okyo MARUYAMA : The maker of &quot;Sessho-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of Pine Trees in the Snow), and the founder of Maruyama school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okyo MARUYAMA : The maker of &quot;Sessho-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of Pine Trees in the Snow), and the founder of the Maruyama school</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okyo MARUYAMA: The maker of &quot;Sessho-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of Pine Trees in the Snow), and the founder of the Maruyama school</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="393">
<j>呉春：『白梅図屏風』--四条派</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Goshun : The maker of &quot;Hakubai-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of White Plum Blossoms), and the founder of Shijo school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Goshun : The maker of &quot;Hakubai-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of White Plum Blossoms), and the founder of the Shijo school</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Goshun: The maker of &quot;Hakubai-zu byobu&quot; (The Folding Screen of White Plum Blossoms), and the founder of the Shijo school</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="394">
<j>伊藤若冲：『群鶏図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jakuchu ITO : &quot;Gunkei-zu&quot; (The painting of fowls)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jakuchu ITO : &quot;Gunkei-zu&quot; (The painting of fowls)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jakuchu ITO: &quot;Gunkei-zu&quot; (The painting of fowls)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="395">
<j>長沢芦雪：『竜虎図襖』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rosetsu NAGASAWA : &quot;Ryuko-zu fusuma&quot; (The Sliding Door of Dragon and Tiger)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rosetsu NAGASAWA : &quot;Ryuko-zu fusuma&quot; (The Sliding Door of Dragon and Tiger)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rosetsu NAGASAWA: &quot;Ryuko-zu fusuma&quot; (The Sliding Door of Dragon and Tiger)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="396">
<j>洋風画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western-influenced works</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western-influenced works</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western-influenced works</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="397">
<j>陰影法・透視図法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shadow method/Perspective drawing technique</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shadow method/Perspective drawing technique</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shadow method/perspective drawing technique</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="398">
<j>司馬江漢：『三囲景図』--エッチング</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokan SHIBA : &quot;Mimeguri Kei-zu&quot; (Landscape of Mimeguri), in which the technique of etching was used</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokan SHIBA : &quot;Mimeguri Kei-zu&quot; (Landscape of Mimeguri), in which the technique of etching was used</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokan SHIBA: &quot;Mimeguri Kei-zu&quot; (Landscape of Mimeguri), in which the technique of etching was used</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="399">
<j>平賀源内：『西洋婦人像』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gennai HIRAGA : The painting of European Woman</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gennai HIRAGA : The painting of European Woman</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gennai HIRAGA: &quot;The painting of European Woman&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="400">
<j>版画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hanga</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hanga</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hanga</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="401">
<j>浮世絵--錦絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukiyoe (Nishikie)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukiyoe (Nishikie)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukiyoe (Nishikie)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="402">
<j>鈴木春信：『お仙茶屋』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Harunobu SUZUKI : &quot;Osen Chaya&quot; (Osen Teahouse)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Harunobu SUZUKI : &quot;Osen Chaya&quot; (Osen Teahouse)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Harunobu SUZUKI: &quot;Osen Chaya&quot; (Osen Teahouse)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="403">
<j>喜多川歌麿：『婦人図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Utamaro KITAGAWA : &quot;Fujin-zu&quot; (Portrait of a Woman)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Utamaro KITAGAWA : &quot;Fujin-zu&quot; (Portrait of a Woman)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Utamaro KITAGAWA: &quot;Fujin-zu&quot; (Portrait of a Woman)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="404">
<j>東洲斎写楽：『二世大谷鬼次の奴江戸兵衛』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sharaku TOSHUSAI : Otani Oniji Ⅱ in the role of Yakko Edobe</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sharaku TOSHUSAI : Otani Oniji Ⅱ in the role of Yakko Edobe</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sharaku TOSHUSAI: &quot;Otani Oniji Ⅱ in the role of Yakko Edobe&quot;</e>
<cmt>スペース削除&quot;補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="405">
<j>葛飾北斎：『富嶽三十六景』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA : &quot;Fugaku Sanjurokkei&quot; (Thirty-six Sceneries of Mt. Fuji)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA : &quot;Fugaku Sanjurokkei&quot; (Thirty-six Sceneries of Mt. Fuji)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA: &quot;Fugaku Sanjurokkei&quot; (Thirty-six Sceneries of Mt. Fuji)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="406">
<j>歌川広重：『東海道五十三次』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshige UTAGAWA : &quot;Tokaido Gojusan-tsugi&quot; (Fifty-three stages in Tokai-do Road)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshige UTAGAWA : &quot;Tokaido Gojusan-tsugi&quot; (53 stages on the Tokai-do Road)</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshige UTAGAWA: &quot;Tokaido Gojusan-tsugi&quot; (53 stages on the Tokai-do Road)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="55">
<sen id="407">
<j>近代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern age</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="408">
<j>明治時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meiji period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meiji period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="409">
<j>幕末、ヨーロッパの万国博覧会に出展した幕府や各藩の工芸品や美術品はすぐれた装飾品として絶賛され、日本の工芸へのヨーロッパからの関心が高まり、外貨を稼ぐ輸出品となる可能性が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, the shogunate and some domains put the handicrafts and art works in the European international exhibition, and they were highly praised as the excellent decorations, so that Japanese crafts attracted the attention of European people, and their export enabled Japanese to gain foreign currency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, the shogunate and some domains put handicrafts and art works in international European exhibitions, and they were highly praised as excellent decorations, so that Japanese crafts attracted the attention of European people, and their export enabled Japanese to gain foreign currency.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, the shogunate and some domains put handicrafts and art works in international European exhibitions, and they were highly praised as excellent decorations, so that Japanese crafts attracted the attention of European people, and their export enabled Japanese to gain foreign currency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="410">
<j>しかし、日本には西洋のような「美術」と「工芸」の厳然たる区別は無く、日本の美術品は総じて装飾的・工芸的とみなされヨーロッパ美術よりも一段低いところに置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the clear distinction between arts and crafts seen in the West did not exist in Japan, so Japanese art, as a whole, was deemed too decorative and technical, and it was ranked a bit lower than European art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the clear distinction between arts and crafts seen in the West did not exist in Japan, so Japanese art, as a whole, was deemed too decorative and technical, and it was ranked a bit lower than European art.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the clear distinction between arts and crafts seen in the West did not exist in Japan, so Japanese art, as a whole, was deemed too decorative and technical, and it was ranked a bit lower than European art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="411">
<j>（しかし、ヨーロッパ美術界でアカデミック絵画の権威や美術と工芸の境界が揺らぎ始めたこの時期、日本の美術品は前衛的な芸術家らにジャポニズムという強力な影響を与えることとなった。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time, however, the prestige of the academic painting began to shake and the boundary between arts and crafts became obscure in the European art community, so Japanese art works greatly influenced European avant-gardists and gave birth to Japonisme.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, however, the prestige of academic paintings began to shake and the boundary between arts and crafts became obscure in the European art community, so Japanese art works greatly influenced European avant-gardists and gave birth to Japonisme.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, however, the prestige of academic paintings began to shake and the boundary between arts and crafts became obscure in the European art community, so Japanese art works greatly influenced European avant-gardists and gave birth to Japonisme.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="56">
<sen id="412">
<j>明治維新後の近代化と社会の激変によりそれまでの日本美術は大きく揺れ動いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Japanese art was also shaken by the modernization and the drastic change of the Japanese society after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And Japanese art was also shaken by the modernization and the drastic change of the Japanese society after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And Japanese art was also shaken by the modernization and the drastic change of the Japanese society after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="413">
<j>政府は早急に西洋式の「ファイン・アート」（純粋美術）を導入してヨーロッパ諸国に恥じない芸術の体裁を整えようとし、一方日本の諸派の絵画などは旧弊なものとみなされ存続の危機に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese government hurried to build a façade of &quot;geijutsu&quot; (art and other artistic skills) that could match the European countries&apos; geijutsu through the introduction of the Western-style fine arts, while the traditional Japanese paintings of various schools faced the crisis of existence because they were deemed old-fashioned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese government hurried to build a façade of &quot;geijutsu&quot; (art and other artistic skills) that could match the European countries&apos; geijutsu through the introduction of the Western-style fine arts, while the traditional Japanese paintings of various schools faced a crisis of existence because they were deemed old-fashioned.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese government hurried to build a façade of geijutsu (art and other artistic skills) that could match the European countries&apos; geijutsu through the introduction of the Western-style fine arts, while the traditional Japanese paintings of various schools faced a crisis of existence because they were deemed old-fashioned.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="414">
<j>また廃仏毀釈や大名家の没落に伴い、多くの優れた美術品が古道具市場にあふれ、美術商だった林忠正らの積極的な売買により欧米に流出しそのまま帰らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, with &quot;haibutsu-kishaku&quot; (a movement to abolish Buddhism) and the downfall of &quot;daimyo family&quot; (feudal lord family) seen notably, the market of secondhand articles began to be filled with many excellent Japanese art works, and through the aggressive intermediary contracts by Tadamasa HAYASHI and other Japanese art dealers, they flew out to the West, never to return.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, with &quot;haibutsu-kishaku&quot; (a movement to abolish Buddhism) and the downfall of &quot;daimyo family&quot; (feudal lord family) seen notably, the market of secondhand articles began to be filled with many excellent Japanese art works, and through the aggressive intermediary contracts by Tadamasa HAYASHI and other Japanese art dealers, they flew out to the West, never to return.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, with haibutsu-kishaku (a movement to abolish Buddhism) and the downfall of daimyo family (feudal lord family) seen notably, the market of secondhand articles began to be filled with many excellent Japanese art works, and through the aggressive intermediary contracts by Tadamasa HAYASHI and other Japanese art dealers, they flew out to the West, never to return.</e>
<cmt>&quot;削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="415">
<j>ただし西洋式の絵画などを導入した動機の最大のものは建築や都市計画などの設計のためというもので、工部美術学校などがその舞台となり、芸術という概念は政府にもなじみの薄いものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese government introduced the Western-style paintings and other culture mainly because it wanted to learn the architecture and city planning from the West, and the Technical Fine Arts School and others played the central role of the learning, but the government itself was not familiar with the concept of geijutsu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese government introduced the Western-style paintings and other culture mainly because it wanted to learn architecture and city planning from the West, and the Technical Fine Arts School and others played a central role in learning, but the government itself was not familiar with the concept of geijutsu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese government introduced the Western-style paintings and other culture mainly because it wanted to learn architecture and city planning from the West, and the Technical Fine Arts School and others played a central role in learning, but the government itself was not familiar with the concept of geijutsu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="416">
<j>しかしここから多くの洋画家や彫刻家が誕生する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But this westernization gave birth to many Western-style painters and sculptors in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But this westernization gave birth to many Western-style painters and sculptors in Japan.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But this westernization gave birth to many Western-style painters and sculptors in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="57">
<sen id="417">
<j>やがて近代化が一段落すると、今度は国粋主義や、民族国家としての民族独自の美術を求める動きが起こり、再び日本美術に目が向けられるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After a while, the modernization of the Japanese society reached a certain point, and instead, there occurred the movement in the opposite direction, such as nationalism and the pursuit of the art unique to Japanese that has the nation-state of its own, so Japanese art attracted people&apos;s attention once again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After a while, the modernization of Japanese society reached a certain point, and instead, there occurred a movement in the opposite direction, such as nationalism and the pursuit of art unique to Japanese that has a nation-state of its own, so Japanese art attracted people&apos;s attention once again.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After a while, the modernization of Japanese society reached a certain point, and instead, there occurred a movement in the opposite direction, such as nationalism and the pursuit of art unique to Japanese that has a nation-state of its own, so Japanese art attracted people&apos;s attention once again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="418">
<j>フェノロサや岡倉天心らは、政府から万国博出展のために「日本美術史」の解説を書いてほしいとの依頼を受け、短期間で日本の美術の通史を書き上げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese government asked Ernest Fenollosa, Tenshin OKAKURA and others to write a guide of Japanese art history, which should be attached to the art works showned in the international exhibition, so they finished writing the complete history of Japanese art in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese government asked Ernest Fenollosa, Tenshin OKAKURA and others to write a guide of Japanese art history, which should be attached to the art works shown at the international exhibition, so they finished writing the complete history of Japanese art in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese government asked Ernest Fenollosa, Tenshin OKAKURA and others to write a guide of Japanese art history, which should be attached to the art works shown at the international exhibition, so they finished writing the complete history of Japanese art in a short period of time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="419">
<j>これが現在われわれの知る日本美術史の原型であるが、その際海外への紹介に適さないとされた作家はリストから零れ落ち、長らく忘れ去られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And this is the prototype of the Japanese art history which we know today, but those artists who were deemed inappropriate to introduce to foreign countries were omitted from the list, and they got to be forgotten for a long time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And this is the prototype of Japanese art history which we know today, but those artists who were deemed inappropriate to introduce to foreign countries were omitted from the list, and they came to be forgotten for a long time.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And this is the prototype of Japanese art history which we know today, but those artists who were deemed inappropriate to introduce to foreign countries were omitted from the list, and they came to be forgotten for a long time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="58">
<sen id="420">
<j>その後フェノロサ・岡倉天心らは日本の美術の優秀性を説き、東京美術学校開校後は岡倉天心らの手により西洋画は排斥され、工部美術学校出身者らは明治美術会を作って対抗する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Fenollosa, Tenshin and others began to emphasize the superiority of Japanese art, and after Tokyo University of Arts opened, Tenshin (the university&apos;s president) and his followers excluded Western-style paintings from the university, so the graduates from Technological Fine Arts School and their sympathizers stood against it through founding Meiji Art Society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Fenollosa, Tenshin and others began to emphasize the superiority of Japanese art, and after Tokyo University of Arts opened, Tenshin (the university&apos;s president) and his followers excluded Western-style paintings from the university, the graduates from the Technological Fine Arts School and their sympathizers stood against it through founding the Meiji Art Society.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Fenollosa, Tenshin and others began to emphasize the superiority of Japanese art, and after Tokyo University of Arts opened, Tenshin (the university&apos;s president) and his followers excluded Western-style paintings from the university, the graduates from the Technological Fine Arts School and their sympathizers stood against it through founding the Meiji Art Society.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="421">
<j>林忠正による印象派の紹介や、海外留学から帰った黒田清輝らの出展で、明治美術会や洋画家らは混乱しながらもヨーロッパの最新の絵画運動を取り入れ活発な活動を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meiji Art Society, Western-style painters, and their sympathizers were thrown into confusion by the counterforce, but they were active in introducing the newest movement in the European painting, which is exemplified by Tadamasa HAYASHI&apos;s introduction of impressionists, and by the exhibition of paintings of Seiki KURODA and others who returned from the study abroad.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Art Society, Western-style painters, and their sympathizers were thrown into confusion by the counterforce, but they were active in introducing the newest movement in European painting, which is exemplified by Tadamasa HAYASHI&apos;s introduction of impressionists, and by the exhibition of paintings of Seiki KURODA and others who returned from study abroad.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Art Society, Western-style painters, and their sympathizers were thrown into confusion by the counterforce, but they were active in introducing the newest movement in European painting, which is exemplified by Tadamasa HAYASHI&apos;s introduction of impressionists, and by the exhibition of paintings of Seiki KURODA and others who returned from study abroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="422">
<j>その後天心らが東京美術学校から追放され、横山大観や下村観山らとともに日本美術院を結成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, Tenshin and his followers were in turn purged from the university, so Tenshin established the Japan Art Institute with Taikan YOKOYAMA, Kanzan SHIMOMURA and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, Tenshin and his followers were in turn purged from the university, so Tenshin established the Japan Art Institute with Taikan YOKOYAMA, Kanzan SHIMOMURA and others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, Tenshin and his followers were in turn purged from the university, so Tenshin established the Japan Art Institute with Taikan YOKOYAMA, Kanzan SHIMOMURA and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="423">
<j>また京都画壇の竹内栖鳳らをはじめ多くの日本絵画の作家らがヨーロッパに留学し、やがてこうした動きから、諸派の絵画や西洋画の影響も取り入れた新しい民族美術として日本画が誕生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And many Japanese-style painters, including Seiho TAKEUCHI (a member of the Kyoto painters&apos; community), went to Europe for study, and after learning from various schools of Japanese-style paintings and from Western-style paintings, they renewed Japanese-style painting as the national art.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And many Japanese-style painters, including Seiho TAKEUCHI (a member of the Kyoto painters&apos; community), went to Europe to study, and after learning from various schools of Japanese-style paintings and from Western-style paintings, they renewed Japanese-style painting as a national art.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And many Japanese-style painters, including Seiho TAKEUCHI (a member of the Kyoto painters&apos; community), went to Europe to study, and after learning from various schools of Japanese-style paintings and from Western-style paintings, they renewed Japanese-style painting as a national art.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="59">
<sen id="424">
<j>1907年、政府によるはじめての公募展、文部省第一回美術展覧会（文展）がおこなわれ、日本画・洋画・彫刻の各部門、新旧の作家らが一堂に展覧された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1907, the annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education - for short, &quot;Bunten&quot; in Japanese - was held for the first time by the government as the first exhibition inviting applicants from the public, and major artists both young and old from every field of Japanese-style painting, Western-style painting, and sculpture, exhibited their works at the same time in the same place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1907, the annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education - for short, &quot;Bunten&quot; in Japanese - was held for the first time by the government as the first exhibition inviting applicants from the public, and major artists both young and old from every field of Japanese-style painting, Western-style painting, and sculpture, exhibited their works at the same time in the same place.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1907, the annual art exhibition sponsored by the Ministry of Education - for short, &quot;Bunten&quot; in Japanese - was held for the first time by the government as the first exhibition inviting applicants from the public, and major artists both young and old from every field of Japanese-style painting, Western-style painting, and sculpture, exhibited their works at the same time in the same place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="60">
<sen id="425">
<j>フェノロサ・岡倉天心</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ernest Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ernest Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ernest Fenollosa and Tenshin OKAKURA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="426">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="427">
<j>日本画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="428">
<j>狩野芳崖：『悲母観音』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hogai KANO : &quot;Hibo Kannon&quot; (Avalokitesvara as a Merciful Mother)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hogai KANO : &quot;Hibo Kannon&quot; (Avalokitesvara as a Merciful Mother)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hogai KANO: &quot;Hibo Kannon&quot; (Avalokitesvara as a Merciful Mother)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="429">
<j>橋本雅邦：『白雲紅樹』『竜虎』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gaho HASHIMOTO : &quot;Hakuun Koju-zu&quot; (the painting of white clouds and autumn leaves)/&quot;Ryuko&quot; (Dragon and Tiger)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gaho HASHIMOTO : &quot;Hakuun Koju-zu&quot; (the painting of white clouds and autumn leaves)/&quot;Ryuko&quot; (Dragon and Tiger)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gaho HASHIMOTO: &quot;Hakuun Koju-zu&quot; (the painting of white clouds and autumn leaves)/&quot;Ryuko&quot; (Dragon and Tiger)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="430">
<j>富岡鉄斎：『武陵桃源』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tessai TOMIOKA : &quot;Buryo Togen&quot; (The Earthly Paradise Found By a fisherman From Buryo)</e>
<cmt>・「武陵桃源」の定訳は見つかりませんでしたので、翻訳者が創作で英訳しています（内容は「武陵（地名）の漁師が見つけた桃源郷」です）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tessai TOMIOKA : &quot;Buryo Togen&quot; (The Earthly Paradise Found By a fisherman From Buryo)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tessai TOMIOKA: &quot;Buryo Togen&quot; (The Earthly Paradise Found By a fisherman From Buryo)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="431">
<j>竹内栖鳳：『斑猫』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiho TAKEUCHI : &quot;Hanmyo&quot; (Tabby Cat)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiho TAKEUCHI : &quot;Hanmyo&quot; (Tabby Cat)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiho TAKEUCHI: &quot;Hanmyo&quot; (Tabby Cat)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="432">
<j>横山大観：『屈原』『生々流転』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA : &quot;Kutsugen&quot; (The Legendary Chinese Poet Qu Yuan)/&quot;Seisei Ruten&quot; (Metempsychosis)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taikan YOKOYAMA : &quot;Kutsugen&quot; (The Legendary Chinese Poet Qu Yuan)/&quot;Seisei Ruten&quot; (Metempsychosis)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taikan YOKOYAMA: &quot;Kutsugen&quot; (The Legendary Chinese Poet Qu Yuan)/&quot;Seisei Ruten&quot; (Metempsychosis)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="433">
<j>下村観山：『木の間の秋』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanzan SHIMOMURA : &quot;Ki no Aida no Aki&quot; (Autumn among Trees)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanzan SHIMOMURA : &quot;Ki no Aida no Aki&quot; (Autumn among Trees)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanzan SHIMOMURA: &quot;Ki no Aida no Aki&quot; (Autumn among Trees)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="434">
<j>菱田春草：『落葉』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shunso HISHIDA : &quot;Ochiba&quot; (Fallen Leaves)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shunso HISHIDA : &quot;Ochiba&quot; (Fallen Leaves)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shunso HISHIDA: &quot;Ochiba&quot; (Fallen Leaves)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="435">
<j>洋画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="436">
<j>高橋由一：『鮭』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuichi TAKAHASHI : &quot;Sake&quot; (Salmon)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuichi TAKAHASHI : &quot;Sake&quot; (Salmon)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuichi TAKAHASHI: &quot;Sake&quot; (Salmon)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="437">
<j>浅井忠：『グレーのポプラ』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chu ASAI : Poplar-trees in Grez-Sur-Loing</e>
<cmt>・「グレーのポプラ」の定訳は見つかりませんでしたので、翻訳者が創作で英訳しています（内容は「グレー・シュル・ロワン（村の名）のポプラ」です）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chu ASAI : Poplar-trees in Grez-Sur-Loing</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chu ASAI: &quot;Poplar-trees in Grez-Sur-Loing&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="438">
<j>黒田清輝：『湖畔』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seiki KURODA : &quot;Kohan&quot; (Lakeside)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seiki KURODA : &quot;Kohan&quot; (Lakeside)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seiki KURODA: &quot;Kohan&quot; (Lakeside)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="439">
<j>藤島武二</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeji FUJISHIMA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeji FUJISHIMA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeji FUJISHIMA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="440">
<j>青木繁：『海の幸』『わだつみのいろこの宮』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shigeru AOKI : &quot;Umi no Sachi&quot; (Gifts of Sea)/&quot;Wadatsumi no Iroko no Miya&quot; (Paradise Under the Sea)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shigeru AOKI : &quot;Umi no Sachi&quot; (Gifts of Sea)/&quot;Wadatsumi no Iroko no Miya&quot; (Paradise Under the Sea)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shigeru AOKI: &quot;Umi no Sachi&quot; (Gifts of Sea)/&quot;Wadatsumi no Iroko no Miya&quot; (Paradise Under the Sea)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="441">
<j>岡田三郎助</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saburosuke OKADA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saburosuke OKADA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saburosuke OKADA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="442">
<j>彫刻</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sculptures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="443">
<j>荻原碌山：『女』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuzan OGIWARA : &quot;Onna&quot; (Woman)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuzan OGIWARA : &quot;Onna&quot; (Woman)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuzan OGIWARA: &quot;Onna&quot; (Woman)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="444">
<j>高村光雲：『老猿』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koun TAKAMURA : &quot;Roen&quot; (Old Monkey)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koun TAKAMURA : &quot;Roen&quot; (Old Monkey)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koun TAKAMURA: &quot;Roen&quot; (Old Monkey)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="61">
<sen id="445">
<j>大正時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taisho period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taisho period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taisho period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="446">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="447">
<j>日本画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="448">
<j>村上華岳：『日高河清姫図』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kagaku MURAKAMI : &quot;Hidaka-gawa Kiyohime-zu&quot; (Kiyohime Crossing the Hidaka River)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kagaku MURAKAMI : &quot;Hidaka-gawa Kiyohime-zu&quot; (Kiyohime Crossing the Hidaka River)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kagaku MURAKAMI: &quot;Hidaka-gawa Kiyohime-zu&quot; (Kiyohime Crossing the Hidaka River)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="449">
<j>上村松園：『序の舞』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shoen UEMURA : &quot;Jo-no-mai&quot; (The Introductory Dance)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shoen UEMURA : &quot;Jo-no-mai&quot; (The Introductory Dance)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shoen UEMURA: &quot;Jo-no-mai&quot; (The Introductory Dance)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="450">
<j>速水御舟：『銘樹散椿』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyoshu HAYAMI : &quot;Meiju-chiritsubaki&quot; (Camellia Petals Scattering)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyoshu HAYAMI : &quot;Meiju-chiritsubaki&quot; (Camellia Petals Scattering)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyoshu HAYAMI: &quot;Meiju-chiritsubaki&quot; (Camellia Petals Scattering)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="451">
<j>土田麦僊：『舞妓林泉』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakusen TSUCHIDA : &quot;Maiko Rinsen&quot; (A Dancing Girl Named Rinsen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakusen TSUCHIDA : &quot;Maiko Rinsen&quot; (A Dancing Girl Named Rinsen)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakusen TSUCHIDA: &quot;Maiko Rinsen&quot; (A Dancing Girl Named Rinsen)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="452">
<j>洋画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="453">
<j>岸田劉生：『麗子像』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryusei KISHIDA : &quot;Reiko-zo&quot; (Portrait of Reiko)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryusei KISHIDA : &quot;Reiko-zo&quot; (Portrait of Reiko)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryusei KISHIDA: &quot;Reiko-zo&quot; (Portrait of Reiko)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="454">
<j>小出楢重：『Nの家族』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Narashige KOIDE : The Family Portrait of N</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Narashige KOIDE : The Family Portrait of N</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Narashige KOIDE: &quot;The Family Portrait of N&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="455">
<j>金山平三：『夏の内海』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heizo KANAYAMA : &quot;Natsu no Naikai&quot; (Inland Sea in Summer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heizo KANAYAMA : &quot;Natsu no Naikai&quot; (Inland Sea in Summer)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heizo KANAYAMA: &quot;Natsu no Naikai&quot; (Inland Sea in Summer)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="456">
<j>梅原龍三郎：『狩野川』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryuzaburo UMEHARA : &quot;Kano-gawa&quot; (The Kano River)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryuzaburo UMEHARA : &quot;Kano-gawa&quot; (The Kano River)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryuzaburo UMEHARA: &quot;Kano-gawa&quot; (The Kano River)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="457">
<j>安井曾太郎：『金蓉』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sotaro YASUI : Portrait of Chin-Jung</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sotaro YASUI : Portrait of Chin-Jung</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sotaro YASUI: &quot;Portrait of Chin-Jung&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;補足スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="458">
<j>佐伯祐三：『広告貼り』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yuzo SAEKI : &quot;Kokoku-bari&quot; (Advertizing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yuzo SAEKI : &quot;Kokoku-bari&quot; (Advertising)</e>
<cmt>Typo</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yuzo SAEKI: &quot;Kokoku-bari&quot; (Advertising)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="459">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handicraft</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handicraft</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicraft</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="460">
<j>民芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Folk art</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Folk art</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Folk art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="461">
<j>芹沢銈介</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Keisuke SERIZAWA</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Keisuke SERIZAWA</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Keisuke SERIZAWA</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="62">
<sen id="462">
<j>大正期新興美術運動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">New art movements in the Taisho period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">New art movements in the Taisho period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">New art movements in the Taisho period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="463">
<j>1920年代の美術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Art in 1920s</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Art in the 1920s</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Art in the 1920s</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="63">
<sen id="464">
<j>現代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Present age</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Present age</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Present age</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="465">
<j>昭和時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Showa period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Showa period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Showa period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="466">
<j>絵画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="467">
<j>日本画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-style paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="468">
<j>奥村土牛：『踊り子』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dogyu OKUMURA : &quot;Odoriko&quot; (Dancer)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dogyu OKUMURA : &quot;Odoriko&quot; (Dancer)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dogyu OKUMURA: &quot;Odoriko&quot; (Dancer)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="469">
<j>堂本印象：『訶梨帝母』『兔春野に遊ぶ』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Insho DOMOTO : &quot;Kariteimo&quot; (the Indian deity hariti, a protector of children)/&quot;Usagi Haruno ni Asobu&quot; (Rabbits Play in a Spring Field)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Insho DOMOTO : &quot;Kariteimo&quot; (the Indian deity hariti, a protector of children)/&quot;Usagi Haruno ni Asobu&quot; (Rabbits Play in a Spring Field)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Insho DOMOTO: &quot;Kariteimo&quot; (the Indian deity hariti, a protector of children)/&quot;Usagi Haruno ni Asobu&quot; (Rabbits Play in a Spring Field)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="470">
<j>東山魁夷：『濤声』『山雲』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaii HIGASHIYAMA : &quot;Tosei &quot; (Sound of Wave)/&quot;Sanun&quot; (Mountain Clouds)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaii HIGASHIYAMA : &quot;Tosei &quot; (Sound of Wave)/&quot;Sanun&quot; (Mountain Clouds)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaii HIGASHIYAMA: &quot;Tosei &quot; (Sound of Wave)/&quot;Sanun&quot; (Mountain Clouds)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="471">
<j>洋画</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Western-style paintings</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="472">
<j>小磯良平：『斉唱』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryohei KOISO : &quot;Seisho&quot; (Singing in Unison)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryohei KOISO : &quot;Seisho&quot; (Singing in Unison)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryohei KOISO: &quot;Seisho&quot; (Singing in Unison)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="473">
<j>前田寛治：『棟梁の家族』『海』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanji MAETA : &quot;Toryo no Kazoku&quot; (The Family of the Boss)/&quot;Umi&quot; (Sea)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanji MAETA : &quot;Toryo no Kazoku&quot; (The Family of the Boss)/&quot;Umi&quot; (Sea)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanji MAETA: &quot;Toryo no Kazoku&quot; (The Family of the Boss)/&quot;Umi&quot; (Sea)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="474">
<j>林武：『梳る女』</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takeshi HAYASHI : &quot;Kushikezuru Onna&quot; (Woman Combing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takeshi HAYASHI : &quot;Kushikezuru Onna&quot; (Woman Combing)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takeshi HAYASHI: &quot;Kushikezuru Onna&quot; (Woman Combing)</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="475">
<j>工芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Handifact</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Handifact</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Handicraft</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="476">
<j>陶芸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ceramic art</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ceramic art</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ceramic art</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="477">
<j>富本憲吉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kenkichi TOMIMOTO</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kenkichi TOMIMOTO</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kenkichi TOMIMOTO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="478">
<j>河井寛次郎</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanjiro KAWAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanjiro KAWAI</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanjiro KAWAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="64">
<sen id="479">
<j>平成時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heisei period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heisei period</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heisei period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), カリン酒(id:175842), Si-take.(id:91094), Eskimbot(id:29676), Urania(id:7213), Kam47625(id:64100), Greenland4(id:114494), El bot de la dieta(id:181702), Towersmidland(id:87195), ReijiYamashina(id:29567), Dorpouter(id:88667), Blowback(id:173308), Nevylax(id:38464), Ko-ken(id:49348), Rei-bot(id:94097), 野良人(id:58574), Shimoxx(id:9332), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 20世紀(前半)美術(id:1785), Cellec(id:207246), Nopira(id:29335), 諸星団(id:72202), 222222(id:58787), Mnd(id:15140), 江口磐世☆(id:168037), 与左衛門(id:159462), 水野白楓(id:22811), Kaznov17(id:68122), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), BodhisattvaBot(id:185411), Sphl(id:122), Mooko(id:36162), YurikBot(id:18605), Wakkubox(id:30396), 福太郎(id:132415), 663highland(id:18755), トホホ川(id:50502), Bot-Schafter(id:94967), Kurohoushi(id:17174), TeaServer(id:55403), LeonardoRob0t(id:25875), LuckyStar Kid(id:79561), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>