<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>氏姓制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The System of Clans and Hereditary Titles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The System of Clans and Hereditary Titles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The System of Clans and Hereditary Titles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>氏姓制度（しせいせいど）とは、古代日本において、中央貴族、ついで地方豪族が、国家（ヤマト王権）に対する貢献度、朝廷政治上に占める地位に応じて、朝廷よりウヂの名とカバネの名とを授与され、その特権的地位を世襲した制度。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shisei Seido (the system of clans and hereditary titles) is a system made in ancient Japan in which the Imperial Court gave the nobles living in the capital and the powerful local clans a clan name and a hereditary title according to each person&apos;s degree of contribution to the state (Yamato Sovereignty) and the position the person occupies in the Government of the Imperial Court and let them kept the special privilege by the hereditary system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shisei Seido (the system of clans and hereditary titles) is a system made in ancient Japan in which the Imperial Court gave the nobles living in the capital and the powerful local clans a clan name and a hereditary title according to each person&apos;s degree of contribution to the state (Yamato Sovereignty) and the position the person occupies in the Government of the Imperial Court and let them kept the special privilege by the hereditary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shisei Seido (the system of clans and hereditary titles) is a system made in ancient Japan in which the Imperial Court gave the nobles living in the capital and the powerful local clans a clan name and a hereditary title according to each person&apos;s degree of contribution to the state (Yamato Sovereignty) and the position the person occupies in the Government of the Imperial Court and let them kept the special privilege by the hereditary system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>「氏姓の制（ウヂ・カバネのせい）」ともいい、「氏（ウヂ）・姓（カバネ）」を音読して「氏姓（しせい）」ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Uji Kabane no Sei&apos; (System of Uji and Kabane); &apos;Shisei&apos; is the Chinese style reading of the same kanji (&apos;on&apos; reading).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &apos;Uji Kabane no Sei&apos; (System of Uji and Kabane); &apos;Shisei&apos; is the Chinese style reading of the same kanji (&apos;on&apos; reading).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &apos;Uji Kabane no Sei&apos; (System of Uji and Kabane); &apos;Shisei&apos; is the Chinese style reading of the same kanji (&apos;on&apos; reading).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>大化の改新ののち、律令国家の形成におよぶと、古代の戸籍制度によって、氏姓はかつての部民（べみん）、つまり一般民衆にまで拡大され、すべての階層の国家身分を表示するものとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japan formed a nation under the ritsuryo codes after Taika Reforms, the clan names and the hereditary titles became given to Bemin (people who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty); in other words, the system of clans and hereditary system was expanded to the general public and Uji and Kabane came to a way to reveal one&apos;s social position in the hierarchy of the state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Japan formed a nation under the ritsuryo codes after Taika Reforms, the clan names and the hereditary titles became given to Bemin (people who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty); in other words, the system of clans and hereditary system was expanded to the general public and Uji and Kabane came to a way to reveal one&apos;s social position in the hierarchy of the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Japan formed a nation under the ritsuryo codes after the Taika Reforms, the clan names and the hereditary titles became given to Bemin (people who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty); in other words, the system of clans and hereditary system was expanded to the general public and Uji and Kabane came to a way to reveal one&apos;s social position in the hierarchy of the state.</e>
<cmt>冠詞をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>氏姓を有しない者は、天皇をはじめとする皇族と奴婢のみとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The person who did not have the clan (family) name and hereditary title became only members of the Imperial family including Emperor and slave.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The person who did not have the clan (family) name and hereditary title became only members of the Imperial family including Emperor and slave.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who did not have the clan (family) names and hereditary titles became only members of the Imperial family including Emperor and slaves.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしたほうが良いと思います。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>政治制度としての氏姓制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The system of clans and hereditary titles as a political system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of clans and hereditary titles as a political system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system of clans and hereditary titles as a political system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>原始共同体においては、氏族や部族が社会の単位となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the primitive community, a clan and a tribe became a social unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the primitive community, a clan and a tribe became a social unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the primitive community, a clan and a tribe became a social unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>氏姓制度の基盤は、血縁集団としての同族にあったが、それが国家の政治制度として編成し直された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basis of the system of clans and hereditary titles was an extended family as a kin group, but it was reorganized as a political system of the state.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basis of the system of clans and hereditary titles was an extended family as a kin group, but it was reorganized as a political system of the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basis of the system of clans and hereditary titles was an extended family as a kin group, but it was reorganized as a political system of the state.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>その成立時期は、5～6世紀をさかのぼらない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The formation period was between the fifth century and the sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The formation period was between the fifth century and the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The formation period was between the fifth century and the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同族のなかの特定の者が、臣（おみ）、 連（むらじ）、伴造（とものみやつこ）、国造（くにのみやつこ）、百八十部（ももあまりやそのとも）、県主（あがたぬし）などの地位をあたえられ、それに応ずる氏姓を賜ったところに特色がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic of this system of clans and hereditary titles is that a specific person within the same extended family was given a position which included Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko, Momo amari yaso no tomo, Agata-nushi and the Imperial Court granted the clan name and the hereditary title that corresponded each position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristic of this system of clans and hereditary titles is that a specific person within the same extended family was given a position which included Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko, Momo amari yaso no tomo, Agata-nushi and the Imperial Court granted the clan name and the hereditary title that corresponded each position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic of this system of clans and hereditary titles is that a specific person within the same extended family was given a position which included Omi, Muraji, Tomo no miyatsuko, Kuni no miyatsuko, Momo amari yaso no tomo and Agata-nushi, and the Imperial Court granted the clan name and the hereditary title that corresponded each position.</e>
<cmt>コンマ→and</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>各姓（カバネ）は以下のごとくである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is a list of each kabane (each hereditary title) and the major clans given this hereditary title:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is a list of each kabane (each hereditary title) and the major clans given this hereditary title:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a list of each kabane (each hereditary title) and the major clans given this hereditary title:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="10">
<j>臣（おみ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Omi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Omi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Omi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>葛城氏（かつらぎ）、平群氏（へぐり）、巨勢氏（こせ）、春日氏（かすが）、蘇我氏（そが）のように、ヤマト（奈良盆地周辺）の地名を氏（ウヂ）の名とし、かつては王家と並ぶ立場にあり、大和王権においても最高の地位を占めた豪族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans who were given the title of Omi were powerful clans that were once in the position to stand with the royal family side by side and who occupied the highest position in the Yamato sovereign including such clans as the Katsuragi clan, Hegri clan, Kosa clan, Kasuga clan, and Soga clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans who were given the title of Omi were powerful clans that were once in the position to stand with the royal family side by side and who occupied the highest position in the Yamato sovereign including such clans as the Katsuragi clan, Hegri clan, Kosa clan, Kasuga clan, and Soga clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans who were given the title of Omi were powerful clans that were once in the position to stand on par with the royal family and occupied the highest position in the Yamato sovereign, including such clans as the Katsuragi clan, the Heguri clan, the Kose clan, the Kasuga clan, and the Soga clan (these clan names were the place names in Yamato (around Nara Basin).)</e>
<cmt>side by side→on par withwho を省略しました。theを補いました。スペルミスを修正しました。訳抜けを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="12">
<j>連（むらじ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muraji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muraji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muraji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大伴氏、物部氏、中臣氏（なかとみ）、忌部氏（いんべ）、土師氏（はじ）のように、ヤマト王権での職務を氏（ウヂ）の名とし、王家に従属する官人としての立場にあり、ヤマト王権の成立に重要な役割をはたした豪族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans who were given a position of Muraji were clans who were powerful families and who were subordinates of Yamato Sovereign as the government officials and the duty they had in the court was made their clan names and they played an important role in establishing the Yamato sovereignty; these clans included Otomo clan, Mononobe clan, Nakatomi clan, Inbe clan, and Haji clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans who were given a position of Muraji were clans from powerful families and were subordinates of Yamato Sovereign as government officials and the duty they had in the court was made with their clan names and they played an important role in establishing the Yamato sovereignty; these clans included Otomo clan, Mononobe clan, Nakatomi clan, Inbe clan, and Haji clan.</e>
<cmt>needs editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans who were given a position of Muraji were clans from powerful families and were subordinates of Yamato Sovereign as government officials and the duty they had in the court was made with their clan names and they played an important role in establishing the Yamato sovereignty; these clans included the Otomo clan, the Mononobe clan, the Nakatomi clan, the Inbe clan, and the Haji clan.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>伴造（とものみやつこ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomo no miyatsuko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomo no miyatsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomo no miyatsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>連（むらじ）とも重なり合うが、おもにそのもとでヤマト王権の各部司を分掌した豪族である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans who were given the position of Kuni no miyatsuko overlaps with those of clans who were given the position of Muraji; mainly these clans were powerful families who took the share of taking care of every division of the Yamato sovereignty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans who were given the position of Kuni no miyatsuko overlaps with those of clans who were given the position of Muraji; mainly these clans were powerful families who took the share of taking care of every division of the Yamato sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans who were given the position of Tomo no miyatsuko overlaps with those of clans who were given the position of Muraji; mainly these clans were powerful families who shared the duties of the divisions of the Yamato sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>Kuni→Tomo英文を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>秦氏（はた）、東漢氏（やまとのあや）、西文氏（かわちのあや）などの代表的な帰化氏族、それに弓削氏（ゆげ）、矢集氏（やずめ）、服部氏（はとり）、犬養氏（いぬかい）、舂米氏（つきしね）、倭文氏（しとり）などの氏（ウヂ）がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans that were given the position of Kuni no Miyatsuko included the representative naturalized clans such as Hata clan, Yamato no Aya clan, Kawachi no Aya clan as well as the clans such as the Yuge clan, Yazume clan, Hatori clan, Inukai clan, Tsukishine clan and Shitori clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans that were given the position of Kuni no Miyatsuko included the representative naturalized clans such as Hata clan, Yamato no Aya clan, Kawachi no Aya clan as well as the clans such as the Yuge clan, Yazume clan, Hatori clan, Inukai clan, Tsukishine clan and Shitori clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans that were given the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko included the representative naturalized clans such as the Hata clan, the Yamato no Aya clan, the Kawachi no Aya clan as well as the clans such as the Yuge clan, the Yazume clan, the Hatori clan, the Inukai clan, the Tsukishine clan and the Shitori clan.</e>
<cmt>Kuni→Tomotheを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>連（むらじ）、造（みやつこ）、直（あたい）、公（きみ）などの姓（カバネ）を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans who received the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko had the hereditary titles such as Muraji, Miyatsuko, Atai, and Kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans who received the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko had the hereditary titles such as Muraji, Miyatsuko, Atai, and Kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans who received the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko had the hereditary titles such as Muraji, Miyatsuko, Atai, and Kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="18">
<j>百八十部（ももあまりやそのとも）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>さらにその下位にあり、部（べ）を直接に指揮する多くの伴（とも）をさす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans that received the position of Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo were beneath the Tomo no Miyatsuko in its rank; many clans who received this title directly took control of common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans that received the position of Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo were beneath the Tomo no Miyatsuko in its rank; many clans who received this title directly took control of common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans that received the position of Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo were beneath the Tomo no Miyatsuko in its rank; many clans who received this title directly took control of common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>首（おびと）、史（ふひと）、村主（すくり）、勝（すくり）などの姓（カバネ）を称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans who received the position of Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo had the hereditary titles such as Obito, Fuhito Sukuri, and Sukuri.The clans who received the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko had the hereditary titles such as Muraji, Miyatsuko, Atai, and Kimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans who received the position of Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo had the hereditary titles such as Obito, Fuhito Sukuri, and Sukuri.The clans who received the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko had the hereditary titles such as Muraji, Miyatsuko, Atai, and Kimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans who received the position of Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo had the hereditary titles such as Obito, Fuhito Sukuri, and Sukuri.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせてtrans１の後半を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="21">
<j>国造（くにのみやつこ）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuni no Miyatsuko</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuni no Miyatsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuni no Miyatsuko</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>代表的な地方豪族をさし、一面ではヤマト王権の地方官に組みこまれ、また在地の部民（べみん）を率（ひき）いる地方的伴造の地位にある者もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clans who received the position of Kuni no Miyatsuko were representative local clans; in certain aspect they were integrated into the local offices of the Yamato Sovereignty so that there were some clans that were in the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko in local sense and took control of the common people in the region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clans who received the position of Kuni no Miyatsuko were representative local clans; in certain aspect they were integrated into the local offices of the Yamato Sovereignty so that there were some clans that were in the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko in local sense and took control of the common people in the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clans who received the position of Kuni no Miyatsuko were representative local clans; in certain aspect they were integrated into the local offices of the Yamato Sovereignty so that there were some clans that were in the position of Tomo no Miyatsuko in local sense and took control of the common people in the region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>国造には、君（きみ）、直（あたい）の姓（カバネ）が多く、中には臣（おみ）を称するものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of the hereditary titles of Kuni no Miyatsuko were Kimi, and Atai; there were some clans that had the title of Omi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of the hereditary titles of Kuni no Miyatsuko were Kimi, and Atai; there were some clans that had the title of Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of the hereditary titles of Kuni no Miyatsuko were Kimi, and Atai; there were some clans that had the title of Omi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="24">
<j>県主（あがたぬし）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Agata-nushi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Agata-nushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Agata-nushi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これより古く、かつ小範囲の族長をさすものと思われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The title of Agata-nushi existed before the Yamato regime employed the ritsuryo system; it seems Agata-nushi means the head of a region which is small in size.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The title of Agata-nushi existed before the Yamato regime employed the ritsuryo system; it seems Agata-nushi means the head of a region which is small in size.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The title of Agata-nushi existed before the Yamato regime employed the ritsuryo system; it seems Agata-nushi means the head of a region which is small in size.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>いずれも地名を氏（ウヂ）の名とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Every Agata-nushi&apos;s clan name was a place name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Every Agata-nushi&apos;s clan name was a place name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Every Agata-nushi&apos;s clan name was a place name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="27">
<j>このように、氏姓制度とは、連―伴造―伴（百八十部）という、王のもとでヤマト王権を構成し、職務を分掌し世襲する、いわゆる「負名氏」（なおいのうじ）を主体として生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As descried above, the system of clans and hereditary titles were born by making the &apos;Naoi no Uji&apos; (naming of the title revealing what the person does); people with these titles constituted the Yamato sovereign and took responsibility by working in the various functions which are hereditary and these hereditary titles included Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo in that order in the rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As descried above, the system of clans and hereditary titles were born by making the &apos;Naoi no Uji&apos; (naming of the title revealing what the person does); people with these titles constituted the Yamato sovereign and took responsibility by working in the various functions which are hereditary and these hereditary titles included Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo in that order in the rank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As descried above, the system of clans and hereditary titles was born by making the &apos;Naoi no Uji&apos; (naming of the title revealing what the person does); people with these titles constituted the Yamato sovereign and took responsibility by working in the various functions which are hereditary and these hereditary titles included Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, Momo Amari Yaso no Tomo in that order in the rank.</e>
<cmt>were→was</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そののち、臣のように、元々は王とならぶ地位にあった豪族にも及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later this giving the hereditary title was extended to the powerful clans that were originally in the same rank with the king.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later this giving the hereditary title was extended to the powerful clans that were originally in the same rank with the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later this giving the hereditary title was extended to the powerful clans that were originally in the same rank with the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="29">
<j>部民などの私有民</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">People who were privately held as Bemin who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">People who were privately held as Bemin who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">People who were privately held as Bemin who belonged to the Yamato Dynasty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>氏姓は元来はヤマト王権を構成する臣・連・伴造・国造などの支配階級が称したものである（王とその一族を除く）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Clan name and hereditary title were originally held by people of the governing classes and these titles were such as Omi, Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, Kuni no Miyatsuko composing Yamato Sovereignty and which constituted the Yamato sovereign (the king and his family were excluded).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Clan name and hereditary title were originally held by people of the governing classes and these titles were such as Omi, Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, Kuni no Miyatsuko composing Yamato Sovereignty and which constituted the Yamato sovereign (the king and his family were excluded).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Clan name and hereditary title were originally held by people of the governing classes and these titles were such as Omi, Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, Kuni no Miyatsuko composing Yamato Sovereignty (the king and his family were excluded).</e>
<cmt>and which以下を削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>しかし、6世紀には一般の民にも及んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the sixth century the clan name (family name) and the hereditary titles were also given to the common people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the sixth century the clan name (family name) and the hereditary titles were also given to the common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the sixth century the clan name (family name) and the hereditary titles were also given to the common people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>これらの一般の民は、朝廷すなわち、天皇、后妃（こうひ）、皇子らの宮、さらに臣、連らの豪族に領有・支配されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These common people were ruled and controlled by the Imperial Court namely Emperor, a queen, a consort, Prince who is a child of an Emperor, and powerful families such as Omi and Muraji, and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These common people were ruled and controlled by the Imperial Court namely Emperor, a queen, a consort, Prince who is a child of an Emperor, and powerful families such as Omi and Muraji, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These common people were ruled and controlled by the Imperial Court namely Emperor, Empress, Imperial princes, and powerful families such as Omi and Muraji, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>用語修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>そのため、一般の民の中から、朝廷に出仕して、職務の名を負う品部（しなべ）、王名、宮号を負う名代（なしろ）・子代（こしろ）、屯倉（みやけ）の耕作民である田部（たべ）などが必然的に生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, naturally there came a group of people who work for the Yamato Regime for various functions; these people included Shinabe who worked at the Imperial court, Nashiro and Koshiro who worked for king and prince, and people who work for the demesne as farmers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For this reason, naturally there came a group of people who work for the Yamato Regime for various functions; these people included Shinabe who worked at the Imperial court, Nashiro and Koshiro who worked for king and prince, and people who work for the demesne as farmers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For this reason, naturally there came a group of people who worked for the Yamato Regime for various functions; these people included Shinabe who worked at the Imperial court, Nashiro and Koshiro who worked for king and prince, and Tabe who worked for the demesne as farmers.</e>
<cmt>work→worked｢田部」の訳を補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>彼らは先進的な部民共同体の中で戸を単位に編成され、6世紀には籍帳に登載されて、正式に氏姓をもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were organized making each house one unit in an advanced community of people who belonged to the Yamato Regime; in the sixth century, their family name and hereditary titles were written down in their register book; in this way they had an official family name and hereditary title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were organized making each house one unit in an advanced community of people who belonged to the Yamato Regime; in the sixth century, their family name and hereditary titles were written down in their register book; in this way they had an official family name and hereditary title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were organized making each house one unit in an advanced community of people who belonged to the Yamato Regime; in the sixth century, their family name and hereditary titles were written down in their register book; in this way they had an official family name and hereditary title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="35">
<j>これに対し、地方豪族の支配下にあった民部（かきべ）は、在地の族長を介して、共同体のまま部（べ）に編入し、族長をへて貢納させる形のものが多かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast to people who were directly belonged to the Yamato Regime, Kakibe, who were under the control of powerful local clans needed to go through the head of the local clan and to be included to Be (group of common people to work for the Yamato Regime in various functions) while keeping their original form of community; and the service of labor offered to the Yamato Regime were often times done through the head of the clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast to people who were directly belonged to the Yamato Regime, Kakibe, who were under the control of powerful local clans needed to go through the head of the local clan and to be included to Be (group of common people to work for the Yamato Regime in various functions) while keeping their original form of community; and the service of labor offered to the Yamato Regime were often times done through the head of the clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast to people who directly belonged to the Yamato Regime, Kakibe, who were under the control of powerful local clans needed to go through the head of the local clan and to be included to Be (group of common people to work for the Yamato Regime in various functions) while keeping their original form of community; and the service of labor offered to the Yamato Regime were often done through the head of the clan.</e>
<cmt>were directly belonged →directly belongedoften times→often</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>そのため、地方豪族の支配下にあった一般の民にまで6世紀の段階で氏姓が及んでいたかどうかは定かではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, it is not certain that the giving of a clan name (family name) and a hereditary title was extended to the common people under the control of powerful local clans at the sixth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, it is not certain that the giving of a clan name (family name) and a hereditary title was extended to the common people under the control of powerful local clans at the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, it is not certain that the giving of clan names (family names) and hereditary titles was extended to the common people under the control of powerful local clans in the sixth century.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました前置詞</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>律令国家による氏の再編過程</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The reorganization process of clan by the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reorganization process of clan by the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reorganization process of clans by the Japanese nation under the ritsuryo codes</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>大化の改新により、氏姓制度による臣・連・伴造・国造を律令国家の官僚に再編し、部民を公民として、一律に国家のもとに帰属させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Yamato Regime reorganized positions such as Omi, Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, and Kuni no Miyatsuko under the system of clans and hereditary titles into bureaucrats of the nation under the ritsuryo codes and changed Bemin into citizen and made them uniformly belong to the nation by Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Yamato Regime reorganized positions such as Omi, Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, and Kuni no Miyatsuko under the system of clans and hereditary titles into bureaucrats of the nation under the ritsuryo codes and changed Bemin into citizen and made them uniformly belong to the nation by Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Yamato Regime reorganized positions such as Omi, Muraji, Tomo no Miyatsuko, and Kuni no Miyatsuko under the system of clans and hereditary titles into bureaucrats of the nation under the ritsuryo codes and changed Bemin into citizen and made them uniformly belong to the nation by Taika Reforms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="38">
<j>664年（天智3年）に、「甲子（かつし）の宣」が発せられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 664, the Imperial Edict &apos;Kasshi no Sen&apos; was issued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 664, the Imperial Edict &apos;Kasshi no Sen&apos; was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 664, the Imperial Edict &apos;Kasshi no Sen&apos; was issued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>これは、大化以来の官位を改め、大氏（おおうじ）、小氏（こうじ）、伴造氏（とものみやつこうじ）を定め、それぞれの氏上（うじのかみ）と、それに属する氏人（うじびと）の範囲を明確にしようとするものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This edict tried to revise the official rank existed since Taika Reforms in that it tried to decide Ouji, Kouji, and Tomo no Miyatsuko clan and to clarify the clan head of each clan and the extent of clan members belonging to each clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This edict tried to revise the official rank existed since Taika Reforms in that it tried to decide Ouji, Kouji, and Tomo no Miyatsuko clan and to clarify the clan head of each clan and the extent of clan members belonging to each clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This edict tried to revise the official rank existed since the Taika Reforms in that it tried to establish Ouji clan, Kouji clan, and Tomo no Miyatsuko clan and to clarify the clan head of each clan and the extent of clan members belonging to each clan.</e>
<cmt>Taika Reforms→theを付けるdecide→establishOuji clan, Kouji clanとするほうが良いと思います</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>つまり、官位の改定によって、大錦位（大氏）・小錦位（小氏）、つまり律令の四、五位以上に位置づけられる氏上をもつ氏を定めたものであり、これによって朝廷内の官位制度と全国の氏姓制度とを連動させようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, in this edict Daikini (Ouji) and Shokini (Kouji) namely clans who had the clan head whose rank can be positioned more than the fourth rank and the fifth rank in the ritsuryo system were decided; by this prescription the Emperor tried to interlock the official rank system in the Imperial Court and the system of clans and hereditary titles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, in this edict Daikini (Ouji) and Shokini (Kouji) namely clans who had the clan head whose rank can be positioned more than the fourth rank and the fifth rank in the ritsuryo system were decided; by this prescription the Emperor tried to interlock the official rank system in the Imperial Court and the system of clans and hereditary titles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, in this edict Daikini (Ouji) and Shokini (Kouji) namely clans who had the clan head whose rank can be positioned more than the fourth rank and the fifth rank in the ritsuryo system were established; by this prescription the Emperor tried to interlock the official rank system in the Imperial Court and the system of clans and hereditary titles.</e>
<cmt>decide→establish</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>さらにこのような氏上に属する氏人を父系による直系親族に限ることとし、従来の父系あるいは母系の原理による漠然とした氏の範囲を限定することとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the edict limited the clan members who belong to the clan head to the direct blood kin by the paternal line and clarified the vague definition of the extent of each clan which were either by the principle of paternal line or maternal line up to that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the edict limited the clan members who belong to the clan head to the direct blood kin by the paternal line and clarified the vague definition of the extent of each clan which were either by the principle of paternal line or maternal line up to that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the edict limited the clan members who belong to the clan head to the direct blood kin by the paternal line and clarified the vague definition of the extent of each clan which were either by the principle of paternal line or maternal line up to that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>これにより、物部弓削（もののべゆげ）、阿倍布勢（あべのふせ）、蘇我石川（そがのいしかわ）などの複姓は、これ以後原則として消滅することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, in principle, the compound surnames such as Mononobe Yuge, Be no Fuse, and Soga no Ishikawa were to disappear after this edict.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the result, in principle, the compound surnames such as Mononobe Yuge, Be no Fuse, and Soga no Ishikawa were to disappear after this edict.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, in principle, the compound surnames such as Mononobe Yuge, Abe no Fuse, and Soga no Ishikawa were to disappear after this edict.</e>
<cmt>As the result→as a resultスペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="43">
<j>684年（天武13）に、「八色の姓（やくさのかばね）」が制定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 684, &apos;Yakusa no Kabane&apos; (eight official titles to be conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 684, &apos;Yakusa no Kabane&apos; (eight official titles to be conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 684, &apos;Yakusa no Kabane&apos; (eight official titles to be conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu) was established.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>その目的は、上位の 4 姓（カバネ）、つまり真人（まひと）、朝臣（あそん）、宿禰（すくね）、忌寸（いみき）を定めることである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The object was to establish four hereditary titles of higher rank and they were Mahito, Ason, Sukune, and Imiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The object was to establish four hereditary titles of higher rank and they were Mahito, Ason, Sukune, and Imiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The object was to establish four hereditary titles of higher rank and they were Mahito, Ason, Sukune, and Imiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>真人は、継体天皇より数えて5世以内の世代の氏に与えられたといわれ、皇子・諸王につぐ皇親氏族を特定したので、飛鳥浄御原令で官位を皇子・諸王と貴族（諸臣）とで区別したことと共通する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the rank of Mahito is given to clans that are within the fifth generation from the Emperor Keitai and in this way clans close to the Imperial Family that are next to princes, princes who did not receive any proclamation to be an Imperial prince were specified; this method is common with the Asuka Kiyomihara Code (a collection of governing rules compiled and promulgated in 689 [late Asuka period]) in which the Code distinguished the official rank between princes, princes who did not receive any proclamation to be an imperial prince and nobles who served the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the rank of Mahito is given to clans that are within the fifth generation from the Emperor Keitai and in this way clans close to the Imperial Family that are next to princes, princes who did not receive any proclamation to be an Imperial prince were specified; this method is common with the Asuka Kiyomihara Code (a collection of governing rules compiled and promulgated in 689 [late Asuka period]) in which the Code distinguished the official rank between princes, princes who did not receive any proclamation to be an imperial prince and nobles who served the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the rank of Mahito is given to clans that are within the fifth generation from the Emperor Keitai and in this way clans close to the Imperial Family that are next to princes, princes who did not receive any proclamation to be an Imperial prince were specified; this method is common with the Asuka Kiyomihara Code (a collection of governing rules compiled and promulgated in 689 [late Asuka period]) in which the Code distinguished the official rank between princes, princes who did not receive any proclamation to be an imperial prince and nobles who served the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>したがって、貴族の姓（カバネ）としては、朝臣、宿禰、忌寸の三つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the hereditary titles for nobles were Ason, Sukune, and Imiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the hereditary titles for nobles were Ason, Sukune, and Imiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the hereditary titles for nobles were Ason, Sukune, and Imiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>以上が「甲子の宣」の大氏、小氏、伴造氏の発展形であり、その間にさらに氏族の再編が進められ、朝臣52氏、宿禰50氏、忌寸11氏に収（おさ）められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What described above are a developed form of Ouji, Kouji, and Tomo no Miyatsuko in &apos;Kasshi no Sen&apos; and the Imperial Court further reorganized and 52 clans of Ason, 50 clans of Sukune, and 11 clans of Imiki were included in the hereditary titles for nobles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those described above are a developed form of Ouji, Kouji, and Tomo no Miyatsuko in &apos;Kasshi no Sen&apos; and the Imperial Court further reorganized and 52 clans of Ason, 50 clans of Sukune, and 11 clans of Imiki were included in the hereditary titles for nobles.</e>
<cmt>needs editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those described above are a developed form of Ouji, Kouji, and Tomo no Miyatsuko in &apos;Kasshi no Sen&apos; and the clan system was further reorganized to include 52 clans of Ason, 50 clans of Sukune, and 11 clans of Imiki.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>大宝律令（701年）で、貴族の三位以上と四、五位の官位にともなう特権が明確にされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 701, with Taiho Code a special privilege for nobles above the third and for bureaucrats above the fourth and fifth office ranks was made clear.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 701, with Taiho Code a special privilege for nobles above the third and for bureaucrats above the fourth and fifth office ranks was made clear.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 701, with the Taiho Code a special privilege for nobles above the third and for bureaucrats above the fourth and fifth office ranks was made clear.</e>
<cmt>冠詞をつけました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>これに対応する氏姓も一応完成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the clan name and hereditary titles corresponding to the above privilege was also completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the clan name and hereditary titles corresponding to the above privilege was also completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan names and hereditary titles corresponding to the above privilege were also completed.</e>
<cmt>Withを削除しました。複数形</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>地方豪族についても、702年（大宝 2）、諸国国造の氏姓を政府に登録することによって、中央豪族と同様の対応がなされたものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in 702 the same treatment with the powerful clans in the capital was made for the powerful local clans by letting the powerful local clans to register the clan name and hereditary title of Kuni no Miyatsuko in the various provinces to the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in 702 the same treatment with the powerful clans in the capital was made for the powerful local clans by letting the powerful local clans to register the clan name and hereditary title of Kuni no Miyatsuko in the various provinces to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in 702 the same treatment with the powerful clans in the capital was made for the powerful local clans by letting the powerful local clans to register the clan name and hereditary title of Kuni no Miyatsuko in the various provinces to the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="51">
<j>一般の公民については、670年（天智9）の古代の戸籍制度、690年（持統4）の古代の戸籍制度によって、すべて戸籍に登載されることとなり、部姓を主とする氏姓制度が完成されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the general public, every one was to be registered in the family register by the ancient family registration system of 670 and the ancient family registration system of 689; thus, with the system of clans and hereditary titles of which the hereditary title of Be was predominant was completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the general public, every one was to be registered in the family register by the ancient family registration system of 670 and the ancient family registration system of 689; thus, with the system of clans and hereditary titles of which the hereditary title of Be was predominant was completed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the general public, every one was to be registered in the family register by the ancient family registration system of 670 and the ancient family registration system of 690; thus, with the system of clans and hereditary titles of which the hereditary title of Be was predominant was completed.</e>
<cmt>年号の誤りを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>しかしながら、現存する702年の大宝2年籍に、氏姓を記入されていない者、国造族、県主族などと記された者がかなり存在するため、このとき、まだ無姓の者、族姓の者が多数いたことが伺（うかが）える。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the existing register of Taiho 2 (7020) contains the parts in which family name and hereditary title were not written down; also there were considerable number of cases in which the name of a group such as Kuni no Miyatsuko group, Agatanushi group were written down; therefore, we can assume that there were many who did not have their own individual title and people who used the group name, to which they identified themselves as his hereditary title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the existing register of Taiho 2 (the year 702) contains the parts in which family name and hereditary title were not written down; also there were considerable number of cases in which the name of a group such as Kuni no Miyatsuko group, Agatanushi group were written down; therefore, we can assume that there were many who did not have their own individual title and people who used the group name, to which they identified themselves as his hereditary title.</e>
<cmt>needs editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the existing register of Taiho 2 (the year 702) contains the parts in which family name and hereditary title were not written down; also there were considerable number of cases in which the name of a group such as Kuni no Miyatsuko group, Agatanushi group was written down; therefore, we can assume that there were many who did not have their own individual title and people who used the group name, to which they identified themselves as his hereditary title.</e>
<cmt>were→was</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="53">
<j>757年（天平宝字1）、戸籍に無姓の者と族姓の者とをそのまま記（しる）すことをやめることとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 757, the Imperial government decided not to write down people with no hereditary title and people with group title as it is into the family register</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 757, the Imperial government decided not to write down people with no hereditary title and people with group title as it is into the family register</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 757, the Imperial government decided not to write down people with no hereditary title and people with group title as it is into the family register</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>これは地方豪族の配下の百姓について以下のことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This shows about peasants under powerful local clans.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This shows about peasants under powerful local clans.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This shows the following about peasants under powerful local clans.</e>
<cmt>☆原文が分割されて点で終っていたので、文末を変更して一文にしました。英文を修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="55">
<j>所属が定まらず無姓のままの者がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some peasants did not have kabane (hereditary title) because they were not under any powerful local clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some peasants did not have kabane (hereditary title) because they were not under any powerful local clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some peasants did not have kabane (hereditary title) because they were not under any powerful local clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>国造、県主の共同体に属することを示すことによって族姓を仮称させた者がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were people who made the group they belonged to kabane (hereditary title) tentatively by showing that they belonged to the community of Kuni no Miyatsuko or the community of Agatanushi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were people who made the group they belonged to kabane (hereditary title) tentatively by showing that they belonged to the community of Kuni no Miyatsuko or the community of Agatanushi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were people who were made to tentatively identify thenselves using their group names by showing that they belonged to the community of Kuni no Miyatsuko or the community of Agatanushi.</e>
<cmt>☆原文の内容に合わせて修正しました☆原文が分割されて点で終っていたので、文末を変更して一文にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>姓を与えられていない新しい帰化人がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There were newly naturalized people to whom a hereditary title was not given.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were newly naturalized people to whom a hereditary title was not given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were newly naturalized people to whom a hereditary title was not given.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>このようなことがが存在していたことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It shows that these things existed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It shows that these things existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It shows that these things existed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>そして、これ以後、このような者たちには正式に氏姓が与えられるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The clan name and hereditary title were given to such people officially after this.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The clan name and hereditary title were given to such people officially after this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The clan name and hereditary title were given to such people officially after this.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="60">
<j>8～9世紀において改賜姓がさかんに行われているのは、八色の姓において、上級の氏姓にもれた下級の身分の者や、これらの農民を主な対象としたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period between the eighth century and the ninth century there were many changes made in the hereditary titles; this change was geared to the people with the lower social position who were excluded from the rank of higher hereditary position in the Yakusa no Kabane Reform as well as these peasants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period between the eighth century and the ninth century there were many changes made in the hereditary titles; this change was geared to the people with the lower social position who were excluded from the rank of higher hereditary position in the Yakusa no Kabane Reform as well as these peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period between the eighth century and the ninth century there were many changes made in the hereditary titles; this change was geared to the people with the lower social position who were excluded from the rank of higher hereditary position in the Yakusa no Kabane Reform as well as these peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>その順位は、1. 無姓、2. →造、公、史、勝、村主、拘登（ひと）、3. →連　というようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The order of Kabane (the hereditary title) is 1. no Kabane, 2. Miyatsuko, Kimi, Fuhito, Sukuri, Suguri, Hito, 3. Muraji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The order of Kabane (the hereditary title) is 1. no Kabane, 2. Miyatsuko, Kimi, Fuhito, Sukuri, Suguri, Hito, 3. Muraji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The order of Kabane (the hereditary title) is 1. no Kabane, 2. Miyatsuko, Kimi, Fuhito, Sukuri, Suguri, Hito, 3. Muraji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="62">
<j>これは、天武朝において氏上に相当する氏が八色の姓に改姓する前段階として、まず連への改姓が行われ、この連＝小錦位以上を基点として、忌寸以上の四つの姓へ改められたことと同様の対応である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the same treatment with the changes made in the Imperial Court of Emperor Tenmu in which the Kabane of the clan corresponding to the head of clan was changed into Muraji as the preliminary step before to get to Yakusa no Kabane (eight official titles conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu in 684); Emperor Tenmu made this Muraji (above the rank of Shokini) a base point and changed into four hereditary titles of above Imiki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the same treatment with the changes made in the Imperial Court of Emperor Tenmu in which the Kabane of the clan corresponding to the head of clan was changed into Muraji as the preliminary step before to get to Yakusa no Kabane (eight official titles conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu in 684); Emperor Tenmu made this Muraji (above the rank of Shokini) a base point and changed into four hereditary titles of above Imiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the same treatment with the changes made in the Imperial Court of Emperor Tenmu in which the Kabane of the clan corresponding to the head of clan was changed into Muraji as the preliminary step before to get to Yakusa no Kabane (eight official titles conferred upon nobles by Emperor Tenmu in 684); Emperor Tenmu made this Muraji (above the rank of Shokini) a base point and changed into four hereditary titles of above Imiki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="63">
<j>氏上である忌寸以上についても、補足的な氏姓の変更が行われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Regarding the above Imiki that is the head of a clan, supplemental change of the clan name and hereditary title was made.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Regarding the above Imiki that is the head of a clan, supplemental change of the clan name and hereditary title was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Regarding the above Imiki that is the head of a clan, supplemental change of the clan name and hereditary title was made.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>氏の名において春日より大春日、中臣より大中臣への変更、また宿禰から大宿禰への変更が行われるなどしたため、氏姓の制は、全般的に、より緻密に浸透することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the clan name the changes of Kasuga to Okasuga and Nakatomi to Onakatomi were made; also Sukune was changed to Osukune; accordingly the system of clans and hereditary titles came to penetrate more pervasively in general.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the clan name the changes of Kasuga to Okasuga and Nakatomi to Onakatomi were made; also Sukune was changed to Osukune; accordingly the system of clans and hereditary titles came to penetrate more pervasively in general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the clan name the changes of Kasuga to Okasuga and Nakatomi to Onakatomi were made; also Sukune was changed to Osukune; accordingly the system of clans and hereditary titles came to penetrate more pervasively in general.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="65">
<j>これらの全般的な特徴として、まず首位の昇叙があり、ついでそれに連なる直系親族のみに対し氏姓の変更が行われるといった順序により同族の中から有力な者が抽出されるという点にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The general characteristic of these lies in the point that at the beginning the top rank is raised and then for the direct line that connected with the raised rank changes of clan name and hereditary title is made; because of this procedural order, an influential person is extracted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The general characteristic of these lies in the point that at the beginning the top rank is raised and then for the direct line that connected with the raised rank changes of clan name and hereditary title is made; because of this procedural order, an influential person is extracted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The general characteristic of these lies in the point that at the beginning the top rank is raised and then for the direct line that connected with the raised rank changes of clan name and hereditary title is made; because of this procedural order, an influential person is extracted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>この改賜姓を認可する権限は天皇にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The right to give permission to change and grant hereditary titles was in the hands of Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The right to give permission to change and grant hereditary titles was in the hands of Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The right to give permission to change and grant hereditary titles was in the hands of Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>氏姓制の変質</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Change in the Quality of the System of Clan Names and Hereditary Titles</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Change in the Quality of the System of Clan Names and Hereditary Titles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Change in the Quality of the System of Clan Names and Hereditary Titles</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="67">
<j>9世紀に、摂関政治により藤原北家が最も有力となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the regency politics, FUJIWARA Hokke (one of the four Fujiwara family lines) became most influential in the ninth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the regency politics, FUJIWARA Hokke (one of the four Fujiwara family lines) became most influential in the ninth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the regency politics, the Northern House of the FUJIWARA clan (one of the four Fujiwara family lines) became most influential in the ninth century.</e>
<cmt>用語統一リストにより英訳を採用しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>また、桓武天皇より平朝臣、清和天皇などから源朝臣の氏姓（ウヂ・カバネ）が生まれたように、諸皇子に氏姓をあたえる臣籍降下が盛んに行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, giving clan names and hereditary titles to princes by demoting them from the nobility to subject came to be executed quite often; examples include TAIRA no Ason from Emperor Kammu and MINAMOTO no Ason from Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, giving clan names and hereditary titles to princes by demoting them from the nobility to subject came to be executed quite often; examples include TAIRA no Ason from Emperor Kammu and MINAMOTO no Ason from Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, giving clan names and hereditary titles to princes by demoting them from the nobility to subject came to be executed quite often; examples include TAIRA no Ason from Emperor Kammu and MINAMOTO no Ason from Emperor Seiwa.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>これらのため、律令的氏姓制度は、人材登用制度としてはほとんど有効に機能しなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For these reasons, the Shisei Seido (the system of clans and hereditary titles) that is related to the ritsuryo system came to hardly function as a system to appoint talented people effectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For these reasons, the Shisei Seido (the system of clans and hereditary titles) that is related to the ritsuryo system came to hardly function as a system to appoint talented people effectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For these reasons, the Shisei Seido (the system of clans and hereditary titles) that is related to the ritsuryo system came to hardly function as a system to appoint talented people effectively.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="70">
<j>一方、律令的戸籍制度も次第に行われなくなり、 10世紀には、地方豪族で実力を蓄えた者は、有力な貴族の家人となり、その氏姓を侵すようにさえなり、いわゆる冒名仮蔭（ぼうめいかいん）の現象が一般化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, family registration system based on the ritsuryo system has been gradually tapered out; in the tenth century, people who became strong among powerful local clans became the retainers of the influential nobles and came to invade the clan names and the hereditary titles; in essence, the phenomenon of so-called Bomei Kain (misrepresentation of one&apos;s clan name and hereditary title) became quite commonplace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, family registration system based on the ritsuryo system was gradually phased out; in the tenth century, people who became strong among powerful local clans became the retainers of the influential nobles and invaded clan names and hereditary titles; in essence, the phenomenon of so-called Bomei Kain (misrepresentation of one&apos;s clan name and hereditary title) became quite commonplace.</e>
<cmt>needs editing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, family registration system based on the ritsuryo system was gradually phased out; in the tenth century, people who became strong among powerful local clans became the retainers of the influential nobles and invaded clan names and hereditary titles; in essence, the phenomenon of so-called Bomei Kain (misrepresentation of one&apos;s clan name and hereditary title) became quite commonplace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>そのため、天下の氏姓は、源・平・藤・橘か、紀、菅原、大江、中原、坂上、賀茂、小野、惟宗（これむね）、清原などに集中されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the clan name and hereditary title in Japan came to concentrate on such names as Minamoto, Taira, Fuji, Tachibana, Ki, Sugawara, Oe, Nakahara, Sakagami, Kamo, Ono, Koremune, Kiyohara and such.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the clan name and hereditary title in Japan came to concentrate on such names as Minamoto, Taira, Fuji, Tachibana, Ki, Sugawara, Oe, Nakahara, Sakagami, Kamo, Ono, Koremune, Kiyohara and such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the clan name and hereditary title in Japan came to concentrate on such names as Minamoto, Taira, Fuji, Tachibana, Ki, Sugawara, Oe, Nakahara, Sakagami, Kamo, Ono, Koremune, Kiyohara and such.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これは家業の成立によって、特定の家柄が固定されるようになったためでもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is because specific family lineage became fixed from the formation of family business.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is because specific family lineage became fixed from the formation of family business.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, this is because specific family lineage became fixed from the formation of family business.</e>
<cmt>Alsoを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="73">
<j>たとえば、越前国の敦賀氏、熱田大宮司家らが藤原氏から養子を迎えて「藤原朝臣」を名乗ったり、それらの氏の女子をめとり母系によって「藤原朝臣」その他の氏姓を称した例もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, Tsuruga clan of Echizen Province, the Atsuta-Daiguji family adopted a son from Fujiwara clan and called themselves Fujiwara Ason; also they took the daughter of Fujiwara clan in marriage and named &apos;Fujiwara Ason&apos; by the maternal line; examples of other clan names and hereditary titles also exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, Tsuruga clan of Echizen Province, the Atsuta-Daiguji family adopted a son from Fujiwara clan and called themselves Fujiwara Ason; also they took the daughter of Fujiwara clan in marriage and named &apos;Fujiwara Ason&apos; by the maternal line; examples of other clan names and hereditary titles also exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, the Tsuruga clan of Echizen Province, the Atsuta-Daiguji family adopted a son from the Fujiwara clan and called themselves Fujiwara Ason; also they took the daughter of the Fujiwara clan in marriage and named &apos;Fujiwara Ason&apos; by the maternal line; examples of other clan names and hereditary titles also exist.</e>
<cmt>theを補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>武士もまた、地頭として、本家、領家の氏姓を侵し、同じ氏姓を名乗る者が増えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Warriors also invaded the clan names and hereditary titles of the head family or proprietors of manor as the land steward; many of them called themselves the same clan name and the hereditary title they invaded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Warriors also invaded the clan names and hereditary titles of the head family or proprietors of manor as the land steward; many of them called themselves the same clan name and the hereditary title they invaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Warriors also invaded the clan names and hereditary titles of the head family or proprietors of manor as the land steward; many of them called themselves the same clan name and the hereditary title they invaded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>ここにおいて、同姓の間でも、さらに族名を分かつ必要にせまられ、貴族では家名、武士では名字（みようじ）が生ずるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this situation, even among the people who share the same hereditary title, there arose the need to divide the clan name and in the case of nobles family name and in the case of the warriors surname came to be born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this situation, even among the people who share the same hereditary title, there arose the need to divide the clan name and in the case of nobles family name and in the case of the warriors surname came to be born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this situation, even among the people who share the same hereditary title, there arose the need to divide the clan name and in the case of nobles family name and in the case of the warriors surname came to be born.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="76">
<j>一方、氏姓のほかに、同時に発達したのが字（あざな）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, besides clan name and hereditary titles, Azana also developed at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, besides clan name and hereditary titles, Azana also developed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, besides clan name and hereditary titles, Azana also developed at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>仮名（けみよう）、呼名（よびな）ともいわれ、一種の私称であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azana was also called Kemyo or Yobina; it was a sort of unofficial name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azana was also called Kemyo or Yobina; it was a sort of unofficial name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azana was also called Kemyo or Yobina; it was a sort of unofficial name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>すでに『日本現報善悪霊異記』に、紀伊国伊刀郡人文忌寸（ふみのいみき）を、上田三郎と称した例がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is already an example in &quot;Nihon Genho Zen-aku Ryoik&quot;i (set of three books of Buddhist stories, written in the late eighth and early 9th century); in this book FUMI no Imiki in the Ito County, Kii Province is called Saburo KAMITA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There is already an example in &quot;Nihon Genho Zen-aku Ryoik&quot;i (set of three books of Buddhist stories, written in the late eighth and early 9th century); in this book FUMI no Imiki in the Ito County, Kii Province is called Saburo KAMITA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There is already an example in &quot;Nihon Genho Zen-aku Ryoik&quot;i (set of three books of Buddhist stories, written in the late eighth and early 9th century); in this book FUMI no Imiki in the Ito County, Kii Province is called Saburo KAMITA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>上田は、伊刀郡上田邑の地名、三郎は三男の意である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamita is a place name of Kamita no Mura, Ito County; Saburo means the third son.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamita is a place name of Kamita no Mura, Ito County; Saburo means the third son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamita is a place name of Kamita no Mura, Ito County; Saburo means the third son.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="80">
<j>氏姓に取って代わることになる苗字（名字）は、このように字の一部分として発生し、さらに字から分離独立したものとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A surname that replaced the clan name and hereditary title occurred in this way as a part of Azana and it seems that later it was separated from Azana and became independent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A surname that replaced the clan name and hereditary title occurred in this way as a part of Azana and it seems that later it was separated from Azana and became independent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A surname that replaced the clan name and hereditary title occurred in this way as a part of Azana and it seems that later it was separated from Azana and became independent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>初期の苗字は、自分の居住地や所領の名であったため、父子兄弟が苗字を異（こと）にしている場合も多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because the early family name was one&apos;s place of residence and the name of territory, many times father, son and brothers have the different family name.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because the early family name was one&apos;s place of residence and the name of territory, many times father, son and brothers have the different family name.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because the early family name was one&apos;s place of residence and the name of territory, many times father, son and brothers have the different family names.</e>
<cmt>複数形にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>しかし、やがて苗字が家名・一族の名前を意味するようになると、他国に移っても一族の苗字は変更されないようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, gradually the family name meant the name of the family and the clan; with this shift in meaning, the family name became fixed and the name was to be kept even the family moved to other province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, gradually the family name meant the name of the family and the clan; with this shift in meaning, the family name became fixed and the name was to be kept even the family moved to other province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, gradually the family name meant the name of the family and the clan; with this shift in meaning, the family name became fixed and the name was to be kept even the family moved to other province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="83">
<j>このため、苗字は、12世紀以後、氏姓と同じように用いられることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this a family name was used in the same way as a clan name and hereditary title after the twelfth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Because of this a family name was used in the same way as a clan name and hereditary title after the twelfth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this a family name was used in the same way as a clan name and hereditary title after the 12th century.</e>
<cmt>数字表記を修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>今日的な意味での姓（セイ）の特徴は、基本的にはこの苗字（名字）から発生している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic of a family name in the current sense comes from this family name derived from Azana basically.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristic of a family name in the current sense comes from this family name derived from Azana basically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristic of a family name in the current sense comes from this family name derived from Azana basically.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Higashi(id:8842), Tomzo(id:16777), Lennon(id:20471), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), MIO(id:31681), Huemat(id:19503), Rocky7(id:29381), Aphaia(id:3132), 葉月(id:25674), Kurz(id:1601), Ef3(id:84901), PrimeN(id:102297), 海衛士(id:19229), Thijssie!bot(id:111619), Shimoxx(id:9332), NDR(id:5500), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>