<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>倉垣荘</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuragaki no Sho (Manor)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuragaki no Sho (Manor)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuragaki no Sho</e>
<cmt>説明括弧を削除しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>倉垣荘（くらがきのしょう）は、平安時代後期から戦国時代 (日本)まで越中国射水郡に置かれた荘園。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuragaki no Sho was a manor in Imizu-gun, Ecchu Province, that existed from the late Heian period to the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuragaki no Sho was a manor in Imizu-gun, Ecchu Province that existed from the late Heian period to the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>eliminated comma after &quot;Province&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuragaki no Sho was a manor in Imizu-gun, Ecchu Province that existed from the late Heian period to the Sengoku period (period of warring states).</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>現在の射水市東部・富山市西部にあたり、射水市海老江・堀岡地区から白石地区・戸破地区を含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The place currently is the eastern part of Imizu City and the western part of Toyama City combined, including the Ebie, Horioka, Shiraishi, and Hibari areas in Imizu City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The manor was located in what is now the eastern part of Imizu City, including the Ebie, Horioka, Shiraishi and Hibari areas, and the western part of Toyama City.</e>
<cmt>rearranged sentence and fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The manor was located in what is now the eastern part of Imizu City, including the Ebie, Horioka, Shiraishi and Hibari areas, and the western part of Toyama City.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>同市黒河地区から富山市老田地区までの30km²に及ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It extends from the Kurokawa area in Imizu City to the Oida area in Toyama City for a total area of 30km2.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The land extends from the Kurokawa area in Imizu City to the Oida area in Toyama City with a total area of thirty square kilometers.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;It&quot; to &quot;The land&quot;; changed &quot;30km2&quot; to &quot;thirty square kilometers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The land extends from the Kurokawa area in Imizu City to the Oida area in Toyama City with a total area of 30 square kilometers.</e>
<cmt>数字に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>領主は賀茂御祖神社（下鴨社）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kamomioya-jinja Shrine (Shimogamo-jinja Shrine) was the landlord for that manor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kamomioya-jinja Shrine (Shimogamo-jinja Shrine) was the landlord for the manor.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;that&quot; to &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamomioya-jinja Shrine (Shimogamo-jinja Shrine) was the landlord for the manor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>寛治4年（1090年）、堀河天皇の仏神事興行政策の中で上下賀茂社に各600町ずつの荘園が寄進された中の一荘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the course of the Buddhist and Shinto ritual performance plan carried out by Emperor Horikawa, Kuragaki no Sho was a part of the manor that was donated in 1090 to the Kamigamo-sha and Shimogamo-sha shrines, with each shrine receiving an area of 595.02 hectares.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Within the Buddhist and Shinto ritual performance plan by Emperor Horikawa, Kuragaki no Sho was part of the manor donated in 1090 to the Kamigamo-sha and Shimogamo-sha shrines, each receiving an area of 595 hectares.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; eliminated numbers after the decimal point since they seemed unecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Within the Buddhist and Shinto ritual performance plan by Emperor Horikawa, Kuragaki no Sho was part of the manor donated in 1090 to the Kamigamo-sha and Shimogamo-sha Shrines, each receiving an area of 595 hectares.</e>
<cmt>Shrines大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>当初は30町であり、室町時代には年貢として200貫の地とされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kuragaki no Sho originally was 29.751 hectares which was worth 750 kg of nengu (land tax) in the Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kuragaki no Sho was originally 29 hectares, which in the Muromachi period was worth 750 kilograms in nengu (land tax).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally; eliminated numbers after the decimal point since they seemed unecessary; changed &quot;kg&quot; to &quot;kilograms&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kuragaki no Sho was originally 29 hectares, which in the Muromachi period was worth 750 kilograms in nengu (land tax).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>文永年間には下鴨社の築垣・犬防の修築費を課せられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Bunei era, the costs of building fences and low lattices were imposed on Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Bunei era, the costs of building fences and low lattices were imposed on Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Bunei era, the costs of building fences and low lattices were imposed on Shimogamo-jinja Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>戦国時代に入ると、越中守護代神保長誠の押領が発生したほか、代官が荘民と結託して荘内の戸破村や白石村の年貢を遅滞するなど混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Sengoku period, there were disputes involving the manor because Nagamoto JINBO, who was the deputy military governor of Ecchu Province, seized Kuragaki no Sho at one time, and another time, local governors and people who lived at the manor conspired to delay local tax payment by Hibari-mura and Shiraishi-mura.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it became the Sengoku Period, there were a number of disputes involving the manor. One instance involviing Nagamoto JINBO, who seized Kuragaki no Sho as the deputy military governor of Ecchu Province. On another occasion, local governors and manor residents conspired together to delay payment of land taxes made by the villages of Hibari and Shiraishi that were part of the manor.</e>
<cmt>split into three sentences for easier reading; changed &quot;Hibari-mura&quot; and &quot;Shiraishi-mura&quot; to &quot;the villages of Hibari and Shiraishi&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it became the Sengoku Period, there were a number of disputes involving the manor: One instance involving Nagamoto JINBO, who seized Kuragaki no Sho as the deputy military governor of Ecchu Province; on another occasion, local governors and manor residents conspired together to delay payment of land taxes made by the villages of Hibari and Shiraishi that were part of the manor.</e>
<cmt>一文に訂正しました。involvingスペル訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>下鴨社領の歴史は、天文 (日本)16年（1547年）に神保長職が近隣国人へ神用年貢の納入を督励したことが最後の記録となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The last record in the history of the estate of Shimogamo-jinja Shrine was made in 1547 and it described Nagamoto JINBO encouraging people in adjacent provinces to pay local taxes for god.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The last record on the history of the estate of Shimogamo-jinja Shrine was made in 1547 describing Nagamoto JINBO encouraging people in neighboring provinces to pay local taxes for god.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The last record on the history of the estate of Shimogamo-jinja Shrine was made in 1547 describing Nagamoto JINBO encouraging people in neighboring provinces to pay local taxes for god.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>荘家の跡は加茂神社 (射水市)（射水市加茂中部）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The remains of the manor management building were found at Kamo-jinja Shrine (Imizu City) (Kamochubu, Imizu City).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remains of the management building of the manor have been found at the Kamo-jinja Shrine (Imizu City) (Kamochubu, Imizu City).</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remains of the management building of the manor have been found at the Kamo-jinja Shrine (Imizu City) (Kamochubu, Imizu City).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>境内に隣接して加茂遺跡 (射水市)が出土し、鎌倉期の居館跡が見つかっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamo ruins (Imizu City) were excavated right next to the shrine grounds, and remains of residences from the Kamakura period have been found.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamo ruins (Imizu City) were excavated right next to the shrine grounds where the remains of residences from the Kamakura period have been found.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kamo ruins (Imizu City) were excavated right next to the shrine grounds where the remains of residences from the Kamakura period have been found.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>現在、周辺地域に倉垣の地名はほとんど残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Currently, the place-name Kuragaki is hardly ever found in this area.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, the place-name of Kuragaki is hardly ever found in this area.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;Currently&quot; to &quot;Today&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, the place-name of Kuragaki is hardly ever found in this area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>しかし、2005年の市町村合併では射水郡下村が射水市となるにあたり、小杉地内では合併で住所が「射水市小杉」となると、同じく射水市となる小杉町との混同を招くとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Note, however, Shimo-mura, Imizu-gun was going to be merged in Imizu City in 2005, and there was a concern in the Kosugi area that, when the post-merger address became &apos;Kosugi, Imizu City,&apos; this address would be confused with Kosugi-machi which was also included in Imizu City.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, when Shimo-mura in Imizu-gun was to be merged with Imizu City in 2005, there were concerns in the Kosugi area that the post-merger address of &quot;Kosugi, Imizu City&quot; would be confused with the part of Imizu City called Kosugi-machi.</e>
<cmt>fixed grammar to read more naturally</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, when Shimo-mura in Imizu-gun was to be merged with Imizu City in 2005, there were concerns in the Kosugi area that the post-merger address of &apos;Kosugi, Imizu City&apos; would be confused with the part of Imizu City called Kosugi-machi.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>その結果、当荘園に由来する古い地名である「倉垣小杉」への町名変更を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For this reason, the name of the town was changed to &apos;Kuragaki Kosugi,&apos; which was an old name coming from the manor, Kuragaki no Sho.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the name of the town was changed to &quot;Kuragaki Kosugi,&quot; an old name based on the manor, Kuragaki no Sho.</e>
<cmt>changed &quot;For this reason&quot; to &quot;As a result&quot;; fixed grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the name of the town was changed to &apos;Kuragaki Kosugi,&apos; an old name based on the manor, Kuragaki no Sho.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合せて&quot;を&apos;に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Doorurban(id:132333), Thunderbird(id:34551), Tiu(id:9523), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>