<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>奉安殿</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan-den</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan-den</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>奉安殿（ほうあんでん）とは、戦前戦中にかけて各地の学校で、天皇皇后の写真（御真影）と教育勅語を納めていた建物のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den was the premises where portraits of the emperor and empress (called &quot;goshin-ei portrait&quot;) and the Imperial Rescript on Education were housed before and during the war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan-den was the premises where portraits of the emperor and empress (called &quot;goshin-ei portrait&quot;) and the Imperial Rescript on Education were housed before and during the war.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan-den was the premises where portraits of the emperor and empress (called &quot;goshin-ei portrait&quot;) and the Imperial Rescript on Education were housed before and during the war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>御真影自体は大正～昭和期にかけて下賜されたため、奉安殿の成立もその時期と推測される（小学校の奉安殿建築は昭和10年前後に活発化）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As goshin-ei portrait in itself was granted as an Imperial gift from the Taisho period to the Showa period, it is estimated that Hoan-den came into existence in those periods (Construction of Hoan-den in the elementary schools became active in around 1935).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As goshin-ei portraits were themselves granted as Imperial gifts from the Taisho period to the Showa period, it is estimated that Hoan-den came into existence in those periods (construction of Hoan-den in the elementary schools became active in around 1935).</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As goshin-ei portraits were themselves granted as Imperial gifts from the Taisho period to the Showa period, it is estimated that Hoan-den came into existence in those periods (construction of Hoan-den in the elementary schools became active in around 1935).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>また学校への宿直も、この御真影の保護を目的として始められた面もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, one of the reasons for setting the system of night duty was to protect the goshin-ei portrait.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, one of the reasons for setting the system of night duty was to protect the goshin-ei portrait.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, one of the reasons for setting the system of night duty at schools was to protect the goshin-ei portrait.</e>
<cmt>学校　を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>四大節祝賀式典の際には、職員生徒全員で御真影に対しての最敬礼と教育勅語の奉読が求められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the four major festivals, all school staff and students were obliged to make a deep bow and read the Imperial Rescript on Education with respect.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the four major festivals, all school staff and students were obliged to make a deep bow and read the Imperial Rescript on Education with respect.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the four major festivals, all school staff and students were obliged to make a deep bow and read the Imperial Rescript on Education with respect.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、登下校時や単に前を通過する際にも、職員生徒全てが服装を正してから最敬礼するように定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, they had to make a deep bow after straightened their clothes not only when they arrived at school and left school, but also whenever they passed in front of the portrait.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, they had to make a deep bow after straightening their clothes not only when they arrived at school and left school, but also whenever they passed in front of the portraits.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, they had to make a deep bow after straightening their clothes not only when they arrived at school and left school, but also whenever they passed in front of the portraits.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>当初は講堂や職員室・校長室内部に奉安所が設けられていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At first, Hoan-sho (place for displaying the goshin-ei portrait and the Imperial Rescript on Education, the predecessor of Hoan-den) was established at auditorium or inside the staff room or principal&apos;s office.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At first, Hoan-sho (place for displaying the goshin-ei portraits and the Imperial Rescript on Education, the predecessor of Hoan-den) was established at the auditorium or inside the staff room or principal&apos;s office.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At first, Hoan-sho (place for displaying the goshin-ei portraits and the Imperial Rescript on Education, the predecessor of Hoan-den) was established at the auditorium or inside the staff room or principal&apos;s office.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>しかしこの奉安所の場合、校舎火災や地震などによる校舎倒壊の際などに御真影が危険に晒される可能性が高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Hoan-sho, there was high possibility that goshin-ei portrait would be exposed to danger, if schoolhouse collapsed due to fires or earthquakes.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in the Hoan-sho, there was a high possibility that the goshin-ei portrait would be exposed to danger, if the schoolhouse collapsed due to fires or earthquakes.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in the Hoan-sho, there was a high possibility that the goshin-ei portrait would be exposed to danger, if the schoolhouse collapsed due to fires or earthquakes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また実際に関東大震災や空襲、校舎火災の際に御真影を守ろうとして殉職した校長の美談がいくつか伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed, some heroic tales of the principles who died for protecting the goshin-ei portrait in the Great Kanto Earthquake, air raids and fires have been passed on.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed, some heroic tales of principles who died protecting the goshin-ei portrait in the Great Kanto Earthquake, air raids and fires have been passed on.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed, some heroic tales of principles who died protecting the goshin-ei portrait in the Great Kanto Earthquake, air raids and fires have been passed on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>このため、さらに万全を期すために、校舎内部の奉安所は金庫型へ改められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, aiming at more perfect system, Hoan-sho established inside the schoolhouse was reformed to the strongbox style,</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, aiming at a more perfect system, Hoan-sho established inside the schoolhouse was reformed to a strongbox style,</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, aiming at a more perfect system, Hoan-sho established inside the schoolhouse was reformed to a strongbox style.</e>
<cmt>カンマ→ピリオド　に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また独立した「奉安殿」の建築が進められていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, the separated premises &apos;Hoan-den&apos; were constructed.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the separated premises of &apos;Hoan-den&apos; were constructed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the separated premises of &apos;Hoan-den&apos; were constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>前者の校舎一体型は旧制中学などに多く、後者の独立建築型は小学校に多く見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former premises incorporated into the schoolhouse was frequently observed in the junior high school under the old system of education, while the latter premises constructed separately was frequently observed in the elementary school.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former premises incorporated into the schoolhouse was frequently observed in junior high schools under the old system of education, while the latter premises constructed separately was frequently observed in elementary schools.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former premises incorporated into the schoolhouse was frequently observed in junior high schools under the old system of education, while the latter premises constructed separately was frequently observed in elementary schools.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>建築物としてみると、実に様々なバリエーションが存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Observed as architecture, Hoan-den had various variations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Observed as architecture, Hoan-den had various variations.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Observed as architecture, Hoan-den had various variations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ギリシャ建築風や鉄筋コンクリート造り、レンガ造りの洋風建築から旧来の神社風建築など、意匠を凝らした物が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Many of them were elaborately designed, ranging from the Hellenized architecture, the ferro-concrete buildings and the Western-style architecture built of brick to the conventional Shinto shrine-style architecture and others.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many of them were elaborately designed, ranging from the Hellenized architecture, the ferro-concrete buildings and the Western-style architecture built of brick to the conventional Shinto shrine-style architecture and others.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many of them were elaborately designed, ranging from the Hellenized architecture, the ferro-concrete buildings and the Western-style architecture built of brick to the conventional Shinto shrine-style architecture and others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>小形ながら頑丈無比の耐火耐震構造、さらに威厳を損ねぬよう荘厳重厚なデザインになるようにとの苦心の跡が垣間見えるようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den provides observers with a glimpse of great efforts to attain the fire-proof and earthquake-proof structure with matchless strength despite its small size, as well as the design with solemnity and gravity so as not to damage the dignity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan-den provides observers with a glimpse of the great efforts to attain a fire-proof and earthquake-proof structure with matchless strength despite its small size, as well as a design with solemnity and gravity so as not to damage dignity.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan-den provides observers with a glimpse of the great efforts to attain a fire-proof and earthquake-proof structure with matchless strength despite its small size, as well as a design with solemnity and gravity so as not to damage dignity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また実際、昭和8年には奉安殿の建築デザインに関するコンペも開かれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the competition concerning the architectural design of Hoan-den was held in 1933.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the competition concerning the architectural design of Hoan-den was held in 1933.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the competition concerning the architectural design of Hoan-den was held in 1933.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>ただし、このような頑丈な小建築には「湿気がこもる」という欠点があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, such strong small buildings had a drawback of &apos;Moisture easily fills the building.&apos;</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, such strong small buildings had a drawback of &apos;Moisture easily fills the building.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, such strong small buildings had a drawback of &apos;Moisture easily fills the building.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>御真影に染みを作ってしまい学校が始末書を提出する羽目に陥ることもしばしばあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Schools were often forced to submit a letter of apology after they carelessly made a stain on goshin-ei portrait.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Schools were often forced to submit a letter of apology after they carelessly made a stain on the goshin-ei portrait.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Schools were often forced to submit a letter of apology after they carelessly made a stain on the goshin-ei portrait.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>昭和20年12月15日、連合国軍最高司令官総司令部の神道指令のため、奉安殿は廃止となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den was abolished because of the Shinto Directive (direction for the separation of government and religion) issued by the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) on December 15, 1945.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan-den was abolished because of the Shinto Directive (direction for the separation of government and religion) issued by the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) on December 15, 1945.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan-den was abolished because of the Shinto Directive (direction for the separation of government and religion) issued by the General Headquarters of the Allied Powers (GHQ) on December 15, 1945.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>奉安殿の多くは戦後解体・もしくは地中に埋められ、御真影も全て奉還された訳ではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war, many of Hoan-den were dismantled or buried in the ground, but not all goshin-ei portraits were returned to the emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war, many of the Hoan-den were dismantled or buried in the ground, but not all goshin-ei portraits were returned to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war, many of the Hoan-den were dismantled or buried in the ground, but not all goshin-ei portraits were returned to the emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかしながら、解体を免れた奉安殿は現在でも全国各地に少数ながら残っており、倉庫として使われていたり、荘厳な外観を生かして神社や納骨堂に転用されていたりする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den that escaped being dismantled still remains even now although the number is small, used as a warehouse or converted to a Shinto shrine or an ossuary, taking advantage of its solemn external appearance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan-den that escaped being dismantled still remain even now although the number is small, used as a warehouse or converted to a Shinto shrine or an ossuary, taking advantage of its solemn external appearance.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan-den that escaped being dismantled still remain even now although the number is small, used as a warehouse or converted to a Shinto shrine or an ossuary, taking advantage of its solemn external appearance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また沖縄の旧美里尋常高等小学校の奉安殿は半壊状態ながら、「戦争遺跡」として文化財に登録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den established by the former Misato Jinjo higher elementary school is registered on &quot;cultural properties&quot; as &apos;war remains&apos;, although it was partially destructed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hoan-den established by the former Misato Jinjo higher elementary school is registered on &quot;cultural properties&quot; as &apos;war remains,&apos; although it was partially destructed.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hoan-den established by the former Misato Jinjo higher elementary school is registered on &quot;cultural properties&quot; as &apos;war remains,&apos; although it was partially destructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>戦前建築の古い校舎・講堂を持つ学校では、校舎内に設けられた「奉安庫」が残る所もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-ko (storeroom for displaying the goshin-ei portrait and the Imperial Rescript on Education, the predecessor of Hoan-den) sometimes remains within the schoolhouse when such a school preserves old schoolhouse or auditorium built in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some Hoan-ko (storeroom for displaying the goshin-ei portrait and the Imperial Rescript on Education, the predecessor of Hoan-den) remain within the schoolhouses where the school preserves old schoolhouses or auditoriums that were built in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some Hoan-ko (storeroom for displaying the goshin-ei portrait and the Imperial Rescript on Education, the predecessor of Hoan-den) remain within the schoolhouses where the school preserves old schoolhouses or auditoriums that were built in the prewar period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="23">
<j>奉安殿は、校舎内に作られることも、校舎外に独立して作られることもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoan-den was established either within the schoolhouse or outside the schoolhouse separately.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hoan-den were established either within the schoolhouse or outside the schoolhouse separately.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hoan-den were established either within the schoolhouse or outside the schoolhouse separately.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>いずれも校長室、職員室、宿直室その他に近い清浄な位置に設けられることとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In either case, it was a rule to establish Hoan-den at a pure location near principal&apos;s offices, staff room, night watchman&apos;s room and so on.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In either case, it was a rule to establish Hoan-den at a pure location near the principal&apos;s offices, staff room, night watchman&apos;s room and so on.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In either case, it was a rule to establish Hoan-den at a pure location near the principal&apos;s offices, staff room, night watchman&apos;s room and so on.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>そのうちのりは最小で奥行85㎝、高さ1.5m、幅1.2mは必要であるとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Inside measurement was requested to be larger than 85㎝ in depth, 1.5m in height, 1.2m in width.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Inside measurements were requested to be larger than 85cm in depth, 1.5m in height, 1.2m in width.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Inside measurements were requested to be larger than 85 cm in depth, 1.5 meters in height, 1.2 meters in width.</e>
<cmt>cm, meters の前にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>構造は鉄筋コンクリート造、壁厚25cm以上、片開または両開の完全な金庫式二重扉を設けることとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for the structure, Hoan-den was needed to be built by ferro-concrete, to have a wall 25cm or more thick and a complete safe-typed and dual-structured door with either a single swing door or double-leaf doors.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As for the structure, Hoan-den needed to be built from ferro-concrete, have walls 25cm or more thick, and a complete safe-typed and dual-structured door with either a single swing door or double-leaf doors.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As for the structure, Hoan-den needed to be built from ferro-concrete, have walls 25 cm or thicker, and a complete safe-typed and dual-structured door with either a single swing door or double-leaf doors.</e>
<cmt>cm, meters の前にスペースを追加しました。more thick →　thicker としました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>耐震耐火構造とし、内外防熱防湿のために石綿材料を施し、内部はさらにキリまたはヒノキ板張りとするとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition to the fire-proof and earthquake-proof structure, Hoan-den was requested to be equipped with the heat-resistant and damp proof structure by using the asbestos material for the inside and outside, as well as by laying boards made from empress tree or hinoki cypress inside.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition to the fire-proof and earthquake-proof structure, Hoan-den were requested to be equipped with heat-resistant and damp-proof structures by using asbestos for the inside and outside, as well as by laying boards made from empress tree or hinoki cypress inside.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition to the fire-proof and earthquake-proof structure, Hoan-den were requested to be equipped with heat-resistant and damp-proof structures by using asbestos for the inside and outside, as well as by laying boards made from empress tree or hinoki cypress inside.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>さらに御真影を奉安する棚の高さは50cmほどのところに設けることとされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, it was regulated that the height of the shelf on which goshin-ei portrait was enshrined was about 50cm.</e>
<cmt>一例文一訳文の例外対処。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, it was regulated that the height of the shelf on which goshin-ei portrait was enshrined was about 50cm.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, it was regulated that the height of the shelf on which goshin-ei portrait was enshrined was about 50 cm.</e>
<cmt>cm, meters の前にスペースを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 0太郎(id:7375), たね(id:10372), 磯キリン(id:64770), ハンチング(id:62686), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>