<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>稷山の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Shokusan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Shokusan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Shokusan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>稷山の戦い（ショクサンのたたかい）は慶長の役において日本軍と明軍との間で戦われた戦闘。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Shokusan of Shokusan was fought between the Japanese army and Ming army during the Keicho Campaign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Shokusan was fought between the Japanese army and the Ming army during the Keicho Campaign.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Shokusan was fought between the Japanese army and the Ming army during the Keicho Campaign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>文禄の役の後続いていた講和交渉は決裂し慶長の役が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The peace treaty negotiations after the Buncho Campaign did not go through and led to the Keicho Campaign.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The peace-treaty negotiations after the Buncho Campaign failed and therefore led to the Keicho Campaign.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The peace-treaty negotiations after the Bunroku Campaign failed and therefore led to the Keicho Campaign.</e>
<cmt>Buncho→Bunroku</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>慶長2年（1597年）の作戦目標は全羅道及び忠清道を成敗することで、目標の達成後は城塞（倭城）を築城し、城の在番担当を定め、それ以外の軍は帰国する計画が定められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1597, the aim of the campaign was to demolish	Jeolla-do and Chungcheong-do and after attaining the aim, the plan was to build fortresses (Japanese castles), choose a resident for the castles and then the rest of the army would return to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1597, the aim of the campaign was to demolish Jeolla-do and Chungcheo-do, and after attaining that objective the plan was to build fortresses (Japanese castles) and choose residents for them, whereupon the rest of the army would return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1597, the aim of the campaign was to demolish Jeolla-do and Chungcheo-do, and after attaining that objective the plan was to build fortresses (Japanese castles) and choose residents for them, whereupon the rest of the army would return to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>釜山周辺に布陣していた日本軍は7月16日漆川梁の海戦で朝鮮水軍を殲滅すると陸上でも全羅道を目指して進撃を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army was based near Busan and demolished the Korean navy at the naval Battle of Chilcheollyang on July 16 and on land, started to move towards Jeolla-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army, which was based near Busan, demolished the Korean navy in the Battle of Chilcheollyang on July 16 and, on land, started its advance toward Jeolla-do.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army, which was based near Busan, demolished the Korean navy in the Battle of Chilcheollyang on August 28 and, as for the land war, started its advance toward Jeolla-do.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>このとき明・朝鮮軍では全羅道と慶尚道との道境付近にある南原城と黄石山城で守りを固めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ming, Korean army was increasing the defenses at Namwon Castle and Hwangsoksan Castle which is between the road boundary of Chilcheollyang and Gyeongsang-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming (Korean) army was increasing its defenses at Namwon and Hwangsoksan castles, between the road boundary of Chilcheollyang and Gyeongsang-do.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming-Korean army was increasing its defenses at Namwon and Hwangsoksan castles, between the road boundary of Chilcheollyang and Gyeongsang-do.</e>
<cmt>Ming (Korean)→Ming-Korean</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>日本軍は左軍と右軍の2隊に分かれ西進し、左軍は8月15日南原城を攻め落とし、右軍は8月16日黄石山城を攻め落とし、両軍は全羅道の中核都市全州市に向かって併進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army divided into two, the left forces and right forces and the left forces captured Namwon Castle on August 15, and the right forces captured Hwangsoksan Castle on August 16 after which the two forces headed toward the core city of Jeolla-do, Jeonju City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army divided into two--the left forces and right forces--and subsequently the left forces captured Namwon Castle on August 15 and the right forces captured Hwangsoksan Castle on August 16, after which the two forces headed toward the core district of Jeolla-do, Jeonju City.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army divided into two, the left army and the right army, and subsequently the left forces captured Namwon Castle on September 26 and the right forces captured Hwangsoksan Castle on September 27, after which the two forces headed toward the core district of Jeolla-do, Jeonju City.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>するとここを守る明将陳愚衷は恐れをなして逃走したため戦うことなく8月24日全州を占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The defending Ming warrior, Chin, became afraid and fled without engaging, and the Japanese conquered Jeonju on August 24.</e>
<cmt>読み不明なので陳愚衷-&gt;陳　Chinとしました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The defending Ming warrior, Chin, became afraid and fled without engaging, and the Japanese conquered Jeonju on August 24.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chin, the defending Ming warrior, was afraid and fled without engaging, and the Japanese conquered Jeonju on October 5.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>ここで諸将は軍議を開き全羅道及び忠清道を平定するため各地へ分進していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here the various warriors held a meeting and separated to conquer Chilcheollyang and Chungcheong-do.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here the various warriors held a meeting and then separated in order to conquer Chilcheollyang and Chungcheong-do.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here the various warriors held a meeting, and then separated in order to conquer Chilcheollyang and Chungcheong-do.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>戦闘経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress of battle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Progress of Battle</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The progress of battle</e>
<cmt>文頭以外小文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>日本の右軍の主力毛利秀元（兵約25000）、加藤清正（兵約10000）、黒田長政（兵約5000）及び軍監太田一吉、竹中重利の五将は兵40000余人を率い8月29日全州を発して北進し9月初旬公州に至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The main 5 groups of the right forces of Japan were Hidemoto MORI(about 25,000 soldiers), Kiyomasa KATO(about 10,000 soldiers), Nagamasa KURODA(about 5,000 soldiers) and Assistant Deputy General	Kazuyoshi OTA, and Shigetoshi Takenaka led about 40,000 troops and left Jeonju on August 29, and headed north, reaching Gongju in early September.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The five main groups of the right forces of Japan, consisting of Hidemoto MORI (about 25,000 soldiers), Kiyomasa KATO (about 10,000 soldiers), Nagamasa KURODA (about 5,000 soldiers), Assistant Deputy General Kazuyoshi OT and Shigetoshi Takenaka led about 40,000 troops and left Jeonju on August 29; they headed north, reaching Gongju in early September.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The five main groups of the right army of Japan, consisting of Hidemoto MORI (about 25,000 soldiers), Kiyomasa KATO (about 10,000 soldiers), Nagamasa KURODA (about 5,000 soldiers), Assistant Deputy General Kazuyoshi OTA and Shigetoshi TAKENAKA led about 40,000 soldiers and left Jeonju on October 10; they headed north, reaching Gongju in the middle of October.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>初め明将陳愚衷が全州を捨てて逃走すると提督麻貴は漢城より遊撃牛伯英を遣わし赴援させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Chin fled Jeonju, Admiral Ma Gui sent for ranger Gyu from Hanseong for support.</e>
<cmt>読み不明なので牛伯英-&gt;Gyu ??</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Chin fled Jeonju, Admiral Ma Gui sent for the ranger Gyu from Hanseong for support.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Ming warrior Chin fled Jeonju at first, Admiral Ma Gui sent for the ranger Gyu from Hanseong for support.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>牛伯英は陳愚衷と兵を合わせ公州に駐屯していたが、日本軍が全州を発して大挙北進するのを聞くと蒼黄となり漢城に退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gyu combined forces with Chin and stayed in Gongju, but upon hearing that the Japanese army had left Jeonju and were headed north, they grew afraid and retreated to Hanseong.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gyu combined forces with Chin and stayed in Gongju, but upon hearing that the Japanese army had left Jeonju and was headed north, they became afraid and retreated to Hanseong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gyu combined forces with Chin and stayed in Gongju; upon hearing that the Japanese army had left Jeonju and headed north, they became afraid and retreated to Hanseong.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>ここにおいて日本軍は抵抗を受けることなく公州を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the Japanese forces took Gongju without any resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the Japanese forces met no resistance in taking Gongju.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the Japanese army met no resistance in occupying Gongju.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="13">
<j>日本軍は公州において路を分かち加藤・太田の2隊は右方に進み燕岐郡を経て9月6日清州に到った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army split at Gongju and the two groups, Kato and Ota, headed to the right and reached Cheongju via Yeongi County.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army split at Gongju, and the two groups--Kato and Ota--headed to the right, reaching Cheongju via Yeongi County.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army split at Gongju, and the two groups of Kato and Ota headed to the right, reaching Cheongju via Yeongi County on October 16.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>秀元は黒田隊を以って先鋒と為し全義を経て同日天安市に到った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidemoto, with the Kuroda group leading, reached Cheonan City via Jeonui the same day.</e>
<cmt>全義 Jeonui</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidemoto, with the Kuroda group leading, reached Cheonan City via Jeonui the same day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidemoto, with the Kuroda group in the van, reached Cheonan City via Jeonui on the same day.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="15">
<j>漢城においては明の経理楊鎬が9月朔日平壌より来り麻貴を促し、出でて日本軍の前進を阻止しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At Hanseong, Keiri Yang Hao of Ming who arrived from Pyongyang on the first day of September, prompted Ma Gui and tried to stop the invasion of the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At Hanseong, Keiri Yang Hao of Ming, who had arrived from Pyongyang on September 1, prompted Ma Gui and tried to stop the invasion of the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At Hanseong, Keiri Yang Hao of Ming, who had arrived from Pyongyang on October 11, prompted Ma Gui to stop the invasion of the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>麻貴は乃ち水原市に到り副総兵解生・遊撃牛伯英・楊登山・頗貴の4将をして精騎2000を率い6日稷山に向かはせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ma Gui reached Suwon City, together with 4 warriors, deputy admiral Kaisei, ranger Gyu, Yang, 頗貴 and 2,000 experienced horsemen, headed to Shokusan on the 6th.</e>
<cmt>頗貴 読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ma Gui reached Suwon City together with four warrior groups--Deputy Admiral Kaisei, the ranger Gyu, Yang, 頗貴 and 2,000 experienced horsemen--and set out for Shokusan on the sixth.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ma Gui reached Suwon City together with four warrior groups of Deputy Admiral Kaisei, the ranger Gyu, Yang, and Haki (pronunciation unconfirmed) leading 2,000 experienced horsemen, and set out for Shokusan on the 16th.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>朝鮮の朝廷もまた李元翼をして兵を率い竹山方向に下り清州路を扼し以て明軍の左翼を警戒させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean court sent troops led by LEE Won-Ik, who headed down Chukusan and took the Cheongju Route to guard the left wing of the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>竹山　ローマ字はChuksan？</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean court sent troops led by LEE Won-Ik, who headed down Chukusan and took the Cheongju route in order to guard the left wing of the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean court sent troops led by LEE Won-Ik, which headed down to Chukusan and took the Cheongju route in order to guard the left wing of the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>9月7日未明、黒田長政は部将黒田図書助・栗山利安等をしてその先鋒の兵若干を領し先ず前進させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamawa KURODA sent some advance troops under Zushonosuke KURODA and Toshiyasu KURIYAMA early morning on September 7,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamawa KURODA sent some advance troops under Zushonosuke KURODA and Toshiyasu KURIYAMA early in the morning of September 7.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa KURODA sent some advance troops led by those including Zushonosuke KURODA and Toshiyasu KURIYAMA, early in the morning of October 17.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>図書助等は進んで稷山まで距離一里許の地に到り日の出と共に敵兵が山野に充満し近迫する様を見る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zushonosuke advanced up to one ri before Shokusan and saw that enemy troops were starting to fill the mountain fields and was drawing closer as it dawned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zushonosuke advanced up to one ri before Shokusan, whereupon it became evident that the enemy troops were starting to fill the mountain fields and were drawing closer with the dawn.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zushonosuke advanced up to about 4 meters before Shokusan, whereupon it became evident that the enemy troops were starting to fill the mountain fields and were drawing closer at dawn.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>諸部将は会して進退を議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The various leaders gathered to decide on attacking or retreating.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The various leaders gathered in order to decide whether they should attack or retreat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The various leaders met in order to decide whether they should attack or retreat.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>毛屋主水曰く「敵は多く我は少なし。我若し一歩を退かば彼必ず追撃し我兵殲きん死は一成り寧ろ進んで死するに若かず且つ我兵一致団結して奮進すれば必ず敵の一部を突破せん。我その機に乗じて退却すれば或は軍を全うするを得ん。是れ武田勝頼が長篠の敗後に攻勢に出て敵の追撃を遅緩ならしめたる故智なり」と。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Said Shusui KEYA, &quot;The enemy are many and we are few.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Said Shusui KEYA, &quot;The enemy are many and we are few.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shusui KEYA said, &apos;The enemy are many and we are few. If we retreat one step backwards, the enemy will definitely give chase and our troops will be cut down, but if we try to advance and face death with all of our troops act together, we will definitely break through our enemy. If we use the chance to retreat, our troops might make it. This was the trick that Katsuyori TAKEDA used after the loss at the Battle of Nagashino, where he attacked in order to discourage the pursuit of his enemies.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。「」内の文をここに１つにまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>衆之を然りと為し乃ち歩率をして斉しく銃射せしめ士卒硝煙中より喊声を発して突撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They had the soldiers shoot guns and have them shout through the smoke while attacking.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They had the soldiers shoot guns and shout through the smoke as they attacked.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They had the soldiers shoot guns and shout through the smoke, as they attacked.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>明軍大いに驚き防戦短時間で破れ退く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This took the Ming army by surprise and they broke ranks and retreated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This took the Ming army by surprise, so they broke ranks and retreated.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This took the Ming army by surprise, so they broke ranks and retreated in a second.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>図書助等これを機とし兵を収めて退く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zushonosuke used this chance to gather the troops and retreat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zushonosuke used this opportunity to gather the troops and retreat.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zushonosuke used this opportunity to rally the soldiers and retreat.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>時に長政は遥かに銃声を先鋒の方向に聞き麾下3000を率いてこれに馳せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time Nagamasa heard the gun shots from afar and led his 3,000 in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, Nagamasa heard the gun shots in the distance and led his 3,000 troops in.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, Nagamasa heard the gun shots from the place in the distance where the spearhead was present and led his 3,000 troops in the direction.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>先鋒の兵敵に追躡せられ其勢は甚だ危うし。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He was pursued by enemy advance troops and was in a dangerous position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, he was pursued by enemy advance troops and was therefore in a dangerous position.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, he was pursued by the enemy&apos;s vanguard and was therefore in a dangerous position.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>黒田三左衛門曰く「先鋒がもし敗れたならば我が本軍もまた恐らくは支え難からん是れ吾が死所なり。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanzaemon KURODA said &quot;If the advance troops lost, our main troops will probably not hold, so this is to be my last stand&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanzaemon KURODA said, &quot;If the advance troops have lost, our main troops will probably not hold, so this is to be my last stand.&quot;</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanzaemon KURODA said, &apos;If the advance troops lost, our main troops will probably not hold, so this is to be my last stand.&apos;</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>そして手兵を以て敵を側撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">and attacked the enemy&apos;s flank with his troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He then attacked the enemy&apos;s flank with his troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, he attacked the enemy&apos;s flank with his troops.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。一原文一訳文の例外対処」と～になっていたので、」までを前列にまとめました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>後藤基次は一高地を占領し其部兵を馳駆せしめ、以て敵をして我衆寡を測らさしめ、且つ先鋒兵に声援する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsugu GOTO held some high ground and sent troops to fight the enemy and support the advance troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsugu GOTO, who held some high ground, sent troops to fight the enemy and support the advance troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mototsugu GOTO, who held a high ground, sent troops to fight the enemy, prevent the enemy from becoming aware that our troops are outnumbered, and also support our vanguards.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>三左衛門遂に先鋒の兵を収容して還る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sanzaemon gathered the advance troops and returned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sanzaemon gathered the advance troops and returned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sanzaemon rallied the vanguards and returned.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="31">
<j>長政は戦場に到着すると直ちに東方の高地に上がって自ら敵情を偵察し、乃ちその隊の部署を改め</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Nagamasa arrived tat the battlefield, he immediately went up the high ground on the east side and inspected the enemy status himself and changed the formation of his troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Nagamasa arrived at the battlefield, he immediately went up the high ground on the eastern side and inspected the enemy&apos;s status, whereupon he changed the formation of his troops.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Nagamasa arrived at the battlefield, he immediately went up the high ground on the eastern side and inspected the enemy&apos;s status, whereupon he changed the formation of his troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>右備一番隊は母里太兵衛・栗山利安・黒田兵庫助をこれに任じ、井上九郎兵衛・野村市右衛門を二番隊としてこれに次き、左備一番隊は後藤基次・黒田三左衛門がこれに当り、黒田図書助・桐山孫兵衛が二番隊としてこれに次く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first group of the right wing was led by Tahyoe MORI, Toshiyasu KURIYAMA and Hyogonosuke KURODA, with Kurobei INOUE and Ichiemon NOMURA leading the reserve, and the left wing was led by Mototsugu GOTO and Sanzaemon KURODA with Sanzaemon KURODA and Magobei KIRIYAMA as the reserve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first group of the right wing was led by Tahyoe MORI, Toshiyasu KURIYAMA and Hyogonosuke KURODA, with Kurobei INOUE and Ichiemon NOMURA leading the reserve, and the left wing was led by Mototsugu GOTO and Sanzaemon KURODA with Sanzaemon KURODA and Magobei KIRIYAMA as the reserve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first group of the right wing, which was led by Tahyoe MORI, Toshiyasu KURIYAMA and Hyogonosuke KURODA, followed by the second group led by Kurobei INOUE and Ichiemon NOMURA, and the first group of the left wijng, which was led by Mototsugu GOTO and Sanzaemon KURODA, follwoed by the second group led by Zushonosuke KURODA and Magobei KIRIYAMA.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>長政は自ら爾餘の兵2000人を率いて本隊たり。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagamasa led the rest of the 2000 troops himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nagamasa personally led the remaining 2,000 troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nagamasa personally led the remaining 2,000 troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>時に明将解生等が水原より到来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, the Ming warrior, Kaisei and others arrived from Suwon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, the Ming warrior, Kaisei and others arrived from Suwon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, the Ming warriors including Kaisei arrived from Suwon.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>遊撃擺賽・千総李盆喬・把総劉遇節等2000人の援軍を得て再び兵気を回復して攻め寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the arrival of 2000 troops led by 遊撃擺賽・千総李盆喬Li・把総劉遇節Ryu, the army regained energy and pressed on.</e>
<cmt>遊撃擺賽・千総李盆喬・把総劉遇節、読みが見つかりませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the arrival of the 2,000 troops led by Chinese leaders such as 遊撃擺賽, 千総李盆喬 and 把総劉遇節, the army regained energy and pressed on.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the arrival of the 2,000 troops led by Chinese leaders ranger Haisen, Senso ribonkyo and Haso Ryogusetsu, the army regained energy and attacked the enemy.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。遊撃擺賽, 千総李盆喬 and 把総劉遇節は定訳は不明です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>両軍末院の野に戦い奮闘数合にして勝敗未だ決せず。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both troops clashed several times at the fields of Matsuin but there was no decisive winner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two sides clashed several times in the fields of Matsuin, but there was no decisive winner.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two sides clashed several times in the fields of Matsuin, but there was no decisive winner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="37">
<j>毛利秀元は天安に在り稷山の戦急なるを聞き、乃ちその兵を率いてこれに赴援し先鋒の将宍戸元続・吉見広行等に先ず進ませた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidemoto MORI at Cheonan heard about the precarious situation at Shokusan, and immediately rushed to support with the advance troops led by Mototsugu SHISHIDO and Hiroyuki YOSHIMI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidemoto MORI, at Cheonn, heard about the precarious situation at Shokusan and immediately rushed to support with the advance troops led by Mototsugu SHISHIDO an Hiroyuki YOSHIMI.</e>
<cmt>space</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidemoto MORI was at Cheonn, heard about the precarious situation at Shokusan and immediately rushed to support the battle at Shokusan with his army, ordered vanguards including Mototsugu SHISHIDO and Hiroyuki YOSHIMI to spearhead the attack.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>元続等急駆してこれに赴き黒田隊を助けて敵の側背に突撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mototsugu hurried and helped the Kuroda troops by attacking the enemy&apos;s rear and flank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mototsugu hurried and helped the Kuroda troops by attacking the enemy&apos;s rear and flank.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those incuding Mototsugu rushed for and helped the Kuroda troops by attacking the enemy&apos;s rear and flank.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>明軍遂に大いに敗れ水原方向に退く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ming army at last were defeated and retreated towards Suwon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming army was at last defeated and retreated toward Suwon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming army was soundly defeated and retreated toward Suwon.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>時正に午後3時を過ぎ、故に日本軍は敢えて追撃せず兵を収めて天安に還る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time was after 3 p.m. and the Japanese army did not pursuit the enemy but gathered troops and returned to Cheonan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was after 3 p.m., so the Japanese army didn&apos;t pursuit the enemy but instead gathered its troops and returned to Cheonan.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was after 3 pm, so the Japanese army didn&apos;t pursuit the enemy, and rallied the troops and returned to Cheonan instead.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>この日の戦闘で日本軍の戦死黒田兵29人、明軍の戦死200餘人。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dead in this day&apos;s battle numbered 29 Kuroda troops for the Japanese army and about 200 troops for the Ming army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dead in this day&apos;s battle numbered 29 Kuroda troops for the Japanese army and about 200 troops for the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dead in this day&apos;s battle numbered 29 soldiers in the Kuroda troops for the Japanese army and about 200 soldiers for the Ming army.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>戦闘後の経緯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progress after battle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progress After the Battle</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progress after the battle</e>
<cmt>文頭のみ大文字</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="42">
<j>稷山に日本軍が進出すると明・朝鮮軍では漢江を防衛線として守りを固める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army headed towards Shokusan and the Ming/Korean army drew a defensive line at Han-gang and strengthened its defenses.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army headed toward Shokusan, and the Ming/Korean army drew a defensive line at Han-gang and strengthened its defenses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Japanese army headed toward Shokusan, the Ming-Korean army drew a defensive line at Han-gang and strengthened its defenses.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>しかし漢城では日本軍の接近でパニックに陥っており、人々は逃走をはかりほとんど無人となるほどであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in Hanseong, people panicked about the approaching Japanese army and fled so the city was virtually empty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in Hanseong people panicked about the approaching Japanese army and fled, so the city was virtually empty.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in Hanseong people panicked at the approaching Japanese army and fled, so the city was virtually empty.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>一方日本の右軍は稷山での戦闘の後、京畿道に入り安城・竹山まで進撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, the right wing of the Japanese army took the Gyeonggi-do and invaded Anseong/Chuksan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the right wing of the Japanese army took the Gyeonggi-do and invaded Anseong/Chuksan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, after the battle of Shokusan, the right army of Japan entered the Gyeonggi-do and invaded Anseong and Chuksan.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>その後計画に従い、京畿道、忠清道、全羅道の各日本軍はそれぞれ反転して朝鮮半島南岸に還り築城を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, following the plan, the Japanese army at Gyeonggi-do, Chungcheong-do and Jeolla-do reversed and went back to the southern coast of the Korean Penninsula to start building castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, following the plan, the Japanese army at Gyeonggi-do, Chungcheong-do and Jeolla-do reversed and went back to the southern coast of the Korean Peninsula in order to start building castles.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, following the plan, the Japanese troops at Gyeonggi-do, Chungcheong-do and Jeolla-do were reversed and went back to the southern coast of the Korean Peninsula in order to start building castles.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>朝鮮の朝廷では日本軍の反転理由が分からず日本軍の罠ではないかと疑った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean court could not understand the reason for this reversal in movement and thought it was a trap by the Japanese army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean court couldn&apos;t understand the reason for this reversal in movement, so it was assumed that the Japanese army was setting a trap.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean court couldn&apos;t understand the reason for this reversal, and assumed that the Japanese army was setting a trap.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="47">
<j>朝鮮半島南岸で築城を急ぐ日本軍に対し明・朝鮮軍は反攻を企画し、建設中の城塞群の内最東端に位置する蔚山城に目標を定めて攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ming/Korean army planned a counterattack against the Japanese army rushing to build castles on the southern coast of the Korean Penninsula, setting their target to the most eastern of the castles being constructed, Urusan-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ming (Korean) army planned a counterattack against the Japanese army&apos;s rush to build castles on the southern coast of the peninsula, and targeted the easternmost castle being constructed, which was Urusan-jo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ming-Korean army planned a counterattack against the Japanese army, which was hurried in building castles on the southern coast of the peninsula, and attacked the easternmost castle being constructed, which was Urusan-jo.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この蔚山城の戦いは12月22日から始まったが、加藤清正等は城を堅く守り、毛利秀元らが救援して翌年1月4日、明・朝鮮軍を大破する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Battle of Urusan-jo Castle started on December 22, but the castle was defended by Kiyomasa KATO and with the support with Hidemoto MORI and others, the Ming/Korean army was shattered on January 4 of the next year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Battle of Urusan-jo Castle started on December 22, but the castle was defended by Kiyomasa KATO and, with the support with Hidemoto MORI and others, the Ming (Korean) army was shattered on January 4 of the following year.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Battle of Urusan-jo Castle started on January 29, 1598, but the castle was defended by Kiyomasa KATO and, with the support of Hidemoto MORI and others, the Ming-Korean army was shattered on February 9.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 玄史生(id:43670), Tokugawa(id:61656), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>