<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>錦の御旗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial standard (made of gold brocade)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiki no mihata (The Imperial Standard)</e>
<cmt>後述に略称・別名がありますので、ローマ字表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiki no mihata (The Imperial Standard)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>錦の御旗（にしきのみはた）とは、朝廷の軍（官軍）の旗印。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial standard is the banner of the Imperial court army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial standard is the banner of the Imperial court army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial standard is the banner of the Imperial court army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>略称錦旗（きんき）、別名菊章旗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Its abbreviated name is Kinki, and its another name is Kikushoki.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Its abbreviated name is Kinki, and its another name is Kikushoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Its abbreviated name is Kinki, and its another name is Kikushoki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>赤地の錦に、金色の日像・銀色の月像を刺繍したり、描いたりした旗（この日之御旗と月之御旗は二つ一組）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial standard is a pair of red brocade banners with a gold sun embroidery in one banner and a silver moon embroidery in the other banner or with a picture of gold sun in one banner and a picture of silver moon in the other banner (It is a pair of a sun banner and a moon banner.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial standard is a pair of banners made of red brocade with a gold sun (Hi no mihata) and a silver moon (Tsuki no mihata) embroidered or pictured on each.</e>
<cmt>簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial standard is a pair of banners made of red brocade with a gold sun (Hi no mihata) and a silver moon (Tsuki no mihata) embroidered or pictured on each.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>朝敵討伐の証として、天皇から官軍の大将に下賜する慣習がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial standard was a symbol of the Imperial court army and it was customary in Japan that the Imperial standard was bestowed by Emperor on his military commanders.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was customary in Japan that an emperor bestowed it on his military commanders as proof of putting down emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>この原文では「錦の御旗」と記載されていませんので、ｉｔを使って全体を簡略化しました。特定の天皇を指していないので、an emperorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was customary in Japan that an emperor bestowed it on his military commanders as proof of putting down emperor&apos;s enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>承久の乱（1221年（承久3年））に際し、後鳥羽上皇が配下の将に与えた物が、歴史上の錦旗の初見とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The retired Emperor Gotoba bestowed the Imperial standard on his warrior in the Joyku War (1221) for the first time in history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Retired Emperor Gotoba bestowed it on his warrior in the Jokyu War (1221) for the first time in history.</e>
<cmt>この原文では「錦の御旗」と記載されていませんので、ｉｔを使いました。スペルミスを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Retired Emperor Gotoba bestowed it on his warrior in the Jokyu War (1221) for the first time in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>戊辰戦争と錦の御旗</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Boshin War and the Imperial Standard</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Boshin War and the Imperial Standard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Boshin War and the Imperial Standard</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>1868年（慶応4年）正月、鳥羽伏見の戦いにおいて、薩摩藩の本営であった東寺に錦旗が掲げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1868 the Imperial standard was unfurled at Toji Temple, which had been the headquarters of Satsuma clan at the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1868, the Imperial standard was unfurled at Toji Temple, which had been the headquarters of the Satsuma clan at the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>「薩摩藩」にtheを補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1868, the Imperial standard was unfurled at Toji Temple, which had been the headquarters of the Satsuma clan at the Battle of Toba-Fushimi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この錦旗は、慶応3年10月6日に薩摩藩の大久保利通と長州藩の品川弥二郎が、愛宕郡岩倉村にある中御門経之の別邸で岩倉具視と会見した際に調製を委嘱された物であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This Imperial standard was decided to be made when Toshimichi OKUBO of Satsuma clan and Yajiro SHINAGAWA of Choshu clan met Tomomi IWAKURA at Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO&apos;s second house in Iwakura Village, Otagi-gun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Imperial standard was entrusted to be prepared when Toshimichi OKUBO of the Satsuma clan and Yajiro SHINAGAWA of the Choshu clan met Tomomi IWAKURA at Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO&apos;s second house in Iwakura Village, Otagi County on November 1, 1867.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ「慶応3年10月6日に」を追記しました。「郡」をCountyに変更しました。「調製を委嘱された」の訳を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Imperial standard was entrusted to be prepared when Toshimichi OKUBO of the Satsuma clan and Yajiro SHINAGAWA of the Choshu clan met Tomomi IWAKURA at Tsuneyuki NAKAMIKADO&apos;s second house in Iwakura Village, Otagi County on November 1, 1867.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="8">
<j>岩倉の腹心玉松操のデザインを元を作った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The design of this Imperial standard was based on the plans of Misao TAMAMATSU, a trustworthy assistant of IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The design of this Imperial standard was based on the plans of Misao TAMAMATSU, a trustworthy assistant of IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The design of this Imperial standard was based on the plans of Misao TAMAMATSU, a trustworthy assistant of IWAKURA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>大久保が京都市中で大和錦と紅白の緞子を調達し、半分を京都薩摩藩邸で密造させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">OKUBO obtained Yamato-nishiki type silk and red and white damask silk from Kyoto City and had one of a pair of the banners made secretly at the residence of Satsuma clan in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OKUBO got Yamato-nishiki type silk and red and white damask silk in Kyoto City and had one of a pair of the banners made secretly at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>「で～を調達」をgot ~ inに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OKUBO got Yamato-nishiki type silk and red and white damask silk in Kyoto City and had one of a pair of the banners made secretly at the residence of the Satsuma clan in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>もう半分は数日後に品川が材料を長州に持ち帰って錦旗に仕立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A few days later SHINAGAWA took the remaining material to Choshu Domain and finished up the other banner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A few days later SHINAGAWA took the remaining materials to Choshu Domain and had the other Kinki made up.</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A few days later SHINAGAWA took the remaining materials to Choshu Domain and had the other Kinki made up.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>その後戊辰戦争の各地の戦いで薩長両軍を中心に使用された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army of Satsuma clan and Choshu clan put up the Imperial standards as a token of Imperial court army at many battle fields of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army of the Satsuma clan and the Choshu clan put it up at many battle fields of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>不要箇所を削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army of the Satsuma clan and the Choshu clan put it up at many battle fields of the Boshin War.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>官軍の証である錦旗の存在は士気を大いに鼓舞すると共に、賊軍の立場となった江戸幕府側に非常に大きな打撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the one hand the banners helped boost the morale of the soldiers of the Imperial court army a lot; but at the same time they gave a serious shock to the soldiers of the Edo shogunate&apos;s army, who came to feel that their army turned into the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While the banner of the Imperial army helped boost the morale of the soldiers of its army very much, it gave a serious shock to the soldiers of the Edo shogunate&apos;s army, who came to feel that their army turned into the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>「官軍の証である」を明確にし、全体を簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While the banner of the Imperial army helped boost the morale of the soldiers of its army very much, it gave a serious shock to the soldiers of the Edo shogunate&apos;s army, who came to feel that their army turned into the rebel army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>当時土佐藩士として戦いに参加し、のちに宮内大臣や内閣書記官長などを歴任した田中光顕は、錦の御旗を知らしめただけで前線の幕府兵達が「このままでは朝敵になってしまう」と青ざめて退却する場面を目撃している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsuaki TANAKA, who joined the war as a retainer of Tosa clan and later became Minister of the Imperial Households and Secretary of the Cabinet, witnessed the white-faced soldiers of the Edo shogunate retreating at the sight of the Imperial standards in the battle fields, saying, &apos;We&apos;d better stop fighting, otherwise we will become the enemy to Emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsuaki TANAKA, who joined the war as a retainer of the Tosa clan and later became Minister of the Imperial Households and Secretary of the Cabinet, witnessed the white-faced soldiers of the Edo shogunate retreating at the sight of the Imperial standards in the battle fields, saying, &apos;We&apos;d better stop fighting, otherwise we will become the enemy of the Emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>定冠詞を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsuaki TANAKA, who joined the war as a retainer of the Tosa clan and later became Minister of the Imperial Households and Secretary of the Cabinet, witnessed the white-faced soldiers of the Edo shogunate retreating at the sight of the Imperial standards in the battle fields, saying, &apos;We&apos;d better stop fighting, otherwise we will become the enemy of the Emperor.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>戊辰戦争に使用された各種錦旗及び軍旗類は、明治維新後は陸軍省の遊就館や宮内省図書寮に保存された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration the Imperial standards and battle flags used in the Boshin War were kept in Yushu-kan, a treasure house of Ministry of Army and in Zusho-ryo, a library of Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Meiji Restoration the Imperial standards and battle flags used in the Boshin War were kept in Yushu-kan, a treasure house of Ministry of Army and in Zusho-ryo, a library of Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Meiji Restoration the Imperial standards and battle flags used in the Boshin War were kept in Yushu-kan, a treasure house of Ministry of Army and in Zusho-ryo, a library of Imperial Household Ministry.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>1888年（明治21年）政府は、長州藩出身の絵師、浮田可成（うきたかせい）に旗の絵を描かせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1888 the Meiji government ordered Kasei UKITA, a painter of Choshu Domain, to draw the Imperial standards.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1888 the Meiji government ordered Kasei UKITA, a painter of Choshu Domain, to draw the Imperial standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1888 the Meiji government ordered Kasei UKITA, a painter of Choshu Domain, to draw the Imperial standards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>それらは17種34枚の絵図に図化され、『戊辰所用錦旗及軍旗真図』（ぼしんしょようきんきおよびぐんきしんず）4巻にまとめられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He painted thirty-four paintings of seventeen types of banners and created a book in four volumes named &quot;Boshin shoyo Kinki oyobi Gunki-shinzu&quot; (Pictures of the Imperial Standards and Battle Flags Used in the Boshin War.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He painted thirty-four paintings of seventeen types of banners, which were compiled into a book in four volumes named &quot;Boshin shoyo Kinki oyobi Gunki-shinzu&quot; (Pictures of the Imperial Standards and Battle Flags Used in the Boshin War).</e>
<cmt>後半を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He painted thirty-four paintings of seventeen types of banners, which were compiled into a book in four volumes named &quot;Boshin shoyo Kinki oyobi Gunki-shinzu&quot; (Pictures of the Imperial Standards and Battle Flags Used in the Boshin War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>錦旗革命事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kinki Revolution Coup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kinki Revolution Coup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kinki Revolution Coup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>大川周明は、共産主義革命に対抗して天皇を頂点とする「錦旗革命（きんきかくめい）」を起こして、日本を正しい方向に導くべきだと唱えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shumei OKAWA argued that we should create the regime with the emperor at its top against the communist revolution to steer Japan in the right direction and drove &apos;Kinki Revolution.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Against the communist revolution, Shumei OKAWA argued for &apos;Kinki Revolution&apos; that aimed to steer Japan in the right direction with an emperor at the top.</e>
<cmt>簡略化しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Against the communist revolution, Shumei OKAWA argued for &apos;Kinki Revolution&apos; that aimed to steer Japan in the right direction with an emperor at the top.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>このため、大川自身も計画に参加した大日本帝国陸軍将校によるクーデター計画・十月事件を「錦旗革命事件」とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, a plot of October Coup in which OKAWA participated, made by the military officers of Imperial Japanese Army, was also called &apos;Kinki Revolution Coup.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the October Incident in which OKAWA participated, plotted by the military officers of Imperial Japanese Army, was also called &apos;Kinki Revolution Coup.&apos;</e>
<cmt>「十月事件」はincidentの方がよく使われているようです。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the October Incident in which OKAWA participated, plotted by the military officers of Imperial Japanese Army, was also called &apos;Kinki Revolution Coup.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 ( ^ω^)(id:71899), DCyokohama(id:26779), 蒼海牧菜(id:78923), Akaman4444(id:249358), Kogane(id:28186), MULTIVAC(id:110454), Pqks758(id:35879), Mop(id:12061), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>