<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>律令法</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsuryo law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsuryo law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsuryo Law</e>
<cmt>law→Law</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>律令法（りつりょうほう）は律令格式（きゃくしき）などの制定法および平安時代になって律令を基礎にして成立した各種の慣習法をふくめたもの。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsuryo law includes statutory laws such as laws of codes and ethics (conduct), and various common laws established in the Heian period based on ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsuryo law includes statutory laws such as; codes and ethics covering conduct, and various common laws established in the Heian period based upon ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>semi-colon inserted after &quot;such as&quot; removed second &quot;law&quot;and added &quot;covering conduct&quot; removing parenthesis, &quot;on&quot; replaced with &quot;upon&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsuryo law includes statutory laws such as; codes and ethics covering conduct, and various common laws established in the Heian period based upon ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>大化改新以後の中央集権的国家の制定した公法を中心とする法体系である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a system of law centered around public law established by the centralized nation after the Reformation of Taika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It&apos;s centered around public law established by the centralized nation after the Taika Reformation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;It&apos;s a system of law&quot; removed and replaced with &quot;It&apos;s&quot;, &quot;Taika Reformation&quot; used in place of previous wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It&apos;s centered around public law established by the centralized nation after the Taika Reformation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>なお、律令それ自体については律令の項を、律令に基づく制度各般については律令制の項を、それぞれ参照されたい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For information on ritsuryo itself and on systems based on ritsuryo, refer to the pages on ritsuryo and ritsuryo system respectively.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For information on ritsuryo itself and systems based on ritsuryo, refer to the pages on ritsuryo and ritsuryo system respectively.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and on systems&quot; changed to &quot;and systems&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For information on ritsuryo itself and systems based on ritsuryo, refer to the pages on ritsuryo and the ritsuryo system respectively.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞必要。 “ ritsuryo system”=&gt;”the ritsuryo system”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>律令法の階級性</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hierarchical nature of ritsuryo law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hierarchical nature of ritsuryo law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hierarchical nature of ritsuryo law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="4">
<j>律令法は、大化改新によって支配権を握った畿内および近国の貴族層が、従来のように豪族を媒介として全国を支配するのではなく、官僚機構によって人民の末端にいたるまで統治するための法であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The goal of ritsuryo law was to enable the kizoku (noble) class in Kinai and Kingoku who gained power with the Reformation of Taika to govern the people at every level through bureaucracy, instead of ruling the nation through local ruling families as in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The goal of ritsuryo law was to enable the kizoku (noble) class in Kinai and Kingoku, who gained power during the Taika Reformation, to govern the people at every level through bureaucracy, instead of ruling the nation through local ruling families like in the past.</e>
<cmt>commas inserted after &quot;Kingoku&quot; and after &quot;Taika Reformation&quot; which was changed from previous wording, and &quot;as&quot; replaced with &quot;like&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The goal of ritsuryo law was to enable the kizoku (noble) class in Kinai and nearby provinces, who gained power during the Taika Reformation, to govern the people at every level through bureaucracy, instead of ruling the nation through local ruling families like in the past.</e>
<cmt>Kingoku→nearby provinces</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>従って貴族制的な身分秩序を法によって確立することが律令法の骨格となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, the framework of ritsuryo law was the establishment by law of a class system somewhat like the kizoku system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, the framework of ritsuryo law was the legal establishment of a class system somewhat like the kizoku system.</e>
<cmt>revised; &quot;legal&quot; added before established, &quot;by law&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, the framework of ritsuryo law was the legal establishment of a class system somewhat like the kizoku system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>律令法の身分制度は人民を良・賤（せん）に二大別することを特徴とし、両者の中間に大化前代の部民（べのたみ）の後身である品部（しなべ）、雑戸（ざつこ）の身分がおかれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The class system in ritsuryo law is characterized by the division of the people roughly into two groups, ryo (law-abiding people)/sen (humble or lowly people), and shinabe (technicians in offices) and zakko (special technicians) who were descendants of benotami (officers and people serving the Yamato dynasty) from pre-Taika era were placed in between them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The class system under ritsuryo law is characterized by the division of the people roughly into two groups, ryo (law-abiding people)/sen (humble or lowly people), and shinabe (technicians in offices) with zakko (special technicians) who were descendants of benotami (officers and people serving the Yamato dynasty) from pre-Taika era placed in between them.</e>
<cmt>&quot;under&quot; placed before &quot;ritsuryo law,&quot; &quot;with&quot; replacing &quot;and&quot; to distinquish a third group that was placed in between the two groups.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The class system under ritsuryo law is characterized by the division of the people roughly into two groups, ryo (law-abiding people)/sen (humble or lowly people), and shinabe (technicians in offices) with zakko (special technicians) who were descendants of benotami (officers and people serving the Yamato dynasty) from pre-Taika era placed in between them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>賤民の身分は、陵戸、官戸、家人古代の家人（けにん）、公奴婢（ぬひ）、私奴婢の5階層に区別され、各階層は同一身分内部で婚姻しなければならないという当色婚の制度によって隔離されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The senmin (humble or lowly people) class was divided into five ranks, namely, ryoko (imperial tomb guard), kanko (slaves to public ministries), kenin (slaves of nobles), kunuhi (government-owned slave), and shinuhi (privately-owned slave), and the ranks were segregated by a tojikikon system where marriage must be between the same class.</e>
<cmt>「家人古代の家人（けにん）」は「家人（けにん）」の誤記と解釈しました（http://dictionary.goo.ne.jp/leaf/jn/68307/m0u/%E3%81%94%E3%81%97/）。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The senmin (humble or lowly people) class was divided into five ranks, namely, ryoko (imperial tomb guards), kanko (slaves to public ministries), kenin (slaves of nobles), kunuhi (government-owned slaves), and shinuhi (privately-owned slaves), and the ranks were segregated by a tojikikon system where marriage must be between those of the same class.</e>
<cmt>&quot;s&quot; added on the ends of the words &quot;guard and slave, and &quot;those of&quot; inserted befoe &quot;the same class.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The senmin (humble or lowly people) class was divided into five ranks, namely, ryoko (imperial tomb guards), kanko (slaves to public ministries), kenin (slaves of nobles), kunuhi (government-owned slaves), and shinuhi (privately-owned slaves), and the ranks were segregated by a tojikikon system where marriage must be between those of the same class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この複雑な賤民の等級は、唐令の賤民制度の継承であるが、それは中世武家法における賤民制度とちがった律令法の特徴をなしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This complex classification of senmin succeeded the senmin system of torei (codes in the Tang era), and characterizes ritsuryo law as something different from the senmin system under the medieval samurai law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This complex classification of senmin succeeded the senmin system of torei (codes in the Tang era), and characterizes ritsuryo law as something different from the senmin system under medieval samurai law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; deleted from medieval samurai law&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This complex classification of senmin succeeded the senmin system of torei (codes in the Tang era), and characterizes ritsuryo law as something different from the senmin system under medieval samurai law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>良民は階級的には貴族と平民に二大別されているが、両者の区別は法的には明確ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryomin (law-abiding people) was roughly divided into two classes, kizoku and heimin (commoner), although distinction between the two were not clear by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryomin (law-abiding people) were roughly divided into two classes, kizoku and heimin (commoners), although distinction between the two were not clear by law.</e>
<cmt>:&quot;was&quot; changed to &quot;were&quot;and &quot;s&quot; added to &quot;commoner&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryomin (law-abiding people) were roughly divided into two classes, kizoku and heimin (commoners), although distinction between the two were not clear by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>ただ五位以上の位をもつものの経済的・政治的特権は法によって保証され、また有位者は一般に課役その他の義務を免除されていた点で、租庸調、雑徭（ぞうよう）などの課税および兵役の義務を負っていた一般平民と区別されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the economic and political privileges granted to those at the fifth or higher ranks were guaranteed by law, and those with a rank generally were exempt from taxes and other duties, distinguishing them from the general heimin who were subject to taxation such as soyocho (corvee, taxes in kind or service) and zoyo (irregular corvee), as well as military service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the economic and political privileges granted to those at the fifth or higher ranks were guaranteed by law, and those with rank generally were exempt from taxes and other duties, distinguishing them from the general heimin who were subject to taxation such as soyocho (corvee, taxes in kind or service) and zoyo (irregular corvee), as well as military service.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a rank&quot; changed to &quot;rank&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the economic and political privileges granted to those at the fifth or higher ranks were guaranteed by law, and those with rank generally were exempt from taxes and other duties, distinguishing them from the general heimin who were subject to taxation such as soyocho (corvee, taxes in kind or service) and zoyo (irregular corvee), as well as military service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>律令法は貴族層が、その特権と支配を維持するための法であるから、賤民制度をふくめた全体の身分の体系は、法によって明確に規定しておく必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose of ritsuryo law was to enable the kizoku class to maintain its privilege and dominance, and therefore, a general class system including the senmin system had to be clearly defined by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose of ritsuryo law was to enable the kizoku class to maintain its privilege and dominance, and therefore, a general class system, including the senmin, had to be clearly defined by law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;senmin system&quot; changed to senmin</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose of ritsuryo law was to enable the kizoku class to maintain its privilege and dominance, and therefore, a general class system, including the senmin, had to be clearly defined by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="12">
<j>律令法によって規定された身分秩序において、独特の地位を占めているのは、天皇の地位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A unique position in the class system defined by ritsuryo law is the position of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A unique position in the class system defined by ritsuryo law is the position of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A unique position in the class system defined by ritsuryo law is the position of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>律令においては、天皇の地位、権限その他については、なんらの規定がない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In ritsuryo, there is no provision on the position, authority, etc. of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In ritsuryo, there is no provision for the position, authority, etc. of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;on&quot; changed to &quot;for&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In ritsuryo, there is no provision for the position, authority, etc. of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>これは天皇が法を超越した存在と考えられていた結果であって、天皇の政治的重要性と矛盾するものではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is due to the fact that the Emperor was considered to be above the law, and is not contradictory to the political significance of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is due to the fact that the Emperor was considered to be above the law, and therefore, is not contradictory to the political significance of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>&quot;therefore&quot; inserted after &quot;and&quot;comma removed after &quot;and&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is due to the fact that the Emperor was considered to be above the law, and therefore, is not contradictory to the political significance of the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>律令制には一種の罪刑法定主義の原則があって、裁判は成文の法規に準拠しなければならなかったが、天皇は法によって拘束されない存在であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was a kind of legality principle in the ritsuryo system, which required trials to comply with statutory law while the Emperor was not bound by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was a kind of legality principle in the ritsuryo system, which required trials to comply with statutory law while the Emperor was not bound by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was a kind of legality principle in the ritsuryo system, which required trials to comply with statutory law while the Emperor was not bound by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="16">
<j>律令法において、天皇の地位、権能について規定がないのも、それが国家的祭祀の執行など大化前代以来の宗教的機能をもっていたことと、専制君主的性格をもったことの結果であって、法を超越した存在と考えられていたからである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The position and authority of Emperors were not defined in the ritsuryo law, due to their religious function such as the performance of national religious services since the pre-Taika era, and as a result of their despotic nature, which made them above the law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The position and authority of Emperors were not defined in the ritsuryo law, due to their religious functions, such as; their performing of national religious services since the pre-Taika era, and as a result of their despotic nature, this made them above the law.</e>
<cmt>simi-colon inserted after &quot;such as,&quot; following revised as: performing of national religious services&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The position and authority of Emperors were not defined in the ritsuryo law, due to their religious functions, such as; their performing of national religious services since the pre-Taika era, and as a result of their despotic nature, this made them above the law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="17">
<j>また、天皇と律令法との関係で重要であったのは、生命刑である死罪 (律令法)執行の大権は天皇のみに帰属していたことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An important point in the relationship between the Emperor and ritsuryo law is that the prerogative for the execution of death sentence (ritsuryo law), a capital punishment, belonged solely to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An important point in the relationship between the Emperor and ritsuryo law is that the prerogative for the execution of death sentence (ritsuryo law), a capital punishment, belonged solely to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An important point in the relationship between the Emperor and ritsuryo law is that the prerogative for the execution of death sentence (ritsuryo law), a capital punishment, belonged solely to the Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>たとえ、刑部省などで死罪が適当とする判決が出されたとしても、3回天皇に覆奏（三覆奏）を行って天皇から許しを得た場合に死罪が執行されることとなっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even if the gyobusho (ministry of justice) decided that death sentence was appropriate, fukuso (reporting to the Emperor after repeated research) was performed three times with the Emperor, and the Emperor had to approve for the death sentence to be executed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even if the gyobusho (ministry of justice) decided that death sentence was appropriate, fukuso (reporting to the Emperor after repeating research) was performed three times with the Emperor, and the Emperor had to approve the execution of the death sentence.</e>
<cmt>&quot;repeated&quot; changed to &quot;repeating&quot;last part revised to &quot;had to approve the execution of the death sentence.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even if the gyobusho (ministry of justice) decided that the death sentence was appropriate, fukuso (reporting to the Emperor after repeating research) was performed three times with the Emperor, and the Emperor had to approve the execution of the death sentence.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞必要。 “that death sentence”=&gt;”that the death sentence”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>従って、天皇の許可が出なければ、流罪に減刑されることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, without approval by the Emperor, the sentence would be reduced to banishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, without the approval of the Emperor, the sentence would be reduced to banishment.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by&quot; changed to &quot;of&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, without the approval of the Emperor, the sentence would be reduced to banishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>なお、流罪の場合でも非常赦と呼ばれる特別な恩赦が出ない限りは生涯流刑地から離れることは許されず、また死刑の際に付随される親族の連坐や除名、資財田宅の没官は宥免されなかったことから、当時の社会においては社会的に完全に抹殺される効果はあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the case of banishment, no permission was given to leave the place of banishment for life unless special amnesty called hiyosha was granted, and the family members could not be pardoned the guilt-by-association, expulsion, and impounding of assets and farm/housing land that came along with the death sentence, which effectively denied their social existence entirely in those times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the case of banishment, it was not permited to leave the place where one was bansihed for life unless special amnesty called hiyosha was granted, and the family members could not be pardoned from guilt-by-association, also, expulsion, and impounding of assets and farm/housing land that went along with the death sentence, which effectively and entirely denied their social existence in those times.</e>
<cmt>&quot;banishment&quot;replaced with &quot;where one was bansihed&quot; &quot;it was not permited to leave&quot; replaced former wording, and &quot;could not be pardoned from guilt-by-association&quot; replaced former wording, &quot;also,&quot; added before &quot;expulsion,&quot;&quot;came along&quot; replaced by &quot;went along&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the case of banishment, it was not permitted to leave the place where one was banished for life unless special amnesty called hijosha was granted, and family members could not be pardoned from guilt-by-association, also, expulsion, and impounding of assets and farm/housing land that went along with the death sentence, which effectively and entirely denied their social existence in those times.</e>
<cmt>“ and the family members”=&gt; “ and family members ”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>まとめ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conclusion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conclusion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conclusion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="21">
<j>天皇を除けば、すべての身分・階層が法のもとに拘束される原則が支配している点で、律令法は一種の法治主義の特色をもっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ritsuryo law can be characterized as a kind of nomocracy, in that the dominant principle was that all classes and ranks other than the Emperor are bound by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsuryo law can be characterized as a kind of nomocracy, in that the dominant principle was that all classes and ranks other than the Emperor are bound by law.</e>
<cmt>revised to begin the sentence with &quot;Ritsuryo law&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsuryo law can be characterized as a kind of nomocracy, in that the dominant principle was that all classes and ranks other than the Emperor are bound by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかしこの原則は律令法の階級性を否定するものでなく、たとえば現実の刑の適用にみられる貴族の特権的地位の保証は、律令法が貴族階級のための法であったことを示している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this principle does not deny the hierarchical nature of ritsuryo law, and for example, the guaranteeing of the privileged position of kizoku with regards to the actual application of penalties, indicates that the ritsuryo law served the kizoku class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this principle does not deny the hierarchical nature of ritsuryo law, for example, the guaranteeing of the privileged position of kizoku with regard to the actual application of penalties, indicates that ritsuryo law served the kizoku class.</e>
<cmt>&quot;and&quot; deleted before &quot;for example,&quot; &quot;s&quot; deleted from the end of &quot;regard,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this principle does not deny the hierarchical nature of ritsuryo law, for example, the guaranteeing of the privileged position of kizoku with regard to the actual application of penalties, indicates that ritsuryo law served the kizoku class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>刑罰について特別の斟酌（しんしゃく）をうける六議（ろくぎ）の制度のみならず、有位者がその位階に応じて罪の軽減をうけたり、また現実には、八虐（はちぎやく）・殺人などの重罪を犯さないかぎり一般の刑罰をうけることがなかったことは、その一例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For instance, in addition to the rokugi (six considerations) system where special allowance was made for punishment, those with a rank had their punishment reduced based upon their rank, or in reality, did not receive general punishment unless they commit crimes such as hachigyaku (the eight most abominable acts or omissions) or homicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For instance, in addition to the rokugi (six considerations) system where special allowance was made for punishment, those with rank had their punishment reduced based upon their rank, or in reality, did not receive general punishment unless they committed crimes such as hachigyaku (the eight most abominable acts or omissions) or homicide.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot; before &quot;rank&quot; deleted, &quot;committed&quot; replaces &quot;commit&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For instance, in addition to the rokugi (six considerations) system where special allowance was made for punishment, those with rank had their punishment reduced based upon their rank, or in reality, did not receive general punishment unless they committed crimes such as hachigyaku (the eight most abominable acts or omissions) or homicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>国家機構と官制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">National structure and rules on administrative organizations</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">National structure and rules on administrative organizations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">National structure and rules on administrative organizations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="24">
<j>特権的な貴族層が、全国の人民を直接支配するためには、中央から地方の末端にいたるまでの体系的な行政・司法の機構を必要とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the privileged kizoku class to directly rule the people nationwide, a systematic administrative/judicial structure covering the center and the deep provinces was necessary.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the privileged kizoku class to directly rule the people nationwide, a systematic administrative/judicial structure covering the center and the remote provinces was necessary.</e>
<cmt>&quot;deep&quot; replaced with &quot;remote&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the privileged kizoku class to directly rule the people nationwide, a systematic administrative/judicial structure covering the center and the remote provinces was necessary.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>武家法と異なる律令法の特色の一つは、この体系的な国家機構および官僚制度の精密な規定にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Precise definition of such systematic national structure and bureaucracy is one of the characteristics which distinguish ritsuryo law from samurai law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Precise definition of such systematic national structure and bureaucracy is one of the characteristics that distinguishes ritsuryo law from samurai law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;which&quot; replaced with &quot;that&quot; and &quot;distinguish&quot; with &quot;distinguishes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Precise definition of such systematic national structure and bureaucracy is one of the characteristics that distinguishes ritsuryo law from samurai law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>それはいちじるしく形式主義的な官制となってあらわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This resulted in remarkably formalistic rules on administrative organizations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This resulted in remarkably formalistic rules on administrative organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This resulted in remarkably formalistic rules on administrative organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="27">
<j>中央政府は二官、八省、一台、五衛府で構成され（二官八省）、各省は職、寮、項目名司の名をもった若干の官庁をしたがえている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The central government was composed of nikan (two departments), hasyo (eight ministries), ichidai (one office), and goefu (five guards)(two departments and eight ministries), and there were several government offices named shiki (agency), ryo (bureau), and Komoku-meishi under the ministries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The central government was composed of nikan (two departments), hasyo (eight ministries), ichidai (one office), and goefu (five guards) (two departments and eight ministries), and there were several government offices named shiki (agency), ryo (bureau), and Komoku-meishi under the ministries.</e>
<cmt>space added between)(to become) (</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The central government was composed of nikan (two departments), hassho (eight ministries), ichidai (one office), and goefu (five guards) (two departments and eight ministries), and there were several government offices named shiki (agency), ryo (bureau), and Komoku-meishi under the ministries.</e>
<cmt>hasyo→hassho</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これらの官庁は原則として長官（かみ）、次官（すけ）、判官（じょう）、主典（さかん）の4等級の官吏で構成され(四等官）、それぞれの権限も法によって規定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In principle, these ministries were composed of four classes of government officials (shitokan), namely kami (director), suke (assistant director), jo (inspector), and sakan (secretary), and their authorities were also defined by law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In principle, these ministries were composed of four classes of government officials (shitokan), namely kami (director), suke (assistant director), jo (inspector), and sakan (secretary), and their authorities were also defined by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, these ministries were composed of four classes of government officials (shitokan), namely kami (director), suke (assistant director), jo (inspector), and sakan (secretary), and their authorities were also defined by law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>この精神は、地方政府組織の末端にいたるまで貫徹し、全体の官僚機構は、相互に秩序ある階層制によって連結された官庁から成っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This spirit was persistent to the tail end of provincial governmental organizations, and the overall bureaucracy consisted of ministries which were interconnected through an orderly rank system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This spirit was persistent all the way to the tail end of provincial governmental organizations, and the overall bureaucracy consisted of ministries that were interconnected through an orderly ranking system.</e>
<cmt>&quot;all the way&quot; added, &quot;rank&quot; changed to &quot;ranking&quot; &quot;which&quot; changed to &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This spirit was persistent all the way to the tail end of provincial governmental organizations, and the overall bureaucracy consisted of ministries that were interconnected through an orderly ranking system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>その形式主義的な機構は、行政の慣行と経験に基づいて形づくられた武家法の官制といちじるしく相違しており、律令法の基本的特徴の一つをなしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such formalistic structure was markedly different from the rules on administrative organizations under the samurai law, which were based on administrative practices and experiences, and is one of the basic features of ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such formalistic structure was markedly different from the rules on administrative organizations under samurai law, which were based on administrative practices and experiences, and is one of the basic features of ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; between &quot;samurai law&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such a formalistic structure was markedly different from the rules on administrative organizations under samurai law, which were based on administrative practices and experiences, and is one of the basic features of ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>“Such formalistic structure”=&gt; “Such a formalistic structure ”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="31">
<j>律令法では、行政官と司法官の区別はなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no distinction between administrative officer and judicial officer in ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was no distinction between administrative officer and judicial officer under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot; changed to &quot;under&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was no distinction between administrative officer and judicial officer under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>以上の行政機構は同時に司法の体系であるのを特色とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These administrative structures were distinctive in that they were both simultaneously judicial systems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These administrative structures were distinctive in that they were both simultaneously judicial systems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These administrative structures were distinctive in that they were both simultaneously judicial systems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>下級の裁判所は、地方では郡司、京では諸司であり、その上に地方では国司、京では刑部省があり、最後に太政官と天皇があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Lower court in the provinces was gunji (sub-provincial district administrators) and in Kyoto was shoshi (leading officials), and above them were kokushi (provincial governors) in the provinces and gyobusho in Kyoto, and finally, daijokan (department of state) and Emperor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Lower court in the provinces was gunji (sub-provincial district administrators) and in Kyoto was shoshi (leading officials), and above them were kokushi (provincial governors) in the provinces and gyobusho in Kyoto, and finally, daijokan (department of state) and Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Lower court in the provinces was gunji (sub-provincial district administrators) and in Kyoto was shoshi (leading officials), and above them were kokushi (provincial governors) in the provinces and gyobusho in Kyoto, and finally, daijokan (department of state) and Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="34">
<j>裁判所の管轄は刑の軽重によって区別され、笞罪・杖罪・徒罪・流罪・死罪_(律令法)の5種があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jurisdiction of the courts were distinguished based on the gravity of the sentences (five types), namely whipping, flogging, imprisonment, banishment, and capital crime (ritsuryo law).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jurisdiction of the courts was distinguished based upon the gravity of the sentences (five types), namely whipping, flogging, imprisonment, banishment, and capital crime (ritsuryo law).</e>
<cmt>&quot;were&quot; changed to &quot;was&quot; &quot;on&quot; changed to &quot;upon&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jurisdiction of the courts was distinguished based upon the gravity of the sentences (five types), namely whipping, flogging, imprisonment, banishment, and capital crime (ritsuryo law).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>これを五刑又は五罪と言った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were called gokei (five sentences) or gozai (five punishments).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were called gokei (five sentences) or gozai (five punishments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were called gokei (five sentences) or gozai (five punishments).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="36">
<j>郡司は笞罪のみを決し、在京諸司は笞罪・杖罪を決し、国司は杖罪、徒罪、刑部省は徒罪、太政官は流罪、天皇は死罪を決するという規定であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the rule, the gunji would decide only on whipping, shoshi in Kyoto would decide on whipping and flogging, kokushi on flogging and imprisonment, gyobusho on imprisonment, daijokan on banishment, and the Emperor on capital crime.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the rules, the gunji would decide only on whipping, the shoshi, in Kyoto, would decide on whipping and flogging, the kokushi on flogging and imprisonment, the gyobusho on imprisonment, the daijokan on banishment, and the Emperor on capital crime.</e>
<cmt>commas inserted after &quot;shoshi and after Kyoto,&quot; &quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;gunji, shoshi, kokushi, gyobusho, daijokan, respectively to clearly separate them from each other</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the rules, the gunji would decide only on whipping, the shoshi, in Kyoto, would decide on whipping and flogging, the kokushi on flogging and imprisonment, the gyobusho on imprisonment, the daijokan on banishment, and the Emperor on capital crime.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>唐の律令の継受</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reception of the Tang ritsuryo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adoption of the Tang ritsuryo</e>
<cmt>&quot;Adoption&quot; seems more appropriate than &quot;Reception&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adoption of the Tang ritsuryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="37">
<j>以上のような律令法の特色は、大化改新後の公地公民制に基づく新しい国家組織そのものの必要から生まれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The characteristic of ritsuryo law mentioned above arose due to the call for a new national organization based on the system of complete state ownership of land and citizens after the Reformation of Taika.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The characteristics of ritsuryo law, mentioned above, arose due to a call for a new national organization based upon a system of complete state ownership of land and citizens after the Taika Reformation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;s&quot; added to &quot;characteristic,&quot; &quot;comma removed after &quot;ritsuryo&quot; and commas inseted after &quot;law&quot; and before &quot;arose,&quot; &quot;the&quot; after &quot;to&quot; changed to &quot;a,&quot; and &quot;on&quot; changed to &quot;upon,&quot; &quot;the&quot; changed to &quot;a&quot; end of the sentence rearranged to read &quot;the Taika Reformation.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The characteristics of ritsuryo law, mentioned above, arose due to a call for a new national organization based upon a system of complete state ownership of land and citizens after the Taika Reformation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>同時に律令法が中国古代法典を母法として継承したことにも理由があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, another reason is that the ritsuryo law succeeded the Chinese ancient code as its mother law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, another reason is that ritsuryo law succeeded the Chinese ancient code that was considered to be its mother law.</e>
<cmt>rewritten</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, another reason is that ritsuryo law succeeded the Chinese ancient code that was considered to be its mother law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="39">
<j>律令法は形式、内容ともに主として唐の律令を模範とした法制であって、この時代の東洋で一種の世界法の役割を果たした唐の律令の日本における分枝とみるべきである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ritsuryo law was a legal system modeled mainly on the Tang ritsuryo in both style and content, and should be seen as a branch in Japan of the Tang ritsuryo, which served the role of world law at that time in the East.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsuryo law was a legal system modeled mainly upon the Tang ritsuryo in both style and content, and should be seen as a Japan branch of the Tang ritsuryo, which served as world law in the East, at that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;The&quot; removed, &quot;on&quot; changed to &quot;upon,&quot; &quot;role&quot; deleted, latter part of the sentence restructured</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsuryo law was a legal system modeled mainly upon the Tang ritsuryo in both style and content, and should be seen as a Japan branch of the Tang ritsuryo, which served as world law in the East, at that time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>したがって継受法としての律令法と、大化前代の固有法との間には断絶があって、固有の慣習法を基礎として成立した武家法制とは性格を異にする点が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there is a disconnect between the ritsuryo law which is the received law and the inherent law from the pre-Taika era, and its nature differs in many ways from the samurai legal system which was established based on unique common law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there is a disconnect between the ritsuryo law which is the adopted law and the inherent law from the pre-Taika era, and its nature differs in many ways from the samurai legal system which was established based upon unique common law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;received&quot; replaced with &quot;adopted&quot; &quot;on&quot; replaced by &quot;upon&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there is a disconnect between the ritsuryo law which is the adopted law and the inherent law from the pre-Taika era, and its nature differs in many ways from the samurai legal system which was established based upon unique common law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="41">
<j>ただ唐の律令を継受するにさいして、日本独自の条件を考慮に入れて重要な修正を行っている事実も注意する必要がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it must be noted that important revisions were made with consideration given to uniquely Japanese conditions when the Tang ritsuryo was received.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it must be noted that important revisions were made with consideration given to uniquely Japanese conditions when the Tang ritsuryo was adopted.</e>
<cmt>&quot;received&quot; replaced with &quot;adopted&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it must be noted that important revisions were made with consideration given to uniquely Japanese conditions when the Tang ritsuryo was adopted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>たとえば、唐の均田制を模範とした日本の班田収授法は、刑法や官制などとちがって、従来の土地所有制度と調整しなければ実行しがたい制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, unlike the criminal law or rules on administrative organizations, the ancient farmland allotment and reception law in Japan which was modeled on the equal-field system in Tang, was a difficult system to implement without adjustments with the traditional landholding system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, unlike criminal law or rules governing administrative organizations, the ancient farmland allotment and reception law in Japan that was modeled on the equal-field system during the Tang dynasty, was a difficult system to implement without adjustments to the traditional landholding system.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;before &quot;criminal&quot; deleted, &quot;governing&quot; replaced former wording, &quot;the Tang dynasty&quot; replaces &quot;Tang&quot; and &quot;with&quot; changed to &quot;to&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, unlike criminal law or rules governing administrative organizations, the ancient farmland allotment and reception law in Japan that was modeled on the equal-field system during the Tang dynasty, was a difficult system to implement without adjustments to the traditional landholding system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>日本の令では唐令を意識的に修正して実施した形跡がみえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese ryo (administrative code) shows traces of conscious revisions made to the torei for implementation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese ryo (administrative code) shows traces of conscious revisions that were made to the torei for implementation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;that were made&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese ryo (administrative code) shows traces of conscious revisions that were made to the torei for implementation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>また大化前代の土地私有制の発展段階の相違が考慮されていることも明らかである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it is clear that differences in the stage of development in the system for private ownership of land in the pre-Taika era are taken into account.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it is clear that differences during the stage of development in the system for private ownership of land in the pre-Taika era were taken into account.</e>
<cmt>&quot;during&quot; inserted before &quot;the stage&quot; and &quot;are&quot; replaced with &quot;were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it is clear that differences during the stage of development in the system for private ownership of land in the pre-Taika era were taken into account.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="45">
<j>唐田令では、官人永業田および賜田は無制限に売買・貼賃（ちようちん）(質入れあるいは賃貸のこと）の自由を有し、庶人の永業田は特別の場合には売買を許され、口分田（くぶんでん）は原則としては売買を禁じ、例外的にこれを許し、諸田地の貼賃なども、原則的に禁止されるにとどまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the toden law, kanjin-eigyo-den (hereditary field of officials) and farmland given by the Emperor could be bought, sold, pledged, or rented without limits, selling and buying of hereditary fields of commoners were permitted under special circumstances, selling and buying of farmland equally given to common people were forbidden in principle and allowed only in exceptional circumstances, and pledging or renting of various farmland was forbidden in principle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under toden law, kanjin-eigyo-den (hereditary field of officials) and farmland given by the Emperor, could be bought, sold, pledged, or rented without any limits, selling and buying of hereditary fields of commoners were permitted under special circumstances, selling and buying rights for farmland equally given to common people was forbidden in principle and allowed only in exceptional circumstances, and pledging or renting of various farmlands was forbidden in principle.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Under&quot; replaced previous wording before &quot;toden law&quot;comma inserted after Emperor, &quot;any&quot; inserted before &quot;limits,&quot; &quot;rights for&quot; inserted before &quot;farmland&quot; &quot;s&quot; added to &quot;farmland&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under toden law, kanjin-eigyo-den (hereditary field of officials) and farmland given by the Emperor, could be bought, sold, pledged, or rented without any limits, selling and buying of hereditary fields of commoners were permitted under special circumstances, selling and buying rights for farmland equally given to common people was forbidden in principle and allowed only in exceptional circumstances, and pledging or renting of various farmlands was forbidden in principle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="46">
<j>これに対して日本令では、すべての田地は絶対にその売買を禁止し、とくに1年間の賃租を許しているにすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the Japanese ryo, selling and buying of any farmland was absolutely forbidden, and only one year renting was allowed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, in the Japanese ryo, selling and buying of any farmland was absolutely forbidden, and only one year rental terms were allowed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;rental terms&quot; replaces &quot;renting,&quot; &quot;were&quot; replaces &quot;was&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, in the Japanese ryo, selling and buying of any farmland was absolutely forbidden, and only one year rental terms were allowed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>このような相違は、国家権力の強さ、土地私有性および交換経済の発展の状態などの相違を反映させたものとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such differences may have been a reflection of the strength in government power and the state of development of the system for private ownership of land and exchange economy.</e>
<cmt>「土地私有性」は「土地私有制」と解釈しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such differences may have been a reflection of the strength in government power and the state of development of a system for private ownership of land and an exchange economy.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the system&quot; replaced with &quot;a system&quot; &quot;an&quot; placed before &quot;exchange&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such differences may have been a reflection of the strength in government power and the state of development of a system for private ownership of land and an exchange economy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>田令ほど重要でない修正は令の各所にみられるが、それに対して律は唐律模倣の傾向が顕著であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are various revisions in the ryo which are less important than those for the codes for farmland, but on the other hand, ritsu (criminal code) clearly had a tendency to mimic the ritsu from Tang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are various revisions in the ryo which are less important than those for the codes for farmland, but on the other hand, ritsu (criminal code) clearly had a tendency to mimic the ritsu from Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are various revisions in the ryo which are less important than those for the codes for farmland, but on the other hand, ritsu (criminal code) clearly had a tendency to mimic the ritsu from Tang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="49">
<j>継受法としての律令法が7世紀以降長期にわたって強行されたことについては、国家権力の強大さ、人民一般の政治的無権利が第一にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The primary reason why the received law, ritsuryo law, was enforced for a long period of time since the seventh century, was the tremendous government power and the lack of political rights of the general public.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The primary reason why the adopted ritsuryo law, was enforced for a long period of time since the seventh century, was the tremendous government power and the lack of political rights for the general public.</e>
<cmt>&quot;received&quot; replaced with &quot;adopted,&quot; &quot;law&quot; deleted after &quot;adopted&quot; and replaced with &quot;ritsuryo law&quot; and &quot;or&quot; replaced with &quot;for&quot; before &quot;the general public.&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The primary reason why the adopted ritsuryo law was enforced for a long period of time since the seventh century was the tremendous power of government and the lack of political rights for the general public.</e>
<cmt>“tremendous government power”=&gt;”tremendous power of government”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="50">
<j>例えば、律令法の行政組織の最末端にある郷里制にもあらわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, it can be seen in the township-neighbourhood system at the tail end of the administrative organization under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, it can be seen in the township-neighbourhood system at the tail end of the administrative organization under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, it can be seen in the township-neighborhood system at the tail end of the administrative organization under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>スペル</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>国・郡・里の里は、50戸をもって構成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among the provinces, districts, and neighborhoods, neighborhoods was composed of 50 homes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the provinces, districts, and neighborhoods, neighborhoods were composed of 50 homes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot; replaced with &quot;were&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the provinces, districts, and neighborhoods, neighborhoods were composed of 50 homes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>この地方制度は画一的・行政的につくりあげられたもので、大化前代からの自然発生的な集落とはまったく関係のない組織であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This provincial system was built uniformly and administratively, and was totally unrelated to the naturally occurring settlements in the pre-Taika era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This provincial system was built uniformly and administratively, and was totally unrelated to the naturally occurring settlements in the pre-Taika era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This provincial system was built uniformly and administratively, and was totally unrelated to the naturally occurring settlements in the pre-Taika era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>地方の民衆生活のなかでは、「村」は基本的な共同体の単位であったが、それが、法的には全然認められていない事実のなかにも、律令法の特徴がみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the provincial lives of people, &apos;village&apos; was a basic unit of community, but the fact that it was not recognized by law at all is an example of the characteristics of ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the provincial lives of people, the &apos;village&apos; was a basic unit of the community, but the fact that it was not recognized by law at all is characteristic of ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot;inserted before &quot;village,&quot; &quot;characteristic of &quot; replaces previous wording in this section of the sentence</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the provincial lives of people, the &apos;village&apos; was a basic unit of the community, but the fact that it was not recognized by law at all is characteristic of ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="54">
<j>したがって律令法のなかに、日本の古代社会の内部に行われていた法慣行を見いだすことは困難である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, it is difficult to find in the ritsuryo law, the legal practices used in the ancient Japanese society.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, it is difficult to find examples of legal practices used in the ancient Japanese society under ritsuryo law,.</e>
<cmt>sentence restructured</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, it is difficult to find examples of legal practices used in ancient Japanese society under ritsuryo law,.</e>
<cmt>“the ancient Japanese society”=&gt;”ancient Japanese society”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>記紀、隋書倭国伝、祝詞（のりと）などの資料によっても、大化前代の地方族長社会においては、神判制度や宗教からまだ完全には分離しない形での法が存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to sources such as Kojiki and Nihonshoki, Zuisho-wakoku-den (Chronicles of the Sui Dynasty), and Shinto ritual pray, in the provincial patriarchal society in the pre-Taika era, law existed in a form not yet completely detached from the trial by ordeal system and religion.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to sources like the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki, the Zuisho-wakoku-den (Chronicles of the Sui Dynasty), and Shinto ritual prayers, in the provincial patriarchal society under the pre-Taika era, law existed in a form not yet completely detached from the trial by ordeal system and religion.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before, &quot;Kojiki, Nihonshoki, Zuisho…, &quot;under&quot; replaced &quot;in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to sources like the Kojiki and the Nihonshoki, the Zuisho-wakoku-den (Chronicles of the Sui Dynasty), and Shinto ritual prayers, in the provincial patriarchal society under the pre-Taika era, law existed in a form not yet completely detached from the trial by ordeal system and religion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>また邪馬台国（やまたいこく）でも公的な秩序・権威の維持のための法が存在したとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, it appears that law existed to maintain public order and authority in Yamataikoku as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, it appears that law existed to maintain public order and authority in Yamataikoku as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, it appears that law existed to maintain public order and authority in Yamataikoku as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="57">
<j>ヤマト王権の時代になれば、刑法を中心とした法が、中国古代法の影響をうけながら不文法の形で発展していたことが推測される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Yamato royalty era, it is believed that laws centered around criminal law developed in the form of common law while being influenced by Chinese ancient law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the royal Yamato era, it is believed that laws centered around criminal law developed as the form of common law while being influenced by ancient Chinese law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;During&quot; replaces words at the start of this sentence, &quot;in&quot; changed to &quot;as,&quot; &quot;Yamato royal era,&quot; changed to &quot;the royal Yamato era,&quot;&quot;ancient&quot; replaced before &quot;Chinese law&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the royal Yamato era, it is believed that laws centered around criminal law developed as the form of common law while being influenced by ancient Chinese law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>唐の律令の継受も、このような土台のうえに可能となったのであるが、秦・漢以来の歴代の専制主義的法制を集大成した唐の律令と大化前代の日本の法とでは、段階の差が、あまりにはげしかったので、律令法は継受法としての性格を強くもたざるをえなかったとみられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Reception of the Tang ritsuryo was possible based on such foundation, but the difference between the Tang ritsuryo which was a comprehensive compilation of successive despotic legal systems since Qin and Han, and the Japanese law was too great that ritsuryo law could not avoid becoming strongly a received law in nature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Adopting theTang ritsuryo was possible based upon such a foundation, but the difference between the Tang ritsuryo, which was a comprehensive compilation of successive despotic legal systems since Qin and Han, and the Japanese law, was too great that ritsuryo law could not avoid becoming, basically, an adopted law by nature.</e>
<cmt>I had a problem with &quot;receiving&quot; and believe &quot;adopting&quot; is the more correct term to use here Puctuation, a comma, was placed after &quot;Japanese law&quot;and before and after the inserted word in place of &quot;strongly&quot; which was &quot;basically&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Adopting the Tang ritsuryo was possible based upon such a foundation, but the difference between the Tang ritsuryo, which was a comprehensive compilation of successive despotic legal systems since Qin and Han, and the Japanese law of the pre-Taika era, was so great that ritsuryo law could not avoid becoming, basically, an adopted law by nature.</e>
<cmt>“was too great”=&gt; “was so great”</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="59">
<j>儒教的性格</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confucian nature</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confucian philosophy</e>
<cmt>&quot;philosophy&quot; seems more appropriate here</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confucian philosophy</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="60">
<j>律令法の継受法としての性質を強調するあまり、それが日本法制史上に果たした役割を過小に評価するのは、事実と合致しない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It would be untrue to the facts to underestimate the role of ritsuryo law in the history of Japanese legal system by placing too much emphasis on ritsuryo law&apos;s nature as a received law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It would be unfaithful to the factual evidence to underestimate the role of ritsuryo law in the history of the Japanese legal system by placing too much emphasis on the philosophy behind ritsuryo law as an adopted law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;unfaithful to the factual evidence&quot; replaces previous wording, rewritten as &quot;the philosophy behind ritsuryo law,&quot; &quot;received&quot; replaced with &quot;adopted&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It would be unfaithful to the factual evidence to underestimate the role of ritsuryo law in the history of the Japanese legal system by placing too much emphasis on the philosophy behind ritsuryo law as an adopted law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="61">
<j>『正倉院文書』その他の資料によると、律令法の公法的部分は、奈良時代においては、継受法とは考えられないほど実際に施行されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shosoin-bunsho&quot; and other sources, in the Nara period, the public law portion of ritsuryo law was actually enforced as is if it was not a received law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to &quot;Shosoin-bunsho&quot; and other sources, during the Nara period, the publiclaw portion of ritsuryo law was actually enforced as is if it was not an adopted law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot; replaced with &quot;during,&quot; &quot;an adopted law&quot; replaces previous wording.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to &quot;Shosoin-bunsho&quot; and other sources, during the Nara period, the public law portion of ritsuryo law was in fact enforced as if it was not an adopted law.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入is削除&quot;actually&quot;→&quot;in fact&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>したがって、中世の武家法の基礎となった慣習法も、純粋な固有法ではなく、律令法を媒介として成長した固有法であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus, the common law which became the basis of medieval samurai law was not a genuine inherent law, but an inherent law which developed through ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus, the common law which became the basis of medieval samurai law was not a genuine inherent law, but an inherent law which developed from ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;developed from ritsuryo law&quot; replaces previous wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus, the common law which became the basis of medieval samurai law was not a genuine inherent law, but an inherent law which developed from ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="63">
<j>また律令法は単に法としてばかりでなく、思想史的にも重要な意味をもった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, ritsuryo law was important not only in the sense of law, but also in the sense of history of thought.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, ritsuryo law was important not only in the legal sense, but also in the sense of the history of philosophical thought.</e>
<cmt>:&quot;sense of Law&quot; changed to &quot;legal sense,&quot; &quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;history,&quot; &quot;thought&quot; replaced by &quot;philosphical thought&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, ritsuryo law was important not only in the legal sense, but also in the sense of the history of philosophical thought.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>律令法の基本思想は、母法と同じく、儒家と法家の思想であったが、ことに儒家の思想は、日本の律令法でも指導的な意義をもっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Similarly to its mother law, the basic thought of ritsuryo law was Confucianist and legalism, and Confucianist in particular was significance as a leading thought in the Japanese ritsuryo law as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Similarly to its mother law, the basic thought of ritsuryo law was Confucianist and legalism, and Confucianist in particular was significance as a leading thought in the Japanese ritsuryo law as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Similarly to its mother law, the basic thought of ritsuryo law was Confucianist and legalist, and Confucianism in particular was significant as a leading strand of thought in Japanese ritsuryo law as well.</e>
<cmt>全体が複雑なため訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>養老の名例律が、不孝を、不義などの罪とならべて、八虐の一つとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meirei-ritsu in Yoro included undutifulness in its hachigyaku along with crimes such as perfidiousness.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meirei-ritsu in Yoro included undutifulness in its hachigyaku along with crimes such as perfidiousness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meirei-ritsu in Yoro included undutifulness in its hachigyaku along with crimes such as perfidiousness.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>例えば、祖父母・父母、夫の祖父母・父母をなぐり、また殺傷する罪を悪逆のなかにいれて、恩赦のさいにもこれをゆるさない規定を設けているのは、儒教の道徳を法制化したものにほかならない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, including the crime of striking, killing and wounding of grandparents, parents, grandparents and parents of the husband in atrocity, and setting a rule for not permitting amnesty, is none other than legislation of Confucian morals.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, including the crime of striking, killing and wounding of grandparents, parents, grandparents, and parents of the husband in atrocity, and setting up rules for not permitting amnesty, is nothing more than legislation of Confucian morals.</e>
<cmt>comma inserted after &quot;grandparents,&quot;&quot;setting up rules&quot; replaces former wording, &quot;is nothing more&quot;replaces former wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, including the crimes of striking, killing and wounding of grandparents, parents, grandparents, and parents of a husband as atrocities, and setting up rules for not permitting amnesty, is nothing more than the legislation of Confucian morals.</e>
<cmt>全体が複雑なため訳し直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="67">
<j>大化前代からの家父長制家族の発達は、このような法を受用する基礎をつくったことは事実であるが、律令法は儒教の精神によって、親または家長の権力を強大にし、同時に女性の法的・社会的地位をいちじるしく低める作用をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Development of patriarchal authority family since the pre-Taika era did build a basis for accepting and applying such law, but under the Confucian spirit, ritsuryo law gave tremendous power to parents or head of family, while drastically lowering the legal and social status of women.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Development of the patriarchal authority family since the pre-Taika era did build a basis for accepting and applying such law, but in the Confucian spirit, ritsuryo law gave tremendous power to parents or the head of the family, while drastically lowering the legal and social status of women.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted after &quot;Development of,&quot; before &quot;Confucian spirit,&quot; before &quot;head of the family,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Development of the patriarchal authority family since the pre-Taika era did build a basis for accepting and applying such law, but in the Confucian spirit, ritsuryo law gave tremendous power to parents or the head of the family, while drastically lowering the legal and social status of women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>律令の改変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changes in ritsuryo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in ritsuryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in ritsuryo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="68">
<j>律令法は、奈良・平安両時代を通じて国家の基本法であることに変りはなかったが、 10世紀の『延喜式』の制定公布の時代前後を境として、重要な変化がみられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsuryo law remained the basic national law through the Nara and Heian periods, but important changes occurred around the time when &quot;Engishiki&quot; (a book of laws and regulation compiled during the Engi era) was established and issued in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsuryo law remained the basic national law throughout the Nara and Heian periods, but important changes occurred around the time when &quot;Engishiki&quot; (a book of laws and regulations compiled during the Engi era) was established and issued in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>&quot;through&quot; changed to &quot;throughout,&quot;&quot;s&quot; added to &quot;regulation,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsuryo law remained the basic national law throughout the Nara and Heian periods, but important changes occurred around the time when &quot;Engishiki&quot; (a book of laws and regulations compiled during the Engi era) was established and issued in the tenth century.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>摂関政治や院政などの新しい政治形態の出現、班田制の衰退と荘園の発展、律令法的身分秩序の解体などにみられる各種の歴史上の変化によって、律令法に基づく新しい慣習法が律令法の各分野で形成されてきた結果である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is a result of new common laws being formed in various areas of ritsuryo law, due to a variety of historical changes such as the emergence of new political formats such as sekkan seiji (politics by regents and advisers) and insei (rule by retired Emperor), decline of ancient farmland allotment and reception system and development of manors, and dismantling of the class system under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is a result of new common laws being formed in various areas of ritsuryo law, due to a variety of historical changes such as the emergence of new political formats like sekkan seiji (politics of regents and advisers) and insei (rule by a retired Emperor), decline of ancient farmland allotment and accepting system and development of manors, and dismantling of the class system under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;by&quot; after &quot;politics&quot; changed to &quot;of,&quot; &quot;a&quot; inserted before &quot;retired Emperor,&quot;&quot;reception&quot; replaced with &quot;accepting&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is a result of new common laws being formed in various areas of ritsuryo law, due to a variety of historical changes such as the emergence of new political formats like sekkan seiji (politics of regents and advisers) and insei (rule by a retired Emperor), decline of ancient farmland allotment and accepting system and development of manors, and dismantling of the class system under ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>これを公家法の時代として区分することができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This can be categorized as the age of court noble law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This can be categorized as the age of court noble law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This can be categorized as the age of court noble law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>律令と官職制度</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ritsuryo and the government service system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ritsuryo and the government service system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ritsuryo and the government service system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="71">
<j>たとえば、官職制度のなかにも各種の重要な変化がおこったが、そのなかで著名なものは蔵人（くろうど）および検非違使（けびいし）の制度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, among the variety of important changes which occurred in the government service system, the system of kurodo (keeper of imperial archives) and kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura periods) is notable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, among the variety of important changes that occurred in the government service system, the system of kurodo (keeper of imperial archives) and kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura periods) is notable.</e>
<cmt>&quot;which&quot; changed to &quot;that&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, among the variety of important changes that occurred in the government service system, the system of kurodo (keeper of imperial archives) and kebiishi (statutory office in the Heian and Kamakura periods) is notable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>検非違使は、刑部省および太政官が司法上の機能を果たさなくなるにしたがって平安初期に設置されたもので、司法警察上の追捕（ついぶ）のみならず、糾弾・断獄の諸権をももつにいたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kebiishi was established at the beginning of Heian period when the judicial function of gyobusho and daijokan was diminishing, and they gained authority for tsuibu (pursue and capture) as judicial police, as well as condemnation and adjudication.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kebiishi was established at the beginning of Heian period when the judicial function of gyobusho and daijokan was diminishing, and they gained authority for tsuibu (pursue and capture) as judicial police, as well as condemnation and adjudication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kebiishi was established at the beginning of Heian period when the judicial function of gyobusho and daijokan was diminishing, and they gained authority for tsuibu (pursue and capture) as judicial police, as well as condemnation and adjudication.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="73">
<j>まもなく民事裁判に関与するようになり、追捕使とともに諸国にもおかれるようになると、百姓からの年貢所当の徴収にまで参与するにいたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before long they began being involved in civil trials, and once they were assigned to provinces along with the tsuibushi (envoys to pursue and capture), they even participated in the collection of render and taxes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before long they became involved in civil trials, and once they were assigned to provinces along with the tsuibushi (envoys to pursue and capture), they even participated in the rendering and collection of taxes.</e>
<cmt>&quot;began being&quot; changed to &quot;became,&quot; &quot;collection of render and taxes&quot;changed to &quot;rendering and collection of taxes&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before long they became involved in civil trials, and once they were assigned to provinces along with the tsuibushi (envoys to pursue and capture), they even participated in the rendering and collection of taxes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>律令制の最盛期とちがって、租税を強力な力なしには徴収できない階級関係の変化が、検非違使の機能の変化にも反映した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Unlike in the prime of ritsuryo system, changes in class relationship made it impossible to collect taxes without strong power, and this reflected in the changes in the function of kebiishi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Unlike during the prime of the ritsuryo system, changes in class relationships made it impossible to collect taxes without enforcing power, and this was reflected in the changes in the function of kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in&quot; replaced by &quot;during,&quot; &quot;s&quot; added to &quot;relationship,&quot; &quot;strong&quot; replaced by &quot;enforcing,&quot; &quot;was&quot; inserted before &quot;reflected&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Unlike during the prime of the ritsuryo system, changes in class relationships made it impossible to collect taxes without enforcing power, and this was reflected in the changes in the function of kebiishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="75">
<j>検非違使の庁例は、使庁の流例ともいわれ、律令の刑法とはちがった性質の慣習法として通用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The cho-rei (law enacted by the kebiishi) of kebiishi was considered the historical custom of kebiishi agency, and was valid as a common law different in nature from the criminal law of ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The cho-rei (law enacted by the kebiishi) of kebiishi was considered the historical custom of the kebiishi agency, and was valid as a common law different in nature from the criminal law of ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;kebiishi&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The cho-rei (law enacted by the kebiishi) of kebiishi was considered the historical custom of the kebiishi agency, and was valid as a common law different in nature from the criminal law of ritsuryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>官庁内部の慣習法は例または行事という言葉で奈良時代からすでに法的に認められてはいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Common law inside the ministries was already accepted as law since the Nara period through terms like rei and gyoji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Common law inside the ministries was already accepted as law, since the Nara period, through terms like rei and gyoji.</e>
<cmt>commas inserted before &quot;since,&quot; and after &quot;period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Common law inside the ministries was already accepted as law, since the Nara period, through terms like rei and gyoji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>公家法の時代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The age of court noble law</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The age of court noble law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The age of court noble law</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="77">
<j>公家法の時代には、法のあらゆる分野で、慣習法の体系が重要な法的意義をもつようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the age of court noble law, the system of common law developed an important legal significance in various areas of law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the age of court noble law, the system of common law developed an important legal significance in various areas of law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the age of court noble law, the system of common law developed an important legal significance in various areas of law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="78">
<j>荘園制を基礎にして発達した本所もその一つであるが、地方の行政組織の内部に発達してきた国衙法（こくが）ともいうべき慣習法もその一例である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of manor) which developed based on the shoen system is one example, as well as the common law which can be referred to as Kokuga (provincial government headquarters) law, which developed within the provincial governmental organizations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor) which developed, based on the shoen system, is one example, as well as common law that can be referred to as Kokuga (provincial government headquarters) law, that developed within provincial governmental organizations.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;manor,&quot; &quot;the&quot; deleted from before &quot;common law,&quot;and before &quot;provincial&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjo (proprietor or guarantor of the manor) which developed, based on the shoen system, is one example, as well as common law that can be referred to as Kokuga (provincial government headquarters) law, that developed within provincial governmental organizations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="79">
<j>国司制度は、基本の形式は平安時代になっても律令法と変りはなかったが、国司の職が封禄と化し、任地におもむかない遥任の国司が増加するにつれて、諸国の行政は留守所あるいは在庁官人が行うようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic format of the kokushi (provincial governors) system was not different from ritsuryo law even in the Heian period, but when the position of kokushi turned into a salary, and yonin who are kokushi who would not go to their place of appointment increased, provincial administration was performed by rusudokoro (the center for all local government administration in a province) or zaichokanjin (local district officials).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic format of the kokushi (provincial governors) system was not different from that of ritsuryo law even during the Heian period, but when the position of kokushi turned into a salaried one, and yonin, who are kokushi who would not go to their place of appointment, increased, provincial administration was performed by rusudokoro (the center for all local government administration in a province) or zaichokanjin (local district officials).</e>
<cmt>&quot;that of&quot; inserted before &quot;ritsuryo,&quot; &quot;salary&quot; changed to &quot;a salaried one,&quot; commas placed after &quot;yonin,&quot; and after &quot;appointment&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic format of the kokushi (provincial governors) system was not different from that of ritsuryo law even during the Heian period, but when the position of kokushi turned into a salaried one, and yonin, who are kokushi who would not go to their place of appointment, increased, provincial administration was performed by rusudokoro (the center for all local government administration in a province) or zaichokanjin (local district officials).</e>
<cmt>スペース削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>そのさい、国衙領は、百姓名（みよう）が奈良時代の戸に代わって基本単位となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the base unit of kokugaryo (public lands) became hyakusho-myo (smaller holdings of shoen held by ordinary peasants), replacing ko (smallest social organization unit in provincial administration) used in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the base unit of kokugaryo (public lands) became hyakusho-myo (smaller holdings of shoen held by ordinary peasants), replacing ko (smallest social organization unit in provincial administration) used in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the base unit of kokugaryo (public lands) became hyakusho-myo (smaller holdings of shoen held by ordinary peasants), replacing ko (smallest social organization unit in provincial administration) used in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>租庸調、雑徭および各種の臨時の賦課も、それに対応した徴収方法を採用しなければならないことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soyocho, zoyo, and various temporary impositions had to adopt corresponding collection methods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soyocho, zoyo, and various temporary impositions had to adopt corresponding collection methods.</e>
<cmt>not sure that &quot;impositions&quot; is the correct translation?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soyocho, zoyo, and various temporary impositions had to adopt corresponding collection methods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>特に国衙領の内部に成立した荘園との関係を規制するためには、律令法にない新しい法をつくり出す必要があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In particular, in order to control the relationship with the shoen formed within kokugaryo, a new law not included in the ritsuryo law had to be created.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In particular, in order to control the relationship with the shoen, formed within kokugaryo, a new law, not included in ritsuryo, had to be created.</e>
<cmt>commas inserted after &quot;particular,&quot; after &quot;shoen,&quot; after &quot;kokugaryo,&quot;after &quot;law,&quot;and &quot;ritsuryo law&quot; changed to &quot;ritsuryo&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In particular, in order to control the relationship with the shoen, formed within kokugaryo, a new law, not included in ritsuryo, had to be created.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="83">
<j>当時の文書において「当国之例」といわれるような慣習法は、このような必要に基づくものであって、それは本所法とならんで、中世の武家法の基盤の一つとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The common law called &apos;tokoku-no-rei&apos; appearing in texts of those days was based on such necessity, and together with honjo law, became one of the foundations of medieval samurai law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The common law called &apos;tokoku-no-rei&apos; appearing in texts of those days, was based on such necessity, and together with honjo law, became one of the foundations of medieval samurai law.</e>
<cmt>comma place after &quot;days&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The common law called &apos;tokoku no rei&apos; appearing in texts of those days, was based on such necessity, and together with honjo law, became one of the foundations of medieval samurai law.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="84">
<j>幕藩体制と明律研究</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Feudal system characteristic of the shogunate and research on Ming code</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Feudal system characteristics of the shogunate and research on the Ming code</e>
<cmt>&quot;s&quot; added to &quot;characteristic&quot; and &quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;Ming&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Feudal system characteristics of the shogunate and research on the Ming code</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>養老律令以後、日本では律令の編纂は行われなくなり、遣唐使の廃止によって中国律令の導入もなくなったが、当然のことながら中国ではその後も歴代王朝で律令の編纂や改訂が行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Yoro code, there has been no compilation of ritsuryo in Japan, and with the abolition of Japanese envoy to China in the Tang dynasty, Chinese ritsuryo was no longer introduced, but naturally, compilation and revision of ritsuryo continued in successive dynasties in China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Yoro code, there has been no compilation of ritsuryo in Japan, and with the abolition of the Japanese envoy to China in the Tang dynasty, Chinese ritsuryo was no longer being introduced, but naturally, compilation and revision of ritsuryo continued in successive dynasties in China.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;Japanese,&quot; &quot;being&quot; placed before &quot;introduced&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Yoro code, there has been no compilation of ritsuryo in Japan, and with the abolition of the Japanese envoy to China in the Tang dynasty, Chinese ritsuryo was no longer being introduced, but naturally, compilation and revision of ritsuryo continued in successive dynasties in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>江戸時代も中期に差し掛かると、世の中は平和になる一方で社会が発展するにつれて新たな社会問題も生じ、古い戦国期以来の法体系を継承した従来の幕藩法体系では対応出来なくなってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By mid-Edo period, while the world became peaceful, new social issues emerged as society developed, and could not be dealt with traditional shogunate system of law which succeeded the ancient system of law since the warring states period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By mid-Edo period, while the world became peaceful and as society developed, new social issues emerged that could not be dealt with by the traditional shogunate system of law that succeeded the ancient system after the warring states period.</e>
<cmt>sentence restructured, comma inserted after &quot;developed,&quot;&quot;law&quot; deleted after &quot;ancient system&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By mid-Edo period, while the world became peaceful and as society developed, new social issues emerged that could not be dealt with by the traditional shogunate system of law that succeeded the ancient system after the warring states period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>更に戦国時代 (日本)の遺風を残した過酷な刑罰に対する批判も出てくるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, there were criticism against harsh punishments which retained relics of the warring states period (Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, there was criticism against the harsh punishments which were left-over relics of the warring states period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;harsh,&quot; &quot;left-over&quot; replaces previous wording. I wonder if &quot;(Japan)&quot; is necessary?</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, there was criticism against the harsh punishments which were left-over relics of the warring states period (Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>そこで旧来の法令に欠けている分野を補完する目的で江戸幕府や諸藩の中で明王朝で使われた明律の研究が始められた（中国では既に清の時代に入っていたが、明の法律文献が多く日本に伝来していたことや清律も明律をほぼ踏襲していた事が影響している。）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, in order to supplement the areas lacking in the traditional law, research on the Ming code used in the Ming dynasty began in the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and various clans (China was already in the Qing period, but many Ming legal documents were introduced in Japan and the Qing code mostly succeeded the Ming code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, in order to supplement the areas lacking in traditional law, research on the Ming code, used in the Ming dynasty, began within the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and various clans (China was already in the Qing period, but many Ming legal documents were introduced in Japan and the Qing code mostly succeeded the Ming code).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; deleted before &quot;traditional,&quot; commas placed after &quot;Ming code&quot; and after &quot;dynasty,&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, in order to supplement the areas lacking in traditional law, research on the Ming code, used in the Ming dynasty, began within the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) and various clans (China was already in the Qing period, but many Ming legal documents were introduced in Japan and the Qing code mostly succeeded the Ming code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>初めは紀伊藩徳川光貞や加賀藩前田綱紀といった有力藩主とその周辺の学者によって行われたのをその嚆矢とするが、光貞の子・徳川吉宗が江戸幕府の第8代将軍になると、幕府内部でも研究が進められるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Initially it was performed by powerful feudal lords such as Mitsusada TOKUGAWA of the Kii Domain, Tsunanori MAEDA of the Kaga Domain, and the scholars around them, but when Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, the child of Mitsusada, became the 8th shogun of the Edo bakufu, research was performed in the bakufu as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Initially it was performed by powerful feudal lords such as Mitsusada TOKUGAWA of the Kii Domain, Tsunanori MAEDA of the Kaga Domain, and the scholars around them, but when Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, the child of Mitsusada, became the 8th shogun of the Edo bakufu, research was performed in the bakufu as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Initially it was performed by powerful feudal lords such as Mitsusada TOKUGAWA of the Kii Domain, Tsunanori MAEDA of the Kaga Domain, and the scholars around them, but when Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, the child of Mitsusada, became the eighth shogun of the Edo bakufu, research was performed in the bakufu as well.</e>
<cmt>8th→eighth</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>その代表格は高瀬喜朴（本名：忠敦、1668～1749）と荻生北渓（本名：観、1669～1754）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Representative examples are Kiboku TAKASE (real name: Tadaatsu, 1668 - 1749) and Hokkei OGYU (real name: Kan, 1669 - 1754).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Representative examples are Kiboku TAKASE (real name: Tadaatsu, 1668 - 1749) and Hokkei OGYU (real name: Kan, 1669 - 1754).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Representative examples are Kiboku TAKASE (real name: Tadaatsu, 1668 - 1749) and Hokkei OGYU (real name: Kan, 1669 - 1754).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="91">
<j>高瀬は紀伊藩の医師・学者で光貞時代から明律研究に参加していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takase was a doctor and scholar in Kii Domain, who participated in the research of Ming code since the days of Mitsusada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takase was a doctor and a scholar in the Kii Domain, who participated in research on the Ming code since the days of Mitsusada.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a&quot; placed before &quot;scholar,&quot; &quot;the&quot; deleted before &quot;research,&quot; and inserted before &quot;Ming</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takase was a doctor and a scholar in the Kii Domain, who participated in research on the Ming code since the days of Mitsusada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>1720年（享保5年）に著された「大明律例訳義」は人道・恤刑思想を重視して正確かつ平易（当時の日本で使われている用語に置き換えた）を旨とした全訳書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Authored in 1720, &apos;Daiminritsureiyakugi&apos; is a complete translation based on accuracy and simplicity, with a focus on thoughts on humanity and merciful punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Authored in 1720, &apos;Daiminritsureiyakugi&apos; is a complete translation based on accuracy and simplicity, with a focus on thoughts on humanity and merciful punishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Authored in 1720, &apos;Daiminritsureiyakugi&apos; is a complete translation based on accuracy and simplicity (translated into terms used in Japan at that time), with a focus on thoughts on humanity and merciful punishment.</e>
<cmt>（当時の日本で使われている用語に置き換えた）を訳出しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>一方、吉宗の侍医として仕えていた荻生は「大明律例訳義」が原文を載せていないことに批判的で1723年（享保8年）に明律原文に校訂・句読を施した「官准刊行明律（訓点本明律）」を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ogyu who served as the court physician of Yoshimune, was critical of the fact that &apos;Daiminritsureiyakugi&apos; did not contain the original text, and in 1723, authored &apos;Kanjunkankominritsu&apos; (kuntenbonminritsu), which added revisions and punctuation to the original Ming code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Ogyu who served as the court physician for Yoshimune, was critical of the fact that &apos;Daiminritsureiyakugi&apos; did not contain the original text, and in 1723, authored &apos;Kanjunkankominritsu&apos; (kuntenbonminritsu), which added revisions and punctuation to the original Ming code.</e>
<cmt>&quot;for&quot; added before &quot;Yoshimune&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Ogyu who served as the court physician for Yoshimune, was critical of the fact that &apos;Daiminritsureiyakugi&apos; did not contain the original text, and in 1723, authored &apos;Kanjunkankominritsu&apos; (kuntenbonminritsu), which added revisions and punctuation to the original Ming code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>後者は法律関連の書籍の発刊が厳しく禁じられた当時に吉宗の特例の許可によって販売が許された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latter received special sales permission by Yoshimune at a time when publication of legal books was strictly prohibited.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latter received special sales permission by Yoshimune at a time when publication of legal books was strictly prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latter received special sales permission by Yoshimune at a time when publication of legal books was strictly prohibited.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>荻生の実兄である儒学者荻生徂徠も弟の影響を受けて「明律国字解」という本を著した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Confucianist Sorai OGYU, the blood brother of Ogyu was influenced by his younger brother and also authored a book &apos;Minritsu kokujikai&apos; (The Ming code, with Japanese explication).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Confucianist Sorai OGYU, the blood brother of Ogyu was influenced by his younger brother and also authored a book &apos;Minritsu kokujikai&apos; (The Ming code, with Japanese explication).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Confucianist Sorai OGYU, the blood brother of Ogyu was influenced by his younger brother and also authored a book &apos;Minritsu kokujikai&apos; (The Ming code, with Japanese explication).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="96">
<j>こうした成果をうけて幕府は残虐刑を減らして「過料」「敲（たたき）」「入墨」などの新しい刑罰を導入したが、「享保の改革」自体が保守的な要素をもっていたため、幕府法の全面的な改訂には至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such achievements led the bakufu to reduce cruel punishments and introduce new punishments such as &apos;correctional fine,&apos; &apos;beating,&apos; and &apos;tattooing,&apos; but due to the conservative factors of &apos;Kyoho-no-kaikaku (Kyoho reform)&apos; itself, it did not lead to an overall revision of the bakufu law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such achievements led the bakufu to reduce cruel punishments and to introduce new punishments such as &apos;correctional fines,&apos; &apos;beating,&apos; and &apos;tattooing,&apos; but due to the conservative factors of &apos;Kyoho-no-kaikaku (Kyoho reform)&apos; itself, it did not lead to an overall revision of the bakufu law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;to&quot; inserted before &quot;introduce&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such achievements led the bakufu to reduce cruel punishments and to introduce new punishments such as &apos;correctional fines,&apos; &apos;beating,&apos; and &apos;tattooing,&apos; but due to the conservative factors of &apos;Kyoho-no-kaikaku (Kyoho reform)&apos; itself, it did not lead to an overall revision of the bakufu law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="97">
<j>これとは対照的に熊本藩細川重賢は明律研究を参考に大胆な司法改革を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, Shigekata HOSOKAWA of the Kumamoto Domain drew upon the research on Ming code to carry out a bold judicial reform.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, Shigekata HOSOKAWA, of the Kumamoto Domain, drew upon the research on the Ming code to carry out bold judicial reform.</e>
<cmt>commas inserted after &quot;HOSOKAWA,&quot; and after &quot;Domain,&quot; &quot;the&quot; placed before &quot;Ming code&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, Shigekata HOSOKAWA, of the Kumamoto Domain, drew upon the research on the Ming code to carry out bold judicial reform.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>1761年（宝暦11年）に制定された「刑法草書」は「徒刑」（懲役刑）制度や保護観察制度、除墨制度を導入した進歩的な法体系であるが、その編纂は明律を参考にしたところが大きいと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Keiho sosho,&apos; established in 1761, was a progressive legal system introducing the &apos;penal servitude&apos; (imprisonment) system, probation system, and tattoo removal system, and is known to have largely consulted the Ming code compilation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Keiho sosho,&apos; established in 1761, was a progressive legal system introducing the &apos;penal servitude&apos; (imprisonment) system, probation system, and tattoo removal system, and is known to have largely consulted the Ming code compilation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Keiho sosho,&apos; established in 1761, was a progressive legal system introducing the &apos;penal servitude&apos; (imprisonment) system, probation system, and tattoo removal system, and is known to have largely consulted the Ming code compilation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>また、同藩では死刑執行の日を毎年一定の時期に限定し、その日は領内から死刑を出したことを恥じるとして藩主以下主だった役人が謹慎をする「死刑日慎」という慣例を定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, the domain limited the executions to a certain time of the year, and established a practice called &apos;shikeibishin&apos; where the major officials including the feudal lords behave themselves on those days due to the shame of having a death sentence within the territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the domain limited the executions to a certain time of the year, and established a practice called &apos;shikeibishin&apos; where the major officials, including the feudal lords, behave themselves on those days due to the shame of having a death sentence within the territory.</e>
<cmt>commas inserted after &quot;officials,&quot; and after &quot;lords&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the domain limited the executions to a certain time of the year, and established a practice called &apos;shikeibishin&apos; where the major officials, including the feudal lords, behave themselves on those days due to the shame of having a death sentence within the territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="100">
<j>熊本以外の藩でも18世紀末頃から熊本藩を見習って、明律を範とした司法改革を行う藩が次々と登場するようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In domains other than Kumamoto, many domains followed the Kumamoto Domain and began carrying out judicial reforms modeling after the Ming code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other than Kumamoto, many domains followed the Kumamoto Domain and began carrying out judicial reforms modeled after the Ming code.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Domains&quot; removed from the beginning of the sentence, &quot;other&quot; capitalized, &quot;modeling&quot; changed to &quot;modeled&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outside Kumamoto, many domains followed the Kumamoto Domain and began carrying out judicial reforms modeled after the Ming code since the end of the eighteenth century.</e>
<cmt>”Other than Kumamoto, many”→“Outside Kumamoto, many... “</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="101">
<j>短期間ではあるが、1870年（明治3年）から11年間に明治新政府で使用された「新律綱領」も明律を継承した清律をモデルにしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &apos;Shinritsu koryo&apos; (Outline of the New Criminal Code), which was used for 11 short years in the new Meiji government since 1870, also modeled the Qing code which succeeded the Ming code.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Shinritsu koryo&apos; (Outline of the New Criminal Code), which was used for 11 short years in the new Meiji government since 1870, was also modeled after the Qing code which succeeded the Ming code.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was&quot; inserted before &quot;also,&quot; and &quot;after&quot; inserted after &quot;modeled&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Shinritsu koryo&apos; (Outline of the New Criminal Code), which was used for 11 short years in the new Meiji government since 1870, was also modeled after the Qing code which succeeded the Ming code.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>また、荻生徂徠の「明律国字解」が司法官の必読書として推奨された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, &apos;Minritsu kokujikai&apos; by Sorai OGYU was recommended as required reading for judicial officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, &apos;Minritsu kokujikai&apos; by Sorai OGYU was recommended as required reading for judicial officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, &apos;Minritsu kokujikai&apos; by Sorai OGYU was put forward as required reading for judicial officers.</e>
<cmt>recommended とrequiredは現実として同時に行うことは矛盾する。→ “was put forward as required reading”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>だが、1881年（明治14年）の刑法導入によって、古代以来の中国法系の刑事法制は幕を閉じ、西洋法系の刑事法制に転換される事になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, with the introduction of criminal law in 1881, the criminal legal system under Chinese system of law since the ancient times ended and was shifted over to the criminal legal system under Western system of law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, with the introduction of criminal law in 1881, the criminal legal system under the Chinese system of law since ancient times, ended and shifted over to the criminal legal system under the Western system of law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the,&quot; placed before &quot;Chinese system,&quot; and deleted from before &quot;ancient times&quot; and words deleted before &quot;shifted over&quot; &quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;Western&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, with the introduction of criminal law in 1881, the criminal legal system under the Chinese system of law since ancient times ended and shifted over to the criminal legal system under the Western system of law.</e>
<cmt>,削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>研究史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of research</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of research</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of research</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="104">
<j>律令条文の解釈・研究は、701年（大宝元年）に大宝律令が施行された直後からはじめられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The interpretation and research of ritsuryo text began immediately after the Taiho code was enforced in 701.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The interpretation and research of ritsuryo text began immediately after the Taiho code was enforced in 701.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The interpretation and research of ritsuryo text began immediately after the Taiho code was enforced in 701.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>すなわち、その年から翌年にかけて、藤原不比等（ふひと）をはじめとする編纂者たちは、 明法博士（みようぼうはかせ）または令官（りようかん）として、分担して律令条文を講説し、また解釈を治定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From that year and on to the following year, FUJIWARA no Fuhito and other compilers took part in lecturing, explaining, and deciding the interpretation of the ritsuryo text as myoho-hakase (illuminators of the law) and ryokan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From that year and on to the following year, FUJIWARA no Fuhito and other compilers took part in lecturing, explaining, and deciding the interpretation of the ritsuryo text as myoho-hakase (illuminators of the law) and ryokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From that year and on to the following year, FUJIWARA no Fuhito and other compilers took part in lecturing, explaining, and deciding the interpretation of the ritsuryo text as myoho-hakase (illuminators of the law) and ryokan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>その後は専門学者が令師（りようし）として解釈の治定にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently, specialized scholars decided the interpretation as ryoshi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently, specialized scholars decided the interpretation as ryoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently, specialized scholars decided the interpretation as ryoshi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="107">
<j>728年（神亀5年）に大学のなかに律令学者の養成機関としての明法科が設けられると、律令の研究もさかんとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 728, when myobo department was established in universities as a training institutions for ritsuryo scholars, research on ritsuryo also flourished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 728, when the myobo department was established in universities as a training institution for ritsuryo scholars, research on ritsuryo also flourished.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;myobo,&quot; and replaced by &quot;a&quot; before institution</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 728, when the myobo department was established in universities as a training institution for ritsuryo scholars, research on ritsuryo also flourished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>これが後の明法道となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This later became the myobodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This later became the myobodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This later became the myobodo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="109">
<j>738年（天平10年）頃には大宝令の私的注釈書「古記」が生まれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around 738, &apos;Koki&apos; (ancient records), a private commentary on the Taihoryo (law of Taiho), was born.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around 738, &apos;Koki&apos; (ancient records), a private commentary on the Taihoryo (law of Taiho), was published.</e>
<cmt>&quot;was born&quot; replaced by &quot;was published&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around 738, &apos;Koki&apos; (ancient records), a private commentary on the Taihoryo (law of Taiho), was published.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="110">
<j>次いで757年（天平宝字元年）に養老律令が施行されたのを契機に、時の権力者藤原仲麻呂は新律令の講書を開催し、みずからも解釈の治定にあたっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Triggered by the enforcement of Yoro code soon after in 757, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, who was in power at the time, held lectures on the new ritsuryo and personally made interpretation decisions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Triggered by the enforcement of the Yoro code soon after in 757, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, who was in power at the time, lectured on the new ritsuryo and personally made interpretation decisions.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;Yoro code&quot;and &quot;held lectures&quot; changed to lectured</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Triggered by the enforcement of the Yoro code soon after in 757, FUJIWARA no Nakamaro, who was in power at the time, lectured on the new ritsuryo and personally made interpretation decisions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>ただし、以上のうちで律令の研究といえるものは「古記」のみで、他は条文の解釈を公的に確定する作業であったというべきであろう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, among the above, only the &apos;Koki&apos; can be referred to as research on ritsuryo, while others were acts of publicly deciding on the interpretation of the text.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, among the above, only the &apos;Koki&apos; can be referred to as being research on ritsuryo, while others were acts of publicly deciding on the interpretation of the text.</e>
<cmt>&quot;being&quot; inserted before &quot;research&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, among the above, only the &apos;Koki&apos; can be referred to as being research on ritsuryo, while others were acts of publicly deciding on the interpretation of the text.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="112">
<j>次いで律令の研究が興隆したのは 8世紀末から 9世紀はじめにかけての時期で、このとき『令集解（りようのしゆうげ）』が引用する令釈、跡記、穴記などの多くの私的注釈書が生まれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, research on ritsuryo became active between the end of the eighth century and the beginning of the ninth century, and many private commentaries such as Reishaku, Sekki, and Kekki, which are quoted in the &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes) were born around that time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, research on ritsuryo became active between the end of the eighth century and the beginning of the ninth century, and many private commentaries such as Reishaku, Sekki, and Kekki, which are quoted in the &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes) were published around that time.</e>
<cmt>&quot;born&quot; changed to &quot;published&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, research on ritsuryo became active between the end of the eighth century and the beginning of the ninth century, and many private commentaries such as Reishaku, Sekki, and Kekki, which are quoted in the &quot;Ryo no shuge&quot; (Commentaries on the Civil Statutes) were published around that time.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>『令義解（りようのぎげ）』はこうした気運のなかで斤定された公的注釈書である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Ryo-no-gige&quot; (commentary on the Ryo) is a public commentary established during such trends.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Ryo-no-gige&quot; (commentary on the Ryo) is a public commentary published during such trends.</e>
<cmt>&quot;established&quot; changed to &quot;published&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Ryo no gige&quot; (commentary on the Ryo) is a public commentary published during such trends.</e>
<cmt>ハイフン削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="114">
<j>その後、公的な律令講書が貞観_(日本)（859年）、延喜（年未詳）、長保（999年）の 3回開かれたことが知られており、またその間に惟宗直本（これむねのなおもと）によって『律集解』、『令集解』が編纂されたが、以後は律・令の全篇にわたる注釈書はみられず、律令学はわずかに惟宗氏、坂上氏、中原氏などに家学として伝えられたにすぎなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, official ritsuryo lectures were held three times, in Jogan (Japan)(859), Engi (year unknown), and Choho (999), and in the meantime, &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; and &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; were compiled by KOREMUNE no Naomoto, but there is no commentary covering the entire ritsu and ryo, and the study of ritsuryo was passed along only as hereditary learning in the Koremune clan, Sakagami clan, Nakahara clan, etc.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, official ritsuryo lectures were held three times, in Jogan (Japan)(859), Engi (year unknown), and Choho (999), and in the meantime, &quot;Ritsu-no-shuge&quot; and &quot;Ryo-no-shuge&quot; were compiled by KOREMUNE no Naomoto, but there is no commentary covering the entire ritsu and ryo, and the study of ritsuryo was passed along only as hereditary learning in the Koremune clan, Sakagami clan, Nakahara clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, official ritsuryo lectures were held three times, in Jogan (Japan)(859), Engi (year unknown), and Choho (999), and in the meantime, &quot;Ritsu no shuge&quot; and &quot;Ryo no shuge&quot; were compiled by KOREMUNE no Naomoto, but there is no commentary covering the entire ritsu and ryo, and the study of ritsuryo was passed along only as hereditary learning in the Koremune clan, Sakagami clan, Nakahara clan, etc.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="115">
<j>降って室町時代に一条兼良は『令抄』を著したが、これも古来の注釈を摘記したものにすぎない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in the Muromachi period, Kaneyoshi ICHIJO authored the &quot;Ryosho,&quot; but this also was simply a summary of ancient commentaries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then in the Muromachi period, Kaneyoshi ICHIJO authored the &quot;Ryosho,&quot; but this also was simply a summary of ancient commentaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then in the Muromachi period, Kaneyoshi ICHIJO authored the &quot;Ryosho,&quot; but this also was simply a summary of ancient commentaries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="116">
<j>ついで江戸時代に入ると漢学者、国学者の双方による律令研究が盛行し、注釈書を残した者に壺井義知（つぼいよしちか）(1657‐1735）、 荷田春満（かだのあずままろ）、稲葉通邦（いなばみちくに）(1744‐1801）、 河村秀穎（ひでかい）、河村秀根（ひでね）、 薗田守良（そのだもりよし）(1785‐1840）、 近藤芳樹などがあるが、依然として研究の中心は解釈学におかれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Next, in the Edo period, research on ritsuryo by both scholars of Chinese classics and scholars of Japanese classical studies flourished, and Yoshichika TSUBOI (1657 - 1735), KADA no Azumamaro, Michikuni INABA (1744 - 1801), Hidekai KAWAMURA, Hidene KAWAMURA, Moriyoshi SONODA (1785 - 1840), and Yoshiki KONDO are among those who left commentaries, but the center of the research was still on hermeneutics.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Next, in the Edo period, research on ritsuryo by both scholars of Chinese classics and scholars of Japanese classical studies flourished, and Yoshichika TSUBOI (1657 - 1735), KADA no Azumamaro, Michikuni INABA (1744 - 1801), Hidekai KAWAMURA, Hidene KAWAMURA, Moriyoshi SONODA (1785 - 1840), and Yoshiki KONDO are among those who left commentaries, but the center of the research was still on hermeneutics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Next, in the Edo period, research on ritsuryo by both scholars of Chinese classics and scholars of Japanese classical studies flourished, and Yoshichika TSUBOI (1657 - 1735), KADA no Azumamaro, Michikuni INABA (1744 - 1801), Hidekai KAWAMURA, Hidene KAWAMURA, Moriyoshi SONODA (1785 - 1840), and Yoshiki KONDO are among those who left commentaries, but the center of the research was still on hermeneutics.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="117">
<j>近代史学の発達とともに、律令の研究はその解釈にとどまらず、多方面にわたって深化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the development of study on modern history, research on ritsuryo deepened in various directions beyond interpretation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the development of studies in modern history, research on ritsuryo deepened in various directions beyond interpretation.</e>
<cmt>&quot;changed to &quot;studies in&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the development of studies in modern history, research on ritsuryo deepened in various directions beyond interpretation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="118">
<j>中田薫 (学者)の『法制史論集』に収める諸論文や滝川政次郎『律令の研究』は、太平洋戦争以前に発表された代表的な研究文献であるが、これらに共通するものは、中国律令法と日本律令法との相違を明らかにしようとする課題意識である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various research papers in the &quot;Hoseishi ronshu&quot; (A collection of essays on legal history) by Kaoru NAKADA (scholar) and the &quot;Ritsuryo no kenkyu&quot; (Studies on Ritsuryo) by Masajiro TAKIKAWA are major research literature published before the Pacific war, and the commonality between them is a sense of issue of an attempt to clarify the difference between Chinese ritsuryo law and Japanese ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various research papers in the &quot;Hoseishi ronshu&quot; (A collection of essays on legal history) by Kaoru NAKADA (scholar) and the &quot;Ritsuryo no kenkyu&quot; (Studies on Ritsuryo) by Masajiro TAKIKAWA are major research literature published before the Pacific war, and the commonality between them is an attempt to clarify the difference between Chinese ritsuryo law and Japanese ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;a sense of issue of&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various research papers in the &quot;Hoseishi ronshu&quot; (A collection of essays on legal history) by Kaoru NAKADA (scholar) and the &quot;Ritsuryo no kenkyu&quot; (Studies on Ritsuryo) by Masajiro TAKIKAWA are major research literature published before the Pacific war, and the commonality between them is an attempt to clarify the difference between Chinese ritsuryo law and Japanese ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="119">
<j>その点では、日本律令そのものを論じたものではないが、仁井田陞『唐令拾遺』も逸することはできない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In that respect, the &quot;Torei Shui&quot; (Collected Laws in the Tang Dynasty) by Noboru NIIDA cannot be ignored, although the Japanese ritsuryo itself is not discussed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In that respect, the &quot;Torei Shui&quot; (Collected Laws in the Tang Dynasty) by Noboru NIIDA cannot be ignored, although the Japanese ritsuryo itself is not discussed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In that respect, the &quot;Torei Shui&quot; (Collected Laws in the Tang Dynasty) by Noboru NIIDA cannot be ignored, although the Japanese ritsuryo itself is not discussed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="120">
<j>敗戦後に研究はさらに深化したが、全体としてみれば個別化し細分化して、個々の条文の意味やそれによって定められた制度などは詳細に解明されつつある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the defeat in the war, research deepened further, but in general, through individualization and fragmentation, the meaning of each text and the systems established based on them are becoming clarified in detail.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the defeat in the war, research deepened further, but in general, through individualization and fragmentation, the meaning of each text and the systems established based on them are becoming clarified in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the defeat in the war, research deepened further, but in general, through individualization and fragmentation, the meaning of each text and the systems established based on them are becoming clarified in detail.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>律令法を総体としてとらえ、法としての構造と特質を明らかにする試みや、律令法に基づいて形成された国家の歴史的特質の解明などは、ようやくその究明に緒がつけられたというのが実情である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As it stands, investigation has finally begun on attempts to grasp the ritsuryo law holistically and to clarify its legal structure and characteristics, and on the clarification of the historical characteristics of a nation formed based on ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As it stands, investigation has finally begun in an attempt to grasp the ritsuryo law holistically and to clarify its legal structure and characteristics, and on the clarification of the historical characteristics of a nation formed based on ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in an attempt&quot; replaces prior wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As it stands, investigation has finally begun in an attempt to grasp the ritsuryo law holistically and to clarify its legal structure and characteristics, and on the clarification of the historical characteristics of a nation formed based on ritsuryo law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), Lennon(id:20471), MASA(id:2399), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), Tamago915(id:11009), Izuamagigoe(id:17784), Shimoxx(id:9332), Suisui(id:69), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>