<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>書道 (大学寮)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shodo (Daigaku-ryo)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shodo (Daigaku-ryo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shodo (Daigaku-ryo)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>書道（しょどう）とは、日本律令制の大学寮において、書道について教えた学科。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shodo was the study of calligraphy under the Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education) of Japan&apos;s Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shodo was the study of calligraphy under the Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education) of Japan&apos;s Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shodo was the study of calligraphy under the Daigaku-ryo (Bureau of Education) of Japan&apos;s Ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>書博士が書生を教えることとされていたが、学令には書生に関する規定はあるものの、学生定員を定めた職員令には書生の定員規定が書かれておらず、若干名であったと考えられている（『続日本紀』天平宝字2年11月甲午条に淳仁天皇から書生に生糸が授けられたとする記事があり、全くいなかった訳ではない）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was thought that shosei (students who were given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties) were taught by sho hakase (professors of calligraphy) but despite the fact that there were regulations regarding shosei in education laws, there were no regulations regarding the fixed number of shosei written within the shikinryo (law which stipulates duties of this ministries) which fixed number of students, and they are thought to have been few in number (an entry in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) for November 758 contains an article stating raw silk thread was awarded to shosei by Emperor Junnin, so it was not the case that there were not any shosei at all).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was thought that shosei (students who were given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties) were taught by sho hakase (professors of calligraphy) but despite the fact that there were regulations regarding shosei in education laws, there were no regulations regarding the fixed number of shosei written within the shikinryo (law which stipulates duties of this ministries) which fixed number of students, and they are thought to have been few in number (an entry in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) for November 758 contains an article stating raw silk thread was awarded to shosei by Emperor Junnin, so it was not the case that there were not any shosei at all).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was thought that shosei (students who were given room and board in exchange for performing domestic duties) were taught by sho hakase (professors of calligraphy) but despite the fact that there were regulations regarding shosei in education laws, there were no regulations regarding the fixed number of shosei written within the shikiinryo (law which stipulates duties of the ministries) which fixed number of students, and they are thought to have been few in number (an entry in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) for December 758 contains an article stating raw silk thread was awarded to shosei by Emperor Junnin, so it was not the case that there were not any shosei at all.)</e>
<cmt>shikinryo→Shikiinryo November→Decemberthis→the (複数形なので）ピリオドを括弧内に。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>書生は書の良し悪しによって優越が判定され、『説文解字』の理解など字体などについての知識も求められた唐の制度よりも簡素化されており、試験に及第して内記などの書記的な官職に配されたようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It appears that the superiority of a shosei&apos;s calligraphy would be judged based on its quality, that the curriculum was simpler than the system of Tang Dynasty China which demanded knowledge of disciplines such as &quot;Shuowen Jiezi&quot; and the formation of characters, and that students who passed examinations were placed in clerical government posts such as that of naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It appears that the superiority of a shosei&apos;s calligraphy would be judged based on its quality, that the curriculum was simpler than the system of Tang Dynasty China which demanded knowledge of disciplines such as &quot;Shuowen Jiezi&quot; and the formation of characters, and that students who passed examinations were placed in clerical government posts such as that of naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It appears that the superiority of a shosei&apos;s calligraphy would be judged based on its quality, that the curriculum was simpler than the system of Tang Dynasty China which demanded knowledge of disciplines such as &quot;Shuowen Jiezi&quot; and the formation of characters, and that students who passed examinations were placed in clerical government posts such as that of naiki (secretary of the Ministry of Central Affairs).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、書博士の職務も本科（後の明経道）の学生に書を教えることが主であったようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It also appears to be the case that the main duty of sho hakase was to teach calligraphy (which later became myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics)) to students.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It also appears to be the case that the main duty of sho hakase was to teach calligraphy (which later became myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics)) to students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also appears to be the case that the main duty of sho hakase was to teach calligraphy (which later became myogyo-do (the study of Confucian classics)) to students.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>平安時代に入ると、書博士の地位を讃岐国多度郡出身の佐伯氏が独占するようになるが、初代東寺長者とされる実恵が書博士の佐伯酒麻呂らから儒学を学んだと伝えられる（ただし、実恵自身も佐伯氏の出身である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Heian period, the position of sho hakase became monopolized by the Saeki clan of Tado District, Sanuki Province but as demonstrated by the fact that Jichie, who is thought to have been the first To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple), studied Confucianism under SAEKI no Sakemaro (although Jichie himself was of the Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Heian period, the position of sho hakase became monopolized by the Saeki clan of Tado District, Sanuki Province but as demonstrated by the fact that Jichie, who is thought to have been the first To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple), studied Confucianism under SAEKI no Sakemaro (although Jichie himself was of the Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Heian period, the position of sho hakase became monopolized by the Saeki clan of Tado District, Sanuki Province but as demonstrated by the fact that Jichie, who is thought to have been the first To-ji choja (the chief abbot of To-ji Temple), studied Confucianism under SAEKI no Sakemaro, sho hakase (although Jichie himself was of the Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt>「書博士の」　訳漏れ対応しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>また、実恵の師である三筆の1人空海も同族であった）ように、明経道の教員の一員同然となり、酒麻呂の子佐伯豊雄も「以彫虫之小、忝学館之末員」（『日本三代実録』貞観 (日本)3年11月11日条）と評されるように官印の刻印を担当する職務（『延喜式』太政官式・中務省式に規定がある）が主となっていくようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jichie&apos;s master Kukai, one of the three famous ancient calligraphers of ancient Japan, was also of the same clan.), they took on the role of myogyo-do teachers and Sakemaro&apos;s son SAEKI no Toyoo also held the position of engraving official seals (regulations under the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) Department of State codes and Ministry of Central Affairs codes) following praise that &quot;owing to his fine seal engraving, he was made a member of the Tengaku Kan&quot; (Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), November 11, 861).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jichie&apos;s master Kukai, one of the three famous ancient calligraphers of ancient Japan, was also of the same clan.), they took on the role of myogyo-do teachers and Sakemaro&apos;s son SAEKI no Toyoo also held the position of engraving official seals (regulations under the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) Department of State codes and Ministry of Central Affairs codes) following praise that &quot;owing to his fine seal engraving, he was made a member of the Tengaku Kan&quot; (Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), November 11, 861).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jichie&apos;s master Kukai, one of the three famous ancient calligraphers of ancient Japan, was also of the same clan), they took on the role of myogyo-do teachers and Sakemaro&apos;s son SAEKI no Toyoo also held the position of engraving official seals (regulations under the &quot;Engishiki&quot; (codes and procedures on national rites and prayers) Department of State codes and Ministry of Central Affairs codes) following the statement that &apos;owing to his fine seal engraving, he was made a member of the Tengaku Kan&apos; (&quot;Nihon Sandai Jitsuroku&quot; (sixth of the six classical Japanese history texts), December 20, 861).</e>
<cmt>旧暦→グレゴリオ暦&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;『日本三代実録』に　&quot; &quot;「評される」「praise」を「statement」に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>11世紀に入ると、書博士そのものが明経博士を世襲した清原氏・中原氏の一族のための待機ポスト（明経道の職に空きが出来るまで暫時任じられる官職）と化してしまい、学科としての書道は完全に消滅したと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 11th century, the position of sho hakase became a standby post (a post to which clan members were temporarily appointed until a myogyo-do position became available) for members of the Kiyohara clan and Nakahara clan which inherited the position of Myogyo hakase (Professor of Confucian classics), and it is though that shodo completely disappeared as an area of study.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 11th century, the position of sho hakase became a standby post (a post to which clan members were temporarily appointed until a myogyo-do position became available) for members of the Kiyohara clan and Nakahara clan which inherited the position of Myogyo hakase (Professor of Confucian classics), and it is though that shodo completely disappeared as an area of study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 11th century, the position of sho hakase became a standby post (a post to which clan members were temporarily appointed until a myogyo-do position became available) for members of the Kiyohara clan and Nakahara clan which inherited the position of Myogyo hakase (Professor of Confucian classics), and it is though that shodo completely disappeared as an area of study.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Straysheep(id:42448), 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>