<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>徒士</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachi (Kachi warrior)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kachi (Kachi warrior)</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kachi</e>
<cmt>カッコ内の補足削除</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>徒士（かち）は、徒歩で戦う下級武士のことをいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term Kachi means lower class warriors who fought on foot.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term Kachi means lower class warriors who fought on foot.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term Kachi means lower class warriors who fought on foot.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>近代軍制でいうと、馬上の資格がある侍（馬廻以上）が士官に相当し、徒士は下士官に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the modern military system, warriors who are allowed to fight on horseback (Umamawari and above) correspond to officers and Kachi correspond to noncommissioned officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the modern military system, warriors who are allowed to fight on horseback (Umamawari and above) correspond to officers and Kachi correspond to noncommissioned officers.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the modern military system, warriors who are allowed to fight on horseback (Umamawari and above) correspond to officers and Kachi correspond to noncommissioned officers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>徒士は士分に含まれ、士分格を持たない足軽とは峻別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachi were categorized into shibun (soldiers who had the status of samurai) and strictly distinguished from ashigaru (common warriors) who had not the status of samurai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kachi were categorized into shibun (soldiers who had the status of samurai) and strictly distinguished from ashigaru (common warriors) who had not the status of samurai.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kachi were categorized into shibun (soldiers who had the status of samurai) and strictly distinguished from ashigaru (common warriors) who had not the status of samurai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>戦場では主君の前駆をなし、平時は城内の護衛（徒士組）や中間管理職的な行政職（目付、勘定奉行の配下など）に従事した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the battle field, they fought as the forerunners of their lords and in peaceful time, they served as the guards (Kachi-gumi (Kachi teams) of castle or engaged in administrative jobs (metsuke (police) or subordinates of kanjo-bugyo (commissioner of finance) as middle class managers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the battle field, they fought as the forerunners of their lords and in peaceful time, they served as the guards (Kachi-gumi (Kachi teams)) of castles or engaged in administrative jobs (metsuke (police)) or subordinates of kanjo-bugyo (commissioner of finance) as middle class managers.</e>
<cmt>Flow, Punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the battle field, they fought as the forerunners of their lords and in peaceful time, they served as the guards (Kachi-gumi (Kachi teams)) of castles or engaged in administrative jobs (metsuke (police)) or subordinates of kanjo-bugyo (commissioner of finance) as middle class managers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸幕府における徒歩組（かちぐみ）は、徳川家康が慶長8年（1603年）に9組をもって成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established 9 Kachi-gumi (Kachi team) in 1603 as the organization of Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established nine Kachi-gumi (Kachi team) in 1603 as the organization of the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu TOKUGAWA established nine Kachi-gumi (Kachi team) in 1603 as the organization of the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>bakufuの補足追加</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>以後、人員・組数を増やした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, the number of persons as well as that of teams was increased.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, the number of persons as well as that of teams was increased.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, the number of persons as well as that of teams was increased.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>幕府安定期には20組が徒歩頭の下にあり、各組毎に2人の組頭が、その下に各組28人の徒歩衆がいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period when bakufu was stable, there were 20 Kachi teams under Kachigashira (superintendant of Kachi teams) and each team had 2 kumigashira (head of Kachi team) and 28 Kachi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外処理</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period when the bakufu was stable, there were 20 Kachi teams under Kachigashira (superintendant of Kachi teams) and each team had two kumigashira (head of Kachi team) and 28 Kachi.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period when the bakufu was stable, there were 20 Kachi teams under Kachigashira (superintendant of Kachi teams) and each team had two kumigashira (head of Kachi team) and 28 Kachi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>徒歩衆は、蔵米の御家人で、俸禄は70俵5人扶持。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kachi were gokenin (immediate vassals of shogun) who were entitled to kuramai (rice preserved in the depository of bakufu) and their salaly was 70 bales, the equivalent of five-men annual rice stipend.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kachi were gokenin (immediate vassals of shogun) who were entitled to kuramai (rice preserved in the depository of bakufu) and their salary was 70 bales, the equivalent of annual rice stipend of five men.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kachi were gokenin (immediate vassals of shogun) who were entitled to kuramai (rice preserved in the depository of bakufu) and their salary was 70 bales, the equivalent of annual rice stipend of five men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>礼服は熨斗目・白帷子、平服は黒縮緬の羽織・無紋の袴。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their formal suit was noshime (a kind of kimono)/shiro-katabira (light white hemp garment) and their normal suit was black crepe haori (Japanese half-coat)/hakama (pleated trousers) with no family crest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their formal suit was noshime (a kind of kimono)/shiro-katabira (light white hemp garment) and their normal suit was a black crepe haori (Japanese half-coat)/hakama (pleated trousers) with no family crest.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their formal suit was noshime (a kind of kimono)/shiro-katabira (light white hemp garment) and their normal suit was a black crepe haori (Japanese half-coat)/hakama (pleated trousers) with no family crest.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>家格は当初御家人（かかえぜき）だったが、文久2年（1862年）に譜代となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Their family status was initially gokenin (kakaezeki (the lowest rank of gokenin)), but it became fudai (the highest rank of gokenin) in 1862.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Their family status were initially gokenin (kakaezeki (the lowest rank of gokenin)), but it became fudai (the highest rank of gokenin) in 1862.</e>
<cmt>Flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Their family status were initially gokenin (kakaezeki (the lowest rank of gokenin)), but it became fudai (the highest rank of gokenin) in 1862.</e>
<cmt>スペース消去</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Extrahitz(id:26245), BitBucket(id:30999), Mankos(id:56678), BAKU(id:55205), ジャニスカ(id:210715), 水野白楓(id:22811), HI(id:72996), くっちゃめ(id:86793), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>