<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>佐伯部</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki be</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saekibe</e>
<cmt>Saeki beとスペースを入れる必要はないと思います。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saekibe</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>佐伯部（さえきべ）は古代日本における品部の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki be is one of the Shinabe (technical groups) that existed in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saekibe is one of the Shinabe (technical groups) that existed in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saekibe is one of the Shinabe (technical groups) that existed in ancient Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>ヤマト王権の拡大過程において、中部地方以東の東日本を侵攻する際、捕虜となった現地人（ヤマト王権側からは「蝦夷」と呼ばれていた）を、近畿地方以西の西日本に移住させて編成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki be was organized in the extension period of the Yamato sovereignty during the invasion of eastern Japan eastward of Chubu region by moving the local people, who became captives, to western Japan westward of Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saekibe was organized in the extension period of the Yamato sovereignty during the invasion of eastern Japan eastward of Chubu region by moving the local people, who became captives, to western Japan westward of Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saekibe was organized in the extension period of the Yamato sovereignty during the invasion of eastern Japan eastward of Chubu region by moving the local people, who became captives, to western Japan westward of Kinki region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>『日本書紀』は下記のように伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nihon Shoki (Chronicles of Japan) narrates as follows.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) narrates as follows.</e>
<cmt>原文は『』なので、&quot; &quot;を追加しました。日本書紀はNihonshokiが正しいので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; (Chronicles of Japan) narrates as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>日本武尊が東征で捕虜にした蝦夷を初めは伊勢神宮に献じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yamato Takeru no Mikoto at first offered the Emishi (native people of Hokkaido) captivated during the eastern conquest to the Ise Gingu shrine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yamato Takeru no Mikoto at first offered the Emishi (native people of Hokkaido) captivated during the eastern conquest to the Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>Ise Gingu shrine→スペルミスです。変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yamato Takeru no Mikoto at first offered the Emishi (native people of Hokkaido) captivated during the eastern conquest to the Ise Jingu Shrine.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>しかし、昼夜の別なく騒いで神宮にも無礼を働くので、倭姫命によって朝廷に差し出された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as they made much noise day and night and also acted disrespectfully to the shrine, they were sent to the Imperial Court by the order of Yamatohime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as they made much noise day and night and also acted disrespectfully to the shrine, they were sent to the Imperial Court by the order of Yamatohime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as they made much noise day and night and also acted disrespectfully to the shrine, they were sent to the Imperial Court by the order of Yamatohime no mikoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>次にこれを三諸山（三輪山）の山麓に住まわせたところ、今度は大神神社に無礼を働き里人を脅かした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emishi were sent to live at the foot of Mount Mimoro (Mount Miwa), where they then acted disrespectfully to the Omiwa Shrine and scared the villagers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emishi were sent to live at the foot of Mount Mimoro (Mount Miwa), where they then acted disrespectfully to the Omiwa Shrine and scared the villagers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emishi were sent to live at the foot of Mount Mimoro (Mount Miwa), where they then acted disrespectfully to the Omiwa Shrine and scared the villagers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>「畿内に住むべからず」との景行天皇の命で、播磨国・讃岐国・伊予国・安芸国・阿波国の5ヶ国に送られたのがその祖である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With the order of Emperor Keiko, the Emishi were forbidden to live within Kinai and were sent to five provinces, namely, Harima Province, Sanuki Province, Iyo province, Aki province and Awa province, and became the origin of Saeki be.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the order of Emperor Keiko, the Emishi were forbidden to live within Kinai and were sent to five provinces, namely, Harima Province, Sanuki Province, Iyo Province, Aki Province, and Awa Province, and became the origin of Saekibe.</e>
<cmt>Provinceが途中から小文字になっているので大文字に統一しました。Aki Provinceのあとにコンマを追加しました。Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the order of Emperor Keiko, the Emishi were forbidden to live within Kinai and were sent to five provinces, namely, Harima Province, Sanuki Province, Iyo Province, Aki Province, and Awa Province, and became the origin of Saekibe.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また、猪名県の佐伯部の者が、仁徳天皇が秘かに愛でていた鹿をそれとは知らずに狩って献上したため、恨めしく思った天皇によって安芸国沼田郡（ぬた）に移されたのが「（安芸国）渟田の佐伯部」であるとも伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nihon Shoki also narrates that the origin of Saeki be of Nuta, Aki province is the member of the Saeki be of Inano Agata who hunted and offered a deer which Emperor Nintoku had been secretly admiring without knowing this and was in turn sent to Nuta, Aki province by the resentful emperor.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; also narrates that the origin of &apos;Saekibe of Nuta, Aki province&apos; was the member of the Saekibe of Inano Agata who hunted and offered a deer which Emperor Nintoku had been secretly admiring without knowing this and was in turn sent to Nuta, Aki province by the resentful Emperor.</e>
<cmt>Nihon Shoki→&quot;Nihonshoki&quot; に変更しました。Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。原文の「」が無視されているので、追加しました。is→wasに変更しました。emperor大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Nihonshoki&quot; also narrates that the origin of &apos;Saekibe of Nuta, Aki province&apos; was the member of the Saekibe of Inano Agata who hunted and offered a deer which Emperor Nintoku had been secretly admiring without knowing this and was in turn sent to Nuta, Aki province by the resentful Emperor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>これらの伝承の史実性はともかくとして、古墳時代の中頃（5-6世紀）には、東国人の捕虜を上記5ヶ国に移住させ、佐伯部として設定・編成したのは事実のようである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Whether these legendary stories are based on historical truth or not, it seems to be true that during the middle of the Tumulus period, the captives of the eastern countries were moved to the 5 provinces mentioned above and were set up and organized as Saeki be.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Whether these legendary stories are based on historical truth or not, it seems to be true that during the middle of the Tumulus period, the captives of the eastern countries were moved to the five provinces mentioned above and were set up and organized as Saeki be.</e>
<cmt>5をスペルアウトしました。Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Whether these legendary stories are based on historical truth or not, it seems to be true that during the middle of the Tumulus period, the captives of the eastern countries were moved to the five provinces mentioned above and were set up and organized as Saeki be.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>「佐伯直」や「佐伯氏佐伯造」といった在地の豪族が伴造としてこれを管掌し、これら地方豪族が更に畿内の中央豪族佐伯氏（後に宿祢に改賜姓された）に管掌された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Saeki no atai and Saeki no miyatsuko of the Saeki clan took charge of it as the Tomonomiyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the imperial court, and these gozoku (powerful local clans) were then taken in control by the Saeki clan (later given the family name of Sukune by the emperor) which was the central gozoku of Kinai.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &apos;Saeki no atai&apos; and &apos;Saeki no miyatsuko of the Saeki clan&apos; took charge of it as the Tomonomiyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial court), and these gozoku (powerful local clans) were then taken in control by the Saeki clan (later given the family name of Sukune by the Emperor) which was the central gozoku of Kinai.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」が無視されているので、追加しました。Tomonomiyatsukoの（）説明のカッコトジルがありません。追加しました。imperial大文字に変更しました。emperor大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Saeki no atai&apos; and &apos;Saeki no miyatsuko of the Saeki clan&apos; took charge of it as the Tomonomiyatsuko (the chief of various departments at the Imperial court), and these gozoku (powerful local clans) were then taken in control by the Saeki clan (later given the family name of Sukune by the Emperor) which was the central gozoku of Kinai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>そのため、佐伯部は間接的に中央佐伯氏の部民とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, Saeki be was indirectly made a bemin (a group of people who belonged to Yamato sovereignty) of the central Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, Saekibe was indirectly made a Bemin (a group of people who belonged to Yamato sovereignty) of the central Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt>Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。bemin大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, Saekibe was indirectly made a Bemin (a group of people who belonged to Yamato sovereignty) of the central Saeki clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>その中からは宮廷警衛の任務に上番させられた者もいたと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that among these people, there were those that were made to serve as guards of the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that among these people, there were those that were made to serve as guards of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>imperial大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that among these people, there were those that were made to serve as guards of the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>部名の由来</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The origin of the name</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>平安時代以来、「叫ぶ」に由来するとされてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Saeki be has been said to have derived from &apos;Sakebu&apos; (to shout) since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。何が「叫ぶ」に由来するのかがないと文が構成できないため「佐伯部」を補って訳しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Saekibe has been said to derive from &apos;Sakebu&apos; (to shout) since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。to have derived→deriveに修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Saekibe has been said to derive from &apos;Sakebu&apos; (to shout) since the Heian period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>『常陸国風土記』茨城郡条には、土着民である「山の佐伯、野の佐伯」が王権に反抗したことが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Ibaraki in &quot;Hitachi no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Hitachi Province), it is written that the natives &quot;Saeki of the mountains and Saeki of the fields&quot; had resisted the sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Ibaraki in &quot;Hitachi no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Hitachi Province), it is written that the natives &apos;Saeki of the mountains and Saeki of the fields&apos; had resisted the sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Saeki of the mountains and Saeki of the fields&quot;は原文で「」なので修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Ibaraki in &quot;Hitachi no kuni fudoki&quot; (the topography of Hitachi Province), it is written that the natives &apos;Saeki of the mountains and Saeki of the fields&apos; had resisted the sovereignty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>そのため「障（さへ）ぎる者（き）」で、朝廷の命に反抗する者の意味と説くものもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, there are those who say that the name of Saeki be is &quot;Saegiru&quot;(an obstacle) and &quot;ki&quot;(person), meaning the people who resist against the imperial court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, there are those who say that the name of Saekibe is &apos;Saegiru&apos; (an obstacle) and &apos;ki&apos; (person), meaning the people who resist against the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>原文で「」なので修正しました。Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。imperial大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, there are those who say that the name of Saekibe is &apos;Saegiru&apos; (an obstacle) and &apos;ki&apos; (person), meaning the people who resist against the Imperial court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>別に上記景行天皇紀に「騒い」だとあることに着目し、「大声を発して邪霊や邪力を追いはらったり、相手を威嚇するといった呪術的儀礼に従事」するのが彼らの職掌で、佐伯部は「サハグ部」であるとの説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Paying attention to the record of the Emperor Keiko where it says that the Saeki be &quot;sawai-da&quot; (made noise), it is also said that Saeki be was engaged in the work of magical ceremonies such as shouting out to drive away evil spirits and powers and to intimidate the opposition, and that the Saeki be is &quot;Sawagube&quot; (the shinabe that made noise).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処。「上記」景行天皇紀、とありますが前述されていないようなので「上記」は省略しました。また、「騒いだ」のは誰かが不明であったたため,一番適当であると思われた「佐伯部」を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Paying attention to the record of the Emperor Keiko where it says that the Saekibe &apos;sawai-da&apos; (made noise), it is also said that &apos;Saekibe was engaged in the work of magical ceremonies such as shouting out to drive away evil spirits and powers and to intimidate the opposition&apos;, and that the Saekibe is &apos;Sawagube&apos; (the Shinabe that made noise).</e>
<cmt>Saeki beのスペースを削除しました。原文で「」なので修正しました。原文で「大声を～に従事」の部分の「」が無視されていたので、訳文に追加しました。shinabe大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Paying attention to the record of the Emperor Keiko where it says that the Saekibe &apos;sawai-da&apos; (made noise), it is also said that &apos;Saekibe was engaged in the work of magical ceremonies such as shouting out to drive away evil spirits and powers and to intimidate the opposition&apos;, and that the Saekibe is &apos;Sawagube&apos; (the Shinabe that made noise).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 胡亂堂(id:263343), Japan Maik(id:254359), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>