<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tael (A Former Japanese Weight Unit, And Also A Former Japanese And Chinese Currency Unit)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo (A Former Japanese Weight Unit, And Also A Former Japanese And Chinese Currency Unit)</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo (A Former Japanese Weight Unit, And Also A Former Japanese And Chinese Currency Unit)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>両（りょう）は、尺貫法における質量の単位であり、また、近世の日本における金貨、および中国における秤量銀貨の通貨単位である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tael served as a weight unit in the traditional East Asian system of weights and measures, and also served as a currency unit both in Japan and in China - in Japan, the unit of gold coins in the early modern ages, and in China, the unit of &quot;hyoryo ginka&quot; (silver coin used as currency by weight).</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・「尺貫法」は狭義では日本における度量衡の単位系を指し、広義では東アジア一帯で用いられる度量衡の単位系を指します。このファイルの以下の内容から、ここの「両」が中国の質量単位としてのそれを含んでいることは明らかであり、従って「尺貫法」も広義に用いているように思われます。（注②）・・・「秤量（ひょうりょう）銀貨」の定訳は見つかりませんでしたが、「秤量貨幣」の研究社・大和英の訳（currency by weight)を参考に&quot;silver coin used as currency by weight&quot;としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo served as a weight unit in the traditional East Asian system of weights and measures, and also served as a currency unit in Japan and in China; in Japan, the unit of gold coins in the early modern ages, and in China, the unit of hyoryo ginka (silver coin used as currency by weight).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo served as a weight unit in the traditional East Asian system of weights and measures, and also served as a currency unit in Japan and in China; in Japan, the unit of gold coins in the early modern ages, and in China, the unit of hyoryo ginka (silver coin used as currency by weight).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>質量の単位としての両は、匁の倍量（貫、斤の分量）単位で、日本では1両＝10匁＝1/100貫＝1/16斤とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a weight unit, tael had a larger scale than &quot;monme&quot; (former Japanese weight unit) and a smaller scale than &quot;kan&quot; and &quot;kin&quot; (kan and kin were both fomer Japanese weight units), and in Japan, 1 tael, 10 monme, 0.01 kan, and a sixteenth kin were equalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a weight unit, ryo had a heavier scale than monme (former Japanese weight unit) and a lighter scale than kan and kin (kan and kin were both former Japanese weight units), and in Japan, 1 ryo, 10 monme, 0.01 kan, and a 16th kin were equalized.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a weight unit, ryo had a heavier scale than monme (former Japanese weight unit) and a lighter scale than kan and kin (kan and kin were both former Japanese weight units), and in Japan, 1 ryo, 10 monme, 0.01 kan, and a 16th kin were equalized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>奈良時代に公布された大宝律令では隋代（唐代初期か）の一両に準じて、おおむね41～42グラムくらいであったが、唐代になり11%程度減少し37.3グラムとなり、日本国内でもこれに近い値となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Taiho Code promulgated in the Nara period, the weight of 1 tael was set around 41- 42 grams, following the standard of the Sui dynasty (or the early stage of the Tang dynasty) China, and when the weight of 1 tael was reduced by around 11% into 37.3 grams in Tang dynasty China, Japan followed China again and took almost the same standard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Taiho Code promulgated in the Nara period, the weight of 1 ryo was set around 41to 42 grams, following the standard of the Sui Dynasty (or the early Tang Dynasty) China, and when the weight of 1 ryo was reduced by around 11 percents into 37.3 grams in Tang Dynasty, Japan followed China again and took almost the same standard.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Taiho Code promulgated in the Nara period, the weight of 1 ryo was set around 41to 42 grams, following the standard of the Sui Dynasty (or the early Tang Dynasty) China, and when the weight of 1 ryo was reduced by around 11 percents into 37.3 grams in Tang Dynasty, Japan followed China again and took almost the same standard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>明治時代以降、日本国内ではほとんど使用されていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Meiji period, tael as the weight unit has rarely been used in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Meiji period, ryo as the weight unit has rarely been used in Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Meiji period, ryo as the weight unit has rarely been used in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>現代の中国の1市両は50グラムである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In today&apos;s China, 1 shi liang is set at 50 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In today&apos;s China, 1 ryo (liang in Chinese) is set at 50 grams.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In today&apos;s China, 1 ryo (liang in Chinese) is set at 50 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>金貨の通貨単位としての両は武田信玄により、鋳造を命じられた甲州金により確立され、江戸幕府に継承されたもので、1両は4分に等しく、また16朱に等しい。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the currency unit of gold coins, tael was established when Shingen TAKEDA adopted it for &quot;Koshu-kin&quot; (the gold coin minted in Koshu Province), and it took root when Edo &quot;bakufu&quot; (Japanese feudal regime headed by a shogun) also adopted it, and Shingen and Edo bakufu equalized 1 tael with 4 &quot;bu,&quot; and also equalized 1 tael with 16 &quot;shu&quot; (bu and shu were former Japanese currency unit).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the currency unit of gold coins, ryo was established by Koshu-kin (the gold coin minted in Koshu Province), which Shingen TAKEDA ordered to coin, and handed down to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); 1 ryo was equalized with 4 bu, or 16 shu (bu and shu were former Japanese currency unit).</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせ、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the currency unit of gold coins, ryo was established by Koshu-kin (the gold coin minted in Koshu Province), which Shingen TAKEDA ordered to coin, and handed down to the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun); 1 ryo was equalized with 4 bu, or 16 shu (bu and shu were former Japanese currency unit).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>小判1枚の貨幣価値に相当し、したがって二分金2枚に、一分金、一分銀4枚に相当し、また二朱金、南鐐二朱銀8枚に、一朱金、一朱銀16枚に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 &quot;koban&quot; (former Japanese gold coin of oval shape) had the currency value of 1 tael, and 1 koban could be exchanged into various other coins, that is, 2 &quot;nibu-kin&quot; (former Japanese gold coin of 2 bu), 4 &quot;ichibu-kin&quot; (former Japanese gold coin of 1 bu), 4 &quot;ichibu-gin&quot; (former Japanese silver coin of 1 bu), 8 &quot;nishu-kin&quot; (former Japanese gold coin of 2 shu), 8 &quot;Nanryo nishu-gin&quot; (former Japanese silver coin of 2 shu), 16 &quot;isshu-kin&quot; (former Japanese gold coin of 1 shu), and 16 &quot;isshu-gin&quot; (former Japanese silver coin of 1 shu).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 ryo had currency value as 1 koban (former Japanese gold coin of oval shape) which 1 ryo was equivalent to 2 nibu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 2 bu), 4 ichibu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 1 bu) or ichibu-gin (former Japanese silver coin of 1 bu), 8 nishu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 2 shu) or Nanryo nishu-gin (former Japanese silver coin of 2 shu), 16 isshu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 1 shu) or isshu-gin (former Japanese silver coin of 1 shu) accordingly.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 ryo had currency value as 1 koban (former Japanese gold coin of oval shape) which 1 ryo was equivalent to 2 nibu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 2 bu), 4 ichibu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 1 bu) or ichibu-gin (former Japanese silver coin of 1 bu), 8 nishu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 2 shu) or Nanryo nishu-gin (former Japanese silver coin of 2 shu), 16 isshu-kin (former Japanese gold coin of 1 shu) or isshu-gin (former Japanese silver coin of 1 shu) accordingly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>明治時代に通貨単位として円 (通貨)（円）が導入されたが、切り替え時に「1圓は1両と等価」とされ、しばらくの間は「圓」のことを「両」とも呼んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, &quot;yen&quot; was introduced as the currency unit, and when the exchange rate among currencies was changed, 1 yen and 1 tael were equalized, so yen was used as the synonym of tael for a while.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, yen was introduced as the currency unit, however, &apos;1 yen was equivalent to 1 ryo&apos; in changeover phase, so &apos;yen&apos; was called &apos;ryo&apos; for a while.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, yen was introduced as the currency unit, however, &apos;1 yen was equivalent to 1 ryo&apos; in changeover phase, so &apos;yen&apos; was called &apos;ryo&apos; for a while.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また江戸時代にも文政年間頃から「両」のことを俗称として「圓」と呼ぶ習慣が一部にあったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And from around the Bunsei era (A.D. 1818 - 1830) in the Edo period, there were some areas where &quot;yen&quot; was custmarily used as the popular name of tael, they say.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And from around the Bunsei era (1818 to 1830) in the Edo period, it is said some called &apos;yen&apos; as &apos;ryo&apos; habitually.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And from around the Bunsei era (1818 to 1830) in the Edo period, it is said some called &apos;yen&apos; as &apos;ryo&apos; habitually.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="10">
<j>質量単位としての両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tael as the weight unit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo as the weight unit</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo as the weight unit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>質量の単位としての両は、古代中国で生まれたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tael as the weight unit originated in ancient China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo as the weight unit originated in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo as the weight unit originated in ancient China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>漢代では『漢書律歴志』に下記のような記述がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Treatise on rhythm and calendar in Book of Han, written in Han dynasty China, says as follows :</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Book of Han, Treatise on rhythm and the calendar&quot; in Han Dynasty says as follows:</e>
<cmt>用語集に合わせ、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Book of Han, Treatise on rhythm and the calendar&quot; in Han Dynasty says as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>「権者銖・両・斤・鈞・石 (単位)也。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The units of weight are &apos;shu&apos; (in pinyin, &apos;zhu&apos;), &apos;tael,&apos; &apos;kin&apos; (in pinyin, &apos;jin&apos;), &apos;kin&apos; (in pinyin, &apos;jun&apos;), and &apos;koku&apos; (in pinyin, &apos;dan&apos;).&quot;</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・翻訳者は原文を「権（はか）る者は、銖・両・斤・鈞・石なり」と読み下した上、「物の重さを測る単位は、銖・両・斤・鈞・石である。」の意味に解しています。（注②）・・・「銖・両・斤・鈞・石」のそれぞれにつき、中国の単位であることもありピンイン（中国語読みのローマ字表記）を併せ記しておきました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The units of weight are shu (in pinyin, &apos;zhu&apos;), ryo, kin (in pinyin, &apos;jin&apos;), kin (in pinyin, &apos;jun&apos;), and koku (in pinyin, &apos;dan&apos;).&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The units of weight are shu (in pinyin, &apos;zhu&apos;), ryo, kin (in pinyin, &apos;jin&apos;), kin (in pinyin, &apos;jun&apos;), and koku (in pinyin, &apos;dan&apos;).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>「所以称物平施知軽重也。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;By diffusing the units, the weight of things can be known.&quot;</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・翻訳者は原文を「物を称する所以（ゆえん）を平（たいら）に施（し）き、軽重を知るなり。」と読み下した上、「物（の重さ）を呼称する手段を広く行き渡らせることで、（物質の）重さを知ることが出来る。」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By diffusing the units, the weight of things can be known.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By diffusing the units, the weight of things can be known.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>「本起於黄鍾之重。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Originally, the name of shu came from the weight of the proso millet grains that are fully put into &apos;kosho pipe&apos; (a kind of flute).&quot;</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・翻訳者は原文を「本（もと）は黄鍾（こうしょう）の重さより起こる。」と読み下した上、「（銖の単位は）もともと黄鍾管（の中に入る黍）の重さが起源である。」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, the name of shu came from the weight of the proso millet grains that are fully put into Kosho pipe, a kind of flute.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, the name of shu came from the weight of the proso millet grains that are fully put into Kosho pipe, a kind of flute.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>「一龠容千二百黍重十二銖。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;The volume of kosho pipe (= 1 &apos;yaku&apos;) is the same as the volume of 1200 proso millet grains, whose weight is 12 shu.&quot;</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・翻訳者は原文を「一龠（ひとやく）は千二百の黍（きび）を容（い）れ、重（ちょう）は十二銖。」と読み下した上、「一龠（ひとやく）の黄鍾管の中に黍の粒1200個が入るが、その重量は12銖である。」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The volume of kosho pipe (= 1 &apos;yaku&apos;) is the same as the volume of 1200 proso millet grains, whose weight is 12 shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The volume of kosho pipe (= 1 &apos;yaku&apos;) is the same as the volume of 1200 proso millet grains, whose weight is 12 shu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>「両之為両。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;And twice the 12 shu is set equal to 1 tael.&quot;</e>
<cmt>（注）・・・翻訳者は原文を「之（これ）を両して両となす」と読み下した上、「これを二つ合わせて1両とする。」の意味に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And twice the 12 shu is set equal to 1 ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And twice the 12 shu is set equal to 1 ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="18">
<j>黄鍾管の体積が一龠部（やく）であり、これに入る黍1200粒を12銖（しゅ。朱はこれの略字）とし、これを二つ合わせた質量すなわち24銖を1両とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In short, the volume of an kosho pipe (= 1 yaku) is the same as the volume of 1200 proso millet grains, and the weight of the 1200 grains was set equal to 12 銖 (朱 in abbreviation [both read as &quot;shu&quot;]), and twice the 12 shu, or 24 shu, was set equal to 1 tael.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In short, the volume of an kosho pipe (= 1 yaku) is the same as the volume of 1200 proso millet grains, and the weight of the 1200 grains was set equal to 12 shu (銖; 朱 in abbreviation), and twice the 12 shu, or 24 shu, was set equal to 1 ryo.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In short, the volume of an kosho pipe (= 1 yaku) is the same as the volume of 1200 proso millet grains, and the weight of the 1200 grains was set equal to 12 shu (銖; 朱 in abbreviation), and twice the 12 shu, or 24 shu, was set equal to 1 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>「両」の漢字には「二つ」という意味がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Incidentally, the Chinese character of 両 (reads as tael) has the second meaning of &quot;twice.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Incidentally, the Chinese character of &apos;両&apos; (reads as ryo) has the second meaning of &apos;two.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Incidentally, the Chinese character of &apos;両&apos; (reads as ryo) has the second meaning of &apos;two.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この両は3銭8分程度（銭は日本の匁と同じ）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, 1 tael was roughly equal to 3 sen (also called monme in Japan) plus 8 bu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, 1 ryo was roughly equal to 3 sen (also called monme in Japan) and 8 bu.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, 1 ryo was roughly equal to 3 sen (also called monme in Japan) and 8 bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>唐代にこれの3倍を大両とする制度ができたが、大両は3銭8分の3倍（11銭4分）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the Tang dynasty China, the new weight unit &quot;larger tael&quot; was made, and 1 larger tael weighs 11 sen plus 4 bu, which is three times as much as 1 tael.</e>
<cmt>（注①）一原文一訳文の例外対処（注②）原文の「唐代」は「隋代」の誤りではないでしょうか。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the Tang Dynasty, the system of larger ryo, which was three times larger than ryo, was established that larger ryo weighed 11 sen and 4 bu, which was three times as much as 3 sen and 8 bu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the Tang Dynasty, the system of larger ryo, which was three times larger than ryo, was established that larger ryo weighed 11 sen and 4 bu, which was three times as much as 3 sen and 8 bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後の唐代に「斤」、「両」の質量が縮小し、開元通宝が1/10両の基準で鋳造されたため、10銭（匁）と等しいとされるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And later in Tang dynasty, the weight standard of kin and larger tael was reduced, and 1 larger tael and 10 sen (or 10 monme) became equal in currency value when &quot;Kaigen Tsuho&quot; (&apos;Kai Yuan Tong Bao&apos; in pinyin, a coin of the Tang dynasty China) was minted at the weight of a tenth of 1 larger tael.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・一原文一訳文の例外対処（注②）・・・「開元通宝」は中国の貨幣ゆえピンインも表記しておきました。（注③）・・・多少質量が縮小して10銭と等しいとされた「1両」は内容的に見て「大両」の方の「1両」だと解されます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And later in Tang Dynasty, the weight standard of &apos;kin&apos; and &apos;ryo&apos; was reduced and Kaigen Tsuho (&apos;Kai Yuan Tong Bao&apos; in pinyin, a coin of the Tang Dynasty China) was minted at the weight of a 10th of 1 ryo which was equivalent to 10 sen (or 10 monme).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And later in Tang Dynasty, the weight standard of &apos;kin&apos; and &apos;ryo&apos; was reduced and Kaigen Tsuho (&apos;Kai Yuan Tong Bao&apos; in pinyin, a coin of the Tang Dynasty China) was minted at the weight of a 10th of 1 ryo which was equivalent to 10 sen (or 10 monme).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>日本にも両方の「両」が伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both units of smaller tael and larger tael were introduced into Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both &apos;ryo,&apos; smaller ryo and larger ryo, were introduced into Japan.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both &apos;ryo,&apos; smaller ryo and larger ryo, were introduced into Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="24">
<j>嘉量による1両は『漢書律歴志』の記述に基づく実測の結果は14.167グラムであり、これは「小両」に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When we weigh 1 tael with the measure of the Xin dynasty China, based on the depiction in Treatise on rhythm and calendar in Book of Han, it is 14.167 grams, which suggests 1 tael here implies 1 smaller tael.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・一原文一訳文の例外対処。（注②）・・・「嘉量」は「中国新代の計測器」と訳しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When we weigh 1 ryo with chia-liang standard measure in &quot;Book of Han, Treatise on rhythm and the calendar,&quot; actual measured value was 14.167 grams which equivalent to 1 &apos;smaller ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When we weigh 1 ryo with chia-liang standard measure in &quot;Book of Han, Treatise on rhythm and the calendar,&quot; actual measured value was 14.167 grams which equivalent to 1 &apos;smaller ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>呉承洛の『中国度量衡史』による隋代の1両は41.762グラムであり嘉量の約3倍、唐代の1両は37.301グラムであり、「大両」に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And when we weigh 1 tael with the standard of Sui dynasty China, based on the depiction in History of Chinese Weights and Measures (written by Wu Chengluo), it is 41.762 grams - about three times as much as the above-mentioned weight in Xin dynasty - and with the standard of the Tang dynasty China, 1 tael weighs at 37.301 grams, which suggests this 1 tael implies 1 larger tael.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And when we weigh 1 ryo with the standard of Sui Dynasty China in &quot;History of Chinese Weights and Measures,&quot; written by Wu Chengluo, the value was 41.762 grams, which was about three times as much as the previously-mentioned weight with chia-liang, and with the standard of the Tang Dynasty, 1 ryo weighed at 37.301 grams which equivalent to 1 &apos;larger ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And when we weigh 1 ryo with the standard of Sui Dynasty China in &quot;History of Chinese Weights and Measures,&quot; written by Wu Chengluo, the value was 41.762 grams, which was about three times as much as the previously-mentioned weight with chia-liang, and with the standard of the Tang Dynasty, 1 ryo weighed at 37.301 grams which equivalent to 1 &apos;larger ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="26">
<j>江戸時代初期までは、この唐代の「両」が日本に伝えられ用いられていたが、寛文元年（1661年）に度量衡の「衡」が統一された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tang dynasty&apos;s larger tael was introduced into Japan and was used as the weight unit until the early Edo period, and in A.D. 1661, the Japanese weight units were standardized.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This Tang Dynasty&apos;s &apos;ryo&apos; was introduced into Japan to be used until the early Edo period, then in 1661, the Japanese weight units were standardized.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This Tang Dynasty&apos;s &apos;ryo&apos; was introduced into Japan to be used until the early Edo period, then in 1661, the Japanese weight units were standardized.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>以後、両替商で用いられる分銅は後藤四郎兵衛家のみ製作が許され、これ以外のものの製作および使用は不正を防止するため厳禁とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And thereafter, Shirobei GOTO and his descendants monopolized the production right of &quot;fundo&quot; (counterweight) used at an exchange house, and the production and use of other kinds of fundo was prohibited strictly for the prevention of illegal exchange.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And thereafter, Shirobei GOTO family was only allowed to produce fundo (counterweight) used at an exchange house, and the production and use of other kinds of fundo was prohibited strictly for the prevention of illegal exchange.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And thereafter, Shirobei GOTO family was only allowed to produce fundo (counterweight) used at an exchange house, and the production and use of other kinds of fundo was prohibited strictly for the prevention of illegal exchange.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>この分銅は「両」を基本単位としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The basic weight unit of the fundo was tael.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The basic weight unit of the fundo was &apos;ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The basic weight unit of the fundo was &apos;ryo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>ただし秤量銀貨の通貨単位は、小判の通貨単位の「両」との混同を避ける意味から「匁」および「貫」が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was &quot;monme&quot; and &quot;kan&quot; that were adopted as the currency unit for hyoryo ginka, lest the term &quot;tael&quot; should be confused with the tael used as the currency unit of koban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, to avoid mixing up &apos;ryo&apos; of the currency unit for koban, &apos;monme&apos; and &apos;kan&apos; were used as the currency unit for hyoryo ginka.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, to avoid mixing up &apos;ryo&apos; of the currency unit for koban, &apos;monme&apos; and &apos;kan&apos; were used as the currency unit for hyoryo ginka.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>すなわち、肆兩（しりょう）の分銅と釣合う丁銀は銀40匁と表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, when &quot;chogin&quot; (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) was balanced with 4 tael of fundo, the chogin&apos;s currency value was depicted as 40 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・「肆兩（しりょう）」は「四両」の当て字です。（注②）・・・「丁銀」は秤量銀貨として用いられた銀貨のことです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, when chogin (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) was balanced with 4 ryo of fundo, the chogin&apos;s currency value was equivalent to 40 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, when chogin (the silver coin used as the currency by weight) was balanced with 4 ryo of fundo, the chogin&apos;s currency value was equivalent to 40 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>江戸時代の1両は分銅の実測によると37.46から37.47グラム程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By measuring the fundo, we know that the weight of 1 tael in the Edo period was around 37.46 - 37. 47 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By an actual measured value of the fundo, 1 ryo in the Edo period was around 37.46 to 37.47 grams.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By an actual measured value of the fundo, 1 ryo in the Edo period was around 37.46 to 37.47 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="32">
<j>一方中国では秤量銀貨の実測値一両（大両）を銀一両（銀両）と表した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile in China, 1 larger tael, measured with hyoryo ginka, was depicted as 1 tael of silver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile in China, 1 ryo (larger ryo) with actual measured value of hyoryo ginka was equivalent to 1 ryo of silver (ginryo).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile in China, 1 ryo (larger ryo) with actual measured value of hyoryo ginka was equivalent to 1 ryo of silver (ginryo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>このため、安政5年（1858年）の日米修好通商条約締結の際、約8.6グラムの質量を持つ一分銀は偶然にも質量としての一両の約1/4であることから額面通り銀1/4両であり、中国の銀一両の約3/4の質量である1ドル銀貨＝一分銀3枚という日本側に不利な交換比率を主張する口実をタウンゼント・ハリスに与えることになり、小判流出の一因となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan was concluded in A.D. 1858, an ichibu-gin had the weight around 1/4 tael (about 8.61 grams), and coincidentally, its currency value (written on its face) was also 1/4 tael of Japanese silver, and meanwhile, an one-dollar silver coin then had the weight around 3/4 tael of Chinese silver, so Townsend Harris claimed that an one-dollar silver coin should be equalized with three ichibu-gin, but this exchange rate was unfavorable to Japan, and it contributed to the outflow of koban.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・語句の順序を変えずに区切ることは困難なので、一文として訳しました。（注②）・・・「額面」とあるのは一分銀の表面にあった「一分」（＝1/4両の貨幣価値）の記載を指します。　　　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan was concluded in 1858, the fact that about 8.6-gram ichibu-gin was coincidentally equivalent to around one fourth ryo in weight, which was worth of one fourth ryo of silver at face value, provided Townsend Harris with the excuse of insisting unfavorable exchange rate for Japan that three ichibu-gin coins changed one-dollar silver coin which was about three fourth weight of Chinese one ryo of silver and led koban flow out.</e>
<cmt>数値および表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan was concluded in 1858, the fact that about 8.6-gram ichibu-gin was coincidentally equivalent to around one fourth ryo in weight, which was worth of one fourth ryo of silver at face value, provided Townsend Harris with the excuse of insisting unfavorable exchange rate for Japan that three ichibu-gin coins changed one-dollar silver coin which was about three fourth weight of Chinese one ryo of silver and led koban flow out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="34">
<j>明治4年（1871年）5月、新貨条例公布の際、当初1戔（匁）＝3.756574グラムとされたが、同年9月に訂正され1戔＝3.756521グラムと定められたため、1両＝37.56521グラムとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the New Currency Act was promulgated in May 1871, the weight of 1 sen (monme) was set at 3.756574 grams, and then in September of the same year, it was reset at 3.756521 grams, so the weight of 1 tael became 37.56521 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the New Currency Act was promulgated in June 1871, the weight of 1 sen (monme) was set at 3.756574 grams at first, and then in October of the same year, it was reset at 3.756521 grams, so the weight of 1 ryo became 37.56521 grams.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the New Currency Act was promulgated in June 1871, the weight of 1 sen (monme) was set at 3.756574 grams at first, and then in October of the same year, it was reset at 3.756521 grams, so the weight of 1 ryo became 37.56521 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="35">
<j>その後、換算の便宜のため、メートル法基準となり、明治24年（1891年）の度量衡法により1貫＝3.75キログラムと定められたので、1両＝37.5グラムとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Afterward, the metric system was introduced into Japan for convenience in conversion among units, and in A.D. 1891, the Weights and Measures Act set 1 kan at 3.75 kg, so 1 tael became equal to 37.5 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Afterward, the metric system was introduced into Japan for convenience in conversion among units, and in 1891, the Weights and Measures Act set 1 kan at 3.75 kilograms, so 1 ryo became equal to 37.5 grams.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Afterward, the metric system was introduced into Japan for convenience in conversion among units, and in 1891, the Weights and Measures Act set 1 kan at 3.75 kilograms, so 1 ryo became equal to 37.5 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>しかし明治時代以降は日本国内では尺貫法としては専ら「貫」、「匁」が使用され、「両」は新貨条例にも度量衡法にも登場せず、ほとんど使用されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the Meiji period, however, only kan and monme became used in the traditional Japanese system of weights and measures, and tael became rarely used because it was not mentioned in the New Currency Act nor in the Weights and Measures Act.</e>
<cmt>（注）ここの「尺貫法」は狭義に用いているように思われます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the Meiji period in Japan, however, only &apos;kan&apos; and &apos;monme&apos; became used in the traditional Japanese system of weights and measures, and &apos;ryo&apos; became rarely used because it was neither mentioned in the New Currency Act nor in the Weights and Measures Act.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the Meiji period in Japan, however, only &apos;kan&apos; and &apos;monme&apos; became used in the traditional Japanese system of weights and measures, and &apos;ryo&apos; became rarely used because it was neither mentioned in the New Currency Act nor in the Weights and Measures Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>その度量衡法も昭和26年（1951年）に廃止され、その後の計量法ではメートル法に統一され公式には使用されなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Weights and Measures Act was abolished in A.D. 1951, and later, the Measurement Act standardized Japanese measurement units into the metric system, when tael was ended in its official use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Weights and Measures Act was abolished in 1951, and later, the Measurement Act standardized Japanese measurement units into the metric system, when ryo was ended in its official use.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Weights and Measures Act was abolished in 1951, and later, the Measurement Act standardized Japanese measurement units into the metric system, when ryo was ended in its official use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="38">
<j>薬種の量目としては1両を4匁（すなわち小両）とするのが一般的であったが、薬種によって4匁4分や5匁とするものもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the weight standards of drugs, 1 tael was commonly equalized with 4 monme (= 1 smaller tael), but occasionally, 1 tael was equalized with 4 monme plus 4 bu (or 5 monme) for some drugs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the weight standards of drugs, 1 ryo was commonly equalized with 4 monme (that is, 1 smaller ryo), but occasionally, 1 ryo was equalized with 4 monme and 4 bu, or 5 monme for some drugs.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the weight standards of drugs, 1 ryo was commonly equalized with 4 monme (that is, 1 smaller ryo), but occasionally, 1 ryo was equalized with 4 monme and 4 bu, or 5 monme for some drugs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="39">
<j>馬一頭が運ぶ荷物の目方（質量）を表す駄法と関連があるとされる記事が、1300年頃に編纂されたとされる『拾芥抄』の中にある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia), which is said to have been compiled around A.D. 1300, there is an article related to &quot;daho&quot; (a system of weight units, seen for the load carried by a horse).</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia), which is said to have been compiled around 1300, has an article that it is related to daho (a system of weight units, seen for the load carried by a horse).</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shugaisho&quot; (an ancient encyclopedia), which is said to have been compiled around 1300, has an article that it is related to daho (a system of weight units, seen for the load carried by a horse).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>そこには、胡粉、白鑞（しろめ）、銅鉄、絲綿紅、蘇芳は大目を用い、金銀、水晶、青木香、ラピスラズリ、緑青、陶器は小目を用いる、とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the article says that &quot;ome&quot; (the weight standard that set 200 monme equal to 1 kin) was used for weighing powdered calcium carbonate, a lump of pewter, copper, and iron, and cotton cloth of crimson and sappan wood red, and it also says that &quot;kome&quot; (the weight standard smaller than the usual one) was used for weighing gold, silver, crystal, Radix Aristolochiae (a kind of herbal medicine), lapis lazuli, malachite, and pottery.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・一原文一訳文の例外対処。（注②）・・・原文1行目の「糸綿紅色、蘇芳色」の部分はよくわかりませんが、「紅色、蘇芳色の綿の生地」の意味に解しています。（注③）・・・「小目」の正確な読み、内容は不明ですが、「大目」との対比から「こめ」と読み、「通常より量を減らした重量基準」と解しています。　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the article says that ome (the weight standard that set 200 monme equal to 1 kin) was used for weighing powdered calcium carbonate, a lump of pewter, copper, and iron, floss silk red (絲綿紅), and sappan wood red, and it also says that kome (the weight standard smaller than the usual one) was used for weighing gold, silver, crystal, Radix Aristolochiae (a kind of herbal medicine), lapis lazuli, malachite, and pottery.</e>
<cmt>原文には 「糸綿紅色、蘇芳色」とありましたが、リンク先の単語のようです。ウェブで確認すると用語が「絲綿紅、蘇芳」となっており、本来はこちらの用語を使用していると思われますので、こちらを訳出し、原文修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the article says that ome (the weight standard that set 200 monme equal to 1 kin) was used for weighing powdered calcium carbonate, a lump of pewter, copper, and iron, floss silk red (絲綿紅), and sappan wood red, and it also says that kome (the weight standard smaller than the usual one) was used for weighing gold, silver, crystal, Radix Aristolochiae (a kind of herbal medicine), lapis lazuli, malachite, and pottery.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>そしてこれらにつき「6銖を1分、4分を1両、12両を1屯、16両を小1斤、3斤を大1斤」とする単位系が記述されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And the article also says that there existed a weight units&apos; system peculiar to those things, in which 6 shu were equalized with 1 bu, and 4 bu were equalized with 1 tael, and 12 taels were equalized with 1 ton, and 16 taels were equalized with 1 small kin, and 3 kin were equalized with 1 large kin.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And the article also says that there existed a weight units&apos; system peculiar to those things, in which &apos;6 shu were equivalent to 1 bu, 4 bu to 1 ryo, 12 ryo to 1 ton, 16 ryo to 1 small kin, and 3 kin to 1 large kin.</e>
<cmt>表現を変え、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And the article also says that there existed a weight units&apos; system peculiar to those things, in which &apos;6 shu were equivalent to 1 bu, 4 bu to 1 ryo, 12 ryo to 1 ton, 16 ryo to 1 small kin, and 3 kin to 1 large kin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="42">
<j>同書ではこれは俗説であるとしているが、唐の駄法にも全く同一の単位系が存在するという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The book says that the existence of the above-mentioned system was just a popular belief, while just the same system is said to have existed in daho of the Tang dynasty China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The book says that the existence of the previously-mentioned system was just a popular belief, while just the same system is said to have existed in daho of the Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>表記を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The book says that the existence of the previously-mentioned system was just a popular belief, while just the same system is said to have existed in daho of the Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>ここで言う1分とは1銭（匁）の1/10とは全く異なるものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, 1 bu is not a tenth of 1 sen (monme) at all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, 1 bu is not a 10th of 1 sen (monme) at all.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, 1 bu is not a 10th of 1 sen (monme) at all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>甲州金および江戸時代の通貨体系となった「両」および「分」は、これを基に定められた可能性が高く、薬種の量目も金銀の単位体系に準じたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Tael&quot; and &quot;bu,&quot; which were incorporated into Koshu-kin and the currency system of the Edo period, are highly likely to have been based on the above-mentioned system, and the weight units&apos; system of drugs was modeled after that of gold and silver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ryo&apos; and &apos;bu,&apos; which were incorporated into Koshu-kin and the currency system of the Edo period, were highly likely to have been based on the previously-mentioned system, and the weight units&apos; system of drugs was modeled after that of gold and silver.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ryo&apos; and &apos;bu,&apos; which were incorporated into Koshu-kin and the currency system of the Edo period, were highly likely to have been based on the previously-mentioned system, and the weight units&apos; system of drugs was modeled after that of gold and silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="45">
<j>中国では国民党政府の時代、1929年に度量衡法を公布し、「1担＝100斤、1斤＝16両、1両＝10銭、1銭＝10分」と規定し、1両は唐代に準じて37.301グラムと規定された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In China, the government of the Nationalist Party promulgated the Weights and Measures Act in A.D. 1929, and in the provision, 1 tan (dan in pinyin) was equalized with 100 kin, and 1 kin was equalized with 16 taels, and 1 tael was equalized with 10 sen, and 1 sen was equalized with 10 bu, and the weight of 1 tael was set at 37.301 grams, which was modeled after the standard in the Tang dynasty China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In China, the government of the Nationalist Party promulgated the Weights and Measures Act in 1929, and in the provision, &apos;1 tan (dan in pinyin) was equivalent to 100 kin, 1 kin to 16 ryo, 1 ryo to 10 sen, and 1 sen to 10 bu,&apos; and the weight of 1 ryo was set at 37.301 grams, modeled after the standard in the Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In China, the government of the Nationalist Party promulgated the Weights and Measures Act in 1929, and in the provision, &apos;1 tan (dan in pinyin) was equivalent to 100 kin, 1 kin to 16 ryo, 1 ryo to 10 sen, and 1 sen to 10 bu,&apos; and the weight of 1 ryo was set at 37.301 grams, modeled after the standard in the Tang Dynasty China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>現代では銭（日本の匁に相当）の10倍を両（市両）とし、両の10倍を斤（市斤）としている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Today, ten times the weight of 1 sen (or 1 monme in Japan) is equalized with 1 tael (or 1 shi liang in pinyin), and ten times the weight of 1 tael is equalized with 1 kin (or 1 shi jin in pinyin).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Today, 10 times the weight of 1 sen (or 1 monme in Japan) is equivalent to 1 ryo (or 1 liang in pinyin), and 10 times the weight of 1 ryo is equivalent to 1 kin (or 1 jin in pinyin).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Today, 10 times the weight of 1 sen (or 1 monme in Japan) is equivalent to 1 ryo (or 1 liang in pinyin), and 10 times the weight of 1 ryo is equivalent to 1 kin (or 1 jin in pinyin).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>ただし、10両を1斤としたのは中華人民共和国となって以降のことで、それまでは16両を1斤としていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it was only in the age of People&apos;s Republic of China that 10 tael was equalized with 1 kin, and until then, 16 taels had been equalized with 1 kin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But it was only in the age of People&apos;s Republic of China that 10 ryo was equalized with 1 kin, and until then, 16 ryo had been equalized with 1 kin.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But it was only in the age of People&apos;s Republic of China that 10 ryo was equalized with 1 kin, and until then, 16 ryo had been equalized with 1 kin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>1市両は50グラムである（市制 (単位系)も参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">1 shi liang is set equal to 50 grams (cf. the section of &quot;Chinese Traditional System of Measurement&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">1 liang is set equal to 50 grams (refer to the article of &quot;Chinese Traditional System of Measurement&quot;).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">1 liang is set equal to 50 grams (refer to the article of &quot;Chinese Traditional System of Measurement&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>1929年当時イギリス領だった香港では現在も1斤16両600グラム、1両37.5グラムである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in Hong Kong, which was under the British rule as of A.D. 1929, the weight of 1 kin and 16 taels are equally 600 grams even today, in other words, the weight of 1 tael is set at 37.5 grams.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in Hong Kong, which was under the British rule as of 1929, the weight of 1 kin and 16 ryo are equally 600 grams even today, in other words, the weight of 1 ryo is set at 37.5 grams.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in Hong Kong, which was under the British rule as of 1929, the weight of 1 kin and 16 ryo are equally 600 grams even today, in other words, the weight of 1 ryo is set at 37.5 grams.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="50">
<j>通貨単位としての両</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tael as a currency unit</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryo as a currency unit</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryo as a currency unit</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="51">
<j>金一両は元来一両（大宝律令では小両、延喜式以降は10匁）の質量の砂金という意味であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, 1 tael of gold meant 1 tael of gold dust, in other words, under the Taiho Code, 1 tael of gold meant 1 smaller tael of gold dust, and under the Engi Code and thereafter, 1 tael of gold meant 10 monme of gold dust.</e>
<cmt>（注）一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, 1 ryo of gold meant 1 ryo (or 1 small ryo under the Taiho Code, 10 monme under the Engi Code and thereafter) of gold dust.</e>
<cmt>表現、用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, 1 ryo of gold meant 1 ryo (or 1 small ryo under the Taiho Code, 10 monme under the Engi Code and thereafter) of gold dust.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>だが次第に質量と額面が乖離するようになり鎌倉時代には金一両は5匁、銀は4.3匁となり、鎌倉後期には金一両が4.5から4.8匁へと変化している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But as times went by, 1 tael of gold (or silver) became far apart from the original weight standard (= 10 monme) - for example, in the early and middle Kamakura period, 1 tael of gold meant 5 monme of gold, and 1 tael of silver meant 4.3 monme of silver, and in the later Kamukura period, 1 tael of gold meant 4.5 monme of gold, and then 4.8 monme of gold.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・一原文一訳文の例外対処。（注②）・・・「質量と額面が乖離するようになり」の意味ですが、まず「額面」は、ここでは「硬貨の表面に書かれた数字」という意味ではない、と思われます。(当時の硬貨は中国からの輸入銭が殆どで、それらには貨幣の名前だけが記されていたからです。）おそらくは前のセルからの流れで「金一両という数字の元来の意味」（＝10匁）というニュアンスで使っているのではないでしょうか。次に「質量」ですが、このセルの後半部分も併せ考えると、（度々変更された）「（金、あるいは銀の一両相当の）重さ」を指すのではないでしょうか。この両者が段々とかけ離れていった、という趣旨に解しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But as times went by, the weight of ryo became far apart from the value of ryo; in Kamakura period 1 ryo of gold was equivalent to 5 monme and that of silver 4.3, then in the late Kamakura period, 1 ryo of gold turned to be 4.8 monme from 4.5.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But as times went by, the weight of ryo became far apart from the value of ryo; in Kamakura period 1 ryo of gold was equivalent to 5 monme and that of silver 4.3, then in the late Kamakura period, 1 ryo of gold turned to be 4.8 monme from 4.5.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>文明 (日本)16年（1484年）、室町幕府により京目一両は4.5匁（約16.8グラム）と公定され、安土桃山時代すなわち元亀、天正年間には、京目一両は4匁4分 （約16.4グラム）と変更され、京目以外の基準は田舎目と呼ばれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In A.D. 1484, Muromachi bakufu officially established &quot;Kyome&quot; (the weight standard used in and around Kyoto, applied to the gold currency), in which 1 tael of gold became 4.5 monme (about 16.8 grams) of gold, and during the Azuchi-Momoyama period (or Genki and Tensho eras [A.D. 1570 - 1592]), Kyome was changed and 1 tael of gold the gold of 4 monme plus 4 bu (about 16.4 grams), and weight standards other than Kyome were called &quot;Inakame.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1484, Muromachi bakufu officially established 1 ryo of Kyome (the weight standard used in and around Kyoto, applied to the gold currency) was equivalent to 4.5 monme (about 16.8 grams) then in Azuchi Momoyama period (or Genki and Tensho eras [1570 to 1592]), 1 ryo of Kyome was changed to 4 monme and 4 bu (about 16.4 grams) and the weight standards other than Kyome were called Inakame.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1484, Muromachi bakufu officially established 1 ryo of Kyome (the weight standard used in and around Kyoto, applied to the gold currency) was equivalent to 4.5 monme (about 16.8 grams) then in Azuchi Momoyama period (or Genki and Tensho eras [1570 to 1592]), 1 ryo of Kyome was changed to 4 monme and 4 bu (about 16.4 grams) and the weight standards other than Kyome were called Inakame.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>甲州金は田舎目一両すなわち4匁（約14.9グラム）を基準としてつくられ、この通貨単位が小判の額面1両の基となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koshu-kin was based on Inakame, in which 1 tael of gold became 4 monme (about 14.9 grams), and the currency units of Koshu-kin became the foundation of koban whose face value was 1 tael.</e>
<cmt>（注）ここに言う「額面」は、文字通り、硬貨の表面に記載されていた金額を指すと解されます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koshu-kin was produced based on 1 ryo of Inakame, that is, 4 monme (about 14.9 grams), and the currency units became the basis for koban&apos;s face value, 1 ryo.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koshu-kin was produced based on 1 ryo of Inakame, that is, 4 monme (about 14.9 grams), and the currency units became the basis for koban&apos;s face value, 1 ryo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>甲州金の通貨単位は「1両＝4分＝16朱＝64糸目」という四進法の単位系であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The currency units of Koshu-kin had the quaternary numeral system, in which 1 tael, 4 bu, 16 shu, and 64 itome were equalized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The currency units of Koshu-kin had the quaternary numeral system, in which &apos;1 ryo, 4 bu, 16 shu, and 64 itome were equalized.&apos;</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The currency units of Koshu-kin had the quaternary numeral system, in which &apos;1 ryo, 4 bu, 16 shu, and 64 itome were equalized.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これが徳川幕府に継承され、江戸時代の通貨の基軸となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And Tokugawa bakugu adopted this system, and made it the foundation of the currency in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This system was succeeded to Tokugawa shogunate which was basis for the currency in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This system was succeeded to Tokugawa shogunate which was basis for the currency in the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="57">
<j>金拾両（じゅうりょう、44匁）は一裹（つつみ）あるいは一枚と呼ばれ、後に大判の量目（質量）の基準となり、銀拾両（43匁）は同じく一裹あるいは一枚と呼ばれ、後に丁銀の量目の基準となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">10 taels (or 44 monme) of gold was called 1 &quot;tsutsumi,&quot; or 1 &quot;mai,&quot; which later became the weight standard of &quot;oban&quot; (former Japanese large gold coin of oval shape), and similarly, 10 taels (or 43 monme) of silver was called 1 &quot;tsutsumi,&quot; or 1 &quot;mai,&quot; which later became the weight standard of chogin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">10 ryo (or 44 monme) of gold was called 1 tsutsumi, or 1 mai, which later became the weight standard of oban (former Japanese large gold coin of oval shape), and similarly, 10 ryo (or 43 monme) of silver was called 1 tsutsumi or 1 mai as well, which later became the weight standard of chogin.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">10 ryo (or 44 monme) of gold was called 1 tsutsumi, or 1 mai, which later became the weight standard of oban (former Japanese large gold coin of oval shape), and similarly, 10 ryo (or 43 monme) of silver was called 1 tsutsumi or 1 mai as well, which later became the weight standard of chogin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="58">
<j>慶長小判の質量は京目一両を基に複雑なやり取りの上決められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokugawa bakufu determined the weight of &quot;Keicho Koban&quot; (the Japanese gold coin of oval shape minted in the Keicho era [A.D. 1596 - 1615]), taking Kyome and other complicated factors into consideration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The weight of Keicho Koban (the Japanese gold coin of oval shape minted in the Keicho era [1596 to 1615]) was determined based on 1 ryo of Kyome by taking complicated factors into consideration.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The weight of Keicho Koban (the Japanese gold coin of oval shape minted in the Keicho era [1596 to 1615]) was determined based on 1 ryo of Kyome by taking complicated factors into consideration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>しかしその後、改鋳により含有率、質量とも劣る小判が発行される様になり、質量単位としての両と通貨単位としての両の乖離は拡大することなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After that, however, reminted koban became inferior to Keicho Koban both in percentage of gold and in weight, and so, tael as the weight unit became far apart from tael as the currency unit.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After that, however, reminted koban became inferior both in percentage of gold and in weight, then ryo as the weight unit became far apart from ryo as the currency unit.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After that, however, reminted koban became inferior both in percentage of gold and in weight, then ryo as the weight unit became far apart from ryo as the currency unit.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="60">
<j>「両替」という言葉は両替商で一両小判を秤量銀貨や銭貨に換（替）えたことに由来する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese word &quot;ryogae&quot; (exchange) came from changing (in Japanese, &quot;kae,&quot; or &quot;gae&quot;) 1 tael (1 &quot;ryo&quot; in Japanese) of koban at an exchange house into various other coins, such as hyoryo ginka and the copper coin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese word &apos;ryogae&apos; (exchange) came from changing (in Japanese, &apos;kae&apos; or &apos;gae&apos;) 1 ryo of koban at an exchange house into various other coins, such as hyoryo ginka and the copper coin.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese word &apos;ryogae&apos; (exchange) came from changing (in Japanese, &apos;kae&apos; or &apos;gae&apos;) 1 ryo of koban at an exchange house into various other coins, such as hyoryo ginka and the copper coin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また銀座で灰吹銀を引取り丁銀と交換した、いわゆる南鐐替（なんりょうがえ）が変化したものであるとする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another theory says it came from what is called &quot;nanryogae&quot; (the exchange of cupellated silver with chogin at a silver mintage site).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another theory says it came from what is called nanryogae that is the exchange of silver by cupellation with chogin at gin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of silver during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another theory says it came from what is called nanryogae that is the exchange of silver by cupellation with chogin at gin-za (an organization in charge of casting and appraising of silver during the Edo period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="62">
<j>天正年間の1両は米4石 (単位)、永楽通宝1貫文、鐚銭4貫文とほぼ等価であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Tensho era (A.D. 1573 - 1592), 1 tael of gold was almost equal to the following things in value, that is, 4 koku of rice, 1 &quot;kanmon&quot; (former Japanese currency unit) of &quot;Eiraku Tsuho&quot; (Yong Le Tong Bao in pinyin, a copper coin minted in Ming dynasty China), and 4 kanmon of bad copper coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Tensho era (1573 to 1592), 1 ryo was almost equal to the following things in value, that is, 4 koku of rice, 1 kanmon (former Japanese currency unit) of Eiraku Tsuho (Yong Le Tong Bao in pinyin, a copper coin minted in Ming dynasty China), and 4 kanmon of bad copper coins.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Tensho era (1573 to 1592), 1 ryo was almost equal to the following things in value, that is, 4 koku of rice, 1 kanmon (former Japanese currency unit) of Eiraku Tsuho (Yong Le Tong Bao in pinyin, a copper coin minted in Ming dynasty China), and 4 kanmon of bad copper coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="63">
<j>江戸時代、小判・丁銀・銭貨の為替レートは日々変動していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Edo period, the exchange rate among koban, chogin, and copper coin fluctuated day by day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Edo period, the exchange rate among koban, chogin, and copper coin fluctuated day by day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Edo period, the exchange rate among koban, chogin, and copper coin fluctuated day by day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>一方江戸幕府は御定相場として慶長14年（1609年）に、金1両は、銀50匁（約187グラム）、銭4貫文（4,000文 (通貨単位)）に等価と布告し、後の元禄13年（1700年）に、金1両は、銀60匁（約225グラム）、銭4貫文と改正した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Edo bakufu set the mint par of exchange, proclaiming in A.D. 1609 that 1 tael of gold should be equalized in value with 50 monme of silver, which weighed about 187 grams, and with 4 kanmon (= 4000 mon) of copper, and later in A.D. 1700, Edo bakufu proclaimed again that 1 tael of gold should be equalized with 60 monme of silver, which weighed about 225 grams, and with 4 kanmon of copper.</e>
<cmt>（注①）・・・一原文一訳文の例外対処。（注②）・・・「御定相場」とは「金貨・銀貨・銭貨の法定平価(mint par of exchange)」を意味します。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Edo bakufu set the mint par of exchange, proclaiming in 1609 that 1 ryo of gold was equalized to 50 monme of silver (about 187 grams), or to 4 kanmon (or 4000 mon) of copper, then later in 1700, proclaimed again that 1 ryo of gold became 60 monme of silver (about 225 grams), or 4 kanmon of copper.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, Edo bakufu set the mint par of exchange, proclaiming in 1609 that 1 ryo of gold was equalized to 50 monme of silver (about 187 grams), or to 4 kanmon (or 4000 mon) of copper, then later in 1700, proclaimed again that 1 ryo of gold became 60 monme of silver (about 225 grams), or 4 kanmon of copper.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>ただ幕府は相場が行き過ぎた場合のみ介入し、普段は市場経済に委ねていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But such interventions were implemented only when the exchange market overheated, and usually the exchange business was left into the hands of the market.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処　</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But such interventions of the bakufu were implemented only when the exchange market overheated, and usually the exchange business was left into the hands of the market.</e>
<cmt>補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But such interventions of the bakufu were implemented only when the exchange market overheated, and usually the exchange business was left into the hands of the market.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="66">
<j>また、貨幣吹替および飢饉の影響などによる変動はあったものの、米1石(当時の人一人の一年分の米消費量にほぼ相当する）の価格は1両前後であり、元禄年間から幕末の世情不安に至る前まで、ほぼこの前後の水準で推移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though some fluctuations were seen under the influence of reminting, famine, and others, the price of 1 koku rice (nearly equal to the amount consumed by a person per year) hovered around 1 tael from the Genroku era (A.D. 1688 - 1704) until just before the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate when the Japanese society became unstable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some fluctuations were seen under the influence of reminting, famine, and others, the price of 1 koku rice (nearly equal to the amount consumed by a person per year) was around 1 ryo from the Genroku era (1688 to 1704) until just before the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate when the Japanese society became unstable.</e>
<cmt>統一リストに合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some fluctuations were seen under the influence of reminting, famine, and others, the price of 1 koku rice (nearly equal to the amount consumed by a person per year) was around 1 ryo from the Genroku era (1688 to 1704) until just before the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate when the Japanese society became unstable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="67">
<j>1両が現在の貨幣価値に換算したらどの程度になるかは諸説ある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There exist various theories about how much currency value 1 tael has today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There exist various theories about how much currency value 1 ryo has today.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There exist various theories about how much currency value 1 ryo has today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>相対的な価値は慶長期と急激な下落を見た幕末期では概ね一桁以上は異なる上に、生活様式が現在と全く異なるため物価基準であるか賃金基準であるかにより、さらに物価も品目により大きく異なる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For, the value of 1 tael varied from time to time - for example, the value of 1 tael in the Keicho era was higher in a digit or more than that in the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate when currency value fell dramatically - and moreover, as life style in the Edo period was completely different from that today, the value of 1 tael varies greatly depending on what criterion (the price level or the wage level) is chosen - and depending on what items are chosen for the example of the price level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Relatively, the value in Keicho era was different in more than one digit from that in the end of Edo period by its sharp depreciation, moreover, since the life style was completely different from that of today, it varied greatly whether it was the standard of wage or commodity price which differed from items.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Relatively, the value in Keicho era was different in more than one digit from that in the end of Edo period by its sharp depreciation, moreover, since the life style was completely different from that of today, it varied greatly whether it was the standard of wage or commodity price which differed from items.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>日本銀行金融研究所貨幣博物館のサイトによると、元文期を基準として米価では1両＝約4万円、賃金で1両＝30～40万円、そば代金では1両＝12～13万円に相当するとの事である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the web site of Currency Museum at Bank of Japan&apos;s Institute for Monetary and Economic Studies, with the standards in Genbun era (A.D. 1736 - 1741), 1 tael of rice at that time roughly equals today&apos;s 40 thousand yen, and 1 tael of wage at that time roughly equals today&apos;s 300 thousand to 400 thousand yen, and 1 tael of buckwheat noodles at that time roughly equals today&apos;s 120 to 130 thousand yen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to the web site of Currency Museum at Bank of Japan&apos;s Institute for Monetary and Economic Studies, with the standards in Genbun era (1736 to 1741), 1 ryo is equivalent to about 40,000 yen in rice price, to 300,000 to 400,000 yen in wage, and to 120,000 to 130,000 yen in buckwheat noodles price.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to the web site of Currency Museum at Bank of Japan&apos;s Institute for Monetary and Economic Studies, with the standards in Genbun era (1736 to 1741), 1 ryo is equivalent to about 40,000 yen in rice price, to 300,000 to 400,000 yen in wage, and to 120,000 to 130,000 yen in buckwheat noodles price.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="70">
<j>一方、中国においては銀錠と呼ばれる銀の塊の重量を測り、それに基づいて貨幣としての価値を決定した（銀両/テール）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, in China, a mass of silver, called silver sycee, served as the currency, whose value depended on its weight, and its currency unit was tael.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, in China, a mass of silver, called silver sycee, served as the currency, whose value depended on its weight, and its currency unit was ryo (also known as ginryo or tael).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, in China, a mass of silver, called silver sycee, served as the currency, whose value depended on its weight, and its currency unit was ryo (also known as ginryo or tael).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>だが、銀錠は民間によって発行されていたため、時代や地域によって形状が異なっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shape of the silver sycee varied depending on the age and area it was minted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shape of the silver sycee varied depending on the age and area it was minted as it was issued by private sector.</e>
<cmt>訳漏れ。「民間によって発行されていたため」を補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shape of the silver sycee varied depending on the age and area it was minted as it was issued by private sector.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>これが完全に廃止されるのは1933年のことであった（廃両改元）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was only in A.D. 1933 that the use of this currency was ended completely, and this currency reform is called &quot;the abandonment of the old &apos;tael&apos; and its replacement with the &apos;yuan.&apos;&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was only in 1933 that the use of this currency was ended completely (the abandonment of the old &apos;ryo&apos; and its replacement with the &apos;yuan&apos;).</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was only in 1933 that the use of this currency was ended completely (the abandonment of the old &apos;ryo&apos; and its replacement with the &apos;yuan&apos;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ligar(id:12623), JAnDbot(id:66507), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), 銀色しっぽ(id:197919), Washn(id:145873), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), Nnh(id:474), 893(id:9349), 水野白楓(id:22811), Cprobot(id:97843), HI(id:72996), PATMAN(id:145791), Lupinoid(id:68), Oh!wenka(id:53059), Martin(id:6394), るがこむ(id:181), Rusk(id:9895), As6022014(id:214263), 海亀(id:48936), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Ws227(id:208643), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>