<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>応永の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oei Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oei Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oei Rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>応永の乱（おうえいのらん）は、室町時代の応永6年（1399年）に、守護大名の大内義弘が室町幕府に対して反乱を起こして堺市に篭城して滅ぼされた事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Oei rebellion (&quot;oei no ran&quot; in Japanese), which broke out in the sixth year of the Oei era (1399) during the Muromachi period, was a revolt against the Muromachi shogunate led by the shugo daimyo Yoshihiro OUCHI, in which he occupied the city of Sakai (modern-day Osaka) and was eventually brought to ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Oei rebellion (&quot;oei no ran&quot; in Japanese), which broke out in the sixth year of the Oei era (1399) during the Muromachi period, was a revolt against the Muromachi shogunate led by the shugo daimyo Yoshihiro OUCHI, in which he occupied the city of Sakai (modern-day Osaka) which was eventually brought to ruin.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation (space between words) corrected</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Oei rebellion, which broke out in the sixth year of the Oei era (1399) during the Muromachi period, was a revolt against the Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) led by the shugo daimyo (feudal lord) Yoshihiro OUCHI, in which he occupied the city of Sakai (modern-day Osaka) which was eventually brought to ruin.</e>
<cmt>(&quot;oei no ran&quot; in Japanese)削除shogunate→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)に訂正しました。(feudal lord)補足</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background leading up to the rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background leading up to the rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background leading up to the rebellion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>室町幕府の征夷大将軍は有力守護大名の連合に擁立されており、その権力は弱体だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shoguns of the Muromachi shogunate had been courting an alliance with the most powerful of the shugo daimyo, because the shogunate&apos;s power and authority was still weak.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shoguns of the Muromachi shogunate had been courting an alliance with the most powerful of the shugo daimyo, because the shogunate&apos;s power and authority was still weak.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shoguns of the Muromachi bakufu had been courting an alliance with the most powerful of the shugo daimyo, because the shogunate&apos;s power and authority was still weak.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufuとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>三代将軍足利義満はその強化を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, was bent on strengthening shogunal power.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The third Shogun, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, was bent on strengthening shogunal power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The third Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA, was bent on strengthening shogunal power.</e>
<cmt>,削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>花の御所を造営して権勢を示し、直轄軍である奉公衆を増強して将軍権力を強化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He displayed his influence by having the Flower palace rebuilt, and he increased the numbers in his hokoshu (guardian) force, essentially an army he personally commanded, thereby boosting shogunal authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He displayed his influence by having the Flower palace rebuilt, and he increased the numbers in his hokoshu (guardian) force, essentially an army he personally commanded, thereby boosting shogunal authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He displayed his influence by having the Flower palace rebuilt, and he increased the numbers in his hokoshu (guardian) force, essentially an army he personally commanded, thereby boosting shogunal authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>また、義満は有力守護大名の弱体化を図り、康暦元年（1379年）、細川氏と斯波氏の対立を利用して管領細川頼之を失脚させた（康暦の政変）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, Yoshimitsu was also bent on weakening the most powerful of the shugo daimyo, and in the first year of the Koryaku era (1379), he skillfully exploited the conflict between the HOSOKAWA and SHIBA families to engineer the overthrow of the powerful Kanrei, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA (in what became known as the Koryaku coup).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Yoshimitsu was also bent on weakening the most powerful of the shugo daimyo, and in the first year of the Koryaku era (1379), he skillfully exploited the conflict between the HOSOKAWA and SHIBA families to engineer the overthrow of the powerful Kanrei, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA (in what became known as the Koryaku coup).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Yoshimitsu was also bent on weakening the most powerful of the shugo daimyo, and in 1379, he skillfully exploited the conflict between the Hoskawa and Siba families to engineer the overthrow of the powerful Kanrei, Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA (in what became known as the Koryaku coup).</e>
<cmt>Hosokawa、Shibaに訂正しました。旧暦削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>康応元年（1389年）には土岐康行を挑発して挙兵に追い込み、これを下す（土岐康行の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first year of the Ko-o era (1389), Yoshimitsu deliberately provoked Yasuyuki TOKI into raising troops and then crushed him (this incident is referred to as Yasuyuki TOKI&apos;s rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first year of the Ko-o era (1389), Yoshimitsu deliberately provoked Yasuyuki TOKI into raising troops and then crushed him (this incident is referred to as Yasuyuki TOKI&apos;s rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1389, Yoshimitsu deliberately provoked Yasuyuki TOKI into raising troops and then crushed him (this incident is referred to as Yasuyuki TOKI&apos;s rebellion).</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>そして、明徳2年（1391年）、11カ国の守護となり『六分の一殿』と呼ばれた大勢力の山名氏の分裂をけしかけ、山名時熙と山名氏幸の兄弟を一族の山名氏清と山名満幸に討たせて没落させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, in the second year of the Meitoku era (1391), Yoshimitsu bent his efforts on creating divisions and strife within the very powerful Yamana clan, which held the role of shugo (de facto governor) for 11 provinces and were called &quot;the lords of one-sixth of all Japan&quot;; Yoshimitsu succeeded in bringing about the family&apos;s ruin when he had the brothers Tokihiro and Ujiyuki YAMANA strike against their own relatives, Ujikiyo and Mitsuyuki YAMANA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then, in the second year of the Meitoku era (1391), Yoshimitsu bent his efforts on creating divisions and strife within the very powerful Yamana clan, which held the role of shugo (de facto governor) for 11 provinces and were called &quot;the lords of one-sixth of all Japan&quot;; Yoshimitsu succeeded in bringing about the family&apos;s ruin when he had the brothers Tokihiro and Ujiyuki YAMANA strike against their own relatives, Ujikiyo and Mitsuyuki YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then, in 1391, Yoshimitsu bent his efforts on creating divisions and strife within the very powerful Yamana clan, which held the role of shugo (de facto governor) for 11 provinces and were called &quot;the lords of one-sixth of all Japan;&quot; Yoshimitsu succeeded in bringing about the family&apos;s ruin when he had the brothers Tokihiro and Ujiyuki YAMANA strike against their own relatives, Ujikiyo and Mitsuyuki YAMANA.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。&quot;の位置訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>さらに、氏清と満幸を挑発して挙兵に追い込み滅ぼした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What&apos;s more, he then provoked Ujikiyo and Mitsuyuki into raising an army and then destroyed them in turn.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What&apos;s more, he then provoked Ujikiyo and Mitsuyuki into raising an army and then destroyed them in turn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What&apos;s more, he then provoked Ujikiyo and Mitsuyuki into raising an army and then destroyed them in turn.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>山名氏は3カ国を残すのみとなってしまった（明徳の乱）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, the Yamana clan was left with just 3 provinces under their control (this episode became known as the Meitoku rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, the Yamana clan was left with just 3 provinces under their control (this episode became known as the Meitoku rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, the Yamana clan was left with just 3 provinces under their control (this episode became known as the Meitoku rebellion).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>守護大名大内氏</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi clan, of shugo daimyo rank</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi clan, of shugo daimyo rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi clan, of shugo daimyo rank</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>大内氏は百済聖明王の皇子琳聖太子を祖と称し、周防国に土着して武士となり、鎌倉幕府の御家人に連なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi clan claimed descent from crown prince Imson, son of King Seong of the Baejje kingdom in Korea; indigenous to Suo province, they became warriors in Japanese society, and reached the rank of gokenin (lower-ranking vassal) under the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi clan claimed descent from crown prince Imson, son of King Seong of the Baejje kingdom in Korea; indigenous to Suo province, they became warriors in Japanese society, and reached the rank of gokenin (lower-ranking vassal) under the Kamakura shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi clan claimed descent from Crown Prince Imson, son of King Seong of the Baejje kingdom in Korea; indigenous to Suo Province, they became warriors in Japanese society, and reached the rank of gokenin (lower-ranking vassal) under the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>Crown Princeに訂正しました。Province大文字にしました。shogunate→Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)では南朝 (日本)に付くが後に北朝 (日本)に帰順して九州の菊池氏らと戦い、幕府から周防国・長門国・石見国の守護職に任じられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Nanbokucho period, they initially sided with the Southern Court, but afterwards switched their allegiance to the Northern Court and fought against the Kikuchi clan and other Southern Court supporters in Kyushu; the Muromachi shogunate rewarded them by appointing them shugo (a position tantamount to military governor) over the provinces of Suo, Nagato, and Iwami.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Nanbokucho period, they initially sided with the Southern Court, but afterwards switched their allegiance to the Northern Court and fought against the Kikuchi clan and other Southern Court supporters in Kyushu; the Muromachi shogunate rewarded them by appointing them shugo (a position tantamount to military governor) over the provinces of Suo, Nagato, and Iwami.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), they initially sided with the Southern Court, but afterwards switched their allegiance to the Northern Court and fought against the Kikuchi clan and other Southern Court supporters in Kyushu; the Muromachi bakufu rewarded them by appointing them shugo (a position tantamount to military governor) over the provinces of Suo, Nagato, and Iwami.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu&quot;Nanbokucho period&quot; -&gt; &quot;period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan)&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="14">
<j>大内義弘は九州探題今川了俊に従軍して九州の南朝方と多年にわたり戦い、豊前国守護職を加えられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro OUCHI joined the army of the local military commissioner (tandai) in charge of Kyushu, Ryoshun IMAGAWA, and fought against the Southern Court forces in Kyushu for many years, and as a reward was made shugo over Buzen province (eastern Fukuoka today) as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro OUCHI joined the army of the local military commissioner (tandai) in charge of Kyushu, Ryoshun IMAGAWA, and fought against the Southern Court forces in Kyushu for many years, and as a reward was made shugo over Buzen province (eastern Fukuoka today) as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro OUCHI joined the army of the local military commissioner (tandai) in charge of Kyushu, Ryoshun IMAGAWA, and fought against the Southern Court forces in Kyushu for many years, and as a reward was made shugo over Buzen Province (eastern Fukuoka today) as well.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>明徳の乱では義弘は大いに奮戦して武功著しく、和泉国・紀伊国の守護職を与えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro fought very hard and valiantly during the Meitoku rebellion, achieving a remarkable number of military victories and exploits, so he was also made shugo of Izumi and Kii provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro fought very hard and valiantly during the Meitoku rebellion, achieving a remarkable number of military victories and exploits, so he was also made shugo of Izumi and Kii provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro fought very hard and valiantly during the Meitoku rebellion, achieving a remarkable number of military victories and exploits, so he was also made shugo of Izumi and Kii Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>また南北朝合一を斡旋して功績があり、足利氏一門の待遇を受けるまでになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro also had the merit of having helped mediate the unification of the two courts, and reached the point that he was treated with the same honors as a relative of the Ashikaga clan itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro also had the merit of having helped mediate the unification of the two courts, and reached the point that he was treated with the same honors as a relative of the Ashikaga clan itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro also had the merit of having helped mediate the unification of the two courts, and reached the point that he was treated with the same honors as a relative of the Ashikaga clan itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="17">
<j>義弘は本拠が大陸と近い地理を活かして李氏朝鮮との貿易を営み巨万の富を蓄えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Making the most of the close proximity of his seat of power to mainland Asia, Yoshihiro also worked to build trade relations between the OUCHI and the Joseon dynasty in Korea, thereby amassing a vast fortune.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Making the most of the close proximity of his seat of power to mainland Asia, Yoshihiro also worked to build trade relations between the OUCHI and the Joseon dynasty in Korea, thereby amassing a vast fortune.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Making the most of the close proximity of his seat of power to mainland Asia, Yoshihiro also worked to build trade relations between the Ouchi and the Joseon dynasty in Korea, thereby amassing a vast fortune.</e>
<cmt>Ouchiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>義弘は朝鮮の要請に従って倭寇の禁圧に努力して朝鮮国王から称賛されており、義弘は使者を朝鮮に送って祖先が百済皇子であることから、朝鮮国内の土地を賜ることを願うなど朝鮮との強いつながりを持っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He made an effort to suppress the wako (Japanese) pirates operating near Korea in compliance with a request by the Joseon king, receiving commendation and praise from the king for his success, and among other overtures, he even sent a messenger to the Joseon kingdom to express his hope that, because the OUCHI had a royal prince of Baekje as an ancestor, he be granted lands in Korea itself; all in all, Yoshihiro had forged a very strong relationship with the Joseon kingdom in Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He made an effort to suppress the wako (Japanese) pirates operating near Korea in compliance with a request by the Joseon king, receiving commendation and praise from the king for his success, and among other overtures, he even sent a messenger to the Joseon kingdom to express his hope that, because the OUCHI had a royal prince of Baekje as an ancestor, he be granted lands in Korea itself; all in all, Yoshihiro had forged a very strong relationship with the Joseon kingdom in Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He made an effort to suppress the wako (Japanese) pirates operating near Korea in compliance with a request by the Joseon king, receiving commendation and praise from the king for his success, and among other overtures, he even sent a messenger to the Joseon kingdom to express his hope that, because the Ouchi had a royal prince of Baekje as an ancestor, he be granted lands in Korea itself; all in all, Yoshihiro had forged a very strong relationship with the Joseon kingdom in Korea.</e>
<cmt>Ouchiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="19">
<j>周防・長門・石見・豊前・和泉・紀伊の6カ国の守護を兼ね貿易により財力を有する強大な大内氏の存在は将軍専制権力の確立を目指す義満の警戒を誘った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi clan had become so powerful--simultaneously shugo of six provinces, Suo, Nagato, Iwami, Buzen, Izumi, and Kii, and possessing great wealth thanks to their trade--that they were bound to put Yoshimitsu, who was aiming to establish a system of despotic rule by the Shogun, on his guard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi clan had become so powerful--simultaneously shugo of six provinces, Suo, Nagato, Iwami, Buzen, Izumi, and Kii, and possessing great wealth thanks to their trade--that they were bound to put Yoshimitsu, who was aiming to establish a system of despotic rule by the Shogun, on his guard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi clan had become so powerful - simultaneously shugo of six provinces, Suo, Nagato, Iwami, Buzen, Izumi, and Kii, and possessing great wealth thanks to their trade - that they were bound to put Yoshimitsu, who was aiming to establish a system of despotic rule by the Shogun, on his guard.</e>
<cmt>スペース補足。-削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>義満と義弘の対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Conflict begins between Yoshimitsu and Yoshihiro</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Conflict begins between Yoshimitsu and Yoshihiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Conflict begins between Yoshimitsu and Yoshihiro</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>応永元年（1394年）義満は将軍職を足利義持に譲り、太政大臣に昇る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first year of the Oei era (1394), Yoshimitsu passed the role and responsibilities of Shogun on to Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA and ascended to the rank of High Chancellor of the realm.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first year of the Oei era (1394), Yoshimitsu passed the role and responsibilities of Shogun on to Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA and ascended to the rank of High Chancellor of the realm.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1394, Yoshimitsu passed the role and responsibilities of Shogun on to Yoshimochi ASHIKAGA and ascended to Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state).</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。太政大臣→Daijo-daijin (Grand minister of state)にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>もちろん、実権は掌握したままだった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It goes without saying that Yoshimitsu retained his tight grip on real power, however.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It goes without saying that Yoshimitsu retained his tight grip on real power, however.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It goes without saying that Yoshimitsu retained his tight grip on real power, however.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>応永2年（1395年）には太政大臣を辞して出家し、道義と称した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1395, he resigned from his post as High Chancellor and took the tonsure, changing his name to &quot;Dogi&quot; (meaning &quot;the way of righteousness&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1395, he resigned from his post as High Chancellor and took the tonsure, changing his name to &quot;Dogi&quot; (meaning &quot;the way of righteousness&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Oei 2 (1395), he resigned from his post as Daijo-daijin and took the tonsure, changing his name to &quot;Dogi&quot; (meaning &quot;the way of righteousness&quot;).</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。Daijo-daijinとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>諸大名、公家はこぞってこれに追従して出家し、義弘もまた出家入道した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quite a few daimyo and court nobles sought to flatter him and so they all took the tonsure; Yoshihiro also took the tonsure and entered the Buddhist priesthood.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quite a few daimyo and court nobles sought to flatter him and so they all took the tonsure; Yoshihiro also took the tonsure and entered the Buddhist priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quite a few daimyo and court nobles sought to flatter him and so they all took the tonsure; Yoshihiro also took the tonsure and entered the Buddhist priesthood.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>この頃までは義満と義弘の関係は良好だったが、応永4年（1397年）、義満は金閣寺の造営を始め、諸大名に人数の供出を求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up until this point, the relationship between Yoshimitsu and Yoshihiro had been very cordial, but in Oei 4 (1397), Yoshimitsu began construction of Kinkakuji temple, and consequently wanted the various daimyo to contribute people towards this project.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up until this point, the relationship between Yoshimitsu and Yoshihiro had been very cordial, but in Oei 4 (1397), Yoshimitsu began construction of Kinkakuji temple, and consequently wanted the various daimyo to contribute people towards this project.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up until this point, the relationship between Yoshimitsu and Yoshihiro had been very cordial, but in 1397, Yoshimitsu began construction of Kinkaku-ji Temple, and consequently wanted the various daimyo to contribute people towards this project.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。-補足。Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>しかし、諸大名の中で義弘のみは「武士は弓矢をもって奉公するものである」とこれに従わず、義満の不興を買った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But among all the daimyo, Yoshihiro alone objected, saying &quot;Warriors should serve with their bows and arrows,&quot; and refused to comply, incurring Yoshimitsu&apos;s displeasure.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But among all the daimyo, Yoshihiro alone objected, saying &quot;Warriors should serve with their bows and arrows,&quot; and refused to comply, incurring Yoshimitsu&apos;s displeasure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But among all the daimyo, Yoshihiro alone objected, saying &apos;Warriors should serve with their bows and arrows,&apos; and refused to comply, incurring Yoshimitsu&apos;s displeasure.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="27">
<j>同年末、義弘は少弐氏討伐を命じられ、筑前国で戦い弟の大内満弘が討死するがその子への恩賞の沙汰が無く不満を募らせ、更に義満が裏で少弐氏と菊地氏に義弘を討つように命じていたとの噂があり憤慨していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of that same year (1397) Yoshihiro was ordered to strike down the Shoni clan, and began fighting with them in Chikuzen province only to lose his younger brother Mitsuhiro OUCHI in battle, and worse still, no order was given to reward the fallen Mitsuhiro&apos;s son for his father&apos;s sacrifice, only increasing Yoshihiro&apos;s discontent; but what provoked his indignation still more was the rumor that Yoshimitsu had secretly commanded the Shoni and Kikuchi clans to strike down Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the end of that same year (1397) Yoshihiro was ordered to strike down the Shoni clan, and began fighting with them in Chikuzen province only to lose his younger brother Mitsuhiro OUCHI in battle, and worse still, no order was given to reward the fallen Mitsuhiro&apos;s son for his father&apos;s sacrifice, only increasing Yoshihiro&apos;s discontent; but what provoked his indignation still more was the rumor that Yoshimitsu had secretly commanded the Shoni and Kikuchi clans to strike down Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the end of that same year (1397) Yoshihiro was ordered to strike down the Shoni clan, and began fighting with them in Chikuzen Province only to lose his younger brother Mitsuhiro OUCHI in battle, and worse still, no order was given to reward the fallen Mitsuhiro&apos;s son for his father&apos;s sacrifice, only increasing Yoshihiro&apos;s discontent; but what provoked his indignation still more was the rumor that Yoshimitsu had secretly commanded the Shoni and Kikuchi clans to strike down Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="28">
<j>応永5年（1398年）来日した朝鮮使節から義弘が莫大な進物を受け取っていたことを斯波義将らが「義弘は朝鮮から賄賂を受け取っている」と義満に讒言し、それが義弘に聞こえて激怒させている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When a Korean envoy arrived in Japan in Oei 5 (1398) and presented Yoshihiro with a vast number of gifts, Yoshimasa SHIBA slandered him to Yoshimitsu, saying &quot;Now Yoshihiro is accepting bribes from Korea,&quot; and when Yoshihiro heard of this slander he was furious.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When a Korean envoy arrived in Japan in Oei 5 (1398) and presented Yoshihiro with a vast number of gifts, Yoshimasa SHIBA slandered him to Yoshimitsu, saying &quot;Now Yoshihiro is accepting bribes from Korea,&quot; and when Yoshihiro heard of this slander he was furious.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When a Korean envoy arrived in Japan in 1398 and presented Yoshihiro with a vast number of gifts, Yoshimasa SHIBA slandered him to Yoshimitsu, saying &apos;Now Yoshihiro is accepting bribes from Korea,&apos; and when Yoshihiro heard of this slander he was furious.</e>
<cmt>旧暦削除しました。原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>大陸との貿易の推進を図る義満にとっても朝鮮と強いつながりを持つ義弘の存在は目障りなものになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Yoshimitsu, who was trying to plan how to proceed in forging trade links with mainland Asia, the existence of someone like Yoshihiro, possessing as he did such a strong bond with Korea, must have been quite obtrusive.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To Yoshimitsu, who was trying to plan how to proceed in forging trade links with mainland Asia, the existence of someone like Yoshihiro, possessing as he did such a strong bond with Korea, must have been quite obtrusive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To Yoshimitsu, who was trying to plan how to proceed in forging trade links with mainland Asia, the existence of someone like Yoshihiro, possessing as he did such a strong bond with Korea, must have been quite obtrusive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="30">
<j>義満は度々義弘へ上洛を催促するが、「和泉、紀伊の守護職が剥奪される」「上洛したところを誅殺される」との噂が流れ、義弘を不安にさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu repeatedly summoned Yoshihiro to the capital, but rumors had spread that &quot;You&apos;ll be deprived of your governorship (shugo) over Iwami and Kii&quot; or even &quot;You&apos;ll be assassinated on the road to Kyoto,&quot; and hearing these, Yoshihiro felt uneasy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu repeatedly summoned Yoshihiro to the capital, but rumors had spread that &quot;You&apos;ll be deprived of your governorship (shugo) over Iwami and Kii&quot; or even &quot;You&apos;ll be assassinated on the road to Kyoto,&quot; and hearing these, Yoshihiro felt uneasy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu repeatedly summoned Yoshihiro to the capital, but rumors had spread that &apos;You&apos;ll be deprived of your governorship (shugo) over Iwami and Kii&apos; or even &apos;You&apos;ll be assassinated on the road to Kyoto,&apos; and hearing these, Yoshihiro felt uneasy.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="31">
<j>追い込まれた義弘は関東公方足利満兼と密約を結んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Trapped into a corner, Yoshihiro made a secret alliance with Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, the kubo (official in charge) of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Trapped into a corner, Yoshihiro made a secret alliance with Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, the kubo (official in charge) of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Trapped into a corner, Yoshihiro made a secret alliance with Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, the kubo (official in charge) of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>この密約には義満によって一方的に九州探題を解任され失脚していた今川了俊が仲介役になっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This secret agreement was reached through the mediation of Ryoshun IMAGAWA, who had unilaterally lost his standing and been dismissed from his post as tandai (local military commissioner) of Kyushu thanks to Yoshimitsu&apos;s machinations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This secret agreement was reached through the mediation of Ryoshun IMAGAWA, who had unilaterally lost his standing and had been dismissed from his post as tandai (local military commissioner) of Kyushu thanks to Yoshimitsu&apos;s machinations.</e>
<cmt>&quot;had&quot; inserted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This secret agreement was reached through the mediation of Ryoshun IMAGAWA, who had unilaterally lost his standing and had been dismissed from his post as tandai (local military commissioner) of Kyushu thanks to Yoshimitsu&apos;s machinations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>さらに、先年の土岐康行の乱で没落していた美濃国の土岐詮直、明徳の乱で滅ぼされた山名氏清の嫡男山名時清、近江国の京極秀満（出雲国守護京極高詮の弟）や延暦寺・興福寺衆徒、楠氏・菊地氏ら後南朝方と連絡をとり挙兵をうながした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Yoshihiro contacted several potential allies, including Akinao TOKI of Mino province, who had been brought to ruin during Yasuyuki TOKI&apos;s rebellion a few years earlier, Tokikiyo YAMANA, eldest son and heir of Ujikiyo YAMANA, who had been destroyed during the Meitoku rebellion, Hidemitsu KYOGOKU (younger brother of Takanori KYOGOKU, the shugo of Izumo province), the warrior monks of Enryakuji and Kofukuji temples, and ex-Southern Court forces like the Kusunoki and Kikuchi clans, urging them to raise troops to oppose the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Yoshihiro contacted several potential allies, including Akinao TOKI of Mino province, who had been brought to ruin during Yasuyuki TOKI&apos;s rebellion a few years earlier, Tokikiyo YAMANA, eldest son and heir of Ujikiyo YAMANA, who had been destroyed during the Meitoku rebellion, Hidemitsu KYOGOKU (younger brother of Takanori KYOGOKU, the shugo of Izumo province), the warrior monks of Enryakuji and Kofukuji temples, and ex-Southern Court forces like the Kusunoki and Kikuchi clans, urging them to raise troops to oppose the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Yoshihiro contacted several potential allies, including Akinao TOKI of Mino Province, who had been brought to ruin during Yasuyuki TOKI&apos;s rebellion a few years earlier, Tokikiyo YAMANA, eldest son and heir of Ujikiyo YAMANA, who had been destroyed during the Meitoku rebellion, Hidemitsu KYOGOKU (younger brother of Takanori KYOGOKU, the shugo of Izumo Province), the warrior monks of Enryaku-ji and Kofuku-ji Temples, and Gonancho (Second Southern Court) forces like the Kusunoki and Kikuchi clans, urging them to raise troops to oppose the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。-補足。Templeとしました。ex-Southern Court→Gonancho (Second Southern Court)としました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="34">
<j>挙兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The two factions begin to raise armies</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The two factions begin to raise armies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The two factions begin to raise armies</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="35">
<j>応永6年（1399年）10月13日、大内義弘は軍勢を率いて分国和泉国堺の浦に着き、家臣の平井新左衛門を入洛させるが、自身は参洛しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the thirteenth day of the tenth month of Oei 6 (1399), Yoshihiro OUCHI led his forces out and arrived at the inlet of Sakai (Osaka) at the border of Izumi province, and sent his retainer Shinzaemon HIRAI on to the capital, but chose not to go himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the thirteenth day of the tenth month of Oei 6 (1399), Yoshihiro OUCHI led his forces out and arrived at the inlet of Sakai (Osaka) at the border of Izumi province, and sent his retainer Shinzaemon HIRAI on to the capital, but chose not to go himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 19, 1399 (Oei era), Yoshihiro OUCHI led his forces out and arrived at the inlet of Sakai (Osaka) at the border of Izumi Province, and sent his retainer Shinzaemon HIRAI on to the capital, but chose not to go himself.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦にしました。年号を（）に補足。Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>義満の元に大内義弘謀反の噂が伝わる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rumors had sprang up around Yoshimitsu that Yoshihiro was plotting to overthrow him.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rumors had sprang up around Yoshimitsu that Yoshihiro was plotting to overthrow him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rumors had sprang up around Yoshimitsu that Yoshihiro was plotting to overthrow him.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="37">
<j>義満は青蓮院門跡尊道法親王に仕える伊予法眼を堺へ送り上洛を促すが、義弘は「意に添わないことがある」と参洛に応じない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu sent the monk Hogen IYO, who worked for Sodoho, aristocratic chief priest (monzeki) of Shorenin temple and imperial prince, to Sakai to insist that Yoshihiro travel to the capital, but Yoshihiro refused to comply, saying &quot;There are some things that will not go according to your will.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu sent the monk Hogen IYO, who worked for Sodoho, aristocratic chief priest (monzeki) of Shorenin temple and imperial prince, to Sakai to insist that Yoshihiro travel to the capital, but Yoshihiro refused to comply, saying &quot;There are some things that will not go according to your will.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu sent the monk Hogen IYO, who worked for the Cloistered Imperial Prince Sondo of Shoren-in Monzeki (head priest of Shoren-in temple), to Sakai to insist that Yoshihiro travel to the capital, but Yoshihiro refused to comply, saying &apos;There are some things that will not go according to your will.&apos;</e>
<cmt>青蓮院門跡尊道法親王→the Cloistered Imperial Prince Sondo of Shoren-in Monzeki (head priest of Shoren-in temple)原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>10月27日、義満は禅宗の絶海中津を使者として堺へ派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the twenty-seventh of the tenth month, Yoshimitsu dispatched the Zen monk Chushin ZEKKAI as his envoy to Sakai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the twenty-seventh of the tenth month, Yoshimitsu dispatched the Zen monk Chushin ZEKKAI as his envoy to Sakai.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 3, Yoshimitsu dispatched the Zen monk Chushin ZEKKAI as his envoy to Sakai.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="39">
<j>義弘は一門重臣たちと対応を内談。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro met privately with his relatives and chief vassals to decide how to respond.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro met privately with his relatives and chief vassals to decide how to respond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro met privately with his relatives and chief vassals to decide how to respond.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>弟の大内弘茂は上意に従い参洛することを主張。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshige OUCHI, his younger brother, asserted that he obey the Yoshimitsu&apos;s will and go to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshige OUCHI, his younger brother, asserted that he obey Yoshimitsu&apos;s will and go to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshige OUCHI, his younger brother, asserted that he obey Yoshimitsu&apos;s will and go to Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>平井備前入道も恭順して嘆願すべきであり、さもなくば朝敵となり御家滅亡になると義弘を説得した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bizennyudo HIRAI also argued along the same lines, trying to persuade Yoshihiro that he should re-swear his allegiance and appeal to the Shogun&apos;s good graces, for if he did not he would be declared an enemy of the Court and his whole family would be destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bizennyudo HIRAI also argued along the same lines, trying to persuade Yoshihiro that he should re-swear his allegiance and appeal to the Shogun&apos;s good graces, for if he did not he would be declared an enemy of the Court and his whole family would be destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bizen Nyudo HIRAI also argued along the same lines, trying to persuade Yoshihiro that he should re-swear his allegiance and appeal to the Shogun&apos;s good graces, for if he did not he would be declared an enemy of the Imperial Court and his whole family would be destroyed.</e>
<cmt>Nyudo としました。スペース補足。Imperial補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>一方、杉豊後入道は将軍は当家を滅ぼそうとしていると抗戦を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gonyudo SUGITOYO, on the other hand, argued that the Shogun was already trying to destroy the Ouchi family, and thus advocated armed resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gonyudo SUGITOYO, on the other hand, argued that the Shogun was already trying to destroy the Ouchi family, and thus advocated armed resistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bungo Nyudo SUGI, on the other hand, argued that the Shogun was already trying to destroy the Ouchi family, and thus advocated armed resistance.</e>
<cmt>Gonyudo SUGITOYO→Bungo Nyudo SUGI</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="43">
<j>義弘は絶海中津と面談。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro met with Chushin ZEKKAI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro met with Chushin ZEKKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro met with Chushin ZEKKAI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>絶海中津は将軍家が義弘を滅ぼそうとしているとの噂を信じず、上洛して将軍家に謝罪すべきことを説く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushin ZEKKAI counseled him not to believe rumors that the shogunal family was bent on destroying Yoshihiro, and that he should make his way to the capital and apologize to the Ashikaga family for not heeding the earlier summons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushin ZEKKAI counseled him not to believe rumors that the shogunal family was bent on destroying Yoshihiro, and that he should make his way to the capital and apologize to the Ashikaga family for not heeding the earlier summons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushin ZEKKAI counseled him not to believe rumors that the shogunal family was bent on destroying Yoshihiro, and that he should make his way to the capital and apologize to the Ashikaga family for not heeding the earlier summons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>義弘は将軍家からの御恩の深さを感謝しながらも、今川了俊に従軍しての九州での戦い、明徳の乱、南北朝合一、少弐氏退治での自らの功績を述べ、それにも関わらず将軍家は和泉国と紀伊国を取り上げようとし、また先年の少弐氏との戦いで討ち死にした弟の満弘の子への恩賞がない不満を述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro said that he remained grateful for the deep favor the shogunal family had bestowed on him, but also listed his own accomplishments in the battles in Kyushu joining forces with Ryoshun IMAGAWA, in the Meitoku rebellion, in unifying the Southern and Northern courts, and in the annihilation of the Shoni family before pointing out his dissatisfaction that despite these deeds, the Ashikaga family was trying to remove Izumi and Kii provinces from his governance, and the fact that his nephew, the son of his younger brother Mitsuhiro--who had died in battle during the recent campaign against the Shoni family--had received no reward for his father&apos;s service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro said that he remained grateful for the deep favor the shogunal family had bestowed on him, but also listed his own accomplishments in the battles in Kyushu joining forces with Ryoshun IMAGAWA, in the Meitoku rebellion, in unifying the Southern and Northern courts, and in the annihilation of the Shoni family before pointing out his dissatisfaction that despite these deeds, the Ashikaga family was trying to remove Izumi and Kii provinces from his governance, and the fact that his nephew, the son of his younger brother Mitsuhiro--who had died in battle during the recent campaign against the Shoni family--had received no reward for his father&apos;s service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro said that he remained grateful for the deep favor the shogunal family had bestowed on him, but also listed his own accomplishments in the battles in Kyushu joining forces with Ryoshun IMAGAWA, in the Meitoku rebellion, in unifying the Southern and Northern Courts, and in the annihilation of the Shoni family before pointing out his dissatisfaction that despite these deeds, the Ashikaga family was trying to remove Izumi and Kii Provinces from his governance, and the fact that his nephew, the son of his younger brother Mitsuhiro - who had died in battle during the recent campaign against the Shoni family - had received no reward for his father&apos;s service.</e>
<cmt>Court大文字にしました。Province大文字にしました。-削除、スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>絶海中津は義弘の忠節は隠れ無きものであり、世の噂を信じるべきではない、また満弘の子への恩賞がないのは上洛しないために行賞できないからだと重ねて上洛を促した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushin ZEKKAI responded by saying that he saw Yoshihiro&apos;s loyalty was beyond question, and that one cannot trust the rumors the world produced; he also reiterated his advice to go the capital, claiming that the reason no reward had been conferred on Mitsuhiro&apos;s son was that Yoshihiro had not obeyed the summons to Kyoto in the first place.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushin ZEKKAI responded by saying that he saw that Yoshihiro&apos;s loyalty was beyond question, and that one cannot trust the rumors the world produces he also reiterated his advice to go the capital, claiming that the reason no reward had been conferred on Mitsuhiro&apos;s son was that Yoshihiro had not obeyed the summons to Kyoto in the first place.</e>
<cmt>grammar, &quot;produces&quot; &quot;s&quot; placed on the end</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushin ZEKKAI responded by saying that he saw that Yoshihiro&apos;s loyalty was beyond question, and that one cannot trust the rumors the world produces he also reiterated his advice to go the capital, claiming that the reason no reward had been conferred on Mitsuhiro&apos;s son was that Yoshihiro had not obeyed the summons to Kyoto in the first place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>これに対して、義弘は政道を諌めるため関東（関東公方足利満兼）と同心しており、ここで上洛すれば約束を違える事になる、来月2日に関東とともに上洛すると言い放った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response, Yoshihiro declared that he had formed an alliance with the Kanto (the kubo, or shogunal representative of Kanto, Mitsukane ASHIKAGA) to remonstrate with the shogunate&apos;s policies, and to go now to Kyoto would violate the terms of that alliance, but said he would be marching on Kyoto together with Mitsukane on the second day of the following month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response, Yoshihiro declared that he had formed an alliance with the Kanto (the kubo, or shogunal representative of Kanto, Mitsukane ASHIKAGA) to remonstrate with the shogunate&apos;s policies, and to go now to Kyoto would violate the terms of that alliance, but said he would be marching on Kyoto together with Mitsukane on the second day of the following month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response, Yoshihiro declared that he had formed an alliance with the Kanto (the kubo, or shogunal representative of Kanto, Mitsukane ASHIKAGA) to remonstrate with the shogunate&apos;s policies, and to go now to Kyoto would violate the terms of that alliance, but said he would be marching on Kyoto together with Mitsukane on the second day of the following month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>事実上の宣戦布告である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was in reality a declaration of war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was in reality a declaration of war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was in reality a declaration of war.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>絶海中津は説得を諦めて帰京する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chushin ZEKKAI gave up his attempts to persuade Yoshihiro otherwise and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chushin ZEKKAI gave up his attempts to persuade Yoshihiro otherwise and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chushin ZEKKAI gave up his attempts to persuade Yoshihiro otherwise and returned to the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="50">
<j>絶海中津からの報告を受けた義満は義弘討伐を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu, after hearing Chushin ZEKKAI&apos;s report, issued an order to hunt down and destroy Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu, after hearing Chushin ZEKKAI&apos;s report, issued an order to hunt down and destroy Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu, after hearing Chushin ZEKKAI&apos;s report, issued an order to hunt down and destroy Yoshihiro.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>ただちに細川頼元、京極高詮、赤松義則の先発隊6000余騎が淀から和泉国へ発向する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The vanguard of the army, more than 6000 riders led by Yorimoto HOSOKAWA, Takanori KYOGOKU, and Yoshinori AKAMATSU, immediately rode out from Yodo towards Izumi province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The vanguard of the army, more than 6000 riders led by Yorimoto HOSOKAWA, Takanori KYOGOKU, and Yoshinori AKAMATSU, immediately rode out from Yodo towards Izumi province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The vanguard of the army, more than 6000 riders led by Yorimoto HOSOKAWA, Takanori KYOGOKU, and Yoshinori AKAMATSU, immediately rode out from Yodo towards Izumi Province.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>11月8日、義満は馬廻2000余騎を率いて東寺に陣を構えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the eighth day of the eleventh month, Yoshimitsu set up camp at Toji temple, with more than 2000 horsemen under his command.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the eighth day of the eleventh month, Yoshimitsu set up camp at Toji temple, with more than 2000 horsemen under his command.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 13, Yoshimitsu set up camp at To-ji Temple, with more than 2000 horsemen under his command.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦にしました。-補足。Temple大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>11月14日、義満は八幡まで進み、管領畠山基国と前管領斯波義将が率いる主力3万騎が和泉国へ発向した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By the fourteenth, Yoshimitsu had advanced as far as Hachiman (shrine), where he met up with the main force of 30,000 riders, led by the kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA and former kanrei Yoshimasa SHIBA, and then they all proceeded towards Izumi province together.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the fourteenth, Yoshimitsu had advanced as far as Hachiman (shrine), where he met up with the main force of 30,000 riders, led by the kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA and former kanrei Yoshimasa SHIBA, and then they all proceeded towards Izumi province together.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By December 19, Yoshimitsu had advanced as far as Hachiman, where he met up with the main force of 30,000 riders, led by the kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA and former kanrei Yoshimasa SHIBA, and then they all proceeded towards Izumi Province together.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦にしました。 (shrine)削除Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="54">
<j>義弘は評定を開き作戦を談じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro called a meeting with his advisors where they discussed military strategy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro called a meeting with his advisors where they discussed military strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro called a meeting with his advisors where they discussed military strategy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>弟の弘茂は城を構えて和泉国、紀伊国に割拠して持ちこたえる策を提案。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshige, his younger brother, proposed that they fortify their castles and hold their ground, defending Izumi and Kii provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshige, his younger brother, proposed that they fortify their castles and hold their ground, defending Izumi and Kii provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshige, his younger brother, proposed that they fortify their castles and hold their ground, defending Izumi and Kii Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>杉豊後入道は機制を制して舟で尼崎市に上陸して八幡の陣を突き決戦することを主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gonyudo SUGITOYO advocated that they seize the opportunity they had been given and travel by ship to Amazaka city, where they could launch a surprise attack against the army at Hachiman and fight one great battle where all would be decided.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gonyudo SUGITOYO advocated that they seize the opportunity they had been given and travel by ship to Amazaka city, where they could launch a surprise attack against the army at Hachiman and fight one great battle where all would be decided.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bungo Nyudo SUGI advocated that they seize the opportunity they had been given and travel by ship to Amagasaki City, where they could launch a surprise attack against the army at Hachiman and fight one great battle where all would be decided.</e>
<cmt>Gonyudo SUGITOYO→Bungo Nyudo SUGIAmagasaki Cityに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>かねてから謀反を諌めていた平井備前入道は出戦は無益であるとし篭城策を説いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bizennyudo HIRAI, who had been warning against any effort to overthrow the shogunate for some time now, asserted that any offensive strike was futile, and proposed that they hole up in their castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bizennyudo HIRAI, who had been warning against any effort to overthrow the shogunate for some time now, asserted that any offensive strike was futile, and proposed that they hole up in their castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bizen Nyudo HIRAI, who had been warning against any effort to overthrow the shogunate for some time now, asserted that any offensive strike was futile, and proposed that they hole up in their castles.</e>
<cmt>Nyudo としました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>義弘は篭城策を採った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro adopted Bizennyudo&apos;s defensive strategy of entrenching themselves in their castles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro adopted Bizennyudo&apos;s defensive strategy of entrenching themselves in their castles.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro adopted Bizen Nyudo&apos;s defensive strategy of entrenching themselves in their castles.</e>
<cmt>Nyudo としました。スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="59">
<j>義弘は材木を集め、井楼48と矢倉1000余を建てて堺に方18町の強固な城を築き、「たとえ百万騎の軍勢でも破ることはできない」と豪語した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro collected lumber and erected 48 major towers and more than 1000 watchtowers, creating 18 castles to serve as strongpoints around Sakai, and began boasting that &quot;the enemy could not defeat us here even if they brought one million men against us.&quot;</e>
<cmt>井楼、矢倉ともに「材木でできた警備用の塔」であり、大きさの差か、または同義で使われることもあるようです。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro collected lumber and erected 48 major towers and more than 1000 watchtowers, creating 18 castles to serve as strongpoints around Sakai, and began boasting that &quot;the enemy could not defeat us here even if they brought one million men against us.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro collected lumber and erected 48 major towers and more than 1000 watchtowers, creating a castle of approx. 1.96 square meters to serve as strong points around Sakai, and began boasting that &apos;the enemy could not defeat us here even if they brought one million men against us.&apos;</e>
<cmt>方18町→approx. 1.96 sq. metersスペース補足原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>一方で、義弘は討死を覚悟して、かねて帰依していた僧を招き自らの葬儀を執り行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Yoshihiro did make preparations against the likelihood of his death in battle, even going so far as to invite the monk who had previously given him the tonsure to come and perform his funeral service.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Yoshihiro did make preparations against the likelihood of his death in battle, even going so far as to invite the monk who had previously given him the tonsure to come and perform his funeral service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Yoshihiro did make preparations against the likelihood of his death in battle, even going so far as to invite the monk who had previously given him the tonsure to come and perform his funeral service.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また、周防国に残した母に形見と遺言を送り、弟の大内盛見には分国を固く守るよう申し送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also sent both his will and a remembrance of himself to his mother, whom he had left at home in Suo province, and sent a message to his younger brother Morimi OUCHI to guard the provinces under their control well and fiercely.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also sent both his will and a remembrance of himself to his mother, whom he had left at home in Suo province, and sent a message to his younger brother Morimi OUCHI to guard the provinces under their control well and fiercely.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also sent both his will and a remembrance of himself to his mother, whom he had left at home in Suo Province, and sent a message to his younger brother Morimi OUCHI to guard the provinces under their control well and fiercely.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>義弘に従う者たちもみな討死を覚悟した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">All of Yoshihiro&apos;s followers had also prepared to die in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">All of Yoshihiro&apos;s followers had also prepared to die in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">All of Yoshihiro&apos;s followers had also prepared to die in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="63">
<j>城攻め</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The assault on the fortifications begins</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The assault on the fortifications begins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The assault on the fortifications begins</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>幕府軍3万余騎は堺を包囲し、海上は四国・淡路島の海賊100余艘が封鎖した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunal army of about 30,000 horsemen surrounded Sakai and laid siege to it, while at sea, pirates from Shikoku and Awaji island blockaded Sakai&apos;s harbor with a fleet of more than 100 ships.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunal army of about 30,000 horsemen surrounded Sakai and laid siege to it, while at sea, pirates from Shikoku and Awaji island blockaded Sakai&apos;s harbor with a fleet of more than 100 ships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunal army of about 30,000 horsemen surrounded Sakai and laid siege to it, while at sea, pirates from Shikoku and Awaji Island blockaded Sakai&apos;s harbor with a fleet of more than 100 ships.</e>
<cmt>Islandとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>義弘は森口城で戦っていた杉九郎と鴨山に配備した杉備中守を立退かせて堺に兵力を集中させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro gathered all available troops at Sakai, and had both Kuro SUGI, who was fighting at Moriguchi castle, and Bicchushu (protector of Bicchu) SUGI, who was deployed at Kamoyama, fall back and join him there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro gathered all available troops at Sakai, and had both Kuro SUGI, who was fighting at Moriguchi castle, and Bicchushu (protector of Bicchu) SUGI, who was deployed at Kamoyama, fall back and join him there.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro gathered all available troops at Sakai, and had both Kuro SUGI, who was fighting at Moriguchi Castle, and Bicchu no kami (the governor of Bicchu Province) SUGI, who was deployed at Kamoyama, fall back and join him there.</e>
<cmt>Castleとしました。Bicchu no kami (the governor of Bicchu Province)に訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>義弘の軍勢は5000余騎。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro&apos;s army numbered about 5000 men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro&apos;s army numbered about 5000 men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro&apos;s army numbered about 5000 men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="67">
<j>11月29日、幕府軍が一斉に鬨の声をあげて総攻撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the twenty-ninth day of the eleventh month, the shogunal army all simultaneously let out a battle cry and began a general frontal assault.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the twenty-ninth day of the eleventh month, the shogunal army all simultaneously let out a battle cry and began a general frontal assault.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 3, 1400, the shogunal army all simultaneously let out a battle cry and began a general frontal assault.</e>
<cmt>旧暦を新暦にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>大内勢はこれに応じて、矢倉からさんざんに射まくった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ouchi forces fought back, raining down arrows on the enemy from their watchtowers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ouchi forces fought back, raining arrows down on the enemy from their watchtowers.</e>
<cmt>word order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ouchi forces fought back, raining arrows down on the enemy from their watchtowers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>管領畠山基国の軍勢2000余騎が北側の一の木戸、二の木戸を打ち破り、三の木戸まで攻め寄せ700人余が死傷する激戦を展開する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the north, the kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA&apos;s force of 2000 men broke through Ichinoki and Ninoki gates, pushing their assault as far as Sannoki gate in what developed into a bitterly fought battle that left more than 700 dead or wounded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the north, kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA&apos;s force of 2000 men broke through Ichinoki and Ninoki gates, pushing their assault as far as Sannoki gate in what developed into a bitterly fought battle that left more than 700 dead or wounded.</e>
<cmt>deleted &quot;the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the north, kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA&apos;s force of 2000 men broke through Ichinoki and Ninoki gates, pushing their assault as far as Sannoki gate in what developed into a bitterly fought battle that left more than 700 dead or wounded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="70">
<j>畠山勢に代って山名時熈の軍勢500余騎が攻め寄せ、城内からは杉豊後ら500余騎が出撃して戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokihiro YAMANA&apos;s 500-man force replaced the Hatakeyama army and pressed the attack, while SUGITOYO and others led a sortie out from the castle to meet them in battle with 500 men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokihiro YAMANA&apos;s 500-man force replaced the Hatakeyama army and pressed the attack, while SUGITOYO and others led a sortie out from the castle to meet them in battle with 500 men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokihiro YAMANA&apos;s 500-man force replaced the Hatakeyama army and pressed the attack, while Bungo Nyudo SUGI and others led a sortie out from the castle to meet them in battle with 500 men.</e>
<cmt>Bungo Nyudo SUGIに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>義弘も200余騎を率いてこれに合力する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro also led 200 riders over to join the fight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro also led 200 riders over to join the fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro also led 200 riders over to join the fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>伊勢国国司の北畠俊康の軍勢300余騎が山名勢に加勢、子息の少将が討死する程激しく戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshiyasu KITABATAKE, the provincial governor of Iyo, came to reinforce the Yamana army with about 300 men, and was caught in such fierce fighting that Toshiyasu&apos;s own son, a major general, was killed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshiyasu KITABATAKE, the provincial governor of Iyo, came to reinforce the Yamana army with about 300 men, and was caught in such fierce fighting that Toshiyasu&apos;s own son, a major general, was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshiyasu KITABATAKE, the provincial governor of Iyo, came to reinforce the Yamana army with about 300 men, and was caught in such fierce fighting that Toshiyasu&apos;s own son, a major general, was killed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="73">
<j>細川氏、赤松氏の5000余騎は南側から、六角氏、京極氏は東側から攻め寄せる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The armies of the Hosokawa and Akamatsu clans, numbering about 5000, attacked from the south of Sakai, while the Rokkaku and Kyogoku clans pressed the assault from the east.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The armies of the Hosokawa and Akamatsu clans, numbering about 5000, attacked from the south of Sakai, while the Rokkaku and Kyogoku clans pressed the assault from the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The armies of the Hosokawa and Akamatsu clans, numbering about 5000, attacked from the south of Sakai, while the Rokkaku and Kyogoku clans pressed the assault from the east.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>戦いは夜まで続き、無数の死傷者が出た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle continued into the night, with too many killed and wounded to count.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle continued into the night, with too many killed and wounded to count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle continued into the night, with too many killed and wounded to count.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="75">
<j>反義満派の蜂起</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anti-Yoshimitsu faction rises up in revolt</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anti-Yoshimitsu faction rises up in revolt</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anti-Yoshimitsu faction rises up in revolt</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>その頃、義弘に同心した土岐詮直が挙兵して尾張国へ討ち入り、美濃国へ侵攻した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, Akinau TOKI, who had formed an alliance with Yoshihiro, raised an army and invaded Owari province, penetrating as far as Mino province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, Akinau TOKI, who had formed an alliance with Yoshihiro, raised an army and invaded Owari province, penetrating as far as Mino province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, Akinau TOKI, who had formed an alliance with Yoshihiro, raised an army and invaded Owari Province, penetrating as far as Mino Province.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>美濃守護の土岐頼益は大内攻めの陣にいたが、直ちに美濃へ引きかえして詮直を打ち破る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that point, the shugo of Mino, Yorimasu TOKI, was at the camp of the army fighting against the Ouchi forces, but immediately returned to Mino and smashed Akinao&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point, the shugo of Mino, Yorimasu TOKI, was at the camp of the army fighting against Ouchi&apos;s forces, but immediately returned to Mino and smashed Akinao&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point, the shugo of Mino, Yorimasu TOKI, was at the camp of the army fighting against Ouchi&apos;s forces, but immediately returned to Mino and smashed Akinao&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="27">
<sen id="78">
<j>山名氏清の嫡男時清も義弘に同心して丹波国へ討ち入り、京都市へ侵入して火を放ち、300余騎で八幡の幕府軍本陣を目指して突入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ujikiyo YAMANA&apos;s eldest son and heir, Tokikiyo, had also allied himself with Yoshihiro, and attacked into Tanba province, invading the capital (Kyoto) and setting fires there before targeting the shogunal army camped at Hachiman and raiding it with three hundred men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ujikiyo YAMANA&apos;s eldest son and heir, Tokikiyo, had also allied himself with Yoshihiro, and attacked into Tanba province, invading the capital (Kyoto) and setting fires there before targeting the shogunal army camped at Hachiman and raiding it with three hundred men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ujikiyo YAMANA&apos;s eldest son and heir, Tokikiyo, had also allied himself with Yoshihiro, and attacked into Tanba Province, invading the capital (Kyoto) and setting fires there before targeting the shogunal army camped at Hachiman and raiding it with 300 men.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>時清の軍勢は幕府軍の陣を次々に打ち破るが力尽きて退却した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokikiyo&apos;s force smashed the camps of the shogunal army one after the other, but exhausted their strength and were forced to withdraw.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokikiyo&apos;s force smashed the camps of the shogunal army one after the other, but exhausted their strength and were forced to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokikiyo&apos;s force smashed the camps of the shogunal army one after the other, but exhausted their strength and were forced to withdraw.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="28">
<sen id="80">
<j>京極秀満は近江国で挙兵して、京への侵攻を図った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidemitsu KYOGOKU raised an army in Omi and planned to invade towards the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidemitsu KYOGOKU raised an army in Omi and planned to invade towards the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidemitsu KYOGOKU raised an army in Omi Province and planned to invade towards the capital.</e>
<cmt>Province補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>園城寺の衆徒500人が勢多で勢多橋を焼いてこれを待ち受ける。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">500 warrior-monks from Onjoji temple burned the Setabashi bridge at Seta and waited to meet Hidemitsu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">500 warrior-monks from Onjoji temple burned the Setabashi bridge at Seta and waited to meet Hidemitsu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">500 warrior-monks from Onjo-ji Temple burned the Setabashi bridge at Seta and waited to meet Hidemitsu&apos;s army.</e>
<cmt>Temple大文字にしました。-補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>秀満はやむなく森山に陣を構えて対峙した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hidemitsu, out of options, drew up battle lines in Moriyama and prepared for the coming battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hidemitsu, out of options, drew up battle lines in Moriyama and prepared for the coming battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hidemitsu, out of options, drew up battle lines in Moriyama and prepared for the coming battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>大内攻めに加わっていた京極勢1000余騎が引き返して森山へ迫ると、秀満は土岐詮直と合流すべく美濃国へ向かうが途中で土一揆の蜂起に遭って潰走、秀満は主従2騎で落ちて行方知れずになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When the Kyogoku force of 1000 men, who had joined the attack against the Ouchi, retraced their steps and neared Moriyama, Hidemitsu, trying to join up with Akinau TOKI, headed for Mino province, but on the way he became caught in the middle of a farmers&apos; uprising and was routed; Hidemitsu slipped away with just one close retainer and disappeared.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Kyogoku force of 1000 men, who had joined the attack against the Ouchi, retraced their steps and neared Moriyama, Hidemitsu, trying to join up with Akinau TOKI, headed for Mino province, but on the way he became caught in the middle of a farmers&apos; uprising and was routed; Hidemitsu slipped away with just one close retainer and disappeared.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Kyogoku force of 1000 men, who had joined the attack against the Ouchi, retraced their steps and neared Moriyama, Hidemitsu, trying to join up with Akinau TOKI, headed for Mino Province, but on the way he became caught in the middle of a farmers&apos; uprising and was routed; Hidemitsu slipped away with just one close retainer and disappeared.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>なお、秀満の官職が金吾（左衛門尉）であったことから、この挙兵だけを指して金吾騒動（きんごそうどう）とも称する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, because Hidemitsu&apos;s official government post was &quot;kingo&quot; (saemon no jo under the ritsuryo system), when referring to just his raising of troops it is also called the Kingo Disturbance (kingo sodo in Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, because Hidemitsu&apos;s official government post was &quot;kingo&quot; (saemon no jo under the ritsuryo system), when referring to just his raising of troops it is also called the Kingo Disturbance (kingo sodo in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, because Hidemitsu&apos;s official government post was &quot;kingo&quot; (saemon no jo under the ritsuryo system), when referring to just his raising of troops it is also called the Kingo Disturbance (kingo sodo in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="29">
<sen id="85">
<j>関東公方足利満兼は1万騎余を率いて武蔵国府中市 (東京都)高安寺まで進んだが、関東管領上杉憲定に諌められて兵を止めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, kubo (shogunal representative) of the Kanto, led about 10,000 men into Musashi province, advancing as far as Koanji temple in the city of Fuchu, but halted his advance after he was warned by the Kanrei of the Kanto, Norisada UESUGI not to continue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, kubo (shogunal representative) of the Kanto, led about 10,000 men into Musashi province, advancing as far as Koanji temple in the city of Fuchu, but halted his advance after he was warned by the Kanrei of the Kanto, Norisada UESUGI not to continue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, kubo (shogunal representative) of the Kanto, led about 10,000 men into Musashi Province, advancing as far as Koan-ji Temple in the city of Fuchu, but halted his advance after he was warned by the Kanrei of the Kanto, Norisada UESUGI not to continue.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。Temple大文字にしました。-補足。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="30">
<sen id="86">
<j>落城</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sakai castle falls</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sakai castle falls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sakai castle falls</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="87">
<j>堺では幕府軍の総攻撃を撃退した大内勢が意気を揚げていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Back in Sakai, morale among the Ouchi forces jumped after they repulsed the general assault launched by the shogunal army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Back in Sakai, morale among the Ouchi forces jumped after they repulsed the general assault launched by the shogunal army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Back in Sakai, morale among the Ouchi forces jumped after they repulsed the general assault launched by the shogunal army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>幕府軍は火攻めを計画して左義長（爆竹）を用意し、道を整えた上で、12月21日早朝に総攻撃を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunal forces resolved to attack the city with fire, and having prepared sagicho rockets (a kind of firecracker), they got the road ready before launching another general attack in the early morning of the twenty-first day of the twelfth month.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunal forces resolved to attack the city with fire, and having prepared sagicho rockets (a kind of firecracker), they got the road ready before launching another general attack in the early morning of the twenty-first day of the twelfth month.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunal forces resolved to attack the city with fire, and having prepared sagicho rockets (a kind of firecracker), they got the road ready before launching another general attack in the early morning of January 25, 1400.</e>
<cmt>新暦に直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>幕府軍は強風に乗じて城中に火を放ち、矢倉を倒して激しく攻め寄せた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taking advantage of a strong wind, the shogunal forces were able to set fires within the castle, and they pressed their assault furiously, knocking down all the watchtowers they could.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taking advantage of a strong wind, the shogunal forces were able to set fires within the castle, and they pressed their assault furiously, knocking down all the watchtowers they could.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taking advantage of a strong wind, the shogunal forces were able to set fires within the castle, and they pressed their assault furiously, knocking down all the watchtowers they could.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="31">
<sen id="90">
<j>杉備中守は今日が最後の戦いになると覚悟し、山名満氏の陣に突撃して見事な討死を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bicchushu (shugo of Bicchu) SUGI resigned himself that this day would be his last battle, and threw all his strength into an assault on the camp of Mitsuuji YAMANA, achieving a spectacular death in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bicchushu (shugo of Bicchu) SUGI resigned himself to the reality that this day would be his last battle, and threw all his strength into an assault on the camp of Mitsuuji YAMANA, achieving a spectacular death in battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bicchu no kami SUGI resigned himself to the reality that this day would be his last battle, and threw all his strength into an assault on the camp of Mitsuuji YAMANA, achieving a spectacular death in battle.</e>
<cmt>Bicchu no kamiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>これを見ていた義弘は項羽の討死の故事を引き、自分も後代に残るような最後を遂げると決意する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro, after seeing this, resolved that he would continue in the tradition of general Xiang Hu&apos;s glorious death, and make such an end for himself as would ensure his fame for posterity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro, after seeing this, resolved that he would continue in the tradition of general Xiang Hu&apos;s glorious death, and make such an end for himself as would ensure his fame for posterity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro, after seeing this, resolved that he would continue in the tradition of general Xiang Hu&apos;s glorious death, and make such an end for himself as would ensure his fame for posterity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>義弘は幕府軍の北側の陣へ斬り込み日本刀を振るって奮戦。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He cut his way into the battle lines of the shogunal army on the north side of the city, striking left and right with his katana in fierce fighting.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He cut his way into the battle lines of the shogunal army on the north side of the city, striking left and right with his katana in fierce fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He cut his way into the battle lines of the shogunal army on the north side of the city, striking left and right with his katana in fierce fighting.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>管領畠山基国の嫡子畠山満家の軍勢200騎がこれに挑むが、義弘はよき敵であると僅か30騎でさんざんに戦った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA&apos;s legitimate son and heir Mitsuie took his force of 200 men and challenged Yoshihiro&apos;s advance, but Yoshihiro proved a worthy opponent indeed, fighting back ferociously even though he had a mere 30 men.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA&apos;s legitimate son and heir Mitsuie took his force of 200 men and challenged Yoshihiro&apos;s advance, but Yoshihiro proved a worthy opponent indeed, fighting back ferociously even though he had a mere 30 men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanrei Motokuni HATAKEYAMA&apos;s legitimate son and heir Mitsuie took his force of 200 men and challenged Yoshihiro&apos;s advance, but Yoshihiro proved a worthy opponent indeed, fighting back ferociously even though he had a mere 30 men.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>その時、石見国の住人200騎が幕府軍に内応してしまう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that moment, the 200 soldiers from Iwami province defected and joined the shogunal force.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that moment, the 200 soldiers from Iwami province defected and joined the shogunal force.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that moment, the 200 soldiers from Iwami Province defected and joined the shogunal force.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>激怒した義弘は石見勢に攻めかかり、恐怖した石見勢は逃げ散った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This enfuriated Yoshihiro, who attacked the Iwami army with such force that the Iwami army became terrified, broke and scattered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This enfuriated Yoshihiro, who attacked the Iwami army with such force that the Iwami army became terrified, broke and scattered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This infuriated Yoshihiro, who attacked the Iwami army with such force that the Iwami army became terrified, broke and scattered.</e>
<cmt>infuriatedスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="32">
<sen id="96">
<j>義弘はなおも満家を討ち取ろうと戦い続け、幕府軍はこれを取り囲んで攻め立てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshihiro ccntinued fighting, attempting to strike down Mitsuie, but the shogunal army surrounded him and launched an unrelenting assault.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshihiro ccntinued fighting, attempting to strike down Mitsuie, but the shogunal army surrounded him and launched an unrelenting assault.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshihiro continued fighting, attempting to strike down Mitsuie, but the shogunal army surrounded him and launched an unrelenting assault.</e>
<cmt>continuedスペル訂正。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>義弘の手勢は次第に数を減らし森民部丞ひとりになってしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number Yoshihiro&apos;s soldiers steadily dropped until only one remained, Minbujo MORI.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number Yoshihiro&apos;s soldiers steadily dropped until only one remained, Minbujo MORI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number Yoshihiro&apos;s soldiers steadily dropped until only one remained, Mori Minbu no jo.</e>
<cmt>民部丞→Minbu no jo (the third officer of tax and urban improvement department)</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="98">
<j>森民部丞は義弘を守って敵陣に斬り込み奮戦して討死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Minbujo MORI protected Yoshihiro as they cut their way into the enemy battle lines, fighting fiercely until being killed in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Minbujo MORI protected Yoshihiro as they cut their way into the enemy battle lines, fighting fiercely until being killed in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mori Minbu no jo protected Yoshihiro as they cut their way into the enemy battle lines, fighting fiercely until being killed in battle.</e>
<cmt>Mori Minbu no joに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>一人になった義弘は満家を目がけて戦い続けるが、取り囲まれ遂に力尽きて「天下無双の名将大内義弘入道である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Alone now, Yoshihiro continued to fight on, trying to kill Mitsuie, but he was surrounded and in the end used up all his strength, letting out a great shout, saying &quot;Yoshihiro OUCHI, great military commander without peer, now enters the next life.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Alone now, Yoshihiro continued to fight on, trying to kill Mitsuie, but he was surrounded and in the end used up all his strength, letting out a great shout, saying &quot;Yoshihiro OUCHI, great military commander without peer, now enters the next life.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Alone now, Yoshihiro continued to fight on, trying to kill Mitsuie, but he was surrounded and in the end used up all his strength, letting out a great shout, saying &apos;Yoshihiro OUCHI, great military commander without peer, now enters the next life.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>討ち取って将軍の御目にかけよ」と大音声を発して、討ち取られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kill me now, and take me before the Shogun for one last meeting,&quot; and with that was struck down.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kill me now, and take me before the Shogun for one last meeting,&quot; and with that was struck down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kill me now, and take me before the Shogun for one last meeting,&apos; and with that was struck down.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="33">
<sen id="101">
<j>南側を固めていた杉豊後守は義弘の死を知らされて敵陣に切り込んで討死。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Bicchushu SUGI, who was reinforcing the south side of the city, was told of Yoshihiro&apos;s death, he cut his way into the enemy&apos;s formation and died in battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Bicchushu SUGI, who was reinforcing the south side of the city, was told of Yoshihiro&apos;s death, he cut his way into the enemy&apos;s formation and died in battle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Bungo no kami SUGI, who was reinforcing the south side of the city, was told of Yoshihiro&apos;s death, he cut his way into the enemy&apos;s formation and died in battle.</e>
<cmt>Bungo no kamiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>東側を固めていた弘茂は今川勢、一色勢を相手に戦っていたが、手勢も討ち減らされ、最早これまでと自害しようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshige, who was reinforcing the east side of the city and fighting against the armies of the Imagawa and Isshiki clans, also found his own soldiers&apos; numbers dwindling, and deciding that he had fought as long as he could, he tried to kill himself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshige, who was reinforcing the east side of the city and fighting against the armies of the Imagawa and Isshiki clans, also found his own soldiers&apos; numbers dwindling, and deciding that he had fought as long as he could, he tried to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshige, who was reinforcing the east side of the city and fighting against the armies of the Imagawa and Isshiki clans, also found his own soldiers&apos; numbers dwindling, and deciding that he had fought as long as he could, he tried to kill himself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>平井備前入道が押し止めて降伏を勧め、弘茂もこれに従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Bizennyudo HIRAI stopped him, counseling that he surrender, advice Hiroshige also took.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Bizennyudo HIRAI stopped him, counseling that he surrender, advice Hiroshige also took.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Bizen Nyudo HIRAI stopped him, counseling that he surrender, advice Hiroshige also took.</e>
<cmt>Bizen Nyudoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="34">
<sen id="104">
<j>その他の大内勢も落ち延びるか自害して、堺は落城した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rest of the Ouchi army having either escaped or killed themselves, the fortifications of Sakai were taken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rest of the Ouchi army having either escaped or killed themselves, the fortifications of Sakai were taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rest of the Ouchi army having either escaped or killed themselves, the fortifications of Sakai were taken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="35">
<sen id="105">
<j>関東公方足利満兼は武蔵国府中から上野国足利荘(栃木県足利市)まで進軍するが、義弘敗死の報を聞いて鎌倉へ引き返した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, the kubo of the Kanto, had taken his army and marched from Fuchu in Musashi province as far as the Ashikaga family&apos;s private estates in Shimotsuke province (modern-day Ashikaga city in Tochigi pref.), but when news of Yoshihiro&apos;s defeat and death reached him, he turned back to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>I think there is an error here; the Ashikaga estates were not in Kuzuke province, but in Shimotsuke. So I have translated it as Shimotsuke.</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, the kubo of the Kanto, had taken his army and marched from Fuchu in Musashi province as far as the Ashikaga family&apos;s private estates in Shimotsuke province (modern-day Ashikaga city in Tochigi pref.), but when news of Yoshihiro&apos;s defeat and death reached him, he turned back to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mitsukane ASHIKAGA, the kubo of the Kanto, had taken his army and marched from Fuchu in Musashi Province as far as the Ashikaga family&apos;s private estates in Shimotsuke Province (modern-day Ashikaga City in Tochigi Pref.), but when news of Yoshihiro&apos;s defeat and death reached him, he turned back to Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。City, Pref.大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="36">
<sen id="106">
<j>戦後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aftermath of the battle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aftermath of the battle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aftermath of the battle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>応永7年（1400年）3月、関東公方足利満兼は伊豆国三嶋大社に願文を奉献し、「小量をもって」幕府に二心を起こしたことを謝罪した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the third month of Oei 7 (1400), the Kanto kubo Mitsukane ASHIKAGA presented a prayer-petition to the Grand Shrine at Mishima in Izu province in which he apologized for double-crossing the shogunate &quot;in my narrowmindedness.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the third month of Oei 7 (1400), the Kanto kubo Mitsukane ASHIKAGA presented a prayer-petition to the Grand Shrine at Mishima in Izu province in which he apologized for double-crossing the shogunate &quot;in my narrowmindedness.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In April, 1400, the Kanto kubo Mitsukane ASHIKAGA presented a prayer-petition to the Grand Shrine at Mishima in Izu Province in which he apologized for double-crossing the shogunate &apos;in my narrow-mindedness.&apos;</e>
<cmt>新暦にしましたProvince大文字にしました。-補足原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>足利満兼を謀叛に誘った今川了俊は幕府から討伐の命を受けたために上洛して謝罪し、助命された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryoshun IMAGAWA, the one who had urged Mitsukane to revolt against the shogunate, was made the target of a search and destroy order from the shogunate, and because of this proceeded to the capital and apologized, for which he was granted clemency.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryoshun IMAGAWA, the one who had urged Mitsukane to revolt against the shogunate, was made the target of a search and destroy order from the shogunate, and because of this proceeded to the capital and apologized, for which he was granted clemency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryoshun IMAGAWA, the one who had urged Mitsukane to revolt against the shogunate, was made the target of a search and destroy order from the shogunate, and because of this proceeded to the capital and apologized, for which he was granted clemency.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>以後は政治活動は起こさず、和歌、連歌に没頭することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, he abandoned political life and immersed himself in the composing of waka (classical Japanese poems) and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, he abandoned political life and immersed himself in the composing of waka (classical Japanese poems) and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, he abandoned political life and immersed himself in the composing of waka (classical Japanese poems) and renga (linked verse).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="37">
<sen id="110">
<j>義満は大内氏の分国和泉・紀伊・石見・豊前を没収。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshimitsu stripped the Ouchi clan of their control over the provinces of Izumi, Kii, Iwami, and Buzen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshimitsu stripped the Ouchi clan of their control over the provinces of Izumi, Kii, Iwami, and Buzen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshimitsu stripped the Ouchi clan of their control over the provinces of Izumi, Kii, Iwami, and Buzen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>周防・長門のみを降参した弘茂に与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To Hiroshige, who had capitulated, he granted only the provinces of Suo and Nagato.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To Hiroshige, who had capitulated, he granted only the provinces of Suo and Nagato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">To Hiroshige, who had capitulated, he granted only the provinces of Suo and Nagato.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>しかし、周防・長門の本拠を守っていた盛見はこれに従わずに抵抗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But Morimi, who had been protecting the Ouchi heartlands of Suo and Nagato, refused to accept this and forcefully resisted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But Morimi, who had been protecting the Ouchi heartlands of Suo and Nagato, refused to accept this and forcefully resisted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But Morimi, who had been protecting the Ouchi heartlands of Suo and Nagato, refused to accept this and forcefully resisted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>弘茂は幕府の援軍とともに盛見を攻めてこれを追うが、応永8年（1401年）に九州で盛見は再挙し、数度の合戦の後、弘茂は佐加利山城（下関市長府）で滅ぼされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hiroshige, together with shogunal reinforcements, attacked and drove Morimi away, but in Oei 8 (1401) Morimi raised a new army in Kyushu and made another attempt to win back the Ouchi lands, and after several battles between them, Morimi destroyed Hiroshige at Sakariyama castle (in modern-day Chufu ward of the city of Shimonoseki).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hiroshige, together with shogunal reinforcements, attacked and drove Morimi away, but in Oei 8 (1401) Morimi raised a new army in Kyushu and made another attempt to win back the Ouchi lands, and after several battles between them, Morimi destroyed Hiroshige at Sakariyama castle (in modern-day Chufu ward of the city of Shimonoseki).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hiroshige, together with shogunal reinforcements, attacked and drove Morimi away, but in 1401 Morimi raised a new army in Kyushu and made another attempt to win back the Ouchi lands, and after several battles between them, Morimi destroyed Hiroshige at Sakariyama Castle (in modern-day Chufu ward of the city of Shimonoseki).</e>
<cmt>旧暦は削除しました。Castle大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="38">
<sen id="114">
<j>盛見は更に安芸国、石見国まで勢力を伸ばす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Morimi then extended his military hegemony even further, gaining control as far as Aki and Iwami provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Morimi then extended his military hegemony even further, gaining control as far as Aki and Iwami provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Morimi then extended his military hegemony even further, gaining control as far as Aki and Iwami Provinces.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>幕府もこれを認めざるえなくなり応永12年（1405年）頃に盛見に周防・長門の守護職を与え、更に豊前・筑前の守護まで加えてようやく帰順させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate, no longer able to avoid acknowledging Morimi&apos;s overlordship of these lands, officially granted him the title of shugo over Suo and Nagato provinces in Oei 12 (1405), and when they added the provinces of Buzen and Chikuzen to his dominion as shugo, he finally reswore allegiance to the Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate, no longer able to avoid acknowledging Morimi&apos;s overlordship of these lands, officially granted him the title of shugo over Suo and Nagato provinces in Oei 12 (1405), and when they added the provinces of Buzen and Chikuzen to his dominion as shugo, he finally reswore allegiance to the Shogun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate, no longer able to avoid acknowledging Morimi&apos;s overlordship of these lands, officially granted him the title of shugo over Suo and Nagato Provinces in 1405, and when they added the provinces of Buzen and Chikuzen to his dominion as shugo, he finally swore allegiance to the Shogun again.</e>
<cmt>Province大文字にしました。旧暦は削除しました。swore allegiance to the Shogun againとしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>こうして、いったんは没落しかけた大内氏は再び勢力を盛り返すことになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this way, the Ouchi clan was able to recover their military strength and rally after being brought once to the brink of ruin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this way, the Ouchi clan was able to recover their military strength and rally after being brought once to the brink of ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this way, the Ouchi clan was able to recover their military strength and rally after being brought once to the brink of ruin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="39">
<sen id="117">
<j>応永記</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Chronicle of the Oei Era (Oei-ki in Japanese)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Chronicle of the Oei Era (Oei-ki in Japanese)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Chronicle of the Oei Era (Oei-ki in Japanese)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>この乱の内容は『応永記』に記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The events of the Oei rebellion are recorded in the Chronicle of the Oei Era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The events of the Oei rebellion are recorded in the Chronicle of the Oei Era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The events of the Oei rebellion are recorded in &quot;the Chronicle of the Oei Era.&quot;</e>
<cmt>原文の『』に合わせ&quot;を補足</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Rusk(id:9895), Jugger90(id:17088), Nnh(id:474), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 水野白楓(id:22811), Himazin(id:22034), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 味っ子(id:17086), Yosemite(id:5808), Saaki(id:43602), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>