<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>足利三代木像梟首事件</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">An incident in which Ashikaga three generation&apos;s wooden images and mortuary tablets were destroyed</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An incident in which wooden images and mortuary tablets of three generations of Ashikaga were destroyed</e>
<cmt>Edited for flowRobert: Don&apos;t believe this is inline with past titles… perhaps the explanation could be included in parantheses, with the title in Romaji? In which case, all further references would have to be renamed to the Romaji name. (Highlighted in red)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident of Ashikaga-sandai mokuzo kyoshu</e>
<cmt>NCのコメントに従って、ローマ字表記としました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>足利三代木像梟首事件（あしかがさんだいもくぞうきょうしゅじけん）は、江戸時代後期、幕末の文久3年2月22日 (旧暦)（1863年4月9日）に、京都等持院にあった室町幕府初代征夷大将軍足利尊氏、2代足利義詮、3代足利義満の木像の首と位牌が持ち出され、賀茂川の河原に晒された事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the incident in which Ashikaga three generation&apos;s wooden images and mortuary tablets were destroyed, heads of the wooden images and the mortuary tablets of the first Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) Takauji ASHIKAGA, the second Seitaishogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, and the third Seitaishogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA were taken away from Kyoto Jito-In on April 9, 1863 in the late Edo period, and exposed on the riverbed of Kamogawa river.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the incident in which wooden images and mortuary tablets of three generations of Ashikaga were destroyed, heads of the wooden images and the mortuary tablets of the first Seitaishogun (commander-in-chief of the expeditionary force against the barbarians, great, unifying leader) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) Takauji ASHIKAGA, the second Seitaishogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, and the third Seitaishogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA were taken away from Kyoto Jito-In on April 9, 1863 in the late Edo period, and were cast to the riverbed of Kamogawa river.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the incident of Ashikaga-sandai mokuzo kyoshu, heads of the wooden images and the mortuary tablets of the first Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;) of Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) Takauji ASHIKAGA, the second Seii taishogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, and the third Seii taishogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA were taken away from Kyoto Jito-in Temple on April 9, 1863 in the late Edo period, and were cast to the riverbed of Kamo-gawa river.</e>
<cmt>マーカー部分変更Seitaishogun→Seii taishogun征夷大将軍の定訳Jito-In→Jito-in TempleKamogawa→Kamo-gawa</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>犯人は平田篤胤派国学の門人である三輪田元綱、師岡正胤とされ、会津藩士も関与。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The criminals were considered to be Mototsuna MIWADA and Masatane MOROOKA, disciples of the school of Atsutane HIRATA in the study of Japanese classical literature, and retainers of the Aizu Clan were also concerned.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The criminals were considered to be Mototsuna MIWADA and Masatane MOROOKA, disciples of the school of Atsutane HIRATA in the study of Japanese classical literature, and retainers of the Aizu Clan were also concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The criminals were considered to be Mototsuna MIWADA and Masatane MOROOKA, disciples of the school of Atsutane HIRATA in the study of Japanese classical literature, and retainers of the Aizu Clan were also concerned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>足利将軍3代を逆賊とする罪状が掲げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was an article of the charge of being Gyakuzoku rebels against the Ashikaga three generations.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There was an article charging the individuals of being Gyakuzoku rebels against the the third Ashikaga shogun.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There was an article charging the three Ashikaga shoguns with being Gyakuzoku rebels.</e>
<cmt>NCの文では意味が違うので書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>それまでの天誅は、開国派や公武合体派であった個人を狙ってのものが大半であったが、この事件では足利将軍の木像を梟首することで暗に倒幕の意味を持つものとして重視された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The heaven&apos;s punishment used to be given to individuals in a group for opening of a country to the world or for integration of the imperial court and the shogunate, but this incident was counted because destroying the heads of wooden images of the Ashikaga Shoguns implied overthrowing the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heaven&apos;s punishment used to be given mainly to members of groups which were in favor of opening Japan to the world and integrating the imperial court and the shogunate, but this incident qualified for this type of punishment because destroying the heads of the wooden images of the Ashikaga Shoguns implied that they wished to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heaven&apos;s punishment used to be given to those individuals that were a part of groups which were for opening Japan to the world, integrating the imperial court and the shogunate, but this incident was counted because destroying the heads of wooden images of the Ashikaga Shoguns implied that they wished to overthrow the Shogunate.</e>
<cmt>原文に沿って書き換えました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="5">
<j>事件は江戸で公募された浪士組の上洛直前にあたり、挑発的行為とも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The incident occurred immediately before roshi-gumi (an organization of masterless samurai) publicly recruited in Edo went to Kyoto, and it is also considered as a provocative action.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The incident occurred immediately before roshi-gumi (an organization of masterless samurai) publicly recruited in Edo went to Kyoto, and it was also considered an act of provocation.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The incident occurred immediately before roshi-gumi (an organization of masterless samurai) publicly recruited in Edo went to Kyoto, and it was also considered an act of provocation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>京都守護職の松平容保は犯人捕縛を命じ、浪士の一斉蜂起も懸念されたが、4月には犯人は逮捕され、8月には処罰される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Katamori MATSUDAIRA, Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto), ordered to arrest the criminals while there was a concern about an all-out uprising by the roshi, but the criminals were arrested in April and punished in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Katamori MATSUDAIRA, Kyoto shugoshoku (Military governor of Kyoto), ordered the criminals arrested despite concern about an all-out uprising by the roshi, but the criminals were arrested in April and punished in August.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Katamori MATSUDAIRA, Kyoto shugoshiki (post of provincial constable), ordered the criminals arrested despite concern about an all-out uprising by the roshi, but the criminals were arrested in April and punished in August.</e>
<cmt>守護職の定訳</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>事件後は浪士取締りが強化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A control over the roshi became stricter after the incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Control over the roshi became stricter after the incident.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Control over the roshi became stricter after the incident.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 トホホ川(id:50502), Boa(id:20845), BAKU(id:55205), Kagetudo(id:163875), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>