<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>平民</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heimin (commoners)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heimin (commoners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heimin (commoners)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>平民（へいみん）は、官位や爵位を持たない普通の人民、市民のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heimin means ordinary citizens without any official rank or title.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heimin means ordinary citizens without any official rank or title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Heimin means ordinary citizens without any official rank or title.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>貴族と対比されることが多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They are often compared with kizoku (nobles.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They are often compared with kizoku (nobles.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They are often compared with kizoku (nobles).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>近代日本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Modern Japan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Modern Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Modern Japan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>日本では、1869年（明治2年）に新設された族称の一つが平民である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The term of heimin was one of the designations of family class, which was newly created in 1869 in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The term heimin designated a class of family and was created in 1869 in Japan.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The term heimin designated a class of family and was created in 1869 in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>公家・大名家及び上級武士を除く家が、平民という族称を享け、華族、士族の下位に置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families other than kuge (court nobles), daimyo-ke (families of feudal lords) and upper-class worrier families were designated as heimin which was ranked below kazoku (nobility class) and shizoku (worrier class.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Families other than kuge (court nobles), daimyo-ke (families of feudal lords) and upper-class warrior families were designated as heimin which was ranked below kazoku (nobility class) and shizoku (warrior classes.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Families other than kuge (court nobles), daimyo-ke (families of feudal lords) and upper-class warrior families were designated as heimin which were ranked below kazoku (nobility class) and shizoku (warrior classes).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>1947年（昭和22年）、貴族制度廃止により廃止。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This designation became annuled in 1947 when the aristocracy system in Japan was abolished.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This designation became annuled in 1947 when the aristocracy system in Japan was abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This designation was annulled in 1947 when the aristocracy system in Japan was abolished.</e>
<cmt>スペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>華族や士族の家に生まれた者も、家を継がず分家して一戸を創設する際には、生家の族称から離れて、原則として平民の族称を享けることとなった（平民宰相といわれた原敬がこの例で、盛岡藩家老の息子だったが平民となった）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any one who was born in a family of kazoku or shizoku but did not succeed the family to set up a new branch family was basically classified to heimin class despite the designation of his first home (for example, Kei HARA who was called a commoner premier became heimin after he was born as a son of the chief retainer of the Morioka domain.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any one who was born in a family of kazoku or shizoku but did not succeed the family to set up a new branch of the family was basically classified as heimin despite the designation of his first home (for example, Kei HARA who was called a commoner premier became heimin after he was born as a son of the chief retainer of the Morioka domain.)</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any one who was born in a family of kazoku or shizoku but did not succeed the family to set up a new branch was basically classified as heimin despite the designation of his parents&apos; home (for example, Takashi HARA who was called a commoner prime minister became heimin after he was born as a son of the chief retainer of the Morioka domain.)</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>もっとも、華族の分家には特旨により特に華族に列せられる例や、家を継がない華族の子には他華族家の養子となる例も見られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, there were seen such cases that some branch families of kazoku became ranked also as kazoku class by special consideration, and that a son of kazoku family who was not an heir of the family was adopted to some other kazoku family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, there were cases where some branch families of kazoku were also ranked as kazoku due to special considerations, and a son of a kazoku family who was not an heir of the family was adopted to some other kazoku family.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, there were cases where some branch families of kazoku were also ranked as kazoku due to special considerations, and a son of a kazoku family who was not an heir of the family was adopted into some other kazoku family.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>士族、平民の称は、明治5年5月太政官布告第29号に「二代以上ノ卒ヲ士族ニ加ヘテ一代抱卒ヲ平民ニ復ス」とあり、両者はただその家系をしめす名称の別にとどまり、なんら法律上の特権などなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Designations of both shizoku and heimin were just to indicate their family lines without any legal privilege, since the edict No. 29 of Dajokan (the Grand Council of State) of 1872 had ordained that &quot;any family of sotsu class (another family rank used before Meiji Restoration) which had continued two or more generations were transfered to shizoku class and other sotsu families within one generation were reclassified to heimin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Designations of both shizoku and heimin indicated family lines without any legal privilege, since the edict No. 29 of Dajokan (the Grand Council of State) of 1872 had ordained that &quot;any family of sotsu class (another family rank used before Meiji Restoration) which had continued two or more generations were transfered to shizoku class and other sotsu families within one generation were reclassified to heimin.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Designations of both shizoku and heimin indicated family lines without any legal privilege, since the edict No. 29 of Dajokan (the Grand Council of State) of May 1872 had ordained that &apos;any family of sotsu class (another family rank used before Meiji Restoration) which had continued two or more generations were transferred to shizoku class and other sotsu families within one generation were reclassified to heimin.&apos;</e>
<cmt>May補足原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;にスペルを修正</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>士族の称は家に従属するもので、人の一身に専属するものではないから、士族が家を去って他家に入ったときはもちろんのこと、分家したときも当然その称をうしない、平民となった（明治7年布告第73号）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The designation of shizoku is associated with each family but not with an individual person, and, therefore, it is no wonder that not only any one who left a family of shizoku and entered other family but also any one who established a separate branch family had to lose the designation of shizoku of his former family and became heimin (Edict No.73 of 1874.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The designation of shizoku is associated with each family but not with an individual person, and, therefore, it is no wonder that not only any one who left a family of shizoku and entered other family but also any one who established a separate branch family had to lose the designation of shizoku of his former family and became heimin (Edict No.73 of 1874.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The designation of shizoku is associated with each family but not with an individual person, and, therefore, it is no wonder that not only any one who left a family of shizoku and entered other family but also any one who established a separate branch family had to lose the designation of shizoku of his former family and became heimin (Edict No.73 of 1874.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>華族は公法上は国家から特別待遇が与えられたが、私法上は士族、平民と同様であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kazoku could receive referential treatments from the state under public laws, but they were treated in the same manner as shizoku and heimin under private laws.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kazoku could receive referential treatments from the state under public laws, but they were treated in the same manner as shizoku and heimin under private laws.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kazoku could receive special treatments from the state under public laws, but they were treated in the same manner as shizoku and heimin under private laws.</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="12">
<j>なお明治8年3月布告第44号には「人民署名肩書ハ何（府県）華族、士族、平民ト記載可致此旨布告候事」とあるが、旧戸籍簿には華族、士族は族称として明示するが、平民の称はこれを記載しなかった（旧戸籍法第18条）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Edict No.44 of March, 1875, had decreed that &quot;people may sign their names and titles with designations of their family&apos;s ranks, either kazoku, shizoku or heimin, in a prefecture,&quot; an actual register of families had clear descriptions of kazoku and shizoku but no designation of heimin (Article 18 of the former Family Registration Law.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Edict No.44 of March, 1875, had decreed that &quot;people may sign their names and titles with designations of their family&apos;s ranks, either kazoku, shizoku or heimin, in a prefecture,&quot; an actual register of families had clear descriptions of kazoku and shizoku but no designation of heimin (Article 18 of the former Family Registration Law.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Edict No.44 of March 1875, had decreed that &apos;people may sign their names and titles with designations of their family&apos;s ranks, either kazoku, shizoku or heimin, in a prefecture,&apos; an actual register of families had clear descriptions of kazoku and shizoku but no designation of heimin (Article 18 of the former Family Registration Law).</e>
<cmt>FBに基づいて修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="13">
<j>イギリス</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The United Kingdom</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The United Kingdom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The United Kingdom</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>イギリスでは、法律上、イギリス国王と貴族（ピアー、peer）以外の者を平民（コモナー、commoner）と呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the United Kingdom, people other than the King of England and peers are called commoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the United Kingdom, people other than the King of England and peers are called commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the United Kingdom, people other than the King of England and peers are called commoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="15">
<j>ここで言う貴族とは、爵位 (peerage) を持つ者の意味であり、以下のような者は平民である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this context, the term &quot;peers&quot; refers to the holders of peerage, and the followings are commoners:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this context, the term &quot;peers&quot; refers to the holders of peerage, and the followings are commoners:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this context, the term &quot;peers&quot; refers to the holders of peerage, and the followings are commoners:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="16">
<j>儀礼称号を持つだけの者は貴族ではなく平民である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any one with only a courtesy designation is not a peer but a commoner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any one with only a courtesy designation is not a peer but a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any one with only a courtesy designation is not a peer but a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>つまり、本人が爵位を持たなければ、単に爵位を持つ者の家族というだけでは貴族ではなく平民である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any one without peerage, even if he is a member of a peer&apos;s family, is not a peer but a commoner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any one without peerage, even if he is a member of a peer&apos;s family, is not a peer but a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any one without peerage, even if he is a member of a peer&apos;s family, is not a peer but a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="18">
<j>男爵より下の、準男爵、ナイトなどの称号は爵位とはみなされないため、これらの称号を持つ者は貴族ではなく平民である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Any one who holds a designation of either baronet, knight or other designation lower than baron is not a peer but a commoner, because neither of these designations are regarded as a peerage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Any one who holds a designation of either baronet, knight or other designation lower than baron is not a peer but a commoner, because neither of these designations are regarded as a peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Any one who holds a designation of either baronet, knight or other designation lower than baron is not a peer but a commoner, because neither of these designations are regarded as a peerage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="19">
<j>ウィリアム・マウントバッテン＝ウィンザーのように、イギリス王室であっても爵位がなければ平民である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As in the case of William Mountbatten-Windsor, even a member of the British royal family without peerage is a commoner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As in the case of William Mountbatten-Windsor, even a member of the British royal family without peerage is a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As in the case of William Mountbatten-Windsor, even a member of the British royal family without peerage is a commoner.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="20">
<j>古代ローマ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ancient Rome</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ancient Rome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ancient Rome</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="21">
<j>共和制ローマでは、貴族（パトリキ、patrici）以外の市民を平民（プレブス、plebs）と呼んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the republican Rome, citizens other than patrici (patricians) were called plebs (plebeians.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the republican Rome, citizens other than patrici (patricians) were called plebs (plebeians.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Republic of Rome, citizens other than patrici (patricians) were called plebs (plebeians).</e>
<cmt>ピリオドの位置移動</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>なお、奴隷は市民ではなく、したがって平民でも（もちろん貴族でも）ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For reference, slaves were not considered citizens so that they were neither plebs nor, of course, patricians.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For reference, slaves were not considered citizens so that they were neither plebs nor, of course, patricians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For reference, slaves were not considered citizens so that they were neither plebs nor, of course, patricians.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 MDR-SK(id:192066), Straysheep(id:42448), U3002(id:66126), Kawai(id:5634), 陽一(id:92099), Kt0807(id:206307), あお。(id:39226), わがまま小皇帝(id:39717), 梅澤 威志(id:17353), Alexbot(id:157199), Aloha-vodka(id:22493), 史家(id:208284), Yhiroyuki(id:84500), Ws227(id:208643), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>