<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>二朱銀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishu gin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishu gin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishu gin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>二朱銀（にしゅぎん）とは、江戸時代末期の日本で流通した銀貨の一種。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishu gin silver is a kind of silver coin circulated in Japan in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishu gin silver is a kind of silver coin circulated in Japan in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishu gin silver is a kind of silver coin circulated in Japan in the end of Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="2">
<j>丁銀や豆板銀が重量を以て貨幣価値の決まる秤量貨幣であったのに対し、額面が記載された表記貨幣である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is Hyoki kahei, whose face value is written on the coins, while Chogin (collective term of silver) and mametagin (a kind of Edo-period coins) are Hyodo kahei (currency valued by weight), whose currency value is determined by weight.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is Hyoki kahei, whose face value is written on the coins, while Chogin (collective term of silver) and mameitagin (a kind of Edo-period coins) are Hyoryo kahei (currency valued by weight), whose currency value is determined by weight.</e>
<cmt>「秤量貨幣」は「ひょうりょうかへい」が一般的と思われますので、変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is Hyoki kahei, whose face value is written on the coins, while Chogin (collective term of silver) and mameitagin (a kind of Edo-period coins) are Hyoryo kahei (currency valued by weight), whose currency value is determined by weight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="3">
<j>形状は長方形。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is a rectangle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is rectangular.</e>
<cmt>形容詞に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is rectangular.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>額面は2朱。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has a face value of 2 shu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It has a face value of 2 shu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It has a face value of 2 shu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>その貨幣価値は金貨である二朱金と等価とされ、1/8両に相当し、1/2分に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is treated as equal to Nishu kin gold, a gold coin, in currency value and worth 1/8 ryo, that is, 1/2 bu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is treated as equal to Nishu kin gold, a gold coin, in currency value and worth 1/8 ryo, that is, 1/2 bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is treated as equal to Nishu kin gold, a gold coin, in currency value and worth 1/8 ryo, that is, 1/2 bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="6">
<j>南鐐二朱銀を嚆矢とし、1859年の安政二朱銀まで鋳造された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting with Nanryo Nishu gin silver, such coins had been minted until Ansei Nishu gin silver in 1859.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting with Nanryo Nishu gin silver, such coins had been minted until Ansei Nishu gin silver in 1859.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting with Nanryo Nishu gin silver, such coins had been minted until Ansei Nishu gin silver in 1859.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>南鐐二朱銀の貨幣面の表記は「以南鐐八片換小判一兩」であったが、安政二朱銀では「二朱銀」と単刀直入なものになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A sentence was written on the surface of Nanryo Nishu gin silver which said &quot;Eight coins of Nanryo can be exchanged with a koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) of 1ryo,&quot; but merely a simple word &quot;Nishu gin&quot; was written on that of Ansei Nishu gin silver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A sentence was written on the surface of Nanryo Nishu gin silver which said &quot;Eight coins of Nanryo can be exchanged with a koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) of 1 ryo,&quot; but merely a simple word &quot;Nishu gin&quot; was written on that of Ansei Nishu gin silver.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A sentence was written on the surface of Nanryo Nishu gin silver which said &quot;Eight coins of Nanryo can be exchanged with a koban (former Japanese oval gold coin) of 1 ryo,&quot; but merely a simple word &quot;Nishu gin&quot; was written on that of Ansei Nishu gin silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>安政二朱銀</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansei Nishu gin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansei Nishu gin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansei Nishu gin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="8">
<j>安政二朱銀（あんせいにしゅぎん）は日米和親条約による安政6年（1859年）6月2日の横浜港の開港に備えて、同年5月25日より小判の海外流出防止の目的で貿易取引専用に鋳造された計数銀貨であり、貿易二朱（ぼうえきにしゅ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ansei Nishu gin silver is Keisu ginka (a silver coin whose value is determined by the amount written on it) minted only for international trade after May 25, 1859, with an intention to prevent drain of koban to foreign countries in preparation to the opening of Yokohama Port scheduled to be on June 2, 1859, due to Japan-U.S. Treaty of Peace and Amity, and it was also called Boeki Nishu (Nishu for international trade).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ansei Nishu gin silver was Keisu ginka (a silver coin whose value is determined by the amount written on it) minted only for international trade after June 25, 1859, with an intention to prevent the outflow of koban to foreign countries in preparation to the opening of Yokohama Port scheduled for July 1, 1859, due to Japan-U.S. Treaty of Peace and Amity, and it was also called Boeki Nishu (Nishu for international trade).</e>
<cmt>時制を変更し、「流出」をoutflowに言い換えました。月日もグレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ansei Nishu gin silver was Keisu ginka (a silver coin whose value is determined by the amount written on it) minted only for international trade after June 25, 1859, with an intention to prevent the outflow of koban to foreign countries in preparation to the opening of Yokohama Port scheduled for July 1, 1859, due to Japan-U.S. Treaty of Peace and Amity, and it was also called Boeki Nishu (Nishu for international trade).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>また大きいばかりで、より小型の一分銀の半分の額面価値でしか通用しなかったことからバカ二朱（ばかにしゅ）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Baka (fool) Nishu, because in spite of its large size it had a face value only half as high as that of ichibu-gin silver, which were smaller in size.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Baka (fool) Nishu, because in spite of its large size it had only half the face value of ichibu-gin silver, which were smaller in size.</e>
<cmt>「半分の額面価値」を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Baka (fool) Nishu, because in spite of its large size it had only half the face value of ichibu-gin silver, which were smaller in size.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>またこの名称は本来の発行目的を果たすことができなかったからであるともいわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Ansei Nishu was called Baka Nishu because it could not achieve the objective for which it had been originally emitted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that it got this name from the failure to achieve its original purpose of the issue.</e>
<cmt>原文に合わせるため、具体的名称を省いて訳し直しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that it got this name from the failure to achieve its original purpose of the issue.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>嘉永6年（1853年）、浦賀沖の黒船来航により江戸幕府は開港を迫られ、安政元年（1854年）5月17日より、下田市了仙寺にて日本貨幣と西洋貨幣との交換比率の交渉が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1853 the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was forced to open its port as a result of the arrival of Kurofune (The Black Ships of Commodore Matthew Perry) at Uraga offshore, and on May 17, 1854, a negotiation was started at Ryosen-ji temple in Shimoda City concerning an exchange rate of Japanese currency to Western currencies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1853 the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was forced to open its port as a result of the arrival of Kurofune (The Black Ships of Commodore Matthew Perry) at Uraga offshore, and on June 12, 1854, a negotiation was started at Ryosen-ji Temple in Shimoda City concerning exchange rates between Japanese and Western currencies.</e>
<cmt>安政元年5月17日をグレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1853 the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) was forced to open its port as a result of the arrival of Kurofune (The Black Ships of Commodore Matthew Perry) at Uraga offshore, and on June 12, 1854, a negotiation was started at Ryosen-ji Temple in Shimoda City concerning exchange rates between Japanese and Western currencies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>アメリカ合衆国側は金貨、銀貨はそれぞれ同一質量をもって交換すべきあると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The United States of America insisted that the same weight of gold or silver coins be exchanged between the two countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The United States of America insisted that gold or silver coins be exchanged respectively in the same weight.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The United States of America insisted that equivalent weights of gold coins and equivalent weights of silver coins should be exchanged.</e>
<cmt>内容を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>一方、幕府側の主張は以下の通りであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the bakufu argued as follows:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the bakufu argued as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the bakufu argued as follows:</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="14">
<j>8.8匁の量目の20ドル金貨は1匁当り銀19匁すなわち1枚あたり、銀167.2匁と評価され、1ドル当たりでは銀8.36匁である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A twenty-dollar gold coin, which weighs 8.8 monme (a unit of weight; approximately 3.75g) can be converted to 167.2 monme of silver, based on a conversion rate of 1 monme of gold to 19 monme of silver, and so one dollar is equal in value to 8.36 monme of silver.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A twenty-dollar gold coin weighing 8.8 monme (about 33g) can be converted to 627g of silver because 1 monme (3.75g) of gold coin is equal to 71.25g of silver, and so one dollar is valued at 31.35g of silver.</e>
<cmt>重さの記述を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A twenty-dollar gold coin weighing 8.8 monme (about 33g) can be converted to 627g of silver because 1 monme (3.75g) of gold coin is equal to 71.25g of silver, and so one dollar is valued at 31.35g of silver.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="15">
<j>また1ドル銀貨すなわち外国銀貨は地金と見做されるため純銀量6匁2分（23.2グラム）に対し二六双替である通用銀（天保丁銀）16匁と評価される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a foreign silver coin including a one-dollar silver coin is regarded as bare metal, its net weight of silver of 23.2g is rated as equal to 16 monme of the silver in currency (Tenpo Chogin), which is 二六双替.</e>
<cmt>読み方・定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a one-dollar silver coin, a foreign silver coin, is regarded as bare metal, its pure silver content, 23.2g, is valued at 60g of common silver currency (Tenpo Chogin), because 10 monme (37.5g) of pure silver is purchased at silver mint for 97.5g of Tenpo Chogin.</e>
<cmt>「二六双替」は読み方不明のため、内容のみ訳出しました。重さの記述や、「すなわち」の訳出も変更しています。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a one-dollar silver coin, a foreign silver coin, is regarded as bare metal, its pure silver content, 23.2g, is valued at 60g of common silver currency (Tenpo Chogin), because 10 monme (37.5g) of pure silver is purchased at silver mint for 97.5g of Tenpo Chogin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>これは1両の約1/4であるから1ドル＝1分である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is equal in value to about one-fourth of 1 ryo, so one dollar is worth 1bu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is equal in value to about one-fourth of 1 ryo, so one dollar is worth 1bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is equal in value to about one-fourth of 1 ryo, so one dollar is worth 1bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>また一分銀は名目貨幣であり、金貨4ドル分の金を含有する本位貨幣である小判の兌換券に相当するものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, an ichibu-gin silver coin is nominal money and the coin certificate of koban, which is a standard coin containing the same amount gold as gold coins worth four dollars.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, an ichibu-gin silver coin is nominal money and equivalent to the coin certificate of koban, which is a standard coin containing the same amount gold as gold coins worth four dollars.</e>
<cmt>「相当する」を訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, an ichibu-gin silver coin is nominal money and equivalent to the coin certificate of koban, which is a standard coin containing the same amount gold as gold coins worth four dollars.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="18">
<j>これらのうち不当に低く評価された金貨は問題外とされ、論争の焦点は銀貨へと絞られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Of those arguments, gold coins were left out of the negotiation because they were too lowly valued, and the negotiation was focused on silver coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Of those arguments, gold coins were left out of the negotiation because they were too lowly valued, and the negotiation was focused on silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Of those arguments, gold coins were left out of the negotiation because they were too lowly valued, and the negotiation was focused on silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>しかしこの時点では交渉はまとまらなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But it was not concluded at this point.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the negotiation was not concluded at this point.</e>
<cmt>「交渉」を訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the negotiation was not concluded at this point.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="20">
<j>安政3年（1856年）9月9日に下田御用所においてアメリカ合衆国総領事のタウンゼント・ハリスとの協議が行われ、ハリスは次のように主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 9, 1856, a conference was held with Townsend HARRIS, American consul general, at Shimoda Goyo-sho (a government office), and he argued as follows:</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 7, 1856, a conference was held with Townsend HARRIS, American consul general, at Shimoda Goyo-sho (a government office), and he argued as follows.</e>
<cmt>月日もグレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 7, 1856, a conference was held with Townsend HARRIS, American consul general, at Shimoda Goyo-sho (a government office), and he argued as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>市中に流通している天保一分銀は2.3匁（8.62グラム）であり、1ドル銀貨は26.73グラムであるから100ドルは一分銀310枚に相当する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Tenpo ichibu-gin silver in circulation weighs 2.3 monme (8.62g), a one-dollar silver coin weighs 26.73g, and so one hundred dollars are equal in value to 310 ichibu-gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As Tenpo ichibu-gin silver in circulation weighs 2.3 monme (8.62g) and a one-dollar silver coin weighs 26.73g, one hundred dollars are equal in value to 310 ichibu-gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt>接続詞を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As Tenpo ichibu-gin silver in circulation weighs 2.3 monme (8.62g) and a one-dollar silver coin weighs 26.73g, one hundred dollars are equal in value to 310 ichibu-gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>従って1ドル銀貨の約1/3の量目（質量）である一分銀3枚を持って1ドルに換えるべきであると主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus three ichibu-gin silver coins, weighing about one third of a one-dollar silver coin, should be converted to one dollar.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus three ichibu-gin silver coins, weighing about one third of a one-dollar silver coin, should be converted to one dollar, he argued.</e>
<cmt>「主張した」を訳出しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus three ichibu-gin silver coins, weighing about one third of a one-dollar silver coin, should be converted to one dollar, he argued.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="23">
<j>結局、実質価値に満たない名目貨幣としての銀貨は国際的には通用しないとハリスに押し切られ、同種同量交換の1ドル＝3分の交換比率を承諾することになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the end, HARRIS won the dispute by insisting that nominal silver coins to which a higher value than their real value was attached would not be internationally accepted, and forced the bakufu to accept an exchange rate of one dollar to 3bu, which was an exchange of the same quantity of the same materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the end, HARRIS won the dispute by insisting that nominal silver coins to which a higher value than their real value was attached would not be internationally accepted, and forced the bakufu to accept an exchange rate of 3 bu to the dollar between same quantity of the same material.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the end, HARRIS won the dispute by insisting that nominal silver coins to which a higher value than their real value was attached would not be internationally accepted, and forced the bakufu to accept an exchange rate of 3 bu to the dollar where the same quantity of the same material was being exchanged.</e>
<cmt>内容を変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>また中国との交易に精通していたハリスは日本の一両も中国と同様に銀一両（テール/37.3グラム）と考え、1ドル銀貨は約3/4テールの量目に相当し一分銀の量目が偶然にも約1/4テールであったことも1ドル＝3分の根拠としての口実となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">HARRIS, familiar with the trade with China, considered 1ryo in Japan to be 1ryo (tael; 37.3g) of silver just as 1ryo in China, and drew his conclusion also from the fact that a one-dollar silver coin weighed about three fourths of a tael and an ichibu-gin silver coin happened to weigh about one fourth of a tael.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">HARRIS, familiar with the trade with China, considered 1 ryo in Japan to be 1 ryo (tael; 37.3g) of silver just as 1 ryo in China, and drew his conclusion also from the fact that a one-dollar silver coin weighed about three fourths of a tael and an ichibu-gin silver coin happened to weigh about one fourth of a tael.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">HARRIS, familiar with the trade with China, considered 1 ryo in Japan to be 1 ryo (tael; 37.3g) of silver just as 1 ryo in China, and drew his conclusion also from the fact that a one-dollar silver coin weighed about three fourths of a tael and an ichibu-gin silver coin happened to weigh about one fourth of a tael.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="25">
<j>そこで幕府は、安政6年（1859年）6月1日より、天保小判の量目の4/5倍に低下させた安政小判と、量目がほぼ1ドル銀貨の半分である安政二朱銀を発行し、これにより1ドル＝一分に誘導し、かつ金銀比価を国際水準に対しやや金高に設定された17.21に是正しようと試みた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus the bakufu emitted Ansei koban, which had been made lower in weight to the four fifths of the weight of Tenpo koban, and Ansei Nishu gin silver coins, which weighed almost half as much as a one-dollar silver coin, on June 1, 1859 in an attempt to shift to an exchange rate of one dollar to 1bu, and to modify the exchange ratio between gold and silver to 17:21, a ratio a little more favorable to gold than the international standard.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus the bakufu emitted Ansei koban, which had been made lighter to four fifths of Tenpo koban, and Ansei Nishu gin silver coins, which weighed almost half as much as a one-dollar silver coin, on June 30, 1859, in an attempt to shift to an exchange rate of 1 bu to the dollar and to modify the exchange ratio between gold and silver to 17:21, a ratio a little more favorable to gold than the international standard.</e>
<cmt>前半を簡略化し、グレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus the bakufu emitted Ansei koban, which had been made lighter to four fifths of Tenpo koban, and Ansei Nishu gin silver coins, which weighed almost half as much as a one-dollar silver coin, on June 30, 1859, in an attempt to shift to an exchange rate of 1 bu to the dollar and to modify the exchange ratio between gold and silver to 17:21, a ratio a little more favorable to gold than the international standard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>一方、二朱銀については一分銀の半分の額面にもかかわらず、約4/3倍の含有銀量であり、出目獲得を目的とした悪貨の発行に慣れた幕府にとって良貨は多量に発行できるものでなかったため、貿易取引に限定するものとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, as to Nishu gin silver coins, which contained about four thirds of silver in spite of its half face value compared with ichibu-gin, the bakufu decided to limit the use of those coins to international trade because it could not emit a large quantity of good money, accustomed to emitting bad money for the purpose of acquiring marginal gain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, as Nishu gin silver coins contained about four thirds of silver in spite that its face value was half of ichibu-gin silver, the bakufu decided to limit the use of those coins to international trade because it could not emit a large quantity of good money, accustomed to emitting bad money for the purpose of acquiring marginal gain.</e>
<cmt>前半を言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, as Nishu gin silver coins contained about four thirds of silver in spite that its face value was half of ichibu-gin silver, the bakufu decided to limit the use of those coins to international trade because it could not emit a large quantity of good money, accustomed to emitting bad money for the purpose of acquiring marginal gain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>またこの二朱銀を鋳造するために必要な銀を賄うために、銀品位を下げた安政丁銀を発行することになったといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that the bakufu had to emit Ansei Chogin with its quality of silver lowered, in order to secure the sufficient amount of silver required to mint the Nishu gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the bakufu had to emit Ansei Chogin with its quality of silver lowered, in order to secure the sufficient amount of silver required to mint the Nishu gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the bakufu had to emit Ansei Chogin with its quality of silver lowered, in order to secure the sufficient amount of silver required to mint the Nishu gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>しかし安政丁銀の発行は安政二朱銀の鋳造停止後の同年12月27日であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Ansei Chogin was emitted on December 27 in the sixth year of Ansei era, after mintage of Ansei Nishu silver coins was terminated that year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Ansei Chogin was emitted on January 19, 1860, after mintage of Ansei Nishu silver coins was terminated.</e>
<cmt>「安政6年12月27日」をグレゴリオ暦に変換しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Ansei Chogin was emitted on January 19, 1860, after mintage of Ansei Nishu silver coins was terminated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>開港場では6月2日より1ドル銀貨との引き換えが始まったが、この二朱銀は開港場のみでしか通用せず、もともと日本国内全般に含有銀量の多い二朱銀を流通させることが困難であり、一般に流通しているのは依然一分銀であったため、国内では一分銀に両替しないと通用しないと定められた大凡貨幣としての機能を欠くものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These Nishu gin silver coins started to be exchanged with one-dollar silver coins at the opened port area on June 2, but they could be used only in the opened port area and lacked functions of a common currency because they had to be exchanged into ichibu-gin silver coins for domestic use, for it was difficult to distribute Nishu gin silver coins, which contained comparatively much silver, all over Japan in the first place, and ichibu-gin silver coins were still generally in circulation.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These Nishu gin silver coins started to be exchanged with one-dollar silver coins at treaty ports on June 2, but they could be used only in those ports and lacked functions of a common currency because they had to be exchanged into ichibu-gin silver coins for domestic use, for it was difficult to distribute Nishu gin silver coins, which contained comparatively much silver, all over Japan in the first place, and ichibu-gin silver coins were still generally in circulation.</e>
<cmt>「開港場」：treaty port</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These Nishu gin silver coins started to be exchanged with one-dollar silver coins at treaty ports on June 2, but they could be used only in those ports and lacked functions of a common currency because they had to be exchanged into ichibu-gin silver coins for domestic use, for it was difficult to distribute Nishu gin silver coins, which contained comparatively much silver, all over Japan in the first place, and ichibu-gin silver coins were still generally in circulation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>交換された貨幣が日本国内において一般に流通するものではなく、かつ1ドル銀貨の日本国内での購買力を1/3に低下させるというこの政策にハリスおよびラザフォード・オールコックら外国人大使は条約違反であると強く抗議し、6月22日、幕府は手落ちを認め以後は1ドル銀貨を一分銀3枚で引き換えるよう開港場奉行に申し渡し翌23日に通用が停止された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Such Japanese policies, in which one-dollar silver coins were exchanged with coins which were not generally circulated in Japan and the buying strength of one-dollar coins in Japan was lowered to one-third, provoked harsh protests from foreign commanders-in-chef including HARRIS and Rutherford ALCOCK, who insisted that such policies violated the treaty, and so the bakufu, admitting its mistake, ordered kaikojo-bugyo (magistrate in charge of the opened port area) to exchange a one-dollar silver coin with three ichibu-gin silver coins on June 22, and terminated circulation of Ansei Nishu silver coins on the next day, June 23.</e>
<cmt>定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Such Japanese policies, in which one-dollar silver coins were exchanged with coins which were not generally circulated in Japan and the buying strength of one-dollar coins in Japan was lowered to one-third, provoked harsh protests from foreign ambassadors including HARRIS and Rutherford ALCOCK, who insisted that such policies violated the treaty, and so the bakufu, admitting its mistake, ordered kaikojo-bugyo (commissioner of treaty port) to exchange a one-dollar silver coin with three ichibu-gin silver coins from June 22, and terminated circulation of Ansei Nishu silver coins on the next day, June 23.</e>
<cmt>「大使」：ambassador、「開港場奉行」：commissioner of treaty portに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Such Japanese policies, in which one-dollar silver coins were exchanged with coins which were not generally circulated in Japan and the buying strength of one-dollar coins in Japan was lowered to one-third, provoked harsh protests from foreign ambassadors including HARRIS and Rutherford ALCOCK, who insisted that such policies violated the treaty, and so the bakufu, admitting its mistake, ordered kaikojo-bugyo (commissioner of treaty port) to exchange a one-dollar silver coin with three ichibu-gin silver coins from June 22, and terminated circulation of Ansei Nishu silver coins on the next day, June 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>したがって安政二朱銀の通用は僅か22日間で終わり、安政小判についても4ヶ月足らずで鋳造停止となるに至った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thus Ansei Nishu silver coins circulated only for twenty-two days, and Ansei koban was minted only for less than four months.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus Ansei Nishu silver coins circulated only for twenty-two days, and Ansei koban was minted only for less than four months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus Ansei Nishu silver coins circulated only for twenty-two days, and Ansei koban was minted only for less than four months.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="32">
<j>このため外国人大使は1ドル銀貨をまず一分銀3枚に交換し、両替商に持ち込んで4枚を小判に両替して、国外に持ち出し地金として売却すれば莫大な利益が得られるというものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, foreign commanders-in-chief could make a large profit by first exchanging a one-dollar silver coin into three ichibu-gin silver coins, further exchanging four ichibu-gin silver coins into koban at ryogaesho (money exchangers), taking koban out of Japan and selling them as bare metal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, foreign ambassadors could make a large profit by first exchanging a one-dollar silver coin into three ichibu-gin silver coins, further exchanging four ichibu-gin silver coins into koban at ryogaesho (money exchangers), taking koban out of Japan and selling them as bare metal.</e>
<cmt>「大使」：ambassadorに変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, foreign ambassadors could make a large profit by first exchanging a one-dollar silver coin into three ichibu-gin silver coins, further exchanging four ichibu-gin silver coins into koban at ryogaesho (money exchangers), taking koban out of Japan and selling them as bare metal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="33">
<j>しかし、グレシャムの法則が働き良貨である小判の鋳造量は衰退し、市場では悪貨である二朱金および一分銀のような名目貨幣が凌駕するような状態であったため、一分銀から小判への両替には大幅な増歩が要求された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on the Gresham&apos;s law, however, the amount of mintage of koban, which was good money, was decreased and nominal coins such as Nishu kin gold and ichibu-gin silver coins, which were bad money, prevailed in the market, so a great amount of premium was demanded for an exchange of ichibu-gin coins into koban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on the Gresham&apos;s law, however, the amount of mintage of koban, which was good money, was decreased and nominal coins such as Nishu kin gold and ichibu-gin silver coins, which were bad money, prevailed in the market, so a great amount of premium was demanded for an exchange of ichibu-gin coins into koban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on the Gresham&apos;s law, however, the amount of mintage of koban, which was good money, was decreased and nominal coins such as Nishu kin gold and ichibu-gin silver coins, which were bad money, prevailed in the market, so a great amount of premium was demanded for an exchange of ichibu-gin coins into koban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>また外国人の1ドル銀貨から一分銀への両替要求が多額に上ったため、開港場では一分銀は瞬く間に払底した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, ichibu-gin silver coins got scarce at the opened port area in no time because foreigners demanded exchanges of so much an amount of one-dollar silver coins into ichibu-gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, ichibu-gin silver coins got scarce at the treaty ports in no time because foreigners demanded exchanges of so many one-dollar silver coins into ichibu-gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt>「開港場」「多額」を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, ichibu-gin silver coins got scarce at the treaty ports in no time because foreigners demanded exchanges of so many one-dollar silver coins into ichibu-gin silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>それでも小判の流出は短期間の間に多額に上り国内の深刻な金貨の不足を起こすような危機には違いなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, so large a quantity of koban was taken out of Japan in so short a time that there was a serious shortage of gold coins in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, so large a quantity of koban was taken out of Japan in so short a time that there was a serious shortage of gold coins in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, so large a quantity of koban was taken out of Japan in so short a time that there was a serious shortage of gold coins in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>外国人大使らは一年間にこのような両替を5～6サイクル程繰り返し、利益を上げることが可能であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that foreign commanders-in-chief could make profits by repeating such cycles of exchange five to six times a year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that foreign ambassadors could make profits by repeating such cycles of exchange five to six times a year.</e>
<cmt>「大使」を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that foreign ambassadors could make profits by repeating such cycles of exchange five to six times a year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="37">
<j>一分銀払底の打開策として7月29日に、ハリスはメキシコ銀および1ドル銀貨を一分銀に改鋳することを提案した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a solution to the scarcity of ichibu-gin silver coins, HARRIS proposed to remint Mexico silver and one-dollar silver coins into ichibu-gin silver coins on July 29.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a solution to the scarcity of ichibu-gin silver coins, HARRIS proposed to remint Mexico silver and one-dollar silver coins into ichibu-gin silver coins on July 29.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a solution to the scarcity of ichibu-gin silver coins, HARRIS proposed to remint Mexico silver and one-dollar silver coins into ichibu-gin silver coins on July 29.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これを受け入れ8月13日より発行されたのが銀品位が洋銀と同一の一分銀安政一分銀であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu accepted this proposal and started to emit Ansei ichibu-gin silver coins, which contained the same quality of silver as foreign ones, on August 13.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu accepted this proposal and started to emit Ansei ichibu-gin silver coins, which contained the same quality of silver as foreign ones, on August 13.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu accepted this proposal and started to emit Ansei ichibu-gin silver coins, which contained the same quality of silver as foreign ones, on August 13.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>しかし全く小判流出防止に効果を果たすものではなく、むしろ流出を促進させたものといえる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But these coins did not prevent the drain of koban to foreign countries; they accelerated the drain instead.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But these coins did not prevent but rather accelerated the outflow of koban to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>「流出」をoutflowに言い換えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But these coins did not prevent but rather accelerated the outflow of koban to foreign countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="40">
<j>安政一分銀の発行によっても貿易港周辺の市中における一分銀の払底は解消されず、ハリスは幕府に対し一分銀の早急な増鋳を要求したが、発行は思うように進捗せず、洋銀に刻印を打って、三分として通用させるよう要求した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The scarcity of ichibu-gin silver coins in cities around the trading port was not improved by issuance of Ansei ichibu-gin silver coins, so HARRIS requested the bakufu to increase mintage of ichibu-gin silver coins in a prompt manner, but they were not emitted so promptly; thus HARRIS requested the bakufu to engrave a mark on foreign silver coins and to make them circulate as 3bu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The scarcity of ichibu-gin silver coins in cities around the trading port was not improved by issuance of Ansei ichibu-gin silver coins, so HARRIS requested the bakufu to increase mintage of ichibu-gin silver coins in a prompt manner, but they were not emitted so promptly; thus HARRIS requested the bakufu to engrave a mark on foreign silver coins and to make them circulate as 3 bu.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The scarcity of ichibu-gin silver coins in cities around the trading port was not improved by issuance of Ansei ichibu-gin silver coins, so HARRIS requested the bakufu to increase mintage of ichibu-gin silver coins in a prompt manner, but they were not emitted so promptly; thus HARRIS requested the bakufu to engrave a mark on foreign silver coins and to make them circulate as 3 bu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>ここで登場したのが、メキシコ8レアル銀貨などに「改三分定」と刻印を打印した改三分定銀であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is how &quot;Aratame-sanbu-sada&quot; gin (silver coins revised to 3bu) were created, by engraving a mark &quot;Aratame-sanbu-sada&quot; on Mexican eight-real silver coins.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is how &quot;Aratame-sanbu-sada&quot; gin (silver coins revised to 3 bu) were created, by engraving a mark &quot;Aratame-sanbu-sada&quot; on Mexican 8-real silver coins.</e>
<cmt>数字表記とスペースを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is how &quot;Aratame-sanbu-sada&quot; gin (silver coins revised to 3 bu) were created, by engraving a mark &quot;Aratame-sanbu-sada&quot; on Mexican 8-real silver coins.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>しかし日本国内ではこの改三分定銀は2分2朱にしか通用せず、刻印打は安政6年（1859年）12月29日より開始されたが翌年の万延元年（1860年）5月12日までの短期間で中断された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But these Aratame-sanbu-sada gin silver coins were worth only 2bu 2shu in Japan, and the engraving operation, which was started on December 29, 1859, was terminated on as early as May 12, 1860.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But these Aratame-sanbu-sada gin silver coins were worth only 2 bu 2 shu in Japan, and the engraving operation, which was started on January 21, 1860, was terminated on as early as June 30, 1860.</e>
<cmt>スペースを修正し、グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But these Aratame-sanbu-sada gin silver coins were worth only 2 bu 2 shu in Japan, and the engraving operation, which was started on January 21, 1860, was terminated on as early as June 30, 1860.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="43">
<j>その後イギリス総領事のオールコックは著書『大君の都』の中で日本の本位貨幣である天保小判が金貨4ドル分の金を含有し、一分銀には素材価値以上の価値が設定されていたことにより金貨流出につながったことを認めているが、それは小判の大量流出が起こった後のことであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, an English consul general ALCOCK, in his book &quot;Okimi no Miyako&quot; (the capital of the tycoon), admitted that gold coins were poured out of Japan because a value higher than that of raw materials was attached to ichibu-gin silver coins while Tenpo koban, Japanese standard coins, contained the same amount of gold as gold coins worth four dollars, but it was after the massive outpouring of koban.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, an English consul general ALCOCK, in his book &quot;Okimi no Miyako&quot; (the capital of the tycoon), admitted that gold coins were poured out of Japan because a value higher than that of raw materials was attached to ichibu-gin silver coins while Tenpo koban, Japanese standard coins, contained the same amount of gold as gold coins worth four dollars, but it was after the massive outpouring of koban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, an English consul general ALCOCK, in his book &quot;Okimi no Miyako&quot; (the capital of the tycoon), admitted that gold coins were poured out of Japan because a value higher than that of raw materials was attached to ichibu-gin silver coins while Tenpo koban, Japanese standard coins, contained the same amount of gold as gold coins worth four dollars, but it was after the massive outpouring of koban.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 220.xx.xx.xx(id:109329), Ligar(id:12623), As6022014(id:214263), Blue sapphire(id:130304), Peehyoro Acala(id:170), BAKU(id:55205), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>