<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>嘉吉の徳政一揆</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokusei uprising in Kakitsu era</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokusei uprising in Kakitsu era</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokusei uprising during the Kakitsu era</e>
<cmt>次の項でこの表現を使っているので統一しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>嘉吉の徳政一揆（かきつのとくせいいっき）は、嘉吉元年（1441年）に徳政令を求めて京都及び近江国など周辺地域で発生した土一揆のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokusei uprising in Kakitsu era was a peasant&apos;s uprising for demanding Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) occurred in Kyoto and its environs such as the Omi Province in 1441(the first year of the Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokusei uprising during the Kakitsu era was a peasant uprising to demand Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) and occurred in Kyoto and its surroundings such as the Omi Province in 1441(the first year of the Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokusei uprising during the Kakitsu era was a peasant uprising to demand Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts) and occurred in Kyoto and its surroundings such as the Omi Province in 1441(the first year of the Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>嘉吉の土一揆（かきつのつちいっき）とも。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called the peasant uprising of Kakitsu era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called the peasant uprising of Kakitsu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called the peasant uprising of Kakitsu era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>六月の嘉吉の乱で将軍足利義教が殺されると政治的混乱の中「代初めの徳政」を求めて（天下一同の徳政令）京都近江坂本の馬借を中心に農民が蜂起、地侍が指導し、数万人の一揆にふくれあがった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the political turmoil after the assassination of Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in the Kakitsu War, the farming population lead by bashaku (shipping agents who used horses) in Omi Sakamoto in Kyoto rose up in rebellion for demanding &quot;daihajime-no-tokusei (acts of virtuous government requested at shogun replacement)&quot; (Tenkaichido no Tokseirei (a debt cancellation order for all throughout the country)), which was directed by jizamurai (local samurai) and swelled to scores of thousands of peoples&apos; uprising.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the political turmoil after the assassination of Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in the Kakitsu War, the farming population lead by bashaku (shipping agents who used horses) in Omi Sakamoto in Kyoto rose up in rebellion to demand &quot;daihajime-no-tokusei (acts of virtuous government requested at shogun replacement)&quot; (Tenkaichido no Tokseirei (a debt cancellation order for all throughout the country)), which was directed by jizamurai (local samurai) and lead to an uprising by thousands upon thousands of people.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the political turmoil after the assassination of Shogun Yoshinori ASHIKAGA in the Kakitsu War, the farming population lead by bashaku (shipping agents who used horses) in Omi Sakamoto in Kyoto rose up in rebellion to demand &apos;daihajime-no-tokusei (acts of virtuous government requested at shogun replacement)&apos; (Tenkaichido no Tokuseirei (a debt cancellation order for all throughout the country)), which was directed by jizamurai (local samurai) and lead to an uprising by tens of thousands of people.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;→&apos; &apos;Tokseirei→Tokuseireithousands upon thousands→tens of thousands</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>各地への波及はなく、京都を包囲する形をとった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It encircled Kyoto and did not affect other provinces.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The uprisings mainly enveloped Kyoto, but not the surrounding regions.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The uprisings mainly enveloped Kyoto, but not the surrounding regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>一揆の流れ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Flow of the uprising</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Events leading up to the uprising</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Events leading up to the uprising</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>六月　義教暗殺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June Yoshinori was assassinated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June Yoshinori was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June: Yoshinori was assassinated.</e>
<cmt>日付の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>八月　近江の馬借蜂起、守護六角氏が徳政令発布。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August Bashaku in Omi rose up in rebellion, and the Rokkaku clan, shugo (provincial constable), promulgated Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August Bashaku in Omi rose up in rebellion, and the Rokkaku clan, shugo (provincial constable), promulgated Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August: Bashaku in Omi rose up in rebellion, and the Rokkaku clan, shugo (provincial constable), promulgated Tokuseirei.</e>
<cmt>日付の表記変更</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>九月　東寺、北野社の占拠及び丹波口、西八条の封鎖。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September To-ji Temple and Kitano-sha Shrine were occupied, and Tambaguchi and Nishi-hachijo were blocked.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September To-ji Temple and Kitano-sha Shrine were occupied, and Tambaguchi and Nishi-hachijo were blocked.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September: To-ji Temple and Kitano-sha Shrine were occupied, and Tanbaguchi and Nishi-hachijo were blocked.</e>
<cmt>日付の表記変更&quot;Tambaguchi&quot; -&gt; &quot;Tanbaguchi&quot; に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>延暦寺が徳政令に反対した事から同支配下の近江の馬借が一揆から離反・敵対するも、一揆は更に清水寺占拠。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Enryaku-ji Temple opposed the promulgation of Tokuseirei and bashaku in Omi ruled by Enryaku-ji Temple broke away from the uprising and fought against the uprising, though the uprising further occupied Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Enryaku-ji Temple opposed the promulgation of Tokuseirei, causing bashaku in Omi ruled by Enryaku-ji Temple to break away from the uprising, even turning against it as the uprising further occupied Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Enryaku-ji Temple opposed the promulgation of Tokuseirei, causing bashaku in Omi ruled by Enryaku-ji Temple to break away from the uprising, even turning against it as the uprising further occupied Kiyomizu-dera Temple.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="9">
<j>一揆軍は京都と外部の連絡を断った上で、酒屋、土倉、寺院を襲撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army of the uprising cut off communication between Kyoto and outside areas, and then attacked sake shops, doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders), and temples.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army of uprisers cut off communication between Kyoto and outside areas, and then attacked sake shops, doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders), and temples.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army of uprisers cut off communication between Kyoto and outside areas, and then attacked sake shops, doso (pawnbrokers and moneylenders), and temples.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>一揆勢は地侍の指導の下、組織的な行動をとり、勝手な略奪を取り締まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Directed by jizamurai, the force of the uprising act orderly and kept surveillance over wild robbery.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the direction of the jizamurai, order was brought to the uprising forces, while robberies were monitored.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the direction of the jizamurai, order was brought to the uprising forces, while robberies were monitored.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>また幕府が当初、農民に限定した徳政令を発布して事態の収拾に乗り出したのに対し、公家や武家も含む一国平均の徳政令を要求し、支配者層の支持をも得ようとしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the shogunate which set out to settle the situation by promulgating Tokuseirei exclusively for the farming population, the uprising force demanded Tokuseirei promulgated throughout the country including the court nobles and samurai in order to obtain support from the ruling classes.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the shogunate which set out to settle the situation by spreading Tokuseirei exclusively for the farming population, the uprisers demanded that Tokuseirei be issued throughout the country including the court nobles and samurai in order to obtain support from the ruling classes.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the shogunate which set out to settle the situation by spreading Tokuseirei exclusively for the farming population, the uprisers demanded that Tokuseirei be issued throughout the country including the court nobles and samurai in order to obtain support from the ruling classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>さらに、管領細川持之が土倉から賄賂一千貫を貰って保護の為に、出兵命令を出したという事実を知った守護大名は出兵を拒否。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) who had learned that kanrei (shogunal deputy) Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA ordered to dispatch troops to protect doso in exchange of a thousand kan of bribery from the doso rejected to dispatch the troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) who had learned that kanrei (shogunal deputy) Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA ordered that troops be dispatched to protect the doso in exchange for a thousand kan bribe from the doso, blocked the dispatch of the troops.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, shugo daimyo (Japanese territorial lord as provincial constable) who had learned that kanrei (shogunal deputy) Mochiyuki HOSOKAWA ordered that troops be dispatched to protect the doso in exchange for 1,000 kan bribe from the doso, blocked the dispatch of the troops.</e>
<cmt>a thousand→1,000</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>事態はさらに混乱した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The situation had further confused.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The situation fell into a further state of confusion.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The situation fell into a further state of confusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>新将軍足利義勝は要求を受け入れ、差し押さえられてから20年未満の質物の返還など、山城一国平均での徳政令を発布（嘉吉の徳政令）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The new shogun Yoshikatsu ASHIKAGA accepted the demand and promulgated Tokuseirei throughout the country which ordered the return of the things that had been pawned no more than twenty years (Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The new shogun Yoshikatsu ASHIKAGA accepted the demand and issued Tokuseirei throughout the country which ordered the return of things that had been pawned no more than twenty years prior (Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The new shogun Yoshikatsu ASHIKAGA accepted the demand and issued Tokuseirei throughout the Yamashiro Province which ordered the return of things that had been pawned no more than 20 years prior (Order for the Acts of Virtuous Government in Kakitsu era).</e>
<cmt>twenty→20「山城一国平均で」とあるので country を Yamashiro Province に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>正長の土一揆では遂に公式な徳政令を出さなかった室町幕府が徳政令を出したことにより、その権威は大きく傷ついた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Muromachi shogunate which had not issued official Tokuseirei against the peasant uprising of Shocho era at all was forced to promulgate Tokuseirei this time, which significantly damaged the prestige of the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Muromachi shogunate which had not issued official Tokuseirei against the peasant uprising of the Shocho era was forced to issue Tokuseirei this time, which significantly damaged the prestige of the government.</e>
<cmt>Edited for flow</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Muromachi bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which had not issued official Tokuseirei against the peasant uprising of the Shocho era was forced to issue Tokuseirei this time, which significantly damaged the prestige of the government.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 でここ(id:9565), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), 玄史生(id:43670), 水野白楓(id:22811), Udon-ya(id:48431), Yosemite(id:5808), LERK(id:4460), 幣原外交(id:97257), 彩華1226(id:64711), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>