<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>日清戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sino-Japanese War; Japanese-Sino War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sino-Japanese War; Japanese-Sino War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sino-Japanese War; Japanese-Sino War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>日清戦争（にっしんせんそう、中国語甲午戦争、第一次中日戦争、英語）は、1894年（明治27年）7月から1895年（明治28年）4月にかけて行われた主に朝鮮王朝をめぐる大日本帝国と清の戦争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-Sino War (Kogo war in Chinese, First Sino-Japanese war in English) is a war fought between Empire of Japan and Quing Dynasty over Korean Dynasties from July 1894 through April 1895.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese-Sino War (Kogo war in Chinese, First Sino-Japanese war in English) is a war fought between the Empire of Japan and the Quing Dynasty over Korean Dynasties from July 1894 through April 1895.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese-Sino War (Kogo war in Chinese, First Sino-Japanese war in English) is a war fought between the Empire of Japan and the Quing Dynasty over Korean Dynasties from July 1894 through April 1895.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>日本での正式名称は明治二十七八年戦役（めいじにじゅうしちはちねん せんえき）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The war was formally named Meiji nijyuhachinen sen-eki (military campaign in the 28th year of Meiji Period) in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The war was formally named Meiji nijyuhachinen sen-eki (military campaign in the twenty-eighth year of the Meiji Period) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The war was formally named Meiji niju-shichi-hachinen sen-eki (military campaign in the twenty-seventh and twenty-eighth years of the Meiji Period) in Japan.</e>
<cmt>「明治二十七八年戦役」の二十七の部分が抜けていましたので訳を入れました。また、&quot;jyu&quot;を&quot;ju&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>戦争目的と動機</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Purpose and motive of the war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Purpose and motive of the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Purpose and motive of the war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>大日本帝国 『清国ニ対スル宣戦ノ詔勅』では朝鮮の独立と改革の推進、東洋全局の平和などが唱われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The imperial prescript of Empire of Japan advocates the cause to promote independence and reform of Korea, peace of the entire East, and so forth.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The imperial prescript of Empire of Japan advocates the cause to promote independence and reform of Korea and peace of the entire East.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The imperial prescript of Empire of Japan advocates the cause to promote independence and reform of Korea and peace of the entire East.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>一方、それは名目であり、実際は朝鮮を自国の影響下におくことや中国の領土割譲など自国権益の拡大を目的とした戦争とする説もある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some suggest, however, that Japan used this cause as a pretext of the war trying to achieve the purpose of putting Korea under control and expanding its own interests by making China cessede its territory.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some suggest, however, that Japan used this cause as a pretext for the war trying to achieve the purpose of putting Korea under control and expanding its own interests by making China give up its territory.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some suggest, however, that Japan used this cause as a pretext for the war trying to achieve the purpose of putting Korea under control and expanding its own interests by making China give up its territory.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>清国</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>アジア諸国の西欧列強による植民地化と日本による朝鮮王朝の開国と干渉に刺激された結果、清国と朝鮮の関係を伝統的な宗属関係から近代的な宗主国と属国の関係（宗主国と植民地の関係）に改めて朝鮮を自勢力下に留めようとした戦争。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As western powers colonized Asian countries and Japan forced Korean to open the country to the world and intervened in it, Qing, as the result, was spurred into using this war to try to transform the conventional relationship between Qing and Korea based on the concept of a family of the same origin into a modern suzerain-dependency relationship (suzerain-colony relationship) and keep Korea under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As western powers colonized Asian countries and Japan forced Korea to open the country to the world and intervene in it, Qing, as a result, was spurred into using this war to try to transform the conventional relationship between Qing and Korea based upon a concept of a family with the same origin into a modern suzerain-dependency relationship (suzerain-colony relationship) and keep Korea under control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As western powers colonized Asian countries and Japan forced Korea to open the country to the world and intervene in it, Qing, as a result, was spurred into using this war to try to transform the conventional relationship between Qing and Korea based upon a concept of a family with the same origin into a modern suzerain-dependency relationship (suzerain-colony relationship) and keep Korea under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>前史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prehistory</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prehistory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prehistory</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>日清戦争は明治維新後近代国家形成をめざす日本と1860年代から洋務運動による近代化を進める中国(清朝)との間で行われた、朝鮮等をめぐる両者の全面戦争である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese-Sino War was a total war over Korea and so forth between Japan aiming at the creation of a modern state after Mieji Restoration and China (the quing dynasty) in the process of modernization since Western Affair Movement in the 1860&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese-Sino War was a total war over Korea between Japan, aiming at the creation of a modern state after the Mieji Restoration, and China (the quing dynasty), in the process of modernization since the Western Affairs Movement in the 1860&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese-Sino War was a total war over Korea between Japan, aiming at the creation of a modern state after the Meiji Restoration, and China (the quing dynasty), in the process of modernization since the Western Affairs Movement in the 1860&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>MiejiをMeijiに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>また歴史的にも日中間の大規模かつ長期に渡る戦争としては最初のものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is historically the first as a large-scale and long lasting war between Japan and china.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is historically the first battle of a large-scale and long lasting war between Japan and china.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is historically the first battle of a large-scale and long lasting war between Japan and china.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="11">
<j>古代朝鮮三国時代 (朝鮮半島)の百済復興のための新羅・唐連合軍との白村江における敗戦、元 (王朝)朝およびそれに服属する高麗による元冦と豊臣秀吉の朝鮮出兵を除けば、これらの三国間で日本が関係した戦争は歴史上きわめて少ない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Historically, there were quite a few wars among three countries that Japan was involved in, except for a defeat in Hakusonko (Battle of Baekgang) in the battle with Silla-Tang allied forces over the revival of Baekje during the three Kingdoms period (of Korean history) of ancient Korea, Genko (Mongol Invasions of Japan) by Yuan (Dynasty) and Goryeo under its control, and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s invasion into Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historically, there were quite a few wars among three countries that Japan was involved in, except for a defeat in Hakusonko (Battle of Baekgang) in the battle with Silla-Tang allied forces over the revival of Baekje during the three Kingdoms period (of Korean history) of ancient Korea, Genko (Mongol Invasions of Japan) by Yuan (Dynasty) and Goryeo under its control, and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s invasion of Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historically, there were just a few wars among three countries that Japan was involved in, except for a defeat in Hakusonko (Battle of Baekgang) in the battle with Silla-Tang allied forces over the revival of Baekje during the three Kingdoms period (of Korean history) of ancient Korea, Genko (Mongol Invasions of Japan) by Yuan (Dynasty) and Goryeo under its control, and Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI&apos;s invasion of Korea.</e>
<cmt>quite a few&apos;は「相当な数の、極めて多い」という意味で原文と意味が反対ですので修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>それはこれらの三国が古墳時代以来朝鮮半島の国々を経て日本に伝播してきた漢字、儒教、仏教、律令制などの文化を共有したことによる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is partly because the three countries have shared cultures, including kanji (Chinese characters), Confucianism, Buddhism, the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), which have been introduced into Japan through countries in Korean Peninsula since the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is partly because the three countries have shared cultures, including kanji (Chinese characters), Confucianism, Buddhism, the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), which had been introduced into Japan through countries on the Korean Peninsula since the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is partly because the three countries have shared cultures, including kanji (Chinese characters), Confucianism, Buddhism, the ritsuryo system (a system of centralized government based on the ritsuryo code), which had been introduced into Japan through countries on the Korean Peninsula since the Kofun period (tumulus period).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>さらに巨大な帝国だった中国諸王朝が中華思想、華夷秩序に基づいて周辺諸国を冊封して朝貢関係を築き、それが経済交流と外交秩序の一定の安定を東アジアにもたらしたことにもよる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Another reason is sovereign-vassal relationship with tributes between Chinese dynasties, great empires, and surrounding countries based on Sinocentrism and Suzerainty, which brought East Asia economic exchanges and a certain stability of diplomatic orders.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another reason is the sovereign-vassal relationship with tributes between Chinese dynasties, great empires, and surrounding countries based on Sinocentrism and Suzerainty, that brought economic exchanges and a certain stability of diplomatic orders to East Asia.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another reason is the sovereign-vassal relationship with tributes between Chinese dynasties, great empires, and surrounding countries based on Sinocentrism and Suzerainty, that brought economic exchanges and a certain stability of diplomatic orders to East Asia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>満州の女真族が建てた後金が国号を清と改め1644年北京に遷都した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokin established by the Joshin tribe in Manchuria change its name of the country into Qing and transferred the capital to Beijing in 1644.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokin established by the Joshin tribe in Manchuria change its name of the country into Qing and transferred the capital to Beijing in 1644.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokin established by the Joshin tribe in Manchuria change its name of the country into Qing and transferred the capital to Beijing in 1644.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>やがて広大な領土支配のため北部と西部方面の辺境地域を藩部とし南のネパール、ビルマ、シャム、越南(ベトナム)、東の朝鮮及び琉球（なお琉球は日本側とも冊封関係にあった）を冊封して清を中心とする国際秩序をアジアに構築、北辺ではシベリアに進出したロシア帝国との間に条約を締結して国境を漸次確定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The dynasty soon established an international order in Asia with Qing as the center by joining northern and western remote regions as its provinces and had its vassal system with Nepal, Burma, Siam, Vietnam in the south and korea and Ryukyu Islands (although ryukyu had also a peerage relationship with Japan) in the east, and temporarily defined its northern border by concluding a treaty with the Russian Empire that had advanced into Syberia.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The dynasty soon established an international order in Asia with Qing as the center by joining northern and western remote regions as its provinces and had its vassal system with Nepal, Burma, Siam, and Vietnam in the south and korea and Ryukyu Islands (although ryukyu had also a peerage relationship with Japan) in the east, and temporarily defined its northern border by concluding a treaty with the Russian Empire that had advanced into Siberia.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The dynasty soon established an international order in Asia with Qing as the center by joining northern and western remote regions as its provinces and had its vassal system with Nepal, Burma, Siam, and Vietnam in the south and Korea and Ryukyu Islands (although ryukyu had also a peerage relationship with Japan) in the east, and temporarily defined its northern border by concluding a treaty with the Russian Empire that had advanced into Siberia.</e>
<cmt>koreaをKoreaに訂正しました。単語間全角を半角スペースに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>朝鮮王朝は1392年李成桂が高麗を滅ぼし建国。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Korean Dynasty was established when Seong-gye YI defeated Goryeo in 1392.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean Dynasty was established when Seong-gye YI defeated Goryeo in 1392.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean Dynasty was established when Seong-gye YI defeated Goryeo in 1392.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>のちに明の冊封を受け明にならい朱子学を国教とし科挙を実施、官僚制中央集権国家を形成する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In later years, the Dynasty, after having its vassal system with the Ming dynasty, adopted the doctrines of Zhu Xi; Neo-Confucianism as its state religion following Ming. and conducted Kakyo/Keju (examinations for Chinese state bureaucrats) to form its burocratic centralized government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In later years, the Dynasty, after having its vassal system with the Ming dynasty, adopted the doctrines of Zhu Xi; Neo-Confucianism as its state religion following Ming. and conducted Kakyo/Keju (examinations for Chinese state bureaucrats) to form its bureaucratic centralized government.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In later years, the Dynasty, after having its vassal system with the Ming dynasty, adopted the doctrines of Zhu Xi; Neo-Confucianism as its state religion following Ming and conducted Kakyo/Keju (examinations for Chinese state bureaucrats) to form its bureaucratic centralized government.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドを修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>その過程で科挙に合格し官僚を独占し世襲化する両班制が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During this process, the yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty) was established in which bureaucrats who succeeded in Kakyo monopolized the bureaucratic positions by inheritance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During this process, the yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty) was established where bureaucrats who succeeded in Kakyo monopolized the bureaucratic positions by inheritance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During this process, the yangban (traditional ruling class or nobles of dynastic Korea during the Joseon Dynasty) was established where bureaucrats who succeeded in Kakyo monopolized the bureaucratic positions by inheritance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>明が清にかわると朝鮮国王に「三跪九叩頭の礼」を強いるなど冊封国としての関係を強めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Qing dynasty replaced Ming dynasty, it forced the Korean dynasty to do the courtesy of &quot;nine kowtows&quot; to strengthen the relationship under the vassal system.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When the Qing dynasty replaced the Ming dynasty, it forced the Korean dynasty to perform the courtesy of &quot;nine kowtows&quot; to strengthen the relationship under the vassal system.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When the Qing dynasty replaced the Ming dynasty, it forced the Korean dynasty to perform the courtesy of &quot;nine kowtows&quot; to strengthen the relationship under the vassal system.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="20">
<j>秀吉の朝鮮出兵は「鼻を削いで首にかえよ」という残虐な侵略戦であったため長く朝鮮民衆の間にその非道が語り継がれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion into Korea was a war of cruel aggression and a story of cruel acts as shown in his order to &quot;cut the nose instead of the head&quot; to show feats were long handed down from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion into Korea was a war of cruel aggression and a story of cruel acts as shown in his order to &quot;cut off the nose instead of the head&quot; as a reminder passed down from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hideyoshi&apos;s invasion into Korea was a war of cruel aggression and a story of cruel acts as shown in his order to &apos;cut off the nose instead of the head&apos; as a reminder passed down from generation to generation.</e>
<cmt>半角スペースを全角に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>徳川幕府は朝鮮王朝と対馬の宗氏の間に1609年己酉約条を結ばせ交易を再開、また朝鮮通信使と日本国王使の往来によりおおむね対等な関係を構築した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa shogunate started again trade with the Korean dynasty by concluding Giyu treaty with the So clan of Tsushima Island in 1609 and established a relationship of almost equality through mutual visits of Korean messengers and Japanese envoys.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa shogunate started trading again with the Korean dynasty by concluding the Giyu treaty with the So clan of Tsushima Island in 1609 and established a relationship of almost equality through mutual visits of Korean messengers and Japanese envoys.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa shogunate started trading again with the Korean dynasty by concluding the Giyu treaty with the So clan of Tsushima Island in 1609 and established a relationship of almost equality through mutual visits of Korean messengers and Japanese envoys.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>他方清との間ではその冊封を受けず限られた貿易のみを容認した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Tokugawa shogunate did not have Sakuho relation with Qing dynasty and allowed limited trade</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tokugawa shogunate did not have a Sakuho relationship with Qing dynasty and allowed limited trade</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tokugawa shogunate did not have a Sakuho relationship with Qing dynasty and allowed limited trade.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>禁教令の徹底などを目的に1630年代の鎖国令によってオランダとの交易を除き西欧諸国との関係も途絶させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">it also broke relations with western countries except Holland by issuing a national seclusion order with an aim to put a complete ban on Christianity.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">it also broke relations with western countries except for Holland by issuing a national seclusion order with an aim to put a complete ban on Christianity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It also broke relations with western countries except for Holland by issuing a national seclusion order with an aim to put a complete ban on Christianity.</e>
<cmt>文頭を大文字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="24">
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>19世紀なかばから東アジア世界に西欧列強による脅威が迫ってきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">East Asia had been faced threats of Western powers since the middle of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">East Asia had been facing threats from Western powers since the middle of the nineteenth century.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">East Asia had been facing threats from Western powers since the middle of the 19th century.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトをアラビア数字に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>清はそれまで広州一港に貿易を限っていたがイギリス(大英帝国)は1840年と1857年のアヘン戦争および第二次アヘン戦争により南京条約(1842年)、天津条約(1858年)および北京条約(1860年)を結び多額の賠償金と香港、九竜半島の割譲、上海など11港の開港と領事裁判権の承認、関税自主権の喪失、片務的最恵国待遇、公使の北京駐在、キリスト教の公認と保護などを清に認めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Qing dynasty had allowed foreign trade only in Canton port, Britain (the British Empire) concluded treaties of Nanjing (in 1482), Tianjin (in 1858), and Beijing (in 1860) after First Opium War and the Second Opium War in 1840 and 1857 to make Qing dynasty pay a large amount of reparations, cede Hong Kong and Kawloon island, open 11 ports including Shanghai, recognize consular jurisdiction, abandon tariff autonomy, grant one-sided most-favored-nation treatment, permit an envoy to stay in Beijing, and officially recognize and protect Christianity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Qing dynasty had allowed foreign trade only at Canton port, Britain (the British Empire) concluded the treaties of Nanjing (in 1482), Tianjin (in 1858), and Beijing (in 1860) after First Opium War and the Second Opium War in 1840 and 1857 to make Qing dynasty pay a large amount of reparations, cede Hong Kong and Kawloon island, open eleven ports including Shanghai, recognize consular jurisdiction, abandon tariff autonomy, grant one-sided most-favored-nation treatment, permit an envoy to stay in Beijing, and officially recognize and protect Christianity.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Qing dynasty had allowed foreign trade only at Canton port, Britain (the British Empire) concluded the treaties of Nanjing (in 1482), Tianjin (in 1858), and Beijing (in 1860) after First Opium War and the Second Opium War in 1840 and 1857 to make Qing dynasty pay a large amount of reparations, cede Hong Kong and Kawloon island, open 11 ports including Shanghai, recognize consular jurisdiction, abandon tariff autonomy, grant one-sided most-favored-nation treatment, permit an envoy to stay in Beijing, and officially recognize and protect Christianity.</e>
<cmt>スペルアウトをアラビア数字に変更しました。また、全角スペースを半角スペースに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>また日本に対しては1853年と翌年アメリカ合衆国は東インド艦隊司令長官ペリーとその艦隊を派遣し、軍事的威圧のもとに日米和親条約つづいて日米修好通商条約を江戸幕府と締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The United States of America dispatched Commodore Perry of an East Indian squadron and other squadrons to Japan in 1853 and the following year and concluded Treaty of amity and commerce between the United states and Japan; The Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan followed by Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan under its military threat.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The United States of America dispatched Commodore Perry of the East Indian squadron and other squadrons to Japan in 1853 and the following yea,r and concluded a Treaty of amity and commerce between the United states and Japan; The Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan followed by Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan under military threat.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The United States of America dispatched Commodore Perry of the East Indian squadron and other squadrons to Japan in 1853 and the following year, and concluded a Treaty of amity and commerce between the United States and Japan; The Treaty of Amity and Commerce between the United States and Japan followed by Treaty between the United States of America and the Empire of Japan under military threat.</e>
<cmt>yea,r→year</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>これにより5港の開港と領事裁判権、片務的最恵国待遇、関税自主権喪失などを認めさせ(後に英、露、蘭、仏とも)幕府の二百数十年続いた鎖国を終わらせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With these treaties, Japan was made open five ports, grant consular jurisdiction, recognize one-sided most-favored-nation treatment, and abandon tariff autonomy (later with Britain, Russia, Holland, and France), being forced out of its 200 and several decades old national isolation of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With these treaties, Japan was made to open five ports, grant consular jurisdiction, recognize one-sided most-favored-nation treatment, and abandon tariff autonomy (later with Britain, Russia, Holland, and France), and forced out of its 200 and several decades old national isolation of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With these treaties, Japan was made to open five ports, grant consular jurisdiction, recognize one-sided most-favored-nation treatment, and abandon tariff autonomy (later with Britain, Russia, Holland, and France), and forced out of its 200 and several decades old national isolation of the bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="29">
<j>幕末には攘夷論が台頭するがそれを克服し、戊辰戦争の後明治政府は西洋文明の積極的な受容による近代国家の建設、幕府が結んだ西欧諸国との不平等条約の改正と南下政策を進めるロシア帝国との国境確定および東アジア諸国との外交関係の再構築と版図の確定という課題に取り組んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan conquered principle of excluding foreigners that emerged in the end of Edo period, and the Meiji Government had tackled with the following issues since the Bushing War: the construction of a modern state through introduction of western civilization; the revision of the unequal treaties that the bakufu signed, with western countries; the definition of the border with Russian that had been promoting southward expansion; and the restructing of diplomatic relations and definition of the territory with East Asian countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan conquered principle of excluding foreigners that emerged at the end of Edo period, and the Meiji Government had tackled the following issues since the Bushing War: the construction of a modern state through the introduction of western civilization; the revision of the unequal treaties that the bakufu signed, with western countries; the definition of the border with Russia that had been promoting southward expansion; and the restructing of diplomatic relations and definition of the territory with East Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan conquered principle of excluding foreigners that emerged at the end of Edo period, and the Meiji Government had tackled the following issues since the Bushing War: the construction of a modern state through the introduction of western civilization; the revision of the unequal treaties that the bakufu signed, with western countries; the definition of the border with Russia that had been promoting southward expansion; and the restructing of diplomatic relations and definition of the territory with East Asian countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>また清でも1860年代から漢人官僚曽国藩、李鴻章らによる近代化の試みとして洋務運動が展開され中国の伝統的な文化、制度を土台としながら軍事を中心として西洋技術の導入を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing had also been introducing western technologies centering on military ones based on Chinese traditional culture;. bureaucrats of the Han race including Zeng Guofan and Li Hung Chang promoted Western Affair Movement in an attempt to modernize China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing had also been introducing western technologies centering on military ones based on Chinese traditional culture;. bureaucrats of the Han race including Zeng Guofan and Li Hung Chang promoted the Western Affairs Movement in an attempt to modernize China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing had also been introducing western technologies centering on military ones based on Chinese traditional culture; bureaucrats of the Han race including Zeng Guofan and Li Hung Chang promoted the Western Affairs Movement in an attempt to modernize China.</e>
<cmt>余分なピリオドを削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>開戦まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the war start</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Until the war started</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Until the war started</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>朝鮮との国交交渉</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Diplomatic talks with korea</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Diplomatic talks with korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Diplomatic talks with korea</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="31">
<j>明治政府は1868年末、王政復古を伝える書契を朝鮮に渡そうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government tried to hand over a note to inform the Korean government of the restoration of imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government tried to hand over a note informing the Korean government about the restoration of imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government tried to hand over a note informing the Korean government about the restoration of imperial rule.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>しかし、その形式が従来と違い文中に中国皇帝のみが使用する「皇」や「勅」の語があったことで、朝鮮側はそれらは朝鮮にたいし日本を上位におくととらえ、また近代化を進める日本を「仮洋夷」として警戒してその受け取りを拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Korean government refused to accept it saying that the note written in a style different from conventional one and containing words of &quot;皇&quot; and &quot;勅&quot;--traditionally used only by Chinese emperors--suggested that Japan be superior to Korea, and warning that Japan&apos;s modernization was based on &quot;a presumed doctrine of excluding western threats.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Korean government refused to accept it saying that the note was written in a style that differed from the conventional one and containing words &quot;皇&quot; and &quot;勅&quot;--traditionally used only by Chinese emperors-- suggested that Japan was superior to Korea, and warning that Japan&apos;s modernization was based on &quot;a presumed doctrine of excluding western threats.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Korean government refused to accept it saying that the note was written in a style that differed from the conventional one and containing words &quot;皇&quot; and &quot;勅&quot;--traditionally used only by Chinese emperors-- suggested that Japan was superior to Korea, and warning that Japan&apos;s modernization was based on &quot;a presumed doctrine of excluding western threats.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>その後数年間交渉が進展しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bilateral talks did not progress for several years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bilateral talks did not progress for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bilateral talks did not progress for several years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="34">
<j>この時朝鮮では幼い国王高宗にかわりその実父興宣大院君が実権を握り、外戚安東金氏の専横と古い体制を打破していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Korea at this time, not King Gojong, still young, but his father Heungseon Daewongun held power trying to doing away with tyranny and old system established by his material relatives, the Kim clan of Andong district.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Korea at this time, not King Gojong, still young, but his father Heungseon Daewongun held onto power trying to do away with tyranny and the old system established by his material relatives, the Kim clan of the Andong district.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Korea at this time, not King Gojong, still young, but his father Heungseon Daewongun held onto power trying to do away with tyranny and the old system established by his material relatives, the Kim clan of the Andong district.</e>
<cmt>全角スペースを半角スペースに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>また1866年8月のアメリカ武装商船ジェネラル・シャーマン号事件と10月のフランス人宣教師9名の処刑(丙寅教獄)、その報復として江華島へ侵攻したフランス艦隊との戦闘(丙寅洋擾)など華夷思想による強固な鎖国・攘夷政策を実行し西欧諸国との間に重大な軋轢を引き起こしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Heungseon Daewongun also firmly carried out a Sinocentrism-based policy to exclude foreigners that caused serious frictions with western countries; the US armed merchant ship General Sherman incident occurred in August 1866, executions of Nine French missionaries in October (Hei-in crackdown of Christianity), and a conflict with French in response to the executions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heungseon Daewongun also firmly carried out a Sinocentrism-based policy to exclude foreigners that caused serious friction with western countries; the US armed merchant ship General Sherman incident occurred in August 1866, executions of Nine French missionaries in October (Hei-in crackdown of Christianity), and a conflict with French in response to the executions.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>日清修好条規と琉球帰属問題</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship and issues of possession of Ryukyu Islands</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship and issues of the possession of the Ryukyu Islands</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>明治政府は朝鮮との国交問題解決のためにも、まず朝鮮の宗主国である清と対等の国交条約を結び、その冊封関係を利用して朝鮮と交渉するという方針をたてた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To resolve diplomatic issues with Korea, the Meiji Government set up a plan to first enter into equal diplomatic relations with China having suzerainty over Korea and then use the lord-vassal relation between China and Korea to have talks with Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">To resolve diplomatic issues with Korea, the Meiji Government set up a plan to first enter into equal diplomatic relations with China having suzerainty over Korea and then use the lord-vassal relation between China and Korea to have talks with Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">OK</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>清の直隷総督李鴻章との間で1871年9月日清修好条規及び通商章程を締結した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship with trade regulations was signed by Li Hung Chang, Governor General of Zhili.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship with trade regulations was signed by Li Hung Chang, Governor General of Zhili.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September 1871, the Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship with trade regulations was signed by Li Hung Chang, Governor General of Zhili.</e>
<cmt>1871年9月が抜けていたので追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これは使節の交換と領事駐在および限定的な領事裁判権、開港と通商および協定関税率を相互に認めるという平等条約であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an equal treaty that mutually authorized exchange of envoys, presence of the consular with restricted consular jurisdiction, opening of the port and commerce, and tariff rates based on an agreement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an equal treaty that mutually authorized the exchange of envoys, the presence of the consular with restricted jurisdiction, opening of a port and commerce, and tariff rates based on an agreement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an equal treaty that mutually authorized the exchange of envoys, the presence of the consular with restricted jurisdiction, opening of a port and commerce, and tariff rates based on an agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>その第二条は「両国好みを通ぜし上は---若し他国より不公及び軽藐する事有る時、其の知らせを為さば、何れも互いに相助け」とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The article 2 of the treaty says, &quot;If other countries impose an unequal demand on or despise either country, the both countries mutually help each other when informed of this event on the basis of their friendly relations.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Article 2 of the treaty says, &quot;If other countries impose an unequal demand upon or despise either country, both countries will mutually assist each other when informed of such an event on the basis of their friendly relations.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Article 2 of the treaty says, &quot;If other countries impose an unequal demand upon or despise either country, both countries will mutually assist each other when informed of such an event on the basis of their friendly relations.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>両国が当時おかれていた西欧列強による脅威を前提に相互扶助を誓約するものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The both countries, on the treaty, promised mutual assistance on the basis that the both countries faced the threat of western powers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both countries, parties to the treaty, promised mutual assistance on the basis that both countries faced threats from the western powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both countries, parties to the treaty, promised mutual assistance on the basis that both countries faced threats from the western powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>他方両国には琉球王国の日清両属という領土問題での懸案もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, there remained bilateral territorial issues on the possession of the Ryukyu islands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, there remained bilateral territorial issues on the possession of the Ryukyu islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, there remained bilateral territorial issues on the possession of the Ryukyu islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>琉球王国は明（1644年滅亡）の冊封を受け東アジア諸国との交易により繁栄していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ryukyu Kingdom was in sakukfu relation with Ming Dynasty (that fell in 1644), and trades with Eastern Asian countries flourished the islands.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ryukyu Kingdom was in a sakukfu relationship with the Ming Dynasty (that fell in 1644), and trade with East Asian countries flourished amongst the islands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Ryukyu Kingdom was in a sakukfu relationship with the Ming Dynasty (that fell in 1644), and trade with East Asian countries flourished amongst the islands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1609年薩摩藩の島津氏による侵攻を受け奄美諸島を薩摩藩の領土として割譲されたうえ琉球は事実上薩摩藩の属国となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After invasion of the Shimazu clan of Satsuma Domain in 1609, the islands became de factor under the rule of Satsuma Domain with secession of some territories.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After an invasion by the Shimazu clan of Satsuma Domain in 1609, the islands came under the rule of the Satsuma Domain with a secession of some territories.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After an invasion by the Shimazu clan of Satsuma Domain in 1609, the islands came under the rule of the Satsuma Domain with a secession of some territories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>それ以降、明や清との朝貢貿易の利益のため江戸幕府と中国への両属とする体制が幕末までつづいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since then, the islands had belonged to China and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who sought benefits from tribute trade with Ming and Quing dynasties.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since then, the islands had belonged to China and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who sought benefits from tribute trade with the Ming and Quing dynasties.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since then, the islands had belonged to China and the Edo bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), who sought benefits from tribute trade with the Ming and Quing dynasties.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>1871年7月の廃藩置県により琉球は鹿児島県に一応編入され、翌1872年9月琉球藩を設置し国王を藩王として華族に列する冊封詔書が授けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryukyu belonged to Kagoshima prefecture according to Haihan-chiken (new administration system to abolish feudal domains and establish prefectures) in July 1871, while the Ryukyu Domain was established and granted Sakuho Shosho (imperial edict, decree) recognizing the peerage with the king of Ryukyu as the king of the domain in September 1872.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryukyu belonged to Kagoshima prefecture according to Haihan-chiken (new administration system to abolish feudal domains and establish prefectures) in July 1871, while the Ryukyu Domain was established and granted Sakuho Shosho (imperial edict, decree) recognizing peerage with the king of Ryukyu as the king of the domain in September 1872.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryukyu belonged to Kagoshima prefecture according to Haihan-chiken (new administration system to abolish feudal domains and establish prefectures) in July 1871, while the Ryukyu Domain was established and granted Sakuho Shosho (imperial edict, decree) recognizing peerage with the king of Ryukyu as the king of the domain in September 1872.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>この後も琉球の日清両属の状態は続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After these events, Ryukyu kept possessed by both Japan and China</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After these events, Ryukyu continued to be possessed by both Japan and China</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After these events, Ryukyu continued to be possessed by both Japan and China</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>さきに1871年琉球船が難破し台湾南部へ漂着した際、先住民による琉球島民殺害事件が発生していたが明治政府はそれを解決できないまま数年が経過した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before that, the Meiji government did not resolve the incident of suicide of Ryukyu sailors whose ship had been wrecked and cast up on the coast of southern Taiwan in 1871, and several years had passed.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Before that, the Meiji government did not resolve the incident of suicide of Ryukyu sailors whose ship had been wrecked and cast up on the coast of southern Taiwan in 1871, and several years had passed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Before that, the Meiji government did not resolve the incident of suicide of Ryukyu sailors whose ship had been wrecked and cast up on the coast of southern Taiwan in 1871, and several years had passed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="48">
<j>征韓論と明治六年政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seikanron (debate on subjugation of Korea) and Meiji roku-nen no Seihen (Coups of 1873)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seikanron (debate on the subjugation of Korea) and Meiji roku-nen no Seihen (Coups of 1873)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seikanron (debate on the subjugation of Korea) and Meiji roku-nen no Seihen (Coups of 1873)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>すでに18世紀末、仙台藩の林子平は海国兵談で海防論を説いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Late in the 18th century, Shihei HAYASHI of the Sendai Domain; had already advocated the way of maritime defense in his book titled Hkikoku heidan (a discussion on maritime nations&apos; soldiers).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Late in the eighteenth century, Shihei HAYASHI of the Sendai Domain; had already advocated the way of maritime defense in his book titled Hkikoku heidan (a discussion on the maritime nations&apos; soldiers).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Late in the 18th century, Shihei HAYASHI of the Sendai Domain; had already advocated the way of maritime defense in his book titled Hkikoku heidan (a discussion on the maritime nations&apos; soldiers).</e>
<cmt>2桁の数字をアラビア数字の表記に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>幕末には経済学者佐藤信淵は土地国有化と海外進出を行う絶対主義国家を論じ、吉田松陰は幽囚録で蝦夷地開拓とともにカムチャッカ半島、朝鮮、台湾、満州等への侵略統治論を展開していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the closing days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Nobuhiro SATO, an economist argued absolutism of nationalizing lands and finding ways into foreign countries, while Shoin YOSHIDA argued in his book titled yuin-roku (descriptions in prison) reclamation of Ezo and invasion for control of the Kamchatkan Peninsula, Korea, Taiwan, Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the closing days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Nobuhiro SATO, an economist argued absolutism of nationalizing lands and finding ways into foreign countries, while Shoin YOSHIDA argued in his book titled yuin-roku (descriptions in prison) reclamation of Ezo and invasion for the control of the Kamchatkan Peninsula, Korea, Taiwan, Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the closing days of the Tokugawa Shogunate, Nobuhiro SATO, an economist argued absolutism of nationalizing lands and finding ways into foreign countries, while Shoin YOSHIDA argued in his book titled yuin-roku (descriptions in prison) reclamation of Ezo and invasion for the control of such as the Kamchatkan Peninsula, Korea, Taiwan, and Manchuria.</e>
<cmt>&quot;such as&quot;を挿入しました。（「満州等への」）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>それらの主張は尊王攘夷運動と明治初期の薩長藩閥政府にも少なからぬ影響を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These claims had not small influences on Sonno Joi Movement (the movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and the policies of the government led by Saccho (Satsuma and Choshu Domains) in early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These claims did not by any means have a small influences on the Sonno Joi Movement (the movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and the policies of the government led by Saccho (the Satsuma and Choshu Domains) during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These claims did not by any means have a small influences on the Sonno Joi Movement (the movement advocating reverence for the Emperor and the expulsion of foreigners) and the policies of the government led by Saccho (the Satsuma and Choshu Domains) during the early Meiji period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>朝鮮との国交交渉が進展しない明治政府内で武力による開国を迫るいわゆる征韓論が台頭した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The so-called Seikanron (debate on subjugation of Korea) supporting military pressure to force Korea to open the country emerged in the Meiji government whose diplomatic talks with Korea did not show progress.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The so-called Seikanron (debate on the subjugation of Korea) supporting military pressure to force Korea to open the country emerged in the Meiji government whose diplomatic talks with Korea did not show any progress.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The so-called Seikanron (debate on the subjugation of Korea) supporting military pressure to force Korea to open the country emerged in the Meiji government whose diplomatic talks with Korea did not show any progress.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="53">
<j>1873年6月の閣議(いわゆる留守政府)において参議板垣退助が交渉の行きづまりを打開するため陸軍一大隊の朝鮮への派遣を主張、西郷隆盛は使節の派遣と自らその職への任命を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a cabinet meeting (of so-called rusu seifu (government with heads away))in June 1873, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Sangi (the Councilor), claimed to dispatch a battalion of Army to Korea to resolve the deadlock in negotiations, and Takamori SAIGO claimed that an envoy be dispathced and he be appointed as the envoy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a cabinet meeting (of the so-called rusu seifu - government while heads were away) in June 1873, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Sangi (the Councilor), claimed to dispatch a battalion of Army to Korea to resolve the deadlock in negotiations, and Takamori SAIGO demanded that an envoy be dispathced and he be appointed as the envoy.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a cabinet meeting (of the so-called rusu seifu - government while heads were away) in June 1873, Taisuke ITAGAKI, Sangi (the Councilor), claimed to dispatch a battalion of Army to Korea to resolve the deadlock in negotiations, and Takamori SAIGO demanded that an envoy be dispathced and he be appointed as the envoy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>その後岩倉具視が帰国し内治優先の立場から使節派遣に反対の上奏をした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later Tomomi IWAKURA, when he returned home, reported to the throne an opposition to the dispatch of the envoy placing a priority on domestic issues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later Tomomi IWAKURA, when he returned home, reported the opposition to the dispatch of the envoy, to the throne, and their placing priority on domestic issues.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later Tomomi IWAKURA, when he returned home, reported the opposition to the dispatch of the envoy, to the throne, and their placing priority on domestic issues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>明治天皇の裁可により派遣延期となり参議西郷、板垣らが辞職する事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji determined to hold over the dispatch, and Saigo and Itagaki, both Sangi, were forced to resign.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Emperor Meiji determined to hold over the dispatch, and Saigo and Itagaki, both Sangi, were forced to resign.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Emperor Meiji determined to hold over the dispatch, and Saigo and Itagaki, both Sangi, were forced to resign.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>(詳しくは征韓論、明治六年政変、西郷隆盛を参照)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See the sect6ions of Seikanron, Meiji roku-nen no Seihen (Coups of 1873), and Takamori SAIGO for more details.)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See the sections on; Seikanron, Meiji roku-nen no Seihen (Coups of 1873), and Takamori SAIGO for more details.)</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See the sections on; Seikanron, Meiji roku-nen no Seihen (Coups of 1873), and Takamori SAIGO for more details.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>また大久保達はこれ以降、政治の実権を握る事になったが、いわゆる「征韓論」に対しては大久保らも、交渉決裂に際して朝鮮半島での武力行使の方針自体には反対ではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Okubo and other leaders, who held power after this event, were not also against Seikanron and the policy of executing military power in the Korean Peninsula after a breakdown in the negotiation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Okubo and other leaders, who held power after this event, also were not against Seikanron and the policy of executing military power in the Korean Peninsula after a breakdown in negotiations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Okubo and other leaders, who held power after this event, also were not against Seikanron and the policy of executing military power in the Korean Peninsula after a breakdown in negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="58">
<j>この征韓論には1871年廃藩置県によって武士としての職を失った士族の不満が背景にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Behind this Seikanron there were dissatisfactions of Shizoku (family or persons with samurai ancestors) who had lost their jobs as the result of Haihan-chiken in 1871.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Behind this Seikanron there was dissatisfaction amongst the Shizoku (family or persons with samurai ancestors) who had lost their jobs as a result of Haihan-chiken in 1871.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Behind this Seikanron there was dissatisfaction amongst the Shizoku (family or persons with samurai ancestors) who had lost their jobs as a result of Haihan-chiken in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>以後1873年徴兵令公布、1876年廃刀令、秩禄処分に至る過程で士族反乱が相次ぎ明治政府はこうした不満を海外に向ける必要もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Revolts by Shizoku occurred one after another during the process that ended in promulgation of Conscription Ordinance in 1873 and decree banning the wearing of swords; decree banning the wearing of sword in 1867, and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend), and the Meiji government needed to turned their satisfactions to the outside of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Revolts by Shizoku occurred one after another during a process that ended in the promulgation of a Conscription Ordinance in 1873 and a decree banning the wearing of swords in 1867, and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend), and the Meiji government needed to turned their attention to the outside of Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Revolts by Shizoku occurred one after another during a process that ended in the promulgation of a Conscription Ordinance in 1873 and a decree banning the wearing of swords in 1867, and Chitsuroku-shobun (Abolition Measure of Hereditary Stipend), and the Meiji government needed to turned their attention to the outside of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="60">
<j>台湾出兵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Taiwan expedition</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Taiwan expedition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Taiwan expedition</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>1871年の琉球島民殺害事件にたいして薩摩藩出身者を中心に台湾出兵が建言された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to murders of Ryukyu sailors in 1871, politicians mainly from Satsuma Domain strongly suggested the dispatch of troops to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to the murders of some Ryukyu sailors in 1871, politicians mainly from the Satsuma Domain strongly suggested the dispatch of troops to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to the murders of some Ryukyu sailors in 1871, politicians mainly from the Satsuma Domain strongly suggested the dispatch of troops to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>征韓論派の下野の後政府は内務卿大久保利通の主導のもと1874年台湾蕃地事務長官に大隈重信、同都督に陸軍中将西郷従道を任命して出兵準備をさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After resignation of supporters of Seikanron, the government led by Toshimichi OKUBO, Secretary of Interior, appointed Shigenobu OKUMA as chief secretary of Taiwan Banchi and Tsugumichi SAIGO, lieutenant general (army), as Totoku governor general of Taiwan in 1874 to prepare for the dispatch of troops.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After resignation of supporters of Seikanron, the government led by Toshimichi OKUBO, Secretary of Interior, appointed Shigenobu OKUMA as chief secretary of Taiwan Banchi and Tsugumichi SAIGO, lieutenant general (army), as Totoku governor general of Taiwan in 1874 to prepare for the dispatch of troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After resignation of supporters of Seikanron, the government led by Toshimichi OKUBO, Secretary of Interior, appointed Shigenobu OKUMA as chief secretary of Taiwan Banchi and Tsugumichi SAIGO, lieutenant general (army), as Totoku governor general of Taiwan in 1874 to prepare for the dispatch of troops.</e>
<cmt>全角スペースを半角に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>兵力は二個大隊であり、うち鎮台兵は一個大隊で残りは「植民兵」として薩摩など九州各地の士族で占領地永住を前提に募集・編成されたものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The military force consisted of two battalions: one was made up of soldiers of chindai (garrison in Meiji era) and the other was formed by former shizoku in Kyushu regions who had been recruited on the condition that they be granted permanent residence of occupied lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The military force consisted of two battalions: one was made up of soldiers of chindai (garrison in the Meiji era) and the other was formed by the former shizoku in Kyushu regions who had been recruited on the condition that they be granted permanent residence of occupied lands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The military force consisted of two battalions: one was made up of soldiers of chindai (garrison in the Meiji era) and the other was formed by the former shizoku in Kyushu regions who had been recruited on the condition that they be granted permanent residence of occupied lands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="64">
<j>しかしイギリスやアメリカの反対意見と局外中立の表明および征韓論にも反対していた参議木戸孝允の反対と辞任により政府は派遣中止を決める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the government decided not to dispatch the troops, because Britain and the US expressed oppositions against the dispatch and rather neutrality, and because Sangi Takayoshi KIDO expressed opinion against Seikanron resigned in opposition of the dispatch.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the government decided not to dispatch the troops, because Britain and the US expressed oppositions against it and the government remained rather neutral, and because Sangi Takayoshi KIDO expressed his opinion against Seikanron and resigned in opposition to the dispatch.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the government decided not to dispatch the troops, because Britain and the US expressed oppositions against it and the government remained rather neutral, and because Sangi Takayoshi KIDO expressed his opinion against Seikanron and resigned in opposition to the dispatch.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>しかし、西郷が5月2日征討軍を長崎から出航させると大久保もこれを追認し、7月1日には日本軍が台湾南部の事件発生地域を占領することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, Saigo allowed expeditionary force to set sail from Nagasaki with additional authorization of Okubo, and, on July 2, the Japanese army occupied the southern region of Taiwan where the murder incident had occurred.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, Saigo allowed the expeditionary force to set sail from Nagasaki with additional authorization of Okubo, and, on July 2, the Japanese army occupied the southern region of Taiwan where the murder incident had occurred.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, on May 2, Saigo allowed the expeditionary force to set sail from Nagasaki with additional authorization of Okubo, and, on July 1, the Japanese army occupied the southern region of Taiwan where the murder incident had occurred.</e>
<cmt>5月2日が抜け、7月1日が2日になっていたので訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>日本軍は先住民の村を焼き払うなどし、日本側の戦死者は12名であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese army burned down villages of indigenous people with only 12 deaths of Japanese soldiers during the war.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese army burned down the villages of indigenous people with only twelve deaths of Japanese soldiers during the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese army burned down villages of indigenous people with 12 deaths of Japanese soldiers during the war.</e>
<cmt>原文に「only」に充当する言葉がなかったので抜きました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>しかし年末までの駐屯でマラリア等による病死者が500名を超える事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the total of more than 500 solders died of malaria and other diseases while they stayed there until the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, a total of more than 500 solders died of malaria and other diseases while they stayed there until the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, a total of more than 500 solders died of malaria and other diseases while they stayed there until the end of the year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="68">
<j>これは近代日本初の海外出兵であったが、清側は直ちに抗議し撤兵を強く求めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the first time for Japan to dispatch troops abroad in the modern times, but Quing dynasty immediately protested demanding the withdrawal of the troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This is the first time for Japan to dispatch troops abroad in modern times, but the Quing dynasty immediately protested demanding the withdrawal of the troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This is the first time for Japan to dispatch troops abroad in modern times, but the Quing dynasty immediately protested demanding the withdrawal of the troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>明治政府は交渉決裂の場合の清との開戦も決し、9月「和戦を決する権」を与えられた大久保が全権大使として北京で交渉した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government, with a determination of starting war with Quing after a breakdown in the negotiation, gave Okubo full authority to &quot;decide on war or peace,&quot; and Okubo had talks in Beijing as a plenipotentiary.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government, with the determination of starting a war with Quing after a breakdown in negotiations, gave Okubo full authority to &quot;decide on war or peace,&quot; and Okubo had talks in Beijing as a plenipotentiary.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government, with the determination of starting a war with Quing after a breakdown in negotiations, gave Okubo full authority to &apos;decide on war or peace,&apos; and in September, Okubo had talks in Beijing as a plenipotentiary.</e>
<cmt>「9月」が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>難航の末イギリスの仲介もあり清は日本の出兵を「義挙」と認め50万両(テール)の賠償をすることで決着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The negotiations floundered but came to the conclusion that Qing would recognize the dispatch of Japanese force as &quot;Gikyo (actions out of justice)&quot; and pay 500 thousand ryo (taes)..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The negotiations floundered, but came to the conclusion that Qing would recognize the dispatch of the Japanese force as &quot;Gikyo (actions out of justice)&quot; and pay 500,000 ryo (taes)..</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The negotiations floundered but, through the mediatiion of Britain, came to the conclusion that Qing would recognize the dispatch of the Japanese force as &apos;Gikyo (actions out of justice)&apos; and pay 500,000 ryo (taes).</e>
<cmt>「イギリスの仲介」が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="71">
<j>これは琉球の帰属問題で日本に有利に働き、明治政府は翌1875年琉球にたいし清との冊封・朝貢関係の廃止と明治年号の使用などを命令した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This put Japan in an advantageous position on the issue of the possession of Ryukyu, and the Meiji government ordered Ryukyu to abolish its sakuho and tribute relation with Qing and use the era name of Meiji.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This put Japan in an advantageous position on the issue of the possession of Ryukyu, and the Meiji government ordered Ryukyu to abolish its sakuho and tribute relationship with Qing and use the era name of Meiji.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This put Japan in an advantageous position on the issue of the possession of Ryukyu and in the following year, 1875, the Meiji government ordered Ryukyu to abolish its sakuho and tribute relationship with Qing and use the era name of Meiji.</e>
<cmt>1875(年）が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>琉球は清との関係存続を嘆願、清が琉球の朝貢禁止に抗議するなど外交上の決着はつかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This issue was not diplomatically resolved, because Ryukyu wanted to maintain a tie with Quing and Quing protested a ban on tributes of Ryukyu to Qing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This issue was not diplomatically resolved, because Ryukyu wanted to maintain ties with Quing and Quing protested a ban on tributes of Ryukyu to Qing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This issue was not diplomatically resolved, because Ryukyu wanted to maintain ties with Quing and Quing protested a ban on tributes of Ryukyu to Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>また清は以後日本の清国領土簒奪への警戒感を持ち北洋艦隊建設の契機ともなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Qing started to have a sense of danger with regard to Japan&apos;s desire to seize Qing&apos;s territory, which led Qing to construct its Northern fleet.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, Qing started to sense danger with regard to Japan&apos;s desire to seize Qing&apos;s territory, which led Qing to construct its Northern fleet.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, Qing started to sense danger with regard to Japan&apos;s desire to seize Qing&apos;s territory, which led Qing to construct its Northern fleet.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>江華島事件と日朝修好条規</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ganghwa Island incident and Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ganghwa Island incident and the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ganghwa Island incident and the Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="74">
<j>1873年12月大院君は失脚し王妃の一族閔氏が政権を握った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Daewongun fell from power in December 1873, the empress&apos;s family, the Min clan, took over political power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Daewongun fell from power in December 1873, the empress&apos;s family, the Min clan, took over political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Daewongun fell from power in December 1873, the empress&apos;s family, the Min clan, took over political power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>朝鮮国内でも通商開化を説く意見が登場した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opinions supporting commerce and civilization emerged within Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opinions supporting commerce and civilization emerged within Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opinions supporting commerce and civilization emerged within Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>明治政府は1874年6月から交渉を再開するがやはり紛糾した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1874, the Meiji Government resumed negotiations, which did not came into conclusion, too.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1874, the Meiji Government resumed negotiations, which did not come to a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1874, the Meiji Government resumed negotiations, which did not come to a conclusion.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>そのため、軍艦数隻を朝鮮沿岸に派遣し海路を測量させて示威を行い交渉を有利に進めることとし、1875年軍艦雲揚、第二丁卯を派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result the government dispatched warships Unyo and Daini Teibo in 1875 and had them sound the sea to a coast of Korea with an aim to gain an advantage by demonstrating its strength.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result the government dispatched the warships Unyo and Daini Teibo in 1875 and had them sound the sea to the coast of Korea aiming to gain an advantage by demonstrating its strength.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result the government dispatched the warships Unyo and Daini Teibo in 1875 and had them sound the sea to the coast of Korea aiming to gain an advantage by demonstrating its strength.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>この雲揚が同年9月20日首都漢城に近い要塞地帯であった江華島に接近し、発砲されたとの理由で3日間にわたり戦闘し22日には永宗島の砲台を攻撃、占領する事件が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 20 of the same year, an incident occurred: this Unyo approached Ganghwa Island, the stronghold base near the capital Hanseong and occupied the island after fights for three days with a reason that it was fired.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 20 of the same year, an incident occurred: this Unyo approached Ganghwa Island, the stronghold base near the capital Hanseong and occupied the island after fighting for three days based on the reason that it was fired upon.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 20 of the same year, an incident occurred: this Unyo approached Ganghwa Island, which was the stronghold base near the capital Hanseong, and fought for three days insisting that she had been fiired, then on 22nd, she attacked the gun batteries and seized Yeongjong Island.</e>
<cmt>占領されたのは江華島ではなく永宋島など原文と英訳の意味が一致せず、また日付（22日）も抜けていたため訳し直しました。原文を見る限り軍艦が主語なのでitをsheに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>(詳しくは江華島事件また日朝修好条規参照)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(See sections of Ganghwa Island incident and Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity for more details.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(See sections of Ganghwa Island incident and Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity for more details.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(See sections of Ganghwa Island incident and Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity for more details.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="80">
<j>明治政府は12月に黒田清隆を特命全権大使に任命し軍艦3隻などの艦隊をともなって朝鮮に派遣した(砲艦外交)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Meiji Government appointed Kiyotaka KURODA as a plenipotentiary in December and dispatched him to Korea with the fleet including three warships</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Meiji Government appointed Kiyotaka KURODA as a plenipotentiary in December and dispatched him to Korea with a fleet including three warships</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Meiji Government appointed Kiyotaka KURODA as a plenipotentiary in December and dispatched him to Korea with a fleet including three warships (gunboat diplomacy).</e>
<cmt>「砲艦外交」が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>その結果1876年2月日朝修好条規が調印された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was signed in February 1876.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, a Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was signed in February 1876.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, a Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was signed in February 1876.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>これは首都への公使駐在と釜山の他二港の開港と日本人の居留通商などを認めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this treaty, Japan made Korea allow Japanese envoy to reside in the capital, open Busan and other two ports, and authorize Japanese residents to trade.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this treaty, Japan forced Korea to allow the Japanese envoy to reside in the capital, open Busan and other two ports, and authorize Japanese residents to trade.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this treaty, Japan forced Korea to allow the Japanese envoy to reside in the capital, open Busan and other two ports, and authorize Japanese residents to trade.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="83">
<j>第一条で「朝鮮は自主の邦にして、日本国と平等の権利を保有せり」とうたいながらも第十条で片務的領事裁判権を規定する不平等条約であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although this treaty stated that &quot;Korea is independent and has rights equal to Japan&quot; in Article 1 but in effect was unequal with Article 10 providing one-sided consular jurisdiction in Article 10.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the treaty stated that &quot;Korea is independent and has rights equal to Japan&quot; in Article 1, but in effect was unequal according to Article 10 providing a one-sided consular jurisdiction in Article 10.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the treaty stated that &quot;Korea is independent and has rights equal to Japan&quot; in Article 1, but in effect was unequal according to Article 10 providing a one-sided consular jurisdiction in Article 10.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>さらに第七条では日本が朝鮮沿岸の測量権を得て軍艦の周航など軍事的進出を容易にすることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, Article 7 allowed to Japan to obtain a right to made a survey of coasts in Korea, facilitating Japan&apos;s military advances including circulation of warships.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, Article 7 allowed Japan to obtain a right to make a survey of coasts along Korea, facilitating Japan&apos;s military advances including the circulation of warships.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, Article 7 allowed Japan to obtain a right to make a survey of coasts along Korea, facilitating Japan&apos;s military advances including the circulation of warships.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="85">
<j>なお「自主の邦」と規定したとはいえ、清は冊封関係において従来から「属国自主」として内政・外交については関与しない立場をとっており、清の宗主権を否定しつくすものでもなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the treaty provided &quot;independent state,&quot; but did not completely deny suzerainty of China, because Qing had conventionally a stance of &quot;independence of subject states&quot;and not being involved in domestic and diplomatic affairs.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the treaty provided for an &quot;independent state,&quot; but did not completely deny suzerainty of China, because Qing had the conventional stance of &quot;independence as a subject state&quot;and was not involved in domestic and diplomatic affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the treaty provided for an &quot;independent state,&quot; but did not completely deny suzerainty of China, because Qing had the conventional stance of &quot;independence as a subject state&quot;and was not involved in domestic and diplomatic affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>ちなみに1882年の朝清商民水陸貿易章程では清の宗主権が明文化されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a side note, Korea-Qing Land and. Sea Commercial Activity Treaty singed in 1882 explicitly expressed Qing&apos;s suzerainty.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a side note, Korea-Qing Land and Commercial Sea Activity Treaty singed in 1882 explicitly expressed Qing&apos;s suzerainty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a side note, Korea-Qing Land and Commercial Sea Activity Treaty singed in 1882 explicitly expressed Qing&apos;s suzerainty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>琉球処分と分島改約案</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryukyu Annexation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryukyu Annexation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryukyu Annexation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="87">
<j>1879年明治政府はいわゆる琉球処分を行い琉球藩を沖縄県とし、琉球王尚泰の東京移住を命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1879, the Meiji Government carried out the so-called Ryukyu annexation to abolish Ryukyu domain and set up Okinawa prefecture and ordered Ryukyu King Sho Tai to live in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1879, the Meiji Government carried out the so-called Ryukyu annexation to abolish the Ryukyu domain and set up Okinawa prefecture and ordered the Ryukyu King Sho Tai to live in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1879, the Meiji Government carried out the so-called Ryukyu annexation to abolish the Ryukyu domain and set up Okinawa prefecture and ordered the Ryukyu King Sho Tai to live in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>琉球内ではそれを不服とし明治政府に様々な嘆願を行い、また清に救援を求める人々もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, some Ryukyuans opposed to this order and submitted petitions to the Meiji government, or others sought Qing for assistance.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, some Ryukyuans opposed to this order and submitted petitions to the Meiji government, or others sought Qing for assistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, some Ryukyuans opposed to this order and submitted petitions to the Meiji government, or others sought Qing for assistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="89">
<j>清は冊封関係の回復にむけ積極的になり日清の関係は悪化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The relation between Japan and Qing worsened as Qing took active steps to recover the sakuho relation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The relationship between Japan and Qing worsened as Qing took active steps to recover the sakuho relationship.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The relationship between Japan and Qing worsened as Qing took active steps to recover the sakuho relationship.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="90">
<j>世界巡遊中の前合衆国大統領ユリシーズ・グラントが明治天皇との会見で西欧列強の介入を防ぐための日清両国の譲歩を助言したこともあり、1880年北京で日清の交渉が行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1880, negotiation talks were held in Beijing through the arbitration of ex-US President Ulysses Grant, who had a meeting with Emperor Meiji during his world tour and advised that both Japan and Qing compromise to prevent interventions of western powers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1880, negotiations were held in Beijing through the arbitration of ex-US President Ulysses Grant, who had a meeting with Emperor Meiji during his world tour and advised that both Japan and Qing compromise to prevent the intervention of western powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1880, negotiations were held in Beijing through the arbitration of ex-US President Ulysses Grant, who had a meeting with Emperor Meiji during his world tour and advised that both Japan and Qing compromise to prevent the intervention of western powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="91">
<j>この時日本は沖縄本島を日本領とし八重山諸島と宮古島を中国領とし、日清修好条規に日本の欧米並みの最恵国待遇を追加する案(分島改約案)を提示し一旦はまとまる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan proposed a plan in the negotiation that Okinawa main island would belong to Japan and Yeyma islands and Miyako-jima island to China and that Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship be revised with an additional clause to grant Japan most-favored nation treatment (proposal for divisional rule over islands and a revision to the treaty), and this proposal was once accepted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan proposed a plan during negotiations that the Okinawa main island would belong to Japan and the Yeyma islands and Miyako-jima island to China and that Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship be revised with an additional clause to grant Japan a most-favored nation treatment (proposal for divisional rule over the islands and a revision to the treaty), and this proposal was once accepted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan proposed a plan during negotiations that the Okinawa main island would belong to Japan and the Yeyma islands and Miyako-jima island to China and that Japan-Qing Treaty of Friendship be revised with an additional clause to grant Japan a most-favored nation treatment (proposal for divisional rule over the islands and a revision to the treaty), and this proposal was once accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>しかし清は元来二島の領有を望まず、冊封関係維持のため二島を琉球に返還し琉球王国再興を求めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Qing whisked to maintain the sakufu relation instead of possessing the both islands changed its mind and requested Japan to return the islands to Ryukyu Kingdom..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Qing whisked to maintain the sakufu relationship instead of possessing both islands changed its mind and requested Japan to return the islands to the Ryukyu Kingdom.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Qing whisked to maintain the sakufu relationship instead of possessing both islands changed its mind and requested Japan to return the islands to the Ryukyu Kingdom.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>分島にたいする琉球人の反対もあり、清は提案受け入れの態度を変えて調印に至らなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing changed its mind hearing opposition of Ryukyuans to the divisional rule over the islands; as the result, the negotiation did not ended in agreement.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing changed its mind upon hearing the opposition of the Ryukyuans to divisional rule over the islands; and as a result, the negotiation did not end in agreement.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing changed its mind upon hearing the opposition of the Ryukyuans to divisional rule over the islands; and as a result, the negotiation did not end in agreement.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="94">
<j>この琉球問題の決裂と日本の台湾への野心の疑いから清側ではこの後対日強硬論が唱えられるに至る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This breakdown in the negotiation over Ryukyu issue and suspected ambition of Japan to rule Taiwan caused opinions supporting a hard-line policy against Japan.to increase in Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This breakdown in negotiations over the Ryukyu issue and the suspected ambition of Japan to rule Taiwan caused opinions supporting a hard-line policy against Japan.to increase in Qing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This breakdown in negotiations over the Ryukyu issue and the suspected ambition of Japan to rule Taiwan caused opinions supporting a hard-line policy against Japan.to increase in Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="95">
<j>この結果、領有権問題の解決は1894年(明治27年)の日清戦争後まで持ち越されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As the result, the issue of the teterritorial right was left over unsolved until the end of Japanese-Sino War in 1894.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, the issue of territorial rights was left unresolved until the end of Japanese-Sino War in 1894.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, the issue of territorial rights was left unresolved until the end of Japanese-Sino War in 1894.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>独立党と事大党の対立</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Independence Party and Serve the Great Party</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Independence Party and Serving the Great Party</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Independence Party and Serving the Great Party</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="96">
<j>江華島事件後の朝鮮では、急進的欧米化を進めようとする親日的な開化派（独立党）と、漸進的改革を進めようとする親清的な守旧派（事大党）との対立が激しくなっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In korea after Ganghwa Island incident, confrontation escalated between the Enlightenment Party (Independence Party), the pro-Japanese group seeking radial westernization, and the Conservative Party (Serve the Great&apos; Party), the pro-Qing group seeking gradual reforms.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In korea after the Ganghwa Island incident, confrontation escalated between the Enlightenment Party (Independence Party), the pro-Japanese group seeking radial westernization, and the Conservative Party (Serving the Great&apos; Party), the pro-Qing group seeking gradual reforms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Korea after the Ganghwa Island incident, confrontation escalated between the Enlightenment Party (Independence Party), the pro-Japanese group seeking radial westernization, and the Conservative Party (Serving the Great&apos; Party), the pro-Qing group seeking gradual reforms.</e>
<cmt>Koreaの頭文字を大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="97">
<j>それとともに、開化派を支援する日本と守旧派を支援する清との対立も表面化してきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this, a confornation between Japan supporting the Enlightenment Party and China supporting the Conservative Party became prominent.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this, conformation between Japan supporting the Enlightenment Party and China supporting the Conservative Party became prominent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this, conformation between Japan supporting the Enlightenment Party and China supporting the Conservative Party became prominent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>壬午事変と甲申政変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jingo Incident and Gapsin Coup</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jingo Incident and Gapsin Coup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jingo Incident and Gapsin Coup</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="98">
<j>日朝修好条規締約後の朝鮮では日本の支援による兵制改革で軍人が失職し、残った旧式軍隊にも給与が遅配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In Korea after Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity, the military system reform with Japanese support made many solders unemployed, and the remaining soldiers in the old-fashioned military force were not paid in time.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Korea after Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was concluded, military system reform with Japanese support left many solders unemployed, and the remaining soldiers in the old-fashioned military force were not paid on time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Korea after Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity was concluded, military system reform with Japanese support left many solders unemployed, and the remaining soldiers in the old-fashioned military force were not paid on time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>また開国後の貿易で日本への米輸出による米価高騰と食糧危機が民衆を圧迫していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also rice exports to Japan due to the trade following the opening of the country caused soaring rice price and food crisis and put people&apos;s lives under pressure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also rice exports to Japan due to trade after opening of the country caused soaring rice prices and food crisis and put people&apos;s lives under pressure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also rice exports to Japan due to trade after opening of the country caused soaring rice prices and food crisis and put people&apos;s lives under pressure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="100">
<j>1882年7月、旧式軍の兵士と市民が漢城で蜂起して新編成の「別技軍」の日本人教官らを殺害し日本公使館を包囲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In July 1882, the old-fashioned solders and civilians rose up in revolt in Hanseong and killed Japanese military trainers of newly formed &quot;Byeolgigun (a modernized special military force)&quot; and seized Japanese legation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In July 1882, the old-fashioned solders and civilians rose up in revolt in Hanseong and killed the Japanese military trainers of the newly formed &quot;Byeolgigun (a modernized special military force)&quot; and seized the Japanese legation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In July 1882, the old-fashioned solders and civilians rose up in revolt in Hanseong and killed the Japanese military trainers of the newly formed &quot;Byeolgigun (a modernized special military force)&quot; and seized the Japanese legation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>翌日には政府と王宮を襲い領議政(首相)と旻氏系高官らを殺害した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the following day, the rioters attacked the government and palace and killed the supreme leader (prime minister) and high ranking officials of Min family.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the following day, the rioters attacked the government and the palace and killed the supreme leader (prime minister) and high ranking officials of the Min family.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the following day, the rioters attacked the government and the palace and killed the supreme leader (prime minister) and high ranking officials of the Min family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="102">
<j>公使館が焼失し(公使自ら火を放つ)、日本人10数人が殺害される事態となった(壬午事変)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legation was burnt down (because fire set by the minister himself) and dozens of Japanese were killed (Jingo Incident).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legation was burnt down (because of fire set by the minister himself) and dozens of Japanese were killed (Jingo Incident).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legation was burnt down (because of fire set by the minister himself) and dozens of Japanese were killed (Jingo Incident).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="103">
<j>日清両国が出兵し、日本から軍を率いた花房義質公使が派遣された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Japanese and Qing sent their forcee;Japanese force led by Yoshimoto HANABUSA, the minister to Korea, was sent.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Japanese and Qing sent their forces; the Japanese force was led by Yoshimoto HANABUSA, the minister to Korea, was also sent.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Japanese and Qing sent their forces; the Japanese force was led by Yoshimoto HANABUSA, the minister to Korea, was also sent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>8月30日、朝鮮と済物浦条約を調印し、日本人被害者への補償5万円、公使館の損害と日本の出兵への補填金50万円と公使館警護のため若干の軍隊の漢城駐留などを取り決めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 30, theJemulpo Treaty was signed with Korea in which Korea promised to pay 50 thousand yen for Japanese victims and 50 thousand yen for damaged legation and compensation for dispatching Japanese forces and allowed small-scale Japanese military presence in Hanseong.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 30, the Jemulpo Treaty was signed with Korea in which Korea promised to pay 50,000 yen for Japanese victims and 50,000 yen for damaged legation and compensation for dispatching Japanese forces and allowed a small-scale Japanese military presence in Hanseong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 30, the Jemulpo Treaty was signed with Korea in which Korea promised to pay 50,000 yen for Japanese victims and 50,000 yen for damaged legation and compensation for dispatching Japanese forces and allowed a small-scale Japanese military presence in Hanseong.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="105">
<j>事変後清は袁世凱らが指揮する軍隊を朝鮮に駐留させ、軍隊訓練や政府顧問をおくなど朝鮮の軍事や内政に積極的に関与した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the incident, Qing began to get actively involved in military and internal affairs of Korea by stationing its military force led by YUAN Shiva in Korea for military training and posting an adviser in the government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the incident, Qing began to get actively involved in the military and internal affairs of Korea by stationing its military force led by YUAN Shiva in Korea for military training and posting an adviser in the government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the incident, Qing began to get actively involved in the military and internal affairs of Korea by stationing its military force led by YUAN Shiva in Korea for military training and posting an adviser in the government.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="106">
<j>1884年6月、ベトナムをめぐるフランスとの対立で朝鮮駐留清軍の半数が帰還した（清仏戦争）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In June 1884, half of Quing troops stationed in Korea returned because of confrontation with France over Vietnam (Sino-French War).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In June 1884, half of Quing troops stationed in Korea returned because of a confrontation with France over Vietnam (Sino-French War).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In June 1884, half of Quing troops stationed in Korea returned because of a confrontation with France over Vietnam (Sino-French War).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="107">
<j>事変後政治的に後退していた日本は竹添進一郎公使を10月30日漢城に帰任させ、済物浦条約の未払い分40万円の返上を申し出させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan in political regression after the incident made Shinichiro TAKEZOE return to his post of the minister to Korea in Hanseong on October 30 and proposed to give up unpaid 40 thousand yen required in the Jemulpo Treaty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan in political regression after the incident made Shinichiro TAKEZOE return to his post as minister to Korea in Hanseong on October 30 and he proposed to give up an unpaid 40,000 yen required in the Jemulpo Treaty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan in political regression after the incident made Shinichiro TAKEZOE return to his post as minister to Korea in Hanseong on October 30 and he proposed to give up an unpaid 400,000 yen required in the Jemulpo Treaty.</e>
<cmt>40,000 yenを400,00 yenに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>開化派は日本公使の支援を利用して事大派政権打倒を計画した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Enlightenment Party planed to use support of the Japanese minister to overthrow the government led by the Serve the Great Party.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Enlightenment Party planed to use the support of the Japanese minister to overthrow the government led by Serving the Great Party.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Enlightenment Party planed to use the support of the Japanese minister to overthrow the government led by Serving the Great Party.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="109">
<j>12月4日郵政局開局祝賀宴に際し事大派要人を襲撃、その後王宮内で6人の大臣を殺害するなどして5日に新しい政権を発足させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On December 4, the Enlightenment Party attacked leaders of the Serve the Great Party in a banquet to celebrate the opening of Postal Agency and six ministers in the palace, and inaugurated new administration on 5th.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On December 4, the Enlightenment Party attacked leaders of Serving the Great Party in a banquet to celebrate the opening of the Postal Agency and six ministers in the palace, and inaugurated a new administration on the 5th.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On December 4, the Enlightenment Party attacked leaders of Serving the Great Party in a banquet to celebrate the opening of the Postal Agency and six ministers in the palace, and inaugurated a new administration on the 5th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>しかし6日に清の武力介入により失敗した(甲申政変)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On 6th, however, this coup was aborted due to military intervention of Qing.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On 6th, however, this coup was aborted due to military intervention by the Qing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On 6th, however, this coup was aborted due to military intervention by the Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="111">
<j>なお、4日夜から日本公使は警護兵百数十を連れて朝鮮王宮に国王保護の名目で参内した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also Japanese minister with a hundred and several tens of escorting soldiers entered the Korean palace at night on 4th on the pretext of protecting the king.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also Japanese minister with a hundred and several tens of escorting soldiers entered the Korean palace at night on 4th on the pretext of protecting the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also Japanese minister with a hundred and several tens of escorting soldiers entered the Korean palace at night on 4th on the pretext of protecting the king.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="112">
<j>開化派を支援しており、重大な内政干渉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is an assistance to the Enlightenment Party and serious interference in the internal affairs.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was an assistance to the Enlightenment Party and a serious interference in internal affairs.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was an assistance to the Enlightenment Party and a serious interference in internal affairs.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="113">
<j>また、清軍との間に王宮で戦闘が続き、双方に死者を出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Additionally, a conflict with Quing continued in the palace, leading deaths in the both sides.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a conflict with the Quing continued in the palace, leading to deaths on both sides.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a conflict with the Quing continued in the palace, leading to deaths on both sides.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>これは近代における日中間の最初の武力衝突となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the first armed conflict between Japan and china in modern times.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was the first armed conflict between Japan and china in modern times.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was the first armed conflict between Japan and china in modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="115">
<j>この時またも公使館が全焼し日本人に30数名の犠牲者を出し、日本国内では朝鮮、中国への反感が高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The legation was completely burned down and more than 30 Japanese people died, provoking antipathy to Korea and China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The legation was completely burned down and more than thirty Japanese people died, provoking antipathy to Korea and China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The legation was completely burned down and more than thirty Japanese people died, provoking antipathy to Korea and China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="116">
<j>天津条約と日本の軍備拡大</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Treaty of Tianjin and military expansion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Treaty of Tianjin and Military Expansion</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Treaty of Tianjin and Military Expansion</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>1885年4月全権大使伊藤博文と李鴻章により天津条約が結ばれ、四ヶ月以内の日清両軍の朝鮮からの撤退と、以後出兵時の事前通告および事態の沈静化後すみやかに撤収すべきことが定められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Plenipotentiary Hirobumi ITO and Li Hung Chang signed Treaty of Tianjin, which provided that both Japanese and Qing troops withdraw from Korea within 4 months and hereafter give a prior notice in dispatching their troops, and call troops home as soon as things have calmed down.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Plenipotentiary Hirobumi ITO and Li Hung Chang signed the Treaty of Tianjin, which provided that both Japanese and Qing troops will withdraw from Korea within four months and hereafter give a prior notice in dispatching their troops, and call troops home as soon as things have calmed down.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Plenipotentiary Hirobumi ITO and Li Hung Chang signed the Treaty of Tianjin, which provided that both Japanese and Qing troops will withdraw from Korea within four months and hereafter give a prior notice in dispatching their troops, and call troops home as soon as things have calmed down.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>その後10年間外国軍隊の朝鮮駐留はなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the following 10 years, no foreign troops did not stay in Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the following ten years, no foreign troops stayed in Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the following ten years, no foreign troops stayed in Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="119">
<j>しかし、これらの事変後明治政府は軍備拡大を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Mieji government promoted buildup of military forces after this incident.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Mieji government promoted the buildup of military forces.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Mieji government promoted the buildup of military forces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="120">
<j>1882年8月山県有朋は煙草税増税分による軍備拡張を、9月岩倉具視は清を仮想敵国とする海軍軍拡と増税を建議した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aritomo YAMAGATA proposed to build up military forces by increasing the tax on cigarettes in August 1882, and Tomomi IWAKURA proposed to increase taxes to build up Navy setting up Qing as an imaginary enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aritomo YAMAGATA proposed building up the military forces by increasing the tax on cigarettes in August 1882, and Tomomi IWAKURA proposed to increase taxes to build up the Navy, setting up Qing as an imaginary enemy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aritomo YAMAGATA proposed building up the military forces by increasing the tax on cigarettes in August 1882, and Tomomi IWAKURA proposed to increase taxes to build up the Navy, setting up Qing as an imaginary enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="121">
<j>陸軍は3年後からの兵力倍増を、海軍は翌年からの8カ年で48隻の建艦計画をたてた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Army planned to double solders and the Navy planed to build 48 warships in 8 years starting the following year.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Army planned to double it&apos;s solders and the Navy planned to build fourty-eight warships in eight years begining the following year.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Army planned to double it&apos;s solders and the Navy planned to build 48 warships in eight years begining the following year.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="122">
<j>これにより、歳出に占める軍事費の割合は1882年度17.4%だったものが、1890年度には30%を超えるまでに増大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With these plans, the ratio of military expenditure to the total annual expenditure increased 17.4% in the fiscal 1882 to more than 30% in the fiscal 1890.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With these plans, the ratio of military expenditure to the total annual expenditure increased 17.4% in fiscal 1882 to more than 30% in fiscal 1890.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With these plans, the ratio of military expenditure to the total annual expenditure increased 17.4% in fiscal 1882 to more than 30% in fiscal 1890.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="123">
<j>また、1883年には徴兵令を改正し、免役規定中の代人料を廃止して兵員増をはかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Conscription Ordinance was revised in 1883 with an aim to increase soldiers by abolishing a payment for a substitute to be exempt from conscription that is provided in the exemption clause.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, a Conscription Ordinance was revised in 1883 aiming at increasing soldiers by abolishing payment for substitutes to be exempt from conscription provided for in the exemption clause.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, a Conscription Ordinance was revised in 1883 aiming at increasing soldiers by abolishing payment for substitutes to be exempt from conscription provided for in the exemption clause.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="124">
<j>1888年には従来の内乱鎮圧型の鎮台を改編し、6師団と近衛師団を創設して海外での戦闘能力を高めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1888, the conventional garrison--the system effective fro claiming domestic conflicts--was reorganized with the creation of 6 divisions and Guards Division to increase abilities to fight abroad.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1888, the conventional garrison --the system effective for claiming domestic conflicts-- was reorganized with the creation of six divisions and Guard Divisions to increase the ability to fight abroad.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1888, the conventional garrison --the system effective for claiming domestic conflicts-- was reorganized with the creation of six divisions and Guard Divisions to increase the ability to fight abroad.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="125">
<j>1889年には徴兵令の免除規定を全廃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1889, the exemption clause was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1889, the exemption clause was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1889, the exemption clause was completely abolished.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="126">
<j>1886年8月には清の北洋艦隊のうち定遠など4隻の軍艦が長崎港に入港した際、上陸した水兵が日本の警官隊と衝突し、双方に死傷者を出す(死者日本側2名、清側8名)騒ぎ(長崎事件)となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August 1866, when four fleets including the Dingyuan of the Qing North Sea Fleet arrived in port in Nagasaki, sailors that landed had conflicts with Japanese police force, resulting in deaths of the both sides (2 deaths in the Japanese side and 6 deaths in the Qing side) (Nagasaki incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1866, when four fleets including the Dingyuan of the Qing North Sea Fleet arrived in port in Nagasaki, sailors that landed entered into conflict with the Japanese police force, resulting in deaths on both sides (two deaths on the Japanese side and six deaths on the Qing side) (Nagasaki incident)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1866, when four fleets including the Dingyuan of the Qing North Sea Fleet arrived in port in Nagasaki, sailors that landed entered into conflict with the Japanese police force, resulting in deaths on both sides (two deaths on the Japanese side and six deaths on the Qing side) (Nagasaki incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>甲午農民戦争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Donghak Peasant Revolution</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Donghak Peasant Revolution</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Donghak Peasant Revolution</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="127">
<j>両事変後、朝鮮において日本は経済的に進出し、90年代朝鮮の貿易で日本は輸出の90%以上、輸入の50%を占めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the two incidents in korea, Japan had promoted economic presence, and Japanese exports occupied more than 90% and Japanese imports accounted for 50% in the Korean trade in the 1890&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the two incidents that occurred in korea, Japan had promoted an economic presence, and Japanese exports amounted to more than 90% and Japanese imports accounted for 50% in Korean trade during the 1890&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the two incidents that occurred in korea, Japan had promoted an economic presence, and Japanese exports amounted to more than 90% and Japanese imports accounted for 50% in Korean trade during the 1890&apos;s.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="128">
<j>米・大豆価格の高騰と地方官の搾取、賠償金支払いの圧力などが農村経済を疲弊させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The rural economy was became exhausted because of soaring rice and soybean prices, exploitation of local officials and pressure to pay compensation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The rural economy was becaming exhausted because of the soaring rice and soybean prices, exploitation of local officials and pressure to pay compensation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The rural economy was becaming exhausted because of the soaring rice and soybean prices, exploitation of local officials and pressure to pay compensation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="129">
<j>1894年5月に朝鮮で、東学教団構成員の全琫準を指導者として民生改善と日・欧の侵出阻止を求める農民反乱である甲午農民戦争（東学党の乱）が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In May 1894, Tonghak Peasant Revolution led by Jeon Bong Jun--a member of Tonghak religious community-- occurred in Korea, calling for improvement of the people&apos;s livelihood and prevention of invasions of Japan and Western countries.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In May 1894, the Tonghak Peasant Revolution led by Jeon Bong Jun --a member of the Tonghak religious community-- occurred in Korea, calling for improvement of the people&apos;s livelihood and prevention of invasions from Japan and Western countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In May 1894, the Tonghak Peasant Revolution led by Jeon Bong Jun --a member of the Tonghak religious community-- occurred in Korea, calling for improvement of the people&apos;s livelihood and prevention of invasions from Japan and Western countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="130">
<j>5月31日には全羅道首都全州を占領した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 31, Jeonju, the capital ofJeolla Province was occupied.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 31, Jeonju, the capital ofJeolla Province was occupied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 31, Jeonju, the capital ofJeolla Province was occupied.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="131">
<j>これにより6月1日朝鮮政府は清の派兵を要請する一方、農民軍への宣撫にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 1, the Korean government asked Qing to dispatch troops and tried to pacify the armed peasants.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 1, the Korean government asked Qing to dispatch troops and tried to pacify the armed peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 1, the Korean government asked Qing to dispatch troops and tried to pacify the armed peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="132">
<j>6月11日農民軍の弊政改革案を受け入れて全州和約を結び、清および日本の武力介入を避けるべく農民軍は撤退した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 11, the government accepted the government reform plan proposed by the peasants, and the peasants withdrew to prevent military intervention of Qing and Japan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 11, the government accepted the government reform plan proposed by the peasants, and the peasants withdrew to prevent military intervention by the Qing and Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 11, the government accepted the government reform plan proposed by the peasants, and the peasants withdrew to prevent military intervention by the Qing and Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="133">
<j>清は6月7日には日本に派兵を通告し12日に900名の軍隊が牙山に上陸した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing informed Japan of the dispatch of the troops on June 7, and 900 soldiers landed Asan on 12th.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing informed Japan of the dispatch of the troops on June 7, and 900 soldiers landed at Asan on the 12th.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing informed Japan of the dispatch of the troops on June 7, and 900 soldiers landed at Asan on the 12th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>日本の伊藤博文内閣は議会との激しい対立（5月30日、内閣弾劾上奏案可決）により政治的に行き詰まっており、対外的に強硬にでて事態打開をはかろうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese Hirobumi ITO cabinet had ran out of policies in the fierce confrontation with Diets (because bill of cabinet impeachment report to the throne was adopted on May 30) and tried to break the deadlock by resorting to an external hard-line policy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Hirobumi ITO cabinet had run out of policies during the fierce confrontation with the Diet (because the bill of the cabinet impeachment report to the throne was adopted on May 30) and tried to break the deadlock by resorting to an external hard-line policy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Hirobumi ITO cabinet had run out of policies during the fierce confrontation with the Diet (because the bill of the cabinet impeachment report to the throne was adopted on May 30) and tried to break the deadlock by resorting to an external hard-line policy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="135">
<j>6月2日閣議は衆議院解散と公使館、居留民保護の名目で朝鮮への混成一個旅団8000名の派兵を決定した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 2, the cabinet dissolved the house of Representatives and decided to send a mixed brigade consisting of 8000 soldiers to Korea in the pretext of protecting Japanese residents in Korea.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 2, the cabinet dissolved the house of Representatives and decided to send a mixed brigade consisting of 8,000 soldiers to Korea on the pretext of protecting Japanese residents in Korea.</e>
<cmt>punctuation, grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 2, the cabinet dissolved the house of Representatives and decided to send a mixed brigade consisting of 8,000 soldiers to Korea on the pretext of protecting Japanese residents in Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>5日には史上初の大本営を設置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 5, the Imperial headquarters was set up for the first time in history.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 5, Imperial headquarters was set up for the first time in history.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 5, Imperial headquarters was set up for the first time in history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="137">
<j>6月10日海軍陸戦隊400と大鳥圭介公使が漢城に入り、後続部隊を合わせて4000名の混成旅団が首都周辺に駐留することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 10, 400 squadrons ofJapanese Navy Land Forces and the minister to Korea Keisuke OTORI entered Hanseong with a plan that the total of 4000 solders of mixed brigade with the following troops would be stationed in the capital and surrounding area</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 10, 400 squadrons of Japanese Navy, Land Forces, and the minister to Korea Keisuke OTORI entered Hanseong with a plan that a total of 4,000 solders of mixed brigades with the following troops would be stationed in the capital and the surrounding area</e>
<cmt>grammar, spacing punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 10, 400 squadrons of Japanese Navy, Land Forces, and the minister to Korea Keisuke OTORI entered Hanseong with a plan that a total of 4,000 solders of mixed brigades with the following troops would be stationed in the capital and the surrounding area.</e>
<cmt>最後にピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>しかし既に農民軍は撤収しており天津条約上でも日本軍の派兵理由は無くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However the armed peasants had been withdrawn, and the cause of the dispatch of Japanese troops had disappeared.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However the armed peasants had withdrawn, and the cause of the dispatch of Japanese troops had disappeared.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However the armed peasants had withdrawn, and the reason of the dispatch of Japanese troops based on Treaty of Tianjin had disappeared.</e>
<cmt>天津条約が抜けていたため補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>清も軍を増派したが首都に入ることは控えて牙山を動かなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quing increased its troops but did not move from Asan without entering the capital.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quing increased its troops, but did not move from Asan to enter the capital.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quing increased its troops, but did not move from Asan to enter the capital.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>開戦準備・日清戦争開戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Preparing for the start of a war and the start of Japanese-Sino War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Preparing for the start of a war and the start of the Japanese-Sino War</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Preparing for the start of a war and the start of the Japanese-Sino War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="140">
<j>甲午農民戦争の停戦後、朝鮮政府は日清両軍の撤兵を要請したが、どちらも受け入れなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Donghak Peasant Revolution the Korean government requested both Japan Qing troops to withdraw their troops, but neither accepted it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Donghak Peasant Revolution the Korean government requested both Japan and Qing to withdraw their troops, but neither accepted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Donghak Peasant Revolution the Korean government requested both Japan and Qing to withdraw their troops, but neither accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>伊藤内閣は6月15日、朝鮮の内政改革を日清共同で進める、清が拒否すれば日本単独で指導するという方針を閣議決定し清に通告し、清がこれを拒否した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Ito cabinet decided on its policy in the cabinet meeting that both Japan and Qing would jointly reform the internal system of Korea and, if Qing refused to do so, Japan solely would undertake instructions, and Qing refused when informed of the decision.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Ito cabinet decided on its policy in the cabinet meeting that both Japan and Qing would jointly reform the internal system of Korea and, if Qing refused, Japan would solely undertake the instructions, and Qing refused when informed of the decision.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 15, the Ito cabinet decided on its policy in the cabinet meeting that both Japan and Qing would jointly reform the internal system of Korea and, if Qing refused, Japan would solely undertake the instructions, and Qing refused when informed of the decision.</e>
<cmt>6月15日が抜けていました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="142">
<j>7月16日条約改正交渉の結果、領事裁判権を廃止する日英通商航海条約調印を経て、20日大鳥公使は朝鮮政府に清軍の撤退と朝清間の条約廃棄を3日間の期限で回答するよう通告した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation was signed on July 16 as the result of negotiation over treaty revisions to do away with consular jurisdiction right, the Minister Oshima gave the notice to the Korean government requesting withdrawal of Qing troops and denunciation of Sino-Korean treaties with a response within 3 days.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation was signed on July 16 as the result of negotiation over treaty revisions to do away with consular jurisdiction right, Minister Oshima gave notice to the Korean government requesting the withdrawal of Qing troops and the denunciation of Sino-Korean treaties with a response demanded within three days.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation was signed on July 16 as the result of negotiation over treaty revisions to do away with consular jurisdiction right, Minister Oshima gave notice to the Korean government requesting the withdrawal of Qing troops and the denunciation of Sino-Korean treaties with a response demanded within three days.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>朝鮮政府は日清両軍の撤兵要求を回答、7月23日未明に陸軍第五師団の二個大隊が漢城の電信線を切断して朝鮮王宮を3時間にわたり攻撃・占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Korean government responded that it wanted the both Japanese and Qing troops to withdraw, and then two battalions of the 5th Divisions of Army cut the telegraph wire in Hanseong and occupied Korean Palace after 3 hours of attack.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Korean government responded that it wanted both Japanese and Qing troops to withdraw, and then two battalions of the fifth Army Division cut the telegraph wire in Hanseong and occupied the Korean Palace after a three hour attack.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Korean government responded that it wanted both Japanese and Qing troops to withdraw, and early on July 23, two battalions of the fifth Army Division cut the telegraph wire in Hanseong and occupied the Korean Palace after a three hour attack.</e>
<cmt>「7月23日　未明」が抜けていたので補足しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>これは開戦の名義を立てるために朝鮮政府の閔氏一族を追放し、大院君を再び担ぎだして政権を樹立して日本に清軍の朝鮮からの撃退を要請させるためであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The purpose was to obtain justification for opening war by pushing Ming family out of the Korean government to get Daewongun to hold again power and requesting Japan to drive back Qing army from Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The purpose was to obtain justification for opening a war by pushing the Ming family out of the Korean government to get Daewongun to again hold power and request that Japan drive back the Qing army from Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The purpose was to obtain justification for opening a war by pushing the Ming family out of the Korean government to get Daewongun to again hold power and request that Japan drive back the Qing army from Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>その後7月25日豊島沖海戦が、また29日に牙山攻撃が行われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then Battle of Pungdo broke out on July 25 and Assan attack on 29.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the Battle of Pungdo broke out on July 25 and the Assan attack commenced on the 29th.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the Battle of Pungdo broke out on July 25 and the Assan attack commenced on the 29th.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>宣戦布告は8月1日である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War was declared on August 1.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War was declared on August 1st.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War was declared on August 1st.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="147">
<j>なお、日本政府の強引な開戦工作に対して、明治天皇は以下のように述べ怒りを発していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For reference, Emperor Meiji is said to have shown his anger by saying the following.</e>
<cmt>「怒りを発していた。」を結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For reference, Emperor Meiji is said to have shown his anger by saying the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For reference, Emperor Meiji is said to have shown his anger by saying the following.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>「これは朕の戦争に非ず。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;This was is not what I want.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;This was is not what I want.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was is not what I want.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>「大臣の戦争なり」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ministers want it.</e>
<cmt>「怒りを発していた。」を結合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The ministers want it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The ministers want it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>宣戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War Declaration</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War Declaration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War Declaration</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="150">
<j>日本政府が、国民に伝えた宣戦の理由（清国ニ対スル宣戦ノ詔勅）の要旨は次のようなものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese government told people the outline of the cause for the war (Imperial Rescript of war declaration against Qing) as follows</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese government explained to the people the outline of the cause for the war (Imperial Rescript of war declaration against Qing) as follows;</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese government explained to the people the outline of the cause for the war (Imperial Rescript of war declaration against Qing) as follows;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="151">
<j>「そもそも、朝鮮は日本と日朝修好条規を締結して開国した独立の一国である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;In principle, Korea is an independent country that opened the country and concluded Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity with Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;In principle, Korea is an independent country that opened the country and concluded a Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity with Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In principle, Korea is an independent country that opened the country and concluded a Japanese-Korea Treaty of Amity with Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>ダブルクォーテーションからクォーテーションに直しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="152">
<j>「それにもかかわらず、清国は朝鮮を属邦と称して、内政干渉し、朝鮮を救うとの名目で出兵した。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Qing has intervened in the domestic affairs of Korea saying Korea is a tributary state, so Japan has dispatched troops for the cause of saving Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Qing has intervened in the domestic affairs of Korea saying Korea is a tributary state, so Japan has dispatched troops to save Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Qing has intervened in the domestic affairs of Korea saying Korea is a tributary state, so Japan has dispatched troops for the cause of saving Korea.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>「日本は済物浦条約に基づき、出兵して変に備えさせて、朝鮮での争いを永久になくし、東洋全局の平和を維持しようと思い、清国に協同して事に従おうと提案した。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, with an intention to remove conflicts eternally in Korea and maintain peace in the entire East, dispatched troops under the Jemulpo Treaty and proposed Quing to work together to do so.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, with an intention to remove conflicts eternally in Korea and maintain peace in the entire East, dispatched troops under the Jemulpo Treaty and proposed Quing to work together to do so.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, with an intention to remove conflicts eternally in Korea and maintain peace in the entire East, dispatched troops under the Jemulpo Treaty and proposed Quing to work together to do so.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="154">
<j>「しかし、清国は様々な言い訳をしてこれを拒否した。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Qing refused it with various excuses.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Qing refused to cooperate with various excuses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Qing refused it with various excuses.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>「日本は朝鮮の独立を保つため朝鮮に改革を勧めて朝鮮もこれを肯諾した。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan advised Korea to carry out a reform to keep the country independent, and Korea accepted it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan advised Korea to carry out a reform to keep the country independent, and Korea accepted it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan advised Korea to carry out a reform to keep the country independent, and Korea accepted it.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>「しかし、清国はそれを妨害し、朝鮮に大軍を送り、また朝鮮沖で日本の軍艦を攻撃した（豊島沖海戦）。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Qing prevented this and sent a large force and attacked Japanese warship off korea (Battle of Pungdo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Qing prevented this and sent a large force and attacked Japanese warship off korea (Battle of Pungdo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Qing prevented this and sent a large force and attacked Japanese warship off korea (Battle of Pungdo).&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>「日本が朝鮮の治安の責任を負い、独立国とさせた朝鮮の地位と天津条約とを否定し、日本の権利・利益を損傷し、そして東洋の平和を保障させない清国の計画は明白である。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">China has a clear plot to deny Japan&apos;s responsibility for public safety, independency of Korea and Treaty of Tianjin, hamper the right and interest of Japan, and prevent peace in the East.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">China has a clear plot to deny Japan&apos;s responsibility for public safety, the independency of Korea, and the Treaty of Tianjin, hamper the rights and interests of Japan, and prevent peace in the East.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">China has a clear plot to deny Japan&apos;s responsibility for public safety, the independency of Korea, and the Treaty of Tianjin, hamper the rights and interests of Japan, and prevent peace in the East.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>「清国は平和を犠牲にして非望を遂げようとするものである。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing tries to achieve its inordinate ambition at the cost of peace.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing tried to achieve its inordinate ambition at the cost of peace.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing tried to achieve its inordinate ambition at the cost of peace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>「事が既にここに至れば、日本は宣戦せざるを得なくなった。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These situations has forced Japan to declare war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These situations have forced Japan to declare war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These situations have forced Japan to declare war.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="160">
<j>「戦争を早期に終結して平和を回復させたいと思う。」</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan intends to terminate the war as soon as possible to recover peace.</e>
<cmt>」を統合しました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan intends to terminate the war as soon as possible to recover peace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan intends to terminate the war as soon as possible to recover peace.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテンションで閉じました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>戦争の経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Progression of war</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Progression of war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Progression of war</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>豊島沖海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Pungdo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Pungdo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Pungdo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="161">
<j>1894年7月25日、豊島沖で大日本帝国海軍第1遊撃隊（司令官坪井航三少将、「吉野 (防護巡洋艦)」「浪速 (防護巡洋艦)」「秋津洲 (防護巡洋艦)」）は、清国軍艦「済遠」「広乙」と遭遇し、戦闘が始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 25, 1894, the first commando unit of Imperial Japanese Navy (commander Kozo TSUBOI &quot;Yoshino (Protected cruiser),&quot; &quot;Naniwa (Protected cruiser),&quot; and &quot;Akitsushima (Protected cruiser)&quot;) encountered Qing warships &quot;Tsi yuen&quot; and &quot;Guangyi&quot; and started war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 25, 1894, the first commando unit of the Imperial Japanese Navy (commander Kozo TSUBOI &quot;Yoshino (defense cruiser),&quot; &quot;Naniwa (defense cruiser),&quot; and &quot;Akitsushima (defense cruiser&quot;) encountered Qing warships &quot;Tsi yuen&quot; and &quot;Guangyi&quot; and started the war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 25, 1894, the first commando unit of the Imperial Japanese Navy (commander Kozo TSUBOI &apos;Yoshino (defense cruiser),&apos; &apos;Naniwa (defense cruiser),&apos; and &apos;Akitsushima (defense cruiser&apos;) encountered Qing warships &apos;Tsi yuen&apos; and &apos;Guangyi&apos; and started the war.</e>
<cmt>ダブル・クォーテーションをクォーテションに変更しました（原文が一重カッコのため）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>優勢な日本海軍の応戦の前に「済遠」は逃亡を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Facing attacks of Japanese army holding the upper hand, the Qing warships tried to escape.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Facing attacks from the Japanese army holding the upper hand, the Qing warships tried to escape.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Facing attacks from the Japanese army holding the upper hand, the Qing warships tried to escape.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="163">
<j>日本海軍の「吉野」「浪速」も、直ちに「済遠」を追撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Yoshino&quot; and &quot;Naniwa&quot; immediately pursued the &quot;Tsi yuen.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Yoshino&quot; and &quot;Naniwa&quot; immediately pursued the &quot;Tsi yuen.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &apos;Yoshino&apos; and &apos;Naniwa&apos; immediately pursued the &apos;Tsi yuen.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>その途上、清国軍艦「操江」及び汽船「高陞号」（イギリス商船旗を掲揚）と遭遇した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the way, the warships encountered Qing warship &quot;Tsao-kiang&quot; and a steamship &quot;Kowshing&quot; (hoisting British merchant ship flag).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the way, the warships encountered Qing warship &quot;Tsao-kiang&quot; and a steamship &quot;Kowshing&quot; (hoisting a British merchant ship flag).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the way, the warships encountered Qing warship &apos;Tsao-kiang&apos; and a steamship &apos;Kowshing&apos; (hoisting a British merchant ship flag).</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="165">
<j>「高陞号」は、戦争準備行動として仁川広域市に清国兵約1100名を輸送中であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Kowshing&quot; is transporting about Qing 1100 soldiers to Incheon Metropolitan city for preparation for war.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Kowshing&quot; was transporting about Qing 1,100 soldiers to Incheon Metropolitan city to prepare for war.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kowshing&apos; was transporting about Qing 1,100 soldiers to Incheon Metropolitan city to prepare for war.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>第1遊撃隊司令官の命により「浪速」艦長の東郷平八郎大佐は「高陞号」に停船を命じて臨検を行うように発砲し、清国兵が停船命令に従わないため、魚雷で「高陞号」を撃沈する（高陞号事件）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Heihachiro TOGO, the captain at the order of the commander of the first commando unit ordered to stop for inspection by threatening with fire, but torpedoed and sunk the steamship. (Kowshing Incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Heihachiro TOGO, the captain commanding the first commando unit, gave an order to stop for inspection after threatening with fire, but torpedoed and sunk the steamship. (Kowshing Incident)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the order from the commander of the first commando unit, Heihachiro TOGO, the commanding officer of &apos;Naniwa&apos; requested &apos;Kowshing&apos; to stop for inspection after warning fire, but when Qing soldiers ignored, he torpedoed the steamship (Kowshing Incident).</e>
<cmt>「浪速」艦長、「高陞号」などが抜けていたので、挿入しました。またクォーテーションに変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>この時、英国人船員ら3人を救助し、約50人の清国兵を捕虜とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, he rescored three British crews and took about 50 Qing prisoners.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, he rescored three British crews and took about fifty Qing prisoners.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, he rescored three British crews and took about fifty Qing prisoners.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="168">
<j>豊島沖海戦による、日本側の死傷者及び艦船の損害は皆無であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There was no Japanese side causalities and damage at all in the Battle of Pungdo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There were no Japanese causalities nor damage at all on the Japanese side in the Battle of Pungdo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There were no Japanese causalities nor damage at all on the Japanese side in the Battle of Pungdo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="169">
<j>他方、清国側には、「済遠」が大破し、「操江」は「秋津洲」に鹵獲され、「広乙」も破壊された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing had &quot;Tsi yuen &quot;severely damaged, the &quot;Tsao-kiang&quot; seized by the &quot;Akitsushima,&quot; and the &quot;Guangyi&quot; destroyed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing had &quot;Tsi yuen &quot;severely damaged, the &quot;Tsao-kiang&quot; seized by the &quot;Akitsushima,&quot; and the &quot;Guangyi&quot; destroyed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing had &apos;Tsi yuen&apos; severely damaged, the &apos;Tsao-kiang&apos; seized by the &apos;Akitsushima,&apos; and the &apos;Guangyi&apos; destroyed.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="170">
<j>なお、「高陞号」を撃沈したことによって、一時英国の世論が沸騰する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For reference, Public opinion once heated to hear that the &quot;Kowshing&quot; was attacked and sunk.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For reference, Public opinion was heated to hear that the &quot;Kowshing&quot; was attacked and sunk.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For reference, Public opinion was heated to hear that the &apos;Kowshing&apos; was attacked and sunk.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>しかし英国が日本寄りの姿勢だった事もあり、イギリスの国際法の権威、ジョン・ウェストレーキおよびトーマス・アースキン・ホランド博士によって国際法に則った処置であることがタイムズ紙を通して伝わると、英国の世論も沈静化する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the public opinions cooled down because of British stance in favor of Japan allowed the Times to carry opinions of experts of International Law, Doctors John Westlake and Thomas Erskine Holland, that Japan took measures following the International law.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, public opinion cooled down because of the British stance in favor of Japan allowed the Times to carry opinions of experts of International Law, Doctors John Westlake and Thomas Erskine Holland, that Japan took measures following International law.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, public opinion cooled down because of the British stance in favor of Japan allowed the Times to carry opinions of experts of International Law, Doctors John Westlake and Thomas Erskine Holland, that Japan took measures following International law.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>成歓作戦・牙山作戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Seonghwan operations and Asan operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Seonghwan and Asan operations</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Seonghwan and Asan operations</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>6月12日に清国軍が牙山に上陸する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On June 12, the Qing force landed Asan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On June 12, the Qing force landed at Asan</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On June 12, the Qing force landed at Asan.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="173">
<j>7月23日時点で4165名に達する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The number of solders reached 4165 as of July 23.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The number of solders reached 4,165 as of July 23.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The number of solders reached 4,165 as of July 23.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="174">
<j>7月25日に朝鮮政府から大鳥圭介公使に対して、牙山の清国軍撃退が要請される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 25, the Korean government requested Minister Keisuke OTORI to expel the Qing troops in Asan by force</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 25, the Korean government requested Minister Keisuke OTORI to expel the Qing troops in Asan by force</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 25, the Korean government requested Minister Keisuke OTORI to expel the Qing troops in Asan by force</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="175">
<j>7月26日に第9歩兵旅団（旅団長大島義昌少将）にその旨が伝達される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 26, the ninth infantry Brigade (headed by major general Yoshimasa OSHIMA) was informed the request.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 26, the ninth infantry Brigade (headed by major general Yoshimasa OSHIMA) was informed of the request.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 26, the ninth infantry Brigade (headed by major general Yoshimasa OSHIMA) was informed of the request.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="176">
<j>7月29日に日本軍は牙城に篭る清国兵を攻撃する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On July 29, the Japanese army attacked Qing troops staying in their stronghold.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On July 29, the Japanese army attacked Qing troops staying in their stronghold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On July 29, the Japanese army attacked Qing troops staying in their stronghold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="177">
<j>午前2時に、清国兵の襲撃により松崎直臣陸軍歩兵大尉ほかが戦死する（日本側初の戦死者）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 2 AM, a sudden attack of Qing soldiers killed Japanese soldiers including Naomi MATSUZAKI, Infantry Captain (the first war deaths on the Japanese side).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 2 AM, a sudden attack of Qing soldiers killed Japanese soldiers including Naomi MATSUZAKI, Infantry Captain (the first war deaths on the Japanese side).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 2 AM, a sudden attack of Qing soldiers killed Japanese soldiers including Naomi MATSUZAKI, Infantry Captain (the first war deaths on the Japanese side).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="178">
<j>午前7時に日本第9旅団は成歓の敵陣地を制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 7 AM, JIA the 9th brigade gained control of the enemy&apos;s camp in Seonghwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 7 AM, JIA the nineth brigade gained control of the enemy&apos;s camp in Seonghwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 7 AM, JIA the nineth brigade gained control of the enemy&apos;s camp in Seonghwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="179">
<j>両作戦の日本側の死傷者は82名なのに対して、清国兵は500名以上の死傷者を出し、武器等を放棄して平壌まで逃亡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese side had 82 solders killed and injured in the both operation, while the Qing troops having more than 500 casualties threw down their arms weapons and fled to Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese side had 82 solders killed and injured in both operations, while the Qing troops had more than 500 casualties and threw down their arms and fled to Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese side had 82 solders killed and injured in both operations, while the Qing troops had more than 500 casualties and threw down their arms and fled to Pyongyang.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="180">
<j>なお安城渡の戦闘で第21連隊の木口小平二等卒は死んでも信号ラッパを離さずに吹き続けたという逸話が残る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fro reference, there remains a story that a private second class solder of the 21st regiment, Kohei KIGUCHI, never let his signal bugle fall from his lips when killed during a battle in the outside of Anseong.</e>
<cmt>安城渡は、英文名不明（安城の郊外）と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fro reference, there is a story that a private second class solder of the twenty-first regiment, Kohei KIGUCHI, never let his signal bugle fall from his lips when killed during battle on the outside of Anseong.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fro reference, there is a story that a private second class solder of the 21st regiment, Kohei KIGUCHI, never let his signal bugle fall from his lips when killed during battle on the outside of Anseong.</e>
<cmt>アラビア数字に変換しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>平壌作戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Pyongyang Operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pyongyang Operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pyongyang Operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="181">
<j>8月に清国軍は平壌に1万2千名の兵員を集中させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing troops concentrated its 12 thousand solders in Pyongyang in August.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing troops concentrated 12,000 solders in Pyongyang in August.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing troops concentrated 12,000 solders in Pyongyang in August.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="182">
<j>9月15日に日本軍が攻撃を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 15, the Japanese army started to attack them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 15, the Japanese army started to attack them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 15, the Japanese army started to attack them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="183">
<j>攻略に当たっていた日本軍の歩兵第18連隊長佐藤正 (陸軍草創期)大佐は銃弾を受け左足切断の重傷を負う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Colonel Tadashi Satoh, the commander of the 18th infantry regiment of Japanese army (in the pioneer days of Army) engaged in assault was shot at his left leg and suffered serious injury, resulting in ampulatation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Colonel Tadashi Satoh, the commander of the eighteenth infantry regiment of the Japanese army (in the pioneer days of the Army) engaged in an assault and was shot in his left leg, suffering serious injury, resulting in an amputation.</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Colonel Tadashi Satoh, the commander of the 18th infantry regiment of the Japanese army (in the pioneer days of the Army) engaged in an assault and was shot in his left leg, suffering serious injury, resulting in an amputation.</e>
<cmt>「18連隊」をアラビア数字に変換しました（二桁のため）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="184">
<j>同日午後4時40分に清国軍は白旗を掲げて翌日の開城を約した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 4:40 in the afternoon on the same day, the Qing troop raised a flag of surrender and promised to open the castle the following day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 4:40 in the afternoon on the same day, the Qing troop raised a flag of surrender and promised to open the castle the following day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 4:40 in the afternoon on the same day, the Qing troop raised a flag of surrender and promised to open the castle the following day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="185">
<j>ところが、清国軍は、約を違えて逃亡を図る。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Qing broke the promise and tried to flee.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the Qing broke the promise and tried to flee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the Qing broke the promise and tried to flee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="186">
<j>同日夜に日本軍が入城する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At night on the same day, the Japanese troops entered the castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At night of the same day, the Japanese troops entered the castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At night of the same day, the Japanese troops entered the castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>黄海海戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Yalu River</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Yalu River</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Yalu River</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="187">
<j>黄海上で遭遇した日清両艦隊は、9月17日12時50分に「定遠」から攻撃が開始される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japanese and Qing warships met on Yellow Sea, a the battle started with an attack of &quot;Dingyuan&quot; at 12:50 on September 17.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Japanese and Qing warships met on the Yellow Sea, a the battle started with an attack by the&quot;Dingyuan&quot; at 12:50 on September 17th.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Japanese and Qing warships met on the Yellow Sea, a the battle started with an attack by the &apos;Dingyuan&apos; at 12:50 on September 17th.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="188">
<j>日本側は連合艦隊司令長官伊東祐亨中将率いる旗艦「松島 (巡洋艦)」以下8隻と第一遊撃隊司令長官坪井航三少将率いる旗艦「吉野 (防護巡洋艦)」以下4隻であるのに対して、清国艦隊は丁汝昌提督率いる「定遠」「鎮遠」等14隻と水雷艇4隻であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese force consisted of a flagship &quot;Matsushima&quot; led by Commander-in-Chief of the Combined Fleet Lieutenant General Yuko ITO and other 8 warships as well as a flagship &quot;Yoshino&quot; led by the commander of the first commando unit Major General Kozo TSUBOI and other four warships, while the Qing consisted of &quot;Dingyuan&quot; and &quot;Chen Yuen&quot; led by Adminaral Jyosho TEI and other 14 torpedo boats.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese force consisted of the flagship &quot;Matsushima&quot; led by Commander-in-Chief of the Combined Fleet Lieutenant General Yuko ITO and another eight warships as well as the flagship &quot;Yoshino&quot; led by the commander of the first commando unit Major General Kozo TSUBOI and other four warships, while the Qing consisted of the&quot;Dingyuan&quot; and the &quot;Chen Yuen&quot; led by Adminaral Jyosho TEI and other fourteen torpedo boats.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese force consisted of the flagship &apos;Matsushima&apos; led by Commander-in-Chief of the Combined Fleet Lieutenant General Yuko ITO and another eight warships as well as the flagship &apos;Yoshino&apos; led by the commander of the first commando unit Major General Kozo TSUBOI and other four warships, while the Qing consisted of the&apos;Dingyuan&apos; and the &apos;Chen Yuen&apos; led by Adminaral Jyosho TEI and other 14 torpedo boats.</e>
<cmt>２桁のスペルアウトをアラビア数字に変更しました。全角スペースを半角に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="189">
<j>日本艦隊は、清国「超勇」「致遠」「経遠」等5隻を撃沈し、6隻を大中破「揚威」「広甲 (巡洋艦)」を擱座させる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese squadrons attacked and sunk the &quot;Chaoyong,&quot; &quot;Zhiyuan,&quot; and &quot;King Yuen&quot; and other 5 ships, did a serious or half damage to the &quot;Yangwei&quot; and &quot;Kwan Chia.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese squadrons attacked and sunk the &quot;Chaoyong,&quot; &quot;Zhiyuan,&quot; and &quot;King Yuen&quot; and another five ships, did serious or half damaged the &quot;Yangwei&quot; and &quot;Kwan Chia.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese squadrons attacked and sunk the &apos;Chaoyong,&apos; &apos;Zhiyuan,&apos; and &apos;King Yuen&apos; and another five ships, did serious or half damaged the &apos;Yangwei&apos; and &apos;Kwan Chia.&apos;</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="190">
<j>日本側は4隻の大中破を出し、旗艦「松島」の戦死者の中には勇敢なる水兵と謳われた三浦虎次郎三等水兵もいる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Four warships were seriously or half damaged with war deaths including Petty office third class Torajiro MIURA, who was sung as a brave seaman.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Four warships were seriously or half damaged with war deaths including Petty office third class Torajiro MIURA, who was sung as a brave seaman.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Four warships were seriously or half damaged with war deaths including Petty office third class Torajiro MIURA, who was admired as a brave seaman.</e>
<cmt>謳われる、ここでは具体的な歌によって「歌われた」わけではないようですので、admiredに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="191">
<j>この海戦で日本側が勝利したことによって、清国艦隊は威海衛に閉じこもることとんり、日本海軍は黄海・朝鮮の制海権を確保した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The victory of Japan in this naval battle forced Qing squadrons to be confined in Weihaiwei, bringing Japan the naval supremacy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The victory of Japan in this naval battle forced Qing squadrons to be confined in Weihaiwei, bringing naval supremacy to Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The victory of Japan in this naval battle forced Qing squadrons to be confined in Weihaiwei, bringing naval supremacy to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>鴨緑江作戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Oryokuko Operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Oryokuko Operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Oryokuko Operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="192">
<j>10月25日払暁に、山縣有朋率いる第1軍主力は渡河作戦を開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At dawn on October 25, the first main force led by Aritomo YAMAGATA started a river crossing operation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At dawn on October 25, the first main force led by Aritomo YAMAGATA started a river crossing operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At dawn on October 25, the first main force led by Aritomo YAMAGATA started a river crossing operation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="193">
<j>日本軍の猛勢に恐れをなした清国軍は我先にと逃走を図り、日本軍は九連城を無血で制圧する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Qing solders scared of enormous power of the Japanese troops rushed to escape, and as the result, the Japanese troops brought Jiuliancheng under their control without bloodshed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Qing solders scared of the enormous power of the Japanese troops rushed to escape, and as the result, the Japanese troops brought Jiuliancheng under their control without bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Qing solders scared of the enormous power of the Japanese troops rushed to escape, and as the result, the Japanese troops brought Jiuliancheng under their control without bloodshed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="194">
<j>この作戦成功により、日本軍は初めて清国領土を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this victory of the operation, the Japanese force occupied a territory of Qing for the first time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With this victory of the operation, the Japanese force occupied the territory of Qing for the first time.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With this victory of the operation, the Japanese force occupied the territory of Qing for the first time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>旅順攻略戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War for capture in Lushun</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War for capture in Lushun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War for capture in Lushun</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="195">
<j>10月24日に大山巌大将率いる第2軍が金州に上陸する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 24, the second force led by General Iwao OYAMA landed Jinzhou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 24, the second force led by General Iwao OYAMA landed at Jinzhou.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 24, the second force led by General Iwao OYAMA landed at Jinzhou.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="196">
<j>11月6日に金州城を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 6, the Japanese force seized the castle of Jinzhou.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 6, the Japanese force seized the castle of Jinzhou.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 6, the Japanese force seized the castle of Jinzhou.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="197">
<j>11月21日に、日本軍1万5千は清国1万3千弱に対して攻撃をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 21, the 15 thousand Japanese troops attacked less than 13 thousand Qing troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 21, 15,000 Japanese troops attacked less than 13,000 Qing troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 21, 15,000 Japanese troops attacked less than 13,000 Qing troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="198">
<j>清国軍の士気は極めて低く、堅固な旅順要塞は僅か1日で陥落することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The morale of Qing solders were so weak that Lushun Fortress fell only in a day.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The morale of Qing solders were so weak that the Lushun Fortress fell only in a day.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The morale of Qing solders were so weak that the Lushun Fortress fell only in a day.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="199">
<j>日本側の損害は戦死40名、戦傷241名、行方不明7名に対して、清国は4500名の戦死、捕虜600名を出して敗退する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The casualties on the Japanese side were 40 deaths, 241 injuries, and 7 missing persons, while 4500 died and 600 were held as prisoner on the Qing side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The casualties on the Japanese side were fourty deaths, 241 injuries, and seven missing persons, while 4,500 died and 600 were held as prisoner on the Qing side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The casualties on the Japanese side were fourty deaths, 241 injuries, and seven missing persons, while 4,500 died and 600 were held as prisoner on the Qing side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="200">
<j>攻略そのものは問題なかったが、その後の占領において大きな問題が発生した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The assault itself has no issues to be criticized but a problem occurred in occupation.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The assault itself had no issues to be criticized but a problem occurred during the occupation.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The assault itself had no issues to be criticized but a problem occurred during the occupation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="201">
<j>『タイムズ』（1894年11月28日付）や『ニューヨーク・ワールド』（同年12月12日付）により、「旅順陥落の翌日から四日間、非戦闘員・婦女・幼児などを日本軍が虐殺した」と報じられたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Times (dated on November 28, 1894) and New York World (dated on December 12, 1894) reported, &quot;Japanese troops massacred non military personnel, women, and children for 4 days after Lushun fell.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Times (dated on November 28, 1894) and New York World (dated on December 12, 1894) reported, &quot;Japanese troops massacred non military personnel, women, and children for four days after Lushun fell.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;The Times&quot; (dated on November 28, 1894) and &quot;New York World&quot; (dated on December 12, 1894) reported, &apos;Japanese troops massacred non military personnel, women, and children for four days after Lushun fell.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に従って&apos; &apos;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="202">
<j>虐殺の有無や、虐殺された人数については諸説あるが、実際に従軍し直接見聞した有賀長雄は清国民間人の巻き添えが有ったことを示唆している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Opinions are divided on whether it massacred or not and, if so, how many people were killed, but Nagao ARIGA who were in service and saw or heard there suggested that civilians were involved in the battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Opinions are divided on whether it was a massacre or not and, if so, how many people were killed, but Nagao ARIGA who wasthere in service and saw or heard what happened suggested that civilians were involved in the battle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Opinions are divided on whether it was a massacre or not and, if so, how many people were killed, but Nagao ARIGA who was there in service and saw or heard what happened suggested that civilians were involved in the battle.</e>
<cmt>くっついている単語を切り離しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="203">
<j>現在、この事件は旅順虐殺事件（英名：the Port Arthur Massacre）として知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident is known as the Port Authur Massacre.</e>
<cmt>「（英名：the Port Arthur Massacre）」は訳出していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident is known as the Port Authur Massacre.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident is known as the Port Authur Massacre.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="204">
<j>この事件は外交的に大きな影響をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident had a great diplomatic influence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident had a great diplomatic influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident had a great diplomatic influence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="205">
<j>当時はアメリカと不平等条約改正を交渉中の最中であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident occurred while negotiation to redress unequal treaty Japan and the USA were underway between Japan and the USA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident occurred while negotiations to redress an unequal treaty between Japan and the USA were underway.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident occurred while negotiations to redress an unequal treaty between Japan and the USA were underway.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="206">
<j>この事件により一時アメリカ上院には条約改正は時期尚早という声が大きくなり、重要な外交懸案が危殆に瀕した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After this incident, there was a growing opinions that it is still too soon to revise the treaty in the US upper House for a while, bringing Japan to a crisis over the important diplomatic issues.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After this incident, there were growing opinions that it was still too soon to revise the treaty in the US upper House for a while, bringing Japan to a crisis over important diplomatic issues.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After this incident, there were growing opinions that it was still too soon to revise the treaty in the US upper House for a while, bringing Japan to a crisis over important diplomatic issues.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="207">
<j>陸奥宗光はこのため『ニューヨーク・ワールド』に弁明せざるを得なくなる事態に陥ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This put Japan to make Munemitsu MUTSU make an excuse on the Newyork World.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This put Japan in a position to force Munemitsu MUTSU to make an excuse in Newyork World.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This put Japan in a position to force Munemitsu MUTSU to make an excuse in &apos;Newyork World.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文に従って&apos; &apos;を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>東学農民軍の再蜂起と鎮圧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Recurrent uprising of Armed peasants in Tonghak</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Recurring uprising of Armed peasants in Tonghak</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Recurring uprising of Armed peasants in Tonghak</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="208">
<j>日本軍の王宮占領後、朝鮮では軍用電線の切断、兵站部への襲撃と日本兵の捕縛、殺害など民衆の「義兵」反日抵抗が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Japanese troops conquered the royal palace, there had been anti-Japanese resistance in korea,--cuts of electric cables for military use, attack of logistics bases, and captures and murders of Japanese solders, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Japanese troops conquered the royal palace, there had been anti-Japanese resistance in korea,--cuts of electric cables for military use, attack of logistics on bases, and capture and the murde of Japanese solders, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Japanese troops conquered the royal palace, there had been anti-Japanese resistance in Korea -- cuts of electric cables for military use, attack of logistics on bases, and capture and the murder of Japanese solders, and so forth.</e>
<cmt>Koreaに訂正しました。スペルミスを訂正（murder）しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="209">
<j>1894年10月9日全琫準を指導者とする東学農民軍が侵入した日本軍を秀吉軍の再来と受け止め再蜂起した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On October 9, armed peasants in Tonghak led by Jeon Bong Jun regarded the invading Japanese troops as the second army of Hideyoshi and rose against it.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On October 9, armed peasants in Tonghak led by Jeon Bong Jun regarded the invading Japanese troops as the second army of Hideyoshi and rose against it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On October 9, 1894, armed peasants in Tonghak led by Jeon Bong Jun regarded the invading Japanese troops as the second army of Hideyoshi and rose against it.</e>
<cmt>1894（年）が抜けていたので補いました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="210">
<j>大院君は農民軍鎮圧のための派兵をしないよう大鳥公使に要請したが、日本は部隊(歩兵独立第十九大隊)を11月初めに派兵し、11月下旬からの公州攻防戦で勝利して農民軍を南方へ退けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Daewongun requested Minister OTORI not to send troops to suppress the peasant army, Japan dispatched a military unit (the 19th independent infantry battalion) in early November and won Gongjubattle starting late November, ousting the peasant army out to the south.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Daewongun requested Minister OTORI not to send troops to suppress the peasant army, Japan dispatched a military unit (the 19th independent infantry battalion) in early November and the won Gongjubattle started late November, ousting the peasant army to the south.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Daewongun requested Minister Otori not to send troops to suppress the peasant army, Japan dispatched a military unit (the 19th independent infantry battalion) in early November and the won Gongju battle started late November, ousting the peasant army to the south.</e>
<cmt>OTORIをOtori に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="211">
<j>ロシアの軍事介入を極度に警戒した日本は農民軍の北進を恐れ朝鮮最西南端の海南さらに珍島まで追いつめて徹底的に殲滅した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Extremely cautious about a military intervention by Russia, Japan drove the armed peasants to Haenam and further to Chindo to annihilate them totally for fear of the expansion of the armed peasant toward the north.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Extremely cautious about a military intervention by Russia, Japan drove the armed peasants to Haenam and further to Chindo to annihilate them totally out of fear of the expansion of armed peasant in the north.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Extremely cautious about a military intervention by Russia, Japan drove the armed peasants to Haenam and further to Chindo island to annihilate them totally out of fear of the expansion of armed peasant in the north.</e>
<cmt>珍島は島なのでisland を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="212">
<j>農民軍参加者はのべ13万人を超えると推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A total of more than 130 thousand farmers are estimated to have joined the armed peasants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A total of more than 130,000 farmers are estimated to have joined the armed peasants.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A total of more than 130,000 farmers are estimated to have joined the armed peasants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>山東作戦・威海衛作戦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Weihaiwei Operation</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Weihaiwei Operation</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Weihaiwei Operation</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="213">
<j>1895年1月20日に日本陸軍は栄城湾に上陸する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On January 20, 1885, Japanese Army landed Rongcheng bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On January 20, 1885, the Japanese Army landed at Rongcheng bay.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On January 20, 1885, the Japanese Army landed at Rongcheng bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="214">
<j>行軍中に歩兵第11旅団長大寺安純少将が戦死する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Second General Yasuzumi ODERA, who led the 11th infantry brigade died while on march.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Second General Yasuzumi ODERA, who led the eleventh infantry brigade died while on march.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Second General Yasuzumi ODERA, who led the eleventh infantry brigade died while on march.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="215">
<j>2月2日に威海衛を占領する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 2, the Japanese Army conquered Weihaiwei</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 2, the Japanese Army conquered Weihaiwei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 2, the Japanese Army conquered Weihaiwei</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="216">
<j>2月5日午前3時20分に威海衛港内に侵入した日本水雷部隊は清国の「定遠」を大破、「来遠」「威遠」等3隻を撃沈した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At 3:20 AM on February 5, the Japanese torpedo boat squadrons invaded in Weihaiwei port and totally destroyed the Chinese Dingyuan, and attacked and sunk three warships including the &quot;Liaoyuan&quot; and &quot;Weiyuan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At 3:20 AM on February 5, the Japanese torpedo boat squadrons invaded Weihaiwei port and totally destroyed the Chinese Dingyuan, and attacked and sunk three warships including the &quot;Liaoyuan&quot; and &quot;Weiyuan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At 3:20 AM on February 5, the Japanese torpedo boat squadrons invaded Weihaiwei port and totally destroyed the Chinese Dingyuan, and attacked and sunk three warships including the &apos;Liaoyuan&apos; and &apos;Weiyuan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="217">
<j>2月9日に「靖遠」を撃沈、「定遠」は自沈する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 9, they attacked and sunk the Chingyuan, and Dingyuan was forced to sink by herself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 9, they attacked and sunk the Chingyuan, and Dingyuan was forced to sink by herself.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 9, they attacked and sunk the &apos;Chingyuan,&apos; and &apos;Dingyuan&apos; was forced to sink by herself.</e>
<cmt>クォーテーションに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="218">
<j>2月12日に丁汝昌提督は将兵の助命を日本側に懇願して自決をする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On February 12, Commodore Ding Ruchang solicited Japan to save lives of solders and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On February 12, Commodore Ding Ruchang solicited Japan to save lives of solders and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On February 12, Commodore Ding Ruchang solicited Japan to save lives of solders and committed suicide.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="219">
<j>伊東司令長官は、鹵獲艦船の中から商船康済号を外し、丁汝昌提督の亡骸を最大の礼遇を以て扱った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">ITO, commander-in-chief, did not seize a merchant vessel and treated his body as courteously as possible</e>
<cmt>「康済」は読み方不明なため訳出していません。一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">ITO, commander-in-chief, did not seize the merchant vessel and treated his body as courteously as possible</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">ITO, commander-in-chief, did not seize the merchant vessel and treated his body as courteously as possible.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="220">
<j>また丁汝昌提督の最期の希望を聞き届け、清国兵を助命する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">He also followed the last desire of Commodore Ding Ruchang and saved the lives of solders</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">He also followed the last desire of Commodore Ding Ruchang and saved the lives of solders</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">He also followed the last desire of Commodore Ding Ruchang and saved the lives of solders.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドを追加しました。全角を半角スペースに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="221">
<j>このことは、通常例を見ない厚遇であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was an unprecedented treatment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was unprecedented.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was unprecedented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="222">
<j>このエピソードは海軍軍人の手本として全世界に伝わった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This episode was spread all over the world as a model for military man.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This episode was spread all over the world as an example for military man.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This episode was spread all over the world as an example for military man.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="223">
<j>現在でもフェアプレイ精神の例として日露戦争の上村彦之丞提督とともに、各国海軍の教本に掲載されていると云う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">What he and Hikonojo KAMIMURA, a Commodore in Russo-Japanese War, did were said to be described as examples of fair play spirit in textbooks of the Navy around the world.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">What he and Hikonojo KAMIMURA, a Commodore in Russo-Japanese War did was described as examples of fair play spirit in textbooks of Navies around the world.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">What he and Hikonojo KAMIMURA, a Commodore in Russo-Japanese War did was described as examples of fair play spirit in textbooks of Navies around the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>講和条約</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Peace treaty</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Peace treaty</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Peace treaty</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="224">
<j>開戦直後からイギリスは講和斡旋へ動きいていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the war opened, Britain had undertook mediation for a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the war, Britain undertook mediation for a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the war, Britain undertook mediation for a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="225">
<j>清も1895年1月に講和使節を日本に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January 1985, Qing sent an envoy to Japan for a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1985, Qing sent an envoy to Japan to conclude a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1985, Qing also sent an envoy to Japan to conclude a peace treaty.</e>
<cmt>「清も」なのでalso を挿入しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="226">
<j>しかし、この時日本は戦後の領有を前提に遼東半島の完全占領を目指していたため、この講和条件を受け入れなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time, however, Japan did not accept the conditions of the peace treaty, because it aimed at complete occupation of the Liaodong Peninsula as a precondition of a post-war domain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time, however, Japan did not accept the conditions, because it aimed at the complete occupation of the Liaodong Peninsula as a precondition of a post-war domain.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time, however, Japan did not accept the conditions, because it aimed at the complete occupation of the Liaodong Peninsula as a precondition of a post-war domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="227">
<j>1895年3月下旬からアメリカの仲介で、日本側が伊藤博文と陸奥宗光、清国側が李鴻章を全権に下関市で講和会議が開かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since late March in 1895, a peace conference was held in Shimonoseki City through the intermediation of the USA, with full authority being given to Hirobumi ITO and Munemitsu MUTSU in the Japanese side and to Hung Chang LI in the Qing side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since late March, 1895, a peace conference was held in Shimonoseki City through the intermediation of the USA, with full authority being given to Hirobumi ITO and Munemitsu MUTSU on the Japanese side and to Hung Chang LI on the Qing side.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since late March, 1895, a peace conference was held in Shimonoseki City through the intermediation of the USA, with full authority being given to Hirobumi ITO and Munemitsu MUTSU on the Japanese side and to Hung Chang LI on the Qing side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="228">
<j>この時日本は台湾の略取を目的にその条件となる日本軍による占領を行うため、3月23日歩兵一個旅団を台湾島西方の澎湖諸島に上陸させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aiming to seize Taiwan this time, Japan sent an infantry brigade to the Penghu islands west of Taiwan island on March 23 to create a precondition that the Japanese troops occupy it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aiming to seize Taiwan this time, Japan sent an infantry brigade to the Penghu islands west of Taiwan island on March 23rd to create a precondition for the Japanese troops to occupy it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aiming to seize Taiwan this time, Japan sent an infantry brigade to the Penghu islands west of Taiwan island on March 23rd to create a precondition for the Japanese troops to occupy it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="229">
<j>台湾領有については松方、陸奥、伊藤ら日本政府要人も1894年以来、その領有の必要性や目的を意見書「威海衛を衝き台湾を略すべき方策」(伊藤)、「台湾島鎮撫策に関して」(陸奥)などでマレー半島や南洋群島に進出する根拠地、中国大陸に将来版図を展開する際の根拠地とする意見を表明していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Leaders in the Japanese government such as MATSYKATA, MUTSU, and ITOH had expressed their opinion in their papers on the aim and necessity for Japan to occupy Taiwan as a based for its expansion to the Maly Peninsula and the South Sea Island or as a base in the future to conquer territory in the Chinese continent since 1894: for example &quot;Strategy for occupation of Taiwa by attacking Weihaiwei &quot; (ITOH), and &quot;A measure to pacify the Taiwan Island&quot; (MUTSU).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Leaders in the Japanese government such as MATSYKATA, MUTSU, and ITOH expressed their opinion in their papers on the aim and necessity for Japan to occupy Taiwan based on its expansion to the Maly Peninsula and the South Sea Island or as a base in the future to conquer territory on the Chinese continent since 1894: for example &quot;Strategy for occupation of Taiwan by attacking Weihaiwei &quot; (ITOH), and &quot;A measure to pacify the Taiwan Island&quot; (MUTSU).</e>
<cmt>grammar, spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Leaders in the Japanese government such as Matsukata, Mutsu, and Ito expressed their opinion in their papers on the aim and necessity for Japan to occupy Taiwan based on its expansion to the Maly Peninsula and the South Sea Island or as a base in the future to conquer territory on the Chinese continent since 1894: for example &apos;Strategy for occupation of Taiwan by attacking Weihaiwei&apos; (Ito), and &apos;A measure to pacify the Taiwan Island&apos; (Mutsu).</e>
<cmt>用語集に従い、名字を「最初の頭文字だけ大文字」に直しました。またItohをＩｔｏに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="230">
<j>しかし、条約交渉において清の全権李鴻章は、日本軍は台湾本土に入っておらず、その割譲要求は筋が通らないと大いに反論した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, Li Hung Chang given full authority argued strongly that the Japanese troops had not entered the main island of Taiwan and thus Japan&apos;s request for the cession of Taiwan was not reasonable.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Li Hung Chang given full authority argued strongly that the Japanese troops had not entered the main island of Taiwan and thus Japan&apos;s request for the cessation of Taiwan was not reasonable.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Li Hung Chang given full authority argued strongly that the Japanese troops had not entered the main island of Taiwan and thus Japan&apos;s request for the cessation of Taiwan was not reasonable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="231">
<j>3月24日に李鴻章が日本人暴漢に狙撃される事件が起こった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On March 24. an incident occurred in which Hung Chang LI was shot by a Japanese thug.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On March 24. an incident occurred in which Hung Chang LI was shot by a Japanese thug.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On March 24, an incident occurred in which Hung Chang LI was shot by a Japanese thug.</e>
<cmt>24の後のピリオドをカンマに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="232">
<j>このため3月30日に停戦に合意した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This incident led to an agreement on a cease-fire on March 30.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This incident led to an agreement on a cease-fire on March 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This incident led to an agreement on a cease-fire on March 30.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="233">
<j>4月17日 下関条約が調印され、5月8日に清の煙台で批准書の交換を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Treaty of Shimonoseki was signed on April 17, and the ratification was exchanged in Yantai, Qing on May 8.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Treaty of Shimonoseki was signed on April 17, and the ratification was exchanged in Yantai, Qing on May 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Treaty of Shimonoseki was signed on April 17, and the ratification was exchanged in Yantai, Qing on May 8.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="234">
<j>条約の主な内容は次の通り</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The outline of the treat is as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The outline of the treat is as follows.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The outline of the treat is as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="235">
<j>清は朝鮮が独立国であることを認め、独立自主を損害するような朝鮮国から清国に対する貢・献上・典礼等は永遠に廃止する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing recognizes independence of Korea and, in consequence, the payment of tribute and the performance of ceremonies and formalities by Korea to China, that are in derogation of such independence and autonomy, shall wholly cease for the future.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing recognized the independence of Korea and, as a consequence, the payment of tribute and the performance of ceremonies and formalities by Korea to China, that are in derogation of such independence and autonomy, shall wholly cease for the future.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing recognized the independence of Korea and, as a consequence, the payment of tribute and the performance of ceremonies and formalities by Korea to China, that are in derogation of such independence and autonomy, shall wholly cease for the future.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="236">
<j>清は遼東半島・台湾・澎湖諸島を日本に譲渡する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing cedes Liaodong Peninsula, Taiwan, Penghu islands to Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing cedes Liaodong Peninsula, Taiwan, Penghu islands to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing cedes Liaodong Peninsula, Taiwan, Penghu islands to Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="237">
<j>清は賠償金2億両（銀両：約3億円）を金で支払う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing agrees to pay to Japan as a war indemnity the sum of 200 million Kuping taels (Silver Tael: about 300 million yen)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing agrees to pay to Japan as a war indemnity the sum of 200 million Kuping taels (Silver Tael: about 300 million yen)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing agrees to pay to Japan as a war indemnity the sum of 200 million Kuping taels (Silver Tael: about 300 million yen) in gold.</e>
<cmt>「金（きん）で」の訳抜け部分を追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="238">
<j>清と欧州各国間の条約を基礎に日清通商航海条約を締結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Qing signs Sino-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation similar to ones previously signed by China with various western powers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Qing signs Sino-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation similar to ones previously signed by China with various western powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Qing signs Sino-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation similar to ones previously signed by China with various western powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="239">
<j>新たに沙市、重慶、蘇州、杭州の4港を開港する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Quing opened 4 ports in addition to those already opened, Shashih, Chongqing, Suchow, and Hangchow.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Quing openedfour ports in addition to those already opened, Shashih, Chongqing, Suchow, and Hangchow.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Quing opens other four ports, ie, Shashih, Chongqing, Suchow, and Hangchow.</e>
<cmt>原文と英訳で意味が異なるため、書き換えました。また他の条約が現在形なので過去形を現在形に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="240">
<j>日本人は清国内の開市、開港場での各種製造業に従事できること。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese is allowed to be engaged in all kinds of manufacturing industries in areas of the open ports.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese are allowed to engage in all kinds of manufacturing industries in the areas of the open ports.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese are allowed to engage in all kinds of manufacturing industries in the areas of the open markets and ports.</e>
<cmt>「開市」が抜けていたので追加しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="241">
<j>この5と6はイギリスが要求して、まだ実現していなかったものであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conditions of these article 5 and 6 were what Britain requested but had not obtained</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conditions of articles 5 and 6 were what Britain requested, but had not obtained</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conditions of articles 5 and 6 were what Britain had requested, but didn&apos;t obtained yet.</e>
<cmt>原文に従って過去完了と過去形を入れ替え、「まだ＝yet」を付け加えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="242">
<j>イギリスの立場を代弁していた様子がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan acted as if it had represented Britain.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan acted as if it had represented Britain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan acted as if it had represented Britain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="243">
<j>これらは最恵国待遇により他の列強にも適用され、以後日本のみならずイギリスをはじめとする西欧列強の清への経済進出と領土分割がより加速されることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most-favored-nation treatment forced China to approve other powers of similar conditions, which allowed not only Japan but also Britain and other western powers to expand economically and divide territory of Qing later among them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most-favored-nation treatment forced China to approve other powers of similar conditions, which allowed not only Japan, but also Britain and other western powers to expand economically and divide the territory of Qing later among them.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most-favored-nation treatment forced China to approve other powers of similar conditions, which allowed not only Japan, but also Britain and other western powers to expand economically and divide the territory of Qing later among them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="244">
<j>これにより、中国と朝鮮との冊封関係は精算された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This put the sakuho relationship between China and Korea came to an end.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This caused the sakuho relationship between China and Korea came to come to an end.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This caused the vassal relationship between China and Korea came to come to an end.</e>
<cmt>冊封（sakuho)はそのままでは意味不明であるのと、他のパラグラフではvassalと訳されているのでvassal relationshipに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="245">
<j>この後日本は紆余曲折を経て度重なる条約締結により朝鮮王朝(大韓帝国)の保護国化と1910年朝鮮併合へ至る道を進むこととなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Subsequently Japan made its way to making the Korean Dynasty (The Korean Empire) a protected state and Annexation of Korea in 1910 through conclusions of treaties many times after complicated negotiations.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Subsequently Japan made its way to creating the Korean Dynasty (The Korean Empire) a protected state and Annexation of Korea in 1910 through conclusions of treaties many times after complicated negotiations.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Subsequently Japan made its way to creating the Korean Dynasty (The Korean Empire) a protected state and Annexation of Korea in 1910 through conclusions of treaties many times after complicated negotiations.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>三国干渉とその後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Triple Intervention</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Triple Intervention</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Triple Intervention</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="246">
<j>当時ロシアは満州（中国東北部）への進出を狙っていたため、遼東半島が日本領になることに激しく反発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those days Russia aiming at expansion into Manchuria (north east of China) strongly opposed to Japan&apos;s acquisition of the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days Russia aiming at expansion into Manchuria (north east of China) strongly opposed Japan&apos;s acquisition of the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days Russia aiming at expansion into Manchuria (north east of China) strongly opposed Japan&apos;s acquisition of the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="247">
<j>このため、ドイツ・フランスとともに遼東半島を清に返還することを4月23日日本政府に要求した（三国干渉）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 23. Russia, France and Germany apply diplomatic pressure on the Japan government for return of the territory to China (Triple intervention) in exchange</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 23. Russia, France, and Germany apply diplomatic pressure on the Japan government for return of the territory to China (Triple intervention) in exchange</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 23, Russia, France, and Germany apply diplomatic pressure on the Japan government for return of the territory to China (Triple intervention) in exchange.</e>
<cmt>ピリオドとカンマを訂正しました（日付の後をカンマ、最後にピリオド）。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="248">
<j>日本政府には、列強三か国に対抗する力は無かったため、これを受け入れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese government reluctantly agreed to the intervention, as it was no power to militarily resist the three major European powers..</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese government reluctantly agreed to the intervention, as it had no power to militarily resist the three major European powers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese government reluctantly agreed to the intervention, as it had no power to militarily resist the three major European powers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="249">
<j>その代償として清から3000万両を得た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In exchange for the return, Japan obtained 30 million Kuping taels from Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In exchange for the return, Japan obtained 30,000,000 Kuping taels from Qing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In exchange for the return, Japan obtained 30,000,000 Kuping taels from Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="250">
<j>以後、日本はロシアを仮想敵国として、清から得た賠償金および利子3億6千万円を、日清戦争戦費(2億2247万円)の3割(7900万円)の補填と次のより大規模な戦争のための軍備拡張費(2億円)とした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan then regarded Russia a hypothetical enemy and, out of the 360 million yen indemnity and its interest obtained from Qing, Japan spent 30% (79 million yen) on compensations for military expenditures for Sino-Japanese war (222,470,000 yen) and on its military build-up for a possible large-scale war (200 million yen).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan then regarded Russia a hypothetical enemy and, out of the 360,000,000 yen indemnity and its interest obtained from Qing, Japan spent 30% (79,000,000 yen) in compensation for military expenditures for the Sino-Japanese war (222,470,000 yen) and on its military build-up for a possible large-scale war (200,000,000 yen).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan then regarded Russia a hypothetical enemy and, out of the 360,000,000 yen indemnity and its interest obtained from Qing, Japan spent 30% (79,000,000 yen) in compensation for military expenditures for the Sino-Japanese war (222,470,000 yen) and on its military build-up for a possible large-scale war (200,000,000 yen).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="251">
<j>その他八幡製鉄所の建設と鉄道・電信事業の拡充および台湾の植民地経営など、国力充実と対外拡張のために使用した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan also spent the indemnity to increase its national strengths and external expansions, such as the construction of Yahata Iron Factory, expansion of the railway and communication industries, and colonial management of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan also spent the indemnity to increase its national strengths and external expansions, such as the construction of Yahata Iron Factory, expansion of the railways, and communication industries, and colonial management of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan also spent the indemnity to increase its national strengths and external expansions, such as the construction of Yahata Iron Factory, expansion of the railways, and communication industries, and colonial management of Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="252">
<j>戦争後、欧米列強各国は清の弱体化を見て取り、中国分割に乗り出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the war Western powers took the opportunity of weakening Qing to started divisions of China.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the war Western powers took the opportunity of weakening Qing to start divisions in China.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the war Western powers took the opportunity of weakening Qing to start divisions in China.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="253">
<j>ロシアは旅順と大連市、ドイツは膠州湾租借地、フランスは広州湾、イギリスは九竜半島と威海衛を租借した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Russian obtained leased territory of Lushun and Dalian City, France obtained Kwangchowan leased territory, and Britain hled the Kawloon Peninsula and Weihaiwei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Russians obtained leased territory of Lushun and Dalian City, France obtained Kwangchowan leased territory, and Britain held the Kawloon Peninsula and Weihaiwei.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Russians obtained leased territory of Lushun and Dalian City, France obtained Kwangchowan leased territory, and Britain held the Kawloon Peninsula and Weihaiwei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>台湾征服戦争(乙未戦争)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">War for invasion into Taiwan (Itsumi War)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">War, the invasion of Taiwan (Itsumi War)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">War, the invasion of Taiwan (Itsumi War)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="254">
<j>下関条約による台湾の割譲は台湾に住む人々にとっては寝耳に水であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan&apos;s cession of Taiwan under Treaty of Shimonoseki came as a surprise to people living in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan&apos;s cession of Taiwan under the Treaty of Shimonoseki came as a surprise to the people living in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan&apos;s cession of Taiwan under the Treaty of Shimonoseki came as a surprise to the people living in Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="255">
<j>彼らは三国干渉に力づけられて5月25日清朝を宗主国とし、台湾巡撫であった唐景崧を総督とする「台湾民主国」を建国する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">They were encouraged by the triple intervention and founded &quot;Republic of Formosa&quot; on May 25 with the Qing dynasty as a suzerain and Tang Ching-sung who had been dispatched as a xunfu, as governor.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">They were encouraged by the triple intervention and founded &quot;Republic of Formosa&quot; on May 25 with the Qing dynasty as a suzerain and Tang Ching-sung who had been dispatched as a xunfu, as governor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">They were encouraged by the triple intervention and founded &quot;Republic of Formosa&quot; on May 25 with the Qing dynasty as a suzerain and Tang Ching-sung who had been dispatched as a xunfu, as governor.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="256">
<j>日本は条約の批准書交換後、樺山資紀海軍大将を台湾総督とし、北白川宮能久親王率いる近衛師団を台湾現地に派遣した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japan, after exchanging the ratification, appointed Naval Captain Sukenori KABAYAMA as governor of Taiwan, and dispatched the Imperial Guards led by Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japan, after exchanging ratification, appointed Naval Captain Sukenori KABAYAMA as governor of Taiwan, and dispatched the Imperial Guards led by Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japan, after exchanging ratification, appointed Naval Captain Sukenori KABAYAMA as governor of Taiwan, and dispatched the Imperial Guards led by Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa to Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="257">
<j>5月29日近衛師団の台湾北部への上陸後唐総督らは台湾を脱出し、清仏戦争の英雄劉永福が民主国政府により大将軍に任じられて台北陥落後の抵抗を担った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 29, when the Imperial Guards landed northern part of Taiwan, Governor Tang and other leaders escaped from the island but the government of Republic of Formosa appointed Liu Yongfu, a hero in Sino-French War, as commander in chief and took the responsibility for resistance after the fall of Taipei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 29, when the Imperial Guards landed in the northern part of Taiwan, Governor Tang and other leaders escaped from the island, but the government of the Republic of Formosa appointed Liu Yongfu, a hero in Sino-French War, as commander in chief and took the responsibility for resistance after the fall of Taipei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 29, when the Imperial Guards landed in the northern part of Taiwan, Governor Tang and other leaders escaped from the island, but the government of the Republic of Formosa appointed Liu Yongfu, a hero in Sino-French War, as commander in chief and took the responsibility for resistance after the fall of Taipei.</e>
<cmt>全角スペースを半角スペースにしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="258">
<j>台南において地元民(高山族)を中心とする頑強な抵抗が続いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Obstinate resistance mainly by local people (mainly by Kao-shan Tribe) continued in Tainan,</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Obstinate resistance mainly by local people (mainly by Kao-shan Tribe) continued in Tainan,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Obstinate resistance mainly by local people (mainly by Kao-shan Tribe) continued in Tainan,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="259">
<j>樺山総督は6月政府に増援を要請、遼東半島の乃木希典中将(後の第3代台湾総督)率いる第二師団を増派した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Governor KABAYAMA requested the government for reinforcement, and the 2nd division led by Maresuke NOGI (later the third governor in Taiwan) was dispatched from the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Governor KABAYAMA requested the government to send reinforcements, and the second division led by Maresuke NOGI (later the third governor in Taiwan) was dispatched from Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Governor Kabayama requested the government to send reinforcements, and the second division led by Maresuke NOGI (later the third governor in Taiwan) was dispatched from Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>KABAYAMA→Kabayama</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="260">
<j>二個師団を上回る兵力が台湾占領にあたった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The troops comprising of more than 2 divisions were assigned a duty of conquering Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The troops comprising of more than two divisions were assigned the duty of conquering Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The troops comprising of more than two divisions were assigned the duty of conquering Taiwan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="261">
<j>住民の武装抵抗のほか、赤痢やマラリア、脚気による被害を受けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese troops not only faced armed resistance of local people but also suffered dysentery, malaria, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese troops not only faced armed resistance of the local people but also suffered dysentery, malaria, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese troops not only faced armed resistance of the local people but also suffered dysentery, malaria, and beriberi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="262">
<j>8月中旬以後日本軍の各隊の罹患者が5割を超える事態となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By mid-August more than a half of the Japanese solder had these disease.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By mid-August more than a half of the Japanese solders had these diseases.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By mid-August more than a half of the Japanese solders had these diseases.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="263">
<j>攻略作戦は11月末には一応終了したが、日本が大本営を解散するのは1896年4月であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conquer operation finally ended in late November, but Japan did not dissolved the Imperial headquarters until April 1896.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conquering operation finally ended in late November, but Japan did not dissolved the Imperial headquarters until April 1896.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conquering operation finally ended in late November, but Japan did not dissolved the Imperial headquarters until April 1896.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="264">
<j>この平定戦での動員兵力5万のうち戦死者は日本軍164人であるが、マラリア等による病死者は近衛師団長北白川宮能久親王はじめ4642人にのぼり、中国側兵士、住民およそ1万4千人の死者を出して終了した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This war to conquer Taiwa ended leaving the Japanese troop 164 war deaths and 4642 deaths, including Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa, caused by disease such as malaria, out of 50 thousand solders in motion, while about 14 thousand of Chinese solders and local people died.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This war to conquer Taiwa ended leaving 164 Japanese war deaths and 4,642 deaths, including Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa, caused by diseases like malaria, out of 50,000 solders in motion, while about 14,000 Chinese solders and local people died.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This war to conquer Taiwa ended leaving 164Japanese war deaths and 4,642 deaths, including Imperial Prince Kitashirakawanomiya Yoshihisa, caused by diseases like malaria, out of 50,000 solders in motion, while about 14,000 Chinese solders and local people died.</e>
<cmt>全角を半角スペースに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="265">
<j>こうした抵抗はこの後も続き、1896年4月には民政に移行するが、総督は軍部が独占した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">With this resistance continuing, power was transferred to a civilian government in April 1896, but the governorship was occupied only by the military persons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the resistance continuing, power was transferred to a civilian government in April 1896, but the governorship was occupied only by military personnel.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the resistance continuing, power was transferred to a civilian government in April 1896, but the governorship was occupied only by military personnel.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="266">
<j>日本による台湾統治は武力による支配という様相を強めることとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Japanese governance over Taiwan, in effect, took on an aspect of military control.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Japanese governance over Taiwan, in effect, took on the aspect of military control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Japanese governance over Taiwan, in effect, took on the aspect of military control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>年表</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chronological Table</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chronological Table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chronological Table</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="267">
<j>1894年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1894</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1894</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1894</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="268">
<j>5月 朝鮮政府、甲午農民戦争（東学党の乱）の鎮圧を清朝に依頼</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May: The Korean government requested Qing dynasty to suppress Donghak Peasant Revolution (the Tonghak Uprising).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May: The Korean government requested Qing dynasty to suppress the Donghak Peasant Revolution (the Tonghak Uprising).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May: The Korean government requested Qing dynasty to suppress the Donghak Peasant Revolution (the Tonghak Uprising).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="269">
<j>5月31日 内閣弾劾上奏決議案が衆議院で可決され、伊藤内閣が倒閣の危機に直面</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">May 31: The ITO cabinet faced a crisis of being overthrown, because a bill of cabinet impeachment report to the throne was adopted in the House of Representatives.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">May 31: The ITO cabinet faced a crisis of being overthrown, because a bill on the cabinet impeachment report to the throne was adopted in the House of Representatives.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">May 31: The ITO cabinet faced a crisis of being overthrown, because a bill on the cabinet impeachment report to the throne was adopted in the House of Representatives.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="270">
<j>6月2日 在韓邦人保護を名目として日本軍の朝鮮派兵を決定。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 2: A dispatch of Japanese troop to Korea was decided on the pretext of protecting Japanese living in Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 2: A dispatch of Japanese troops to Korea was decided upon the pretext of protecting Japanese living in Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 2: A dispatch of Japanese troops to Korea was decided upon the pretext of protecting Japanese living in Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="271">
<j>衆議院を解散。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The House of Representatives was dissolved</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The House of Representatives was dissolved</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The House of Representatives was dissolved</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="272">
<j>6月5日 大本営を開設し、朝鮮への派兵を開始</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">June 5: The Imperial headquarters was set up to start dispatching soldiers to Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">June 5: Imperial headquarters was set up to start dispatching soldiers to Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">June 5: Imperial headquarters was set up to start dispatching soldiers to Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="273">
<j>7月16日 日英条約改正(日英通商航海条約)が実現</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 16: Anglo-Japanese treaty (the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation) was finally revised.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 16: Anglo-Japanese treaty (the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation) was finally revised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 16: Anglo-Japanese treaty (the Anglo-Japanese Treaty of Commerce and Navigation) was finally revised.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="274">
<j>7月20日 朝鮮政府に対して清軍の撤兵を要求する最後通牒を発令</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 20: The final notice calling for the Korean government to withdraw the Qing troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 20: The final notice calling for the Korean government to demand the withdrawal of the Qing troops.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 20: The final notice calling for the Korean government to demand the withdrawal of the Qing troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="275">
<j>7月23日 旅順西海岸の制海のため連合艦隊が佐世保を出港。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 23: Combined fleets set sail from Sasebo to win command of the west coast of Lushun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 23: Combined fleets set sail from Sasebo to win command of the west coast of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 23: Combined fleets set sail from Sasebo to win command of the west coast of Lushun.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="276">
<j>7月23日 日本軍が漢城（ソウル）に入城し、朝鮮王宮を勢力下に置く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 23: The Japanese army entered Seoul and put the Korean royal palace under control.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 23: The Japanese army enters Seoul and puts the Korean royal palace under control.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 23: The Japanese army enters Seoul and puts the Korean royal palace under control.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="277">
<j>7月25日 豊島沖海戦（高陞号事件）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">July 25: Battle of Pungdo (Kowshing incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">July 25: Battle of Pungdo (Kowshing incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">July 25: Battle of Pungdo (Kowshing incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="278">
<j>8月1日 日本・清国が互いに宣戦布告</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 1: Japan and Qing declare war to each other.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 1: Japan and Qing declare war on each other.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 1: Japan and Qing declare war on each other.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="279">
<j>8月26日 日本は朝鮮に圧力を掛け親日政権を樹立、共同で清国に対処する方針を採らせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">August 26: Japan applied pressure on Korea to have the pro-Japanese government set up and have a policy to work with Japan in take measures against Qing.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">August 26: Japan applies pressure on Korea to have a pro-Japanese government set up and have a policy to work with Japan in take measures against Qing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">August 26: Japan applies pressure on Korea to have a pro-Japanese government set up and have a policy to work with Japan in take measures against Qing.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="280">
<j>9月15日 明治天皇が戦争指揮のため広島に移ったことに伴い大本営も移動(広島大本営)。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">September 15: The Imperial headquarters is relocated to Hiroshima, because the Emperor Meiji; Meiji moved there to command the war. (Hiroshima Imperial headquarters)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">September 15: The Imperial headquarters is relocated to Hiroshima, because Emperor Meiji; Meiji moved there to command the war. (Hiroshima Imperial headquarters)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">September 15: The Imperial headquarters is relocated to Hiroshima, because Emperor Meiji; Meiji moved there to command the war (Hiroshima Imperial headquarters).</e>
<cmt>スペースを半角に訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="281">
<j>1895年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1895</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1895</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1895</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="282">
<j>3月 遼東半島全域を制圧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">March: Japan conquered the all the area of Liaodong Peninsula</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">March: Japan conquered the total Liaodong Peninsula</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">March: Japan conquered the total Liaodong Peninsula</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="283">
<j>4月17日 講和条約締結（下関条約）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 17: A peace treaty was concluded (Treaty of Shimonoseki)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 17: A peace treaty was concluded (Treaty of Shimonoseki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 17: A peace treaty was concluded (Treaty of Shimonoseki)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="284">
<j>4月23日 三国干渉により遼東半島を返還</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">April 23: the Triple Intervention forced to Japan to return the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">April 23: the Triple Intervention forced to Japan to return the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">April 23: the Triple Intervention forced to Japan to return the Liaodong Peninsula.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>日本軍の損害</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Damage to the Japanese troop</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Damage to Japanese troops</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Damage to Japanese troops</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="25">
<tit>
<j>脚気</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Beriberi</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Beriberi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Beriberi</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="285">
<j>当時、脚気歴史は、原因不明の病であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In those day, beriberi was a disease of unknown etiology.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In those days, beriberi was a disease of unknown etiology.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In those days, beriberi was a disease of unknown etiology.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="286">
<j>しかし、比較実験の結果、麦の摂取が脚気に有効であるとの実証結果を得ていた海軍では、兵食に麦飯を採用し、脚気による死者がほとんどいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, few died of beriberi in the Navy because it had obtain the result of a comparative study demonstrating that eating barley is effective in preventing beriberi and adopted barley rice.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, few died of beriberi in the Navy because it had obtain the result of a comparative study demonstrating that eating barley is effective in preventing beriberi and they adopted barley rice.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, few died of beriberi in the Navy because it had obtain the result of a comparative study demonstrating that eating barley is effective in preventing beriberi and they adopted barley rice.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="287">
<j>（ただし、その航海食はビタミン不足であり、後年、艦船の行動範囲拡大などにより、脚気患者が大幅に増加した。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">(Nevertheless diet during a voyage was short of vitamins, and the number of patients having beriberi significantly grew due to the expansion of sphere of actions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(Nevertheless the diet during a voyage was short of vitamins, and the number of patients having beriberi significantly grew.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(Nevertheless the diet during a voyage was short of vitamins, and the number of patients having beriberi significantly grew.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="288">
<j>（ちなみに国内で脚気が完全に根絶されたのは1952年以降）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For reference, it was until 1952 that beriberi was eradicated.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">(For reference, it wasn&apos;t until 1952 that beriberi was eradicated.)</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">(For reference, it wasn&apos;t until 1952 that beriberi was eradicated.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="289">
<j>陸軍はその海軍の兵食改革（麦飯支給）に否定的であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army was skeptical of the reform of food for solders (eating barley rice) of the Navy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処「大本営陸軍部の大本営組織をつとめる」は、大本営陸軍部の大本営全体の組織を担当する、と訳してあります。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army was skeptical about reforming food for solders (keaping barley rice) like the Navy did.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army was skeptical about reforming food for solders (keaping barley rice) like the Navy did.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="290">
<j>大本営陸軍部の大本営組織をつとめる石黒忠悳（軍医総監・陸軍省医務局）や軍医部長の一人森鴎外医学功績と脚気問題から見た再評価（森鴎外）などが科学的根拠がないとして、麦飯の支給に強硬に反対した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tadanori ISHIGURO responsible for the entire system of the Army of the Imperial headquarters (surgeon general of Medical department of Ministry of Army) and one of directors of army surgeons, Ogai MORI and other surgeons were strongly opposed to supplying barley rice; suggesting that reevaluation in view of medical achievements and beriberi Ogai MORI) lacks scientific evidence.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tadanori ISHIGURO responsible for the entire system of the Army of the Imperial headquarters (surgeon general of Medical department of Ministry of Army) and one of directors of army surgeons, Ogai MORI and other surgeons were strongly opposed to supplying barley rice; suggesting that reevaluation in view of medical achievements and beriberi Ogai MORI) lacks scientific evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tadanori ISHIGURO responsible for the entire system of the Army of the Imperial headquarters (surgeon general of Medical department of Ministry of Army) and one of directors of army surgeons, Ogai MORI and other surgeons were strongly opposed to supplying barley rice; suggesting that reevaluation in view of medical achievements and beriberi Ogai MORI) lacks scientific evidence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="291">
<j>このため、とくに日清戦争後の台湾平定戦では、高温という脚気が発生しやすい条件も重なり、患者が急増した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, the number of the patients rapidly increased particularly in the battle to suppress Taiwan after the Sino-Japanese with another cause that beriberi is prone to occur at a high temperature.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, the number of the patients rapidly increased particularly in the battle to suppress Taiwan after the Sino-Japanese with another cause that beriberi is prone to occur at high temperatures.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, the number of the patients rapidly increased particularly in the battle to suppress Taiwan after the Sino-Japanese with another cause that beriberi is prone to occur at high temperatures.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="292">
<j>最終的に陸軍は、罹患者・約4万人、病死者・数千人であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">About 40 thousand solders suffered from the disease and thousands of solders died of the disease.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">About 40,000 solders suffered from the disease and thousands of solders died of the disease.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">About 40,000 solders suffered from the disease and thousands of solders died of the disease.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="293">
<j>その死者数は戦死者・数百人を上まわった（資料によって人数が異なる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The deaths from the disease outnumbered those died in the battle--a few hundreds solders--(although the number differ from material to material).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The deaths from the disease outnumbered those who died in battle--a few hundred solders--(although the number differed from material to material).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The deaths from the disease outnumbered those who died in battle--a few hundred solders--(although the number differed from material to material).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="294">
<j>なお当時は、軍の輸送能力が低いこともあり、兵站が滞ることがしばしばであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, the transportation capacity of the troops is not so high that war supplies were often delayed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, the transportation capacity of the troops is not high so, that war supplies were often delayed.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, the transportation capacity of the troops is not high so, that war supplies were often delayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="295">
<j>たとえば、平壌の戦いでは、野津師団長以下が国内の下層民さえ食べないという黒粟や玄米などで飢えをしのぐ場面が度々あった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For example, a division under Division head Nozu often staved off hunger by eating black millets or unpolished rice that people in lower stratums would not have eaten in Japan.</e>
<cmt>野津師団長の野津の読み不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For example, a division under Division head Nozu often staved off hunger by eating black millets or unpolished rice that people in lower stratums would not have eaten in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For example, a division under Division head Nozu often staved off hunger by eating black millets or unpolished rice that people in lower stratums would not have eaten in Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="26">
<tit>
<j>凍傷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Frostbite</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Frostbite</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Frostbite</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="296">
<j>当時の日本陸軍は、まだしっかりした冬季装備と厳寒地における正しい防寒方法を持っていなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Japanese Army in those days did not have proper equipment for winter and did not know how to prevent cold in area of intense cold.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Japanese Army in those days did not have proper equipment for winter and did not know how to combat cold in areas of intense cold.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Japanese Army in those days did not have proper equipment for winter and did not know how to combat cold in areas of intense cold.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="297">
<j>結果として冬季の戦闘で多くの将兵が凍傷にかかり、相当な戦力低下を招いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently, many solders suffered from frostbite during the battle in winter, significantly reducing military power.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently, many solders suffered from frostbite during battles in winter, significantly reducing military power.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently, many solders suffered from frostbite during battles in winter, significantly reducing military power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="298">
<j>日清戦争後、この教訓を基にして防寒具研究と冬季訓練が行われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Based on this lesson, study on cold weather protection gears and winter time training began. after the Sino-Japanese war,</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Based on this lesson, study of cold weather protection gear and winter time training began. after the Sino-Japanese war,</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Based on this lesson, study of cold weather protection gear and winter time training began, after the Sino-Japanese war.</e>
<cmt>カンマとピリオドの位置が反対なので、入れ替えました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="299">
<j>後年、対ロシア戦を想定した訓練中に発生したのが八甲田雪中行軍遭難事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Death March of Hakkoda Mountains Incident occurred during such a training with Russia regarded as a hypothetic enemy.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Death March of the Hakkoda Mountains Incident occurred during such training with Russia regarded as a hypothetic enemy.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Death March of the Hakkoda Mountains Incident occurred during such training as preparation for a possible attack by Russia.</e>
<cmt>訳を訂正しました（ロシアと訓練をした、という訳ではないので）。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="27">
<tit>
<j>その他</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Others</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="300">
<j>海外では日清戦争の事を第一次中日戦争と呼んでいるが、実際には日本軍と中国軍が戦ったのは歴史的に見れば2度目である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the Sino-Japanese War was called the First Sino-Japanese War abroad, this was in effect historically the second battle between the Japanese troops and Chinese troops.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Sino-Japanese War was called the First Sino-Japanese War abroad, this was in effect historically the second battle between the Japanese troops and Chinese troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Sino-Japanese War was called the First Sino-Japanese War abroad, this was in effect historically the second battle between the Japanese troops and Chinese troops.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="301">
<j>一度目は文禄・慶長の役である（元寇は通常モンゴル帝国扱い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first battle was the Bunroku-Keicho War (Mongol invasion of Japan was usually regarded as a war against he Mongolian Empire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first battle was the Bunroku-Keicho War (Mongol invasion of Japan was usually regarded as a war against he Mongolian Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first battle was the Bunroku-Keicho War (Mongol invasion of Japan was usually regarded as a war against he Mongolian Empire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="302">
<j>日清戦争、日露戦争、第一次世界大戦は、順に1894年、1904年、1914年と、下一桁が4の年に始まっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sino-Japanse war, Russo-Japanese War, World War 1 started in 1884, 1904, and 1914, respectively--the years that end in &quot;4.&quot;</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sino-Japanse war, Russo-Japanese War, World War On1 started in 1884, 1904, and 1914, respectively--the years that end in &quot;four.&quot;</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sino-Japanse war, Russo-Japanese War, World War On1 started in 1884, 1904, and 1914, respectively--the years that end in &quot;four.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="303">
<j>また十年毎の戦争のためか死の三十年という語呂合わせもある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also some call these 3 decades as &quot;years for death,&quot; because these wars broke out every 10 years.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also some call these 3 decades as &quot;years of death,&quot; because these wars broke out every ten years.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also some call these 3 decades as &quot;years of death,&quot; because these wars broke out every ten years.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="304">
<j>1895年に日本が清に勝利すると下関条約が締結され、日本は清に朝鮮が自主独立国であることを認めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Japan won China in 1895, Treaty of Shimonoseki was concluded in which Japan made Korea recognize independence and autonomy of Korea.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Japan beat China in 1895, the Treaty of Shimonoseki was concluded in which Japan had Korea recognize the independence and autonomy of Korea.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Japan beat China in 1895, the Treaty of Shimonoseki was concluded in which Japan had Korea recognize the independence and autonomy of Korea.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="305">
<j>1897年にもはや清の服属国でなくなったことから改革が実施され、「国号」を「大韓」と改め、高宗が皇帝に即位、大韓帝国が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Being no longer a state subject to China, Korea performed a reform in 1897: &quot;the name of the country! was changed into &quot;Korea,&quot;Gojong acceded to the throne, and the Korean Empire was founded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Being no longer a state subject to China, Korea performed a reform in 1897: &quot;the name of the country! was changed into &quot;Korea,&quot;Gojong acceded to the throne, and the Korean Empire was founded.</e>
<cmt>spacing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Being no longer a state subject to China, Korea performed a reform in 1897: &apos;the name of the country&apos; was changed into &apos;Korea,&apos; Gojong acceded to the throne, and the Korean Empire was founded.</e>
<cmt>スペースを訂正しました。（全角から半角）また「！」を除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="306">
<j>この際、清の冊封の象徴であった「迎恩門」や「恥辱碑」といわれる大清皇帝功徳碑を倒し「独立門」を記念に建てた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At this time &quot;Yeongeunmun&quot; and the Samjeondo Monument that is dubbed as &quot;disgrace gate&quot; were destroyed and &quot;Independence Gate&quot; was errected to celebrate its independence.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At this time &quot;Yeongeunmun&quot; and the Samjeondo Monument that is dubbed as &quot;disgrace gate&quot; were destroyed and &quot;Independence Gate&quot; was errected to celebrate its independence.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At this time &apos;Yeongeunmun&apos; and the Samjeondo Monument that is dubbed as &apos;disgrace gate&apos; were destroyed and &apos;Independence Gate&apos; was errected to celebrate its independence.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="307">
<j>欧米の軍事的脅威を感じた日清両国は欧米からの武器輸入を進めていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Both Japan and Qing had promoted import weapons from European nations for fear of military threats of those countries.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Both Japan and Qing had promoted importing weapons from European nations for fear of military threats of those countries.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Both Japan and Qing had promoted importing weapons from European nations for fear of military threats of those countries.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="308">
<j>だが、各軍（日本の場合は藩）がそれぞれの基準によってバラバラに輸入を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, individual troops (each domain in Japan) imported weapons according to its own standard.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, individual troops (each domain in Japan) imported weapons according to its own standard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, individual troops (each domain in Japan) imported weapons according to its own standard.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="309">
<j>さまざまな国籍・形式のものが混在してしまい、弾薬の補給やメンテナンス面でも支障をきたしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Consequently different types made of different nations were mixed, hindering proper supplies of ammunition and maintenance of weapons.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Consequently different types made in different nations were mixed, hindering the proper supply of ammunition and maintenance of weapons.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Consequently different types made in different nations were mixed, hindering the proper supply of ammunition and maintenance of weapons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="310">
<j>1880年（明治13年）、日本陸軍の村田経芳が日本で最初の国産小銃の開発に成功する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1880, Tsuneyoshi MURATA of Japanese ARmy succeeded in developing the first Japanese-made rifle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1880, Tsuneyoshi MURATA of the Japanese Army succeeded in developing the first Japanese-made rifle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1880, Tsuneyoshi MURATA of theJapanese Army succeeded in developing the first Japanese-made rifle.</e>
<cmt>スペースを訂正しました。（全角から半角）</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="311">
<j>陸軍はこれを村田銃と命名して全軍の小銃の切り替えを進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Army named it Murata rifle and replaced it with conventional ones in the entire Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Army named it the Murata rifle and they replacedconventional ones in the entire Army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Army named it the Murata rifle and they replaced conventional ones in the entire Army.</e>
<cmt>replacedとconventionalがくっついていたため離しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="312">
<j>その後、同銃は改良を進めながら全軍に支給されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Improvements were made to the rifles, which were provided to the entire Army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Improvements were made to the rifles, which were provided to the entire Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Improvements were made to the rifles, which were provided to the entire Army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="313">
<j>日清戦争当時、村田銃の最新型が全軍に行き渡っていたわけではなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the time of Sino-Japanese war, all the solders carried the latest types of Murataju rifle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the time of the Sino-Japanese war, all the solders carried the latest types of Murataju rifle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the time of the Sino-Japanese war, not all the solders carried the latest types of Murataju rifle.</e>
<cmt>「行き渡っていたわけではなかった」ので、部分否定です。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="314">
<j>弾薬や主要部品に関しては新旧の村田銃の間での互換性が成り立っていたため、弾薬などの大量生産が行われて効率的な補給が可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ammunition and major components were compatible with both new and old Murata guns, making mass production of ammunition and more efficient supplies possible.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ammunition and major components were compatible with both new and old Murata guns, making mass production of ammunition and more efficient supplies possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ammunition and major components were compatible with both new and old Murata guns, making mass production of ammunition and more efficient supplies possible.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="315">
<j>戦争終結後の1896年8月1日に、特殊切手として2銭・5銭の切手が各2種類発行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On August 1, 1896, after the end of the war, two types of specials stamps were issued in two types each for 2 seen and 3sen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On August 1, 1896, after the end of the war, two types of specials stamps were issued in two types each for two sen and three sen.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On August 1, 1896, after the end of the war, two types of specials stamps were issued in two types each for two sen and three sen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Tommy6-bot(id:171289), Los688(id:12316), Trudi3194(id:283128), Sat666(id:127263), Green3558(id:59508), Shizhao(id:1325), Okome(id:98), Lord nihon(id:86446), Webkid(id:5484), 0null0(id:582), 22010515528(id:43149), Eskimbot(id:29676), Lupinoid(id:68), AQu01rius(id:66690), Re:RENA(id:86666), 0太郎(id:7375), Kyle the bot(id:145991), Greenland4(id:114494), OKBot(id:143139), Hermeneus(id:380), Jugger90(id:17088), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), MioUzaki(id:89034), RON ST(id:156891), 曾禰越後守(id:183605), BotMultichill(id:132395), Lulusuke(id:44392), Point136(id:211299), Yo987(id:205612), ASAMA501(id:91947), YukkeBot2(id:251491), 涼車(id:105110), DumZiBoT(id:230315), ArthurBot(id:265089), 浩(id:70121), Open-box(id:17893), Tears for Asia(id:61412), Nallimbot(id:230812), 宇宙人(id:98147), Kome(id:46586), TEy(id:32722), Sh(id:2707), 敷島健一(id:270317), Fryed-peach(id:63402), RoboDick(id:34097), Alecs.bot(id:194707), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Tci tct(id:224383), Chlewbot(id:33904), McBot(id:159617), Tonbi ko(id:27171), 蔭人(id:80171), Nsq(id:54991), Mameneko(id:785), Suisui(id:69), 三日月(id:19540), ネッツ(id:150295), TT(id:46431), 釣ちごちゅが(id:22605), 唐変木(id:17050), Straysheep(id:42448), ちとせ(id:81263), Lime citrus soda(id:28200), Kawai(id:5634), Fukupulio(id:287222), MelancholieBot(id:31942), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Udon-ya(id:48431), Dobata2008(id:253774), Njt(id:11249), 花鳥(id:240256), Ix680(id:25168), 明治(id:110234), Aizawa1(id:45968), 冒涜的な利用者名(id:14641), 現代の魔女(id:136024), Prism11 VYB05736(id:171949), Dokutou(id:14850), Kone(id:377), Chobot(id:20846), Kazaguruma(id:39892), Yosemite(id:5808), Nopira(id:29335), Setuzoku2(id:191045), KASAGI(id:24405), Bankokuya(id:91191), Izayohi(id:13095), ののの(id:79362), Kzy(id:9253), J-ishikawa(id:74471), Oyoyoyo(id:196287), Rambler(id:59491), 水野白楓(id:22811), HALPHA(id:51616), Solaris0120(id:125788), J8takagi(id:20409), 3rdOfLupin(id:158056), 雲居雁乃(id:15842), Cave cattum(id:41235), Oh!wenka(id:53059), Denki(id:72786), ワルゥ(id:28207), Ongakutai(id:34103), 喧嘩屋朝日(id:271894), Tanuki Z(id:612), VolkovBot(id:105371), Kaba(id:17904), ZERO13(id:53029), Kyube(id:9866), ゐ(id:795), 梅桃桜(id:35850), E-niku(id:116006), Miya.m(id:4662), Louperibot(id:128971), Tokugawa(id:61656), SieBot(id:126695), Chuta(id:10457), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>