<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nanbokucho Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nanbokucho Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nanbokucho Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<sen id="1">
<j>日本における南北朝時代（なんぼくちょうじだい）とは、中世の時代区分の1つである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nanbokucho era (the period of Northern and Southern courts) in Japan refers to one subsection of medieval Japanese history</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nanbokucho era (the period of Northern and Southern courts) in Japan refers to one subsection of medieval Japanese history</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nanbokucho era (the period of the Northern and Southern Courts) in Japan refers to one subsection of medieval Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>ピリオド補足&quot;the period of Northern and Southern courts&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>一般的には鎌倉時代の後で、元弘の変や建武の新政も南北朝時代の出来事として扱うが、正確には1336年（延元元年/建武 (日本)3年）に足利尊氏による光明天皇の践祚、後醍醐天皇の吉野遷幸により朝廷が分裂してから、1392年（元中9年/明徳3年）に両朝が合一するまでの期間を指し、室町時代の初期に当たる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Events that occurred at or right after the end of the Kamakura period such as the Genko War and the Kemmu Restoration are usually considered part of the Nanbokucho period, but strictly speaking, the term refers only to the span of time between 1336 (Engen 1/Kemmu 3), when Takauji ASHIKAGA raised Emperor Komyo to the Chrysanthemum throne, thus leading to a schism in the Imperial Court after Emperor Go-Daigo departed Kyoto and established his Court at Yoshino, and 1392 (Genchu 9/Meitoku 3) when the two courts were again unified; it overlaps with the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Events that occurred at or right after the end of the Kamakura period such as the Genko War and the Kemmu Restoration are usually considered part of the Nanbokucho period, but strictly speaking, the term refers only to the span of time between 1336 (Engen 1/Kemmu 3), when Takauji ASHIKAGA raised Emperor Komyo to the Chrysanthemum throne, thus leading to a schism in the Imperial Court after Emperor Go-Daigo departed Kyoto and established his Court at Yoshino, and 1392 (Genchu 9/Meitoku 3) when the two courts were again unified; it overlaps with the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Events that occurred at or right after the end of the Kamakura period such as the Genko War and the Kenmu Restoration are usually considered part of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts, but strictly speaking, the term refers only to the span of time between 1336, when Takauji ASHIKAGA raised Emperor Komyo to the Chrysanthemum throne, thus leading to a schism in the Imperial Court after Emperor Godaigo departed Kyoto and established his Court at Yoshino, and 1392 when the two courts were again unified; it overlaps with the early Muromachi period.</e>
<cmt>Kemmu→Kenmu(Engen 1/Kemmu 3) (Genchu 9/Meitoku 3)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除Go-Daigo→Godaigo&quot;the Nanbokucho period&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>この間、日本には南朝 (日本)（大和国吉野行宮）と北朝 (日本)（山城国平安京）に2つの朝廷が存在し、それぞれ正当性を主張した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the period, two Imperial Courts existed in Japan, the Southern Court (located at the Emperor&apos;s residence in Yoshino, Yamato province), and the Northern Court (in Heian Kyo (Kyoto), Yamashiro province), and each Court tried to claim sole legitimacy for itself.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the period, two Imperial Courts existed in Japan, the Southern Court (located at the Emperor&apos;s residence in Yoshino, Yamato province), and the Northern Court (in Heian Kyo (Kyoto), Yamashiro province), and each Court tried to claim sole legitimacy for itself.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the period, two Imperial Courts existed in Japan, the Southern Court (located at the Emperor&apos;s residence in Yoshino, Yamato Province), and the Northern Court (in Heian Kyo (Kyoto), Yamashiro Province), and each Court tried to claim sole legitimacy for itself.</e>
<cmt>province→Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>南朝を正統とする論者は「吉野朝時代」と称する（南北朝正閏論参照）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those who argue that the Southern Court was the true Court prefer to call this timespan &quot;the Yoshino Court period&quot; (see also the article on the Nanbokucho seijunron, the debate over legitimacy between the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those who argue that the Southern Court was the true Court prefer to call this timespan &quot;the Yoshino Court period&quot; (see also the article on the Nanbokucho seijunron, the debate over legitimacy between the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those who argue that the Southern Court was the true Court prefer to call this timespan &apos;the Yoshino Court period&apos; (see also the article on the Nanbokucho seijunron, the debate over legitimacy between the Northern and Southern Courts).</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>南北朝成立まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background leading up to the establishment of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background leading up to the establishment of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background leading up to the establishment of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="5">
<j>鎌倉時代末にあたる寛元4年（1246年）、後嵯峨天皇の退位後に天皇家は皇位継承を巡って大覚寺統と持明院統に分裂してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1246 (Kangen 4), towards the end of the Kamakura period, the Imperial family fell into a struggle over the Imperial succession upon the abdication of Emperor Go-Saga, splitting into two groups, the Kameyama (Daitokuji) lineage and the Go-Fukakusa (Jimyoji) lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1246 (Kangen 4), towards the end of the Kamakura period, the Imperial family fell into a struggle over the Imperial succession upon the abdication of Emperor Go-Saga, splitting into two groups, the Kameyama (Daitokuji) lineage and the Go-Fukakusa (Jimyoji) lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1246, towards the end of the Kamakura period, the Imperial family fell into a struggle over the Imperial succession upon the abdication of Emperor Gosaga, splitting into two groups, the Kameyama (Daitokuji) lineage and the Gofukakusa (Jimyoin) lineage.</e>
<cmt>(Kangen 4)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除Go-Saga→GosagaGo-Fukakusa→GofukakusaJimyoji→Jimyoin</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>そこで鎌倉幕府の仲介によって、大覚寺統と持明院統が交互に皇位につく事（両統迭立）が取り決められていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that point, through the mediation of the Kamakura shogunate, a compromise was reached in which it was decided to alternate between the two lineages, choosing the Emperor from each lineage in turn (called &quot;ryoto tetsuritsu&quot; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that point, through the mediation of the Kamakura shogunate, a compromise was reached where it was decided to alternate between the two lineages, choosing the Emperor from each lineage in turn (called &quot;ryoto tetsuritsu&quot; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>&quot;in which&quot; replaced with &quot;where&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that point, through the mediation of the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun), a compromise was reached where it was decided to alternate between the two lineages, choosing the Emperor from each lineage in turn (called &quot;ryoto tetsuritsu&quot; in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun)</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="7">
<j>1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）、大覚寺統の後醍醐天皇は全国の武士に討幕の綸旨を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then in 1333 (Genko 3/Shokei 2), Emperor Go-Daigo, of the Daikakuji lineage, issued an Imperial edict to the warriors all over the country to strike down the shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then in 1333 (Genko 3/Shokei 2), Emperor Go-Daigo, of the Daikakuji lineage, issued an Imperial edict to the warriors all over the country to strike down the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then in 1333, Emperor Godaigo, of the Daikakuji lineage, issued an Imperial edict to the warriors all over the country to strike down the shogunate.</e>
<cmt>(Genko 3/Shokei 2)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除Go-Daigo→Godaigo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>これに応えた足利高氏（当時）や新田義貞らの働きで鎌倉幕府は滅び、建武の新政と呼ばれる後醍醐天皇による親政がはじまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to the efforts of Takauji ASHIKAGA (at this point his name was still written with the character for &quot;taka&quot; meaning &quot;high&quot;) and Yoshisada NITTA, who responded to Go-Daigo&apos;s order, the Kamakura shogunate was destroyed, and in what was called the Kemmu Restoration, an era of direct Imperial rule by Emperor Go-Daigo began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to the efforts of Takauji ASHIKAGA (at this point his name was still written with the character for &quot;taka&quot; meaning &quot;high&quot;) and Yoshisada NITTA, who responded to Go-Daigo&apos;s order, the Kamakura shogunate was destroyed, and the Kemmu Restoration, an era of direct Imperial rule by Emperor Go-Daigo began.</e>
<cmt>&quot;in what was called&quot; deleted as unnecessary</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thanks to the efforts of Takauji ASHIKAGA (at this point his name was still written with the character for &quot;taka&quot; meaning &quot;high&quot;) and Yoshisada NITTA, who responded to Godaigo&apos;s order, the Kamakura bakufu was destroyed, and the Kenmu Restoration, an era of direct Imperial rule by Emperor Godaigo began.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigoshogunate→bakufuKemmu→Kenmu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>しかし政局の混乱が続き、また恩賞の不公平により武士階級の支持を得ることはできなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the political situation remained bogged down in chaos, and because of inequalities and unfairness in the giving of rewards, Go-Daigo was never able to gain control over the warrior class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the political situation remained bogged down in chaos, and because of inequalities and unfairness in the giving of rewards, Go-Daigo was never able to gain control over the warrior class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the political situation remained bogged down in chaos, and because of inequalities and unfairness in the giving of rewards, Godaigo was never able to gain control over the warrior class.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>中先代の乱を討伐に向かった尊氏がそのまま新政から離反すると、不満を抱えた武士たちの多くが尊氏に従った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After putting down the Nakasendai Revolt (a counter-rebellion against Go-Daigo, literally meaning &quot;the revolt of the intermediate generation (a brief respite between the control of the HOJO and the ASHIKAGA ruling clans)), Takauji remained in Kamakura, becoming alienated from Go-Daigo&apos;s government, and this prompted many disgruntled warriors to flock to his banner.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After putting down the Nakasendai Revolt (a counter-rebellion against Go-Daigo, literally meaning &quot;the revolt of the intermediate generation (a brief respite between the control of the HOJO and the ASHIKAGA ruling clans), Takauji remained in Kamakura, becoming alienated from Go-Daigo&apos;s government, and this prompted many disgruntled samurai to flock to his banner.</e>
<cmt>double parenthesis after &quot;clans&quot; changed to single parenthesis, &quot;warriors&quot; changed to &quot;samurai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After putting down the Nakasendai Revolt (a counter-rebellion against Godaigo, literally meaning &quot;the revolt of the intermediate generation (a brief respite between the control of the HOJO and the ASHIKAGA ruling clans), Takauji remained in Kamakura, becoming alienated from Godaigo&apos;s government, and this prompted many disgruntled samurai to flock to his banner.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigo原文にない説明が補足されているが、分かりやすいのでママ。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>後醍醐天皇は新田義貞や北畠顕家に尊氏討伐を命じる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo commanded Yoshisada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE to hunt down and destroy Takauji.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Daigo commanded Yoshisada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE to hunt down and destroy Takauji.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo commanded Yoshisada NITTA and Akiie KITABATAKE to hunt down and destroy Takauji.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigo</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>新田軍は箱根・竹ノ下の戦いでは敗北し尊氏らは京都へ入るが、やがて陸奥国から下った北畠軍の活躍もあり駆逐された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But the NITTA army was defeated in the battles of Takenoshita in Hakone, and Takauji&apos;s forces entered Kyoto; Takauji was finally driven from the city later through the efforts of the KITABATAKE army, which had marched down from Mutsu province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But the NITTA army was defeated in the battles of Takenoshita in Hakone, and Takauji&apos;s forces entered Kyoto; Takauji was finally driven from the city later through the efforts of the KITABATAKE army, which had marched down from Mutsu province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But the NITTA army was defeated in the battles of Takenoshita in Hakone, and Takauji&apos;s forces entered Kyoto; Takauji was finally driven from the city later through the efforts of the KITABATAKE army, which had marched down from Mutsu Province.</e>
<cmt>province→Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>尊氏らは九州へ下り、多々良浜の戦いに勝利して勢力を立て直したのちの翌年に、持明院統の光厳天皇の院宣を掲げて東征する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji&apos;s forces moved off to Kyushu, and having regained their momentum with victory in the battle of Tatarahama, the following year they regrouped and marched east again under the Imperial edict of Emperor Kogon.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji&apos;s forces moved off to Kyushu, and having regained their momentum with victory in the battle of Tatarahama, the following year they regrouped and marched east again under the Imperial edict of Emperor Kogon.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji&apos;s forces moved off to Kyushu, and having regained their momentum with victory in the battle of Tatarahama, the following year they regrouped and marched east again under the Imperial edict of Emperor Kogon of the Gofukakusa (Jimyoin) lineage.</e>
<cmt>of the Gofukakusa (Jimyoin) lineage補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>迎え撃つ宮方は新田義貞・楠木正成が湊川の戦いで敗れ、比叡山に篭った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Imperial faction forces, led by Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI, that marched to meet them were defeated in the battle of the Minato river, and holed themselves up on Mt Hiei.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Imperial faction forces, led by Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI, that marched to meet them were defeated in the battle of the Minato river, and holed themselves up on Mt Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Imperial faction forces, led by Yoshisada NITTA and Masashige KUSUNOKI, that marched to meet them were defeated in the battle of the Minato river, and holed up on Mt Hiei.</e>
<cmt>慣用句。“ holed themselves up”=&gt;” holed up”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>尊氏は後醍醐天皇との和解を図り、三種の神器を接収し持明院統の光明天皇を擁立（北朝）した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji sought reconciliation with Emperor Go-Daigo, and having regained control over the three Imperial Regalia, he became the principal support for Emperor Komyo of the Go-Fukakusa (Jimyoji) lineage (the Northern Court).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji sought reconciliation with Emperor Go-Daigo, and having regained control over the three Imperial Regalia, he became the principal support for Emperor Komyo of the Go-Fukakusa (Jimyoji) lineage (the Northern Court).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji sought reconciliation with Emperor Godaigo, and having regained control over the three Imperial Regalia, he became the principal support for Emperor Komyo of the Gofukakusa (Jimyoin) lineage (the Northern Court).</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→GodaigoJimyoji→JimyoinGo-Fukakusa→Gofukakusa</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>その上で建武式目を制定し、施政方針を定め正式に幕府を開く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, Takauji enacted the Kemmu Code, established an administrative policy and formally created a shogunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Takauji enacted the Kemmu Code, established an administrative policy and formally created a shogunate.</e>
<cmt>&quot;In addition&quot; changed to &quot;Additionally&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Takauji enacted the Kenmu Code, established an administrative policy and formally created a shogunate.</e>
<cmt>Kemmu→Kenmu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>後醍醐天皇は京都を脱出して吉野へ逃れ、「北朝に渡した神器は贋物であり光明天皇の皇位は正統ではない」と主張して吉野に南朝（吉野朝廷）を開き、北陸や九州など各地へ自らの皇子を奉じさせて派遣する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Daigo, on the other hand, escaped from Kyoto, fleeing to Yoshino and insisting that &quot;The Imperial Regalia I handed over to the Northern Court are fake; Emperor Komyo&apos;s throne is not the true Imperial throne&quot; before establishing his own Court at Yoshino (the Southern Court), sending his own sons in obedience to his wishes to various areas, including Hokuriku and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Daigo, on the other hand, escaped from Kyoto, fleeing to Yoshino and insisting that &quot;The Imperial Regalia I handed over to the Northern Court are fake; Emperor Komyo&apos;s throne is not the true Imperial throne&quot; before establishing his own Court at Yoshino (the Southern Court), sending his own sons in obedience to his wishes to various areas, including Hokuriku and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo, on the other hand, escaped from Kyoto, fleeing to Yoshino and insisting that &apos;The Imperial Regalia I handed over to the Northern Court are fake; Emperor Komyo&apos;s throne is not the true Imperial throne&apos; before establishing his own Court at Yoshino (the Southern Court), sending his own sons in obedience to his wishes to various areas, including Hokuriku and Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigo</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>観応の擾乱と南朝勢力の衰微</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance and the Decline of the Southern Court&apos;s Influence</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kanno Disturbance and the Decline of the Southern Court&apos;s Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kanno Disturbance and the Decline of the Southern Court&apos;s Influence</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="18">
<j>南朝方は名和長年・結城親光・千種忠顕のほか、北畠顕家・新田義貞らが1338年（延元3年/暦応元年）までに次々と戦死し、軍事的に北朝方が圧倒的に優位に立つ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">By 1338 (Engen 3/Ryakuo 1) the Southern Court faction had seen its military leaders, including Nagatoshi NAWA, Chikamitsu YUKI, and Tadaaki CHIGUSA, and in addition Akiie KITABATAKE and Yoshisada NITTA, die in battle one after the other, and were overwhelmingly outmatched militarily by the Northern Court faction.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By 1338 (Engen 3/Ryakuo 1) the Southern Court faction had seen its military leaders, including Nagatoshi NAWA, Chikamitsu YUKI, and Tadaaki CHIGUSA, and in addition Akiie KITABATAKE and Yoshisada NITTA, die in battle one after the other, and were overwhelmingly outmatched militarily by the Northern Court faction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By 1338 the Southern Court faction had seen its military leaders, including Nagatoshi NAWA, Chikamitsu YUKI, and Tadaaki CHIGUSA, and in addition Akiie KITABATAKE and Yoshisada NITTA, die in battle one after the other, and were overwhelmingly outmatched militarily by the Northern Court faction.</e>
<cmt>(Engen 3/Ryakuo 1)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>1348年（正平 (日本)3年/貞和4年）には四條畷の戦いで楠木正成の子楠木正行・楠木正時兄弟が足利方の高師直に討たれ、吉野行宮が陥落して後村上天皇ら南朝一行は賀名生（奈良県五條市）へ逃れ、衰勢は覆い隠せなくなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Masashige KUSONOKI&apos;s sons, the brothers Masatsura and Masatoki KUSUNOKI, were struck down by Ko no Moronau of the Ashikaga faction in the 1348 (Shohei 3/Jowa 4) battle of Shijonawate, the Imperial residence at Yoshino was overrun by the Ashikaga, and Emperor Go-Murakami and the rest of the Southern Court faction were forced to flee to Ano (the present-day city of Gojo in Nara Pref.); the decline of the Southern Court&apos;s power and influence could no longer be concealed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Masashige KUSONOKI&apos;s sons, brothers Masatsura and Masatoki KUSUNOKI, were struck down by Ko no Moronau of the Ashikaga faction in the 1348 (Shohei 3/Jowa 4) battle of Shijonawate, the Imperial residence at Yoshino was overrun by the Ashikaga, and Emperor Go-Murakami and the rest of the Southern Court faction were forced to flee to Ano (the present-day city of Gojo in Nara Pref.); the decline of the Southern Court&apos;s power and influence could no longer be concealed.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the brothers&quot; changed to &quot;brothers&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Masashige KUSONOKI&apos;s sons, brothers Masatsura and Masatoki KUSUNOKI, were struck down by Ko no Moronao of the Ashikaga faction in the 1348 battle of Shijonawate, the Imperial residence at Yoshino was overrun by the Ashikaga, and Emperor Gomurakami and the rest of the Southern Court faction were forced to flee to Ano (the present-day city of Gojo in Nara Pref.); the decline of the Southern Court&apos;s power and influence could no longer be concealed.</e>
<cmt>Moronau→Moronao (Shohei 3/Jowa 4)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除Go-Murakami→Gomurakami</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>しかしその後、尊氏が政務を任せていた弟の足利直義と足利家の執事の高師直が対立が表面化し、観応年間には観応の擾乱とよばれる幕府の内紛が起こる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But thereafter, the feud between Takauji&apos;s younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, whom Takauji had entrusted with the running of the government, and the Ashikaga clan steward, Ko no Moronau, spilled out into the open, and during the Kanno era, the shogunate experienced an internal struggle known as the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But thereafter, the feud between Takauji&apos;s younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, whom Takauji had entrusted with the running of the government, and the Ashikaga clan steward, Ko no Moronau, spilled out into the open, and during the Kanno era, the shogunate experienced an internal struggle known as the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But thereafter, the feud between Takauji&apos;s younger brother Tadayoshi ASHIKAGA, whom Takauji had entrusted with the running of the government, and the Ashikaga family steward, Ko no Moronao, spilled out into the open, and during the Kanno era, the shogunate experienced an internal struggle known as the Kanno Disturbance.</e>
<cmt>Moronau→Moronao&quot;Ashikaga clan&quot;→&quot;Ashikaga family&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>政争に敗れた直義は南朝に帰順し、尊氏の子で直義の養子になっていた足利直冬も養父に従い九州へ逃れて戦う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After being defeated in this political struggle, Tadayoshi switched his allegiance to the Southern Court, and Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s son and Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted child, followed his adopted father in switching sides, fleeing to Kyushu and fighting against the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After being defeated in this political struggle, Tadayoshi switched his allegiance to the Southern Court, and Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s son and Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted child, followed his adopted father in switching sides, fleeing to Kyushu and fighting against the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After being defeated in this political struggle, Tadayoshi switched his allegiance to the Southern Court, and Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, Takauji&apos;s son and Tadayoshi&apos;s adopted child, followed his adopted father in switching sides, fleeing to Kyushu and fighting against the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>山名時氏など守護の一部も南朝に属して戦い、京都争奪戦が繰り広げられるなど南朝は息を吹き返すことになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A fraction of the provincial Protectors (shugo were tantamount to governors) like Tokiuji YAMANA also joined the Southern Court faction and fought for them, and with the struggle to recapture Kyoto widening in this way, the Southern Court gained a reprieve.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A fraction of the provincial Protectors (shugo were tantamount to governors) like Tokiuji YAMANA also joined the Southern Court faction and fought for them, and with the struggle to recapture Kyoto widening in this way, the Southern Court gained a reprieve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A fraction of the provincial Protectors (shugo were tantamount to governors) like Tokiuji YAMANA also joined the Southern Court faction and fought for them, and with the struggle to recapture Kyoto widening in this way, the Southern Court gained a reprieve.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>後村上天皇は南朝方の住吉大社の宮司家である津守氏の住之江殿（正印殿）に移り、そこを住吉行宮（大阪市住吉区）とする。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Go-Murakami relocated to Suminoe Palace (Shoin Palace) of the Tsumori clan, Southern Court supporters whose family held the chief priesthood of the Grand Shrine at Sumiyoshi; the palace was renamed &quot;the Imperial Residence at Sumiyoshi&quot; (located in modern-day Sumiyoshi Ward in the city of Osaka).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Go-Murakami relocated to Suminoe Palace (Shoin Palace) of the Tsumori clan, Southern Court supporters whose family held the chief priesthood of the Grand Shrine at Sumiyoshi; the palace was renamed &quot;the Imperial Residence at Sumiyoshi&quot; (located in modern-day Sumiyoshi Ward in the city of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Gomurakami relocated to Suminoe Palace (Shoin Palace) of the Tsumori clan, Southern Court supporters whose family held the chief priesthood of the Grand Shrine at Sumiyoshi; the palace was renamed the Imperial Residence at Sumiyoshi (located in modern-day Sumiyoshi Ward in the city of Osaka).</e>
<cmt>Go-Murakami→Gomurakami原文に『』のない&quot;　&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="24">
<j>1351年（正平6年/観応2年）には、尊氏が直義派に対抗するために一時的に南朝に降伏し、年号を南朝の「正平」に統一する「正平一統」が成立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1351 (Shohei 6/Kanno 2), Takauji temporarily submitted to the Southern Court&apos;s authority in an effort to undercut the Tadayoshi faction, and the era name was unified under the Southern Court&apos;s name, Shohei, in what was called &quot;the Shohei Unification.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1351 (Shohei 6/Kanno 2), Takauji temporarily submitted to the Southern Court&apos;s authority in an effort to undercut the Tadayoshi faction, and the era name was unified under the Southern Court&apos;s name, Shohei, in what was called &quot;the Shohei Unification.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1351 (Shohei 6/Kanno 2), Takauji temporarily submitted to the Southern Court&apos;s authority in an effort to undercut the Tadayoshi faction, and the era name was unified under the Southern Court&apos;s name, Shohei, in what was called &quot;the Shohei Unification.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>これにより、尊氏は征夷大将軍を解任された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result of this Shohei Unification, Takauji was dismissed from his position as Sei-i taishogun (Shogun).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result of this Shohei Unification, Takauji was dismissed from his position as Sei-i taishogun (Shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result of this Shohei Unification, Takauji was dismissed from his position as seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;).</e>
<cmt>スペース。 “t” が日本語フォントになっている。. “position seii ｔaishogun” =&gt; “position as seii taishogun”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>南朝はこの機に乗じて京都へ進攻して足利義詮を追い、京都を占拠して神器も接収する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Court, seizing this opportunity, launched an attack on Kyoto and drove out Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, occupying Kyoto and seizing the Imperial Regalia.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Court, seizing this opportunity, launched an attack on Kyoto and drove out Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, occupying Kyoto and seizing the Imperial Regalia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court, seizing this opportunity, launched an attack on Kyoto and drove out Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA, occupying Kyoto and seizing the Imperial Regalia.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>義詮は北朝年号を復活させ、再び京都を奪還するが、南朝は撤退する際に光厳・光明両上皇と、天皇を退位した直後の崇光天皇（光厳の皇子）を賀名生へ連れ去った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshiakira revived the Northern Court era name and recaptured Kyoto, and when the Southern Court forces withdrew from the city, they took both Retired Emperors Kogon and Komyo, as well as Emperor Suko (Kogon&apos;s son), who had just abdicated the throne, back with them to Ano.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshiakira revived the Northern Court era name and recaptured Kyoto, and when the Southern Court forces withdrew from the city, they took both Retired Emperors Kogon and Komyo, as well as Emperor Suko (Kogon&apos;s son), who had just abdicated the throne, back with them to Ano.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshiakira revived the Northern Court era name and recaptured Kyoto, and when the Southern Court forces withdrew from the city, they took both retired Emperors Kogon and Komyo, as well as Emperor Suko (Kogon&apos;s son), who had just abdicated the throne, back with them to Ano.</e>
<cmt>Retired→retired</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>このため北朝は、光厳の皇子で崇光の弟の後光厳天皇を神器無しで即位させ、併せて公武の官位を復旧させ、尊氏も征夷大将軍に復帰した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In response to this, the Northern Court took Kogon&apos;s son, Suko&apos;s younger brother, and raised him to the throne as Emperor Go-Kogon without the Imperial Regalia; thereafter the Northern Court restored both its nobles and warriors to their former ranks, and Takauji also was reappointed Shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this, the Northern Court took Kogon&apos;s son, Suko&apos;s younger brother, and raised him to the throne as Emperor Go-Kogon without the Imperial Regalia; thereafter the Northern Court restored both its nobles and samurai to their former ranks, and Takauji was also reappointed Shogun.</e>
<cmt>&quot;also was&quot; changed to &quot;was also&quot; &quot;warriors&quot; changed to &quot;samurai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this, the Northern Court took Kogon&apos;s son, Suko&apos;s younger brother, and raised him to the throne as Emperor Gokogon without the Imperial Regalia; thereafter the Northern Court restored both its nobles and samurai to their former ranks, and Takauji was also reappointed seii taishogun.</e>
<cmt>Go-Kogon→GokogonShogun→seii taishogun</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="29">
<j>南朝の北畠親房は関東地方で南朝勢力の結集を図り、篭城した常陸国小田城にて南朝の正統性を示す「神皇正統記」を執筆する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE, of the Southern Court, planned to concentrate the Southern Court&apos;s forces in the Kanto, and wrote the Jinno shotoki (Succession of Heavenly Imperial Rulers), a document trying to show the Southern Court&apos;s legitimacy, while besieging Oda castle in Hitachi province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chikafusa KITABATAKE, of the Southern Court, planned to concentrate the Southern Court&apos;s forces in Kanto, and wrote the Jinno shotoki (Succession of Heavenly Imperial Rulers), a document trying to show the Southern Court&apos;s legitimacy, while besieging Oda castle in Hitachi province.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Kanto&quot; changed to &quot;Kanto&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chikafusa KITABATAKE, of the Southern Court, planned to concentrate the Southern Court&apos;s forces in Kanto, and wrote the Jinno shotoki (Succession of Heavenly Imperial Rulers), a document trying to show the Southern Court&apos;s legitimacy, while besieging Oda castle in Hitachi Province.</e>
<cmt>province→Province</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>1339年（延元4年/暦応2年）に後醍醐天皇が死去すると親房が南朝の指導的人物となるが、親房が1354年（正平9年/文和3年）に死去すると南朝はまた衰微し、幕府内での抗争で失脚した細川清氏が楠木正儀らと南朝に帰順して一時は京都を占拠するものの1367年（正平22年/貞治6年）に敗れ、以降は大規模な南朝の攻勢もなくなり、足利義詮時代には大内弘世や山名時氏なども帰服する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Emperor Go-Daigo passed away in 1339 (Engen 4/Ryakuo 2), Chikafusa became the de facto leader of the Southern Court, but when Chikafusa himself died in 1354 (Shohei 9/Bunwa 3), the Southern Court again fell into decline; having lost the internal power struggle within the Ashikaga shogunate, Kiyouji HOSOKAWA switched allegiance to Masanori KUSUNOKI and the Southern Court and together managed to briefly occupy Kyoto, but in 1367 (Shohei 22/Joji 6) they were defeated, and thereafter the Southern Court lost its large-scale military might, and even suffered the loss of Hiroyo OUCHI and Tokiuji YAMANA, who submitted to the shogunate during the rule of Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Emperor Go-Daigo passed away in 1339 (Engen 4/Ryakuo 2), Chikafusa became the de facto leader of the Southern Court, but when Chikafusa himself died in 1354 (Shohei 9/Bunwa 3), the Southern Court again fell into decline; having lost the internal power struggle within the Ashikaga shogunate, Kiyouji HOSOKAWA switched allegiance to Masanori KUSUNOKI and the Southern Court and together managed to briefly occupy Kyoto, but in 1367 (Shohei 22/Joji 6) they were defeated, and thereafter the Southern Court lost its large-scale military might, and even suffered the loss of Hiroyo OUCHI and Tokiuji YAMANA, who submitted to the shogunate during the rule of Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Emperor Godaigo passed away in 1339, Chikafusa became the de facto leader of the Southern Court, but when Chikafusa himself died in 1354, the Southern Court again fell into decline; having lost the internal power struggle within the Ashikaga shogunate, Kiyouji HOSOKAWA switched allegiance to Masanori KUSUNOKI and the Southern Court and together managed to briefly occupy Kyoto, but in 1367 they were defeated, and thereafter the Southern Court lost its large-scale military might, and even suffered the loss of Hiroyo OUCHI and Tokiuji YAMANA, who submitted to the shogunate during the rule of Shogun Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→Godaigo (Engen 4/Ryakuo 2) (Shohei 9/Bunwa 3) (Shohei 22/Joji 6)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>義詮の死後は、足利幕府は幼い将軍足利義満を補佐した管領細川頼之の指導により、南朝方の中心的武将であった楠木正儀（正成の子）を帰順させるなど対南朝工作を行い、幕府体制を確立する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Yoshiakira died, governance over the shogunate fell to the Kanrei Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, acting as advisor to the young Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA; under Yoriyuki&apos;s direction, the shogunal system was firmly established, and the Northern Court launched various maneuvers against the Southern Court, including forcing Masanori KUSUNOKI (son of Masashige), the Southern Court&apos;s chief military commander, to switch allegiance to the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After Yoshiakira died, governance over the shogunate fell to the Kanrei Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, acting as advisor to the young Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA; under Yoriyuki&apos;s direction, the shogunal system was firmly established, and the Northern Court launched various maneuvers against the Southern Court, including forcing Masanori KUSUNOKI (son of Masashige), the Southern Court&apos;s chief military commander, to switch allegiance to the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After Yoshiakira died, governance over the shogunate fell to the Kanrei Yoriyuki HOSOKAWA, acting as advisor to the young Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA; under Yoriyuki&apos;s direction, the shogunal system was firmly established, and the Northern Court launched various maneuvers against the Southern Court, including forcing Masanori KUSUNOKI (son of Masashige), the Southern Court&apos;s chief military commander, to switch allegiance to the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>九州の情勢と南北朝合一まで</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The status of the conflict in Kyushu, and the events leading up until the unification of the Southern and Northern Courts</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The status of the conflict in Kyushu, and the events leading up until the unification of the Southern and Northern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The status of the conflict in Kyushu, and the events leading up until the unification of the Southern and Northern Courts</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="32">
<j>九州地方では、多々良浜の戦いで足利方に敗れた菊池氏などの南朝勢力と、尊氏が残した一色範氏や仁木義長などの勢力が争いを続けていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On Kyushu, the fight continued between the Kikuchi clan, who had been defeated by the Ashikaga army in the battle of Tatarahama, as well as other Southern Court forces against the armies of Yoshinaga NIKKI and Noriuji ISHIKI, whom Takauji had left in charge in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Kyushu, the fight continued between the Kikuchi clan, who had been defeated by the Ashikaga army in the battle of Tatarahama, as well as other Southern Court forces against the armies of Yoshinaga NIKKI and Noriuji ISHIKI, whom Takauji had left in charge in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>&quot;on Kyushu&quot; changed to &quot;In Kyushu&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Kyushu, the fight continued between the Kikuchi clan, who had been defeated by the Ashikaga army in the battle of Tatarahama, as well as other Southern Court forces against the armies of Yoshinaga NIKKI and Noriuji ISHIKI, whom Takauji had left in charge in Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>南朝勢力を強化するために、後醍醐天皇の皇子である懐良親王が征西将軍として派遣され、筑後川の戦い（大保原の戦い）では、南朝方の懐良親王、菊池武光、赤星武貫、宇都宮貞久、草野永幸らと北朝方の少弐頼尚、少弐直資の父子、大友氏時、宇都宮冬綱ら両軍合わせて約10万人が戦ったとされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In order to bolster the Southern Court&apos;s military might in Kyushu, Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s son Prince Kaneyoshi was dispatched there as Seisei shogun (General of the West), and in the battle of the Chikugo river (also known as the battle of Ohobaru) over 100,000 men were said to have fought, including Prince Kaneyoshi, Takemitsu KIKUCHI, Taketsura AKEBOSHI, Sadahisa UTSUNOMIYA, and Nagayuki NAGANO for the Southern Court, and father and son Yorihisa and Naosuke SHONI as well as Ujitoki OUCHI and Fuyutsuna UTSUNOMIYA for the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In order to bolster the Southern Court&apos;s military might in Kyushu, Emperor Go-Daigo&apos;s son Prince Kaneyoshi was dispatched there as Seisei shogun (General of the West), and in the battle of the Chikugo river (also known as the battle of Ohobaru) over 100,000 men were said to have fought, including Prince Kaneyoshi, Takemitsu KIKUCHI, Taketsura AKEBOSHI, Sadahisa UTSUNOMIYA, and Nagayuki NAGANO for the Southern Court, and father and son Yorihisa and Naosuke SHONI as well as Ujitoki OUCHI and Fuyutsuna UTSUNOMIYA for the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In order to bolster the Southern Court&apos;s military might in Kyushu, Emperor Godaigo&apos;s son Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi was dispatched there as Seisei shogun (General of the West), and in the battle of the Chikugo river (also known as the battle of Ohobaru) over 100,000 men were said to have fought, including Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi, Takemitsu KIKUCHI, Taketsura AKABOSHI, Sadahisa UTSUNOMIYA, and Nagayuki KUSANO for the Southern Court, and father and son Yorihisa and Naosuke SHONI as well as Ujitoki OUCHI and Fuyutsuna UTSUNOMIYA for the Northern Court.</e>
<cmt>Go-Daigo→GodaigoImperial補足AKEBOSHI→AKABOSHINAGANO→KUSANO</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>この戦いに敗れた北朝方は大宰府に逃れ、九州はこの後10年ほど南朝の支配下に入ることとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Northern Court forces were defeated and fled to Dazaifu, and for about the next ten years, Kyushu passed under the control of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Northern Court forces were defeated and fled to Dazaifu, and for about the next ten years, Kyushu passed under the control of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Northern Court forces were defeated and fled to Dazaifu, and for about the next ten years, Kyushu passed under the control of the Southern Court.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="35">
<j>また観応の擾乱が起こると足利直冬が加わり、三勢力が抗争する鼎立状態となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And then, after the Kanno Disturbance, a new faction emerged under Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, and a three-way struggle began.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And then, after the Kanno Disturbance, a new faction emerged under Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, and a three-way struggle began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And then, after the Kanno Disturbance, a new faction emerged under Tadafuyu ASHIKAGA, and a three-way struggle began.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>この頃、朝鮮半島や中国の沿岸などで倭寇（前期倭寇と呼ばれる）と呼ばれる海上集団が活動し始めており、懐良親王は倭寇の取り締まりを条件に明朝から冊封を受け、「日本国王」としての権威で勢力を強める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this time, maritime groups of pirates called Wako (meaning Japanese pirates) began to raid the coasts of the Korean peninsula and China (these are labeled the &quot;early period Wako&quot; to distinguish them from later pirate groups of the same name), and a request, called a Sakuho, from the Ming court that the pirates be brought under control was sent to Prince Kaneyoshi, addressed to the &quot;King of Japan&quot;; Kaneyoshi thereby received a boost to his authority.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Around this time, maritime groups of pirates called Wako (meaning Japanese pirates) began to raid the coasts of the Korean peninsula and China (these are labeled the &quot;early period Wako&quot; to distinguish them from later pirate groups of the same name), and a request, called a Sakuho, from the Ming court that the pirates be brought under control was sent to Prince Kaneyoshi, addressed to the &quot;King of Japan&quot;; Kaneyoshi thereby received a boost to his authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Around this time, maritime groups of pirates called Wako (meaning Japanese pirates) began to raid the coasts of the Korean peninsula and China (these are labeled the &quot;early period Wako&quot; to distinguish them from later pirate groups of the same name), and a request, called a Sakuho, from the Ming court that the pirates be brought under control was sent to Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi, addressed to the &apos;King of Japan&apos;; Kaneyoshi thereby received a boost to his authority.</e>
<cmt>Imperial補足原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>室町幕府は今川貞世を九州へ派遣して南朝勢力を鎮圧し、直冬も幕府に屈服したため、足利義満の代には九州も幕府の支配するところとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then the Muromachi shogunate dispatched Sadayo IMAGAWA to Kyushu to subjugate the Southern Court forces there, and after Tadafuyu also yielded to the shogunate, Kyushu passed back under the control of the shogunate during the rule of Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then the Muromachi shogunate dispatched Sadayo IMAGAWA to Kyushu to subjugate the Southern Court forces there, and after Tadafuyu also yielded to the shogunate, Kyushu passed back under the control of the shogunate during the rule of Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then the Muromachi bakufu dispatched Sadayo IMAGAWA to Kyushu to subjugate the Southern Court forces there, and after Tadafuyu also yielded to the bakufu, Kyushu passed back under the control of the bakufu during the rule of Shogun Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>その後、足利義満が新たに冊封されて「日本国王」となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thereafter, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was sent a new official message (Sakuho) from the Ming Court labeling him the &quot;King of Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thereafter, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was sent a new official message (Sakuho) from the Ming Court addressing him as the &quot;King of Japan.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;labeling him as the&quot; changed to &quot;addressing him as the&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thereafter, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was sent a new official message (Sakuho) from the Ming Court addressing him as the &apos;King of Japan.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文の「」に合わせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="39">
<j>弘和/永徳・元中/至徳 (日本)年間に入ると、南朝は動乱初期からその支えとして活躍してきた懐良親王、北畠顕能、宗良親王の相次ぐ死と、対北朝強硬路線を通していた長慶天皇の譲位により、衰退を極める事となったが、明徳年間の足利義満による相次ぐ有力守護大名勢力削減により、北朝に抵抗する術を殆ど失うようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But having reached the period of the Kowa/Entoku and Genchu/ Shitoku eras, Prince Kaneyoshi, Akiyoshi KITABATAKE, and Prince Muneyoshi, those who had been fighting for the Southern Court from the early days of their anti-shogunal struggle, and had been the Southern Court&apos;s main support, died one after the other, and when Emperor Chokei--who had been such a stalwart opponent of the Northern Court--abdicated, the Southern Court entered a period of extreme decline; during the Meitoku period, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was able to greatly reduce the power and influence of the strongest shugo daimyo one after another, until almost all means to resist the Northern Court had been lost.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But having reached the period of the Kowa/Entoku and Genchu/ Shitoku eras, Prince Kaneyoshi, Akiyoshi KITABATAKE, and Prince Muneyoshi, who had been fighting for the Southern Court from the early days of their anti-shogunal struggle, and had been the Southern Court&apos;s main support, died one after the other, and when Emperor Chokei--who had been such a stalwart opponent of the Northern Court--abdicated, the Southern Court entered a period of extreme decline; during the Meitoku period, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was able to greatly reduce the power and influence of the strongest shugo daimyo one after another, until almost all means to resist the Northern Court had been lost.</e>
<cmt>&quot;those&quot; after &quot;Muneyoshi,&quot; deleted</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But having reached the period of the Kowa/Entoku and Genchu/Shitoku eras, Imperial Prince Kaneyoshi, Akiyoshi KITABATAKE, and Imperial Prince Muneyoshi, who had been fighting for the Southern Court from the early days of their anti-shogunal struggle, and had been the Southern Court&apos;s main support, died one after the other, and when Emperor Chokei--who had been such a stalwart opponent of the Northern Court--abdicated, the Southern Court entered a period of extreme decline; during the Meitoku period, Yoshimitsu ASHIKAGA was able to greatly reduce the power and influence of the strongest shugo daimyo one after another, until almost all means to resist the Northern Court had been lost.</e>
<cmt>スペース削除Imperial補足</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>このような情勢の中で1392年（元中9年/明徳3年）、足利義満の斡旋で、大覚寺統と持明院統の両統迭立と、全国の国衙領を大覚寺統の所有とすること（実際には国衙領はわずかしかなかった）を条件に、南朝の後亀山天皇が北朝の後小松天皇に三種の神器を渡し、南北朝が合体した（明徳の和約）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amid such circumstance, in 1392 (Genchu 9/Meitoku 3), through Shogun Yoshimitsu&apos;s mediation, under the conditions that the alternate succession between the Kameyama (Daitokuji) and Jimyoin lineages be restored, and the Kameyama (Daitokuji) lineage be officially made owner of all the Kokuga (public) territory in the entire country (although in actuality, there was very little such territory due to the proliferation of shoen), Emperor Go-Kameyama of the Southern Court handed over the Imperial Regalia to Emperor Go-Komatsu of the Northern Court, and the Northern and Southern Courts were unified (in what was called the Peace Treaty of Meitoku).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amid such circumstance, in 1392 (Genchu 9/Meitoku 3), through Shogun Yoshimitsu&apos;s mediation, under the conditions that the alternate succession between the Kameyama (Daitokuji) and Jimyoin lineages be restored, and the Kameyama (Daitokuji) lineage be officially made owner of all the Kokuga (public) territory in the entire country (although in actuality, there was very little such territory due to the proliferation of shoen), Emperor Go-Kameyama of the Southern Court handed over the Imperial Regalia to Emperor Go-Komatsu of the Northern Court, and the Northern and Southern Courts were unified (in what was called the Peace Treaty of Meitoku).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amid such circumstance, in 1392 (Genchu 9/Meitoku 3), through Shogun Yoshimitsu&apos;s mediation, under the conditions that the alternate succession between the Kameyama (Daitokuji) and Jimyoin lineages be restored, and the Kameyama (Daitokuji) lineage be officially made owner of all the Kokuga (public) territory in the entire country (although in actuality, there was very little such territory due to the proliferation of shoen), Emperor Gokameyama of the Southern Court handed over the Imperial Regalia to Emperor Gokomatsu of the Northern Court, and the Northern and Southern Courts were unified (in what was called the Peace Treaty of Meitoku).</e>
<cmt>Go-Kameyama→GokameyamaGo-Komatsu→Gokomatsu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>後南朝</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gonancho (ex-Southern Court forces)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gonancho (ex-Southern Court forces)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gonancho (ex-Southern Court forces)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="41">
<j>合一が行われるものの、両統迭立の約束が守られることはなく持明院統の皇統が続いたため、南朝の遺臣たちによる皇位の回復を目指しての反抗が15世紀半ばまで続き、後南朝と呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the unification was completed, however, the promise to uphold the alternate succession was broken and the Jimyoin lineage continued to monopolize Imperial succession, and consequently former Southern Court retainers continued their resistance, in their attempts to restore their own lineage to the Imperial throne, into the middle of the fifteenth century, and were later dubbed &quot;gonancho&quot; (ex-Southern Court forces).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the unification was completed, however, the promise to uphold the alternate succession was broken and the Jimyoin lineage continued to monopolize Imperial succession, and consequently former Southern Court retainers continued their resistance, in their attempts to restore their own lineage to the Imperial throne, into the middle of the fifteenth century, and were later dubbed &quot;gonancho&quot; (ex-Southern Court forces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the unification was completed, however, the promise to uphold the alternate succession was broken and the Jimyoin lineage continued to monopolize Imperial succession, and consequently former Southern Court retainers continued their resistance, in their attempts to restore their own lineage to the Imperial throne, into the middle of the fifteenth century, and were later dubbed &quot;gonancho&quot; (ex-Southern Court forces).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>彼らの抵抗は持明院統嫡流が断絶した1428年（正長元年）以後、激化することとなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">gonancho resistance only intensified after 1428 (the first year of the Shocho era), when the Jimyoin lineage running from the eldest son was broken.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">gonancho resistance only intensified after 1428 (the first year of the Shocho era), when the Jimyoin lineage running from the eldest son was broken.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gonancho resistance only intensified after 1428, when the Jimyoin lineage running from the eldest son was broken.</e>
<cmt>文頭大文字に(the first year of the Shocho era)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>1443年（嘉吉3年）には南朝の遺臣や日野氏一族が御所に乱入し南朝皇族の通蔵主・金蔵主兄弟をかついで神璽・宝剣を一時奪還する禁闕の変が起きる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1443 (Kakitsu 3), in what became known as the Kinketsu Incident (the incident at the Forbidden Palace) some of the surviving Southern Court former retainers, along with the entire household of the Hino clan, broke in to the Imperial Palace where they stole two of the Three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the Ama-no Murakumo no Tsurugi (the heavenly cloud gathering sword) and the Yasakani no Magatama (the Grand Jewels) before fleeing with Tsuzosu and Gonzosu, brothers of the Southern Court lineage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1443 (Kakitsu 3), in what became known as the Kinketsu Incident (the incident at the Forbidden Palace) some of the surviving Southern Court former retainers, along with the entire household of the Hino clan, broke in to the Imperial Palace where they stole two of the Three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the Ama-no Murakumo no Tsurugi (the heavenly cloud gathering sword) and the Yasakani no Magatama (the Grand Jewels) before fleeing with Tsuzosu and Gonzosu, brothers of the Southern Court lineage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1443, in what became known as the Kinketsu Incident (the incident at the Forbidden Palace) some of the surviving Southern Court former retainers, along with the entire household of the Hino clan, broke in to the Imperial Palace where they stole two of the Three Imperial Regalia of Japan, the Ama-no Murakumo no Tsurugi (the heavenly cloud gathering sword) and the Yasakani no Magatama (the Grand Jewels) before fleeing with Tsuzosu and Gonzosu, brothers of the Southern Court lineage.</e>
<cmt>(Kakitsu 3)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>宝剣はすぐに幕府の手で取り戻されたが、神璽は後南朝に持ち去られたままになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Sword was soon recovered by shogunal forces, but the gonancho forces were able to escape with the Grand Jewels.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Sword was soon recovered by shogunal forces, but the gonancho forces were able to escape with the Grand Jewels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Sword was soon recovered by shogunal forces, but the gonancho forces were able to escape with the Grand Jewels.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>後南朝は、嘉吉の乱で滅亡した赤松氏の再興を目指す赤松遺臣によって、1457年（長禄元年）に南朝後裔の自天王・忠義王なる兄弟が殺害され、神璽が奪還されることによって、実質的に滅亡した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But in 1457 (the first year of the Choroku era), the gonancho forces were essentially ruined when they were betrayed by the surviving retainers of the AKAMATSU clan, who were seeking to restore the clan after their annihilation in the Kakitsu rebellion; the Southern Court descendants, the brothers Jitenno and Chugio, were assassinated, and the Grand Jewels were restolen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But in 1457 (the first year of the Choroku era), the gonancho forces were essentially ruined when they were betrayed by the surviving retainers of the AKAMATSU clan, who were seeking to restore the clan after their annihilation in the Kakitsu rebellion; the Southern Court descendants, the brothers Jitenno and Chugio, were assassinated, and the Grand Jewels were restolen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But in 1457, the gonancho forces were essentially ruined when they were betrayed by the surviving retainers of the AKAMATSU clan, who were seeking to restore the clan after their annihilation in the Kakitsu rebellion; the Southern Court descendants, the brothers Jitenno and Chugio, were assassinated, and the Grand Jewels were restolen.</e>
<cmt>(the first year of the Choroku era)特に年号が問題になる箇所ではないので、削除</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>土地支配の変化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Changes in how land was controlled</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Changes in how land was controlled</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Changes in how land was controlled</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="46">
<j>鎌倉時代初期には、国衙領や、荘園のうち皇室・公家や寺社の領地には、武家の支配がおよんでいなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the early days of the Kamakura shogunate, jurisdiction over the Kokugaryo (public) lands and the shoen (private estates) was held by the Imperial household, the aristocracy (the Court nobles), and the temples and shrines; warriors had not yet begun to intrude on questions of land ownership.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the early days of the Kamakura shogunate, jurisdiction over the Kokugaryo (public) lands and the shoen (private estates) and the temples and shrines was held by the Imperial household, the aristocracy (the Court nobles), samurai had not yet begun to intrude on questions of land ownership.</e>
<cmt>restructured to place temples and shrines together with other properties before &quot;was held by the Imperial household,&quot; &quot;warriors&quot; changed to &quot;samurai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the early days of the Kamakura period, samurai had not yet begun to challenge the ownership of kokugaryo (public) lands and shoen (private estates) by the Imperial household, the aristocracy (the Court nobles), and the temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt>shogunate→period原文と意味はずれている部分があるため、大幅に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>鎌倉時代を通じて、武家の統治機構である守護・地頭に属する武士が、地頭請や下地中分という形で国衙領や荘園を蚕食し始めるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">But as the Kamakura period progressed, the warrior-based administrative system, the warriors serving as shugo (Protectors) and jito (estate stewards) began to take over kokuga (public) territories and shoen through such means as jitouke (in which an estate steward was contracted by the rightful owner of an estate to guard it) and shitaji chubun (whereby lands were divided between steward and owner).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">But as the Kamakura period progressed, the samurai-based administrative system, warriors serving as shugo (Protectors) and jito (estate stewards) began to take over kokuga (public) territories and shoen through such means as jitouke (in which an estate steward was contracted by the rightful owner of an estate to guard it) and shitaji chubun (whereby lands were divided between steward and owner).</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; deleted before &quot;warriors serving as&quot; and &quot;warriors&quot; changed to &quot;samurai&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">But as the Kamakura period progressed, the samurai-based administrative system, warriors serving as shugo (Protectors) and jito (estate stewards) began to take over kokuga (public) territories and shoen through such means as jitouke (in which an estate steward was contracted by the rightful owner of an estate to guard it) and shitaji chubun (whereby lands were divided between steward and owner).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>この傾向は南北朝時代に入ると顕著になり、荘園の年貢の半分を幕府に納める半済や、年貢の取立てを守護が請け負う守護請が一般化した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These trends became still more prominent in the Nanbokucho period with the spread of the half-tax, in which half of the yearly proceeds of a shoen were turned over to the shogunate, and the shugosei system, in which the shugo was contracted with the duty of collecting the land tax.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These trends became still more prominent in the Nanbokucho period with the spread of the half-tax, in which half of the yearly proceeds of a shoen were turned over to the shogunate, and the shugosei system, in which the shugo was contracted with the duty of collecting the land tax.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These trends became still more prominent in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts with the spread of the half-tax, in which half of the yearly proceeds of a shoen were turned over to the shogunate, and the shugouke system, in which the shugo was contracted with the duty of collecting the land tax.</e>
<cmt>shugosei→shugouke&quot;the Nanbokucho period&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また、鎌倉時代の御家人の3大義務であった大犯三ヶ条（大番催促、謀反人・殺害人の検断）に加えて、刈田狼藉の取締も守護の役務となり、荘園領主は守護の立入を拒むことができなくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, in addition to the Taibon sankajo, the three great duties (of answering the call to guard Kyoto, and of hunting down traitors and assassins) required of the gokenin (lower retainers) of the Kamakura period, the shugo were also tasked with protecting the rice fields from those who sought to avoid the tax by harvesting rice illegally, and as time passed the rightful owners of the estates could no longer dare refuse to hire a shugo for their lands.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, in addition to the Taibon sankajo, the three great duties (of answering the call to guard Kyoto, and of hunting down traitors and assassins) required of the gokenin (lower retainers) during the Kamakura period, the shugo were also tasked with protecting the rice fields from those who sought to avoid the tax by harvesting rice illegally, and as time passed the rightful owners of the estates could no longer dare refuse to hire a shugo for their lands.</e>
<cmt>&quot;of the Kamakura period&quot; changed to during the Kamakura period&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, in addition to the Taibon sankajo, the three great duties (of answering the call to guard Kyoto, and of hunting down traitors and assassins) required of the gokenin (lower retainers) during the Kamakura period, the shugo were also tasked with protecting the rice fields from those who sought to avoid tax by harvesting rice illegally, and as time passed the rightful owners of the estates could no longer dare refuse to hire a shugo for their lands.</e>
<cmt>定冠詞不要。“avoid the tax ”=&gt;”avoid tax ”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>これらを通じて、土地支配上の武士の立場は、荘官・下司として荘園領主に代わって荘園を管理するだけの立場から実質的な領主へと変化していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Thanks to these conditions, the position of warriors as regards control over land changed from being mere managers of shoen, tax collectors and subordinates to the rightful owners, to essentially supplanting the titular owners and assuming de facto control over the shoen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thanks to these conditions, the position of samurai regarding the control over land changed from being mere managers of shoen, tax collectors and subordinates to the rightful owners, to essentially supplanting the titular owners and assuming de facto control over the shoen.</e>
<cmt>correction: &quot;samurai regarding the control over land&quot; replaced original wording</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In these conditions, the position of samurai regarding the control over land changed from being mere managers of shoen, tax collectors and subordinates to the rightful owners, to essentially supplanting the titular owners and assuming de facto control over the shoen.</e>
<cmt>“Thanks to these conditions,” =&gt; “In these conditions,”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>守護は、このような武士と主従関係を結ぶようになり、領国内への支配権を強め、守護大名と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shugo took such warriors in their newfound positions of power and forged a master-follower bond with them, thereby strengthening their hegemony over their own territories, and eventually began to be called &quot;shugo daimyo&quot; (daimyo literally means &quot;big name&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shugo took such warriors in their newfound positions of power and forged a master-follower bond with them, thereby strengthening their hegemony over their own territories, and eventually began to be called &quot;shugo daimyo&quot; (daimyo literally means &quot;big name&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shugo took such warriors in their newfound positions of power and forged a master-follower bond with them, thereby strengthening their hegemony over their own territories, and eventually began to be called &quot;shugo daimyo&quot; (daimyo literally means &quot;big name&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>南北朝合一時に国衙領がほとんど残っていなかったのはこのような背景による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is due to these circumstances that, by the time the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, almost no kokuga (public) territories remained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is due to these circumstances that, by the time the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, almost no kokuga (public) territories remained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Because of this, by the time the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, almost no kokuga (public) territories remained.</e>
<cmt>語句の問題。→ “Because of this, by the time the Northern and Southern Courts were unified, almost no kokuga (public) territories remained.”</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>なお、荘園公領制が完全に崩壊するのは、南北朝時代よりも2世紀後の太閤検地によってであるが、この南北朝期に既に大きな転機を迎えていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nevertheless, although the shoen koryo sei (system of controlling private and public lands) did not completely collapse until more than 200 years after the reunification of the Southern and Northern Courts, when the Taiko Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI ordered his great country-wide land survey, land ownership had already reached a major turning point during the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nevertheless, although the shoen koryo sei (system of controlling private and public lands) did not completely collapse until more than 200 years after the reunification of the Southern and Northern Courts, when the Taiko Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI ordered his great country-wide land survey, land ownership had already reached a major turning point during the Nanbokucho period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nevertheless, although the shoen koryo sei (system of controlling private and public lands) did not completely collapse until more than 200 years after the reunification of the Southern and Northern Courts, when the Taiko Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI ordered his great country-wide land survey, land ownership had already reached a major turning point during the period of the Northern and Southern Courts.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Nanbokucho period&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="54">
<j>戦乱により公家や朝廷の政治力が衰え、政治の主導は完全に武家へ移ることになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The political authority of the aristocracy (Court nobles) and the Imperial Court was sapped away through wars and rebellions, and true leadership over the country&apos;s government passed completely over to the warrior class.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The political authority of the aristocracy (Court nobles) and the Imperial Court was sapped away through wars and rebellions, and true leadership over the country&apos;s government passed completely over to the warrior class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The political authority of the aristocracy (Court nobles) and the Imperial Court was sapped away through wars and rebellions, and true leadership over the country&apos;s government passed completely over to the warrior class.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>また、武家社会でも、それまで当たり前だった全国に分散した所領の支配が難しくなり、分散した所領を売却・交換し、一箇所にまとめた所領の一円化傾向が顕著になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, even within warrior society, the system of dividing and distributing ownership and control of lands throughout the country, which until that point had been thought fair and natural, became problematic, and the tendency for owners to sell or exchange some of these distributed lands to concentrate their power and influence in one place became pronounced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, even within the samurai society, the system of dividing and distributing ownership and control of lands throughout the country, which until that point had been thought fair and natural, became problematic, and the tendency for owners to sell or exchange some of these distributed lands to concentrate their power and influence in one place became pronounced.</e>
<cmt>&quot;warrior&quot; changed to &quot;samurai,&quot; &quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;samurai society&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, even within the samurai society, the system of dividing and distributing ownership and control of lands throughout the country, which until that point had been thought fair and natural, became problematic, and the tendency for owners to sell or exchange some of these distributed lands to concentrate their power and influence in one place became pronounced.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>これに伴い、関東の狭い「苗字の地」から新恩の広い地方へ移り住む例が多くなる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a result, many clans relocated from their cramped family lands in the Kanto to more spacious lands they had been newly awarded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a result, many clans relocated from their cramped family lands in Kanto to the more spacious lands they had been newly awarded.</e>
<cmt>&quot;the&quot; deleted before &quot;Kanto&quot; and &quot;the&quot; inserted before &quot;more spacious lands&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a result, many clans relocated from their cramped family lands in Kanto to the more spacious lands they had been newly awarded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>後年</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2"></e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later years</e>
<cmt>訳を補足しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="57">
<j>近世以来、南北朝のいずれが正統かをめぐって南北朝正閏論が行われてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Starting in more recent years, debate has been raging over which lineage, that of the Southern or Northern Court, is legitimate (called the Nanbokucho seijunron in Japanese).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Starting in more recent years, debate has been raging over which lineage, that of the Southern or Northern Court, is legitimate (called the Nanbokucho seijunron in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Starting in more recent years, debate has been raging over which lineage, that of the Southern or Northern Court, is legitimate (called the Nanbokucho seijunron in Japanese).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>明治時代には皇室は南朝が正統とされ、文部省は国定教科書で「吉野朝時代」の用語を使うよう命じた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Imperial household declared the Southern Court to have been the legitimate Court, and Ministry of Education, Culture, and Sports ordered that government-controlled textbooks begin using the term &quot;Yoshino period&quot; instead of &quot;Nanbokucho.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Meiji period, the Imperial household declared the Southern Court to be the legitimate Court, and the Ministry of Education, Culture, and Sports ordered that government-controlled textbooks begin using the term &quot;Yoshino period&quot; instead of &quot;Nanbokucho.&quot;</e>
<cmt>&quot;to be&quot; replaced wording after &quot;Southern Court&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Meiji period, the Imperial household declared the Southern Court to be the legitimate Court, and the Ministry of Education, Culture, and Sports ordered that government-controlled textbooks begin using the term &apos;Yoshino period&apos; instead of Nanbokucho.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に原文に『』のない&quot;　&quot;を削除</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>第二次世界大戦後も南朝が正統とされているが、歴史の実態に合わせて再び「南北朝時代」の用語が主流になった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Southern Court was still officially considered the legitimate Imperial Court after the Second World War, but in harmony with the historical reality, the term &quot;Nanbokucho period&quot; once again came into widespread use.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Southern Court was still officially considered the legitimate Imperial Court after the Second World War, but in harmony with the historical reality, the term &quot;Nanbokucho period&quot; once again came into widespread use.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Southern Court was still officially considered the legitimate Imperial Court after the Second World War, but in harmony with the historical reality, the term &apos;Nanbokucho period&apos; once again came into widespread use.</e>
<cmt>原文の「」にあわせ&quot;を&apos;に</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>また、北朝が優勢な期間が長く、最終的に北朝に統一されたことを重視して「北南朝時代」の用語を提唱する者も存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, there were also some who advocated changing the term to &quot;HokuSouthern period&quot; to emphasize the fact that the Northern Court&apos;s period of predominance had been longer than the Southern Court&apos;s, and that in the end the Southern Court was unified into the Northern Court, not the other way around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, there were also some who advocated changing the term to &quot;HokuSouthern period&quot; to emphasize the fact that the Northern Court&apos;s period of predominance had been longer than the Southern Court&apos;s, and that in the end the Southern Court was unified into the Northern Court, not the other way around.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, there were also some who advocated changing the term to &apos;Hoku Southern period&apos; to emphasize the fact that the Northern Court&apos;s period of predominance had been longer than the Southern Court&apos;s, and that in the end the Southern Court was unified into the Northern Court, not the other way around.</e>
<cmt>スペース挿入</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>文化・社会風潮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cultural and social developments of the period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cultural and social developments of the period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cultural and social developments of the period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="61">
<j>ばさら、二条河原落書、連歌など</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basara, &quot;Scribblings from the Nijo riverbank,&quot; and Renga (linked verse)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basara, &quot;Scribblings from the Nijo riverbank,&quot; and Renga (linked verse)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basara, &quot;Scribblings from the Nijo riverbank,&quot; and Renga (linked verse)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>人物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Notable figures</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Notable figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Notable figures</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="62">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)の人物一覧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A list of prominent figures of the Nanbokucho period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A list of prominent figures of the Nanbokucho period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A list of prominent figures of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Nanbokucho period&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>南北朝時代の元号</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Era names of the Nanbokucho period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Era names of the Nanbokucho period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Era names of the period of the Northern and Southern Courts</e>
<cmt>&quot;the Nanbokucho period&quot;→&quot;the period of the Northern and Southern Courts&quot;に変更しました。</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>天皇</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperors</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperors</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Noir(id:45654), Nnh(id:474), Pazuzu(id:103079), Novo(id:87875), 888asa88(id:161608), 経済準学士(id:22656), Eskimbot(id:29676), TXiKiBoT(id:107492), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Damdamdamd(id:109603), アスカ(id:9205), Kamakura(id:472), Greenland4(id:114494), Johncapistrano(id:969), でここ(id:9565), カメックスリザードンアルセウス(id:180800), A6M4(id:14155), NPD(id:58640), 秀の介(id:490), 怪蘇(id:45514), Loveless(id:129239), Shimoxx(id:9332), Yas(id:739), Yosemite(id:5808), Mnd(id:15140), Forestfarmer(id:59407), 水野白楓(id:22811), Himazin(id:22034), Tcyiswalk(id:7279), LiDaobing(id:14511), Ro-(id:36890), Kamitani(id:30757), Rusk(id:9895), Murasagi(id:79122), Doshoka(id:139380), Yonoemon(id:55450), SilvonenBot(id:190970), 史跡めぐり(id:95651), Junger(id:10282), Louperibot(id:128971), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>