<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>江戸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>江戸（えど,日本語以外ではEdo、Yedo、Yeddo、Yendo、Jedoなど諸表記あり）は、東京の旧称である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Edo&quot; (also described as Yedo, Yeddo, Yendo, Jedo) is the old name for Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Edo&quot; (also described as Yedo, Yeddo, Yendo, Jedo) is the former name for Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Diction -- really a matter of preference.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Edo&quot; (also described as Yedo, Yeddo, Yendo, Jedo) is the former name for Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>特に、江戸城を中心とする現在で言う東京特別区中心部（東京都千代田区・中央区 (東京都)周辺）を指す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It especially referred to the area centering on the Edo Castle, the current central area of Tokyo Special Ward (Chiyoda and Chuo Wards and their surrounding areas).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It refers to an area centered around Edo Castle that encompasses the center of present day Tokyo Special Ward (Chiyoda and Chuo Wards and their surrounding areas).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It refers to an area centered around Edo Castle that encompasses the center of present day Tokyo Special Ward (Chiyoda and Chuo Wards and their surrounding areas).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸は明治維新により東京とされるまで皇居を置かなかったため都ではなかったが、江戸時代には江戸幕府が置かれた事実上の日本の首都(行政首都)であり、日本の政治経済の中心地として発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Until the Meiji Restoration, when Edo was renamed Tokyo, Edo was not an official capital city because the Imperial Palace was not located in Edo, but as a matter of practice, Edo had been served as an administrative capital of Japan and developed as the center of Japanese politics and economy since a feudal government was established in Edo in the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo did not become the capital until the Meiji Restoration when it was renamed Tokyo because the Imperial Palace was not located there; However, Edo served as the seat of Bakufu authority and thus the defacto capital of Japan (administrative capital) in the Edo period, and developed into a political and economic center of power.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo did not become the capital until the Meiji Restoration when it was renamed Tokyo because the Imperial Palace was not located there; However, Edo served as the seat of Bakufu authority and thus the defacto capital of Japan (administrative capital) in the Edo period, and developed into a political and economic center of power.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>また、江戸城は徳川氏の征夷大将軍の居城であり、江戸は幕府の政庁が置かれる行政府の所在地であると同時に、自身も天領を支配する領主である徳川氏（徳川将軍家）の城下町でもあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Castle was the residence of successive Tokugawa shoguns, aka. Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians&quot;), while Edo was where bakufu (feudal government) was established along with all the government offices, and it also was a castle town (a town created around the castle of a feudal lord) of the Tokugawa clan (the Tokugawa Shogunate Family) who was the feudal lord of shogunal demesne in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Castle was the residence of successive Tokugawa shoguns, or Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who pacifies barbarians&quot;), and the city of Edo was both the site of bakufu administrative organs and the personal castle town of the Tokugawa Clan that ruled over the shogunal domain.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Castle was the residence of successive Tokugawa shoguns, or Seii taishogun (literally, &quot;the great general who pacifies barbarians&quot;), and the city of Edo was both the site of bakufu administrative organs and the personal castle town of the Tokugawa Clan that ruled over the shogunal domain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>幕末になると政治的中心が再び京都に移り、15代将軍徳川慶喜は将軍としては江戸に一度も居住しなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, at the end of the Edo Period, the political center was returned to Kyoto, and therefore, the 15th shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, did not reside in Edo as a shogun even once.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The political center had shifted back to Kyoto by the end of the Edo Period, and the 15th shogun TOKUGAWA Yoshinobu never resided in EDO.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The political center had shifted back to Kyoto by the end of the Edo Period, and the 15th shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA never resided in EDO.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA YoshinobuをYoshinobu　TOKUGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>1868年（明治元年）に発せられた江戸ヲ称シテ東京ト為スノ詔書により江戸は東京と改称され、続く天皇の東京行幸により江戸城が東京の皇居とされた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1868 (the first year of the Meiji Period), Edo was renamed Tokyo in accordance with the promulgated imperial edict, followed by the Emperor&apos;s visit to Edo and the appointment of the Edo Castle the Imperial Palace in Tokyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1868 (the first year of the Meiji Period), Edo was renamed Tokyo in accordance with an imperial edict, and Edo Castle became the Imperial Palace in Tokyo after the Emperor&apos;s arrival.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1868 (the first year of the Meiji Period), Edo was renamed Tokyo in accordance with an imperial edict, and Edo Castle became the Imperial Palace in Tokyo after the Emperor&apos;s arrival.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>翌年には明治新政府も京都から東京に移され、日本の事実上の首都となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following year, all the functions of the new Meiji government were moved to Tokyo from Kyoto, paving the way for Tokyo to officially become the capital city of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the following year, all of the functions of the new Meiji government were transferred to Tokyo from Kyoto, paving the way for Tokyo to become the capital city of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Missing Particle; diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the following year, all of the functions of the new Meiji government were transferred to Tokyo from Kyoto, paving the way for Tokyo to become the capital city of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>また、東京への改称とともに町奉行支配地内を管轄する東京府庁が開庁された（1871年、廃藩置県に伴い新・東京府に更置）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, to coincide with the renaming of Edo, Tokyo-fucho (Tokyo prefectural office) was established to take over the governance of the area the town magistrate once ruled (in 1871, Tokyo-fu (Tokyo Prefecture) was re-established in accordance with the Haihan-chiken system [abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Along with the renaming of Tokyo to Edo, the Tokyo-fucho (Tokyo prefectural office) was established to govern the town magistrate (In 1871, Tokyo-fu (Tokyo Prefecture) was re-established in accordance with the Haihan-chiken system [Abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures]).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Along with the renaming of Tokyo to Edo, the Tokyo-fucho (Tokyo prefectural office) was established to govern the town magistrate (In 1871, Tokyo-fu (Tokyo Prefecture) was re-established in accordance with the Haihan-chiken system [Abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>1889年に、市制施行で東京市となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1889, Tokyo-shi (Tokyo City) was established based on the municipal organization.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1889, Tokyo-shi (Tokyo City) was established in accordance to munipal organization.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1889, Tokyo-shi (Tokyo City) was established in accordance to municipal organization.</e>
<cmt>munipal→municipalに修正</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>1943年の戦時体制下で、東京府と東京市は廃止されて、東京都が設置された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1943, when Japan was under the wartime regime, Tokyo-fu and Tokyo-shi were both abolished and Tokyo-to (Tokyo Metropolis) was established.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the wartime governance in 1943, Tokyo-fu and Tokyo-shi were both abolished, and Tokyo-to (Tokyo Metropolis) was established in their place.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the wartime governance in 1943, Tokyo-fu and Tokyo-shi were both abolished, and Tokyo-to (Tokyo Metropolis) was established in their place.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸の町は、大きく分けて見ると江戸城の西に広がる山の手の武家屋敷と、東の隅田川をはじめとする数々の河川・堀に面した庶民の町（下町）に大別される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The town of Edo was largely divided into two areas; an uptown area in the west of the Edo Castle, where samurai resided, and a downtown area developed along various rivers including Sumida-gawa River and moats, where common people lived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town of Edo was roughly categorized into an uptown area west of Edo Castle where samurai lived, and a downtown (shitamachi) area facing several rivers and moats beginning with the Sumidagawa riverwhere commoners lived.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town of Edo was roughly categorized into an uptown area west of Edo Castle where samurai lived, and a downtown (shitamachi) area facing several rivers and moats beginning with the Sumidagawa riverwhere commoners lived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>川・堀の水路網と蔵は江戸を象徴する町並の特徴であり、蔵造りの町並が残された川越市、栃木市、佐原市などの関東地方の河港都市は、江戸に似た構造という点や江戸と交流が深かったという点から「小江戸」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Channel networks of rivers and moats and kura (the earthen-walled storehouses) are the typical townscape of Edo, and the areas which still have the beautiful scenery of kura, such as Kawagoe City, Tochigi City and Sawara City, all of which are river port cities in the Kanto region, are now commonly called &apos;small Edo&apos; for their resemblance to Edo in terms of the city structure and also for the active exchange they had with Edo in the past.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Channel networks of rivers and moats and kura (the earthen-walled storehouses) characterized the Edo cityscape, and those river port cities in the Kanto area where the kura cityscape have survived such as Kawagoe, Tochigi, and Sawara are called &quot;small Edo&quot; for their architectural resemblance to Edo and the fact that these cities were actively traded with Edo.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Channel networks of rivers and moats and kura (the earthen-walled storehouses) characterized the Edo cityscape, and those river port cities in the Kanto area where the kura cityscape have survived such as Kawagoe, Tochigi, and Sawara are called &quot;small Edo&quot; for their architectural resemblance to Edo and the fact that these cities were actively traded with Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>徳川氏以前の江戸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo before the arrival of the Tokugawa clan</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo prior to the arrival of the Tokugawa clan</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo prior to the arrival of the Tokugawa clan</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="13">
<j>「江戸」という地名は、鎌倉幕府の歴史書『吾妻鏡』が史料上の初見で、おおよそ平安時代後半に発生した地名であると考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The name &apos;Edo&apos; first appeared in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), a history book of the Kamakura-bakufu feudal government (c.1185 - 1333), but it is considered that the establishment of Edo dates back to the latter half of the Heian Period (794 - c.1185).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first written record pertaining to the name &apos;Edo&apos; first appeared in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), a Kamakura-bakufu (c.1185 - 1333) history, but the name itself is said to be a place name that emerged in the latter half of the Heian Period (794 - c.1185).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first written record pertaining to the name &apos;Edo&apos; first appeared in &quot;Azuma Kagami&quot; (The Mirror of the East), a Kamakura-bakufu (c.1185 - 1333) history, but the name itself is said to be a place name that emerged in the latter half of the Heian Period (794 - c.1185).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>地名の語源は諸説あるが、江は川あるいは入江とすると、戸は入口を意味するから「江の入り口」に由来したと考える説が有力である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although there are many theories on the etymology of the place name, the widely-accepted one is that &apos;Edo&apos; means &apos;the entrance of a river or a cove&apos;, as &apos;E&apos; means a river or a cove and &apos;Do&apos; means an entrance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although there are many theories on the etymology of the Edo as a place name, the theory that the Character &quot;e&quot; [江] refers to a river or mouth of a river, and &quot;to&quot; [戸] as a gate or theshhold and hence &quot;entry to a river&quot; has been widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although there are many theories on the etymology of the Edo as a place name, the theory that the Character &quot;e&quot; [江] refers to a river or mouth of a river, and &quot;to&quot; [戸] as a gate or theshhold and hence &quot;entry to a river&quot; has been widely accepted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>当時の江戸は、武蔵国と下総国の国境である隅田川の河口の西に位置し、日比谷入江と呼ばれる入江が、後の江戸城の間近に入り込んでいた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed, Edo at that time was located in the west of the estuary of Sumida-gawa River which served as a provincial border between Musashi Province and Shimosa Province, and Hibiya cove stretched close to the place where the Edo Castle was constructed in later years.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed, Edo was established west of the Sumidagawa River estuary which served as a provincial border between Musashi Province and Shimosa Province, and Hibiya inlet stretched across the area where the Edo Castle was later constructed.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed, Edo was established west of the Sumidagawa River estuary which served as a provincial border between Musashi Province and Shimosa Province, and Hibiya inlet stretched across the area where the Edo Castle was later constructed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>江戸の開発は、平安時代後期に武蔵国の秩父地方から出て川越市から入間川 (埼玉県)（現荒川 (関東)）沿いに平野部へと進出してきた桓武平氏を称する秩父党の一族によって始められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The development of Edo was initiated in late Heian Period by a family of the Chichibu party, Kanmu-Heishi (the Taira clan), who entered flatlands from the Chichibu region of Musashi Province through Kawagoe City by advancing along Iruma-gawa River (present-day, Ara-kawa River in the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo was founded in the late Heian Period by a clan of the Chichibu party that claimed the name of Kanmu-Heishi (the Taira clan) who entered the plains along the Irumagawa River ((Saitama Prefecture) (Present-day Arakawa (Kanto)) from Kawagoe City from the Chichibu region of Musashi province.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; Diction (e.g., development--&gt; founded)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo was founded in the late Heian Period by a clan of the Chichibu party that claimed the name of Kanmu-Heishi (the Taira clan) who entered the plains along the Irumagawa River ((Saitama Prefecture) (Present-day Arakawa (Kanto)) from Kawagoe City from the Chichibu region of Musashi province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>11世紀に秩父氏から出た江戸重継は、江戸の桜田（のちの江戸城）の高台に居館を構え、江戸の地名をとって江戸太郎を称し、江戸氏を興す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 11th century, Shigetsugu of the Chichibu clan built his own residence (later, the Edo Castle) on the hill of Sakurada, and founded the EDO clan by renaming himself Taro EDO after the area name, Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the 11th century, Shigetsugu of the Chichibu clan built his own residence (later, the Edo Castle) on a hill overlooking Sakurada, and founded the EDO clan by renaming himself EDO Taro after the place name Edo.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the 11th century, Shigetsugu of the Chichibu clan built his own residence (later, the Edo Castle) on a hill overlooking Sakurada, and founded the EDO clan by renaming himself EDO Taro after the place name Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>重継の子である江戸重長は1180年に源頼朝が挙兵した時には、当初は伊勢平氏方として頼朝方の三浦氏と戦ったが、後に和解して鎌倉幕府の御家人となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo raised an army in 1180, Shigenaga EDO, the son of Shigetsugu, first took the side of Ise-Heishi (the Taira clan) and fought against the Miura clan of the Yoritomo side, but later switched sides to Yoritomo and became a gokenin (shogunal retainers) of Kamakura bakufu (headed by Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo raised an army in 1180, EDO Shigenaga, the son of Shigetsugu, initially fought against the Miura clan that was allied to Yoritomo as an ally of Ise-Heishi (Taira Clan), but later made peace with the Yoritomo and became a gokenin (shogunal retainers) of Kamakura bakufu (headed by Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When MINAMOTO no Yoritomo raised an army in 1180, EDO Shigenaga, the son of Shigetsugu, initially fought against the Miura clan that was allied to Yoritomo as an ally of Ise-Heishi (Taira Clan), but later made peace with the Yoritomo and became a gokenin (shogunal retainers) of Kamakura bakufu (headed by Yoritomo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>弘長元年10月3日 (旧暦)（1261年）、江戸氏の一族の一人であった地頭江戸長重が正嘉の飢饉による荒廃で経営ができなくなった江戸郷前島村（現在の東京駅周辺）を北条氏得宗家に寄進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to records, Nagashige EDO, who was a member of the Edo clan and held a post of jito (manager and lord of manor) donated to the Tokuso family of the HOJO clan the Maeshima Village of Edo-go (present-day, the area surrounding the Tokyo Station) in 1261, because the area was destroyed and went out of control by the Shoka Famine.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to historical records, EDO Nagashige, who was a member of the Edo clan and held the post of jito (manager and lord of manor) donated Maeshima Village of Edo-go (Area around present-day Tokyo Station) to the Tokuso family in 1261, because the area became ruined and unmanageable due to famine.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes, Name Order,</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to historical records, Nagashige EDO, who was a member of the Edo clan and held the post of jito (manager and lord of manor) donated Maeshima Village of Edo-go (Area around present-day Tokyo Station) to the Tokuso family in 1261, because the area became ruined and unmanageable due to famine.</e>
<cmt>EDO　NagashigeをNagashige EDOに修正島地亜。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>長重はその被官となり、1315年までに得宗家から円覚寺に再寄進されていることが記録として残されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nagashige became a retainer of the Tokuso family, and the land was again donated to Enkaku-ji Shrine by the family before 1315.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Historical records reveal that Nagashige became a retainer of the Tokuso family, and the land was again donated to Enkaku-ji Shrine by the family before 1315.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; Continuity with the previous sentence.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Historical records reveal that Nagashige became a retainer of the Tokuso family, and the land was again donated to Enkaku-ji Shrine by the family before 1315.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="21">
<j>鎌倉幕府が滅びると、江戸氏は南北朝時代 (日本)の騒乱において初め新田義貞に従って南朝 (日本)方につき、後に北朝 (日本)に帰順して鎌倉公方に仕えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Kamakura bakufu collapsed and the turmoil of the Northern and Southern Imperial Courts begun, the Edo clan first took the side of the Southern Court by following the order of Yoshisada NITTA, but later switched sides to the Northern Court and served Kamakura kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the collapse of the Kamakura bakufu and the ensuing turmoil of the Northern and Southern Court Period, the Edo clan initially allied itself to the Southern Court serving NITTA Yoshisada, but later changed allegiances to the Northern Court and served as the Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; Capitalizing Titles; Reversing Name Order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the collapse of the Kamakura bakufu and the ensuing turmoil of the Northern and Southern Court Period, the Edo clan initially allied itself to the Southern Court serving Yoshisada NITTA, but later changed allegiances to the Northern Court and served as the Kamakura Kubo (Governor-general of the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>NITTA YoshisadaをYoshisada NITTAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかし、室町時代に次第に衰え、本拠地を多摩郡喜多見（現在の東京都世田谷区喜多見）に移した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in the Muromachi Period, the power of the Edo clan waned, forcing the clan to relocate its base to Kitami of Tama County (present-day, Kitami, Setagaya Ward, Tokyo Metropolis).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the power of the EDO clan gradually waned throughout the Muromachi Period, prompting it to relocate to Kitami of Tama County (Present-day, Kitami, Setagaya Ward, Tokyo Metropolis).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the power of the EDO clan gradually waned throughout the Muromachi Period, prompting it to relocate to Kitami of Tama County (Present-day, Kitami, Setagaya Ward, Tokyo Metropolis).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="23">
<j>代わって江戸の地には、関東管領上杉氏の一族扇谷上杉家の有力な武将であり家老であった太田資長（のちの太田道灌）が入り、江戸氏の居館跡に江戸城を築く。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In place of the Edo clan, Sukenaga OTA (later, Dokan OTA), a powerful military commander and chief retainer of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan (a branch family of the Uesugi clan, Kanto Kanrei [shogunal deputy for the Kanto region]), entered Edo and built the Edo Castle based on the residence of the Edo clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">OTA Sukenaga (later, OTA Dokan), a powerful military commander and chief retainer of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan (a branch family of the Uesugi clan, Kanto Kanrei [shogunal deputy for the Kanto region]) entered Edo and built the Edo Castle over the site of the former residence of the Edo clan.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; switching name order; Spelling mistake in word bank</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sukenaga OTA (later, Dokan OTA), a powerful military commander and chief retainer of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan (a branch family of the Uesugi clan, Kanto Kanrei [shogunal deputy for the Kanto region]) entered Edo and built the Edo Castle over the site of the former residence of the Edo clan.</e>
<cmt>OTA　SukenagaをSukenaga　OTAに修正しました。OTA　DokanをDokan OTAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>江戸城は、一説には長禄2年（1456年）に建設を始め、翌年完成したという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to one theory, the construction of the Edo Castle started in 1456 and completed in the following year.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to one theory, the construction of the Edo Castle began in 1456 and was completed in the following year.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to one theory, the construction of the Edo Castle began in 1456 and was completed in the following year.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>太田資長は文明 (日本)10年（1478年）に剃髪し道灌と号し、文明18年（1486年）に謀殺されるまで江戸城を中心に南関東一円で活躍した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even after entering into priesthood in 1478 by shaving his head and calling himself Dokan, Sukenaga OTA served as a powerful lord throughout the southern Kanto region with placing its military base in the Edo Castle, until assassinated in 1486.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even after entering into priesthood in 1478 by shaving his head and calling himself Dokan, OTA Sukenaga ruled over the southern Kanto region from his base of power in the southern Kanto region until his assasination in 1486.</e>
<cmt>The original translation included details not included in the original. I am not quite sure how you can translate 活躍 as &quot;served as a powerful lord.&quot; Japanese reading for chronology is included.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even after entering into priesthood in 1478 by shaving his head and calling himself Dokan, Sukenaga OTA ruled over the southern Kanto region from his base of power in the southern Kanto region until his assasination in 1486.</e>
<cmt>OTA　SukenagaをSukenaga　OTAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>道灌の時代、現在の神田川 (東京都)並びに日本橋川の前身である平川（平河）は日比谷入江に流れ込んでおり、西に日比谷入江、東に江戸湊（但し『東京市史稿』は日比谷入江を江戸湊としている）がある江戸前島周辺は中世には、浅草や品川湊と並ぶ、武蔵国の代表的な湊であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Around this period of time, in Edo, Hira-kara River (present-day, Kanda-gawa River and Nihonbashi-gara River in Tokyo) poured into Hibiya cove, and the area which had Edo Maejima in the center, Hibiya cove in the west and Edo-minato Port in the east, served as an influential port of Musashi Province during the medieval period rivalling the ports of Asakusa and Shingawa. (however, in the &quot;Tokyoshi Shiko&quot;, Hibiya cove is identified as Edo-minato Port).</e>
<cmt>道灌の時代：省略しています。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the time of Dokan, the Hirakawa River (present-day, Kanda-gawa River and Nihonbashi-gara River in Tokyo) poured into Hibiya inlet, and the area around Edo Maejima east of the Hibiya cove and west of the Edo-minato Port served as an influential port of Musashi Province during the medieval period rivalling the ports of Asakusa and Shingawa (however, in the &quot;Tokyoshi Shiko&quot;, Hibiya inlet is identified as Edo-minato Port).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes (It makes stylistic sense to locate Edo Maeshima in relation to the two locations raised, rather than vice-versa.).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the time of Dokan, the Hirakawa River (present-day, Kanda-gawa River and Nihonbashi-gara River in Tokyo) poured into Hibiya inlet, and the area around Edo Maejima east of the Hibiya cove and west of the Edo-minato Port served as an influential port of Musashi Province during the medieval period rivalling the ports of Asakusa and Shingawa (however, in the &quot;Tokyoshi Shiko&quot;, Hibiya inlet is identified as Edo-minato Port).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>江戸や品川は利根川（現在の古利根川・中川）や荒川 (関東)などの河口に近く、北関東の内陸部から水運を用いて鎌倉・小田原城・西国方面に出る際の中継地点となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Edo and Shinagawa were located close to the estuaries of Ara-kara River and Tone-gawa River (present-day, Furutone-gawa River and Naka-gawa River), they served as a relay point for water transportation from inland areas of the North Kanto region to places such as Kamakura, the Odawara Castle and to as far as the western part of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to their proximity to the Ara-kara River and Tone-gawa River (present-day, Furutone-gawa River and Naka-gawa River) estuaries, the ports of Edo and Shinagawa served as important hubs for riverine transportation from inland areas of the northern Kanto to places such as Kamakura and Odawara Castle, and locations as far as western parts of Japan.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to their proximity to the Ara-kara River and Tone-gawa River (present-day, Furutone-gawa River and Naka-gawa River) estuaries, the ports of Edo and Shinagawa served as important hubs for riverine transportation from inland areas of the northern Kanto to places such as Kamakura and Odawara Castle, and locations as far as western parts of Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="28">
<j>道灌の死後、扇谷上杉氏の衰亡と共に、江戸城は後北条氏の支城となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Dokan and the collapse of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan, the Edo Castle was taken over by the Gohojo clan and used as its subsidiary castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Dokan and the collapse of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan, the Edo Castle was taken over by the Gohojo clan and used as its subsidiary castle.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Dokan and the collapse of the Ogigayatsu-Uesugi clan, the Edo Castle was taken over by the Gohojo clan and used as its subsidiary castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>後北条氏末期には北条氏政が直接支配して太田氏や千葉氏を統率していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the later years of the Gohojo clan, Ujimasa HOJO seized a direct control over the Castle and lead the Ota clan and the Chiba clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the later years of the Gohojo clan, HOJO Ujimasa seized direct control over the castle and led the Ota clan and the Chiba clan.</e>
<cmt>spelling error; unneccessary particles; unnecessary capitals; name order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the later years of the Gohojo clan, HOJO Ujimasa seized direct control over the castle and led the Ota clan and the Chiba clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>徳川時代の江戸</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo during the Tokugawa Period</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo during the Tokugawa Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo during the Tokugawa Period</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>一介の地方の城下町から巨大都市への大改造を実現した人物は、徳川家康であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who transformed a local castle town into a huge metropolis.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was TOKUGAWA Ieyasu who transformed a regional castle town into a huge metropolis.</e>
<cmt>elision in original translation;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was Ieyasu TOKUGAWA who transformed a regional castle town into a huge metropolis.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA IeyasuをIeyasu　TOKUGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>1590年、後北条氏が小田原の役で豊臣秀吉に滅ぼされると、後北条氏の旧領に封ぜられ、開拓の命を受けた徳川家康は、関東地方の中心となるべき居城を江戸に定めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1590, when the Gohojo clan was destroyed by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in the Siege of Odawara, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who was assigned to oversee the territory of the Gohojo clan and to reclaim lands, designated Edo as where he would reside to oversea the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the destruction of the Gohojo clan by TOYOTOMI Hideyoshi in the Siege of Odawara (1590), TOKUGAWA Ieyasu, who was assigned to govern and develop former Gohojo territories designated Edo as the central place in the Kanto region from where he would govern.</e>
<cmt>Name order; stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the destruction of the Gohojo clan by Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI in the Siege of Odawara (1590), TOKUGAWA Ieyasu, who was assigned to govern and develop former Gohojo territories designated Edo as the central place in the Kanto region from where he would govern.</e>
<cmt>Hideyoshi　TOYOTOMIに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="32">
<j>同年の旧暦8月1日 (旧暦)（八朔）、家康は駿府から居を移すが、当時の江戸城は老朽化した粗末な城であったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Ieyasu moved into the Edo Castle from Sunpu, but it is believed that the Edo Castle at that time was an aging, humble castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the very same year, Ieyasu moved from Sunpu and took residence in Edo Castle, but it is said that Edo Castle was then an aging and humble castle.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the very same year, Ieyasu moved from Sunpu and took residence in Edo Castle, but it is said that Edo Castle was then an aging and humble castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>家康は江戸城本城の拡張は一定程度に留める代わりに城下町の建設を進め、神田山を削り、日比谷入江を盛んに埋め立てて町を広げ、家臣と町民の家屋敷を配置した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Instead of extending the main enclosure of the Castle more than necessary, Ieyasu promoted the construction of the Edo castle town by digging Mt. Kado and redeeming Hibiya cove to expand the area, and houses and residences were also built for his vassals and townspeople.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ieyasu prioritized the construction of the surrounding castletown over the expansion of the main castle enclosure by levelling Mt. Kado and reclaiming the Hibiya inlet to expand the habitable areas and build residences for vassals and townspeople.</e>
<cmt>diction; stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ieyasu prioritized the construction of the surrounding castletown over the expansion of the main castle enclosure by levelling Mt. Kado and reclaiming the Hibiya inlet to expand the habitable areas and build residences for vassals and townspeople.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>突貫工事であったために、埋め立て当初は地面が固まっておらず、乾燥して風が吹くと、もの凄い埃が舞い上がるという有様だったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that due to the rushed construction, the redeemed area was not firm even after the completion of the work, and when a wind blew, a massive amount of dust was flying into the air.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that the earth of the newly reclaimed land had not yet hardened due to the rushed nature of the reclamation project, and massive plumes of dust were blown into the air even after the earth had dried.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that the earth of the newly reclaimed land had not yet hardened due to the rushed nature of the reclamation project, and massive plumes of dust were blown into the air even after the earth had dried.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>この時期の江戸城はこれまでの本丸・二ノ丸に、西丸・三ノ丸・吹上・北ノ丸があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo Castle in this period had not only Honmaru (a main enclosure) and Ninomaru (second bailey), but also the extended wings including Nishinomaru (west compartment), Sannomaru (third bailey), Fukiage and Kitanomaru (north compartment).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処吹上：具体的な内容が分からないため、説明していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo Castle in this period constituted a central Honmaru (a main enclosure) and Ninomaru (second bailey), as well as the extensions that included Nishinomaru (west compartment), Sannomaru (third bailey), Fukiage and Kitanomaru (north compartment).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo Castle in this period constituted a central Honmaru (a main enclosure) and Ninomaru (second bailey), as well as the extensions that included Nishinomaru (west compartment), Sannomaru (third bailey), Fukiage and Kitanomaru (north compartment).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>また道三掘や平川の江戸前島中央部への移設、それに伴う埋め立てにより、現在の西丸下の半分以上が埋め立られている（この時期の本城といえるのはこの内、本丸・二ノ丸と家康の隠居所として造られた西丸である）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as Dosan Moat and Hira-kawa River were moved to the central area of Edo Maejima, followed by the landfill of the Moat and River, more than half of the current Nishinomaru-shimo area was a redeemed area (during this period, the main enclosure indicated Honmaru, Ninomaru, and Nishinomaru [a retreat for Ieyasu]).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the diversion of the Dosan Moat and Hira-kawa River to the central area of Edo Maejima, and the concurrent reclamation project led to the reclamation of more than half of present-day Nishinomaru-shimo area (During this period, the main castle enclosure included Honmaru, Ninomaru, and Nishinomaru [a retreat for Ieyasu]).</e>
<cmt>Diction (The rerouting of rivers and moats are referred to as diversions)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the diversion of the Dosan Moat and Hira-kawa River to the central area of Edo Maejima, and the concurrent reclamation project led to the reclamation of more than half of present-day Nishinomaru-shimo area (During this period, the main castle enclosure included Honmaru, Ninomaru, and Nishinomaru [a retreat for Ieyasu]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="37">
<j>家康が1600年の関ヶ原の戦いに勝利して天下人となり、1603年に征夷大将軍に任ぜられると、幕府の所在地として江戸の政治的重要性は一気に高まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After Ieyasu won the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600 to become a ruler of the country and was appointed as Seii taishogun in 1603, Edo where Ieyasu had resided was turned into a place with a political significance, because the feudal government was established there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo rose in political prominence when it became the seat of the Bakufu government when Ieyasu &apos;s became the ruler of Japan after his victory in the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and was annointed &quot;Seii taishogun&quot; in 1603.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo rose in political prominence when it became the seat of the Bakufu government when Ieyasu &apos;s became the ruler of Japan after his victory in the Battle of Sekigahara in 1600, and was annointed &quot;Seii taishogun&quot; in 1603.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>また、徳川家に服する諸大名の屋敷が設けられ、江戸に居住する大名の家臣・家族や、徳川氏の旗本・御家人近世の御家人などの武士が数多く居住するようになるとともに、彼らの生活を支える商人・職人が流入し、町が急速に拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, residences of many daimyo (feudal lords serving the Tokugawa family) were built, and a large number of daimyo&apos;s vassals and families, and shogunal bannermen and retainers moved in, followed by the influx of merchants and craftsmen who supported the lives of those people, all of which contributed to the rapid expansion of the town.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, residences of many daimyo (feudal lords serving the Tokugawa family) were built, and a large number of daimyo&apos;s vassals and families, and shogunal bannermen and retainers moved in, followed by the influx of merchants and craftsmen who supported the lives of those people, all of which contributed to the rapid expansion of the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, residences of many daimyo (feudal lords serving the Tokugawa family) were built, and a large number of daimyo&apos;s vassals and families, and shogunal bannermen and retainers moved in, followed by the influx of merchants and craftsmen who supported the lives of those people, all of which contributed to the rapid expansion of the town.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="39">
<j>一方、江戸城とその堀が幕府から大名に課せられた普請によって整備され、江戸城は巨大な堅城に生まれ変わり、城と武家屋敷を取り巻く広大な惣構が構築された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Edo Castle and its moats were renovated by daimyo who was assigned to labor service by the government, and the Castle was reborn as a massive, strong fortress, and expansive defensive structures were constructed to encompass the castle and samurai residences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the Edo Castle and its moats were renovated by daimyo who were consigned to labor by the government, and the castle was reborn as a massive, hardened citadel, and big defense facilities were also constructed in a way to surround the Castle and samurai residences.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the Edo Castle and its moats were renovated by daimyo who were consigned to labor by the government, and the castle was reborn as a massive, hardened citadel, and big defense facilities were also constructed in a way to surround the Castle and samurai residences.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>都市開発の歴史については後の都市の章で述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Please see the chapter of &apos;Metropolis&apos; for urban development.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Please see the section on &apos;Metropolis&apos; for the history of urban development.</e>
<cmt>&quot;Chapter&quot;--&gt; &quot;Section&quot; because the text may not necessarily be printed in a book</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Please see the section on &apos;Metropolis&apos; for the history of urban development.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="41">
<j>1657年の明暦の大火の後、再建事業によって市域は隅田川を超え、東へと拡大した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657, reconstruction work started and the city was again expanded eastward over Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the reconstruction of the city after the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657, the city expanded east of the Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the reconstruction of the city after the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657, the city expanded east of the Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>その人口は絶えず拡大を続け、18世紀初頭には人口が百万人を超え、八百八町といわれる世界有数（一説によると当時世界一）の大都市へと発展を遂げた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While the population of the town was continuously increasing, as of the beginning of the 18th century, it exceeded one million and the city became one of the biggest international metropolises with 808 towns (according to one estimate, it was the biggest in the world).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population continued to increase, and exceeded one million at the beginning of the eighteenth century, and became known as a city of a &quot;eight-hundred-and-eight-towns&quot; (metaphor for an infinite towns)- one of the world&apos;s great metropolises (By some estimates, it was the most populous metropolis in the world.).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population continued to increase, and exceeded one million at the beginning of the eighteenth century, and became known as a city of a &quot;eight-hundred-and-eight-towns&quot; (metaphor for an infinite towns)- one of the world&apos;s great metropolises (By some estimates, it was the most populous metropolis in the world.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>人口の増大は、江戸を東日本における大消費地とし、東日本各地の農村と結ばれた大市場、経済的先進地方である上方（近畿地方）と関東地方を結ぶ中継市場として、経済的な重要性も増した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population increase in Edo turned the area into the biggest consuming city in eastern Japan, and Edo played a part as a relay point to link between the Kanto region, consuming area, and Kamigata (Kinki region), a big market place with connection to farming villages throughout Japan and also an economically advanced region, which helped to lift the economical stature of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population growth in Edo turned the city into the consumption center of eastern japan, and faciliated its rise to economic prominence as a significant market that linked the farming villages of various regions of eastern Japan, and a hub market that linked the economically advanced Kamigata (Kinki region) and Kanto regions.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population growth in Edo turned the city into the consumption center of eastern japan, and faciliated its rise to economic prominence as a significant market that linked the farming villages of various regions of eastern Japan, and a hub market that linked the economically advanced Kamigata (Kinki region) and Kanto regions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>当時の江戸は、『東都歳時記』、『富嶽三十六景』の「東本願寺 (東京都台東区)」など、漢風に「東都」とも呼ばれる大都市となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo in this period was regarded as a huge city at home and abroad and called &apos;Toto&apos; (literally, eastern capital) in Chinese style, as described in &quot;Toto Saijiki&quot; (Customs of the Eastern Capital) and &apos;Higashi Hongan-ji Temple (Taito Ward, Tokyo)&apos; of &quot;Fugaku Sanju Rokkei&quot; (Thirty-six views of Mount Fuji).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this time Edo had grown into a large metropolis was referred to in Chinese-style as &apos;Toto&apos; (literally, Eastern Capital) as described in &quot;Toto Saijiki&quot; (Customs of the Eastern Capital) and &apos;Higashi Hongan-ji Temple (Taito Ward, Tokyo)&apos; of &quot;Fugaku Sanju Rokkei&quot; (Thirty-six views of Mount Fuji).</e>
<cmt>;Stylistic Changes; Spelling Changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this time Edo had grown into a large metropolis was referred to in Chinese-style as &apos;Toto&apos; (literally, Eastern Capital) as described in &quot;Toto Saijiki&quot; (Customs of the Eastern Capital) and &apos;Higashi Hongan-ji Temple (Taito Ward, Tokyo)&apos; of &quot;Fugaku Sanju Rokkei&quot; (Thirty-six views of Mount Fuji).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="45">
<j>18世紀末から19世紀初めには、上方にかわる文化的な中心地ともなり、経済活動や参勤交代を通じた江戸を中心とする人の往来は江戸から地方へ、地方から江戸へ盛んな文化の伝播をもたらした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From the end of the 18th century through the beginning of the 19th century, Edo was developed into a cultural center, replacing Kamigata, and traffic of people into and from Edo for economic activities and Sankinkotai (a system for feudal lords to live in Edo every other year) brought a lot of local cultures to Edo and vice versa.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From the end of the 18th century through the beginning of the 19th century, Edo surpassed Kamigata (This is a commonly used term referring to Kyoto and the Kansai region) as a cultural center, and the active traffic of people between Edo and the provinces due to economic activities and the sankinkotai (a system that required feudal lords to reside in Edo every other year) facilitated the active transmission of culture between Edo and the provinces.</e>
<cmt>&quot;上方&quot; should not be translated alone as &quot;kamigata&quot;-- there should be additional information included in the parenthesis; unnecessary capitals; Please check to see if sankin kotai required feudal lords to live Edo every other years, because I believe it was every three years.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From the end of the 18th century through the beginning of the 19th century, Edo surpassed Kamigata (This is a commonly used term referring to Kyoto and the Kansai region) as a cultural center, and the active traffic of people between Edo and the provinces due to economic activities and the sankinkotai (a system that required feudal lords to reside in Edo every other year) facilitated the active transmission of culture between Edo and the provinces.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>一方で、膨大な人口が農村から江戸に流入して、様々な都市問題を引き起こすことにもなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, however, the mass-migration of people from farming villages to Edo caused various urban problems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, a massive influx of migrants from rural farming villages to Edo caused various urban problems.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, a massive influx of migrants from rural farming villages to Edo caused various urban problems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>江戸の人口と識字率</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population and literacy rate of Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population and literacy rate in Edo</e>
<cmt>grammar correction.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population and literacy rate in Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="47">
<j>ロドリゴ・デ・ビベロによって1609年ごろに15万人と伝えられた江戸の人口は、18世紀初頭には100万人を超え、世界一ないしはそれに匹敵する規模であったと推定されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is estimated that after Rodrigo de Vivero reported Edo&apos;s population as 150,000 around 1609, it exceeded one million at the beginning of the 18th century and Edo became the biggest or an equivalent-sized city in the world.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population of Edo, which was reported by Rodrigo de Viveroto be around one-hundred-fifty-thousand in 1609, exceeded the one million mark at the turn of the eighteenth century--prompting many to presume that Edo had become one of the biggest if not the biggest city in the world.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; population offered in arabic numerals retranslated in English to ensure consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population of Edo, which was reported by Rodrigo de Viveroto be around one-hundred-fifty-thousand in 1609, exceeded the one million mark at the turn of the eighteenth century--prompting many to presume that Edo had become one of the biggest if not the biggest city in the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>成人男性の識字率も幕末には70%を超え、同時期のロンドン（20%）、パリ（10%未満）を遥かに凌ぎ、ロシア人革命家メーチニコフや、トロイア遺跡を発見したドイツ人のハインリッヒ・シュリーマンらが、驚きを以って書いている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The literacy rate of adult males living in Edo exceeded 70 per cent at the end of Edo Period, by far higher than those of London (20%) and Paris (below 10%), which a Russian revolutionist, Ilya Ilyich Mechnikov, and a German archaeologist, Heinrich Julius Schliemann who discovered Trojan Ruins, reported with astonishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The literacy rate of adult males living in Edo exceeded seventy per cent by the end of Edo Period, far higher than those of London (20%) and Paris (below 10%), which a Russian revolutionist, Ilya Ilyich Mechnikov, and German archaeologist, Heinrich Julius Schliemann who discovered Trojan Ruins, reported with astonishment.</e>
<cmt>Comparing the literacy rates between Edo and contemporary European cities is fine, but I don&apos;t see the relevance of the rest.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The literacy rate of adult males living in Edo exceeded seventy per cent by the end of Edo Period, far higher than those of London (20%) and Paris (below 10%), which a Russian revolutionist, Ilya Ilyich Mechnikov, and German archaeologist, Heinrich Julius Schliemann who discovered Trojan Ruins, reported with astonishment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>また、武家だけではなく農民も和歌を嗜んだと言われており、その背景には寺子屋の普及があったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also said that not only samurai but also peasants could write waka (Japanese poetry), and it is considered that popularized terakoya private schools greatly contributed to the high literacy rate of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also said that waka (Japanese poetry) was not only cherished by samura, but also peasants- it is considered that this is a result of the popularization of terakoya (elementary education offered in temples).</e>
<cmt>Initial translation significantly differs from the original--and includes additional information of the first translator; 嗜んだ=cherished; I object to the characterization of &quot;terakoya&quot; as &quot;private schools&quot; since many were established for the purpose of making education available to those children whose families could not have otherwise afforded education.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also said that waka (Japanese poetry) was not only cherished by samura, but also peasants- it is considered that this is a result of the popularization of terakoya (elementary education offered in temples).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>その様に世界的に見れば極めて高い水準であると言うことができる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is safe to say that compared to other parts of the world, Edo&apos;s literacy rate was very high.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this manner, one can say that the literacy rate in Edo was significantly high vis-à-vis the rest of the world.</e>
<cmt>The term 極めて is mistranslated as &quot;kime,&quot; when it should be &quot;kiwamete&quot;-- a word that denoting the extremity of adjectives that follows it.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this manner, one can say that the literacy rate in Edo was significantly high vis-à-vis the rest of the world.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="51">
<j>ただ、人口に関しては、記録に残っているのは幕末に60万人近くとなった町人人口のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for population, extant records only tell the number of townspeople; it was around 0.6 million at the end of the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, as for population, extant records only reveal the number of townspeople, which was close to six-hundred thousand in the waning days of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; numerals speleed out in English.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, as for population, extant records only reveal the number of townspeople, which was close to six-hundred thousand in the waning days of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="52">
<j>人口100万人とは、幕府による調査が行われていない武家や神官・僧侶などの寺社方、被差別階級などの統計で除外された人口を加えた推計値である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;One million people&quot; is no more than a total estimated figure which included demographics not targeted in the population census, such as samurai households, Jisha-gata (those working for shrines and temples including Shinto priests and Buddhist monks), and discriminated classes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;One million people&quot; is an approximate figure based on the retroactive inclusion of several elements of society such as the samurai households, Jisha-gata (those working for shrines and temples including Shinto priests and Buddhist monks), and ostracized castes who were not included in the original population census.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; I think the term &quot;discriminated class&quot; is in correct, although the translation itself is correct, I think ostracized caste is more appropriate.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;One million people&quot; is an approximate figure based on the retroactive inclusion of several elements of society such as the samurai households, Jisha-gata (those working for shrines and temples including Shinto priests and Buddhist monks), and ostracized castes who were not included in the original population census.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="53">
<j>武士の人口は、参勤交代に伴う地方からの単身赴任者など、流動的な部分が非常に多く、その推定は20万人程度から100万人程度までとかなりの幅があり、最盛期の江戸の総人口も68万人から150万人まで様々な推定値が出されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the estimated population of the samurai class ranges from 0.2 million to 1 million as it was very fluid due to the Sankinkotai system, which ordered provincial samurai to live in Edo every other year, and the total estimated population at the peak of the Edo Period also varies, ranging between 0.68 million and 1.5 million.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Estimates for the samurai residing in Edo vastly ranges between two-hundred thousand and one million due to many fluctuating factors such as the unaccompanied assignments of regional samura in accordance to the requirements of the Sankinkotai system, and the total population for Edo during its apex has ranged from 680,000 to 1.5 million.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Estimates for the samurai residing in Edo vastly ranges between two-hundred thousand and one million due to many fluctuating factors such as the unaccompanied assignments of regional samura in accordance to the requirements of the Sankinkotai system, and the total population for Edo during its apex has ranged from 680,000 to 1.5 million.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>雑記等に記される同時代人の推定も50万人から200万人まで幅がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &apos;Miscellaneous notes&apos;, the total estimated population of the same period also ranges from 0.5 million to 2 million.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Estimates of the population offered by miscellaneous documents of contemporaries also vary widely between five-hundred-thousand and two million.</e>
<cmt>According to &apos;Miscellaneous notes&apos;, the total estimated population of the same period also ranges from 0.5 million to 2 million.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Estimates of the population offered by miscellaneous documents of contemporaries also vary widely between five-hundred-thousand and two million.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="55">
<j>町奉行支配下の町方・寺社方町人人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population of townspeople (Machi-gata and Jishsa-gata) living in the area ruled by machi-bugyo (the town magistrate&apos;s office)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population of townspeople and clerical personnel (Machi-gata and Jisha-gata) residing in areas administered by the machi-bugyo (the town magistrate&apos;s office).</e>
<cmt>Spelling errors; elision in translation; stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population of townspeople and clerical personnel (Machi-gata and Jisha-gata) residing in areas administered by the machi-bugyo (the town magistrate&apos;s office).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="56">
<j>江戸の国勢調査の最古の記録は、『正宝事録』の註釈として記された元禄六年（1693年）六月十七日の35万3588人であり、徳川綱吉が浮説雑説を唱えた者を探すために行われたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the annotation of &quot;Shoho Jiroku&quot;, the oldest record of a census of Edo, the population of Edo on June 17, 1693 was 353,588, and the census was conducted by Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to crack down on people who spoke of rumors and tales about the government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The earliest extant record of a census conducted in Edo surivives in an annotation in the &quot;Shoho Jiroku,&quot; (Chronicles of the Shoho Era) which indicates that there were 353,588 people in Edo as of June 17th, 1693 (6th year of Genroku), and it is also said that this was ordered by TOKUGAWA Tsunayoshi to root out demagogues.</e>
<cmt>According to the annotation of &quot;Shoho Jiroku,&quot; the oldest record of a census of Edo in June 17th, 1693 indicated that the population was 353,588, and that the census was conducted by TOKUGAWA Tsunayoshi to crack down on people who rumoured or spoke ill of the government.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The earliest extant record of a census conducted in Edo surivives in an annotation in the &quot;Shoho Jiroku,&quot; (Chronicles of the Shoho Era) which indicates that there were 353,588 people in Edo as of June 17th, 1693 (6th year of Genroku), and it is also said that this was ordered by Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA to root out demagogues.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA TsunayoshiをTsunayoshi　TOKUGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="57">
<j>しかし、実際に人口調査の体裁が整えられてたのは、徳川吉宗によって子午改（6年毎）の全国人口調査が開始された享保六年（1721年）以降であり、大岡忠相から有馬氏倫へ提出した書類の形式で伝えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the official format of a population census was established by Yoshimune TOKUGAWA in 1721 or later for a census to be conducted every six year, and the census records were presented in the form of documentation by Tadasuke OOKA to Ujinori ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the census system was only formally put into place after hexannual national census surveys were implemented by TOKUGAWA Yoshimune in 1721 (year) and formalized in the document presented by Ooka Tadasuke to ARIMA ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic issues; change in name order.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the census system was only formally put into place after hexannual national census surveys were implemented by Yoshimune TOKUGAWA in 1721 (year) and formalized in the document presented by Tadasuke OOKA to Ujinori ARIMA.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA　YoshimuneをYoshimune　TOKUGAWAに修正しました。ARIMA　ARIMAをUjinori ARIMAに修正しました。Ooka TadasukeをTadasuke OOKAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>徳川吉宗は享保八年（1723年）九月から享保九年（1724年）四月の間の9263人の急激な人口減少、享保十年（1725年）四月から六月の間の1万0394人の急激な人口増加に気付き、季節的な人口変動の理由を調べさせた結果、冬の火災の多さから特に子女は近隣実家等へ疎開する、春以降火災からの復興再建や土蔵の建築が増えて労働転入者も増える、などといった実態が判明している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As gathering the information on population, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA noticed a sharp decline by 9,263 from September of 1723 to April of 1724 and also a surge by 10,394 from April of 1725 to June, the same year, and ordered to investigate the cause of this rapid seasonal population change, and found out that frequent fires in winter drove women and children evacuated to neighboring towns or their birthplace and reconstruction works after fires and increased building works of dozo (earthen storehouse) after spring brought in workers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In gathering demographic information, TOKUGAWA Yoshimune noticed a sharp population decline of 9,263 persons between September 1723 to April 1724 and a population surge of 10,394 persons between April and June 1725; After ordering an investigation into the seasonal fluctuations in population, it was discovered that frequent fires in winter prompted women and children to take shelter in neighboring towns and parental residences, and reconstruction work and the construction of dozo (earthen storehouse) from spring brought in an influx of workers.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In gathering demographic information, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA noticed a sharp population decline of 9,263 persons between September 1723 to April 1724 and a population surge of 10,394 persons between April and June 1725; After ordering an investigation into the seasonal fluctuations in population, it was discovered that frequent fires in winter prompted women and children to take shelter in neighboring towns and parental residences, and reconstruction work and the construction of dozo (earthen storehouse) from spring brought in an influx of workers.</e>
<cmt>TOKUGAWA　YoshimuneをYoshimune　TOKUGAWAに修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="59">
<j>以下公文書の他、複数の史料に記録として残っている江戸府内の町人の人口を男女別構成とともにまとめる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the following chart, the populations of townspeople residing in Edo-fu are posted by sex, based on the records in official documents and other historical materials.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The populations of townspeople residing in Edo prefecture, which have been compiled in the following official document in additional to several other historical documents, have been compiled by sex.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The populations of townspeople residing in Edo prefecture, which have been compiled in the following official document in additional to several other historical documents, have been compiled by sex.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>江戸の範囲は随時変わっており、寺社門前地が正式に御所内に組み込まれたのは1745年以降であり、朱引・墨引という呼称ができたのは1818年以降である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The official border of Edo changed frequently and it was not until 1745 or later that Jisha-Monzenchi (lands in front of gates of temples and shrines) were officially incorporated into the Imperial Palace, and also not until 1818 or later that the words of &apos;Shubiki&apos; (drawing a border of Edo-fu in red) and &apos;Sumibiki&apos; (drawing a border of the area ruled by the town magistrate&apos;s office in black) were coined.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The official borders of Edo changed frequently, and it was not until after 1745 that Jisha-Monzenchi (lands in fron to of temples and shrines) were officially incorporated into the Imperial Palace, and it was also not until 1818 that the terms &apos;Shubiki&apos; (drawing a border of Edo-fu in red) and &apos;Sumibiki&apos; (drawing a border of the area ruled by the town magistrate&apos;s office in black) were coined.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The official borders of Edo changed frequently, and it was not until after 1745 that Jisha-Monzenchi (lands in fron to of temples and shrines) were officially incorporated into the Imperial Palace, and it was also not until 1818 that the terms &apos;Shubiki&apos; (drawing a border of Edo-fu in red) and &apos;Sumibiki&apos; (drawing a border of the area ruled by the town magistrate&apos;s office in black) were coined.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>また安政元年以降は新吉原・品川・三軒地糸割符猿屋町会所を含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first year of the Ansei era, Shin-yoshiwara, Shinagawa and Sankenchi itowappu Saruya-cho kaisho were also incorporated into Edo.</e>
<cmt>三軒地糸割符猿屋町会所：意味が不明瞭のため、訳出していません。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first year of the Ansei era, Shin-yoshiwara, Shinagawa, and Sankenchi itowappu Saruya-cho kaisho were incorporated into Edo.</e>
<cmt>Minor stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first year of the Ansei era, Shin-yoshiwara, Shinagawa, and Sankenchi itowappu Saruya-cho kaisho were incorporated into Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>明治二年(1869年)四月に施行された江戸市街調査によると江戸は町地269万6千坪(8.91 km2, 15.8%)、寺社地266万1千坪 (8.80 km2, 15.6%)、武家地1169万2千坪(38.65 km2, 68.6%)より構成されていたが、この内武家地の人口は江戸時代を通じて調査より除外された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to the urban survey conducted in April 1869, Edo was comprised of 15.8% of lands for ordinary town use (8.91 km2), 15.6% of those for temples and shrines (8.80 km2) and 68.6% of those for samurai households (38.65 km2), but populations living in the lands for samurai households were never surveyed throughout the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A municipal survey conducted in April 1869, revealed that land usage in Edo comprised 15.8% of lands for ordinary town use (8.91 km2), 15.6% of those for temples and shrines (8.80 km2) and 68.6% of those for samurai households (38.65 km2), but populations living in the lands for samurai households were not included in the census throughout the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A municipal survey conducted in April 1869, revealed that land usage in Edo comprised 15.8% of lands for ordinary town use (8.91 km2), 15.6% of those for temples and shrines (8.80 km2) and 68.6% of those for samurai households (38.65 km2), but populations living in the lands for samurai households were not included in the census throughout the Edo Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="63">
<j>公文書の形式で残っているもの（重宝録、享保撰要類集、町奉行支配惣町人人数高之改、天保撰要類集、市中取締類集）以外は信頼度が低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population figures, unless recorded in official documents such as Choho-roku, Kyoho senyoruishu, 町奉行支配惣町人人数高之改, Tenpo senyoruishu and Shichu Torishimari ruishu, are not reliable.</e>
<cmt>重宝録、享保撰要類集、町奉行支配惣町人人数高之改、天保撰要類集、市中取締類集：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population figures, unless recorded in official documents such as Choho-roku, Kyoho senyoruishu, Machibugyo Shihaiso chonin ninsukonokai, Tenpo senyoruishu and Shichu Torishimari ruishu, are unreliable.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population figures, unless recorded in official documents such as Choho-roku, Kyoho senyoruishu, Machibugyo Shihaiso chonin ninsukonokai, Tenpo senyoruishu and Shichu Torishimari ruishu, are unreliable.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>出典のうち『江戸会雑誌』や勝海舟の『吹塵録』、『江戸旧事考』、『統計学雑誌』などは明治時代中ごろにまとめられた二次的史料であり、元となる江戸時代の史料が現在では不明となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sources such as &quot;Edo-kai zasshi&quot;, &quot;Suijinroku&quot; of Kaishu KATSU, &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; and &quot;Tokeigaku zasshi&quot; were secondary historical materials, as they were compiled in the middle of the Meiji Period, and the historical sources written in the Edo Period on which these documents were based are unaccounted for at present.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sources such as &quot;Edo-kai zasshi&quot;, &quot;Suijinroku&quot; of Kaishu KATSU, &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; and &quot;Tokeigaku zasshi&quot; are secondary materials materials compiled in the mid-Meiji Period, and the primary documents on which these secondary sources are are based have not been accounted for.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sources such as &quot;Edo-kai zasshi&quot;, &quot;Suijinroku&quot; of Kaishu KATSU, &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; and &quot;Tokeigaku zasshi&quot; are secondary materials materials compiled in the mid-Meiji Period, and the primary documents on which these secondary sources are are based have not been accounted for.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>斜体で示した数字は (1) 他の年月に酷似した数字が登場しており、共に誤記が疑われるケース (2) 元の史料の人口に対して寺社方人口や新吉原などの計外人口を独自に加算したと推測されるケースのいずれかであり、信頼性が低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The figures in italic face are not reliable either because 1. writing errors are suspected as similar numbers frequently appear over different months, or 2. it is highly likely that populations of Shaji-kata and those living in Shin-yoshiwara are added to official figures in later times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The figures in italics are of questionable accuracy because (1) the recurrence of similar figures over several months points to the likelihood of entry errors; and (2) there are several cases in which the populations of Shaji-kata and Shin-yoshiwara that were not included in the original estimates were retroactively added to the figures in later times.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The figures in italics are of questionable accuracy because (1) the recurrence of similar figures over several months points to the likelihood of entry errors; and (2) there are several cases in which the populations of Shaji-kata and Shin-yoshiwara that were not included in the original estimates were retroactively added to the figures in later times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="66">
<j>女2万9438人)を含む)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">including women of 29,438.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This includes 29,438 women.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This includes 29,438 women.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="67">
<j>（大田南畝 「寛政十年戊午江戸人別」 『一話一言』 巻26 (1820年) 山下重民 「江戸市街統計一班」 『江戸会雑誌』 1冊（2号） pp. 18–26（1889年） 勝海舟 「江戸人口小記」「正徳ヨリ弘化迄江戸町数人口戸数」 『吹塵録』（1890年） 小宮山綏介 「府内の人口」 『江戸旧事考』 2巻 pp. 19–23（1891年） 『日本財政経済史料』 9巻 pp. 1210–1243（1922年） 柚木重三、堀江保蔵 「本邦人口表」 『経済史研究』 7号 pp. 188–210（1930年） 幸田成友 「江戸の町人の人口」 『社会経済学会誌』 8巻（1号） pp. 1–23（1938年） 鷹見安二郎 江戸の人口の研究」 『全国都市問題会議』 第7回1（本邦都市発達の動向と其の諸問題上） pp. 59–83（1940年） 高橋梵仙 『日本人口史之研究』 三友社（1941年） 関山直太郎 『近世日本の人口構造』 吉川弘文館（1958年） 南和男『幕末江戸社会の研究』 吉川弘文館（1978年）より作成。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sources: Nanbo OTA, &apos;Kansei 10 nen, Bogo, Edonin betsu&apos; from vol. 26 of &quot;Ichiwa Ichigen&quot; (1820); Shigetami YAMASHITA, &apos;Edo shigai Tokei Ippan&apos; from vol.1 (pp. 18-26) of &quot;Edokai zasshi&quot; (1889); Kaishu KATSU, &apos;Edo Jinko Shoki&apos; from &quot;Suijinroku&quot; (1890); Yasusuke KOMIYAMA, &apos;Funai no Jinko&apos; from vol. 2 (pp. 19–23) of &quot;Edo kyujiko&quot; (1891) and vol. 9 (pp. 1210–1243) of &quot;Nihon Zaise Keizai Shiryo&quot; (1922); Juzo YUZUKI and Yasuzo HORIE, &apos;Honpo jinko hyo&apos; from vol. 7 (pp. 188–210) of &quot;Keizaishi Kenkyu&quot; (1930); Shigetomo KODA, &apos;Edo no Chonin no Jinko&apos; from vol. 8 (pp. 1–23) of &quot;Shakai Keizai gakkaishi&quot; (1938); Yasujiro TAKAMI, &apos;Edo no Jinko no Kenkyu&apos; from the 7th conference (pp. 59–83) of &quot;Zenkoku Toshi Mondai kaigi&quot; (1940); Bonsen TAKAHASHI, &quot;Nihon Jinkoshi no Kenkyu&quot; from Sanyusha publishing (1941), Naotaro SEKIYAMA, &quot;Kinsei Nihon no Jinko Kozo&quot; published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. (1958); Kazuo MINAMI, &quot;Bakumatsu Edo Shakai no Kenkyu&quot; published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. (1978).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sources: Nanbo OTA, &apos;Kansei 10 nen, Bogo, Edonin betsu&apos; from vol. 26 of &quot;Ichiwa Ichigen&quot; (1820); Shigetami YAMASHITA, &apos;Edo shigai Tokei Ippan&apos; from vol.1 (pp. 18-26) of &quot;Edokai zasshi&quot; (1889); Kaishu KATSU, &apos;Edo Jinko Shoki&apos; from &quot;Suijinroku&quot; (1890); Yasusuke KOMIYAMA, &apos;Funai no Jinko&apos; from vol. 2 (pp. 19–23) of &quot;Edo kyujiko&quot; (1891) and vol. 9 (pp. 1210–1243) of &quot;Nihon Zaise Keizai Shiryo&quot; (1922); Juzo YUZUKI and Yasuzo HORIE, &apos;Honpo jinko hyo&apos; from vol. 7 (pp. 188–210) of &quot;Keizaishi Kenkyu&quot; (1930); Shigetomo KODA, &apos;Edo no Chonin no Jinko&apos; from vol. 8 (pp. 1–23) of &quot;Shakai Keizai gakkaishi&quot; (1938); Yasujiro TAKAMI, &apos;Edo no Jinko no Kenkyu&apos; from the 7th conference (pp. 59–83) of &quot;Zenkoku Toshi Mondai kaigi&quot; (1940); Bonsen TAKAHASHI, &quot;Nihon Jinkoshi no Kenkyu&quot; from Sanyusha publishing (1941), Naotaro SEKIYAMA, &quot;Kinsei Nihon no Jinko Kozo&quot; published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. (1958); Kazuo MINAMI, &quot;Bakumatsu Edo Shakai no Kenkyu&quot; published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. (1978).</e>
<cmt>Check fo consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sources: Nanbo OTA, &apos;Kansei 10 nen, Bogo, Edonin betsu&apos; from vol. 26 of &quot;Ichiwa Ichigen&quot; (1820); Shigetami YAMASHITA, &apos;Edo shigai Tokei Ippan&apos; from vol.1 (pp. 18-26) of &quot;Edokai zasshi&quot; (1889); Kaishu KATSU, &apos;Edo Jinko Shoki&apos; from &quot;Suijinroku&quot; (1890); Yasusuke KOMIYAMA, &apos;Funai no Jinko&apos; from vol. 2 (pp. 19–23) of &quot;Edo kyujiko&quot; (1891) and vol. 9 (pp. 1210–1243) of &quot;Nihon Zaise Keizai Shiryo&quot; (1922); Juzo YUZUKI and Yasuzo HORIE, &apos;Honpo jinko hyo&apos; from vol. 7 (pp. 188–210) of &quot;Keizaishi Kenkyu&quot; (1930); Shigetomo KODA, &apos;Edo no Chonin no Jinko&apos; from vol. 8 (pp. 1–23) of &quot;Shakai Keizai gakkaishi&quot; (1938); Yasujiro TAKAMI, &apos;Edo no Jinko no Kenkyu&apos; from the 7th conference (pp. 59–83) of &quot;Zenkoku Toshi Mondai kaigi&quot; (1940); Bonsen TAKAHASHI, &quot;Nihon Jinkoshi no Kenkyu&quot; from Sanyusha publishing (1941), Naotaro SEKIYAMA, &quot;Kinsei Nihon no Jinko Kozo&quot; published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. (1958); Kazuo MINAMI, &quot;Bakumatsu Edo Shakai no Kenkyu&quot; published by Yoshikawa Kobunkan Inc. (1978).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>史料によって若干異なる場合は一方のみを記した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In case that the population figure for a certain year varies from one source to another, only one of them was used.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Where population figures vary between sources, only one of those figures have been implemented.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Where population figures vary between sources, only one of those figures have been implemented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="69">
<j>享保三年十二月、享保七年三月、享保八年五月、享保九年七月、享保十年九月、享保十六年四月、享保十七年十一月の数字を仮に町方並寺社門前の人口として扱ったが、公文書では少なくとも享保十年六月までは町方支配場の人口のみしか集計しておらず、そもそもこれらのほとんどにアナグラム的な数字の誤記が見受けられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this chart, the figures of seven censuses (December 1718, March 1722, May 1723, July 1724, September 1725, April 1731 and November 1732) are treated as the combined populations of townspeople and Jisha-Monzen, but all of the official figures compiled before June 1725 represent only townspeople (excluding Jisha-Monzen), and most of these records have numerical errors.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this chart, the figures of seven censuses (December 1718, March 1722, May 1723, July 1724, September 1725, April 1731 and November 1732) provisionally treated represent the combined population of the townspeople and those around Jisha-Monzen (Literally translated as area in front of temples and shrines); However, according to official documents, censuses up to the June 1725 (Year 10 Kyoho) only take account of townspeople, but even these records include numerical errors.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this chart, the figures of seven censuses (December 1718, March 1722, May 1723, July 1724, September 1725, April 1731 and November 1732) provisionally treated represent the combined population of the townspeople and those around Jisha-Monzen (Literally translated as area in front of temples and shrines); However, according to official documents, censuses up to the June 1725 (Year 10 Kyoho) only take account of townspeople, but even these records include numerical errors.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>また『吹塵録』の「江戸人口小記」は町方並寺社門前の人口として子午年改の人口をまとめているが、『重宝録』では享保六年十一月の人口を町奉行支配場のみの町人人口として記載している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, &apos;Edo Jinko Shoki&apos; of &quot;Suijinroku&quot; compiled population figures every six year under the title of &apos;townspeople and Jisha-Monzen&apos;, whereas &quot;Chohoroku&quot; compiled the figure of November 1721 under the name of &apos;townspeople&apos;.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although, the &apos;Edo Jinko Shoki&apos; of &quot;Suijinroku&quot; compile the figures from the hexannual census, whereas the &quot;Chohoroku&quot; compiles the figures of November 1721 under the name of &apos;townspeople.&apos;</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although, the &apos;Edo Jinko Shoki&apos; of &quot;Suijinroku&quot; compile the figures from the hexannual census, whereas the &quot;Chohoroku&quot; compiles the figures of November 1721 under the name of &apos;townspeople.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>よって、享保十一年、元文三年、延享元年の数字も町奉行支配場町人人口として扱った。）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this chart, therefore, the population figures of 1721, 1738 and 1743 are treated to represent townspeople only.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In this chart, the census figures for 1721 (Kyoho 11), 1738 (Genbun 3), and 1743 (Enkyo 1) only represent townspeople.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In this chart, the census figures for 1721 (Kyoho 11), 1738 (Genbun 3), and 1743 (Enkyo 1) only represent townspeople.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="72">
<j>寛政十年五月（1798年）と天保十一年五月（1840年）に関しては三郡（豊島郡 (武蔵国)、荏原郡、葛飾郡）に占める江戸の人口が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As for 1798 and 1840, populations of three counties, Toshima-gun (Musashi Province), Ebara-gun and Katsushika-gun, are also shown in the chart.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The populations of the three counties Toshima-gun (Musashi Province), Ebara-gun and Katsushika-gun for May 1798 (Kansei 10) and May 1840 (Tenpo 11) are as indicated in the chart.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic change.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The populations of the three counties Toshima-gun (Musashi Province), Ebara-gun and Katsushika-gun for May 1798 (Kansei 10) and May 1840 (Tenpo 11) are as indicated in the chart.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="73">
<j>江戸末期には出世地別の統計や地方に籍を置く出稼人の人口もまとめられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the end of the Edo Period, populations by birthplace and populations of migrant workers who had a domicile address other than Edo were also compiled.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By the end of the Edo Period, the census collected and compiled population by place of birth and the population of migrant workers residing in Edo.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By the end of the Edo Period, the census collected and compiled population by place of birth and the population of migrant workers residing in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="74">
<j>算総人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Total Estimate Population</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Total Estimate Population</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Total Estimate Population</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="75">
<j>公文書で出稼人を加えた町人人口が最大（58万7458人）となったのは天保十四年七月（1843年）であり、出稼人を除いた町人人口が最大（57万5901人）となったのは嘉永六年九月（1853年）のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to official documents, it was July 1843 that the population of townspeople including migrant workers reached the largest (587,458) and also in September 1853 that the population excluding migrant workers did the same (575,901).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Official documents reveal that the total migrant population combined with the population of townspeople reached its apex (587,458) in July 1843 (Kyoho 14), and the population of townspeople excluding migrant workers reached its apex (575,901) in September 1853 (Kaei 6).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Official documents reveal that the total migrant population combined with the population of townspeople reached its apex (587,458) in July 1843 (Kyoho 14), and the population of townspeople excluding migrant workers reached its apex (575,901) in September 1853 (Kaei 6).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="76">
<j>但し『江戸旧事考』は出稼人を加えた町人人口が最大となった天保十四年の人口を59万6448人とし（内訳等の数字は公文書の天保十四年七月のものと似ている）、出稼人を除いた町人人口が最大になった数字として100年前の寛保二年（1742年）の59万1809人を挙げている（『江戸旧事考』の数字は多くの場合計外人口を加算しているものと思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, according to &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot;, the population of 1843, when Edo was the most populous including migrant workers, was 596,448, (its broken-down figures are similar to those in the official document of July 1843), and the biggest population excluding migrant workers was 591,809 as of 1742, a hundred years before the official record (however, most figures in &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; are believed to cover non-targeted demographics as well).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, according to the &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; (Ruminations on Old Edo) Edo&apos;s population reached its height in 1843 with approximately 596,448 including migrant workers (The broken-down figures are similar to those in the official document of July 1843.); excluding migrant workers, the Edo population reached its height in 1742--a hundred years before the official census (Most of the figures in the &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; are believed to cover non-targeted demographic subjects as well.&quot;) with a local population of 591,809 as of 1742, a hundred years before the official record (however, most figures in &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; are believed to cover non-targeted demographics as well).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, according to the &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; (Ruminations on Old Edo) Edo&apos;s population reached its height in 1843 with approximately 596,448 including migrant workers (The broken-down figures are similar to those in the official document of July 1843.); excluding migrant workers, the Edo population reached its height in 1742--a hundred years before the official census (Most of the figures in the &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; are believed to cover non-targeted demographic subjects as well.&quot;) with a local population of 591,809 as of 1742, a hundred years before the official record (however, most figures in &quot;Edo Kyujiko&quot; are believed to cover non-targeted demographics as well).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>また『江戸会雑誌』は享和三年正月（1803年）の数字として60万7100人を挙げている（但し男性の人口を誤って十万人多く記載していると思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;Edokai zasshi&quot;, the population of 1803 was 607,100 (however, it seems the male population overstated by 100,000).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, according to &quot;Edokai zasshi,&quot;the population in New Years 1803 (Japanese Years) was 607,100 (However, it is believed that the male population was mistakenly overstated by 100,000).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;Edokai zasshi,&quot;the population in New Years 1803 (Japanese Years) was 607,100 (However, it is believed that the male population was mistakenly overstated by 100,000).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>江戸は地方からの上京者が多く、江戸時代中期には男性が女性の倍近くいたが、末期には男女差がかなり解消された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo had many migrants from provinces, and in the middle of the Edo Period, male population was double the number of female one, but the population difference was significantly reduced by the end of the Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many provincial migrants, many of whom were male, resided in Edo to the extent that the male population was nearly double that of the female population in the mid-Edo period, this gender imbalance was greatly alleviated by the end of period.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes; unnecessary capitals; The original Japanese text can be clearer (It should state that the majority of migrants were male, which is obvious, but only implied in the text).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many provincial migrants, many of whom were male, resided in Edo to the extent that the male population was nearly double that of the female population in the mid-Edo period, this gender imbalance was greatly alleviated by the end of period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="79">
<j>このほか大田南畝の『半日閑話』、岩瀬京山の『蜘蛛の糸』、『乙巳雑記上』などは、天明六年十月廿八日（1786年）または天明七年五月廿五日以降（1787年）に江戸の町人の人口が100万人を超える128万5300人であったと伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Other sources including &quot;Hannichi Kanwa&quot; of Nanbo OTA and &quot;Kumo no Ito&quot; and &quot;乙巳雑記上&quot; of Kyozan IWASE, describe that in 1786 or 1787, the population of townspeople reached over one million, 1,285,300. to be exact.</e>
<cmt>乙巳雑記上：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Other sources including OTA Nanbo&apos;s &quot;Hannichi Kanwa&quot; and &quot;Kumo no Ito&quot; and IWASE Kyozan&apos;s &quot;Otomizakki jo&quot; point that the population of towns people exceeded the one million mark and reached 1,285,300 by June 1786 (Tenmei 6) or May 1787 (Tenmei), t.</e>
<cmt>Name Order changed;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Other sources including Nanbo OTA&apos;s &quot;Hannichi Kanwa&quot; and &quot;Kumo no Ito&quot; and Kyozan IWASE&apos;s &quot;Otomizakki jo&quot; point that the population of towns people exceeded the one million mark and reached 1,285,300 by June 1786 (Tenmei 6) or May 1787 (Tenmei), t.</e>
<cmt>個人名、姓名の順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>また天保八年（1837年）の人口として128万4815人という数字も伝わっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, another source describes the figure for 1837 was 1,284,815.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Another source indicates that the population in 1837 (Tenpo 8) was 1,284,815.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Another source indicates that the population in 1837 (Tenpo 8) was 1,284,815.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>共に災害の直後の非常時であったため、これらが武家人口を含めた真の江戸の人口であるとする解釈があるが、(1) 男女比が逆転している (2) 50年隔てた両年の人口や後述の計外人口の構成が酷似しているなど信頼性が低い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Some people believe that these numbers include samurai households, and therefore they reflect a true size of the town, because the statistics were carried out in the time of emergency immediately after disasters, but it is unreliable because 1. the male-to-female ratio was switched, and 2. the populations of targeted demographics, as well as the ones of non-targeted demographics are very close in the two different years over 50 years of interval.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Some have interpreted that these figures, collected shortly after a state of emergency due to a disaster, reveal the true population of Edo that takes into account the population of samurai households, but the reliability of this document is questionable because (1) the male-to-female ratio is reversed, and (2) the populations and composition of non-targeted demographics are similar in spite of a fifty year interval.</e>
<cmt>I find it really strange that the original Japanese document does not include any information concerning &quot;災害の直後の非常時,&quot; If it is so significant, such information should not be elided; Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Some have interpreted that these figures, collected shortly after a state of emergency due to a disaster, reveal the true population of Edo that takes into account the population of samurai households, but the reliability of this document is questionable because (1) the male-to-female ratio is reversed, and (2) the populations and composition of non-targeted demographics are similar in spite of a fifty year interval.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="82">
<j>新吉原、神官・僧侶の人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population of Shin-yoshiwara (a red light district), Shinto priest and Buddhist monk</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population of the Shin-yoshiwara (The red light district), Shinto Priests and Buddhist Monks</e>
<cmt>Capitals; Pluralized; (Assuming that this is a title).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population of the Shin-yoshiwara (The red light district), Shinto Priests and Buddhist Monks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="83">
<j>吉原 (東京都)は1657年の明暦の大火の際に江戸郊外に作られた居住地区であったが、安政元年よりも前は町奉行の支配下に入っておらず、江戸御府内人口の統計から除外されてきた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Yoshiwara (Tokyo Prefecture), a residential area built in the suburb of Edo after the Great Fire of Meireki of 1657, was outside the control of the town magistrate&apos;s office, it was excluded from population statistics of Edo-fu Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the Yoshiwara (Tokyo Prefecture) was initially constructed as a residential in a suburb of Edo after the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657, it remained outside the control of the town magistrate&apos;s office and was excluded from the census taken within Edo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>Translator elided pertinant information.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the Yoshiwara (Tokyo Prefecture) was initially constructed as a residential in a suburb of Edo after the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657, it remained outside the control of the town magistrate&apos;s office and was excluded from the census taken within Edo Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="84">
<j>また神官・僧侶は特殊階級とみなされ、人口の統計から除外されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, Shint priests and Buddhist monks were regarded as a special class and therefore, they were also excluded from a population census.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, Shinto priests and Buddhist monks were regarded as belonging to a special class and excluded from a population census.</e>
<cmt>Spelling error; stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, Shinto priests and Buddhist monks were regarded as belonging to a special class and excluded from a population census.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="85">
<j>以下複数の雑記に記録されている計外人口を列挙する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following is the list of population figures not covered by a census but recorded in a several miscellaneous notes.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is a list of population figures for demographic elements not covered by the census, but recorded in a several miscellaneous notes.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a list of population figures for demographic elements not covered by the census, but recorded in a several miscellaneous notes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="86">
<j>しかし、時代を超えて数字が酷似していることから、数点の元史料をもとに数字が伝えられ、誤記により変化した考えられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, as the figures are quite similar throughout the ages, it is believed that they were based on one or two sources and mis-descripted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, since the figures remain oddly similar over time, it is thought that they were plagiarized from several historical documents, but changed over time through mis-transcription.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, since the figures remain oddly similar over time, it is thought that they were plagiarized from several historical documents, but changed over time through mis-transcription.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="87">
<j>寺社方人口として一番控えめな数字を採用すると約4万人程度となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most modest population figure of Jisha-gata is around 40,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most conservative estimates for temple and shrine constituents point to a population of 40,000.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most conservative estimates for temple and shrine constituents point to a population of 40,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="88">
<j>また新吉原の人口は約1万人程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the population of Shin-yoshiwara was around 10,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, the population of Shin-yoshiwara was around 10,000.</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, the population of Shin-yoshiwara was around 10,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="89">
<j>寺社門前町支配下の農民、町人の人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population of peasants and townspeople in temple towns</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population of peasants and townspeople in temple/shrine towns</e>
<cmt>Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population of peasants and townspeople in temple/shrine towns</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="90">
<j>御府内の範囲は時代によって異なり、特に寺社門前町の取り扱いについては幕府役人の間でも問い合わせがあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area governed by the town magistrate&apos;s office frequently changed over times, and especially how to handle temple towns was a big challenge for magistrate officers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area governed by the town magistrate&apos;s office varied with time, and the handling of temple/shrine towns was a particularly troublesome issue among Bakufu officials.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area governed by the town magistrate&apos;s office varied with time, and the handling of temple/shrine towns was a particularly troublesome issue among Bakufu officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="91">
<j>実際朱印内であってもかなりの農地が武家屋敷とともに存在した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Indeed, even in Shuinchi (lands allocated for temples and shrines), a fair amount of farm lands existed along with samurai residences.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Indeed, a significant number of farm plots and samurai residences existed in Shuinchi (lands allocated for temples and shrines).</e>
<cmt>Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Indeed, a significant number of farm plots and samurai residences existed in Shuinchi (lands allocated for temples and shrines).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="92">
<j>そのため町奉行支配下の町人人口として計上されている寺社門前地の人口には、農地に点在する農民、一部町人の人口が含まれていないとする解釈がある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, some say that populations of temple towns, which were incorporated into the population of townspeople, do not include peasants living in such farm lands and some other townspeople living in the Shuinchi.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the abovementioned reason, there are those who interpret that the population of temple towns that have been accounted for in the population of townspeople, do not include peasants living in such farm lands and some other townspeople inhabiting the shuinchi.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; diction; unnecessary capitals removed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the abovementioned reason, there are those who interpret that the population of temple towns that have been accounted for in the population of townspeople, do not include peasants living in such farm lands and some other townspeople inhabiting the shuinchi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="93">
<j>鷹見安二郎（1940年）によると住宅密集地区外に点在する民家は文政年間で約9500戸程度と見積もられ、約4万3500人程度である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasujiro TAKAMI (1940) estimated that in the Bunsei era, there were around 9,500 households outside of the ordinary residential area, about 43,500 people in total.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">TAKAMI Yasujiro (1940) estimated that there were 9,500 households and approximately 43,500 people inhabiting the dense residential area.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; diction.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">TAKAMI Yasujiro (1940) estimated that there were 9,500 households and approximately 43,500 people inhabiting the dense residential area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="94">
<j>被差別階級の人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population of discriminated classes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population of Eta and Hinin (Discriminated Outsider Castes)</e>
<cmt>Diction; I think word choice here depends on readership.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population of Eta and Hinin (Discriminated Outsider Castes)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="95">
<j>以下『江戸会誌』2冊（10号）37頁による。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following figures are based on &quot;Edo Kaishi&quot; (p. 37 of No. 10).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following figures are based on &quot;Edo Kaishi&quot; (p. 37 of No. 10).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following figures are based on &quot;Edo Kaishi&quot; (p. 37 of No. 10).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="96">
<j>松右衛門手下</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Underlings of Matsuuemon</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disciples of Matsuuemon</e>
<cmt>Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disciples of Matsuuemon</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="97">
<j>武士及び使用人の人口</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Population of samurai and servants</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Population of samurai and servants</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Population of samurai and servants</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="98">
<j>武家屋敷に使用人として住む町人の人口は、幕府の管理下になかったため、江戸の人口統計から除外されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The population of servants living in samurai residences was not under control of bakufu, and therefore, it was excluded from population statistics of Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The population of servants living in samurai residences was excluded from the Edo census because it was not an administrative responsibility of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Good translation of the original Japanese document, but I think it was also quite literal. Considering the context, a change in style was necessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The population of servants living in samurai residences was excluded from the Edo census because it was not an administrative responsibility of the Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="99">
<j>また軍事機密保持なども理由に、武士階級全体の人口がそもそも統計として残っていない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, in order to maintain confidentiality on military matters, populations of samurai were never counted throughout the Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, the population of the samurai was never recorded since it was strategically sensitive information.</e>
<cmt>Again, it could have been literally translated as &quot;Furthermore, the population of samura was never recorded for the reason of protecting military secrets- among other reasons,&quot; but I have chosen to avoid such a translation in favor of a more streamlined version.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, the population of the samurai was never recorded since it was strategically sensitive information.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="100">
<j>いくつかの雑記は江戸在中の武士の人口として2億人を超える荒唐無稽な数値（享保十七年四月（1732年） 2億3698万7950人（『月堂見聞集』）、享保二十年（1735年）：2億3608万5950人（『半日閑話』）、寛政三年（1743年）及び文化十二年（1815年）：2億3658万0390人（『甲子夜話』））を記載しているが、唯一『土屋筆記』は御屋敷方の人口として70万0973人（年次不明）という比較的現実的な人口を伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In a several miscellaneous notes, populations of samurai residing in Edo were irrationally estimated as large as over 0.2 billion (236,987,950 in 1732 [&quot;Getudo Kenmon shu&quot;], 236,085,950 in 1735 [&quot;Hannichi Kanwa&quot;] and 236,580,390 in 1743 and 1815 [&quot;Kasshi yawa&quot;]), whereas &quot;Tsuchiya Hikki&quot; describes a realistic figure of 600,973 (years unknown).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In a several miscellaneous notes, populations of samurai residing in Edo were irrationally estimated as large as over 0.2 billion (236,987,950 in 1732 [&quot;Getudo Kenmon shu&quot;], 236,085,950 in 1735 [&quot;Hannichi Kanwa&quot;] and 236,580,390 in 1743 and 1815 [&quot;Kasshi yawa&quot;]), whereas &quot;Tsuchiya Hikki&quot; describes a realistic figure of 600,973 (years unknown).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In a several miscellaneous notes, populations of samurai residing in Edo were irrationally estimated as large as over 0.2 billion (236,987,950 in 1732 [&quot;Getudo Kenmon shu&quot;], 236,085,950 in 1735 [&quot;Hannichi Kanwa&quot;] and 236,580,390 in 1743 and 1815 [&quot;Kasshi yawa&quot;]), whereas &quot;Tsuchiya Hikki&quot; describes a realistic figure of 600,973 (years unknown).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="101">
<j>また『柳烟雑記』は享保九年五月（1723年）の武家人口として、大名264人、旗本5205人、御目見以下1万7004人、与力・同心並びに六尺・下男3万0909人、その他487人と伝えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, according to &quot;柳烟雑記,&quot; samurai warriors in 1723 was comprised of 242 daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), 5,205 hatamoto (bannermen), 17,004 of those below these ranks, 30,909 yoriki (police sergeant), doshin (police constable), rokushaku (servant), genan (houseboy), and 487 others.</e>
<cmt>柳烟雑記：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, according to the &quot;Ryuenzakki&quot; [柳烟雑記] (Miscellaneous Records of Smokey Willow), the samurai population as of May 1723 (Kyoho 9) comprised of 264 daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), 5,205 hatamoto (bannermen), 17,004 subordinates, 30,909 of those including yoriki (police sergeant), doshin (police constable), rokushaku (servant) and genan (houseboy), and 487 others.</e>
<cmt>The population of Daimyo has been mistranscribed; dates elided in the original</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, according to the &quot;Ryuenzakki&quot; [柳烟雑記] (Miscellaneous Records of Smokey Willow), the samurai population as of May 1723 (Kyoho 9) comprised of 264 daimyo (Japanese feudal lord), 5,205 hatamoto (bannermen), 17,004 subordinates, 30,909 of those including yoriki (police sergeant), doshin (police constable), rokushaku (servant) and genan (houseboy), and 487 others.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="102">
<j>小宮山綏介（1891年）は、『柳烟雑記』の統計を元に諸藩の在府者と家族の人口を12万1100人、旗本御家人と家族の人口を8万3403人、その家来・従事者5万8936人、合計約26万人程度と推定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yasusuke KOMIYAMA (1891) estimated based on the statistics from &quot;柳烟雑記&quot; that the total population of samurai households was around 260,000; 121,110 of domain-retained samurai and their family, 83,403 of hatamoto and their family, and 58,936 of their retainers and servants.</e>
<cmt>柳烟雑記：読み方不明です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yasusuke KOMIYAMA (1891) estimated based on the statistics from &quot;柳烟雑記&quot; that the total population of samurai households was around 260,000; 121,110 of domain-retained samurai and their family, 83,403 of hatamoto and their family, and 58,936 of their retainers and servants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yasusuke KOMIYAMA (1891) estimated based on the statistics from &quot;柳烟雑記&quot; that the total population of samurai households was around 260,000; 121,110 of domain-retained samurai and their family, 83,403 of hatamoto and their family, and 58,936 of their retainers and servants.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="103">
<j>また天保十四年の調査に対しては、合計約30万人程度と推定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, his total estimate of samurai households for 1843 is around 300,000.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, a survey performed in 1843 (Tenpo 14) estimates the total population to be approximately 300,000.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, a survey performed in 1843 (Tenpo 14) estimates the total population to be approximately 300,000.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="104">
<j>一方鷹見安二郎（1940年）は明治初年の華族・士族人口や石高の統計などをもとに、諸藩の在府者と家族の人口を約36万人、幕府配下の武家と家族の人口を約26万人、合計約62万人と推定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, Yasujiro TAKAMI (1940) estimated, based on the population statistics conducted in 1868 on peerage and warrior classes and crop yields, that the total population of samurai households was around 620,000, with 360,000 of domain-retained samurai and their family and 260,000 of bakufu-retained samurai and their family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Yasujiro TAKAMI (1940) estimated the population of domain-retained samura and their dependents to be approximately 360,000, and the population of samurai and dependents administered by the Bakufu to be approximately 260,000 for a combined total of 620,000 based on an 1864 (meiji 1) census carried out over peerage and warrior classes.</e>
<cmt>Mistranslation (crop yield?), changes in style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Yasujiro TAKAMI (1940) estimated the population of domain-retained samura and their dependents to be approximately 360,000, and the population of samurai and dependents administered by the Bakufu to be approximately 260,000 for a combined total of 620,000 based on an 1864 (meiji 1) census carried out over peerage and warrior classes.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="105">
<j>関山直太郎（1958年）は、旗本御家人と家族約11万5千人、その家来・従属者約10万人、諸藩の在府者と家族約18万人、幕府直属の足軽・奉公人等約10万人、合計約50万人と推定している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While SEKYAMA Naotaro (1958) estimated that the total population of samurai households was around 500,000, including 115,000 of hatamoto and their family, 100,000 of their servants, 180,000 of domain-retained samurai and their family, and 100,000 of ashigaru (common foot soldier) retained by bakufu and their servants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, Naotaro SEKIYAMA (1958) estimated that the aggregate population of samurai households was around 500,000, composed of 115,000 hatamoto and their dependents, 100,000 of their servants, 180,000 domain-retained samurai and their dependents, and 100,000 of ashigaru (common foot soldier) and servants retained by Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>Name Order; Stylistic changes; Mistranslation (How can ashigaru (common foot soldiers) have their own servants?)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, Naotaro SEKIYAMA (1958) estimated that the aggregate population of samurai households was around 500,000, composed of 115,000 hatamoto and their dependents, 100,000 of their servants, 180,000 domain-retained samurai and their dependents, and 100,000 of ashigaru (common foot soldier) and servants retained by Bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="106">
<j>過去の人口推定値として海外でしばしば引用されるTertius Chandler（1987年）は、町奉行支配下の町人人口の3/8程度を武士人口とし、18万8千人（1701年）から約21万5千人（1854年）と見積もっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tertius Chandler, whose population estimates are frequently cited in other countries, estimated that three-eighth of the population of townspeople was samurai, ranging from 188,000 (1701) to 215,000 (1854).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tertius Chandler, whose estimates for historical populations are frequently cited in other countries, estimated that three-eighths of the population of townspeople were samurai, and approximated the demographic shift from 188,000 in 1701 to 215,000 1854.</e>
<cmt>phrasing</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tertius Chandler, whose estimates for historical populations are frequently cited in other countries, estimated that three-eighths of the population of townspeople were samurai, and approximated the demographic shift from 188,000 in 1701 to 215,000 1854.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>江戸から東京へ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Edo to Tokyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Edo to Tokyo</e>
<cmt>OK</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Edo to Tokyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="107">
<j>1868年に戊辰戦争が起こり、鳥羽・伏見の戦いで幕府軍が敗れると、薩摩藩長州藩軍の大軍が江戸に迫り、江戸は戦火に晒される危険に陥った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Boshin War started in 1868 with the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, and when the bakufu army was defeated in the Battle, a large force of Satsuma and Choshu Domains advanced to Edo, putting Edo under the threat of warfare.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Boshin War broke out in 1868, and when the Bakufu army was defeated in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, a large force of combined Satsuma and Choshu Domains advanced on Edo, putting the metropolis under the threat of warfare.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Mistranslation (The Battle of Toba Fushimi was not the first engagement of the Boshin War).</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Boshin War broke out in 1868, and when the Bakufu army was defeated in the Battle of Toba-Fushimi, a large force of combined Satsuma and Choshu Domains advanced on Edo, putting the metropolis under the threat of warfare.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="108">
<j>幕臣勝海舟は早期停戦を唱えて薩長軍を率いる西郷隆盛と交渉、最後の将軍徳川慶喜は江戸城の無血開城し降伏、交戦派と官軍の間の上野戦争を例外として、江戸は戦火を免れた（江戸開城）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A shogun&apos;s retainer, Kaishu KATSU, advocated an early cease-fire and negotiated with Takamori SAIGO who lead the Saccho army, and as a result, the last shogun, Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA, surrendered the Edo Castle without shedding any blood, saving Edo from warfare, except the Battle of Ueno between domain fighters and the government army.</e>
<cmt>交戦派：意味不明瞭です。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KATSU Kaishu, a retainer of the Shogun, advocated an early cease-fire with SAIGO Takamori --commander of combined Satsuma and Choshu forces; Consequently, the last Shogun TOKUGAWA Yoshinobu surrendered Edo Castle without any bloodshed and spared Edo from the ravages of war with the exception of the Battle of Ueno fought between domain and government forces.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Name Order; Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaishu KATSU, a retainer of the Shogun, advocated an early cease-fire with Takamori SAIGO--commander of combined Satsuma and Choshu forces; Consequently, the last Shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA surrendered Edo Castle without any bloodshed and spared Edo from the ravages of war with the exception of the Battle of Ueno fought between domain and government forces.</e>
<cmt>個人名、姓名の順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="109">
<j>同年、江戸は東京と改名され、翌1869年には東京城（江戸城）に東京行幸した明治天皇が入って「皇城」とされて、かつての将軍の居住する都市・江戸は、天皇の行在する都市・東京となった（東京奠都）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same year, Edo was renamed Tokyo and in the following 1869, the Tokyo Castle (formerly, the Edo Castle) was officially appointed as a temporal &apos;Imperial Palace&apos; while Emperor Meiji was staying in the Castle, and the &apos;metropolis Edo&apos; where shogun had once resided was turned into the &apos;metropolis Tokyo&apos; where Emperor was staying temporarily (Tokyo Tento [transfer of the national capital to Tokyo]).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shortly after the fall of the Bakufu, Edo renamed Tokyo, and in the following year the Tokyo Castle (formerly, the Edo Castle) was officially recommissioned as the &apos;Imperial Palace&apos; with the 入居 of the Meiji Emperor-- the metropolis Edo once overseen by the shogun became the &apos;metropolis Tokyo&apos;-- temporary residence of the Emperor (Tokyo Tento [transfer of the national capital to Tokyo]).</e>
<cmt>I have translated this within the context of the rest of the document, eliding an unnecessary repetition of the year;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shortly after the fall of the Bakufu, Edo renamed Tokyo, and in the following year the Tokyo Castle (formerly, the Edo Castle) was officially recommissioned as the &apos;Imperial Palace&apos; with the 入居 of the Meiji Emperor-- the metropolis Edo once overseen by the shogun became the &apos;metropolis Tokyo&apos;-- temporary residence of the Emperor (Tokyo Tento [transfer of the national capital to Tokyo]).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="110">
<j>東京の町並が東京市、東京都へと変遷しつつ拡大してゆく過程で、かつての江戸は都心となり、その中核としての役割を果たしている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Tokyo was transforming itself into Tokyo City and to Tokyo Metropolis through territorial expansion, the area once-called Edo became a downtown area of Tokyo and is now playing a central role in Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the townscape of Tokyo expanded and transformed from a city to a metropolis, the area formerly known as Edo became downtown Tokyo, and serves as its center.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Style.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the townscape of Tokyo expanded and transformed from a city to a metropolis, the area formerly known as Edo became downtown Tokyo, and serves as its center.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>都市</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Metropolis</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Metropolis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Metropolis</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="8">
<tit>
<j>江戸の範囲</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Border of Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Extent of Edo</e>
<cmt>Preferrance</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Extent of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="111">
<j>江戸の地名で呼ばれる地域は、元々は平安時代に存在した荏原郡桜田郷（江戸城の西南）の一部であったが、やがて豊島郡 (武蔵国)江戸郷と呼ばれるようになっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, the area called Edo was a part of Sakurada-go, Ebara County (in the southwest of the Edo Castle) which existed in the Heian Period, but later named Edo-go, Toshima County (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area called Edo was originally part of the Heian Period village Sakurada-go in Ebara County (southwest of the Edo Castle), but it later became referred to as Edo-go of Toshima County (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area called Edo was originally part of the Heian Period village Sakurada-go in Ebara County (southwest of the Edo Castle), but it later became referred to as Edo-go of Toshima County (Musashi Province).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="112">
<j>江戸時代前期頃の江戸の範囲は、現在の東京都千代田区とその周辺のみであり、江戸城の外堀はこれを取り囲むよう建造された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the first half of the Edo Period, Edo was as small as current Chiyoda Ward and its surrounding areas, and the outer moat of the Edo Castle was constructed to surround the area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the first half of the Edo Period, the city was no bigger than present day Chiyoda Ward and its surrounding areas, and the outer moat of the Edo Castle was dug to encompass this area.</e>
<cmt>Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the first half of the Edo Period, the city was no bigger than present day Chiyoda Ward and its surrounding areas, and the outer moat of the Edo Castle was dug to encompass this area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="113">
<j>明暦の大火以後、その市街地は拡大。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Great Fire of Meireki, the urban area greatly expanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The urban areas expanded after the Great Fire of Meireki.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The urban areas expanded after the Great Fire of Meireki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="114">
<j>通称「八百八町」と呼ばれるようになる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo was grown to be called &apos;808 towns&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo came to be called as the city of &quot;eight-hundred-and-eight towns&apos; (The number eight-hundred-and-eight is traditionally associated with innumerable.).</e>
<cmt>The cultural significance and meaning of the number 808 needs to be explained in parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo came to be called as the city of &quot;eight-hundred-and-eight towns&apos; (The number eight-hundred-and-eight is traditionally associated with innumerable.).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="115">
<j>江戸の市域は「御府内」と呼ばれ、正式な区域は1818年に地図上の朱引きで、さらに町奉行の管轄する区域は墨引きで示されるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The city area of Edo was called &apos;Gofunai&apos; and the official border of Edo was indicated by &apos;Shubiki&apos; (drawing a border of Edo-fu in red) for the first time in 1818 and the area ruled by the town magistrate&apos;s office was also indicated by &apos;Sumibiki&apos; (drawing a border of the area ruled by the town magistrate&apos;s office) on a map.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The urban area of Edo was called &apos;Gofunai,&apos; and the official borders of Edo cartographically delineated by &apos;shubiki&apos; (literally &quot;red-ruled lines.&quot;) for the first time in 1818, and the area administered by the town magistrate&apos;s office were distinguished by &apos;sumibiki&apos; (literally &quot;black-ruled lines&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic changes; Japanese Dates added for consistency.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The urban area of Edo was called &apos;Gofunai,&apos; and the official borders of Edo cartographically delineated by &apos;shubiki&apos; (literally &quot;red-ruled lines.&quot;) for the first time in 1818, and the area administered by the town magistrate&apos;s office were distinguished by &apos;sumibiki&apos; (literally &quot;black-ruled lines&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="116">
<j>朱引きは旧東京市の15区より若干広く、現在の豊島区、渋谷区、荒川区、北区 (東京都)、目黒区の一部、品川区の一部、板橋区の一部をも含む。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area indicated by &apos;Shubiki&apos; was slightly larger than the fifteen Wards of the former Tokyo City, including the areas of current Toshima Ward, Shibuya Ward, Kita Ward and portions of Meguro, Shinagawa and Itabashi Wards.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The area encompassed by &apos;Shubiki&apos; was slightly larger than the fifteen wards consisting Old Tokyo, and include parts of present day Toshima, Shibuya, and Kita wards, as well as parts of Meguro, Shinagawa, and Itabashi wards.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The area encompassed by &apos;Shubiki&apos; was slightly larger than the fifteen wards consisting Old Tokyo, and include parts of present day Toshima, Shibuya, and Kita wards, as well as parts of Meguro, Shinagawa, and Itabashi wards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="117">
<j>墨引きは旧東京市の15区とほぼ一致する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The area indicated by &apos;Sumibiki&apos; was almost equal in size to the fifteen Wards of the former Tokyo City.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shubiki delineated areas roughly match with the fifteen wards of Old Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shubiki delineated areas roughly match with the fifteen wards of Old Tokyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="118">
<j>朱引きは明治以降も存続し、数度の改正を経て、最終的には旧墨引に近い形となり郡区町村編制法施行時に旧東京15区となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The practice of &apos;Shubiki&apos; continued after the Meiji Period, and with a series of revisions, the area of Edo was officially set in accordance with the Act for the alignment of local government system to cover the fifteen Wards of the former Tokyo City, almost the same size as indicated by &apos;Sumibiki&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The practice of &apos;shubiki&apos; continued into the Meiji Period; After several revisions the shubiki areas assumed a shape similar to those of sumibiki areas, and the administrative boundaries of the fifteen wards of Old Tokyo were finalized in accordance to the promulgation of the County-Ward-Township-Village Organization Act.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; &quot;郡区町村編制法&quot; has been retranslated as County-Ward-Township-Village Organization Act.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The practice of &apos;shubiki&apos; continued into the Meiji Period; After several revisions the shubiki areas assumed a shape similar to those of sumibiki areas, and the administrative boundaries of the fifteen wards of Old Tokyo were finalized in accordance to the promulgation of the County-Ward-Township-Village Organization Act.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="119">
<j>江戸は、江戸後期に現在の、千代田区・中央区 (東京都)・港区 (東京都)・新宿区の東側（四谷付近まで）・文京区・台東区・墨田区・江東区の辺り、のちの東京市の内十五区部分ぐらいまで広がったといわれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that in later Edo Period, Edo almost covered the fifteen Wards of later-Tokyo City, current Chiyoda Ward, Chuo Ward, Minato Ward, the east side of Shinjuku Ward (up to Yotsuya), Bunkyo Ward, Taito Ward, Sumida Ward and Koto Ward.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that in later Edo Period, Edo almost encompassed fifteen Wards of later-Tokyo City, present-day Chiyoda, Chuo, Bunkyo, Taito, Sumida, and Koto wards, as well as the east side of Shinjuku Ward (up to Yotsuya).</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that in later Edo Period, Edo almost encompassed fifteen Wards of later-Tokyo City, present-day Chiyoda, Chuo, Bunkyo, Taito, Sumida, and Koto wards, as well as the east side of Shinjuku Ward (up to Yotsuya).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="120">
<j>以下に江戸に含まれる主な歴史的地名をあげる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The following are the names of historical places in Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The following is a list of historical place names in Edo.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The following is a list of historical place names in Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="121">
<j>神田 (千代田区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanda (Chiyoda Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanda (Chiyoda Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanda (Chiyoda Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="122">
<j>日本橋 (東京都中央区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nihonbashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nihonbashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nihonbashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="123">
<j>京橋 (東京都中央区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kyobashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kyobashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kyobashi (Chuo Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="124">
<j>本郷 (文京区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hongo (Bukyo-ku Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hongo (Bukyo-ku Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hongo (Bukyo-ku Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="125">
<j>下谷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shimotani</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shimotani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shimotani</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="126">
<j>上野 (台東区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ueno (Taito Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ueno (Taito Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ueno (Taito Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="12">
<sen id="127">
<j>浅草</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Asakusa</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Asakusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Asakusa</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="13">
<sen id="128">
<j>本所 (墨田区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Honjo (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Honjo (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Honjo (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="14">
<sen id="129">
<j>深川 (江東区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fukagawa (Koto Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fukagawa (Koto Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fukagawa (Koto Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="15">
<sen id="130">
<j>両国 (墨田区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryogoku (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryogoku (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryogoku (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="16">
<sen id="131">
<j>向島 (墨田区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mukojima (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mukojima (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mukojima (Sumida Ward)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="17">
<sen id="132">
<j>元々、徳川家康自身が岡崎市出身の一大名であったように、岡崎を初めとする西三河系の地名が、江戸には多く移植されている（例：秋葉原 三河の隣国、遠江国の秋葉山本宮秋葉神社に由来）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was originally a daimyo of Mikawa Province (present-day, Okazaki City, Aichi Prefecture, Western Japan), Edo has a lot of place names from the west side of Mikawa, including Okazaki City (e.g. Akihabara is derived from Akihasan-hongu Akiha-jinja Shrine of Totomi Province, a neighboring province of Mikawa).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Many place names of Nishimikawa beginning with Ozaki, have been transposed to locations in Edo (For example, &quot;Akihabara&quot; was a name for a country bordering Mikawa, which originaltes from the Akihayama Motomiyaakiha Shring of the former country of Totoumi.), because TOKUGAWA Ieyasu was originally the daimyo of Mikawa Province (present-day Okazaki City of Aichi Prefecture in Western Japan.).</e>
<cmt>Diction; Style; Translator elided parenthesis.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Many place names of Nishimikawa beginning with Ozaki, have been transposed to locations in Edo (For example, &quot;Akihabara&quot; was a name for a country bordering Mikawa, which originaltes from the Akihayama Motomiyaakiha Shrine of the former country of Totoumi.), because Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was originally the daimyo of Mikawa Province (present-day Okazaki City of Aichi Prefecture in Western Japan.).</e>
<cmt>個人名、姓名の順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="18">
<sen id="133">
<j>実際には、既に触れたように江戸の地は平安時代末期から関東南部の要衝であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In fact, as mentioned earlier, Edo had served as an important strategic place of the southern Kanto region since late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In fact, as mentioned earlier, the location of Edo was one of vital strategic importance in the southern Kanto region since the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In fact, as mentioned earlier, the location of Edo was one of vital strategic importance in the southern Kanto region since the late Heian Period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="134">
<j>確かに徳川氏の記録が伝えるように、後北条氏時代の江戸城は最重要な支城とまではみなされず城は15世紀の粗末なつくりのまま残されていたが、関八州の首府となりうる基礎はすでに存在していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was true as records of the Tokugawa clan show that the Edo Castle in the era of the Gohojo clan was not regarded as the most important branch castle and left untouched and as humble as it was constructed in the 15th century, but Edo was certainly equipped with necessary features to be developed into a metropolis of the eight provinces of the Kanto region.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As the records of the Tokugawa clan reveal, the Edo Castle was not regarded as a vital branch-castle in the time of the Gohojo clan and its modest structure that was constructed in the 15th century remained; However, it should be noted that the foundations that would enable Edo to develop into the capital of eight provinces had already been laid.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As the records of the Tokugawa clan reveal, the Edo Castle was not regarded as a vital branch-castle in the time of the Gohojo clan and its modest structure that was constructed in the 15th century remained; However, it should be noted that the foundations that would enable Edo to develop into the capital of eight provinces had already been laid.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="19">
<sen id="135">
<j>しかし、江戸が都市として発展するためには、日比谷入江の東、隅田川河口の西にあたる江戸前島と呼ばれる砂州を除けば、城下町をつくるために十分な平地が存在しないことが大きな障害となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, it was a huge setback for Edo, in an effort to develop into a metropolis, to have scarce flatland to build a castle town, except Edo Maejima, a sandbar, located in the east of Hibiya cove and in the west of the estuary of Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">With the exception of the sandbar known as Edomaeshima, which is east of the Hibiya inlet and west of the Sumidagawa Estuary, the lack of level land not only posed a significant obstacle to development of the castletown, but also hampered the development of Edo into metropolis.</e>
<cmt>Frankly, the phrase &quot;と呼ばれる&quot;doesn&apos;t translate very well into English- it is unnecessary.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">With the exception of the sandbar known as Edomaeshima, which is east of the Hibiya inlet and west of the Sumidagawa Estuary, the lack of level land not only posed a significant obstacle to development of the castletown, but also hampered the development of Edo into metropolis.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="136">
<j>そこで徳川氏は、まず江戸城の大手門から隅田川まで道三堀を穿ち、そこから出た土で日比谷入江の埋め立てを開始した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Frist of all, the Tokugawa clan dug a moat (called Dosan Moat) from the Ote-mon Gate of the Edo Castle to Sumida-gawa River and redeemed Hibiya cove using the dug-out soils.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In response to this issue, Tokugawa dug the Dosan moat stretching from the Ote-mon Gate of Edo Castle to Sumida-gawa (river), and initiated the reclamation of Hibiya inlet using the earth from the prior previous moat construction.</e>
<cmt>Spelling error; Stylistic changes; diction;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In response to this issue, Tokugawa dug the Dosan moat stretching from the Ote-mon Gate of Edo Castle to Sumida-gawa (river), and initiated the reclamation of Hibiya inlet using the earth from the prior previous moat construction.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="137">
<j>道三堀は墨田川河口から江戸城の傍まで、城の建造に必要な木材や石材を搬入するために活用され、道三堀の左右に舟町が形成された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Dosan Moat was used to convey timbers and stones from the estuary of Sumida-gawa River up to the Edo Castle for reconstruction of the Castle, and funamachi (ship towns) were also built on the banks of Dosan Canal.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Dosan canal was used to transport timber and stone building materials required for the construction of the castle from the Sumidagawa estuary up to the Edo Castle, and a funamachi (riverine port town) was built one both banks of the canal.</e>
<cmt>&quot;convey&quot;? diction; uncessary plurals; Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Dosan canal was used to transport timber and stone building materials required for the construction of the castle from the Sumidagawa estuary up to the Edo Castle, and a funamachi (riverine port town) was built one both banks of the canal.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="138">
<j>また、元からあった平地である今の常盤橋門外から日本橋の北に最初の町人地が設定された（この時と時期を同じくして平川の日比谷入江から江戸前島を貫通する流路変更が行われたと思われる）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, on the flatland stretching from the current Tokiwabashi Gate to the north of Nihon-bashi Bridge, the first choninchi (area where merchants and artisans lived) was set up (to coincide with the construction of choninchi, it is believed that the route of Hira-kawa River was diverted so that it passed through Edo Maejima from Hibiya cove).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the first townspeople (residential) zone was designated north of the outside of the Tokiwa-bashi Gate and Nihon-bashi bridge (an area designated for the habitation of merchants and artisans) (It is thought that the course of Hira-kawa River stretching towards Hibiya inlet was diverted to pass through Edo Maejima.)</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the first townspeople (residential) zone was designated north of the outside of the Tokiwa-bashi Gate and Nihon-bashi bridge (an area designated for the habitation of merchants and artisans) (It is thought that the course of Hira-kawa River stretching towards Hibiya inlet was diverted to pass through Edo Maejima.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="139">
<j>これが江戸本町、今の日本銀行本店や三越本店がある一帯である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is the area called Edo Honmachi, presently where the central branch of the Bank of Japan and the main store of Mitsukoshi stand.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This area known as Edo Honmachi encompassed the area where the central branch of the Bank of Japan and the main store of Mitsukoshi currently stand.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This area known as Edo Honmachi encompassed the area where the central branch of the Bank of Japan and the main store of Mitsukoshi currently stand.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="140">
<j>さらに元からあった周辺集落である南の芝 (東京都港区)、北の浅草や西の赤坂、牛込、麹町にも町屋が発展した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furthermore, machiya (merchant houses) were also built in the villages, such as Shiba in the south (Minato Ward), Asakusa in the north and Akasaka, Ushigome and Kojimmachi in the west.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furthermore, machiya (merchant houses) were also built in the villages such as Shiba in the south (Minato Ward), Asakusa in the north, and Akasaka, Ushigome and Kojimachi in the west.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic changes; romanization error</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furthermore, machiya (merchant houses) were also built in the villages such as Shiba in the south (Minato Ward), Asakusa in the north, and Akasaka, Ushigome and Kojimachi in the west.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="141">
<j>この頃の江戸の姿を伝える地図としては『別本慶長江戸図』が知られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The most famous map of Edo in this period is &quot;Beppon Keicho Edo zu&quot;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The most famous map of Edo in this period isThe &quot;Beppon Keicho Edo zu,&quot;is known as a map that reveals Edo as it was.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The most famous map of Edo in this period isThe &quot;Beppon Keicho Edo zu,&quot;is known as a map that reveals Edo as it was.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="20">
<sen id="142">
<j>江戸は「の」の字形に設計されたことが一般の城下町と比べて特異であるといわれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Edo was structured in the form of &apos;の&apos; (a letter of Kana syllable, pronounced &apos;no&apos;), a quite unique design, compared to other castle towns.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Edo was structured in the form of &apos;の&apos; (a letter of Kana syllable, pronounced &apos;no&apos;), a quite unique design, compared to other castle towns.</e>
<cmt>It is often stated that Edo&apos;s unique &quot;no&quot; (character &quot;no&quot;) shaped layout distinguishes it from other castle towns.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Edo was structured in the form of &apos;の&apos; (a letter of Kana syllable, pronounced &apos;no&apos;), a quite unique design, compared to other castle towns.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="143">
<j>つまり、江戸城の本城は大手門から和田倉門、馬場先門、桜田門の内側にある本丸、二の丸、西の丸などの内郭に将軍、次期将軍となる将軍の世子、先代の将軍である大御所が住む御殿が造られ、その西にあたる半蔵門内の吹上に将軍の親族である徳川御三家の屋敷が置かれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In this structure, palaces of shogun, his heir and ogosho (ex-shogun) were positioned in the center compound of the Edo Castle (Honmaru, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru) surrounded by three gates (Ote-mon Gate, Wadakura-mon Gate, Babasaki-mon Gate and Sakurada-mon Gate), and residences of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) were placed in Fukiage in the west of the Castle, guarded by the Hanzo-mon Gate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The palaces of shogun, his heir and ogosho (ex-shogun) were constructed the central castle compound of the Edo Castle within the Honmaru, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru interior castle that were enclosed by the Ote-mon, Wadakura-mon, Babasaki-mon, and Sakurada-mon cates, and the residences of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) were reserved west of the Castle and behind Hanzo-mon gate Gate.</e>
<cmt>Significant stylistic adjustments.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The palaces of shogun, his heir and ogosho (ex-shogun) were constructed the central castle compound of the Edo Castle within the Honmaru, Ninomaru and Nishinomaru interior castle that were enclosed by the Ote-mon, Wadakura-mon, Babasaki-mon, and Sakurada-mon cates, and the residences of Tokugawa gosanke (three privileged branches of the Tokugawa family) were reserved west of the Castle and behind Hanzo-mon gate Gate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="144">
<j>内城の堀の外は東の大手門下から和田倉門外に譜代大名の屋敷、南の桜田門の外に外様大名の屋敷と定められ、西の半蔵門外から一ツ橋門、神田橋門外に至る台地に旗本・御家人が住まわされ、さらに武家屋敷地や大名屋敷地の東、常盤橋・呉服橋・鍛冶橋・数寄屋橋から隅田川、江戸湾に至るまでの日比谷埋立地方面に町人地が広げられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outside of the inner moats, residences of fudai daimyo (hereditary vassal to the Tokugawa family) were built in the eastern area where the Ote-mon Gate and the Wadakura-mon Gate stretched, residences of tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord) were also built in the south of the Castle, outside the Sakurada-mon Gate, and ones of Hatamoto and Gokenin (shogun retainers) on the western hillside stretching from the Hanzo-mon Gate, Hitotsubashi-mon Gate to Kandabashi-mon Gate, while in the east of samurai and daimyo residences, choninchi was expanded into the reclaimed lands in the Hibiya area that covered Tokiwa-bashi Bridge, Gofuku-bashi Bridge, Kaji-bashi Bridge, Sukiya-bashi Bridge, Sumida-gawa River and the Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Residences of fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa clan) were built on the western outskirts of the interior castle moat between the Oote-mon and Wadakura-mon gates, an area south of the Sakurada-mon gate was designated the residence of the tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord), and Hatamoto and Gokenin (shogunal retainers) were housed on a hillside stretching between the outskirts of the western Hanzo-mon gate to Hitotsubashi-mon and Kandabashi-mon gates; choninchi (residential and commercial areas for townspeople) the reclaimed lands in Hibiya stretched between Tokiwa-bashi Bridge, Gofuku-bashi Bridge, Kaji-bashi Bridge, Sukiya-bashi Bridge, Sumida-gawa River and the Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt>Style; Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Residences of fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa clan) were built on the western outskirts of the interior castle moat between the Oote-mon and Wadakura-mon gates, an area south of the Sakurada-mon gate was designated the residence of the tozama daimyo (nonhereditary feudal lord), and Hatamoto and Gokenin (shogunal retainers) were housed on a hillside stretching between the outskirts of the western Hanzo-mon gate to Hitotsubashi-mon and Kandabashi-mon gates; choninchi (residential and commercial areas for townspeople) the reclaimed lands in Hibiya stretched between Tokiwa-bashi Bridge, Gofuku-bashi Bridge, Kaji-bashi Bridge, Sukiya-bashi Bridge, Sumida-gawa River and the Edo Bay.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="145">
<j>これを地図で見るとちょうど大手門から数寄屋橋に至るまでの「の」の字の堀の内外に渦巻き上に将軍・親藩・譜代・外様大名・旗本御家人・町人が配置されている形になる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As shown on the map, shogun, shinpan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives), fudai daimyo, tozama daimyo, hatamoto and townspeople were positioned inside and outside the moats, in the area stretching from Ote-mon Gate to Sukiya-bashi Bridge, in a spiral shape of &apos;の&apos; (no).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The layout of Edo is evident on the map as the shogunal, shinpan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives), fudai daimyo, tozama daimyo, hatamoto and townspeople are positioned inside and outside a &quot;の&quot; shaped moat stretching from Ote-mon Gate to Sukiya-bashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>Style; Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The layout of Edo is evident on the map as the shogunal, shinpan (Tokugawa&apos;s relatives), fudai daimyo, tozama daimyo, hatamoto and townspeople are positioned inside and outside a &quot;の&quot; shaped moat stretching from Ote-mon Gate to Sukiya-bashi Bridge.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="146">
<j>巻き貝が殻を大きくするように、渦巻き型に柔軟に拡大できる構造を取ったことが、江戸の拡大を手助けした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a snail&apos;s shell grows bigger and bigger, Edo grew into a metropolis by adopting a city structure of a spiral shape to expand flexibly.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Just as a snail expands its shell as it grows, the adoption of a spiral structure facilitated the flexible expansion of Edo.</e>
<cmt>Style; Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Just as a snail expands its shell as it grows, the adoption of a spiral structure facilitated the flexible expansion of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="21">
<sen id="147">
<j>家康の死後、二代将軍徳川秀忠は、江戸の北東の守りを確保するため、小石川門の西から南に流れていた平川をまっすぐ東に通す改修を行った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Ieyasu, the second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, improved the channel of Hira-kawa River, which originally run from the west of the Koishigawa-mon Gate to the south, so that it run straight from the west to the east in order to reinforce the defense of northeastern Edo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Ieyasu, the second shogun, TOKUGAWA Hidetada ordered the the diversion of the Hirakawa River, which flowed southwards from west side of the Koishigawa-mon gate, to flow eastwards to secure a defensive barrier for Northeastern Edo..</e>
<cmt>Style; Diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Ieyasu, the second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA ordered the the diversion of the Hirakawa River, which flowed southwards from west side of the Koishigawa-mon gate, to flow eastwards to secure a defensive barrier for Northeastern Edo..</e>
<cmt>個人名、姓名の順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="148">
<j>今の水道橋から万世橋（秋葉原）の間は本郷から駿河台まで伸びる神田台地があったためこれを掘り割って人口の谷を造って通し、そこから西は元から神田台地から隅田川に流れていた中川の流路を転用し、浅草橋を通って隅田川に流れるようにした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kanda Plain, which stretched from Hongo to Surugadai (present-day, Suido-bashi Bridge to Mansei-bashi Bridge [Akihabara]), was dug to create an artificial valley so that the Hira-kawa River run through the valley, joined Naka-gawa River in the west (which originated in the Kanda Plain and poured into Sumida-gawa River) and run under Asakusa-bashi Bridge to pour into Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">An artificial valley was dug between the Kanda Plateau that stretched from Hongo to Surugadai (The areas between present-day Suido-bashi and Mansei-bashi bridges [Akihabara]) to dug to create an artificial valley so that the Hira-kawa River run through the valley, joined Naka-gawa River in the west (which originated in the Kanda Plain and poured into Sumida-gawa River) and run under Asakusa-bashi Bridge to pour into Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">An artificial valley was dug between the Kanda Plateau that stretched from Hongo to Surugadai (The areas between present-day Suido-bashi and Mansei-bashi bridges [Akihabara]) to dug to create an artificial valley so that the Hira-kawa River run through the valley, joined Naka-gawa River in the west (which originated in the Kanda Plain and poured into Sumida-gawa River) and run under Asakusa-bashi Bridge to pour into Sumida-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="149">
<j>これが江戸城の北の外堀である神田川 (東京都)である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The river was renamed Kanda-gawa River and served as an outer northern moat of the Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This would later become the Kanda-gawa River, which became the outer northern moat of the Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This would later become the Kanda-gawa River, which became the outer northern moat of the Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="150">
<j>この工事によって平川下流であった一ツ橋、神田橋、日本橋を経て隅田川に至る川筋は神田川（平川）から切り離され、江戸城の堀となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the channel improvement work, one downstream channel of Hira-kawa River, running under Hitotsu-bashi Bridge, Kanda-bashi Bridge and Nihon-bashi Bridge and poured to Sumida-gawa River, was detached from Kanda-gawa River (former Hira-kawa River) and rebuilt as a moat of the Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Through this channel improvement work, the lower reaches of the Hira-kawa River that flowed into Sumida-gawa River after passing through Hitotsu-bashi Bridge, Kanda-bashi Bridge, and Nihon-bashi Bridge, was cut-off from the Kanda-gawa River (former Hira-kawa River) and became the Edo Castle moat.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Through this channel improvement work, the lower reaches of the Hira-kawa River that flowed into Sumida-gawa River after passing through Hitotsu-bashi Bridge, Kanda-bashi Bridge, and Nihon-bashi Bridge, was cut-off from the Kanda-gawa River (former Hira-kawa River) and became the Edo Castle moat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="151">
<j>この堀が再び神田川に接続され、神田川支流の日本橋川となるのは明治時代のことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Meiji Period, this moat was reconnected to Kanda-gawa River and renamed Nihon-bashi River as a branch of Kanda-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was not until the Meiji Period that this moat was reconnected to Kanda-gawa River and renamed Nihon-bashi River-- a branch of the Kanda-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was not until the Meiji Period that this moat was reconnected to Kanda-gawa River and renamed Nihon-bashi River-- a branch of the Kanda-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="22">
<sen id="152">
<j>更に3代将軍徳川家光はこれまで手薄で残されてきた城の西部外郭を固めることにし、溜池や神田川に注ぎ込む小川の谷筋を利用して溜池から赤坂、四ッ谷、市ヶ谷を経て牛込に至り、神田川に接する外堀を造らせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, started reinforcing the outer compound in the west which was left untouched, and built an outer moat by using the valleys of streams that run into a reservoir and Kanda-gawa River, and the constructed moat stretched from the reservoir through Akasaka, Yotsuya, Ichigaya to Ushigome and poured into Kanda-gawa River.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, the third shogun, TOKUGAWA Iemitsu decided to reinforce the castle&apos;s western exterior enclosure, which was left untouched, and built an outer moat using the reservoirs and streams that coursed through Akasaka, Yotsuya, Ichigaya to Ushigome before flowing into Kanda-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA decided to reinforce the castle&apos;s western exterior enclosure, which was left untouched, and built an outer moat using the reservoirs and streams that coursed through Akasaka, Yotsuya, Ichigaya to Ushigome before flowing into Kanda-gawa River.</e>
<cmt>個人名、姓名の順に修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="153">
<j>全国の外様大名を大動員して行われた外堀工事は1636年に竣工し、ここに御成門から浅草橋門に至る江戸城の「の」の字の外側の部分が完成した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This construction work finished in 1636 with tozama daimyo throughout the nation mobilized, meaning that the outer portion of &apos;の&apos;, equivalent to the area from Onari-mon Gate to Asakusabashi-mon Gate, was also completed.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The construction of the moat, which required a massive mobilization on the part of tozama daimyo, was finished in 1636, and marked the completion of a outer portion of the spiral-shaped urban layout that spanned the Onari-mon and Asakusabashi-mon gates.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic Changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The construction of the moat, which required a massive mobilization on the part of tozama daimyo, was finished in 1636, and marked the completion of a outer portion of the spiral-shaped urban layout that spanned the Onari-mon and Asakusabashi-mon gates.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="23">
<sen id="154">
<j>城下町において武家地、町人地とならぶ要素は寺社地であるが、江戸では寺社の配置に風水の思想が重視されたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jisha-chi (lands for temples and shrines) was an important constituent of a castle town along with Bukechi (lands for samurai) and Choninchi (lands for townspeople), and it is said that in Edo, Feng Shui played an important role in the construction of temples and shrines.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among the elements that constitute castletowns, the significance of jisha-chi (lands for temples and shrines) was on par with the bukechi (lands for samurai) and Choninchi (lands for townspeople), but it is said that geomancy also dicated the location of temples and shrines during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Unnecessary capitals</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among the elements that constitute castletowns, the significance of jisha-chi (lands for temples and shrines) was on par with the bukechi (lands for samurai) and Choninchi (lands for townspeople), but it is said that geomancy also dicated the location of temples and shrines during the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="155">
<j>そもそも江戸城が徳川氏の城に選ばれた理由の一因には、江戸の地が当初は北の玄武は麹町台地、東の青龍は神田川 (東京都)、南の朱雀は日比谷入江、西の白虎は東海道、江戸の拡大後は、玄武に本郷 (文京区)台地、青龍に大川（隅田川）、朱雀に江戸湾、白虎に甲州街道と四神相応に則っている点とされる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">One reason why the Tokugawa clan chose the Edo Castle as its main residence is that Edo was believed to have Shijin-soo (an ideal topography for the four Taoist gods, with a river in the east, a broad avenue in the west, a basin in the south, and a hill in the north); it was considered that in the original Edo town, Genbu (god of water) resided in Kojimachi highland in the north of the Castle, Seiryu (Blue Dragon) in Kanda-gawa River in the east, Suzaku (red Chinese phoenix) in Hibiya cove in the south, and Byakko (White Tiger) in To-kaido Road in the west, and after the expansion of Edo, Genbu was placed in Hongo highland (Bunkyo Ward), Seiryu in O-kawa River (Sumida-gawa River), Suzaku in Edo bay and Byakko in Koshu-kaido Road.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">One reason why the Tokugawa clan chose the Edo Castle as its primary residence was that the geographical location of Edo was ideally aligned with shijin-soo philosopy that sought geographic analogs of the four Daoist gods Genbu (God of Water), Suzaku (Red Phoenix), Seiryu (Blue Dragon) and Byakko (White Tiger) respectively manifest in the geographic forms of hills in the north, a basin to the south, a river in the east, and a broad avenue to the west; Such geographic analogs of geomantic ideals were manifest in the Kojimachi plateau to the north, the Hibiya Inlet to the south, the Kanda-gawa River in the east, and the Tokai-do road to the west; the geographic analogs of geomantic ideals were respectively reconfigured to the Hongo highlands (Bunkyo Ward), Edo bay, O-kawa River (Sumida-gawa River), and the Koshu-kaido Road in response to the growth of Edo.</e>
<cmt>Significant stylistic changes (Elements rearranged to a north, south, east, and west order to simplify the passage.)</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">One reason why the Tokugawa clan chose the Edo Castle as its primary residence was that the geographical location of Edo was ideally aligned with shijin-soo philosopy that sought geographic analogs of the four Daoist gods Genbu (God of Water), Suzaku (Red Phoenix), Seiryu (Blue Dragon) and Byakko (White Tiger) respectively manifest in the geographic forms of hills in the north, a basin to the south, a river in the east, and a broad avenue to the west; Such geographic analogs of geomantic ideals were manifest in the Kojimachi plateau to the north, the Hibiya Inlet to the south, the Kanda-gawa River in the east, and the Tokai-do road to the west; the geographic analogs of geomantic ideals were respectively reconfigured to the Hongo highlands (Bunkyo Ward), Edo bay, O-kawa River (Sumida-gawa River), and the Koshu-kaido Road in response to the growth of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="156">
<j>関東の独立を掲げた武将で、代表的な怨霊でもある平将門を祭る神田明神は、大手門前（現在の首塚周辺）から、江戸城の鬼門にあたる駿河台へと移され、江戸惣鎮守として奉られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanda Myojin-Shine which enshrined TAIRA no Masakado, a samurai who aimed at the independence of the Kanto region and who later turned into the most famous vengeful ghost, was moved from Ote-mon Gate (present-day, the area around Kubi-zuka) to Surugadai in the northeast of the Edo Castle, the direction called Kimon (an unlucky direction in Onmyodo [yin-yang philosophy]), and Masakado was enshrined as the Shinto deity of Edo there.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanda Myojin-Shine which enshrined TAIRA no Masakado, a renown samurai who sought the independence of the Kanto region and who said to have later turned into a vengeful ghost, was relocated from Ote-mon Gate (The area surrounding the present day Kubi-zuka [Mound of Heads]) to Surugadai to the northeast of Edo Castle which was known as a kimon (Literally translated as the &quot;demons gate,&quot; which signified an inauspicious direction in Onmyodo [yin-yang philosophy]), and enshrined their as a Shinto deity and protector of Edo.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanda Myojin-Shine which enshrined TAIRA no Masakado, a renown samurai who sought the independence of the Kanto region and who said to have later turned into a vengeful ghost, was relocated from Ote-mon Gate (The area surrounding the present day Kubi-zuka [Mound of Heads]) to Surugadai to the northeast of Edo Castle which was known as a kimon (Literally translated as the &quot;demons gate,&quot; which signified an inauspicious direction in Onmyodo [yin-yang philosophy]), and enshrined their as a Shinto deity and protector of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="157">
<j>また、江戸城の建設にともなって城内にあった山王権現（現在の日枝神社）は裏鬼門である赤坂へと移される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, during the reconstruction of the Edo Castle, Sanno Gongen (present-day, Hie-jinja Shrine) was moved from the Castle compound to Akasaka in the southwest, the direction called Urakimon, another unlucky direction in Onmyodo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Additionally, the Sanno Gongen (present-day Hie-jinja Shrine) was relocated from the castle compound to Akasaka in the southwest where the Urakimon (literally translated as the back-demons&apos; gate) during the reconstruction of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>Unecessary capitals; stylistic changes, diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Additionally, the Sanno Gongen (present-day Hie-jinja Shrine) was relocated from the castle compound to Akasaka in the southwest where the Urakimon (literally translated as the back-demons&apos; gate) during the reconstruction of Edo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="158">
<j>更に、家康の帰依していた天台宗の僧天海が江戸城の鬼門にあたる上野忍岡を拝領、京都の鬼門封じである比叡山に倣って堂塔を建設し、1625年に寛永寺を開山した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Moreover, the monk of Tendai sect, Tenkai, whom Ieyasu strongly trusted, was granted the land called Ueno-Shinobugaoka in the Kimon direction, where he elected temple buildings and founded Kanei-ji Temple in 1625 to purify Kimon by following the method of Mt. Hiei in Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Moreover, Ieyasu entrusted land in Ueno-Shinobugaoka which faced the kimon to the Tenda sect monk Tenkai, who erected a stupa in the likeness of Mt. Hiei which contains the demon&apos;s gate (kimon) and founded the Kanei-ji Temple in 1625.</e>
<cmt>Diction; Stylistic changes</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Moreover, Ieyasu entrusted land in Ueno-Shinobugaoka which faced the kimon to the Tenda sect monk Tenkai, who erected a stupa in the likeness of Mt. Hiei which contains the demon&apos;s gate (kimon) and founded the Kanei-ji Temple in 1625.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="159">
<j>寛永寺の山号は東叡山、すなわち東の比叡山を意味しており、寺号は延暦寺と同じように建立時の年号から取られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The sango (the mountain name given to each temple) of Kanei-ji Temple was To-eizan, meaning Mt. Hiei-zan in the east, and the jigo (temple name) was named after the era in which the temple was elected, as was Enryaku-ji Temple (in Mt. Hiei) which was built in the Enryaku era.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;sango&quot; (A name bestowed to each temple.) for Kanei-ji Temple was Toei-zan, which meant the Mt. Hiei of the east; and its &quot;jigo&quot; (temple name) was the era in which the temple was erected-- akin to Enryaku-ji Temple (in Mt. Hiei) which was built in the Enryaku era.</e>
<cmt>Minor stylistic changes.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;sango&quot; (A name bestowed to each temple.) for Kanei-ji Temple was Toei-zan, which meant the Mt. Hiei of the east; and its &quot;jigo&quot; (temple name) was the era in which the temple was erected-- akin to Enryaku-ji Temple (in Mt. Hiei) which was built in the Enryaku era.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="24">
<sen id="160">
<j>江戸は海辺を埋め立てて作られた町のため、井戸を掘っても真水を十分に得ることができず、水の確保が問題となる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Edo was expanded on the redeemed seashore, wells in Edo did not give enough fresh water, and therefore, securing fresh water became a challenge for the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Water security became an issue for Edo as it grew, since it was a town built over reclaimed shoreline, and digging wells alone could not secure ample fresh water.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Water security became an issue for Edo as it grew, since it was a town built over reclaimed shoreline, and digging wells alone could not secure ample fresh water.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="161">
<j>そこで、赤坂に元からあった溜池が活用されると共に、井の頭池を水源とする神田上水が造られた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a solution, not only a reservoir in Akasaka was utilized, but also the Kanda Josui Water Supply was built to bring water from Inokashira Pond.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a solution, the Kanda Waterworks that was fed by water from from Inokashira Pond, and a prexisting reservoir in Akasaka were used to supply water to the city.</e>
<cmt>Stylistic changes; diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a solution, the Kanda Waterworks that was fed by water from from Inokashira Pond, and a prexisting reservoir in Akasaka were used to supply water to the city.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="162">
<j>やがて江戸の人口が増えて来るとこれだけでは供給し切れなくなり、水不足が深刻になって来た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As a population of Edo grew larger, these two systems could not supply enough water to the people, and water shortage became a serious issue.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">As a population of Edo grew larger, these two systems could no longer supply enough water to the populace, and the city faced serious water shortages.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">As a population of Edo grew larger, these two systems could no longer supply enough water to the populace, and the city faced serious water shortages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="163">
<j>このために造られた水道が1653年完成の玉川上水である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">To combat the problem, another water supply, the Tamagawa Josui Water Supply, was built in 1653.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Tamagawa Waterworks was built in 1653 to alleviate such shortages.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Tamagawa Waterworks was built in 1653 to alleviate such shortages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="164">
<j>水道は江戸っ子の自慢の物の一つで、「水道の水を産湯に使い」などと言う言葉がよく使われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This water supply was one of what Edo people were very proud of, and they often said that &apos;I used tap water to give my baby its first bath&apos;.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The water works were a source of pride for the peoploe of Edo, and they are noted as saying that &quot;[they] used tap water to give [their] newborns [their] first bath.&quot;</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The water works were a source of pride for the peoploe of Edo, and they are noted as saying that &quot;[they] used tap water to give [their] newborns [their] first bath.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="25">
<sen id="165">
<j>1640年には江戸城の工事が最終的に完成し、江戸の都市建設はひとつの終着点に達した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1640, the reconstruction of the Edo Castle was completed, and the urbanization of the Edo town also ended with a fair amount of achievement.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The reconstruction of the Edo Castle was completed in 1640, marking one end point in the urban development of Edo.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The reconstruction of the Edo Castle was completed in 1640, marking one end point in the urban development of Edo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="166">
<j>しかし、1657年に明暦の大火が起こると江戸の町は大部分が焼亡し、江戸城天守も炎上してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the Great Fire of Meireki occurred in 1657, burning down most of Edo, and the tenshu (tower) of the Edo Castel burst into flames as well.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, most of the city including the tenshu (tower) of Edo Castle was destroyed during the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, most of the city including the tenshu (tower) of Edo Castle was destroyed during the Great Fire of Meireki in 1657.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="167">
<j>幕府はこれ以降、火事をできるだけ妨げられるよう都市計画を変更することになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the fire, bakufu changed its urbanization plan, placing more focus on prevention of fires.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the fire, the bakufu revised its urban planning policies to minimize the risk of fire hazards.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the fire, the bakufu revised its urban planning policies to minimize the risk of fire hazards.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="168">
<j>これまで吹上にあった御三家の屋敷が半蔵門外の紀尾井町に移されるなど大名屋敷の配置換えが行われ、類焼を防ぐための火除地として十分な広さの空き地や庭園が設けられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Residences of daimyo were relocated, the mansions of Tokugawa gosanke in Fukiage were also moved to Kioi-cho Town outside the Manzo-mon Gate, and large empty lots and gardens were also set up to prevent spreads of fires into neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo residences such as as those of the Tokugawa gosanke in Fukiage were relocated to Kioi-cho Town outside the Manzo-mon Gate, and large empty lots and gardens were established to prevent fires from spreading to neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt>diction</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo residences such as as those of the Tokugawa gosanke in Fukiage were relocated to Kioi-cho Town outside the Manzo-mon Gate, and large empty lots and gardens were established to prevent fires from spreading to neighboring areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="26">
<sen id="169">
<j>大名屋敷が再建され、参勤交代のために多くの武士が滞在するようになると、彼らの生活を支えるため江戸の町は急速に復興するが、もはや外堀内の江戸の町は狭すぎる状態だった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">As Daimyo residences were being reconstructed and an increased number of samurai were moving in for the Sankinkotai system, the town of Edo revived quickly to support their lives, but in practical terms, the Edo town inside the outer moat was too small to accommodate all these people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The town of Edo recovered as daimyo reconstructed their residences and as an ever increasing number of samurai migrated to the city in accordance to the Sankinkotai system, the town of Edo rapidly recovered to support their needs; but in practical terms, the town of Edo could not longer be contained within its outer moat.</e>
<cmt>diction; style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The town of Edo recovered as daimyo reconstructed their residences and as an ever increasing number of samurai migrated to the city in accordance to the Sankinkotai system, the town of Edo rapidly recovered to support their needs; but in practical terms, the town of Edo could not longer be contained within its outer moat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="170">
<j>こうして江戸の町の拡大が始まり、隅田川の対岸、深川・永代島まで都市化が進んでいった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The surge in population made the town expand even more, and Fukagawa and Eitaijima, which were located in the opposite shore of Sumida-gawa River, were also urbanized.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is within this context that the town of Edo began to expand, urbanization spread beyond the banks of the Sumida-gawa and Fukagawa-rivers, and advanced to Eitai-jima.</e>
<cmt>diction; style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is within this context that the town of Edo began to expand, urbanization spread beyond the banks of the Sumida-gawa and Fukagawa-rivers, and advanced to Eitai-jima.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="171">
<j>南・西・北にも都市化の波は及び、外延部の上野 (台東区)、浅草が盛り場として発展、さらに外側には吉原遊郭が置かれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The urbanization also began in the south, west and north of Edo, and Ueno (Taito Ward) and Asakusa, both on the edge of Edo, were developed into an amusement area surrounded by Yoshihara yukaku (red-light district).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The urbanization also began in the south, west and north of Edo, and Ueno (Taito Ward) and Asakusa on the peripheries of Edo developed into amusement districts, and the Yoshiwara yukaku (red-light district) became located outside of this area.</e>
<cmt>diction; style</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The urbanization also began in the south, west and north of Edo, and Ueno (Taito Ward) and Asakusa on the peripheries of Edo developed into amusement districts, and the Yoshiwara yukaku (red-light district) became located outside of this area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="9">
<tit>
<j>神社仏閣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shrines and temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shrines and temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shrines and temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="10">
<tit>
<j>神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinto shrines</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinto shrines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinto shrines</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="172">
<j>神田明神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanda Myojin-Shine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanda Myojin-Shine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanda Myojin-Shine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="173">
<j>日枝神社（日枝神社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hie-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hie-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hie-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="174">
<j>根津神社（根津神社）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nezu-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nezu-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nezu-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="175">
<j>富岡八幡宮</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tomioka Hachiman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tomioka Hachiman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tomioka Hachiman-gu Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="176">
<j>築土神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tsukudo-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tsukudo-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tsukudo-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="177">
<j>鳥越神社</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Torigoe-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Torigoe-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Torigoe-jinja Shrine</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="178">
<j>湯島天神</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushima tenjin</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushima tenjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushima tenjin</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="11">
<tit>
<j>寺院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Buddhist Temples</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Buddhist Temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Buddhist Temples</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="179">
<j>浅草寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senso-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senso-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senso-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="180">
<j>寛永寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kanei-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kanei-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kanei-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="181">
<j>増上寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zojo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zojo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zojo-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="182">
<j>伝通院</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Dentsu-in Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Dentsu-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Dentsu-in Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="183">
<j>護国寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gokoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gokoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gokoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="184">
<j>泉岳寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Sengaku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Sengaku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Sengaku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="185">
<j>廟</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mausoleum</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mausoleum</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="186">
<j>湯島聖堂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yushima Seido (Sacred Hall at Yushima)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yushima Seido (Sacred Hall at Yushima)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yushima Seido (Sacred Hall at Yushima)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="12">
<tit>
<j>江戸近郊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suburbs of Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suburbs of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suburbs of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="187">
<j>目黒不動（瀧泉寺）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meguro Fudo (Ryusen-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meguro Fudo (Ryusen-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meguro Fudo (Ryusen-ji Temple)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="188">
<j>池上本門寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ikegami Honmon-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="189">
<j>柴又帝釈天</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shibamata Taishakuten</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shibamata Taishakuten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shibamata Taishakuten</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="190">
<j>東海寺 (東京都品川区)</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tokai-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tokai-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tokai-ji Temple (Shinagawa Ward, Tokyo Metropolis)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="13">
<tit>
<j>豪徳寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gotoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gotoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gotoku-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="191">
<j>- 彦根井伊家の菩提寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The family temple of the Hikone Ii family</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The family temple of the Hikone Ii family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The family temple of the Hikone Ii family</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="192">
<j>深大寺</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Jindai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Jindai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Jindai-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="193">
<j>武蔵国分寺跡</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Remains of the Musashi Kokubun-ji Temple</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Remains of the Musashi Kokubun-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Remains of the Musashi Kokubun-ji Temple</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="14">
<tit>
<j>江戸の生活と文化</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Life and culture of Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Life and culture of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Life and culture of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="15">
<tit>
<j>娯楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Entertainment</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Entertainment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Entertainment</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="194">
<j>行楽（参詣、花見、月見、紅葉狩り、雪見など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Outing (visiting temples and shrines, cherry blossom viewing, moon viewing, autumn leaves viewing and snow viewing)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Outing (visiting temples and shrines, cherry blossom viewing, moon viewing, autumn leaves viewing and snow viewing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Outing (visiting temples and shrines, cherry blossom viewing, moon viewing, autumn leaves viewing and snow viewing)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="16">
<tit>
<j>江戸近郊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Suburbs of Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Suburbs of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Suburbs of Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="195">
<j>- 飛鳥山、武蔵野、深大寺詣で、小金井桜、富士塚</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Mt. Asuka-yama, Musashino and a visit to Jindai-ji Temple, cherry blossoms in Koganei and the Fujizuka Mound</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Mt. Asuka-yama, Musashino and a visit to Jindai-ji Temple, cherry blossoms in Koganei and the Fujizuka Mound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Mt. Asuka-yama, Musashino and a visit to Jindai-ji Temple, cherry blossoms in Koganei and the Fujizuka Mound</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="17">
<tit>
<j>江戸から関東各地</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">From Edo to Kanto provinces</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">From Edo to Kanto provinces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">From Edo to Kanto provinces</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="196">
<j>- 大山 (神奈川県)詣で、富士講</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A visit to Mt. Daisen and climbing and praying of Mt. Fuji</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A visit to Mt. Daisen and climbing and praying of Mt. Fuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A visit to Mt. Daisen and climbing and praying of Mt. Fuji</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="197">
<j>歌舞伎 - 市川團十郎 - 十八番、浄瑠璃（人形浄瑠璃、常磐津など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kabuki - Danjuro ICHIKAWA - Ohako (one&apos;s forte) - Joruri (Ballad drama) (ningyo joruri [traditional Japanese puppet theater] and Tokiwazu [Theatrical music])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kabuki - Danjuro ICHIKAWA - Ohako (one&apos;s forte) - Joruri (Ballad drama) (ningyo joruri [traditional Japanese puppet theater] and Tokiwazu [Theatrical music])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kabuki - Danjuro ICHIKAWA - Ohako (one&apos;s forte) - Joruri (Ballad drama) (ningyo joruri [traditional Japanese puppet theater] and Tokiwazu [Theatrical music])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="198">
<j>落語、講談</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">rakugo (comic story telling) and kodan (storytelling)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">rakugo (comic story telling) and kodan (storytelling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">rakugo (comic story telling) and kodan (storytelling)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="199">
<j>錦絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nishiki-e (colored woodblock print)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nishiki-e (colored woodblock print)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nishiki-e (colored woodblock print)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="18">
<tit>
<j>浮世絵</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ukiyo-e (Japanese woodblock prints)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ukiyo-e (Japanese woodblock prints)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ukiyo-e (Japanese woodblock prints)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="200">
<j>- 葛飾北斎、歌川広重、東洲斎写楽</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA, Hiroshige UTAGAWA, Sharaku TOSHUSAI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA, Hiroshige UTAGAWA, Sharaku TOSHUSAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Hokusai KATSUSHIKA, Hiroshige UTAGAWA, Sharaku TOSHUSAI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="19">
<tit>
<j>黄表紙本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kibyoshi bon (the illustrated book with yellow covers)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kibyoshi bon (the illustrated book with yellow covers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kibyoshi bon (the illustrated book with yellow covers)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="201">
<j>- 戯作、洒落本</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Gesaku (the light literature), Sharebon book (a gay-quarter novelette)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Gesaku (the light literature), Sharebon book (a gay-quarter novelette)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Gesaku (the light literature), Sharebon book (a gay-quarter novelette)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="20">
<tit>
<j>俳諧</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Haikai (seventeen-syllable verse)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="202">
<j>- 松尾芭蕉、小林一茶</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basho MATSUO, Issa KOBAYASHI</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basho MATSUO, Issa KOBAYASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basho MATSUO, Issa KOBAYASHI</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="21">
<tit>
<j>花火</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fireworks</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fireworks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fireworks</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="203">
<j>- 玉屋、鍵屋</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tamaya, Kagiya</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tamaya, Kagiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tamaya, Kagiya</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="204">
<j>風呂</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furo (bath)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furo (bath)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furo (bath)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="22">
<tit>
<j>服装</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Costumes</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Costumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Costumes</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="205">
<j>着物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kimono</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kimono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kimono</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="206">
<j>振袖</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furisode (kimono with long, trailing sleeves)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furisode (kimono with long, trailing sleeves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furisode (kimono with long, trailing sleeves)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="207">
<j>浴衣</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yukata (an informal cotton kimono)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yukata (an informal cotton kimono)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yukata (an informal cotton kimono)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="208">
<j>履物</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Footwear</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Footwear</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Footwear</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="209">
<j>下駄 足駄 草履 雪駄</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Geta (Japanese wooden sandals), Ashida (wooden clogs), Zori (Japanese straw sandals), Setta(Japanese leather-soled sandals)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Geta (Japanese wooden sandals), Ashida (wooden clogs), Zori (Japanese straw sandals), Setta(Japanese leather-soled sandals)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Geta (Japanese wooden sandals), Ashida (wooden clogs), Zori (Japanese straw sandals), Setta(Japanese leather-soled sandals)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="23">
<tit>
<j>食事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meals</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meals</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="210">
<j>百珍（豆腐百珍、卵百珍など）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Delicacy (Tofu hyakuchin [100 Tofu delicacies], Egg hyakuchin [100 egg delicacies])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Delicacy (Tofu hyakuchin [100 Tofu delicacies], Egg hyakuchin [100 egg delicacies])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Delicacy (Tofu hyakuchin [100 Tofu delicacies], Egg hyakuchin [100 egg delicacies])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="211">
<j>初カツオ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bonito in early season</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bonito in early season</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bonito in early season</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="212">
<j>蕎麦飯</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soba rice (rice with noodles made from buckwheat)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soba rice (rice with noodles made from buckwheat)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soba rice (rice with noodles made from buckwheat)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="213">
<j>雑炊</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Zoshi (rice gruel)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Zoshi (rice gruel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Zoshi (rice gruel)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="214">
<j>沢庵漬け</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takuanzuke (yellow pickled radish)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takuanzuke (yellow pickled radish)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takuanzuke (yellow pickled radish)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="215">
<j>江戸前寿司</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edomae-zushi (hand-rolled sushi)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edomae-zushi (hand-rolled sushi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edomae-zushi (hand-rolled sushi)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="216">
<j>蕎麦</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Soba (noodles made from buckwheat)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Soba (noodles made from buckwheat)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Soba (noodles made from buckwheat)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="217">
<j>天ぷら</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tenpura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tenpura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tenpura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="218">
<j>振売</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Furiuri (peddler)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Furiuri (peddler)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Furiuri (peddler)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="24">
<tit>
<j>諺・故事成語</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kotowaza (proverbs) and Koji Seigo (Chinese origin and proverb)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kotowaza (proverbs) and Koji Seigo (Chinese origin and proverb)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kotowaza (proverbs) and Koji Seigo (Chinese origin and proverb)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="219">
<j>江戸前</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edomae (Tokyo style)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edomae (Tokyo style)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edomae (Tokyo style)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="220">
<j>火事と喧嘩は江戸の華 &gt;&gt;江戸の火事</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kaji to Kenka ha Edo no Hana (literally, fires and fighting are flowers in Edo &gt;&gt; fires in Edo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kaji to Kenka ha Edo no Hana (literally, fires and fighting are flowers in Edo &gt;&gt; fires in Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kaji to Kenka ha Edo no Hana (literally, fires and fighting are flowers in Edo &gt;&gt; fires in Edo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="221">
<j>江戸の敵を長崎で討つ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo no Teki wo Nagasaki de Utsu (literally, avenge the deteat in Edo in Nagasaki. [Avenge oneself on a person in an unlikely place])</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo no Teki wo Nagasaki de Utsu (literally, avenge the deteat in Edo in Nagasaki. [Avenge oneself on a person in an unlikely place])</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo no Teki wo Nagasaki de Utsu (literally, avenge the enemy from Edo in Nagasaki).</e>
<cmt>deteat　in　Edoを意味不明のため、enemy　from　Edoに変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="222">
<j>江戸っ子は宵越しの銭は持たぬ</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edokko ha Yoigoshi no Kane ha Motanu (literally, those born in Edo spend all of the day&apos;s eanings before midnight)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edokko ha Yoigoshi no Kane ha Motanu (literally, those born in Edo spend all of the day&apos;s eanings before midnight)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edokko ha Yoigoshi no Kane ha Motanu (literally, those born in Edo spend all of the day&apos;s earnings before midnight)</e>
<cmt>eaningsをearningsにスペル修正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="223">
<j>江戸っ子は五月の鯉の吹き流し</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edokko ha Gogatsu no Koi no Fukinagashi (litarally, those born in Edo move from one place to another like a cloth streamer blown by May winds)</e>
<cmt>http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:W_HFSRi51y0J:sajun.org/index.php/Japanese_proverbs+%E6%B1%9F%E6%88%B8%E3%81%A3%E5%AD%90%E3%81%AF%E4%BA%94%E6%9C%88%E3%81%AE%E9%AF%89%E3%81%AE%E5%90%B9%E3%81%8D%E6%B5%81%E3%81%97%E3%80%80edo&amp;cd=4&amp;hl=ja&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=jp</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edokko ha Gogatsu no Koi no Fukinagashi (litarally, those born in Edo move from one place to another like a cloth streamer blown by May winds)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edokko ha Gogatsu no Koi no Fukinagashi (litarally, those born in Edo move from one place to another like a cloth streamer blown by May winds)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="224">
<j>江戸っ子の梨を食うよう</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edokko no Nashi wo Kuu you (those born in Edo are frank)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edokko no Nashi wo Kuu you (those born in Edo are frank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edokko no Nashi wo Kuu you (those born in Edo are frank)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="225">
<j>江戸っ子の初もの食い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edokko no Hatsumono Gui (those born in Edo like to eat first fruits of a season to show it off)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edokko no Hatsumono Gui (those born in Edo like to eat first fruits of a season to show it off)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edokko no Hatsumono Gui (those born in Edo like to eat first fruits of a season to show it off)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="226">
<j>江戸っ子の産れ損なひ金を貯め</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edokko no Umare zokonai Kane wo Tame (failed children of Edo tend to save a lot of money)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edokko no Umare zokonai Kane wo Tame (failed children of Edo tend to save a lot of money)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edokko no Umare zokonai Kane wo Tame (failed children of Edo tend to save a lot of money)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Poppy(id:6431), 0null0(id:582), DragonBot(id:161936), 天然ガス(id:98149), HI(id:72996), Lupinoid(id:68), ＲＪＡＮＫＡ(id:118019), Tribot(id:186681), Mishika(id:276), Alex K(id:86829), るがこむ(id:181), Yujiyosi(id:54807), Opponent(id:720), Natunohi(id:6550), ぎゅうひ(id:9206), AlnoktaBOT(id:135808), NoriBeat(id:2074), 永井こうじ(id:148220), WikiBotas(id:144938), みらい(id:14772), 日陰のコスモス(id:3802), IwaimBot(id:190695), Knua(id:66861), 汲平(id:18186), Point136(id:211299), Shimoxx(id:9332), Morio(id:35464), Chao35(id:34986), Ata(id:3587), ウィキ豊(id:82961), Newt(id:218172), Kurayamizaka(id:7150), 浩(id:70121), Osu-mike(id:61051), たね(id:10372), ちちぶ(id:184715), ZZZ(id:9462), BOT-Superzerocool(id:65015), Martin(id:6394), BodhisattvaBot(id:185411), Himetv(id:21833), MDR-SK(id:192066), Rusk(id:9895), Thijs!bot(id:69644), Villeneuve1982(id:22620), きたし(id:81414), Beagle(id:45036), SuisuiBot(id:10165), ヤマト(id:8425), Mdem(id:42519), Ribbon(id:172), ヒスタミン(id:63497), トホホ川(id:50502), Orichalcum(id:33360), Kitab-al-Azif(id:163278), NIKE(id:16342), Junger(id:10282), Nog(id:53565), JAnDbot(id:66507), 水原怜雅(id:62300), Andre Engels(id:202), Πrate(id:11329), MIsogi(id:20599), Reggaeman(id:6214), Urania(id:7213), Cassiopeia sweet(id:29811), Edo1800(id:313474), Im224(id:57113), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Charon(id:9162), やしろべえ(id:73200), Kogane(id:28186), Mintleaf(id:2216), LifeGuards(id:159934), ミッキーマウスのぬいぐるみ(id:80103), Ganman(id:96316), Ekakinomachi(id:71650), 16toki(id:60127), Chobot(id:20846), うぃき野郎(id:53567), 竹麦魚(id:11012), 越中掾(id:149423), Iiyaman(id:193472), Ognirdaed(id:174660), Kentin(id:6768), Izayohi(id:13095), ととりん(id:31982), 水野白楓(id:22811), Kalz(id:92749), Juyukichi(id:16958), Koh-etsu(id:55555), Sat.K(id:3751), Yanahan(id:2437), R2c2(id:45847), Robbot(id:3063), Shinkansen(id:13703), Vina-iwbot(id:56449), Carkuni(id:79281), L26(id:119681), VolkovBot(id:105371), アンサイクロペディアン(id:89886), N yotarou(id:60870), MS472(id:58603), Fievarsty(id:201483), Corwin(id:973), Safkan(id:423), SieBot(id:126695), Katsuya(id:21306), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>