<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>宝亀の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoki no Ran</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hoki War (the rebellion of Emishi in Rikuzen Province in the Nara period)</e>
<cmt>用語を変え、補足しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hoki War (the rebellion of Emishi in Rikuzen Province in the Nara period)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>宝亀の乱（ほうきのらん）は奈良時代に東北地方（後の陸前国）で蝦夷が起こした反乱である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Hoki no Ran is the rebellion which Ezo caused in Tohoku region (Rikuzen Province in the later period) in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hoki War was the rebellion of Emishi (natives of the Japanese islands of Hokkaido and northern Honshu that opposed and resisted the rule of the Japanese Emperors) in Tohoku region (later Rikuzen Province) in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hoki War was the rebellion of Emishi (natives of the Japanese islands of Hokkaido and northern Honshu that opposed and resisted the rule of the Japanese Emperors) in Tohoku region (later Rikuzen Province) in the Nara period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>首謀者の名から、伊治呰麻呂の乱（これはりのあざまろのらん）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called KOREHARI no Azamaro no Ran by the name of ringleader.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called the KOREHARI no Azamaro War by the name of the ringleader.</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called the KOREHARI no Azamaro War by the name of the ringleader.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>乱の原因</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Cause of Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Cause of the War</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Cause of the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>伊治呰麻呂（これはりのきみあざまろ、これはるのきみあざまろ）は、陸奥国府に仕える俘囚の指導者で、上治郡（此治郡の誤記として「これはりぐん」、「これはるぐん」とする見解が有力）大領となり、蝦夷征討の功により宝亀9年6月25日 (旧暦)（778年7月24日）には外従五位下に叙されていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">KOREHARI no Kimi Azamaro was a leader of the barbarians who served Mutsu Province and became Dairyou of Kamihari-gun (The view that advocates that this is a writing error of KOREHARI-gun or Koreharu-gun is dominant); he was conferred Gejugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, given to persons outside Kyoto) in the Hoki era June 25, 9 (in the old calendar) (July 24, 778) by success of subjection of indigenous inhabitants in eastern Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">KOREHARI no Azamaro (also known as KOREHARI no Kimi Azamaro or KOREHARU no Kimi Azamaro), the leader of the barbarians who served the provincial office of Mutsu Province, became Tairyo (the director of the County) of Kamihari County (from the major view, it was a writing error of &apos;Korehari County&apos; or &apos;Koreharu County&apos;) and conferred Gejugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, given to persons outside Kyoto) in July 28, 778 for the success of the subjection of the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>用語、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">KOREHARI no Azamaro (also known as KOREHARI no Kimi Azamaro or KOREHARU no Kimi Azamaro), the leader of the barbarians who served the provincial office of Mutsu Province, became Tairyo (the director of the County) of Kamihari County (from the major view, it was a writing error of &apos;Korehari County&apos; or &apos;Koreharu County&apos;) and conferred Gejugoinoge (Junior Fifth Rank, Lower Grade, given to persons outside Kyoto) in July 28, 778 for the success of the subjection of the Emishi.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>『続日本紀』には、陸奥按察使紀広純は、はじめ呰麻呂を嫌ったが、後にはなはだ信用するようになったこと、しかし同じ俘囚出身である牡鹿郡大領の道嶋大盾は呰麻呂を見下して夷俘として侮り、呰麻呂は内心深く恨んでいたことが記載されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to &quot;Shoku Nihonngi (Chronicle of Japan Continued),&quot; the Inspector of Mutsu (Mutsu no azuchi) KI no Hirozumi disliked Azamaro at first, but later he came to trust Azamaro; however, Dairyo of Oshika-gun, MICHISHIMA no Otate, who was the same barbarian as Azamaro, looked down on Azamaro and brought Azamaro into contempt as Azamaro was If (Emishi); accordingly Azamaro&apos;s heart bore a deep grudge against Otate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that the Inspector of Mutsu (Mutsu no azuchi) KI no Hirozumi disliked Azamaro at first then fully trusted him later, but Azamaro secretly bore a deep grudge against MICHISHIMA no Otate, Dairyo of Oshika County, who was the same barbarian as Azamaro, looked down on Azamaro as Ifu (Emishi).</e>
<cmt>表記、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot; (Chronicle of Japan Continued) describes that the Inspector of Mutsu (Mutsu no azuchi) KI no Hirozumi disliked Azamaro at first then fully trusted him later, but Azamaro secretly bore a deep grudge against MICHISHIMA no Otate, Dairyo of Oshika County, who was the same barbarian as Azamaro, looked down on Azamaro as Ifu (Emishi).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>このことから乱の原因については一般に怨恨説が取られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Because of this description seen in &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; the grudge theory is most common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">By this description, the theory that the grudge caused the war is most common.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">By this description, the theory that the grudge caused the war is most common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="7">
<j>乱の経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Course of the Rebellion</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Course of the War</e>
<cmt>用語を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Course of the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>宝亀11年3月22日 (旧暦)（780年5月1日）、紀広純が覚べつ城建設を建議し伊治城を訪れた機会をとらえた呰麻呂は、俘囚の軍（俘軍）を動かして反乱を起こし、まず大盾を殺し、次に広純を多勢で囲んで殺した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the 22nd of March in Hoki 11 (the old calendar) (May 1, 780), KI no Hirozumi proposed the construction of Kakubetsu-jo Castle and visited Korehari-jo Castle; Azamaro, who caught this opportunity, moved the armed forces of barbarians (military of barbarians), and woke up rebellion; at first he killed Otate; next killed Hizozumi by surrounding him with many soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 5, 780 when KI no Hirozumi visited Korehari-jo Castle proposing the construction of Kakubetsu-jo Castle, Azamaro, who caught this opportunity, moved the armed forces of barbarians (military of barbarians), and woke up rebellion to kill Otate at first, then Hirozumi surrounding with many soldiers.</e>
<cmt>スペル、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 5, 780 when KI no Hirozumi visited Korehari-jo Castle proposing the construction of Kakubetsu-jo Castle, Azamaro, who caught this opportunity, moved the armed forces of barbarians (military of barbarians), and woke up rebellion to kill Otate at first, then Hirozumi surrounding with many soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>陸奥介大伴真綱だけは囲みを開いて多賀城に護送されたが、城下の住民が多賀城の中に入って城を守ろうとしたのに対し、真綱と掾の石川浄足はともに後門から隠れて逃げ、住民もやむなく散り散りになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Azamaro stopped his enveloping attack only for Mutsu no suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) Matsuna OTOMO and Matsuna was escorted to Taga-jo Castle; the residents in the castle town tried to enter the Taga-jo Castle and tried to protect the castle; however, Mutsu no Jo ISHIKAWA no Kiyotari and Matsuna escaped together secretly from the back gate; so residents scattered out of necessity.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Azamaro stopped his enveloping attack only for Mutsu no suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) Matsuna OTOMO and transferred him to Taga-jo Castle, while, the residents in the castle town entering the Taga-jo Castle tried to protect it, however, ISHIKAWA no Kiyotari, the jo (secretary of provincial offices), and Matsuna escaped together secretly from the rear gate then the residents scattered out of necessity.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Azamaro stopped his enveloping attack only for Mutsu no suke (assistant governor of Mutsu Province) Matsuna OTOMO and transferred him to Taga-jo Castle, while, the residents in the castle town entering the Taga-jo Castle tried to protect it, however, ISHIKAWA no Kiyotari, the jo (secretary of provincial offices), and Matsuna escaped together secretly from the rear gate then the residents scattered out of necessity.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>数日後に俘囚軍は多賀城で略奪放火をして去ったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that after several days the military of barbarians plundered at Taga-jo Castle and left the castle after setting fire.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that after several days the military of barbarians left the Taga-jo Castle after plundered and set fire.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that after several days the military of barbarians left the Taga-jo Castle after plundered and set fire.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>当時多賀城の倉庫には、「兵器粮蓄、勝げて計うるべからず」（『続日本紀』）とある。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At that time in the warehouse of Taga-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At that time, in the warehouse of the Taga-jo Castle,&apos;the storage of weapons and foods were not enough to win the battle&apos; (in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>原文が途中で分割されていたため1文にし、原文に合わせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At that time, in the warehouse of the Taga-jo Castle,&apos;the storage of weapons and foods were not enough to win the battle&apos; (in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>しかし、正史の記録は以後の経過を記さない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the record of official history does not go any further on this matter.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the record of official history does not go any further on this matter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the record of official history does not go any further on this matter.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>多賀城の略奪についても、その指揮官は不明であり、征東大使藤原継縄の投入後も戦闘は拡大したと見られている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In terms of the plunder of the Taga-jo Castle, the commander is not known; e, it is considered that even after the addition of Seito Taishi (great general who subdues the eastern barbarians) FUJIWARA no Tsugutada the battle was further expanded.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The commander of the plunder of the Taga-jo Castle is unknown as well, it is considered that even after Seito Taishi (great general who subdues the eastern barbarians) FUJIWARA no Tsugutada joined, the battle was further expanded.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The commander of the plunder of the Taga-jo Castle is unknown as well, it is considered that even after Seito Taishi (great general who subdues the eastern barbarians) FUJIWARA no Tsugutada joined, the battle was further expanded.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="14">
<j>戦後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the War</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the War</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>記録がないために戦闘の終了時期は不明だが、9月には藤原小黒麻呂が征東大使となり、翌天応 (日本)元年（781年）には「征伐事畢入朝」と『続日本紀』に見えることから乱は終結に向かったと推察されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The time the battle ended is not known because no records exist, but in September Taishi FUJIWARA no Oguromaro became the Seito Taishi; as an event of the following year (781), we can see such descriptions &apos;the subjugation was done&apos; in &quot;Shoku Nihongi&quot;, it seems that the rebellion was subdued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The time the battle ended is unknown since no records exist, however, considering the description of &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; as FUJIWARA no Oguromaro became the Seito Taishi in October and &apos;the subjugation was done&apos; in 781, the following year, it is estimated that the war was subdued then.</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に直し、表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The time the battle ended is unknown since no records exist, however, considering the description of &quot;Shoku Nihongi,&quot; as FUJIWARA no Oguromaro became the Seito Taishi in October and &apos;the subjugation was done&apos; in 781, the following year, it is estimated that the war was subdued then.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>しかし「遺衆猶多」と残党が多くいたことも見えている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&apos;Shoku Nihongi, however, writes that &apos;there are still many remnants,&apos; so we can see that there were still many remnants.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, it is written that &apos;there are still many remnants&apos; as well.</e>
<cmt>表現を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, it is written that &apos;there are still many remnants&apos; as well.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Carkuni(id:79281), 味っ子(id:17086), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), アヒャってる人(id:100527), Libertas(id:40611), Law soma(id:45202), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>