<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>観音寺騒動</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kannonji family feud</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kannonji family feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kannonji family feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>観音寺騒動（かんのんじそうどう）は、戦国時代 (日本)の永禄6年（1563年）に、南近江国の戦国大名・六角氏の家中で起こった御家騒動。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kannonji family feud is the family trouble that broke out in the family of Rokkaku clan that was a warring load of Minami Omi Province in 1563 during the Sengoku period (the Warring State Period of Japan).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kannonji family feud is the family trouble that broke out in the family of Rokkaku clan that was a warring load of Minami Omi Province in 1563 during the Sengoku period (the Warring State Period of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kannonji family feud is the family trouble that broke out in the family of Rokkaku clan that was a warring load of Minami Omi Province in 1563 during the Sengoku period (the Warring State Period of Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>事件の概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary of the feud</e>
<cmt>原文通りに訳しました</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary of the feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>六角氏は六角定頼が当主（あるいは陣代）の時代、北近江の戦国大名であった浅井氏を事実上の支配下に置き、さらに室町幕府からも管領代の地位を与えられるなどして全盛期を迎えていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokkaku clan entered into the height of its prosperity when Sadayori ROKKAKU was the family head (or Jindai, a deputy whose role was to proceed to battlefield on behalf of his load during the Muromachi period thereafter) and dominated in effect Azai clan who was the warring load of Kita Omi Province, besides he was assigned for Kanrei-dai (representative of a shogunal deputy) by Muromachi Shougunate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Sadayori ROKKAKU was the family head (or Jindai, a deputy whose role was to proceed to battlefield on behalf of his load during the Muromachi period thereafter), Rokkaku clan entered into the height of its prosperity such as dominating in effect the Azai clan who was the warring load of Kita Omi Province and being granted the post of Kanrei-dai (representative of a shogunal deputy) by Muromachi Shougunate.</e>
<cmt>若干、原文とニュアンスが異なる部分がありましたので、文全体を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Sadayori ROKKAKU was the family head (or Jindai, a deputy whose role was to proceed to battlefield on behalf of his load during the Muromachi period thereafter), Rokkaku clan entered into the height of its prosperity such as dominating in effect the Azai clan who was the warring load of Kita Omi Province and being granted the post of Kanrei-dai (representative of a shogunal deputy) by Muromachi Shougunate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>定頼の死後、後を継いだ六角義賢は、当時管領代となり、畿内に一大政権を築きつつあった三好長慶と抗争して、中央政界での勢力を拡大しようとしたがこれに失敗。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Sadayori, his successor Yosikata ROKKAKU attacked Nagayoshi MIYOSHI who was then Kanrei-dai and started building up a strong political power in Kinai area and tried in vain to expand his strength among the national political arena.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Sadayori, his successor Yosikata ROKKAKU attacked Nagayoshi MIYOSHI who was then Kanrei-dai and started building up a strong political power in Kinai area and tried in vain to expand his strength among the national political arena.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Sadayori, his successor Yosikata ROKKAKU attacked Nagayoshi MIYOSHI who was then Kanrei-dai and started building up a strong political power in Kinai area and tried in vain to expand his strength among the national political arena.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>逆に六角氏の畿内における影響力は減退してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, the importance of Rokkaku clan declined in Kinai area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the contrary, the importance of Rokkaku clan declined in Kinai area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the contrary, the importance of Rokkaku clan declined in Kinai area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>そのうえ、定頼の死去を見て服属下にあった浅井氏が自立傾向を見せ始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Besides, Azai clan under domination by Rokkaku clan started to show signs of independence at the opportunity of the death of Sadayori.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Besides, Azai clan under domination by Rokkaku clan started to show signs of independence at the opportunity of the death of Sadayori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Besides, Azai clan under domination by Rokkaku clan started to show signs of independence at the opportunity of the death of Sadayori.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>永禄3年（1560年）、義賢は大軍を率いて浅井氏を討とうとしたが野良田の戦いで浅井長政に敗れた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1560, Yosikata intended to defeat Azai clan heading a battalion but was defeated by Nagamasa AZAI at the Battle of Norada.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1560, Yosikata intended to defeat Azai clan heading a battalion but was defeated by Nagamasa AZAI at the Battle of Norada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1560, Yosikata intended to defeat Azai clan heading a battalion but was defeated by Nagamasa AZAI at the Battle of Norada.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>近江佐々木氏の家中問題も絡み、六角義賢の近江における権威は低下した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosikata ROKKAKU declined his authority in Omi with the family trouble of Omi Sasaki clan too involved.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosikata ROKKAKU declined his authority in Omi with the family trouble of Omi Sasaki clan also involved.</e>
<cmt>too　を　also に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosikata ROKKAKU declined his authority in Omi with the family trouble of Omi Sasaki clan also involved.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>この前年に家督を子の六角義治に譲っていた義賢は、この敗戦を契機に出家する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yosikata, having handed over the patrimony to his son, Yoshiharu ROKKAKU, in the previous year, entered into priesthood taking the occasion of this defeat.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yosikata, who had handed over the patrimony to Yoshiharu ROKKAKU, his son in the previous year, entered into priesthood taking the occasion of this defeat.</e>
<cmt>文全体を訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yosikata, who had handed over the patrimony to Yoshiharu ROKKAKU, his son in the previous year, entered into priesthood taking the occasion of this defeat.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="9">
<j>跡を継いだ義治であるが、永禄6年に六角氏の有力な重臣であった後藤賢豊を観音寺城内において暗殺してしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Yoshiharu succeeded the patrimony, he had Katatoyo GOTO assassinated in the Kannonji Castle in 1560 who was an important chief retainer of Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>「観音寺騒動－Wikipedia」にて永禄6年＝１５６０を検索。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Yoshiharu succeeded the patrimony, he assassinated Katatoyo GOTO in the Kannonji Castle in 1563 who was an important chief retainer of Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>文法的なあやまりが見られたので(assassinatedの使い方）、訂正しました。また、永禄6年は、指定されたサイトで確認したところ1563年でした。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Yoshiharu succeeded the patrimony, he assassinated Katatoyo GOTO in the Kannonji Castle in 1563 who was an important chief retainer of Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>理由は諸説あるが、賢豊は定頼時代からの六角家中における功臣として人望も厚く、進藤貞治と共に「六角氏の両藤」と称されるほどの宿老で、奉行人として六角氏の当主代理として政務を執行できる権限を有していたことから、賢豊の権力と若年の当主・義治とが争った末に、当主としての執行権を取り戻すために暗殺したと言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Amongst various views of the background, it is said that Yoshiharu had Katatoyo assassinated in order to recover the authority as the family head, after struggles between Katatoyo&apos;s authority and the young family head Yosiharu since Katatoyo was such a well respected chief vassal as a meritorious retainer of Rokkaku clan since the period of Sadayori and well admired of as &quot;twin To (phonetic alphabet of 藤 後藤, GOTO and 進藤, SINDO) of Rokkaku clan&quot; that he held the authority to execute administrative affairs on behalf of the family head.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Amongst various views of the background, it is said that Yoshiharu assassinated Katatoyoin order to recover the authority as the family head, after struggles between Katatoyo&apos;s authority and Yosiharu, the young family head, since Katatoyo was such a well respected chief vassal as a meritorious retainer of Rokkaku clan since the period of Sadayori and well admired of as &quot;twin To (phonetic alphabet of 藤 後藤, GOTO and 進藤, SINDO) of Rokkaku clan&quot; that he held the authority to execute administrative affairs on behalf of the family head.</e>
<cmt>文法的なあやまりが見られたので(assassinatedの使い方）、訂正しました。また、the young family head を　Yoshiharu の後につけました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Amongst various views of the background, it is said that Yoshiharu assassinated Katatoyoin order to recover the authority as the family head, after struggles between Katatoyo&apos;s authority and Yosiharu, the young family head, since Katatoyo was such a well respected chief vassal as a meritorious retainer of Rokkaku clan since the period of Sadayori and well admired of as &quot;twin To (phonetic alphabet of 藤 後藤, GOTO and 進藤, SINDO) of Rokkaku clan&quot; that he held the authority to execute administrative affairs on behalf of the family head.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>事件後</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Aftermath of the Kannonji family feud</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Aftermath of the Kannonji family feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Aftermath of the Kannonji family feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="11">
<j>観音寺騒動は、六角氏の家臣団に大きな衝撃を与えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kannonji family feud caused a big impact on the vassals of Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kannonji family feud caused a big impact on the vassals of Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kannonji family feud caused a big impact on the vassals of Rokkaku clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>賢豊は前述したように重臣の筆頭格であり人望も厚かったから、この事件（義治が賢豊を討ち取った名目は無礼討ちとされていた）は、佐々木六角氏の家督問題と関係して六角家臣団の義治に対する不信を持たせることにつながった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since Katatoyo was regarded as the top of senior vassals and well respected as described above, this feud, the pretext why Yoshiharu killed Katatoyo being feigned to be bureiuchi (death penalty by sword slash for rudeness), led up to distrust of Yoshiharu among the feudatory of Rokkaku clan, connected with the trouble of reigns of the both families of Rokkaku clan and Sasaki clan, the latter being Rokkaku clan&apos;s root.</e>
<cmt>「佐々木泰綱-Wikipedia」にある、佐々木氏が六角氏の祖であるという記載、および「佐々木定賢-Wikipedia」にある佐々木氏と六角氏の間の嫡流問題に係る記載を参照して、佐々木六角氏を、the trouble of reigns of the both families of Rokkaku clan and Sasaki clan, the latter being Rokkaku clan&apos;s root と訳す。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since Katatoyo was regarded as the top of senior vassals and well respected as described above, this feud (the pretext why Yoshiharu killed Katatoyo being feigned to be bureiuchi (death penalty by sword slash for rudeness)) led up to distrust of Yoshiharu among the feudatory of Rokkaku clan in connection with the trouble of reigns of the both families of Rokkaku clan and Sasaki clan, the latter being Rokkaku clan&apos;s root.</e>
<cmt>（　）表示がもれていたため、付け加えました。また、connected with を　in connection with に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since Katatoyo was regarded as the top of senior vassals and well respected as described above, this feud (the pretext why Yoshiharu killed Katatoyo being feigned to be bureiuchi (death penalty by sword slash for rudeness)) led up to distrust of Yoshiharu among the feudatory of Rokkaku clan in connection with the trouble of reigns of the both families of Rokkaku clan and Sasaki clan, the latter being Rokkaku clan&apos;s root.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>そして浅井氏が六角氏を攻める動きを見せたことで、浅井方につく者まで現れ始めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And in response to Azai&apos;s movement to attack Rokkaku clan, there appeared in Rokkaku clan some traitors to stand for Azai&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">And in response to Azai&apos;s movement to attack Rokkaku clan, there appeared in Rokkaku clan some traitors to stand for Azai&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">And in response to Azai&apos;s movement to attack Rokkaku clan, there appeared in Rokkaku clan some traitors to stand for Azai&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="14">
<j>さらに義治はこの事件に不満を抱く一部家臣団によって、父と共に一時的に観音寺城を追われてしまった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Further, Yoshiharu, together with his father, was deported from Kannonji Castle temporarily by elements of the Rokkaku feudatory who were discontented over the feud.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Further, Yoshiharu, together with his father, was deported from Kannonji Castle temporarily by elements of the Rokkaku feudatory who felt discontented with the feud.</e>
<cmt>were discontented over を felt discontented with the feud　に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Further, Yoshiharu, together with his father, was deported from Kannonji Castle temporarily by elements of the Rokkaku feudatory who felt discontented with the feud.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>蒲生定秀・蒲生賢秀親子の仲介により、義賢・義治親子は観音寺城に復帰することになったが、家督を六角義定（義治の弟）に譲ること、さらに「六角氏式目」に署名して、六角氏の当主権限を縮小することを認めざるを得なくなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the parent and child of Yosikata and Yoshiharu, returned to Kannonji castle through the mediation by the parent and child of Sadahide GAMO and Katahide GAMO, Yoshitaka and Yoshiharu had to consent to hand over the patrimony to Yoshisada ROKKAKU (Yoshiharu&apos;s brother), and furthermore, to clip the power of Rokkaku clan as the family head through signing for &quot;Rokkakushi shikimoku (Rokkaku clan&apos;s bunkokuho, laws and standards established by Sengoku daimyo to govern their territories)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>「分国法-Wikipedia」参照。分国法（ぶんこくほう）は、戦国時代に戦国大名が領国内を統治するために制定した法律規範である。以下のように訳す。laws and standards established by Sengoku daimyo to govern their territories</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Yosikata and Yoshiharu, father and son, returned to Kannonji castle through the mediation by Sadahide GAMO and Katahide GAMO, father and son, Yoshitaka and Yoshiharu had to consent to hand over the patrimony to Yoshisada ROKKAKU (Yoshiharu&apos;s brother), and furthermore, to clip the power of Rokkaku clan as the family head through signing for &quot;Rokkakushi shikimoku (Rokkaku clan&apos;s bunkokuho, laws and standards established by Sengoku daimyo to govern their territories)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>親子　の部分を2箇所訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Yosikata and Yoshiharu, father and son, returned to Kannonji castle through the mediation by Sadahide GAMO and Katahide GAMO, father and son, Yoshitaka and Yoshiharu had to consent to hand over the patrimony to Yoshisada ROKKAKU (Yoshiharu&apos;s brother), and furthermore, to clip the power of Rokkaku clan as the family head through signing for &quot;Rokkakushi shikimoku (Rokkaku clan&apos;s bunkokuho, laws and standards established by Sengoku daimyo to govern their territories)&quot;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="16">
<j>なお、後藤氏の家督は長男・壱岐守が父と共に誅殺されていたため、次男の後藤高治が継いだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Meanwhile, the patrimony of Goto clan was succeeded by the second son, Takaharu, because the first son, Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province) had been murdered together with their father.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, the patrimony of Goto clan was succeeded by Takaharu GOTO, the second son, because the first son, Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province) had been murdered together with their father.</e>
<cmt>原文通り、姓をつけて訳したほうが、良いと思われますので、GOTOを付け加えました。また、the second son の前に、Takaharu GOTOを移動させました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, the patrimony of Goto clan was succeeded by Takaharu GOTO, the second son, because the first son, Iki no kami (governor of Iki Province) had been murdered together with their father.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>騒動の原因と影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Cause and influence of the feud</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Cause and influence of the feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Cause and influence of the feud</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="17">
<j>騒動の原因であるが、六角氏が守護大名から近世戦国大名へと完全に脱皮していなかったことが挙げられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It can be given as the root of the feud that Rokkaku clan had not grown out thoroughly from shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal loads) to warring load of the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It can be given as the root of the feud that Rokkaku clan had not grown out thoroughly from shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal loads) to warring load of the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It can be given as the root of the feud that Rokkaku clan had not grown out thoroughly from shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal loads) to warring load of the early-modern times.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>六角氏の家臣の多くは国人領主であり、被官化されていたとはいえ独立性が高かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Most of Vassals of Rokkaku clan were such local samurai loads that they were highly independent although they were retained.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Most of Vassals of Rokkaku clan were such local samurai loads that they were highly independent although they were retained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Most of Vassals of Rokkaku clan were such local samurai loads that they were highly independent although they were retained.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>名君である定頼存命中は彼らも服属していたが、定頼の死後、後を継いだ義賢・義治は三好長慶や浅井長政に対して失策を重ね、後藤氏のような有力国人衆への統制を失うこととなったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Those vassals served obediently during the period of Sadayori who was a wise ruler, but Yosikata and Yoshiharu repeatedly made political errors against Nagyoshi MIYOSHI and Nagamasa Azai, and lost control over powerful local loads (kokujin) like Goto clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Those vassals served obediently during the period of Sadayori who was a wise ruler, but Yosikata and Yoshiharu who succeeded to Sadayori after his death repeatedly made political errors against Nagyoshi MIYOSHI and Nagamasa Azai, and lost control over powerful local loads (kokujin) such as Goto clan.</e>
<cmt>「定頼の死後、後を継いだ」訳漏れのため、付け加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Those vassals served obediently during the period of Sadayori who was a wise ruler, but Yosikata and Yoshiharu who succeeded to Sadayori after his death repeatedly made political errors against Nagyoshi MIYOSHI and Nagamasa Azai, and lost control over powerful local loads (kokujin) such as Goto clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>この騒動は戦国大名への体制転換の最中での事件であると定義できる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This feud can be characterized as affairs that happened in the middle of the system conversion into warring loads in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This feud can be defined as affairs that happened in the middle of the system conversion into warring loads in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>characterized から　defined に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This feud can be defined as affairs that happened in the middle of the system conversion into warring loads in the Sengoku period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>また、義賢・義治が六角本家でないとする異説によれば、六角氏内部には「定頼 - 義賢 - 義治」の陣代箕作家より家格が上の、「氏綱-義実-義秀-義郷」と続く六角本家があり、本家と義賢ら陣代家の間は対立関係で非常に危うい状態だったという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also it was said among Rokkaku clan, according to a different view which denied Yosikata and Yosiharu as the head family of Rokkaku clan, that there was the legitimate Rokkaku family whose heads were &quot;Ujituna-Yoshizane-Yoshihide-Yosisato&quot; that held higher social standing than Mitsukuri family whose role was Jindai and whose heads were &quot;Ujitsuna-Yoshizane-Yoshihide-Yoshizato&quot;, and the relationship between the legitimate Rokkaku family and the family of Jindai like Yosikata was opposing to each other and very uncertain.</e>
<cmt>「箕作家-Wikipedia」参照。箕作家は宇多源氏佐々木氏の支流を称し、室町時代に六角定頼が、近江国箕作城（現在の滋賀県東近江市五個荘山本町）に住んで箕作を称したのに始まるという。その後箕作家は美作国に移り現在の岡山県美作市楢原に住み、箕作貞辨の代に医家となった。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also according to a different view which denied Yosikata and Yosiharu as the head family of Rokkaku clan, among the Rokkaku family, there was the legitimate Rokkaku family whose heads were &quot;Ujituna-Yoshizane-Yoshihide-Yosisato&quot; that held higher social standing than Mitsukuri family whose role was Jindai and whose heads were &quot;Sadayori-Yoshikata-Yoshiharu&quot;, and the relationship between the legitimate Rokkaku family and the family of Jindai including Yosikata was opposing to each other and very uncertain.</e>
<cmt>it was said among Rokkaku clan は不要のため削除しました。文中の名前が相違していましたので、&quot;Ujituna-Yoshizane-Yoshihide-Yosisato&quot;から&quot;Ujituna-Yoshizane-Yoshihide-Yosisato&quot; に訂正しました。また、like を　including に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also according to a different view which denied Yosikata and Yosiharu as the head family of Rokkaku clan, among the Rokkaku family, there was the legitimate Rokkaku family whose heads were &quot;Ujituna-Yoshizane-Yoshihide-Yosisato&quot; that held higher social standing than Mitsukuri family whose role was Jindai and whose heads were &quot;Sadayori-Yoshikata-Yoshiharu&quot;, and the relationship between the legitimate Rokkaku family and the family of Jindai including Yosikata was opposing to each other and very uncertain.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="22">
<j>この観音寺騒動は六角氏本家だけではなく、南近江の国人連合の結束と勢力の衰退につながった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kannonji family feud led to the decline of unity and power of not only the head family of Rokkaku clan but also allied local samurais in Minami Omi area.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kannonji family feud led to the decline of unity and power of not only the head family of Rokkaku clan but also allied local samurais in Minami Omi area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kannonji family feud led to the decline of unity and power of not only the head family of Rokkaku clan but also allied local samurais in Minami Omi area.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>それを好機と捉えた織田信長は永禄11年（1568年）に南近江に侵攻する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA took the opportunity to invade Minami Omi in 1568.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Nobunaga ODA took this opportunity to invade Minami Omi in 1568.</e>
<cmt>took の後にthis を加えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Nobunaga ODA took this opportunity to invade Minami Omi in 1568.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>一度は織田を共通の敵とする三好三人衆の助勢を得て撃退するも、翌年には箕作城を攻められ落城することになり、同時に観音寺城周辺の地盤も失った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although Rokkaku clan once defeated back ODA with support by Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate) who ware also opposed to ODA, the next year Mitsukuri Castle was attacked to fall, and Rokkaku clan also lost their footing around Kannonji Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although Rokkaku clan once defeated back ODA with support by Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate) who were also opposed to ODA, the next year Mitsukuri Castle was attacked to fall, and Rokkaku clan also lost their footing around Kannonji Castle.</e>
<cmt>ware スペルミスのため、 were に訂正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although Rokkaku clan once defeated back ODA with support by Miyoshi Sanninshu (Miyoshi Triumvirate) who were also opposed to ODA, the next year Mitsukuri Castle was attacked to fall, and Rokkaku clan also lost their footing around Kannonji Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>六角氏は甲賀郡に拠点を移すことになり、蒲生定秀親子ら一部国人は織田方に属することとなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokkaku clan was made to transfer their foothold to Koga county, and some local lords like Sadahide GAMO and his children became to belong to ODA&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokkaku clan was made to transfer their foothold to Koga county, and some local lords such as Sadahide GAMO and his children became to belong to ODA&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>like を　such as に変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokkaku clan was made to transfer their foothold to Koga county, and some local lords such as Sadahide GAMO and his children became to belong to ODA&apos;s side.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>この騒動は六角氏零落の序曲であり、同時に信長がその本拠、岐阜からの上洛のルートを確保する上では、大変に好都合な出来事だったといえるのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While this feud was a prelude to the fall of Rokkaku clan, it was a very favorable incident for Nobunaga to secure the route for Kyoto that was the capital from Gifu where he headquartered.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While this feud was a prelude to the fall of Rokkaku clan, it was a very favorable incident for Nobunaga to secure the route for Kyoto from Gifu where he headquartered.</e>
<cmt>that was the capital　は、特に入れなくても良いと思いましたので、削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While this feud was a prelude to the fall of Rokkaku clan, it was a very favorable incident for Nobunaga to secure the route for Kyoto from Gifu where he headquartered.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Ks aka 98(id:35909), Jackrover Jin(id:282030), Reggaeman(id:6214), R28Bot(id:177951), KurmUmy(id:202680), BitBucket(id:30999), BuxWV(id:169145), Point136(id:211299), U.S.S.Momotaro(id:646), シェーラ(id:17988), 氏名不詳者(id:133523), 相模守信久(id:189309), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>