<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>元弘の乱</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genko no Ran (Genko Incident)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genko no Ran (Genko Incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genko no Ran (Genko Incident)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>元弘の乱（げんこうのらん）は、1331年（元弘元年）に起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genko no Ran was an anti-Kamakura shogunate movement broke out in 1331.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genko no Ran was an anti-Kamakura shogunate movement broke out in 1331.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genko no Ran was an anti-Kamakura bakufu movement broke out in 1331.</e>
<cmt>幕府＝bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>後醍醐天皇を中心とした勢力による鎌倉幕府討幕運動である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The movement was driven by the powers gathered together with Emperor Go-Daigo as the central figure.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The movement was driven by the powers that had gathered together with Emperor Go-Daigo as the central figure.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The movement was driven by the powers that had gathered together with Emperor Go-Daigo as the central figure.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）に鎌倉幕府が滅亡に至るまでの一連の戦乱を含めることも多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genko no Ran often includes a series of conflicts fought until the fall of the Kamakura Bakufu (shogunate government) in 1333.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">References to Genko no Ran often include a series of conflicts fought until the fall of the Kamakura Bakufu (shogunate government) in 1333.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">References to Genko no Ran often include a series of conflicts fought until the fall of the Kamakura Bakufu (shogunate government) in 1333.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>以下では1331年から1333年までの戦乱について述べる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The conflicts from 1331 to 1333 will be described below.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The conflicts from 1331 to 1333 are described below.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The conflicts from 1331 to 1333 are described below.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元弘の変（げんこうのへん）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Genko no Ran is also called Genko no Hen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Genko no Ran is also called Genko no Hen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Genko no Ran is also called Genko no Hen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>背景</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Background</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="6">
<j>鎌倉時代後期、鎌倉幕府では北条氏得宗家が権勢を振るっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Kamakura period, the Tokuso Family of the Hojo clan exercised authority over the Kamakura shogunate government.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Kamakura period, the Tokuso family of the Hojo clan exercised authority over the Kamakura shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Kamakura period, the Tokuso family of the Hojo clan exercised authority over the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>幕府＝bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>北条一門の知行国が著しく増加した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Hojo family notably increased its fiefdoms.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Hojo family significantly increased its fiefdoms.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Hojo family significantly increased its fiefdoms.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>一方で御家人層では、元寇後も続けられた異国警固番役の負担、元寇の恩賞や訴訟の停滞、貨幣経済の普及、所領分割などによって没落する者も増加していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In contrast, increasing number of those in the gokenin (immediate vassal of the shogunate) stratum went rack and ruin.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Contrastingly, an increasing number of those in the gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) stratum were ruined.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Contrastingly, an increasing number of those in the gokenin (immediate vassals of the shogunate) stratum were ruined because of the burden imposed on them by ikoku-keigoban-yaku (a kind of military service imposed on the gokenin in which they had to guard areas other than those they usually guarded), which continued even after the Mongolian expeditions against Japan; delays to the provision of rewards and settlement of lawsuits following the Mongolian expeditions; the gradual emergence of a monetary economy; and the division of their territory.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕府は徳政令を発して対応する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate government coped with the matter by issuing the Tokuseirei (ordering return of land sold and dissolution of debts), but the society was still in chaos.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate government coped with the matter by issuing the Tokuseirei (ordering the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts), but society remained in chaos.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate government coped with the matter by issuing the Tokuseirei (ordering the return of land sold and the dissolution of debts), but society remained in chaos.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>社会的混乱から諸国では悪党の活動が活発化し、幕府は次第に支持を失っていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That activated Akuto (a villain in the medieval times) in respective Provinces and the bakufu had gradually lost the support.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That activated Akuto (a villain of the medieval times) in the respective provinces, and gradually the bakufu lost support.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That activated Akuto (a villain of the medieval times) in the respective provinces, and gradually the bakufu lost support.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="11">
<j>朝廷では、13世紀後半以降、後深草天皇の子孫（持明院統）と亀山天皇の子孫（大覚寺統）の両血統の天皇が交互に即位する両統迭立が行われていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the late 13 century, the Imperial Court took ryoto tetsuritsu (alternate accedence from two ancestries of imperial families) system.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the late thirteenth century, the Imperial Court took up the ryoto tetsuritsu (alternate accession from two ancestries of imperial families) system.</e>
<cmt>number</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the late thirteenth century, the Imperial Court adopted the ryoto tetsuritsu system, a system in which succession to the imperial throne alternated between the two ancestral lines of the imperial family: Emperor Gofukakusa (the Jimyoin line) and Emperor Kameyama (the Daikakuji line).</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。As an explanation of the &quot;ryoto tetsuritsu system&quot; is already provided, the explanation in parentheses is unnecessary.</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>だが、公家社会の中に支持皇統による派閥が生じるようになるなど混乱を引き起こした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That led disruption among the Imperial nobles such as being factionalized according to the supporting imperial lines.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That led to disruption among the Imperial nobles, by which they became factionalized according to the supporting imperial lines.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That led to disruption among the Imperial nobles, by which they became factionalized according to the supporting imperial lines.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これは、幕府による朝廷の制御を困難にした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That disruption hindered the shogunate government from controlling the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The disruption hindered the shogunate government from controlling the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The disruption hindered the bakufu from controlling the Imperial Court.</e>
<cmt>幕府＝bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="14">
<j>1318年（文保2年）、大覚寺統の後醍醐天皇が即位。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1318, the Emperor Go-Daigo from the Daikakuji line acceeded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1318, Emperor Go-Daigo from the Daikakuji line acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1318, Emperor Go-Daigo from the Daikakuji line acceded to the throne.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>天皇親政を理想に掲げ、鎌倉幕府の打倒を密かに目指していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Godaigo held up an ideal of a direct administration of an emperor, harboring an aim of overthrowing the Kamakura shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo espoused the ideal of direct administration by the Emperor, but he harbored the aim of overthrowing the Kamakura shogunate government.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo espoused the ideal of direct administration by the Emperor, but he harbored the aim of overthrowing the Kamakura bakufu.</e>
<cmt>幕府＝bakufu</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>1324年（正中 (元号)元年）の正中の変は六波羅探題によって未然に察知された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Shochu Conspiracy in 1324 was prevented by Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shochu Conspiracy of 1324 was prevented by Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shochu Conspiracy of 1324 was prevented by Rokuhara Tandai (an administrative and judicial agency in Rokuhara, Kyoto).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>後醍醐は幕府に釈明して赦されたものの、側近の日野資朝は佐渡島へ流罪となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo vindicated himself to the bakufu and was pardoned, but his close adviser Suketomo HINO was exiled to the Sadoga-shima Island.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo vindicated himself to the bakufu and was pardoned, but his close adviser Suketomo HINO was exiled to Sadoga-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo vindicated himself to the bakufu and was pardoned, but his close adviser Suketomo HINO was exiled to Sadoga-shima Island.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>だが後醍醐は、処分を免れた側近の日野俊基や真言宗密教の僧文観らと再び倒幕計画を進めた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo&apos;s close adviser Toshimoto HINO was exempted from punishment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo&apos;s close adviser, Toshimoto HINO, was exempted from punishment.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo resumed his plan to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu with his close adviser Toshimoto HINO, who had been exempted from punishment, and a monk called Monkan from the Shingon-shu sect of Tantric Buddhism.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>経過</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Developments</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Developments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Developments</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>笠置山・赤坂城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Mount Kasagi and Akasaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Mount Kasagi and Akasaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Mount Kasagi and Akasaka-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="19">
<j>1331年（元弘元年）8月、後醍醐の側近である吉田定房が六波羅探題に倒幕計画を密告。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In August, 1331, Godaigo&apos;s close adviser Sadafusa YOSHIDA informed Rokuhara Tandai about the plan of overthrowing the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In August 1331, Godaigo&apos;s close adviser Sadafusa YOSHIDA informed Rokuhara Tandai of the plan to overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In August 1331, Godaigo&apos;s close adviser Sadafusa YOSHIDA informed Rokuhara Tandai of the plan to overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>またも計画は事前に発覚した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The plan was revealed again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The plan was revealed again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The plan was revealed again.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>六波羅探題は軍勢を御所の中にまで送った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Rokuhara Tandai sent the army into the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rokuhara Tandai sent the army into the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rokuhara Tandai sent the army into the Imperial Palace.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>後醍醐は女装して御所を脱出し、比叡山へ向かうと見せかけた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo escaped from the Imperial Palace in female clothing and pretended to head for Mount Hiei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo escaped from the Imperial Palace in women&apos;s clothing and pretended to head for Mount Hiei.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo escaped from the Imperial Palace in women&apos;s clothing and pretended to head for Mount Hiei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>そして、山城国笠置山 (京都府)で挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo was in fact in Mount Kasagi in the Yamashiro Province (Kyoto Prefecture) and raised an army there.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo was in fact at Mount Kasagi in Yamashiro Province (Kyoto Prefecture), and there he raised an army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo was in fact at Mount Kasagi in Yamashiro Province (Kyoto Prefecture), and there he raised an army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>後醍醐の皇子・護良親王や、河内国の悪党・楠木正成もこれに呼応して、それぞれ大和国の吉野および河内国の下赤坂城で挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo&apos;s Prince, Prince Morinaga, and Masashige KUSUNOKI, a villain in the Kawachi Province, raised their armies in concert with Godaigo&apos;s raising of army in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo&apos;s Prince, Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI, a villain in Kawachi Province, raised their armies in concert with the rise of Godaigo&apos;s army in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Following this, Godaigo&apos;s son Imperial Prince Morinaga raised an army in Yoshino, Yamato Province, while at the same time Masashige KUSUNOKI, a villain from Kawachi Province, raised an army at Shimo Akasaka-jo Castle in Kawachi Province.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="25">
<j>幕府は大仏貞直、金沢貞冬、足利尊氏（後の尊氏）、新田義貞らの討伐軍を差し向けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched the punitive force formed by Sadanao OSARAGI, Sadafuyu KANAZAWA, Takauji ASHIKAGA, and Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu dispatched the punitive force that had been formed by Sadanao OSARAGI, Sadafuyu KANAZAWA, Takauji ASHIKAGA and Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched the punitive force that had been formed by Sadanao OSARAGI, Sadafuyu KANAZAWA, Takauji ASHIKAGA and Yoshisada NITTA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>9月に笠置山は陥落（笠置山の戦い）、次いで吉野も陥落した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In September, Mount Kasagi fell (the battle of Mount Kasagi), and subsequently, Yoshino fell.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In September, Mount Kasagi fell (the battle of Mount Kasagi), and subsequently Yoshino fell.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In September, Mount Kasagi fell (the battle of Mount Kasagi), and subsequently Yoshino fell.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>楠木軍が守る下赤坂城のみが残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle defended by the army of Kusunoki survived.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Only Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle, defended by the army of Kusunoki, survived.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Only Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle, defended by the army of Kusunoki, survived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>ここで幕府軍は苦戦を強いられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Here, the army of bakufu was forced into a hard battle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Here, the army of the bakufu was forced into a hard fight.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Here, the army of the bakufu was forced into a hard fight.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="29">
<j>楠木軍は城壁に取り付いた幕府軍に対して大木を落としたり、熱湯を浴びせかけたり、予め設けておいた二重塀を落としたりといった奇策を駆使した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The army of bakufu clung to the wall of the Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The army of the bakufu clung to the wall of Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The army of the bakufu scaled the wall of Shimo Akasaka-jo Castle while the army of Kusunoki employed unprecedented tactics against the bakufu army, such as throwing enormous trees down onto them, pouring boiling water over them, and collapsing the outer layer of the two-layered wall to which they were clinging.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="30">
<j>だが楠木正成は、長期間の抗戦は不可能であると理解していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI, however, knew that they was not able to afford prolonged resistance.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Masashige KUSUNOKI, however, knew he couldn&apos;t afford a prolonged resistance.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Masashige KUSUNOKI, however, knew he couldn&apos;t afford a prolonged resistance.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="31">
<j>10月、自ら下赤坂城に火をかけて自害したように見せかけ、姿をくらませた（赤坂城の戦い）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In October, he set fire on the Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle by himself and pretended to commit suicide, and vanished (the battle of Akasaka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In October, he set fire to Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle by himself and pretended to commit suicide, and then vanished (the battle of Akasaka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In October, he set fire to Shimo Akasaka -jo Castle by himself and pretended to commit suicide, and then vanished (the battle of Akasaka-jo Castle).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>後醍醐は側近の千種忠顕とともに幕府に捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo was arrested by the bakufu together with his close adviser Tadaaki CHIKUSA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo was arrested by the bakufu together with his close adviser, Tadaaki CHIKUSA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo was arrested by the bakufu together with his close adviser, Tadaaki CHIKUSA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="33">
<j>幕府は持明院統の光厳天皇を即位させ、元号を正慶と改めさせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu enthroned the Emperor Kogen from the Jimyoin line and changed the imperial era name to Shokei.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu enthroned the Emperor Kogen from the Jimyoin line and changed the imperial era name to Shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu enthroned the Emperor Kogen from the Jimyoin line and changed the imperial era name to Shokei.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="34">
<j>1332年（元弘2年/正慶元年）3月、日野俊基や北畠具行、先に流罪となっていた日野資朝らを斬罪とし、後醍醐を隠岐島へ配流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In March, 1332, the bakufu beheaded Toshimoto HINO and Tomoyuki KITABATAKE as well as Suketomo HINO who had already been lived in exile, and condemn Godaigo to exile.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In March, 1332, the bakufu beheaded Toshimoto HINO and Tomoyuki KITABATAKE as well as Suketomo HINO, who had been in exile, and condemned Godaigo to exile.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In March, 1332, the bakufu beheaded Toshimoto HINO and Tomoyuki KITABATAKE as well as Suketomo HINO, who had been in exile, and exiled Godaigo to Okino-shima island.</e>
<cmt>「隠岐島へ」を入れました。確認お願いします。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>こうして倒幕運動は鎮圧されたかに見えた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The anti-bakufu movement seemed to be suppressed in this way.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The anti-bakufu movement seemed to be suppressed in this way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The anti-bakufu movement seemed to be suppressed in this way.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="4">
<tit>
<j>千早城の戦い</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Battle of Chihaya-jo Castle</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Battle of Chihaya-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Battle of Chihaya-jo Castle</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="36">
<j>護良親王と楠木正成は潜伏して機会を伺っていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI hid and waited for the right moment.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI hid and waited for the right moment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Prince Morinaga and Masashige KUSUNOKI hid and waited for the right moment.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>1332年（元弘2年/正慶元年）11月、楠木正成は河内国金剛山 (金剛山地)の千早城で挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In November, 1332, Masashige KUSUNOKI raised an army in the Chihaya-jo Castle in Mount Kongo in the Kawachi Province (Highland Kongo).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In November 1332, Masashige KUSUNOKI raised an army at Chihaya-jo Castle in Mount Kongo, in Kawachi Province (Highland Kongo).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In November 1332, Masashige KUSUNOKI raised an army at Chihaya-jo Castle in Mount Kongo, in Kawachi Province (Highland Kongo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>同月、護良親王も吉野で挙兵して倒幕の令旨を発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the same month, Prince Morinaga also raised an army in Yoshino and issued ryoji (order issued by prince, etc.) of overthrowing the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the same month, Prince Morinaga also raised an army in Yoshino and issued ryoji (order issued by a prince, etc.) to overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the same month, Prince Morinaga also raised an army in Yoshino and issued ryoji (order issued by a prince, etc.) to overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>正成は12月に赤坂城を奪回した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In December, Masashige regained the Akasaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In December, Masashige regained Akasaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In December, Masashige regained Akasaka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>1333年（元弘3年/正慶2年）1月には六波羅勢を摂津国天王寺などで撃破した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In January, 1333, he defeated the Rokuhara Tandai army at the Tenno-ji Temple in the Settsu Province and the like.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In January 1333, he defeated the Rokuhara Tandai army at Tenno-ji Temple in Settsu Province, etc.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In January 1333, he defeated the Rokuhara Tandai army at Tenno-ji Temple in Settsu Province, etc.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="41">
<j>幕府は再び大仏家時、名越宗教、大仏高直らが率いる大軍を差し向けた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched a large army led by Ietoki OSARAGI, Munenori NAGOE (or NAGOSHI), and Takanao OSARAGI, again.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu again dispatched a large army led by Ietoki OSARAGI, Munenori NAGOE (or NAGOSHI), and Takanao OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt>grammar, punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu again dispatched a large army led by Ietoki OSARAGI, Munenori NAGOE (or NAGOSHI), and Takanao OSARAGI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>まず幕府軍は正成の配下の平野将監らが守る上赤坂城へ向かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">First, the bakufu army headed for the Kami-Akasaka-jo Castle defended by Shogen HIRANO who was a vassal of Masashige.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">First, the bakufu army headed for Kami-Akasaka-jo Castle, which was being defended by the Masashige vassal Shogen HIRANO.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">First, the bakufu army headed for Kami-Akasaka-jo Castle, which was being defended by the Masashige vassal Shogen HIRANO.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="43">
<j>上赤坂城の守りは堅く幕府軍も苦戦するが、城の水源を絶ち、平野将監らを降伏させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kami-Akasaka-jo Castle had a strong defense, which forced the bakufu army to engage in a bitter fight, but the bakufu army cut off the water supply to the Castle to make Shogen HIRANO give in.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kami-Akasaka-jo Castle had strong defenses that forced the bakufu army to engage in a bitter fight, but the bakufu army cut off the water supply to the castle in order that Shogen HIRANO would be forced to surrender.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kami-Akasaka-jo Castle had strong defenses that forced the bakufu army to engage in a bitter fight, but the bakufu army cut off the water supply to the castle in order that Shogen HIRANO would be forced to surrender.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="44">
<j>同じ頃吉野でも護良親王を破った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">At the same time, the bakufu army defeated Prince Morinaga in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">At the same time, the bakufu army defeated Prince Morinaga in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">At the same time, the bakufu army defeated Prince Morinaga in Yoshino.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="45">
<j>残るは正成がわずかな軍勢で篭城する千早城のみである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Only the Chihaya-jo Castle remained undefeated with Masashige KUSUNOKI held up with a small number of soldiers.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, Chihaya-jo Castle remained undefeated, and Masashige KUSUNOKI remained inside with a small number of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, Chihaya-jo Castle remained undefeated, and Masashige KUSUNOKI remained inside with a small number of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="46">
<j>だが楠木軍は、鎧を着せた藁人形を囮として矢を射掛けるといった奇策により、再び幕府軍を翻弄した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kusunoki army gave a drubbing the bakufu army again.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kusunoki army thus gave the bakufu army another drubbing.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kusunoki army then gave the bakufu army another drubbing by employing the novel strategy of shooting arrows from among straw figures dressed in armor that acted as decoys.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="47">
<j>幕府軍は水源を絶とうとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu army attempted to cut off the water-supply to the castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu army attempted to cut off the castle&apos;s water supply.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu army attempted to cut off the castle&apos;s water supply.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="48">
<j>しかし、千早城では城中に水源を確保しておりびくともしなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kusunoki army, however, maintained the water source in the Chihaya-jo Castle and stayed undaunted.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kusunoki army, however, maintained a water source in Chihaya-jo Castle and was therefore undaunted.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kusunoki army, however, maintained a water source in Chihaya-jo Castle and was therefore undaunted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="49">
<j>さらに楠木軍は一部が打って出て幕府軍を奇襲した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">A part of the Kusunoki army charged to make a surprise attack on the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">A portion of the Kusunoki army charged, attempting a surprise attack on the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">A portion of the Kusunoki army charged, attempting a surprise attack on the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="50">
<j>そして、軍旗を奪って城壁に掲げ嘲笑してみせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kusunoki army snatched the color from the bakufu army, displayed it on the castle wall, and made fun of the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kusunoki army snatched the color from the bakufu army, displayed it on the castle wall, and made fun of the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kusunoki army snatched the color from the bakufu army, displayed it on the castle wall, and made fun of the bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="51">
<j>楠木軍は90日間にわたって幕府の大軍を相手に戦い抜いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kusunoki army had fought through 90 days against the large bakufu army.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kusunoki army had fought through 90 days against the larger bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Kusunoki army had fought through 90 days against the larger bakufu army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="52">
<j>そうしている間に、幕府軍が千早城に大軍を貼り付けにしながら落とせずにいるとの報に触発され、各地に倒幕の機運が広がっていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the meantime, provinces received the news that the bakufu army had clung to the Chihaya-jo Castle but yet to take the Castle.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Meanwhile, provinces received news that the bakufu army had clung to Chihaya-jo Castle but yet to take control of it.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Meanwhile, on receiving the news that, despite having been engaged in fighting to take Chihaya-jo Castle for such a long time, the bakufu army had yet to take control of it, the feeling that the time was ripe to overthrow the bakufu spread throughout the provinces of Japan.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="5">
<tit>
<j>六波羅攻略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occupation of Rokuhara</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Occupation of Rokuhara</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Occupation of Rokuhara</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="53">
<j>播磨国では赤松則村（円心）が挙兵し、その他の各地でも反乱が起きた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Harima Province, Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) raised an army, and revolts occurred in the other areas.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In Harima Province, Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) raised an army, and revolts occurred in other areas.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In Harima Province, Norimura AKAMATSU (Enshin) raised an army, and revolts occurred in other areas.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="54">
<j>中でも赤松則村は周辺の後醍醐方を糾合し京都へ進撃する勢いであった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Among others, Norimura AKAMATSU had a great power to storm Kyoto by rallying the Godaigo armies around.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Among others, Norimura AKAMATSU had great power to storm Kyoto by rallying the Godaigo armies.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Among others, Norimura AKAMATSU had great power to storm Kyoto by rallying the Godaigo armies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="55">
<j>このような状況を見て、閏2月、後醍醐天皇は名和長年の働きで隠岐島を脱出した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Having seen the circumstances, in leap February, Godaigo escaped from the Oki no shima Island with the aid of Nagatoshi NAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Having seen the circumstances, in leap February Godaigo escaped from Oki no shima Island with the aid of Nagatoshi NAWA.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Having seen the circumstances, in leap February Godaigo escaped from Oki no shima Island with the aid of Nagatoshi NAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="56">
<j>そして、伯耆国の船上山に入って倒幕の綸旨を天下へ発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Godaigo entered Mount Senjo in the Hoki Province and issued rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) of overthrowing the bakufu to the nation.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Godaigo reached Mount Senjo in Hoki Province and issued a rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) for the nation to overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Godaigo reached Mount Senjo in Hoki Province and issued a rinji (the Emperor&apos;s command) for the nation to overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="57">
<j>幕府は船上山を討つため足利尊氏、名越高家らの援兵を送り込んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched reinforcements led by Takauji ASHIKAGA and Takaie NAGOE to defeat Mount Senjo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu dispatched reinforcements led by Takauji ASHIKAGA and Takaie NAGOE to defeat the combatants at Mount Senjo.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched reinforcements led by Takauji ASHIKAGA and Takaie NAGOE to defeat the combatants at Mount Senjo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="58">
<j>しかし、4月27日には名越高家が赤松円心に討たれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On April 27, Takaie NAGOE was defeated by Enshin AKAMATSU..</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On April 27, Takaie NAGOE was defeated by Enshin AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On April 27, Takaie NAGOE was defeated by Enshin AKAMATSU.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="59">
<j>足利高氏は所領のあった丹波国篠村八幡宮で幕府へ反旗を翻す。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA rose in revolt against the bakufu at the Shinomura-Hachimangu Shrine in the Tanba Province which was is shoryo (territory)</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Takauji ASHIKAGA rose in revolt against the bakufu at Shinomura-Hachimangu Shrine in the Tanba Province, which was a shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Takauji ASHIKAGA rose in revolt against the bakufu at Shinomura-Hachimangu Shrine in the Tanba Province, which was a shoryo (territory).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="60">
<j>5月7日、足利高氏は佐々木道誉や赤松則村らと呼応して六波羅探題を攻め落とし、京都を制圧した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 7, Takauji ASHIKAGA defeated Rokuhara Tandai in cooperation with Doyo SASAKI, Norimura AKAMATSU, and the like, and conquered Kyoto.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 7, Takauji ASHIKAGA defeated Rokuhara Tandai in cooperation with Doyo SASAKI, Norimura AKAMATSU and the like, and conquered Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 7, Takauji ASHIKAGA defeated Rokuhara Tandai in cooperation with Doyo SASAKI, Norimura AKAMATSU and the like, and conquered Kyoto.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="61">
<j>北条仲時、北条時益ら六波羅探題の一族郎党は東国へ逃れようとした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Families and followers of Rokuhara Tandai including Nakatoki HOJO and Tokimasu HOJO attempted to escape to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The families and followers of Rokuhara Tandai, including Nakatoki HOJO and Tokimasu HOJO, attempted to escape to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The families and followers of Rokuhara Tandai, including Nakatoki HOJO and Tokimasu HOJO, attempted to escape to Togoku (the eastern part of Japan, particularly the Kanto region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="62">
<j>しかし、5月9日、近江国の番場蓮華寺で自刃し、光厳天皇、後伏見天皇、花園天皇は捕らえられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 9, they committed suicide with their sword at the Renge-ji Temple in Banba of the Omi Province, and the Emperor Kogen, the Emperor Gofushimi, and the Emperor Hanazono were arrested.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 9, they committed suicide with their swords at Renge-ji Temple in Banba of Omi Province, and the emperors Kogen, Gofushimi and Hanazono were arrested.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 9, they committed suicide with their swords at Renge-ji Temple in Banba of Omi Province, and the emperors Kogen, Gofushimi and Hanazono were arrested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="6">
<tit>
<j>鎌倉攻略</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Occupation of Kamakura</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Occupation of Kamakura</e>
<cmt>article</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Occupation of Kamakura</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="63">
<j>5月8日、新田義貞が上野国生品神社で挙兵した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 8, Yoshisada NITTA raised an army in the Ikushina-jinja Shrine in the Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 8, Yoshisada NITTA raised an army at Ikushina-jinja Shrine in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 8, Yoshisada NITTA raised an army at Ikushina-jinja Shrine in Kozuke Province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="64">
<j>新田軍は一族や周辺御家人を集めて兵を増やしつつ、利根川を越えて南進した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nitta army pushed southward across the Tonegawa river while increasing soldiers by rallying the clan and neighboring gokenin.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Nitta army pushed southward across the Tonegawa River while increasing the number of soldiers by rallying the clan and neighboring gokenin.</e>
<cmt>case</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Nitta army pushed southward across the Tonegawa River while increasing the number of soldiers by rallying the clan and neighboring gokenin.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="65">
<j>足利高氏の嫡子千寿王（後の足利義詮）らも合流した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Senjuo, the legitimate son of Takauji ASHIKAGA (later, Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA) also joined the Nitta army.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Senjuo, the legitimate son of Takauji ASHIKAGA (later Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), also joined the Nitta army.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Senjuo, the legitimate son of Takauji ASHIKAGA (later Yoshiakira ASHIKAGA), also joined the Nitta army.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="66">
<j>新田軍は数万規模に膨れ上がったと言われる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Nitta army was allegedly blown up to tens of thousands of soldiers.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Thus it is said that the Nitta army grew to a number in the tens of thousands.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Thus it is said that the Nitta army grew to a number in the tens of thousands.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="67">
<j>幕府は北条泰家らの軍勢を迎撃のために向かわせる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched the army led by Yasuie HOJO to intercept the enemy.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu dispatched the army led by Yasuie HOJO to intercept the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu dispatched the army led by Yasuie HOJO to intercept the enemy.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="68">
<j>しかし、小手指ヶ原の戦いや分倍河原の戦い (鎌倉時代)で敗退し、鎌倉へ追い詰められた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The bakufu army was defeated at the battle of Kotesashi ga hara and the battle of Bubaigawara (the Kamakura period), and cornered in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The bakufu army was defeated at the battles of Kotesashi ga hara and Bubaigawara (the Kamakura period), and was cornered in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The bakufu army was defeated at the battles of Kotesashi ga hara and Bubaigawara (the Kamakura period), and was cornered in Kamakura.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="69">
<j>新田軍は極楽寺坂、巨福呂坂、そして義貞と弟脇屋義助は化粧坂の三方から鎌倉を攻撃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Kamakura was attacked from three directions.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Kamakura was attacked from three directions.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kamakura was attacked from three directions, with the Nitta army attacking from the Gokurakji-saka and the Kobukuro-zaka and the army of Yoshisada NITTA and his younger brother Yoshisuke WAKIYA attacking from the Kesho-zaka.</e>
<cmt>一文に戻しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="70">
<j>しかし天然の要塞となっていた鎌倉の切通しの守りは固かった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The natural fortress of the kiridoshi in Kamakura had a strong defense.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The natural fortress of the kiridoshi in Kamakura offered strong defenses.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The natural fortress of the kiridoshi in Kamakura offered strong defenses.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="71">
<j>極楽寺坂では新田方の大館宗氏も戦死した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Muneuji OOTACHI (or OODACHI) in the Nitta army was killed in the battle at the Gokurakji-saka.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Muneuji OOTACHI (or OODACHI), of the Nitta army, was killed in the battle of Gokurakji-saka.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Muneuji OTACHI (or ODACHI), of the Nitta army, was killed in the battle of Gokurakji-saka.</e>
<cmt>ＯＯＴＡＣＨＩ→ＯＴＡＣＨＩ</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="72">
<j>戦いは一旦は膠着した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The battle was once in a stalemate.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The battle was temporarily in a stalemate.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The battle was temporarily in a stalemate.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="73">
<j>新田義貞は一計を案じ、幕府軍の裏をかいて稲村ガ崎から鎌倉へ突入した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yoshisada NITTA devised a plan and outmanoeuvred the bakufu army by charging Kamakura from Inamura ga saki.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yoshisada NITTA devised a plan and outmaneuvered the bakufu army by charging Kamakura from Inamura ga saki.</e>
<cmt>spelling</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yoshisada NITTA devised a plan and outmaneuvered the bakufu army by charging Kamakura from Inamura ga saki.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="74">
<j>幕府軍は5月22日、北条高時ら北条一門は東勝寺において滅亡した（東勝寺合戦）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On May 22, the bakufu army fell, and the HOJO family including Takatoki HOJO fell at the Toshoji-Temple (Toshoji Gassen (Tosho-ji War)).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On May 22 the bakufu army fell, and the HOJO family, including Takatoki HOJO, fell at Toshoji-Temple (Toshoji Gassen (Tosho-ji War)).</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On May 22 the bakufu army fell, and the HOJO family, including Takatoki HOJO, fell at Toshoji-Temple (Toshoji Gassen (Tosho-ji War)).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="75">
<j>鎮西探題北条英時も、少弐貞経、大友貞宗、島津貞久らに攻められて5月25日に博多で自刃した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinzei tandai (the military governor of Kyushu) Hidetoki HOJO was also attacked by Sadatsune SHONI, Sadamune OOTOMO, and Sadahisa SHIMAZU, and on May 25, committed suicide with his sword in Hakata.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The chinzei tandai (the military governor of Kyushu) Hidetoki HOJO was also attacked by Sadatsune SHONI, Sadamune OOTOMO and Sadahisa SHIMAZU, and on May 25 he committed suicide with his sword in Hakata.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The chinzei tandai (the military governor of Kyushu) Hidetoki HOJO was also attacked by Sadatsune SHONI, Sadamune OTOMO and Sadahisa SHIMAZU, and on May 25 he committed suicide with his sword in Hakata.</e>
<cmt>ＯＯＴＯＭＯ→ＯＴＯＭＯ</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="7">
<tit>
<j>影響</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Influences</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Influences</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Influences</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="76">
<j>後醍醐天皇の討幕運動は遂に成功を見た。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Emperor Godaigo&apos;s anti-bakufu movement succeeded after all.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo&apos;s anti-bakufu movement had succeeded after all.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo&apos;s anti-bakufu movement had succeeded after all.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="77">
<j>後醍醐は京都へ帰還し、元弘の元号を復活させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo returned to Kyoto, and restored the imperial era name Genko.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo returned to Kyoto, and restored the imperial era under the name of Genko.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo returned to Kyoto, and restored the imperial era under the name of Genko.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="78">
<j>念願であった天皇親政である建武の新政を開始する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Godaigo launched the Kenmu Restoration which was the direct Imperial rule Godaigo had been ambitious for.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Godaigo launched the Kenmu Restoration, which was the direct imperial rule that Godaigo had long envisioned.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Godaigo launched the Kenmu Restoration, which was the direct imperial rule that Godaigo had long envisioned.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="79">
<j>だが元弘の乱の論功行賞において、後醍醐の側近が優遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The grant of rewards after examination of services for the Genko no Ran was unfair.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The granting of rewards after the examination of services for the Genko no Ran was unfair, however.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The granting of rewards after the examination of services for the Genko no Ran was unfair, however.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="80">
<j>しかし、赤松則村をはじめとする多くの武士層が冷遇された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">While Godaigo&apos;s close advisers were favored, many of those in the samurai stratum including Norimura AKAMATSU were treated coldly.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">While Godaigo&apos;s close advisers were favored, many of those in the samurai stratum, including Norimura AKAMATSU, were treated coldly.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">While Godaigo&apos;s close advisers were favored, many of those in the samurai stratum, including Norimura AKAMATSU, were treated coldly.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="81">
<j>こうしたことが新政への支持を失わせた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">That treatment undermined the support for the new administration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">That treatment undermined the support for the new administration.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">That treatment undermined the support for the new administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="82">
<j>そして、足利尊氏の離反と室町幕府の成立へと結びついていく。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Accordingly, Takauji ASHIKAGA alienated from Godaigo and established the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Accordingly, Takauji ASHIKAGA became alienated from Godaigo and established the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Accordingly, Takauji ASHIKAGA became alienated from Godaigo and established the Muromachi bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Okt(id:18107), BOTarate(id:185620), Bakkai(id:7233), Masanori88(id:20692), Law soma(id:45202), 水野白楓(id:22811), 巴投(id:181114), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), Yas(id:739), お掃除大好き(id:99320), VSA-itama(id:25395), Cave cattum(id:41235), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), Kamitani(id:30757), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>