<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>鎮西奉行</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinzei Bugyo (a magistrate of Kyushu region)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinzei Bugyo (a magistrate of Kyushu region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinzei Bugyo (a magistrate of Kyushu region)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>鎮西奉行（ちんぜいぶぎょう）とは、鎌倉幕府において、鎮西（九州）の御家人の指揮統制を行った職である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Chinzei Bugyo was an appointed position within the Kamakura shogunate which commanded the gokenin (shogunal retainers) of Chinzei (Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Chinzei Bugyo was an appointed position within the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which commanded the gokenin (shogunal retainers) of Chinzei (Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>shogunate→ bakufu としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Chinzei Bugyo was an appointed position within the Kamakura bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) which commanded the gokenin (shogunal retainers) of Chinzei (Kyushu region).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>鎮西守護（ちんぜいしゅご）とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also called Chinzei Shugo (Provincial Military Governor of Chinzei).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also called Chinzei Shugo (Provincial Military Governor of Chinzei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also called Chinzei Shugo (Provincial Military Governor of Chinzei).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1185年（文治元年）、源頼朝が天野遠景をこの職に任じて、九州の御家人の指揮統制にあたらせたのが始まりである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1185, the appointment of Tokage AMANO by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo as the magistrate (Bugyo) to command the gokenin of Kyushu is said to be the beginning of this position.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1185, the appointment of Tokage AMANO by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo as the Bugyo (magistrate) to command the gokenin of Kyushu is said to be the beginning of this position.</e>
<cmt>Bugyo (magistrate)とし、日本語（英語）の順の表記にしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1185, the appointment of Tokage AMANO by MINAMOTO no Yoritomo as the Bugyo (magistrate) to command the gokenin of Kyushu is said to be the beginning of this position.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>平家の残党及び源義経一党らの追捕がもともとの任務であったが、その後全九州の御家人の統轄にあたるようになり、大宰府の機能も継承した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The search and capture of the remnants of Heike and the party of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune had been the original mission as well as its job description, but it effectively inherited the function of Dazaifu (the local government office in Kyushu region) as well, as it subsequently adopted the supervisory role of the gokenin for the entire region of Kyushu,.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The search and capture of the remnants of Heike (the Taira family) and the party of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune had been the original mission, but it effectively inherited the function of Dazai-fu (the local government office in Kyushu region) as well, as it subsequently adopted the supervisory role of the gokenin for the entire region of Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>平家→Heike (the Taira family) としました。Daizai-fu としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The search and capture of the remnants of Heike (the Taira family) and the party of MINAMOTO no Yoshitsune had been the original mission, but it effectively inherited the function of Dazai-fu (the local government office in Kyushu region) as well, as it subsequently adopted the supervisory role of the gokenin for the entire region of Kyushu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="6">
<j>頼朝は、1180年（治承4年）に鎌倉に侍所を置き御家人を統制し、さらに1185年には、義経の追捕を理由に、各国へ守護・地頭を設置し、全国の支配権を確立した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1180, Yoritomo controlled the gokenin by creating the Board of Retainers in Kamakura, and in 1185, for the reason of search and capture of Yoshitsune, he brought the entire country under his jurisdiction by positioning military governors and estate stewards in every province.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1180, Yoritomo controlled the gokenin by creating the Board of Retainers in Kamakura, and in 1185, for the reason of search and capture of Yoshitsune, he brought the entire country under his jurisdiction by positioning Shugo (provincial constable) and Jito (estate stewards) in every province.</e>
<cmt>守護、地頭　読みを追加しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1180, Yoritomo controlled the gokenin by creating the Board of Retainers in Kamakura, and in 1185, for the reason of search and capture of Yoshitsune, he brought the entire country under his jurisdiction by positioning Shugo (provincial constable) and Jito (estate stewards) in every province.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>そして地方には、京都守護を、九州には鎮西奉行を、奥州には奥州総奉行をそれぞれ設置して統制させた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">For the local regions, he established the Kyoto Shugo (Military Governor of Kyoto), Chinzei Bugyo for the Kyushu region as well as the Oshu Sobugyo (the General Magistrate of Oshu region) and delegated control to each of them.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">For the local regions, he established the Kyoto Shugo (Military Governor of Kyoto), Chinzei Bugyo for the Kyushu region as well as the Oshu Sobugyo (the General Magistrate of Oshu region) and delegated control to each of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">For the local regions, he established the Kyoto Shugo (Military Governor of Kyoto), Chinzei Bugyo for the Kyushu region as well as the Oshu Sobugyo (the General Magistrate of Oshu region) and delegated control to each of them.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>遠景の後について、中原親能・武藤資頼が継いだとする説もあるが、瀬野精一郎は、遠景後の後継者について諸説あることをまとめた上で、「鎮西奉行は一般的呼称にすぎず、鎌倉幕府の正式な官職名ではなかったとする説（佐藤進一説）もあるごとく、その性格がなお不明瞭な点が多いことに起因しているといえる」と指摘している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There are theories stating that Nakahara no Chikayoshi and Sukeyori MUTO succeeded the post of Chinzei Bugyo after Tokage, but alluding to the existence of numerous theories regarding the successor of Tokage, Seiichiro SENO (Japanese historian) points out that, &quot;The Chinzei Bugyo was nothing but a common title and we can say that this is due to its vague nature as a job as there are theories denying it an official title (theory purported by Shinichi SATO).&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">There are theories stating that NAKAHARA no Chikayoshi and Sukeyori MUTO succeeded the post of Chinzei Bugyo after Tokage, but alluding to the existence of numerous theories regarding the successor of Tokage, Seiichiro SENO (Japanese historian) points out that, &apos;The Chinzei Bugyo was nothing but a common title and we can say that this is due to its vague nature as a job as there are theories denying it an official title (theory purported by Shinichi SATO).&apos;</e>
<cmt>&quot; → &apos;　としました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">There are theories stating that NAKAHARA no Chikayoshi and Sukeyori MUTO succeeded the post of Chinzei Bugyo after Tokage, but alluding to the existence of numerous theories regarding the successor of Tokage, Seiichiro SENO (Japanese historian) points out that, &apos;The Chinzei Bugyo was nothing but a common title and we can say that this is due to its vague nature as a job as there are theories denying it an official title (theory purported by Shinichi SATO).&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Kurz(id:1601), AlleborgoBot(id:119729), Pontafon(id:33761), Cyuuritsu Na Shitenn(id:102276), Yukichin(id:725), 水野白楓(id:22811), Chlewbot(id:33904), ふたりはGoki鰤MaxHeart(id:19635), Andee(id:20421), Kjml(id:250165), 伏儀(id:142093), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>