<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>甲賀流</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga-ryu school</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga-ryu school</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>甲賀流（こうかりゅう、こうがりゅう）とは、伊賀流と並んで最も有名な流派の忍術であるが、近江国甲賀の地に伝わっていた忍術流派の総称で「甲賀流」という名称の流派が存在したのではない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga-ryu (or Koka-ryu) is the most famous school of ninjutsu (ninja technique) along with Iga-ryu, but it is the name that refers to collectively the schools originating from the Koka region in Omi Province and the school named &quot;Koga-ryu&quot; did not exist.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga-ryu (or Koka-ryu) is the most famous school of ninjutsu (ninja technique) along with Iga-ryu, but it is the name that refers to collectively the schools originating from the Koka region in Omi Province and the school named &quot;Koga-ryu&quot; did not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga-ryu (or Koka-ryu) is the most famous school of ninjutsu (ninja technique) along with Iga-ryu, but it is the name that refers to collectively the schools originating from the Koka region in Omi Province and the school named &quot;Koga-ryu&quot; did not exist.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>甲賀は本来「こうか」と読み、地名に因る名称であるが、忍術に関してのみ「こうが」との誤読が一般的となっている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga, originally pronounced &quot;Koka,&quot; is a toponym, but only when referring to the ninjutsu, the mistakenly pronounced &quot;Koga&quot; has become common.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga, originally pronounced &quot;Koka,&quot; is a toponym, but only when referring to the ninjutsu, the mistakenly pronounced &quot;Koga&quot; has become common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga, originally pronounced &quot;Koka,&quot; is a toponym, but only when referring to the ninjutsu, the mistakenly pronounced &quot;Koga&quot; has become common.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>山を一つ隔てた場所に伊賀流が存在する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Iga-ryu exists in the region separated by only a mountain.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Iga-ryu exists in the region separated by only a mountain from that of Koga-ryu.</e>
<cmt>甲賀流が伊賀流と山を一つ隔てていたことが分かるように補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Iga-ryu exists in the region separated by only a mountain from that of Koga-ryu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="4">
<j>特徴</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Characteristics</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>今の滋賀県甲賀市(こうかし)、湖南市にあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It originated from today&apos;s Koka and Konan Cities in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It originated from today&apos;s Koka and Konan Cities in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It originated from today&apos;s Koka and Konan Cities in Shiga Prefecture.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>普段は農業をしたり、行商をしたりして各地の情報を探る一方、指令が下ると戦場やその後方へ出向き、工作活動に励んだ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The people of Koga-ryu were usually engaged in farming or peddling to collect information in various places, and once called they went to the war fronts or the rear of the battlefields to engage in espionage.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The people of Koga-ryu were usually engaged in farming or peddling to collect information in various places and, once called, they went to the war fronts or the rear of the battlefields to engage in espionage.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The people of Koga-ryu were usually engaged in farming or peddling to collect information in various places and, once called, they went to the war fronts or the rear of the battlefields to engage in espionage.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>忍術の流派の中でも薬の扱いに長けており、その名残として甲賀には今も製薬会社が多い。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga-ryu was highly skilled at dealing with medicine among the ninjutsu schools, a vestige of which can be seen in many pharmaceutical companies in Koka even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga-ryu was highly skilled at dealing with medicine among the ninjutsu schools, a vestige of which can be seen in the fact that many pharmaceutical companies are located in Koka even today.</e>
<cmt>ニュアンスの違いを修正しました。余分なスペースを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga-ryu was highly skilled at dealing with medicine among the ninjutsu schools, a vestige of which can be seen in the fact that many pharmaceutical companies are located in Koka even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="8">
<j>甲賀は六角氏の傘下に属しながらも「惣村」(そう)を形成し、郡に関わる全ての案件を多数決によって決定（合議制）・運営するなどしていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Though Koga belonged to the Rokkaku clan, it formed a soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association), in which all issues were decided and managed by majority (council system).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Though Koga belonged to the Rokkaku clan, it formed a soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association), in which all issues were decided and managed by majority (council system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Though Koga belonged to the Rokkaku clan, it formed a soson (a community consisting of peasants&apos; self-governing association), in which all issues were decided and managed by majority (council system).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これはこの時期では全国的に見てもきわめて珍しいことである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This was quite unusual at the time even at the nationwide level.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This was quite unusual at the time even at the nationwide level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This was quite unusual at the time even at the nationwide level.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="10">
<j>また、甲賀忍者には、上忍はなく、最高位は中忍である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Koga ninja had no Jonin (highest level of ninja) and the highest level of the Koga ninja was Chunin (middle level of ninja).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Koga ninja had no Jonin (highest level of ninja) and the highest level of the Koga ninja was Chunin (middle level of ninja).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Koga ninja had no Jonin (highest level of ninja) and the highest level of the Koga ninja was Chunin (middle level of ninja).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="11">
<j>歴史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>室町時代後期、観音寺城に本拠を構える近江佐々木六角氏が着々と力を蓄え、足利幕府の命令を軽視あるいは無視し始めたことから、1487年に将軍足利義尚がこれを征討するために軍を発し、六角勢との間に戦いが行われた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the late Muromachi period, the Sasaki Rokkaku clan of Omi Province built up the military force steadily with the Kannonji-jo Castle as their headquarters and started to take light of the orders from the Ashikaga shogunate or even ignore them, therefore Shugun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA brought with him an army to subjugate the Rokkaku clan and the battle with them broke out.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the late Muromachi period, the Sasaki Rokkaku clan of Omi Province steadily built up the military force with the Kannonji-jo Castle as their headquarter and started to take light of the orders from the Ashikaga shogunate or even ignore them, therefore Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA sent an army to subjugate the Rokkaku clan in 1487 and a battle broke out.</e>
<cmt>将軍の綴りを修正しました。文法を修正しました。年号が抜けていましたので補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the late Muromachi period, the Sasaki Rokkaku clan of Omi Province steadily built up the military force with the Kannonji-jo Castle as their headquarter and started to take light of the orders from the Ashikaga shogunate or even ignore them, therefore Shogun Yoshihisa ASHIKAGA sent an army to subjugate the Rokkaku clan in 1487 and a battle broke out.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>これを「鈎の陣」という。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This battle is called &quot;Magari no jin&quot;.</e>
<cmt>陣は陣営の意味で、直訳すると&quot;Encampment at Magari&quot;ですが、この場合は戦いの名前なので訳しませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This battle is called &apos;Magari no jin&apos;.</e>
<cmt>記号を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This battle is called &apos;Magari no jin&apos;.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="14">
<j>義尚が諸国の大名を動員して六角氏の本拠観音寺城に迫ると、六角久頼・六角高頼父子は直接対決を避けて甲賀城に移動した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">When Yoshihasa mobilized daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) from various provinces and got close to the Kannonji-jo Castle, the headquarters of the Rokkaku clan, the elder and junior Rokkakus, Hisayori and Takayori, avoided a direct confrontation and moved to the Koka-jo Castle.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">When Yoshihisa mobilized daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) from various provinces and got close to the Kannonji-jo Castle, the headquarter of the Rokkaku clan, the father and the son Hisayori and Takayori Rokkaku moved to the Koka-jo Castle to avoid a direct confrontation.</e>
<cmt>義尚の綴りを修正しました。the elder and junior Rokkakusという言い回しに違和感を覚えますので修正しました。語順を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">When Yoshihisa mobilized daimyo (Japanese feudal lords) from various provinces and got close to the Kannonji-jo Castle, the headquarter of the Rokkaku clan, the father and the son Hisayori and Takayori Rokkaku moved to the Koka-jo Castle to avoid a direct confrontation.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>そこで義尚は本陣を栗太郡に位置する鈎の安養寺へ移し、甲賀城を攻めてこれを落城させるのだが、脱出した六角父子は配下の甲賀武士達に命じ、山中でゲリラを展開して頑強に抵抗した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Then, Yoshihisa moved the headquarter to Magari no Anyo-ji Temple located in Kurita-gun County and attacked the Koka-jo Castle, and the Koka-jo Castle fell, but the elder and junior Rokkakus escaped and ordered the Koga warriors who followed them to resist adamantly against Ashikaga by guerrilla warfare in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>鈎の安養寺→Magari no Anyo-ji Temple「鈎之安養寺」として一つの名詞扱いhttp://www.shiga-bunshin.or.jp/rekishikairou/Bukaijigyou/ukiyoeroman/ rittou2.html</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Then, Yoshihisa moved the headquarter to Magari no Anyo-ji Temple located in Kurita-gun County and attacked the Koka-jo Castle, and the Koka-jo Castle fell, but the father and the son Rokkaku escaped and ordered the Koga warriors who followed them to resist adamantly against Ashikaga by guerrilla warfare in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>Rokkakusを修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Then, Yoshihisa moved the headquarter to Magari no Anyo-ji Temple located in Kurita-gun County and attacked the Koka-jo Castle, and the Koka-jo Castle fell, but the father and the son Rokkaku escaped and ordered the Koga warriors who followed them to resist adamantly against Ashikaga by guerrilla warfare in the mountains.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>甲賀武士達は山中でその地の利を生かしてさまざまな奇襲をかけ、また時には夜陰に義尚の本陣に迫って火や煙を放つなど、さんざん幕府軍を苦しめたという。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is said that Koga warriors took a geographical advantage in the mountains to make various surprise attacks against the bakufu army and tormented them by using fire and smoke on Yoshihisa&apos;s headquarters during the night.</e>
<cmt>地の利→geographical advantage本文中では位置というより地形的な有利さという意味を出したかったので定訳のlocational advantageを使いませんでした。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is said that Koga warriors took a geographical advantage in the mountains to make various surprise attacks against the bakufu army and tormented them by using fire and smoke on Yoshihisa&apos;s headquarters during the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is said that Koga warriors took a geographical advantage in the mountains to make various surprise attacks against the bakufu army and tormented them by using fire and smoke on Yoshihisa&apos;s headquarters during the night.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="17">
<j>そのためなかなか決着はつかず、1489年には義尚が陣中に没したため、足かけ3年にわたった戦いは終結、六角氏は生き残った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">So, the battle did not easily end until Yoshihisa died in the battle in 1489, which marked an end of the three-year conflict, and the Rokkaku clan survived.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">So, the battle did not easily end, but the death of Yoshihisa in battle in 1489 marked the end of the three-year conflict, and the Rokkaku clan survived.</e>
<cmt>文法を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">So, the battle did not easily end, but the death of Yoshihisa in battle in 1489 marked the end of the three-year conflict, and the Rokkaku clan survived.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>この時の神出鬼没のゲリラ戦やその高い戦闘力の印象が、甲賀武士達を全国に知らしめることになったのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The elusive and effective guerrilla warfare and high combat ability in this battle were so impressive that the name of Koga warriors became well-known throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The name of Koga warriors became well-known throughout the country because their elusive and effective guerrilla warfare and high combat ability in this battle were so impressive.</e>
<cmt>自然な文になるように構造を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The name of Koga warriors became well-known throughout the country because their elusive and effective guerrilla warfare and high combat ability in this battle were so impressive.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>そして、この戦いに参加した五十三家の地侍達を「甲賀五十三家」と呼び（さらに五十三家の中で六角氏より感状を貰い重きを置かれた家を「甲賀二十一家」と称した）、甲賀の地が織田信長に席巻されるまでの間、六角氏の下で諜報活動に戦闘にと活躍していった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 53 families of jizamurai (literally, soldiers of the land) that participated in this battle were called the &quot; 53 families of Koga&quot; (among them, the families which received a letter of commendation from the Rokkaku clan for taking part in the battle and were taken into their confidence were called the &quot;21 families of Koga&quot;) and they were active in both intelligence and fighting activities under the Rokkaku clan until the Koka region was seized by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>甲賀五十三家→the 53 families of Koga定訳不明甲賀二十一家→the 53 families of Koga定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 53 families of jizamurai (literally, soldiers of the land) that participated in this battle were called the &quot;53 families of Koga&quot; (among them, the families which received a letter of commendation from the Rokkaku clan for taking part in the battle and were valued were called the &quot;21 families of Koga&quot;) and they were active in both intelligence and fighting activities under the Rokkaku clan until the Koka region was seized by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>不要なスペースを削除しました。「重きを置く」はvalueとしました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 53 families of jizamurai (literally, soldiers of the land) that participated in this battle were called the &quot;53 families of Koga&quot; (among them, the families which received a letter of commendation from the Rokkaku clan for taking part in the battle and were valued were called the &quot;21 families of Koga&quot;) and they were active in both intelligence and fighting activities under the Rokkaku clan until the Koka region was seized by Nobunaga ODA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="9">
<sen id="20">
<j>その後、甲賀の地が織田信長を経て豊臣秀吉の支配下に入ると、甲賀武士達は徳川家康の監視活動を主な任務に命じられる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, when the Koka region became under the control of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI from Nobunaga ODA, the Koga warriors were mainly missioned to spy on Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the Koka region fell under the control of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI from Nobunaga ODA, the Koga warriors were mainly missioned to spy on Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>文法と語句を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Koka region fell under the control of Hideyoshi TOYOTOMI from Nobunaga ODA, the Koga warriors were mainly missioned to spy on Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>このことは江戸時代になって、「伊賀忍軍対甲賀忍軍」という形で講談や読本の題材となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This fact was taken as the subject for the Kodan storytelling or Yomihon (books for reading) in the Edo period, in the form of &quot;Iga ninja force versus Koga ninja force&quot; stories.</e>
<cmt>伊賀忍軍→Iga ninja force 定訳不明甲賀忍軍→Koga ninja force 定訳不明</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">This fact was featured in storytellings or Yomihon (books for reading) in the Edo period, in the form of &quot;Iga ninja force versus Koga ninja force&quot; stories.</e>
<cmt>「題材となる」の訳を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">This fact was featured in storytellings or Yomihon (books for reading) in the Edo period, in the form of &quot;Iga ninja force versus Koga ninja force&quot; stories.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>実際には徳川と豊臣との代理戦争だったわけであるが、今日でもよく、「伊賀対甲賀」という構図が小説や忍者漫画に出てくるのもこのためと言えよう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Actually it was a war by proxy between Tokugawa and Toyotomi, but because of this the confrontation plot of &quot;Iga vs. Koga&quot; often appears in novels or ninja cartoons even today.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Actually it was a war by proxy between Tokugawa and Toyotomi, but because of this the confrontation plot of &quot;Iga vs. Koga&quot; often appears in novels or ninja cartoons even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Actually it was a war by proxy between Tokugawa and Toyotomi, but because of this the confrontation plot of &quot;Iga vs. Koga&quot; often appears in novels or ninja cartoons even today.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="10">
<sen id="23">
<j>忍術屋敷</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninjutsu Yashiki</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninjutsu Yashiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninjutsu Yashiki</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>甲賀市甲南町竜法師2331番地に、甲賀五十三家の筆頭格であった望月氏甲賀望月氏（近江国）の旧居が甲賀流忍術屋敷として残る（「甲賀の里忍術村」とは別）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The former residence of the Koga Mochizuki clan (Omi Province) that was a leader of the 53 Families of Koga is extant as Koga-ryu Ninjutsu Yashiki at 2331 Ryuboshi, Konan-cho, Koka City (which is different from Koga-no-sato Ninjutsu-mura [Koga Ninja Village]).</e>
<cmt>望月氏甲賀望月氏→どちらかが重複表記だと思われます。望月出雲守は甲賀望月氏の系統のため、甲賀望月氏をとりました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The former residence of the Koga Mochizuki clan (Omi Province,) the leader of the 53 Families of Koga is extant as Koga-ryu Ninjutsu Yashiki at 2331 Ryuboshi, Konan-cho, Koka City (which is different from Koga-no-sato Ninjutsu-mura [Koga Ninja Village]).</e>
<cmt>that was a leader →the leader</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The former residence of the Koga Mochizuki clan (Omi Province), the leader of the 53 Families of Koga is extant as Koga-ryu Ninjutsu Yashiki at 2331 Ryuboshi, Konan-cho, Koka City (which is different from Koga-no-sato Ninjutsu-mura [Koga Ninja Village]).</e>
<cmt>Province,)→Province),</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>元禄年間建造の屋敷は、一見普通の農家だが、内部には縄梯子・落とし穴・回転戸・地下道などが仕掛けられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The residence built during the Genroku era (from 1688 to 1703) looked like an ordinary farmer&apos;s house, but the inside has traps such as rope ladders, pitfalls, revolving doors and underground passages.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The residence built during the Genroku era (from 1688 to 1703) looked like an ordinary farmer&apos;s house, but the inside has traps such as rope ladders, pitfalls, revolving doors and underground passages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The residence built during the Genroku era (from 1688 to 1703) looked like an ordinary farmer&apos;s house, but the inside has traps such as rope ladders, pitfalls, revolving doors and underground passages.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また、当時の小道具も展示されている</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The weaponry and other historical artifact used are also displayed.</e>
<cmt>小道具→weaponry and other historical artifactこの文章中の意味は演劇の小道具を意味するpropとは異なるため上記の訳としました。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The weaponry and other historical artifact used are also displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The weaponry and other historical artifact used are also displayed.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="11">
<sen id="27">
<j>忍術</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ninjutsu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ninjutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ninjutsu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Izayohi(id:13095), Bakkai(id:7233), YurikBot(id:18605), Plattic(id:15680), カイの迷宮(id:72682), Reggaeman(id:6214), ジャビ(id:88014), 北斗白影(id:113612), Point136(id:211299), West(id:8787), TX55(id:134817), YAMAARASHI(id:18211), Yunoki(id:22436), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>