<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>幕藩体制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakuhan-taisei (the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakuhan-taisei (the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakuhan-taisei (the feudal system characteristic of the shogunate)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>幕藩体制（ばくはんたいせい）とは、近世日本の社会体制のあり方を、幕府（征夷大将軍）と藩（大名）という封建制度的主従関係を基点にとらえた歴史学上の概念である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">&quot;Bakuhan-taisei&quot; is a historical concept of social system of Early Modern Japan viewed basically from feudal homage between bakufu (shogunate) (or seii-taishogun, literally &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians) and han (clans) (or daimyo, meaning &quot;feudal lords&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">&quot;Bakuhan-taisei&quot; is a historical concept of social system of early modern Japan viewed basically from feudal homage between bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (or seii-taishogun, literally &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians) and han (domains) (or daimyo, meaning &quot;feudal lords&quot;).</e>
<cmt>Early Modern→early modern,「幕府」の部分を修正しました。clans→domains と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">&quot;Bakuhan-taisei&quot; is a historical concept of social system of early modern Japan viewed basically from feudal homage between bakufu (Japanese feudal government headed by a shogun) (or seii-taishogun, literally &quot;great general who subdues the barbarians) and han (domains) (or daimyo, meaning &quot;feudal lords&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>戦前段階には狭義に政治体制自体を指していたが、戦後の歴史学の進展に伴い、近世日本の社会体制全体の特色を示す概念として使われるようになった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the World War II, the term meant a political system itself in the narrow sense, but along with development of the historical science in the post-war era, the term has become to mean a concept that indicates features of the entire society system of the early modern Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the pre-war days, the term meant a political system itself in the narrow sense, but along with the development of the historical science in the post-war era, the term has become to mean a concept that indicates the features of entire society system of the early modern Japan.</e>
<cmt>「戦前段階」を修正しました。the について修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the pre-war days, the term meant a political system itself in the narrow sense, but along with the development of the historical science in the post-war era, the term has become to mean a concept that indicates the features of entire society system of the early modern Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>幕藩制（ばくはんせい）ともいう。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Bakuhan-sei&quot; (literally, &quot;a system of bakufu and han&quot;).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is also called &quot;Bakuhan-sei&quot; (literally, &quot;a system of bakufu and han&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is also called &quot;Bakuhan-sei&quot; (literally, &quot;a system of bakufu and han&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="4">
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>コロンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>江戸幕府を全ての武士の頂点とし、最高の統治機関としながらも、各大名がそれぞれの領地においてある程度独立した統治機構（藩）を形成していることと、米などを現物で納めさせて年貢とする石高制をその基礎においていることが特徴である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was characterized with the Edo Shogunate as the supreme govering institution at the top of warriors, and yet with each feudal lord which maintained kind of independent govering structure in its own territory (han or domain), as well as with the tax system based on annual yield of rice, Kokudaka-sei, whereby tax is paid by rice and other actual goods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was characterized with the Edo bakufu as the supreme governing institution at the top of warriors, and yet with each feudal lord which maintained somewhat independent governing structure in its own territory (domain), as well as with the tax system based on annual yield of rice, Kokudaka-sei, whereby tax is paid by rice and other actual goods.</e>
<cmt>Shogunate→bakufu,govering→governing,kind of→somewhat,カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was characterized with the Edo bakufu as the supreme governing institution at the top of warriors, and yet with each feudal lord which maintained somewhat independent governing structure in its own territory (domain), as well as with the tax system based on annual yield of rice, Kokudaka-sei, whereby tax is paid by rice and other actual goods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>諸大名を親藩、譜代大名、外様大名に分け、参勤交代や改易によってこれを統制した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo (feudal lords) were classified into Shinpan Daimyo (descendants of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA), Fudai Daimyo (hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family) and Tozama Daimyo (non-Tokugawa feudal lords), all of which were controlled by Tokugawa shogunate through Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in their residences in Edo) and Kaieki (change or forfeit of ranks).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo (feudal lords) were classified into Shinpan daimyo (descendants of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA), Fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family) and Tozama daimyo (non-Tokugawa feudal lords), all of which were controlled by Tokugawa shogunate through Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in their residences in Edo) and Kaieki (change or forfeit of ranks).</e>
<cmt>Daimyo→daimyo と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo (feudal lords) were classified into Shinpan daimyo (descendants of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA), Fudai daimyo (hereditary vassals to the Tokugawa family) and Tozama daimyo (non-Tokugawa feudal lords), all of which were controlled by Tokugawa shogunate through Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords were required to spend every other year in their residences in Edo) and Kaieki (change or forfeit of ranks).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>また、士農工商などといわれる身分制度によって武士を支配階級に位置づけた（もっとも士農工商という言葉は当時の階級を正確に表してはいないと指摘されている）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Samurai (warriors) were positioned at the govering class in then hierarchy called &quot;Shinokosho&quot; (&quot;warriors, peasants, artisans and merchants&quot;), although it is pointed out that the term of &quot;Shinokosho&quot; was not correctly representing the order of hereditary social status at that time (the Edo Period).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Samurai (warriors) were positioned at the governing class in the hierarchy called &quot;Shinokosho&quot; (&quot;warriors, peasants, artisans and merchants&quot;) (Although it is pointed out that the term of &quot;Shinokosho&quot; was not correctly representing the order of hereditary social status at that time.)</e>
<cmt>govering→governing,then→the と修正しました。パンクチュエーション、カッコ内を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Samurai (warriors) were positioned at the governing class in the hierarchy called &quot;Shinokosho&quot; (&quot;warriors, peasants, artisans and merchants&quot;) (Although it is pointed out that the term of &quot;Shinokosho&quot; was not correctly representing the order of hereditary social status at that time.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="8">
<j>石高制については安土桃山時代に兵農分離が行われ検地によって徐々に形成されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kokudaka-sei tax system was gradually formed through heino-bunri (the separation of warriors and peasants) and kenchi (cadastral surveys) during the Azuchi-Momoyama Period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kokudaka-sei tax system was gradually formed through heino-bunri (the separation of warriors and peasants) and kenchi (cadastral surveys) during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>Period→period と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kokudaka-sei tax system was gradually formed through heino-bunri (the separation of warriors and peasants) and kenchi (cadastral surveys) during the Azuchi-Momoyama period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>幕藩体制を形作る諸制度は初代将軍徳川家康以降、2代徳川秀忠、3代徳川家光の時代に、鎖国体制や知行制、村請制などが確立されていった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Various social systems to build up Bakuhan-taisei (the feudal system featured by Shogunate at the top in the Edo Period), including systems of sakoku (national isolation), chigyo (enfeoffment) and murauke (village wide, collective responsibility for tax payment) were established under the reigns of the first to third shogunates, namely Ieyasu, Hidetada and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Various systems to build up Bakuhan-taisei, including systems of sakoku (national isolation), chigyo (enfeoffment) and murauke (village wide, collective responsibility for tax payment) were established under the reigns of the first to third shogunates, namely Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>social を削除しました。「幕藩体制」のカッコ部分は既存説明があるため削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Various systems to build up Bakuhan-taisei, including systems of sakoku (national isolation), chigyo (enfeoffment) and murauke (village wide, collective responsibility for tax payment) were established under the reigns of the first to third shogunates, namely Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, Hidetada TOKUGAWA and Iemitsu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>武家諸法度や朝廷に対する禁中並公家諸法度、寺社への統制なども行う。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also enforced were Buke Shohatto (various laws for warrior class families) and Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (a set of regulations that applied to the Emperor and the Kyoto nobles) as well as administrative systems for temples and shrines throughout the country.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also enforced were Buke Shohatto (various laws for warrior class families) and Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (a set of regulations that applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles) as well as the administrative systems for temples and shrines throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>Emperor→emperor と修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also enforced were Buke Shohatto (various laws for warrior class families) and Kinchu Narabini Kuge Shohatto (a set of regulations that applied to the emperor and the Kyoto nobles) as well as the administrative systems for temples and shrines throughout the country.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="11">
<j>江戸時代には商人資本の成長や農村への商品経済の浸透、それらによる身分制の変質など、村落共同体の動揺は一揆や打ちこわしを招き、幕府や諸藩は幕政改革や藩政改革を行い再編を試みる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">During the Edo Period, growth of merchant capitals and penetration of a commodity economy to agricultural villages contributed to the transformation of hierarchy of village communities, which, however, caused such turmoils in the society as uprising peasants and destructive riots and compelled both Bakufu (shogunate) government and Han (local domain) governments to try to reform their political systems.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">During the Edo period, the growth of merchant capital and the penetration of the commodity economy to agricultural villages contributed to the transformation of the hierarchy of village communities, which, however, caused such turmoils in the community as uprising peasants and destructive riots, and compelled both Bakufu (shogunate) government and Han (local domain) governments to try to reform their political systems.</e>
<cmt>Period→period, capitals→capital,a→the,society→community と修正しました。the, カンマを補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">During the Edo period, the growth of merchant capital and the penetration of the commodity economy to agricultural villages contributed to the transformation of the hierarchy of village communities, which, however, caused such turmoils in the community as uprising peasants and destructive riots, and compelled both Bakufu (shogunate) government and Han (local domain) governments to try to reform their political systems.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="12">
<j>幕末には幕府は鎖国政策を改めて開国し、朝廷権威も伸長して公武合体路線が進められる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, bakufu (shogunate) government ended its seclution policy and opened the country to the world, and along with the extension of the authority of the Imperial court, reconciliation between Imperial court and shogunate was promoted.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, bakufu (shogunate) ended its seclusion policy and opened the country to the world, and along with the extension of the authority of the Imperial court, reconciliation between the Imperial court and shogunate was promoted.</e>
<cmt>government を削除しました。seclution→seclusion,スペースを修正しました。the を補いました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the last days of the Tokugawa shogunate, bakufu (shogunate) ended its seclusion policy and opened the country to the world, and along with the extension of the authority of the Imperial court, reconciliation between the Imperial court and shogunate was promoted.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>大政奉還、王政復古 (日本)により解体された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakuhan Taisei (the feudal system of shogunate in Japan) was dissolved by Taisei Hokan (the transfer of power back to the Imperial court) and Osei Fukko (the restoration of imperial rule in Japan).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakuhan-taisei (the feudal system of shogunate in Japan) was dissolved by Taisei Hokan (the transfer of power back to the Imperial court) and Osei Fukko (the restoration of imperial rule in Japan).</e>
<cmt>Bakuhan Taisei→Bakuhan-taisei と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakuhan-taisei (the feudal system of shogunate in Japan) was dissolved by Taisei Hokan (the transfer of power back to the Imperial court) and Osei Fukko (the restoration of imperial rule in Japan).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治初期には旧藩による統治は維持されるが、中央集権政策のもと版籍奉還、廃藩置県により幕藩体制は終結する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Although the govering structure by old han (feudal domains) was maintained for a while in the early Meiji Period, Bakuhan Taisei was eventually brought to the end through a series of Hanseki Hokan (the return of lands and people to the Emperor) and Haihan Chiken (the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) under the new policy of centralization.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although the governing structure by old han (feudal domains) was maintained for a while in the early Meiji period, Bakuhan-taisei was eventually brought to the end through a series of Hanseki Hokan (the return of lands and people to the Emperor) and Haihan Chiken (the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) under the new policy of centralization.</e>
<cmt>govering→governing,Period→period,Bakuhan Taisei→Bakuhan-taisei と修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although the governing structure by old han (feudal domains) was maintained for a while in the early Meiji period, Bakuhan-taisei was eventually brought to the end through a series of Hanseki Hokan (the return of lands and people to the Emperor) and Haihan Chiken (the abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) under the new policy of centralization.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="6">
<sen id="15">
<j>学説史</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">History of Theories:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">History of Theories</e>
<cmt>コロンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">History of Theories</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="7">
<sen id="16">
<j>戦前段階</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Before the World War II:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Pre-war stage</e>
<cmt>文脈より修正しました。コロンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Pre-war stage</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>日本資本主義論争</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Disputes on Japanese Capitalism:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Disputes on Japanese capitalism</e>
<cmt>Capitalism→capitalism と修正しました。コロンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Disputes on Japanese capitalism</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>伊東多三郎説</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Theory of Tasaburo ITO:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Theory of Tasaburo ITO</e>
<cmt>コロンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Theory of Tasaburo ITO</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="8">
<sen id="19">
<j>戦後以降</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In and after the World War II:</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In and after the World War II</e>
<cmt>コロンを削除しました。ここでの”以降”の意味確認が定かでありません。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In and after the World War II</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>幕藩体制論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakuhan Taisei-ron (a theory on shogunate ruling system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakuhan Taisei ron (a theory on shogunate ruling system)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakuhan Taisei ron (a theory on shogunate ruling system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>幕藩制構造論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakuhansei Kozo-ron (a theory of structure of shogunate system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakuhansei Kozo ron (a theory of structure of shogunate system)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakuhansei Kozo ron (a theory of structure of shogunate system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>世直し状況論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Yonaoshi Jokyo-ron (a situational theory on social reform)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Yonaoshi Jokyo ron (a situational theory on social reform)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Yonaoshi Jokyo ron (a situational theory on social reform)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>幕藩制国家論</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Bakuhansei Kokka-ron (a theory on the nation of feudal shogunate system)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Bakuhansei Kokka ron (a theory on the nation of feudal shogunate system)</e>
<cmt>ハイフンを削除しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Bakuhansei Kokka ron (a theory on the nation of feudal shogunate system)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Nnh(id:474), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), Parmesan(id:14582), Nerimaman(id:61206), Tomika(id:43050), 竹麦魚(id:11012), Matsubara-kou(id:41153), BAKU(id:55205), Emonue(id:11273), くにゃこ(id:38684), Johncapistrano(id:969), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>