<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20080607-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>正中の変</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shochu Incident</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Shochu Incident</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Shochu Incident</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>正中の変（しょうちゅうのへん）とは、鎌倉時代後期の1324年（正中 (元号)元年）に起きた、後醍醐天皇による鎌倉幕府討幕計画が事前に発覚して首謀者が処分された事件である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The &quot;Shochu Incident&quot; was an incident that occurred in 1324 (late Kamakura Period), where a plan to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu by Emperor Godaigo was discovered beforehand and the main perpetrators were sentenced.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The &quot;Shochu Incident&quot; occurred in 1324 (late Kamakura Period), where a plan to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu by Emperor Godaigo was discovered beforehand and the main perpetrators were executed.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。首謀者の「処分」は「処刑」に該当すると思われますので、変更の検討をお願いします。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The &quot;Shochu Incident&quot; occurred in 1324 (late Kamakura period), where a plan to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu by Emperor Godaigo was discovered beforehand and the main perpetrators were executed.</e>
<cmt>periodl小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="2">
<j>後醍醐天皇は父である後宇多天皇に代り1324年から親政を開始し、記録荘園券契所の再興などの政治を始める。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo started direct governance in 1324 in stead of his father, Emperor Gouda, and started policies such as re-establishing the Office for the Investigation of Estate Documents (Kiroku Shoen Kenkeijo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo started direct governance in 1324 in the stead of his father, Emperor Gouda, and started policies such as re-establishing the Office for the Investigation of Estate Documents (Kiroku Shoen Kenkeijo).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo started direct governance in 1324 in the stead of his father, Emperor Gouda, and started policies such as re-establishing the Office for the Investigation of Estate Documents (Kiroku Shoen Kenkeijo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="3">
<j>後宇多法皇は死の間際まで皇太子の邦良親王を大覚寺統の嫡流として、後醍醐天皇は一刻も早く譲位を行うように命じていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Up until his death, the retired Emperor Gouda continued to order Emperor Godaigo to handover the throne to the Crown Prince Kuniyoshi as the legitimate direct heir to the Daikakuji line.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Up until his death, the retired Emperor Gouda continued to order Emperor Godaigo to handover the throne to Crown Prince Kuniyoshi as the legitimate direct heir to the Daikakuji-to line.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Up until his death, the Cloistered Emperor Gouda continued to order Emperor Godaigo to handover the throne to Crown Prince Kuniyoshi as the legitimate direct heir to the Daikakuji line.</e>
<cmt>法皇→the Cloistered Emperor に訂正しました。-to削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>法皇の死後、邦良親王は後醍醐天皇に譲位を行わせるべく鎌倉へ伺いを立てていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the Hoko&apos;s death, Crown Prince Kuniyoshi informally asked the Kamakura bakufu to force Emperor Godaigo to abdicate.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the cloistered emperor&apos;s death, Crown Prince Kuniyoshi informally asked the Kamakura bakufu to force Emperor Godaigo to abdicate.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the Cloistered Emperor&apos;s death, Crown Prince Kuniyoshi informally asked the Kamakura bakufu to force Emperor Godaigo to abdicate.</e>
<cmt>Cloistered Emperor大文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>また、持明院統もまた、邦良親王の即位後に光厳天皇を皇太子にする事を条件にこの動きを支持した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Jimyoin line also supported this movement on the condition that Emperor Kogon became Crown Prince after Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi ascended the throne.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Jimyoin-to line also supported this movement on the condition that Emperor Kogon became Crown Prince after Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Jimyoin line also supported this movement on the condition that Emperor Kogon became Crown Prince after Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi ascended to the throne.</e>
<cmt>Jimyoin-to lineの-to削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="6">
<j>当然、後醍醐天皇は邦良親王や持明院統、そしてこのような皇位継承を決めた鎌倉幕府に対して激しく反発した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Naturally, Emperor Godaigo strenuously rebelled against Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, the Jimyoin line and the Kamakura bakufu which decided on such a succession.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Naturally, Emperor Godaigo strenuously rebelled against Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, the Jimyoin-to line and the Kamakura bakufu which decided on such a succession.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Naturally, Emperor Godaigo strenuously rebelled against Imperial Prince Kuniyoshi, the Jimyoin line and the Kamakura bakufu which decided on such a succession.</e>
<cmt>Jimyoin-to lineの-to削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>後醍醐天皇は六波羅探題南方の北条維貞（北条得宗一族）が鎌倉へ赴いている最中に鎌倉幕府討幕を企て、側近の日野資朝、日野俊基らは諸国を巡って各地の武士や有力者に討幕を呼びかけていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo planned to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu while the Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata, Koresada HOJO (Hojo Tokuso family) was heading for Kamakura, and Suketomo HINO, Toshimoto HINO and others traveled around the country to convince samurai and other influential people to help overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Emperor Godaigo planned to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu while the Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata, Koresada HOJO (Hojo Tokuso family) was heading for Kamakura, and Suketomo HINO, Toshimoto HINO and others traveled around the country trying to convince samurai and other influential people to help overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Emperor Godaigo planned to overthrow the Kamakura bakufu while the Rokuhara Tandai Minamikata, Koresada HOJO (the Hojo-Tokuso family) was heading for Kamakura, and Suketomo HINO, Toshimoto HINO and others traveled around the country trying to convince samurai and other influential people to help overthrow the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>the 補足しました。Hojo-Tokusoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>13世紀中ごろから畿内などでの活動が活発であった悪党や、奥州での安東氏と蝦夷の対立など、政情不安に乗じてのものだとも考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is thought that the movement tried to take advantage of political unrest such as the akuto (people who rebelled against shoen owners and the government) that were active in the Kinki area and the conflict between Ando Family and Ezo in Oshu around the middle of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is thought that the movement tried to take advantage of political unrest such as the akuto (people who rebelled against shoen owners and the government) that were active in the Kinki area, and the conflict between the Ando Family and Ezo in Oshu around the middle of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is thought that the movement tried to take advantage of political unrest such as the akuto (people who rebelled against shoen owners and the government) that were active in the Kinki area, and the conflict between the Ando family and Ezo in Oshu around the middle of the 13th century.</e>
<cmt>family小文字にしました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="9">
<j>9月19日には、六波羅探題が察知して計画は事前に発覚し、土岐頼兼、多治見国長、足助重範など密議に参加した武将は討伐される。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On September 19, the Rokuhara Tandai uncovered the plan beforehand and samurai who participated in secret talks such as Yorikane TOKI,, Kuninaga TAJIMI, Shigenori ASUKE were subdued.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On September 19, the Rokuhara Tandai uncovered the plan before it was executed and samurai who had participated in secret talks such as Yorikane TOKI,, Kuninaga TAJIMI, and Shigenori ASUKE, were subdued.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On September 19, the Rokuhara Tandai uncovered the plan before it was executed and samurai who had participated in secret talks such as Yorikane TOKI, Kuninaga TAJIMI, and Shigenori ASUKE, were subdued.</e>
<cmt>不要な, 削除しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>俊基らは赦免されたが資朝は鎌倉へ連行され佐渡島へ流刑となり、側近の万里小路宣房らが鎌倉へ赴いて釈明を行い、後醍醐天皇は幕府に釈明して赦されるが、7年後の1331年（元弘元年）に2度目の討幕計画である元弘の乱を起こす。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Toshimoto and others were forgiven, but Sukemoto was taken to Kamakura and then exiled to Sado Island, the aide, Nobufusa MADENOKOJI went to Kamakura to offer clarification and Emperor Godaigo was forgiven by the bakufu after an apology, but seven years later, in 1331, he leads his second plan to overthrow the bakufu, the Genko no Ran (Genko Rebellion).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Toshimoto and some others were forgiven, but Sukemoto was taken to Kamakura and then exiled to Sado Island, an aide, Nobufusa MADENOKOJI went to Kamakura to offer clarification and Emperor Godaigo was forgiven by the bakufu after an apology, but seven years later, in 1331, he led his second plan to overthrow the bakufu, the Genko no Ran (Genko Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Toshimoto and some others were forgiven, but Suketomo was taken to Kamakura and then exiled to Sado Island, an aide, Nobufusa MADENOKOJI went to Kamakura to offer clarification and Emperor Godaigo was forgiven by the bakufu after an apology, but seven years later, in 1331, he led his second plan to overthrow the bakufu, the Genko no Ran (Genko Rebellion).</e>
<cmt>資朝→Suketomoに訂正しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="11">
<j>古典『太平記』で巻一に正中の変の顛末が記されており、無礼講と称して討幕計画や、計画に参加していた土岐頼員が妻に謀反の計画を漏らし、六波羅探題に事情を密告する話などが記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The first scroll of the classic, &quot;Taiheiki (Records of Great Peace)&quot;, has an account of the Shochu n Hen, depicting it as an overthrow plan disguised as &quot;bureikou (do as you please)&quot;, and a story about Yorikazu TOKI, who was participating in the plan, leaking the rebellion plan to his wife who betrayed them to the Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The first scroll of the classic, &quot;Taiheiki (Records of Great Peace)&quot;, includes an account of the Shochu-no-Hen (Shochu Incident), depicting it as an overthrow plan disguised as &quot;bureikou (do as you please)&quot;, and a story about Yorikazu TOKI, who was participating in the plan, leaking the rebellion plan to his wife who then betrayed them to the Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The first scroll of the classic, &quot;Taiheiki&quot; (Records of Great Peace), includes an account of the Shochu no Hen (Shochu Incident), depicting it as an overthrow plan disguised as &quot;bureikou&quot; (do as you please), and a story about Yorikazu TOKI, who was participating in the plan, leaking the rebellion plan to his wife who then betrayed them to the Rokuhara Tandai.</e>
<cmt>説明括弧書き位置を訂正しました。ハイフン削除、スペース補足。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>西大寺 (奈良市)系の律僧も参加していたと記されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It has that risso (monks following Rishu) of the Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) branch also participated in the plan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It states that risso (monks following Rishu) of the Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) branch also participated in the plan.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It states that risso (monks following Rishu) of the Saidai-ji Temple (Nara City) branch also participated in the plan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="13">
<j>後に建武の新政において役職を務める伊賀兼光や律僧の文観の関与も指摘されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The participation of Kanemitsu IGA, who will later becomes an official during the Kenmu Restoration, and the risso, Monkan, have also been suggested.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The participation of Kanemitsu IGA, who later became an official during the Kenmu Restoration, and the risso, Monkan, have also been suggested.</e>
<cmt>表現を変更しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The participation of Kanemitsu IGA, who later became an official during the Kenmu Restoration, and the risso, Monkan, have also been suggested.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lonicera(id:20638), クマー(id:114361), Non-stop24(id:10471), Miketsukunibito(id:10208), UMBRO(id:100484), Sat.K(id:3751), 武蔵野武蔵(id:7343), 越中掾(id:149423), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>