<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf>jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>公事銭</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujisen</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujisen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujisen</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>公事銭（くじせん）とは、中世日本において、公事の代銭納として現物（労力を含める）の代わりに納付する銭のこと。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujisen was money paid in place of taxes in kind (including labors) as daisenno (paying dues in cash instead of in kind; commutation) for kuji (public duties) in the Medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujisen was money paid in place of taxes in kind (including labor) as daisenno (paying dues in cash instead of in kind; commutation) for kuji (public duties) during Medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujisen was money paid in place of taxes in kind (including labor) as daisenno (paying dues in cash instead of in kind; commutation) for kuji (public duties) during Medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>公用銭・公事役銭とも呼ぶ。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It was also referred to as Koyosen and Kuji yakusen.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was also referred to as Koyosen and Kuji yakusen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was also referred to as Koyosen and Kuji yakusen.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="3">
<j>農業生産の向上や商工業及び交通の発達によって貨幣流通が盛んになるにつれて広く行われるようになり、室町時代には最初から銭納を想定した公事に対してもこの名称が用いられた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It had widespread, as money became circulating more rapidly due to agricultural production increase, and development of commerce, industry, and transportation; and in the Muromachi period, this name was also applied to kuji which was decided to be paid by money from the beginning.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It was widespread, as money became circulating more rapidly due to agricultural production increase, and development of commerce, industry, and transportation; and in the Muromachi period, this name was also applied to kuji which was decided to be paid by money from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>grammar</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It was widespread, as money became circulating more rapidly due to agricultural production increase, and development of commerce, industry, and transportation; and in the Muromachi period, this name was also applied to kuji which was decided to be paid by money from the beginning.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、実際の公事銭徴収は名目別に行われ、都市の住民に対しては棟別銭・地子銭・間別銭など、市場に対しては市庭銭・座役銭の名目で徴収された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Kujisen was virtually collected for each title; therefore, for the city residents, taxes were collected by the titles of munebetsu sen (household tax),. jishi sen (land tax), and mabechi sen (building and land tax), and for the market, taxes were collected by ichiba sen (marketplace tax), and zayaku sen (guild tax.)</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Kujisen was virtually collected for each title; therefore, for the city residents, taxes were collected by the titles of munebetsu sen (household tax),. jishi sen (land tax), and mabechi sen (building and land tax), and for the market, taxes were collected by ichiba sen (marketplace tax), and zayaku sen (guild tax.)</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Kujisen was virtually collected for each title; therefore, for the city residents, taxes were collected by the titles of munebetsu sen (household tax), jishi sen (land tax), and mabechi sen (building and land tax), and for the market, taxes were collected by ichiba sen (marketplace tax), and zayaku sen (guild tax).</e>
<cmt>(household tax),. のピリオドを除去しました。文末のピリオドを括弧の外に移動させました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>