<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>歴名土代</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryakumyo dodai</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryakumyo dodai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryakumyo dodai</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>歴名土代（りゃくみょうどだい/れきめいどだい）とは、中世日本の四位・五位の位階補任（叙位）の記録簿である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ryakumyo dodai (also called rekimei-dodai) was the record book of Ikai-Bunin (directory of Court rank) (the conferment of a court rank) of Shii (Forth Rank) and Goi (Fifth Rank) in the medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Ryakumyo dodai (also called rekimei-dodai) was the record book of Ikai-Bunin (directory of Court ranks) of Shii (Fourth Rank) and Goi (Fifth Rank) in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>unnecessary explanations; spelling; articles</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Ryakumyo dodai (also called rekimei-dodai) was the record book of Ikai-Bunin (directory of Court ranks) of Shii (Fourth Rank) and Goi (Fifth Rank) in medieval Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>元は2巻2冊であるが、現存本（東京大学史料編纂所所蔵本）は1冊。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original records consisted of two volumes and two books but the existing record book (a book possessed by Historiographical Institute The University of Tokyo) has only one book.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original records consisted of two volumes and two books but the existing record book (a book possessed by Historiographical Institute The University of Tokyo) has only one book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original records consisted of two volumes and two books but the existing record book (a book possessed by Historiographical Institute The University of Tokyo) has only one book.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>現存本は天文 (元号)6年（1537年）に山科言継が編纂し、後に息子の山科言経が加筆を行ったものとされている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is believed that the existing book was compiled by YAMASHINA Tokitsugu in 1537 and touched in later by his son, Tokitsune YAMASHINA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is believed that the existing book was compiled by YAMASHINA Tokitsugu in 1537 and touched up later by his son, Tokitsune YAMASHINA.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is believed that the existing book was compiled by YAMASHINA Tokitsugu in 1537 and touched up later by his son, Tokitsune YAMASHINA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>ただし、実際には言継自身が清原氏や広橋兼秀所蔵の『歴名土代』から書写したことを原本の識語に記している。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, in fact, Tokitsugu himself noted in the original books that he transcribed it from &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; possessed by the Kiyohara clan or Kanehide HIROHASHI.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, in fact, Tokitsugu himself noted in the original books that he transcribed it from &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; possessed by the Kiyohara clan or Kanehide HIROHASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, in fact, Tokitsugu himself noted in the original books that he transcribed it from &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; possessed by the Kiyohara clan or Kanehide HIROHASHI.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>元々は禁裏や公家の諸家に除目などの公事の参考とするために同様の本が編纂・所蔵されており、それぞれの家にあった本が互いに貸借・校合されていく過程で詳細な山科家のそれが通行して他家の本が行われなくなったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Originally, similar books were edited and possessed by kinri (Imperial Palace or residence) or each clan of court nobles to consult them for political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court such as jimoku (appointment ceremonies), and it is believed that the Yamashina family&apos;s detailed version was generally used and books in other families had been no longer in use in the course of borrowing and lending, or collating of those books of each clan.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Originally, similar books were edited and possessed by the Imperial Palace or each clan of court nobles to consult for political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court such as appointment ceremonies, and it is believed that the Yamashina family&apos;s detailed version was generally used and books in other families had been no longer in use in the course of borrowing and lending, or collating of those books of each clan.</e>
<cmt>too many parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Originally, similar books were edited and possessed by the Imperial Palace or each clan of court nobles to consult for political operations and ceremonies of the Imperial Court such as appointment ceremonies, and it is believed that the Yamashina family&apos;s detailed version was generally used and books in other families had been no longer in use in the course of borrowing and lending, or collating of those books of each clan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>室町時代の『康富記』（嘉吉4年正月6日条）に勅命によって“補任”“歴名”と呼ばれる記録の校訂を行った記述が見られ、『親長卿記』（文明7年2月1日条）にも外記に代わって「補歴」の改訂を行ったとする記述が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">There is the description that revision of the record called &quot;Bunin&quot; (directory of the succession) or &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; (record list) by an Imperial order was conducted in &quot;Yasutomi ki&quot; (Diaries of NAKAHARA Yasutomi) (the item of January 6, 1444) and other descriptions of revision of &quot;Bureki&quot; (directory or record list) was also conducted on behalf of Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State), in &quot;Chikanaga kyo ki&quot; (diary of Chikanaga KANROJI) (in the item of February 1, 1475).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処補歴の訳語が見つかりません。directory or record list としておきます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is recorded that a revision of the record called &quot;Bunin&quot; (directory of the succession) or &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; (record list) by an Imperial order was conducted in &quot;Yasutomi ki&quot; (Diaries of NAKAHARA Yasutomi – entry for January 6, 1444) and other descriptions of revision of &quot;Bureki&quot; (directory or record list) was also conducted on behalf of Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State), in &quot;Chikanaga kyo ki&quot; (diary of Chikanaga KANROJI – entry for February 1, 1475).</e>
<cmt>too many parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is recorded that a revision of the record called &quot;Bunin&quot; (directory of the succession) or &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; (record list) by an Imperial order was conducted in &quot;Yasutomi ki&quot; (Diaries of NAKAHARA Yasutomi – entry for February 3, 1444) and other descriptions of revision of &quot;Bureki&quot; (directory or record list) was also conducted on behalf of Geki (Secretary of the Grand Council of State), in &quot;Chikanaga kyo ki&quot; (diary of Chikanaga KANROJI – entry for March 17, 1475).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>『実隆公記』（文亀元年3月6日条）には三条西実隆が禁裏の「歴名」を借りて「歴名土代」を沙汰したとする記述が見られる（最古の『歴名土代』の記録）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In &quot;Sanetaka koki&quot; (Sanetaka&apos;s Diary) (in the item of March 6, 1501), there is another description that Sanetaka SANJONISHI ordered &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; by borrowing &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; of kinri (the oldest record of &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In &quot;Sanetaka koki&quot; (Sanetaka&apos;s Diary – March 6, 1501), there is another description that Sanetaka SANJONISHI ordered &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; by borrowing &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; of kinri (the oldest record of &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>too many parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In &quot;Sanetaka koki&quot; (Sanetaka&apos;s Diary – April 3, 1501), there is another description that Sanetaka SANJONISHI ordered &apos;Ryakumyo dodai&apos; by borrowing &apos;Ryakumyo&apos; of kinri (the oldest record of &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot;).</e>
<cmt>グレゴリオ暦に変更しました。原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>同時代の諸記録（言継の『言継卿記』を含め）に「補任歴名」あるいはこれを略した「補歴」という言葉が見られる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the various records (including &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot; (Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA)) in the same period, the term &quot;Bunin-Ryakumyo&quot; or its shortened form &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; was found.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the various records (including &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot;, the Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) in the same period, the term &quot;Bunin-Ryakumyo&quot; or its shortened form &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; was found.</e>
<cmt>too many parentheses</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the various records (including &quot;Tokitsugu Kyoki&quot;, the Dairy of Tokitsugu YAMASHINA) in the same period, the term &apos;Bunin-Ryakumyo&apos; or its shortened form &apos;Ryakumyo&apos; was found.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="9">
<j>これが『公卿補任』及び『歴名土代』の元になった公的記録であったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">This is considered that this was the formal record that became the base of &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Ryakumyo dodai.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is considered that this was the formal record that became the base of &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Ryakumyo dodai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>this-&gt;it</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is considered that this was the formal record that became the base of &quot;Kugyobunin&quot; (directory of court nobles) and &quot;Ryakumyo dodai.&quot;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>東京大学史料編纂所には『歴名』、国立歴史民俗博物館には「補任」の引用と見られる『補略』と呼ばれる書物が所蔵されており、その内容より「補任」は公卿を官位順に記したもの、「歴名」は親王・公卿・諸王・殿上人を官位順に記したものであったと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Historiographical Institute The University of Tokyo possesses &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; and National Museum of Japanese History has books called &quot;Horyaku&quot; cited from &quot;Bunin&quot; and according to their contents, it is considered that &quot;Bunin&quot; recorded court nobles in the order of official court rank and &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; recorded Imperial princes, court nobles, Shoo (princes who didn&apos;t receive any proclamation to be an Imperial Prince), or tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) in the order of official court rank.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Historiographical Institute of The University of Tokyo possesses &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; and National Museum of Japanese History has books called &quot;Horyaku&quot; cited from &quot;Bunin&quot; and according to their contents, it is considered that &quot;Bunin&quot; recorded court nobles in the order of official court rank and &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; recorded Imperial princes, court nobles, Shoo (princes who didn&apos;t receive any proclamation to be an Imperial Prince), or tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) in the order of official court rank.</e>
<cmt>prepositions</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Historiographical Institute of The University of Tokyo possesses &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; and National Museum of Japanese History has books called &quot;Horyaku&quot; cited from &apos;Bunin&apos; and according to their contents, it is considered that &apos;Bunin&apos; recorded court nobles in the order of official court rank and &apos;Ryakumyo&apos; recorded Imperial princes, court nobles, Shoo (princes who didn&apos;t receive any proclamation to be an Imperial Prince), or tenjobito (a high-ranking courtier allowed into the Imperial Palace) in the order of official court rank.</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>また、「土代」とは元は「土台」と同義語であり、文書などの下書きを指した言葉である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In addition, originally, &quot;Dodai&quot; (土代) was a synonym of &quot;Dodai&quot; (土台: base), which meant the draft of documents.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In addition, originally, &quot;Dodai&quot; (土代) was a synonym of &quot;Dodai&quot; (土台: base), which meant the draft of documents.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In addition, originally, &apos;Dodai&apos; (土代) was a synonym of &apos;Dodai&apos; (土台: base), which meant the draft of documents.</e>
<cmt>&quot; &quot;を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>このため、『歴名土代』とは元々は「歴名」のうち「補任」（あるいはこれを元にした『公卿補任』）などの他の記録と重複する公卿などの記述を省いて、予め四位・五位の叙位が予定されている人名を列記し、実際の叙位が行われた後に「歴名」を参考にして日付などが追記され、更に校合の過程で一部の整理がなされたと考えられている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Therefore, &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; is considered that it originally listed the names of persons who were scheduled to be conferred a court rank of Shii and Goi and added dates etc. with the help of &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; after the conferment of actual court rank and also organized parts of them in the process of collating, except for the descriptions of court nobles which overlapped other records such as &quot;Bunin&quot; (or Kugyobunin based on this) among &quot;Ryakumyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Therefore, &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; is considered to have originally listed the names of persons who were scheduled to be conferred a court rank of Shii and Goi and added dates etc. with the help of &quot;Ryakumyo&quot; after the conferment of actual court rank and also organized parts of them in the process of collating, except for the descriptions of court nobles which overlapped other records such as &quot;Bunin&quot; (or Kugyobunin based on this) among &quot;Ryakumyo.&quot;</e>
<cmt>that it-&gt;to have</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Therefore, &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; is considered to have originally listed the names of persons who were scheduled to be conferred a court rank of Shii and Goi and added dates etc. with the help of &apos;Ryakumyo&apos; after the conferment of actual court rank and also organized parts of them in the process of collating, except for the descriptions of court nobles which overlapped other records such as &apos;Bunin&apos; (or Kugyobunin based on this) among &apos;Ryakumyo.&apos;</e>
<cmt>原文「」の部分を&apos; &apos;に変更しました。</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="13">
<j>南北朝時代 (日本)北朝 (日本)の貞和6年（1367年）を最古とするが、四位・五位が揃うのは応永6年（1399年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The oldest &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; was found in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Northern Court of Japan in 1367, but it was in 1399 when both Shii and Goi were set.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The oldest &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; was found in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Northern Court of Japan in 1367, but it was in 1399 when both Shii and Goi were set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The oldest &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; was found in the period of the Northern and Southern Courts (Japan), Northern Court of Japan in 1367, but it was in 1399 when both Shii and Goi were set.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>ただし、この時期の記述は抄出であり、本格的な記述は嘉吉年間以後である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the record in this period was an extract version and full-blown descriptions was started after the Kakitsu Era (1141-1144).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the record in this period was an extract version and full-blown descriptions was started after the Kakitsu Era (1141-1144).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the record in this period was an extract version and full-blown descriptions was started after the Kakitsu Era (1141-1144).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>下限は慶長11年（1606年）である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The latest description was done in 1606.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The latest description was done in 1606.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The latest description was done in 1606.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>朝廷の実務官僚である四位・五位の官人のみならず中央・地方の武家や神官などの叙位について記録されている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It recorded not only government officials (esp. one of low to medium rank) of Shii and Goi, governmental officials responsible for practical works of the Imperial court but also court ranks of central and local samurai family and Shinto priest.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It recorded not only government officials of Shii and Goi, and governmental officials responsible for practical works of the Imperial court, but also court ranks of central and local samurai family and Shinto priests.</e>
<cmt>unnecessary explanations; added “and”; punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It recorded not only government officials of Shii and Goi, and governmental officials responsible for practical works of the Imperial court, but also court ranks of central and local samurai family and Shinto priests.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="17">
<j>元は2巻本で上巻に四位、下巻に五位の記述がされていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The original books were consisted of two books and Shii was recorded in Volume 1 and Goi, in Volume 2.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The original books consisted of two books and Shii was recorded in Volume 1 and Goi, in Volume 2.</e>
<cmt>deleted “were”</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The original books consisted of two books and Shii was recorded in Volume 1 and Goi, in Volume 2.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>総収録数はのべ4243名である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The total number of recorded officials was 4,243 persons.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The total number of recorded officials was 4,243 persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The total number of recorded officials was 4,243 persons.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="19">
<j>『群書類従』雑部に採録されていたが、『新校群書類従』編纂時に文亀3年（1503年）から享禄4年（1531年）分の120名分が欠落するなどの問題があった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The names were recorded in &quot;Gunsho Ruiju&quot; Zatsubu (&quot;Classified Collection of Books,&quot; Miscellaneous Section), but there was a problem such that the records of 120 persons were lost during the compiling &quot;Shinko Gunshoruiju (library)&quot; from 1503 to 1531.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The names were recorded in &quot;Gunsho Ruiju&quot; Zatsubu (&quot;Classified Collection of Books,&quot; Miscellaneous Section), but there was a problem such that the records of 120 persons were lost during the compiling &quot;Shinko Gunshoruiju (library)&quot; from 1503 to 1531.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The names were recorded in &quot;Gunsho Ruiju&quot; Zatsubu (&quot;Classified Collection of Books,&quot; Miscellaneous Section), but there was a problem such that the records of 120 persons were lost during compiling &quot;Shinko Gunshoruiju (library)&quot; from 1503 to 1531.</e>
<cmt>theを除去しました。</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="20">
<j>後に電話会社に勤務していた湯川敏治（中世公家日記研究会）によって『歴名土代』のデータベース化の試みがなされ、平成8年（1996年）にそれを元にした翻刻版が続群書類従完成会より刊行された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Later, Toshiharu YUKAWA (Chusei kuge nikki kenkyukai (Society for Research on the Medieval Court Nobles&apos; Diaries)) who worked at a telephone company tried to make a database of &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; and in 1996, the republication version based on this database was published from the &quot;Classified Documents, continued&quot; completing committee.</e>
<cmt>中世公家日記研究会の訳語が用語集にありません。Society for Research on the Medieval Court Nobles&apos; Diaries としておきます。</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Later, Toshiharu YUKAWA (Society for Research on the Medieval Court Nobles&apos; Diaries) who worked at a telephone company tried to make a database of &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; and in 1996 the revised version based on this database was published from the &quot;Classified Documents, continued&quot; completion committee.</e>
<cmt>punctuation</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Later, Toshiharu YUKAWA (Society for Research on the Medieval Court Nobles&apos; Diaries) who worked at a telephone company tried to make a database of &quot;Ryakumyo dodai&quot; and in 1996 the revised version based on this database was published from the &quot;Classified Documents, continued&quot; completion committee.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 水野白楓(id:22811), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>