<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<art orl="ja" trl="en">
<inf yea="">jawiki-20090527-pages-articles.xml</inf>
<tit>
<j>江戸幕府</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo bakufu</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo bakufu</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="1">
<j>江戸幕府（えどばくふ）は、徳川家康が創設した武家政権である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo bakufu was a samurai government established by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Edo bakufu was a samurai government established by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Edo bakufu was a samurai government established by Ieyasu TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="2">
<j>江戸（現：東京）の地に本拠を置いたのでこう呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is called as such because it was headquartered in Edo (present Tokyo).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">It is so named because its headquarters were located in Edo (present-day Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>called as such&gt;so named. headquartered in&gt;its headquarters were in. present&gt;present-day</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">It is so named because its headquarters were located in Edo (present-day Tokyo).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<sec id="1">
<tit>
<j>概要</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Summary</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="3">
<j>江戸幕府は、1603年3月24日（慶長8年2月12日 (旧暦)）に徳川家康が征夷大将軍（以下、将軍）に任官されて始まった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo bakufu was founded on March 24, 1603 when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed as Seii Taishogun (hereinafter shogun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu was founded on March 24, 1603 when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed as Seii Taishogun (hereinafter shogun).</e>
<cmt>The Edo bakufu sounds more natural</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu was founded on March 24, 1603 when Ieyasu TOKUGAWA was appointed as Seii Taishogun (hereinafter shogun).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="4">
<j>1867年11月9日（慶応3年10月14日 (旧暦)）に15代将軍徳川慶喜が大政奉還を行なった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On November 9, 1867, the 15th shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA made Taisei Hokan (transfer of power back to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On November 9, 1867, the 15th shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA transferred power back to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>Taisei hokanを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On November 9, 1867, the 15th shogun Yoshinobu TOKUGAWA transferred power back to the Emperor).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="5">
<j>後の慶応3年12月9日の王政復古の大号令において慶喜の将軍辞職と幕府の廃止が決定、江戸幕府は幕を閉じた（1868年の江戸開城の時とする見解もある）。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Decree (of 1867) for the Restoration of Imperial Rule on December 9, the resignation of Yoshinobu from shogun and the abolishment of the bakufu was determined, and the Edo bakufu was ended (some people say the end of the Edo bakufu was the time of the surrender of Edo Castle).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Decree for the Restoration of Imperial Rule on December 9, 1867 finalised the resignation of Yoshinobu as shogun and the abolishment of the bakufu, thus the Edo bakufu came to an end (although some say the end of the Edo bakufu was the time of the surrender of Edo Castle in 1868).</e>
<cmt>In the..was determined&gt;The...finalised.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Decree for the Restoration of Imperial Rule on December 9, 1867 finalised the resignation of Yoshinobu as shogun and the abolishment of the bakufu, thus the Edo bakufu came to an end (although some say the end of the Edo bakufu was the time of the surrender of Edo Castle in 1868).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="6">
<j>徳川家が将軍を歴任したので「徳川幕府」とも呼ばれる。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Since the Tokugawa family took over the position of shogun for generations, it is also called as the Tokugawa bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Since the Tokugawa family monopolised the position of shogun for generations, it is also called as the Tokugawa bakufu.</e>
<cmt>took over&gt;monopolised</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Since the Tokugawa family monopolised the position of shogun for generations, it is also called as the Tokugawa bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="7">
<j>この間の264年間を「江戸時代」もしくは「徳川時代」と呼び、徳川家が実質的に日本を支配した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The 264 years of the Edo bakufu are referred to as the &apos;Edo period&apos; or &apos;Tokugawa period,&apos; and the Tokugawa family substantially tool control of Japan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The 264 years of the Edo bakufu are referred to as the &apos;Edo period&apos; or &apos;Tokugawa period,&apos; and the Tokugawa family took a significant amount of control over Japan.</e>
<cmt>substantially tool&gt;took a significant amount of</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The 264 years of the Edo bakufu are referred to as the &apos;Edo period&apos; or &apos;Tokugawa period,&apos; and the Tokugawa family took a significant amount of control over Japan.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="8">
<j>江戸幕府は日本の歴史で最後の武家政権である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Edo bakufu was the last samurai government in the Japanese history.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu was the last samurai government in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>The Edo Bakufu.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu was the last samurai government in Japanese history.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="2">
<tit>
<j>幕藩体制</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate system</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate system</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="9">
<j>江戸幕府の支配体制は幕藩体制と呼ばれ、中央政府である幕府と地方政府である藩の二重支配になっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The ruling system of the Edo bakufu was called shogunate system, in which both bakufu (the central government) and domain (the local government) controls the people.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The system of rule of the Edo bakufu was called the shogunate system, in which both bakufu (the central government) and domain (the local government) controlled the people.</e>
<cmt>ruling system&gt;system of rule</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The system of rule of the Edo bakufu was called the shogunate system, in which both bakufu (the central government) and domain (the local government) controlled the people.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="10">
<j>将軍は大名に対して朱印状を与えてその知行を保障し、大名は当該知行内に藩を形成し、支配していた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shogun gave shuinjo (a shogunal license for foreign trade) to daimyo (Japanese feudal lord) and guaranteed their chigyo (enfeoffment), while daimyo formed a domain within the chigyo and controlled it.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shogun gave shuinjo (licenses for foreign trade) to daimyo (feudal lords) and guaranteed their status as feifs, while the daimyo formed a domain within their given feifdom and controlled it.</e>
<cmt>chigyo (enfeoffment)&gt;their status as feifs. chigyo&gt;their given feifdom.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shogun gave shuinjo (licenses for foreign trade) to daimyo (feudal lords) and guaranteed their status as feifs, while the daimyo formed a domain within their given feifdom and controlled it.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="11">
<j>寛文4年（1664年）には全国の大名に一斉に朱印状を交付する寛文印知が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In 1664, kanbuninchi was conducted in which shuinjo was issued to the daimyo across the country at the same time.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In 1664, the Kanbuninchi was conducted, whereby shuinjo were issued to daimyo across the country at the same time.</e>
<cmt>in which&gt;whereby. was&gt;were.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In 1664, the Kanbuninchi was conducted, whereby shuinjo were issued to daimyo across the country at the same time.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="12">
<j>なお、将軍の直轄地（天領）では大名の代わりに代官を置いた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the directly controlled land of shogun (tenryo), local governor was placed instead of daimyo.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In lands directly controlled by the shogun (tenryo), local governors were appointed instead of daimyo.</e>
<cmt>the land&gt;lands. placed&gt;appointed.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In lands directly controlled by the shogun (tenryo), local governors were appointed instead of daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="13">
<j>ただし、「天領」「藩」の用語は江戸時代においては公式文書で使用されることはなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, the terms &apos;tenryo&apos; and &apos;domain&apos; were not used in official documents of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, the terms &apos;tenryo&apos; and &apos;domain&apos; were not used in official documents of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, the terms &apos;tenryo&apos; and &apos;domain&apos; were not used in official documents of the Edo period.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="14">
<j>明治維新後に正式用語として認められたものである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">These were determined as official terms after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">These were determined as official terms after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">These were determined as official terms after the Meiji Restoration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="15">
<j>また幕府も「（御）公儀」と呼ばれていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, bakufu was called as &apos;goki&apos; or &apos;gokogi.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Also, bakufu was called as &apos;goki&apos; or &apos;gokogi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Also, bakufu was called as &apos;goki&apos; or &apos;gokogi.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="16">
<j>広義の幕藩体制は明治4年（1871年）の廃藩置県をもって終焉する。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The shogunate system in a broad sense ended at the time of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in 1871.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The shogunate system in a broad sense ended at the time of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The shogunate system in a broad sense ended at the time of Haihan-chiken (abolition of feudal domains and establishment of prefectures) in 1871.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="17">
<j>江戸幕府の支配下、各藩大名に対して参勤交代を強いたり、築城・治水工事を命じたりした。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the control of Edo bakufu, each daimyo (other than daimyo of Edo Jofu (a Daimyo feudal lord&apos;s retainer who remained permanently in the Edo with the lord&apos;s and their own family in the Edo period) such as the Mido domain) was obliged to participate in Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and to engage in castle constructions and flood prevention works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the control of the Edo bakufu, all daimyo were obliged to participate in Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and to engage in castle construction and flood prevention works.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the control of the Edo bakufu, all daimyo were obliged to participate in Sankinkotai (a system under which feudal lords in the Edo period were required to spend every other year in residence in Edo) and to engage in castle construction and flood prevention works.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="18">
<j>（水戸藩等江戸定府大名を除く）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1"></e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, this did not include daimyo of Edo Jofu - a feudal lord&apos;s retainer who remained permanently in Edo with the lord and their own family - such as the Mido domain</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文例外対処</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, this did not include daimyo of Edo Jofu - a feudal lord&apos;s retainer who remained permanently in Edo with the lord and their own family - such as the Mido domain</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="19">
<j>大きな財政負担を与えることで弱体化させ江戸幕府に対して武力反抗できないようにする政策を執った。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The Edo bakufu aimed to weaken the domains by putting large financial burdens and not to let them revolt against the Edo bakufu.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Edo bakufu aimed to weaken the domains by placing them under large financial burdens and not letting them revolt against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>putting&gt;placing them under. the Edo bakufu&gt;the bakufu</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Edo bakufu aimed to weaken the domains by placing them under large financial burdens and not letting them revolt against the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="20">
<j>政治機構内においては初代徳川家康と二代徳川秀忠、三代徳川家光、五代徳川綱吉、八代徳川吉宗、十一代徳川家斉の治世は征夷大将軍親政で政治が行なわれた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Under the political structure of the Edo bakufu, it is considered that during the time of the first shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the fifth shogun, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, and the eleventh shogun, Ienari TOKUGAWA, the country was ruled by the shogun himself.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Under the political structure of the Edo bakufu, it is considered that the country was ruled by the shogun himself during the rules of the first shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the fifth shogun, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, and the eleventh shogun, Ienari TOKUGAWA,</e>
<cmt>順番を変えました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Under the political structure of the Edo bakufu, it is considered that the country was ruled by the shogun himself during the rules of the first shogun, Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, the second shogun, Hidetada TOKUGAWA, the third shogun, Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, the fifth shogun, Tsunayoshi TOKUGAWA, the eighth shogun, Yoshimune TOKUGAWA, and the eleventh shogun, Ienari TOKUGAWA,</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="21">
<j>しかし、それ以外の将軍は幕閣に政治を任せるか、前将軍（または将軍の父）である大御所に唯々諾々と従う存在であったかのように思われがちである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">And other shogun were often considered that they let the cabinet officials of the Shogunate to conduct the politics or just followed the orders made by the former shogun (or the father of the shogun).</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The other shogun are often considered to have left political matters to Bakufu cabinet officials, or to have merely followed the orders made by the former shogun (or his father).</e>
<cmt>Andを省略し、were&gt;are. of the shogunate&gt;bakufu. just&gt;merely</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The other shogun are often considered to have left political matters to Bakufu cabinet officials, or to have merely followed the orders made by the former shogun (or his father).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="22">
<j>しかしこれは徳川期及び明治・大正期における大いなる誤解である。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">However, this is a big misunderstanding in the Tokugawa, Meiji and Taisho periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">However, for the Tokugawa, Meiji and Taisho periods, this is a critical misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>順番を変え、big&gt;critical</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">However, for the Tokugawa, Meiji and Taisho periods, this is a critical misunderstanding.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="23">
<j>歴代の徳川将軍は能力の優劣はあったとしても、それぞれにおいてそれなりに政治に関与していた事実は確かであり、また逆に完全に独裁者として振る舞っていた訳でもない。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">It is true that to some extent every shogun was involved in the politics although some were better than others, and it is also true that none of them acted as a complete dictator.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Although some were more competent than others, every shogun was to at least some extent involved in politics, and it is also true that none of them acted as a complete dictator.</e>
<cmt>change sentence order</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Although some were more competent than others, every shogun was to at least some extent involved in politics, and it is also true that none of them acted as a complete dictator.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="24">
<j>歴代将軍の中でも一番独裁性の強かった徳川家康の治世においても、諌言したり政策立案する幕閣は存在したのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Even under the rules of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, whose control had the strong aspect of dictatorship among all the shoguns, there were cabinet officials of the Shogunate who remonstrated against the shogun or who was engaged in formulation of policies.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Even under the rule of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, whose governance had the strongest aspects of dictatorship of all the shoguns, there were cabinet officials in the Shogunate who remonstrated against the shogun and were engaged in formulation of policies.</e>
<cmt>rule&gt;governance. strong aspect&gt;strongest aspects</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Even under the rule of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, whose governance had the strongest aspects of dictatorship of all the shoguns, there were cabinet officials in the Shogunate who remonstrated against the shogun and were engaged in formulation of policies.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="25">
<j>家康はむしろ諌言する家臣を好み、また意見の相違で家臣とつかみ合いの喧嘩をする事もあった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Ieyasu rather liked vassals who remonstrated against him, and sometimes he grabbed and pulled with such vassals for the difference of opinions.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Rather than being angry, Ieyasu actually liked it when vassals remonstrated against him, and when there was a difference of opinion he would sometimes have physical fights with them.</e>
<cmt>rather than being angryを入れ、rather&gt;actually.</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Rather than being angry, Ieyasu actually liked the vassals who remonstrated against him, and when there was a difference of opinion he would sometimes have physical fights with them.</e>
<cmt>liked it when vassals remonstrated -&gt; liked the vassals who remonstrated</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="26">
<j>また逆に三代将軍徳川家光の場合、治世の初期は大御所・徳川秀忠に従う存在でしかなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the other hand, in the case of the third shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA, during the early stage of his reign, he just followed ogosho Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">On the other hand, the third shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA was completely different, and during the early stage of his reign, he simply followed Ogosho Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>in the case of&gt;was completely different. just?simply</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">On the other hand, the third shogun Iemitsu TOKUGAWA was completely different, and during the early stage of his reign, he simply followed Ogosho Hidetada TOKUGAWA.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="27">
<j>秀忠死後は政治のかなりの部分を幕閣に任せており、家光が親政を行なったというのは幕閣がそのように宣伝した結果であるとも言われている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">After the death of Hidetada, Iemitsu let his cabinet officials of the Shogunate conduct most of the political works and people&apos;s perception that Iemitsu engaged in politics himself is said to be the result of the publicity by the cabinet officials.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">After the death of Hidetada, Iemitsu let the Bakufu cabinet officials conduct most of the political works and people&apos;s perception that Iemitsu personally engaged in politics is said to be the result of propaganda by cabinet officials.</e>
<cmt>of the Shogunate&gt;bakufu. publicity&gt;propaganda</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">After the death of Hidetada, Iemitsu let the Bakufu cabinet officials conduct most of the political works and people&apos;s perception that Iemitsu personally engaged in politics is said to be the result of propaganda by cabinet officials.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="28">
<j>基本的にどの治世においても将軍は完全な独裁者、もしくは（将軍が幼少の場合を除き）幕閣の完全な傀儡という状態ではなく、老中を中心とする幕閣による合議で決定された事案を将軍が決裁するシステムが存続した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Basically, none of the shogun was a complete dictator nor a complete puppet of the cabinet officials (other than when the shogun was very young), and there was a system in which the issues discussed by the roju-centered cabinet officials were determined by the shogun.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Basically, no shogun was a complete dictator nor a complete puppet of the cabinet officials (other than when the shogun was very young), and there was a system in place whereby the shogun had the final say on issues discussed by cabinet officials (mainly senior councilors, &quot;roju&quot;).</e>
<cmt>were determined by the shogun. &gt;the shogun had the final say. roju-centered&gt;mainly senior councilors, &quot;roju&quot;</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Basically, no shogun was a complete dictator nor a complete puppet of the cabinet officials (other than when the shogun was very young), and there was a system in place whereby the shogun had the final say on issues discussed by cabinet officials (mainly senior councilors, &quot;roju&quot;).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="29">
<j>八代将軍徳川吉宗は、江戸の開幕以降最大の幕政改革を行ない、「江戸幕府の中興の祖」と呼ばれている。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The eighth shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA conducted the reformation of the shogunate government, which was the largest in scale ever since the foundation of the Edo bakufu, and he is called &apos; the restorer of the Edo bakufu.&apos;</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The eighth shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA conducted the largest-scale reformation of the shogunate government since its foundation, thus earning the title &apos;Restorer of the Edo bakufu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>which was the largest in scale ever since the foundation of the Edo bakufu&gt;since its foundation. he is called&gt;thus earning the title</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The eighth shogun Yoshimune TOKUGAWA conducted the largest-scale reformation of the shogunate government since its foundation, thus earning the title &apos;Restorer of the Edo bakufu.&apos;</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<sec id="3">
<tit>
<j>大名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</tit>
<par id="1">
<sen id="30">
<j>大名は以下のように分類された。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Daimyo were classified as follows.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Daimyo were classified as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Daimyo were classified as follows.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="2">
<sen id="31">
<j>徳川氏の一族である親藩</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Shinpan, the family of the Tokugawa clan.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Shinpan, from Tokugawa clan families.</e>
<cmt>内容を修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Shinpan, from Tokugawa clan families.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="3">
<sen id="32">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い以前から徳川家に仕えていた譜代大名</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Fudai daimyo, who had been serving the Tokugawa clan before the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Fudai daimyo, who had been serving the Tokugawa clan before the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Fudai daimyo, who had been serving the Tokugawa clan before the Battle of Sekigahara.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="4">
<sen id="33">
<j>関ヶ原の戦い以降から徳川家に仕え始めた外様大名（関ヶ原の戦いで東軍として戦った豊臣系大名も含む）</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Tozama daimyo, who began to serve the Tokugawa clan after the Battle of Sekigahara (including the Toyotomi-related daimyo who fought as the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara).</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Tozama daimyo, who began to serve the Tokugawa clan after the Battle of Sekigahara (including the Toyotomi-related daimyo who fought as the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Tozama daimyo, who began to serve the Tokugawa clan after the Battle of Sekigahara (including the Toyotomi-related daimyo who fought as the East squad in the Battle of Sekigahara).</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
<par id="5">
<sen id="34">
<j>この分類では、政権内の権力で大きな差となっていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">According to this classification, there was significant differences in the authorities under the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">According to this classification, there were significant differences in the daimyo&apos;s political authority.</e>
<cmt>authorities under the administration.&gt;the daimyo&apos;s political authority</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">According to this classification, there were significant differences in the daimyo&apos;s political authority.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="35">
<j>特に、幕府の要職には全て譜代大名をもって充てた事は、鎌倉幕府、室町幕府からの大きな転換であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Especially the fact that all the important roles were taken by Fudai daimyo was a major shift from the Kamakura and Muromachi periods.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fact that all the important roles were taken by Fudai daimyo was a particularly major shift from the Kamakura and Muromachi periods.</e>
<cmt>Especially&gt;particularly</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fact that all the important roles were taken by Fudai daimyo was a particularly major shift from the Kamakura and Muromachi periods.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="36">
<j>鎌倉・室町幕府においては、（時によっては将軍家・執権すらしのぐほどの）有力御家人・守護大名が要職に就いていた。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, major senior vassals and shugo daimyo (shugo, which were Japanese provincial military governors, that became daimyo, which were Japanese feudal lords) (who were sometimes even stronger than the shogun family or regent) took important roles.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, major senior vassals and shugo daimyo (provincial military governors, who became feudal lords) took important roles and were sometimes even stronger than the shogunal family or regent.</e>
<cmt>守護大名の説明文を簡潔にさせました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In the Kamakura and Muromachi periods, major senior vassals and shugo daimyo (provincial military governors, who became feudal lords) took important roles and were sometimes even stronger than the shogunal family or regent.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="37">
<j>また、豊臣政権末期の五大老制は有力大名による集団指導体制であり、外様大名である徳川家康の政権簒奪を防ぐことができなかった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Also, the Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) system at the end of the Toyotomi government was a collective leadership system by major daimyo, which could not prevent Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, a tozama daimyo, to deprive the administration.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) system at the end of the Toyotomi government was a collective leadership system by powerful daimyo, however they were unable to prevent Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, a tozama daimyo, for usurping power.</e>
<cmt>major&gt;powerful. could not&gt;were unable. to deprive the administration&gt;usurping power</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The Gotairo (Council of Five Elders) system at the end of the Toyotomi government was a collective leadership system by powerful daimyo, however they were unable to prevent Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, a tozama daimyo, from usurping power.</e>
<cmt>for -&gt; from</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="38">
<j>これに対して、江戸幕府では譜代大名が幕府の要職を独占した。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">On the contrary, in the Edo bakufu, fudai daimyo dominated the important roles of the bakufu.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In contrast, in the Edo bakufu, it was the fudai daimyo who dominated important roles in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>on the contrary&gt;in contrast. It was...whoを入れました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In contrast, in the Edo bakufu, it was the fudai daimyo who dominated important roles in the bakufu.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="39">
<j>元は豊臣政権時代は一大名に過ぎなかった徳川家康のさらに臣下であった譜代大名は、さほど有力ではない小大名が中心であった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">The fudai daimyo, who were just a vassal of Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who himself was just a daimyo under the Toyotomi government, were mainly not-so-powerful small daimyo.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">The fudai daimyo, merely vassals to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who himself had been a simple daimyo under the Toyotomi government, were mainly uninfluential, small daimyo.</e>
<cmt>just a vassal&gt;merely vassals. not-so-powerfuil&gt;uninfluential</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">The fudai daimyo, merely vassals to Ieyasu TOKUGAWA, who himself had been a simple daimyo under the Toyotomi government, were mainly uninfluential, small daimyo.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="40">
<j>有力な大名は外様大名として政権の要職に就く事が無くなった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Major daimyo became tozama daimyo in the Edo bakufu and they did not have a chance to take important roles under the administration.</e>
<cmt>一原文一訳文の例外対処</cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Major daimyo became tozama daimyo in the Edo bakufu and thus did not have a chance to take on important roles in the administration.</e>
<cmt>they&gt;thus. take&gt;take on. of&gt;in</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Major daimyo became tozama daimyo in the Edo bakufu and thus did not have a chance to take on important roles in the administration.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="41">
<j>つまり、徳川将軍個人の独裁体制ではないものの、徳川家という枠組において独裁体制を敷いていたのである。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">In other words, the Edo bakufu was not a dictatorship of the Tokugawa shogun himself, but was a dictatorship in the framework of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">In other words, the Edo bakufu was not a dictatorship of the Tokugawa shogun himself, but a dictatorship in the framework of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>wasを省略しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">In other words, the Edo bakufu was not a dictatorship of the Tokugawa shogun himself, but a dictatorship in the framework of the Tokugawa family.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
<sen id="42">
<j>またこの事により、あまり政治に関与しなかった将軍であっても、幕閣の完全な傀儡になる事はなく、政権の簒奪も未然に防止することが可能となった。</j>
<e type="trans" ver="1">Due to this fact, even the shogun who was not deeply involved in politics did not become a complete puppet of the cabinet officials of the Shogunate, and therefore the usurpation of the administration could be prevented.</e>
<cmt></cmt>
<e type="trans" ver="2">Due to this fact, even if the shogun was not involved in politics, he would not become a complete puppet of the cabinet officials, and equally usurping of power could be prevented.</e>
<cmt>原文に応じて修正しました。</cmt>
<e type="check" ver="1">Due to this fact, even if the shogun was not involved in politics, he would not become a complete puppet of the cabinet officials, and equally usurping of power could be prevented.</e>
<cmt>修正なし</cmt>
</sen>
</par>
</sec>
<copyright>copyright (c) 2010 Lusheeta(id:11139), Nnh(id:474), V-TWIN POWER(id:49244), Okome(id:98), 経済準学士(id:22656), HI(id:72996), Lupinoid(id:68), Damdamdamd(id:109603), Kamakura(id:472), Gombe(id:27), でここ(id:9565), Shelling ford 221b(id:35237), るがこむ(id:181), Archivist(id:52904), Michey.M(id:906), 新芽(id:50924), 俊(id:14924), Washiucho(id:108096), Shimoxx(id:9332), 百楽天(id:5266), Maakun(id:16735), FlaBot(id:30804), Calvero(id:38360), ウィキ豊(id:82961), DCyokohama(id:26779), Osu-mike(id:61051), YonaBot(id:125006), Kouyama.h(id:36157), Ytp.rs(id:202698), 彩華1226(id:64711), はるひ(id:59079), 白拍子花子(id:244805), MDR-SK(id:192066), SuisuiBot(id:10165), 総督(id:124846), KSKS(id:97637), 三菱善次郎(id:21924), トホホ川(id:50502), 伏儀(id:142093), Bot-Schafter(id:94967), Suisui(id:69), Jade0416(id:104181), Hyuuga(id:14767), Reggaeman(id:6214), 凹凸(id:262207), 廃土①伍禄(id:126436), Mintleaf(id:2216), Kotoito(id:21045), Tr-909(id:25414), Bmeg(id:118515), ベム・ウーゴ(id:198047), ShikiH(id:181574), Yubonian(id:213184), 錬金初級(id:214460), 嫦娥(id:81469), Rei-bot(id:94097), Chobot(id:20846), 李(id:10582), Yosemite(id:5808), LERK(id:4460), 初瀬(id:74855), 水野白楓(id:22811), Law soma(id:45202), Mkill(id:22697), 酢溜まり氷(id:65987), Hogué(id:18263), 松平定治(id:146386), Heyjudo(id:15552), 兵砂(id:58388), きまま(id:183217), 独立行政法人情報通信研究機構．このテキストの利用はCreative Commons Attribution-Share-Alike License 3.0 の条件の下に許諾されます．（この著作権者一覧には、Wikipedia IPユーザーを含んでおりません．この点に関するお問い合わせはこちらまで：kyoto-corpus@khn.nict.go.jp）</copyright>
</art>